recording hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hero the show that we code a
complete game live on stream we are in
the middle of some lighting stuff and we
kind of have a bit of a you know
question a conundrum to deal with today
today is day 404 which of course means
that this episode will not be findable
by HTTP but if you take a look at where
we're at in the code base I'll show you
what we threw in at the end of the
stream yesterday and it kind of brought
up a good question that we I think need
to or want to address relatively soon
so here is the current little test room
with no lighting in and then if I go
ahead and run our sort of offline test
lighting version you can see the
reflector solution for it and if we go
ahead and switch to viewing the the
actual world colored with the lighting
solution you can actually see that oddly
enough it's starting to look pretty nice
in terms of how the lighting gets
computed however we do have this sort of
question I was asking at the end of the
stream last time which is what are we
going to do about actually
reconstructing the per-pixel lighting
from the you know course lighting
computations that we do and what you can
see here is that in some circumstances
when because what we're what we're
actually sending down here is a vertex
based lighting just as a test and so
what you can see here is we're computing
the lighting at the vertices basically
not exactly at the vertices but a better
way to say it might be we're putting
little panels near the vertices to
determine what we think they should be
how that we think they should be lit and
then each one of these cubes or sprites
as well depending on the circumstance is
getting lit by interpolating among
that solution to give it a color wash
and what you can see is that actually
looks really nice like here or here or
here and here down in this area and so
on I it actually looks pretty good
because you end up with a solution where
the the lighting tends to be fairly
smooth across the vertices and doesn't
vary very much but the problem that you
quickly get into with the with doing
schema sway is when you do the
interpolation you can see how you get
banding in cases where you know you've
got two dark vertices and to light
vertices opposed but you know opposing
each other and it just says that it does
not produce and a satisfying lighting
solution at all right it's definitely
not something that you would want you
just don't want that look right that's
not going to be satisfying at all
now all the lighting that we're
contemplating doing is approximate so
it's not as if there's something you
know inherent in here that I'm objecting
to in terms of its accuracy it's I'm
just objecting to the fact that we will
have these artifacts and we don't want
those artifacts so what we're trying to
do here is come up with some way of
making it less likely that we'll get
artifacts of this nature and that way we
can I just want something that will
produce smoother nicer results here and
the the question that we have to address
in order to figure out how you know what
our strategy is going to be for avoiding
that problem is that we don't know how
we're going to be reconstructing the
lighting from a lighting solution we
know we are going to have a lighting
solution that will be coarser than the
optimal solution in terms of bouncing
light around
and I'm actually starting to be
relatively pleased with this sort of
reflectors idea here and how it's
working basically just light samples
that are taken throughout the world and
we actually do relatively good lighting
computation on those I think we're going
to be able to make that work I suspect
I'm not sure but I think we probably
will be able to make it work on the GPU
and so it'll be able to run reasonably
quickly however what I don't really know
how we're going to do is take that and
no matter what we do right we're going
to have something like this like it
works where it's a core sample of
lighting I don't know how we're going to
take that and convert that into actual
lighting for the pixels in the game and
there's a number of different ways that
we could try to make this work and I
just don't know which of them is going
to be the most intelligent or or I
shouldn't even say that it's more that I
don't even really know what the space of
total options are inside the space of
what we could do like I just don't even
really know what all of our options are
if you look you can kind of see that if
you just take a look at these reflectors
here then you know one one way we could
approach this problem is by just trying
to use these sample points for the
lighting as something that we gather up
to compute the lighting at any given
pixel right and that's a pretty
reasonable way to approach this problem
it's just an interpolation problem so
the idea is the first path splashed down
a number of different light samples like
this and then the rendering actually per
pixel just goes and tries to find what
light samples are close by right now the
problem with that and I'm not sure
exactly how we would want to deal with
this but there's a problem with that
kind of a scheme like the gather light
kind of
and that is what happens at edges such
as this one so if you take a look at you
know if I swap between these quickly you
can kind of see what the problem would
begin to be if I want to know what the
color should be in this area then you
know I'm sampling the lighting from say
this and this I don't really know where
it goes from red to grey right I just
know that somewhere in between here it
changed and so we would have to kind of
have a relatively smart reconstruction
filter probably something which said oh
you know this surface the lighting
samples from this surface and the
lighting samples are from this surface
when I'm reconstructing this surface
wait the samples from this surface more
heavily than from this surface or
something because otherwise you end up
getting a lot of way too much color
bleed like this right here will be like
fully red like this as it interpolates
between the red and the grey and that's
not really what you want right you want
a nice hard edge there like we have now
this is really the more accurate way to
look at that and so you know again like
I'm not 100% certain how we really want
to do that
so it may be that we just want to send
down local interpolators one of the
ideas that someone came up with on the
last stream or I mean at least this is
how I interpreted the idea not unless
they're exactly what they're going for
but one of the things we could do is per
quad just send down the for
interpolation points have our own
interpolation scheme that we use and
just go from there
right meaning we don't actually do a
global gather at all we just do an
interpolation scheme that's not based on
that and if we think about how that
would have to work it's actually not
that difficult to determine how that
should probably work basically all we
need to do is come up with some
different way of specifying the color
wash over the surface
so that it doesn't have that sort of
banding artifact kind of thing happening
to it right so that idea
those last thing we discussed right it
was basically saying well you know I
forgot we got a sprayer of some free up
some GPU resources for Milton so if you
take a look at what's going on with the
current interpolation the current
interpolation is doing interpolation
like this so let's say we have dark dark
and light and then we imagine it's a
quad so you know we get the problem
where there's light over here as well so
what will happen here is because dark
and dark are on the diagonal here this
entire diagonal will be dark right it
will always be completely dark in fact
if you imagine that these are just the
value 1 and the value 0 and we have the
value 1 here what you can see will
happen when you do this kind of
interpolation is that everything across
this line will be 0 because the the
linear interpolation across this line
right will always stay at 0
there's never anywhere else for it to go
because this point isn't involved in the
interpolation across this triangle line
right so this point will correctly be
point 5 you know that is what that point
will be but this point will still be 0
so that's why you get that dark band
that comes down so the other question is
well what would happen if we were doing
proper bilinear here you know what would
that look like
so if you imagine we have bilinear that
was you know built on the same
distribution of of magnitudes then along
this diagonal we no longer get that same
behavior because if we bilinear these no
matter which way we do it we're going to
get point 5 here and we're going to get
point 5 here right because we know
that's true we know that even if we did
it the other way we would get point 5 in
both cases right and so now when we
interpolate this position we're actually
gonna get point 5 here right
so this produces a more rectilinear
blend of the colors which in art because
all of our stuff is rectilinear may well
produce less objectionable artifacts for
this very reason so what this would do
instead is this would produce something
that was like bright up here right and
then got sort of a little bit darker as
it got to here right the standard
bilinear interpolation pattern and then
as we got further out to the ones it's
going to have the same thing here where
it's got kind of a bright bit here and
then darker like so and this is the that
part is very dark there and so you could
imagine this producing a less objection
artifact perhaps however you're still
going to end up I think if you went this
route and we could test it certainly but
I think you're still going to end up
with objectionable artifact they're just
going to be crosswise right you're going
to end up with weird like patterns that
look like this this sort of a of a thing
just like you do with bilinear filtering
right you know you know the pattern I'm
talking about it looks like this kind of
a thing I don't know if we can find
someone who's drawn that diagram
bilinear yeah it's right in fact there
it is very first thing so you see those
plus patterns those plus patterns is
what we would get kind of blown up
pretty large right I don't know if
there's any other images that would show
it well doesn't look like it looks like
these are all talking about sort of
something a little more not really well
there you go that's a pretty good one
too
right so this right here is not sure
what exactly this is a curve based one
or whatever yeah this right here is the
kind of thing that we would see sort of
in the Centers of our pixels I think and
potentially around edges it's again like
I said kind of hard to really know
exactly what it would look like I don't
know if I can zoom in on this can i yeah
there we go so I can't tell they don't
have any of the worst-case in here like
I was talking about where there's two
bright pixels on either side and two
dark pixels on either side which is kind
of the thing that we want to see but I
need like a little thing where I can
just put in something to by linear
filter so anyway the point there is
simply that they're still going to be
artifacts if we use a bilinear filter
however this is lighting and lighting
tends to be more radial right because
the fall-off curve across a plane tends
to be more about distance and distance
tends to be radial it doesn't tend to be
linear right it's linear along you know
a line I guess you could say you could
approximate linearly but not as that lot
as that line becomes a plane right
because if you imagine you know of the
light being very far away and casting on
here then as it gets dimmer it does form
sort of a linear interpolation but if
you imagine the light being very close
then it's typically going to be very
curved right so one thing we could think
about in addition is saying well if
we're going to interpolate lighting
across a quad and we've only computed
things at the vertices or you know maybe
we even get a little fancier and compute
more than just the vertices like maybe
we go nuts and there's just like tons of
points that we computed I don't know
right but let's suppose we do something
where we've got some number
sample points we could choose to
reconstruct them with something that
isn't linear right we could use
something like a radial you know some
kind of radial normalized interpolation
like a weighted some kind of a thing
that normalizes the contribution up
based on a distance value so that these
points are actually radio right and have
radial interference patterns and that
again might give us something that looks
more lighting esque than reconstructing
it with simply a linear interpolation
since we probably have plenty of per
pixel time to do that I would think on a
higher end card and we can if we want to
play it a little bit fast and loose
there and maybe do different things
depending on whether we're on the front
depth field or not right like our first
step feel we could do stuff like doing
the lighting differently per destiel if
we need to speed wise or I don't know
that could lead to artifacts so I'm not
sure on high-end GPUs I really don't
think we're going to have a problem
because you know they have so much
horsepower to spare and hey you can
always turn lighting down to a low
quality setting if it turned out to be
something we needed to get rid of so
point being I think we would have time
to do something fancier there where the
where the quads themselves are sort of
shaded with something a little bit more
fancy and so if we thought about you
know if we if we took a look at how we
were going to do that potentially the
problem is we need access to these
things a you know in our shaders right
and in order to have access to these in
our shaders we have to kind of again
decide how we want to interpolate our
lighting and how we're going to access
the interpolation to our lighting and so
again that brings us just back to the to
the very basic question of do we want to
interpolate across primitives or not
right meaning is this going to be a
global lookup of the lighting or is it
just going to be local to the primitive
we happen to be sending down meaning if
this or our sample points do we want to
have all of these sample points
available to the primitives so that when
the primitive is shading itself it looks
up into say a texture that has these
sample points encoded or are we going to
do something that is you know unrelated
to this in some way and you're just
going to send down information for how
to shade a particular triangle right or
something like this and I really like I
said I really don't know so this is all
experimental I have no particular idea
about what the best way to do this would
be what I will say is I'm definitely
tempted to do something that uses all
the samples meaning that allows the per
pixel reconstruction to actually take
into account everything that it sees
everything that we've computed the
reason for that is it feels a lot like
throwing information away if for example
when we go to shade you know this thing
right here we've really done ourselves a
disservice it seems if we throw away the
lighting information for the you know
for the piece of the ground that's right
next to it because man that seems like
useful information right and it seems
like we could get much nicer lighting
solutions by you know gathering from the
things that are closeby
so it definitely seems like the kind of
thing that's a little bit tough - it's
just the kind of thing that seems a
little bit a little bit hard to pass up
it's like it seems like we want to push
that information down to the card and
have it do the reconstruction
so that raises the question of how we
would store and how we would index you
know into something that looks like this
and again that's kind of one of those
things that I wish I had a better idea
of how we should do it
I don't but let me just talk through a
little bit of it here oops
of course the the classic cannot access
the tablet I do not know why that
happens no one seems to know all right
so here we are on day 404 lighting
lookup so what I need to do here is I
need to take what is essentially spatial
data right so I've got you know only
take that corner case that we have there
for example so let's suppose we're
looking at the place like this where we
sort of have the wall here and the
ground here and we're trying to light
this stuff so we know right now that we
took lighting samples at effectively
these locations but that's not really
the important part you know the
important part is we took some lighting
samples and those ladies samples we
could really distribute anywhere
honestly right because the point of the
reconstruction is to take lighting
samples that we distributed and do
something sensible with them so we
probably don't really need to think too
hard about where the lighting samples
are we just need to think about the fact
that we have some lighting samples in
space and now we need to reconstruct
lighting from them right okay so once we
have these lighting samples in space
then what we want to do is say okay when
I am computing something like one of
these pixels I want to be able to take a
neighborhood around where I am and see
what all of the lighting is in that area
right so it's kind of like a sphere
full query wow that's some handwriting
there you go so it's kind of like a
spherical query in a sense that what we
would ideally like to do is we'd like to
be able to say okay I'm going to shade
this pixel please tell me all of the
lighting samples that are within you
know are some radius of me and I'm going
to take all those samples and average
them together based on how far away I am
from them let's say right by the way
this is some good lemonade anyway so we
need two things for this first of all we
need to send samples to the card
right and we don't know in the future
those lighting samples might not be sent
to the car they may actually just be
created on the card right
so saying sending lighting samples so
the card is really just for our current
test purposes so that's you know this is
really just something we need to do for
right now because we would like to go to
compute lighting on the CPU at least for
now we may not compute lighting on the
CPU in the long run we may just have the
GPU do it but you know that's neither
here nor there so at some point we have
to send like a filter card which means
we need a storage format for them and
number two we need to be able to quickly
spatially query them right so we need
two things we need a storage format that
will store these lighting samples with
something that the graphics card can
access and the second thing we need is a
way to quickly spatially query what up
what lighting samples are near to a
particular 3d point in space right those
are the two things we need in order to
do those two things they're actually the
first ones pretty straightforward I
think right if we think about how we
would store these well we know that a
lighting sample is like an X Y and a Z
right and then you know a RG and a B
intensity so really we can just store
this with to RGB textures maybe there's
something more clever we would want to
do at some point but really you know the
without thinking too hard about it too
RGB textures I will store them all
there's there's really nothing more to
it than that right
then for the spatial query aspect of it
that parts a little bit trickier but we
do have options for it so the simplest
option probably is just going to be a
voxel right so what we would do if we
wanted to store a spatial query that was
not particularly intelligent in any real
fancy way but which we you know like I
said wanted to construct something that
was a relatively simple spatial query we
could do something that was sort of a
you know a lookup structure that was you
know 256 by 256 by say 32 something like
this which is not a huge amount of space
even though it is a voxel right it's um
let's say we probably need 16 I guess it
depends on how many reflections we have
don't love it so you know it's probably
let's say each one of those needs to be
16 bit so it's 4 megabytes which is not
the end of the world right
but in that 2 3 6 by 2 6 by 32 texture
what we would do is it each cell we
would just store an index to the the
texture set right so in this texture
series here in in this these these two
textures right we've got two textures
imagine that they were just either 1d
textures or 2d textures that we treat it
as 1d textures either way doesn't really
matter but imagine that we've got you
know the XYZ texture and the RGB texture
they're just some big list of lighting
samples however many we decide to take
right and you imagine the first Texel is
zero and then the you know 6 5 5 3 6
well just uh 5 3 5 is the maximum one
what you can imagine is in this texture
we just store a single 16-bit value that
says we're
the textures for this where the letting
samples for that block start right and
we could choose to store account in here
as well if we want to make this a 32-bit
texture so it's 8 megabytes we could
store an offset and account and then we
would know how many of them to read as
well or we could just assume that there
is like a fixed number of there's a
fixed number store or a null terminator
right you could imagine that when the
XYZ value that you encounter has some
special value so for example if you just
put you know in inside X or something
like this you know you've hit the null
terminator so you know you've got
different ways you can can deal with it
and it depends whether you care about
this texture getting bloated or this
texture getting bloated I'm not sure I
know off the bat which one of those
would be better this RGB right here this
texture can be 24-bit this texture here
probably can't be this texture here
probably has to be actually a float
texture or a 16-bit per channel texture
just because it's storing positions in
space and we need to be able to
reconstruct that with some fidelity so
it suggests to me that this would
probably be a fairly large texture if we
assume that that this texture is if we
if we assume that this texture is
actually a floating point then it's
actually 32 64 what 96 bit because it's
right
[Music]
so this entire thing when taken together
is 96 plus 24 bits or 120 bit right so
yeah if we just if you think about 120
bit texture versus this one wasting
space wasting 120 bits in here every
time you have a null terminator it
depends I it's really hard for me to say
I really don't know because in here this
would bloat all of these even the ones
that don't have anything in them so you
know if you if you made this one go from
16-bit to 32-bit you're doubling the
size of this you're not doubling the
size of this so the fact that this one
stores a lot more bits per it's out of
note you can see why it's a tough trade
out there you'd have to kind of think it
through a little better but hopefully
this makes some sense my the thing that
makes me a little nervous about this in
general is that it does it is kind of
its kind of compute shader a I assume
let me see here
where is the there it is
[Music]
I assume if I'm not mistaken although I
might be mistaken I don't know if you
can do like I don't really know if you
can do anything sensible for creating
this kind of a lookup structure on the
graphics card however on the CPU it's
not so onerous because we're just doing
testing so we could pretty trivially
create one of these on the CPU obviously
but this wouldn't be a very good way to
store it for GPU generation and the
reason for that is because packed
storage of this of this kind is
difficult for the GPU to recreate in
parallel right
using Atomics you could make a linked
list version of this so you could add
the lighting samples to the voxel as
sort of a using Atomics every time you
went to write one in you would write one
in and put a link like a next pointer
effectively into one of them so you
could do something like that but again
it's pretty it's just pretty dicey right
it's a pretty it's a pretty nasty
operation to have to do so we could do
something like that but it is going to
be a little bit tricky I don't know if
we if we would therefore have to move up
a level of of OpenGL shading because I
don't know where Atomics come in I don't
know when you can get atomic operations
in shaders they are a very old concept
but they're not i don't know how widely
supported they are right let me see
so it seems like
atomic counter is not really what I'm
looking for
let's also see here
because I'm pretty sure that basically
if we wanted to compute lighting on the
graphics card and provide it to the game
in a way that was easy for it to look up
I'm pretty sure that it would require
fancier shading than what we have I'm
just I'm not 100% certain but I believe
it would be I can't think of a lot of
ways to look up lighting that wouldn't
require that but I could be wrong about
that trying to think
yeah I mean all I can say is if we want
to do something now which will allow us
to play around with it this would be
fine because creating this on the GPU on
the CPU is not hard and we don't care
how long it takes to run because we're
just doing a test pass so the problem is
just if we wanted to do something if we
were trying to do something that was
forward-looking but I don't know how
necessary that is because we don't
really even know how well this will work
right and it might be just premature to
be thinking about how we will run things
on the GPU before we've actually gotten
to the point where we're happy with the
results that said it is sort of true
that we may not need something that
complicated for example in terms of like
the key if we did have a voxel where we
eventually dump things into the voxel
maybe it would be possible to just use
that directly to store the lytic
information where we just kind of
average our lighting samples into a
voxel after we compute them I don't
really know and so you could just
imagine getting your lighting from the
voxel and you just don't bother with the
secondary lookup I mean if you think
about it right you could imagine taking
the lighting samples and rendering the
lighting samples into a voxel as sort of
just a rasterized version of the
lighting and then everyone reconstructs
by just looking up into the voxel and
interpolating between the various points
in the voxel and we could use a better
interpolator than bilinear or try linear
in this case we could use it better
interpolator than trilinear if we wanted
to seems like not a terrible idea it's
not necessarily a good idea
but that would mean we wouldn't really
have to deal with any kind of a like
more elaborate lookup structure
[Music]
yeah hard to say let's maybe let's maybe
try that I mean I guess we could sort of
look at both options to a certain extent
but maybe we could just try that and
because it if you know if we wanted to
we could imagine that just sending down
a very high-resolution voxel is sort of
an approximation to this anyway so we
could kind of also see by changing sort
of the resolution of the voxel we could
maybe figure out - you know to some
extent how we wanted the light how the
lighting would improve if we were if we
were doing a scheme that more that used
sparse storage in order to make things
clearer but yeah but it does seem
it does seem alright
all right okay I can I can I could maybe
believe that so let me take a look at
see what our options are in GLSL three
here in terms of sampling from a 3d
texture I assume we can do that because
that's pretty old-school right so you
can see here we've got texture lookup
for a 3d sampler and we can just pass in
a 3d uvw and it will give us back
exactly what we would have expected so
that seems pretty easy no big deal there
I guess uh projective texture look up
with us we don't need we shouldn't
really need anything else I don't think
so it depends on the circumstance we may
want to do a textile fetch instead this
will this will give us back I don't know
that might not be true so hmm if we turn
off any filtering then the texture
lookup would give us what we need I
think
[Music]
so I think we could just use the regular
texture fetch with no filtering and then
if we want to we can grab you know
multiple samples from the texture and
average them together or rather radially
blend them together based on distance or
something like I was talking about
before to give ourselves interpolation
of the lighting
so the thing that makes me a little
nervous about this is that I'm worried
about the artifacts that we'll get from
things moving across cell boundaries so
for example imagine that you have a
lighting sample that's right here and
another letting sample that's right here
when they get box two lives they'll each
be setting what the lighting is in their
part of the voxel however if you then
moved this whatever this was was a
moving thing and it moved so that on the
next frame
they're both inside one I didn't draw
this very well let me draw a little
bigger
so here's frame zero here's frame one
and imagine that I have you know to
letting samples one here and one here
and then on the next frame they're
moving in this direction so they both
end up in the same cell so if we do a
voxel scheme that can't record all the
reflectors so they're not moving
continuously around the world they would
have to get averaged together here which
means you'll get a very different
lighting result on frame one as from
frame 0 because in frame zero you're
considering the contribution of each one
of those reflectors separately and on
frame 1 you're having to smush them
together and being they have to be
considered as a pair as a lookup
combined pair uh and I don't love that
because again that that puts us back to
a sort of artifact a pretty pretty heavy
artifact potential I would think so I
guess I don't know that I really believe
that that that putting things into the
voxel as you know just a single sample
per voxel and everything else gets
mushed down to that but that's really
going to be what I want in the end I
suspect that I probably will need
something that's going to treat each
reflector individually and store all the
reflectors
Hey
well I guess what I'm going to say then
is let's just do the original thing I
was talking about and let's see what it
how it results right in other words
let's suppose that we're going to do
lighting here and I want to encode the
this lighting information into some
bitmaps that a graphic card could accept
and use to reconstruct lighting you know
somehow so so if we imagined that we
were going to do that and I was going to
do an output lighting here and what I
want to do inside this output lighting
is I want to do like an output lighting
textures something like this so what I
want to do is I want to basically do a
voxel where I place each reflector into
like into a voxel and then sort of make
those up take take that voxel and
convert it into one of the texture
formats that we you know that we can
send to the card so for example what I
would want to do here is say that
lighting solution as a thing
notes in your stomach there it is so if
we imagine that lighting solution has
some voxel information in it that it's
going to generate and also has some
[Music]
place to store these elements let's say
I've got something like this so I've got
a position texture that's just going to
be you know however many lighting
elements I have at maximum which is 4096
in this case I've got a RGB texture so
that's just going to be well I guess
there's not really good way to do that
but this is the color texture and it's
going to be three of these each and I
don't think we really need like I could
do a you thirty-two pack 232 but there's
really no point because we only need the
are G and the B I'm not sure there's
anything else that you need there so
those are lighting samples and then we
need the voxel lookup
so the voxel lookup is going to have a
count and a like a count in an index
essentially and I guess that really the
count has to be small so really you
could probably fit the count and the
index into 24 bits
you don't need 32 bits for that because
the count is in fact the count could
even be if you just use the single
16-bit value the camp could even be sort
of snuggled in there probably with it
because you probably can't have that
many in there but
you won't get that fancy just yet
because that's probably putting the cart
before the horse so I guess we'll just
say that this is the voxel lookup or
something and who knows what that is I
certainly don't but probably something
like that right so these are the things
that we would send down to the graphics
card and like I said I don't know if we
want to just make this a 32-bit texture
because I don't know there's nothing the
problem is there's nothing else to
suppress to store in there at least not
that I can think of because our lighting
is just going to be RGB intensity and
there's really nothing else to put
informational e in there but I guess you
know what one thing we could say is
we're trying to do this is the test so
let's just keep it simple since we have
functions that pack this stuff already
and maybe that's just an easier way to
go so you imagine we've got our box to
look up in here and I guess again that
will make that a u-32 because we'll use
a 16-bit index and a 16-bit offset it's
a bit index of 6 to account for now so
there we go let's see how big that is
I'm just curious how much data that is
it's a lot it's 4096 times I guess
that's three floats times 4 so that is
that's just 4000s kind of for and I
think we said this is eight megabytes
right yep
so this is 16 K just give just 8 a.m.
and I guess 49 152 1024 is 48 right so
you know these are tiny and that is
understandable right because they do
those really don't take up any space by
comparison because there's only so many
reflectors that we actually have and
they're not multi-dimensional so they're
pretty tiny the box will look up is what
takes up all the space and of course
that's because it's massively redundant
like there's way more space taken up by
it than it probably needs so this is
really good lemonade you know it's
Newman's own lemonade I'm kind of a
Newman's Own fan I don't get paid to say
that
I just am they have really good little
Newman O's the little like Oreo kind of
cookie things those are really good and
so are the chocolate chip cookies
alright so what we want to do is fill
this out
and in order to keep this relatively
condensed for now like I said to make it
easier on us we probably don't want to
make it be a skip list kind of a thing
well skip list is probably one word a
linked list I don't know how we would
create a structure like this on the GPU
efficiently and the
for that is because things have to get
packed so the way we would have to do
this and we can just on the CPU very
easily but on the GPU I don't know or
even just how we would do a fast version
of it on the CPU also seems a little bit
tricky which is to say that if we want
to make it so that the all of the
reflectors that occur inside a given
voxel that all of them are packed
together in the PC texture list so that
we can have just a count that tells you
how many there are and you read it
that is pretty difficult to do because
it that requires sort of pre-processing
the data so that you know ahead of time
which how many go into each bucket and
then fill the bucket so in theory we
could test as well a more like a more
likely version of this if you will and
that would be something that was you
know let's say like this that would be
something where we store you know that
so in here we actually have something
like this and each one of these stores
the position of the light reflector and
the next one that you should look at
inside this array so you kind of like
skip you know skip through it as a
lookup that's something that's more
likely to possibly be created on the
card again I don't really want to say
that too firmly but basically you know
that it's more or less what happens and
then this box will look up would just be
a single 16 bit so just tell you where
the first one was and then this would
where the next one was now of course
again we don't really need a full 32-bit
value here you know this could be a
16-bit value but I'm not really sure I
see a lot of ways of how we would pack
the rest of this stuff down in a way
that made sense
we still need 24 bits for the color at
least and so that doesn't really help us
if we could make this an 8-bit value
that would be amazing
because then you could do this and that
would be kind of Awesome but
unfortunately if the element list is
4096 long than having a next pointer
that's only 8-bit doesn't really help
you and so it seems like that's a bit of
a non-starter so again I think that's
probably putting the cart before the
horse in trying to make that work so
we're just going to leave it like that
for now we'll try to figure out how to
do some shenanigans later to make that
less problematic perhaps on the other
hand it is worth noting like I said this
is the small part of the problem so it's
really not the most important part if
the box will look up that's the big one
and it's kind of nasty right so let's go
ahead and see how we would make
something like this I think you'll be
surprised at just how simple it actually
is especially if we do a linked list
version like this creating it is
actually really basic so if we have a
lighting solution and we're trying to
make one of these texture things out of
it we can actually do that pretty
directly one thing I can do is pull this
out so it's a little bit more explicit
lighting textures and we can just call
the P C and look up so if you and I
guess this is actually like key next I
guess it's both of those so if you take
a look at what happens here we've got
some number of lighting elements that
we've computed
right and when we do output lighting
textures we don't need to output quads
right that's not necessary so what we're
going to do here is pretend that we're
taking a lighting solution and we are
going to take one of these lighting
textures and that lighting those
lighting textures will get filled out by
this routine so the first thing that we
want to do is we want to clear right
everything in the lookup because we need
to start with that lookup structure the
voxel lookup structure we need to start
with that being completely clean so it
needs to have zero everywhere and we'll
just say that zero is the sort of the
the null value it's unused right and if
we wanted to we could also beef up this
number if we want to be able to store
more of these things we probably should
but we'll get to that a bit later so
when we come through here when we start
with a completely empty lookup what we
know is that every time we get one of
these element values here so let's take
a look for example at just a single
element value so if you take a look at
one of these elements values what we can
see is we've got a front emit that we
generate this way and can pack down
consuming
so we can create a color from it by
doing exactly what we're doing before
where we pack this down and we don't
have anything to merge it with anymore
right we're just packing in the the
front emit color of this lighting sample
now it's worth noting that we want to do
something smarter here than what we have
been doing so what that front emit
lighting is telling us is how much light
we've received I can't remember if we've
modulated by our bounce I think we have
so what we're going to want to do is
take that out of the equation in fact we
can do that right now let's just do that
so what you can see for example in
output lighting quads what you can see
here is we take the front emit and we
just pack that down directly right when
we're when we're just showing reflectors
so what I want you to see here is when
we run the lighting solution sorry I'm
coming up this a roundabout way I'm not
sure how to explain it other than to
show it to you what we see here is I'm
also not sure why that's wearing slower
all sudden is it just because of the
size of the thing changed now we don't
need to upload anything I guess it's
just because we use more memory there
I'm not sure why that is
I feel like that's taking more time than
sorry give me one second I just want to
know why that would be the case its
world mode nobody uses the lighting
textures what did I do wrong maybe I'm
maybe I'm mistaken maybe it was very
going that slowly
well I guess there's not a whole lot we
can do that at the moment because it
looks like it's entirely spent and swap
buffers
you
hmm
well I'm not sure what to make of that I
guess we can investigate later anyway so
if we take a look at what happens here
back to what I was saying for what you
can see is for example this is red and
this is blue that's actually not the
lighting that's falling on this point
that's the lighting modulated by the
color of the surface and we actually
want to stop doing that now the reason
we want to stop doing that now is
because we're going to assume that a
surface will take its color into account
when it gets rendered so presumably
because that way we can interpolate
between lighting samples even if the two
surfaces are different so what we want
to do here is we want to change it so
that the way we were computing the front
emit C which is actually here the way
we're computing the front emit C we want
to
[Music]
here we go when we do our light color
and we do our bounces here what we want
to do is make it so that when we do this
Hadamard reflect color - when we're
computing our total light so this is the
total light that comes in we actually
don't want to do this here right what we
want to do is just use the total light
value as the result instead of as how
much light we're storing is coming from
this surface like so so like that and
then what we want to do is say okay we
still do want that reflected color to
actually be what happens when light
bounces off a surface so when we are
actually grabbing the light in the first
place right when we say the source is
front emit see that is where we're going
to do that multiplication so the light
color that comes in is going to be the
sources reflected color times the
sources front emit color right and so
what that means is that when we store
this in the first place and we do that
sort of front end it's the color RGB
part of it right where the color RGB is
putting the rest in there we don't
actually want to do that anymore
so we just want to set the front
emission to be you know a colorless
version because it will get the color
when it actually does that initial out
right okay
so now when we make this go in theory
those should just be well alright that
did not go anywhere close to what I
thought it would do but that's okay I
somehow I took that out and still did
exactly the same thing how is that even
possible
let's try that one more time
so obviously ya didn't do a very good
job with that I'm assuming it doesn't
get modulated here right like it
definitely doesn't it's just the front
emit X Y Z right yeah
Oh awesome
I said I was going to get rid of it and
I didn't rate it there we go there we go
so now this is just a a pure lighting
solution that we're drawing right so
it's the light that got bounced around
and how it got bounced around so if that
makes sense
now what that means is you can still get
red twinges and stuff like that when you
bounce something off of like a red
surface or whatever and we should in
theory be able to create some
circumstances where we get very clear
examples of that and I will try to do
that here let's see if we can get
something like that I don't know I don't
seem to be really getting it so I may
have messed something I've left to check
because there should be ways for me to
get like blue bounce and stuff like that
on two surfaces here but I'm not really
seeing it so I think we still maybe have
some problems here let me just go check
what light color that's used for yeah so
in theory this should this line should
still take whatever the emitted color is
going to be and color it by whatever the
sources reflectance is right so we still
should be getting that contribution we
don't really seem to be which is a
little odd
why is photons or speeds still here
there yeah so I'm a little weirded out
by that because in theory in theory that
bounce light should still colorize
itself right any light that bounces off
surface and goes to another surface
should be getting colorized by this
Hadamard product here where the
reflection color and the mist front emit
color merged together to produce the
light color that will actually get used
for the diffused contribution right so I
don't really know why that busted
because it certainly seems like that
should work
what is the global lighting render
iteration count these days for
apparently since we're not using the
seclusion iteration anymore so this is
probably not super relevant you could
just get rid of it
yeah I don't really I don't know why I'm
not seeing anything other it's almost I
mean I mean there are some places where
you do get a little bit of that bounce
color in there but it just doesn't seem
nearly as much as I would have expected
like you get a very little bit there but
it's just it's so little it's odd to me
and I think that that could be I mean it
could just because our letting equations
aren't real yet like it could be that we
just need to make our letting equations
actually be reasonable but anyway let's
ignore that for now I don't love it but
let's ignore that for now and when we go
through the letting equations to try to
make the transfer be more accurate I
will pay closer attention to that for
now I just wanted to point out the fact
that this is now a more pure lighting
solution but doesn't that every point
tells you what the actual lighting is
not the lighting times whatever the
surface is at that location and so then
if we go in here and say we don't want
to look at the reflectors anymore then
what you can see is now we've got a
solution that's a little bit more true
because it gets modulated at the end by
the vertex color and so we were kind of
doubly modulating before which is not
right so this is a little bit more
accurate and this is what we actually
want to send down like I said to the
card in the first place for
reconstruction okay so now if we want to
actually do the slaving Pacal's guy
saying packing these things into a look
up texture it's not very difficult like
you can see we do the simple pack here
we've got the the color and we know that
now we just have to figure out a way to
place these things into these lighting
textures here so we've got two things we
need to do fir
we need to store the elements position
and color into the lighting textual
information and then we need to add to
the lookup chain this Texel so both of
these are pretty easy to do right first
of all the only real thing is mapping
the position correctly into the lookup
that's about it right so I guess there's
two things we probably need to need to
be aware of here and and mostly the only
difficult part of it is the lookup
structure we have to figure out how
that's mapped but let's assume
temporarily that we know where we are in
the lookup structure so let's assume we
have something like this so we have some
way of knowing where this element is in
the lookup structure right let's say
we've got that so far well if we have
that then everything else becomes fairly
straightforward we know that whatever
the wherever we're going to pack this
this particular lighting element we know
what that is because every time we add a
new element we just increment by one
right so you know we basically have a
pack index that starts at zero what
we're going to do is we're going to
assert that the pack index is less than
the number that can fit in here
and we're going to pre-increment it now
why are we going to pre-increment it
we're going to pre-increment it because
I said that zero is not a valid value so
if I started at zero I'm just going to
pre increment it and then do my test
because I'm going to put it in this
particular location right so once I've
got that I know that I'm going to look
at my peen X at that location and in
fact I could disclose Phoenix and I know
I need to set two things I need to set
the next pointer basically and the
p-value the p-value we just have it's
whatever the elements location was right
and the P next value here we know that
that's going to be whatever was in the
lookup right so whatever was previously
the value and lookup tail at that point
that's going to be our next pointer then
we just do the standard linked list
addition we put ourselves at the head of
the lookup so that makes that voxel
structure we take whatever the chain was
that was hanging off that point in the
voxel we make that hang off of us and
then we make ourselves the head right
very straightforward prostitution we do
that a million times on hand material so
after that we still need to use that PAC
index one more time because we also need
to take our desk color here and store
that but of course we can do that with
just one simple storage right there we
go and that's it right so really the
only problem that we have is how to do
this part how to map into where the
textile supposed to be dupes I don't
know why there's a Hadamard still in
there I don't need to multiply it so
really the only problem that we have oh
and I should the only problem that I
have is figuring out how to map a
position like this element P into the
lookup table in the first place
so there's a couple different ways we
can do this and it's kinda tricky right
it's a kind of touchy problem I'm going
to do a very straightforward version of
it first but we will probably have to do
something fancier in the future and I
can try to explain why so let me let me
show you what's going on here so a voxel
you generally think of as something that
you know looks like this or whatever
right it's a bunch of cubes in space and
we just think of looking up into them to
find out what's inside a particular
region of space but it's worth noting
that you don't have to do that for your
voxel right if you think about how we
view the world in a 3d game it's a
perspective projection so there's an ear
clip plane and a for our clip plane and
if you imagine putting one of these
voxels in world space right like this is
here it would be something that looked
you know like this right and what you
can see is that the space of things
that's covered by the camera view is a
different sort of geometric density in
screen space as this voxel would be
because when you get closer to the
viewer the cells are much larger per
unit of screen space than when you get
further from the viewer when they're
much smaller right so chances are
indexing into the voxel we don't really
want to do world space because look what
happens if we try to align our voxel so
that it covers the entire camera space
well it's got to be as big as the far
cliff plane right so we know that it has
to look basically like this
right that's what we know however you
can see that now a bunch of our voxel is
getting used for stuff that is not on
the screen and so probably what we would
want to do to make more economical use
of it is to bend the voxel so that it
actually looks more like this right now
you may think that there is some kind of
that that's like really difficult to do
or something it's like oh wait but we
only have a 3d texture lookup and we
just have you because remember we are
allowed to pass anything we want to the
lookup to the 3d texture we're under no
obligation to pass world space
coordinates so what we could do is we
could use a perspective divide to
actually prospectively project our uvw
coordinates so that they create a warped
look up now the voxel doesn't work it's
still just space in memory right it's
not changing what we're storing it just
changes how we look up into what we're
storing and like I said that's probably
something we're going to want to do we
just don't want to do it right away
because it just adds another thing to
get wrong into the set of things we're
trying to do right now and so getting
things working one at a time is a lot
better so we'd rather do is get the
voxel working first regularly because
that's much simpler and then work on
warping it after right
okay so the next thing we need to do
then is come up with some simpler scheme
from index for indexing into our voxel
and there's a pretty easy way we can do
that especially since we're computing
this offline we don't have to care about
the speed at the moment we can do
something pretty basic what I'm going to
do is I'm going to take a min corner and
a max corner I'm just going to spin
through all of the lighting elements
that we computed I'm just going to
compute the bounds right I'm just going
to say all right I think we've got a
real thirty-two minimum and real through
to maximum here I have these I don't
even know
yeah okay area so all I'm going to do is
I'm just going to set these to the min
and Max values they can possibly be now
you'll notice I set the min corner to
the maximum and the max corner to the
minimum right which is like an inverted
infinity rectangle which by the way
would be a great name for a album what I
want to do is I want to go through each
of the lighting elements that we have
first and I just want to take in the
position and set each of the min quarter
and Max corners to the lowest possible x
y&amp;z value and the highest possible XYZ
value we ever see right now I don't know
if we have a math function for this oh
hey look we actually have this function
already to that we only have it in 2d
huh because that's actually what we want
oh well but that's okay no big deal so
all I want to do here is I want to say
alright the min corner for our vector
you can see here I've got an e value
here for each of these guys I don't know
why it gets this is old code so it still
uses the real 32 value okay so what do I
do is I want to go through each of the
mid corner max corners and I want to set
them to the minimum value and the
maximum value of themselves like so and
whatever the new value is for P there we
go
so basically just spinning through here
it's something you call it minimum so
basically what this will give us is this
will give us the minimum possible value
that anything can take and the maximum
possible value that and they can could
take in our system now once we have that
we then know the bounds of the voxel in
three dimensions so at that point we can
actually map things into the voxel in a
fairly straightforward fashion just by
using basic discrete map right
so let's say we've got this min corner
in this max court the min corner math
corner I want to expand them a little
bit just to give us so that we're not
fetching to the very end of them I find
it usually that's a little bit more
convenient you don't have to do that if
you don't want to if you want to ride
the epsilon edge you can definitely have
you know you can you can
he is as brash as you wish here we go so
I'm just going to expand it by pushing
the min corner and the max corners out
just a little bit and then what I'm
going to do is I'm going to create the
span value for these and what the fan
value is is I'm basically saying all
right a doesn't mean quarter the max
corner I know what I'm going to have to
do is every time a position comes in I
need a way of mapping this into my voxel
we've done this a lot of times before
like when we want to put things into
grids right and so you imagine we've got
sort of a thing that looks like this so
on for each one of these axes we're
going to want to say oh we've got a p
value that came in here
well that better not be because that's
outside the zone let's say people I
became in here we just need to figure
out what grid square is in so all we're
going to do here is we're just going to
figure out by dividing by this you know
cell size here essentially how big the
cell sizes we're going to figure out how
many of them we would have to go to get
to this one and we're going to truncate
that value obviously because we want it
to be stored we want to produce the next
lowest value right so if it's here we
want to produce 0 not 1 if it's here we
want to produce 1 not 2 right so we want
to create basically the divide truncated
down and that's all we're trying to do
and like I said we've done this before
we did this in the world code
[Music]
let's see where we've got that just so I
can show you what what we're talking
about here I think we did oh no we
switch it to a hash table goodnight
goodnight we didn't do that I think we
did at one point we just don't do it now
so anyway that's all I really want to do
so what I need to do is create that span
value and the span value is just going
to be the min corner minus the max
corner so that now we have an X Y and a
Z value that is how big each of those
dimensions are right
in fact I could just solve this
dimension so then what I need to do is
come up with a way of doing that divide
so we know that we've got these various
cell values here and we know how big
they have to be so what I'm going to do
is I maybe compute that like light look
up X or something line Z and I'm putting
these in an arbitrary order here it
doesn't really matter which order we do
them in if we wanted to be fancier maybe
we would put them in reverse order
because that's a little more consistent
with how we tend to do things we tend to
put the X as the minor the Y is the
major so the Z would therefore be the
you know the most major at that point so
maybe that's the easiest way to keep
that doesn't really matter the choice is
arbitrary how we wish to look up into
our texture all that matters is the one
that we want to look up to the Z can be
smaller don't ask me why I made that 2
to 6 you probably still could I don't
know how big would that be and that's a
lot bigger they're 64 Meg's just for the
lookup if Z is not under sampled all
right so anyway back there so anyway
once we know what those are we can then
produce the size of a cell because we
now know that like the cell dimension is
just going to be a series of divides
right so we've got the dimension X and
we need to divide by how many of them
there are in X right it's got the
dimension Y and we need to know how many
there are and why
so we can now produce how big each cell
is and furthermore we can produce the
inverse of that as well right so if we
wanted to do the inverse seldom which is
what we actually need the fact they
don't know that we ever need this one so
we could just I think we might be able
to produce the inverse cell dimension
always which is just one over how big
the cell is and so what that will do
right is the inverse seldom is something
that takes an actual position and turns
it into an index into our voxel which is
exactly what we want so we know that the
voxel position is the element position
kinds that inverse cell right now we
have to be careful here because really
that just gives us the span that the
stepping we still need one more thing
here which is a way of centering it
around where the voxel is and again
that's the min corner part of that right
so by first subtracting we the min
quarter now we know we're relative to
the inside of the voxel space then by
Hadamard product with the inverse cell
dimension we then know okay we are now
in the numerical space of this voxel
zero one two three four in each of the
dimensions at that point but we still
have fractional here and we don't want
to look up by fractional so we need to
truncate each of these to get the actual
voxel x y&amp;z so to produce those values
we want to do a truncate and to just
truncate each of these to place it into
the voxel at the location it should go
right
and I guess I said we were doing it this
way right and that should basically do
it oh this is off of the destination
there that should basically do it like
that pretty much a you know modular bugs
will give us the the complete set of
textures we would need to pass down to
the card in order to determine all of
the lighting gathers that we might need
to do right and that's it that's all
there is to it so at that point we would
just need a way of sending these down to
the card and then we could actually use
them when we are when we are actually
doing you're letting equations however
we yeah obviously have a bunch of work
we would have to do there and I don't
know how much time we really have here
we only have about 15 minutes left so
I'm not really sure I guess what I'll do
here is say well you know
[Music]
inside handmade worldin mode here when
we have put this lighting maybe I'll
just say hey like I guess what we'll say
is alright let's have a letting texture
in there when you when you generate the
lighting once you also generate the
lighting textures just so we can we
could test it and that should run that
code path we just can't see if it's
actually working we don't know what it
created and so you know there's that
I guess what I could do real quick and
this does seem like maybe a good idea is
I could make an output routine that just
puts little Splatt Splatt squads
everywhere to show the values of the
voxel in all locations that actually
seems like a pretty good idea yeah let's
let's do that
so so let's let's figure out a way to
make that happen
when we call output lighting here let's
actually call output lighting with the
test textures as well and so here where
we're going to do a why call the desk
here we're going to output this stuff
let's say that if we got the textures
that we're going to do some kind of a
quad output lighting that comes just
from those right so what I'll do here is
I'll copy this routine and I'll just
call this some kind of debug texture
output right
and we don't really know ahead of time
how many there are because we don't know
how many are in these textures here so
we'll probably have to pass the lighting
solution I guess just so we have that
value we could store it in the textures
as well but again this is just for debug
so it probably shouldn't matter and so
then what we could do here is we could
just say well alright let's just step
through each of these axes and let's
just output the cost of the voxel
because that way at least we know what's
in there right and that's better than
you know starting next week not knowing
whether we built our voxel correctly and
we still have to figure out with what we
sent down to the card was even remotely
correct all right so the textures look
up we are going to
get the first one out here so this is
our like first index or I guess we
should just say it's just our index and
we just want to loop so we're going to
grab out the T next I guess I don't we
need to do it well little bit done so
we're going to grab out that PMF value
we're going to look at it but then
immediately after we'll just keep going
on it so so we know that this is the
location and we know the color is just
whatever that index is so that gives us
the position and the color value and so
now we can make something we could you
know push a cube or something on here I
guess that had that that letting color
in fact maybe that's what we'll do since
we don't have normals anymore right at
this point maybe that's exactly what
we'll do let me see what our options are
for doing something like push cube
so pushed you will take the render group
the bitmap ID which is just a white
bitmap we don't want an actual different
bitmap on there but we know the position
we know the radius should just be some
small radius and yeah I don't know what
to do about the height exactly and then
the color is just going to have to be an
unpack seems dumb to pack and then
unpack this in that way but what are you
going to do
this code really needs to be cleaned up
a bit in fact the way that we're doing
this now we in fact I could clean this
up right now let's just do this it looks
like the push cube what is the
difference between these two routines
that one takes a bitmap ID and this one
takes the resolved bitmap and it also
takes an emission value all right
so let's just make this take a color
value
and I guess the only question is can we
trust the people who have passed us in
are going to actually pre-multiply it
properly
alright maybe I won't do that maybe I
want alright so what we need to do here
is we need to unpack this this normal
value see here so this unpack is going
to leave things essentially the way they
are so when we do that unpack 4x8 these
are going to be in the 255 space so we
really need to do you know just to get
it out of there I so once you've got
that we can pass it down and I guess
that's fine
all right so let's see here
this should allow us if we do this
output texture debug bit here this
should allow us to see cubes that
represent everywhere that we stored a
lighting sample in our voxel now it
doesn't quite show us yet exactly what
whether the voxel got sorted properly it
would just show us whether we stored
stuff properly at all the reason I say
it doesn't say whether we store it in
the Box property properly is well we're
going to get stuff out and we're going
to draw it at the location that's
supposed to be drawn at so even if we
sort it in the wrong voxel location we
would still output it in the right place
so at the moment we're really only going
to be be able to debug well of course
since we don't do anything that's a good
sign that we still have bugs to work on
we're only really going to be able to
debug the fact that the things restored
and we'll have to come up with a clever
way to figure out whether they were
stored in the right place right so we
have those two separate things to do all
right
so let's start by stepping through this
I'm going to switch out of of optimized
mode
and I'm going to go ahead and just set a
breakpoint
I think it's called lighting test let's
do let's just go output learning
textures we don't really care about rest
of the I suppose I so we don't care
about lighting test actually because
that's mostly irrelevant we got to wait
for a while for our extremely slow debug
to happen and then we got a take a look
at this
although now I think about the other
thing I probably do just turn the Ray
casting count down because we don't
really need to be doing anything
particular with the lighting solution at
this point so we're really just blowing
a bunch of random time on that effect
let me go ahead and do that oh it is
only doing eight man the debug version
of this is so much slower I wonder why
it would be interesting to see what I
guess probably because all these things
turn into function calls all right we'll
wait for it
this is one of those things where you
really wish you could just put a little
block around something and say optimize
just this one routine but Visual Studio
can't really do that because it it won't
inline functions who are outside of that
block like it's yeah it's kind of a mess
all right so if we take a look at what
happens here let's first start by trying
to look and see whether the min Corner
and Max corner are reasonable those do
seem pretty reasonable I guess it makes
sense that they're basically exactly the
same values because of the way we sort
of symmetric recreate the world there's
a little suspicious but I'll give them
that
so let's see here
so if we compute one of these voxel P
values see what the x y&amp;z is 144 130 10
those are saying we look up to look up
at which should always be 0 first time
through we do some color packing there
and we say ok the lookup value is going
to point to us we are going to point to
nothing we set the position just fine
that's all good and then we've got our
destination color that we set so that
all seems pretty reasonable so let's
take a look at output texture debug
so we never get in here even though we
saw that oh wow
not a great day for oh man alright well
I'm glad I didn't spend too much time
looking for that like I didn't even pass
the values that we were trying to look
up that's great good job nice wonderful
[Music]
Wow anyway let's go ahead and see how
that goes here in in release mode
alright that did produce a bunch of
cubes but they are weirdly positioned
and if I switch to the non debug camera
I can't see them anymore
so something is a little off I'm just
not sure what
[Music]
we are still starring the element P when
we do the app protects your debug
hmm
I'm not sure what's going on there they
seem to be slightly invalid values
somehow I'm just not sure how here's a
question can we do that
that could work or that didn't work that
looks like that works surprisingly well
should do that more often that seems
like a perfectly sane value that does
not look anything like a perfectly sane
value
hmm so how is that
how is that getting generated so the
Alpha should always just be one right
that does RGB a unpack already do that
for me
I mean it sure doesn't look like it
right that should produce the zero to
255 version of the impact values
hmm so I'm not sure what's up with that
let me try this
so that looks like we are storing
lighting samples pretty much the way
they should be stored we don't know if
they're in the right Vox containers so
it looks like it's just the color that
is wrong to me so all we have to do is
just debug the color value and then we
should be good to go it looks like the
front emit our G and B they're being
clamped zero to one then we're doing in
RGB pack four by eight it looks like we
forgot the 255 there yeah so basically
this is the only problem and then I
think we're good
there we go I so I think we now have a
nice little world of lighting samples
there we go and we're pretty much ready
for next time so let me go to the Q&amp;A
and I'll remove the fragment
anyone have questions on what we did I'm
pretty interested to see how this works
like I'll be very interested to see how
the gathering works well because at this
point the other really interesting thing
that I find about this is we no longer
really have to care where we put the
lighting samples for week because if we
reconstruct the lighting samples per
pixel then we can scatter our lighting
samples around the world in whatever
places make the most sense for creating
good lighting solutions we don't have to
put them in particular locations because
we know we need to output the values
asset location directly
oh thanks okay so you guys made a gist
that was
this is a pretty advanced you guys had a
lot of stuff in here
I don't see any questions
let's see Rome 0 0 0 1 0 1 1 maybe it's
a non-issue but because the entity is
tilted when it walks in front of a cube
it is being cut is there an elegant
solution for it
well actually we kind of have some
solutions for that already well I I
don't know if we want to play with this
too much at the moment but basically
what we what we see here is a little bit
difficult because we don't have actual
representative artwork in right now the
artwork is kind of drawn as an angle
that is not the angle that the actual
artwork is for the game so the cutting
problem will actually be lessened a
little bit but we already do have some
solutions in there for that we have a
bias value that you can add in which
causes things to appear in front of
where they actually are to prevent these
kinds of problems so for example yeah
like if I if I put the hero bitmap back
in so we have somebody we can actually
drive around
so there's the clipping well okay we've
also have that giant light in the way
which isn't going to help but there's
you can still see the clip there we go
you can see the clipping problem that
you're talking about there so we have
ways in which that can be modified so
for example if we wanted to we could
increase the degree - with it
- which bitmaps get biased V values for
example let's say let me see where we've
got this here this is the lighting code
we don't want line segments we just want
bit maps so you can see the Z bias
values here that gets added into the
into the sprites that we output we have
really we can adjust this however we
want and again it's always kind of a
hack to try and put things that are 2d
into 3d so there isn't really a right
answer to this but you could imagine
making it a much more pronounced Z bias
value right so for example and this is
course creates a problem within your
clip plane but you can see now there's
actually that hero appears in front of
these cubes up until it gets clipped by
the near clip plane which is actually
out pretty handsome I pull back a little
bit here now you can kind of see that he
doesn't get clipped anymore right so we
do have sorry about the light that's in
the way there we were like if they were
playing with lighting so we're not
really in a position to start talking
about sprites so you can kind of see how
the Z bias value does allow you to deal
with these problems in some ways but
it's always a little bit of a trade-off
because you know the more Z bias you add
in there the more you get problems of
like I don't know if I can go downstairs
anymore because we kind of kick cart
caved ourselves off but you can imagine
problems of like now when I'm standing
in front of you know this this red piece
right here for example
maybe I can get in a place where I
should be clipped by it like right there
and I'm not so the problem with using Z
bias too aggressively
is that you can only really put it to a
certain level before it becomes a
problem right I'm not sure what the
really best way to deal with some of
this stuff is in the end we just have
tools we can use to try to combat the
obvious problems my hunch is we won't
have to do as much with it in the future
because the artwork will be centered
more properly on the squares and we
won't have as much problem with overlap
but it's hard to say right so will that
we'll play around with it and you know
we'll see how bad it is when we actually
have to put together the final stuff but
there's never going to be I don't think
a perfect solution when you're trying to
place to do things in 3d
when we made the high-end low-priority
thread cues how did we make the hike you
actually have a higher priority I can't
find the difference between them in the
implementation if that makes sense so
that nomenclature is about how we are
treating the cues in our code they are
not higher or lower priority in Windows
so what the high priority queue is is
the thing that all threads will take
work out of so here I can sort of show
you
ah okay so here's where we create the
queues right and we create two low
priority queues and six high priority
queues the high priority queues are
strictly for doing CPU work that has to
be finished immediately right so it's
just like the software renderer run
through the high priority queues the low
priority queues are things that are just
waiting for stuff to happen like oh I
have to do a load like I have to load a
file and so I'm waiting to like load
some data out of the file or something
like that right so if you look at how
those end up getting used what you can
see is that here we add entries for
example to these low priority queues
right and then those low priority queues
are going to call us back for example on
this I believe that no it's not quite
here where is it where is low desk at
work dirty so this the the low priority
queue is going to be calling back here
at the the load asset work call right
that's what's going to happen so if you
take a look at how that sort of thing
works and you take a look at instead how
say the the renderer works there's a big
difference between the two of them and
the big difference is the complete all
work operation right so when we use the
high priority queues what we tend to do
here is we push a bunch of stuff into
these queues and then we say complete
all work on the queue that we used right
whereas when we're doing something
that's just a slow overlap operation we
push stuff on to the queues but we never
call complete all work right now why
does this make one a high part if you
would want a low priority queue well the
reason is because when we call complete
all work
when we call complete I'll work but
we're essentially doing is taking cue
and we're forcing ourselves to do all
the work out of the cue that we can do
right so we're just like going down that
we're putting a bunch of work into a cue
then we're forcing ourselves to even on
the thread that launched that work we're
going to sit there and keep doing work
until the queue is empty right similarly
if you take a look at how the thread
proc works it's just going to do get
work out of the queue do the work that
we prologue with you and then wait if
there isn't any work to do right if we
run out of work we we will just sort of
pause right you can see like we should
sleep that value is false if we did work
if we didn't do if we didn't financing
the cue then we say that we should sleep
right so essentially what we do is we
just partitioned our work into two
queues one that will just we push
everything into we know that the other
threads as they wake up will do work out
of that queue and then we will also sit
there on that queue and just do the work
that's in it till we're done so everyone
will focus on that cue work and you know
it will it will happen right the low
priority queues are different there's
just two threads sitting around doing
work in those queues all the time if
there's anything in them but nobody will
actually block on them to finish right
so we've never actually we don't
actually do anything to try and make
these choose higher or lower priority in
any particular sense all we're really
doing is all we're really doing is
treating one differently than the other
and we put more threads on one than the
other is another way that it's higher
priority right if we wanted to be fancy
or we could be fancier what we could do
is we could say all right all threads
when they wake up pull out of the high
priority 2 first and if there's nothing
there then they pull out the low
priority queue right so we could have
actually made all threads that exist
focus on the high priority queue work
but the reason we didn't do that is
because we're not really treating the
low priority queue as something where
work gets done it's more something just
sits around waiting for files to come in
right so there didn't seem to be a need
to like actually try to make ourselves
be perfectly subscribed hopefully that
makes some sense
hmm
if I was to guess I would say the
problem is not the 2d entities in 3d
space at rather 2d entities with 3d
entities if those cubes are sprites like
the trees it would work just fine sadly
that's not really true I mean I guess it
depends on how you look at it in terms
of your how you want to phrase it so
maybe this is what you mean but the
problem is in fact the three deenis of
the world so if you look at the fact
that these want to be in perspective and
you can even see how the trees are
warped in perspective slightly as well
the fact that we want some perspective
to the world that's actually the problem
it doesn't matter whether they're
sprites forth or cubes or anything else
as long as there is a flat surface that
wants to have some perspective to it
that can flip that's the problem if we
let this sprite fold back to match what
was happening here then we'd have no
problem right but what we're trying to
do is fake it so that the world has the
ability to have perspective in it and
because we're doing that we run into
these problems right so if you want to
call that 2d entities with 3d entities
problem that's fine it's really more a
2d entities with perspective problem
might be the best way to put it
in the suffer render we aligned the
memory to 16 bytes for Cindy but then we
use the unalloyed load and storage
instructions why is that um so it
depends on the situation one thing that
was very strange I guess I don't think
it's actually that strange my
recollection was that we found that it
was no slower to do unaligned rights
than aligned rights that was my
recollection however we don't use all
unaligned reads and writes for example
this is this is aligned right that's an
aligned load these are both aligned
that's aligned so all of our pixel loads
are actually aligned
what's unaligned is reading from the
texture sorry remember correctly
[Music]
actually I guess the text but the
texture I guess isn't loaded well all
right so I don't know do we still have
any online loads where are the I don't
see any on the line loads where are the
under line loads are they gone I guess
they're gone I remember using one as
well but I guess it's not there anymore
so Alex come beware what on a line load
and store I guess are you talking about
am i searching for the wrong thing
pretty sure load you and store you is
the mnemonic for them
yeah I don't remember that actually
being a speed wind though I think we
just I can't remember if it actually
helped I think that modern ships may
just not care very much about unaligned
versus aligned so I don't know if if the
chip actually cares but we did do it and
that said this is actually pretty old
ship so if ships didn't care this ship
might still care and the other thing is
to remember is the reason to align those
is actually not just because you want to
use a lined load and stores it's also
because you don't want false sharing of
the cache line so you need to make sure
that the tiles of the tiled renderer end
on a cache boundary so right if you want
to have thread 0 working on this tile
and thread 1 working on this tile right
at the boundary here you have to
remember that if both people are writing
to pixels that are at the boundary you
have to make sure that they're not
sharing cache line okay because what
will happen is if thread 0 and thread 1
are both pounding on the same cache line
you're going to be in a world of hurt so
you want to make sure that the cache
lines which are 64 bytes you want to
make sure that they end right right at
the end and this one starts on a fresh
cache line so that the cache line
doesn't have to bounce back and forth
between the two threads to write to the
different portions of it right so so the
real reason to be aligned there I
suspect is action
much more stringent than the unaligned
loads and stores would be it's actually
because you would get bad memory
behavior at the boundary due to false
sharing as the cache line bounced back
and forth between the cores
uh-uh so anyway all right that's about
it for today I think we've covered
enough when I go ahead and close down
the street alright everyone thanks for
joining me for this sort of handmade
share it's a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
the series at home you can always peer
to the game on handmade hero org it
comes to the source code so you can
follow along at home we also have forum
site and go to to ask questions the
patreon page and go to if you want to
support the video series that is if we
don't get the platform for I don't know
doing something patreon doesn't like
apparently it's on the table now we also
have a schedule bot that tweets the
schedule you if you want to go ahead and
no we're going to be live and an episode
guide that you can go to if you want to
catch up on old episodes for example if
you want to know about aligned loads of
stores and when we put those in and out
you can go ahead and use that it's got a
handy search feature too now that's
pretty awesome that's about it I will be
back next weekend to play around with
getting the GPU to reconstruct that
lighting that we send down to it and
then we're getting close to having some
real lighting we're going to have to
start figuring out how we can put the
lighting computation on the graphics
card that's going to be a little bit of
a journey but hey you know what can you
do
so we've got a couple more weeks of
lighting left and it's starting to get
kind of come together which is kind of
exciting so hopefully you're joining me
for that until then have fun programming
and I'll see you on the Internet take it
easy everybody