hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete game
live on stream I have updated the github
with an issue list that we can turn over
to Anna to fix the art and this I think
was a important thing because you know
she just gives us art assets and at some
point we should just move the game over
to her machine so she can run it to and
work on things herself but in the
meantime when we discover errors we
didn't really have any way to log them
and so they never really had a way to
get fixed because if an artist has to
fix them but we're the people who find
them we need some communication channel
there and so what I did is I just used
the issue list that we had on github
since we went through the trouble of
setting up a github these issues marked
with art on the side should be easy
enough for her to just go like this and
see just specifically what the art
problems are so far and that way we can
just like kick those over and have them
fixed sort of asynchronously and then we
can update the art assets so I went
ahead and did that these are the ones
that I remember us encountering on the
stream I added them in there if anyone
can think of any that we did not list
here that we've seen feel free to add
them yourself if you're on the github or
just mention it in the chat and all add
them when we get to the Q&amp;A today so I
will with with that in mind I will get
started on what we're doing now if I
recall correctly we stopped yesterday on
what I think well it's it's either a bug
or a missing feature let's put it that
way we have a particular art asset and I
will show you the art asset for those of
you just joining us we have a particular
art asset that at least looks reasonable
in the in like a viewer right and we
look at this and we we looked at it
lined up with a template as well and we
just you know
look to see whether or not this thing
had anything in other squares and it
doesn't it's just these four squares of
import four different directions of the
flour now they go in the wrong order I
already found a bug on that but
regardless only four tiles should have
been extracted from this 4x4 but what we
actually saw when we look is that six
tiles were being extracted from the 4x4
and so something has gone wrong here
either when I said either it's a bug or
missing feature what I meant by that was
either there's a bug and the bug is that
we're Rowan ously determining through
some you know slip-up in the code that
there's actually content in cells that
don't have any content so that's an
obvious bug and we would need to figure
out what's happening there right or the
other option is that actually this file
does have some really like alpha of you
know one out of 255 or something in
these squares and if that's the case
then it's a missing feature because what
we would probably want to do is we we
probably don't want to require the
artist to be so diligent about cleaning
up squares that have nothing in them
that they can't have what is essentially
invisible alpha m'm so we would probably
want to do a thing that thresholds a
square and says look if we don't see
anything any pixels higher than like 16
out of 256 and maybe even more stringent
than that we might even say look we want
to see at least 64 different pixels all
of which have more than this or
something right you know we might want
to have some kind of a metric that's
like like you know like given the size
of the square that we find we want to
make sure that the number of pixels we
counted with some reasonable proportion
of that Square had more than like a
nominal alpha you know what I mean um
and so that's why I mean I'm missing
feature is that if it turns out is not a
bug and the codes actually doing what we
told it to do it still it probably needs
some
improvement so that we don't have to
have such a person tickity you know I
don't want to have to constantly raid
bugs back to the to the art and say oh
go clean up this square that doesn't
even look like icing in there like
that's just annoying it's annoying for
everybody it's annoying for me it's
annoying for the artist nobody wants
that so we can fix that type of thing in
the code using a little bit of like
fuzzy detection so we should so the
first thing I want to do is is determine
which of those two things is going on or
if it's or mysterious category 3 which
is some other bug in the art pipeline is
just seriously creating those things
right we I mean there could be that too
there could be a reason that we're
getting six is due to some something I
have not contemplated so we need to
figure out which of those three things
is going on and that's the first thing
I'm going to do I think what I'd like to
do here is say look we can load this
thing in an external sort of way and
look at what the Alpha is in each square
or something like that and then you know
give us some idea of what's going on now
I think that the easiest way to do that
would be to say look we've got right you
know we actually have a little art a PNG
like like contester thing right like
this test PNG thing still compiles if I
remember correctly I guess I don't
really know if that's Yeah right here we
still compiled our little test PNG here
and that test PNG allows us to yeah it
allows us to load one image in and then
write out a bunch of images like the RGB
in the Alpha so what I can do there is I
can have something that writes out an
alpha bitmap that's like let's say like
thresholded right so if I want to I
could take and anywhere that there was
alpha I could if there was any off at
all I mean if it's just if it's non zero
I could write it as full white you know
what I mean and then that would show me
anywhere that there was any possibility
of detection of the image so let's do
that
all right so in here you can see we have
the art count here and we do these right
outs with this repple a I'm gonna do a
pixel op threshold a-and I'm gonna
introduce one of those up here which is
threshold a when this gets written out I
will test it like this and down inside
the code what we'll do is after
everything is done right where we do the
replicate alpha and all that stuff well
I guess actually probably do it earlier
here where we do mol alpha and repple
alpha right before that I think what
I'll do is do if Thresh that's great
don't ask me how I type that in there we
go
what I'm gonna do is just say all right
every time we get that let's go ahead
and do a Thresh a on it
and that'll just be something that we
have I guess we put these in a sort of a
you know reusable section here I don't
really I I don't think I actually want
that to be the case so probably what
I'll do is I think I'll take this code
here and I'll put that I'll just put the
threshold version in here the rest shelf
do it like that and what we'll do is
we'll threshold the Alpha by extracting
it so the same way we're doing it here
we don't actually need to extract the RG
and be here right because we're not
actually going to use them differently
so we only really need to extract the
Alpha like so and then what we want to
do is
if the Alpha is anything at all
besides zero then it equals full alpha
so we're just gonna threshold it
directly up to one then when we reset
this we just need to combine it with the
original like so but remember the
original potentially has some alpha in
it so we could you know do that to mask
it off but remember the only thing we're
doing here is thresholding it so really
we don't even have to do that because
whatever the high bits were of see that
where the alpha we're just gonna either
leave them the same in which case the or
does nothing or rob them with FF in
which case we don't care what they were
they all get set to one so really this
is all we needed to do there isn't
anything else to it
so I think that's it now if we want to
do a threshold of the Alpha in theory
now that we've recompiled test up P and
G I should be able to do that let's go
ahead and try it so if I go ahead and
load out of handmade sources based game
art that I believe was item hat oh three
so here I can do you know just W temp
hat three RGB bitmap W temp hat three
alpha dot bitmap and in theory we should
get something that we can view now right
so here's the RGB from the Hat and you
know that looks about right and hey that
looks pretty suspicious there doesn't it
and then here's the alpha from the Hat
what it looks like to me so it looks
like the Alpha is actually clean meaning
I don't see anything in there right you
can see that this did threshold it right
all of these parts that were previously
fuzzed
are not fuzz anymore but the RGB is
there right there's some some RGB
happening like right here there doesn't
seem to be any in any of the other
places so I'm not sure
about that but at least that tile does
have them um so what I'd like to do is
say let's go check to see where that
data actually was coming like what I
suspect we probably have is that alpha
channel is probably set to not actually
be there so it's eliminating the image
but the RGB that's there is getting
detected as valid right so inside import
if I if I go in here and let's see we've
got no I don't need a right image that's
this right here probably so that's down
sample process multi tile so this is the
detection code to see whether or not
we're going to extract one of these and
inside here you can see that we are just
looking at only the Alpha as far as I
can tell right
at least yeah I mean so this is looping
over it right here you can see it it's
using min and Max looping over the alpha
like so so that seems fine meaning it
doesn't look like we're using the RGB at
all there right
so I'm not sure I don't know why we are
having that issue
[Music]
hmm so I'm gonna have to step through
this code because it looks like I mean
just from doing this analysis I don't
see I don't see any reason why we would
be picking that up even though there is
some there to be picked up in the square
that we picked up the alpha value is not
there isn't alpha there so there isn't
alpha there so I don't really know
that's that's a tough one because you
would think I mean based on the
pathology of the bug it seems like what
I would have expected to see here is
testing sorce by itself right and then
you would have seen something where the
RGB values got you know where what what
was triggering the the indication that
there was something in the grid cell so
I don't know about that and hmm
I think I'm just gonna have to step
through because that that's really my
that's all I've got I don't have it I
don't have another theory that comes to
mind looking at if I open this up with
the the jimp here we go
and I take this is the that the item
overlay so I can see exactly what's
going on in terms of grid squares
there's that overlay I'm going to change
this to multiply so that you can see
through it or I'm going to try it there
it is so you can see here that these all
lie entirely within the grid squares
except for this one this is this other
square that was getting exported however
I will admit there was one other square
that did get exported and it's not
showing up here so it is true that
really I guess even this I shouldn't
have really expected because there isn't
any indication of why the other grid
square would have gone out just if you
bear with me for a second here if I load
up tab view so inside the
inside the base game and we look at the
asset listing so you know when we
imported the item list there here it is
when you look at what we're seeing for
import lists you know the the import
list for it here we go
so you can see that to 0 to 1 to 2 to 3
which is here here here and here
that's this row and that's correct
to 1 which is this line here that's this
square and that would have been a dead
giveaway and I would have expected to
find while I looked and you know would
have expected to find that to be the
case but it is true that 3 3 is also
marked as having something in it and
that doesn't have any indication of why
there would be something there looking
back here you can see like there's
nothing there's nothing in it right so I
guess I'd have to admit my theory just
isn't very good anyway because why would
fixing this fix the the lower corner so
something else is still wrong somehow
this piece of code is getting tripped up
and I'm not exactly sure how
looking at the image width and height
here I'm assuming these are all set
reasonably but I don't know maybe
there's some kind of a padding problem
but I don't think we even store a stride
for these so none of the code would work
properly if there was some kind of a
padding problem so I've got nothing so I
think what we're gonna have to do now is
I'm going to have to force process multi
tile import to get called and I'm gonna
have to force it to get called on
this particular file so that we can look
and see what actually is going on now
it's possible just looking at it I might
be able to cheese out and do the
following don't I'm not gonna promise
that I can but I'm gonna try because if
I can this will be an easier way to
debug it if we copy process multi file
multi tail import in here and we get rid
of all of this other stuff so we're only
saying here is the image like this we
should be able to run this again if we
know that this is always these these are
rate counts here I think they're set to
sixteen by sixteen normally right and
then you know all of this stuff I mean
this can just be a printf right because
this is a routine that you know just
just print stuff out so if I'm lucky I
may be able to just run this directly in
the PNG importer and have it tell me
what it thinks is going on when we do
this nonsense here
it doesn't require any access to the art
asset system so in theory all of this
stuff can still happen and yeah I think
we're I think we're good to go so this
way I can debug it in a nice controlled
environment that doesn't involve us
having to run anything else it'll also
allow me to verify it externally so that
then we could see well hey if it doesn't
fail here maybe it's some other problem
deeper into the art system that we
should know about
so I don't care about any of this
because we don't need to know any of
this so really all that has to happen is
now I just have to say whether or not we
would have extracted this tile
right because we you know if we got in
here we would have done so and so then
what we want to say is these this stuff
here is the the extraction so it's like
that I think and then I could just
literally keep this math as it was being
done pret previously and then get rid of
all of this so this would tell me you
know exactly what happened in theory I
can just compile it I don't think
there's anything that it depends on it
all right so now I could just call
process multi tile import or maybe we'll
call it test of all types I'll import
and so then here when we're actually
doing after we do the load we can do the
test and we just pass this image and
that's it right and that should do it
so now if I come back and rerun this
line of code this test PNG line I should
be able to see what it thought it was
extracting right and so you can see that
this is great I'm this is fantastic you
can see that it does actually do six
extractions that means the bug does
reproduce outside of the art pipeline
which should give us all we really need
you know I'm saying okay so I guess the
next question is how do we want to debug
this first of all I think the extraction
code should probably have in it which X
index and Y index it was actually doing
so maybe something like this where we
can say all right X index Y index that
way we can get some sort of a you know
easy for us to understand and it would
also match what's in the tab view just
so we can see which one's the wrong one
so if we look here we know that that's
correct these are correct and then this
and this are wrong you know I'm saying
now if you look at where
these are they are tiny right there
they're very small I will print out the
dimensions here as well
so if I did I do we have I think we've
got a rectangle - I think that has a
bunch of stuff in it that we might want
there as well although those are floats
I don't know if we do a rectangle - I we
do so we could do one of these rectangle
two eyes here I don't know if we've got
to get dim for it it looks like we don't
so yeah less useful anyway
maybe we shouldn't make one let's
actually make this rectangle - I hear
guess maybe I'll do it this way
there's the min on both here's the max
on both oops that's no good
and now we can just do extract-min X
stretch and Y stretch max X expect X Y
and now I can print out some size
information so here we can do extract
max X - extract min X and extract max Y
- extract min Y and that I just wanted
so I don't have to do that math in my
head so what you can see is these are
like garbage little tiny things says 17
by 17 right and so where that's coming
from
I have no idea but I want to find out
somehow there's this sort of bogus in
bogus stuff coming out of here and
what's weird is when you look at the
values that we're getting in the PNG it
you know we could say oh maybe our PNG
parser was busted and it's writing out
some garbage there but we looked at
dumps of it and we'd seen anything now
we did see something in this square but
we're not looking at the RGV so that
shouldn't have been a problem and we
didn't see anything in this square right
there's there was nothing there so it
does seem like especially we just
concentrate on this one this three three
we see nothing there and yet we're
getting this this extraction you know
getting triggered the fact that they're
both 17 by 17 does sort of suggest that
we have some kind of a fancy bug
happening like maybe we're looking in
the wrong place somehow when we do some
of the source pixel advance sing or
something like this code is slightly off
or I don't know right but but it does
seem like we've got something Squinkie
happening here and we need to get a
little bit more insight into what it
thinks it's extracting in these cases
right
now fortunately for me I can just do
that right we've got a thing that heat
right here that's like hey man why don't
you write this out what I should be able
to do is write out the Alpha Channel and
it will like it write out both if I
wanted to write
I could write out each of these things
as an extraction test and say look show
me what you thought the pixels work you
know it's just a reasonable start so in
here if I'm gonna do an extraction what
I would want to do is get that width and
height so so in here I'm going to say
this is the the width and height that
I've already computed for purposes of
printing it out and I'm just going to
keep it so that I can use it in here so
curiously extract width and the extract
height now I need to take that info
stream so if there's a place that dump
errors I probably should have done that
to begin with because I could have just
used that as the place and I could have
used out F's in the first place but I
think we just want to do that right and
so here where it's gonna take that info
stream I'll just pass that along like so
and then when it does this nonsense here
I just need to give it a name so when
we're doing this right what I can do is
say alright you know I've got a little
buffer here and a little buffer here let
me go ahead and sprint up into those
nothing interesting happening here and
again this is just cheesy nonsense
nothing nothing good so I need to get
the extract pixels pointer here this is
going to be the location where if you
were gonna start you would youwould this
is where you'd move to the problem for
me is unfortunately in order to do that
I need like I would need a stride for
right top-down image rgba and what you
can see here is that this doesn't
actually take one so this would this
needs to actually condense what it's
this needs to sort of do that extract
and again I think you know because this
was actually doing extract image here
right I suspect what I could do is again
just keep calling that so if I look at
extract image oops this code right here
it does do it does the alpha multiply
which I don't really want unfortunately
but I can use it so if we take this and
get rid of that what I can probably do
well and you know what I guess we have
that so I could just do this I could
literally do it exactly this way what I
could do here is just don't you know
don't do this right so instead it would
just be copy directly
and leave it at that so if I want to do
that I need one more thing I need to be
able to pass the memory rename here just
to keep this flowing exactly the way it
was before so that would look like this
and then we could just call it the way
we were calling it before so if we
wanted to do that then this becomes even
easier because now we have an image u32
here which is this is the extracted oops
the extracted image and then we would
just say alright extract image extract
min extract min Y extract max extract
max Y and I don't actually remember the
other things this takes so it needs the
source image which was what just image
yeah so it takes the source image the
rectangle and the temporary no and
that's it then the extract width and
height is it's actually now we can just
say extracted with extracted height this
doesn't need to occur anymore these can
happen and then here we just say
extracted with extracted height
extracted pixels so there's no other
stuff there and we may need to cast that
though
so right so that needs to be you 8
pixels what was it was au 32 so that
needs to go like that
[Music]
there we go okay so at that point I
think we're good to go
we'll find out but now we should get
like just a local dump of those files in
theory right so here they are it's one
it's like one alpha dot
so they both think there is literally
one alpha dot just sitting there and so
now we're left unfortunately still with
a conundrum because we didn't see an
alpha dot there but I guess we can make
sure by looking at this maybe in a real
program because you know you can't
really trust microsoft with something
like that lo and behold so there is one
alpha dot there and one alpha dot there
all right so we almost need to make this
bloom out the alpha or something because
that doesn't so yeah I mean I don't know
anyway we saw those it is exactly what I
thought it was at the start it's hard to
detect those what I'm going to try to do
now I think is just change that
detection routine to be more forgiving
and so what I think we want to do here
you say hey when we do the multi tile we
probably want to just prevent things
that are too small just in general right
so when we do multi tile extract so this
code here what we want to do is when
we're doing this we then do like the
expansion here we probably want to say
look is the minimum you know is the
sighs exceeded or not you know so let's
figure that out what we would do there
is say first of all the min X has to be
less than the max X and the min Y have
to be Lexx in the max Y right so it
would you know it has to be it has to
have found something and the only
problem is so the way we're doing it
here like if you look at this with the
min X and the max X and stuff there
isn't really a way to add some to that
so I'm not sure exactly how we want to
do that I think what we'd want to say is
something more like this
so what i'm doing here is i'm just doing
a computation of the length that is safe
so it's just saying or at least somewhat
safe it's saying look we're gonna start
with zeros here if you found something
determine what the width is and then i'm
gonna say if test dim X is greater than
let's say 4 and test dim Y is greater
than 4 then off we would go right and
you know the pixel cap you know what I'm
thinkin maybe that doesn't even matter
now I think about it
maybe I don't need to do this at all
what if we just counted the number of
pixels so if in here we just said look
how many pixels are there then we coming
here I want to see the valid pixel count
is greater than the 16 and write the min
x max X right has has some thing to say
about that right and then I think we
probably also want in here I want
probably a second layer which is that
once we know that the thing has area we
don't really need to test that I guess
because that would just automatically
happen um and so this this really is
just this
[Music]
so I think we also maybe want the the we
want the purr of pixels to have to be
properly proportioned to the area
possibly to so the bigger the area the
more pixels should have to be filled up
to a certain number right because we'd
really like to say look if there's not
like 128 pixels it's probably isn't
valid but if it was some small little
thing then maybe that's fine like for
the fonts or whatever right
so maybe what I'll do is say something
like pixels per area right and then
we'll say if the valid pixel count is
greater than eight which is like the
lowest number we're gonna accept or
something for for I don't know and then
what we want to do is take the area so
we would say max X minus min X times max
Y minus min Y right so we do the
multiplication to find out what the area
is there and then we would want to take
the valid pixel count and sort of like
determine how many pixels per unit area
we have covering us I think so then we
would have loops then we'd have I don't
know what that just did don't want to
know thank you windows for whatever that
awesome thing that just happened was our
pixels per area would want to be the
valid pixel counts divided by the area
right and so what we want to say is look
you know something like this if the
pixels per unit area is not sufficient
then it's probably just noise right and
off we go
so the problem with this is that if you
just had like a little splotch we
wouldn't necessarily be able to tell
that you know that wasn't what you
wanted but then
again you know fonts and stuff they
don't really go in here for the most
part so I feel like because they get
generated by a separate path their
process does a single tile import so I
do wonder if maybe it would be okay to
be more stringent right and say that
like at least 25% in the area at least
you know I don't know but saying 10% of
the area has to be covered should be
enough and since we have to have more
than just one pixel that would get rid
of the case that we're looking at now I
just don't know if we're really still we
still probably aren't quite testing as
stringently as we need to in the pixels
for area Department because like for
example in this case a little 3x3 filled
solid pixel would pass but maybe it
should I mean I don't know so I'm gonna
claim that that is what should happen
here and I'm gonna see if now we can
repress our at our art assets and and if
they all pass correctly and see you know
see if that actually works if that makes
sense
yeah I mean the only thing I think is
this maybe really should be more like
sixty you know so I'm gonna say sixteen
and I also don't know if this needs to
have a secondary counter that's like
actually stronger pixels so pixels with
an alpha value that's higher you know
that's that's like more than say sixteen
or something like that we may want to do
that as well like so maybe we would do
something like this
and so this way we would say look
there's a solid pixel count and a valid
pixel count valid pixel count just lets
us know we saw anything solid pixel
count is sort of separate right so we
here where we've got oops in here where
we've got the Alpha production what I'd
like to do is say like alpha equals
shifted so we'll shift it down we'll see
if there's anything there if there is
something there then we will look at it
and this will only increment that if the
Alpha is greater than 16 that's gonna be
our alpha threshold right the magic
number 16 everyone knows it and so in
here we're gonna look to see if we got
any region at all if we did we're gonna
look at the area that was covered by
that region and see whether or not the
solid pixel area actually was reasonable
right I think that's about it
it's not a great routine but hopefully
that'll get us started okay so if I now
run an asset rebuild so let's suppose
that we go in here I'm gonna also inside
test PNG I'm gonna if this code now just
to leave it the way it used to work so
what I want to do now is just go back in
and have it do a full rebuild and see if
they can import everything like it's
supposed to so if I go to handmade data
and we just dell base game HHA and intro
cutscene hij so now there's nothing left
right it's gone there's no game data
whatsoever if I now force it to actually
I mean low up remedy here if I force it
to run and rebuild everything that it
had there we go what does it do right
does it actually grab everything
properly or did I you know horribly ruin
it you know we'll see
I love how Linux just like you know
initializes a mouse it's on it's plugged
in it's powered up but forget it we
can't read that Mouse why because we're
Linux and we don't read mice all right
so I think this is where we were
actually so it looks like it did read
everything properly but we want to get
rid of the quick thing so that we can
look at the old asset and see whether it
got imported properly so inside the
where we actually create the player we
want to go ahead and remove the part
where we added that that we were a cook
because we're not a cook and now we can
run and see what's up with that
so that fixed our problem I'm not sure
that code is really all that great but
it's at least better than it was and so
now we have at least some protection
against garbage alpha pixels that just
sneak through causing issues that we
can't see all right so that's good
enough for now we may need to revisit
that code later because it's sort of
just a you know a sort of arbitrary
heuristic that we you know we just kind
of pulled out and so it's not you know
it's not really something that's robust
enough probably to last us the entire
time but for now we're gonna call that
good so so all right let's we got to do
some thinking now I think we're at the
point where it's time to start doing any
work cuz I don't think there was
anything else that I had to do or wanted
to do here yeah I don't think so
I might before I do the entity work
I might maybe possibly want to go ahead
and well actually you know what I do
want to do as well is I want to turn off
all these rectangles let's go in here so
what I'd like to do is why did that not
weird just took a while I guess so what
I would like to do now is I'd like to
play some furniture I guess would be the
next obvious thing to do and then after
that I'd like to go address the entity
system like the reason we need to
upgrade a couple things in there now
because we want to do stuff like be able
to change our body to a cook body
without changing our head to a to some
other head as well right so we have some
things we need to do there that we
haven't really addressed and that will
allow us to create our orphans properly
as well so there's a bunch of stuff like
that that we'd like to do I suppose
another thing that we might want to do
here is also like set up the rest of the
wharf and heads and bodies so that there
they have such snap points and that
stuff we also need to think about
scaling so we just have a lot of work to
do because we're sort of opening up a
bunch of world creation sorts of stuff
and so then there's just tons of work we
can do there all right so everything
else seems to be looking fine and of
course we have a nice flower on our head
now which is always a plus as well and
let me just make sure that like these
guys are still hopping around they are
they never set they're facing direction
they should
is there a reason they don't suck
they're facing direction we're just
we're just being lazy I'm assuming
inside brain here
where's the snake so when it actually
does the transactional occupy like I
think we would want to do this right we
want to take that Delta and do the a tan
on it I think why re tan to doesn't take
a vector no idea yeah there we go so I
don't know why they weren't doing that
to begin with I also don't know why this
guy can hop diagonally cuz that doesn't
make any sense
so this is probably totally wrong as
well what we probably should be doing
here is saying look if the Delta X is
greater than the Delta Y then it's X
otherwise it's Y you know I'm Sam so it
should be something like you know
whichever one's greater then the Delta y
equals zero and the Delta X zero here
something like that you know I'm saying
I also don't know why this is why this
isn't normalized so this was just I
think this is just crap code we typed in
because no one would write that I don't
know why anyone would write that but
that's what it should have been right
and so now it should only be able to hop
vertically or horizontally like you're
not allowed to hop diagonally so I don't
know why this was probably from a time
period where we hadn't necessarily said
that that was so or something I don't
know so now you can only hop you can
only hop along the grid as it should and
you know it can go around and have a
little party and whatever else it wants
but anyway it looks like all of those
are working fine and sorry I didn't
quite explain what I was doing there I
didn't really
care about that could I just wanted to
not leave it in weird state it's just
this was picking a random direction but
it also ends up with a random length and
we don't really need it to have a random
length we just need a random direction
so I made it so it would basically
threshold and say whichever one was
greater don't go diagonal so just either
go X or Y and then once you zero out the
one that's lesser normalize it so that
it's going to be one in one of the four
cardinal directions this code we
probably will have pulled out at some
point to like get random direction
that'll just give us one of the the four
cardinal directions right but for right
now I just wanted to clean it up in
place so it wasn't sitting around being
crappy I don't remember how we got in
here wasn't this way was it was the
other way yeah we need to put in some
punching codes because they're kind of
again that's game play stuffs not really
my domain all right so I think we're all
that stuff's fine and now what I want to
do is I would like to make a I would
like to take some time now and figure
out like how we want to place furniture
probably I think that's what I want to
do the other thing I want to do is make
sure that entities can have multiple
that I have a strategy that I want to
try for making entities have more
flexibility with how the tags are set
there's a way that I think I want to do
that that you know I want to try I'm not
sure if it's gonna be correct or not how
much time do we have is maybe the best
way to look at that
[Music]
so I think we have 45 minutes left
probably so assuming we have 45 minutes
left what I'd like to do is do the
furniture I think so inside room Jen I
want to be able to place like just an
inanimate object and I don't really
think that we mean separate entity
brains or anything for this because it's
literally just an entity that sits there
it doesn't do anything it just occupies
a square so that that square can't
actually have anything on it in terms of
walking or anything right so I think in
order to do that what I would need to do
is when we place monsters so inside
inside room Jen we've got stuff that
places monsters sometimes right and well
I guess where is that that's like in the
here right fine place to put entity
right so that's where we're gonna place
these entity groups that I think is how
we would do it and there's a couple
things that we're gonna have to do later
I'm not probably gonna do them now I'm
gonna let them fail and then we'll deal
with it later
but what I want to do is place furniture
using this system I think that will
actually allow furniture to block exits
which we don't want it to do
and so we will probably make that be
something that we add to the checking
here when it's actually placed and we'll
go from there
so I don't remember how to use any
systems because of course we haven't
used them in a real long time but when
we actually push these on inside the
gencode which i think is in here
[Music]
anyone here it is uh so when we do this
stuff right you can see us here's place
cap it goes through the options for
where cats can be right and adds them in
so I think the same is true for
furniture so we can really just when
replacing things we can just place
furniture as and as a pass that comes
after I think that's probably the
easiest way to do it I don't actually
know we could just do it at the time as
well maybe that's a better idea so maybe
in here what we want is really this
right we want this this code to just
place it in a room so you know inside
create orphanage here we added all these
rooms and maybe inside the main room we
want to add some furniture so like yeah
like this so this thing is a chair it's
facing some direction this is going to
have to be the function that adds that
thing
why isn't add orphan shouldn't there be
a door Fionn as a function oh I bet
those are in the energy gen those are
those were call backs yeah you can see
them unfortunately the jump call doesn't
know it doesn't understand the macros
here so it can't know where those are so
I think what we have here is like add
cat right it just puts a thing on there
and it doesn't have a brain that's what
we want so I think we want something
this which is like all right this is add
[Music]
scenery I guess maybe we'll call it AB
obstacle because it it does like place
itself on to the thing that's standing
on probably I don't know so it's gonna
be something like that and it has the
collider on it it doesn't have you know
anything here it's it's just scenery
and so all of that should be the same in
this connect piece to world thing we
would need yeah this would be the same
and that doesn't have to happen so it's
really just this so I think this is add
obstacle we say it's a chair we say this
is the facing direction here's where
we're placing it we add the entity in
and that should be it so I think that's
all I don't think we need any the other
code because all the other code was
there for other to handle other aspects
of it alright so what is the problem
here for add entity by the way it takes
a Gen and an entity creator add obstacle
is one of those and Gen is a world
generator right
Oh result is not that so identity
returns a gen entity there so we need to
do this something like this maybe this
that might take care of all of it
actually so I think that's it and then
when I run I don't know if we actually
got a chair or not I tried to put a
chair in the main room
it'll since we don't have any
sophisticated lyoko right now it should
just be in the upper corner or the first
place it can be and it actually is there
it is and of course it blocked the
entrance whoops so okay so that lets us
place furniture everywhere we don't
actually have the different directions
of furniture so I should probably use
the only direction we actually have
which is to say that's well I'll leave
that in for now that it should be facing
in the direction so now we need some way
of actually placing this stuff in some
way that makes sense this may require us
to have more of a explicit layout not
really sure how we want to do that
because I think probably when we're
creating rooms we're going to want to
lay them out by some various game design
criteria and so you know here we can you
can kind of see there's our right
there's our chair there so we want to be
able to do stuff like place those in a
way that makes more sense and I'm not
sure exactly how or where we want to do
that we have to think about more about
like what's gonna be required for
gameplay to have that happen and yeah I
would like also to be able to control
the size a little more easily because
for example you know the chair is too
small probably at the moment it should
really be the whole size of the square
inside the add obstacle like there's the
sizing there's a couple different ways
we can do that we could just
even at one point oh I don't again don't
really know what the best way to do this
would be we could leave it at one point
oh and if we do then the way that we
would adjust the size would actually be
like encoded into the placement point so
for example we would go like this and
say oh this thing right it's default
placement size is on here right and then
we would size it up to however big it
was and also we would place it like in
the square right and maybe that's the
right thing so everything is just 1.0 by
default and you scale it up in there
right but again like you don't really
know exactly how we want that to go so
I'm not sure yet but something like that
and so then you know if that's not what
I wanted
i ex adieu the game also that's wrong
that's not our title screen we got to
add a different query it looks like does
the rest of our stuff work okay yeah so
the rest of the stuff works just fine so
I think our title screen doesn't have
the right query on it anymore let's take
a look
[Music]
shot index one layer index one title
screen so yeah if we go to cutscene I
think it's still using the old query for
when we didn't have a separate thing for
the title screen so we probably want
that yeah
so that should now actually pick out the
title screen properly and you know we
can add more layers later there's only
one layer for telson right now but
that's that's what it should have done
because remember we added tag to that I
guess we never went in and actually done
anything about it so yeah much better
now um alright so this is getting there
now we're able to drop things in pretty
easily
maybe that scale should just always stay
1.0 and then the alignment points
adjusted that does seem like a pretty
good way to go so yeah I guess I don't
really know what to do next
we've got a ton of time left so I don't
know if that means I should go in there
and actually start the furniture layout
stuff I just really don't know
[Music]
all right hand me yours over I can't
think what to do next weird we're done
yeah so I don't actually know what we
should be doing now the next two things
to start on both seeing bigger than
stuff that we would want to start at the
end of the episode crumpets
so because yeah we either want to start
doing layout for stuff that goes into
the world or we want to upgrade the
entities to have the tag problem fixed
and I don't yeah I don't know about
either of those so what you know what we
could maybe do instead is how I turn
those rectangles off maybe we should go
in and put in a little UI for turning on
and off debug overlays or something like
that because it does seem like the kind
of thing that we do pretty often here so
there's that I could also go make some
tree I could extract the trees and then
we could put in some trees that seems
like it might be a good idea I don't
know I would like to see how the trees
look let's put in some trees I don't
know I thought we were gonna have more
work to do today than it turned out we
did so that was a you know sometimes
programming you get a bug it takes you
forever and so you know you spend a lot
more time than you think and then other
times you're just like oh all that stuff
just worked so I guess we don't care uh
so yeah if I wanted to get the trees in
there let's let's look at that inside
handmade sources in the base game area
so of the stuff that we didn't do right
you know here we got the temp chairs
that I did oh I should ask for the
chairs in different orientations perhaps
well we can always leave that for later
I guess I could put some lamps in
let's put lamps and trees and just just
cuz alright so in here we've got some
trees I don't really know what to do
about the trees the problem is about how
we're labeling them labeling them or it
wise and minoo I guess there's like
destroyed versus snowy I guess I don't
know so there's kind of two axes there
and I don't really have a strong opinion
about how those should should work so
we'll just do our best
I guess if I load up the carrot the sort
of the character at the item template
and I say alright for the item template
and you know what yeah you know what I
should do too you know let's go hog-wild
here let's just go hog-wild if I go back
here I could just say like that there's
templates in here right so that our
templates are all in the same place
which kind of seems like a good idea to
me
so character template there's no other
templates are there so let's just go
back here and we'll say inside sources
underneath templates there's character
template so I've got these two templates
I'd go ahead and open this one up into
the jimp and then I'll go grab out of
base game art this tree thing open with
this I convert convert I guess and so if
I didn't want to do that did I open as
layers item template so if I okay nope I
take it back I did want to do that so if
I go over here and I grab some of these
out so let's say I grab this tree okay
let's say I grab this tree and I paste
that in there
and then we just pretend that these axes
are what I just said they are so damaged
is on one end
so like
and snow-covered is on the other
so if it's something like this
and then we say okay that's my tree like
scenery or I guess this actually needs
to be it since it's going to have a
different sort of labeling system I
guess I want this to be some other word
besides scenery this is like an out
outdoor or something
I don't really know so it's like outdoor
it's like an outdoor tree or it might
just be yeah I don't know I know I
almost don't want to do it because if we
just use the other thing we could just
get away with not having so maybe
there's just like a damage but you know
so so I'm gonna take that back I must
say that we just have the snow covered
going this way maybe so the variant is
just that or maybe it's maybe it's just
a separate one for each of them so
they're just a couple different variants
I don't know it would only be the top
row so I think maybe that's what I'll do
so I think what I'll do is say look
there's gonna be one for each of these
so I'll just like put them up like this
on top of themselves
oops
right and then I'll just save them out
separately so like this is just going to
be damaged tree this is like a pine tree
right or an evergreen
and then this is snow-covered
and then this is just regular
that seems good for some definition of
good and I don't know about these guys
exactly so let's just start there inside
the base game tag file here I want to go
to where we were like defining scenery
there and I'll just say like hey scenery
scenery evergreen PNG and this is like
you know tree evergreen or something
like this and we'd have three of these
there was like the damaged one and there
was the snow one right I think this is
what I called them so evergreen damaged
evergreen snow and so we need tags for
those out in here so I don't know if
we've got snow as a tag yet tag snow so
we need those tags and I guess we could
call like ever the other kind of tree
deciduous but that's about it
right and that way we can just sort of
set those tags and then if someone wants
to access them they can
so that should import those they should
work as is and then inside like the room
Jen where it was placing walls before
you know you can see oh we even have an
app we have an ad lamp call interesting
we should put lamps in there's a call
for it so what we want to do here is say
look the places where we were gonna put
walls before we don't put walls when
it's not a room so if it's outdoors we
like to skip that and you can kind of
see like alright here's the connection
stuff here's adding the entities here's
the wall height blah blah blah and so
what happens here is you can see you've
got a thing that actually does the tag
wall tag wood stuff right and it looks
like the way we're doing that right now
is if you're on the boundary the wall
height goes up we set the on boundary
tag if you're outdoors to like not be
there right but I think that's actually
not quite what we want to do so what we
actually want to do is if we look at
that on boundary right here this code is
like if we're outdoors we would place a
tree otherwise we'd do that right and so
up here we want to probably get rid of
this code and in here we would want to
actually place an entity that is a tree
on this square right and so
whether or not those should actually be
entities is a little hard to say I'm
gonna say yes for now so we're gonna do
something like this
and I'm going to try to put that entity
on top here so this code basically is
probably what I would do
for place unity I think
so honestly I guess it's really just
this and later on we would say all right
so at the end of this we would want to
say after you've placed this like if
we're supposed to place a tree put a
tree on top of it I guess right
and so that is essentially this code
here it would be like we need to get the
tile but we already know what the tile
is so we don't need that we need to look
to see whether or not we can grab the
structural element out of it it has to
be I guess in this case so that part
like we already know it's just the
entity that we're placing here so I
don't think that that matters at all so
this is is just this and then here where
we do place entity I think this is all
good all we really have to do is like
create a tree here and add that so I
don't know what kind of tree we're
necessarily gonna do right but since we
only have evergreens at the moment we'll
hard-coded to that maybe snow ones and
if we go ahead and do that all we really
need here is just a straightforward
identity I think and we need to add one
visible piece which is just the tree
like the the scenery of it I think we
can just call the creator function here
so we should be able to do just add
obstacle
and that probably would do it I think so
that was kind of a random thing to do
[Music]
I'm not sure why that failed
so tile structural entity and the idea
gets from so this what is the complaint
here so somebody's no but it should
always be valid right this entity should
be valid
so I suppose it's possible that the
thing just doesn't have a traversable
which I suppose we should check why it
wouldn't have one on a place where it's
going to place a tree though that I'm
not sure about but we certainly can
check so in here we could say hey yeah
like
well no I mean how could it not have I
guess we'd have to say if it's open
because it would have to right am I
missing something I must have just been
missing something symbol there let's
take a look so it did not it it looks
like it removed that from the set though
which is a little bit weird so right
like for some somehow that activity of
saying if spec outdoors at place three
equals true like made us not actually
get any any visible piece here at all
which doesn't make a lot of sense unless
I'm missing something so let me just
verify I want to make sure that this is
actually the cause of that
know so I ruined something else there
what did I do
I thought that was the only thing I
changed but evidently that is not the
only thing I changed because I clipped
out all of the stuff that was around the
perimeter there accidentally you can see
it the same thing happened here right so
what did I accidentally change there
that I didn't mean to so we come through
here and we say are we on the boundary
previously what I said is if we're on
the outside then the answer is that we
are not right so I guess the main change
was that
now I thought on boundary only really
ever did one thing so it won't go in
here ah I see but we do need a
traversable there so I guess on boundary
is probably is the wrong thing there
because we do want to go in here and we
do want to specify that it's grass and
that sort of stuff right so I guess we
do need to do this we want to leave this
this way and we want to say okay yeah
like
we want to say something a little bit
more specific here so inside you know we
do this sort of stuff and you know all
of this should still happen the way that
it's happening I guess we do call this
and then the only thing that happens is
the place tree call if we're in here we
want to make sure that we're not on a
connection so I think we want to do that
but otherwise we're okay
right I think that's all we really need
and so that should place our trees
[Laughter]
I forgot it also has to be on the actual
boundary so that's what we need that for
so we really need something like this
that's just a few too many trees is the
problem so let's see now that we've got
some trees we should also probably size
them they're gonna be sized wrong but
there we go so now there's at least a
tree boundary and normally you know
we're gonna want to do a lot more stuff
there to make this look like a forest
and all kinds of other things so you
know they're stuff that has to happen
there let's go ahead and also look why
didn't the baby get placed there that's
another issue I think we have yeah I
mean we've got a lot of work to do on
this code this doesn't really do
anything right now but we'll get there
so if we want these to be the right size
we need them to be you know I don't know
something more like that probably
right
I think that's roughly what we're
looking for
and that way you know there's some big
trees and stuff and they look fine that
seems reasonable we would probably want
to like vary that height a little bit as
well but it seems to work pretty well
the occlusion looks about right
I don't know if that center point is is
quite right though let me let me look at
that a little bit more closely on
something like here
if that looks a little mouse a little
better it's never quite right you know
because it's to its 2d trying to be 3d
right so it's never quite right but
seems a little bare it may be a little
left shifted as well
now it looks a little right shifted
right
seems about right
all right so I think that's sufficient
for trees for now and again like in
theory anyway we should be able to just
like change those parameters pretty
easily one thing that I'm not sure about
is so let's say that you have an entity
here I don't actually know if entities
are tracked to any significant degree
but you know like if we did do that so
that's camera F what is nothing not sure
how I would want that to work but just
you know just to sort of show you what
I'm thinking about here inside the
editor we I don't really remember what
we track cuz it looks like we just use
assets we don't actually use entities I
think anywhere I think and so it would
be nice to have access to the entity
itself as well so that we could you know
actually tweak some of those parameters
that's so that we could look at what
happens when we change tags you know I'm
saying so that would be a nice thing to
do I just don't know it's it's not we
only got ten minutes left let's find out
something we should do now but point
being so if we like inside the I don't
want this to accident accidentally get
overwritten by the way what I would like
to do is take a look at the code where
we're actually placing this stuff we
could in here randomize this value so
instead of this like you know we could
do just to prove that we can
I think this would give us like an
assortment of the trees that we had in
there in theory I believe it's damaged
right is the tag is that did we not put
that in there yes I didn't put that in
there
I didn't see if I add that in and say
that there's a damaged here like so
then I should also be able to randomize
on that previously it looks like I
wasn't actually marking that and so now
we should have some different trees
possibly and actually new so I could
only pick the damaged ones there and I'm
not really sure why
[Music]
that should have in us a random number
between zero and one for the snow and
for the damaged
I guess the tag matching is the tag
matching biased against zero values
because if so that would be a problem
for us we have to do some work on our
tag matching anyway and it's been on the
to-do list forever but just in terms of
getting best match asset
I'm not sure now it doesn't look like it
because the match vector would just be
zero there and so the difference should
be also zero
so I don't I don't see why that's a
problem
hmm well let's find out also I feel like
the alignment is probably the same on
all these so I can probably just do this
right I don't need to like manually
align each of those because they're
gonna all be the same
I would assume anyway uh so yeah let's
find out why that matches we're
happening weird because I assume all
those folks got different tag values and
so I feel like they should all have like
they should all have different pics
there and I'm not sure why what you can
see is it looks like it's biased against
things that don't have the tag in them
at all so in other words things that
have snow or things that have damaged
are both matching like reasonably but
things that have neither are not
matching right so it's like it's it's
like refusing against that are saying
that doesn't have the channels that were
requested at all but I'm not sure why it
would do that because in theory if those
values are 0 that shouldn't actually
give it much but maybe that's because
we're doing some kind of other thing
there but anyway other than that it
looks okay and you can see like yeah
treat evergreen never got picked even
though there should be some where these
have less than point each of these are
less than 0.5 it should be the preferred
right at that point but it's not and I'm
not sure why looking at the asset picker
if the tag just doesn't if the if the
tie just doesn't exist at all
see we're looping over the tags the
asset actually has right and then what
we do is say all right for each tag that
the asset actually has it gets like a
better it gets the more things that can
match the better so I guess the problem
that we see here is that if you didn't
have a tag at all then you don't get any
credit for it in the match so even
though you were closer it doesn't count
and I'm not sure that maybe the way we
want it to be you know because we may
want to control what the parameters are
of the matching so like I don't know you
know one way to look at it would be
you'd want to do this for things that
were on there and another way would be
well oops
right and that would allow you to say
like okay this all participates in the
matching so we're not trying to like
eliminate anybody but really my son my
feeling on that is it's probably just
needs that we need to extend the tag
system to know the difference between
those two types of picking right and say
oh all right if we're going to pick
amongst these then you can tell me if a
tag is something that should always
count whether you've got it or not
and or whether it's something that
should only count for people who
actually have the tag right and I think
those two need to be kind of handled
separately anyway that's fine for today
so I'll go ahead and go to Q&amp;A here let
me go ahead and
and while we're at it I'm a while I'm
waiting for the questions to come in we
could also add lamp back in so the thing
that does the add lamp this thing if we
actually did do add lamp we could now
actually place a lamp which we don't
really want to do because it's gonna be
stupid and weird because there's gonna
be so many stupid lamps like you can see
like just how much light there is but
what we could do is just put one in each
room so this on lamp maybe it only does
just like just this one for now and so
on here it will place the lamp
all right so if I said we had an on lamp
now then this same thing would happen
right
and this actually here could just be
shared probably and so I don't know
something like this where is that add
lamp yeah so add lamp would then become
one of those like helper functions so
yeah like much like add scenery or
whatever it is I know that was your
summer right we just had it add obstacle
that's what it was
so we'd have like a gen create entity
add lamp for now and I don't know it
would be like well actually I guess we
don't really even need that because
probably what you would do is just do
this and so that's the color of the lamp
right and this would just be the
obstacle a durp thingy and we would say
well it's a lamp right so you don't
really need an actual add lamp call
because the add lamp is not actually
having to do anything that the scenery
doesn't do it just sticks another one on
there right so this is like the light
the lamp light let's say so I think that
would do it I don't know that we need
anything else there for that and so now
we could also have little lamps again
they're just kind of scattered around in
a stupid way
that doesn't make any sense
this has to look like that and then I
think we're good
maybe so now we've got little lamps in
there and that's fine so there's always
lamps in the corner of every room for no
reason
and you know we can align those a little
bit better too if you want to so yeah if
I go over here and look at that and I
want to make that seem like it's not
totally wrong it's probably like
something like that maybe let's say so
now we've got the furniture lamp thing
and that's fine and we still don't
really know we're gonna do about the
chairs oh yeah we got lamps outdoors
that's good probably shouldn't do that
huh
all right got any question that's what
do you got for questions we'll be fixing
the lighting who knows when I want to
what's your favorite game of all time
mm-maybe Dance Dance Revolution is there
going to be lighting affecting the
shading of the entities yes if so would
that lighting strength be uniform along
the height of unity within a square no
we'd probably do a little bit more than
that just to add some directionality to
it but you know it'll depend a little
bit on on how we end up wanting that to
work when we get a little closer let me
get a little closer to wanting to deal
with that if you have normal maps you
can also do other stuff there right
suppose no he's supposed to point in
whatever direction you pointed him so
you can appoint him in any direction you
want there is an art bug right now where
the in the actual art file the left
that's supposed to point left and that's
supposed to point right but the heads
are reversed so that's why there's a bug
filed in the github when we get an art
pack update that will fix itself like
you're supposed to be able to like punch
backward and walk forward so it's never
supposed to change your facing direction
if that makes sense
thoughts on creating some sort of
weather system and/or sun noon dusk etc
system well in our case we have an
inbound lighting direction we haven't
really played too much with it yet but
basically what happens there is you
could for free
probably just change that I'm guessing
to just make it be like day or night or
whatever if you could just change that
inbound lighting direction and that
would probably give you most of what you
want right that makes sense
it seems like the tree graphics are for
different seasons I don't think the one
evergreen is supposed to be damaged oh
so you think that that's no I think
that's supposed to be damaged I don't
know though I agree that snow might be
pointless how will we do shadows I don't
know how we want to do shadows we
probably will just use some darkening of
the region underneath for that I'm not
sure how we want to do that yet
I don't super miss them much so I don't
know how much I really care about
anything other than darkening the area
underneath seems probably fine so yeah
but you're right snow should probably
not be there probably winter is better
so that it's more uniform that seems
probably like a good idea so if we can I
revert this buffer no so if I kill and
then reload this and look for snow maybe
this should be winter oops winter
like that and then maybe we could change
the tags to not have that so this tag is
like deprecated now wait up well I guess
I can just mow since we reparse I could
just even change them but I'm not going
to so so I'm going to remove that one
sort of temporarily and if we go could
condense the tags I'll change it around
but but for now we'll deprecated that
tag and make a deal with trans dead I do
think that's a good idea
alright looks like we're good so I'm
going to close it up
thank you everyone for joining me from
episode of handmade heroes my pleasure
coding with you as always if you want to
follow along the series at home you can
always peer to the game on handmade hero
org and it comes with a source code
and we will try to in the very near
future since we're kind of wrapping up
the art import stuff put up a complete
set of the current art assets as they
exist on my machine that should help get
us to a point where it's pretty easy for
new people to just download and build
and build their art assets as well which
is something we hadn't really be able to
do in the past because it was kind of
like piece mail so that'll be a nice
thing to do too and maybe next weekend
we can get to that point cuz it seems
like things are going pretty well at
this point we should be able to kind of
do a an art pack update at that point
that's about it until next week have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the
Internet take it easy everybody