hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream so we're in a bit of a
bind now we basically got our octahedral
sampling working we believe the lighting
is working properly with it actually so
you know we tested some putting
basically test values into the
octahedral voxel distribution and it
looks good I mean it seemed to work
pretty well actually
and so now we're at sort of the point
where we have to kind of finish things
off and in order to get there we well we
need two things really
we need to debug our lighting sort of
stability and sampling over time and
then the other thing which is the really
big one because debugging is just
something we can just do right that's
just a process the big one is the
unknown and I do not know exactly what
we're gonna do for it which is that we
need some way of sampling the diffuse
component of the lighting so with the
octahedral Maps what you'll remember
what you'll recall about them is at the
moment anyway we saw them as eight by
eights they have a one pixel border as
well but the actual lighting information
is an eight by eight and if you recall
the idea behind these is that they can
tell us the light that's incoming from
any particular direction which is great
unfortunately for us in order to do a
diffuse lighting equation when we look
at a surface and say how much light is
bouncing off the surface in a particular
direction well normally what you have to
do is sum the light that's coming in
from a whole host of other directions
right that's what makes a surface
diffuse is that it doesn't just go from
one direction so normally what we would
do is if we were just computing specular
all we need to do is one octahedral look
up in the octahedral map and it tells us
exactly within the error tolerance of
the low number of samples but it tells
us exactly from the maps perspective
what the incoming light at that point
should be so that's what we want for
specular but once we move to diffuse and
we say what's the
uess like coming out in this direction
that actually would require us to sample
all of the directions in a hemisphere
and at an 8 by 8 that means we're
looking at something like a 8 by 4 right
so we require 8 by 4 samples to produce
a diffuse that completely accurate from
given the map answer it would be it
would literally be like in a that many
samples to produce a answer for how much
light there should be coming out right
and so that's just really really
expensive and so it's unclear that we
would ever want to actually have it you
know that we'd ever want to do the
scheme that way especially when we
consider that we're taking these samples
very often and so it's like especially
at render time right especially you know
it's one thing to talk about how we're
doing it when we actually do the light
sampling for propagation because there
we're probably sampling less often and
there maybe you would say just sample
the thing and pay the cost but when
we're actually talking about run time
every pixel on the screen goes through
this lighting equation and sampling all
of that is not necessarily a good idea
it's hard to say but it doesn't seem
like it right now admittedly maybe
that's just wrong you know I'm saying I
don't actually know and it may be
something that we kind of want to test
because if we actually go in and look we
may find that when we when we actually
see how much it costs maybe the card
already has the information on it that
we need so you know maybe the card
already has when you pull in that
texture it already grabbed the region
around it so taking all those extra
samples just doesn't matter right there
like more or less free to add together
that could be I don't think that story
would hold up on lower-end
but it might hold up on hiring cards as
far as the rest of its concerned well it
does seem like we have some options we
could explore for example if we
downsample our maps so they're much
smaller like let's say that we down
sample our maps down to a two by two
right at that point it may be the case
that well now you can just take one
sample and you basically get the
incoming lighting right because at that
point you've averaged things together
and you sort of produced like average
lighting over the hemisphere the problem
with this is it's not cosine weighted
which it should be in order to be you
know a correct sort of letting equation
it should actually be cosine weighted
now I don't know how much that would
really matter because again we're not
trying to get the lighting accurate
we're just trying to get lighting that's
good that looks good so my assumption
like I'm assuming our best way out of
this is to just do a down sample of the
map that's my assumption so my guess is
what we're probably gonna want to do is
we're probably gonna want to say all
right let's take this map let's down
sample the map down to probably a two by
two so basically the maps in general
would be four by four so two by two with
a one pixel border that's just a copy of
the two by two parts and then that's
what we're going to put put in there now
if that actually worked well that would
be support like let's suppose that was
good I don't know if it will be it might
be crappy but let's suppose that was
good if that was good
that would be pretty compelling for a
number of reasons primarily what we
would really like about that is that now
we have a fairly small map to send down
to the graphics card right because now
instead of a 10 by 10 for every probe we
have a 4 by 4 that's significantly less
right that's more than
a four to one savings right a 10 by 10
to a 4 by 4 is going from a hundred to
16 right which is very very good for in
terms of the bandwidth we would have to
have to send it down to the card
similarly it's a lot easier to sample a
4x4 pulls in a lot less than a 10 by 10
if you're sampling a lot of stuff from
it right that's just a less memory
footprint to go through the card so if
that worked that would be great and
furthermore I think we could probably
say well what if we wanted a slightly
better quality than that we probably
could do something more like if we took
a 4x4 with a one pixel border so that we
ended up with so you know two by two of
the one pixel border is a 4x4 maybe two
4x4 were the one because board that'd be
a 6x6 right that might be better because
at that point we could take multiple
samples from the interior 4x4 weight
those together and we know that taking
like a few samples like two or three or
four probably wouldn't kill us so we
could do something like that and so that
would be like a hybrid in between the
two so if we need more directional
fidelity from our lighting which you
know thinking about it if if you think
about what a 2x2 is it's really probably
not enough but a 4x4 might be right so
thinking about in-betweens a 4x4 for the
interior or a six by six total seems
like it might be reasonable that's
something we could do and that would
allow us to take less samples as well
but still get some more directional
fidelity for all I know we wouldn't even
really have to do much summing there it
might be like just two samples or even
one sample with the bilinear might be
enough to get you what you need right
and then finally we could just say all
right if we want
non down Sam like we want to do down
sampling but we want to just take one
sample at runtime we know that that's
actually possible to because we could
just pre compute what the diffuse should
be from each point the reason that's not
so attractive is because the down
sampling operation becomes very
expensive because technically in order
to do that we would need to take sums of
the entire 8x8 we have to take sums of
entire sections of that and then sum
them down into the parts that we write
out and that is somewhat expensive right
now it may be that that's still fine and
maybe that that's the what we want to do
I don't actually know it could be that
we want sort of a hybrid of these two
schemes so maybe what we want to do is
like blur the 8x8 down to a 4x4 first
and then do this I don't really know but
my that's my feeling right is that's
where we're at so my guess is what we
should start with is probably a full
solution and see where that gets us so
you know maybe we do something like take
the PI eight actually do the cosine
waiting on it or something and produce
another 8x8 that's and this is just a
disaster like the reason that we
wouldn't do this normally is because
it's just it's too much math right the
number of operations you need to take a
8x8 and produce a new 8x8 that is the
cosine weighted diffuse that maps so 8x8
specular to an 8x8 diffuse is more or
less every single you know even if you
write it optimally out every single one
of the 8x8 in the output so that's 64
texels that you have to write that's oh
each 64 Texel each each one of the 64
texels itself has to some at least 32 of
the inputs right
so it'd be 32 times 64 operations for
every 8x8 right
at a minimum it's 2048 operations for
each one of these things and so when you
look at how many of those we have if
you're talking about 32 by 32 by 32 by
32 by 64
here's your operation count at best
right you're talking about 67 million
math ops now the problem is again we
have this sort of CPU GPU side problem
maybe the answer there would just be
well you know if you moved ray-tracing
to the GPU well this doesn't look so bad
anymore because the GPU just has tons
and tons of flops sitting around so
throwing 67 million flops at it isn't a
huge deal it will you know be able to do
that because these are parallelizable
they're in fact perfectly parallelizable
because every 8x8 is independent of
every other 8x8 right on the GPU signed
I'm a minister I'm CPU side I'm not as
optimistic even if we assume you know
this thing has like even eight threads
operating the Sun at time each one of
those threads would have to do eight
million ops it's it's not great right I
mean it's possible you know if we
furthermore actually got the parallelism
down it's 2 million
it's just it just looks scary right it
just looks scary and this is on top of
whatever you were doing for lighting so
it's it's like this is an additional
stage that has to happen so you can see
why this is kind of scary to me I don't
really know I'm not super confident that
that this is a great way to go unless it
is on the GPU and so I just don't know
what to do to to make this work and
that's roughly where we're at now so
yeah so I guess my first thought is
maybe we should do it because then at
least we'll have a gold standard
reference so at least then we know what
it will look like if we actually do sort
of the optimal thing and then we can
figure out how much was that costing us
you know how bad is this right and from
there we can maybe figure out what what
our strategy is going to be going
forward it does mean that I think if I'm
not mistaken that if we were to do it
this way and you know I don't know to
what extent we're gonna want some
specular sampling it may be that we want
specular sampling in which case we still
have to have the padding on the original
but if we never use the specular for
sampling if it's just used as an
accumulation buffer effectively then we
wouldn't need the padding on that so we
could drop our 10 by 10 initial map to
an 8 by 8 because you know it's more or
less free to do that once you stop
sampling from it so that's another thing
and I don't know but that's where we're
at so maybe I'll start with that we'll
just try we'll see we'll see where we
get I'm not optimistic about it but you
know we'll see what happens so I'm gonna
go ahead and get started looking at what
that would entail and if we go back to
the way that we had so our code we kind
of wired up everything and it's we can
flip it between the two but we do
really have an answer for the raycast
path yet cuz we don't really have a way
to sample the rate the diffuse lighting
so if we go in here and we change to
doing our test lighting so when we look
at the test lighting pass and you know I
don't I don't even know why we have this
anymore
we can just get rid a lot of this stuff
I don't think any of this stuff makes
any sense we don't need any of this
stuff do we yeah none of this stuff
another stuff ISM is necessary what of
what is all this for I don't even know
okay right any stuff it's going away
it's gone so anyway if we go in here and
we just change our code at the immediate
moment to use the diffuse sort of I'm
sorry the the the point radio like the
the sphere radius light so we're just
stuffing the values in then what we
should be able to see is when we
actually run it in here so right here
what we should be able to see when we
run it is we should be able to to see
that it's you know specular everywhere
right and so when we hop out to you know
a larger room or something like we can
do out here so when we hop out to a
larger room and we take a look you can
kind of see right that the lighting is
very specular right it's it's responding
to me all over the place as I move the
camera around and so if we wanted to get
the filtering in there what we would
probably primarily need to do here right
is say all right what if we wanted this
light to now be a diffuse light so that
when we sample it we're actually getting
diffuse lighting not specular lighting
right so we want to be able to produce
out of our out of our specular version
we want to actually do that summation
down so what would have to happen there
is you know you can see us doing a loop
here where we output everything you can
see us doing the the voxel offset right
so that's the actual edgeville there but
right here here's us writing into the
output voxel and you can see here
grabbing out of the cell and writing it
in or you know doing the sphere version
right either way it's just the test code
it's not good code and then we output to
the voxel the information that we have
right here and so the difference would
be instead of actually outputting to the
voxel here and an actual thing as we get
it
what we will be doing instead is
building up these values and outputting
them to do you know effectively a
summation right so we'd have a temporary
buffer where we produce all of these
light values by you know either doing
them here or outputting them right and
then what we would do when we write them
out is we would just go ahead from there
and do the sort of the summation on it
now in order to avoid us having to
actually do sort of two different passes
here what I'd like to do is change the
way that we've got this code set up so
that rather than having the test
lighting happen in here I'd rather have
it so that actually we go back to this
method where we've got a test cast from
probes versus a compute light
propagation and we already and we always
actually send it down with the transfer
code I think that would be preferable
right and so if in here we said all
right like in test cast from probes
which is in here if we actually use this
code to to generate the stuff for us and
not this code here I think that would be
the first step so we could move like
basically this code out to here and make
sure that works reasonably so you know
[Music]
switching to this and this
I want to go ahead and get get that
transfer ready all right so you can see
here we've got some weird weirdness go
in there I don't know what that's from
exactly
in fact that's kind of that's kind of
strange what what is that how how is
that how is that producing such a tight
well that's weird how is that producing
such a tight interpolation around around
the edge that's kind of peculiar to be
honest with you I wouldn't have thought
we could have got such a tight
interpolation out of the edge oh you
know why that is I think that's cuz this
one doesn't like point then yeah yeah
yeah that's why cuz it doesn't point the
normals at it but isn't that weird like
why are we getting that weird and what's
what's that weird sort of like cut in
the middle there I'm not sure what
that's from that's just pretty peculiar
right I don't know if it's some kind of
map sampling weirdness or something
so anyway I'd like to get that working
more reliably and that way when we write
the sphere so I want to still be able to
do this thing so I want to be able to
still do this in that in the in the
tests and code but I want to get rid of
this pass and so we only ever do a pass
where we actually produce the diffuse or
whatever we want to send to the card
right but I don't want to have this
separate debug pass so I want to always
write through in tests castrum probes
again I'm not sure what this is doing
that's weird there you can see it
writing the light see versus the clamp
see here in doing spam voxel but I'm not
sure why it's producing drastically
different results in that sort of weird
line case but what I'd like to do here
is again so where this happens right
kind of see it going on here instead of
calling spam voxel what I'd like to do
is
is basically have another one of these
so instead of test castrum probe there'd
be something else which is like you know
test lightsphere something something
like this and then this code here just
exists to fill the voxel itself so
essentially like you know we would do
exactly the code we're doing using the
hot damn and everything we would come
through here fill in the hole like light
thing
no checkerboard and no transfer but
instead now we will look up the voxel
cell and instead of going this way we'll
go the other way right so this just
allows us to write into the voxel our
test pattern so that we're always
picking it up from the test pattern
later if that makes sense right all
right so I think that's all we really
need there and that produces our test
sphere pattern so we could get rid of it
here and we could call that we could
leave it on transfer right and instead
of test cast from probes we can call
test light sphere with the solution and
have that work now we will need the hot
dim because we call that right well
we'll need all the stuff that's here so
we need like the light solution in the
light position in that that junk so I'm
gonna go ahead and grab that out here
we'll grab this all this stuff like that
and the hot dim should be up here
somewhere know where it is there it is
and we just need the lighting solution
here and then I'll just grab all the
things that we don't have
we need commands in hot dim
[Music]
yeah group and light UVW where is light
UVW being used right now all right there
okay all right what else
so setup that's just something we get
off the render command group there we go
all right so I think that should give us
what we need I hope anyway there we go
and so now inside that code we should
get our light test and we do like that's
exactly what we were getting before
right so now that that's been isolated I
can clean this code up and get rid of a
lot of this stuff right so now we can
just say all right we don't actually
need in fact the if I'm not mistaken I
cut that out as well yes so in in voxel
dem can just be placed in here as well
so this code can now you know get rid of
all of this stuff right
it won't need any of these things and it
just needs the transfer code which we
can now improve as well so we can nuke
that we can delete all of this like so
and we can just make these be direct
assignments
right so now we can see what that copy
is actually doing right that's all it's
gonna do and we can get rid of a bunch
of these values so we don't need any of
this stuff or any of this stuff and now
we're good all right so now you can see
we cleaned up that code nicely so we've
isolated that test code so it's you know
it's easier to read and easier for us to
work with as well and so now we just
need to go okay what would we actually
put in here to create more diffuse
lighting so in this stage right here
where we're actually outputting these
things that's the part we would actually
need to know this just copies edges in
the light voxels so whatever we put in
the edge copy will work just fine so we
just need this part to do something
different meaning when it writes this
out it needs to do some kind of
summation here or something right all
right
so our biggest problem here again is
just how many of these things we have to
do so if we want to actually put out 8
by 8 of these then you know this is the
loop that writes out 8 by 8 so this is
the you know this loops over 8 things
this loops over 8 things so 64 total on
the interior and each one of these wants
to figure out what the lighting
contribution would have been for every
other one of them and so if you look at
what this would look like worst case
right it's just more loops right so in
other words it would look more like this
where there's a sampling from here like
so and so for every one of these we need
to sample every one of these right and
again you can see why this is so
terrible we know that this voxel cell is
shared so we're talking about the same
cell regardless right we're always
summing inside the cell and we're
summing on each of these we know that
when we write it out it'll just look
like this so we know that that's the
case the question is what are we
actually writing out so if we actually
did want to sum this thing we need to
know like for each one of these things
that were summing we need to know what
the contribution is for every other
thing now again I'm just gonna do the
crappiest possible thing here but for
each of the 64 outputs we would need to
know the weights of the 64 inputs a lot
of which would be 0 half of which would
be 0 right we're close to zero so if we
were to do a table that just told us
this it would be 4096 entries which is
not much right so again the the actual
like information we need for the
transfer even if we don't compress it at
all is actually fine it's just the
number of operations we actually have to
do that's bad because you know it's 4096
operations per mass
that we have to account for right 64
outputs with 64 input spur not great so
anyway if we want to do that I say we
just do it because that's you know the
easiest thing to do and so what we would
want here is some kind of a weight map
something that you know lets us figure
out what the weight map would be so
something like this so we'd say all
right we've got these weight maps so
let's look one up
we know we're trying to look up the TYT
X weight map and then in here what we
want to do is say let's sum these up so
we have our light results I guess we
could even just call this what it is so
we've got our light C and I mean we
could just have our light D as well but
again I don't really care about that so
I'm not gonna look at it yet and for
each one of these I'm just gonna sum in
the sampled one so I'm going to say the
light C equals the weight
times so right and so you can see here
you can see why this is so you know we
talk about order notation stuff like
this expensive is something right an
order notation is usually just another
way of saying how many loops do you have
and what do they loop over right they're
the same thing effectively so you can
see here we've got a Z loop a while loop
and X loop a TYT x sys X and this is why
this is the kind of thing that makes me
so nervous that much like we have so
many loops we have a voxel which is huge
like Z times y times X just a lot of
order there we've got a texture map for
each one that we're filling in which is
you know T Y times T X and then for each
one of those we have to loop over every
other element so it's s y times X X
right and by the way this is often times
we hear about separable filters right
one of the reasons why you so often hope
that you can make your filter be
separable which in this case may be we
can write and we're gonna look at that
for sure is because if you can break
even one of these loops out like if I
could just even do this which is what
you're doing with a separable filter do
the Y pass first then the X Pass for
example if you can figure out a way to
just even do that which maybe we can
that turns a multiplied into an ad so
instead of 8 times 8 operations it would
be 8 plus 8 operations it goes from 64
to 16 right very good so you can see why
when you talk about filtering that's
intercept well people talk about
separable filters a separable filter is
the ability to take two nested loops and
move them into two sequential loops and
if the number is small let's say you
have two is the number
well you don't care because 2 times 2 is
equal to 2 plus 2 right so a separable
filter doesn't buy anything well the
number is large 8 16 a thousand it's
really big deal a thousand times a
thousand is so much bigger than a
thousand plus a thousand right
so that's why separable filters are so
important it's tree pollen season by the
way so I am like completely allergy I'm
just a running faucet all right so
anyway all we would need to do to do
this is build the weights table right
because you look here and you see okay
we've got this whole thing compiling
just fine there's nothing to it we just
don't know where we're getting the
weights from this can be initialized to
zero because it just is a sum and so at
that point we just need to know what
this thing looks like so if I to find
this thing well it's pretty pretty
obvious it's just an 8 by 8 matrix right
it's just the same as these things
except it's missing the border because
it doesn't need the border right and in
fact when actually when I look at this I
suppose since it doesn't need the border
I should just do this right you know I'm
saying because you don't we don't
actually need that border to be there so
I can do that in one of two ways I'm not
sure which ways is easier but off you go
you know what probably this way is
easier for the come time I feel like a
Pilar not for me obviously none of them
matter to me I can do them anyway but
that's probably the easiest for the
compiler I would guess right so we loop
over we sample everything and we sum it
up and then we write it out and that's
all we would really need and then we
just need some kind of a notion of what
the heck this thing is and so in here we
need the weights and again like if we
did want to do the D I could even do the
D here
like this so I just pull that weight
expression out and just multiply the two
the color component the depth component
separately multiplied by W and then you
fall out you've got both of them and you
just write them back right so again
really straightforward not a lot to it
it's not gonna be efficient or good but
it at least like let us play with this
and see if it works so at that point we
can say all right we just need this
weight map and you know we know it looks
like this right it doesn't have the
border because we don't care now another
way to look at this would be we could
also just include the border and the way
we would include the border is just
write the same weights into the border
region in other words this loop can
write our border for us too
because it's just a general look up so
we could have just done the whole thing
I'm not gonna do that just yet but when
we actually go to do this we may find
that we want this loop to write the
border and the way we would do that
right is just set the weights so that
the border pixels equal have the same
exact weight map as whatever the thing
is they were going to mirror right I
wish I had more water right now so again
pretty straightforward not a lot of
complexity here so now all we need to do
is just actually pre compute some of
these for us to use so we've got our
sampling Hemisphere for example and now
we would also have our weight maps so
I'm gonna call this diffuse weight map
like so and the same thing would would
happen here we would have just like
we've got these
like so and we wouldn't use all of them
I also guess I guess that's what we
actually want I think about it but we
might as well leave it like this so the
lookup is is works the way it should we
don't want this to keep reading because
we're changing the sizes of things so at
that point I think we're good and now we
need a loop at startup time we only need
to initialize these once they stay the
same forever because the directions are
not changing so now we just need to
produce this wait map and all the wait
map is is saying what the transmission
rate is between these directions it's
saying for this incoming for this
outgoing Direction what would it need to
sum across all of the incoming
directions to produce the correct result
right and so what I'd like to do is make
a thing that's going to loop over these
at an it time and produce them so at an
it time when we actually start the you
know the lightning computation will
actually say when we start the when we
actually do the initialization of the
lighting solution right here we could
actually do this so we can have a thing
here that's like you know build diffuse
light Maps and this will tell us that
mapping so when we call build diffuse
light Maps I'll pass the solution we'll
have a little function here that will do
it like so and all we need to do now is
loop over these values to init almost
exactly the same way so like literally
this code that we're using to actually
do the sum we just want to do the exact
same thing so we'd come in here and
instead now what we're going to be doing
is accumulating weights for each of
these so what we want to do is say all
right let's loop through and we'll
compute each of these weight maps in
turn right so we're gonna go ahead and
grab the weight map for this thing and
then we're gonna go through each of
these and write them out so we're gonna
let compute awaiting for each of these
somehow right and write it back in
okay
so exactly the same way as we were doing
here we're gonna go ahead and and try to
produce that light map now what we know
is that we've we want we have in here
like a way that we're actually producing
what vectors correspond to which voxels
right so we kind of have both of those
equations in here already and that's
what we're actually going to need so
when we look at where's our actual so
here's our right our get octahedral
offset for a particular direction so
what we effectively want is the opposite
of this code and we already have this
code right we in our lighting when we're
doing our test our test sphere oops
so in here where we've got our test
light sphere our test light sphere code
we want that to to mirror it so the
exact thing that it's doing this this
nonsense here where we've got like unit
vector from octahedral for the sample
dur we want that to be something we can
call in general right so we want to
think here that's like direction from
txt Y right and that's just gonna do
this exact code right exactly this code
like that and it's going to return that
sample Durer to whoever inputted the txt
Y so in here there's a T X T Y that gets
sent in we do a bunch of nonsense and
out it comes at the end of the day right
so that means in here we would just do
v3 sample dirt equals blah like that and
that should work right meaning we should
we should get exactly one from that
because all we did was replace we just
pulled some code out and now we call it
so that test fair should work and so now
in here we can use these
to pull out the directions for our
corresponding samples so here we're
going to have a lighting direction
coming from the TX dy here so this is
the out you know the outgoing vector and
here's our incoming vector right so now
we have what the incoming vector for
light that we're sampling and the
outgoing vector that we're trying to
transmit along and so now we just need
the cosine wave between them so if we
take that inner product of the outgoing
in the incoming when we do that now we
have that cosine fall-off but of course
it can be negative so we just want to
clamp it and now we've got our
transmission right so there's our cosine
weighted fall-off so now we're building
all of those Maps so we now know what
the diffuse contribution will be from
each of those and if we run the code now
despite the fact that we'll probably run
so slowly is to be unusable we should
actually have diffuse lighting from our
light right and you can already see that
although we don't know if it's correct
or not you can already see that it does
actually look like diffuse lighting not
specular lighting now right kind of see
there's our sphere and again it's just
so dog slow right and this is because
we're throwing all of this stuff at the
CPU and it's very hard for it to deal
with that number of flops especially
when we're not paralyzing it now we
could if this is all we needed to do we
could in theory be okay because we just
thread this and probably call it a day
right and so let me go ahead and hop
over here
see if I can actually rotate around you
and so now we can see that like hey
we're sampling the lighting with a
specular bounce right so we still are
doing quote-unquote specular lighting in
a sense like we are sampling the
lighting in a in a directional sense but
the lighting itself the surfaces have a
diffuse reflectance function right so
now we get what I mean
honestly what kind of looks like pretty
reasonable lighting right not with any
shadows right but it looks like a pretty
reasonable sphere light quite good in
fact right I don't see a lot of
artifacts from the octahedral really so
you know good on us now I don't know we
might have some bugs in there I'm not
sure right I have no idea like you know
I really couldn't tell you like to what
extent we've got issues with the with
the computation in there so maybe it's
totally wrong but at least we now see
like hey yeah it kind of looks that
looks sort of reasonable if I look out
here we do get a sphere of fall-off on
it right I have no idea what that is
over there that's kind of weird don't
you think so is our voxel wrapping
because that's actually if since our
lighting voxel ends here
I believe I wonder if that's what that
is I don't know what that is then we'll
have to find out what that like look at
that it's just our voxel copied over for
lighting so I guess our voxel must be
set to wrap not clamp or something I'm
guessing I'm not sure cuz there's no
lighting information out there at all I
don't think anyway so uh yeah like I
said our main problem with this is just
speed and you know it may be possible
for us to speed this up
I have to think about like how we would
do that obviously we can make it for
wide and speeded up for X and then we
could thread it and you know I don't
know maybe that's what we want to do I'm
not entirely certain what we want to do
there exactly but you know the other
thing I can do too is I can turn on the
drawing so we can look at the results of
this blurring which might help us a
little bit probably not a lot because
there's not a lot of it's not gonna be
immediately intuitive what should or
shouldn't be happening so you know if I
turn on drawing the actual buffers I
don't know that we're gonna learn
anything from seeing them right you know
there's the the the blurred buffer so
what I will say is they look to be look
overly bright right and I guess that
doesn't seem wrong though because they
should be
I mean it's adding all of that light
together and it's supposed to be and
this buffer is just drawing 0 to 1
whereas our lighting right now is not on
0 to 1 in a particular way so I think
it's all probably fine would be my
assumption right like I don't think
there's anything weird about that um and
it looks alright you know again I don't
think there's much we can glean from
that because it's like well I mean is it
wrong or is it not I don't know you know
it looks fine it's hard to say yeah um
so again don't really know not sure what
to make of it exactly yeah
really couldn't tell you but again so if
we do want to actually speed that up we
could actually just speed this up to a
certain extent and it's not like super
hard to think about how we would do that
so remember the only part you know the
slow part is this right here and there's
you know
probably a fair number of things he
could do to make this faster at the very
least sorry not that that's test
lightsphere this at the very least we
could do it for wide and you know that
would cut down on our iteration pretty
dramatic dramatically presumably I mean
literally just for wide just the outer
loop presumably would be sufficient like
just like the TX right so do for for
with the and and then we would cut down
that number of iterations pretty
dramatically so we could try that I'm
trying to think if there's anything
weird about doing that and I don't think
so because then you just have two of
these right so we could just try just
just doing that doing doing this for
wide on the outer loop leaving this code
exactly the same making the diffuse wait
map just load for wide so there's just
like to you know this just happens twice
right and then the voxel offset see part
of things we would only computes we
would only compute one and we'd write
out in chunks of four so I feel like
that's probably a reasonable thing to do
because it doesn't change the algorithm
at all like literally at all I don't
think all of this would still happen
exactly the same way and the only
difference would be that these two this
would be a four right so it would be
like that and you would
well hold on a second
so to look up the light see where we're
sampling here so that's not entirely
true
no it is never mind so you would
basically just loft this up to four wide
right so you'd load one sample in for
each of these loft it up to four wide
multiplied by the weights that go into
each of these and then each of these
would just be four wide right that would
be it
pretty sure and then when you write it
out you just need to write out four wide
but that would more or less be it so
when you produce the C and D offsets
here like that and then you go to write
these out what you'd actually be doing
is is this alright give me you know the
the commands light voxel C give me the
like float pointers for these things
right and at that point you should be
okay the only weird part about this at
that point right so now you're just
doing this is convincing it not to use
aligned stores so I may have to write
this code myself rather than do it the
way that I'm doing it here because we're
gonna render the problem with with it's
gonna generate a line stores probably
here and then it's gonna crash if it I
don't know how to you know I don't know
if I can convince it not to do that
maybe I can we'll see
but anyway so if we just do this
right so now we have a TX 4
and the TX 4 is just gonna be - it's
gonna be 0 1 and done right it's gonna
look up weights they're gonna be four
wide it's gonna do the summation four
wide and then write it out four wide I
think that just speeds it up by 4x I
think that's my claim the TX here is
just one it's just you know we don't
we're not gonna actually advance that
value at all
these are addresses and so now just
confuse map itself loading that out is
just going to be you know loading a the
f32 4x out of it we're just gonna have
to change where we store that but other
than that we're good right so yeah this
is supposed to be a v3 4x but other than
that think we're all right
so on the storage front I'd have to
think about that part because the v3 4x
so
so I guess that part's not as easy
unfortunately right because the packing
order is wrong I want to say we're
loading up light color vectors but we
actually want to write out RGB RGB RGB
RGB right and that's a little bit of an
issue for us because we don't actually
want to compute in that way we want to
compute ar-ar-ar-ar gggg bbbb just
because that's the thing that would be
in multiples of 4 if we did RGB it's
only threes which is you know less good
so that does create a bit of a problem
for us I'm not sure what the right
solution that that is we obviously could
just leave the maps that way but it
doesn't seem like a very good idea so
this is a little bit nastier I'm trying
to think if there is a way I could have
done it to avoid that problem well so
maybe there kind of is
it's just kind of a little bit ugly I
mean I suppose you could say look it's
eight wide times three components
that's 24 divide that by four and you
just get six so you could just have six
weights you load yeah but that doesn't
really work either yes so I'm not sure
hmm not sure how we would do this
exactly trying to think if there's any
other way to do it then makes some sense
yeah that could still be done for wide
easily I'm wondering what would happen
if we did the very most outer loop for
wide so you just load four rows and
composite the rows and then uncompelled
doesn't seem like a good idea though
so I think what we'd want to do here is
fuse the depth and the color together
then so we'd have four wide I mean that
really seems like what you'd want to do
and the because that way you get even
spacing of everything unfortunately like
for some reason they didn't want to do
that in the actual paper they always
kept the depth and the RGB separate and
to be honest we don't really know if
we're ever gonna use depth so that's
kind of another problem right if you
fuse them together though you'd be
really happy because then everything
would be a 4 wide packet and you'd be
happy you know off the races
[Music]
well I mean I guess the one thing we
could do easily that we could just fall
back on for now is without doing any
other work we could just load these as a
v3 4x I'm sorry as an f32 4x and do the
ops on them that way right and then when
you write him out you just only go by
threes we could do that and then you'd
get 3x instead of 4x feet up from it and
you know I don't know to what extent
that's you know enough but I'm just not
seeing I'm not seeing the obvious way to
to make this work other than just by
Swizzle Adada if the data was planar you
know what I just typed in is all we need
but with the data not being planar it's
packed not sure how to get around it now
what we can do is you know we can
Swizzle it out so we could load it
Swizzle it and load it on Swizzle it but
that seems really bad too so I don't
know
let's think about this everyone sit in a
moment of silence and consider your sim
D choices
you
so it's worth noting that we would only
Swizzle on output because since we're
summing here you only have to swizzle
when you get to here so maybe that's
fine I mean this whistles aren't that
expensive so maybe that's really only
you need hard to say right but that
would look like this so we have the desk
color and the dusty and we're writing
them in here right and when we actually
do this and we go through here what we'd
be saying is all right
we're doing the light color and we are
gonna sum the light color for four
vector for four elements at a time and
then we need to write out those four
when we get to here right so I don't
know that there is a Swizzle on a vector
right now that swaps it around to the
other way but that's what we actually
want it to do since we can't quite do
that and we need to write this out what
we kind of want to do here is say like
alright we've got our two ik r TX 4 and
when we write out for wides here we need
to take and write three of them so it
would really be this
you know I'm saying so what we need to
do is write out these in chunks and we
need the Swizzle chunks to line up we
could probably make this just a product
you know a thing that works on these
v.34 X's where you just say look I need
you to swizzle this thing and that's a
known operation so we just write them
out that way and in fact I suppose at
that point we could actually just do it
this way again like I had it so maybe we
just do it like this so we have a v3 for
X we write it out this way but we need
to do like a transpose on this thing and
then this transpose on our handmade sim
D I guess that's in all in line so I
guess we actually will leave everything
in line that's gonna want to take a
value and it's gonna want Swizzle the
components and just so I can show you
what we're actually doing here I'll draw
it out what we want to be able to do
here is take each of the blackboard up
so what we want to do here is we want to
say okay we've got something that stores
data in the following pattern
ar-ar-ar-ar gggg bbbb right and each of
these is effectively like a sim Delaine
right so each of these is basically like
four floats for floats four floats and
you know they're in registers or
something right XM m 0 XM m 1 XM m to
something like this right and so what we
want to do now is we want to swap these
out so that we get a different pattern
you know what we're trying to do is like
some nasty you know Swizzle operation
here where we get RGB RGB RGB so if we
look at what these sub index - this is
our byte order here right so you have 12
of these 12 floats going in that order
what we want to end up with in memory
order again this is memory order reading
in memory order because remember if you
actually look at the way we write things
often times for registers we go the
other way round so it would be inverted
if we were looking at it little endian
we'd read that way and it would be our 0
over here so we want to interleave these
so that we would end up with our 0 B 0 G
I'm sorry our 0 G 0 B 0 right and then
right here we would now want to put our
1 so in a single sim d'Alene we're
taking like 0 oh sorry
0 1 2 3 0 1 2 3 and oh no I never do
that way so we want the first of each of
these to go in here and then we want you
know the next one to be sort of half in
in half and half in the first register
house in a second right and then we I
don't know why keep writing be next one
be one that was right
R - G - and that ends this one and then
we have our B 3 r r3 g 3 B 3 so this is
what we actually want we want to be able
to Swizzle these together and so what we
need is some kind of operation that lets
us select these things from you know
composites and luckily for us as you can
see there's a rather relatively simple
interleave because you know at no point
do we have to pull from more than one
source if you have to pull from multiple
sources like 3 4 5 it's pretty nasty of
course if you only have 4 lanes with
floats that's not super possible but if
for four wide anyway but you know you
could imagine if each one of these had
to come from a different input that
would be bad but for to the rest there's
only 2 and most Intel instructions that
involve Swizzle intact - inputs and
produce an output so we're in good shape
we should be able to do something that
allows us to pick our 0 G 0 B 0 and then
our 1 right
relatively cleanly I guess well though
now I think about it we do have to do
one intermediate step because if you
look we actually do have 3 nevermind
this G here right makes a problem for us
so we're gonna have to do some series of
steps we probably can't do one
instruction for each because if you look
at how these are broken up here we
wouldn't yeah there would be no real way
to do that at least not that I can see
right
yeah there's there's no real way we can
we can make that work it's not that I
can tell ya um so that's how we would
have to switch Alon right now the only
other thing that I'm wondering as I'm
looking at this - I'm just thinking well
the way that we were doing this here we
just know that we have to write out
these values and if we look at what's
actually coming in when we load up these
components I'm just wondering is there
any reason we can't just make these
weights pull the correct stuff in so
that's already in this order because
there any reason r1 can't just be there
so I mean just looking at this I'm
thinking maybe like if we just have the
weight Maps whistled itself does that
just produce the right answer here you
know I'm saying if we build the weight
map so the weight map is just written so
that it produces the values in this
order like why did I think we couldn't
do that cuz this just starts zero it
doesn't have to load anything it's just
gonna sum up these values
shouldn't it be able to solve any values
so now and I think about it I think
maybe I'm just being stupid because I
was sort of thinking well we loaded
values in but we didn't load any values
in right there was no actual loading so
I'm wondering if this can just be made
to do it so if we load a v3 for X here
what are we actually getting out of this
thing right well when we load that let
me see where that actually goes
when we load this in right that's just a
broadcast to each of these so I would
think that we could just make sure that
the broadcast does what we need it to do
let me think about this
because this I mean essentially this
part I guess would have to do what the
the loads per Lane right
so yeah
yeah if we just sew here let's just
think about this so if we're going to
load these here's our light C for this
cell right what we're loading in here
and we can load this in any pattern we
can load out of this as actual Swizzle
values if we want to right so meaning
right now we're loading this in
broadcasting X Y Z but we could load
this and not broadcast right so instead
what we could do is we could load in the
source this right here which we don't
really have a name for I suppose but
this source here the sample we could
load that in so we have basically like
you know our s GS BS and I guess it's 0
0 0 RS 1 right so we can load it so that
we get the RGB and our for this for you
know the the cell here we could load it
so that that comes in aligned this way
and then when we sum these together we
could leave them in say we're still
gonna have to swivel this because we
need to get this over here for a
summation right
so it's really this load here that's the
problem because if we do a load
broadcast here so that we can sum
everything up then everything that's
what makes these lanes come out lined up
RGB right that's this is the part that
does that and once we do that then our
light color will always be in those same
lanes obviously the light D is
irrelevant because that's just there's
no packing order for those can't say I
can think of a better way around this at
the moment
maybe someone out there is thought of a
way already but I don't see one it's
sort of the standard problem you run
into when you have these four wide
things right like you tend not to want
to operate on them in the way that the
sim D wants this is why GPUs have all
the swizzles built in and sadly Intel
didn't and here we are but yeah not
seeing it so let me go back to the
transpose just to see if we're gonna do
with that if we want to do this
transpose so if we just did a basic
select to get our initial values here so
we can do each of these in two selects
basically right
I assume let me take a quick look at
what we've got four options oops I
wanted that to be a new window doesn't
look possible how about this there we go
so if we take a look at what we've got
and if I restrict us just to you know
the basics here I don't know what we
allow ourselves to use but assuming that
we're gonna do shuffles
you know here are some options so we've
got the main shuffle which would be like
this one for example
chef PS and chef PS is the one that
allows us to pick from the inputs in a
not particularly great way like to be
completely honest if you look at the way
that chef PS works you can kind of see
that the the issue with it is its lane
constricted so when you issue a chef
PS you end up being able to pick
whatever you want from a the first
parameter in the first and second lanes
and then whatever you want from the
second parameter in the next two lanes
but you can't just arbitrarily go from
any lane to any lane right you can if
you pass the same parameter twice that
works but you can't otherwise right and
so in order to do one of these what you
would assume you want to do you want to
try we know we can't do it in one
shuffle what we want to try and do is
get it so that eat you know we could do
it in maybe six shuffles right so we
want to end up with RGB r RG RG b RG BG
b RGB as our you know four results and
we want to start with this so we want to
be able to go you know do that Swizzle
and so if you look at what we probably
want to do and we have some other
options too one of the things that's
worth noting is that there is if you
don't want to do a shuffle there is
other ways you can do it there's these
things called unpacks and packs don't
actually remember how these things are
set up let's see
yeah so they also give you these and the
way that these work is they interleave
these things together which is more sort
of what we're trying to do here you can
see how these work like interleaved D
words right and the way this works is it
takes the source from 0 to 31 first and
then the desk from 0 to 31 right and
then the the same thing from 1 &amp; 2 again
from 63 to 3 to 6 332 right and so what
that's designed to do is that's just
designed to combine like the two vectors
into into one that goes in alternating
order so if you look at how these bytes
are arranged if you take 32 I'm sorry
these bits are arranged if you take 32
bits out of each this does sort of what
we're looking for if you apply it
repeatedly so for example if we have
this as one input
and this is memory order going this way
again it's it's hard to write these
sometimes because memory order goes this
way but processor order goes the other
way so yeah what can you do if we
actually call an inter leave on these
what we would get is our 0 G 0 R 1 G 1 R
2 G 2 R 3 G 3 right and so if you look
at what would happen if we call the
unpack low right which unpacks the low
part of these we would get this and if
we called unpack high which impacts the
high part of these we would get this
right because it takes one from the
first one one from the second one from
the first one for the second and again
takes the low ones for unpack low then
if we call the unpack high we'd get this
and that starts to look pretty good
right this is not what we want but it's
close right and so then the question is
well what do we do to get the bees in
there and then you would say well okay
we know now what are we looking for at
the end well at the end we said we were
looking for RGB R right so we're looking
for R 0 G 0 B 0 R 1 right
well we've got our G 0 and we've got R 1
so the only thing that we're actually
looking for in this case is is the you
know the B 0 which has to come
unfortunately from another vector right
so that's like well not really quite
what we were looking for for that
particular unpack because it's like how
are we gonna get that in there if we
unpacked with B right so let's suppose
we start here and then we do the unpack
again with B we end up with not what we
want because we'd end up with R 0 B 0 G
0 B 1 right
and that doesn't help us either
you know I'm saying because that's not
again we've got sort of a mismatch here
so we need to figure out some other way
of getting that in there we now have we
do have a vector right that has
everything we need in it if it was
combined with B 0 so if we then did I'm
sorry with the B vector right so if we
had some way of taking the first two
then just one right which is the b0 and
then sliding that RR one over so if we
could pick arbitrarily for them we'd be
super happy but again we can't and again
this is just this is why like sse is
terrible right no one should have to do
any of the thinking that I'm doing right
we just have these three registers and
we want them to go to those three
registers it's just a giant Swizzle you
want this to just be road but SSE is
like a horrible instruction set just
absolutely terrible and so as a result
you spend literally all your time
drawing crap out like this eventually if
you do it enough which I don't you start
to learn the tricks like oh okay no
that's just I can do like you know this
unpack and that unpack and then we're
all good or whatever right so anyway
let's keep trying a couple other things
let's suppose instead of doing it that
way
we take the bees instead right so now
let's unpack these and we do an unpack
on those we'd get our zero right B 0 R 1
B 1 right so that'd be an unpacked low
on those we get this vector and remember
what we were looking for is how do we go
from this to our G R 0 G 0 B 0 R 1 right
how do we get there and the answer is
well now at least if we did R &amp; B
together right so the first and the
third instead of the first in the second
component now at least we know that an
unpack operation with something and we
don't know what that thing is would
actually put R 0 and B 0 in the right
locations right so if you magically had
something here that was G 0 R 1 which
who the heck knows how we would ever get
that but if magically we could right if
somehow you could get that vector well
at least this part's correct and then
the unpack would produce that right but
of course in our situation we're like we
don't know how we'd ever get that right
so how would we ever produce G 0 R 1
look where would that come from well a G
0 first component anything that would
unpack or shuffle would be able to do
that if Jesus if the green vector was
the first one the problem is this R 1
like where's the R 1 going to come from
because our ones the second component of
this thing and there's no way to get the
sick of one of this thing in there
because an unpack would stick an R 0
there right which doesn't help us and a
shuffle can't pull from that lane right
because if the G 0 has to go first well
it can't pull from there so again really
not a lot we can do there right we're
kind of back to square one there's no
obvious way we're gonna be able to do an
unpack there so again really not great
pretty tricky to see how this would play
out and this is what again why I say
like SSE terrible instruction set neon
has none of these problems neon just has
this whistles built-in you can do
anything you want with that if I
remember correctly even unload it can
just do this whistle for you in a store
could unsold
just the obvious thing you would do
until didn't do it because they were
just like oh all programmers can just
convert everything over it too packed
and you're like no they can't that's
very hard to do especially when you're
working with a GPU that expects to
sample things in the other way but yeah
anyway all right so we still have a
problem here it's like can we get this
down to two I don't still don't know if
we can obviously we could get it down to
three that's not so hard because at that
point you can just literally do three
selects I have three chefs and you're
probably okay but you can see why I'm
worried about this right because I can't
quite figure out how to get it down just
to two so if we unpacked this way not
clear exactly what we would be doing
there if we unpack the other way wasn't
clear what we'd be doing here
so now we go well alright what if we did
a non interleaved unpack because what we
can also do is let's say we do an unpack
hi PD right so PS right unpacks per
element so it's 0 0 1 1 2 2 3 3 PD
unpacks pairs of elements so if we
wanted to we could produce a vector
that's R 0 R 1 B 0 B 1 right we can
unpack this way
as well like by pairs so the question is
could we use that to get us something
that we need right and again it's not
clear whether it can or can't but we can
experiment and find out right so let's
suppose that we wanted to try and get
something that will get us closer to our
RGB our pattern that we want here
what would we actually do to try and
make that
happen well if we unpacked our arse and
jeez together it doesn't seem I mean
well I mean maybe it's the intermediate
stage hard to say but again the main
issue that we're gonna face here is
where this r1 is going to come from
because anything else we do with the RGS
and B's actually makes a regional amount
of sense the question is how does the
one get into this position right because
no amount of unpacks is gonna help you
there so in a sense this one sort of
looks like a problem that we're gonna
have to do deal with you know a chef and
the chef is Lane based this way right so
the inputs have to stay on the side of
the bar that they're on right so the
question is what can we do that would be
efficient that would somehow put the R
on this side for this guy right so the R
goes into that location just somewhere
in the second side of things with a B's
with a b0 so somehow an r0 r1 and a b0
would end up in the same side of
something right to allow that that stuff
to happen or alternatively a g0 and an
r1 like is there any way a g0 and an r1
can come out in that way right both both
of those be on the same side of
something it doesn't matter what same
side they're on by the way they just
have to get it together somehow right in
some way and again I don't know I guess
let's try it so let's suppose that we
were going to do some kind yeah like
what would we do I don't even know it
seems like it just an impossibility that
that's ever going to happen
in two steps it's not that I can see so
because you have to think about it right
let's just say we ever wanted these two
to come out in the same lane ever right
I'm not sure how you break that sequence
right it just you fundamentally can't so
you know you've got a b0 and what I want
to do is I want to say okay is there any
way to get this and this to come out so
they're like here or here right so you
know in a way to combine these two
things um and I don't know I don't even
know if we if we extended ourselves out
I don't know if we'd even have any
better options there I don't think we do
right yeah because I don't think there's
much zero select what's that
it's that function call that does the
Select
where's it only in a VX
now there's that there's a select call
in here by just I'm blanking on the name
it's not extract it is called blend
that's what they called it don't ask me
why
so if we were out at SSE for which I
don't know if we want to be although
it's probably safe to be now we could
also use a blend function for that and
what those do is those do let you use
combinations of lanes in the same Lane
so you could do a blend where if you
have this you could get a B 0 R 1 in
here by using a blend I don't think
there's any way to get B 0 R 1 without
that in one instruction I don't think
there's any way to pull the second one
of one thing and the first of another
into the first like two elements am I
wrong about that is there any other way
to do that I don't think there is
and I don't think packs would help us
here right because those are all gonna
contract the values which doesn't help
so I'm pretty sure only unpacks help us
unpack some shuffles anyway
so I don't know I guess we've got two
ways of doing this I can so I can think
of how to do it that way right because
then it's pretty easy I think let's see
let's see if we have a if we used blend
let's see if we could do it in a low
number of things so to get our 0 G 0 B 0
R 1 we would have to do even that I'm
it's still pretty hard right because I
think you would waste yeah I don't know
if you can even do it even with that
because I think you would waste one of
your things doing the in the transpose
because you'd end up with an R one in
two different places right but we can
sort of look at that a little bit more
carefully so if we did look at what we
would need here let's just think about
what happens so if we wanted all of our
values the next one would be G 1 B 1 R 2
G 2 right
so our 2g2 looks like just an unpack
right so an unpack hi would be our 2 G 2
R 3 G 3 right and the last one is B 3
oops be 2 R 3 G 3 B 3 right that's the
last one and so getting the are the G 3
B 3 that looks like an unpack on that B
2 R 3 again so these are always gonna be
the problem show children right it's
basically this vector is lovely because
it's aligned right G 1 B 1 R 2 G to the
each lane here is the same index so G 3
B 3 and R 2 G 2 G 1 B 1 R 0 G 0 those
are all much more straightforward to
produce because they're on the same
lanes it's the two threes and the zero
ones here that are happening that are
kind of ugly
right cuz otherwise I think this
wouldn't be so so heinous so anyway
we're gonna end up with a B 0 G 0 I
think either way we do this all right so
let's just start seeing if we can
permute these down so if we want an R 0
G 0 that's going to be an unpack our G
right so you would want to do like an
unpack low on our G and that would give
us the R 0 G 0 it would also give us the
R - G - no it wouldn't because it's
unpacked low so we'd also need to do an
unpack high on our G and that would get
us this and this
then we need an unpack low and high on
the g's
and bees right so that would give us
these and then we need the B 0 R 1 B 2 R
3 and those would be blends it looks
like now the question is if we've
already done these do we then have some
options of how to do these with these
interim values and so the question would
be can we produce from this a B 0 R 1 or
B 2 R 3 right
and so thinking about what these would
give us this would just give us R 0 G 0
R 1 G 1 this would give us R 2 G 2 R 3 G
3 and this would be G 0 B 0 G 2 P 2 G 3
oops
G 1 B 1 G 3 B 3 right so that's what we
would then end up with and now we're
just asking well B 0 R 1 and B 2 R 3 how
does one get these right so looking at
what we've got here B 0 and R 1 right up
here only in those two locations and in
the original and unfortunately like from
the looks of it they don't necessarily
appear in any nests in any of a better
location for that so B 0 is on this side
r1 has moved which helps us a little
it's in a second lane so now we can have
our 1 in either lane so maybe that's
sufficient
you know or maybe it's not not sure I
mean I guess it does seem plausible
and b2 are three are also yeah are also
in separate lanes now
and for it's nice they don't really see
much good that comes from this
so would there be any way to produce a B
0 R 1 B 2 R 3 vector would be the next
question probably not so B 0 R 1 nope
because they're all in different lanes
yet again right so hasn't helped us even
a little bit and so yet let's just see
though if we want to make so of the
things we wanted to make here right
we want our R 0 G 0 B 0 R 1 and then G 1
B 1 R 2 G 2 so G 1 B 1
G 1 V 1 R 2 G 2 is totally taken care of
with one op so once you build these you
can do one operation and get that and
then you have these two but you don't
have those two and that's so that's the
only rub now and again so it looks like
this would take to write three things it
looks like this would take just
tremendous number of instructions so
again I'm probably just not doing it
very well we can look up by the way this
summer we could easily look up the
answer to this question of like what's
the optimal four by three transpose for
SSC but again we'd never worked one of
these out on stream before I thought it
might be a good idea to do so and I
haven't done someone in a really long
time so I forget most of it I guess one
other way to look at this might be to
just write all of those possible unpacks
out right so of the things you can
generate from the input
oops
so other things you can generate from
these we know that you know we've got
unpacks which do interleave right so we
know we've got this and I'll just focus
on the lows for now so this this right
this and then the reverses of those
which I don't think we ever care about
reverse as much because you can usually
do its symmetrically either way so
probably you only care about the fact
that these are the things we could
produce right in terms of combinations
of lanes so we can produce any of those
we can then also produce selects right
so we can swap any two lanes arbitrarily
or grab any other thing so you know we
can do any of these like R 0 R 1 we
could swap those and get any of the
other I guess we can we can combine with
a shuffle any two from one vector and
any two from another right and it's
unclear how we write that out it's
something we can actually look at but
any combination of these basically right
so we could do something like this you
know what I mean
so we can we can transpose these on the
interior and that might be useful right
because we were having trouble figuring
how to get things to a line and it may
be that if we shuffle some of these
first we could do something shooting
there we can also grab any other values
right so we can combine these two and
you know we could do like R 0 R 2
you know G 1 G 3 if we want it right
because again as long as we stay in
these two on halves
right we can pretty easily pull anything
we want using the shuffle so that's not
hard right so the question is source
wise what do we need at the end of the
day and it's really like I said it's
really hard like I have a really hard
time guessing these things it's just not
easy so if we want to pull from one of
these then what we know is there's
really only two I suppose ways that this
can work one is that it's a shuffle
between two vectors so that it's split
this way right which means that there's
one vector that has an R 0 G 0 in it
somewhere and another vector that has a
B 0 R 1 in it somewhere right so we can
either be pulling from something that
has an R 0 G 0 and a B 0 R 1 something
like this right into separate vectors so
either that implies that those two
things are into separate vectors or it's
an inter leave and R 0 and B 0 in one
vector and G 0 R 1 or another vector so
the two things we could say I guess
about this constraint and this maybe is
a good way to look at I never thought
about this before is that either this
has to be true so vector a has those and
vector B has those or this has to be
true
right so either this pattern exists in a
vector you know in one pair and this is
in one pair or this is a pair and this
is a pair split on lanes exactly as as
is right so these have to be together in
one vector and these have to be together
another vector or these appear in a
vector they don't to be together
these appear in a vector and don't have
to be together right so those are these
can be separated so those are the
constraints that we have right and we
know that that that's the two
constraints we get from this vector so
writing those out let's just write those
out as we go so the final ops right that
right these we know we've got R 0 G 0 B
0 R 1 G 1 B 1 R 2 G 2 and finally be 2 R
3 G 3 B 3 and so then we have two things
we have the shuff constraint right for
each of these and we get to pick we have
a shuff constraint and an unpacked
constraint so the shuff constraint is
like these things just have to exist
somewhere right so in the chef
constraint we would say that there has
to be a vector that has both are 0 and G
0 in it but we don't care where and then
another vector that has B 0 and R 1 in
it and we don't care we're right
same thing with here the test of G 1 and
B 1 in it don't care where R 2 G 2 in it
don't care we're right this is vector a
this is vector B same thing here B 2 R 3
G 3 B 3 so that would be if chef were
used to write them if unpack were used
then we know that it's split this way
and they have to be paired right so you
can't actually split them up so now we
know there's an R 0 B 0 in something
together and a B 0 R 1 oops
no G 0 R 1 right same here it would be a
G 1 R 2 and a B 1 G 2 right same here it
would be a B 2 G 3 R 3 P 3 so these are
our combination choices right in terms
of what we know the next set of vectors
has to be so in each case we have
constraints on the vectors that would
propagate forwards so we'd have an
unpack here with an A and a B we know
that this tells us a lot if we choose to
unpack the last time round we know a lot
about our vectors because these have to
actually be together right and
furthermore that's being the same side
so these both have to be high or both
have to be low right so this tells us a
lot this tells us significantly less
this just tells us that there's an R 0 G
0 in something somewhere and a b0 and b1
in something somewhere right so here's
the question for you which of these have
the same inputs well here's a pair right
here right here's B R
right B 0 R 1 B 2 r 3 no i'm santi
here's another pair r RG RG and then G B
G B so if we said look can we do this in
six shuffles the answer appears to be
yes because if we produce the vector B 0
if we produce a vector that has these
things in it r1 r3 b0 b2 right then we
have the vector input we need for this
right for these two opps for writing
these two and we know we can produce
this because this is just a chef with RB
so chef RB gives us this and then using
this vector as chef's here will give us
these right r 0 g 0 r 2 g 2 in this case
same thing so it just be r 0 r 2 g 0 g 2
that's just a chef r g and finally this
one same thing so a G 1 G 3 B 1 B 3 is
just a chef GB so in 6 shuffles we can
do it right in 6 shuffles that works now
the question is are any of these things
duplicitous they don't appear to be
right and so the only question would be
you know and so if you looked at what
these vectors have to contain at that
point you would just say I don't think
there's any way to do it in less than 6
shuffles if you're doing shuffles
meaning if this if this last thing is
all shuffles it looks like that's that's
all you could do that's the best you
could do but of course we know you don't
have to do that you could do unpacks
right and so the question is well would
an unpack get rid of one of these
somehow or make it less make there be
less of it right and if we look at what
we've got here you know I can't say I
see much possibility for that so six
shuffles looks like it would be required
for at least the naive implementation
right we've done nothing fancy and it
would take six shuffles let's try it I
don't know if we have a shuffle
I think it's just called shuffle yeah so
I guess we don't have an mm shuffle in
here anywhere um but let's just try it
and so we want to do here is make a
result and we're literally just doing
exactly this and we can think of this as
our Gees and B's as well but doesn't
really matter right and so if we look at
this if we wanted these to be ours two
x's you know G's or Y's and you know B's
or whatever it is not very complicated
to figure out how this would work
we just need to then go all right we're
gonna do a bunch of shuffles here right
this is an mm shuffle PS and we know
that inside here we need temporaries
right so we know that we need to
actually have like our F 3 4 X's in this
case see what we've got here there we go
and maybe we just make the shuffle work
on that so maybe we just say something
like this and I think what we probably
want to do here is make this a macro
right and I'll show you why in a second
but so let's just see what we would
actually want to pick here so in memory
order if we want to do to reduce this we
need our our vectors are our G vector
right so we'd have our our G vector
which is an X Y in this parlance right
Apolo should have done that with
ex-wives to begin with but you get the
idea so our X Y vector here is gonna get
shuffled and what we want to do is we
want to pick out 0 0 right so if we look
at what we would get for shuffles here
or our vector what we're thinking of we
want zero and two right
and then when we do our shuffle for our
next one we want that to be well and you
know what I forgot the X components so
here we want Br
we want these 0 R 1 so that's going to
come from our be R vector so that's this
one or I should say our B vector so
that's our X Z vector so we want to take
0 &amp; 2 from this vector and then we want
to take 2 0 you can see the transpose
and at work here right from the other
one our next one is G 1 B 1 so that's
going to come from here it's 0 2 again
from the G B vector so the G B vector is
a Y Z vector right and then we need B 1
I'm sorry and then we need a human be 1
and then we need our 2 G 2 2 G 2 right
so we need in this case 1 3
I mean that from the RG vector finally
for Z we need B to R 3 so that would be
from the Y Z the X Z vector and that's
three no oh yeah it is three one right
and then finally we need g3 b3 g 3 b3
such a 1 3 on the Y Z vector so
that's the production for each of the
final results we still need these
vectors so we need our X Y vector our Y
Z vector and our X Z vector and those
would be shuffles as well and so the
final thing we need to do here is
produce these actual vectors so we need
r1 r3 b0 b2 for our X Z vector here's
our X Y vector we'll do that first since
I wrote that first 0 2 and that's from
our input right and then from why we
need 0 2 as well right from y&amp;z what we
need to do here is say well when we do
our shuffle for 4y that's going to be 1
3 and then 4 z it's 1/3 as well
and then finally we just need our X Z
vector which is 1 3 0 2 and that's going
to be on X and Z right so in theory this
does our Swizzle and you know I don't
know what the minimum number of
operations would be for this so I'm not
sure how close we are to being good
right 6 might be too many you know 5 may
be a more likely goal but there you can
see what we would do now we just need
our actual shuffle and we'd like to be
able to write this as an actual function
but like I said we're not going to be
able to we're gonna have to write it as
a macro and the reason for that is
because there's no actual way to because
this is an actual instruction the value
that we pass to the chef PS has to be a
constant right so if you look in here
this is an immediate that gets compiled
with the instruction so it has to be a
constant value so there's not much we
can do about that and we passed 0 1 2 or
3 depending on what we are going to pick
here and we weld these together into a
bit stream so you can see like the first
two bits control the first choice the
next two bits control the next choice
and so on so what we need to do here is
take each of these that we have so we
have like you know
s0 s1 s2 s3 and then we have like the a
and B like so and that becomes an in and
shuffle PS of a and B and these we need
the actual p-value for like so that's
the packed version and that will return
the result you know that we actually
want so we can I don't know how we cast
that exactly here we go
so now we just need to weld you know s0
or s1 or s2 or s3 together we need to
weld these into a single immediate value
by shifting them each up some amount
right so each of these values has to get
shifted up by something and I'm not
actually sure which order we want them
in but it will be something like this
right so that's roughly what we're
looking for here there we go so I think
that's mostly what we want and that if
we actually go debug it is the transpose
that we're looking for
I would like to debug that before we go
any further I will have to fill in
something just to compile it but I would
like to step to this and bugger there's
a really easy way we can then find out
if we've got this thing working properly
and that is just to fill these with
values we actually know what they
already are so for example if we want to
know where everything ends up we can
just fill the input with something and
see that the output gets the transposed
version of that something so for example
if I do this
oops right beforehand
I can watch where everything goes right
similarly if I do this I can watch even
better because now every element has a
different thing in it right
and finally if I just transpose this
myself I can actually see exactly what
the heck happens by making sure it
actually goes into its correct location
so for example I can do this oops let me
just do it this way so now if I want to
I could actually inter leave these right
so I could say all right so we actually
want to go zero oops
four eight one five nine two six 10
three seven eleven right so I do that
now we've actually got something that if
the routine works properly should put
these numbers in order
right so let's start there shuffle the
output should just read off in order
right so you know at the end of the day
we would expect to see or actually here
I would expect to be able to see x e0 e1
e2 like that and this would let me see
if this transpose actually works right
so let's go ahead and nerf this for just
one second and it's pretty easy to do so
if I go into diffuse weight map if I
expect this to be of F 32 for X here and
then this would not step on the same
number of things so what that would mean
is like this value here right would
would do that so then in here when we
actually write these out it's actually
pretty straightforward because we can
actually still produce it this way and
say like oh okay so for producing this
many of these things you could do like
it you know
something like this and then at the end
we can just combine them together right
and it's not exactly right but it's good
enough at the moment the reason I say
it's not exactly right is because now
it's not we'd have to actually make this
a four I loop which I don't know if we
actually want to do I mean I guess we
could why not
right and so now we can go take a look
at that D Swizzle and see if it actually
does anything right and we can also run
this to see what the speed would be
because even though it's probably wrong
the speed is presumably there and you
can see it you know it does get you
quite a bit actually it's not nothing so
let's go ahead and debug that Swizzle
and then we have to go debug the rescue
but we're mostly done now so let's go
ahead and go to our build turn this to
addy so we can actually step through it
here to the transpose set a breakpoint
we go run its
and whoa
uh what happened here
oh that's exactly what I said I was
afraid of see what I'm saying
why do you ever produce a dqa sir I
never wanted eq i remember i said like
aligned would be a problem for us
fine all right I'll do it myself
so we need our store PS here to do a
store unaligned which it doesn't look
like we have some I don't know we're
gonna have to add one of those I guess
but track ID I did not want it to ever
generate in a line store but of course
it does and there's not much I can
really do about that so what I want to
do here is just like force it to not do
that right I want to force it to do a
non-aligned store so I want to say look
just don't do that okay
not sure how to actually make this thing
sink it through but probably that it's
just a pain in the butt right but again
all I'm doing there's nothing important
happening here at all this is just
busywork stupid I'm just trying to tell
it not to store these things aligned
what's the complaining about cannot
convert argument 1 to float star why
doesn't that take a void pointer anyone
know no one knows so yet we're just
gonna write to that and we should be
good now back to our show so I really
want to stop if the transpose right I
don't actually care about any of that
oh and hey if I wanted to bug the
transpose I should probably call it huh
so yeah in order to store the light see
we need to transpose it here let's add
that in and now I'm just going to run
real quick to see if we actually made
transpose that works at all so just
trying to bug that and so what we can do
first is just take a look after we do
these chefs I set up this order array
here so we can see what they came out to
be right and you can see this is garbage
right so we've got some issues here
that's not what we want
oh oops that's cuz I put the wrong thing
in there though for the test
sorry cuz I should a result yeah there
we go we want to look at the result not
the input obviously although good to
verify the input I suppose alright let's
try that one more time and just take a
look at what comes out so again
transposed pre transpose data goes in so
now we expect ordered data to come out
zero five one one six ten for the F no
good right so two things could happen
here one is this is wrong and the other
is this is wrong right so we don't know
which of these two is a fault here right
it could be the thing we built to do
this first of all this is obviously
wrong when I just said it's something
like this so each of these is two bits
so we know that at the very least it
needs to be that now we don't know what
the order is it could be that these are
actually three zero one two so I'll take
a look at that but actually we can
literally just fire-and-forget now if we
want to hmm we can just try the
different permutations and not have to
worry about reading the Intel spec to
find out what it actually is but yeah
let's start with that
all right so that's at least a little
bit more sane which is good you know
because it was pretty crazy before but
you can see still not quite right let's
take a look at what these internal
values are just for here so I can see so
let's take a look at like what XY so
let's just take a look at this one first
so if you remember what we expect to see
here is X 0 X 2 y 0 Y 2 so X 0 is
correct X 2 is not and I'm I'll be
honest I'm not even sure how we could
possibly have produced this how would it
ever have gotten an 8 from that
oh wait x0 x2 so yeah no that is
actually correct X 0 X 0 X 2 y 0 Y 2
yes never mind I'm I'm crazy so that
doesn't appear to be producing what we
want so this should give us 1 3 1 3 so y
1 that's correct
y 3 that's correct 3 and 11 4 2 &amp; 3 see
if those are right yeah
so that's correct and then last one is X
Z oops that don't didn't want to do that
at all
turn it hit some key accidently get back
here run to there again please
okay um one more time XE XE actually can
I just do this why am i why am i blowing
that out for no reason just make it type
and work for myself there we go
so X Z vector is 4 1 10 7 so it should
be 3 1 from X 3 1 1 4
[Music]
so that doesn't Oh No
so I'm reading the wrong one one in
three from X that's fine I was like
what's going on
zero and 2 from A's from a-z it's your
own - yeah alright so all of those do
look like exactly what we expect them to
be right and so maybe did we kind of
mess up what we were thinking here so
now if we look at what we've got this is
like X 0 2 y 0 - that's what we have in
here so now in the X vector we want to
produce like you know we're looking to
produce this and then this right so we
want to produce something that has X 0
in it which makes sense here and then we
want to produce something that has X 3
in it which this did not
right so this seems like it's slightly
wrong in this case did we screw
something up here in the way we were
looking at this so let's see which one
that was that was the first one the x1
right and we said we were going to
produce RGB are here right so
oh so actually now I just flooded these
values wrong though I did a 4x3
transpose did the other way round so
actually if we look at what these are
these are not quite interleaved the way
that I should have interaction 0 3 right
because it's it's every 3 that gets
interleaved I did every 4 don't ask me
why
so actually what we want here is if
these were previously rrrr and we want
them to be RGB RGB right so this should
actually be like our miss the G miss the
B are again right so it's 0 1 2 3 right
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 right should it look
like that so that was just me doing the
wrong thing
this is what it should have looked like
I mean it's it's a transpose right so it
should just read out the columns so I
think it's just been a slow morning
probably because I'm like completely
allergy stricken at this point but
that's actually what we should have had
I mean that's just common sense right
because this matrix is what's gonna get
transposed so I did that for some reason
when I did it I did it by 4 because you
could do the 4 by 3 or the 3 by 4 you
could do either one and they come out
differently right so that may have just
mean me putting in the wrong test
pattern wouldn't that be nice huh let's
find out
hmm not sure why I can't set a
breakpoint there let me do it now but it
didn't let me do it before all right hey
look 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11
yeah so that's good so that appears to
work properly and I guess we don't know
if we set it up right meaning we don't
actually know if the rest of the code is
correct but now we can get rid of this
and we know that our shuffle actually
works as a I guess I should leave these
in for people who want to try and make a
faster shuffle that way they can quickly
see
alright let's go ahead and leave that
for today and we'll pick it up again
tomorrow
we could also thread that and then at
this point it would probably run totally
fine for our purposes although again
just it's unfortunate that it's so
expensive right so you can see like
we're probably close to good but I think
we may we may have a bug in there I
think we still have a bug so you can see
it's not quite right it's almost right
but yeah the the stride is off or
something like this so it's close to
correct but not quite and I'm not sure
who's at fault there right could be
anybody we've done enough stuff now that
it's a little bit confusing like our
weight vectors could be wrong we don't
know so we're we're actually writing out
these
yeah that's that's wrong so this code is
not quite correct so this w value that
was supposed to load for one of each of
these this is looping over the wrong
thing so the SX X Y B is still supposed
to to be there right and actually what
gets written less is the TX value right
because that's where the actual loop
happens so it's this is what's actually
supposed to happen right and then so
then when you do this part here where
you get the directions lofted up that's
the actual part where you where you
actually need to write it out properly
so I think what we would want to do
there again is we probably don't
actually want to do this part this way
because it's probably just easier since
we don't need to sim di as this routine
it's probably simpler to say look just
leave it the way it is you know don't do
this
and then actually compute this map and
then convert it at the end right to what
we actually want it to be so when we
actually go through and produce these
and we do the summation here we would
probably do something more like this
so we've got the sy SX there
so once we actually just produce these
in standard scalar form so we have to
deal with it then at the end what we
would probably do is say alright now
let's actually move them out to where
they belong and when we load up one of
these what we're effectively doing right
is we're just taking four of these at a
time so it should be as simple as just
as picking off of these right I guess
the the bummer is that means it actually
has to be out here right in terms of the
way it actually gets written back so
yeah a little bit nasty just looking at
it right so we're gonna produce each one
of those and then we need to for each
outgoing direction we're gonna produce
the weight matrix and now we want to do
is slice that up so that we're pulling
out the weights for subsequent TX values
as we go so really all that means is
this now has to kind of be four wide I
guess would be the way to look at it
right or we can just sort of point into
the part of the diffuse map that we're
actually talking about either way but
what that means is like when you look at
the actual lighting code this here is
you know not gonna look like this
anymore
so well I guess I redid it so you can
see there's there's a lot less in than
there right so when we're actually
looking into this one
what we would want to do is say alright
which weight map are we actually gonna
write into on every single one right so
like when we come through here we're
gonna want to write into a particular
weight map for the that specific TX and
that specific you know
yeah for that specific txt why to
everything so if we're gonna do it this
way we need to do this part properly so
we would have to do like alright T Y
minus 1 right because we're looking up
into 1 that's just the just the square
that's not true when we look up into
this how do we look up into this yeah so
here's what's grabbing the weights out
here so we are looking into T YT x4 and
then we just pull out the things by sys
X right so yeah so this is wrong so
since these are always going to be
pulled out by sys X right when we
actually do the lighting what that means
is that these remain at this dimension
the entire time right and when we right
back into the wait map we're just gonna
actually right back into it like this so
the only question is yeah like when we
write back in we're writing back in wide
and we're writing back in for multiple
of the T X's at once right so that was a
little bit of a brain bender but that's
how it's actually supposed to work so if
we look in here and we say okay let's
try to make this work properly then when
we grab the correct one out here this
this is the thing that's actually gonna
grab out the weight map multiple times
interior to here right so I mean I guess
another way to say it would be that
there's multiple of these that we do
before I loop over trying to think of
how we do that but I guess we would just
try and do they look up in here we'll
see how this works but yeah so then at
this point we have to say all right the
addressing of the diffuse weight map is
now complicated what actually is going
to happen is we have to look up the
wait map this way where we take the TX
value we subtract one from it and then
we divide by four to figure out where
we're actually looking up right so
that's the actual weight map that we
want and then when we're right in here
we write the residual of that so we go
in here and we say s y sx the element of
this it's nuts right the element of this
is the TX minus 1 mod 4 right so the
remainder goes in here and that's
actually how the weights get written in
there it's actually this so that
properly unpacks them for the way that
they were actually addressed right and
now I think we have close to correct
it's still probably wrong and we'll have
to track the values through but that's
at least more what it should have been
so a ton of work right and again this is
why I say like the SSE instruction set
just sucks and the reason for that is
very simple the amount of time it takes
to turn an algorithm from a scalar
algorithm into an SSE algorithm it's
just way too much thought yes you can
rely on libraries or a vectorizing
compiler to do it for you perhaps but
all of that thought that I'm doing had
to be done by the library authors and
they have to figure out a way to provide
an interface or the compiler has to have
all of that stuff that I just did and
hope that it does it well right and it
adds a ton of complexity something's
already complex it's just not good right
if the instruction set it just had
swizzles built in that routine just
would have been instant you wouldn't
have to do any of that stuff right you
just say here's what I'm loading just
you know I'm loading Swizzle to do the
ops and then writes whistled and that'd
be it
and that would have been a good
instruction set and way more stuff could
take advantage of somebody at that point
because anybody could write it and you
wouldn't have to know anything
all right so I still want to be more
debugging on that but I think that's
good for today so yeah I mean I think
we're all right there we can do diffuse
lighting and specular lighting now
pretty straightforward so I think we're
pretty good to go and the question is
just like is that gonna be too slow
right I'll go to a quick QA and by the
way we should search at some point
I mean maybe we'll search later to see
if there's a faster than six shuffles
cuz there's probably a faster than six
shuffles transpose and be nice to know
what it was just so for our own
education that it for our own
edification because people spend a lot
of time working on these transposes and
stuff and so there's probably like a
definitive answer somewhere or it's like
oh if you use an unpacked you can do it
in five or whatever right if you just
put the unpack here you can save to two
of the shuffles with one unpack
something like that right
[Music]
and by the way just so folks know
because I saw a question on the stream
up that is related transposes are
symmetric generally speaking so you
usually don't have to think too hard
about which way you're going right but
in this particular case because it's a
four by three versus a three by 4 and so
on kind of have to think about it a
little more carefully but so what we
were trying to do is we were trying to
go from rrrr gggg bbbb to RGB RGB RGB
RGB RGB right vulva so why can't you do
the unpack on the GPU side um so yeah
well it depends exactly what you mean by
that but if we had a little bit more
specificity so if we weren't using
OpenGL we probably could do a texture
submission where we submitted the data
in a format that was Swizzle and was
easier for us to use right since we are
using OpenGL the only way that we would
really be able to do that without
extensions and stuff is if we've just
stored a read texture a green texture in
a blue texture right and the reason we
don't want to do that is because then we
would have to actually take a lot more
texture samplers which just grat like it
complicates the shader look it forces a
shader to do more instructions and it
forces more texture bandwidth to because
it's gonna pull in the whole block of
ours the whole block of G's and the
whole block of B's even though we only
needed an RGB right
the big Fox says it looks like in this
article they do it in six shuffles
similarly to how you do it great
seriously so I mean you mean that was
the best we could do
although wait but that says to and
56-bit AVX so with a VX it still takes
six levels but is a VX doing six
shuffles to do twice as many though or
not really
could be feasible to pack into a
different GPU supported format maybe
even compressed well you so Carolee pack
into a compressed format right because
you have to do the compression right so
that wouldn't be really considered
packing that's like compressing and sure
it's feasible
you'd have to if you're going to use
like a DX TC format or something you
would have to sum up your values and
figure out what your two interpolated
values were going to be and stuff like
that but you could do it right
alright well if they say that six is the
best for 128-bits well that's what we
did so kudos to us I guess I don't know
how fast six shuffles would be so
they're dependent shuffles you're
issuing three of them shuffles like I
want to say shuffles on port five and
only on port five let me see if I'm
wrong about that
[Music]
doing it didn't and didn't do so yeah
yeah so this code is gonna suck is
basically what it boils down to so like
basically the only saving grace for this
code and the reason that it's fine
probably in this case is that if you
look at where this is being done we're
basically doing it transpose and then a
bunch of stores and then we never care
right and so I think the saving grace
for this code is that it plows a bunch
of crap on to port 5 and then plows a
bunch of stuff on to port 2 and 3 that
comes out right no 4 &amp; 5
I'm sorry so what what is this
two and three so I was right the first
time
oh no I wasn't sorry three and seven two
three seven and four
those must be the reckon the right ports
four and seven I've believe it or not
I've studied writing hardly at all
because most of my work on low-level
observation ends up happening on meow
hash which never writes anything so my
knowledge of the right port situation is
like bad so anyway either way I think
the only saving grace er is the fact
that basically we just pile a bunch of
crap onto port five and then we do our
rights
nobody needs those values so since
what's about to happen here is mostly
multiplies in ads which are not on port
five I mean they can be but they don't
have to be like the ads can be on zero
and one and the moles aren't on five I
don't think yeah so basically port zero
and one floods here and then five floods
here so we don't need to worry about the
fact that like we're basically just
putting enough stuff in for 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 5 so
that the fact that they all happen
together is okay because it'll just
interleave those in the window I think
so the the 6 shuffle thing is not
horrible but you can see why that would
if you actually had to use the results
of the shuffle so if we add a bunch of
further operations that we're gonna pile
up behind the 6 shuffles that would suck
because you can only issue one shuffle
per cycle so it would literally be six
cycles sitting around with these
shuffles right because it'd just be port
5 block part 5 block 4 five block four
five block four five block you'd just be
blocking on port five all day long right
would you consider using the vector
extension from clang if you went clang
only um so like I would probably try
turning it on just to see if it did a
good job right and then we could just
avoid optimizing things until later I
don't think I'd probably counted it to
do much work for me because I'm assuming
I'm still gonna probably have to do it
but let's do all the work we do for
generating serious nipples not using no
we use it we're not using it at the very
immediate moment because we're just
plugging in the test pattern right but
the sphere samples get used as soon as
we switch to the actual light transport
as soon as we debug this right so if to
debug this and make sure we're still
getting the same results whether or not
we use for wide and I'm pretty sure we
probably screwed something up so to go
verify that that pipeline flows properly
but it's going to do that we switch over
to the light transport that still uses
the sphere samples right so yeah it's
all it's all good and and then we're
done we're just maybe slow but when we
switch over to the actual light
transport that's full lighting real-time
lighting per pixel with indirect believe
it or not and so we might be slow but we
did it right and and yeah let's see how
how we feel about it at that point
yes 15 Sh yep sure why not
the problem is it's on cpu side so it's
never gonna get any faster right that's
the only downside if it were GPU we
could probably say yeah 15 frames per
second sure a couple years and my heroes
finished the GPUs will all be way faster
thought you know all good don't worry
about it
but CPUs that doesn't really happen so
at the very least we'd have to move all
the letting go to the GPU right
scallywag what's next let's do this
after lighting after a lighting we'll
probably go in and try to do some world
building so like building some levels
and so that we can start working on the
art like level structure communication
stuff just make sure that's all working
because just needs a little refinement
is there a reasonable performance
difference on a line to done align move
in SSE - no there's no difference
they're the same so basically the way
that the way that a line versus
unaligned works these days is it doesn't
matter they're the same speed the only
difference between the two on modern
processors is if you happen to cross a
boundary that is important so for
example an aligned right can never cross
a page boundary so if you imagine pages
are 4k long right and aligned right can
never straddle two 4k pages because
since it's a line - 16 bytes
there's no way to write to an aligned
set of 16 bytes that crosses a page
doesn't happen it can't it can't happen
right an unaligned right can cross a 4k
page and if you cross a 4k page you pay
32 cycle penalty I think for that
operation
three just like--all zany that much
actually so if you only do it every once
in a while you probably don't care
unless you're really maxing out your
throughput right look on meow - maybe we
care on most algorithms probably you
don't because you probably can't get the
algorithm running fast enough that that
thirty-two cycle bubble can't just hide
a bunch of calculations you were doing
anyway right so I don't want to say
there's no difference cuz I just
explained to you a difference but it's
almost no difference so really when
you're talking about aligned versus
unaligned you're usually talking more
about some other thing false sharing for
cache purposes so basically ruining your
multi-threading because your unaligned
to cache boundaries or something that
could be a thing again pretty unlikely
cuz the fact that algorithm you probably
wouldn't have written it that way but
you know just pointed out other
processors so old X 64 processors did
care about a line versus unaligned or
x86 processors I should say and some
other you know embedded processors you
know phones or whatever you may have
problems on those so you may care but
it's probably not going to be on an x64
right
how do you reason about separable
filters when say running along the
y-axis for an image kernel might incur a
cache miss on a sequential access for
non block storage well the answer there
is just don't do that right so a
separable filter is still not usually
infinitely wide so a separable filter
usually can do something like process in
blocks so you process say you know you
write out 64 bytes of your answer and
then you can do the next row and do 64
bytes of your answer there right so
usually a separable filter you can do
still do it in chunks you know I mean
is there a reason to use move APs
instead of move ups no there never
should have been a move ApS that was
just a design bug there there never
should have been a move aps and there
never should have been non veep the so
the way that it works on ecstasy for is
non v prefix instructions and I'm only
talking to people here I guess who know
what any of this stuff is but non V
prefix instructions throw an exception
if the memory parameter is unaligned
that was also a huge mistake they fixed
it with V prefix instructions so if
you're actually writing modern code for
modern processors you just go look we're
gonna start with a V X we'll put V
prefix structures on everything and then
now there's no such thing as an aligned
anything you never type move a PS for
any reason it just doesn't exist as far
as you're concerned and you just have mu
V ma view PS and V everything else right
and so that's you know really the main
thing right amar how do we go back to
60fps now well I mean we got to get our
lighting to the point where we're gonna
consider it done from a like what the
look is standpoint and once we're sure
that it's done then we just optimize our
code which there's a lot of optimization
potential that we can tap into here and
that may involve moving it to a GPU it
may involve just optimizing the CPU side
because there's a lot of fat in there
right now due to all the experimentation
and we don't know so it's not clear
exactly what we're gonna want to do
going forward we're gonna have to play
that by ear but as it stands currently
there's a ton of you know work we can do
to improve the performance so you know
60 frames a second might not happen
right 30 frames a second might be the
best we can do
non non non GPU like meaning not moving
into the GPU if we move it to a GPU then
you know you have an RT X card it'll eat
this thing for breakfast you know I mean
a thing can do the ray tracing for us
right so so it's mostly just if we leave
it on the CPU side how far from release
well who knows right
depends how much game you put into it I
mean people are still making updates to
like Stone Soup right and stuff like
that I mean there's games that have been
in development for 30 years just keep
adding to them so who knows as long as
it it is as long as we keep one and add
stuff to it as long as I'm not bored if
I'm like I am tired adding stuff to this
then I guess we release it
all right let me wrap it up
thank you everyone for dreaming from the
episode of handmade hereit's when a
pleasure coating with you as always if
you would like to follow on the series
at home you can always peer to the game
on hand mahir org and it comes to source
code so you can play around with it
yourself I'll be back here tomorrow at
which point we will just kind of clean
up the code and make sure that we iron
the bugs out of the for wide version
maybe we'll throw it on a thread at that
point just so it's out of our hair and
then we can go ahead and move on to the
work of actually finishing the
raycasting stuff and then that'll be
that I think we can actually do this on
the same threading so basically we just
the lighting code we'll take one set
like one row of the voxel do the
lighting on the row update and then also
do the bake down of the you know the
diffuse bake so the threading model is
actually trivial for us which is great
so threading it would be free
effectually and that's probably what
we'll do tomorrow is move those through
things together and then I think yeah
we're just in a situation of looking at
the transport trying to get that quality
to a good place playing around a little
bit with some level building to put so
we can put some lights in places and see
if we're getting reasonable results but
I think that's mostly you know where
we're at
so hope to you back here tomorrow when
we'll put that stuff in place and then
hopefully next weekend we can start
working on the transport stuff like
getting that cleaned up and nice and
yeah cross our fingers that our
Lighting's good at the end of it alright
until then have fun program everyone and
I will see you on the Internet take it
easy everybody