hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we did the work yesterday
of making sort of a permanent source
code file that we generate ourselves
which has sampling spheres in it for
sampling our lighting and the reason
we're doing this is because we don't
want the burden of producing high
quality sampling patterns at runtime
because that would cost too much so we
want to do instead is build some
sampling patterns that we can just use
that don't cost us anything because we
just have them stored as raw data arrays
and we just use them directly that's
what we want to do and so we did all the
work to do that but we haven't done yet
is actually put something into that
generator that produces nice like high
quality sampling patterns that actually
sort of cover the sphere in a nice
uniform way now there's a lot of ways we
might do this and we're gonna have to
talk about those now but that is our
goal for today is just to take that code
we wrote yesterday and augment the part
that generates the spheres to instead of
just spewing white noise and normalizing
it out to the sphere what we want to do
instead is have some sort of a nice
uniform covering of that sphere that's
noisy meaning it's random points but
that they still tend to have a sort of
roughly equidistant kind of you know
covering to them right so what I'm gonna
do now is I'm just gonna show you what
I'm talking about for those people who
missed our stream yesterday and then
we're gonna talk about some strategies
that we can use to try and solve this
problem right so here goes the build
just making sure everything's built okay
I also should probably note that there
was a Oh where's our github I should
also note some people were saying for
GCC we wanted to put our line as it's
just a mop for Linux compiles there's a
line ass movement we want to do so maybe
I'll do that really quick to just to
help those folks out in the sphere
generator this has nothing to do but I
wanted
this has nothing to do with what we were
going to do today but it's just a really
quick change we can make so basically
what happened is we wanted to make sure
that these things were aligned so that
in case the compiler generated sse loads
that required alignment they would be
correctly aligned to sixteen by
boundaries this global align as here is
the line in question and what they
wanted was just to say look global has
to come after it or GCC gets really
confused so will try just doing that
move we've got two of those there's one
here and there's one here and it's
assuming they don't cause us any
problems we're just gonna leave it like
that again that's just to allow people
comply with GCC which we don't do but
people who try to follow a long series
on GCC just trying to make it so they
don't have to make any changes to the
code base to compile it right that's all
we're doing there okay so anyway if we
go ahead and compile and just verify
that everything compiles okay we're not
actually running this at the moment but
we can probably add some stuff for that
in a minute if we go to the debugger and
we run the debug build of our game which
is a little slower frame rate rise but
when the lighting isn't running it's
still totally usable that's the main
difference lighting takes up a heck of a
lot of frame time in in debug mode so if
I go ahead and take a look here what you
can see is those are all our light probe
points we're gonna be starting with
these or our purple points after we're
trying to get working as light probing
there and in order to sample we sort of
built this little sphere here that we're
just visualizing the lighting directions
that we're generating on the sphere and
you can see it kind of hanging out
around up here and what you can see is
this this is a white noise and white
noise for those of you who haven't filed
a series much and don't know the about
the colors of noise white noise is
basically pure entropy it's entropy that
is as close as possible to real random
events so something that has no
correlation or pattern to it whatsoever
that's what we've done here we've done
as close as we can to white noise on a
cube or inside a cube I should say so
just generating points inside of cube
and then we pressed those points out to
their closest point on the sphere and
we got here and that's why you can see
it's roughly like pure entropy like
you've seen here it just looks like a
random clustering of points some far
some close right which is what you say
from randomness but you can see that
there is some really sparse obvious
places along the faces of the cube and
that's to be expected because there's
more area more volume out if you look at
the different cube in a sphere there's
more area of that a volume of that cube
in the corners right that all gets
mushed down that whole part gets smushed
down to the same general region of the
cube and so even if we were trying to do
pure entropy this isn't a good way to do
it right and we knew that we were just
trying to put something in there to make
sure our whole code path works so this
is kind of roughly what we would expect
to see for white noise inside the volume
of a cube then pressed on to a sphere
but that's neither here nor there
because I just want to show you it
running right now because we don't want
white noise anyway and so let's talk
about the kind of noise we want we've
talked about before and handmade here oh
you should all know what blue noise is
but we'll talk about it one more time
blue now is also called plus lon noise
sometimes they have slightly different
meanings but for our purposes they're
usually oops used interchangeably what's
going on all right sorry about that
all right so let's just talk about this
really quickly on the on the blackboard
I'll mention the blue noise and what
we're trying to accomplish with that
and then we can talk about how we're
going to get it or ways we could get it
so we're gonna talk about blue noise
slices today and I'm gonna talk about
sampling patterns in general a little
bit here and we'll just kind of go over
what we might want to do so like I said
if we are talking about let's just say a
2d domain because that's a little bit
easier to describe first then we could
talk about the types of noise that we
might be talking about and we could have
blue and white this we could call you
know sort of entropy and this we could
call Poisson perhaps we could also call
this random who knows depends on how you
want to talk about it but this is not
right this this is not going to be that
so white noise is the equivalent of
literally randomly picking a point so if
I pick some point here the next point
that I pick can literally be anywhere
there are no restrictions on where that
point could be and there's no reason I
mean literally a pure random
distribution of points could have two
points on top of each other my first a
second point can be in the same place in
an entropic distribution right why
because pure chance could someday
produce that right I may get the exact
same point twice it's possible with pure
entropy what you generally see with pure
entropy right is just complete you know
it's just this it just looks like
complete random there's no pattern to it
you can't find a pattern
knowing one point or some sequence of
points tells you nothing about the point
that comes next to it that next point
could be right next to the from that one
you just did it could be completely off
in the other direction there again
there's no guarantees about it at all
all you could really say about pure
entropy is that if you took enough of it
you should see something that you know
you shouldn't be able to get
extraordinarily improbable things like
everything clustered right there right
if you take a big enough random series
you should see a relative coverage of
the space with some gradually varying
density right but you should generate
we cover everything because if it's
really random there shouldn't be any
bias eventually towards putting
everything in one place but that's it
that's all you really know you don't
really know anything else about it
because it's random and if you could
know something about it it wasn't random
right it's unknowable my face now blue
noise or loss on distribution or
depending on how you want to want to
phrase it there
there's different words for it I when we
talk about that distribution there is
something you could know about it it's
still random meaning you're not supposed
to be able to predict what the next
point is from any given point in the
series in any precise way but unlike the
unknowable pure entropy distribution a
Poisson distribution or a blue noise
distribution is supposed to contain the
property that once a point any point is
placed into the system you will not
place another point near to that point
so there is some sort of a fundamental
distance that usually when we're talking
about these blue noise patterns we care
about that distance and we specify it
perhaps once we've placed on a point
while I cannot tell you anything else
about where I'm going to place my next
point I can tell you it will not be in
here and that goes for the sequence
forever
every time I place a point that
neighborhood around the point is removed
permanently and no future point may land
within there it's not just the next
point that can't land within there it's
any point now these sorts of noise have
different things that you might care
about in terms of audio production or
who knows what but for graphics work we
care about Poisson distributions or blue
noise or whatever you want to call it we
care about these for a number of reasons
they come up a lot and the reason is
because there's two different things
both of which are very important to
graphics and both of which really wants
noise the first one is random
distributions of things that are
supposed to mimic what happens in the
real world okay when things are placed
in the real world
in reality they typically don't follow a
white noise pattern and the reason for
that is that while there is enough
general stochastic randomness entropy in
the real world to produce white noise on
top of that white noise there is
typically some constraint that reduces
it to blue noise and let me give you a
concrete example because you may be
going like ha I don't understand let's
take something like trees
how will trees be placed in the real
world well a tree we get one of them and
it can grow someone planted the seed who
knows how it got there but the first
tree grows that tree produces seeds
those seeds occur throughout the tree
they will fall onto the ground and a
huge number of factors will control
where they fall they will fall near to
the tree to a certain extent but then
the wind will randomly we have no idea
how the wind is going to blow but it
will blow some of the seeds around
animals will eat the seeds and poop them
out somewhere else weak it'll get
situations where you know a bird might
grab some of these things and move huge
numbers of completely unpredictable
things act on these seeds so that
probably we would expect within a region
around the tree we would see basically a
white noise distribution of these points
that is perhaps distributed only with
the density function that says that the
further away you get from the tree the
less you get so we would expect a little
bit of a knowable thing about our white
noise which is that the density of the
noise is centered around the tree and
gets less and less as you get further
from the tree but other than that we
have no idea right so you might think
that if you want to know where trees
grow you would say ah just pick random
points and maybe we'll throw them out
with a higher percentage chance as we
get further from the tree right does
that produce a good estimate of where
trees
and the answer is no why because after
we distributes the seeds what determines
whether a tree grows has a lot to do
with one really big factor how close is
it to an existing tree an existing tree
takes all the sunlight takes nutrients
from the ground takes all the following
rain right and so in order for a new
tree to survive it must be at least some
distance away from the existing tree now
what happens when that new tree grows
this same pattern of white noise will
reoccur and we continue what that means
is a forest is like a huge blanket of
white noise that then had a constraint
put on top of it that any two trees too
close together aren't going to grow
right that means that something like
blue noise is a really good
approximation for what you visually see
when you look at a forest a somewhat
random distribution of trees with no two
trees being too close together right
again
it's not a perfect simulation of it
we're not actually simulating all the
things and in nature you probably can
get certain situations where two trees
go very close to each other because the
light was just right and this tree kind
of bent too far this way because of a
storm right so if you really wanted to
really simulate how trees grow there's a
lot more we can add to that simulation
to make it really good right but to a
first approximation and certainly one
that no one would bat an eyelash at blue
noise is perfect white noise isn't
because nobody would look at what you
generated first it would see tons of
places where there's all these trees
clump together and then some spaces
where there were no trees and then more
clubs right it would look really weird
and even like I don't know that that
forest looks weird right
whereas blue noise you'd be like yeah
that looks that looks roughly like a
forest right and the same is true for
lots of stuff flowers in a field grass
on a field etcetera etcetera blue noise
for distributing the individual plants
makes a lot of sense because they
compete for resources right
and so that's one place that we see blue
noise you know coming up it's just I
want to distribute things you know but
another place that we see it is where
we're talking about today so I want to
give you that perspective because now
you know one place that it comes up
here's the one that comes up today what
if this has nothing to do with
distributing things that have two
members the real world or competition
for resources or anything like that but
what if I just have a limited amount of
work I can do I'm limited
right because computing power is not
infinite so I'm limited in the amount of
work I can do and I have something
anything that I need to do that work on
right I have limited resources and I
want to do something to a very large
data set right and the question is if I
know I can't process everything that I
want to process I can't just do all the
work how might I distribute that work
across everything I could do to get a
reasonable approximation of the result
and of course that is what we talk about
when we talk about sampling if I can't
afford to do a perfect solution and I
have to just pick a few things to do
that will approximate the correct result
for anything I might want for any work
how can I best distribute the locations
of that work right and so I can give you
any number of examples of what I mean by
this but for example a really simple
thing I want to take a image really
really dense image right it's 50 billion
pixels by 50 billion pixels
I can't even load it into memory it's so
big right and I want to ask you what is
the average color
of this image right so I can't even load
it into memory and I quickly really
quickly I want to get an estimate of
what is the average color of the pixels
now normally in an image that is
anything that we would normally process
in computing a small image right to be
six five 256 a little tiny sprite
it's larious if that's a little tiny
sprite when that's the whole size of the
screen I'm like an Apple 2 or something
but you know the times they have a
change a little tiny sprite what do I do
I just go through all the pixels in the
image adding them up and I divide by the
total and I got the average right it's
easy no problem but if now you tell me
there are trillions and trillions and
trillions and trillions of pixels in
this thing which is what would happen if
you had a 50 billion by 50 50 billion
image because it's 50 billion squared
pixels right I don't want to wait for
that I don't want to go pay the AWS fee
to have all of all of these cloud
machines taking little segments of this
image and adding them up I just want an
estimate right so the question is how
would you distribute if you know you can
only afford to load 50,000 of the pixels
and add them together and average them
how would I distribute them throughout
the image in order to maximize the
chance that I am going to get a good
result a good approximation now those
examples are not that exact particular
example is not as good as it could be in
today's day and age when we know there
are other constraints involved so
talking about pixels is probably not the
right thing to do you probably want to
talk more about blocks of the image that
you could load but either way I have
some finite element of the image I can
load and I know I can't load all of the
trillions that there are how should i
distribute them and the answer for any
kind of sampling problem is actually
again it comes back to the Poisson
distribution the blue noise distribution
blue noise is the most effective way to
turn something where you cannot do all
the work but you want an approximate
answer it's a
way to turn a trillion points into a few
hundred points and still get a good
approximate answer and you may ask me
why why is blue why not white nice why
not random right and the answer has to
do with the quality of the sampling that
you get coming out of these answers
right if you pick something highly
structured because let's look at what
the alternatives are right
this was alternative one right and I
didn't really give an alternative to I
just simply said hey here's this
solution right because we were talking
about what we're going to do and we're
going to do this but there's another
alternative right this is random this is
structured right I could choose to
sample things completely regularly bamp
bamp bamp bamp bamp bamp bamp bamp bamp
at that route right in a grid or
something right so there's two kind of
polar opposites you could say that
you know there's like a line between
completely random and completely not
random right and structured completely
structured sampling or distribution is
like a very regular pattern that has a
completely regular structure imposed
over the top of it whereas a completely
entropic pattern like white noise has
literally no structure impose that
there's nothing you could say about the
structure ever it's completely nuts
right so if we take a look at these two
extremes
why don't we want one of them why don't
I want purely entropic sampling why
don't I want purely structured sampling
and the answer is because structured
sampling will fall prey to any structure
of the image let's suppose I have an
image with it's just a series of stripes
right and I ask you what's the average
color of the image like I said what's
the average what is it well if I just
have a series of stripes and those
stripes happen to be placed
you know an interval that doesn't line
up with a structuring pattern with this
with this sampling pattern I would say
the image is just completely black if
like if this area is black and this area
is white it's a it's an all black image
there's nothing in it right but actually
the average color is actually somewhat
bright it's a gray because there's all
these stripes in it I just missed them
all right because my sampling pattern is
regular and the image pattern is regular
and I missed them all right and that's
very easy to do with real-world images
because real-world images that have
structure often right so what you see is
if you feed any image in with any kind
of structure your sampling pattern will
pick up the bias in that structure and
go one way whichever way it is either
it'll over sample the stripes or under
sample the stripes and you end up with a
very inaccurate result entropy on the
other hand right pure white noise will
never fall prey to that problem it
doesn't matter if you feed it a
structure image because you have an
equal chance of landing on the stripe as
in the black area proportional to the
area of those things which is exactly
what you would have wanted however
because it is purely entropic it will
tend to cluster in some regions and
leave open space in other regions what
that means is again if there is a
different kind of structure to the image
where it's got some areas of brightness
some areas of darkness the entropic
version the purely entropic version will
fall prey to sampling bias where it over
samples some areas in under samples
other areas right so again it will get a
less accurate result because it's
concentrating its samples randomly
concentrating them but concentrated
unless in some areas and randomly
missing other features of the image so
again it falls prey to image structure
even though it itself doesn't have an
overt structure to it because there is
some structure that emerges from the
entropy right and that's the density is
non-uniform
that leaves us with this desire we wish
we could have right here in the middle
can we have something that has just
enough structure to ensure that we do
not under or over sample any regions of
our image but which does not have so
much structure that it falls prey to
highly structured images causing it to
over under sampling something and the
answer is yes we can and it is blue
noise blue noise is precisely that kind
of noise which is evenly distributed
across the entire thing but in no
predictable way right it gives us the
best of both worlds for what we actually
want no structure we can't say anything
about how these points come together but
no varying variance in distribution the
distribution is uniform right across the
entire thing and that's exactly what we
want so that brings us to our sphere
today we are trying to sample the
lighting right that comes in from the
entire world you know and I'm saying we
have like an entire sphere of light
coming from walls being a bouncing off
walls coming from light sources from the
ceiling from the moon from the floor
that bounces up an entire sphere of
incident light is coming into a point in
the world and our light probe is that
point in the world it wants to look out
and see what is the lighting look like
so in order to do this we need to have
some way of sampling that sphere now in
a perfect world we would have some
magical computing device that just knows
the entire lighting and somehow it can
just figure it out right maybe it's so
powerful that it's like the real
universe and our CPU can simulate twilly
ins and trillions of rays coming out
from this sphere and cover it so densely
that 100% of the light is basically
captured perfectly right
we crank up that sampling so high that
no human could ever see the error in it
it's that covered you know it's just a
solid solid ball when we draw all the
points you know I'm saying if we have
that device we probably wouldn't care
any sampling is fine even regular
sampling is probably fine because the
contribution of each individual point is
so low that even though there is still
that structured bias as light moves by
it it will have essentially a regular
pattern of kind of bias going through it
this contributions of those things are
like one one trillionth of a color value
right
we can't see it so we don't care about
sampling very much at all we don't care
about sampling very much at all when
we're overpowered right it's law you
don't care about sampling very much in a
lot of places in handmade hero where we
do things too like pixels because when
we know we have so many of them that the
I just can't really see the error we're
okay
but when it comes to lighting that's
never the case it's a way to high order
prominence way too many light rays
bouncing around any real world scene to
ever count them all and so we're nowhere
near the level of detail that we need to
just say it doesn't matter
we're always way under it and that's
where sampling becomes very important
you need to make sure your sampling is
at least decent because otherwise your
results are going to be way worse than
they could have been because you're
under sampling the problem by such a
drastic amount right so what I want to
do to my sphere is exactly what I wanted
to do in my previous example when I
talked about how do you actually produce
good coverage of say a plane for
sampling the pixels of an image to
average them like I just gave that
example what we're trying to do the
exact same thing really but just on the
surface of a sphere I want to take a
good uniform covering of my sphere to
catch all the incident light but I don't
want it to be structured because if it's
structured it will fall prey to sort of
stair-stepping patterns or stuff like
that
as things hit the bias of that sampling
pattern its structure and play against
it I want to get rid of that right and
so blue noise is the perfect thing for
this it's the perfect way if I can
figure out some way to do it if I can
figure out some way of sort of covering
my sphere with a uniform coverage that's
still completely random so there's no
way to predict where those points are
but they are equidistant from each other
or roughly right not equally but
similarly distant from each other that
gives me a good uniform coverage of my
sphere without structured sampling
artifacts that's exactly what I want
okay so what I need to do that right is
I need to take well that's a really bad
circle so is that though so you know I'm
gonna take my sphere and I want to try
and put points on the sphere you know
that kind of cover it but that stay
pretty you know pretty well separated
from each other right there's sort of a
a spherical on the surface of the sphere
there's a circular region sort of on the
sphere and I don't let other points go
inside there right so once I place one
down I keep that region clear from then
on of these other points right as I'm
placing them and that's how we were
doing it what I was doing before is we'd
set we just tuned a constant that was
how far we wanted that region to be we'd
place something on the sphere and we
make sure that nothing else we place on
the sphere would go into that region
right now I don't really want to do it
that way especially because we're
offline now and have as much time as we
want we can let this to run overnight if
we want to we don't care it could run
all week as long as it comes up with a
good answer at the end of the day we
just get an any file we can plug into
our game and that's instant right we
don't pay any more costs for it so I'm
free to do whatever stupid crappy you
know algorithm I want as long as it
produces the good result at the end of
the day I'm okay so I can't really
consider anything I want here especially
because I know the number of points
isn't that high we're not producing a
million points in the sphere we're
producing like
points on the sphere or a hundred points
in the sphere in fact it's 18 times four
points on the sphere right times the
number of spheres I want who knows
something that is so it's something like
that an N squared n cube even an N cubed
really right algorithm not that bad a
million computations not that bad a
modern computer has four five sorry it's
not a million company a billion has four
or five billion cycles every second they
can do I'm not concerned about things on
the order of a billion operation so we
can use cube routines and with impunity
at this order of N and we know that yeah
it may take a day to run our thing if it
really gets ridiculous or something you
know there's like 50 n cubed algorithms
happening in there or something we'd
still be okay right so we've got a lot
of leeway here and we know that we're
not shipping this to an end user so we
don't have to worry about the largesse
okay so what don't I like about our old
method of placing down a point and then
saying hey mister point make sure nobody
else gets into your region the thing I
don't like about that is the tuning I
don't like the fact that you had to tune
that radius because again let's just
think of it in the 2d realm because
they're not that different but think
about what that means if I want to place
a good coverage of this thing down and I
know that I need let's say five points
well I need to guess right like what
this distance is that allows five points
to fit in there but only those five if I
pick too low right let's say I pick a
thing that's grotesquely wrong well then
I could end up with all my points
clustered in one area and it and it
would still work right because I'm not
getting too close you know what I mean
so I have to tune this constant to find
out where is the breaking point so that
I'm just at the right thing where I can
still put five points but I haven't I
haven't done it's so large that it can't
five points but I haven't done it so
small that it could cluster them
together right so I'd rather get rid of
the tuning now that we don't care how
long this takes to run and what I'm
thinking is again maybe like a repulsion
scheme would actually be a little bit
nicer
so repulsion scheme just says look I
know I can just place random points down
here and who knows where they go and
then if I say I want them to erupt
equidistant well maybe I just do a thing
where I take the distance from each
point to every other point and add a
little bit of like force that tries to
push them apart right if each of these
things has kind of I don't want to say
magnetic repulsion but if each of the
points just repulsed the other points
and I run a little simulation they
should all sort of naturally settle into
positions where they're equidistant from
each other roughly right I think that
should give me more or less uniform
coverage of the sphere without any
obvious structure to it I think I think
and I can't really think of offhand I
should probably you know if we really
cared we should probably go read some
research papers there's been a lot of
recent research in the past ten years
about generating blue noise patterns so
to be honest like there might be some
ways we can jump sort of right to what
the correct tuning constant is and then
it's more efficient to generate these
things as like place and step kind of
functions but I think at least in the
without doing a more advanced sort of
deep dive into the properties of Poisson
noise and stuff like this I feel like
this most straightforward thing we could
do is just repulsion place random points
the number of them that you want so we
say we want a thousand points or
whatever we place those randomly on the
sphere and then we let them push each
other by looking at how far apart they
are on the sphere and we apply sort of a
force that falls off in proportion to
distance right if we run that for a
little while we should see our points
settle into locations that are
relatively sane and and relatively good
in terms of covering the sphere now
there's one other thing I talked about
which is slicing and what that is is
once we have this uniform coverage we
have a separate step which is the
slicing set right which is that once we
have a uniform coverage of the sphere
that has our entropic properties that we
want so we've got this nice like
coverage over here whatever this is not
very good you know what I mean a good
equal density but random coverage right
so something that looks sort of like
this once we have this we want to break
it up into chunks that are done every
frame so if we have like we were talking
about 16 times 18 times 4 this is how
many samples right that's how many
samples per frame we're doing on one of
these spheres and then we have 16 frames
it's spread out across
right what we want to do is take this
nice uniform distribution that we now
have and we want to break it up into a
set of sixteen distributions each of
which retains most of the good qualities
of the total distribution that we're
computing over time and so I don't
really know how we're going to do that
what we might do is like pick a point
and then pick the farthest away point
and then pick the furthest point from
those two and then from those three
right until we've picked 18 times four
points we remove them from the system
and then we do the same process again
for each slice I think that might do it
but I'm not totally sure so we need to
come up with a good slicing regime after
we're done but for now today I just want
to focus on building the first step of
the process that I've explained a detail
now which is how do we produce a nice
total blue noise coverage of the sphere
and then we can worry about the slicing
as a second step right okay so if you
take a look at what we've got already we
are doing the first step just kind of
naturally this right here is a thing
that places points onto the sphere
poorly right I mean it's good enough
though it places a bunch of points onto
the sphere completely at random and then
I'm sorry places them into the cube
completely at random and then just
pushes them onto the surface of the
sphere this is a biased distribution
like I showed you it's got some holes
and some clusters right but because
we're about to distribute our points
using a sort of forcing function to get
them equidistant around the sphere in
theory I'm guessing that initial bias
doesn't matter because the points are
going to move around now and sort
themselves out into a nice distribution
in theory it shouldn't matter so I don't
think and I don't know for sure but I
don't think we really have to worry
about this particularly much because I
don't think it's actually going to
matter I think we can just place these
points poorly at first right so I'm
going to label these steps
so I'm going to call this white noise
cube projected to sphere surface right
so we're going to just do a white noise
cube projected out to the sphere surface
that this right here is the white noise
cube right just completely randomly
picking inside the cube and then this
right here is the projection the surface
take each one of those vectors normalize
it right so done now after we're done
with that step we want to do the next
step that I said which is to try and let
these things diffuse so how do we do
that well let's just start by saying
look we're gonna run a number of
relaxation steps so we're gonna do like
a little simulation almost like a game
would do where we're gonna take a number
of steps on each step we're gonna move
the points a little bit right so we're
gonna say each step and let's say we're
gonna do a thousand of these steps I
don't know how many we're gonna do but
we're just gonna do some right we don't
care well tune this constant it doesn't
matter we actually might in the future
not even use the constant we might just
look at how far our points have moved if
our points haven't moved much then
they're then they've converged right so
this may just be a non-issue eventually
but for now I'm just gonna do this as
the first step but we can probably
remove this this constant as well so
we're gonna do about a series of steps
and for each step we're going to
displace our points and so the way that
we're going to displace our points is
I'm going to create a secondary array
here that's going to be like our for
Sarang and the forest array is literally
just a another set of VIII's that's
going to be how much we expect each
point to move right and so we've got two
steps here the first step computes the
force the second step applies it so what
I'm going to do here is say we've got a
jerk index the dur index goes to the
total direction counts on both cases
in each case I'm going to take the force
here it should be called forces so I'm
going to take the force in both cases in
this case I'm going to sum into that
force something in this case I'm going
to apply it so in this case I'm this is
the more simple part of the process by
far this is just directions here or here
are like you know Direction vectors each
one of these forces tells us how we're
going to push it so in order to push it
forwards I just have you know some force
you know I guess we don't really need to
call it forces it's a little misleading
maybe displacements it's better let's
say so we're basically looking at like
here's a displacement and we compute
those in place because we don't need to
integrate the force or any that's that's
not really physics it's just a basic
displacement um so we have whatever
displacement we said was supposed to
happen and so all we're going to do
alright don't ask me why she did that
there we go all we're gonna do is take
whatever the direction was and apply
this placement right so we're just gonna
say look for a particular displacement
we want to do we're gonna take whatever
the direction was we're gonna add the
displacement vector so this is however
much the the request was to move this
point as computed in this loop you
haven't yet we move it by that much and
then we want to reproject it to the
sphere right so we want to then say
equals Naz right there like so right now
like I said maybe we want this loop to
be a little bit better so what I might
do is just say look what we're gonna do
is say there's a total displacement
distance that we're going to
and so when we come in here what I'm
going to do isn't going to take whatever
emotion was produced
you know however far I wanted to move
this thing I'm gonna do this as sort of
a right back step so I'm gonna say all
right let's take the direction here
maybe I'll do it this way let's take the
displacement and the direction let's do
our update step so I'm going to take the
direction I'm gonna add this placement
to the direction I'm then gonna
normalize the direction and then
eventually I'm going to write it back
like so right
and I'm also by the way in that step
going to clear the displacement probably
because well I guess you know do we want
to do it that way yep probably so I'm
gonna clear this thing down in here
right so we start out with the
placements of zero and every time I want
to zero this placement out again so that
this thing can fill it up right so when
I come through here I take the
displacement I apply it I reproject onto
the sphere to make sure I'm staying on
the sphere because I don't want to have
to try and guarantee that with the
motion with the displacements that I I
want to be sloppier about those
displacements and then what I want to do
is before doing the right back I want to
take the length right I might take this
as a sum of squares just to keep things
easier but what I'm gonna do is say all
right I've got a squared length here of
the difference between the current
direction whatever it is and the place
that I was going to put it so this is
the total displacement right the the
this is like the effective displacement
squared right and I just want to sum
those up
so that'll tell me how far I've moved
all of my points and I add them all
together how far are they moved and so
what I want to do here is say look if
the total displacement squared uh ends
up being less than some you know nominal
number so you know that let's say um or
maybe even that I don't know how much I
want to say these things should not be
moving but we have some cutoff
thresholds so these things are all
moving around and eventually they stop
moving right and what we want to do is
say once these things have stopped
moving a certain amount let's say this
for now we'll see what ends up happening
we'll cut to Tunis after they stopped
moving enough we know that we're pretty
much done with how much we need to shake
the system out right okay the last thing
I want to hear is exactly what I said
before I just want to clear the
displacement so if the next time through
its summing up a fresh amount all right
so here comes our N squared right I
remember I told you we were probably
going to be N squared n cubed here
because we don't want to really do too
much with this so what I want to do here
is I want to take the all of the things
that aren't this particular look I'm
going to call these like the repulsors
or whatever I want to take every point
that's not this point right so this is
our repulsor I also need this
so I'm gonna look up which direction I'm
on I'm gonna look up which direction or
rather which yeah which direction is
repulsing me right and I'm gonna skip
myself
so if dur index is not equal to rep
index right I don't want to compute the
repulsion on myself now we can be more
efficient here if we wanted to certainly
by only considering pairs because the
repulsion is going to be the same
between the two pairs I'm not gonna do
that yet right I'm gonna be the
stupidest possible thing
so I'll just say like to do so I'm not
gonna bother with that rather obvious
optimization I'm just gonna write it
just for one and let the loop take care
of it right because again this is
offline don't care rather want to keep
it simple that's probably gonna be the
best plan in the long run okay so we
grab the direction we grab the repulsor
we now know basically right we know what
the sort of action this the sort of
action line is between these two if we
just say look if I subtract right or the
force line right if I take the person
who I'm talking about and I subtract the
person who's gonna be pushing on him
then that's the direction the push would
happen right it's gonna come from the
repulsor toward the direction so
direction - repulsor okay and then I can
trivially say maybe I don't really want
to consider all the points for repulsion
I just want points that are somewhat
close to this one right so I want to
take that force line and I want to make
sure that it points let's say somewhat
sideways might be a way to say it right
so I have a direction that direction
let me let me draw the sign I'm
visualizing all this into my head as I
go and I realize not everyone is so
let's you know for the sake of the
beginner let's let's go ahead and sort
of show explicitly what this is so let's
suppose that I have my sphere like so
and I'm talking about for a particular
direction on the sphere like this I'm
talking about some other direction on
the sphere is going to push on it right
it's pushing on it and the idea is it's
gonna push it away and it's probably
gonna push it more strongly the closer
it is maybe or maybe not love to see how
we want to do that but what we
definitely know is once something is
like more than like half a sphere away
like if it was all the way over here I
don't probably want it to push anymore I
only want things to push if they're in
like the same hemisphere let's say and
anything that's further away than that
on the other side of the sphere I don't
want to use well if I already know that
I've got two normals the you know the
repulsor is already in normal and the
direction is already in normal if I just
dot-product those together I form you
know the standard dot product here right
so I've got a and B if I take the dot
product of a and B I know that that
equals zero per precisely at ninety
degrees right as I go behind it it
becomes negative as I'm in front of it I
come positive so I can pretty clearly do
a quick clip in here where I say hey if
your app there is less than zero
I don't want it so I'm going to restrict
my force computations to only things
that are positive dot product so those
two things are less than 90 degrees
eighty nine point nine nine nine nine
nine degrees is okay but ninety is not I
want everything to be less than 90
degrees apart if they're going to be
applying forces towards each other right
now if I literally wrote this right here
if that was what I left in there we kind
of have a system that may be a little
ill behaved and why might it be a little
because now I've got forces who knows
what I'm gonna write in here first
computation but I've got a hard clip
right and if in math land right
this is mr. function right maybe this is
the force of repulsion right and this is
the distance or something there's some
function I'm about to write that's how
hard this thing pushes this other thing
away right if I insert an if and if is
just a hard clip right it will say look
as soon as I get to this one point we no
longer use that function and we drop
straight down to zero right that means
as I'm running this as people come in
and out of that hard clip they get the
force or not get the force or not right
and it could cause jitter and just bad
behavior what I'd much rather have he's
a smooth fall and hey I just wrote one
right
I literally have the smooth fall off
sitting in my in my coat and I chose not
to use it right so no keep that in there
we've got that inner product let's use
that as part of our fall off so here
we'll just say look if the fall-off is
greater than zero use it if it's less
than zero don't
so that way we come down nice fall off
and then we stop we clip right where we
already knew we were at zero so that if
doesn't cause a discontinuous change in
our force amount it only causes the
discontinuous change potentially in the
derivative but we don't care so much
about that right converges properties in
a lot of stuff is kind of out of scope
of what we're talking about here but you
can see why in general you want sort of
smoother fall-off curves so that your
system isn't dealing with forces that
turn on and turn off turn on turn off
right it helps if they kind of fall off
to zero because then there's always a
smooth continuous force that it's
finding and this these turn into like
hard edges in search spaces and we could
go on for a long time about
how you search through space for
solutions that's tough but that's
getting into really advanced territory I
don't think we want to go um so let's
just keep it simple and say for reasons
you can sort of Intuit at least a little
bit you don't want your forces turning
on and off randomly like that in cuz the
thing that's trying to converge these
points is having to deal with these like
real surprises all the time something
that smoothly goes down produces a more
gradual like rest into place which is
kind of what we hope these things will
do right so we're gonna come up with a
fall-off it's gonna be based on the
inner product between these two if the
inner product is positive we keep it if
it's negative we don't so that means
points don't suck like they won't turn
the polarity and start sucking each
other in right we're just not gonna deal
with that we could maybe it would be
better who knows because it's still
continuous either way so maybe that
would be better but we're just not going
to do that what points are gonna pull
they're only gonna push alright so once
we know that we're going to push we're
gonna take our force line like this and
I think what we would say is the force
line again
we want to apply that displacement based
probably on this fall-off so if two
points were right on top of each other
right we would want the maximum fall-off
unfortunately if two points are actually
right on top of each other they can't
tell which way to separate we could try
to break that tie but let's just hope
other points would break that tie for
them but in any other case where we
produce that line the line is
automatically going to be longer based
on the distance right so effectively
just adding just the line in might be
enough but I think we may want to double
up on that by effectively multiplying
that by that inner product so as you get
down to here
right again because as the line gets
longer the push would get stronger in
fact you know what now I think that's
the opposite of what we want right we
want the opposite of that so we do want
to take this and we want to normalize
that I think we want to take the
distance between in the direction and we
want to I think get rid of that length
and then we want to reintroduce the
length as being the opposite way the
further
you get the less repulsion there is
again this gives us exactly that
fall-off so we just need the force line
to be the direction right
and then we'll reintroduce that amount
okay so then we want to say all right
the displacement for this point is now
gonna get added in this force line times
the fall-off right times some constant
that is our you know maximum
displacement basically right so we have
some idea of what's the maximum
displacement per step we want to see and
so on a sphere we don't want these
things jumping wildly we know the sphere
has radius one we probably don't want
anything moving more than like you know
a tenth of a unit mm-hmm cuz that's a
pretty big move inside something that's
only you know it's sphere that's got a
radius of one so it's two units across
in diameter we don't want something
moving you know anywhere close to one
whole unit there because that's just too
much motion per step we're trying to do
this gradually right so maybe that's the
maximum and if you're right next to each
other you can move that much away from
each other because again remember this
will be effectively doubled in a sense
if two points are right next to other
they'll each move on way from each other
at that speed so in effect you could
double it right so the max displacement
per step wants to probably be pretty low
and it might even want to be lower than
this we'll see because that might move
too far in fact I might set it to
something quite a bit lower for now just
so that we kind of more gradually move
it and now we've kind of done what we
wanted to do at this point we've gotten
to a place where I think and let's put
this way let's put this min total
displacement per step is like maybe this
right meaning if nobody is moving at
least that much then we're kind of done
right alright and so last things last
you've got a breakout or the loop at
some point but I think then we're good
to go so we sum up our total
displacement we see whether or not
everyone's more or less stopped moving
if they have we're good to go
and that should in theory happen when we
get enough people kind of balanced
throughout the sphere again it may have
to be this tolerance may be too high it
may be that or too low so we're gonna
have to tune our movement a little bit
there may be a better way to do that and
I'm not sure what it actually is
so I'll tell you what you know I think
there is a better way to do that I think
there is I'm gonna change my mind on
that so what I'm gonna do here is I'm
going to say alright this conditions
actually gonna happen here before the
step before we take the step and what
we're gonna do here is we're gonna
recognize that we're already doing an N
squared loop while we do that N squared
loop let's sum up the distances let's
let's take all the distances from
everybody to everybody else and let's
see what they are right so for any given
point we will look at what the distance
is between that point and all other
points as like a it's like an average
it's not really what I want I'm not sure
if that's really what I want
you know so the goal of this
distribution is to ensure minimum
distance between points right so what I
actually want to do is I just want to
find what's the closest point so for
every direction what I want to do is
find what is the closest point distance
right so this is the thing I actually
want to find and I can find it squared
just don't really I don't even need to
take any square roots in here so when we
come through here what I'm going to do
is say all right we're gonna get the
forced line that we're going to compute
here right and this force line I'm going
to compute like this and then I'm going
to do the force line length right like
this and then I'm going to say if force
line length is oops
I spell it correctly it's greater than
Syria we're gonna do this right so I'm
basically going to normalize the forest
line after but I'm gonna remember what
that force line length was I'm then
gonna say if the closest distance
squared right
oh and I guess since I have to do this I
don't even need to do squared I think
about it because I had to do the square
root anyway to normalize the vector so
doesn't matter so if the closest point
distance right is greater than the force
line length that I know I found a new
closest point right so now I know what
the closest point distance is for each
one of these for every point right and
so what I'm going to do here is on every
time through the loop I'm gonna say the
min closest point distance equals f2 due
to Max and the max closest point
distance because f-22 min meaning him to
start them on the opposite end spectrum
and each time through the loop I'm going
to just track what they were right so
when the minimum closest point distance
gets updated it's gonna become the
minimum of itself and the closest point
distance for this point and the same
will be true of the maximum just the
other way round
right so exiting the loop I now know for
all of the points in the system I know
the smallest like the closest any two
points are and I know the farthest that
any two points are right I know those
two numbers and so now what I can do is
I can say let's get to the point where
our minimum closest point distance and
our maximum closest point distance to me
do I want to say converge or just not
change that's a tough one
[Music]
so I guess I want to say so what I want
is I want the minimum close distance to
stop improving right that's sort of what
I want and so if the like previous
minimum closest distance didn't get any
better right so you know if I you can
imagine this
I essentially want to say look if the
last minimum closest point distance like
if I didn't get any better June and I'm
saying you know I can't put this down
here though I just realized well so if
the last minimum closest point distance
didn't get any better like if if I
actually you know I'm not really
converging so if the last minimum you
know if the absolute value between these
is like starting to be less than our
epsilon value would be something like
this so if we really can't spread these
points out any better so the whatever
the last if the app if the absolute
value of the last move close to quite
distance minus the minimum closest point
is if it hasn't improved right then
we're kind of done and again I don't
really know really I guess we want this
to be directional even right if if the
last minimum closest point distance
minus the minimum closest point distance
if this hasn't gotten bigger right
meaning if this number is is like going
up that's just bad right because it
should always be going down right the
last minute closest point doesn't should
have it higher
I guess that would do it I don't know
we're gonna have to this is going to be
the interesting part of this I think
probably uh so that's what we kind of
want to do here and we don't really know
what this is going to do because we just
spewed a bunch of code into it and we
haven't thought too hard about the
numerical conditions of it
so who knows but wait where's my um know
why that wasn't in the recent list there
there it is all right
so if I step into this I'm going to take
a look at this code and
and see what happens here here's me
calling oops generate lighting pattern
set the breakpoint on that function so
when I come through here what we're
gonna do is we're gonna look at this
loop we're gonna go through our
directions here and we're gonna compute
this minimum closest point distance
let's just let's just step through this
a little bit once just to see what's
going on
so here's us with a direction and a
repulse or here's the direction here's
the repulsor right there two different
points in the world they're fairly well
spread apart actually we happen to have
a fall-off value that is positive
although probably not super positive no
it is actually is that right should it
be that positive oh yeah okay yeah
actually they are somewhat close
together compute the force line look at
the length we normalize the force line
so now our force line should be you know
a normal looking thing and it sort of is
we then take our max this step and we
supply our displacement that
displacement by the way should be zeros
now we should get something in there let
me do this would be a small displacement
we look to see about the closest point
distance and we update that that should
be set to basically float max by the way
I think this is a nice feature of I
don't know if you noticed this I
actually asked George to add this and he
didn't it's awesome if something happens
to be exactly float Max or one of those
other classes it shows you how cool is
that
right so you don't have to look at this
and wonder if it's quite float max you
just know it's like it's load Max and so
that's really really nice feature I love
that feature I don't know if Georgia now
if you're with us today but that's a
great vibe I've loved it it's been great
because I often set things to the
maximum values like that and it's nice
to see them shown exactly as a human
readable value so you don't have to
guess so in here when we do our closest
point updating you know we're gonna you
know
as we go through we're gonna kind of
look and see if we tracked which one is
closest hopefully we do eventually we're
gonna update our min max closest point
let's see if that looks at all
reasonable so min closest point distance
max closest point distance looks like
float min didn't maybe work there unless
our float min is wrong which it might be
I'm not sure
oh you know what that's not that's not
in the sea thing is it negative float
men it might be I don't know George
help us anyway here where we get maybe I
maybe I set that constant wrong I don't
even know but anyway here's our min
closest point there's our max this point
I'm looking at the wrong place and look
why are they the same that's why the
same so here's the thing that's farthest
away and here's the thing that's closest
it looks like our check is wrong here oh
yeah cuz that's going the wrong way I
set that wrong didn't I cuz that number
is supposed to be getting larger so no
wonder it I was like why did it exit so
soon this should take a while so this
should actually be zero right because
you're moving them you're moving things
further apart over time are you trying
to right so this is more what I would
have expected it to take a long time to
run and now the question is let's see
what we're getting on each individual
step right so you can kind of see it's
slowly getting larger right
slowly slowly slowly as we go let's let
it run for a while and so what it looks
like to me is it looks like our our
displacement step is maybe not as big as
it should be because I feel like we
should be able to converge a little
faster than that also our maximum
displacement step might want to be
proportional to those min distances so I
feel like this may want to get a
adjusted right so like if you look at
the last minused point distance we may
want to start subtracting that away from
our step or something like that at the
moment I'm gonna crank that up a little
bit so the points can move more and just
see what that does to our convergence so
that it looks like at that point the
next step moves things a little too far
so I do think what we want to do is make
this max dispersed step I do think we
want that to kind of be conditioned on
the current state of affairs if you will
that leads me to go maybe I'm gonna
introduce a little more n-squared miss
here because hey to M Squared steps it's
not that different than one N squared
step in terms of whether or not this
thing can run I so maybe what I'll do is
say look what if we said first we're
gonna take the in fact oh you know what
we don't have to do that so the max dis
first step is just x placement we can
just sum without knowing it right
because it's just a scalar that affects
the total distance moved so what we can
do here is say look let's move this down
and say let's put it in here let's take
the max displacement first step we'll
take it into this this equation here
where we do our displacement we'll
multiply it here we don't care how much
they moved any more I don't think I care
about that total displacement so we're
just going to get rid of that I'm gonna
get rid of
of all of this right so don't care about
that we write them back so all I want to
do now is say let's condition the motion
whatever that whatever movement we're
going to do let's condition that on our
new minimum so whatever the minimum
closest distance is I don't want to move
you know when two people are close
together or you know we could actually
use the maximum I don't want to move
however far apart the two furthest
people are I don't want to move any one
more than a certain amount of that
distance let's say right so you know
maybe we do something more like this so
when things are far apart we can move
them maybe a tenth of that distance at a
time when things are not we slow it down
right and maybe this needs to be a
higher maybe that needs to be more like
a quarter of the distance I don't know
but that way at least it's based on
something we measure and let's see how
that goes
all right I want to watch the
convergence to myself so here we go so
here's our min closest point distance
and you can see it kind of converging
there towards what what kind of
oscillate it a little bit I feel like
that was too ungentle doesn't need to be
on the mini closest point distance the
problem is that could be effectively
nothing that's a hard one
I feel like we're still not picking the
right way of doing it like this is much
better
right you can see that converging really
good it kind of started off with big
movements and now it's getting smaller
movements to try and dial that in and I
think that's exactly what we wanted to
see and so I think again like the
problem here is I'm not quite I'm gonna
go draw down the blackboard I think
because I wanna I feel like we can get
this pretty good right still working on
that sort of end point there
well we is there a new version of remedy
by the way so I just glanced over the
chat I saw that oh darn man there's an
8.1
what's an 8.1 I don't even know all
right so this eventually converged which
is what we want so we now know that this
sort of works right and we need to
improve our convergence I think but we
could talk about that as a separate part
let's first see if this produced is any
good results we could have tons of bugs
in there
so it could have been converging on
total garbage right
we watched dude nice convergence on
something but who knows if we were
measuring that something correctly so I
believe that wrote it out to the
handmade sphere yeah here's our handmade
sphere as we look in it you know
generated some some sphere right for us
who knows if it's good but there it is
so if I go ahead and copy the handmade
sphere by NL to W handmade code handmade
was like sphere sampling or sampling
Spears if I go ahead and copy that into
the actual game right I should now be
able to go run the game
oh and autosave turned on autosave is
pretty cool by the way it just saves
things automatically for you so you can
just kind of like hop around do you have
to think about it anymore
so I'm going to go ahead to win32
handmade art eug I'm going to compile it
like so so that we've got our new
spheres in there and then I'm going to
try to yeah run it
now if I go look at those points up here
I don't know what I'll see that looks
like the same set of points what am I
missing
there's no way that produced the exact
same set of points I don't think I mean
but that looks pretty close
did I not rebuild that properly
pretty sure I did that right
maybe we've got some pretty nasty bugs
in here I don't know
we should have seen something change
right it seems unlikely that we produced
exactly the same thing at least it seems
unlikely to me
let me take a quick gander so the fact
that I didn't see an exclamation point
and this didn't change so what happened
did my copy not work did I screw
something up
because this is not the right it didn't
update the file let me maybe four coders
saved it or something let's just find
out there we go that's that's the right
one now right okay so now let's see what
our sphere looks like cuz I guess I
don't know what I did wrong there but I
did something wrong there because it
didn't seem to update the file now maybe
that's a totally separate issue but
here's the actual sphere I guess still
looks wrong like it doesn't really look
like they fanned out as much as they
should to me right it's a little hard to
see because we're seeing all the sides
of the sphere at once but you can see
that those are not blue noise by any
stretch of imagination those two are way
closer than those so that that just does
not look correct to me at all right and
this is clearly the new one I think
right so we're definitely building we're
definitely rebuilding with the correct
sphere file well so much for a quick
victory I guess we've got some issues
here that we've got to look at so what's
the deal how did that not really push
our stuff around very much would be my
first question so taking a look at what
we're doing here let's see you know what
we probably would like to be able to to
draw this out you know it would be nice
to be able to see it happen over time
which maybe we need to do in order to
actually debug it so if I can't get this
working relatively soon I may just move
it into the game and have it be a thing
we can run every frame and watch but if
I look at what's happening in here right
at the moment and we take a look and see
what the dplacement steps are and so on
so let me just make sure I'm not doing
anything too stupid so if we look at the
displacements I grab those out here
I take whichever direction I'm currently
on I'm gonna write that displacement
step to be honest I don't I guess I
didn't really need to to zero those cuz
I actually sum them up just in place so
I think I might get rid of that as a
thing so that it's not in there anymore
as an additional factor so all I really
need to do here is actually say look at
the end of this you have to write this
back into the displacement array that's
going to get applied but when you start
out here it's just going to be zero so
you start out with no displacement you
sum the displacement here and then you
apply just recorded at the end and
that's that's the end of it right so
anyway for each individual point I'm
going through all the other points in
the system I'm ignoring the point itself
and then once I know that it's not the
same point I look up the point so I have
both the one I'm talking about and the
one that's going to push me I look at
what their fall-off is relative to each
other by taking the inner product
because I know they're both normalized
the fall-off has to be greater than zero
so they have to be in the same
hemisphere and when they are I then look
at what's the direction that I would
push this guy to push it away and I
apply that amount I apply the fall-off
based force along that line so I
normalize the forest line first and then
push it now granted I could do better I
could take the perpendicular in the same
direction right if we wanted to and just
to give some perspective on that what I
mean there is just that
if you look at what's gonna happen on a
great arc so you know on the sphere you
know I've got somebody here and
somebody's pushing them who's over here
this arc in between them right so I look
at that arc from the side I have
somebody pushing here and somebody
pushing here right the line between the
two of these is not actually the
direction along the sphere I would push
it has an outward component and what
that means is the amount that I push it
some of it gets eaten up by the
renormalization because if you look at
what happens right if I were to travel
around the sphere I would be going this
way but I'm actually pushing it this way
and that renormalization causes me to
move less than I normally would right
and I move less proportional to how far
away I am so one might argue perhaps
that we're over we're over damping by
using both thus fall off and the
renormalization step but that doesn't
explain why we don't seem to get any
real separation that's just a tuning
issue and it probably wouldn't account
for everything I don't think right okay
so we sum up all of the displacements
here and then we come through this part
of the code and we have a termination
criteria we know that we're not
terminating particularly early because
we watched it run several iterations on
each iteration we load up the
displacements in question we no longer
need this we could just do this because
we don't clear it so we load up the
displacement that we're going to use we
take the direction part here we're gonna
update that we don't need this right so
we're just doing that we apply whatever
the displacement is that we asked for so
like so times whatever the size of
displacements we're going to do so these
displacements here are some of
displacements and the max of each of
them that each of them could have been
was this amount
so we're just multiplying that using the
distributive property noting knowing
that a sum of things that can each be
this long itself could just be
multiplied by a unit displacement summed
together so that's what we've got then
we renormalize to project the direction
back onto the sphere and we write it
back into the location in the array that
it came from and that's it right now to
me that seems pretty simple and then
from there we just pluck those out like
this into our our samples right without
really doing anything else to them and
so that to me suggests that we should be
seeing a pretty good distribution here
in theory now there are other errors we
could have right we don't know for
certain that our output is being
correctly like we do a weird little
casting thing to get around the fact
that C++ was horrible and was screwing
us so it I don't know offhand that we
actually have the exact right thing
happening in terms of transporting our
results over to the to the new to the
saved side of the system and so it is a
little bit hard to know to be fair
exactly what's going on there but what I
would like to do is let's just take a
quick look like a sanity check if you
will on h8 sphere and I'm gonna go ahead
and just go full banana cakes here and
say I'm gonna write out the actual file
I think it's handmade sampling Spears
right so when we run this thing in the
debugger it will actually just overwrite
the file right full up so if I go ahead
and do a double you hand made
odhh handmade sampling spheres and I
just do it
Dell on that if I run it now um
after it finishes with the apparently
really crappy repulsion steps that I've
written that don't work it will write
them out to that file and this will just
verify that we're actually writing to
the thing that we then compile and use
which I just want to make sure is the
case because if we're testing it by
looking at it visually I want to know
that I'm actually getting that result
and so in here I'm gonna go ahead and
and also I'm gonna kill that buffer so
the spheres aren't loaded at all and off
we're gonna go I should also add a
little printf 2h8 sphere inspector while
this is running I might
that's so you know like when we go in
here and we're going to do another round
I might just say let's print out
[Music]
something like this
we're like generating points and then I
might do like this where we just look at
the difference between these two things
and I'll put this down at the end here
so this the top so basically what's
gonna happen is I'm gonna print out in
here like what the men closest point
distance was and what the max closest
point distance was and then the max
minus the min because we really want
those things to be getting closer
together right okay so this ran and now
if I do a derp on that see it's there
and it is right so if I run this right
here's where we can kind of see those
those differences right and you can see
them supposedly converging right this is
the difference between the biggest
distance which means unit between any
two points and the smallest distance
between any two points
that's not good sorry it's the biggest
and smallest distance to the closest
point right and you want those things to
get very close together and you know
they are really close together so I'm
kind of I don't really understand why
we're not getting a better result out of
this but I don't know so another thing
we could do here let me see about
actually looking at that as the value so
if instead of looking at the last min
right if instead I just look at this
convergence here right and actually I
guess I still do want one of these but
instead of last min closest point
distance I want to look at last min max
separation and so I want that value to
get very small and so in here if I said
all right let's just do this where we
compute the min max separation and
that's just the max closest point
distance minus the min closest point
distance right then at each step I want
the min max separation to have gone down
right so I want to say whatever the last
min max separation was minus the you
know the new one I want to have taken a
positive improvement step so the last
one should be higher than the new one
and so if for some reason it's not if it
gets like down to the point where it's a
pretty if it's like too small of an
improvement then we bail right
something like this
and so we're just looking for an
improvement each time through the loop
oops
yeah and it looks like maybe I've got
that little bit backwards let's just
take a look here alright so we've got
our min Max separation is the closest
point - like the met the farthest away
closest point versus the right so the
separation here is going to be tracked
over time so the next separation it's
actually got worse which I suppose could
happen that's why we exit is that really
right
that means our min closest point
distance got more than our max gosh I
don't really know yeah we're gonna have
to say this a little bit a little bit
harder so let's suppose I did a
different one let's suppose I did this
so it'll run for a long time and we just
watch what happens I just want to see
what happens so here are those numbers
and you can see that they do seem to be
kind of converging so I guess it must
just be the first step is a little too
large and causes a general displacement
I don't know why this is why that it's
not a real number though what did I
screw up there
all right so with exception of the first
time where we print out garbage
obviously because of that you can see
the improvement here
it just gets lower and lower each
individual time right and then it starts
going up
weird
it's kind of oscillating in that general
region but you can see that according to
our metrics we are still like we're
still supposedly getting better right
and now we're getting worse like this
number is now going up
hmm so I think we're gonna have to do a
better job here sort of the crappy thing
that I pooped out is not good enough and
we're gonna have to figure out like how
to actually repulse these things in a
way that that's gonna be more stable
again I'm not really sure what the
actual problem is and we're gonna have
to analyze it and find out what caused
it otherwise we're just kind of like
going blind there and if we look at the
maximum closest point distance and we
use we you know we're kind of using that
as a guide to how much we allow things
to repulse yeah I don't really know I
don't really know what we want to do
with with respect to that it I do wonder
if we want this thing to just only use
the cosine as the fall-off and we want
to push them we want to kind of rotate
things more so you know like make sure
that their their displacement Direction
is more based on where they actually are
and we could do that pretty easily
because with just a few cross products
you can see how that was work for
example you know if I wanted to do a
tangential push right so I want to push
this along the tangent it's not that
hard if I have you know this vector and
I say I want to push it that direction
but what I really want to do is push it
along the sphere in that direction well
I know this direction because that is
just this direction it's the actual
thing I'm pushing and so if I took this
direction and the the place that you
know the push that I want and I take the
cross-product right you can see what
that's going to do it's going to create
a vector coming out the side of those
two right and then if I recross right if
I then recross I will get the tangent
that is along that
line right so if I cross the force line
if I do force line cross direction right
this way I get a thing that comes out
here and then if I do direction cross
that product I get something that comes
out here right so what I could do is
something more like this
so again just right hand rule crossing
the force line itself with the direction
that gives me one thing
then I cross the direction again with
the force line that gives me the push
direction right and then I can proceed
as normal
all right I just normalize that thing
and off we go
that's not the problem almost certainly
we've got other issues but point being I
can do something like that
and you know who knows right it
certainly has an effect on the system
that one thinks it converged right but
who knows what that means I mean you
know like I said it looks like we got
bugs so we'll we'll focus on this next
weekend and get that worked out but
using the tangential push let's see if
we resulted in any kind of a different
actual result because I don't you know I
don't know what that looks like since we
can't see it when it's running there
so here's our sphere and this is so
creepy
like it looks exactly the same I'm kind
of wondering if there isn't a bug
separate from this that has nothing to
do with here what I want to know I want
to see if I kind of want to see if our
if our like if the compiler is doing
some alignment casting issues because we
had that we had to do some weird stuff
right with C++ to get this to work at
all and so I want to see if that if this
thing is actually causing a problem here
you know I'm saying to you I don't see
how it could because everything's still
on the sphere so I don't think that
could really be the case but I'm pretty
weirded out by this because I don't see
how we're doing so much moving of things
around and not anything that's not
getting better and maybe there's an
obvious reason for why that would be but
I don't know what it actually is right
maybe I'm just measuring the wrong thing
I don't know I'm curious now - can we
get down to another level of precision
now that I'm pushing along the other one
there oh it's not the program I asked
ran around
so this one can get pretty low it seems
so something is up right I mean it just
doesn't make sense we've just got some
obvious bugs in here that we can find
but this is supposed to measure the
difference between the two points that
are farthest and the two points that are
closest I'm not too far to the first in
tourism but for each point right it's
saying for every point what's the
closest point to me and I'm looking for
the highest and lowest of those values
and we're it's this is claiming that the
set of points that the thing is
outputting has almost no difference so
every point is equidistant roughly from
its closest point I mean maybe you got
to measure more points than that to get
an actual fair output
maybe but like it sure seems like we're
not getting that distribution I mean in
other words when I go and run so let's
say I run the program that means I
shouldn't be able to see any two points
that are obviously closer together than
any other two points right
the closest point to every point should
be about the same distance away you know
I mean
trying to get this and I need a way to
squiggly Center I need a button for like
center around the weird sphere thing I
made it takes too long to get it into
position so I mean just looking at it
it's obviously not true right so look at
this point and you can see the closest
points are there or there right there's
nothing closer to it and yet you come up
here and those two points are like right
next to each other so it's obvious that
even our measurement is wrong so the
question is how is our measurement wrong
if I look here and I take this direction
and I'm looking at all of the other
points in the system
I think right unless there's just a bug
in that just full stop when we unless
I'm not outputting all my points but
anyway when we look here at these so I
guess I'm not looking at ones on the
other side of the hemisphere but that
shouldn't matter right because your
closest point isn't going to be on the
other side of the hemisphere so when we
look at this we take the subtraction of
those two right oh that's the problem
this has to be done right here right so
the only reason this thing was getting
better was because we were fussing with
it in the middle of this probably right
so the force line length here when we
actually take it it has to be taken here
that wasn't the problem before though
because we were doing we were still
doing that so I don't know that this
doesn't really explain the bug this is
just we introduced a bug sort of in here
if that makes sense so this force line
length has to be taken here basically
and this has to be a NAS right so
but again doesn't really help us so I
just don't understand yeah I just don't
understand what's going on there so that
fixes that within with respect to sort
of the the tangent push but I don't
suspect that will help us us at all
because we were wrong we were it was
working correctly the way it used to be
and now it's it's gonna I don't know if
it'll be able to converge with the
forest line push or not but even if it
if it does or doesn't we we don't have
any explanation for what we were seeing
before right
so looking at this it's having a hard
time really getting down particularly
low which kind of suggests to me that
maybe we've got issues with with how our
convergence is working like maybe one of
the constants is bad or something like
this let's just take a quick look
so if we take a look down here you know
maybe this is too large so let's take a
small let's take small steps see what
happens
and so this number continues to climb
which is sort of what we want so we just
want this number to always be going up
and then this number will do whatever
this number does and eventually
hopefully this will catch up to it as
this number stabilizes right
um and you can see that with a smaller
step it looks like before we were maybe
taking two largest steps and we were
overstepping things because you can see
this appears to be converging much more
cleanly right and so you know it's kind
of you know it's a monotonically
improving system now by the things
you're measuring now I'm expecting it to
still not be any good because I'm
expecting if we go because like those
spheres just look completely ridiculous
when you looked at anything look like
what we were measuring made any sense so
I'm not expecting this to actually fix
the problem but at least now what we're
looking at in terms of convergence looks
proper right you can see these two
things moving towards each other and
they just constantly move towards each
other over time right and so now if we
looked at this value I would expect to
be able to see this converge after the
first few iterations where we kind of
get things more going in the right
direction
eventually we should see this number
start to go down to something too low to
be worth it
and that would be kind of the end of the
convergence right and the question is
just how low can this get and I don't
know so let's take a look at what we can
tune this constant to just to see if
there's anything more sensible and then
we maybe have to think about how to
actually compute that constant in some
way that isn't ad-hoc right so again
let's just take a look now we're moving
at you know we're moving at a tenth of a
step a tenth well a hundredth I guess
and now we're moving it at corridor sort
of a tenth of a tenth so you know 0.025
and looking at that again still looks
like it's kind of going properly so the
the min distance is monotonically
increasing the the number up here is
kind of just doing whatever it's doing
but this number continues to climb and
this number should in theory stop
climbing at some point in theory
because we want things to always be
getting further apart so we want this
number to kind of go up and then this
number should stop going up at some
point
so again that all looks kind of good I'm
gonna keep pushing it and just see if I
can sort of manually route fine to find
the amount of repulsion that tends to
work for the system and then I think we
really want to maybe do a better job and
try to figure out how to actually
compute that number like or figure out
what it should be for a given system so
that we don't have to tune a magic
constant because again we want to be
able to change the number of sample
points and still have it work and I
think if we tune a magic constant it'll
probably sensitive to the number of
sample points so we probably want to
throw out a way to compute that even if
we have to take maybe we have to take in
account the number of sample points but
we still want to be able to do that
right
so again it still looks pretty good
right and you can see it sort of it's
this number is constantly going down and
this number is constantly going up which
is what we want and yeah so like what
the level of convergence is that we can
actually expect in this case I'm not
sure and again that's why I say we kind
of want to solve these numbers we want
to go look at these numbers and actually
do a better job analyzing them so we
know what to set things to and what to
look for for our termination criteria
rather than just I'm intuitively looking
so now we're we're in a situation where
we've we've definitely gotten ourselves
a little bit screwed you can see this
number was oscillating a little bit so
it's kind of going up and down which
means this number doesn't doesn't
continue to improve right so it's really
hard to say like yeah what we want to do
that was my plot this
so anyway I guess what I would say is
I'm gonna use point o2 as the cutoff for
now we're just gonna see what happens if
you write it out at that
and that's something to which it seemed
to converge relatively quickly and I'm
just gonna have I just want to see you
like what it writes out at that point
right and it's not gonna be great but
I'm just interested to see so what it
would appear like happens is now when we
go to run this thing I've compiled it
oops
I always fat-finger that you know
ideally we'd see a nice fear we're not
gonna we're gonna see the same exact
sphere we always see and so I guess yeah
we're gonna have to put some structured
art in here and figure out what's going
on because I have no idea but like you
look at these and it's just like it's
nothing like what we're actually getting
I don't think on the readout right so if
we look at that readout the readout
would would have had us believe right I
mean like let's let's recall what that's
actually printing here so when we were
looking at that number that's point oh
two that means that if you took the
closest point to any given point the two
furthest ones and the two closest ones
differ by only 0.02 right where the
sphere radius is 1 so two hundredths of
the sphere radius is the difference
right
hundreds between the farthest away right
so if we were to look at like somebody
who's out in the middle of nowhere here
let's say this saucy gentleman right
here this one the closest point to that
guy is like there and the argument is
that the difference between that
distance right
and say that distance is two hundredths
of this length
it's just nonsensical right it doesn't
work so we know we've got a bug like a
bug bug not an algorithmic bug an
algorithmic bug would be like if this
was was reporting numbers that were
looked about congruent to that then we
would expect what we get what we're
seeing but we're not seeing that what
we're seeing is things that are
massively further apart than our
algorithm thinks they are and that means
we're just doing something fundamentally
stupid we just don't know what it is
right so we're measuring something wrong
or we're writing out the values wrong
somehow which doesn't make any sense
because they wouldn't be on the sphere
presumably right so something's really
busted but we don't know what probably
like this stuff here somehow or
something like the way that when we're
taking this closest point distance right
so you know I don't know somehow this
thing we're taking the closest point
distance and then when we remember the
minimum and the maximum of it somehow
we're just I don't know I mean that
looks like that's right so I just don't
know I don't know how we're managing to
get such a laughably wrong number when
it looks pretty correct it's just it's
almost like we're just not using this
right like it's not actually somehow
using the output but since there's only
one array I'm not sure how that's
possible right like I'm not sure how it
could be doing anything else so I don't
know so we'll go to a Q&amp;A briefly but
we've got our work cut out for us
because there's something nasty going on
in there and maybe over the week those
of you who want to try your hand
debugging can try to bugging this
yourself and see if you could find it
oh did I type it wrong alright so as
usual the chat spots my typos before I
do
that's a pretty bad typo
okay good so now you can see this number
here is oscillating a lot more wildly
than it was before and we're not getting
a good monotonic descent at all there
right so but I gotta be honest even so
we're still in a little bit of a bad
predicament cuz that's not that much of
a displacement to be completely honest
with you but it's still enough right
yeah so let me try setting the our
convergence our Maximus place it down a
little bit now that we have a better
measurement here and let's see
if we can get anything resembling
convergence on this right
all right let me go to the QA well that
saucy gentleman is running
when we start recharging recession never
the rule of the show is I may not take
hints from the chat while the show is
going so because we want the chat to be
interactive at the end of the show I
can't really avoid spoilers right but
the point is when I actually when I'm
actually doing the programming on stream
I'm not supposed to be getting any help
because we're supposed to see what I do
right so I don't get it's because that's
unfair right it's like having a bunch of
extra programmers finding bugs for me
and the point of the show is to show
what happens when a regular programmer
is working on stuff you know someone
with a lot of experience but you're
supposed to see me make mistakes and
you're not supposed to see me get
outside help right you're supposed to
see what I have to do so no never is the
answer I will never I'll never read the
chat during the stream because we're
supposed to get at least two hours of me
trying to do my best
without hints because obviously if you
have more eyes on the problem you get
better right the more people that are
looking at it the better you'll do and
you know especially since some people
watch this show watch this show are
themselves very experienced programmers
so you have a lot of experienced
programmers watching you can find a lot
of boats because those people all bring
all their experience with it too right
so
so looking at this convergence right it
looks a lot better but it looks like
it's never gonna get to much below like
an 0.0 0.0 3 5 we can look to see what
that actually looks like but again I'm
not expecting this to actually fix the
problem to be honest so could you use a
function like gravity and just sum up
all the forces applied by all the other
points where the force is proportional
to the distance squared that's exactly
what we're doing that's exactly what
we're doing like literally it's just
gravity we don't at the moment quite use
distance squared we use a cosine
fall-off rather than just and squared
but they're you know pretty similar so
I don't know like maybe this thing is
now too low and should actually set a
little bit more aggressively just
looking it looks like it is still kind
of doing a pretty good job reducing that
total number but it would remove the if
statements I mean you're never gonna get
rid of all the if statements right
because even gravity if two things are
directly on top of each other gravity
doesn't have a solution for that right
because you don't want to apply the
distance squared as the force you want
the inverse of the distance squared and
so when the distance approach is 0 you
get a singularity so you still got the
if if something like a golden spiral
method two deterministic um yes and no
we if you forget this particular episode
because we're doing something specific
here if you go back to the original
episodes when I was doing the
hemispherical sampling you can see us
talk about various methods and what we
determined roughly was that you really
do want blue noise there are other
sampling patterns as well and people
have done some sampling patterns that
are supposedly like brand-new ones
actually that came out in just a flash
few months where people are like hey I
think we found a way to do blue dye
sampling on hemispheres with a
structured pattern that's actually about
as good you can use something like that
right you can if you want to
is there a save/load state of the entire
game for resume purposes like
serialization not at the moment we don't
do that
no we will add something like that for
the shipping version for sure because
you'll want to while we probably won't
allow you to save your game because it's
sort of a roguelike kind of thing we
will presumably allow you to quit the
game in the middle of a run and then
restart and be in the middle of the run
again looks like our separations getting
worse right now even though our minimum
distance is continuing to climb so we
may be kind of hitting the threshold
hard to say look it might end up going
back down again as long as the second
number as long as this number here right
continues to climb we're still getting
better in a sense but the problem is
this number is also climbing that's why
this number was not going down but now
we've gotten to a point where this
number is going down again so who knows
right let's see how do you measure
stalls that happen on a particular
memory load oh man I mean I want to say
you can't really do exactly what you're
saying meaning there is no real way to
say tell me the exact number of times
that I had a cache miss on this
particular memory stall and the reason
for that is kind of like a Heisenberg
thing because you actually could measure
that but by actually looking at the
difference between the two performance
counters right around the load you would
probably change the actual number right
so it's pretty hard to do exactly what
you're talking about but a version of
what you're talking about
is not impossible so if you just want to
know generally speaking between two
points in your code how many times did
you stall on memory you can do that
there called the performance counters
they're inside all of like like you know
you look at an Intel chip if you go look
at the documentation for it it documents
a bunch of program counters and what
those programmer counters are is they're
effectively things that you arm you can
only have a couple of the Mac of any one
time I think it's like 4 active at a
time I want to say or although it may be
more than that but anyway you can only
arm a certain number of them at a time
but basically what you do is you say I
have four counters I can activate at any
given time which for do I want and you
can say
I want number of l1 cache misses number
of l2 cache misses number of l3 cache
misses and number of cycles stalled in
the scheduler waiting on a cache filler
or something right there's a whole bunch
of these right now what you can do is
you can arm those counters run some
amount of code hopefully a large amount
and then look at them at the end and
then you tweak the code run it again and
look at the difference so you can do a
thing that helps you start to eliminate
memory stalls by arming those those
things right and when you arm those
things and look at their differences you
can start to make improvements to the
code does that make sense so there are
things you can do it's just it's not as
fine grained as you might want but again
by structuring that or like another way
to do it would be like vtune for example
tries to do stochastic methods to do
some attribution of like oh it's ever
this was the instruction pointer at the
time when this kind of thing sold or
whatever you know what I mean
so you can't you can do things like what
you're asking you just can't do it
exactly because modern CPUs are so
intricate that if you actually tried to
measure just the behavior of just that
one line exactly right you would affect
the behavior just by the act of
measuring it that's just the just nature
of the beast I'm afraid
I only caught the end of maybe of saying
wolf the points get further and further
from the spheres controlling almost the
end no we normalize every time through
the loop so you're correct
that's exactly what would happen the
sphere would just expand forever but
what we do is every time we update we
project back down to the sphere so we
forced we forced them to stay on the
sphere as they move each step but you're
absolutely right if we were doing that
only at the very end of all the
iterations that's exactly what happened
they just get further and further from
the sphere
what spatial partitioning method will be
used on this problem well it's it's a
bit premature for me to really say
because we haven't profiled it so we
don't know what's taking most of the
time on each individual step so I
wouldn't really want to recommend
anything without knowing what's actually
slow right so you know we would have to
think about how we would want to cluster
our points but we could probably just do
a pretty rough-and-tumble clustering
based on you know some kind of
directional buckets you know or
something but but again I don't want to
speculate because unless we've actually
sat down and going what do we need to
speed up it's pretty hard for us to to
guess what the correct spatial partition
would be right
okay this is kind of out of left field
for a dedicated server using wind
sockets how would you send the player
data is like a json serialization
possible or should i use other formats
to send player game state to all clients
like every x tix so what I would say is
serializing to something like json
doesn't make a whole lot of sense for a
real-time transmission situation the
reason for that is twofold
one is that json is way larger than it
needs to be and so when you're talking
about something like a server your goal
is trying to minimize the amount of
bandwidth that that server is using and
so you certainly don't want to bloat all
your data out by turning it into
structured text first write something
like JSON may be perfectly reasonable
for using for debugging or for just
getting the thing working if you want to
be able to inspect what the things look
like maybe you send JSON at first just
to get it working but you really don't
want to stick with something like JSON
because you're massively increasing the
amount of bandwidth for no real benefit
right there nobody benefits from having
it be JSON so once you're going to send
stuff over the net and you're talking
about a performance oriented scenario
such as a game server where you want to
minimize events because you're paying
for that bandwidth where somebody is
what you want to do is figure out how to
make the data as small as possible so
that usually boils down to is sending it
in binary and probably sending it some
way that is actually Delta compressed
off of existing data so typically what
you want to do is you want to look at
what the last ACK was you received from
a client and see what they know about
the world and when you go to send them
something else you say what's the
minimum set of changes I would need to
send to them in order for them to
understand the new state of the game now
right but that's usually what you're
doing so no JSON not a great idea it may
work for games that are very simple and
don't have a lot of players don't have a
lot of entities don't have a lot going
on right but for real-time 30 or 60
frames per second games trying to update
their servers that close to that a lot
of game servers run
undersampled because they're crappy and
poorly written but when you're trying to
accomplish that you want to minimize the
amount of text that's flying around and
you want to keep your packets binary
clean tight and hopefully difft so that
you can send the minimum amount of
information and send it as often as
possible
right that's usually what you want
converging to the situation where the
closest point Max and min distance are
similar
isn't that something like trying to
produce a regular solid polygon with
interfaces and then rotate it by
arbitrary angles it's something like
that but it's not exactly like that
because remember we do want this to be
noisy and so we want there to be some we
want to be irregular and that would be
regular right so it's not entirely
different but it's not really what we
want it's slightly different because of
that structure that it has by the way is
this thing almost converged down to the
amount we actually are looking for no
not quite it's like it's it's only
barely there I'm gonna try this and see
if we can run one that we can actually
see what it looks like I'm guessing we
still got other bugs though maybe we run
this and it's just great but I'm
guessing we've got some bugs and so I'm
gonna try it but I'm guessing that even
after we do this it's just not gonna be
sufficient right yeah that's just not
it's not in it's not in the realm of
possibility right
that's it for questions there are
questions probably
on a shipping game would you hardcore
the shooter into the game or have it in
the asset file that decision would
probably be made based on a couple
factors that probably aren't gonna help
you and I apologize but I would say it
depends on the engine and the
development process first of all if
there's only a few shaders I wouldn't
bother putting in the asset file because
it just adds a load dependency that
doesn't really need to be there if
there's hundreds of shaders then they
probably belong in the asset file but
that depends a lot on the development
process if I have a way to do like some
meta programming where I just write my
shaders in my codebase and it
automatically like hot loads them during
development but can bind them directly
into the code at runtime or something
bla bla bla
then I might not want them in the asset
file right because I generally don't
want them in the asset file they're not
assets really their core engine features
that kind of need to be there so I would
say it really depends but I would skew
away from asset file depending on what I
actually have to work with Jeff products
that are voxel octree based not at the
moment not really no let's see another
possible invitation would be starting
with a regular polygon distribution then
apply an initial random displacement for
us to continue simulating yes that that
would probably one way to do it so it
looks like we've finished by the way so
we should be able to build and run here
so you can see it's the exact same
sphere right basically so I'm pretty
sure we've got some bugs in just the way
we're like writing and reading this or
something is happening because there's
no way we can really be measuring the
distances the way that we say we are if
they were actually getting measured
correctly we would not not be able to
see a sphere that looks like this so we
just have some bugs some other bug right
and we just want to
oh and no we don't have the buffer open
the buffer is not open and for at the
moment by the way so we just have some
other bugs here I don't know what they
are but we've got a look at them and
figure out what's going on there you
know I don't know whether it has to do
with how we're drawing them or what's
going on there right but we're probably
just straight up like doing something
stupid like not drawing the stuff that
we actually saved out or who the heck
knows right if we look at where we're
actually drawing them you can see us
doing it here we go through the sampling
spheres one by one in theory and then we
go through the bundles and we load them
out right
and you know it looks okay
you know it all looks well enough so you
know I don't I don't see any obvious
bugs in here certainly
so it's hard to say you know there's a
lot of places that bugs could be lurking
in here though because for example when
we look at this one question here is
what when we look up at that are we
actually seeing you know a thousand
points and so one way we could maybe
like also to bug this a little bit more
is by saying well you know if we were to
change the total number so like in here
right when we look at HH s-- fear if we
were to say like what if we just only
did one then we would expect 18 times
four points right and so who knows like
what exactly that I'll give us here but
like as we sort of push our things
around you can see them kind of
oscillating well that's why I say our
constants need to get tuned a lot better
because they're you know they're they're
not convergent in fact they don't even
make sense I mean you look at what's
happening here and like supposedly our
repulsive force is making things get
closer together right which just doesn't
make a lot of sense at all so you know
something about what's going on here is
just it's just kind of busted but we can
reduce the number of points and then we
should be able to get some kind of
situation that yeah I don't know what
one question I guess I do have here is
also like you know does this just end up
oscillating around some minimum that it
actually is finding you know and I don't
know the answer to that question either
because we're not really looking at it
too much this should probably draw some
stuff as well right but that's sort of a
separate issue so you know you look at
that and you're like well that doesn't
look particularly good right and if I
twist the constant there to make it so
that that can converge
think it's literally that bad right
what's this
and so if we look at what that displayed
there we should now just as a sanity
check if I rebuild I should see only
those you know 18 times four points on
the screen and they should be placed
poorly right so there they are right and
like so right there I can tell we've got
a bug right which is good I'm glad I did
this so if you count the number that are
there let's do it one two three four
five six seven eight nine 10 11 12 13 14
15 16 17 18 but there shouldn't be 18
should there there should be 18 times 4
so if you look at how this is running
right here when it's outputting these
things either we're outputting the same
point multiple times so meaning either
this code is incorrectly writing out the
same point every time and it doesn't
look like it is because it looks like
we're doing you know 1 2 3 right 1 2 3 1
2 3 right so it looks like it's
certainly writing out them separate but
who knows and so the question is like
what's going on and here is this wrong
this is doing this comp index thing
where it calls getcomponent
on a particular one of these is that
busted I don't know let's find out so if
I come in here and look at what happens
with one of these it sure doesn't look
wrong to me but you know we know that we
know this number we know this number is
18 and so the question is if we're
drawing four of these why are we only
what if we're drawing four times for
every one of 18 then
you know where's my 72 points why aren't
they there and so as we go through here
something is busted about some aspect of
this and I'm not sure what it is right I
don't know why we're seeing that
duplication so one thing we maybe should
do is just step in here real quick take
a look at what's happening there so if I
go to handmade lighting here and we jump
oops we jump down to this piece of the
code you know like what's up so here I
am in this routine I've got sphere index
I've got point index and so when we look
at the particular sphere we pulled out
we've got the sample directions here and
that's what we're going to be accessing
if we look at one of these right sample
directions what we should see there's
our X Y Z is each of these XY z-- and
Z's should have four elements and the
four elements should actually be
different and they're not so that's
pretty much all we need to know we're
duplicating things four times for some
reason right so that's problem one since
we're pretty sure siapping in the head
end what I'm guessing is that we're
losing those points possibly in the pull
out stage so here's what I'm wondering
it may be that the C++ rules don't
require this to actually step each time
because like undefined behavior or some
nonsense like this right so maybe let's
say we do this
and I'm saying now C++ can't screw us
being the incredibly crappy universally
complete garbage language that it is now
it has limited ability to ruin
everything like it always does and so
the question is like yeah assuming
there's no bug in here which I don't
think there is that may have been the
problem right so let's see if that helps
at all don't know if it will but we can
certainly try also I think this doesn't
actually need to do this if it's just
picking it out this way like you know
directions you know this could just move
to the outside
in fact
this should have been times floor as
well though so that looks like a
different problem to right
so I think let's let's fix both of these
I think we just had bugs in the in the
readout right
we start with directions each time
through we pull out four of them and off
we go
that may have been it honestly scary as
that sounds no want to actually rerun
this fear generator here no so I'm just
gonna rebuild with that you know newly
built sphere set there and then I want
to hopefully stop the same breakpoint
and just verify that we actually wrote
out different values this time so here's
a sample direction looking at the X the
Y and the Z and all of these should now
have separate values in here and hey now
they do right so now I show you this
noticing 18 points I should see my 72
points and that may have been the
entirety of the book like that could
have been it right so now if we look at
these hey hey that's a pretty regular
looking sphere isn't it right
so now let's crank it back up to what we
were doing before and again we still
need to solve this directional problem I
don't want to be sitting around doing
this garbage right so this is a big
to-do here
determine what the real convergence
criteria is and that's gonna take some
math thing on our part so we're gonna
have to do that because we don't want to
have to this that value I don't want to
have to set as a magic constant we
certainly could but I'd rather since we
haven't really done anything like this
on handmade Hiro before I'd rather show
how you go through working on that part
of the process at some point but if I
change it back to 16 spirits now and run
it again here's us like doing that
convergence and let's see if our
algorithm actually is pretty good and it
was just our read and write that was
scrappy I'm assuming we don't have any
more questions no see post-post wasn't
write C++ it just screws us all the time
it's just a bad language it creates all
kinds of bad bugs that really she's had
no reason to be there right it's it's
like yeah C++ is like the ultimate bad
language it's extremely error-prone it
has lots of really stupid things you can
do that allow the compiler to generate
garbage and things that are not
intuitive based on what you've written
but at the same time not offering almost
any features right it has almost no
features that they're all really
terrible and very underpowered compared
to the versions that exist in other
languages that did them better right so
it's kind of like CLS is like the
ultimate in crap
but to be fair one of the bugs was ours
it was the the fact that we didn't
stride by the right amount so we had two
bugs actually one was ours and one was
seized
Miles's
maybe you can convince John to make
arguments evaluate left to right in ji I
don't care what order they evaluate in I
just want them to not do something
stupid like if you have 4 plus pluses
that shouldn't all just be able to be
represented by one plus plus which is
what was happening there as far as I
could tell right like the number of
times I increment something should it
should happen in an order right and I'm
pretty sure in C++ the plus less
operator doesn't have to do that right I
want to say don't quote me on that but
that's what I want to say
so this converges to a pretty tight
tolerance here so when we go look at
this fear I'm expecting it should look
very nicely covered
will I be in the dry clothes Veda I
don't know you should ask John but if he
wants we can definitely play around with
it on handmade here a bunch like we
could do a few streams where I try to
learn it right and then people can watch
and learn it along with me and we can
write down like any feedback we have or
whatever I've totally be up for that
if it helps I mean we could take some of
our utilities like our PNG processor our
font renderer whatever and just
reimplemented in ji and just see how you
know how it goes all right so let's see
how our sphere is now I'm recompiling
with the new sphere I NL
beautiful so our algorithm was pretty
good as it turns out look at that
good how lovely look at that we did a
great job actually well that's not true
our convergence is crappy and our
constant is fixed so we didn't do a
great job we did a decent job we just
had a bug in terms of how we were
writing them out look at that
that's lovely right quite nice and so
our next goal is just to slice this and
that won't be too hard is just to slice
this into pieces so that we can have
1/16 of the spear sampled on each time
and then we can just roll that in as our
sampling sphere and we're good to go so
we're pretty close we just had to come
up with a good algorithm for slicing it
right and again that could be just a
pretty simple N squared algorithm it
takes like farthest points or something
I'm not sure if that would work well but
that's that's roughly what we want to do
so I'll be back here next weekend and
we'll do that until then let's just
appreciate how lovely our sphere looks
right now because it really does look
pretty darn lovely
like no part of its really that regular
right but it all is still pretty
uniformly covered like everything is
just a little jittered but it still kind
of always has a nice density pretty much
everywhere so seems pretty good but I
don't know who knows or
as you decrease the magic number does
this method converge towards a uniform
distribution hmm
probably it would probably if you set
the number too low and force it you
probably would eventually get some kind
of a regular pattern because if you
don't leave any slop it can't be
completely random so we don't want it to
converge to like too too tight of a
tolerance right so all right I'm gonna
wrap it up pretty happy with that sphere
though thank you everyone for joining me
for the episode of handmade hero and a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along series at
home you can always pier to the game at
hand made here at uh org
it comes with source code so hey you can
try your own sphere point generator and
see how you do I'll be back here next
week when we'll work on tuning those
constants and figuring out exactly how
we want to do the repulsion stuff just
to tune that a little bit more and then
we'll do the slicing and then I think
we're good to go for actually using
these spheres as our sampling spheres
which is great and that's another piece
of our lighting puzzle solved that's it
for today I hope to see you back here
next week until then have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the
Internet
they can use everybody
you