hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero shall we code a complete game live
on Twitch no library's no engine all our
own code and well we're at a Friday
where we finished the thing we were
supposed to do yesterday and so the next
thing that we wanted to do I kinda
didn't want to start it just on a Friday
when we're just ending so we're kind of
in a little bit of a snail here where
I'm not sure what we should really start
doing we could try to look for the
variable I don't think that's gonna pan
out especially not in just one session
so we got to figure out something else
to do now somebody on the pre stream
mentioned that they thought they might
have seen a bug in the collision
detector that was about you know a typo
regarding what what we were supposed to
test against I introduced a new variable
instead of we were testing against it
and then I didn't like type it in in the
right place or something and so I feel
like maybe since again we don't
necessarily know exactly what we should
be doing today let's let's tackle that
first and we'll see what emerges from it
now of course it is day 88 so if you're
following along at home and you
pre-ordered the game download day 87
source code that's the stuff that I am
working with today
and so you should be on that as well now
they were saying that it was a thing to
do with test PE so let's take a look at
what test B was doing and and make sure
that it actually does something
reasonable with that so I guess what I
will say is the fact that we introduced
SP here and then never use it suggests
that either there actually is a bug as
the person was suggesting or we just got
rid of the need to do it but let's take
a look here so we're doing a test T test
be we're doing a speculative collide of
this entity and this other tests entity
and then assuming that it actually
occurs we don't use test P for anything
in particular so I'm not sure let's take
a quick look and see it's been a while
since we've looked at this code let's
take a quick look and see what we were
doing with speculative collision so with
Beckett if collide it looks like for the
most part
yeah we are we're really doing more of
uh we're doing more of a direct query
here which I assume we probably meant to
do spec to let spectacle I'd take this
test fee right I suspect that's what we
were meaning to do and then just never
did it so I suspect we would want to
actually have that work out so again in
the ground point is no longer actually a
thing we kind of said that the entity
ground point is always actually there so
I'm not sure you know we could pass test
P but we need to have get entity ground
point work through that test fee hmm so
it's a little tricky well so let's take
a look if we were going to pass test P
to this too speculative collide and say
here is where we actually want to know
you know if you could actually do this
you pass in the the test point then
really what we want to do here is say
that this move or ground point thing we
want that to be based off of test peak
now if we were still like I said to
allow entities to return ground points
however they wanted what that
essentially means is that the get any
ground point would have to be able to
take like four for an FTP it would then
have to return the ground point if the
entity were in that location basically
right and in this case we pretty much
know that that's always just going to
return this directly but it does seem
like maybe we want to do it that way
just so we can kind of I don't know
allow that that sort of that sort of
thing to happen we could also make it so
that old code worked okay like code that
didn't want to know anything about that
could just pass the MVP like so so it
could you know do the same thing it used
to be doing pretty trivially right so
this would allow us to still to do that
call with a test P and yeah like we
didn't really have a bug that was
manifesting itself so it's not like we
can really test that and again we're
kind of haven't finished really the
detection stuff that we really need to
do and so at some level it's hard for us
to know whether this thing is working or
not yeah it's kind of it'd be kind of
hard to know like we wouldn't
necessarily see it either way so we will
need to put the stairwell back in
probably first of all so maybe we'll
also do that and yeah of course we we
aren't really necessarily ready for that
because we aren't doing the multiple
ground level rendering stuff yet but
we'll see we'll see how it goes so let's
see add stair
I think the stairwell was the only thing
that ever used that speculative
collision so far so yeah all right so
let's put those stairs back in there and
see how that goes so you know if I if
I'm coming up here oh man there's so
many ground patches all over the place
now that's hilarious
and of course there's more than fit in
our cache so like you can occasionally
see them blinking in and out because now
we've got two layers of them happening
that's pretty trippy yes so
unfortunately it's pretty hard to tell
whether we would actually be fixed
whether we'd actually fix that bug or
not right because we don't really have a
clean way to have it manifest itself so
there's nothing we can really do about
that for now I guess so yeah what I
should do is I should update our ground
cache a little bit just in preparation I
should say that we're gonna have a
slightly bigger ground cache let's take
a look here
where is that got our grab buffer count
so let's let's make that a little bigger
let's make that 64 for now so we can
handle both stairwells so that you know
because again generation is super picky
right now it's super slow doing that
generation and so we kind of want to
make sure that everything once it has
been generated it stays generated until
we actually have some some more
efficient stuff happening there but
either way it'd be nice to have a little
bit more here yeah so I think we're okay
at least you know if that bug was
actually going to manifest itself we
would have seen it before now so I think
it's one of the things that we're kind
of just fixing because it's you know it
should be bus it just doesn't happen to
show itself so we can't really test to
see whether we fixed it but yeah so you
know one thing that we're probably gonna
have to do and I guess maybe this is
that indication maybe we should do this
today do this a little provisionally I
don't know if it's a good idea or a bad
idea but you know everything's just kind
of drawing in a random order now so we
can't even see sort orders and stuff
like that so maybe what we will have to
do now is is actually go in there and do
a little preparation for next week where
we're actually putting things into some
sort of a render list you know so that
we can sort them and do other stuff like
that because we may be in a situation
where we can't really do anything more
logically you know we can't we can't
really do anything even just as test
code without having it so that we can at
least sort things in the renderer to
some degree we are we're getting there's
a texture seam down there and I assume
that that's just the two different
levels being on top of each other yeah
you know we've got another problem too
that we're gonna have to face it's it's
a lot of this stuff is just order
dependencies and I'm not sure exactly
what we should do to break them but like
if we've got multiple levels of ground
one problem that we have is we don't
have any way to scale bitmaps at the
moment right and so without any way to
really scale bitmaps it's going to be
hard for us to do anything in terms of
you know when things get smaller and
we're
on different height levels so you know
what we may have to do as well is do
something like where we are we go back
to pure orthographic just for a little
while so that when we draw things on top
of each other they're still the same
size we don't make them smaller when
they when they recede but I'm not sure
again this will be fixed once we have an
actual render but I just don't know the
order to do those in so all right so
yeah let's take a look at the to do list
briefly and see what's going on here
we've got our Z stuff we've got
collision detection I've got multiple
sim regions per frame and debug code
asks the streaming audio meta games yeah
this I'm not sure I'm really not sure
what we should tackle we need some
little bite-sized thing we could do
today that would be useful and I don't
actually know what that would be maybe
starting to pull things out into a
render list just is the best thing to do
I don't know it seems like it certainly
could be it's plausible right so maybe
we'll just do that you know maybe that's
what we'll do so let's let's start it
let's do let's do a handmade render
group or something like this let's let's
go ahead and just start shunting things
out here because we've got a bunch of
code that does rendering and let's let's
try to start unpacking it into something
useful that just seems like it seems
like the smartest thing I guess all
right so what we need to start doing in
terms of rendering stuff is we need to
start buffering things up somehow so
that we can sort them right at the very
least not to mention the fact that we we
have other things that we'd probably
like to do during that buffering like
doing the translation of the coordinate
systems meters to pixels and why and all
that stuff being flipped in other things
like that we really don't want the game
code thinking about those things we want
the game code code to just work in world
units all the time as much as it can and
and we want the renderer to just take
care of stuff that has to do with
rendering so that if you change out the
renderer or how it's being rendered or
changed the resolution or do all those
sorts of things
we really don't want that to infect the
game code right we want the game code to
be able to work in some canonical set of
Units in a canonical way and have it
just put out what it needs to be
rendered and then the renderer can take
care of sort of all of that fussing
right all the fussing that has to go on
in there and so if we take a look we've
already kind of got some of this right
we've already got this this sort of
buffering that's going on here where
we've got piece groups right so we've
got entity visible piece group and those
piece groups get pushed right and you
know they they get built up and then at
the end after the the things all get
pushed on there
there's a there's sort of like an event
that happens down here where they
actually get rendered and so what we
could do instead of what we're doing now
is just pull that piece group concept
out and make that actually just record
all the pieces right so that it just
does all the pieces and then draws all
the pieces so we're kind of like almost
there already right if we just kind of
when it took it a little further so
maybe that's what we'll start with okay
so I'm gonna say that we're gonna go
ahead and just pull out one of these end
of the entity visible piece group things
right so I'm gonna pull that out here
and we're going to start fussing with
that as you know as basically a render
thing so let's see empty visible piece
where is the piece group there it is
this is just a part of the render push
buffer hey look we have it to do that
says this is exactly what we should do
and you know what I agree with that so
I'm going to go ahead and pull that out
there and I'm going to include this as
we have included our other things so I'm
gonna say all right we've got ham eh
we've got handmade render oops and made
render group H and we've got a handmade
render group dot CPP so
let's go ahead and compile this and I
should actually make one of those there
we go so hmm
all I'm gonna do at first is try to
expand that notion of the piece group
there I'm not even gonna change the name
yet I'm literally just gonna try to make
it so that it doesn't get zeroed out it
just tracks everything right and in
order to do that we obviously have a
problem and that problem is the piece
count here is going to be way too low
for all the things that we actually need
to render now what I could do up you
know at first is I could just make it
not be too low right I could just say oh
you know it's giant and so maybe that's
what we'll do at first and and we'll see
how that goes so if I go ahead and take
this excuse me and I go ahead and take
this out of a loop and say all right
we've got a piece group here I will get
that out of the transient arena right
I'll just say okay let's let's get one
of those I call them mandalas in my in
my main code base nobody uses that term
so I used to Reena on the screen but
okay so what I actually want is this so
the transient arena what I want to do
here is I want to to push one of these
entity visible groups on there so now
we're actually getting it in sort of
that inside this temporary memory region
so eat a lot of mat if they get flushed
for us we don't really have to do
anything special there right and then
I'm going to compile it we're gonna get
that back as a pointer so the piece
group here now is actually going to be
in directed and that's actually kind of
nice because it means we don't have to
take the address of it everywhere right
so that just works like this and so on
and then we're gonna have to do one more
thing right which is actually kind of
going to be a little complicated but it
sets us up for what we need to do so
it's all good
and that is that the actual rendering
now if I were to move that outside so
you know let's say I move that out here
you can kind of see that we have this
loop over all the entities so we're
pushing them all into this into the
piece group
if I do this now after when I loop over
all of those pieces we have a problem
which is that and you can actually just
see from the compile error you can
actually see that when we use me what is
that I'm sorry yeah or maybe not from
the compile error okay nevermind it
would be nice if this were scoped inside
here to say the least but unfortunately
it isn't I guess we could do that in a
way that the compiler would probably be
okay with we do something like this if
that makes sense where we're just going
through and actually referencing at each
time but yeah what are you gonna do
alright what I was trying to say is this
right here where we get an entity ground
point in order to base off where all the
pieces are supposed to go that's a
problem right because now all the pieces
are in one giant buffer so we've kind of
we've we've taken all of the pieces that
we want to render we've put them in a
giant buffer and now we have no idea
which one goes with which entity right
so we need some way of knowing for a
given piece what is its basis like what
where was it supposed to be relative to
right and so what I'm going to introduce
on top of this for now and you know I'm
not totally sure that's exactly how we
want to do it but it's something similar
I'm gonna introduce a basis here for our
piece groups right so I'm just going to
call this a render basis for now and
what this is is this is going to be some
thing off of which other people can you
know can reference their coordinate
system right so you know like we were
saying here we were saying we want that
entity base P and the reason that we
didn't store that at the time was
because we might actually move the
entities around after we've built up
their kind of render state which you
know to be fair isn't necessarily
something that we want to do in the long
run so that may not actually persist but
if it does we want to be able to do that
adjustment after the fact and so doing
that adjustment after the fact here it's
just something I'm going to allow for
now in the renderer and in order to do
that we need some method of indirection
and so what I want to do
is I want to do something excuse me
where are our render basis can actually
be set sort of after after that fact so
let's let's see how we would do that
here so when we grab out an entity and
we're going to actually do some
rendering for it assuming that I guess
we we actually know whether we push the
bitmaps in here right where we're doing
these push but push bitmaps that sort of
thing what I want to do is I want say
all right give me a render basis right
give me some basis that these guys can
be off of and you know set this as the
current default basis that everything
that we render is going to be based off
of so maybe you know I'll do it like
this where we do like a push basis kind
of call on the piece group right and
then we can set that basis later all
these things will be relative to it
right and then at the very end we could
do a pop basis and maybe we don't I
don't know if we want push and pop you
know maybe we'll just do a you know a
new basis or something like that so I'm
not exactly sure how we want to do that
well we'll sort of find to that later
but anyway that'll give us back that
basis and then after we do our entity
movement right then we can go in after
the fact and set whatever that that
p-value was you know directly off of
what we would have done in the past
right so like this and so in order to
get this out here what we need to do is
we need to see what the piece that we
had pushed on what its basis was and
just grab the point that you know that
basis point off of there so like this
right and so all I'm really doing is
deferring that setting till the end so
in order to make this work rec I said
each one of these guys each one of these
pieces has to know what basis is
relative to right and so and then we
also need to know for these guys at any
given time what the default basis
actually is right so this way when you
push something on one of those piece
groups when you when you basically push
piece groups on to the list of things to
fill
you each one of them like when we do
push bitmap push rekt whatever it calls
the push piece function what we can do
in that push piece function just say oh
okay
anytime you push a piece on will just
say that whatever the basis that's
currently set in the piece group as the
default basis that's the basis that'll
actually be used right for the piece
group you know essentially that is what
this coordinate will be relative to
right this would also allow us to fix
our shadow problem there's a couple
things we could do there too but again
I'm just kind of doing this in sort of a
very ad hoc fashion just to sort of play
around with it and start to compress it
down into something more usable I don't
know that we'll want to do it this way
in the past because there's some
indirect like we don't know what our
performance situates going to be in how
much in Direction's gonna be a problem
here so I'm just literally porting the
code as we had it and then later we can
decide whether we think that's a good
idea or not that makes sense
so anyway I've introduced that basis and
now when we actually initialize that
piece group you know at the start of
things which is really you know now our
kind of our renderer we need to have a
default basis right and the default
basis can literally just be you know
something that doesn't actually displace
anything right so we can say that the
default basis is just 0 0 0 it
essentially doesn't actually change
anything that's going on right and then
we just point to that so now everything
by default is rendering there but you
know in circumstances where in
circumstances where we actually want to
start changing it we can right and so we
could also do this this way in fact we
could do this this way for now without
actually having to add any actual
functionality to the the piece group
itself although we want to get there
eventually I can just say all right
every time we want to make a new one of
these we just get one out of the
temporary memory store we go ahead and
and set the default basis for our piece
group to be this one so that everything
that we push will be based on it right
in fact yeah do it that way
and then at the end we go ahead and set
that basis be we come back through here
and we pick it back up again for each
individual piece and it's important to
note that we never have a piece that
doesn't have
the easiest because we start out with
one that's the default one right
we don't initialize this corner - no we
initialize it to actually a valid basis
and that way we don't ever have to check
to see whether a piece has a base we
just assume that it does right so this
now should in theory anyway render all
of our stuff in that second in a second
pass here right it should go ahead and
actually give us exactly the same thing
that we had before at least in theory or
maybe not actually I just realized
something we did not do this actually
does not get cleared here which is not a
good idea so hold on one second
well I actually do that and then we can
go back to what I was about to say so
default basis gamestate piece count is
zero there we go and so that should in
theory work we push those bases on we
push everything relative to them we set
them to the correct thing we then come
through and draw everything so let's
let's find out let's see if that works I
don't know if it will or not it appears
to be the same as it was before which is
what we want which is good and so that's
all you know that's all pretty
reasonable no worries there and so now
if we wanted to we could actually sort
the things in there as well we could
sort the things by their Z values and
other stuff like that so if we wanted to
fix this like going behind trees problem
like that we could fix that now it's not
a good time to teach how to sort things
so we probably won't do that right now
but that that is something we would do
after probably sometime soon all right
so this allows us to essentially this
allows us to see essentially what we're
doing with the render what I want to do
is actually put everything through this
now like literally everything that there
is just to sort of get us even closer to
having sort of something that looks more
like a renderer or at least the the
skeleton of a renderer where the
renderer would go so what I'm going to
do is I'm going to grab isn't this to do
actually goes down here I'm going to
grab this piece group and I'm going to
move the piece group up and sort of give
it its
of its own memory effectively so that it
can it can operate mm-hmm and do all of
the rendering for us
and I suppose actually for now the
temporary memory that we have here begin
temporary memory I could actually
enclose this for now in just a thin
another one of those right so this is
render memory and these guys are
overlapping and so at the end what I'm
gonna do here is I'm just going to end
temporary temporary memory for both of
them right so this is not what I
actually want to do in the long run but
it's you know it's good enough for now
and so based I just move the piece group
up there you can see that that doesn't
really have any effect yet things are
still working exactly the same way as
they were before but now what I can do
is start to change all of the draw calls
that we were doing before I want to
change them all into draw calls that
operate off of this this piece group
right that's what I'd like to do and so
let's let's go ahead and just do that
slowly so we've got push rect right and
push rect is a thing that allows us to
draw rectangles using the piece group
stuff and so you know let's just
translate this stuff I guess somewhat
directly into the piece group although
you know what maybe this first one I'm
not actually certain that I I mean what
I just said because let's actually save
that one since that's actually kind of a
special call this is a clear right and I
think we might want to add that as a
real call alright so first let's do this
bitmap calls here these are the ground
buffers so in order to do this if we
were going to draw all the ground
buffers if we turn this to a push bitmap
call then really let's see what I have
to do is pass an offset which we don't
need oh I guess this actually is the
offset sorry it's ground X ground Y
would be our offset in fact I guess I
don't need to pass it as an X Y I can
just pass it like so as it actually
already is a vector right and then
alignment this a push bitmap call this
was aligned
off of just off of its own center-right
it's it's this right here so really we
could pass this in as if it was the
alignment I don't know if we actually
want to do that or not we could just say
there's no alignment for now but if you
know more correctly it might be to pass
in a messy alignment and I think that's
all we really need to do for pushing the
bitmaps on for the ground buffers right
or not that is not that's not what we
wanted to see all right I take it back I
take it back entirely that is clearly
not the right place that we're actually
trying to draw these from oh well you
know what I just realized
this is still doing all of the
translation like the X the Y this is
still doing all of that sort of
inversion scaling meters to pixels doing
all that stuff and we don't actually
need that to happen anymore because
that's actually happening you know in
the actual mm-hmm
in the actual quote unquote renderer now
so let's take a look in there at how
that's working so push I'm gonna copy
these guys out so I can see them so I
can more readily kind of look at them
right I'm gonna take these guys I'm just
gonna put them in here so I can see them
let's take a look at that okay so all
right if I look at these guys here
looks like essentially we do some
translations so we do translation of the
Y we flip the Y here alignment is is
actually not in world units it's in it's
a bitmap unit so we this is a bunch of
stuff that we really want to clean up so
let's take it one step at a time but
that's really I think that's maybe what
I want to start doing there because
that's that's really it's just it's
gonna be impossible to get this stuff
right it's so janky basically that we
kind of want to start start thinking
about how to regularize all of these
sort of ad hoc rendering things push
them down to something clean so that we
can get kind of get rid of all that that
craziness but yeah so if we take a look
at this we don't need to do meters per
pixel to pixel anymore the Delta just is
the Delta we don't have to invert Y
anymore so that's so just going to be
straight
the alignment that's in pixels we want
that to be half the width half the
height right and so let's go ahead and
put that actually into the alignment
field because we want that to be again
done in pixels not in in pixel space not
in in meters in meter space so there we
go get that out there and we don't need
to adjust for the screen Center anymore
because that's taken care of for us as
well so really Delta X Delta X Delta Y
is just where the ground is which means
essentially it's just that right so
let's take a look at that and see where
we're at there what is the complaint the
complaint is those are integers that's
true let's see cannot give our argument
three from Veet okay it just wants the X
Y there huh
where was the Z so push bitmap where
does the Z go offset Z so for some
reason we lost our offset Z here but it
would be that right like so however six
from v-22 real yeah okay so that's that
all right sorry about that that was a
little janky there all right well we're
not quite there yet because we're now
drawing our tiles in the wrong places
unfortunately because you can see that
our seams have come back right although
actually you know what
that may just be the draw order because
now we're drunk two sets in one of those
sets is potentially Z shrunk so let me
go ahead and do our turn off our
stairwell against we're not really ready
for that yet all right so okay now we're
back to something we know is actually
there so let's see so that we have
introduced something that's not drawing
these in the place that we actually want
them to be drawn so why is that what
have we done incorrectly here
delta z let me just double check that
delta z is not causing us problems as
well since we don't really have a we I'm
assuming it's not yeah because Delta Z
should be 0 in these cases all right so
let's figure out what we've done wrong
here in terms of rendering let me make
sure again that we are actually doing
something saying with the with the Y
values and so on so let's take a look
we're properly doing our meters to
pixels here and we're negating that Y
offset which is what we want now we
should take a look at what's going on in
the draw code so I guess I don't
technically know what we're doing here
anymore since I don't actually remember
so the basis P is not actually being
used at all because that'll just be
zeros right so that's not going to
affect it the screen Center X in screen
Center Y is what we were using before
we've already negated the offset Y right
that already happened and we've got that
alignment that should be correct because
we we did that as as half the width and
height which is what we want the entity
Z is still going to be 0 so that's good
so that one affected either and the Z
fudge the Z fudge only multiplies values
that were already 0 right so this should
all this should really just only amount
to screen Center X plus the Delta X
which is what we wanted I guess entity
this piece entity zc x entity Z of
course entity z is 0 so that term will
also be not there so it looks at least
somewhat to me if that looks like that
should be coming out to the same values
and I'm not sure why it isn't that looks
like that should have been the same
values as what we were passing to it
originally right and so so let's take a
look and see if there's if there's
something I I did that was more subtle
that makes some sense as to why it
wasn't working so with the Delta
subtraction we're grabbing that out
right we've got the alignment is half
the width and the height because we want
to move it backwards well I'm assuming
yet that's the alignment point so that
doesn't need to be negative because we
already negate it there yeah so that's a
little unusual so what that looks to me
like it should have been correct and I'm
not entirely certain why it wasn't what
I'd like to do is be able to step
through this and look at it a little
more carefully in order to do that I
feel like I'd have to cut down on the
number of things going through this list
so I can see them although you know what
this is the ground buffers are gonna be
like the first thing in the list anyway
so that that does help but let's just
I'll take one more look at it to see if
I guess why anything but then otherwise
I guess we're gonna have to kind of dig
in a little bit and see what's going on
yeah because otherwise that looks that
looks fine to me
it looks like it should compute the same
value right because screen and the
between around point Xtreme Graham MD
ground point x and y are gonna be screen
Center X screen Center Y right like here
in here and then the piece offset X Y
X&amp;Y the piece offset Y has already been
negated right to go in the opposite
direction so that's already correct and
then we should ends up passing the exact
same stuff to draw a bitmap
that we were passing before right and so
there shouldn't really be there
shouldn't be that kind of weirdness
happening there and I'm not sure why
there is because before we were just
doing a draw a bitmap of
of exactly that with this the
displacement yeah off from the center of
the screen so that's really odd that is
really odd to me and I'm gonna see if
there's something that I can easily you
know what it's drawing the same bitmap
everywhere why is that I feel like I've
introduced a bug where we're always
drawing the same bitmap what oh snap
so that you see what happened there I
don't know if you saw what happened
there I'll give you I'll give you guys a
little bit if you haven't already got it
yet you maybe you had it before me right
so in order to conserve on memory right
we were just we weren't actually sending
the whole loaded bitmap down we were
just using one on the stack right and so
what we wanted to do this is kind of
funny so what we wanted to do is we want
to defer that rendering and we were not
saving the actual loaded bitmap itself
we were instead doing a pointer to it
but doing a pointer to it means that
this trick doesn't work anymore right
this trick doesn't work anymore because
we don't actually have a bitmap to point
to it's just the same stack bitmap all
the time that we were reusing so that
yeah that's not very helpful I wonder
what we want to do to solve that we
could push whole bitmaps on every time
we render that seems wasteful so I
wonder if maybe the smartest thing to do
is just say alright well you know the
number of ground buffers is relatively
low so maybe it just was not it didn't
make any sense for us to store that
every time
I'm not sure the other thing we can do
is is use kind of a dual we could do
something where we when we do render
pushes we eventually have two pieces of
information that go with it one is the
size of the thing and one is you know is
it's actually the sort of the the the
pointer to the bits well I think I'll
just go ahead I mean it was it was it
was a silly thing to do anyway
I think we'll go ahead and say let's
just just put that back to being a whole
bitmap you know why not all right so if
we do that let's do that if we do that
then now we don't have to do this
anymore right we don't have to do the
ground bitmap template thing so I'll go
ahead and pull that out you have to do
that right and so our ground buffers we
can now actually just get the buffer
that's actually off of RAM buffer itself
like that good map so and got to take
the address of it let's see here and
these are now arrows so buffer is now
changing this is all those things that
it's so lame and see that you have to
keep flipping between two things it
shouldn't matter which one it is it's
it's always lame but you have to deal
with that anyway ground bitmap template
is not it's not a thing you're very
correct that it is not a thing so all we
need to do here is just change this to
actually be the thing that we wanted to
use in the first place so that'll save
the bitmap and similarly here we can
just go ahead and and call call that out
say alright get the ground buffer bitmap
anyway get rid of that sort of cash in
there entirely okay that was pretty
funny so we actually were drawing it
just fine I think it was just a case of
we can't defer rendering on that
particular thing because we didn't have
anywhere to say where the bitmap itself
actually was all right so let's see if
that fixes our problem
and it does so that's good so now
everything is going through the deferred
path we're building up
well not quite everything guess we still
have a few more things potentially to
get rid of let's take a look here oh no
I guess we did so really the only thing
yeah the only thing that we're calling
the only the only place we're calling it
is there so we've gotten draw a
rectangle calls those are are actually
still occurring right but we don't have
any more draw at that goal so all the
drum pitfalls are going through the same
path so that's that's pretty cool
yeah yeah all right
so what I would like to do here I don't
know why we're still doing this this was
some old test code I died that we were
trying to draw some I don't even know
what we were trying to draw I don't even
remember what it was from but these are
not actually things we actually needed
let's get rid of those so what we would
like to do now is we'd like to actually
get rid of that other draw rectangle
call this one right here and what this
was was this was just a clear right and
so what I want to do is I want to I kind
of want to get get that in as its own
call that makes sense and the reason
that I want to do that is because not
only do we want that to be its own call
probably like clearing the buffer should
be something the renderer knows about
but that'll actually be our excuse to
now turn this into more of an actual
quote unquote rendering system or at
least the the skeleton of one alright so
what I want to do first of all let's
let's stop calling this entity visible
piece group because that doesn't
actually make any sense let's call this
a render droop right and now what I want
to do is is change entity visible piece
group to be render group like so and
this is literally just search and
replace right all I'm gonna do is just
is just straight-up search for the place
so let's see here
all right so search and replace a lot of
fun for the whole family we have search
and replace we now have a render group
and this is actually for now I think
what I'm gonna mmm I'm not sure exactly
how I want to do this it's hard to say
I'm thinking it through but what I would
like to do is I would like to extend
this notion so that you can have
multiple things pushed on to this render
stack and I don't know whether I want
them to be fixed size with not the thing
is to know how far to skip to the next
one all right here's what we're gonna do
I'm just going to do it this way for now
and we'll see whether we like it or not
alright so what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna say that the render group no
longer has this kind of weird thing
where it's just got some number of
pieces or whatever it is there right I'm
gonna say that I'm gonna I'm gonna
actually do this as a as a linked list I
think I'm really torn with how I want to
do it I really just don't know I don't
really want to be a linked list I kind
of want it to be a packed set all right
no I changed my mind again I'm I'm I'm
wildly in my head there's all these like
voices saying which one that maybe we
should start with and when that happens
it's best to just pick one go and then
you see where you end up because it
usually means that there's no perfect
decisions but anyway
here's what I'm actually gonna do I'm
gonna say that we've got some memory
right and that memory is is the push
buffer right and the phrase push buffer
is usually used in rendering to refer to
a buffer that you just push things on
right and so what we're gonna do is
we're gonna you've already kind of seen
it happening right we just organically
created it which is we were kind of
putting these visible pieces these
entity visible pieces we're kind of
putting them onto this buffer and then
we're drawing them all right and then
when we're done drawing them all we just
throw the whole thing away it's a song
right goodbye and so what I'd like to do
is extend that notion to say oK we've
got a push buffer that
which buffer is now just gonna be some
chunk of memory and we use up that chunk
of memory and then we would go back and
retire it in order or we do other fancy
things who knows right but I'm just
gonna extend that counselor to say okay
we now we don't have that we actually
have some kind of arbitrary memory in
there and when you do a push piece call
you actually push a certain size on to
that push buffer so it's gonna I'm gonna
do something like push buffer size here
like how big it is and I'm gonna do
another thing here which is like max
push buffer size right and then I'm
gonna actually introduce I know you've
only seen this once or twice for me it's
it's scary I'm actually gonna do
something that actually just creates one
of these like allocate render grib right
you've seen me do this maybe once or
twice before I know it's rare but you're
gonna do allocate render group and
that's gonna pass in whatever that max
push buffer size is right and what this
is responsible doing is this is
basically responsible for getting us one
of these buffers that we're going to
work with right and and so obviously
that's going to need to be able to get
it from somewhere and the place that
that's gonna get it from is gonna be one
of our memory arenas right so that's
going to take a memory arena to get it
from and what's gonna happen here is
this going to push space for itself on
to the arena and then it's also going to
push space for the push buffer rank so
it's gonna do a push size after that and
the push size call is well you know what
to do we actually even have a push last
call we don't really we don't really
have one let me see here
push size EP so that's the only place it
actually gets used so I'm gonna change
that the bat okay okay so we've got to
push size call now in theory I will
implement one it's not really
implementing a push size so that Bob is
typing in right now really all I'm
talking about it's making us a macro
right and the reason I'm making this a
macro is for debugging reasons that
we'll see later I'd like things that
work with the
I would like them all to go through a
macro I don't want anything that calls
the allocator going directly through a
function call so I just wanted to nip
that in the bud all right so we want the
max push buffer size to get allocated
here and I want to store that in that
that push buffer base pointer like so
and yeah that's basically it
I'm going to initialize all of the
fields of this render group and and I'm
gonna do it exactly the way that we were
doing it again
this is really just again more of that
sort of compression oriented approach
that you know I like to take I'm going
to essentially pull out what we were
already doing this whole stuff here I'm
just gonna do that in here and I'm gonna
call this render group thing like so I'm
gonna call allocate render group right
here and that's gonna come out of the
transient arena and I don't know how big
our push buffer is gonna be I'm gonna
say that I push buffer is going to be
four megabytes
I have no rhyme or reason for that at
all
totally random to do KC decide what our
push buffer size is right so yeah so
when we go in here now we're actually
doing mm initialization and a little bit
slightly more formal fashion I want the
default basis I would like that default
basis to actually get allocated as well
right so I'm gonna push that on here
push that that render basis struct right
and then I'm going to initialize it like
so right we've got the game state so
we're gonna need that to be passed in
here although to be honest with you I
don't know why it even needs the game
state I don't remember so I'm assuming
that game state was used in here oh it's
4 meters 2 pixels is that true
is there any other use for it no it's
just music so I'm not gonna store the
gamestate instead what I'm gonna store
is meters to pixels for now and that's
because I would like to get this into a
state where it's clearer sort of where
these like translations and stuff are
happening so that's what I'd like to do
so that we're not accessing the game
state and so meters to pixels is
actually gonna be in here temporarily
that's probably going to go away in a
little bit as well
all right so we allocate that we need to
receive a visa data this is piece count
we did that so now let's initialize
these guys the push buffer size is zero
right now the max first buffer size is
whatever we were told that it was and
now we have our renderer right piece
count is actually okay so now we've got
a problem
and that is that when we do push piece
we can't actually get one because we
don't have that pieces or anymore of
course what I should do also is is kind
of take a look at some of these others
to see what we're getting here push
sighs did I did I mess up the macro for
precise push size yes I did there we go
okay ignore that error for now push
sighs oops
and one more bug it's supposed to be an
underscore okay so let's see where we're
at
push struct piece group undeclared no
why don't I replaced those but evidently
I didn't
alright default basis goes push-truck
render basis that needs to come off the
arena allocate render group function
doesn't take two parameters you are
correct it takes game state meters two
pixels now let's see here
printer group pieces yes I know that
piece group undeclared identifier okay
and now we just have to change piece
group render group and we should be
pretty good yeah yeah alright so we're
in pretty good shape we just need to do
a little more work here to get our our
push buffer situation straightened out
and so I'm gonna do here is I'm gonna go
ahead and say in push piece what we're
going to do is instead of using any of
this stuff what we're going to do is say
alright assert that however big this
this this push piece is actually
potentially gonna be one of many things
we push on there so I'm actually gonna
do is is do a push size onto buffer or
push a know we're gonna call this push
on to push buffer push render I don't
know push render elements I'm not sure
don't know what that's gonna be called
point being we've got a thing that is
going to take our render group and a
size some size and it's going to push
that size on to our render group right
so what it's going to do is it's going
to say alright let's see we're gonna
have a result here right let's see if
the group can fit this thing on it so if
the max push buffer size plus our size
right if that is less than I'm sorry if
the current push buffer size plus our
size if that is less than the max buffer
size then we can fit the thing that we
want to push on to our push button
so that's all good and so if that's true
then we can go ahead and take whatever
part of of the memory is at that
location so push buffer base right plus
that push buffer size we can go ahead
and take that and make that be what the
result is that's the the actual place
that that we can write to in our push
buffer right and then hmm I realize I'm
going through this kind of quickly
because I wanted to kind of finish it up
so in the Q&amp;A I'll I'll kind of go over
it a little bit more so that everyone
knows what I'm talking about here
but anyway so then we're gonna just
increment that push buffer size by
whatever the size is right if we
couldn't get it I don't know if we have
invalid code paths we do awesome if we
couldn't get it we're gonna mark up some
valid code back now it's not actually
going to cause a crash or anything but
it is gonna be something that we know
we've overflowed the push buffer we've
done too much rendering and we can't
store anymore render commands right so
we want to make that be an alert that
that would tell the program where
something's gone wrong so that's our
push render element and so if we want to
get a piece here like this what we can
do is say you know push render element
instead of doing this and then we can
just say okay we want to take a you know
the size of entity visible piece and I
want to push it on to this group that
will get us one back right and that
should just totally work no oddness
going on there everyone's happy
everything's good and so the only thing
we have to do now is we just have to
figure out a way to actually walk those
pieces and since we're running out of
time let's kind of just stub that out
for now let's just say all right we're
gonna grab the render group push buffer
base we're gonna cast that you know to a
piece like so and what we're going to do
instead is we're going to say like a
base address right our base address of
zero while the base address is less than
the push buffer size we are going to
continue processing and so what we're
gonna do here is just say alright grab
out whatever the push buffer base
plus the base address is that's going to
be the the next piece and then for now
we'll just say increment it by the size
of an entity visible piece right so
let's do that hopefully about the work
it does and off we go
so we've just got to the point where
it's the QA so I will probably I will
probably actually start the Q&amp;A here
let's do that but what I'm going to do
before I start looking at the actual
questions is just quickly go over what I
did because I slammed it in there pretty
fast so let's take a little bit on the
whiteboard I mean on the blackboard to
just explain what I did there just just
kind of refresh things I was a little
manic today I admit that it was a manic
day things kind of went manic all right
so here's what happened if you recall we
had a thing called a piece group right
and a piece group was something that we
had we had in it sort of invented we
invented as a strong term we had
introduced a piece group because what
was happening was we wanted to draw
characters right that were multiple
pieces right we had the hero he's got a
cape he has a head he has a torso right
he has a shadow these were four separate
pieces and they were all based on the
same point there's a point and each one
of these was like offset from the point
in some way right but we didn't know
where the point was until after we'd
already done the after we already
executed the code that wanted to
assemble this so what we did is we
introduced this console of a piece group
which just recorded those things so what
it would do is it would say oh okay I've
got a head I've got a cape I've got a
torso I've got a shadow and it would
record these offsets so it say oh the
head is this offset from the point then
I don't know yet but at some point the
cape is over here are the torsos over
here are the shadows over here right
then after we were done and we knew what
this point was we'd feed this point into
this list and basically say okay using
this
we walk through the bitmaps that you
recorded and draw them using that basis
point okay that's what we had it started
today what I decided to do was turn this
into a render group which basically sets
us up for our renderer so all I did was
say let's do the exact same thing but
instead and I did this in steps as you
could see so I didn't do it too big at
one time and that's just again that's
compression rented program I'm just
trying to do things in a way that slowly
moves them towards the right solution so
that you can constantly see whether all
your decisions are right and all of your
pieces are working together properly
because it's always the
interconnectivity and the
interrelationship between things that
makes programming hard it's not any
individual piece of code individual
pieces of code are different they could
be algorithmically hard but it's a
separate thing it's not how code gets
messy right so anyway so what I wanted
to do here was say let's let's turn it
into something we're instead we've got a
render group which is basically a buffer
right that's just some memory so it's
just some memory we're going to set
aside and then we're gonna do is we're
gonna write things into this memory that
tell us what to render right and so we
did exactly the same thing as here so
the head gets read in here the Cape gets
written in here the torso gets written
in here and so on right and so we're
doing that already we've we've already
got that set up but what we haven't done
yet is made it so that this can be
heterogeneous right right now these are
just piece there those those visible
piece things right just like they were
back here but what we're going to do
maybe we'll start this on Monday is
we're gonna turn this into a
heterogeneous push buffer which means
that things in here can be all sorts of
different stuff so maybe one of them
says to draw a bitmap another one says
to draw a rectangle and we were
supporting that in this one as well
another one says to clear the screen
another one says to do you know whatever
whatever right and so this will
basically become our this render group
will be a group of commands that the
renderer is supposed to issue in order
to draw something and and again it
unlike before we were just doing it for
one character of time now we're just
doing everything in there and we'll
figure out a way to bake our sorting
into this as well but we haven't really
thought about that yet so that's all I
really did today it was just a bunch of
code sort of massaging really but that's
it
so let's see if we got any questions
questions if you'd like to ask a
question please prefix it with Q :
so I can see it and also please keep it
to stuff that we've done today stream or
a previous stream if you want to ask
off-topic questions we do that typically
before the stream starts so if you want
you to come back Monday 15 minutes
before starting time we're usually here
just hanging out chatting anyone anyone
is this gonna be a zero question
straight pro stream well things like
filters end up in the render group yeah
probably
basically anything that we're going to
do will probably end up being
represented in the render group because
yeah I didn't have a drink today I don't
know what I was thinking
I started making tea and I forgot to
pour it the render group will basically
be the thing that we hand to the actual
renderer and say go and so for the most
part everything will have to be in there
that's parameter izybelle so you know
maybe filters won't be in there because
filters might not be fram trusts maybe
they're applied the same way all the
time but assuming that the filters like
turn on and off and have different rates
and stuff the render group will probably
want to encapsulate most of that stuff
that we want to do filter wise in a
parametric way we'll have to go in there
because it'll get handed to OpenGL if
OpenGL supposed to render it it'll get
handed to our software renderer if our
suffer and your supposed to render it
it'll get handed to mantle or whatever
we implement a renderer for you know the
render groups gotta gotta keep that
stuff encapsulated and so and that's the
only way we're really gonna be able to
have switchable renderers right which
I'd like us to be able to do and so
pretty much everything including filters
is probably gonna have to go in there
but again if it's something that
literally doesn't need to be specified
at runtime it's just kind of known then
that is then then we wouldn't need to
put it in there how long will the
renderer take I have no idea I really
don't know I mean part of it depends on
what we decide to what we decide our
goal is there's two ways we could look
at it right one way is that we're
strictly doing the render as an
educational experience and we literally
don't care how fast it is so we're just
trying to write a full renderer that's
that does exactly the right things in
the way that is most educational to do
them but then we always ever just run
with hardware acceleration right that's
one way we could go another way we could
go is we actually want the game to
actually run on software rendering in a
way that you could play it so it's got
to be fast enough for that and I don't
know which is the right answer of those
right I suspect what we'll probably do
is we'll probably take a cautious
approach to optimization and say let's
write the renderer as if it were a
graphics card and so it's basically a
simulation of a graphics card and we
will try to make it run reasonably fast
so we'll we'll show how to do code
opposition in there but we won't try to
do algorithmic optimizations that are
totally different from what a GPU would
do because that that ceases to be very
interesting in an educational sense
potentially so I don't know so I'm not
sure exactly how we'll take it but
depending on how far we want to push
optimization I would say is what could
could sort of control the length of time
that that the renderer takes up can you
give us examples of what some of the
simpler things will be in the render
group yeah clear so that was the one
that I would have hoped I had would have
time to get I didn't quite clear will be
a command in there like clear the buffer
right
are there any static code analysis tools
for C visual studio that would help pick
up bugs like unused variables etc hmm
you know I don't know I know there are
our good ones for clang so if you're
compiling on Linux there's a bunch of
built-in things in clang that do both
both static and dynamic analysis tools I
think there's like address sanitizers
and stuff like that I don't know if
Visual Studio has them or not I mean
obviously there's thousands of
aftermarket things for Visual Studio
that do but whether it's got a built in
I don't know I never used them so I have
no idea but but do you think they would
by now if they don't you know one option
is it's usually good to maintain like a
Linux or Mac port anyway and claim does
have them and you can turn them on and
so that's another option is just make
that an excuse to port your code Linux
or whatever get your thing running on
Linux you can run it if you do like
we're doing where the platform code is
completely isolated you don't even have
to port to Linux and actually get it
running to run address sanitization you
could run the game in in a in a loop
just not throwing away the output right
and using address sanitization the
static analysis tools to find stuff for
you right and so that's a pretty cheap
way to do it and you don't have to buy
an aftermarket thing for Visual Studio
but it may be that Visual Studio 2013 or
something has those already so I would
do some searching online because it may
be that they have I just don't know
because I don't use them
so are you planning on abstract away the
render as a layer similar to how we
separated the platform from the game
code so that the various renderers will
be operating on the same data structures
yes essentially I'm not sure I
necessarily understand what you mean by
operating the same data structures but
basically yeah we will have a render
when we're done with this we'll have a
render group spec basically that's like
this is the format for a chunk of memory
that means draw the stuff in this way
and anyone who wants to implement a
renderer for that can do it right and so
it then becomes free to just plug more
renderers in well free you have to write
the renderer but it becomes it doesn't
require us doing any work inside
handmade hero to support alternative
renderer so if you want you know and
people could go nuts with that if
someone wants to do like a d3 deport and
a mantle port and a whatever port
whatever and we don't do those on the
stream because we pick some other things
to use or whatever
it should be very easy for people in the
community to go ahead and say oh I
wanted to make a renderer for
such-and-such so I did right if you were
going to write an algorithm to generate
pseudo cout puzzles how would it work
that is that sorry that's sort of a pre
stream question that really doesn't have
anything to do with what we've been
working on unused variables are a
warning on my compiler did you turn that
warning off I use an allow local macro
when I want it to ignore the variable I
did turn that that off however I think
I'm not sure but I think what GPL White
was asking for when he says are there
any static analysis tools that would
help pick up bugs like unused variables
I assume because he said static analysis
tools he wasn't talking about the
trivial ones that the compiler catches I
assume he was talking about more
complicated ones that you know aren't
easy like that involve function calls or
something that like Visual Studio are
playing won't by default catch for you I
assume that's what he was talking about
but I don't know if he's only talking
about
getting visuals to just say hey this was
done use variable then yeah all you have
to do for that is just turn that warning
on would it make sense for the render
group to contain render groups itself
sorry Friday means fried brains here
yeah it I've I mean I can't say for sure
that that's what we'll do but that is
totally something we might do actually
in the course of what we're working on
I don't know because I probably would
say that we'll end up with the render
group kind of being a bit of a tree like
thing inside itself anyway so I don't
actually know whether that'll actually
be necessary but it's a totally
reasonable thing
do you Seven Samurai I meant whether you
plan for the data describing what needs
to be rendered to be in a format such
that it's suitable for both suffer and
hardware rendering yes the only thing we
won't do is try to get maximum hardware
throughput because we're a 2-d game so
we don't need it it's like hardware
throughput is so astronomically higher
than what we have we don't have to
really worry too much about that but so
you know you would build your push
buffers in the hardware format if you
wanted to be absolutely the fastest you
could possibly be and we have this
intermediate buffer format which
introduces some overhead in terms of
processing time so the only thing we
won't do is is eliminate that processing
time and the reason is because it won't
affect our framerate at all but if you
really were trying to like get down to
it that would be something you would
want that would be different for
hardware than in software but yet so for
other than other than that we will be
doing it so that it's basically friendly
eight for both well our hero always be
taller than the treetops no he's giant
right now just because eventually he
will be probably a little shorter than
the trees but not as much shorter as he
would be in real life it is not it is
not quite to scale in terms of how the
art will look in the final game the the
art will be you know it's its
interpretive it's an interpretation so
think people are not the same size
relative to trees that they possibly
should be
let's see any more questions any more
questions are there any more I do not
see any more programming questions but
maybe I am just missing them maybe I am
just missing them alright well I guess
that is that I guess we've finished
earlier okay
so let's go ahead and let's see let's
close this down close that down throw
that out and back to square one
all right double check here are we
keeping the 5:00 p.m. schedule well I
guess we've got a little bit extra time
here I don't know what do people think
about the 5:00 p.m. schedule I guess
it's a little bit weird to ask here
because the people who are here are
people who made the 5:00 p.m. schedule
but yes I think I would like to keep the
5:00 p.m. schedule I also feel like I
know this is a little paradoxical but I
feel like on the 5:00 p.m. schedule we
haven't been getting as much noiz in the
chat which I feel like might actually be
better I know it's like maybe not as
good for if we're trying to make the
series as popular as possible but at the
end of the day I feel like kind of
having a more sensible chat is valuable
for people and I'm not I am NOT a web
2.0 maximizing consumer acquisition
rates kind of a guy and so if it turns
out that this is a friendlier time in
terms of keeping the chat saying less
work for the moderators and stuff like
that I kind of feel like maybe that's a
good thing you know but if that could
just be a bad that could just be that
this week was happened to become
and easier so I don't know so yeah so
we'll see I'll try to post this weekend
on the forums a question to see if
people are having trouble with the 5:00
p.m. slot but I think we'll try it from
the Rica I like it I think it's good
and so yeah
all right well let's wrap it up then I
think it's a reasonable time to wrap it
up
thank you everyone joining me for
another episode of handmade hero we
started the rant renderer push virus up
today I wasn't anticipating doing that
but it just it just happened and so I
think what that kind of means for us is
again stuff may go crazy stuff may stuff
may go crazy maybe next week we'll be
doing renderer stuff I don't know like I
said we made it to do list it wasn't
meant to be in order
so I reserve the right to pick out the
stuff if we have momentum on something
that we're working on then I say we go
with it I don't like having any kind of
procrustean bed that we've got to sleep
in every night so yeah we'll see I
thought we were gonna do ground level Z
stuff tomorrow
maybe we'll Act I mean on on Monday and
starting next week but maybe we'll
actually go through and do some renderer
stuff and get us into a better position
with rendering I don't know
right it could happen don't quote me on
it either way but that said thank you
for joining me for another hour of
coding with handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
with a source code you can pre-order the
game on handmade hero org it comes with
a source code and then you can download
it every night get a little link that
allows you downloaded every night and
follow along which is kind of cool if
you want to play around stuff we've been
doing on your own I highly recommend it
we also have of5 that there we go we
also have the forums I changed it from
news and forms to forums cool it's
really there's no news it's just forums
so you have a forum site you can check
out ask questions on look at basically
community ports to Mac and Linux there's
an anti demo
when we get the annotated episode guide
up a little bit get it
upping more automatically maybe I'll put
the link here and so the YouTube archive
as well but point being there's also a
schedule bot that tweets the schedule at
you which is good to keep up with if you
want to know when when it is again I
think it's gonna be 5 p.m. next week the
same time as this week but just in case
that tweet bot helps you keep up to date
with the schedule if you want to know
when that thing's gonna air that's all
it does is sit there and tweet the
schedule and also there's a patreon if
you ask for
video series you can always subscribe to
that it's much appreciated but again the
video series is always going to be free
so that's strictly if you're just doing
a nice thing like I said you don't have
to pay for it I like that it's it's it's
all the videos are always free so anyway
thank you very much for joining us and I
hope to see you next week and yeah I
don't know maybe we'll do rendering
stuff we'll see what happens
and if you do want to give feedback on
the new timeslot please do so on the
forums I read them I read everything on
the forums I don't always reply to stuff
I'm busy a lot of time so but I always I
always look and if there's something
that I can help out with I try to jump
in so so anyway thanks very much
and I hope see you next week take it
easy everyone and have a good weekend