all right welcome everyone to another
episode of handmade hero the show we cut
a complete game live on stream it is day
294 I don't really know what we should
be working on today but I think I still
wanted to play around with the movement
mode stuff some more we have a bunch of
little like entities sort of working I
don't I don't know I don't know what
we're gonna do I really don't you know
what forget that unpacked 80 to 93
source code if you want to follow along
at home you know what I want to do today
actually I want to attack something I
think that seems like a good idea to me
so let's put combat in I think that's a
good idea so what I want to do here is
I'm going to load up where we were at
and just make sure everything is still
kosher yeah so here we go we've got mr.
snakey poo I'm gonna go in those snakes
are too darn long they take up way too
much room for testing purposes so I'm
gonna I'm gonna make those snakes a
little bit shorter here 12 is absurd so
I'm gonna make I'm gonna make those
snake considerably shorter so they're
not clogging up everything so there's
the snakes and and I'm I'm here hopping
around and so what I'd like to do is I'd
like to go ahead and get it so that I
could attack something because that's a
major thing that we haven't done really
we did we played around a little bit
with this with throwing a sword kind of
a thing way back in the early days when
we were just kind of working on entity
systems in a sort of very basic way but
I haven't really ever implemented it for
real so let's let's do that and now that
we have our brain system this is a
pretty easy thing for us to do as well I
think so
let me go I'm just gonna make I think I
don't know what we've got for for art
assets in there right now at some point
we're gonna have to switch up to a new
art asset pack but
I think I'll just make like a little
square that I can use just a little I
won't even use like a bitmap for it cuz
I don't know if we have anything
appropriate I don't really want my dude
to attack with a copy of his own head
which of course we could do but I want
to make something where I can attack and
so what I'd like to do is I want to make
it so that you know I've got my dude
here and when I'm when I'm sort of
hopping around right now you can sort of
already see that I face in whatever
direction I push the you know the arrow
keys but and the WASD keys is what I was
using to move around right but what I
actually want the arrow keys to do
although they may also additionally set
that facing Direction what I want them
to do is I want them to actually do the
attack in the direction that I push
right and you can see that these guys
have hit points here like that dude
who's bouncing around like a maniac
right he's got three hit points I've got
three hit points they're just throwing
us those little red squares under there
and so while I'm gonna probably have to
slow this guy down because he's kind of
crazy fast at this point we haven't
really done anything in terms of making
monsters or do a reasonable thing but
point being I should be able to make
something where I can go up there and
kind of whale on him right and and hit
the monster so that would be good
because if we get that going that would
also motivate us to sort of get our
collision detection stuff a little more
solidified which is another big thing
that we want to do you know it's if
there's some of it in there already but
it was really not made for the current
state of affairs and so we want to take
another look at that anyway and kind of
get that going as well so let's let's
let's see what happens here let's see
what's going to happen so the first
thing is the way that the the hero
attacks in general is there's a couple
pieces of the hero right there's the
head of the hero there's the torso and
there's the cape part right and the the
idea behind the heroes you could see
from the intro sequence we haven't
played the intro sequence in a while
although I guess I could play it right
now just to just to point that out right
because if I go back here
it just goes to the quote-unquote title
screen that no one's drawn yet but then
it I think goes in to the attract mode
right it should yeah there it goes
so you know the the the point here the
the the idea of of what's supposed to
happen is the hero has this little glove
this magical glove that Krampus of
course gave him and that glove is what
he uses to attack so I want that piece
to be floating by him all like it should
actually be on the screen so that's
gonna be like an actual separate entity
and depending on what glove you have at
any particular time you know it should
be visible there right it should it
should be clear like oh i i've got this
in this particular type of glove or
whatever it looks you know visually
distinct and you can sort of say okay
that's that's the glove that i'm using
at this particular point in time
floating next to me and so when the when
i push in a door in one of the arrow
keys then i want the sort of I want the
glove to do that at an attack in that
direction like a punch right so it
should kind of pray it should probably
be I'm guessing something like a swipe
sort of a thing I don't know like kind
of an arc like motion in whatever the
direction is that I push and depending
on the type of glove obviously it's
going to do different things but that's
the basic attack method so given that I
need to create an additional entity for
the glove and I need that entity to kind
of float around by the hero and it'll
probably be relatively lockstep compared
to where the hero is so it won't be like
the head and the body where they can
kind of float separately it'll probably
be just wherever the body is the hand is
like floating right next to it always
and as the body moves the hand moves
directly with it and then when you
attack that it does it does that swipe
motion probably quite quickly and I'm
guessing that we'll probably have like
sort of a blurred swipe because you know
probably it won't take long enough to
swipe to really be all that visible so
I'd probably like blur across you know
some kind of a swept also have to look
to it but anyway yes so plate being this
is this is the the magic glove kind of
thing and so I want that thing to be
hovering nearby to the hero as
adventurers around and you know we'd
probably attach some particle effects to
it because you can kind of see the art
can you know the the conception of it
artistically speaking is that it's kind
of got these particle trails on it and
it's sort of glows and so you know we'll
probably make that be reflected in the
actual programming of it all right so
that's what we're doing
so let's go to add hero or sorry add
player and so really all I want to do
here is say that there's going to be a
glove as well and you can see that we've
sort of got a lot of residual stuff in
here right these like Collider things
you know a lot of these flags I feel
like and and how the collision stuff
works now is probably going to be the
time for us to solidify that because now
we'll actually have we have everything
in place and how it's working we can
make some decisions here I don't know
that all these are gonna be necessary
right I don't because we may you know
now that we specify a collision thing
maybe you don't ever need to say that I
have a collision thing but I don't
collide it's like if I don't collide I
wouldn't need a collision thing right
and that might not be true if I need to
have the notion of things that collide
with other things if they have their
collision flag set but the other things
don't collide in the reverse if they
don't right so there's ways we might set
those there's ways those flags might
mean something but it's also highly
likely that they want
so anyway we've got our glove and it's
brain slot is going to be brain Kiro
glove and it's brain ID is obviously the
brain ID of the hero and what I'm gonna
do now well in addition to closing out
the entity obviously is I'm gonna need
to give it some sort of asset I don't
know like I said I'll double check just
to see what kind of assets I have
because maybe there was something in the
in the asset system that I can use here
so what would that have been in I think
that was in file formats so I've got a
shadow a tree a rock grass tough stone
head cape font so I you know I could use
a liquid asset sword even though we
didn't have a sword in there so I could
grab a rock you could just use a rock
that's what we were using before I think
so I'll just add boobs I don't want to
edit that I want to copy it and I guess
we'll just say okay there's a rock and
we'll see what happens
alright so if we create a rock there and
we've got that floating next to the to
the hero we now just need a little bit
more information this won't be all so I
guess this guy would be kind of floating
off the ground but that's a separate
issue so anyway the glove of the hero is
is going to need a slot in the brain
system because we want the hero to know
about his glove and I think let's see
here Oh something collision here a body
collision let's see
we'll know love collision and we don't
really know how this stuff is gonna play
out so I'm just going to continue making
you know a dummy for here and then we
can turn it onto something because we're
gonna need to know when it collides
right so now in theory we should get oh
these have to be retired in the same
order when we actually build things and
I'm glad we put that assertion in there
to catch that because I would have
totally forgotten so this has to be
retired
yeah first right because when you open
one of these you then have to close it
and it keeps track of those so yeah all
right so now what we've got to do I
don't know why we don't see that entity
here though we should have seen it I
think we did and it's here we did add
that I guess I don't know I should
probably double-check that there
actually is
okay there it is so I guess the rock
there just isn't a rock asset at the
moment is that true cuz it looks like if
I set it to rock we don't get one so
that may be true maybe I need to use
sword oh my god
alright that's a little bit large let's
let's be honest that's too big that
needs to be significantly smaller so
let's try that one more time okay so
that's much better so now we've got a
stupid rock there that's not very
interesting but we've got it and so now
what I want to do is I want to make that
follow me around and swipe when I push
in a direction right so that's what I
would like to do and so I'm going to
need a couple things for this first of
all in the brain code for the hero I
need something that places that thing in
a particular location right so when I'm
walking around I want to do something
here you can see that I've got sort of
this notion of the entity parts I can
grab my glove out of the entity part so
if I if I have a glove here it is if I
have a glove I can I can do something
with it and so what I might do is say
well okay if I've got a glove let's just
put it next to the body that's why I say
like okay if I have a glove and I know
where am i but my actual body is right
and and I guess I could sort of do it
could follow the head as well I don't
know which it would follow I think it's
the body that it should follow
personally so I'm gonna say body so if I
have the body what I need to sort of
know is what is the facing direction and
that facing direction will probably
determine where I want to place it
because you know as the as the character
rotates I want it to be sort of off to
the side of where the care
there is but what side you know what is
the side of the character is determined
by the direction the characters facing
so at first I'll lock it in but then
we're gonna want to change that up so
the first thing to do is just say well
whatever the glove whatever the body
position is the glove position is just
going to be the body position plus some
fixed offset right and let's say that
fixed offset is you know some some sort
of very basic thing whatever that is
right and you know maybe I'll get rid of
this this offset for now and so now you
know when I walk around that sort of
thing we'll be off to my side now it's
not in a great location right now I
think I might argue that that should be
let's see here brain argue that that
should be a little bit further up right
um which I can do let me
let me just tweak this here so I should
be able to you know move this up to
roughly where it should be you think
that was pretty good
so now I think that's roughly you know
that's that's sort of what we might want
you know if you imagine to putting a
real glove asset in there it should
probably hover right about there and as
I'm moving around you can see it just
kind of stays just on that outside and
what I want is I want it to move so that
it's gonna whatever direction I'm facing
you know it will it will align to that
side properly so we we do know the
facing direction of the character at any
given time right we've we sort of set
that facing direction here but that
facing Direction is is actually a like a
scalar like it's a it's an angle and we
don't really I don't really know if we
want it to
well maybe we do I don't know let's try
just using the angle directly right so
I'm just gonna take that angle and I
think we already have sort of an armed
construction here right so if I say I'm
gonna take an angle which is whatever
the facing direction is of the body and
I want a vector that's like pointing out
in that direction now I could say well
if I have something pointing in that
direction I now want to to take that
displacement instead of this 0.6 here
right I want to take that displacement
and I want to use that plus whatever the
upward thing is and that upward thing
should really be going in the Z but we
still haven't fixed our Z and so maybe
this you know honestly this this glove
situation could actually be the thing
where we just use this as the emphasis
to finish both things the collision
detection and our Z
determination which is the other you
know is other big thing that really
isn't it hasn't been nailed down yet in
the renderer right we've we've toyed
with that Z displacement a ton and that
and I said a few weeks ago I was like
here's the final way that it's gonna
work and so now we actually have to go
in and do that right all right so I
could do arm X here and arm why like so
now arm X and arm Y in this case they're
going to mean something specific so
facing Direction is is giving me a
direction that's what we're the hero's
facing so if it was 0 you know it's it's
we're talking about something where it's
like this is zero degrees right and then
we kind of come around as as we go so
you know this would be 180 right or you
know or PI right and this would be PI
over 2 up here and this would be 3 PI
over 2 or in terms of towels right this
would be 1/4 tau 1/2 to 3/4 tau so you
know this is the circle we're talking
about if the hero is facing this
direction then I want the arm to be you
know off to the side so really we want
to take 3/4 tau and add it to that
facing direction so that we can get the
direction we actually wanted right we
basically you know we want that right is
the actual thing and just to underscore
that point let's let's go ahead and and
and turn that term off temporarily and
you can see so here's the thing and it's
right it's displaced out to the side
right but it's displaced in the
direction I am facing at any given time
which is not where I want my glove to
actually be so we need to add that
displacement to the angle to sort of
swap it to be to my side right and now
it's to my side now I don't want it that
far out so again I kind of want it to be
a little closer into the hero by default
it would have been one unit but I want
it more like half a unit and so there
you go
so now I'm holding that you know my
quote/unquote glove which is actually a
weird plate rock thing now I'm holding
that you know kind of to the side where
I am and as I move around I can I can
sort of face in a direction and there it
is but now I need to be able to kind of
swipe attack
that thing out in front of me right I
need to be able to do sort of an arc
attack and then what I also want to do
is I need to know when that thing
collides with another object right
because I'm gonna need to come over here
and punch this thing right this and and
when I you know we need some way of
knowing whether I hit it or not right so
that's another it's another situation
that needs situation Inge right alright
so let's think about how we're gonna do
that in here we already know when I push
in that direction because we have
information about how the hero was
pushing I believe we called it like
sword push or whatever yeah you can see
it here right here's a bunch of sword
information so d sword tells us what the
user was trying to do in terms of
pushing in a particular direction and
you can see me setting the facing
direction here using it now
you'll also note of course that we do
something kind of stupid which is this
is one of those hey we eight and two to
get an angle and then we can we cosine
sign it out again later
huh so you know not the most efficient
thing you but we don't really care about
that sort of thing now but just you see
some of the times that thing and
programming you're like oh hey maybe I
should start just storing this as a
vector instead but yeah we need the
atan2 for lookups for other reasons so
you know it's not it's not the end the
world anyway so when I push this button
I want to initiate a strike right I want
to initiate a swipe of that thing and we
have this concept of movement mode in
entities and I think that's probably a
good movement mode to have and you know
maybe it's swiping or attacking I don't
know tax swipe I'm not sure and so what
I'd like to do is I'd like to set the
hand into that swipe mode because
essentially when it's while you're doing
that swipe you can't Reese wipe right
like you're committed to the attack for
a couple frames and you just have to let
it run its course you can't retry to
attack in a different direction until
the attack in the direction you
initially specified is done so this is
going to be very similar to the hopping
code only instead of going between
occupied regions
it's it's really not occupying anything
it's just it's just doing this arc
motion so let's go ahead and get that in
there first world mode and you know what
to this stuff this world mode stuff
might be time to pull out into the
entity code because this is really all
entity code but you know not sure that
really matters all that much but you see
how we've got sort of like X cube brain
this could now be a simulate enemy call
right because this is all just something
that happens on an entity and so if we
want to pull it out over there we
usually could I don't know if it makes
sense to do so but we certainly good so
yeah if I've got movement mode hopping
there now let's say that I've got
another movement mode and the movement
know that I have here is that attacks
life mode and then in here I want to do
the same exact stuff that I was doing
before so you know essentially I want to
say well when I get to the end of the T
movement phase of things right I I want
to go back to whatever mode I was you
know whatever the neutral mode is right
so I want to say
movement mode equals movement mode
planted probably and so while we're in
that movement mode and we say we've
gotten above here or sorry when we're
not above here then we do the swipe
behavior and then as soon as like we
Everest done we go back to planted so
the way the swipe behavior would work is
again like you know the entity P is
gonna probably be based off of some kind
of a you know I I got to figure out some
kind of parameterization what I'm saying
I want this thing to attack I need some
notion of how that attack is supposed to
you know play out right speaking of that
I do wonder if this came from makes any
sense anymore
I feel like this came from should
perhaps no longer be a actual
traversable reference
that's beside the point anyway
so we need some way of parameterizing
this sort of arc and or thinking about
this and so you know if mike euro is
here and I've got the the glove here and
I'm talking about this kind of motion
right it pretty much needs to go out and
you know I had toyed with this I don't
know I I think I'm gonna go ahead and
say that this is how this works too I
feel like it probably should do
something like you swipe and it goes to
this side and then you swipe again and
it comes back to this side so you're
kind of doing left and right side
swiping as you alternate through right
and so I want a way of saying Arc around
and then arc back and and that's really
yeah that's really good so yeah so in
this case when we're doing this
operation really this is a relative
space thing so I got to think about how
I want this to work while we're in the
attack swipe phase you know I don't
really one of the things that I kind of
find is I'm I'm I'm finding that like as
I code these things they're very you
know I kind of want to just code them
custom but then I usually want to reuse
them and so it's always a kind of a
question of exactly how that should go
I'm gonna stick with the the thing I've
been doing which is just write it
explicitly first and then make it more
reusable as we as we sort of move
forwards so if I want to do that attack
swipe motion I feel like I want to leap
you know I want this to stay
parametrized in a very similar way you
know to this this sort of thing here and
so I would say that we probably want you
know something like this and what we
want to do is we want to interpolate the
angle based on that
that team movement that that team
movement information right and so that
team movement if we go to the entity is
gonna have something like you know angle
target like you know swipe angle start
or swipe angle target something like
this right and and
I guess what I would say about this is I
don't know exactly how I want the facing
direction all right so here's what I
think I actually I dunno
so the facing direction will stay fixed
during a swipe even if you push in
another direction you won't change
facing direction all right so that's
fine so yes so we have a swipe angle
start and we have a swipe angle target
and it'll go between these two and I
think that'll be fine that's that's my
that's my assertion there and you know
I'll be honest it might be that it might
be that this is kind of just always
capable of working this way I don't know
we'll see this is this is again code
that I'm not super I don't normally
write a lot of enemy code and so it's
always a little bit when we're going
through this you're kind of watching
literally me decide as I go like how do
I like this do I not like this and and
see how things shake out so I'm
constantly like evaluating where do I
want to put this piece of code and I'm
trying to let it sort of organically
settle into place so I can make good
decisions about that all right so anyway
if we were going to use this this attack
swipe mode and I wanted to make the arm
be placed in this angular way what I
could say is like well okay so there's
you know there's a movement mode
you know angle offset or something
and an angle attack swipe and these are
for things that are sort of relative ARM
based move movers you know and so this
oops what just happened
there we go so this code right here
right you know is is the constant angle
offset version and this would be like
off of the the you know the facing
direction that would be set in the brain
so it would be saying like oh let's take
the facing direction and let's let's set
you know the gloves facing direction
maybe to the bodies facing direction so
that you know they're always facing in
the same direction and then here we
would just say like oh okay the entities
facing direction I'm gonna take those
angle interpolant and I'm gonna to use
those two to change what's going on and
you know even as I'm saying this I'm
sort of thinking - well couldn't I just
actually move the entities through like
I couldn't I just animate the facing
direction
yeah that's tricky well I'm gonna keep
going I'm gonna keep going to see how it
shakes out but I'm pretty sure we're
gonna go through a couple of revisions
here because I kind of sense like oh
yeah I kind of see how this should go
and it's not quite what I'm what I'm
typing in right so let's keep going down
this path though so if we were gonna do
this literally I would just say okay
excuse me here's the angle offset
movement mode I'll let these cases drop
through here's how we position one of
these things right and we'll parametrize
as much as you want right now we don't
really have to do much of that yet but
you know we'll see how that goes so yeah
I can just say whatever my what was I
saying starting angle
so whatever my starting angle is plus
whatever my facing direction is is going
to be where I place myself and off we go
or maybe I should do something like this
so this is basically just creating a
relative reference frame off of wherever
my facing direction is I'm going to take
my angle that I am currently at I'm
going to displace the thing there and
presumably we would parameterize this
more specifically later right and so
then my entity P here is just going to
be a my edit EP is going to be a
displacement off of whatever my you know
my my base is and so then in the brain I
would sit with those are whatever I want
those to be so I'm saying that the
gloves base angle base is going to be
the body's PD location and then I'll set
its entity p equal to these just like we
were doing before so really very
straightforward then in the attack swipe
and like I said I think this isn't great
and I'll kind of touch on why I think
there's a better way to do that a little
later on anyway so then we're when we're
in the attack swipe face again we would
then switch we would regress back to
angle offset but when we were done I
similarly here we would want to
initialize our movement mode of the
glove to movement mode angle offset and
so that when we actually create
the entity in the first place can add
player that's something that you know we
would want to put in here right so when
we are creating this glove in the first
place we'd say hey the movement mode of
the glove is going to be the angle
offset movement mode that's how it's
placed in the world so then when we do
the attack swipe the attack swipe is
really nothing more than saying that you
know the entity angle current equals the
lerk of and I don't remember what we
actually call just I never do we called
it lerp this is going to be the lerp
between whatever the start angle is
we're gonna take that entity T movement
and we're gonna make the angle and
target again we're gonna alert between
those and at the very end of it we'll
make sure that the angle current equals
the angle target in fact I guess we
could say that this is what we do when
it's less than one is this and otherwise
we do this right so we do that T
movement lerp I don't really remember
how that gets actually incremented like
who is actually incrementing T movement
and when this is this this I ask you
right
somebody has to to update T movement
there it is so for the attack swipe we
have to also increment T movement at
some point as we go right I don't know
whether this is the right policy for it
exactly when this is happening but yeah
I could clamp it here as well
and that looks like something that we
should pull off as well okay so yeah
that's that's the the T movement stuff
that'll give us the the looping that we
want there and then when it gets to the
angle target it will just sort of record
that now we're like I said we kind of
flip flop around between those and so
our angle target when we go to actually
execute one of these our angle target is
going to it's going to sort of toggle
back and forth so what I kind of want to
do is say well whatever the whenever we
get a decent to do so first of all I
never want to set the gloves facing
direction in a case where I'm I'm doing
an attack right so what I kind of want
to do is say okay if I've got a glove
and I've got a body and you know what I
should probably just copy all this stuff
well we'll see we'll see how we won't do
it in a second they'll leave that down
there I've got if okay so I've got a
glove in a body I know I'm gonna set the
angle base I know missed at the facing
direction but I also know that if I'm in
the middle of a swipe I don't want to
change the body spacing direction right
so what I kind of want to do here is say
that well if the gloves you know
movement mode
is movement mode angle offset right then
I'll set it but otherwise I don't want
to set it because until the swipes done
I don't want to update the facing
direction of the of the body right I
mean yeah to be that of the head attack
swipe undeclared identifier is that so
you're right you're right sorry I just
wanted to actually make that start
happening okay so now we actually need
to set those other angles up and so to
start off with when the hero is first
created right I want at the same time
when I do the angle offset I want to set
the starting angle or I guess the
current angle I want to set that to be
the angle I actually wanted the hand to
be at and so you know we'll start off
right-handed and then it'll switch to
left-handed on the first punch and
vice-versa so that's just this right
and now you can see that it's it's in
the it's on the right side always
wherever I'm pointing and so now when I
do that D sword I want to initiate that
attack so I'm gonna go into the brain
and when we do the D sword initiation
which is in here and I think what I want
to do is say something like attacked was
false and in here I would say that if we
attacked that we set that to true so if
we attacked then I'm going to set the
facing direction right if we are in fact
I guess now I think about that would be
the better place to do this so probably
we always take the heads facing
direction so it's more like if we
attacked if we tried to attack we're
gonna see if the glove movement mode is
angle offset if it's if it's not we'll
turn attack to false right so basically
like if we don't have a glove or if the
glove is at rest or if the glove isn't
at rest then we didn't attack right or I
should say we will say that the attack
did not occur if we have a glove and
it's not capable of attacking right now
otherwise we'll say that we did because
maybe there's some other meaning of that
I don't know maybe we need to be more
explicit about this as well there might
be at two different kinds of attack but
we'll see so if we actually do get into
the attacked face then we will set the
facing direction and similarly if we're
in the attack phase and we have a
of right in fact I guess we could do
this in here well maybe not so if we
have a glove and we have an attack that
occurred then I'm going to set the glove
to a movement mode that it reflects the
the angle 1 right the angle slight swipe
and I want to set the starting angle to
be whatever the current angle is well I
should call it current angle but some
reason I didn't call it that and I want
the angle target to be you know it's
either gonna be that it's other gonna be
75 or negative 25 right it's either
gonna be I started scaling to be 75 or
25 but the way round goes is going to
matter I suppose should think about this
a little bit actually so if this is the
facing direction I probably wanted to
call that negative 25 now that I think
about it so that it goes from 25 to
negative 25 seems like a better idea so
let's call this 25 and what I want to do
is say well where is the glove currently
and I'm either gonna pick negative 25 or
25 and in a pic based on which side of 0
I'm on so if the glove is on the left
side of the hero it'll swipe towards the
right side if the glove is on the right
side it'll swipe towards the left right
that's that's what I'm gonna try to do
anyway now there's a little weirdness to
this and I don't know whether I like it
or not and we'll have to sort of think
about this first of all it's way too
slow so I got to speed that up a lot but
otherwise that's doing essentially what
I wanted it to do let's take a look to
you movement mode mint I just want to
change the swipe speed so there's that a
tax wipe so I want that to be quite a
bit faster
um so I'm just going to speed that up a
bit that's much better
might even need to go a bit faster
that's probably about right okay so
anyway having my little punching glove
here punching is good it probably needs
to go out a little bit from where I am
though as it goes and so when we do the
swipe attack I might add a little bit of
arm motion in there a little bit of arm
extense right so that's pretty easy to
do right you can see in here we've kind
of got this notion of of the
displacement and so maybe what I'll do
is say well alright so these aren't
exactly the same they aren't exactly the
same thing there is a displacement and
well you know what I could still leave
it to be honest it's probably fine what
I can do is say well inside the entity
because I'm already gonna want to do
this anyway
where are you there we go
we would want like something like angle
based distance or something and angle
swipe distance and so in here we could
say well and then we'd also need the
current distance right distance so we
just feel like all right you know this
right here this 0.5 is actually going to
be the entity angle current distance
right it's just polar coordinates here
right so I'm saying this is how far out
the thing is from the body and in here
we could say that the entity angle
current distance maybe is some kind of a
like interpolation that you know gives
me at 0.5 you know it kind of goes out
and then back in again right so it kind
of like comes out from the body and then
comes back so we'll worry about that
part in a second but this is going to be
something right it's not gonna be a lerp
we would probably call this you know
like a triangle or a parabola 0.5 or
something like that we would want to do
some kind of a parabola thing where we
say okay it's the same kind of thing as
our lerp function it's gonna take the T
movement and it's going to take the
angle based distance and the angle swipe
distance and it's gonna you know it's
gonna interpolate between them and it
sort of a you know you know like gets
bigger in the middle and falls off again
at the end right and yeah I think that's
all I really need to do there and then I
just need to set those things when I
actually create this so when I create a
player
I'm going to go in here and say we've
got the angled face distance and the
angle swipe distance and the angle
current distance and this will be 0.5
the base distance will be 0.5 the swipe
distance will let's say be 1.0 right so
now all I need is a parabola function or
some other me doesn't have to be a
parabola for any particular reason
let me see where's my where's my work
right there in the line 32 and really
you know rather than phrasing it this
way probably the better thing to do
would be to say lerp right and then do
parabola go 5 map on just the T value so
that way you can use it with any of the
lerp functions no matter what they're
lurking whether they're vectors or
whatever and you don't have to introduce
another function that has multiple forms
right so when you when you plug in a
t-value here let's take a look at this
right what I want to do is a function
that kind of looks like that right and I
could I suppose maybe I don't want a
parabola I don't know maybe I want more
of a cosine arc right because that's
what that would be right so maybe I want
a cosine arc that's that's just
normalized so it goes from 0 to 1 right
so it's just like cosine of t over pi
basically write something like this
that kind of thing seems as reasonable
as any now it's a little more expensive
unfortunately but you know so that seems
to still be evaluating
that seems to be evaluating oddly
because I would not expect that I would
expect that to stay at 0.5 ah well
that's not exactly true if my parabola
function is busted which it probably is
I like that I called it parabola 0.5 and
then in a cosine curve that's that's
wonderful
nice work but yeah in theory when we do
this we should and I and I guess this is
probably something I should do more like
this I should probably keep these the
same in theory it should return it
should it should regress back to base
distance which is 0.5 right which you
can see that it now does because I hard
set it but it wouldn't have otherwise
and if I slow down the T here you can
see that the movement is totally wrong
right so that this this is not at all
correct
so my angle base distance to my angle
swipe distance and my parabola functions
or not not right at all and so let me go
let me double check to make sure they're
created properly the base distance is
0.5 and the swipe distance is 1.0 right
so those are what I would have thought
they should be so the question is is my
parabola function busted it might be see
here of course is not a parabola for one
thing but let's just double check let's
see what happens if I just always return
zero I should say it at point five the
whole time and I do and similarly if I
return one
I should be four all the way out the
whole time yeah Jimmy
so then for some reason I'm not sure why
when I duty from 0 to 1 ah I did it
backwards right I want it to go to PI I
want it to go from 0 to PI so my cosine
curve would be would be this right T
starting at 0 and also great I want it
to start it Syria so it's a sine curve
not a cosine curve even better great day
to day Casey nice work so that's
actually correct that's what I actually
wanted to do the problem is this is
called parabola and that's not a
parabola so I should probably do like
sine 0 1 or something like that is
actually what that should be called it's
also probably better to use a parabola
cuz signs are a lot more expensive have
been parabolas but you know but that's
pretty good
and I don't know that might actually be
a little bit more eccentric than it
should be I'm not entirely sure like or
a little less eccentric than it should
be so maybe like 0.5 isn't even enough I
don't know it's a good question and I'm
not sure so like it could be that maybe
you know this should be like even as low
as zero point three I'm not entirely
sure but we could check it out and
presumably the swipe distance would vary
per gloves well right like some gloves
have higher swipe distances
so probably you know this stuff the base
distance swipe distance current distance
stuff I'm just guessing that basically
all of these things would it would sort
of be things that that change as part of
the entities setting but I think that's
basically it
so really the next phase would just be
let's attach the collision detector to
that and then I can start to swipe
things right and you can kind of see why
there's a number of kind of weird
gameplay things that are somewhat
interesting too about the way that this
game is designed not necessarily saying
they're good because I am NOT a game
designer but the way that the hero works
is kind of unusual right like because
the thing you attack with is not the
thing you're moving there's like a fair
bit of of kind of like strategic thought
involved in where you are going to place
your head versus your body and what
direction you're going in at any given
time if that makes sense so it'll be
interesting to see kind of how that
shapes up right we'll see anyway so
that's all I really wanted to do anyway
and like I said I think we're pretty out
of time so we'll just work on the
collision detection next week and yeah
we're getting pretty close though I
would like that - probably Bob up and
down as well like it should kind of be a
little floaty so we can maybe get that
back in there but that's that's roughly
it and like I said you know that value
can be sort of amped up quite a bit
you know the swipe distance when when
this thing attacks like in here or
whatever you know I can make that that
can increase that distance if for some
gloves right that wanna
have more of a sweep to him I feel like
that's one reason use a parabola you can
kind of see how it it flies out quite a
bit at the end and I feel like you kind
of want it a lot narrower than that
potentially so you know maybe I don't
want that as the function either let me
just see what some other functions look
like there so let's do like triangle
zero one and this would just be you know
if as as T goes from zero to one I want
it to actually be when it's at at 0.5 I
want it to be at 1 right so I want the
result to actually be twice T so it goes
up there quickly but then if it's
greater than right if it goes past point
5 I want to diminish back down so I want
to basically say like if result is it's
greater than 1 then I want to subtract
it from 2 right so to make a little
notch triangle and I don't know that
might be better
and that does feel a little better
although it may want to be even more
eccentric than that all right I'm not
sure
alright let's go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A
with support Nintendo's power gloves I
probably not because I don't have one
nor do I think I have the leet hacks or
skills necessary to plug it into a PC
but I gotta cut some wires and do some
splicing
soy sauce the kid our chain attacks
going to be in by any chance
ie slash slash thrust no not in that
sense and the reason for that is there
isn't well there aren't multiple attack
buttons if that makes sense the attack
the buttons for attack are the direction
to attack there isn't a button that does
a different type of attack
it's that make sense so they'll probably
be some things code wise a little bit
like that which are based on like the
pattern in which you may have hit the
attack button for example double tapping
the attack button will probably be
different than single tapping the attack
bucket button but there won't be like a
you know X X Y kind of a thing
no VIN what are your thoughts on
switching to simulating adjacent rooms
rather than using the simulation apron
well my thought is that we probably want
to set the apron to be the adjacent
rooms but not actually explicitly code
it as such and the reason for that is
because we may want to reserve the
flexibility to change the size of rooms
and if we hard-code a bunch of stuff to
be like simulate the next room over it
might be a little unclear what that
actually means in situations like where
there isn't a clear room or heaven
forbid we decide that a certain room is
smooth scrolling and goes on for a while
so I'm thinking that apron may be the
best thing for the time being but you
know I don't really know since we don't
care like the sim region code doesn't
care how you do the gather we have a
pretty like we can make that decision
right up until they until we ship the
game right it's like we don't have to
make that decision at any particular
time so when we see how the game is
playing way on down the line you know
200 episodes from now we can make that
call then and it's not going to really
change any of the rest of the code I
don't think
how is the familiar intended to attack
some kind of projectile or doing some
kind of glide move and physically
getting a foe I'll be honest I have not
really thought that much about familiars
we will probably have them in the game
but they're not a part of the design I
really worked on very much there'll be a
post on Mali rocket forums not this week
but probably the next week that actually
has a lot of information about some
handmade hero stuff that's happening
that will give a little more insight
into that sort of stuff but basically
what I'd say is the reason I put
familiars in there during this coding
session was not because they were this
big part of the game design but rather
be just because they were a nice
understandable thing that everyone knows
what they are so that we could just play
with coding one and make sure that our
system allowed that to happen right
will there be a boot to match the glove
no there's only gloves at the moment for
particle effects for the glove are we
going to be doing something similar to
what we did or similar to what we did
earlier using head assets yes and no the
yes part is that we you know the basics
of a particle system are always the same
the no part is we probably don't need
some of the we don't really need the oil
Arian grid-based stuff for something
like glove particle effects so a lot of
the particle effects will be simpler
than the stuff we implemented as the
when I did the sort of like here's an it
here's how to do particle systems kind
of just example stream so the particle
effects of the glove will probably be
much simpler than that but otherwise
yeah they'd be similar mid blue I'm
wondering if it could be cool mechanic
if you could swipe and change your
facing direction while you swipe thus
prolonging the swipe into a potentially
never-ending spinning punch so there are
sort of the control of the glove will be
different depending on which glove you
have and I would like to try some after
touch on it but at the moment it's a
little early for me to say what of those
kinds of things are gonna go in the game
because I kinda have to play with them
and see like stuff like that is a little
too feel based to really know what's
going to be good or bad in actually
playing the game
have you played Planescape torment your
handmade hero totally needs a Mort style
familiar I I guess maybe my my
preference would would actually probably
be if I was gonna get familiars would be
HK 47 from kotor I liked his vantur more
than mort's to be honest willing Guzman
will attacking the interrupt such as
attacking an unanimity entity or someone
attacked the player from behind in it
jump opposite to the attack example old
Zelda so are you talking about the way
that it pushes the player I'm not sure
what aspect of it are you talking about
I'm not sure I know exactly what you're
asking in general attacks will not
interrupt the player probably unless
they were a very special kind of attack
but attacks may interrupt enemies so if
the enemy was doing something the enemy
may get knocked back or whatever now
sometimes the player might get knocked
back as well but you you know probably
most you know enemies wouldn't often
have that kind of ability just cuz I
think it's kind of annoying to
constantly be pushed around but but you
may get gloves that do that and then you
would have more you know when you had
that ability you could use it often and
that sort of stuff duro I'd say why not
leave the glove swipe to the artist
animator of the game so because there is
no animator if there is an animator then
you have to make a little bit of a
trade-off there meaning even if you have
an animator it doesn't mean you always
want to leave everything to animations
and the reason for that is animations
are not parametric they don't have any
logic in them right and so for something
as crucial as say the way the player
hops around and or the way that the
glove swipes you know there's only so
much you can do in a can set of
animations and I don't know that I want
I don't know that I would want those to
be canned even if there was an animator
on the game because you know I might
want I want there to be more logic to
how it like restores and what it does
and I also want to be more parametric so
it's like every glove that you might get
is animated differently depending on
stats and things like that and I think
for you know the hopping in the glove I
think I would probably want to hand code
how those worked to a large extent even
if it was a game that was being hand
animated by somebody for other things
like monster attacks
thing which are perhaps less interesting
from the standpoint of hand coding the
animation but
it looks like there's really no
programming questions here so I'm just
gonna go ahead and wind down let's go
ahead close this out all right thanks
everyone for joining me for another side
of a handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home you can
always peer out of the game on handmade
hero Oregon it comes with the source
code so you can play around with it at
home even as we are building it we have
a forum site you go to ask questions if
you have questions about the programming
we also have a patreon page you can go
to if you want support the video series
you have a schedule bot where we tweet
the schedule if you want to catch the
stream live and we have an episode guide
by our very own Niblo who you can also
support on patreon if you want to catch
up with past videos in the series that's
about it for this week of handmade hero
we'll be back next week - well I think
we've got two big tech things to do
before we can sort of consider our
entity stuff fairly fairly solid and
that is we got a deal with our Z
placement stuff and we've got to deal
with our collision detection so those
will be some pretty big topics which
will probably start delving into next
week but it's pretty cool I mean we're
already at the point now where the game
is starting to look a little bit more
gamey and the world already has that
weird feeling of being a little bit
active and alive even though there's
really not very much code in there for
it it's just kind of interesting you
know I mean it's weird right
if you run if you just run even what
we've got right now it's weird the
transition to once things are active in
the world it just kind of feels like
something a place all of a sudden that
it didn't feel like before and now that
there's stuff happening and especially
when something happens like somebody
comes down from the top you know and
onto the screen it adds this weird like
sort of I don't know
it's sort of I guess what I'd say is now
that we've done sort of the entity brain
stuff the the world inside handmade hero
has crossed that threshold to me to
where it feels like it's actually a
thing and and that's kind of fun so I'm
looking forward to kind of getting our
tech stuff finished up the few remaining
issues we've got that I want done before
we move forwards with specific gameplay
things because I think it's gonna be fun
to just start dumping a lot of stuff in
there that's just my opinion
so anyway of course as I say that now
Jude never came down why don't you come
down to visit us ever what did we ever
do to you mr. worm creature he's just
kind of chilling out there isn't he yeah
all right anyway I don't even know why
I'm focusing on that point being so I
think it's kind of cool and I'm looking
forward to just you know basically
dumping it's fun to when you have art
assets like you know it'll be fun to
dump into some monsters and and then
start fighting them or whatever and so
it's kind of cool to see that starting
to come together anyway that's about it
I will see you guys back here next week
check the schedule bot for the schedule
if you would like to catch those streams
until then have fun programming and I
will catch you guys on the Internet
take it easy everyone