hello everyone
and welcome to handmade hero co came
where we code to complete
oh wow show where we go to complete came
on stream
yeah it's gonna be that kind of day i
can tell um
we are right in the middle right now of
just uh
fixing up sort of the way we do asset
lookups
we never really had anything in
particular for this
uh we made sort of a tag lookup system
at the very early like very early on
uh and we never really revisited it and
so
now that i'd like to start kind of being
able to put
um the like i'd like to be able
to go through really uh
straightforwardly
adding asset stuff and there was just a
bunch of things that were obviously not
very good
um about how it was working and so all i
really wanted to do
was take a look at what would be
required to simplify
you know just make it uh easy for us to
add lots of assets and make it easy for
stuff to work
the way we want it to work and so all
we're doing right now is changing to us
from a system where we passed very like
um
like very large floating point vectors
if this makes sense um which were just
completely generalized into something
that's much simpler so now what we're
doing is we're basically passing
something that's going to be
uh very discreet and which is
you know tailored to the assets we
actually have rather than bef when we
first started where we didn't have any
idea
so we just had to kind of put something
in to get started um
and that was of course why we didn't do
anything fancy with it originally was
just because
before you actually know what's going on
with your assets
you don't want to spend a lot of time
like trying to optimize the system
to like look them up or whatever because
if you spend all that time
once you then find out what your assets
actually look like in the end
you're going to find that you optimize
the wrong thing right
so now that we have some idea of what
we're doing we kind of know
what we would need in terms of like and
we saw this last time
we we more or less know what we need
in terms of flexible lookup versus
rigid lookup right so we have sort of
two types of things we need to do
one type of thing is like a very
concrete discrete
exact lookup and that's just something
like
okay i know that i'm making the walls of
the orphanage
so i want to be able to uniquely
identify things that are from the wall
of the orphanage
right and so the way we do that is we
use the asset tag hash now and you can
see if i center my keyboard properly
here asset tag hash
um you can see that these are just
now 64-bit values and the 64-bit values
they come from a
a set of functions here that can
generate those
by taking a bunch of tags so we used to
have these various tags
it can take a bunch of tags and it will
uh sort of
conglomerate them into a single u64
uh and produce this this you know
value directly from that
and so when you think about what's going
on here we're replacing a system where
we used to pass these very large vectors
with like ones in a few places and
it had to be weighted and so on by just
saying okay what we're going to do
instead is we're just going to use
ordered sets of tags we're going to mush
those into a 64-bit value that 64.5 is
going to be a unique identifier
for a family of uh assets and those
assets are then going to be matched so
we
will spin over a few assets there we're
gonna we are going to look at the assets
that match
this 64-bit value for matching
in one or two other categories that are
more flexible meaning we don't know
exactly what's in there
and those will be things like facing
direction
and um variant
are two of the things that we know will
have we might have others but we know
we'll have those
uh and in fact at the moment we we
already have those defined here as you
can see
in this asset match vector element we
currently only use two floating point
values now and we don't necessarily even
use both of them right but we're going
to use
up to two and those get matched
in a fuzzy way so the artist for example
can
make these as dense as they want them to
be
so if an artist wants to input
more facing directions for a character
like this like if a character
wanted eight facing directions instead
of four
instead of one right you could have a
thing that can only ever face one
direction right so no matter what
direction it's moving you don't have
we want the ability to like dynamically
change that resolution
without the game having to think about
it so we don't want the game code
uh essentially to know um
anything about that right we don't want
the game code to have to think
oh for each art asset i have to have
a like knowledge in the code of
how its facing directions were laid out
so what we've essentially done here
right is we've
condensed those uh the sort of
fuzzy entirely fuzzy matching
from the previous way we were doing it
ever since the beginning of handmade
hero
we've condensed that down into now a
very specific way of looking up
assets and then still retained a little
bit
just just the amount of the fuzzy
matching
that we think we will actually use and
the reason we wanted to do that
was because a it's much more
straightforward so
now when i'm coding those parts of the
game which is what we're about to do
like we're going to want to start
putting all these assets in right and
like
i want to be able to like start putting
stuff around the orphanage and the
different characters different monsters
i want to be able to put those in the
game i don't want to be sitting around
trying to make these huge vectors and
match them with fuzzy like i just want
to know okay i'm specifying this
thing uniquely and then the only things
i want to be fuzzy are things that i
legitimately don't care
what they map to right so facing
direction and variant
are examples of not caring what
something maps to
because we know that it's just look
we're telling you
some random number between zero and one
for the variant and a facing direction
between zero and pi uh probably 2 pi i
think that's what we did 0 to 2 pi
for facing direction so when we pass
those
down right what we know
is that we're sending the data we need
exactly what we exactly what the game
code knows
and wants is being specified to the
asset system and then the asset system
will take care of the rest and so that's
makes it
exactly split the way i want so that's
one reason the second reason
is because this will be much faster so
once we start piling tons of assets into
the game
the list of assets will get very long
and before we were literally walking
through like all of the body
assets and match matching it's right it
was it was like an
o n per lookup and it just wouldn't have
scaled very well right
now we have a hash table that will cut
down the actual identification
of which subsets of assets might match
into a very small number so depending on
how wide we make that hash table we can
cut it down dramatically
to basically only assets that are in
that facing direction
or that variant set and since we know
we're only ever going to have four
facing directions
maybe eight tops if for some particular
monster type that really has a lot of
face direction or something and no more
than say like 16 variants
of anything and we don't really do
variance for facing direction at the
moment
we know that we're not going to have to
loop through many elements
right we're going to be able to look at
elements very quickly
and furthermore because we have control
over that hash table it gets built
at load time we should also be able to
accelerate that if we needed to
so we can make it just be a linked list
that hops through
assets in a fairly slow way and that may
not
ever cost us much because we just don't
have to hop through very many elements
but if we find that there are
you know 32 or 64 elements in some of
these
chains what we can do is we can
we can aggregate the
matching values for those into
arrays that we pre-allocate that are all
together
we can load up the entire
set of match values in like two or three
cmd block reads right so just like you
know literally
three or four memory accesses
one cache line right of 64 bytes
could have all the values like quantized
or something then we could do the match
right there in one
operation that produces the correct
index out of there
and then we just look that one up right
so the fuzzy matching
condensing that down so that we're
matching only against
a set of very well-known
discrete groups uh means that i don't
have any concerns
about scaling this up at all because we
should be able to handle
any amount of asset complexity dumped
into this system
because now we know that for all of the
complexity that occurs on the side of
what asset you're loading
that is now effectively can be made
instant and then the matching
is also arranged in a way that i'm not
scared about scaling it up to
32 64 possible entries which should be
more than enough
uh because we can always make the hash
table wider so any given asset match
shouldn't really get
much above that right so
uh off we go um so now what we want to
do is just finish
we what we did is we created some code
for doing all this stuff we haven't
finished actually porting stuff that
uses it so here you can kind of see
in here we've got this adding tags to
the entity here where it's putting these
on there
i do like the way that that's working
but
i don't necessarily like the fact that
it's happening on the entity
specifically
and the reason for that is because
entities are not really where these tags
get stored anymore
the reason for that is we no longer
actually want to specify per
entity tags what we want to do is
specify per piece tags
because we want entities to be able to
grab pieces from multiple different
asset types right because pieces of
entities uh
you know it's fine if you want to say
that all of the pieces in an entity are
all the same asset type
but we don't really want to force that
we want to be able to have like an
entity comprised of pieces that come
from anywhere
is this a puss eye here oh my goodness
oh my goodness hello sweet plus what's
going on
what's going on come on up do you want
to say hi to everyone on the stream
do you want to say hi hmm how you doing
what's going on you just mousing around
this morning you came up here you opened
the door all by yourself
i think you've done a good job learning
how to open that door
yeah that's a good puss
that's a good puss what's going on
hmm
what do you think you know i can't
really program
uh when you're on my shoulder though
unfortunately and this is really this is
a problem with task chairs
so let me just
say one thing out there for anybody
who has product design experience this
is
a product that i desperately want and i
do not know anything about product
design so i cannot make it
but i need a chair like a task chair
attachment or just a task chair itself
that i can buy
that has like a thing right here
to support the puss even just like just
like a little thing that comes in here
oh no
don't edit the code molly um
um so basically when the puss is up here
right
i could actually start working but i
need to support
her legs right you see how i'm doing
this with my shoulder
like right here i have to keep my arm up
so i could do
something one-handed just fine with my
left hand
but i can't type with two hands because
one
arm is is dedicated to support the puss
you know what i'm saying and so what i
want
is i want some way of
supporting the puss so she can stay on
my shoulder which is where she always
wants to be
if she can she would she would just like
live on the shoulder
um support the puss's
hind legs so she can just stay on my
shoulder while i code and then she's
happy
i'm happy everything's good um and i'd
probably code better because it's great
having a puss around
they they help with your with your
coding
when you can actually code you know what
i'm saying
so it just needs it needs to be
something that would support
you know the puss out out there
yeah i thought about a baby pouch but i
don't know if it would work
because um it's not it's not really on a
shoulder
right um so i don't know if it would
satisfy her i could try
ordering a baby pouch and she could she
could be like here
or something but i don't i don't know if
a baby pouch would do it
i've had that same thought believe me i
just don't
it's not really putting her in the
position she wanted to be in so i don't
think she would stay
um but i don't know another thing would
be if it was back here she could curl
around your neck she would probably do
that too but she likes being up
you know so i don't know don't eat my oh
baby those are my headphones
don't eat my headphones okay go go go
see they gotta put the headphones away
she always eats my headphones if they're
left out
anyway that is a product i very much
would love to have so if somebody out
there
knows how to make that happen i will be
your very first customer
um i will i when the kickstarter goes up
for like task cat
or whatever it's going to be um
i will i will be the very first backer
and i will back like the highest level
um okay so um
thank you in advance whoever's gonna
make that that's great we need that
so what i was saying here is what i want
is effectively an asset tag
uh like aggregator so
what i want to be able to do here is
just say okay
so like when we're doing generation code
like we're doing here
um what i'd like to be able to do is do
something
where uh and we and we sort of have in
the gen
code right there's this like gen entity
idea and there's this gen entity tagged
with with tags of four and you could see
here
like it was kind of set up to push these
things on in the first place
what i don't super understand though is
why
it's baked in here i guess because we
never really needed to pull it out
this is something that i think we just
want to have right
in general we don't need these f32
values here
anymore really um to
uh well i mean maybe we do
that's a little bit harder to say um but
what what i'm basically suggesting here
is inside this like instead of having it
be raw we want like a gen entity
uh tag bundle
i don't know uh
something like this where these are
placed
something like this and that way when we
go through
and build these tags we can create one
of these
like this is what i want to do right i
want to create one of these
uh and then i just want to push
like tags on it incrementally so when i
do
add tag in here when i have this
tag builder it would be more like this
right
so this is how i actually wanted to do
it um where instead of pushing it onto
an
entity which is now not really a thing
we would do
instead we're going to push it onto
a tag builder and then when we actually
are done so when we have
all of the tags on this thing that we
need
then we would just you know finalize
those tags
effectively right so we
we would push the tags on we would then
go
to here where we're about to build them
and we would just say like
you know finalize tags here so it'd just
be like
this
oops
now the only thing i'm not sure about is
where exactly the asset type would
flow in here when you do add piece
you're supposed to pass it the full the
entity piece
asset thing
and you can see that that's like the
hash plus the variant
right and so in this case we don't
really have a variant
um and so
we would need something that produces
the tags like this
right or maybe this and it would
presumably
be able to do that so you can see we
have here the helper function
that does that from these we would just
have one an equivalent one
that generates it from in addition to
uh generating it from the tags laid out
like this it would generate it from
the tag builder so when we say get piece
asset what we need to do here is
we need to also say what you know in
this case i believe it's always scenery
so we would say like that it's
asset scenery we would pass the tag
builder and then we would pass the
variant here
except i don't think that we have
variance in this part of the code
meaning this part of the code never
bothers passing down a variant anyway
one thing that i would suggest is it
probably just we never thought of that
but
we probably want there to be one so we
probably want
this to be like a random unilateral here
that takes the entropy
the uh the world entropy stream and just
sets
like these pieces to have random
variants
because that way if the artist
sticks more for any piece of scenery
that we ask for
if the artist happens to stick variants
into the system
they'll be used
i have to trim molly's back nails really
need a trim check out
she tried to crawl up on me look at i've
got the like scratch
bleed to prove it
um she's a very sweet puss and
she never scratches you on purse purpose
but sometimes when she slips
she extends her like you know back or
front
uh nails and she tries to grab to not
slip
and and you get a a good old scratch on
you
um we try to keep her nails
trimmed short but you know they
she sharpens them quickly let's put it
that way
um so i think this is roughly what we
want here
my only question about it uh at this
point is whether or not
we actually have to um
order these in any particular way so you
can kind of see here that we've got them
ordered pretty strongly
it's always like wall or floor
comes first and then like wood stone or
grass
comes next and so we're actually already
adding them
in the order they appear um and
like i said before we could do work in
the asset system to de-order tags
meaning that any set of tags can match
in any order meaning
you don't have to put them in the same
order they appear in here
but actually i think i want it this way
because i may want this to be i may want
to use
order as a thing at some point i don't
know that i will but i might
so i'm not going to add that in yet
and i'm going to see whether it's fine
doing it this way
um in other words if you said like
orphan earth was different than earth
orphan
like in english word order matters
in this case maybe the tag order should
should also have that um
and and i just don't know so i don't
want to say for sure that that's the
right thing
because i don't know but uh i do
just kind of want to yeah i just i kind
of want
to um uh
leave that be for now like i wanna i
wanna i don't wanna push that
so you can see we've got a tag builder
here and this tag builder was in the
asset system
right uh and we may be able to
regularize these we may be able to
to bake these together uh i'm not
actually sure but i don't care about
that right now so i'm not going to
really look at that
um i just want to take a look at the
various add tag functions we have here
so this is the gen entity one this is
the one that we're
we're presumably not really going to be
using anymore so instead this is the one
that would take the tag builder so this
would take
um
sorry i'm so slow today uh so that would
this is the one that would take
the gen eddie tag builder so this one
right here
that will always use this
like so and it doesn't need the f32
value because that's just not
related right so it will take the
builder
it will use the builder
to push a tag on to the set like so
and it doesn't need the value here
because there is no such thing as the
value
now we may want to do something like
this
and that would just be something that
allows you to snuggle the variant
in here um so we could do something like
you know oh there's facing direction and
variant or in here
but i don't think we really want that
necessarily uh
i mean maybe we do sometimes we do want
to specify that facing direction
and so uh you know i'm not sure
it's hard to say if you go look um
at the way we would have to do that
facing direction is kind of tricky
because it kind of wants to come
from the entity itself but you can
imagine wanting facing directions
to be specified rigidly for things like
scenery
assets that can face multiple directions
that are just stationary
and so i don't really know what you
would do with that but i suspect what we
would want to do with that
is you would actually want that not to
be specified on the tag builder
but rather to be specified on the entity
so in other words
you would probably do something like
this where you have the facing direction
specified
and then the entity type itself when you
look at that
is going to have a facing direction and
that facing direction would just be
specified here
you know specifically right at some
point we've gotta like port
fully to like f32s instead of r32s right
so yeah um but anyway
uh so if you imagine moving forward from
here we would say that the facing
direction went on the gen entity
um i'm not sure why gen create entity is
oh because it's a
pound of fine it's like that's not why
it's not highlighted um
so the genetic tag builder we would have
one of those
plus a facing direction in here
like so uh and then any time anyone was
specifying something from that they
would specify it
by specifically targeting the tag
builder right
so in this case where we're doing
something like place cat and this needs
to add a tag
for cat on here right instead of result
it's going to be like result tags
but that's it uh and oh then of course
we don't need
the 1.0 anymore and that would be true
for any of these things
and then when we have facing direction
like this where you're going to specify
the facing direction like i saying
before
that would actually be like a tag
specifier
so the facing direction would actually
be
specified thus right so
i think that's basically what we would
need
is not a member that's a good point i
meant
that so i think that's all we would
really need and now it's just a question
of of
turning through the code uh and
basically porting this old code that we
had
and making it work uh properly right
okay um i think that's it
i don't know why that looks like this we
don't need the gen
to be passed anymore so all of that
should be fine
um in fact all of these are now more
simple because they don't actually
require
uh any of that stuff the orphan name tag
here does go second so again i'm i'm
seeing mostly what's happening
is the tags are already um
they already appear to be going in the
order uh
that we would want them to appear so it
seems like we don't really have much
work to do
there and so that again suggests that
maybe we just don't care
about making the order non-specific
so that seems fine uh we've got some
like test code here that was adding some
scenery
uh we'll go ahead and put that in there
i really do want to know and i and you
know
at this point i've got a
oops this one is actually just a facing
direction
i really do have to take a look at my
list of things here
i don't remember where it ended up but i
had
a set of things that needed to get
looked at
here it is uh and i just have to make
sure
that all of that it looks like the mark
vertical got done already but i need to
uh i need to go ahead and turn through
my list here
of four coder things that are still uh
still there and
it looks like
um
it looks like yeah i've got this on my
list with the token movements
um
so the token movements
are still kind of busted so when i
delete something it deletes way too much
yeah but i've done most of these
so we're almost there on the editor side
of things we're almost there
but not quite um i'll have to remember
to look at some of those
i'll talk to ryan about it we're still
waiting for allen to ship the new four
coder
um beta so i think ryan and i are both
kind of waiting
um we both contributed some code uh some
new code stuff
to it and uh we're just waiting for that
to to actually get baked
um so i don't know what the status is of
that hopefully
not too long for a new four coder but
uh we'll see anyway uh so again just
these are pretty straightforward right
we're just gonna change these so that
the tags
get added on these little tag builder
things um
you can see here like so
uh and i think that's all we really
needed this now needs to get
written because it hasn't been right um
i'm not sure what this is about i don't
know why this got highlighted actually
does anybody else know why
i have to go over there to read it
although i just read it at the bottom i
shouldn't have done that um function
does not take three arguments
get entity at traversable does not take
three arguments
really
where is that function
so somehow get entity at traversible is
not found
how is that possible that there can be
no matches when it's actually
highlighted
like it has to be somewhere right
so it seems a little weird that there
isn't one
um one would assume that
get entity at traversible exists in here
somewhere
like in the sim region for example is
where i'd probably expect it to be um
that's really strange
so how is it possible that this is found
by the indexor
but four coder literally can't find it
right is that just a bug
um so let's
let's take a look
what's the actual code hold on a second
the strings and then the path
right get
entity at
traversible
well it didn't find it so how so what
so this must not actually
it's but it says right there c
declaration
of get entity at traversible right
i'm so confused right now also this one
compiled
oh wow i'm typing it wrong
about slow day uh
all right so the question here is just
what does it actually need and it needs
in this case
um a uh
rip uh so anyway uh
this needs the base hash so it's just
wants
in addition to the uh in addition to the
thing it's standing on right when it
actually does a gen
entity at that it needs to know what the
actual tags are
so you can see here like the get tree
tags bit
is going on um we don't actually
so the only thing about that is it
doesn't use that
right um
[Music]
so we actually don't care what this
passes
as far as i know because it doesn't
actually add oh it does no it does
add tag lamp so it does actually uh
want that so we can actually do we can
say uh
get asset piece or get peace asset right
so that's that's not true we can say
look we wanted a tag lamp
um it's scenery
uh and we just didn't have anything else
there wasn't anything else in here right
so it was just just a tag lamp uh and
off it goes
now the there is one sort of uh
there is one sort of weirdness there
which is to say
that i don't actually know
the the tags file right so
if we go into base game and we look at
what lamp has
so we look here you can see that it's
the orphan lamp that's being placed here
um so there's orphan lamp and orphan
lamp large
for example um and
so i don't know to what extent we want
that to remain but presumably
we do want to specify that in its
entirety
in its entirety and whether we want to
be large or not i suppose
is irrelevant but um
we at least need to specify those two
things
if we then look over here uh at
the next problem we've got we don't want
that one um these should all be
basically the same so here
we're placing um we're placing the
actual entities in here
this again this part which was being
done
previously is now like doesn't even need
to exist anymore
because we can do it in one go so this
is just going to do
be a a get piece asset call that
passes in the that tag
builder right so the pending entity
tags will get placed we'll get passed to
that
for get piece asset and that's all we'll
need
the only thing we don't know here is
what type
of entity this actually is right so
that part is a little confusing like
when we do gen entity at traversible
and it passes that in it doesn't know
which one this is
so presumably for this case we would
pass
asset none and then the asset itself
gets filled in right late by the actual
gen code when it puts in the different
asset base types like the body and the
head or whatever else it needs
so i think that's more or less what
we're doing
uh and so then the only question here is
like
where you know we got to write this
function but that's but that's basically
it
so ingen entity where that code is here
um oops gen or entitygen
uh and we've got that
that call to do get piece asset we kind
of just need
entity piece asset here again uh
and this it's the same code as this it's
just
it needs and it also needs the variant
right
um so that get piece asset call
which exists here
will default to being the zero variant
doesn't matter
um so when we actually have the call
that passes
the uh the asset basic category
and then the uh the tag builder
so the gen entity tag builder uh
and then the variant oh no the variant's
already on there
uh all we need to do is just sort of
feed this forward
right so we just need to say like okay
if this is what you're producing
uh then the result is just going to be a
call to the more explicit version
that passes cat and then passes the four
tags
that exist right and since those tags
will be initialized to asset none anyway
uh we don't actually have to worry about
that part
uh because we'll just be passing you
know the zero value through
as we go
so that's pretty much it and uh
yeah if four coder is completely broken
right now like i said we're still
waiting for allen to fix it
uh so we you know we the indentation is
just completely broken
um and i have no idea why uh
i believe ryan said it had something to
do with the fact that like
there was some call that it was making
about parentheses that was
like that maybe the four code or flurry
code was
not returning the right value so it may
actually not be the four code is broken
it's like the customization layers
broker and i i still don't know
um so again waiting for that i was
really hoping for that this week but
maybe next week i'll i'll bug out about
see where we're at
um so i think that's
all we need for that um we've got
some complaint here
about oh so we don't need these
to be indirected anymore these can just
be direct
right um
so when we're actually doing these gen
entity tags none of this
this is all nonsense right that doesn't
have to happen anymore
uh and so when we're adding tags to the
tag builder we can just
add them right so we can just do this
and we don't need it to be fancy anymore
and so
in theory
this will just work now
um get piece asset it has a
basic category the tag builder oh and i
forgot
the variant override so in this case
we we do want a way to override the
variant probably
although actually no why would we do
that we don't really need that
so instead what we should do here is
just set that variant
right so we should say like tag builder
variant equals
random unilateral right like if we want
that we should just set it before we
make the call
that seems better right
okay with entity visible piece here
where we're adding this piece
in um again this is just pretty
straightforward i think this just wants
to be
reorganized slightly so that we add the
piece after the fact
here we can get the asset tag directly
we don't have to use a builder for any
particular reason so what we can
actually do is
roll these all into this the one call uh
so we can just say like
get uh get peace asset it's a block
that's a floor grass block
um and that's it right
and we can pass variants to these if we
want later but at the moment i suppose
we don't really need to
um although maybe we should if we look
here
at adding the tree tags uh that's
been replaced by get tree tags and so if
we do a get tree tags
and pass that along that just produces
the thing we actually needed
so when we do gen entity at
p we just pass that
result of that that produces the tags we
wanted uh
and then we're done we
need to now look at anything else that's
all our compile errors
um we're not out of the woods yet
because we haven't actually written all
the code that we need
uh that's like a nominal port but the
asset system
is not actually going to be putting
anything into this
tag hash so if we ran the game now it
would just
roll over and die because it doesn't
have any way to access
like any assets at all right
so if you imagine us you know running it
here
uh all we're gonna do is yeah and you
can you can see
um we're just gonna get garbage out of
here
and we're not going to find any assets
for anything so uh
let me let me switch to a debug build
here
um just so we can get our
our errors better uh but what we're
gonna have to do now is
when we start loading assets we have to
actually put them
into the hash you know what i'm saying
so let's go ahead and do that
[Music]
uh
okay
so i'm not sure exactly why this is
failing
in this way so it might be interesting
to just kind of
look at what's happening here it could
be
that somebody's not properly returning
like a a cleared value when they should
so it might be nice to just you know
take a quick look at that
uh and figure out what's going on just
to remove a bug
even though we know that this shouldn't
work it shouldn't fail
in quite that way i don't think so i'd
rather
just be uh clear about it right
um so if we take a look here when it
passes the peace cube
uv layout uh into here that's going to
call get
bitmap with this id uh
and that id is the second thing passed
right so the thing that it's looking for
here is this bitmap id
um
so it's passing a zero bitmap id so it
what in here where it says
get bitmap with an id of zero i feel
like that
texture handle is should not be
returning
a is valid
um because 0 should never be valid
to be fair i suppose it should never
actually be calling this like if the id
0 it should just
skip this all together presumably but
now that we have a case where that's
actually happening i kind of want to
figure out what this should do and do it
right
so if we look at what's going on with
this and we call get asset with
zero right um the if
asset call here should
should this should produce hopefully a
a null pointer is what we would want
so what you can see here is it wouldn't
do that because it's actually
passing a get asset of zero will
actually just give you the zero with
asset
which presumably i don't know
why we necessarily do that maybe we
wanted to produce a null
asset the problem with producing a null
asset is i'm not sure what happens
at that point when you then ask for like
the texture handle right which would be
this thing
but presumably it should just be all
zeros there
anyway so we may what we may want to do
um in this case
is we may want to spend a little bit of
time
making sure like if we actually return a
null asset that it actually works
so what probably happened here was
somebody like loaded one of these things
in
um
so like i'm gonna do this real quick
because i want to see what happens uh
just to see right and
just eliminating the union part of this
yeah so i think the problem here
is that uh the null so you can see where
we run into trouble if we make these a
union
then the problem is that the null asset
being the zero with asset
always creates a problem for us
specifically because of the fact that
it is doesn't know which of these you're
actually using
so it can't produce the correct null
version of each of these
which is probably what we need so i'm
going to go ahead and say
that for now we'll just let that stand
because it's totally fine
they're they're not particularly large
uh like if you look at loaded font i
don't think it's yeah it's like
there's really not much in there so
having this be the asset control
structure is fine with me
uh i do think like to do uh
in the end we probably want to make
separate asset structs
uh for each of these because they are
handled so differently now
it may not make a whole lot of sense
to have a single
large asset type
um but that seems fine uh
there's really not a lot else uh that
needs to happen
in order for us to run because now we
run just fine right
so i think that was all that the problem
was and we'll leave it at that
all right so now we need to actually add
assets into the
asset hash table because if we don't do
that then we're not actually
going to be able to do anything right
like if we don't add
uh the asset
if if we don't add assets into the
assets by tag
hash then
we won't ever find any when we look so
that's the
the part that we need to actually take
care of
i don't know why this says does this
need to be a prime hash
because we know that it doesn't need to
be a prime hash since we're using
uh an actual hash function now right uh
we're using
we're using a strong hash function
very strong this should be pretty close
to random bit distribution
and we can verify that but
you know we
we know we can make this be basically
random bit
distribution so we shouldn't need this
to be a prime hash
for any reason because the only reason
you make
the only reason you ever would make a
hash table be
a prime number of entries is if your
hash function itself
is weak so if the thing that you're
using to hash the inputs is weak
then the bits won't be randomly
distributed and so having there be a
prime
number of entries in the hash makes it
so that when you do the modulus
you're not uh biasing towards certain
bits
in the uh in the input
but if you know that all of your bits
are evenly distributed
in the hash anyway then you don't ever
need that so
how do you verify that well it's pretty
easy for us to later we could count
how many assets go into each uh of these
and we can
actually look and see if we can just
take a histogram basically
and see uh if they are
right so we can verify that later
um so what we want to do is fill out
this assets by tag
so in this first asset of type nonsense
here
what we want to do um is in first assets
uh first asset of type let me just look
for
first asset of type um
what we're doing is inserting like we're
inserting
into that right so if you look at
uh like set asset type for example
we want this to now be a more general
version right and you can see here
we're talking about it right
and so what we want to do is actually
just have a like
update hash you know uh
we want like an update hash for this
thing
right that's what we want so we want to
get rid of first asset
uh and the only place that that was
being used in the asset lookup
so now what we want to do is some way of
of making this
uh look we want to look at all the
places that use it right so we want to
look at all the call sites for set asset
type
uh and we want to figure out how to make
that work so you can see
here like here's where we're loading
right so this just is where we load all
of the asset metadata
so in here this is one place where we
would do it
right we've loaded all the tags
and you know off off we would go
and then here's another place where we
would do it and this is where we update
the actual asset metadata where we say
you know here's what's going on so
i think what we want to do is just
change this
um and we want to do something like this
we want to say like um update
update asset hash table right
and we want to pass the assets we want
to pass the asset index that we're
trying to update
and then we need some way of sending it
like tags
we need to send it the tags that we
actually have right
and what you can see here is this
actually does
a bunch of tag appending here like you
can see it
you know doing doing this thing and
uh it looks to see whether the tags
differ
and then it does some updating to like
add the tags
in uh like here right
and so what we may want uh and i don't
really know
but what we may want to do here is
remove an asset from the hash table
at the head of this and then insert it
to the hash table later so what we may
want
is two calls um remove
asset from hash like so
uh and we would say this right
we can preserve this error check because
apparently this is an error check we
care about
right so we'd say remove this asset from
the hash table
and if it doesn't exist in the hash
table at the moment that's fine too
right and then later down here what we
can do
is say once we're done with all of it
add it back in
right
so we can remove it from the hash table
we can add it to the hash table
and then what we would do is the other
place that this gets called
we would only add it right
and this is the global asset index is
what we cared about
there and off we go so
now we just need that function right
um we need to be able to instead of
doing set asset type
which is not a thing we would do anymore
we have a remove asset from hash
which takes the you know asset index
uh and an an an ad asset to hash
and these are like you know functions
that work together
uh and so
we remove asset from hash
there we go uh and so then our only
problem is we now have to actually
figure out how to write this function
which is nominally pretty easy but there
is one sort of nasty
element to it which is that we've never
actually tried to load
tags out of the tag set for an asset and
actually build
um one of our internal tag hashes from
it so we need to kind of go
learn how that works uh
and so when we remove an asset from a
hash you know
or when we add an ass to the hash
they're both going to use presumably
uh the same function to compute the hash
offset uh which is to say they're going
to spin through the asset set
and find that asset hash so
when we look and and this
get asset from this right here where we
do
the hash 32 mod assets by tag so that
right there um presumably also wants to
be
a value like get asset
hash slot like that and
this function here would be something
that takes
one of these tag hashes
like this and produces the hash slot in
question
so that probably wants to be
this sort of thing we would return
the result is the hash slot and that way
everyone's using the same computation
right so we know that it's uniform we
don't have to worry about like how
that's working
um so everyone here would do the same
thing right we'd all
say well if we're going to add an asset
to the hash we need to get the asset
hash lot
but what you can see is we don't have
one of these so the other piece of the
puzzle is we need a way to get that hash
slot
from an actual asset
something like that right so
we would expect this to do something
probably it will call this
from like this tag hash right
this is the part we don't know
and everyone's going to call this
so again i'm just setting this up so
that everyone can share the code so we
only have to write it once
and in both these cases what we need to
do is
modify the uh hash itself
so when we say get asset from hash lot
um
we're then going to loop through and we
can see that code
in fact right here when it's doing the
checking
right um
so it would look a little bit like this
we'd load out the first one we would
loop through like so exactly the way
this was doing
um oops this is in the wrong function
there we go
um so we looped through and we would try
to find
the asset that we're looking for right
now we would know that
we only need to find the we only need to
find the asset
that we're actually like that we're
pointing to right
so because like we're just looking for
this and we just want to
undo the like this is basically a chain
right so the hash table
is basically just a chain of assets that
fall into that slot
so all we're trying to do is like get
rid of it right we're just trying to
like get it out of that chain
so we just need like a pointer to the
previous
like index slot
right or the previous slot
uh and so if we say this is what we're
actually looking for
so we want the previous slot here to
point to
whatever this thing is right we want to
look and say
while the previous slot is not equal to
the asset index
we're good right
um and we also want to make sure that
previous slot actually exists
right because if we get to zero um
i mean another way to do this was is
while there's a previous slot
and um
it's not equal to asset index we keep
going
right and so i think
we just want this and if we
at the end if the preview slot is not
a zero value then all we would have to
do and we kind of want to pre
we we kind of want to grab this as well
again right we can see what i'm doing so
take a pointer to whatever this previous
slot
is the location of the previous slot
um we then say while there is something
there so while it is pointing to an
asset and it's not pointing to the asset
we actually want to remove
then what we do is we go one forward and
we
point to the the next pointer
the next index in the slot
the one more down the chain
eventually we're either going to run out
of links in the chain
meaning this asset was never in the ash
to begin with
or we're going to find somebody's next
pointer
that points to this asset and if we
found that then what we need to do
uh first of all if we found that it
should only if we if we claim we found
it
it should always be the one we were
looking for because that's the only way
we should have been able to end without
it being zero
we will then um look up the asset
that uh oh we don't even need to do that
so then we will just say
the asset that we're pointing to we want
to just take its next pointer and
blast it over uh the thing that was
pointing to it
right so we're removing it from the the
chain
so
this is presumably all we need to remove
ourselves from the hash right
and if we weren't in the hash no big
deal to add to the hash it's way
way way way simpler right all we have to
do is see whether there's anything we
need to link
and if there is we link otherwise we
just cold write it
so let's suppose we say all right um
we've got the the hash slot in question
is there something in there
if there is uh then we have to chain
ourselves
uh oops i guess we'll close next then we
have to chain it in here so what we
would say is like
okay um
let's get the asset to which that
corresponds
this by the way should be that
oh no we don't have to do this what am i
talking about let me just do this one
so we'll just get the asset that we're
adding right
um and we should probably assert that
asset
index is not equal to zero because we
don't ever wanna
uh insert the null like the null asset
should never really be in the hash
so unless we wanna do that sometime in
the future i'd like to know
if anyone tries to do that because that
would just be
presumably indicative that somebody
failed upstream that we
shouldn't have allowed to get here so i
just want to know about that
but we'll get this asset um we know that
the asset
in fact now that i think about it all
this stuff is useless i was thinking
about
that we were linking the other way
around um so
the next asset in the hash is just going
to be
whatever the head entry was and then the
head entry is going to be us
so that's it um there really isn't
anything
more complicated than that uh
the hash slot needs to come out of here
though
uh and that's it so now we're just left
with the problem i was talking about
before which is we don't really know how
to build a tag hash
from an asset and so
how this i think would have to work is
if we look
in here uh we've got all this
nonsense specified but we've never
actually loaded it
so this is the part that is going to be
the problem for us
which is to say that we need to be able
to find the tags
um that come
like the tags that this asset
uh is actually using right i want to say
i
this isn't really
we don't really need that
anymore do we
because we just this doesn't matter
anymore
because it will just pick the closest
one anyway
right so so i
i don't think this i
i don't think this is means anything
anymore
so i'm gonna say i'm gonna pull that
match any flags
stuff out of there for now um and if we
need it for some reason
later you know we can put it back in but
i'm going to say that's
not relevant right uh
like that just doesn't seem like that
would be necessary
anyway uh so
get asset hash lock here this get asset
from
uh is presumably not able to find that
because
it's in uh we didn't like
we didn't put it up in here
so that would need to be there
unfortunately it's behind my head there
you go
um
[Music]
and so and this is not a function
anymore
yeah and so i think we're pretty much
done with everything other than figuring
out
how we're going to update these tag
hashes
so at the moment like writing this
particular function now i think about it
is actually trivial because we're
expecting the assets to have this in
there
themselves um so really the problem was
more that
it's more how are we gonna fill these
out because they're expected to be
filled out for any asset
that we load in the first place right
um so that's a little trickier
did someone in the chat just call this a
vim color scheme
this is it's
it's not vim it's for coder
um
see
uh anyway so the
the problem that we are going to have is
not that we have to build it here
because this is actually trivial and in
fact we probably didn't really need
to do any of this as this this hash that
from
nonsense actually can just go away uh
because
what we would do is we just get the
asset like we were doing here
and then we would say okay the asset tag
hash just gets passed directly
from it right and the same thing would
be true here because we know we're going
to need the asset to compare at the end
anyway
so what we would do is we'd just say all
right you know let's just do it like
that
right so it's pretty straightforward
we we just call the the function we had
before so
the problem is actually not that the
problem is that in the two places where
we add the asset to the hash
we need to uh
go ahead and add asset to hash
um in the two places that we add the
asset to the hash
we need it to know about
the um so here's one
we need the asset hash tag hash to have
been updated so like
this would be a place where we would
need to do that for example
and then we'd need to do the same thing
in the importer
you know what i'm saying so in both
places
we need to make sure that the hash part
is
updated before we try to add this thing
to the hash because otherwise it'll just
fail now you can see here
where we're pulling out the basic
category um
by looking for that particular piece of
information
um so you can see that like that's
stored as a tag value
right and blah blah um
but what we really need to do here is
now is be a little bit more broad
right so what we need to do here is we
need to
to create a more coherent
um
version of the like like probably by
using like one of these
right so this tag builder type thing is
probably
mostly what we would want here right we
want to be able to push these tags on
one after the other
um and you can see here that we're
actually storing the asset type
as a thing we probably should
just take in the file and store the
asset tag
itself like that would probably be the
smarter thing to do anyway
um which is to say like
we probably want to just store
tag hashes so that when we load
stuff out we don't have tag sets but
since we have this entire system working
already
it seems like just patching them here is
probably the right thing to do
for the immediate moment right
um if that makes sense so
if we look at the the tag builder or
something like that we could use that
here for example and push the tags on
one at a time
uh so we could do something like this
where we just said like tag builder
right um and we just look at the the
tags and for each tag we would just oops
um we'd just look and see if it's not
one of the other things like facing
direction
or that sort of stuff then we just set
it in here right
the only reason i don't think we want to
do that
is because i feel like we probably want
this to be
a little more generic than that so we
probably want to be able to push these
tags into a thing that then kind of like
regularizes them
if that makes sense because the other
piece of code
is going to have to do the same thing
right so like in here
right you can see it doing like the tags
build
on this thing uh and we're gonna need
this to work
in the same way so you can see the tag
builder thing where we do begin tags
here
and it's doing this nonsense so you know
presumably we need that to work
again like i said before it i don't know
maybe we should just go full pull and
change the asset file
uh if we were to look at the way these
are are done
you know uh and we look at uh
like the hha header
so there's this tag count and the asset
count if we were just to say like these
are going to go away now
so there are no tags it's just an array
of assets
and annotations on the assets um and we
had to imagine what was going to happen
in there
and we just have these tag hashes right
uh
then each asset you know would have
the match vector and it would have the
the tag right and that would be a much
better way to do the file format the
problem is that it's not particularly
flexible right like the way we have it
right now
where you can just stick as many tags on
there as you want is a little bit nicer
so i think we're just going to do this
at import time it's a little sloppy
but i think that would probably just be
better so i think what we probably want
here
is a thing that just takes the asset
range and builds the tag hash from it
so when we have an add asset to hash
and only then
so when we actually add asset to hash
what i'm going to do
is say at that time we will rebuild
the tag the hash like
we'll rebuild what we expect to have
happen
there so we'll have
an asset match vector
and we'll have an asset um
tag hash and we'll produce those two
things
we will get the asset we will like
loop over the tags um and we will
i guess in here what we could also say
is so these
uh these are like the new hash
or maybe just yeah we'll just call it
the hash
and the vector so
we'll just start out with these being
nothing
right and then at the end we'll
apply them
so we will set them in here
i'll name these the same as we're
calling them on the outside
okay um so what we'll do is we'll
make a thing that just when we add
something to the hash it does the
refresh right there
so it loops through the tags and tries
to do the right thing
what that also means is that if we go
look
at the import code so you know
um that's an asset that's cpp
uh where's that's right
add asset to hash so
in here where it has to produce the type
id now this
is not necessary right
um so if something didn't have one of
these
this is where it should complain so this
doesn't have to happen anymore
right um it would really be
this right
so what we want to do is assert that the
type id
is not equal to zero because that would
mean that like the importer was broken
or something and then
in here is where we would want to do the
build
so you can see here that this is where
we'll extract the type id
this really probably you know wants to
be a switch statement
so we would take this id and we would
switch on it
we know what we do in the case of basic
category
where that's you know uh gonna be where
we're gonna get the type id from
but then we also have a couple other
things that we expect to find and treat
specially
right so we know that tag variant is a
thing that we're going to tweet
especially and we know that tag facing
direction is also a thing that we're
going to
treat especially and so those are going
to set
elements of the match vector uh
since we're you know playing around with
this here
um the the tag array in the han
in the asset uh in the game assets type
right
man i really need this to tell me
which one of these it is like that is
not helpful
right um you need to know which of these
is the thing
did i write that down
jay needs to
show which our
forward declares
i'll send an email this after the stream
um because that's the way mine used to
work but when we switched
over to like using the
the sort of merged one it doesn't have
that so it's like i have no idea which
of those is the forward declaration
in which of those is the actual type
declaration so i'll be jumping all day
and i never get there right um it's it's
like totally useless
so the uh
what we want to do here is say all right
we've got this tag array with the hha
tags in it right
so let's pull that out so we can
actually see it
um and reference it a little bit easier
right so we're looking at this
particular
tag index right and then we can switch
on the tag id
and we can use the value here uh to like
basically decrypt these tags
into something that we know how to work
with
so we know we want facing direction to
be pulled out like this
and we know we want variant to be pulled
out like this
and then everything else unless there's
some tags that we want to like
specifically avoid
so we're trying to like filter them out
or something but assuming that we
actually want to have something specific
go
on here what we would then do is say all
right
in that case now we want to take
any tag that's in here and add it to our
list of tags
so we would have a asset tag id
tags we know that this is only allowed
to have four
right and uh we know that we've got um
our tag count
which we'd start with here and so what
we do here is say
look uh we know that the tag count in
this case has to be
uh less than the tag size
in this particular case what we really
want to do is produce an error here
um and we want to produce an error on
the asset system
so what we probably want is not an
assertion we want like this
right like something like that um and i
don't know
to what extent we want to actually print
that
but you know we could do something like
this
right i
i don't know
yeah um so if we end up in a situation
like this
where we have the source file name and
all that stuff like you can see here
right and we've grabbed it uh then what
we probably want to do
is say like uh like invalid tag set
or something
right and then what we could do is since
we don't really want this function to be
doing something like printing an error
from the inside we can just say like
errors or you know hat errors
um or or uh
maybe we'll just call it result
in this case
uh and what we'll do is we'll say like
look in the case where
you know any of these things didn't
happen
so if the type id is zero uh we're going
to complain about that
if we can't get the right number of tags
we're going to complain about
that and then we'll just assume we
succeeded otherwise something like this
uh so assuming we can get this what
we'll do is we'll just say like okay
then for the tags we will take the tag
and we'll produce
the rounded value of that tag oh we
don't have to round it it's just
whatever the tag id
actually is and we'll throw away the
value
right when we're done uh we know how to
produce the tag hash and in fact now we
don't really need
that so we know how to produce the tag
hash because it's just
a get tag hash with the type id
of the asset and then the tags
right and since we don't want to have to
know we don't want to have to clear them
at the end we'll just clear them at the
beginning
to make it easier on ourselves so we
don't care so that adds to the hash
i believe uh properly we
want to change it to have a
boolean return type again just for error
reporting
um and we probably want to pro
to report those errors at export time
as well or import time i should say
uh so that seems relevant
uh as well so or on a second asset
tag id
get tag hash in this case may be defined
somewhere else
so i'm going to go ahead and move these
up
i don't think get variant count should
have be happening anymore so we should
probably get rid of that
as well
conflict
uh let's see we don't need any of this
anymore so let's fix that
so source file grid expert y we don't
need any of these
um
we probably want
asset index and file maybe well maybe we
don't i don't know we'll just leave it
like this
for now um so is get variant count
used anywhere um
because i don't think we would want that
yeah so so this we we recovered
uh we don't need to do that anymore so
so that should be fine um
so get variant count can go away
as well and things are looking
relatively clean here
um there's more we could do and probably
more we should do
but we're closing in on on this being
relatively sane
uh like i said we may want a
an out f here where we do like um
report on there being something wrong
with this asset
uh so you know something where we do
like
if not um
there we go and i think
that was also done properly here right
so if not
yeah so if we can't add it to the hash
for some reason
uh then we'll just say you know invalid
tag set
and so now we've reported the error on
import and
on load so in both places that could use
it
um we can tell the person that they
screwed up
when they define the tags in the tag
file right and the reason i'm doing it
that way instead of an assert is because
if somebody in a tag file just types the
wrong tags we want to just report that
so they can fix it we don't want to just
crash the program with an assert
dialogue or something
right
all right so uh we have to now kind of
step through this code
and figure out what's not working
um surprisingly that's actually
more working than i would have expected
uh
that's like quite a bit of working
actually so it looks like the only thing
that didn't really
quite load properly because even our
little sprites look like they're
important is the
uh cube maps uh
cube wrappings they're not cube maps in
the like lookup sense of the term cube
map but
so that's surprisingly close
and it looks like the only thing that we
weren't finding there
was the uh
in the so maybe in the gen code like
when we're generating rooms or whatever
we're like we're putting together
uh tag sets that don't like
work properly for some reason you know
what i mean
so in the hht like if we imagine trying
to find some of these things like we've
got like a cube
one of these like blocks right
so if you imagine what a wall would have
right it's wall
wood and then man-made was like over
here
right um now
i don't know what the point of that is
exactly uh
i guess i could kind of see why that is
the way it is
uh because you're like well it's a wall
versus a floor and then it's like
man-made or not and then it's made out
of this thing
but it seems like uh
it seems like man-made is kind of like
are we outdoors or not
it's more of a primal thing
it really should be like maybe up at the
top or something
um whereas like this part is like
more specific so i kind of almost feel
like these are kind of in the wrong
order a little bit
but even if we assume not right also the
wood
versus stone bit like seems like it
wants to be separate so
i do kind of feel like these are maybe a
little bit wrongly ordered
maybe right but that's
why it was failing so somehow all of our
code probably worked correctly
and now we just it's this the order
dependence of these
i guess these tags are just not very
good
so i don't really know how i want to
deal with them
um if that makes any sense but
yeah if you look here like
if you're outdoors it ends up being
grass
it's just over specified right
like i almost just don't care about the
man-made thing
it doesn't do anything like
it's just kind of dumb you know what i
mean
so i kind of just want it to not be
there because i'm not sure why you would
ever care
what it was um
i guess to just you know just to
distinguish between like
yeah i don't know i mean this is like a
wood floor wood wall you know
and maybe if you argue that you want to
know man-made or not
as to whether or not like a a wall of
wood
i mean we don't even call it a wall of
wood elsewhere
probably just because we were stupid but
like tree
is just called tree it's not a
non-man-made wood wall which is what a
tree is
right so i don't know
we should think about that harder at
some point
for right now i want to see what happens
if we just say
this is not constructive so we're
getting rid of these for
now um and we'll we'll think about this
a little harder later
and i think what we want to do is do
this the opposite of the way that we
were doing it
um in the sense that what we really want
is we want this code
to have the tags lined up based on the
way it's actually generating indoors
versus outdoors
you know wall versus floor and then
these tags should just correspond to
which part of this code you're using
right that's what i think should be
happening personally
so we'll take a look at that in a little
bit but
okay um so we have to kind of look at
assets a little bit here
which i'll be completely honest i don't
really remember much about how this
this stuff works it's been so long um
since we've looked at any of this stuff
uh in terms of like assets and and all
sorts of things like that
um so i don't really know anymore like
we've got like sort of asset inspection
stuff on here but
i don't think that i don't know if that
works if you
if the asset doesn't exist right it
probably gets knocked out
so we can't unfortunately look at assets
that didn't
actually like get matched
so um uh
what i think i want to do is step
through that code i don't know i don't
even know basic stuff anymore because we
haven't done this in so long
i don't know if i need to like ask it to
rebuild
or if it would automatically rebuild
because of
the fact that the uh
asset files have changed i think we
we do it manually so it may also be that
all i really have to do here
is do like a reload um you can see here
like reload
so what i might do is is try that
um because it may be that we just want
to do a reload
and a save and that's it because we
don't automatically update
i think we consciously decided not to do
that because we wanted to like be able
to do a reload
uh to refresh and then we wanted to save
only if we thought that it worked
properly right
so doing a reload of the hhts doesn't
seem to have done anything
right um so i you know we do have to
kind of step through and debug this and
figure out what is going on there right
because it doesn't look like
anything actually happened um and
you can see it incrementing the load
number and nothing actually occurs
so i do think that actually
you know i mean it did whatever updating
it was going to do
and we don't see any difference here so
i'm going to do a save
on that to save the hhts um
and it looks like yeah it looks like no
changes
i don't know if that means that it did
actually load
the hhts automatically when we ran the
game
i guess it did because we definitely
changed them
um so i don't know so so i guess we just
have a matching error there and so what
we need to do now is go
find out what's what's wrong right
okay so we know we're trying to match
like wall wood
for example right and what you see here
is that when we come
through through this thing and we say on
wall
you know add the wall add the wood
uh or you know or floor in this case
and and then uh wood or snown
right or grass
all of those tags look right and then
we're saying okay we want to add a piece
here
which is a cube piece and we want to do
a scenery asset
um and we want to do this tag this set
of tags from the tag builder
that we that we made here right
and so we expect that to to have just
worked because
it should have just built something that
matches like floor wood or something
and off we go our question is why
didn't that happen and
one question i have is
i guess i don't know about whether these
are set to scenery i assume they must be
because of block
you know so i'm assuming that block
automatically sets that
uh and so what i probably want to do
here
is just step through the match
probably and find out
why we're not matching any assets
so what i probably want to do for this
is the easiest place to start would be
in the entity
uh rendering code where we actually push
a cube on
um to look at what the tags were that
were actually
trying to be matched in the first place
and then maybe back that out
and go look at when we actually did the
matching
right and so uh
in this case
so you can see us pushing a cube on here
so we should be able to just say look
it's it's going to be
it's going to be having been this call
for the uh bitmap asset let's let's
start here and just see what the piece
even has
on it at all um and we'll go from there
for some reason i am not able to set a
breakpoint there
which doesn't make a lot of sense
um
what is the reasoning behind that
so for some reason this doesn't let me
set any break points
is that just a remedy problem
what's the deal there
i feel like uh george was here
wasn't he at some point
george you happen to know what's going
on there
i wonder what we're doing wrong this is
a debug build
right so it should have full access to
all the debug information but it
looks like no such luck
you know what i'm saying
now i wonder if this is
oh we need three one three all right we
can update
our remedy
i don't know if i have a later version
of visual studio but let's just see
let's make sure
i don't think i updated but let's just
make sure
about that um
okay so let me grab a remedy
from itch io
which always has like the worst user
interface for
getting stuff you already own um
let's grab remedy
and save it
too
okay
so i've grabbed a new version of remedy
and let us see let's find out if that is
our problem
uh i mean sure you can save
the session um so let's grab a three one
the three one four five nine seven
let's grab the latest latest action
and we'll go ahead and drop that in here
and we'll see if we can break point
so in uh i guess i don't
really need these anymore um so
back in the same code i'm just going to
try and set a breakpoint in exactly the
same place and if it works this time
then it does look like it was
updated vc debug information yep
that looks like what it was because that
set just fine
weird i guess they changed it huh is
that what happened
um
i should probably also uh
update my work computer with that
i haven't run into that i i tend to keep
things very old on my work computer like
i don't plug it into the internet i
don't update the software because stuff
usually works if you don't update it
when you update things break like that
right because you have like
visual studio decides to update
something like
new debug info and then all your tools
that used to work the old debug info
won't work anymore
and you're like thanks for that what did
you why did you do that
and usually the answer is no reason
other than weird internal organization
garbage
because there's never any new features
or anything like they don't actually
improve anything they just
change the debug format and make
everyone's lives difficult
anyway so uh let's see what happened
here so we're assuming this bitmap id is
zero
right because it won't have found
anything and so what we want to do now
is look and see
like are we asking for the right tags
before we start
investigating the asset system to see
like what's wrong
um we want to see if like the asset hash
itself
has something filled out sensibly so
here's a randomized variant value that's
what we would expect to see
um in here we've got a packed
hashtag right you can see it here
um and we'd like a way to be able to
decrypt that
if we can so let's just take a look um
at the get tag hash function and you can
see us packing
this stuff in here so if we look the
like asset category
is in the bottom eight bits of this
thing
so if we take a look at what's in the
bottom
eight bits of this thing it's like one
eight
hacks right it's
that um which i don't even know
what value that is it's 24 apparently
um and
uh if we that's not what i wanted
um so if we take a look at which of
these in the basic category we're
talking about
like zero one two three four five
six seven eight nine 10 11 12 13 14 15
16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24
it's exactly what we'd expect i suppose
i probably could have done this huh
can i in the remedy
so i guess i can't um
i'm not even sure what that's doing
that's a bit wonky so i was just gonna
see if it would tell me the name of this
thing
um if i cast something to it
but it doesn't look like it
uh that would be a nice feature to have
if there's a remedy feature request
um but it is correctly asked asking for
asset scenery
and then we've got these other ones so
like through from eight to so if we
shift down eight
i mean we know exactly what we're doing
here right we shift down eight
and then we mask off
um the 14 bits that are
there we should be able to you know
look at the other values as well so the
piece oops
peace hash
uh if we actually take a look at this
and we look at it more specifically so
we
shift it down by eight um
we're looking at just this portion now
it just so happens that this is a zero
value out here anyway
so it looks like ox12 is like the next
tag in the set um
so what would that be and i don't know
um is that plausible right
so like 0 1 2 3 4 5 6
7 8 9 10 11 12 13
14 15 16 17 18. so that's floor
right so these do seem to be i mean they
seem to be built correctly
right like it it's looks like it's using
the right hash
value for all intents and purposes right
um let's just double check the last one
so if we
shift it down 22 it's 19 so that would
be
[Music]
floor grass so floor grass
is a totally valid thing to expect to
see
would be this and
honestly though you know that one thing
that does
concern me a little bit about that so
suppose we
keep going here um
just uh look at it is you know
the grass part seems to be there
actually doesn't it
so floor grass is looking up properly
because hey look at that
uh there's often the area where the
lighting
is like out of bounds because you can't
see over here
at the moment but if i zoom over there
the debug camera
it looks like floor grass is kind of
there
potentially i i don't know for sure but
i mean it's not completely missing it's
not zeroed
um so that makes me a little bit nervous
because then it's like hmm okay so floor
grass works but floor wood does not
that's a bit strange
right um and that suggests almost that
the tags weren't actually updated or
something because
this one we didn't change i don't think
so the one we didn't change is looking
at properly the one we did change
isn't i don't want to call that
a problem yet but i mean so one thing
too
is like let's suppose we compile and
release mode real quick
and like hopped over there
yeah i mean that looks like it's there
right it's really weird
all right what's going on with that
that is some weird stuff
so actually no
that does not work because that's where
flora grass would actually be
these are actually places that got
filled in
that's in the like landfill section
thing
right apron the apron code
so in the apron code the apron code
aha that's the problem
these are blocks not scenery
okay lesson learned i forgot
how our own code works this happens all
the time
uh when you only program once a week on
something
um so actually this that may be most of
it i don't know
oops
so this right here where we're doing
acid scenery
um
this would have to be asset block
actually
and now it could find it because it was
looking for the wrong type of asset
um and we're still a little screwed you
can see like
there's some weird thing that happens as
soon as we start going like the lighting
dies uh somehow right so there's
something still
uh really weird happening there
um at the moment so i have no idea what
that problem is but some kind of weird
like feeding a nan
into the system kind of a thing right
furthermore our
hero sprite is gone so that's also wrong
uh so like bodies and heads
look like they're not being looked up
properly either
um but the glove is and the ground is
now
and so we only have a few only have a
few
issues going on here i don't know what's
going on that lighting
bug though that's like a weird something
must be getting fed in that's like
uh highly erroneous and and poisoning
the system
especially it's especially weird because
it only happens when we move
like the lighting is running as it
should
right now and then moving um
well i guess not moving just changing
facing direction
was it
okay now i'm super confused
what caused that because that was a
really bizarre bug
something caused that
all right so we've got some we still got
some weird bugs going on here
um which is to be expected when we
change this much stuff
but we gotta go find out what's
happening
so let's take a look at the tag files
uh i guess that's the hht files
for things like body hero it's orphan
hero
is what's in there and then it's got
like facing direction tags
on it but i think that's the only other
thing that it has on it right
so orphan hero with an asset type of
body
is what we would expect for um for
creating the player
right like we want to actually create a
player in the world
um so here's the function for add player
and you can see it
doing the piece asset thing it's calling
change hash to take like the orphan hero
hash and modify it
my guess is like the change hash
function probably just
doesn't work like we probably just like
threw that in there and it's broken
right um so
if we look and see how this works you
can see the basic category here
it's saying get tag hash by passing the
type
and then whatever the source piece
assets original hash was
um so that probably that code probably
isn't broken
um but this code
probably is so this right here right
um
it doesn't look particularly broken to
me
um
i i can't say i know
what would be wrong about that
so i mean you're just taking the
category and you're oring it in
to this other tags system
and you're you're knocking out
everything but the bottom
eight bits which is exactly what you
need to or in there
so you know that doesn't seem
particularly suspicious
does it i mean seems
like what you would expect so
hard to
hard to think about where that would be
going
[Music]
pear-shaped you know um
doesn't seem doesn't seem super
plausible
that that's broken so
it would be nice to know
it would be nice to know if those tags
were wrong or right
um there's a sort of separate thing here
that i'm
thinking about as well that's worth
noting
um so i'm going to point it out so
if we just said that the asset
basic category is just another
tag id you know what i'm saying
um then this whole thing would be a lot
more straightforward
it would just be the category would be
the first tag
and then off you would go i wanted to
bug this first but i think the next
thing i want to do
is just get rid of basic category
altogether and it's just another tag
so if you want to say that something's a
block you just put block as the first
tag
right and that could be automatically
added by the asset system
so we could just automatically include
that thing as the first tag always so
you don't have to do it
it's the same thing but the code on the
inside doesn't
think about basic categories as being
special
because they're not asset type is
special like is it a sound or a bitmap
that we actually have to know about
but basic category doesn't mean anything
like
it's just a texture one way or the other
we don't care
what the category is right so i do think
that
probably wants to get uh
replaced but that still
doesn't answer the question of why these
tags aren't being matched here
uh and so what i'd like to do is take a
look at why that's happening
so let's go ahead over to uh debug build
and just step through and see
like what is going on with the body head
hat uh all that stuff why is that not
working
like what's the problem
and uh i don't know so what is the
problem
if we
maybe i'll go into that add player
function
maybe this is the best way to do it um
so when we add the player we'll just
look at what the pieces what the
individual pieces are
that end up getting looked at so
you know if we look through here um
let's look at like the hero tags
so here's the hash value
and as expected like the bottom is zero
and then we've got ox26 and
oxa are probably the two
things um so let's let's just act but
you know
let's actually do these correctly
so there's the first tag and
there's the second tag so it's actually
not shifted up differently sorry
um so if we want to know
what ox 26 and ox 28
are uh they're 38 and 40.
so looking at uh the asset
tag id oops
uh 38 and 40 zero one two three
four five six seven eight nine ten
eleven twelve
thirteen seventeen eighteen nineteen
twenty twenty one two two
twenty eight twenty nine thirty three
one three two three three four three
six three seven thirty eight
and forty so we're producing
the correct tags for that
um so
20x26 and ox28 are the correct
you know hero tags um
when we go to body piece
let's just see if that hash gets
is then the same hash value
only with the bottom bits modified and
so you can see it is so it's just the oa
got inserted there which is exactly what
we would expect
and for ox uh oops o
x o a uh the only question is
is 10 right uh the
right asset type for for this
you know um and so let's see 0
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
10. so like it
seems to be asking for the correct piece
um so the only thing i can think of
is that somehow so unless something more
subtle is going wrong like the tags that
are built for this
thing like aren't working
uh the only thing other thing i could
think of
is like is the matching code borked
right
so when we do the load asset although if
it was how would the glove be working
right that's the only thing like if we
run this
what we see is that uh
we do have something where facing
direction is working
the glove right so if we change the
facing direction of the glove
you can see that it actually does pick a
facing direction for the glove
um at least it doesn't the downward
glove
doesn't pick the correct one but all the
rest appear to
um so it is picking a facing direction
for the glove
just not the hero
so what's going on there like let's look
for some clues
so if we were to look at the body data
file
this is it right and
so there is other stuff in here we don't
know
um you know we don't load those at all
at the moment um here's the glove data
file
right and they they line up in the sense
that these are the same
uh inputs for all intents and purposes
right
so the only question is like okay so our
body
and and hand is there something like
materially different happening
in in there right and there might be i
don't know
um oh
well
there there actually might be so
let's take a look at where asset body is
used
in the importer which is here
um what very well may be happening
is these and
yeah so it's the other things you can
see these things getting added
right the tag attack uh and stuff like
that
so actually probably what's happening
is this case one here so
zero is idle one is dodge left and right
uh three is move
hit attack one and two
uh but actually so in anything in case
zero
tag idle is being added that's probably
the
problem actually
right um
so let's just not do that
let's just not do that uh because if tag
idle's not there
then i think that would work uh because
tag idle is probably what's producing
the problem now we could
shove tag idle on there but i don't
think we want to do that
so for dynamic tags we would probably do
something slightly different than this
so we're probably going to want to fix
this actually
eventually but you know just not right
now
but that's probably the only issue
would be my guess is it's just there's
tags on there that we don't want
yep that's exactly what it was um
and so i don't really know what happens
with that
that load thing that occurs there it
looks like it's probably just because
things get reloaded because the tags
changed
and when you actually go and save them
you won't have that happen so my guess
is
this is just uh because of like tag
reloading or something right and once
all the tags have been straightened out
then you're good
that's my guess anyway okay so head is
probably the same problem
right uh so in here
it's probably the same thing this wants
no tag
to be added um
and off you go
yeah um so then i think we're all good
i think
it's really interesting
so now i'm just wondering like yeah so
if i go in here and do
reload save says no changes
so what is that what is that weirdness
it's like if i change the facing
direction there's some kind of weird
like load time bug there that we need to
fix
um with the lighting that i don't know
what is i have no idea what is actually
causing it but there's some kind of like
weird like
submission error like a texture that
doesn't get submitted properly or
something like that
right um
and i just don't know i don't know what
it is
um but we're almost there and as we
clean up more of this it should be
easier for us to find
uh those problems anyway let me take
another look
at uh some of the stuff so
facing direction wise let's take a look
at facing direction
uh in the generator real quick not in
base game
um so
[Music]
entity
world gen probably this
so when we add orphan here
and we're doing this stuff i i kind of
want
to make the our orphans fix fix our
orphans
you can see us adding orphan to this
uh right we're we're adding the tag
orphan
but we don't specify like which orphan
it is
um it's it's this i guess
is the problem which we're not using so
i feel like what we want to do here and
also
if you look at at this
when we're doing our entity
work we you can see here like these
things get added to the result tags
and i'm not sure that that
check this room to see if it meets other
criteria
so we add the orphan tag
we add the name tag and then we return
that result the gen entity right
and
i guess the only thing i'm kind of
confused about is is that so
is that what why wouldn't that work
it should shouldn't it should it
well actually no so
how does it know like is it where does
it add like body and head and stuff
right uh
so it calls the add orphan function
right
so where is that
so it it calls the add orphan function
when it wants to actually do this
it it uses the two things that gets
passed from base asset which should have
been right i think
um and it adds those pieces
in here so i feel like that
should probably work um at least in
theory
so that why why is this not working is
is the only thing i want to kind of
finish up on so
is this somehow wrong like
is it not orphan with the name tag uh
is that not working for some reason like
why is that not working
so i'm gonna break in that function just
because i i want to see like what it
actually produces for the tag set there
and then we'll go from there so in add
orphan
let's go ahead and run uh and we'll just
see
what what this is actually adding
because i have no idea
like what's in base asset for starters
right
what did that actually entail and in
fact we can even look at this a little
bit easier because we assume these
functions are working properly now
um so if we look at the thing that made
this piece hash
like where this was actually created you
can see that it's
calling um this like pending entity tags
bit so if i just look at pending entity
tags that should tell me like what this
was supposed to have in it right
so it's supposed to have orphan baby
and and that feels like it should work
right orphan baby and then nothing
afterward
um and so when it calls uh
when it smushes that down you know well
i mean we can double check but it should
have produced orphan baby as the two
um pieces here as well so
you know um and i and 26 ox26
is orphan and presumably 9c is baby
um
so it sure seems right so i don't know
why those aren't being found
uh so that's like a little weird because
in the hht
all of those should be there right so
like orphan baby
uh is right here there's the body
um and so we'd at least see the body and
the head should also be here as well
right there it is
just saw it so it's really kind of a
little confusing
i don't get it
i do not get it maybe we'll save this
for next weekend
maybe
yeah so i don't know why it's not
finding that um because
uh again we removed the idle
from from the body import so in theory
that shouldn't be there anymore
right um you know and maybe it still is
and maybe that's part of the problem i
don't know
um but let's save that for next time and
we'll kind of continue down this road
for now we'll do brief q a um
and we'll go from there
um so a question about
uh reading knr to learn c
and the question is do you think i
should be able to solve all the
exercises one by one or could i skip
them and continue with the text and get
back to them later
for example before chapter one there's
an exercise to remove comments from a c
program
and i'm having trouble to solve it at
this stage
um so i would say yeah the
there's two things to say about that one
would be
that in my experience exercises
in books should have been written
so that you should do them all because
practice is very important
but my recollection from most
programming books that i've read
is that the exercises are not
particularly well architected
to actually guarantee that you could
possibly solve them at that stage
and more importantly at the point where
you are
trying them it doesn't offer the right
kind of help
to like get you to be able to solve them
so i think what i would probably say is
try the exercises
but if one of them seems like way too
hard
then definitely skip it and try to come
back to it later
because i i don't think that
most programming books especially ones
that are that old
but even today they usually don't have
particularly well thought out exercises
so it's entirely possible that there's
an exercise in there that's like way too
difficult
for the level of programming that you
would be at if you'd read the book up to
that point that's
probably quite common
do you think that possibly optional
memory safety features are desirable to
have in a language or should it be the
programmer's job
i guess what i would say is
i don't really think
so i have two things to say about that
the first one
is that 99 of all memory safety features
that people talk about
only exist because the way that people
write code
is bad so the idea that you just malloc
tons of stuff and then like right around
or whatever is just a terrible way to
program and so
there's tons of like memory errors that
occur because the way that the programs
were written was bad
having a bunch of stuff in your language
to try to paper over that problem
isn't interesting to me and is kind of a
waste of time
so things like rust or whatever are kind
of just garbage in my opinion and that
don't think they have
any real future other than if people
continue to pursue
poor programming practices then maybe
languages like rust are interesting
because they try to help you
not be as bad at bad programming
that said there are actual things that
languages can do
that can make it much easier for you to
catch errors that you will have in
programs that are not written
exceedingly poorly
so just because lots of memory checking
stuff
only applies to very poor ideas about
programming in the first place
doesn't mean there aren't plenty of
memory errors
that aren't about bad programming that
we're about you know
actually trying to program something
properly but then you know it's just
hard
and usually what those boil down to is
indexing problems
and indexing problems in c are very
difficult
to check for because it requires you to
manually add assertions everywhere
and go through like help or functions to
like check to see that the indexing that
you're doing
is proper there are definitely features
languages could add to make those things
work better
and obviously some languages uh
already have the ability to do more uh
robust index checking
and they do that unfortunately by
requiring you to use certain types
that do that index checking for you
right
so one could imagine a better language
would be one that allows the user to
construct types
that get the same kind of compile time
checking
for indexing use that a built-in type
would have
in a language that forces you to use
their built-in types
to get the memory checking that you
wanted right
so there's definitely things languages
could do some languages are doing them
most aren't and most languages focus
on problems that you just wouldn't have
if you weren't using already bad ideas
in that language
right that's about all i could say
would you like to participate in our
regular competition for javascript and
typescript developers
prize fund 100
okay i'd just like to point out the fact
that like i don't know
of like anywhere maybe
maybe if you specifically went to a
country
who's that was whose currency was
economically depressed
maybe you could find no i still don't
think you could
i simply don't think it's possible to
find a game
engine developer who would ever think it
was worth
any to worth it to do anything for a
hundred dollars
game engine developers get paid
fantastically large amounts of money
to do what they do a hundred dollars is
absolutely absurd
like that's a ridiculous number
to throw out for a prize fund for game
engine developers
i i don't even know what to say not
trying to be snooty it's just like
come on man who what game engine
developers ever going to want to
participate
in a competition for a hundred dollars
it's nonsense
it's absolutely nonsense
it doesn't make any sense
do you think that using void star as
some blank data
is good okay sorry this is i can't quite
translate this sentence out
do you think that using void star as
blank data is good practice
for example if you have some generic
struct called item and then based on
what item type it is is void
star uh points to different destructed
okay i think i think
maybe i understand what you're saying
are you just saying do you think void
pointer like
do you think having a point a typeless
pointer
is useful um
not particularly often so
i do think occasionally you need
pointers that point to something where
you don't know what it is and then later
you turn it into something that you do
know what it is
um it's kind of a way to do things that
have
that have like some polymorphic uh or
pass-through
things to it so like for example in c
plus plus sometimes people will make an
inheritance hierarchy to do what you're
talking about
um i do think void star
is useful in certain circumstances but
i don't tend to use it that often so
it's
it's a relatively rare thing to do but
there's nothing wrong with it you just
have to make sure that
you actually want that exact behavior
i will oftentimes rather than that use
unions
so i'll put a discriminated union in
there
and the main reason for that is because
avoid star
so there's a difference between a void
star
and a discriminated union
in both cases someone needs to know the
type of the thing eventually or they
can't do anything with it
so in both cases you probably have an
enum that says like what is the thing
the reason i tend to like the union case
more than the void star case is because
it tends to be if you put all of your
stuff together in a union and then use
the
the enum to say which one of the things
you're actually storing
you know that you'll automatically get a
nice uniformly sized chunk that you can
work with in memory very easily
like void star is usually about i don't
want to ever
waste some memory here use for things
that i don't use
and that's why i didn't make a union
right but
most of the time i find that it's
better to make everything be a uniform
size even if there's some wastage
because then you can make your memory
allocation
and clearing and organization all work
with fixed known sizes and that's just
usually like
way more efficient and the little bit of
wastage that you tend to have in those
cases
is actually just fine because memory is
usually not what you care about you just
care about cash
right so typically it just really
doesn't matter the one other thing i'd
say
is that in the case where it does matter
so when i actually get to a point where
i do need to know this
that implies that it's a very high
throughput thing where the cache would
matter and in that case
void star is usually also not the right
decision because usually what you want
to do is have
segregated lists by type and then just
go straight over the list without having
to do any tests at all
right so typically that's why you don't
see me using the void star
thing and then change it into a real
type later at some later
that's why you don't see me do that very
often is because it's usually just
not the right answer to
any particular problem um
but that said once in a while it is so i
don't want to make it sound like you
never use it it's just
most of the time discriminated union or
separate
arrays of type by
type those are usually preferable
solutions to that solution
and by the way those two things are
usually preferable solutions to the
inheritance hierarchy solution as well
so tip like typically the most common
thing that people do which is inherent
hierarchies or something similar
is almost always wrong i'll just go out
and say it's always wrong
um it's never the right solution of the
problem either discriminated union
or separate lists of uh identical types
is usually the correct solution to
either of those two
and that maybe hopefully will give you
some
clarification there do game engines use
a common library to import assets from
say
maya and blender uh well i guess they
don't all use a common library but
they usually do license that from
somebody whether it's an open source
thing
um or like a commercial thing in fact i
did one of the main commercial ones that
is used today
which is this
uh so this is a you know
i guess over 5000 titles use this
apparently
um this is one that i wrote and
it does that so it it imports from like
max and maya and stuff like that
uh and tons and tons and tons of people
use that
there's at least some open source ones i
don't know like colada was one at one
time
um i honestly don't know
like i think autodesk now ships like a
film box one
uh
uh like this thing
it's from autodesk so it's almost
certainly horrible because every piece
of software they ever ship
is horrible um but like it's there
right so uh this is another example of
one that
people might use i don't know to what
extent people do
use it but it's there uh
and and i'm sure there are others i just
i don't know what they are
right um
watch your design chat with john which
is really cool are you moving into
designing the gameplay for handmade hero
uh no handbag hero like i mean we are
doing that now but handmade hero like i
i don't
really plan to do much in the way of
game design for it
it's it's not that kind of thing right
it's just was to make the engine which
is basically done so we're just going to
put some stuff in there so you can play
it
and then that's the end of it right um
but the reason i was asking john was
just because
of some star code galaxy stuff i was
doing and i was just curious
it was sort of it was sort of a separate
sort of spare time thing i was thinking
of
if i wanted to make a game with modding
interface or a lot of items how should i
go about it
in both cases union based polymorphism
that you just described doesn't seem the
best solution
um i mean
the the question you have to ask
yourself is in what way do you expect
this thing to be modded
right um
if you want things to be modded
then you have to ask
what level of modding is happening do
you expect people to be like
shipping dlls that do their own like
processing so you can really have very
flexible
uh changes to what's going on
or are you expecting people to do things
more like
provide pseudoscript sort of things that
expect the back end of the game engine
to do stuff like figure out how these
things are stored or whatever right
and in terms of how you adapt to that
with your code internally
uh i guess what i would say is i'd still
absolutely go the union route
that would that would absolutely be what
i would do um
and what i would do is i would just say
well
at startup time all of the mod
all of the mods are just queried for how
large
their stuff is and we just guarantee
blocks of that size
right um and i might
go so far as to also do the other way
because if i was
going to bother with that system i would
say well at that point
because the mod system people are just
adding all this stuff to it
i now know that i will probably have to
spend some time
doing work with the mods to support that
what i might do is switch
to go to the more efficient way anyway
and just say okay in that case
everything's its own array um and i
expect
the mod to basically it only operates on
its array of stuff
that's probably what i would do right
so so if i was doing modding i would
probably i would probably pre
pre-do like segregated arrays of uniform
types
right
do you remember reading a book about
wednesday about to begin uh yeah it was
pet sold was the first one i read
do you already have something on your
agenda after you finish handmade hero
well i mean i
already have like you know what three
separate projects i'd have to do
for my day job so i'm not sure what you
mean like have something on my gender
after finish hammer here handmade hero's
just something i do on the weekend
all right that looks like about it um so
i think we're more or less done with our
asset tag port which is great
and now it's just a question of like
finishing like the debugging and
and then maybe going through a little
bit of cleanup um
in just how we use the tags because now
that we kind of know what we're doing i
think we can sort of like
clean that stuff out right
um and and just kind of like say okay
now we're good
uh we we've got uh
we've got a coherent strategy this is
how tags work all the assets will just
be tagged this way and off we go
right um so that's about it uh
i'll be back here next weekend to
continue on that uh if you go to
handmadehero.org it's got all the stuff
it says what the schedule is obviously
and also if you want to follow along
with the source code at home you can
always pre-order the game and it comes
with the source code so you can download
it
day by day and follow along with me as i
code uh also we've got
uh the episode guide is going now you
can click this little full screen button
and if you want to look at past episodes
it's it's pretty handy right you can
look at stuff oh you know where does
casey do
like cmd programming or whatever um
and you can like you know say oh let's
let's see what he says about this or
whatever and it'll jump right there
um and you can you know watch like any
any
part of like an old part of handmade
hero really easily
right uh it also has other stuff on
there that's pretty good now
uh like for example there's if you go up
to this little window there's there's
other stuff it's got the uh
the uh handmade um
are they in the handmade chat well they
used they used to be here
the handmade there's the handmade con
stuff that was in here before
i don't know i thought it was in here
miblo where did it go i don't know where
it is
um so i don't know
where handmade
con stuff went uh
but it was on here and so i guess i'll
have to find out where it actually went
i don't do i don't maintain the guide
[Music]
miblo maintains the guide so i i don't
really remember like how
how to get those let me see are they
just on here is it that you can't
highlight them from the thing
yeah it does seem that way so there they
are right
here's all the handmade con stuff so
like if you want to go see like ron
gilbert's
interview right um so i don't know why
it's not there i'll have to ask miblo
you can see it kind of like does a weird
thing here where you can't i don't know
how you get back
uh so i'll have to ask him about that
but there's the two handmade con
sets too as well so check that out if
you haven't and you're
if you're interested in old video stuff
this is by far the best way to get at it
it's a lot better than trying to go
through it on youtube
directly yourself um using youtube links
only really good if you want to like
subscribe to be notified like if you if
you subscribe on here
it'll notify you like when the new
videos are posted
and that's useful but finding old
episodes on youtube their search
is crappy this is way better so if
you're looking for a particular old
episode this is definitely the place
to do it um all right
that's about it um
i have nothing else to say right now
uh so have a good weekend and i'll see
you next time
take it as everybody