start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade here are the show
recode a complete game live on stream we
we're doing a bunch of font stuff
yesterday and we pretty much did all the
stuff that I wanted to do yesterday but
we just as we just as we finished I was
like okay now there's this whole bunch
of the stuff I want to talk about but
let's wait till tomorrow because they
don't want to start it since it's the
stuff that we're gonna be doing tomorrow
so I want to talk about it so we got
stuff to talk about today that's fonts
and it has to do with what we did
yesterday so if you haven't watched
yesterday's dream you are at a huge huge
disadvantage just huge unrecoverable
it's just I'm sorry you know you're
going to watch the stream and it just
can be like I just don't get it but then
you're going to go back and watch
yesterday's dream and to come back to
the stream you can be like oh right
alright cool bro and that's gonna be
fine right and if you did say bro then
you probably also going to ask me like
if I lift and stuff I do not
unfortunately I'm sorry uh you know I I
don't lift I don't really have any
broker dentals I like going to see
Broadway musicals that I think
automatically disqualifies you as well
but you know to each his own anyway that
said let's get started today is day 1 69
so if you would like to follow along at
home and you pre-ordered the source or
you pre-order the game on here to org so
you want to use the source code zip
that's up there you want day 168 source
code so unzip that into a directory and
you will be right where I am so let's go
ahead and you know take a look take a
little look if you will a little peek at
what I was talking about when I said we
did the work yesterday so let me go
ahead and do a build here and get our
compilation directory set so if you take
a look at where we were you can see that
we've got some fonts up here and
actually you know what I think now might
be a good time to return the music off I
don't think we need any any music for
now
either we can we can probably just stop
that from happening and no one will
really mind I'm suspecting ok so if you
take a look at where we're at with font
situation you can kind of see that I
started adding some debug dump stuff up
here which is kind of the goal what we
were trying to do with foxes get debug
stuff happening and what I said was the
whole point of yesterday was to get some
debug fats some debug readout stuff
happening so that we could see what we
needed in terms of font information in
order to make fonts render properly and
what I hope that you can already sort of
see from what we've got here is there's
a number of things that we would like to
fix if we were just looking at this and
going we want to start getting this to
be a good font system what is the sort
of stuff that we would need to do to it
right and you can see a couple things
first of all all of our letters are the
same size right if you look in here
we're drawing everything at the same
scale and that's because the way our
renderer system works right now you
basically just tell it how high you want
something and it automatically scales it
to that size so obviously if we wanted
this to work properly and look like a
real font the first thing that we'd have
to go in and do is we'd have to make it
so that the the actual fonts themselves
are scaled proportional to how high they
actually were you know in terms of
pixels in the original source art right
now that's something we can probably do
without any more information because we
know what the pixel sizes of bitmaps and
stuff like that are so we wouldn't
necessarily need to know any additional
information we could probably just get
that out of the asset information
already right and so you know we could
do that we could totally do that so
let's take a look at how that might work
right that'd be the first thing that I
think we should start on the road to
better looking fonts right so we've got
our debug test line thing here write
text line and here it is drawing some
font stuff we added stuff during the Q&amp;A
as someone was asking about embedding
escape codes that did stuff like change
the color
us or change the size and you can see
that in here right so we did that you
know I don't know it's not really my jam
but if that's something that you like to
do we'll leave it in there for anyone
who wants to play with it it's all fine
so if we come in here and we take a look
at the output routine you can see the
problem right here is is car scale right
we're passing that and the way that
we've defined our renderer to work is
that you say how tall you want something
and that's how tall it makes it right
and that's pretty good for what we want
to do in our game because typically we
want to say oh I want to draw a tree I
want it to be this high and then it just
makes the tree that high and that's what
we want but with something like the
fonts they're kind of a little bit of a
special case where we want them
potentially to be proportional to the
size that they were because it's like
it's it's not really about the game ever
adjusting those sizes individually they
all need to be kind of consistent so if
we take a look at how push bitmap works
you can see in here that it does the
width / height thing so it's doing that
sort of alignment in the line percentage
all that stuff right and you can see
that that's you know that's what's
creating this problem for us so what we
would rather do is we'd rather have a
way that we can deal with that
information in a more you know in a more
specific pixely fashion when we need to
now if we look there's a question of can
we get that information before we load
it because remember one of the things
about push bitmap is it's not
necessarily going to always have the
bitmap that it's actually going to want
right like like right here for example
when we get the bitmap you can see that
sometimes the bitmap doesn't exist right
that's why our font like pages in as the
as the background asset loading occur is
right and stuff like this so the thing
to remember there is it you know the
bitmap might not actually be there so we
have a question of is the information we
actually need which is the original
pixel height of this thing is that even
available to us right or do we have to
wait till the actual thing is loaded so
that's one the first question asked and
I guess what I would say about that is
the asset itself right in our asset file
I guess that would be in hand
the file formats in the file format we
can actually look at what's stored in
the asset information you can see the
HHA pit map here inside that there is a
dim to right and that's part of the
table that's loaded at the beginning of
the game so even though the bitmap isn't
loaded we can get the actual dimensions
out of it so what we would like to do is
we would like to be able to get that
information out so that you know right
here we'd be able to do that information
so what we need is we need the bitmap
info and I believe we actually have a
way of doing that somewhere I don't even
remember but I feel like that sort of
thing actually existed I thought there
was a good fit mapinfo kind of thing
maybe that went by the wayside I don't
even remember we've written so much code
at this point and at only an hour of a
night sometimes I forget where we are
okay it looks like we did get sound info
but just not get bitmap info right so if
we just added to get bitmap info for
that's the exact same thing and we just
did HHA bitmap instead that would allow
people to get that information back at
no cost right it's just a really simple
array look up nothing expensive doesn't
actually have to load anything can just
go ahead and do its thing don't ask me
why these guys did not have returned
where it normally does it just doesn't I
guess have that anyway so if I came in
here and said I would like to see the
info for this bitmap please I'm going to
pass the assets so it knows how to look
it up obviously and then we've got oops
that's probably a bitmap ID obviously
there we go I'm going to pass the ID of
the pit map and so that I now will know
how big that thing will be because the
info has the dimension it so I can then
say okay I want you to do the character
scale right but now what I'm going to do
instead is say that the character stale
instead of being this font scale thing
right where we're scaling the flat by a
certain amount there I'm just going to
say it's going to be whatever the native
scale the font actually was just for
just for the rich for a moment right
well I guess you know what I could do it
this way just set that to one right so
now I'm just going to say however big
the font naturally was that's the scale
we're going to have and so what we'll do
is we'll
multiply that value times whatever the
height of the font naturally should have
been right so we go in here and we say
okay we've got that that dim now but
we're going to take the the why of that
dim and that will give us a way of
recovering the information potentially
so let's just see what that does course
our font and I will probably be huge I
don't remember what we rendered it out
yet gigantic right it's part of the
problem but you know what if what out
what are gonna do right well one thing
that we can do here right is now since
we have that big memb information i can
actually advance by the size of the
actual character as well so that might
help us a little bit it's not going to
be enough probably but it'll be
something so we can actually do
something where we do like that sort of
thing for now it's not what we're going
to want to do at the end of the day but
it would work right so oh and of course
I guess I have to do a little dim thing
here so it would have to do a Kerrigan
and I don't know what the default care
dim would be that's kind of again
another thing where we need to start
this is where we you start getting those
texts metrics but so I'm just going to
hack it in for a second and then we're
going to come through here and start
talking about what all these things
actually need to be so there's a the
carriage am right and you could record
it so then as we move forwards we can
actually make sure that that it gets its
added properly okay so there we go
getting a little bit better there but
still not probably what we want but
anyway so there's our font and as you
can see the font is really really huge
and so one thing that we probably want
to do here i'm just guessing at the
outset we would probably like to just
say we since this is a debug font we
don't want it to be quite so gigantic
although i guess we could also just for
now we could just live with that and set
like the line height or something up to
be big again these are just temporary
solutions just to sort of take things
one step at a time and so if we wanted
to do that you know when our at y
advances right we're doing this this one
point 2f x font scale thing that's not
nearly enough you know we would need
something
where we were closer to whatever the
actual size of the font was going to be
which I don't have any idea what that
actually is about point you get the idea
right point being we'd have to do
something ridiculous like this yeah wow
these are these are gigantic characters
I think I may have been overzealous
there when I did the asset Packer with
just how big these things are right okay
but you can start to see we're getting a
little closer right so now if we take a
look at the font you can see that now
characters are at least the right size
relative to each other right the capital
letters are taller than the lower case
letters which is what we would like to
do right now we also have a separate
problem here which is that the alignment
for this character for the characters is
in their Center because that's the
default thing that we do with our assets
right if you don't set the alignment and
so you can also see something else going
on here which is that all of the line
itself right is kind of arranged so that
everything is like centered you know
along a center line which is not at all
how you would line up fonts right so
that's another thing just beware but you
can kind of see it hopefully everyone
can notice what I'm talking about there
you can see how everything lines up up
along the center line based on however
tall the character is bitmap why's it
does that alignment along the center so
that's something now one thing that I'm
not sure about and I'm just looking at
it because that that makes very sense
that's what I would expect to see that
and that is what we see what I don't
super understand is why some of these
characters are as long as they are I
guess that's because we're adding in the
wrong way if i may just to elaborate on
this a little bit so what happens is we
draw a character and right now we're
centering the character you know the
characters drawn around its own Center
so what that means is we move a certain
distance let me draw this in the way but
I want to make sure people understand
what's going on here because it was an
interesting artifact and it took me a
second to think of what exactly was
happening so
want to make sure everyone kind of zon
the same page okay so we draw we have a
position and right now we're drawing
around the center of the font so if you
were to draw a large thing in here right
you would get that and then what will
happen is you would advance by the size
of it that's what I programmed it in to
do right so you take this amount and you
would go that far forward so you imagine
taking the width obviously you slide it
to where sort of the center line is
right you'd go that far forward and now
the next character you draw here well
the next character might be relatively
thin right let's say it's like a simple
little T that's very short right so it
looks like this right well now it's got
like a much smaller with right now
advances that much and the next guy here
is going to be much closer to this guy
than this dude is so so it's really not
the right amount to advance by at all
right because it's based on the width of
this character but half of that was
behind him right and so you're you're
looking at the total wrong amount of
advancement right so just I just want to
make sure you know we haven't done
anything for advancement yet that should
be correct so it's not surprising that
its rump I just want to make sure every
wonder stands how and why it's actually
wrong at the moment right okay so now
that we're drawing the font at its
natural size again it'd be pretty easy
when we go back there will probably want
to go ahead and make the font a lot
smaller for our actual whatever actual
debug font that we pick that we want to
use we want that Davos to be much
smaller than this because it's going to
be way too large for our purposes but
now that we see it you're looking at
there what I would say is we're at the
point where I think everything is
rendering properly so we want to start
talking about the text metrics like I
saying what will we actually need to get
this to look like a correct line of text
instead of all jumbled up like with the
wrong spacing like I said with the weird
like being centered about them on the
vertical and it's not to say that you
don't sometimes want to send her text on
the vertical you know sometimes that's
an effect you're actually going for it
but
most of the time right certainly when
you're drawing text on the screen you
want it centered in you want it like
vertically aligned in a different way
okay so let's talk about the stuff that
we're going to need and then let's go
see if we can put that into the font
file and actually use it right so let's
take a look at this so what are the
first things that we need to do the
first thing that I would say we need to
do is to start aligning the text
properly right we need to start getting
it vertically aligned properly and like
I was saying at the beginning when I
talked about fonts thoughts have a
natural concept called a baseline and
what a baseline is it's that's kind of
the line of twere the text is aligned to
it's the thing that sort of is the
constant horizontal line that runs
through a piece of text and the way that
it works is different letters have
different relationships to the line that
we all understand right and so if you
were to take a look at some example
letters like I've written here you can
see that we've got the baseline which is
right here the baseline is a very
constant meaningful vertical line to the
text where lowercase letters without
descenders as these are called sit on
the line they typically like just touch
it right like this sort of thing capital
letters almost never go below that
baseline unless it's a fancy font but
they usually rest on it right and then
lower case letters with descenders those
descenders typically come below the line
like I'm Jays and G's and wise and stuff
like that right so what we would like to
start doing is we'd like to start having
the notion of a baseline where we want
our text to appear and we would like to
be able to say that for any given
character we want to be able to place
that character such that it lines up
with the baseline so my argument would
be that we want the alignment of the
font itself right of the bitmaps to be
placed such that the alignment point in
Y is wherever the baseline would pass
through that font glyph in a normal
alignment situation seemed reasonable so
that's what I would like to start out by
doing so let's see how we might go about
getting that information right now we
know and which is the nice thing about
our asset system already we know that
our asset already stores an alignment
point right it has an alignment
percentage that's based on the size of
the pit map right so we already have the
ability you remember like remember this
a line percentage we already have the
ability to specify sort of where in the
bitmap we actually want that alignment
point to be and so we don't really need
to do any more work to support this
through the pipeline our bitmaps will
just render with that pivot point
properly no problem we just have to
actually set it to something reasonable
in our asset processor where's right now
we're just setting it to the middle and
that doesn't really help anybody so
let's take a look at that here we are
and when we set the bitmap stuff up here
I don't really remember exactly how this
goes let's take a look here load LIF pic
map there we are so there's our bitmap
dim here and I guess the problem right
is that we don't actually have in here
the align percentage set to anything at
all right we we're just letting it be
set to the standard the standard point
five point five right so what we'd like
to do is we'd like to be able to set
that a line percentage to something more
useful now loaded bitmap itself has what
in it exactly loaded bitmap nothing
really so the thing that we're getting
back from this I feel like what we want
to do here is actually pass that desk in
so that the load glyph bitmap thing
could actually write into the align
percentage if it 1 &amp; 2 seems like the
easiest thing to do to me so what I'd
like to do is go to load lifted map and
this right here should take one of these
guys which is a HH a load our bitmap
right that right I think that's what
that is dest hhhhhh a asset is what that
is sorry so yes if I go to test asset
builder and go to load cliff bitmap this
is going to be an HHH asset asset so and
then when we come in here we should be
able to set those alignment percentages
to something meaningful so how would we
do that right well I guess the easiest
thing probably for us to do is to just
recognize that when we were extracting
the fonts from windows like when we're
starting the fonts from Sean we may have
to do this slightly differently so we'd
have to do we'd have to maintain both
paths unfortunately that's just how
that's going to go but if we take a look
at how this works in here the font
itself windows will already I believe
have aligned it properly so that they'll
all be aligned roughly the same and so I
think if we get the text metrics here we
should know what pixel is actually
corresponding to the baseline and then
when we go extract things out we just
look at where that pixel is relative to
the rectangle that we're extracting we
should be able to remember that
information so if we take the text
metric here I'm going to go ahead and go
to look that up on msdn so we can see
what's in it I'm hoping that it tells us
what the baseline
is but I do not remember if it does it
does look like it does you can see that
we've got a lot of information here such
as height ascent and descent which
should be enough for us to get the
information that we need so you can see
here the height is the total size of the
characters together the ascent is the
units above the baseline and the descent
is the units below the baseline which
means that we're essentially getting
back information that looks like this
oops here is that height here is the
essent here is the descent right so all
we need to know to figure out where the
baseline is is we can either start from
the top and go down by the ascent and we
would be at the baseline or we can start
from the bottom and go up the descent
amount oops up the descent amount and
we'd get the baseline so it actually is
over specified I believe because as we
know height is a cent plus descent so
that basically means that if we just
follow either one of them we could get
to the baseline right I guess what I'm
saying is you really only need TM height
and TM baseline was all you'd really
need and the rest of this you could
figure out but that's not how they chose
to do it so whatever so anyway TM ascent
or tmd scent is probably what we want to
start looking at but let's figure out
how that's actually going to work so
we've got our text metric here we
probably want to leave that out as a
little guy like so you know what I just
realized we're going to have to do some
more work here these statics are really
not going to work if we start extracting
multiple fonts right
so what we need to do here is we need to
have something where pass you know the
font has to be part of the spec when we
call load with bitmap so that way we
could bundle those up not terribly hard
to do but anyway you get the idea so
that is definitely something that we can
address a little bit later on when we
start to do multiple fonts but it's
worth remembering so that we don't go
why isn't it working in well that's why
it's not so anyway if we have this text
metric we then know that we can access
the ascent of the descent so now when we
come down here what we want to figure
out is once we have this get text extent
point 32w thing that's going to tell us
that rectangle of extraction we go
through and we look at what part of it
is filled right and we end up with
essentially a bounding box right we
don't need to do apron because we
actually are doing the apron now right
there's the apron right there and so
what we need to know now is in this
bitmap right which is this high we just
need to know where exactly the that
alignment point is now it's actually
pretty tricky right because we looked at
it here and this this search through the
whole bitmap in the space of the min x
and the min Y and all that stuff right
we know what the baseline would be right
we know that the baseline is just going
to be you know because since this bitmap
I think we decided was what did we
decide what did we decide this bitmap
this bitmap is actually bottom up right
it's a bottom-up bitmap and so we could
have actually written this guy in a
forward copy unlike the Seans when
sean's were top-down bitmaps right so
what that means is in a bottom-up what
we know is that a bottom-up bitmap that
first row of pixels right the like y
equals 0 is actually going to be the
bottom most line and so to get up to the
baseline from the bottomless line that
would be the
the descent number would tell us how
many how many to go up from that bottom
right so when we get down here and it's
time to actually fill in I guess this
guy at the end here HHA asset when we
get down to the end and it becomes time
to fill in that asset oops like so
bitmap align percentage 05 percentage
one so I'm going to also just for the
for ease of use here i'm going to set
our align percentage x 20 so that the
align percentage so the alignment is the
left edge of the character at the moment
although there is something we could do
slightly differently there because
that's actually the apron that's
actually the line of the apron what I'm
actually do is set it one pixel in so
that it starts at the actual first
filled pixel which seems a little bit
better and of course so to do that I
want to go one pixel in and in order to
go one pixel in i need to divide by i
need to its normal eyes right switch
1021 it's our storing this percentage i
want to go one pixel in out of the
number of pixels that there are right
however however big the actual thing is
now i have to think about that for a
second
but that's okay I was trying to figure
out I just wanted to thank briefly about
whether it's actually that right if I
wanted to align with the last guy like
ha what is the actual alignment range
run to and I think what we want is to
say that one you know one would be the
end of it exactly so I think it's one
over the result with but sometimes those
off by one things there come tricky to
think about so anyway I want one pixel
in as the left alignment and now for the
Y alignment what I'd like to do is since
our bitmaps are from the bottom up right
what I want to do is say that however
high this guy ends up being I need to
you know it would be something what is
that called like Tex metrics or whatever
text metric whatever that descent is
right I could say like oh it's however
big the scent is over the height right
and that would you know tell me how far
up it is right but that's not quite
correct right that's not really going to
be right and the reason for that is
because we're doing an extraction here
so windows right made a bitmap and you
know maybe let's say here is here is TM
s descent rather right is is this that
value right it's how tall that is right
but the but the letter was like
lowercase a so what that means is that
the bitmap that we actually save out is
only that big and it starts right at the
base line so the value that we actually
would want to have for alignment is like
Mutt you know the aprons one pixel but
it would just be it would be like one
point 0 over the height right but that's
not where we're going to get we're going
to get whatever the ascent is like five
pixels or 15 pixels or high don't know
how many it is right we're getting at 15
over the height and that's not right at
all that's going to put it like up here
or something right or way up here and
that's no good so what we need to
recognize is that actually TM ascent is
in the space of the whole bitmap
that we did there the whole extraction
region not the part that we actually
found that had content in it so I think
the first thing that we want to do right
is we want to say okay what was min X
right like how far up did we have to go
before we actually hit something and we
want to subtract that away from that
dissent right we want to say like okay
we are starting at min x that's like our
origin effectively right so I want to go
one pixel in for the apron and then I
want to go however many pixels more the
descent would be over whatever them in X
is right because here's that min x line
is right where this is and so I only
want however much of the descent went
above that right I want to like rebase
it to here and I think that's a more
correct statement about where that
baseline should be ok so I'm going to
start off by running that so we really
rebuild our text assets and then I'm
going to see what we get at this point
okay so we're getting a little bit
better but we're not quite out of the
woods yet right i would say we're still
we're still quite a bit janky or there
than i would like and you can see i
don't really know exactly what is
happening there but you can kind of see
we're off by something for example like
our p is totally wrong and so some
things looking right like roughly
correct like the ck looks likely correct
there on the bottom the UI is almost
correct but it's a little bit off like
why is the you a little bit lower than
it should be and then some letters like
p are just totally wrong right there
just like totally wrong so I'm not quite
at the point yet where I'm interpreting
that data correctly but we're getting
closer like it looks a lot better than
it did it's just not there yet okay so
let's take a look
what can we do to try and improve upon
this so oh well for starters that's
supposed to be min Y so that's just a
typo uh hum run that again and see if
that's just a little bit better ok
anyway ok so we're that this is a little
bit more consistent that's a little bit
the MINIX middx was not a good idea
let's just be honest the ex was not
involved in that so I was happening so
what you can kind of see happening here
is I think we've got a little bit of a
top-down bottom-up kind of a situation
going whereas you can sort of see we're
aligning more to the top of things
rather than to the bottom of things
which is not what we would have actually
wanted we're getting much closer but
it's not right that's just not right so
we're kind of our extraction is a little
bit it's a little bit incorrect there
and we still have weird stuff with the P
as well so I think we're just not really
look understanding these values properly
that we're getting back and we probably
have to think a little bit harder about
exactly what is going on there and and
the flip and all that stuff doesn't help
another thing we could do here too is we
could think about not actually doing the
flip any more like like we're flipping
both things right which is not necessary
at all you know so like one way we could
make this I think quite a bit easier on
ourselves right is we could just say
like oh when we're doing all this stuff
why don't we just go the right side
round right why don't we just do it this
way right where we're actually stepping
through properly and then we don't need
any of this stuff right
oops right so this just pre steps by one
row and this you know this free steps by
max with right I feel like that might be
a little bit of senior a thing to do now
now everything isn't upside down all the
time and it might be a little bit easier
for us to think about so let's just be
bug that real quick just so we don't
have that kind of craziness oh oh my or
not uh let's see there destro is stepped
down one which is correct and then the
source rube it's me and watch as masters
I feel like that should have been a
pretty straightforward change don't you
think what did I mess up there oh I know
what the problem is it's because it's
actually max height minus one might have
been why mmm okay all right that's not
as straightforward as I thought it would
be straightforward to reverse this one
and not so straightforward to reverse
that one so let me think that through
for a second because the death row is
really legitimately pretty easy it's
just exactly what I said but this one
since it has to actually get down to the
the max the mac side of the thing right
because this is actually stepping
backwards that way as well it's starting
at max height and going back from up
from the bottom to find that stuff
alright so I'm going to play with this
just for a second bear with me it's just
something that I like to do I'm going to
see what happens if i go ahead and scan
from the top down so now we've got the
rectangle proper and then i'm going to
stand this guy from the top down as well
so hopefully that guy has the rectangle
properly and we'll see if that does
anything better than than before right
result height minus one minus one again
is just flipping the nature of that so
we just want that and this guy is just
going to pre step 2 I mean why right all
right all right I just want to see I
just want to see if that makes that a
little cleaner to look at their man it
is just hard to get any luck today oh oh
bitmap fiddle eNOS let's c 0 so this is
going through all these guys and we step
by the max with every time so that's
just looking through their right for for
the pixels which is what you would
expect this calculates exactly what I
would think that it does destro result
up memory and we start the source row at
the bits plus the men y which is the
earliest thing that we found right so
that should that should be relatively
reliable so I'm not sure actually I'm
not sure why that was grumpy right
because it should be it should be that
no matter which way these bits go right
it should be that we can just because
we're not scanning the whole bitmap man
you just can't
you just can't win with Windows
extraction so do you see what's
happening there yeah we kind of had it
we had to deal with this yesterday and I
guess there's no easy way to do that
scan the way that I wanted it to work I
wanted it to be able to be simplified
slightly and we could flip we could flip
it around but that's really not going to
help as much as I thought it's because
when we when we're up here we pre
restrict our region and that pre
restriction only works if we're going
bottom-up right there's no offset in
here we could build an offset into it
but then we have even more complexity so
yeah so now we're still in like Jack
tastic mode which is annoying but what
are you gonna do that's just life it's
fine we'll live with it not my favorite
thing though we'll live with it so all
right so our next question is what's
actually going on here why are we seeing
the sort of weird alignment behavior I
also i want to make sure but i'm pretty
sure that our render group doesn't do
anything weird like flip things around
it doesn't it treats the alignment the
same in both cases and that's what we
would have expected so that's totally
fine right so our alignment percentages
here for some reason we seem to be
getting a very odd sort of situation
happening with our descent here and so
I'm just going to see least what I
believe to be happening is what I drew
up here so what I believe to be
happening right is we're extracting
something out of the bottom of the
bitmap like so right and so what I
believe to be happening is here is our
min Y here is our max why right in what
I believe to be happening is the descent
value i believe is this
that is why what I what I tried to do is
subtract them to find out how far there
was to go there and that would then be
the alignment point for that particular
font live right but that looks obviously
not true and so what I'm wondering is
this is that a incorrect interpretation
either of the descent or of the actual
geometry of the extraction is my
conceptualization right of the geometry
of the extraction actually wrong and
that's one of the reasons I wanted to
take some of the complexity out of it
because then it would make it a little
simpler to debug but you know if you
can't then you can't so anyway if we
assume that that's the case I would like
some more information about that TM
descent what I might do is step in there
of course I also take a look in here and
just take a look at those or anything
that I'm missing about that it doesn't
seem like I should be missing that much
about it yeah the amount of leading
space inside the bound set by the TM
height member ascent Dora let's see the
amount of space though as between rows
outside the font it contains no marks
yeah that all seems reasonable overhang
me out of some synthesized fonts for
security felt care blah blah blah blah
blah don't care about any of this stuff
really I don't think so I feel like that
descent should have been that value
since it's not i'm a little unsure of
what actually means it could be that
it's negative i'm gonna step in here
because I want to just look I just want
to look at the value I want to see what
the value actually is so that I have
some kind of an understanding you know
of that so let's see here oh and you
know there's another thing that I'm not
sure about as well which is I don't
actually know like when we do get text
extent point 32 and in fact you know
what maybe let's just take a look at
that document
I don't actually know how that lines up
the font which is something that is kind
of important for us now right because we
need to know where things are ok so
let's see the Congress traitor takes his
account when dealing with ticks on Santa
calculated string width of what is about
the height tell me about the height
that's all you got that's it so it
doesn't tell it at all doesn't consider
new line or care to turn characters when
it computes the height of a text string
ok well I don't know say about that
let's see carissa different computer
dimension of the strings within
heightened logic and computer without
you considering a clipping blah blah
blah click the extreme it takes an
account today I txt file screaming
chicken or taste account all that's all
with this is all with this horizontal
the statement blah blah blah so yeah
like I guess what I'm saying what I'm
trying to verify is when this thing
prints things out I don't know if it
respects the baseline or not so I don't
know if there's maybe we could also see
if there's a way to get some metrics
about our individual character which
maybe is something we could do instead
of trying to do the lineup in case it
doesn't line those up properly so I
don't know so we could take a look at
that obviously get character placement
these things maybe one of these things
would tell us something that we care
about Carrick string such as a character
with scary positioning ordering the
string glyph rendering let's see here
max extent I don't know that we care
about this this doesn't seem it just
doesn't seem that useful extech out
again also not that useful I feel like
get text metrics should have been what
we wanted all right so I'm going to step
into it I'm just want to see a little
bit more carefully what's going on there
just so I can just so I can make sure
there's nothing redic
what's going on with it so here we go
into the asset builder and I'm going to
step into the lift app stuff and I just
want to get out what those what those
texts metrics values actually are okay
so there's the asset and the descent
there is the height itself right and so
these two these things are supposed to
add up and hey they do so that's at
least something I suppose so let's take
a look at an individual character we
don't really need that memory so much
anymore so I'm gonna expand this out
what I'd like to do is see I guess I
don't know exactly where we are in here
when we do kind of the code point so if
I do care code point right what i could
do is step into that the next time it's
going to extract one instead of letting
it do the extraction I could change the
code point I could just edit what that
was and so instead of 34 I could set it
equal to the lower case P which is the
value that was a little oops the lower
case P can you are you looking at that
I'm typing one and because visual studio
is so awful all the time it inserts to
and then it makes it an error God you
just want learn code all right anyway so
I'm going to set the code point to be
the P so like because I know that
character was doing some unusual things
so I just want to see what it's going to
do right so if I come in here I know
that this is the height the descent
stuff so I've got that information I
want to know what the min Y max why and
end result height are right i just want
to see what those turn out to be so it
says that the min Y is 41 it says that
the max y is 1 15 now what strikes me as
odd about that already is that that
doesn't really jive with this at all
in my mind because if the descent is 33
pixels then I would expect the P to go
basically to the bottom of this font and
it doesn't really which makes me think
that we're still other or that I'm still
thinking of this thing upside down or in
the wrong orientation or whatever you
know what I'm saying like I'm not
getting something about it I'm not I'm
it's like it's not sinking in right and
so the problem is the min Y and Max why
are basically are probably I'm think
those are those are probably flipped
right in our heads from where they
actually would be so the descent is the
correct thing that that says how to go
up from the bottom and that is the value
that we want but really it's not min why
that is that baseline right min why
doesn't actually correspond to this
position it corresponds to this position
flipped and max why is the other way is
the other way round right so what we
would actually want to know is where
would max why how would max why and and
the descent interrelate but the problem
is right max why is the flipped version
so what we need to know is like the
flipped version max why we need to know
what the what the expected height of
this thing was so what do we actually
have that value where is that value
that's in here right but unfortunately
those things get overwritten because
that's the actual value that I wanted to
know I want to know what these guys are
I suspect that basically those guys are
the 10 because there they are there in
size yeah that's fine so you can kind of
see 127 right that see why that looks a
lot more right to me if that ran right
up against that that's what I would
expect from the P so I think what we
actually want to do here is we want to
say okay whatever that original size was
max why runs up to that and TM descent
is it's like max why it's like this
right it's like sighs see why is that
length right max why is this length
right and then TM descent is somewhere
in here and so the actual value I
actually want right is something like
sighs see why right which is this amount
minus the TM descent right that puts me
at this actual location it's that value
relative to the max why right and I feel
like that will actually give me what I
what I wanted right so yeah so if i go
ahead and do that I need to preserve
these somehow like this and off we go
are so what I want to do is I want to
say all right let's let's try that let's
see if my thinking there is correct so
that's the bound wit I'm bound height
rather minus the descent and that's
going to be relative to that that that
is what's going to be relative to them
in Y so that I think is a little bit
better that that seems thought through a
little bit more carefully than before
don't know if it's correct or not but
that's at least a little bit better than
I I don't want to rerun the asset
processor but I did so now let's switch
back to handmade hero right and let's
see where we're at so that's
surprisingly that's a little bit odd I
feel like that should have changed
something we're pretty evenly aligned in
a lot of places with the top edge except
for that p again is still yeah that's
really weird I don't feel like that
changed very much for such a
significantly different thing to have
done oh I've got that going the wrong
way still there right so bound height
minus DM descent that's going to be the
location of it and min Y min wise not
the variable I said right
yeah so this is actually what I said
first of all but like I said it's going
and I think it's going in the wrong
sense as well so I even still have one
more further thought bug right which is
that what we want is we want a positive
value for our alignment right the
positive value is supposed to go upwards
right so when we subtract max why well
max y is going to be lower than these
things are so we really want this going
the other direction it's really the max
y minus these guys right is that is the
more correct version right so it's this
not the other way around said I was
tired today I wasn't kidding definitely
was a heavy it was a heavy brain day at
the office whatever that means all right
so let's see let's see if that makes a
little more sense there we go so that's
more what i expected to see and now you
can actually see that we're actually
lined up properly you can see us kind of
lining along the baselines we're
definitely getting a lot closer that
looks a lot more correct to me in terms
of what the font would actually have one
have wanted to appear as as doing right
now we still have i've got like about
seven minutes left i think we started it
at 5 10 so we'll save kerning for next
week but at the moment we can still
improve a little bit on this stuff here
so let's take just a quick second to
take a look at how we're advancing our
characters I'm just sort of set us up
for doing the kerning tomorrow right so
let's take a look at that inside
handmade hero where we're doing our
character advancing you can see we're
advancing by carriage am which is
whatever the the the height of the thing
was and that well that was just kind of
dumb actually now that I think about it
that's never what you want so what we
actually wanted to do was was just make
it that's the height of the character we
want to be based on the width of the
character and that should fix hopefully
that's just a stupid typo that should
fix our alignment and so there
can see actually now we're spacing out
the characters and more consistently
right as well but we're not kerning them
or anything so they're not going to be
looking good that way we could make it a
little bit better by just adding a
little bit of slop in there right like
you know separate characters by you know
two pixels or something like that
something like this right just to make
it a little easier on the eyes but you
know oops I don't mean to start the
fountain again but again what we really
want to do is kerning so we'll save that
for next week so now we've got text
aligning on the baseline that's good we
have got things kind of aligning more
properly left to right but we have to
fix that to make it a little bit better
and we'll do that next week and the
other thing that you have to do that you
can see immediately is we also still
have no idea about the spacing between
the lines that's why we're losing our
top line right it's gone because we
don't even know how far down and move to
like a line it with the top of the
screen we have no idea we don't know
anything about how to advance between
lines I just you know made up a value
there so those are the metrics that we
want to keep getting so next week as we
sort of push through and finish up the
font stuff that's what we'll be doing we
want to get those values out and use
them in some way that makes some sense
right I also feel like and I could be
wrong about this but I feel like we have
another problem here I'm just going to
point it out which is that the
extraction is not I don't think using
premultiplied alpha or something can you
see how the G has some little things on
there that are not they don't look right
to me and I suspect that that is because
we are not prepping this with
premultiplied alpha so what I wanted or
something I don't know or maybe we are
and we shouldn't be I don't know what's
going on exactly something weird is
happening there I think let's see here
oh yeah you know what it probably is
it's we're probably not and we're not
doing gamma either right we're not we're
not gaming this at all so we have this
stuff we're set we're not gaming the
Alpha so if you remember if you remember
we went through that whole gamma thing
because launched on made us do it you
can blame one for this
because I wasn't going to do it but he
was like you got to do gamma and I was
like fine so you remember we did this
stuff right we convert to linear and
then multiply by a and then convert back
right we did this whole thing that is
what we actually would want to do in
order to make sure that our alpha
blending is correct I believe because
otherwise what the it's going to be
unpacked and properly right so what we
want to do there is we want to probably
just follow this exact pattern right we
probably just want to do this right
exactly something like this we could
even sort of make this a little utility
function right if we wanted to and so we
could do texel here right and texel
would just be whatever that like this
gray value here when we convert it we
could just go ahead and divide that gray
value x 225 right that sort of thing and
then we could get rid of all of that
right and say that okay the texel is
just all gray like so although actually
that's not true I guess what we really
do is we'd set these two white set that
alpha value to gray we would do the srgb
the linear multiply the RGB and then we
retire it right that seems like I think
the correct thing to do
set that knots to be an r32 so let me
just see because I'm just when I noticed
little things like that I just like to
take a look at them and and see if we
haven't introduced a annoying thing oh
dear certainly made some kind of a typo
there because we got nothing back from
that what was the problem there I read
out the texel right oh it's srgb to d5
to linear one so these actually are
still 255 based values I guess is the
problem so we really just need that is
that correct these are supposed to be
255 255 something like that I don't
really remember how we did that but I
think it was something like that what am
I missing there do you guys know what
I'm missing you probably already see it
on the on the stream like I said such a
sleepy day today so I'm assuming that
people are faster than I am right now so
yeah that looks like it doesn't it
doesn't divide it out so it's just
taking the the 255 values right and
that's exactly what we would be doing
here right it would do srgb to linear to
do the conversion that would write it
out to test
which seems totally sane right right
that's a desk so what's what's the
problem there what what happened why did
you not oh I didn't rerun it that's all
so hey guess what it's fixed now right
you can see that we're not getting that
black fringe on there and so yeah you
know what are the one of the things
about getting graphics right if you
really want to get it right as you got
to kind of be ever vigilant about those
sorts of things because you know any
little thing causes an artifact for you
right so that's that's correct now and I
did a nice clean edge on that and
everybody's happy and everything looks
nice and fun so that's all good i'm
going to turn off our particle fountain
at this point someone was mentioning we
probably shouldn't be spewing nothings
everywhere because we're currently using
the window 32 extraction path not the
STD library extraction path so i feel
like that is a good point it's a good
point so maybe we'll go ahead and and
calm these particles down a little bit
just say save that for some other time
when particles are more on the menu and
with that i think it is a good time to
go to the Q and a so if you could please
send me your questions now put a cue
colon in front of them so that I can see
them and we will go from there
ronald dragon does sdb treat i provide
text metrics for this sort of thing will
you show how to get them from the stb
lib on stream yes actually that is is
not particularly difficult if you want
to use the library for that an SUV
truetype you can actually see there's a
get font v metrics thing that you can
use to get this information and it is
exactly the same information actually as
the information we were just using so
you can see that you get the SN number
the descent number and the line def
number the only difference is if I
remember correctly Sean does the descent
backwards like negative whereas windows
does it forward so it's positive so that
you can't just literally copy the value
but otherwise it's the same same thing
really be covering right-to-left text so
there really isn't a difference between
right-to-left text and left right X it's
just whether you subtract or add to the
advancer but you know I don't know that
I super care about handling
right-to-left text again the game is not
really about text so we're not doing
much in the way of text handling do you
have any proprietary dependencies I have
no idea what that means tactile dactyl
if you can clarify I could answer the
question what were the things you just
took off I'm assuming something for your
wrists oh yeah we're wrist braces can
you go over how you computed a line
percentage one again yes I can so here
is a line percentage one right and let's
go ahead and you know draw it out on
here
so you can see that what we have on the
whiteboard we have 1 plus quantity max y
minus the quantity the height minus the
descent / the bitmap height right so I
guess the way I should probably do this
is maybe 1 plus y max right minus the
height of the extraction region minus
the descent right / that height of the
whole of the of the bitmap of that was
the pout that we're saving I guess we
could say right the height of the bitmap
right so this is what we're writing out
and so let's take it piece by piece
right so HB is actually the thing that
we're storing right that's the height of
the thing that we're storing right so
that is you know if we take that
lowercase a basically the lower case a
is like they're right it fills the
entire thing except for a 1 pixel apron
right so it's like that and there's like
a 1 pixel like apron around the side so
it makes sense ok and HP is the height
the total height of the whole thing with
the one pixel apron so the actual height
of the character is like hb- too that's
actually the height of the a and in
pixels right so up here on the top what
do we have well we have the quantity the
height of the extraction region which is
some larger region right we have the
height of the extraction region minus
the descender right whatever the scent
metrics was and that what I was saying
is that's taking this and moving us up
to some line right
that makes sense that's what we're sort
of trying to do conceptually i'm not
going to draw that in quite yet because
we have more we're taking that amount
and we're subtracting it from the wimax
right so again this thing is the
difference right it's the difference
between where the descender was and
where the height of the whole thing was
right so H E and this is d now it's
worth noting that since these are in a
subtraction we could have phrased this
in a different way we could have phrased
this as plus D minus H right i mean we
could we could distribute this plus if
we wanted to i mean this this
subtraction right if we wanted to but
anyway so anyway right this quantity
here right is is the is the height of
the extraction area which is a wider
again a wider region so it's this thing
it's that height minus whatever the
descender height is which is some other
you know it's some some quantity that
just says this right so we're basically
talking about this amount right here
right the part from here down that's
what we're talking about right if that
makes sense we're then subtracting wimax
wimax is the height of the whole thing
right and the reason that I had to do it
in this extremely torture the wimax is
is the height of the you know I think I
probably drew this wrong now I think
about it that's why isn't actually the
light of the whole thing it's this thing
right it's this line over here
so I said that wrong it's not bite of
the whole thing it's the height of this
thing right here right so again so what
I'm trying to do there is say okay I
need to know if I was to start where I'm
actually going to extract my pixels from
where with that that where would that
descender line be in reference to this
guy how many pixels up from the start of
the extraction area would I have to go
to get there right so I had to do this
super tortured version because the thing
was bottom up so I couldn't just take a
sort of the I only have the descender
because the way that it gives me a text
metrics I only have that descent value
relative to the extraction region the
extraction region is what Windows is
telling me is where it plays the
character and it's telling me that it's
the sender was relative to that so I
have to compute it that way and then
once i compute it that way once i
figured out where that is then i could
subtract where i'm actually extracting
from and do you know where i'm actually
starting the actual values from and then
i can do it right because like i said
the extraction region being here the
port we're actually starting to copy the
pixels or where we're saving the bitmap
from comes in here once i have that
value right once i know how big that is
that's actually going to be the
alignment point right that's where I
want it to be but the alignment is
phrased as a percentage it phrases a
percentage of the total height of the
bitmap so what I need to do is I need to
say okay if I've got how many pixels I
go up right if I've got a pixel count
for going up what I want to do is take
that pixel count and divide it by the
total pixel count right to get the
percentage but the problem is we
introduce an additional one pixel wide
apron because that's how the fonts were
actually you know how we're specking a
bit messed to be stored so technically
the descender is actually one further
than it was before that's what this is
and the height is actually to greater
than it was before and that's what HP is
right so instead of p / h we actually
have one
us that that value whatever we want to
call that I'm point P here but whatever
you want to call the quantity they're
right this quantity we actually have one
plus that divided by the big height the
height of the whole bit map that has the
apron in it right so hopefully that's a
little bit more I know it's crazy but
that's just what we had to do
are you developing this engine with the
intent to use it beyond this game no it
is only designed to be used for this
game colon friend aren't we currently
using a fixed width font so advancing by
some fixed distance ascendant method
should improve letter spacing even
before discussing kerning in full Jenner
in full generality um not necessarily it
probably looks better if you do it this
way even on a fixed width font because
fix with fonts look like they have too
much space in them typically but yeah I
mean who knows what you want to do is
the kerning thing that we're going to do
next week so now that you have text
handled will there be a net hack mode
for handmade hero uh no tactile dactyl
proprietary dependencies anything that
you need to pay a license fee for to
develop our sell copies of the game ok
so you I guess you must be a new viewer
potentially then know like hameed heroes
written from scratch we wrote everything
literally everything the only thing that
we did not write is an optional
component that I showed how to use
because people wanted to see how to use
a library so sdb truetype is optional
but even it is completely free it's in
the public domain and you don't have to
use it in handmade hero you can actually
just not use it by setting this use
fonts from windows 21 so so yes we we
wrote everything from scratch there's no
components in it that we didn't write
let alone that we would have to pay for
I think that is it for questions that I
see that are related to the coding
off topic saved this for the end because
i forgot to mention in the beginning I
had a dream with you and Jeff in it you
guys were in my neighborhood on
Halloween trick-or-treating and going
door to door asking for candy at some
point I was trying to put on my costume
and it got stuck and Jeff was laughing
at me all right I don't know that that's
a question so there's nothing really for
me to answer although i would say that I
don't know that Jeff would laugh at you
he tends to be in person very helpful so
you would probably try to help you get
the costume on would be my guess
any other questions any other questions
we've got five minutes left but i can
always end early no Jo Jo I did forget a
question how did you guys get into my
dream I do not know I guess we just had
some kind of magic astral projection
spirit walking dream manifestation
happening and that's where he popped in
you know we popped in
CSX 3214 you could try answering the one
I just asked that's not a coding
question
itz cash why not use block-based bright
fonts for debugging and avoid the
windows font headache so you know I
wouldn't be opposed to that so I don't
want to say don't do that but I felt
like that wasn't a particularly
productive thing to do because I feel
like we'll probably want fonts in the
actual game and so why not just write in
actual font system and then we can have
all the fonts we want instead of just
writing one like kind of ugly
block-based thing I mean block-based fox
just don't look professional the only
time you really should be using those as
if your whole game is like a bitmap
pathetic and you're sure you're going
for that old-school thing but our game
does not have that aesthetic like it's
act it's like fairly painterly art and
so we're going to need regular font
support for the game so it just seemed
like you might as well do it once and
have it and then you use that for both
the debugging and for the regular you
know what do you use for version control
at work I use a program called see
mirror that I wrote although we were in
the process of transitioning away from
it I just haven't had a chance to
actually finish all the code for the new
one so we're still kind of a little
hybrid but that's the one that's still
in use at the moment
let's see who is John Galt oh man John
Galt is the fever dream of one very
messed up woman from the 1930s all right
looks like that's the end of the stream
proper so I'm going to go ahead and
close down that's it that is it oh the
game still running okay well didn't mean
do that that it's okay we didn't need
those electrons no one was using them so
we put them to use all right thank you
everyone for joining me for another
episode of handmade hero if you would
like to follow along at home you can
always pure to the game on handmade hero
org and it comes to the source code
which you can then play around with and
tweak and you know learn from and other
sorts of good stuff so if you want to do
that check out ham a hero or gets got
the pre order button on there you can go
nuts we also have a forum site you can
go to ask questions you can also check
out stuff there that's like ports to mac
and linux people been working on and
community and anti episode guides pretty
cool stuff like that we also have a
patreon page you want to support the
video series and handmade hero in
general and then we also have a tweet
bought the tweets the schedule at you if
you would like to know when the streams
gonna be live that's the thing to check
out so that's about it I hope everyone
will have a good weekend and I will see
you back here on Monday if you want to
know what the schedule is for next week
again check the tweet but i will be
posting it this weekend and yeah until
then have fun coding everyone and i will
see you guys on the internet take it
easy