hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show recode a complete game live on
stream before we get started today just
really briefly wanted to mention that
abner whom many of you may know he was
kind of the original organizer of
handmade Network which is the place
where a lot of projects like for coder
the editor reason stream remedy the
debugger we used on stream a lot of
those projects have a home at a place
called handmade Network and he was the
original organizer of that project he
worked with a couple people involved
drone and Andrew and there's a bunch of
people who made it happen but he's you
know Andrews I'm sorry Abner's kind of a
organization kind of guy and so he has
decided to run a conference and it's
gonna be in Seattle and it's
specifically for the sorts of folks who
like low-level programming like who
watch this stream and he has announced
the date
it's November 16th and again that's
that's in Seattle so if you are interest
you think you might be interested in
this there's obviously he hasn't really
posted much information about it so
you'll probably seeing some posts later
on about you know what's gonna be like
and you know who's gonna be talking if
there's talks or whatever you know I
don't know exactly how he's organizing
it but whatever he ends up putting
together for the program that hasn't
been announced yet but if this is your
kind of thing you might want to go ahead
and make a mental note to keep or go
into your calendar and mark November
16th as something to to leave open and
you can also go to this website that he
is set up handmade Seattle comm and you
can put your email address in here too
and click on that notify button to be a
part of the mailings which will say you
know for example when there is more
program information and talking about
sort of what the conference will entail
you can get mailed and and also when to
gonna say like you can't buy tickets to
it yet or anything like that either so
all that information is forthcoming and
if you're coming to the conference I
would highly recommend going handmade CL
comm make note of that date and put your
email address in here and then Abner
will send those notifications out and
you can take a look the conference in
more detail once he's posted the sort of
the need agree but yeah just want to
make everyone aware of that it's again
it's the cut it's a conference
specifically for the type of people who
like to do low level programming like to
care about performance like to care
about the quality of the code that they
write and if you're watching this show
that's probably you so if you're
interested in get together of that
nature this is this is something to
check out I will probably mention it
again on the stream once there's more
information but obviously not everyone
catches every stream so I thought I
would just bring it to your attention
now for those folks watching and again
just so you can keep your calendar free
if that's something you might like don't
plan any mid-november vacations just yet
stay tuned to abner stuff for a little
bit more information coming down the
pipe also again that's handmade Seattle
the old handmade con domain name I also
remapped here so that we will be keeping
an unofficial conference list so you can
see it's showed up there and so we will
try - generally speaking keep people
appraised of if there are conferences
for low level programming that people
let us know about we will try to keep
them listed here obviously we don't
expect there to be too many low level
programming it's not exactly the kind of
thing that most people care about these
days but for those who do we remap that
as well so if you do go to handmade
con-com or
or handmade batch Seattle dot was it
calm or door yeah yeah it'll calm yeah
or handmade Seattle calm you can get
that information and I think there's
also a little newsfeed here which has
like a little bit more information like
where the venue is sort of what the
layout looks like you can see it here so
I guess the the plan is gonna be to have
sort of booths for people doing
low-level software stuff just to give
demos and you know show what they've
been working on that kind of thing
and then I guess there's a set up for
doing presentations and that's sort of
stuff so again details will be
forthcoming once there's a more concrete
program for the conference but for now
just keep the keep the slot free if it's
something you're interested in and maybe
just poke your email address into that
into that mailing list so that you can
get the information as soon as it's
available and get notified for tickets
it's not a huge venue it's similar in
size to the first handmade con I think
so depending on what the depending on
what the demand is for tickets it that
one it could sell out I think if it sold
as many tickets as hand VidCon to sold
it would probably would probably be at
capacity or over capacity so so you
probably do want if it's something issue
you want to get on that early it could
possibly sell out I don't know cuz I
don't remember exactly what the capacity
was when Abner's talking about it but it
sounded like it was only about as much
as the first handmade con and him back
onto I think sold more than the capacity
of that so just keeping that in mind all
right
all that being said let's go ahead and
get started today we basically put the
structural sort of scaffolding in place
for doing sound we had already
implemented that on handmade hero and so
we have all the code that we need but
we've added the notion of tags files as
a way of listing all the stuff that we
want
into the game for shipping and it's a
way of marking it up with the
information that we want it to have and
so since we've done that I just want to
merge that wave processing code into the
standard path so that people can hot
load WAV file entries and have them
listed in the same sort of manifest that
everything else gets listed in for art
it just makes it nice and simple and
clean so you don't have to think about
how to produce multiple assets different
ways or that there's a big difference
between art assets and sound assets I'd
rather just have it be nice and uniform
and easy to understand especially since
this is an educational project and
people probably do want to put their own
art assets in eventually and stuff like
that to add things to the game or you
know anything like that so I feel like
it's worth money sometime in there just
making sure that all that stuff works
relatively well now if I go ahead and
open up the import layer and I open up
the wave layer which has the parse wave
function in it what I would like to do
here okay can we note midlow can we note
this part of the stream midlow are you
out there
can we note just what just happened
there was a green flash on the for coder
the green flash is something that we put
in specifically to show a render buffer
overflow so I want to be able to send
this to alpha so whatever that timestamp
was for the green flash I need to send
it to Alan because I that indicates that
the thing I was talking about on the for
coder Jam about render buffer overflow
did happen actually so that's good
so hopefully we can get that marked I
don't know what the stream time is right
now thanks me blue thank you very much
okay sorry about that that was just a
little for coder interruption there
anyway so what I want to do now is
basically take the if zero block out of
here so I want to go ahead and get rid
of this you know sort of racer that's
around here that was preventing this
code from being compiled what I want to
do is transition this code over from
what I was doing before to basically
doing things the way we need to do now
but we basically want to do exactly the
same thing as it was doing which is to
say we want it to read a WAV file or WAV
file parse the information in it and
give us back a basically the blocks of
sound samples that it uses and while
it's doing that we don't really ever
want to do an assertion this is file i/o
so if it fails what I'd rather do
because since this is in the actual game
proper now that we have a coherent way
of streaming errors out I would like to
issue errors on the stream and allow
those errors to be displayed to the
person who did the import so if they
know that something went horribly
horribly wrong
right so for example you know the
previous way this code was working in a
command-line utility because we didn't
really care if you didn't input a sound
at 48 K 16 bits per sample PCM it would
just assert right but we don't really
want to do that because an assert
effectively crashes our app you know for
all intents and persons it runs crimes
moving to a halt if somebody was running
the game what we would much rather have
it do is just say hey you know some of
those sound samples that you just tried
to import these ones here are the wrong
format you know you need to you need to
go reformat them right so we'd rather be
a little more user friendly there since
we now have the opportunity to display
error messages we already did that for
the other parts of the system and so all
of this stuff invalid channel count like
the same
per second format tag the whether not
the headers are right you know all that
stuff should now be handled as errors
that we expect to encounter sometimes
when someone gives us a bad file and
we'd like to just print out what the
problem was we don't have to be hyper
aggressive if someone feeds us truly
corrupted garbage and we crash I don't
mind this isn't supposed to be like a
secure system or anything like that
but we might as well take the basic
errors we expect to see turn them into
printout that an artist or a sound
designer would understand and go from
there right that's our that's our
primary goal for getting rid of those as
well all right so if we take a look what
happens when we come in to parse Wow if
we've got a stream set up here where we
can start reading from it the first
thing that we wanted to do will work
just fine which is we want to consume
one of these wave header structures and
then like I said really what we want to
do now is just get rid of these
assertions and turn them into something
that actually just looks to see what it
was that we got back and issues an error
in the case where we don't get what we
expect so assuming that the header looks
like it has the things in it that we
want we're gonna call that good and if
it doesn't we're gonna issue an error
now this is similar to what we did in
the PNG so you can see in the PNG right
that it's got like errors that that come
out here and that error when we do like
a particular call we pass an Airstream
to it so you can see what's going on in
here when this call gets made and you
get the stream file there what's gonna
happen is whenever we want to print out
info like if we're just trying to dump
information which is in case we're using
this as part of a command line utility
or something like that it goes to the
info but when we have an error when yes
thing that actually failed right okay
then what we want to do is use the dot
error stream right and that dot error
stream I don't actually know what comp
date is that just a renaming of I assume
that's what file is but renamed yeah you
can see here that it basically says hey
I'm gonna take that file error stream
and make a
I'm going to make it onto a memory I'm
gonna use that file Airstream as the
error output for it right
so anytime we're doing something with
this file bit here which is the same as
getting passed into our web parser we
should be able to say if we want to
output an error no no worries
all we have to do is just say like the
error stream that we were given as part
of this stream so when we're parsing
this stream if we see an error in the
stream we send it to this other stream
right it's sort of saying like when
you're parsing this stream errors for it
can go here just a convenience Abunda
knows two things together we can say
like error unable to parse wave header
right and again we don't really know
what that means
right we have no idea what's actually
going on there and it's okay like we
only need to understand the kinds of
wave files we expect to see so if
there's some other kind that someone's
trying to import it's not our problem
right we're not a sound editing package
we don't have to try and support all
kinds of crazy formats we can just look
at the basic ones that we want now the
same thing is going to happen here so
what we want to do instead again instead
of these assertions is we want to have a
notion here of like format okay
right and we want to basically have
something in here that's doing the check
and says whether the format's okay or
not right so when we encounter a wave
chunk format field what we want to do is
do like an if here oops
that was a bad taste there we go um so
we want to do is turn this check into
something that says look if all of these
things turn out to be true right like
that so if the format's PCM if the
samples per second is 48 K and the bits
per sample is 16 then this is the format
for sound that we expect we also check
the block alignment because we don't
actually support multiplying length we
could support more of those but you know
six of one half dozen or so anyway if we
need to we will but so assuming that the
format is what we expect we're good to
go so we can say like format okay equals
true we can say that the channel count
equals however many channels it said
that there were and so once we know that
format we're good to go if it's not the
case we can air out like we were before
but we can also print out for example
into the Airstream what the offending
settings are just so people know might
make it a little bit easier to see
what's going wrong so we can say into
the file Airstream you can just be like
its Airstream unsupported WAV format you
know percent u comma percent u comma
percent u common percent you kind of a
thing and maybe I'll label these so like
maybe something like this that's the
format here's the Hertz here's the bits
per sample and here's the alignment and
then I can just print these values out
and that way if we do encounter waves
that are set to something wrong this
would tell you what the setting actually
was right so that you would know that
you could at least eyeball it and say oh
it's supposed to be 4800 and you know
the thing reported 44 you know that kind
of thing so let's just go ahead and dump
those values out here so here they are
and samples per sec its per sample and
block the line and then we will you know
have an easier way to see that if we see
wave chunk ID data that's basically
telling us what we actually want to know
there the problem here is we're now at
the point where the Rif iteration part
of things comes in and we want some way
of using we probably want the equivalent
of the Rif iterator to access the data
in here and so I don't actually know
again exactly how we want to do that we
have to go look and see how we would
like the interface to go and whether it
should sort of be a part of the stream
API or not I think ideally I would like
it to be but you know we need to play
around with that so I'm gonna leave that
and just assume that we will mimic this
API one way or the other and I'm gonna
proceed down to the next part of the
code so in here we've got an assertion
where we've got channel count and sample
data and so what that is doing is saying
let's make sure that we got both this
and this right now maybe one thing we
could do is just say you know maybe we
can use that as good enough I was gonna
have that format okay in there but maybe
we can just use this and so we can do
here say look if both of these are okay
then we can go ahead and do the parsing
if they're not okay then we're back to
another one of these sort of air
conditions so I can say you know error
couldn't
I guess like unrecognized wave either
way out because basically if we you know
if we get here then the problem is we
can't actually know once we get to this
point we don't know like what kinds of
other wave chunks might be in wave files
right there's probably extended versions
of these things that don't use either
that maybe the format or the data or
both and they've got other chunks that
specify information that we just won't
understand and so when somebody gives us
one of those that doesn't have you know
everything that's the right exactly way
we want we're not gonna try and figure
out what's going on we're just gonna air
out and say look we don't understand
this wave file save it in a simpler
format use a different tool to convert
it or who knows what but we need
something more basic right but assuming
that we do get both the sample data and
the channel count then we can sort of go
from there if you look at what's going
on here you can see we're sort of
starting to set like result information
that result is one of these sound 16
things we can still basically do exactly
what we're doing here to set the channel
count
we just set it to exactly what it says
to figure out the sample count we have
to do a divide because it looks like we
don't ever the wave data block just
gives us a size it doesn't tell us how
many samples there are so it assumes
that we're gonna do a divide to figure
out how big the the data that's in there
is so that's what we have to do so when
we do this you can see here we've got a
channel count like one two thing I I
don't love that I feel like we should
just go ahead and support arbitrary
numbers of samples you know it's
channels because it's not particularly
hard for us to do that and so if you
look at what's going on here you can see
for whatever reason we kind of do
arbitrary garbage here where we are like
patting out the end of
thing two blocks of eight looks like I
think that's just in case we want to
load them sim D wise you know what I
mean
none of that is relevant to us I don't
think I don't think we actually care
about that and padding we definitely
don't care about either and the reason
that I say I don't think they care about
that is because our model for asset
loading now is pretty reasonable and
when we load in we could do the padding
on load right because we're gonna load
into a block of memory that's designed
to be handed to our mixer and so we
don't actually have to do padding into
the actual destination that seems like
it's totally unnecessary so any kind of
like padding like that just seems dumb
and I think we'll just skip that right
unless I can find some reason when I
actually go to do the block based
loading of these that makes it so that I
can't do what I just said I'm not super
inclined to pad the storage because
there's no reason to pad the storage of
the things we might as well just pad the
in-memory version right okay so if we
want to expand this part of the code to
be better about actually unpacking any
arbitrary number of channels then what
we want to do obviously when we get the
sample count and we do this operation
here what we want to do is save that
sample count right so at least we have
that now so this basically gives us a
way of setting all of the result stuff
and the only thing we haven't done yet
is is the samples part of things right
now I think probably the easiest way to
do this like I say is we want the code
that's calling us to be able to think
about these things in terms of just
straight-up samples that are D
interleaved by default I believe the way
the WAV format will work and you can see
us doing the D multiplex here actually
right
by default what happens I believe is
they come in like order of channels
first then sample so it's like if you
know if you had a stereo sound it would
be like sample for a Channel Zero sample
of channel one sample for Channel Zero
sample channel one right so they're
interleaved and all of the samples that
you would want for a given specific
sample each channel sample are all
packed together I don't you know we're
not gonna want that I don't think you
rarely do you want things organized that
way well you know I say that and as I'm
saying that I'm actually probably wrong
if you think about what's you know what
probably happens in the mixer is you you
would apply all of your operations to
one sample across all channels so you're
probably going to do something like load
an eight wide float register with all of
the samples for with all of the channel
samples for a particular sample index
apply like the volume multiply against
that and then continue
so in some sense keeping them
interleaved does seem to make a fair bit
of sense because you're going to want
them interleaved when you actually
process them later right I mean you see
what I'm saying they're the reason I'm
hesitant to really do that is because
most of the time you don't really do
samples that have a check you don't
really do sounds that have you know
eight channels or something as the sound
you know a 7.1 sort of thing where you
have like eight actual channels that
you're outputting to
some kind of a crazy sound setup I don't
think that usually actually has eight
sound samples because typically you have
two spatial eyes the sound first
so you're usually dealing more with a
Mont like a mono sample like a mono one
channel and then the spatialization
outputs what should be going to each of
the like surround sound things because
that's the only way you can have sounds
move around right so sometimes you have
particular sounds that have been
mastered to be played and they're gonna
they're not going to be moving or if
they are moving it's baked in how they
move like so they're just it's like a
fixed thing and that would want to be
interleaved in that way obviously
because I think that would be the most
efficient but just thinking it through
I'm like is that really the case that we
normally have because it's it kind of
feels like it's not right and so I
really just don't know what to make of
that I think so I think what we really
want to do is just have the sample so we
would load them in we would blow out
each you know we do a series of unpacks
to blow them out to at least four Y
possibly eight wide do the mix down on
the mono to put it to each of the
different channels and then go from
there right so again that just really
feels to me like not interleaved if we
were gonna know if we knew we were
always playing back 7.1 direct and we
didn't have to map an N Way map to the
different channels then sure but I just
I don't think that's realistic I I just
don't see us doing that so I'm thinking
again that this just should be D
interleaved and essentially when you
load a sound that's got multiple
channels in it they'll be treated as
multiple sounds more or less right on
the outside so you know like our sound
assets we may literally never allow a
multi-channel sound ass
ever it may be that we just have if we
want multiple channels for one of our
sounds like for example if the music
wants to have a left and a right channel
or something like this then what we
would do is have two sound assets one
with the left tag and one with the right
tag and you load them both and play them
at the same time and assign their
channel
you know accordingly I think that's more
what I want and again it's just sort of
guessing based on how I see these things
tend to go you know your mileage may
vary think it through and think about
what you're actually doing and you know
the answer should become clearer as you
go further down but that just feels like
the right thing to me because I think
most of our sounds are gonna be mono and
then they'll get sort of spatialized and
that just suggests that D interleave a
path that expects check per channel work
just makes a little bit more sense to me
in terms of how things will fall out
later down the line so once we get the
channel in sample counting here doing
that the interleave shouldn't be too big
of a deal we know exactly how big of a
sound we're gonna need we can use this
right here to do our push right and so
in a sense actually I guess this will
get done for us so really I can just do
this I can say look here it's the
channel count here's the sample count go
ahead and do that push for me this will
give me exactly what I want I think so
I can just say that arena that you gave
me to store the thing in go ahead and
make a block of memory in there with
this sample count this channel count you
can see that doing the layout there we
can make this a little bit more
understandable by doing this you know
it's the same exact equation but just
that way people can see that this is
it's - you know what's - maybe they'd
think that was like for stereo or
something right if they didn't think
about what was going with the channels
if I put that size of in 16 there at
least you know people maybe think oh
right that's that's the sample format so
that's where they're getting that from
it just makes that line a little bit
easier to read maybe for people coming
at the code first time I should I should
use our form so there's a s 16
so coming back here we've got the wave
chunk IDs stuff we're reading that stuff
out coming through here got both of
those if we you know assume we got both
of those then we can come through and
actually do our our reservation
here's we now got the memory so then all
that remains is we now have to kind of
do that D intra leaf we don't know how
many channels we have coming into this
so we have to make our loops actually
use a variable number of channels
because channel count could be set to
literally anything so what we want to do
is do a sample index here where we loop
through all the samples that we got like
so and then we're gonna come through and
loop over the channels like this and
then that should give us all we need to
do multiplex the you know 2d interleaf
those samples as they come you can see
here we were setting up some pointers I
don't really care about that right now
I'm gonna get rid of that and you can
see what we were using for that D
multiplexing or D interleaving planning
I want to talk about that right here so
what we were doing is saying oh okay
let's grab the sample out exactly like
this you can actually see how we were
doing it I I guess so what we did here
is we actually just D interleaved it in
place right you can see us doing that
here we would like load the source save
it and then do it like this I don't
really care about that we don't need to
be conscientious about the memory use
here so I'm not super inclined to
Swizzle it in place I don't really see
the point so I don't know that that just
seems like it's not particularly
necessary so what I think I'll do
instead is just have like a sample
pointer and so we'll just demultiplex it
into you know from a source into a
destination basically and we'll go from
there now what I
might do as well is I might make
essentially an internal call here on the
sound 16 that allows you to get out
where each channel starts right so I
kind of want something that's like get
channel samples right and this way you
can say for a given sound 16 that you
wanted to access and you tell me which
channel index you wanted right
first of all I'll search for you that
you're not asking for an out-of-bounds
one because that's just a straight-up
bug it shouldn't happen so we'll make
sure if you're asking for one that's
okay assuming that you are
we will then say okay whatever the
sample pointer was we're gonna give you
back the correct block of samples in
this overall block that's the one you
wanted so doing that's easy we know that
there are sample count samples per thing
so we just need to say look whatever the
channel index is times whatever the
sample count is is how far we would go
for every different one now remember we
don't have to multiply by the size of
this s 16 because this all of these
pointers are already s 16 so C will
silently do a little shift up by one in
there for us to account for the size of
the actual sample so I believe we should
be done with just that go this many
samples forward based on the channel
index you provided because it's already
in a 16 pointer it will move twice that
far in actual memory space that's what
we want so in here what we can do now is
just say alright for every one of these
channels we just say get channel samples
for this channel index and for each of
these we just would pass whatever the
result you know that that result is this
will give us back where we want to write
and so we can just say alright wherever
that block was right in whatever the
sample is that we're talking about here
so this sample data right I can start at
the beginning of it
like that and we know that this points
to the beginning of all of the samples
and we know they're interleaved so I
should be able to literally just do you
know that
so basically get one sample at a time
and spread it out to each channel as we
go so take channel zero sample put it in
there take channels one sample put it in
there right so we're just grabbing the
samples one at a time in order and
diffusing you know we're scattering them
out to each channels now unified block
of samples in sort of just a very simple
scatter operation taking an interleaved
source and putting it into D interleaved
destination we don't need this anymore
this was the old one right so that
should produce for us clean versions
where each channel has its own block of
contiguous samples ready to be accessed
by the external code for whatever it
wants to do now coming through here you
can see this was there was even it to do
here so maybe this is just I don't even
know if this code guess what we didn't
really even finish it
I'd only supported one channel I guess
you can see it cold setting the channel
count to one and so we're already better
than that now this was this padding and
stuff all this stuff I should just go
away we don't really want to do that and
in here where we do this else was just a
vestigial remains from the old one it's
actually that now right and this is the
finished routine so really it's pretty
great right loading a sound out of a WAV
file is is like you know here's the PNG
right here's all the PNG code we had to
write to load the images because of the
you know compression I guess that's in
there which is kind of janky it's not a
great compression format and for the lab
since we don't have any compression it's
really pretty straightforward if you
have a way to iterate riff
so that just leaves us with one more
task which is we have to have some way
of doing that that riff parsing so let's
go ahead and jump to the riff iterator
that we had already written and just
take a look at it here you can see it
I'm gonna grab this code and then we're
gonna decide what we want to do with it
so this is the code that we wrote for
the original asset importer obviously we
want more or less the same thing but we
need to think for a second about how we
want it to look so let's take a look at
that figure out what we want to do so if
we're talking about a stream
specifically and so if I go over to the
stream set of things here you can see
that the stream sort of expects to be
able to operate on top of a variably
filled chunk buffer right like it it
doesn't assume that everything is
contiguous so you have things like
grabbing bits out per and so on so you
know it looks to me like this is just
something where the original way we were
doing the riff Federation probably just
is better and so I'm gonna go ahead and
say let's keep the code the way that it
was it just looks structurally better I
don't think we want to support reading
WAV files out of this stream format
because we don't need to there's no
reason for us to chunk them we can load
the whole thing at once
so I think we want to just say forget it
like let's just make our own version
that does use that does use the the Rif
format reading and let's take a look at
what that would look like so if in here
I do a handmade riff just to put these
in so here's our refrigerator and that
way this can be used to read any old
riff thing we want and so we can just
say look there's the iterator it's just
a pair of
wieners it expects a contiguous thing to
parse and then I'll pull this stuff out
here and look and even do a little sort
of header version where we just show how
you might do this I don't remember what
all the things are that we actually call
here but I think we actually call all of
these and I am I wrong about that I
think I think all of these are actually
called so if we just kind of convert
this to like our modern way that we were
doing things leave it like this think
we're in good shape there we go
and just you know here's a little riff
reader with a little API for it's all
nice and bundled up for you and should
be pretty easy to use now okay that's
interesting so for some reason we I
guess we were using this stuff here
because the wave chunk actually was the
was all we would ever need but we should
probably not do it quite that way
we should probably actually have a thing
here where we use a specific chunk
header right something like something
like that is it let's wave chunk right
so it's actually this this is the one
we're talking about although they are
the same right something like this so
here we kind of say look there's a
[Music]
there's a riff chunk header and that way
we won't require there to have been a
wave chunk defined in any of these kind
of surf
circumstances right so I can just do
that because these are just hard-coded
to read wave I mean it would have it
would have worked for any other thing as
well but we might as well just clean
that up a little bit
right so that seems good and if I go
ahead and just clean up the rest of this
and make this good to go I think we we
can just start using that now there's a
couple other things we want to go look
at real quick but we'll get to those in
a second this all looks fine let me see
here I think we want to make might wanna
make a little way a cleaner way of
saying that you want to read the initial
header that's sort of a separate part so
we can take a look at that in a second
here let me just get these two calls in
there and there's our riff reader
that'll looks pretty good and again that
allows you to navigate through the whole
riff file pretty easily so I think the
only weird part is that in the wave
reader you can see right here we say
like we want to get the header and
there's that wave header so I I'm kind
of wondering just trying to think this
through how wants to work I wonder if
this is generic like I kind of feel like
this might just generally be a riff
header like other riff things would have
this in it
and if that's the case it shouldn't be
called wave headers we called riff
header
similarly this wave chunk doesn't really
need to be here either
in fact I guess I don't know that anyone
even use that yeah so so really this
doesn't even need to be there and I'm
and I'm thinking that maybe this can
just be riff header right and then the
first call you can have is get the riff
header out of this thing
just what I'm thinking I'm gonna take a
quick gander at the docks assuming if
there are any and see if that's true
because I don't actually know so let's
see I mean I probably did know at one
point but I've longed for
so where is the definition of the header
of the thing let's see
so are these docked anywhere format
[Music]
isn't there something that just says
what the header would be
all right let's see here
whoa this is actually the Library of
Congress the Library of Congress
actually has an information about the
Rif okay that's pretty cool anyway so
I'm just want to see if there's a
definition of header that that suggests
that across multiple RIF files that
that's the same header file generally
speaking because I don't know if that's
true or not so I'm kind of interested to
know how that works I know that the
chunks are generic but I just don't know
about the headers being generic or not
that I really just don't know I would
assume that they are but I just kind of
wanted to I was hoping that I could get
some kind of a more specific definition
that said that that was true this is
probably what I want compound file
structure so maybe I assume maybe 2:18
maybe not
let's take a look I can't actually tell
well no that's not really what I want
yeah I just want something that says
what starts at the top of the file
that's like all I really wanted but
doesn't look like that's forthcoming
unfortunately come on people
I'm just looking in the wrong place I
mean I know it's not that this isn't
defined it's got to be like it's got to
say what the file starts with if it
starts I mean you would think that they
would have something that just says
here's what it is right these
[Music]
RIF wave so it's like they do have a
definition so the fact that they sort of
have RIF wave in it suggests that it is
a standard chunk type right
so that rift parentheses I think because
I see it everywhere I can just assume
that the header is the same on all of
these and it's just the four CC and it
should be the same so I'm rather than
continuing to sort of pour over those
docks to try and find the official
confirmation I'm gonna say that this is
actually also generic right so I think I
should be able to do something like this
where I just say all right these are
actual file specific things this like
WAV format and these enums but this is
not and also you know this riff code
thing should probably go in here right
that's how you would create that and
this we also would want for for this we
can probably make that exist outside so
we could say that I don't actually know
if we want to do that exactly but
something like that right I don't know
so assuming that we have something like
this we could potentially use us to read
any kind of riff file now so that's all
I really wanted to get to in terms of
how the parsing starts on one of these
so this is the part where we don't
really have anything in specific you can
see that it starts the parse chunk at
stuff here where it skips over the
header so what I'd rather do than that I
think is I would rather have a call that
you know get rid of this and do
something more like up here see how
would I do this I do something like this
that up here let's go ahead and loop
over an iterator like so I'm gonna get
the next chunk down here so it's a while
loop now and the iterator will just flow
through here so we'll do something like
you know iterate riff like this and
rather than ever calling parse chunk at
we will just have this provide us with
the buffer that's the contents we'll
pass that in and when we do this
iteration we will have a thing that
allows us to get back that header so
we'll assume we have a RIF header like
this and we'll say what are we saying
here for it get next chunk get header
chunk something like that so maybe this
how are we doing okay so we're just
doing it this way
this makes sense that seems a little bit
better to me and now this would work for
any rift file even though we're not
really doing anything differently it's
just the fact that we kind of unlatch
with how we'd parse any RIF file which I
just think is a better way to go in case
we ever wanted to use this code for
anything else it's just you know there's
no reason not to just do a little bit of
cleanup there so it's not dependent on
wave for no real reason so I think we
can do it this way where we just say
like iterate this riff get us the header
chunk out of it which is you know we
know that's gonna be the first thing in
the file I then go ahead and we can
cross the rest of it and go to the next
chunk you know here's the we can't even
do this if we want because we don't
really need to do it we're not gonna
actually if we don't actually recognize
what this is this right here would be
that and off we would go so I think that
should do it
and then the rest of these calls are
exactly the same as they were that's
really it I don't know about this guy
this seems maybe not as good because if
we do do a get chunk data that's not
actually guarantee guarantee of the size
is correct so we may want to actually
have a more specific look we could
actually have this take what it's trying
to look for and then validate it I don't
know not sure how I feel about it one
way or the other I'm gonna go ahead and
pass errors as a separate stream now so
we can get rid of this and then we can
go through all of this and have that
output to the air stream and that should
be good
I need these two
calls to actually exist now so I need a
way to iterate riff over a buffer and
then I need a way to get a header chunk
from one of these iterators so looking
at how we did the iterator I guess the
size part on so I'm guessing maybe this
API wouldn't quite work because the next
chunk part of things wouldn't actually
work it has to be on chunk header for
that to occur so I think maybe what we
want to do is change this a little bit
and say that this should look more like
this right so this would move us to the
first chunk automatically and because
that's the only thing that we actually
can do there's no way for us to do
anything else really
so in here it would be more like this
right and then this code just looks like
that and off we go so I think I'll do it
that way that just seems a little bit
better we'll leave it like that for now
and if I see if it turns out that that's
really bad and everything is horrible
then we'll you know we'll figure out a
way around it so assuming that we look
it looks like that then really what
we're gonna do here is we're gonna call
parse chunk at right off the bat right
so what we want to do is say okay
assuming you know that the buffer is
large enough we'll do something useful
here otherwise we won't
so we'll sort of have a case where we
would just clear whatever was passed
into us if the buffer isn't big enough
so if I go ahead and jump to our buffer
struct that's not what I wanted there it
is
so we have countin data here so I'm just
gonna say look if the count is greater
than or equal to the size that I expect
for a RIF header then we're in business
if it's not there's nothing I can do so
assuming that it's all good then what
I'll do is I'll just say great let's
read the header out of here and then
let's actually parse the chunk that's
one ahead so here on RIF header this is
valid it's probably important for us to
do as well
well okay we'll get to there so anyway
this RIF header the buffer data that
we're actually looking at here we can
just say let's interpret that as a
header structure put it in here give it
back to the person who's looking at it
later and we'll assume that they will
validate it however they want to
validate it after that's done assuming
that it actually worked what we'll do
there is we'll take an iterator and
we'll initialize that to something that
has the correct structure for this so I
will return an iterator that comes back
from this parse trunk at call right so
now what we want to do and I can look at
the original one we did here you can see
how we were doing that parse chunk that
we want that to essentially occur look
right here right so you can see what we
were doing we're saying alright so
wherever the header actually was we want
to go one pass that and then we also
have the header size field minus four
for the advancement that's saying how
much header day there is I guess let me
look and see so this size field
wait so could we actually have used it
as if it were one of these maybe we
could have
maybe I was wrong about that because it
does actually have a science field in it
so I wonder if this advancement code is
actually the same
it looks like it's not because it looks
like you have to account for the fact
that the file type ID was actually known
to be there because you see that - for
right oh wait no but that's fine because
that would just be the size of the chunk
header so it feels like you could just
call next chunk so I think maybe that
was premature because these are actually
the same right this is actually the same
here right one of these is in there so I
might just do that
maybe I maybe I maybe I spoke too soon
so maybe and we'll see if this is
actually true but maybe if you call
iterate riff all you really have to then
do is is tell it to parse the chunk at
that location and it can just advance as
it normally would because I think this
is what it would produce anyway I don't
see a lot of reason why that would fail
you're just advancing by the size which
is what you would expect to do anyway
although the stopped winner
you know the stop pointer would be the
same right because it's just the end of
the file I'm really I'm torn I don't
really know how I want to approach that
um I'm gonna I'm gonna keep it separate
I'm gonna keep it separate
we'll keep it doing the way that we were
doing it and we'll go from there
all right so what I want to do here is
say okay the buffer data fields that
we're talking about where the data
actually lives here what we want to do
is start after the RIF header right and
then in here we this is exactly the same
thing so we're actually just passing the
exact same thing but we want to take
that header size and and say that's how
much of the file we're willing to read
and then the minus four I'm assuming is
getting rid of the file type ID which is
part of the contents because these block
sizes I guess are inclusive right they
include their own data as well as all
the sub data and so this is just saying
here's the range right we're gonna go
from here to to there I might introduce
a pointer just for that just so it's
clear that these are exactly the same
like so and so it's just data start and
data start plus header size minus four
and I think that would do it I'm gonna
see about how that plays out and if
there's anything that I don't like there
we need to include that obviously inside
handmade CBP when we're actually
including like things and webs and all
that nonsense we need to include our
reader and so in the H file and in the
CPP file where we were previously
including file info stuff
think we're good so let's see here
what's going on
missing types best of fire what did I
not have we have riff iterator as a type
don't we yeah it's right there what's
the problem did I not save the file or
some things and made that H oh all right
so let's move along here what have we
got so the wave fmt stuff what's the
problem why are you complaining
the rift codes here how is that not
defined
oh yeah it isn't defined that's actually
true yep I agree with that first chunk
at does not take one premiere well we
fixed that um let's see previous local
iterate riff next chunk that's true
don't didn't want that that was just a
bug and see what else we got
wave format undeclared identifier okay
so did I not to find that so it it's is
here
Oh eyes right I made these lower case
because I didn't like the fact that they
were capitalized that looks like the
only place we used it though so we
should be okay
static function sound a sixteen parts
valve so we changed the format of that
so we got to go ahead and change the
forward declaration in the call so
instead of what we were doing for what
we need to do that and so we should get
an error where that was called here it
is so if you take a look at the content
stream that's being made here we
actually don't need that now we're gonna
pass these two things directly and that
to do turns out to be true right we want
to pass
the buffer so the answer to the to do
was yes we should so that finishes up
the the web parsing and that's great
and so now we can debug that code and
make sure we can actually parse wow
that's just fine what won't actually
happen is our asset won't be imported
the reason is because process audio
import is now what we have to actually
implement right so assuming that we got
our sound samples we would get we would
come in here and we would end up in a
situation where we actually didn't you
know we just feel like alright you told
me in poor this thing but I don't know
how to do that right so that part right
here we just have to figure out a way to
update the HHA file with that new
information and that's something again
that we we've already done so it's not
like we really have a whole lot of work
to do here what you can see is inside
the asset we now have like data offset
data size first tag when passed last tag
type you know that stuff if we just set
up that information exactly the way we
were setting it up for everything else
we end up down here in the the HHA sound
part of things that has the sample count
and the channel count and the chain
information which is if we want to break
it up into pieces and what you can see
is the data that it wants is exactly the
data we provided so we should be able to
write that out pretty much verbatim
because this is all exactly what we want
so the only thing we really need to do
here is the HHA sound chain part of
things I don't actually quite remember
how this was supposed to work but I
think what we want to do is we set HHA
sound chain advanced and then I think
what it does is it just adds one to the
asset number so basically we just put
these assets like in a row into the file
and that allows it to do streaming music
you know for things that we don't want
to load the whole thing in at once if I
just quickly do a search because I'm
just I just want to see where the HHA
sound chain
stuff is at so HHH sound chain advance
inside the actual handmade like this
part here right I just want to verify us
what happens you can see it happening
it's just taking that asset ID and
adding one so what we can do inside the
import asset you know path here is we
can look at the sample count and say how
often do we want to hit the disk for
this thing right alternatively we can
also look at the channel count stuff but
again well I think I want to do is just
break them up into channels so I think
what I want this this to look like
eventually should be something like this
right i channel index equals zero
channel index is less than sound channel
counts plus plus channel index each of
these should be its own asset export it
should use a tag in the file format
that's about which channel it is so for
example in here where we've got you know
all these different tags to identify
what's going on in our data I think what
we want here is channel index right so
that way sounds can just say this is the
the channel index that I'm talking about
for this sound and and off we would go
so that's this in here
that would just allow us to again de-mux
those sort of compounds out if if
someone does feed us some kind of weird
like Dolby 77.1 is kind of a more
standard thing nowadays right yeah I
love tool B's so such a train wreck in
progress
all of these sound formats are so
ridiculous but anyway so I believe 7.1
is kind of what you would do nowadays
most of the time like I mean just look
at these things look at how many stupid
formats like God just I don't even want
to get into it I hate this kind of crap
like how hard is it to just come up with
a spec for sound it's like the simplest
thing and they massively overcomplicated
it's nuts anyway uh so Dolby 7.1 is
probably a pretty safe format to go with
the reason I like 7.1 is because it
happens to pad out to an even number for
Simbi right if you're gonna mix down to
7.1 you've got eight Sindhi lanes which
is two SSC registers or one ATX register
and that's just kind of nice right
so I would say Dolby 7.1 is where we
should live here so if anyone does feed
us some giant eight sample eight channel
sound will de-mux it later on in the
mixer when we're mixing everything down
we output to eight channels we can
restore that sound as it was if we
wanted to and other sounds that are
supposed to be spatialized we can place
them as we want them placed at that time
but George thinking I want those
channels I think separated out into
separate assets when we are doing this
this way also for each one of these I
want to divide the channel up into
blocks based on the sample count so that
we can have some notion of what the
maximum sample count is we want to read
I don't know what that's gonna be just
yet but let's just say
you know that we said that we wanted I
don't know something like that 64k worth
of samples
I don't know 256k worth of the sample
count it's really so 128 would be if
each ones 16-bit right then each sample
count is gonna be that'll be 200 is 8k
of load per time you know we'll make up
something there that we like who knows
what it is but what we want to do is say
all right there's some max sample count
if someone feeds is a sound that's
longer than that sample count so it's
like music or a very long sound effect
we're gonna break it up into blocks that
can be streamed incrementally because
obviously we have that support in the
mixer already so we might as well use it
so what we'll do here is say okay when
you feed us one of these sounds will
sort of do a loop here going through
what we've got and using the max sample
count to break it up into chunks as
necessary so we'll enter into a loop
here and we'll say all right the sample
count right now we can actually do this
here will say like samples remaining or
maybe sample count remaining so what
we'll do here is we'll say load up the
sample count we'll do a for loop here
and we'll say the sample count for this
interior section here is going to be the
sample count remaining if that sample
count that we end up with is higher than
the maximum so we would overflow what
we're saying we want our maximum block
size to be will truncate then we'll
write it out and we'll take the sample
count remaining and subtract that sample
count from it right we can also do a
sample pointer right so we can say the
samples are
oops the samples are here so get those
and every time we advance by however
many we consumed that leaves us here
with a nice way of ready to write out an
asset of particular sample count and a
particular sample pointer and we're
ready to go
right so I think that should allow us to
do an audio import there as we you know
as we would and so just looking at how
the asset data stuff would happen you
can see like the sketch of that in the
image version of this right you can see
all that happening here and so what I
want to do is have that same thing
happen in process audio import so what
we would be doing there is saying all
right get you know this exact same
operation where we reserved the data and
everything we want to do exactly that
and then we want to actually set up the
rest of this stuff
accordingly the file asset indices part
we'd even use but it would just be for 0
0 because we oh well no yeah we we don't
really need anything any other
information there that that's pretty
much sufficient right alright so looking
at this we'd have the same thing here's
the asset index that we would try to
figure out where we be writing it you
know if we already have an existing
asset index for it I guess we can just
overwrite that asset and so that's all
we're doing here so we want to do that
same process and again we just don't
need the tile part of that so I don't
know if we want to make this stuff I
don't know how much of this we want to
just clone and how much we want to
actually have like a code path that we
share so I made try to pull some common
code out here once I see what it looks
like but we'll cross that bridge when we
come to it
so assuming that we look into 0-0
location because there's no such thing
as a gridded sound import for us
assuming that we get it we use it if we
don't then we reserve it and off we go
assuming we got one we now know we know
what the asset size is gonna be right
because we know that it's just a sample
count times that 16 right that's just
how big it is not a whole lot we have to
do there we don't need to do anything
well yeah we would need to do an unload
here we don't have an unload for sound
so hmm
oops you may have to make one of those
you can see in here doing the the clear
on this asset we don't need to clear
like the equivalent of a texture handle
because there isn't such a thing so I
don't really know that we need something
quite this hardcore but you know if I do
do an unload audio and we pass like a
audio ID what is this sound ID yeah so
if I if I pass one of these and we do
the exact same thing I don't I don't
really think we need to do anything else
fancy there what we can do is just go
ahead and and and set it to unloaded I
don't know that we need to do anything
else because there's nobody depending on
it but we should keep that path in place
so that in case we do need to do
something we're fancy in the future we
could I think that's probably what we
want to do alright so in here where we
have the asset file index test phone
it's like curiosity what clearing the
texture handle I guess we just let it
get reclamators some other time yeah I
guess the least recently used I'll just
clean that up but anyway so we then need
to finish this off so we're gonna say
the DES file index and all this stuff is
pretty much the same so that does kind
of argue for
maybe sharing this code pass we need to
reserve data for it if we don't have
enough room assuming we do I don't know
why this 64k part is relevant I don't
think we care about that so now we need
to do is we need to set the actual sound
data so in here where we look at how
those sound those hij sounds are set up
here's where they are we got the sample
count in the channel count so we know
what those are there's a sample count
and instead of source image it's just
you know that's just the sound so there
we go
at the moment for some reason those are
actually big so we don't actually have
to truncate them
we could have truncated the channel
count probably we didn't decide because
we had nothing else to store in that
room that we would have used there you
looking at this probably what we should
have done is weld the make a u16 channel
count in a u16 chain ID there's really
no need for those to both be 32 that's
just just just way too large there's no
point to that but
um so that's just kind of dumb but you
know no one's gonna care that's you know
you have these sounds that take up many
many kilobytes and then we just have
like sixteen wasted bits in here no
one's gonna care right it's not gonna
affect anything we can do with these so
it's not important to get it right but
you know it's just worth noting it's
dumb regardless so anyway getting rid of
all this stuff I don't think we need any
of this that can go so what we really
need to do here is just make sure that
it's labeled as a sound the rest of this
stuff is all exactly the same this stuff
is also set to zero all that stuff gonna
be exactly the same so again I do think
we could share a lot of this code it's
it's very very highly correlated to the
previous routine the bitmap version of
this so it does seem like we probably
want to pull some of this out so that's
not so that you know if we do need to
modify it change the way it was being
done that it won't you know we don't
have to remember to do it in whole bunch
of different places so I think we're
down to mostly the end now where we just
need to say okay the chain part of
things when we actually do that so a
couple things
[Music]
I'm thinking in my head as well that
actually we should reuse the grid system
here too we could have the grid actually
correspond to the channels that kind of
sounds somewhat compelling to me I like
that I think we should probably embrace
that that might require a couple of
changes but I think that might be nice
alright so going through here when we
actually have to fill out the chain data
we actually do know what that would be
and if this case gets hit that's when we
know we need to chain so what I propose
is we just have a chain value here we
set the chain value right off the bat to
be none and so normally when you now put
a sound it'll just get a none chain but
then when we come in here if we had to
clip that down to a max ammo count we
know that will go more times and so
we'll want to do an advance on that one
that way when we get down here it's time
to store it we just know what it was
that we needed to store so finally what
I guess I would say is now we can make
the while loop happen we can just say
well there were any samples keep going
and I think we're done so that's a
pretty stable way to output that that
looks pretty good I'm gonna slap it to
do in here because at some point we're
gonna know what we want our block size
for streaming to be because we'll have
some idea about how the streaming reads
perform and we'll want to say look use
this big of a buffer because that's what
we're using for backing so they'll be
something clearer about this at some
point right and so that's when we want
to take a look at that now when we do
the sort of output of the sounds here
remember they are not tagged so that's
the other end of this that we have to
make work and you can see that there is
part of it that won't work in fact let's
actually just go do it because we're
gonna have to so the part that won't
work is the fact that we split these up
into multiple channels and assets so we
kind of need to actually make this be
aware of that so in here where we do our
process audio import for each channel we
need to create a new asset ID and and
you can see that happening in here it's
not going to work properly right and
this asset index needs to this asset
index needs to increment as we go per
channel and per trunk so really this
part here this is pretty tricky
we need to reserve effectively a block
of assets and so as we go each time we
need to like set to incrementing asset
IDs as we go right
the only tricky part about that is right
now we don't actually compute how many
asset IDs we're gonna need ahead of time
but it's not particularly hard to do so
maybe we should just do that so let's
jump to reserve asset here and you can
see that when we do this we just have to
you know we would just need a thing
that's like normally just reserves a
single asset so we would want to say if
asset count plus asset count is less
than or equal to max asset count then
we're good to go
otherwise it's an error so in here when
we get this and we reserve one of these
what we could do now is say oh well the
results going to be asset count but then
we're gonna add an arbitrary number to
it so we basically reserve these in
blocks so then when we get this asset
index here that asset index is actually
going to be something a little bit more
Squinkie
so outside of here we have to do a
contiguous asset block acquire right and
so we have to think about this a little
bit harder as a result because that
asset index is actually a block of asset
indices and then we go through getting
them out one by one
what I don't really have a good way of
doing here is knowing whether I need to
rewrite them or not
but I think we could just let the
routine below do that like it can just
look at each individual asset and see
what part of it it needs to rewrite like
whether it needs to get new data or
whether can just rewrite to the same
location because it's the it's not going
to change size or something seems okay
so in here where we do asset index file
and we grab out just the 0 0 1 I really
we just need to know inside this piece
of information how many of these in a
run we're gonna do and we know that here
the thing that's gonna be tricky is in
the stamping so so in the stamping when
we go through each of these things to do
the the tag the problem that we have is
this that array of tags there that we're
storing in that asset source file as a
piece of information we don't really
have a way to do that for for sounds
because they could have arbitrarily long
asset chains associated with them and so
I'm not sure how to harmonize these two
paths because we basically want to call
the same thing and it almost works so
for any sound that wasn't streaming it
would work and we could even use the the
file asset indices to just record the
channels so that almost works but we
just don't have a run count for them and
I guess what we would need to do is add
that in here
but yeah oh wait
I'm over complicating this aren't I we
don't need to apply any tags at all to
the asset chunks that are just streaming
chunks because only the first chunk gets
pulled based on tag and then it just
advances to the next chunk so actually
we're fine yeah that that's actually not
a problem at all I take it back entirely
so really all we need to do is do this
per channel so inside here where we go
oh you know while sample count remaining
right before that part this is where we
would reserve the number of assets that
we think we need for the sample count
that we have right and so we would just
say like total chunk count and we would
say however many sound samples there are
whatever that max sample count is let's
do a roundup right so however many
chunks we're gonna have is this many
right because we're gonna when we do
that divide we know that we're gonna
have a rounded up number of chunks right
get that total chunk count reserve that
many assets right and so in here when we
get out which asset index we're using I
don't have a way of knowing whether this
audio can be used again the way that it
was because unless we actually stored
something in there that said how many it
was we actually can't figure that out I
don't
think right because just knowing the
base index we would have to go read the
chain length ahead of time which I guess
we could just do yeah I actually I
suppose we could just do that just check
the chain length actually yeah okay so
what we would do is do this we just say
look if we don't get an asset index then
we've got to go like that
and we've got to get you know out of the
asset store a chunk that's as many you
know we've got to get a block of
allocated asset and this is contiguous
that are as many as we need we can look
and see if from this asset index could
would it have reserved as many as we
wanted it to right we can't actually do
that because all we would have to do is
look through each individual one and see
whether or not it actually can be
chained right so in here when we get a
sound asset right in here if we just got
each asset as we go and verify that that
each one is set to chaining um I think
that's all we need right we don't really
need to do anything else and then we can
just save the exact we can just use the
exact set of asset IDs that we want so
in here we would just say for you know
shunk index equals zero chunk index is
less than blah plus plus chunk index
right and we would say look we want to
go up through we don't need to check the
last chunk because we don't care what
that's set to but for all of the other
chunks we just need to get them out of
the file which is this right and we need
to make sure that they're actually set
to streaming so we need to make sure
that like this thing is set to load its
next chunk so if we look at one of these
assets which is HHH sound dot chain if
it's equal we're fine if it's not equal
to what we want then we're done and you
know all bets are off right so basically
what we're doing is we're saying okay we
know we need this many contiguous at
contiguous asset indexes indices right
because we're gonna have to store this
sound as a block of that many assets
when we broke it up so what we want to
do is look at the current chain that we
recorded is it that long if it's more
than that long great if it's less than
that long then we need to allocate a new
block right so just change the chain and
see if it goes that long problem solved
so looking in here if I go up to file
formats and I put loop in there and we
go that will give us whether or not we
need to allocate new absently if we do
need to allocate a new asset index off
we go and we can store which one you
know we can do reuse asset equals false
or true or whatever I don't know and
then we can just do it here
so then when we come down in here we can
just do if you're if we're supposed to
reuse the asset block here then get it
out otherwise don't bother and we would
just need a way of making sure the asset
index gets updated appropriately which
is pretty simple to do so in here we
would just do this that gets out the one
from that chain and so if we're going to
reuse it we reuse it if not we just
start with nothing and off we go the
asset index at the end of this has to be
incremented because every time we're
gonna use a different slot and then
we're done so really the only thing
we're left with now is that this part
here it needs to take the channel index
and that's fine
what that means is we do have a maximum
channel count it's 64 channels like I
could even do it this way right what's
that
where's that where's that at show me
where that is at so what I could do even
is is address it like that right so we
can actually use asset import grid max
times asset grid port in max grid max
worth of channels we do still need to do
a check to make sure that we don't have
too many of those because that is still
a thing that could happen right soak in
here like we do have one other asset
memory problem of this error is not in
the right place either it should be
probably here if we didn't get one right
so if asset index isn't true we just do
the out here and say we ran out of
memory so think that's all good I don't
see anything else particularly
problematic about that everything seems
good there yeah so the only thing we
don't have is we currently don't have a
way of oh and also the error can happen
here too right so we need to clamp that
and we know the max channel count is
just however much we could have stored
in here so asset import grid max squared
that's however many things we can fit
and still flush through the pipeline I
you could argue that we should probably
that we maybe should have done this a
different way that could be true I don't
really know but you know just keeping
the pipelines simple or we might as well
not do anything too fancy
then the import grid tags side of things
that import grid tags can now have the
channel tag included on here so back
where we were actually gonna stamp this
guy so you know in the import path right
where we come through here oops sorry
that's the parser when we do update
asset metadata you know what I mean
that's got the the grid tags sort of
baked into it so you can see we've got
the append tags here on the import tag
array that's what we parse out and then
we have the grid tags here and that's
what comes from like the type of file so
this grid tag just needs to be set to
what
normally want to create four sounds
which is channel ideas for everything
and so that's pretty easy for us to do
we just need to save a version of this
that's like our global audio version of
that right and so that's what we would
need to do next time to get those
channel things correct
so effectively like in this h HT context
here like this part right what we would
want to do is have a thing that's like
these are the import grid tags that we
use like this like that right and so in
here where we come through and say oh
it's a sound or music we would just say
oh good just use the audio channel tags
and that'll stamp everything with the
correct tags for a channel as we go
right and that would be it so everything
else would just work and the metadata
update would just correctly stamp
everything which is awesome and I think
that's what we want right
that's source file
that's an audio ID by the way so sorry
why did I call it sound ID I don't know
just looping through here a sample count
it's true just make sure all that gets
lined up properly good I think that's it
I don't think there's anything else we
got to do there so I'm gonna call that a
day and so we've got I think we actually
have almost other call in there I do
need to actually create those channel so
I need to do this I need to make that
grid with the stamped ones but that's it
and so what I would like to do is go
ahead and save that for next weekend
everything seems to be in place so it's
really just a question of let's go
through and actually get out the
fine-tooth comb to bug it get it working
properly but then I think we're
importing sounds properly and music and
streaming really so everything's in
place and so next weekend we should be
able to actually go through there and
and get it working let's go ahead and go
to Q&amp;A if there's any questions about
what we were doing there let's get those
going
not related but do you have any thoughts
on Pony Lang nope I've never used it
no questions and that's good
flit let's hippo how are you feeling
about the way the asset system is
working out so far it's pretty good I
think I I don't know about the grid
based import idea really you know it's
basically I guess you know spritesheet
import thing I think it makes it easier
for the artists but I don't know so I'm
not not sure if that cuz we could have
just had you save out individual pngs or
something right so I'm not sure I don't
know if that was the right decision not
I like the way it's shaping up so far
basically the the there's a few things
about you know how the import goes that
you know we definitely could do better
if you know if I was working 8 hours a
day on this there's a bunch of things
I'd clean up but you know you can only
do what you can do but it's pretty good
what does good documentation look like I
think I've heard about you and John talk
about documentation being really bad and
soul-sucking when it's auto-generated so
what does good human documentation look
like for program reason for users I
guess what I say is I do like
auto-generated documentation for one
aspect of things which is I like
everything to be hyperlinked and that's
something that an auto generator can do
well so I do like that part
you know like MSDN actually used to do
this pretty well it kind of got a lot
worse but if you look at something like
you know create file X or something
right
we're sorry create file a it's fine so
it used to be I think and maybe I could
be maybe I'm making this up but you know
these were hyperlinked so you can click
on handle and get to the definition of
handle right when you come down in here
sometimes that happens so you know it's
like oh I go down to security attributes
and it's hyperlinked so I can go to that
and that's good
but I prefer all of those to really be
hyperlinked as well right and I like
that aspect of auto-generated right and
see also and those sorts of things I
like having a really dense
interconnectivity so I can just click
around what I don't love about
auto-generated is that when I need
documentation and this is not
necessarily a popular opinion so you
know I'm talking about my preference I
actually don't like this kind of doc you
people seem to like it I don't I don't
need you to tell me that LPC stur LP
file name is the file name right a lot
of times I see this documentation it's
like DD word desire to access the
desired access right and it's like I
don't need you to tell me that what I
need you to tell me is all the stuff I
can't tell by looking at this prototype
right so what I want to know is stuff
like okay you know when do I need to
fill out each template file and how are
they related this other thing so
parameter Docs actually don't like what
I like is per concept Docs so you know
give me a section called template file
and say the creation disposition flag
and the template file parameter work
together in this way if it's set to 1
then the tempo files to be pointing to
this kind of template you know that sort
of stuff and go through each of the
things that I need to understand to use
this effectively that's what I like
furthermore I like that as a broader
thing for individual Docs for a function
as well so create file should have close
handle discussed in it like I'd like to
see that create file close handle or
create file read right close right so I
can see like oh okay so this is supposed
to be like a set of things that go
together I like seeing that like okay I
open one of these I close it in-between
I can read and write or whatever right
so bringing me into the sort of the
stuff that you know cuz you made the API
but I don't know because I've never seen
it before giving me like what those
bundles are and how they work together
that helps a lot to write so keeping
those things in mind I think are pretty
good right I'm gonna take this reverse
order so like UNIX man pages because
they leaned closer to conceptual
documentation would be more preferable
yeah actually I like it broken down by
concept not by element because the
elements often work together if if one
of these parameters is truly standalone
so maybe DW share mode doesn't depend on
anything then great document that by
itself because that's what it is but
assuming you've got pieces that work
together I want you to discuss them
together does the C code run faster in
general if you play something like width
divided by 2 and height divided 2 by the
left binary shift no the compiler knows
those pretty well so usually you won't
usually the code that's generated by
those two would be the same sometimes
not but most the time yes
let's see about meow hash Germany
resources on how you came up with it or
where I could learn more about designing
such I guess what I would say is if you
want to design your own hash function
there's a lot of things that you want to
learn and I would say first of all you'd
have to have a good reason for why you
wanted to do it like why why do you want
to design your own hash function might
be the first start if it's just for
curiosity's sake
that's great otherwise I would say don't
make a new hash function unless you have
a goal with me I actually was to try and
be fast right because there really
aren't any fast hash functions out there
that are any good and that's still kind
of the case now hash isn't as good as
I'd like we're trying to make a better
one that still runs at full speed we
haven't quite gotten there yet we
thought we sort of had but we hadn't
quite yet so we're still working on that
so we're hoping that the final version
of meow hash will be higher quality than
the current meow hash is while still
running it basically the same speed
that's what we're working on now but
again like it's a pretty complex topic
you probably want to work with a
cryptographer on it if you're really
trying to do things serious cuz you need
a lot of domain expertise that's what
I'd say do modern gamers have their own
sound synthesizer or do they just import
sounds from other software libraries I
would say it's a mix typically what
happens is you have a bunch of audio
editing software that you that your
sound designers are using to produce all
sorts of stuff but then in the game
engine you typically do have something
that's more advanced than handmade hero
so at the very least you typically have
a lot of sound effect sort of stuff like
adding reverb dynamically depending on
like where the player is in the world
you know
having sort of different things Oh a
grenade went off near the player so now
the sound is like their ears are a
little shocked and things are happening
there and so it alters the sound as it
comes out of that or oh we're slowing
down time and so that's a fact right so
typically at least have all those
effects whether or not a modern game
engine employs employ stuff like FM
synth that really depends more on the
game and whether it makes any sense for
them to be doing things like that but
but it can certainly happen really again
it just depends on what you're doing if
you're using an audio library nowadays
those audio libraries like you know rad
ships the mouth sound system and like
there's all kinds of stuff in there
right like I mean it's just who even
knows I'm not up-to-date on like a lot
of stuff is but there's tons of crap
like mixing modifications and how sounds
go together and all this sort of stuff
and then there's like F mods another
popular one and again like I mean honest
don't even know like all this garbage
right I mean there's a modulator for
thing I'm who knows right I haven't
looked at any of this stuff but
basically yeah you've got just tons of
crap going in to the sound system how
much of it's actually necessary or makes
any difference whatsoever is I think
probably up for debate but what most of
it is designed around is sound designers
come from a specific world and they
think in a specific way a lot of what
those tools are designed to do is to
make it as easy as possible for them to
put to utilize their vocabulary of how
to make sound sound good without them
having to learn like a whole bunch of
other things right so a lot of what
those tools try to enable is let's give
the sound designer an interface similar
to what they're used to in a sound
package for what happens in the
one time game so when they tweak stuff
they can tweak stuff correctly like
endow unintuitive Lee right
[Applause]
can you demonstrate Lipstadt how you
implemented see mirror version control
it seems very interesting I mean yeah
maybe we can go in at some point the
short answer is the the version of see
mirror that I use now which is a
complete rewrite it's a totally it has
nothing to do with the one that was
publicly released it's it's based on the
concept that you just in addition to
storing the versions of files you also
store the all of the metadata in a
separate database and every machine
keeps that and then two machines talk to
each other they just ask each other what
they've got and update it that way right
so it's really a mirroring system that
happens to also understand versioning
and it just works way better than
anything that I've used before because
instead of all this nonsense about
branching and merging in all this crap
it's just like look I don't care about
any of that stuff I realize there's
reasons for it but I don't want any that
I just want all my machines to stay in
sync and if I create multiple versions
of a file because I edit it in two
places just give me both vs. freaking
file and I'll deal with it later
right and so that's what it's designed
to do is to keep all your machines in
sync and if there's if you've done
different things on different machines
instead of making that be this big
emergency that breaks everything it just
puts them all in place and says look do
whatever you want
here's several versions of this file
because everyone changed it I'm gonna
leave yours and you just merge in these
changes when you get around to it
right and it's much more pleasant that
way for for situations like what I do
where there's very few programmers or
artists or whatever have very very few
people doing things it just makes things
so much easier than the like let's grind
the entire team to screeching halt
because some source code control
conflict happened which is like the git
way of living with git
everyone's like running stash all the
time trying to like it's just a system
but how many times have people give me
the old why reinvent the wheel line I've
never seen a discussion about building
code from scratch not have at least
someone smugly break that one out yeah
like I guess what I would say about that
is that it's I don't even really
understand why people use that phrase
like we don't have any wheels anyway
like I mean the concept that we have
something as good as a wheel right now
and programming is ludicrous we don't
you know I think I've said this before a
wheel is a perfect machine the reason
you say why reinvent the wheel is
because it does exactly what you want it
to do there is literally nothing like
that in computing there is no game
engine you can get that's even close to
good let alone perfect and so it's
always you're making trade-offs right
you're saying well I want to save time
so if I use this you know it's similar
to saying like you know we have square
wheels is what we have in our world
right now and if you don't want to go
through the trouble of forging your own
wheel that might be better you can use
these like square shaped wheels and your
car will like go like this but you know
at least you didn't have to build a
wheeler yourself right so that's what
we're at so anyone who says why reinvent
the wheel I think fundamentally doesn't
understand what a wheel is might be the
way it is that is a and B even if you do
understand what a wheel is and you
thought that our current wheels were
similar like our current stuff we
haven't computing is similar to actual
wheels which i think is a ridiculous
notion that if you actually think that I
don't understand you you probably don't
really understand computing very much I
guess is what I'd say because we're just
not even close but let's say you thought
that even in the real world
how many vendors of tires are there in
the world and how many types of tires
are there I mean there are thousands of
different types of tires in the world
right
now and that's just the wheels that go
on a car there's the number of different
wheels made by people in the world is
stunning like there's all kinds of
wheels inside mechanisms those are all
made by different people and they're
different sizes and they work different
ways made out of different materials
with different heat profiles different
surface textures
there's wheels that are used for
grinding there's wheels that are used
for driving there's wheels that are used
in gearing there's wheels that are used
as disc brakes there's wheel I mean
saying why we have to do is just dumb
it's like it's sort of like saying I'm
too stupid to believe that humans can
make progress or something right like I
just believe we're done it just doesn't
make sense even people who make wheels
make new wheels right now and that's the
wheel it's been around for thousands of
years right I got nothing like I just
don't know what to say to people like
that it's like their brain just can't
even conceive of something better than
what they have it's like a child playing
in a sandbox they just don't they it's
like it's a very immature statement I
guess is what I would say speaking about
MSDN I had an issue where an old version
of Doc's had a remark that was important
for a certain call that some value
should be set a certain way destruct not
there on the new version oh great yeah
that does happen act anyway doesn't the
remark section usually have information
on things like closed file for the
create files call and so on yes and and
I like MSDN on the whole I think it's
pretty good documentation like if you've
ever used like Apple's documentation for
example it's a pretty clear step down
and so I think MSDN you know if you can
manage to produce dominations that's as
good as MSDN you're actually in good
shape that's a pretty high bar actually
for documentation a lot of documentation
isn't as good as MSDN so I wasn't trying
to slag MSDN at all there MSDN is pretty
good I think
got worse like it used to be better the
CD version you know you used to be able
to put in your machine it was a lot
better you had a faster index you could
use to jump to things quickly it had
more hot linking that worked better so
it's it's degraded over time as they've
done the web nonsense to it and they
probably ended up with people who don't
really know what they're doing you know
making that website so it got worse than
it was but it's still pretty good you
know in the pantheon of documentation
quality it's it's pretty high up there
and if if you produce documentation
that's as good as MSDN that's good
enough right could you do better sure
but you're already doing pretty good if
you've got to that level right a lot of
Doc's just fundamentally learn is good
my is functional programming not
dominating corporate programming cuz I
don't really understand the question
functional programming like any style of
programming is useful for some things
and not useful for others and I would
say generally speaking most people do do
functional programming if they're good
programmers they do do functional
programming in places where it's
possible but in a lot of cases it's just
not feasible to do functional
programming for the things you want to
do and so you know functional program
intends to live down in the leaf layers
of things business apps or otherwise all
right I think we're done here
oh I changed a bugger to remedy if you'd
go to remedy B GHI oh it's in there I
should probably change I don't know if
we let me ask let me look I don't
actually know if we can can we do
something here we're like let me see so
so if I go to boy scoot I don't know if
I don't know how to do this but I'm
gonna try so if we go to channel on
twitch if I edit
let me see edit panels so if I say I'm
gonna go ahead and try to add in here
links at the bottom of the twitch window
so if you're watching the stream live
you can get those
so let me link to those here or try to
and you can tell me if this works so
I'll put that one there
and for coder
I'll put cubes put here and
we'll see if this will update so let me
see
all right so if you refresh your twitch
window if you're watching this on Twitch
underneath there's like a thing that
says like about handmade here and
there's thing that says how to support
the project I added a line that says you
can also buy the tools used on stream
the editor is for a coder and the
debugger is remedy if you click on those
for coder or the remedy link they should
now take you to the itch to the itch i/o
page for each of those products so if
you want to buy the editor or buy the
debugger that we use on stream at some
point you should be able to find them
there that's I guess yeah that's that's
the way I would I would say it's easiest
to get to those things cuz I'm there
yeah there those links should probably
just be generally available someone
could probably bake those into in sohbat
as well who knows how to use in sohbat
so that when people ask on stream you
could answer
now for coder and remedy or commercial
you have to pay them they're very cheap
they're much cheaper than they probably
should be I think they're like nine and
twelve dollars so like yeah that's about
as cheap as any piece of software should
be in my opinion
do you know why functional protein
languages tend to be closely tied to
formal verification and more
theoretically a chance
yeah it's because thinking that you want
purely functional stuff is usually the
domain of programmers who want to be
thinking very analytically and formally
about things they just go hand in hand
to the mentality people who want to do
more like I'm programming a computer
computers aren't functional they're
procedural right so you know that's the
kind of thing that you want to that's
the kind of thing that you that's the
kind of thing that's just the people who
would bother making a pure functional
language or are close to it are there
gonna be people who are thinking along
those lines because why else you would
never build one otherwise CPUs aren't
functional you would never you would
never go I want to program a computer
with a functional language if what you
cared about its programming the computer
computers are functional so it's it's
inherently not the right language for
programming a computer but if you want
to program a theory right if you're
trying to make a theoretical verifiable
thing then function is exactly what you
want is the only thing you can verify
right is something that has 100%
deterministic input-output right I and
so you know I think those things make
perfect sense people who want to program
computers and get the most out of them
they want procedural people who want to
program computers and be able to prove
things about what they write they want
functional because you have to have it
you procedural languages is it's just
incredibly difficult if not impossible
to do formal verification on them you
know is it license based no neither are
license based in the sense that they
don't require any kind of DRM they are a
license based in the sense that you have
to buy a license per one that you want
to use but once you buy the license it
just installs in your machine you don't
have to run DRM or anything
all right last question from Brian
greetings Casey how do you find balance
balance of duplicating code versus
trying to generalize a function as an
exercise I took format string for hammer
here on wrote a format wide string in
the end I chose to simply take the
format call utf-8 for me to sing call
format string on a temp buffer and then
utf-16 from utf-8 but now I sacrifice
performance for maintenance other than
if it becomes a bottleneck when
profiling what other things do you look
for choosing to duplicate code and
making it more a pain to maintain then
the benefits of having specific versions
I would say you kind of stated it
exactly the right way maintenance costs
are real debugging costs are real they
cannot be ignored because you only have
a limited amount of development time so
usually what you want to do if you can
just do something like utf-8 to 16 and
then 16 to you if you fate or whatever
just do that first and then see whether
that becomes a hot spot just like you
said when you're profiling your app if
you start to see those things show up
then it's the time to start looking into
it if that never shows up on a profile
then it's not worth it right so you do
want to be aware you know you want to
remain aware of what's costing your time
but if you just don't see things like
that showing up that it's just not the
right time to to be focusing your
efforts there because again just like
you said I think I stated very well if
you make things more performant you
typically let's make them less
maintainable and that's a real cost and
so you don't want to pay the cost if
you're not getting the benefit and
having increased performance for a
particular routine only matters if that
routine actually is showing up is
costing you something right
okay let's wrap it up thank you everyone
for joining me for those sort of
handmade he wrote so no pleasure coding
you with you as always if you are
following series at home you can always
peer to the game on hand me here org it
comes to the source code so you can
follow along into your own experiments
with it I also want to remind everyone
handmade Seattle as I talked about at
the beginning of the stream Abner is
running a conference for those who don't
know him he's the fellow who organized
everyone to do handmade Network the
place where a lot of these products are
hosted and that's gonna be in Seattle on
November 16th so March of calendars and
if you are interested in that head over
to handmade Seattle comm put your email
into this notification box here and hit
notify data loops that's great
that'll basically put put you on the
mailing list so that when the conference
scheduled and when to buy tickets and
details on stuff come out you will get
notified with that information so you
can yeah plan the trip anyway that's it
for today I'll be back next weekend to
go ahead and get that sound import stuff
debugged I'm assuming we've you know all
we did was type it in assuming you got
some bugs in there so we want to go
through and actually put all this stuff
together and make sure that all of it
works that's about it until then have
fun programming I'll see everyone on the
Internet take it easy everybody