hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream we have a new member of
the handmade hero family today I am
pleased to say as you know since
starting the series we have had Allen
Webster create an editor that we now use
on the stream so we no longer use canoe
Emacs we use for coder on the stream and
it turns out that we now are able to
switch over to our own drawing program
as well and let me be it's called Milton
and it's actually on the handmade
Network site much like for coder is and
I wish that I could pronounce that I'll
tell you a little story I as well I
won't say used to because we probably
will do more episodes in the future but
every so often myself and Jeff Roberts
we do a podcast called the Jeff and
Casey show and on this podcast quite
some time I believe before a hand made
hero even was the thing we got an email
from someone named Sergio and I tried we
liked would read mail on the air like
when we receive letters to the show we'd
read them it for the episodes and it
just so happened that for some reason I
wanted to try and say like Sergio in
like a in like a sexy Spanish I want to
be like say Akio or something like this
and I and I was like but I don't know
how I was like I don't have any Spanish
skills whatsoever like I I have no idea
how to say Sergio properly let alone
sexily and so it was just it was a bit
of a joke at the time but point being
that happened well fast forward to after
handmade hero and it turns out that this
paint program is actually made by the
same and I'll just say Sergio so I won't
try to pronounce his name in the sexy
fashion because I I have been informed
that I already failed at it but point
being if you scroll down on here Milton
handmade network you will get to him
here he is
let's let's say it's Sergio Gonzales
Sergio I don't know you know what
Sergio send me a wave file of you saying
your name if you want to say it sexy you
can say it sexy if you wanted to say it
regular you could say it regular but
least it'll be pronounced correctly and
so I can finally like you know get past
that problematic pronunciation that I
did on the Jeff and Kate show which was
horribly wrong and not sexy at all but
point being you can go and you can check
this out this drawing program yourself
it's basically a replacement for what we
have been using you know it's got like
infinite canvas and stuff like that just
like mischief did but it's actually
quite a bit better than a mischief in a
number of ways like it automatically
saves your progress and stuff so you
don't have to worry about any of that so
it kind of seems like it might actually
be a little bit better than then
mischeif was much like for coder is
starting out to be better than the new
Emacs so upgrades all around and point
being he did not have a patreon when I
last checked but it looks like this is
actually happening now alright so there
is a brand new patreon that you can
support as well I will be supporting it
immediately after this and and yeah I
always try to like any products that we
use on stream I try to put some money
from the handmade here at patreon over
into those every month to help the folks
who are making stuff that we can use and
so here is the package some really cool
stuff about it actually is I love that
the old-school deluxe paint interface
kind of thing where if you hit the tab
key everything goes away I really like
that and it doesn't have the bug of alt
tab switching to eyedropper mode which
is a huge pain in mischief
so already like you know this is a bit
of an improvement
but there's still some kinks to work out
so we're just trying it out we're gonna
try it for a while mostly the only thing
that I noticed is the the tracking speed
seems a little laggy and I think that
might have something to do with well
actually I don't know yet
yeah the source code is actually
available so I was gonna go take a look
at it on this particular machine this
graphics card is is awfully old too and
so you know anything that's that's not
just so maybe causing it to be a little
bit hiccup II so we'll see but as it is
it seems like it's pretty easy to do
like you know I can go ahead and say de
277 just like before and I can write so
like I said kind of cool that we're
eventually switching over to all
handmade stuff and like I said the
source code to this is actually
available as well so we can actually go
check it at some point maybe if we do a
stream and see what's happening in terms
of the the refresh rate on this machine
there might be some things we can do to
to fix it on this machine for speed
because that was the only thing that I
noticed that was different I liked
everything else more and it doesn't have
that that nasty bug that always kind of
plagued me which is pretty great so
there we go
so that's a new member of the team here
at handmade hero and so now really I
guess we just have to figure out some
way if the debugger you know if we can
replace Visual Studio we're down to
almost nothing I guess we got the
compiler but you know we're getting
close to no tools but the compiler
really that that aren't from the
handmade hero community itself which is
pretty pretty awesome if I do say so
myself but all that being said we still
have some programming to do that is you
know we've got to get down to business
and say 277 so if you want to follow
along with the programming at home
you're gonna want to unpack day to set
276 is source code into a directory
somewhere and that will be right
matching up with where I am myself now
what we ended on last time was we had
pretty much
gotten the hoppin under control in terms
of what I wanted and basically we're
waiting for probably some some new art
and so what we'll probably do is revisit
the hopping to when we get new art
because I've kind of got it all shrunk
down and and and scaled all weird and
stuff because that's sort of the
roundness that I expect or need the art
to be eventually so like I said that's
gonna be something that kind of has to
get taken care of with art assets but
for now the feel is actually feeling
okay so the actual playability of it
seems pretty reasonable to me and of
course it's hard to say that until I
actually start interacting with the game
proper so we'll see how it goes but it's
at least good enough at the moment for
us to sort of for me to feel comfortable
moving on to other parts of the game and
bringing them up to speed I'm pretty
confident that we can make this work as
it is with you know with more tuning and
more artwork we can figure out a way to
make that happen all right so what are
we going to do next well I think what I
would like to do next is I would like to
sort of try to move the entity system
and the structure of the world mode I'd
like to start trying to move those
towards something more real like it's
always kind of been a dumping ground
where we just been like okay whatever
we're doing it's fine doesn't matter and
we kind of have to sort of start making
that a little bit more real and we need
to do that in two ways one way is we
have to actually upgrade sort of the
logic side of that and how it's working
to be a little closer to what I think is
a proper system because we've always
sort of put the enemy system off and I
think now is a good time to actually
make it happen so we need to do that and
then the other thing that we need to do
is I would like to get the rendering
under control now that I know exactly
what we're going to be doing in terms of
how scenes are basically so as far as
I like layers are composited we want to
sort of going and clean out that Z and
all that sort of stuff so I think what
I'm gonna do is I'm gonna partition us
into a couple sort of passes through the
code base the first thing that I'm gonna
do is I'm gonna start by cleaning up the
entity processing like that whole just
the whole logic side of things I'm gonna
start by doing some passes over that to
sort of get that into a more reasonable
place and that includes like the storing
of the you know it's where things are
stored and how and how they get unpacked
and repacked and all those sort of
things I want to take that and give that
a good sort of once-over and then what
I'd also like to do is ping pong after
that over to the rendering thing and get
seams rendering properly so that now
that we know like how rooms sort of work
I want to get that sort of nailed down
as well and then we can come back and
start really working on the entity stuff
once that render part is complete and
that'll be you know working on stuff
like how we generate worlds and how we
do
AIS and that sort of thing and just
basically putting in the gameplay stuff
the kind of code that I hate as you know
because it's really kind of arbitrary
and doesn't have much to do with
anything but you kind of have to do it
so anyway that's what I'd like to do and
so right now I just probably want to
spend some time taking stock of where
things are and I want to talk to you a
little bit about sort of how I'm
conceptualizing this stuff working and
it's a little bit crazy and so I'm going
to sort of tell you what my plan is
going forwards and so here it is
so in fact I I'll get some good usage
out of out of Milton I think just to say
the least so here's the deal there's
lots of ways you can do entity systems
right there's and you know what I might
do - I might change this brush size a
little bit I don't think it needs to be
quite so big
that's a little better yeah so there's
lots of ways you can do entity systems
and to the best of my knowledge oh wow I
didn't draw that right to the best of my
knowledge it's really not the case that
there is canonical good and bad and you
know that there isn't like some holy
grail of enemy systems that somebody
figured out at some point and if you
just do it this way everything works out
great I've never really seen that to be
the case
people have arguments about these sorts
of things there's the object-oriented
parts of the arguments of things but
there's also all these other sorts of
things people throw on the term
component en Mnet's or entity component
system they all these names for stuff
but really a lot of it is is pretty
underbaked right it's not like this is
this isn't you know compiler Theory this
isn't something where people have really
codified like what an entity system
actually is what it does what the
different ways to do it are what the
complexities of those are like it's an
that it's a real like black art kind of
a thing and you know like many things
just because people like to get into
arguments about something or claim that
they have a very good way of doing
something or somebody says that this is
the way to do it and don't do it this
way you know people like to have those
arguments but only in some cases is
there any actual back you know sort of
sort of looking for actual theory or
proof to back it up a lot of times
they're just kind of spouting stuff and
these systems are pretty much that way
now there has been a lot of different
kinds of or ways that people write in
these systems obviously there's there's
ones that look a lot like a traditional
object-oriented program and the way
those work is you know there might be
some base class right that is just like
oh these are you know this is entities
just in general and then you know under
here you know maybe we've got you know
orcs right and then we've got humans or
something like this you know and then
under here you know we've got things
like oh yeah there's you know there's
the Prince you know or whatever and then
there's the like you know
and I don't I don't know what there
would be over here oh there's a night
for something like that you know there's
the different types of things that are
in here and over here there's you know
there's the necromancer or whatever I
don't know why this a necromancer or
something like that but anyway you see
there's been attempts of doing things
this way and in general this style of
sort of really really old-school object
orientation for stuff pretty much nobody
thinks is a good idea anymore as far as
I know right like I don't see many
people offering this as like a pretty
good way to do things and the reason for
that is because usually in games there
are not rigor like like really rigid
categorizations for things usually the
units that you create in a game or the
entities that you create in a game they
borrow from lots of places right so you
know it isn't like there's all unique
code in Printz all unique code in human
and all unique code in entity so prints
is just a prince human entity code base
and it all just works like usually
that's not the case usually there's some
stuff for example shared between the
necro and the prince right and there's
also stuff shared between you know the
night and the necro but that the knight
and the prince don't share but then
there's stuff in the print right and so
trying to break things into a class
hierarchy often falls apart and so you
know again that's separate from you know
I rant about obturator partnering all
the time
you know week that's all separate stuff
this is literally like forget whether
you're even thinking of joining or not
let's just say it doesn't mean they do
it that you're just saying I'm going to
classify these things hierarchically
just that act is kind of fraught with
peril and doesn't work out particularly
well so what people tend to do nowadays
in a lot of circumstances is they sort
of dispense with this kind of notion to
a large extent and instead they use you
know sort of a for like a more
compositional approach if you will which
is to say okay you know yet maybe if I'm
doing object-oriented programming so
maybe I'm a
during a program and I still do a little
bit of C++ or maybe you're someone like
John Lowe for example who does things
this way who isn't really much of an
auditorium programmer doesn't super like
it but typically does like to have
dispatcher and stuff handled for him and
a few other things like this you know
maybe you get rid of all that but say we
still have we still have one any big
class but then everyone else is is just
the thing that comes off of that right
you know there's a necro the prince and
the knight and so on and now what we're
gonna do is those things if they share
rather than before thinking of it was
like Oh a prince and a knight both have
certain things that they share because
they're human and we'll put that in here
right rather than try and do that
because it breaks down when then this
guy wants to share one little piece of
that but doesn't want to share the rest
of it or whatever rather than do that
what they do is they sort of put these
things inside these objects as sort of
like components so you can think of it
as you know I have my my struct well
this is struct necro and maybe it's got
an inheritance of entity so maybe it
does pull that in and again that's
optional if you're not an option area
programmer you wouldn't have that if you
are you would and then in here you would
have some things like oh well my necro
uses you know the the burn you know
burnable thing and that's like what you
need if you're gonna be someone who can
catch on fire let's say right and so
burnable is in here and and you know if
it needs to catch on fire then you can
use this or add that to a list or you
know whatever you want to do right and
so what ends up happening is rather than
stuff going into inheritance it goes
into containment right it's like I'm
Kurd struck in this thing and I put the
things that I want for this guy in there
okay that's you know been certainly one
way another way that's been looked at
for these sorts of things yet another
way is like the act react model which
was something from Looking Glass and
this is sort of like it parallels in a
lot of ways the AOS versus SOA thing
so remember when we talked about an
array of structure as versus a structure
of arrays and we sort of talked about
like oh well okay so a necro like what
is that well that's you know like one
burnable and and one you know health
attribute or whatever you know and so on
so it's got these things in it right it
has its a has a relationship as you
would say if you were in a land right
they would do it this way
and that's very much like the array of
structures method right so when you do
things like you can imagine in vertex
land we were doing things like okay
we've got a struct for our vertex and
then we have an some real 32s in here
for X Y Z and W right and that we called
array of structures because we have an
array and each entry in the array is a
structure containing the components that
we needed right but when we started
talking about Cindi programming where
you want to operate on all the X's at
once all the Y's at once we'll disease
it once we you know sort of went into
this other way of doing things SOA which
was like okay now instead of having like
a vertex star for our vertices instead
we have a pointer for each of the
different types of vertices let's say
and maybe we don't actually really quite
do it that way but you know what I mean
conceptually speaking where we have
pointers for each of these right and now
all the X's come together all the Y's
come together all the Z's come together
and so I use a specific index to refer
to my particular one I'm talking about
what vertex I want but it's in a
different array for each element and
that's to facilitate processing them you
know in bulk well the act react system
is very much the analog of that this was
introduced by looking glass on theif the
dark project and that's a way of
basically rotating this concept so that
instead of saying I have a struct it's
got these things in it instead I say
well actually what we have is the
burnable table right for everything
that's burnable has its burnable there
and then i have the health table
right and so on and these things get
processed individually so the burned
stuff does it's burning update the hell
stuff does its health update whatever
and then if I want to ask what a
particular entities state is with
respect to whether it's burning or not I
look up in this table using it's like
entity key whatever its ID is right so
it's much more like a sort of multi
table database sort of a thing the way
that it's sort of conceptualized and
again is the implementation deals I'm
just trying to give you sort of the
broad picture right so there's been lots
and lots and lots of ways that people
have approached this problem and you can
see why it's a tricky problem
the reason it's a tricky problem is
because you are inherently trying to
sort of compress down the information in
a very sort of flexible broad space
gameplay is a very flexible broad thing
you typically want everything to be able
to happen everywhere except when you
don't right and so it's this very weird
mix of like oh I did want that being
fire but not if the guy has this thing
and oh there should be this rule that if
two things are on fire an extra so they
should do this and and OH
fire effects health and health effects
fire right so you kind of have this
really crazy space of just it's whatever
the human imagination that was designing
the game wanted to have happen no matter
how crazy and theoretically unsound for
any other particular reasons those
things maybe that is nonetheless what
the game design is and you need to get
it working if you would like to ship
that game as opposed to some other game
so you have this very difficult problem
of such a flexible crazy you know not
clearly delineated set of operation that
it's very very tricky to figure out the
right ways of structuring these things
cleanly so that you don't have problems
okay so let me tell you some very basic
problems that you have typically if you
do lockdown sort of things in in you
know in various ways so for example
let's say I was going to do a struct
necro this way okay it would be very
very fast to process this truck necro
for any four
any code that was specific to how a
necro worked it'd be pretty easy to
write that code here because the
compiler knows exactly where those
things are it doesn't have to get them
from anywhere you can just do what it
needs to do and it's nice compiled C
code you know it's gonna be really fast
okay but compare that something like
this where every time I want to talk
about some aspect of it I gotta go go to
a table right so I want to press this
necro alright well to press the necro
the first thing I do is look up its
burnable second thing I'm gonna do is
look up its health right there's two
queries right there and then maybe I got
to do even more who knows how many a
file in a you know and you might have
ten twenty thirty properties that matter
you know it can get there can be a lot
of overhead all of a sudden in
processing one of these things because
I'm doing all these lookups but because
it's this general table system where you
can just say oh does this entity have
any of these things
well now it's completely dynamic at
runtime as well right like when I say
necromancer well maybe it started out as
a necromancer but if I wanted to add
some property that it didn't have before
like maybe I want to add you know
ballerina to it or whatever cuz it's got
you know or like ballet state which is
the state of it's like dainty dancing
all of a sudden I can because all I have
to do is well we know that if this is
something the game understands there'll
be a Balor valeria that's good let's cut
it again they'll be a ballerina table
and wow I can't I can't spell today
ballerina
there we go there'll be a ballerina
table and all I have to do is just
create a new record for whatever this
person's key is inside that table so I
can always just dynamically add
properties to any entity and that's
obviously very valuable because that
adds a lot of flexibility to the game
that wouldn't have been there if you had
to rigidly define what these trucks are
now maybe you don't care right like
maybe you're doing a game where that's
just not relevant in which case this is
not a win but you can see why it might
be a win because if you want that
flexibility for things to be sort of
mutable you have that that sort of need
there right
so yeah and of course this system
already explained the downsides of this
systems just you know I don't really
think anyone really takes that serious
anymore but you know you've got systems
like these sorts of things and that's
sort of one example of how those might
work another way that those might work
is you can imagine doing something
another sort of transmission on this
where it's like okay I don't want to go
this route but I do want to have the
EULA dynamically add stuff so maybe
instead of having these be wrote in here
I have like a prop list in here instead
and I just add props to this array or
whatever it is right so all that stuff
is eminently possible there's you know
various ways we could store it etc etc
so what I thought we would do on a
handmade hero because I think this is
probably one of the more interesting
parts if that makes sense is I think we
should just do a new entity system one
that as far as I know and no one's ever
done before and that way we can sort of
see well okay what is it like to create
one of these from scratch what are the
trade-offs what do we do well and what
don't we do well and how did it come out
and so you can sort of see that from
first principles and I think that would
be pretty cool and since it forms the
backbone of the entire game experience
it's something that's worth spending
time on and worth you know being a major
part of the development process of
handmade hero because it's what will
drive everything in the game as far as
logic is concerned right okay so I'm
gonna introduce this concept and like I
said I don't know of anyone ever having
done this before doesn't mean no one has
a lot of times in development or in
programming in general you'll find that
just because you do something from
scratch and you've never heard of it and
even if many people you know haven't
heard of it that doesn't mean that
someone somewhere hasn't done it maybe
they just didn't tell anyone
or maybe you just didn't hear about it
I'm gonna do something and there are a
number of reasons why this is a
absolutely crazy idea but I'm gonna do
it anyway I'm gonna do something I call
the sparse entity system oh wow
Franklin what's happened there sparse
entity system and what this thing is is
it was my way of trying to come up with
sort of a different way of looking at
entities that preserved all of the speed
of how you would write code in C to deal
with stuff when you know what you are
dealing with but still have all the
benefits of having entities that can do
anything and become anything in any way
right and so this is what I came up with
and it's kind of a crazy idea
but the only way you know whether idea
is truly crazy or not is to try it and
see if it works and if it works it
wasn't that crazy so here's how it works
first I would like to say a little bit
about inheritance because there's
something about inheritance that I say
often and people look at me kind of
funny but it's it's like obviously true
I think so I don't think it's like
contentious I think I just don't often
take the time to explain it and it's not
the way people maybe think about it
normally so I'm just gonna say it here
because it bears on what I'm about to
say with smarts any system so
inheritance is this concept that if
you're a C++ programmer you've come to
understand as meaning something
relatively specific and now it doesn't
necessarily mean something quite that
specific in the general operating
context but either way we can use this
as sort of a point something to get the
point across and what that is is
inheritance is sort of like saying well
I've got this struct right and I'm gonna
call it foo and in that struct I have an
integer
X
and I know that anytime I've got this
integer X that there are some things
that I might want to do on that integer
X right so I have algorithms that depend
on this integer X and maybe to make it a
little bit more realistic typically you
know we're gonna be bundling something
so we have an integer X and then we've
got some other thing here which is like
a boolean I might as well use my types
on s 32x and ab32
which is like you know is it fat is it
fatty right is it is it kind of like a
bloated thing so I've got these two
pieces of information here and then I've
written these algorithms right that
depend on those two things being
together so X and fat are both supposed
to be there and then I can write things
in CC lets me write things very cleanly
in ways that understand this so I can do
something like you know make a function
called D fatty Phi which takes one of
these things in right here's my foo and
this D FATA Phi is gonna do something
like if you know the foo X is you know
less than 10 then we'll just just a
state from now on that the fat is is not
fat anymore okay now again I know this
looks really simple but I really want
you to think about what is going on here
because it's very very important and
it's the cornerstone of understanding a
lot of how architecture actually works
at a low level okay there is no
difference in terms of actual what we
are doing theoretically right between
writing D fat if I like this and writing
D fat off' i in the equivalent way like
this
okay
oops
does that make sense now you can see it
how it looks there right and on the left
side we have something where we pass in
a foo and we're going to say if the X in
the foo is less than 10 then set the fat
in the food to false but the logic and
what this function does change is not at
all if I were to just pass a pointer to
an X and a pointer to a fat right now
what has happened when I do this
operation when I go from here to here is
I've made this function more flexible
right because now it can operate on any
pair of X and fat instead of having to
operate on ones that were right next to
each other okay
so in a sense this is an optimization of
this
it's an optimization in two ways first
it optimizes our ability to semantically
write the program because now it takes
us less time if we know that we often
have X's and fats occurring together in
a meaningful way now we can use that foo
everywhere instead which saves us typing
and keeps our code more organized and
reduces the errors we might make right
but it also helps the compiler optimize
because now it knows well I can just
pass one pointer and know that there's a
fixed offset for getting from the food
from the X and the fat right and so I
can do less work in the resulting
machine code to accomplish the same
operation okay so this is more
cumbersome and slower potentially right
it's both of these things potentially
then this is and so typically we prefer
this even though this is more powerful
right it can do more things because
instead of I only have to call it with a
foo you could do it this way and so this
function there'd be times when you have
to bundle these things together pass
them in and then unbundle them on the
way out right it can
do the other operations that this can do
necessarily without essentially writing
all this pre and post amble write very
very obvious like I said there's nothing
particularly interesting happening here
I just wanted to get that out so you can
see that right so now inheritance is
essentially the same sort of
understanding if I am now to say that I
would like to inherit from struct foo
and I would like to make a struct bar
all right then obviously what I could do
with really no loss of generality or
anything else is I could just make a
food pointer here that says well there's
a foo right or it better yet I could
just contain the flu entirely myself
right and then anytime I actually want
to use this this foo I just take the
address of it right and I pass it
through to the person who wants to use
it right so I can call all the things
that I would have called on bar on the
foo and that will just work okay now
when I do this I typically presumably
want to add some more information here
so maybe I add a real 32 here which is
like you know swim pee it's half scrimpy
the thing is right you know is it
particularly swim pee I don't know maybe
there's a zero to one number that's a
swim penis right so I'm going to add
that in here and so now what we're going
to do is say well all right if you look
at what happens when I try to you know
when I try to construct this it starts
to become a little bit cumbersome for me
because now every time I have to call
Dee fat if I on one of these bars I have
to take the address of the foo inside it
in order to call it right and that's
kind of annoying so really all I want
the compiler to do here for me it's just
could you do that automatically you know
that foo is the first thing in there
right and so if you knew foo was the
first thing you could just go ahead and
pass the same pointer because a pointer
to a bar and a pointer to foo are the
same thing they always have a flue at
the top right and so inheritance was
just saying oh okay you know well if I
have a bar I
want to be able to say that it's got a
public foo inside of it right
that's probably should be lowercase
there it's got a foo and then I only
define the new things here right and now
the compiler knows Oh anytime someone
was expecting one of these I can just
pass you know it regularly and it'll
just work so it's all good okay and the
reason that happened is because we
preserved the condition that we needed
to do the optimization just like here we
know the relative offsets of things from
the base pointer so everything can just
be compiled with that knowledge in place
right there's no difference we could
have just stuck with this and every time
we want to call D phat affiance
something passed those pointers to the
actual internal parts that we care about
but it's just semantically much more
much easier to use the inheritance way
right and it's faster using this way
because we know where everything is
and that is why of course the base
inheritance mechanism in C++ is so rigid
and is so you might say underpowered
compared to the inheritance mechanisms
in other arbitrary to program Ed's for
example it's because it was trying to
retain this fast property of knowing
where everything was relative to the
base pointer so now let's look at
precisely why this starts to fall apart
and what it was actually doing when it
fell apart or what it was trying to
preserve when it fell apart that maybe
we don't know preserve well I don't want
a spoiler warning it too much on it
looses say let me show you some more
things all right so here are my
structures I was talking about typically
what happens now is when we start
talking about this in the more realistic
context you can start to see why
inheritance begins to break down a
little bit in the cases that we wanted
to talk about above where we were
talking about oh we've got burner bulls
we've got health we've got those sorts
of things so now if I want to start
talking about something and I wanted to
create one of these structs right like
let's say I wanted to create one of
those necros like I was talking about
well now I want to do some inheritance
here and I want to say
it's I want to use it with things that
expect you know a health thing there
right and I also want to be able to use
it with something that that supports you
know a burnable right and and there's
all these things I might want to inherit
from okay because I my way of saying
that I use functionality comes from
inheritance okay I want to be able to
grab all the functionality that I want
well this obviously starts to break down
very quickly and it's why you know this
is the multiple inheritance case right
that's very terrifying to C++
programmers because it's so wacky but
you can do it multiple inheritance is
very problematic because now you can no
longer use the trick that si was using
we can't just say well I want to be able
to pass this thing around to any
function that expected one of the things
that it it like kind of does it kind of
looks like right
it's a healable thing it's a burnable
thing it's a whatever thing I can't keep
using that trick because the trick I
used was to put it first but only one
thing can come first right and so now a
pointer to a necro is no longer also a
pointer to a health and a pointer to a
burnable and a pointer to everything
else because only one of those is
actually going to be first so yes
passing it to a health a thing that
affects health that may work because
that's the first thing let's say but
passing it to a burnable that won't work
the pointer has to be adjusted because
the burnable is in a different place
relative to that top necro pointer so
when pointers get passed they have to be
readjusted right and so now things start
to break down and it starts to be a
little more cumbersome but you can do it
right you could still do it and you
could lean on the multiple inheritance
system and try to make that work believe
me people have done it but now we get to
the final problem and the one that's
obviously just never works in C++ and
that is if we wanted to make this
dynamic if I built my whole code base
around C++ as multiple inheritance and
now I want to say
oh you know what I created a necro he
was running around and then he had the
spell cast on him that gives him this
extra property that normally doesn't
have right uh what do I do
I I can't add new inherited things to a
C++ struct at runtime right that's not a
capability that the language allows and
for a good reason
the language is a compile-time language
the inheritance is compile-time oriented
all of these things with the offsets and
the pointer fix ups that I just talked
about which have gotten much more
complicated with the multiple
inheritance all get baked into the code
so now it's it's an answer I literally
can't just choose what things I want to
add to it and expect those to work and
furthermore it wouldn't even make sense
because where in the code would it ever
be called there's there's so many
reasons why that doesn't really work
right so now comes the part about
inheritance that I want to say that
people don't usually understand when I
say it but I'm so I'm gonna say it here
what I normally say is inheritance is
compression it's a compression algorithm
and that's it that's all inheritance
it's it's strictly a compression
algorithm it doesn't do anything else
and let me tell you what I mean by that
let's say that I was to take every
possible thing that could ever be
contained in an entity right so let's
say I've got all these properties right
and I don't know how many there are
let's say there's there's 200 of them
okay let's say I was to take those and
just actually put them all in one big
struct right just they're all in there
so I just have a giant struct and
instead of anything to instead of trying
to be clever here I was just to say okay
I just have one giant struct and inside
the struct is every last property that
there is all of them right so here's you
know the what did I have I had an S 32
that was my X component I had to be 32
for the fat
I had that our 32 for the was ask
wimpiness I had the squid penis right so
I had all of these things in here down
down down atomic everything that could
possibly occur in an entity was all in
there in fact much like what we have
going on in here where I just said let's
just stuff it in there and not care
about it for now it's just anything that
anyone ever wanted is sitting there it's
giant right it's like a 64k structure or
something it's just huge well if I had
that that could be the thing that I pass
to any function because any whatever the
function was whatever it was gonna do
it'll work the stuff it's looking for is
there and furthermore it's much more
powerful than any of these because it
can actually operate across different
any two pieces or more if it wants to
grab something from the health and
something from the burnable I don't need
to make a health burnable class that's a
thing that has member functions for
those in or any of the other things I
don't need to do any of that I can just
say hey go look at the health and go
look at the burnable there alright in
this big struct right so what you're
doing when you create an inheritance
hierarchy in an object-oriented
programming language is you're just
compressing things that's all you're
doing you're doing compression on the
Struck's that you have by saying instead
of putting everything into one giant
struct I'm gonna take just the sub
configurations that I believe actually
ever get used in the program that I need
to actually talk about I'm gonna take
just those and make those out of the
inheritance hierarchy right so hey stuff
there are some things that have an X of
fat in ask Wimpy so that's why we had a
foo in a bar underneath it right and
there's other people who need just ask
wimpy so we made one of those but
there's never somebody who needs a you
know I don't know like
carrot top and ask wimpy so that never
occurred together and we just don't have
that right so essentially if you imagine
all of the data right so if you imagine
this is all the data that could possibly
occur and maybe we could even we could
even take this into the theoretical
realm and just say even if that means it
is infinite meaning it doesn't even
matter how big it is every possible
configuration of stuff that could occur
we've made it so that it can all coexist
together in a giant struct if we took
that and we specialized it by just
picking out the ones the combinations we
actually ever use that is what an
inheritance hierarchy is doing right to
the data now we can talk about
dispatches separate and dispatch is just
a function the glorified function
pointer so hopefully there's going to be
too much talk about that but that's what
we're actually doing to the data so data
wise inheritance is just a compression
algorithm it lets you not store a ton of
stuff you don't need that is it right
now this is where the sort of object
oriented programming lunacy comes in
because a lot of people would be like
well you know it's it's it's good
programming to like high data that isn't
necessary from other functions mostly
like okay if that's your thing you know
go away I don't want to hear from you
like go have your weird party over in
la-la land
assuming that you actually care about
what the CPU is actually doing at the
end of the day this the thing that
inheritance actually was gonna do for
you was it was going to make it so that
you aren't storing data that you don't
actually need to store which isn't
necessarily a waste of time right that's
important again for cash concerns and
all this stuff even if we don't care
because we have plenty of actual memory
which we don't always have either you
know we care about the footprint of
things and that is what inheritance lets
us do but it comes at that very specific
drawback of having a very hard time
mixing things in
very ways because we have to pre declare
all the different mixed kinds that we
might want rather than just letting them
happen organically at runtime we have to
care about that right and now
opportunity to program programming
languages that are dynamic and that
aren't like C++ in that compile time way
they obviously take a speed hit but they
get around this problem by saying well
we'll still keep the idea of having that
sort of inheritance kind of crazy thing
but now we'll just let you decide who
derive from it run time or do other
things like that that get around that
problem of having to decide everything
at the outset right okay so my idea for
this ridiculous enemy system that's the
one that I the third of the architecture
I want to try first is to do exactly
this so what I want to do is I want to
make a struct entity and this struct is
going to be epically huge okay it is
going to have everything in it like so
64 K think yeah it is a 64 K entity
struct maybe more okay it is really
really really really large epically huge
that's actually gonna be what it is and
what we're gonna do is we're just gonna
say alright look we know that we can't
possibly have every entity in the game
taking up 64 K all the time and
furthermore we don't really want to
process 64 K worth of any data all the
time but we already know that the
structure of our game involves sim
regions we simulate a region where we
load everything up and then we simulate
it and we put it all back right that's
already how it works so that we can pull
things into a common unified euclidean
space do some stuff and then put it back
right so my idea is well let's make a
thing that has everything in it that's
the over entity it's a
has all the possible properties it has
everything it's the most ridiculous
think you know binding of issac after 17
hours and it's got all this crazy stuff
on it can do everything it's it's
everything that everything could
possibly be that is what this is and
what we do is when we go to start
simulating we do a decompress to get
this entity structure and then we do a
compress when we're done so what happens
is we decompress out of a storage
basically our - like cold storage if you
will into our MV structure we then
compress the energy structure back out
when we go to store it and what this
will be is we've got this sort of you
know we've got this these world chunks
and what this will be is essentially a
streaming system well swim a bunch of
entities and then we'll go which
entities fall into this you know we're
writing them out to a world chunk we
open up the world chunk we write out all
the entities by compressing them in okay
and then that world chunk is closed and
it's stored right when we then want to
simulate that world chunk we open it
back up again and we decompress them out
okay now what do I mean by compress and
decompress well I don't mean try to run
like LZ on them or anything although
maybe that's a smarter way to do it
than what I'm thinking I don't even
really know it could be that that's
actually quite a good idea for all I
know like some kind of simple compressor
and we'll see when we start testing
things what I mean is more like and the
reason I called it sparse mate as far as
entity is because I'm thinking more like
a sparse matrix solver so basically this
entity has a bunch you know maybe it's
got you know a thousand things in it
right a thousand properties or something
well what I want to do is basically just
mark off which one of them's which ones
of them we decompressed and then when we
simulate the end of the we mark any ones
that we've added and we D mark ones that
we remove and then when we compress we
only look through we only grab those
ones that are actually there make sense
now you may be asking why do this right
why try this it sounds like it's
strictly worse than just keeping a list
of property
sort of like this sort of a system up
here that I talked about right here why
not just put those things into a list
and forgo this whole sort of operation
well the reason is because now all of
the simulation code right the simulation
code that's going to access this all of
this simulation code just gets written
in straight C style where it knows the
offsets of everything it can be written
at full speed it doesn't have to do any
lookups it's based and it has free rein
to do whatever it wants any single piece
of simulation code can pull it doesn't
have to go oh
does it have a health property doesn't
have a burnable property okay well if it
adds both of those properties it doesn't
do any of that stuff it can just ask
directly by literally looking up into
the thing and just grabbing out what it
is right that's the idea and again this
mirror is basically what a sparse matrix
solver does as far as matrix solver says
well I've got this big array potentially
in in memory of what this matrix is and
I may actually store the whole matrix
right like I may say that I actually
have like memory reserve for let's say
64,000 entries this way and 64,000
entries this way right but I actually
only go poke in certain values and I
remember where those values actually
were and then later when I want to store
this matrix out again I just grab out
just the ones that I know that I put in
there right but because I've done that
anybody who wants to do something like
oh what's my symmetric element can still
just do a direct look up on the - you
know the M and n you know the tooth on J
indices of this matrix can still do
direct lookups and get exactly the value
right back out again right so everything
still full speed when you're looking at
the matrix itself but when you unpack
and pack it you're only looking at those
specific cherry-pick values right so
that's the idea and so that's what I
would like to play with I would like to
make a little thing we'll go take our
world chunks will actually make them
some storage will have a decompress step
and an entity structure and then will
have a compressed step and will have it
so that there's just a giant entity
thing that has every last thing we want
our enemies to have and that way there
are no limitations on what an entity can
be if you have a tree and you want to
start walking around no problem if
somebody casts the walking thing on it
it just becomes a walking tree because
anything that you could have done like
walking or hopping or shooting or
punching or jumping or anything else
they're all just properties of the same
entity and you know that they all you
know operate on the same strike so it's
always free to just go ahead and turn on
whatever the thing is that you want on
any entity ever anywhere right which
basically gives us the complete
flexibility to have the game design do
whatever it wants right and I think that
is really the goal of this particular
part of the of the game so that's what
I'm gonna try and I can't say ahead of
time whether it will work because I've
never tried it before I can't think of
any immediate reason why it might not
work
I mean why it wouldn't work but I can't
think of reasons why it might not work
for example the traffic for this
decompressed compress might be too great
right the memory footprint for storing
you know however many 500 of these might
be too big right maybe that's too much
I don't know that cache concerns are
really such a big deal they might be I'm
not sure but since we're only touching
it sparsely it's not like we're ever
actually touching the 64k unless we
actually need to use all of it there is
a some false sharing problems because
you know things are not packed tightly
so we do lose some cache throughput but
not as much as not nearly much as you
might think because again we're not
touching the whole city for K or
anything so it's hard to say so there
definitely are reasons why I think it
might not work but nothing that's an
obvious red flag where I'm like it's I
wouldn't try it and so we will try it
that's about it for today I'm glad I got
that all explained I wasn't necessary
planning on explaining that today but
now I did means we can start on tomorrow
which is nice I will see if I can go
ahead and start the Q&amp;A here
xD a FAL can you talk about the dynamic
dispatch yes I can certainly talk about
the dynamic dispatch so so what are we
what are we trying to trying to find the
place Rev run's okay so what are we
trying to do with dispatch okay so
hopefully data data is the part I
actually cared about and this the part
that's relevant to the suggestion so I
skipped dispatch but I'll talk about
dispatch briefly see what dispatch is is
saying okay I want a way to associate a
function with a memory location that is
essentially what dispatch is right
because normally what happens is the
other way around I call a function and I
pass it some data this is a case where I
have some data and I want it to tell me
the function right that's that's sort of
what we're talking about here
so the typical case right is you know
going back to our foods and bars if I
have a struct foo and I have a struct
bar then it's very simple for me
obviously to write some code and that
code looks like you know do foo and it
takes a foo and does something and then
I have a function that's called a do bar
and that takes to something right
probably make that it be so we call
these in code and anywhere at the point
where we're gonna call it it's a fixed
thing right it's like at the point where
we might call one of these we know which
one we're calling we're calling do foo
or do bar and we're passing it a foo or
a bar right but at some point we may
want to say okay instead of me telling
you at this location in the call write
it so I'm at some point in the program I
call my do foo at that point in the code
maybe I don't want to know which
function I'm actually calling I know I
want to call a claw family of functions
I know I want to call the do family
right I want to do something but what I
want to do is going to be based on the
the memory location I'm talking about so
if this memory location happens to exist
over here that I want to do one thing if
it's this other one over here I want to
do this other thing
etc and so forth right and so what I
will do right if I'm writing this myself
is I will just add a function pointer
okay and so what I might do and I can
even say that this I don't even need bar
for this part of this example if I can
just say okay in here there's some
function pointer and the function
pointer is whatever the do is for this
foo and so now I can just say oh all
right if I have a foo I can psych foo
arrow do and I can pass itself to it and
off I go right what this has now let me
do is this has let me associate a
function with a particular block of
memory so this this storage the actual
data now also has information about how
it might be processed under certain
circumstances right and you've seen us
do this in a couple different places in
hand-made here are actually well may or
not a couple but at least two maybe
that's a couple and so you know once in
a while you do want this it's not that
it's not as common in fear a new plan
that's all over the place right but it's
not that common really in real code
it's not super important but there are
times when it is necessary right or or
it is appropriate so that's what this is
let me do now obviously I may want to do
something where now I've got two
different types okay
they have different information in them
this one has an r32 right here's my
value this one has a be 32 and here's my
value and so I want to now not even know
which one of these two I'm talking about
right well now I can actually still use
this because even if the thing was a bar
and I thought it was a foo it doesn't
matter because it's the first element in
the structure I'll still call the do and
if the do happens to be a function here
that takes a bar where little call the
right function and don't think it's a
bar and do the right thing so I can
actually I don't really have to do very
much to make this work if I wanted to
but you know you get the idea
okay so basically at this point once I
settle on the standard of I'm gonna put
the function pointer at the top of the
thing then what I need to process it I
just call that function pointer now it's
free for me to create as many of these
as I want with all sorts of different
data in them and anybody who needs to
invoke do on them can do so trivially
because all they do is look at the first
thing in it and they invoke that on it
and off they go right and if they don't
have to ever care what type they were
actually handed they know how to call
that
that thing right okay so that's dynamic
dispatch in the basic sense now C++ for
reasons that nobody understands right
and I have no idea why I wish I could go
back in time and or maybe ask somebody
be like what were you thinking they
picked the worst possible way to
implement this that I think anyone
probably ever has I mean maybe you could
find a language that implemented it
worse than this I don't know but what
they decided as well okay this is a sort
of thing that programmers will do
programmers often will create function
pointers and they'll put function
pointers into two structures so that
when they are going to use that
structure they can call the function
pointer now remember there are many many
different things we could have done here
right
and I'd like to tell you what they all
are first of all just just so you can be
aware of exactly how bad C++ this
implementation of it is and this again
has nothing to do with object-oriented
programming this is literally a problem
with C++ specifically and that is
several things I could have one
structure right or I can have two
structures they can have one pointer or
they could have two right and maybe this
guy has them as well okay so we can have
multiple structures we can have multiple
functions in the structures that we
might call write multiple met you you
know these are like methods in C++ or
whatever or member functions I should
say right could have multiple of those
there's many things that we might do
what C++ decided was the only one you
were ever going to get to do because for
some reason they just couldn't conceive
that there were others or they didn't
know or they had never programmed a
computer before I don't know they
decided that you only got one of these
and what it was was you could have a
bunch of functions in a static table
right it's a table somewhere off in the
distance and the only thing you get is
at the top of a thing you get a pointer
to one of these tables that's it now in
doing that they gave up a tremendous
amount of functionality oh and by the
way you don't ever get to see this
pointer can't change it it's not there
as far as you know now in choosing to
implement it that way they basically
lost almost all of the power of dynamic
dispatch the actual dynamic dispatch
support you get in C++ is the weakest
possible dynamic dispatch you could ever
imagine right you cannot change anything
about it at runtime at all right so for
example if I wanted to when I have this
old way what if I implement it by hand
I can set due to whatever I want
whenever I want I want to change this
particular one I could change it right
make sense so any given object can
change what it's due function was at any
time dynamically that is a great feature
gone completely gone in C++ forget it
can't add that right I can furthermore
change things independently right so I
could say oh I want to change its other
pointer but not its due pointer so I'm
going to change only one of his member
functions rather than both of them for
example that's double gone because
everything's in a table in the C++
version so I can't do that either right
you can't touch the table pointer and
furthermore if I did want to implement
it this way so let's say I did a flip
teal pointer but at least I put the
table pointer in there then I could at
least switch the type of the object
between tables at runtime I can even do
that right
technically I can by going around the
C++ spec and not worrying about breaking
stuff because I could just go in and
rewrite the table pointer manually but
technically to the original spec of C++
when they designed it back in the day in
the 80s or whenever you can't do any of
those things so you lose all of the
power of dynamic dispatch completely
goes away in C++ you get the weakest
possible kind right and again what did
it see it seems like what they cared
about which is not probably what they
were cognitively thinking but it ended
up being that compression is really the
only thing they got this is the most
compressed way this could possibly work
really is having the table pointer point
to a static table because then any two
instances of an object don't need to
have a whole table of function pointers
they each just point to that table
however all the things you give up for
that are myriad right it's slower
because you got a double dereference
everything whatever you're gonna jump
it's less flexible because you can't set
it per object if you want to right and
furthermore they made the weird decision
of not letting you ever touch that table
pointer which is absolutely ridiculous
right now if you don't want to expose
the table pointer directly okay that's
one thing but at least give us some
built-in functions that can switch like
what's in the table or what the tail is
pointing to like that would be pretty
obviously right that you would do and
they didn't even do that right
so the C++ dynamic dispatch is a
complete complete complete waste really
really bad I don't know why anyone ever
uses it but it's for some reason they
still do so
if you actually want dynamic dispatch I
highly recommend doing it this way
meaning I would just make it yourself
because it's so much more powerful you
can do so many more things with it that
I don't know what that this simple
syntactic sugar of not having to
actually put the function pointer in
there doesn't seem to me to be enough of
a reason to give it up but you know I
don't know different people I guess have
different preferences but so the dynamic
dispatch that they are talking about is
literally just the kind that can be
derived from one of these hierarchies
and that is the like sort of baked at
that compile time but that is not really
very useful dynamic dispatch in my mind
dynamic dispatch is much better handled
by saying what is my program actually
need from this dispatch what matches
that most directly for example maybe I
have only one type of strap maybe I
don't even have multiple types of trucks
but I do have multiple types of
operations well then I want dynamic
dispatch just like a function pointer in
there right or a couple function pairs
in there maybe I do have lots of
different types and maybe they all have
the same kind of dispatches between them
so I'm going to use that like a table
based method but I'd like to be able to
switch them at runtime because sometimes
I want this object to have these sorts
of just practices sometimes I want to
have these other types of just answers
right then I'm going to use that table
pointer scheme right Ambala and only if
you're actually talking about a
completely immutable table based you
know system that operates on a hierarchy
would you ever use C++ is dispatch which
is never
I don't know when you use that you don't
as far as I know so yeah in our system
we are not going to use dynamic dispatch
probably at all and here's why the
reason that I don't probably want to use
much dynamic dispatch is because
entities in our system again I'm going
for that really rich bizarreness kind of
an entity system I don't ever want to
define what an entity is I don't want to
say this entity is the hero this entity
is this type of villain what I want to
do is say this entity has this set of
parameters strewn throughout the 64k
thing and when I render it I draw from
those parameters to come up with this
visual representation
but at no time do I actually want to
know what it is because if at any time I
lock it down and say this is this
subclass of this thing with this pointer
to this function suddenly I've lost the
ability to have that fluid weird like
mutability and I'm just I'm going for
mutability first in this one I want
everything to be miscible I want every
ending the game to be able to turn into
any other type of entity I want every
property we ever glommed on every other
property I just want to be the complete
most flexible thing possible and I'm
willing to give up other things I'm
willing to for the code to be harder to
write I'm willing for it to be difficult
to debug I'm willing for it to be slow
if it has to be I will optimize those
things and work those things if I can
get that sort of holy grail of
everything is super weird and dynamic
and unchangeable right so I want to try
and do the system that way and so you
know maybe there are some cases where
function pointers make some sense there
but I think more likely what we'll be
using is a lot of enums and then to
figure out what we're gonna do we'll
look at a couple different enums and say
oh you know what type of walking does
this entity do oh it's this and like
what type of this is do okay grab those
together and then say oh they're not
probably you know I should draw some
legs on here or maybe I should do this
right and so I want to kind of make it
so that it can look at multiple things
where as a function pointer you don't
usually test function parsers I mean as
you could but it's more like I want to
take multiple piece of information and
use that to synthesize who we call and
so that's going to be more logic based
and probably less function point based
popcorn do you use the struct entry
method in your current game my current
game does not have any entities
kind of scroll down to the cue Collins
SSS McGrath have you seen my pseudo
hacked discriminated Union inheritance
system that I use in my game on stream
it's pretty cool no I haven't but I like
discriminated unions as you can tell
from the fact that like 99% of the
things in handmade here are
discriminated unions so I'm probably in
favor of whatever it is you're doing but
I don't know what it is at the moment
but I would probably like it I guess is
what I'm saying what made you choose
this approach over an AO s style Plus
story indices of each separate component
in the main entity struct okay so
basically the reason that I didn't want
to do that is because I want all of the
code to have hardwired offsets like I
want it to just be straight C code fully
optimizable by the compiler to just go
in and grab what it needs and do its
stuff on a flat piece of memory always
if that makes sense
Juden basement I missed it what about
the matrix IJ I was confused there so
what I was saying there is that it's
essentially like if you think of how
matrix operations work a lot of times
matrix operations need to look at
particular elements like what's one
above me or what's my reflected element
in this matrix right and if you have
sparse storage for your matrix that just
says where those things are then either
you have to constantly do lookups in
there or you have to scan one or the
other and they're both very slow so
instead sometimes what you would do in
the old days and this is less true
potentially now but what you do in the
old days is you would just say oh I'll
just make a big block of memory and I'll
put things in there and I'll basically
like initialize it all to zero once and
then all the operations I do I'll just
put things in there and then remember to
take them back out again when I'm done
so that I can always do direct lookups
right it's kind of like a perfect hash
table for the matrix entries in that
sense parsnip how and where would you go
about checking if a property existed on
your mega struct whenever you want to do
your operations with the allbeing
they'll present undefined so there's
none of them are pointers it's actually
the data for the property so the whole
all the data is actually in there and
they're all just initialized to there
this thing isn't happening State so if
it's like how on fire am i it's zero
right and so then when you go to to ask
how much fire is there you always get
back the answer whether it's on fire or
not it's got a value in there that says
that that makes sense
tea Terrace what are you going to use to
track which strecht members have been
touched
/ setback - no to be honest I'm not sure
yet I need to do some testing probably
during development depending on the
speed of it
I may not meaning I may just always
actually scan so you just actually walk
the full 64k which is going to be slow
right or I mean I don't know it's gonna
be slow because who computers are so
fast these days it's going to be slower
than it would be and then when we sort
of get further down and we're worried
about potentially optimizing things then
I will think about based on what we have
how I want to go about making it so that
we track
Jesse Meyer what portions of this design
could you foresee causing pur issues
well like I said the fall sharing is
probably the single biggest concern and
what I mean by that is you know if if
well let's tart with this so basically
you can think of a struct as being
broken up into 64 byte chunks okay so
here is my struct entity and then we
start listing the members in here and
I'm just gonna make stuff up but let's
say I've got you know a v3 position
right and I've got an r32 alpha I don't
know why right and an r32 you know
movement T or whatever and as you start
to add these up right you start to get a
sense of how big they are right this is
four bytes this is three times four
bytes right so that's 16 bytes right
there and so then you know you could
imagine if this is 16 bytes here imagine
some other blocks here here's another 16
and maybe here's 32 bytes so here's a 64
byte chunk okay and then after that's
another 64 byte chunk maybe there's I
don't know why there's a there's a name
field here that's 16 bytes long I don't
know why we would have that but we do
all of a sudden and then we have like a
bitmap ID and that's more so we just
have imagine just lots of 64 byte chunks
okay that is how the cache to a first
approximation sees this entity right now
there's all sorts of things like
aliasing and all there there's a whole
host of issues that are like super
complicated crazy things but to a first
approximation if you want to know how
cache friendly this entity is that's
what you're thinking about inside every
block of 64 bytes if we are to touch one
of these during processing we have to
bring all 64 bytes into the cache right
so if I want just the T value and that's
all I use in this particular entity none
of these other things are valid now why
that would be I have no idea cuz I was
in peas gonna be Valhalla but pretend
that was true right all I wanted to
touch was this T
well that's four bites but I actually
had to touch sixty extra bites that I
didn't use so what that means is
depending on how our structures
organized and depending on how the
sparseness works out in depending
depending depending we could have a lot
of extra memory bandwidth getting used
that is not actually doing anything
right it's wasted and so it's a gamble
right you don't know maybe that's okay
because most of the time you are able to
pack things well that they happen to
work out so you don't waste too much
memory maybe it's horrific and you're
oftentimes getting into this sort of
nightmare scenario it's really hard to
say and so that's certainly one huge
reason why I don't think it's a
slam-dunk of an idea by any stretch of
the imagination because it's like well
there's a pretty clear reason why you
know this could be bad fortunately it's
the kind of could be bad thing that is
not super dangerous because entity
processing in this way you know how many
entities are there going to be well
there's not going to be a hundred
thousand entities on the screen and this
is processing for the things that we
actually see and immediately around it
right so we don't have to worry about a
processing a hundred thousand entities
at 60 frames a second right but we
probably have to worry about processing
like 300 entities at 60 frames a second
maybe right or at least 30 frames a
second so you know it's still it's it's
not so few you know there are certain
games that have so you know let's say it
was Street Fighter right well there's
like two you know maybe miles morning to
but you know how many eighties are there
really gonna be 10 20 not very many so
you wouldn't care it would not matter
but you know as that number gets up to a
couple hundred or even if it's a
thousand right you're starting to get a
little nervous because now it's like
well if I blow half two thirds of my
memory bandwidth they're pulling these
things in that's kind of uncomfortable
potentially right so I don't know so
we'll see
we'll see I don't think it's dangerous
enough that I don't want to try it but
it's definitely not safe enough that I'm
happened that I'm comfortable saying oh
it won't be any problem don't worry
about it like we won't have to worry at
all be great you know it's two kids
could still go wrong
Connor rents what are some alternatives
to an entity system well there is really
no alternative to an entity system if
the game has entities in a sense that no
matter how non system E it is you still
have one I mean you know if you went
back to maybe pac-man or something like
this then you could say well there's no
any system right there's just some
specific code where you know you've got
an array of like four ghosts and you are
gonna do a third thing to each one of
them and each ghost that certain thing
you can still call that an ende system
right and it has two types ghosts and
pac-man or whatever right or you know
those sorts of things so you know I mean
any action game like that has an entity
system because it is inherently about a
bunch of discrete things that you know
shoot at each other or touch each other
and do something and so pretty much the
basis of any traditional action game in
that sense is going to be an entity
system now if you're doing something
else right you know maybe you're doing
something like a walking simulator where
nothing happens right it's called
nothing happens the game which there are
a lot of on steam maybe you don't need
one because maybe the it's about
something else and so really there's
just a huge static world and you don't
ever have this notion of entities that's
not a thing right or maybe you're making
a game like we are 1935 at Mali rocket
it's you know it looks and plays kind of
like a movie and your interaction is
about interacting with a dialogue well
entities aren't a thing anymore right
it's not an there's no nobodies
we don't do collision detection to find
out if two entities interacted with each
other right like none of that is
happening it's about you know a very
different thing so you can see why that
would be presumably
well that would be presumably not
necessary in certain titles Allen
Webster are you already thinking of a
back-up plan for the entities and how
you would transition to that system if
you had to know because you know
typically speaking whatever we write if
there is a problem with it we will see
that problem occur and have a measure of
it like if it's the cash problem or if
it's something else and what the problem
is and where it's occurring will
presumably drive our solution in how we
will modify the system to avoid that
right so you know it's like I said it's
not we're not going for super high
throughput here this game is not about
processing as many and as easy as
possible so I'm not really that worried
that we wouldn't be able to solve it at
all with something in the ballpark of
this right but what it will exactly look
like by the end I don't know because I
just don't know exactly how some of
those trade-offs will play out so
alright looks like we're done um do I
play Street Fighter who is your favorite
character uh no I do not play play
Street Fighter I was always a Mortal
Kombat guy I really liked Mortal Kombat
1 I've never liked any of the subsequent
Mortal Kombat's although I only played
two and three or something I never
played any beyond that so I don't know
but I really really liked the original
Mortal Kombat I never really liked the
original Street Fighter or Street
Fighter 2 or any of the subsequent
follow-ons
you know what kind it's what it is
really is
I don't like animation pause I can't
handle it I can't handle animation pause
you know when like when like somebody
like uppercut somebody and it freezes
and then it continues
having that in a fighting game ruins
bunningham I can't play it so it was
always a bit of a rough thing for me and
I just didn't like the feel of Street
Fighter for whatever reason so I
couldn't get couldn't get into it which
is too bad because that was the more
popular one so we used to play at the
arcades I used to like playing you know
versus other people and I used to play
against other people in world comment
one all the time but there just weren't
enough people it was very easy in my
hometown and surrounding areas to be the
best person at Mortal Kombat 1 let me
tell you that right now
whereas it probably would not have been
as easy to be the best Street Fighter
I'm guessing because more people would
would have been playing that well the
enemy system include things such as
particle effects no part of the VEX are
a graphical effect that typically get
launched so the enemy system would spawn
particle effects but it's not going to
process them because they're very
specialized and designed for very high
throughput and they typically don't have
on they don't have mutable property
that's like okay if this is a thing that
like spawned some fire then the fire
just particle spawn up it doesn't like
those don't change to water in like of
their own accord somebody like reaches
in from somewhere else and makes that
change right
do you play bomberman these are not on
topic people you can't stand this sweet
fritter pause but you like the Myrtle
count Rose cape no I didn't like the
Mortal Kombat rotoscope either well
first of all snot rotoscope it's just
it's actually just video but I like the
fact that it doesn't pause right because
that affects the feel the look is a
separate from the feel right and I
didn't I don't like the look of either
game I think both games are not good
looking really but if I had to pick one
obviously streetfighters better looking
the Mortal Kombat I think certainly but
I don't really like the look of either
but I like the feel of Mortal Kombat
better because it doesn't have that
pause I could never get past that pause
drove me nuts so yeah
oh and as far as I'm just grabbing a
thing I know this wasn't a question but
someone was saying it does seem unlikely
that you get 300 undies meaning 60
frames a second simulation and you know
it's yes and no because again the whole
world in this game is kind of made out
of entities in some sense like each
ground element will be an entity so you
know if there's you know let's say that
we're doing a 17 by 9 tile well there's
gonna be something like you know if
there's two entities on every tile the
tile itself and then something standing
on it well that's three hundred and six
entities right there right and maybe
they've each got a bullet so you know I
could see 600 entities being a
reasonable entity load for this game and
I wouldn't want to necessarily say that
we shouldn't have that many that that's
too many so I would say like you know I
will probably want to stress test this
with a thousand IVs at 60 frames a
second so you know if we're talking
about oops if we're talking about 60,000
entities or something like that then
doing the back of the envelope like
three times a thousand times a thousand
times a thousand so if let's say it's a
three gigahertz machine or something and
I want 60 frames a second and I want to
have 600 or sorry a thousand of these
you know that's not very many cycles
right that's just not that many cycles
now thankfully I've got multiple cores
to play with potentially but still it's
just it's it's you know it's it's
something to be nervous about I guess
it's what I would say since this is GPU
accelerated you know we don't have a lot
of work to do graphics wise so that's
good but 50,000 cycles per entity is is
not a it's not a abundance right it's
not like so much that you'd never be
worried about anything going wrong in it
so you know it's it's you know yeah
we'll see well we'll see what happens
all right so my understanding is I don't
actually have to do anything here
because this actually just saves itself
which is kind of awesome so I'm gonna go
ahead and close these guys down and see
here thank you everyone for joining me
for another episode of hand made here
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with the series at home you can always
pre-order it on handmade hero org using
this handy dandy button and it comes to
source code so you can play around with
it yourself we also have a forum site
you can go to if you want to ask
questions we have a patreon page you can
use if you want to support video series
and we have a schedule bot which will
announce the schedule so that if you're
trying to get the series live you know
what it is finally we have a episode
guide if you're trying to catch up with
videos in this series from the past that
is a great place to go and and check
those out that is about it that that is
that is it for today I will be back here
tomorrow 5:00 p.m. Pacific Daylight Time
and we'll start taking a look probably
at implementing the entity system
exactly the way that I just said it and
seeing how that starts to to shake out
that's it for me have fun programming
everyone and I'll see you guys on the
Internet