everybody and welcome to handmade here
the sure we code a complete game live on
stream I got asked a question during the
pre stream that I kind of wanted to
record a very brief very simple answer
to I know that's uncharacteristic of me
but the question was like what high
level languages do I find interesting
and the answer generally speaking is
none and I'd like to kind of explain
just really quickly why and I think a
graph was the right way to explain it
just one of these very simple like not
really a real graph just a kind of
abstract graph but if you look at you
know what the if we were to simplify
programming languages down to just like
two ratings right which is like
performance let's say we put performance
here right so this is like a high
performance right for memory or CPU or
whatever we choose so basically for
whatever we define performance to be on
a CPU scale maybe that's not using very
much memory maybe that's being very very
fast you know whatever it is that we
want but the programmer decides what
their criteria for performance is we
would rate it here and then on this axis
we would say that we want to measure
like the amount of work that the
programmer has to put in for the you
know to finish the program actually make
the program in question and since I we
want to kind of make like going further
out is better let's say what I want to
do is call this like speed of
development right so this is basically
like over here is like I'm fast
and here is slow okay and so if you look
at something like assembly language
assembly language is like here right
so I can do anything I can make the best
program but it takes an incredibly long
time for a number of reasons one is that
it I have to manually code lots of stuff
that arguably maybe a computer could
have been doing for me including things
like instruction scheduling register
allocation things like this so you know
it takes a very very long time to
program it
but anything the CPU could do anything
the most theoretically best possible
performance for any situation I can get
it because there's nothing a computer
can do that I can't do right 100% so
what you end up with is high level
languages you know C is maybe like I
don't really know where to put it but
maybe like here let's say I'm not really
sure exactly where it goes but C is like
here somewhere high level languages all
the ones I've ever really seen they're
all like over here somewhere or over
here some of them are here which is
ridiculous but they're basically like in
this band and so there's kind of this
quadrant like up here that there's
nothing there's nothing that's like I
can do the best possible thing and be
very fast now it's worth noting that
this what I'm talking about here is for
the same program so it doesn't count to
say let's say you can write inline
assembler in your C program that doesn't
put it up here right because if as soon
as I have to write inline assembler I'm
back to this slow right I've moved
backwards so I would go back to here so
for example if you take a language you
know your language is you know rust or
something like this if it's only
actually as good as C meaning it only
really produces
same speed win in terms of development
as see when you're writing code that's
as fast to see then it's only like here
and if it added a little bit to that
then maybe you know it can go to like
here or something or there or whatever
right but I want to see this language
right I want to see the language that
allows me to construct Azzam programs
exactly the way that I think they should
be constructed but in a fraction of the
time that it would have taken me right
and I actually think this is achievable
I don't think this is a pipe dream I
think what happens is no one tries like
nobody tries to do this they sit down
oftentimes the people who make languages
don't even know this they're like people
from a university who don't actually
program the semi language very often
right if at all they aren't really sure
what the maximum performance is for most
things on their computer and only like
somewhere down the road Jews if their
language becomes popular does it get a
back end with an optimizer and stuff and
then some people are working on it who
care about this but it's too late at
that point because no one was thinking
about the design of the language right
in terms of those performance so most of
the time they're not even thinking about
this and you know you're just not
getting people who actually try I think
with multi-threading this becomes even
more important right because now we're
talking about wanting to have language
features that allow me to write like
things very easily that can be
distributed to lots of threads in the
optimal way and stuff like that again
really really important for someone to
understand what the optimal
multi-threading code looks like for a
lot of situations before they can even
think about designing that language
it can't be an afterthought you can't
add multi-threading as a secondary step
to your language that's totally not
gonna work right so I think that this is
the problem and this is why I don't tend
to like any new high-level languages is
because they they always ask me to go
further down to get further out and I
don't want to go down
I want to remain here and I want to move
this way and if I ever saw a high-level
language that actually allowed me to
move laterally I would probably start
using that language but it would have to
be reasonably far because like if I'm
only gonna get a little bit further I'm
it's not gonna be worth the effort to
switch over right so what you want is a
big lateral movement this way and you're
probably not gonna get all the way to
here because that's like the perfect
language or something right the fastest
and best or whatever but you know I
think we can get a lot further into this
quadrant that we have before so that's
my feeling about high level languages
even the name sounds dumb to me I think
as soon as you call it a high level
language you're sort of admitting defeat
to begin with I think what you want is a
high productivity low level language if
you want good software if you're just
interested in sitting around and
collecting your Series A funding or
whatever it is
do whatever you want doesn't matter
right there's way more software existing
in the world right now than there are
good programmers so it's like you know
it's a it's the type of world where you
can at the least at the moment it's
pretty easy to get by on not even
mediocrity just like poor I just I don't
even know it's easy to get to get by
without much and what what place on this
graph is jii I don't know I've never
used it it's also not done yet I mean
they're still working on it I don't know
but you know once it's ready I think
it'll it probably be pretty favorable on
that graph I don't know it's gonna get
quite as far to the other side because J
I is still more I think about producing
a language John likes to program in than
it is as a focus on performance kind of
language but in terms of high level
languages it's definitely got more
performance sensibilities than a lot of
languages that I've seen so I think that
bodes well for it but you know like I
said I've never used it so I have no
idea all right so let's get started that
was just
that you know that's just oh where is
this one that crap Lisp is is kind of
over in the other it's pretty down low
it's it's Lisp is extremely bad at
performance the reason I said this was
interesting in the pre stream was just
because it has for a very early language
it had a lot of good ideas it was like
oh okay
how can we make things very flexible so
that the programmer can produce code
directly as part of the program which
allows a lot of powerful meta
programming things to occur and
unfortunately not a lot of languages
picked up on that who weren't similarly
kind of non-performing interpreted but
you can do a lot of things with stuff
like that if you just like restrict them
maybe to compile time or if you ship
with a JIT I think those things are
important right all right so let's get
started let's do it I've been watching
there's a show on YouTube well I guess I
don't know what the show is called but
the channel is called because I don't
know if the show has a name but the the
channel is called Google I think it's GU
GAF ODS and I think it's it's this guy I
think he's Brazilian and he he does like
all these like really good like meat
tests like he's got all these like
steaks and every show he'll like do
something interesting with the steaks as
a test so like one example was he took
like four steaks and he packed them in
various like packings that people had
said would we're good for tenderizing
steaks like pineapple or just like salt
you know like different kinds of things
that people have said and then he you
know did it tested them grilled them
each and then he test the flavor right
and it's a pretty cool if you like beef
if you like meat things which I do it's
a pretty cool show you'll enjoy it you
should go check it out
but he has this really cool his voice
and I don't really it you know some of
its accent but I think most of it just
him he just has an interesting voice and
so every time right when he's about to
like do whatever the like the money shot
is like he's about to do the grip like
the fire up the grill and like put the
the super steaks on which are super
looking forward to because they're all
like oh he's beautiful he goes let's do
it he just has this really funny way of
saying it and it totally sticks in my
head you'll see when you see he has a
key he has a really good voice for four
shows I don't really but because it's
not very distinctive but but he does and
it sounds cool you'll see you'll you'll
end up you'll end up appreciating it
it's also it's just a good show he has
like I don't know if it's like his
nephew or if they're related or
something I haven't gone back and
watched like the original introduction
ones so I don't actually know but he
always has this other guy there with him
at least one other guy his name's angel
and he he doesn't tell him like what
they're doing right and so like he he's
always very like okay he's prepared this
crazy test and then he's like okay angel
like let's test it out and like it's
it's good you just go check it out watch
the show if you like beef at all watch
the show I don't know if they think
besides beef I think they do sometimes
it's just mostly they do beef and I
think because they're very popular now
it's not a it's not like some weird
small show I found it it's like it's a
very popular show I think they get um
like sponsors to send them beef now so
they get all kinds of crazy beef I think
maybe not I don't know if they actually
pay for it themselves
some of the beats very expensive but I
guess you hey you got a popular youtube
show you're probably making reasonable
ad revenue anyway all that aside let's
get started we sort of took the first
steps
Saturday I was planning to be able to
pick him Sunday but I got sick I'm still
a little bit sick but I'm mostly
recovered now my voice is not worn out
so I can do the show I wasn't like so
sick I couldn't do the show or something
in terms of like physically it was just
my throat was so aggravated that I
couldn't talk I'm still fine I could
walk around I you know good it was I
wasn't really sick sick in that sense I
just I couldn't really I wouldn't have
been able to do two hours of talking I
would have been like but anyway so what
we didn't get to do on Sunday was sort
of get started on the implementation of
what we had discussed doing on Saturday
and what that is is moving our system
over to just use light probes because I
finally realized after reading a paper
well I haven't actually read the whole
paper because I wasn't even looking at
that sort of stuff but I just wanted to
see what the answer was to something
that I thought you couldn't do and it
turns out that like basically everyone
already does this thing and it's
actually a pretty easy answer which was
just how you how you propagate light
with light probes if you don't have an
offline solution and I didn't realize it
was as simple as it was I should have
thought of it felt kind of stupid if
you're missing why I was stupid I
discuss it on Saturday streams to go
take take a look but anyway so we're
pretty much not really changing very
much about our lighting algorithm at all
we're using the exact same thing that we
were using for all intents and purposes
we're going to modify it fairly fairly
mildly today or over the next couple
weekends but the big thing that I had
wanted to always redo if I could have
done but didn't think I could was reduce
where we're sampling from and that's
what light probes are I couldn't think
of a way to do that exactly because I
didn't realize you could just sample
them at run time during the propagation
phase I don't know why that never
occurred to me it just didn't so anyway
that's all we're doing and it's gonna
take us a little while do it but because
you know lighting is complicated I
always say it's one of the hardest
things you can do in graphics so it's
gonna take a while but there's nothing
magic here you've already seen me make
the whole lighting system it works
pretty well we're just talking about
making it more efficient and so
switching to light probes one of the
things I was starting to do here and I
think we actually well actually I know
where it is it's down here so but I
think we got started on it and then I
said well we're gonna save it for
tomorrow in fact here it is
so this builds spatial partition for
lighting function and you can see that's
doing the lighting solution here uh
basically what we want to do is oh sorry
I take it back we already had that oh
yeah that's right we already had one in
there nevermind that's not the one I
wanted to talk about that one is
actually the one that we're using during
the Ray casting which we may also want
to update here but I thought we added
one for voxel izing did we not I thought
that's one thing we added in here that
that I started before before we ended no
because that's not it right what
happened here
yeah here's our light probe spatial
index didn't we have this here it is all
right we did I just for some reason I'm
blind and can't see it anyway
so on Saturday we started with this
function and this is basically just
saying look I want to be able to add
these things to a spatial index and the
reason that I want to add them to a
spatial index is because I need to look
up to be fast
I don't probably want to go before we
had sort of a like a I want to call it a
light cut system that's usually what
they call it in the literature where you
have like one large lighting thing that
encompasses your entire scene and then
it breaks into smaller ones breaks the
Samanas breaks the swamis so when you're
ray casting you just say depending on
how far out I am as I as I leave the
immediate region that I'm in I'm gonna
look at like less and less detail how
the scene is described right and that's
the kind of thing that I'm not sure if
we're really gonna want to do anymore
we're probably gonna leave it in at
first because it's already there we're
not gonna like pull it out proactive
like preemptively but we might not
really want it anymore
however you may ask the question well
why don't you just use that it is a
spatial partition it is but we're going
to need a very very fast very very fast
spatial partition for looking up the
light probe contributions to any
individual hit and the reason for that
is we're going to have to do a lot of
those evaluations and again I really
think we we want to do it in something
like a voxel again I'm not 100% certain
that we don't want to use a multi
resolution structure for this but I'm
pretty sure we want to do going forward
is to just use regular ray casting no
level of detail because we're gonna
count on the light probes to move stuff
around for us and probably not really
use the hierarchical stuff anymore
so you know the hierarchical stuff we
may be used for hit detection but you
know we're we're gonna stay away from
that probably four acts
doing the lighting sampling because I
think we can probably get away now with
just doing direct lighting sampling
everywhere
don't know as I'm saying it I'm sort of
having second thoughts I'm like maybe we
should be using a hierarchy for that and
it's hard to say because if you think
about what happens there you know that
hierarchy that you build we could just
have it always be a light probe
hierarchy meaning we take all of our
lighting probes we merge them together
and so when you recast something as you
get further out you just use that
composite light probe I don't know it
doesn't thrill me so I think I'm going
to try and say let's let's stay away
from that and we'll just concentrate on
when we do our spacial hierarchy we're
just gonna do a we're just gonna use
that for accelerating our hit detection
and we're not really gonna do anything
else with it
that's probably what I will what I'll
stick with okay so moving on as we do
add probe spatial index here we sort of
sketched out what this routine would
look like as you can see we need some
kind of a function that will take the
spatial index in question and it will
take a position like something that says
here is where you know some some 3d
position in space and from that we want
to get back something that is in our
spatial index right because it spatial
index is basically a big voxel that
we're laying over the scene and we want
to map things into that voxel when we
loop through all of the voxel points we
will then insert this probe in there if
this is the best probe and what you can
see here we're not actually using any
kind of tests we need to use some kind
of test here but what's happening is
saying look let's get whatever light is
in this facial index at the moment when
we get what light is in this particular
portion of the spatial index what we
want to do is we want to figure out
whether or not we should replace it with
a new one that's getting inserted right
that's what we're trying to do here that
way each cell of our voxel
we'll always have some look up into a
light probe that's supposed to be used
there now remember these things will
need to be sampled all together so when
we actually go to do a sample we need to
find like the ones that are at the the
corners in it's a little bit tricky I
mentioned this at the end of the stream
I'm gonna mention it again because it's
something that we're gonna have to
grapple with it's probably the most
interesting bookkeeping element of this
scheme but what happens with our voxel
is if you look at any given voxel cell
we're going to have a fundamental
problem where all right here's our axis
Y X Z if we always just consider the
minimum corner primal so this is our
minimum corner so we know very very
easily with a very simple multiply and
truncation we can index into our voxel
engine like basically to ops right
pretty pretty pretty straightforward we
may need a clamp in there but you know
so for op stops if we clamp there if we
actually just make sure we only ever
allow inbounds values by sizing the
voxel abruptly then you only have two so
you're two or four either way very very
cheap right so in here when we when we
get this particular index back we can
then look up something right this this
value is gonna give us something in our
light probe set right or I should say
group so in our light probe group will
have data but the question is just what
data now in a perfect world we would
just have a light probe and you would
just use it and so right here would just
be the probe right and that'd be the
most efficient thing I look up in the
voxel I get the probe I
light with the probe so why can't I just
do that well the answer is because at
some point there's another probe right
so at some point down the voxel as I
keep going this way at some point I'm
going to get another probe there's a
probe here right that gives me a good
answers for things inside this cell and
there's a probe over here at some point
you should be lighting with this probe
not this one right and if all I did was
for every voxel I just picked the
closest light probe and used that then
we would see somewhere in here when that
answer changed you would see a lighting
pop so as my object would move through
the voxel and across the voxel boundary
into the next voxel where the answer
changed and it might not change here
like maybe it's the same here so the pop
wouldn't be here and it's over here that
the pop is right who knows but some
number of voxel cells later as I pass
into one that has a different closest
light I'll see that lighting pop so what
I need to be able to do here is I need
to be able to provide a set of light
probes like some number of light probes
that I can use together to blend right
and as I'm saying it I'm realizing that
actually it's simpler than I think it is
because there's no penalty for having
two voxel cells next to each other have
the same light probe actually okay so
what we could do instead is just
discretize okay
I think we have the answer here as I'm
saying it so here's what I think we do
let's just tell ourselves that the
requirement for our voxels is that the
voxels themselves will be aligned with
the world such that the light probes are
always considered to be okay so the only
thing I'm we're not worried about is if
I ever want to have a moving light probe
so let me just say this first and then
we can talk about that case in a second
if we just assume that we'll place our
voxel grid reasonably and for any given
voxel cell we will just say that there
is only one light probe and that light
probe is considered to be in the middle
of the voxel cell right then all we
would have to do is just assign every
voxel a light probe and even if two
voxel cells next to each other had the
same light probe that'd be fine right
and then when we go to gather you just
use the like eight voxel cells whatever
their eight answers are is what you use
right and that's it you just blend
between those and you're done and that's
great the only thing that that doesn't
really work well for is if light probes
move around because if light probes move
around then the approximation that
they're just in the center of the voxel
cell doesn't really work right because
as they move and right we when we look
up the light probe we can get its actual
position so it's not a storage problem
we know where the light probe actually
was but the problem is we can't really
use that because if we used where the
light probe actually was we would again
get discontinuity as we move across the
boundary if this light probe is like
right here and then the next voxel cell
over there was
like probe that was close that was ends
up being closer then as you move between
these unfortunately you would you would
as you well I guess the more interest
let's say it was like really close to
that boundary as I move through here
inside this voxel right I'm still using
this and I'm not really vocalizing this
properly I think this is an actual
problem but every time I try to vocalize
I'm like well that's not really
technically a problem let me use a 2d
example see if I can work it out so here
are the points at which we store which
light probe is closest right so what I'm
worried about
in terms of light probes moving is
suppose I have an entity and the entity
is taking a path right however it wants
to through my voxels you know I'm saying
and maybe that's a little bit too
regular that path so maybe it's like
this kind of a thing
so I have an entity that's moving
through these and what I want to
guarantee is that at no point so these
are all the places where the equation
changes as it crosses that voxel
boundary right my equation will change
now how will the equation change right
the equation will change because the
light Pros under consideration change if
we take only the 2d problem then while
you're inside this region right these
are the light probes these these they're
not necessary light bulbs their indexes
light probes these are the indices to
light into the light probe array that
you would be using we don't know what
they are but we know there's four of
them right so you're using light probes
a B C and D which might all be the same
they might all be a right it might be
there's only one light probe in this
whole region so it's all using a or they
may all be different maybe a B C and D
right but while you're in here this is
what you're using now when I cross this
boundary here I change right if this is
ABCD then C and D remain in the active
set but a and B go away and whatever the
answer is here would be its E and F
that's what I'm going to use now so I've
moved from using a window that looked
like this to using a window that looked
like this right so it used to be that
it's now that and so what must be true
in order for this to be to not see a
lighting discontinuity like a change in
lighting that's perceivable as a pop by
the player every time they move across
that boundary or any time a monster
moves across that boundary right if you
look at what will happen here we're
gonna be blending these together so that
means there are weights right there's a
W 0 W 1 W 2 W 3 right there are weights
multiplying these lighting contributions
what that means is by the time I get to
this barrier here these have better go
to 0 if I just pretend that the
contribution of this lighting source is
sort of effectively you know or if I
just assume it's like right there or
whatever I want to see what's like a
diamond or something I don't know
whatever I want to assume if I want to
assume that it goes to 0 as I hit this
boundary these two this and this if I
want to assume it goes to 0 as I hit
this boundary that effectively treats
its contribution as if it were in the
center now that doesn't mean that we
have to use our computation of how the
lighting gets placed on the entity
doesn't necessarily have to use that
position but it does have to use those
weights because as you move closer to
this cell you must get rid of your
contribution from here or you'll see the
pop right so
same with these all in this line when I
first crossover the weights on this and
this those had better be none right
because I can't suddenly get a
contribution of that lighting so all I'm
trying to say is that there's a a
trilinear blend by linear in the case of
the 2d example but trilinear when it's
actually a voxel that has to control the
light probe contribution for any voxel
cell what that means is that when a
light probe itself is on the move so if
I was to move a light probe around then
we effectively have we have this issue
where as it crosses the boundary we
would produce a discontinuous lighting
change because when I think anyway when
it's here and it crosses over into here
that change in which cell it's in will
change which contributions it gets which
will which would have to itself have
been done smoothly right so that would
mean that when we are actually talking
about these particular like these actual
lights as they move through the voxel
boundary we would have a problem and we
would have to effectively be smearing
them out so that they their position
also was getting blended and that just
again starts to get just a little too
complicated right so what I'm wondering
is
I'm wondering if that just means that
you know for our purposes the simplest
thing to do is just say light probes
don't move they're fixed in the world
and you just use them as if they were at
the center of the voxels that you're in
in terms of blending and off you go it's
a solution it has some drawbacks but
compared to the other options I'm not
sure I'm really not sure how to I'm
really not sure how to do anything else
because if you think about how we want a
structure our lighting at the lower
level we definitely want a fixed
algorithm for sampling I think I don't
think we want to go down the route of
having our pixel shaders doing
ridiculous crap like you know like going
and looking up into spatial hierarchies
and stuff like this I just don't think
we want to go that route we want
something where we know we do a fixed
set of operations that produce a fixed
set of lights that we then use right a
nice clean like fetch and things do and
ops done right and so that just puts you
into voxel territory there's not much
you can do about it and once you're in
voxel territory I think you're kind of
stuck with having things make their
contributions based on their arrangement
in the voxels which means we kind of
just want to place lights light probes
at the Centers of voxels and be done
with it I think that's fine though cuz
again what we're trying to do here is
have a nice soft ambient lighting to the
world right we're not we're not doing
hard shadows we're not doing any kind of
like harsh it's supposed to be soft warm
like a pleasant glow to it it's
Christmas time you know and Krampus is
out so that's I think okay
and so I think what we would want to do
is say the voxel is like fixed in world
space in terms of its alignment and we
will just take our light probes and
consider them to be inside at the center
of those voxels I think that will be
okay
I think and what we can probably do is
we can probably make it so that we also
because we know we're placing those
light probes we can probably also do
some work with making sure that every
nothing is too wonky there I think this
will work out so I'm gonna I'm gonna I'm
gonna give that a try it's a lot it's a
lot better I think than what I was gonna
do there I think that's the right answer
I think that's the right answer
um so I'm gonna go ahead and move
forward with this and I'm gonna just do
a simple I'm gonna make it even yes more
straightforward then then we were gonna
originally I'm gonna make it pretty
pretty simplistic actually which is nice
because the simpler the better was
something like this that has to run at
runtime it's not an offline light
process so anyway in our hand probe
spatial index I still want to retain
this part because we still may want to
flood fill regions for lighting it so
that places that don't have actual light
plug facing them can just use nearby
lighting and still work I think that's
good so we want to maintain the flood
fill but we're just gonna say look
there's just one light index per voxel
that's all we're gonna do we're just
gonna go from there
so when we
need to actually place something in the
light into the system we would say here
you can see us asking for the existing
index getting that light probe out and
if we get a light probe out well
actually in this case we have to you
look at what happens with get probe here
there has to be something there because
existing index would have been zero if
there wasn't so actually this well you
know I probably wrote that because I was
going to do this maybe so what we want
to do here is say look if the centroid
of the voxel if it's closer to us than
it is to the probe that's already in
there we'll fill it if it's not we won't
right so we're pretty much gonna want to
do like distance to us and distance to
existing like that and then what we want
to do is compare those and in this case
because it's a comparison we don't need
to do a square root here because the
squared version which we'll get when we
do the distance squared which again
would you know avoids use of square root
for no reason it's just extra ops we
don't need we can just compare the
squares if the squares compare one way
the square roots will compare the same
way because we know they can't be
negative all right so in this case we
can say look if the distance to the
existing is greater than the distance to
us then we will then we will replace
what's in there with us otherwise what's
there stays so all we really need to do
now is figure out how to actually
compute these two and obviously a light
probe in this case which we haven't
actually stored in any particular way
you can see we don't have them yet but a
light probe once we make it should have
this information meaning a light probe
should obviously have in it a p-value
that says where the light verb was right
and then it's got some other stuff and
we don't really know what that stuff is
yet but it's got some other things
probably like a color value right and
that color value would be four
maybe the six faces of a cube because we
assume it's gonna have like a you know
some kind of lighting if you wanted to
go kind of down a more theoretical paths
you could consider using some of the
other ways of storing lighting
information there's spherical harmonics
and things like this we're probably not
going to go down that road route because
I haven't played much with those kind of
lighting representations and I'm not
sure how good they really are and so
before I would start teaching some of
those I would want to experiment them a
little bit myself and decide on the math
whether I think they're worth it or
whether I think they're just kind of one
of those fools errands so we're not
going to do that but we'll do some kind
of encoding of a directional light here
and so maybe we'll say we've got you
know a cube mappy style lookup so you
know maybe we've got something that
looks kind of like that which is we we
have six directional colors in there and
those are the light contributions that
we have from each of our six directions
and that would be our light probe right
so it's a pretty straightforward system
it's basically just seven three threes
and that's all there is it's a little on
a line II it would be nice if they're at
eight VIII's but I'm not sure what the
last one would be I mean one thing we
could do is keep track of the exact
light direction but I don't know that we
really want to complicate things that
way it doesn't seem like it makes much
sense to do so
yeah I can't think of any real reason to
do that so I think we would just yeah we
would probably just do something like
that I don't know you know there's other
ways we could approach it but again it's
a little unaligned but it's okay
right so there's our light probe if we
got one of those out like in this case
here then it should be fairly
straightforward to go from there at the
outset of this we can get the one that
we're talking about here so this is this
probe and maybe I'll call that distance
to this if I would just do the exact
same call for the one that we got out of
the system itself out of the spatial
index if I just do that real quickly and
get the probe that we're asked to use
here then what I can do is this equation
would be the same so I would just say
well okay I know this business of this
probe is this probe maybe this is
existing probe so in both cases I know
the location so all I need to do is just
take the length squared of the vector
between the place I want to measure for
closest myth for closeness and the
position of the probes that closest
position is the centroid right so this
is the voxel or I should say the cell
center right um and so when I'm in here
I need to be able to come up with the
cell center for a particular set of
voxel coordinates right and so this
right here this v3u is our cell
coordinates right and so I want to be
able to ask for this spatial index and
these coordinates what's the cell center
right when that comes back then I can go
ahead and with my get corner light index
here I can pass the same coordinates
down and then I can
just finish up the work here by you know
taking the links squared with that
Center so this would fill out the
spatial index with exactly what I wanted
which is great and then when we actually
it comes to lighting time what I want to
do here is say something like you know
get lighting for or something like this
and when we pass in the spatial index
and presumably we would do two versions
of this maybe something like that we're
gonna have like a cell position and then
world position and these get sort of
translated right so in here we would
want some way of saying map well we have
it right here map into grid and then we
can just sort of thunk through so we can
call it with a real position and if we
do what we'll do is convert it to a grid
position and then call this and then
when we do this operation what we need
to do is from the cell position we need
to be able to get effectively each of
the eight surrounding probe values and
we are going to blend between those
right so what we want is eight probes
and when I said eight of course I mean
zero through seven right so I need to
get eight probes and then I need to
blend their results together and I guess
I'm not sure what the most efficient way
to do that would be but I think the
answer is that you actually just want to
produce the blended probe because that's
probably less work than doing the
lighting for each probe and then
blending the result I would think but I
don't know it's hard to say right
because there's two ways we could do
this one is that you like with all eight
probes and then you blend the results
the other is you blend the probes and
then light with just one with just that
composite result
[Music]
I'll be honest I really don't know if I
can tell the difference when those two
we may have to analyze that a little bit
carefully but but just you know trying
to blind guess I'm not sure it would
depend a lot on what the lighting
equation we were going to compute
actually was in this case at this is
during light propagation time this would
be called and during light propagation
time as you might expect light
propagation time is strictly propagating
like a diffuse lighting effectively and
so we wouldn't really be computing much
of a lighting equation it would just be
a cosine fall-off kind of a thing
probably not really much else and so
it's possible that would just be quicker
to do the light computation on each
probe first and then blend the results
it's possible I'm not really sure
however what I will say is that it
brings up something that we need to be
able to do here that we're not doing as
well which is this needs to have a UVW
come back
that is the lerp values that we would
get to blend these things together
because as you might imagine in order to
blend between them we would need to know
not just the coordinates of the
particular cell in the voxel but where
you were inside that cell normalized out
so the UVW would need to come in here as
well so during this map into grid here
we would need to also get that residual
value and so this here would need to be
computed and it probably wants to be
computed as part of this right so I'm
guessing that it would be something sort
of this map in the grid would probably
be something we'll have to write out
that returns both of them but we'll see
what happens in a second so when we do
get probe lighting for Europe this is
what we're gonna want when we want to
get our lighting probes out not
particularly hard to do I think we just
say get probe buy or get probe from cell
or something like that and we just say
like cell P right and for some reason
the lighting solution is not getting
past year but it needs to be go so in
order to look up the probes here we need
to get this multiple times right oops so
what we're gonna do here is walk always
we can right so I mean I could write it
out completely longhand here to just say
like this is the the one we don't offset
it at all here is the one where we just
offset one here's another here's another
here's another oops I forgot
and so these are all of our different
possible light positions right positions
in the voxel each of the different
vertices of the cube right so I've got
them all here and so then if I want to
blend them together like I said I'm not
really sure which way we want to do this
but you can imagine something where I
would say like okay
let's just blend the probes together
first
maybe so here's our composite probe and
what I want to do is for each color
right all six of the faces of that cube
I want to blend all six together using
this uvw as the determiner so what I
want to do is like I want to like do a
thing where we some light probes in here
so like an accumulate or like accumulate
probe something like that
so I'd say all right this is the probe
we're accumulating into I want to
accumulate p0 in there I and I want to
have some way of talking about the
weights that I want to use to summit
right and so the thing that we're going
to get here is we've got three weights
and each weight should affect each of
the corners differently so for example
if you look at the UV W X Y &amp; Z here
well as those go up I am moving away
from the minimum corner so because this
is 0 0 0 the weighting here is going to
be like this
if all three were 0 that's the maximum
right
I could have and by the way there's no
sense in passing all of these because we
know that it's just going to multiply
them together so that's what my actual
waiting is going to end up being right
as I move along any of those three axes
I fall off to zero as I get to the end
of that axis right so this is basically
what we're looking at and we just know
we're going to do a bunch of these right
I'm going to accumulate each of these in
here and as I accumulate each of these
in here I'm going to change based on
this right I'm going to change which one
of these which of the UVW are negated in
which aren't so in this case this is the
one that's on the far end of the x-axis
but that means that I don't want to
negate the UVW of X the the X component
right we come down to the next one and
the same is true of Y right so this
probe was on the maximum end of the y
axis so we want to stop getting that one
this one's on the maximum end of the z
axis so we want to stop negating that
one this one was on the maximum of both
the y and the z axis and then oh that's
the opposite
there we go uh and this one and then
finally this one all right now this last
one is out the maximum of all of them so
it doesn't get any of these okay so I
think that looks about right those match
up nicely this accumulates those into
our probe ends off we go right now
it's a little bit wasteful because
technically the first one you don't need
to accumulate you could just set it
directly it would save us the trouble of
setting this to zero but maybe we'll get
lucky in the optimizer will help us who
knows at the end of that of cumulation
we have a single light probe and we can
now actually get the probe lighting back
right we can figure out what the light
probe looks like that we actually need
to light against and what I'm gonna do
here is I'm gonna say maybe we actually
just we send back what the lighting
probe was that's just how we'll do it
right for right now hopefully this will
help we'll see so I think we're gonna do
it like this this allows us to get
whatever the composite light would be at
this location and so once we actually do
that accumulation we now know what that
light is and we can return it right and
so that's actually I'm gonna call that
result now because that's what that
actually is and then we're good to go
so once we have all that really this map
and a grid and part of things a bit of a
problem here so we're gonna need to
write that and we're gonna need to make
sure we can get our you VW's from it but
we're also going to need one other thing
here which is that once we have one of
these we need some way of computing the
actual lighting from you know like a
normal right so if you imagine now we
want to do like get light get incoming
light something like that if we have or
light with probe something like this
so we care if we say look give us a
probe and give us a zooming position in
a normal
we're supposed to be able to return the
light now we don't really need the
position anymore because once we have
the light probe we've already assumed
that the position of that we were taking
has been blended with the lighting has
been blended with the probes the
neighbor it to produce a single probe
that's accurate for that point and so
once we do that we don't really need to
take into account the position I don't
think anymore so we just need the normal
and what the normal is gonna do is tell
us all these six phases which ones are
going to be combined to to produce the
actual value of of the light right so
that's what we need to do here now the
normal itself kind of tells us the
answer in a way but not exactly what we
need to do now is have some kind of a
function that takes colors that are
sampled for particular directions and
produces a smooth blend between them
right and this is not as easy as it
maybe sounds because these are values
don't interpret Li kind of cleanly if
you will let me try to give you a little
bit of a perspective on what I mean by
that and that's a little bit confusing
never put our day marker here
so if you take a look at what's actually
happening here
let's just take a cross-section of what
happens with the normal and pretend we
have a few lighting values of the kind
of talking about and you can maybe see
what I mean by we have sort of an issue
here
so if I have a direction and what I'm
saying fundamentally with something like
a cube lighting map like this is I'm
storing like a color at each thing so
maybe there's a color off in this
direction so this is color Y right and
there's a color off in this direction so
this is color X and I want to know
what's the color incoming at N if I
assume that I want to smoothly blend
between these two incoming light values
and color is probably the wrong way to
say it it's a light value could be
whatever we want right but point being
whatever we're storing for our
irradiance here well I guess it's in
incoming light so I don't know what you
would measure that exactly in but let's
see see if I can use the right term yeah
so I think we want your radiance right
it's the if the radiant flux received by
a surface per unit area so even if we
were trying to make a physically
accurate thing and so we have like an
actual
physical light incoming value here or
here no matter what it is or how
accurate it is we still have the same
problem of we're only storing it at a
fixed set of sample points and we need
to produce a smooth blend between them
for our lighting so we need to know for
a particular normal what is the correct
contribution between this and this now
we know that the normal itself is
represented as n X&amp;Y
and of course there's an NZ but we're
not talking about that right now because
we're just doing the 2d slice before the
MX and Y it would be nice if we could
just do something like well how about
just NX x CX plus NY times CY right the
problem here is that the normal in this
case is you know as its name would imply
is normal
it's a normalized value what that means
is this is true
right this is the equation that tells
you something as a normal the vector
Euclidean length of that normal is equal
to one that's why it's normal right but
the problem is if you look at that
equation that's not the same equation
that we would want for blending for
blending right this is normal it is also
another way of saying to norm okay
now I don't know that we ever talked
about norms before but what norms are
are there's a set of ways you can talk
about normalized values this is just one
of them the Euclidean to norm in this
case is when you Square and then square
root right so square the components sum
them together square root them that's
the two norm but there is also a one
norm by the way there's also an infinity
norm I think I've mentioned these on
hand made here before that's when you
raise everything to the infinity and
then infinite root them and that just
has the effect of picking out the
maximum value right so this is just
what's the max right well the one norm
is exactly the same as the two norm is
exact the same as the infinity norm
you're just playing with the power so
the one norm is the non root I don't
know if that's a thing you can write but
of everything raised to just one power
right so it's effectively NX plus and y
equals one that's the one norm now why
did I bring any of this up am I just
going off on one of these tangents well
no we actually care the reason we care
about the one norm is the one norm is
the thing that produces a linear blend
right if the blend weights sum to 1 then
we have properly linearly blended our
values together if the square of the
values Square rooted sums to
well this is not the same write this
equation he is not true these are not
the same for any number of reasons even
just the most basic observation can show
you that if you had a negative here it
would have gotten erased immediately by
the square right so clearly these aren't
even the same even with respect to sign
but they're not gonna be the same with
respect to quantity either because
although a value squared Square rooted
will only lose its sign right but
otherwise the matter is the same once
you add two things together a plus a
squared plus B squared Square rooted is
not the same as a plus B right it
doesn't the the square root does not
distribute across terms like that across
across additive terms it's not mr. Davis
so because this is not true we can't
really use NX plus NY because the values
will be wrong we want them to look like
this but instead they will look like
that and we will end up over adding
we'll end up with brighter light than we
should have added when we're adding
those light values together right what
can we do what can we do are we just
screwed is that it is that the end of
the ball game well no fortunately if you
look at what has to happen here if I
want to enforce this equation right if
this is something that's true I want to
be true I want to be true well it's just
math right how would I make it true
well what I know right now is I want an
X like effectively what I'm saying is I
want like an N X prime plus an and Y
prime I want those to equal one right
but what I've got right now is I've got
an NX regular plus an NY regular that
equals some other thing right
and in fact whatever that other thing is
I don't really care
let's just say it equals some random
value it just a right who cares what it
is so if I know I have this right but I
want to have this how can i how can I
get somewhere with that right well it's
pretty easy to produce this equation out
of this equation actually right because
if you look at what's happening on this
side the only difference between these
two equations is the a right if I just
divide these by a right if I just divide
by a I actually get this equation here
right so I don't even have to really do
the math and solve for anything I can
just see that actually dividing by a
produces the correct result right so
since I have a normal right and I know
that I can add the values and I will
always get a nonzero answer right
because they can't be negative it's a
normal you know I'm saying I can just
absolute value them if I want to write I
can just say that if I want to um I can
just enforce them to be positive I know
they always have a reasonable magnitude
they can't both be 0 1 could be 0 if the
other can't right so when I add these
together I know and I shouldn't say this
when I add these together if I just
don't let them be net is there their
absolute value I would get a value that
if divided would give me valid sum to
one right that produces a clean linear
blend for me so if I want to I actually
can in here do something like alright
let's force this to be linear blendable
let's force us let's find a way to get a
UVW out of this end right
so what I can do there is say all right
step one is just to say let me produce
an absolute value for each of these and
I think we have yeah
so let's first take the absolute value
of each of these parameters right and
we'll talk a little bit about what we
need to do with the sign later because
we will actually use that sign we just
don't need it for blending right so we'd
want to produce the absolute value here
and then what we'd want to do is make
sure that our uvw is divided by so
basically some kind of like inverse norm
here we want to produce that inverse a
value so we want to produce one over a
here and what did I say a was well it's
just the sum of all the values right
it's the one norm so once we produce
that inversion for pretty much good to
go we've got the blend values we
actually want and so then the only
question is well what do we actually
blend together well obviously we need to
know with our light probe nope we go
with our light probe here obviously we
need to know which of these six
corresponds to the things that we're
going to blend together but as you can
imagine if we're sampling out of a cube
right so the idea here is that we've got
some cube right and each of the faces
has some lighting information on it
right then what we can effectively
imagine is almost like a star pattern
right here's my Z my y+ X right and I've
got a sample at each of those locations
so I've got a sample at negative and
positive right each one of those and so
what I want to do here is I want to
produce whatever the color colors are
the way should blend between I want to
first select a positive or negative
based on the sign of what the normal was
before I absolute valued it right so
that's why I was seeing this app survive
we're going to use a sign we're just not
using it yet so we want to know the sign
and we're gonna produce one value for
each of these but once we produce the
value then we're good to go from there
right so all we really need to do is say
alright we're gonna produce and you know
wherever the normal is let's say the
normals pointing out that direction or
something right we know we're just going
to collect okay it's pointing down like
negative Y so we're gonna grab the
negative Y one it's positive Z's we're
gonna grab the positive Z color and
negative x so we're gonna grab those
three colors and then we'll do our blend
with just three things using the uvw
that we actually have right so in here
we can just say all right let's do that
the result is just our u VW x times our
X color ru VW y times our Y color and
our UV wz x our Z color right and that's
the result and the key here is we just
need to pick these colors so our X color
is something our Y color is something
and our Z color is something and the
question is what is it right and so here
we have our color table I believe there
we go we are have already had a
convention and we should stick to it so
that everything in the game uses the
same convention you can see what they
were here it was like negative Y
positive Y positive X negative x for the
axes oh sorry this is the direction so
we watch they want to use this part of
it this is these are the axes you would
impose on there so this is X positive
that's alright X negative this is X
positive right and so in here we would
pick one of either color you know X
negative x positive so we kind of do
like if you know NX less than 0 and the
same would be true for each of these you
can see it just goes up the axis set and
so that would get us all of our colors
that we need here and then we're done
so that lets us pick up well if we don't
have a type over done so that lets us
pick which of our colors we're gonna
blend between and then we blended
between them to get the final result
based on where the normal was pointing
so that's a way of collapsing down six
samples into one based on a normal that
can like smoothly vary around them right
now there's ways we can probably make
this better than it is right I this like
like the way these are happening here
you could imagine us doing an actual six
way blend which might actually be faster
I by just using a clamp right so you
would do like like this can be made off
with it to do it
there's a lot we can do to just make
this not have any branches in it or
anything like that absolute value
obviously doesn't require any branching
either it just knocks out the sign bit
so we can knock out the sign bit do the
blend and we'll just use min and Max to
threshold our values and I think we can
make this just a thing that's like a
bunch of ads right it's just a six-way
mad that you know it's not nothing
there's a lot of because each color you
know there's a lot of values there so
that it's a fair number of floppies but
it's not gonna be really all that much
and so this makes it look worse than it
is we can do a much more straightforward
thing here that doesn't require like a
conditional move or something like this
does we can just use a select there in
fact would be another way to do it right
so we could we could do three opps to
build the color values and then do the
combine or something like that so
there's a lot of things we can do here
this is not an ugly routine it can be
made quite clean and simple I think but
I don't want to do that optimization
till we get everything going so that we
can see how we want to slot in because
maybe we'll end up being we might be
doing four of these at a time for all I
know who knows what we're gonna end up
doing so I think we kind of want to wait
a little bit on that before we get too
fancy so looking at the rest of this now
you can see we've got a few functions we
need to sort of implement here and I'll
go ahead and do that so here's my
accumulate probe function I gotta do
that's gonna take a light probe we'll
call that a for accumulator then we're
gonna have the T value that we're
actually gonna use or maybe we'll call
the C value for coefficient there's only
one of them and we're not it's not alert
it's actually just a cumulation and then
we have a p0 value there that p 0 value
is the light probe that's the source and
so here what we want to do is again
we're we're just sort of doing a color
summation here so what we want to do is
for every one of these we want to
effectively just add the corresponding
value in the light probing question oops
right so it's literally just a
distribution of this I only even wrote
this function just so I wouldn't have to
type that that many times but it's
literally just a distribution of the sum
so these would just get in lined and
this would just be happening directly
right so again very very very simple
just producing a summation there nothing
fancy so I think that's almost
everything and then we have our kind of
lighting stuff more or less solved I
think and we can move on to the next
phase which is trying to integrate it in
which we'll probably have to wait till
tomorrow to do but if you take a look at
what we still have remaining the only
thing we did not do is fussing with the
grid so all of the grid you can see here
all the grid functions are currently
stubbed and there's nothing there
to implement them so you can see that
we've got a bunch of things for that
let's go ahead and lay out what they are
oops so assuming we have a spatial index
one of the things we want to do is
produce the center of a particular cell
that's one thing we want to be able to
do another thing we want to be able to
do is get back the slot this is what's
actually stored in the spatial index
which is just that residual really
simple 16-bit integer that tells you
which light probe in the set of light
probes we're talking about uh and so
final thing is map it to create and this
one's gonna be the harder one this one's
gonna have because we have to return the
u VW's potentially as well I don't know
exactly how we're gonna work that out
we'll have to think about it a little
bit anyway so in this case for get
center of for the spatial index we know
that we've got a min corner somewhere
right we're gonna have to have that in
fact it's already written in there right
I'm gonna have to score the cell Bhim
because why not so if we do the min
corner plus the cell cord times the cell
dim right eye that gives us the corner
of the cell in question and we just need
to move half a grid cell further right
that's all we actually need to do there
um trust
I think that's what we want anyway
doesn't really matter I was trying to
think of is this the best way to
organize the grid but yeah well that
will become clear in time we need to
make adjustments anyway
when we're doing get center of here what
I want to be able to do now is say all
right I need you to get this is the min
corner in fact you know we could just
duplicate this routine if we want to get
the actual center all we would need to
do here is add half an index right
when we do our multiply so that's pretty
straightforward now in both cases we
need a way of converting a V through 3 u
2 V 3 that's fine well have that and
then I think you know once we implant
that the once we implement those V 3
years which we kind of already have
implemented and we're just going to move
them into the math library they were
called gen v3 s before but we're gonna
implement them as a v3 u that should all
be fine and then so finally when we do
to get corner light index in this case
now we just need ways of looking up into
the spatial index for now I'm going to
stick with assertions but I don't know
if we want to use clamping in the future
it may be best to use clamping again
because that can be it's pretty cheap in
SSE it's not very hard to do clamping so
sometimes you just do it instead so it's
hard to say exactly how we want do that
but either way we know that to get our
light index
what we want to do here is take that
array that stores the all the
information in the voxel and we want to
move by the cell cords somehow right so
we're going to be doing something like
this and so to look at how these would
get added in there I intentionally sort
of said there's a dim power of 2 here
which means the light probes facial
index is not gonna really be allowed to
be an arbitrary number you always have
to have the sides be a power of 2 and
the reason I wanted to do that is
because it just makes indexing easier it
means that instead of having to do any
of this stuff we can literally just
build a composite index value sort of
something like this what do I want to
call this get
something like that
I don't know but basically if you give
it back if you give it some self
coordinates what we want to be able to
do is just produce an index out of those
and we can produce that literally by
just bit manipulation so the Z would get
shifted up by something the Y would get
shifted up by something and the X would
not it would just get bored in there
right and we do need in this case the
spatial index bit here but after that
we're good to go so here we would just
say all right the dim pao2 here imp out
to here and so we know that let's say
that the dimension power of 2 you know
what's that going to be let's say the
dimension power of 2 is you know five
eight who knows that means there's 286
values X could take on right so we just
need to shift up by eight to make sure
why does it interfere with that done and
then when we get to Z we need to shift
up by that twice right so it's really
just saying shift it up by that two
times right what's the musing about that
is that's just a double shift right if
you want to do
oops it that way you can I'll let that
be the compilers discretion I don't
really care how it wants to do depends
on what kind of code it's gonna generate
there but point being we just want to
shift up by twice that again for the Z
value that will produce a composite
index and then we return the index and
we're done right easy peasy lemon
squeezy so if we want to make sure that
these things are always inside the
bounds when we actually look them up
then they're also you know we kind of
have to come Jimmy take some care for
now I'm just gonna say whatevs
let's just you know take them and we'll
start to deal with out
this later on right one way we could do
that too is just say look here let me do
this let's get that phoenixon plank like
so what I can do here is say look let's
put an assertion in we know that the
index has to be less than the dim POW to
multiply it out right so if we take the
dim POW - and we say we know that each
one of the sides of this is going to
effectively be like race that power -
right like if it was zero it's one
dimension it's it's one if it was two
it's two if it's three it's four if it's
if it's for its 16 and so on right
so we know that this is one I'm trying
to explain this but my brain is having a
hard time coming up with the word so I'm
just going to draw it for you we know
that if we want to produce 2 to the N
right that one shifted up by n gives us
that value right so when we see dim
power of 2 that's just an N right that's
just this so anytime we want to know how
many are on one of our voxel sides it's
just 2 to the N which is just one
shifted up by n right now if we want to
know how many there are total in the
voxel we know that we would just
multiply the number of ones along x
times the number of ones along Y times
the number of ones along Z right which
is to DN x to the n x to the N now we
know that if you are going to add 2 to
the ends together I'm sorry if you're
going to multiply
together you're just gonna add the ends
right because multiplication is just
adding more powers so it's really just n
plus n plus n right it's 2 to the n plus
n plus n that means if we want to do
this shift we're really just talking
about one shifted up by n plus n plus n
right but we don't really need to do n
plus n plus n because that's just three
n right so really we just want that
and so one shifted up by three n is
actually going to give us the total
number of things that can be in our
voxel I know how to say that without
having things to point to so sorry
anyway so when we do this all we need to
do to figure out how many there are
total that's something there are along
one all we need to do to figure out how
they're how many there are along all our
that and if they were different we could
just instead of three times we could
just do plus there right so we could do
Dimpy 2x plus dim POW 2 dot y times 2
times Z or something right so we can
actually be flexible there if we want to
so you know we could we could play
around that if we find that it's like to
discrete and Z or whatever I don't know
right so just you know keep that in mind
that this is this doesn't really get
particularly more complicated at all if
we want them to be different spatial
dimensions for each one in fact we maybe
we should just write it that way now I
don't know you know you can like if we
were to do that it would literally just
be this
right I don't think there's anything
else we would have to do and the same is
true for this you would just say well
there's the Z there's the Y and I need
to account for this y shift in here
right oh I'm sorry
right because the I almost put Y there
you don't want to shift up Y by Y is
power 2 because you're making room for X
in the bottom bits so what you're doing
is shifting up by however many X needed
to use right then when we come up here
we want to shift by how many ye to use
but we need to have already been shifted
by X right now since we're already doing
this shift by X we can instead of doing
two shifts there we can also just do
well why don't we just merge these two
together first and then do the shift as
as a group right so if you look at doing
it this way that makes it a little
cleaner potentially right so let's say
we took we have that whole thing there
we go
so here you can see I take the Z
coordinate I shift that up by Y I or in
the Y component I shift that up by X I
or in the X component so that way it
reduces the shifting I only have to
shift up once for each thing I merge in
and that that could be possibly a little
bit more fun who knows right alright so
I think that gets me everything I need
and now you can even set these things to
arbitrary scales power too because I
don't know that we it doesn't look like
it's really any more expensive to do it
one way or the other it's not really an
issue
so in here once we do or get probe
lighting for we know we've got and also
we use it here in map into grid we know
we've got one more thing we've got to do
which is if we have an arbitrary
position we have to have some way
of producing the actual oops we have to
have some way of actually producing from
an arbitrary 3d point what the
coordinates of the grid are which are
like a discrete thing right and we've
done this so many times I hand me here
I'm not going to belabor the point but
it's trivial right for any given spatial
index we know we have the minimum corner
so first we just make the P relative to
the minimum corner right that's the
vector from the minimum corner of our
spatial index to the point in question
after we do that we know all we have to
do is say well after we get that
relative one we know that each cell is
exactly this large so we can just say
let's take it and divide it effectively
right because multiplying by the inverse
cell dimension is the same as dividing
by the cell dimension again that's an
actual per element multiplication so we
got to do we got to invoke a Hadamard
product there I don't use vector product
doesn't multiply because who knows what
that means you want dot product you I
had a Myra product runtime vector cross
product there's all kinds of vector
products out there so I like to say
which one I'm using in this case it's
Hadamard product that gets us back the
coordinates in float so this is
basically our you know our F chord F
chord and I probably didn't just tell
mine F word because I don't have perfect
pitch but you know I'm saying anyway the
F chord is still in floating-point so
now what we want to do is to be able to
truncate that coordinate down and in so
doing we will also be able to produce
that UVW that's the that's the reason
why I was sort of suggesting that we
probably want to produce both values
here but we'll get to that a second so
if I want to now get my my v3u out of it
I want to be able to do like a truncate
on this F chord here and that will
produce my result
but once I have you know that truncation
I could pretty easily produce the you
know with using this F chord I can
pretty pretty easily produce the UVW
right the UVW in this case is just the F
chord - whatever the truncated version
was right uh so there's that
who knows how we want to implement that
but point being we would like to return
this value as well because a lot of
people actually need it as you can see
here and they don't have F chord you
could just ask them to do this
themselves outside but they don't have
the multiplied version and they need
that multiplied version because
otherwise it's not the right scale right
for those zero to one values so that'll
raise the question of how do you want to
return this back let's say we do this
I'm happy with it there we go
hopefully everyone else is too and then
when you call map into grid if you only
want one of the things you just get one
of the things if you want both of the
things you take them so here I can get
myself chord but I can also get a UVW
right
so that seems fine and when we do the
map in the grid here we only really
wanted the cell cord so we can just
pluck that out and skip the UVW entirely
because we don't care what that UVW was
anyway and then I think we're pretty
much good to go
I need the v3u to exist and since we've
already kind of implemented it I'm going
to just say now is probably the time to
upgrade our gen v3 into a real value
because we want it and you can see
basically everyone needs it there so
let's go ahead and do that oops I didn't
mean to make a new buffer so if we take
a look at our gen math you can see we've
got this Union Gen b3 here I'm gonna go
ahead and type def agenda b3 to a v3u
because I want to now make this a
first-class citizen there
I know those RS 32s so I guess this is
really v3 s but I'm also fine with that
I don't really care if it's a U or an S
in this case so I think that'd be fine
we could do this and then I'll use v3
S's in the rest of the stuff as well I
think there's a hand made types here
where we actually define these guys and
so I'll follow suit there and just say
here we've got a v3 s in the mix and
yeah I'll just leave it at that for now
there's more we could do there but there
but I'm not going to bother for the time
being
and then in the lighting stuff I'll just
say alright you know when I said v3 you
I think pretty much everywhere we'll
just use this instead sorry for the
psych-out but that's just how it's gonna
be and I don't think there is very much
we have to do to fix that
oh and this probably should get moved
out into here as well
let's make that an incredibly long and
ridiculous name go and live than that
not a lot we have to do so we're just
gonna have to implement that v3s I think
then we're good to go right not a whole
lot else to do there
this needs to exist and that's an S and
that's it so we now need to actually
take that gen math dot CPP and we're
gonna have to get yeah we didn't really
do much with it as you can see here so
those are all part of those gen volumes
which are a different thing so in the
math in the math world of things I'm
gonna go ahead and start implementing
some of these so we've got our V 3s here
and just want to make sure we actually
have some operators that it can use
so we'll start with those and then
really mostly what we need is just ways
of converting these things so mostly
what I need is like I want a truncate
oops - v3 s for v3 and I thought we had
like a look at of truncate so you know
what floor is fine Flores is totally
what I want anyway effectively so I'm
find that so in here where we're doing
this sort of floor function we're just
going to do that on each of its values
and that'll produce the floor that we
wanted so that's actually totally
fuck-ups that's actually totally fine I
think all those are fine to know whirly
words there so then the only other thing
we I think needed I can't quite remember
is the ability to change one of these v3
s is into it back into a v3 that's just
a simple load that's not going to do
anything interesting at all doesn't
really even change the value i and
that's it
all right so let's start to clean things
up here as we go
looks like we wanted a short hand there
for creating one of these which makes
sense again pretty simple what else we
need get probe from cell so I think
that's just this right
so we do have a bit of an issue here
that I think we kind of want to be aware
of but actually I guess it's fine
because there's already a zero so we
always want to return a value from this
but I realized that I guess we kind of
can because if there's a zero we just
returned the null zero probe which is
just has nothing in it so that's
actually fine so here we want to take
this nonsense right and we want to do
the indexing so that's in this case just
going to piggyback on top of this
function actually so where we get the
spatial index address and the corner
light in the nexus stuff here all we're
doing is we're really just going to call
that and we're gonna say give us what
what would be whatever the index is in
there and we want to get that probe
right and so this is really just a
convenience function built out of things
we already knew we needed and in some
cases already wrote there's assigned
unassigned mismatch somewhere probably
this
yeah and then finally we need a way of
actually getting one of these and hey
I'm out of time which is good because we
just finished it's money everything
tomorrow can be the day when we actually
try to wire some of this stuff up all
right anything else we got
so cell dimension here was just a typo
we meant to get that off of the spatial
index so that's that's nothing big there
here this is just needs to get its new
ridiculous long name here where we've
got that truncate it's really just
called floor and then we finally have a
get probe lighting for which I don't
remember what that actually took
I think it just means that didn't have
the solution which it needs to look up
the light probes and then I think we're
done and you can see that you know
there's no sense in running this at this
point because it can't do anything and
the reason for that is we aren't
actually submitting or generating light
probes right
and you can see that by the fact that
we're those light probes would be they
don't actually exist right so in other
words in here somewhere there has to be
something that actually stores the light
probes so right here right we would need
that and that produces a correctly
compiling program but that one that
can't actually do anything because
nobody will ever put any light probes in
there and so there's no reason to
actually call these functions but that's
exactly what we can start doing tomorrow
I will go ahead and go to the brief Q&amp;A
now actually doesn't have to be brief I
think suppose to be a regular Q&amp;A
long boolean concerning moving light
probes could you have special-purpose
light probes that only affect the
lighting of certain things that move so
you would end up with things that move
and things that don't and most other
probes in the lighting system would be
unmoving and perhaps the moving probe
could use some of the unmoving
information and the unmoving could
gradually sample from the moving uhm yes
so I guess the main problem would be in
the shader so if you think about what's
gonna happen in our shader we're gonna
have to sample somehow and in order to
sample lighting for the world in general
like all the grass and all the walls and
you know the all the stuff that fills up
most of screen that's gonna want a
sample from you know a common set of
light probes that just interpolates
between so that's all good but if you
wanted to have accurate sampling of a
moving object that had its own probe
what we could do is have a different
sampler a different pixel shader that
instead of sampling from eight light
probes and blending between them it
actually just sampled from one specific
light probe that it had the index to
right and then we would just assign
certain object to that shader and they
would do that right now I don't know
that I actually care about that so I
don't think we will do that but there's
no reason you couldn't do it right and
furthermore they don't actually need to
be involved in the system at all in any
other way they can just be a separate
side band of light indices that don't
even contribute to the lighting solution
they could literally just be
ten moving light probes that you just
stick to enemies in the hero for more
accurate lighting or something and they
just accumulate their results themselves
right and you could totally do that I
don't know that we need to do that I
don't know that there's any real benefit
to doing that because I don't know that
we need any kind of special accuracy in
that way but you could totally there's
no reason you couldn't do a system like
that you know be totally fine when and
how often do we plan to compute the
light probes well every frame they're
updated it's it's literally just the
same lighting we're running right now
we're just running we're gonna change to
running these so right now our world
geometry is also the collection geometry
the only change we're making is now our
probes are going to be the collection
geometry and the world is going to be
the reflection geometry and so we're
just gonna be exactly the way we're
doing it now where we have about I think
a hundred frame window of averaged out
values so it's it's you know once a
second or so at 60 frames a second maybe
once every two seconds more like the
lighting has been completely changed but
it's very gradual so that you don't see
too much flicker in terms of like lower
sampling and what that value is that
will actually set it to eventually I
don't know we'll have to see what
happens right but we'll go from there
but it's continuously updated all the
time
how our square roots computed and how
fast are they the answer depends on how
accurate you want the square root to be
so it's pretty similar to division in
that sense but I'll show you
all right so I if you take a look if you
just put in square root to the Intel
intrinsics guide this is a pretty good
guide to how fast square root will be
just as a pure ballpark estimate on the
CPU side remember the GPU does has its
own separate speeds for all of the
operations so it depends if you're
talking about in a shader you need to
look up information on the particular
GPU in question but assuming you're
talking about a CPU side almost
everything is x64 unless you're on a
phone or something which is arm and then
you need to look up different tables for
square root right but on here what you
end up with is when we look at the like
the available square root of a trans you
can see there's quite a few different
ones now most people are not going to
have avx-512 yet so we're not going to
talk about things that are up in that
range let's talk about just stuff that
you know everybody who plays a game on a
PC will have right so that's this now
soon most people will also have this
right and maybe even that but at the
moment we're just talking about this and
you can see like most of these are there
once you get to this it's you're out
into huge numbers of benders depending
on where you're using masking and know
this is how why you're doing it and blah
blah blah but you know point being this
is mostly where we're at so if you take
a look at these functions there's two
ways you can compute a square root and
they're not the same so let's talk about
just actually computing the square root
first
so the packed single-precision square
root this is 4 so see that SS versus the
PS there so the difference between the
SS and the PS is just whether it does
four at a time which is the square root
PS or whether it does just one which is
the square SS right
now ignore Knights landing Knights
landing is a completely there's it has
nothing to do with gaming that's a HPE
see part that's its al-arabi core thing
it doesn't have any like just ignore
that so we're looking at like skylake or
if that's what the modern chips all are
or one of these other ones down here if
you're looking at more compatibility
with with older machines so most of you
looking at a skylight core and what you
can see on a skylight core if you're
doing a square root of either four or
just one value is you can expect to pay
13 cycles from start to end so when you
issue the square root it will take 13
processor cycles to get the answer back
but you can ask for one every three
cycles so if you start a square root you
can actually ask for another one three
cycles later and another one three
cycles after that and other one three
cycles after that so in terms of the
pipelining you can actually potentially
get a lot more than one done every 13
cycles you can actually get one done
every three cycles if you have a bunch
of them to do right so that's probably
the more useful number to look at which
is to say that in a long dependency
chain where you're pushing a you know a
huge set of sequential operations
through and that's all you have to do
then you know it's 13 cycles but if you
have lots of things to do on multiple
things at once you can get some
pipelining there you're gonna pay closer
to just the three right so usually in
heterogeneous computing where you got a
lot of stuff going on you can you can
look at this number as being closer to
what you'll actually receive than this
number which is more of the worst
possible case when you don't have
anything else you can be doing at the
chip
so that's basically the idea right and
you can see that that modern scarlet
cords can do four of these at once as
well with no penalty so that's pretty
cool now that's the most expensive way
to do it I mean unless you want to do
double precision which we don't right so
there you go if you want something
cheaper you actually have an option and
that is the reciprocal square root so
the reciprocal square root does it
doesn't produce the square root it
produces one over the square root which
is like a square root and it divided
together right why is that instruction
well it's because normally what you do
after you square root something is you
divide by it right it's a normalization
it's usually what you're doing so they
do both of those together so you're
actually saving the divine and the
square root doing it in one right and
when you do this the only caveat you can
see how fast it is it's actually it's
latency for bus throughput one you can
do you can issue one every cycle right
but what you we can see here is that
reciprocal square root it doesn't quite
give you the right answer right so the
error is you know proportional to this
value here which is what half half the
bits are wrong something like that up to
half the bits could be wrong I'm just
thinking there's a 24 bit mantissa and a
floating point value so 1.5 times two to
the twelfth negative twelve is like half
the bits I guess it's 1.5 so it's a
little more than half the bits maybe
it's thirty thirteen of the 24 bits I
don't know so I'm not really sure how to
read that I'm not a floating point
accuracy kind of guy otherwise I would
have a very strong statement about what
that was I'm not the point being if you
just needed to be in the ballpark like
I'm trying to normalize this thing more
or less then actually you can do it even
faster right so rather than waiting
three cycles
to issue the next one you can issue it
every cycle you can issue a new one and
they still take forward to come back but
hey that's better than 13 right as well
so even if you have to wait for the
result it's okay so in the old days of
square u square root used to be awful
you really didn't want to do it and in
fact we did all kinds of hacks to not do
it nowadays a square root is kind of
free like it's not free but it's really
low on the set of things you're worried
about whereas before it used to be
really high on the set of things you
were worried about and so there was
definitely a mental shift there when CPU
started getting fast reciprocal square
root because you can tighten and they
now have fast regular square root too
right
so you've got both of those things at
your disposal
and if you want to you can also most of
these routines that give you approximate
results they're set up to also allow you
to refine the results so if you needed a
better answer than this you could
usually do like a newton-raphson a style
refinement step if you want right and
again this all just depends but whether
that's faster than just doing the
correct thing now that it's they're hard
to say right
scrt dependency a Visual Studio feature
only or do other compilers such as GCC
and clang habit 2 also does the
dependency inclusive of us or just see
actually it's it's arguably even worse
in GCC in LLVM but it really depends on
what you're doing what I would say is
that compilers in general have a very
bad habit of relying on their runtime
library to produce code I personally
think that if a compiler if you do not
if you do not pound include anything in
your C program at all a compiler should
produce zero dependencies that is not
what happens compilers actually produce
a ton of dependencies to their own CRT
stack probe calls memset calls mem copy
calls Frank stack frame checking C++
static initializer walking it's awful in
my opinion that should be completely
unacceptable like it shouldn't you
should be absolutely not allowed to
release a C compiler or a C++ compiler
that with no includes and no libs when
you just compile a program somehow it
produces a dependency that should be
completely off the table sadly it's not
so what you will see is that a lot of
compilers both Visual Studio GCC and
clang all of them insert a ton of
garbage into the compiled code that you
then have to produce your own
implementation for if you want to link
without this runtime library I wish that
was just considered completely
unacceptable
like you wouldn't be able to even pass a
single benchmark compiler benchmark if
you did that sadly it's not and so we're
stuck with it
I didn't really see this pop up before
do you think using direct2d for a 2-d
game is a good idea if I want to
implement it from scratch or would you
rather use the x11 12 today
so it's direct 2d I don't even know is
that still around I didn't even realize
that was still around but maybe it is I
wouldn't go anywhere near direct2d it's
a complete pile of garbage I I would
definitely just use the x11 you probably
know ver this last week but how do you
plan to make this faster than what we
had before there's actually two ways
it'll be much faster one we can use mint
many fewer sample points which is
critical and two we can compute those
sample points faster because we don't
have to do stuff like looking at when
something hits a face which sample point
it's using so our ray casting and speed
up dramatically as well so I think we'll
be able to do better now it may not be
the case that it gets it may not get
that much faster on the Ray casting side
because of the expensive voxel lookup
but we'll see
hey I love the trick with the hot
learning but having a hard time grasping
the general idea
could you make a kind of generic
overlooking explanation I mean I
explained it and implemented it in like
one video so I'm not sure how I would
make something more straightforward than
that I mean it's literally like one
video where I like explain it and
implemented it right so I'm not really
sure what I could do to be more clear
than that and asked for whether it works
with third-party libraries I mean that
would completely depend on the
third-party library right again in that
way that I find most people's modern way
of programming to be very bad I would
consider it a bare minimum that any
library you ship should of course work
with hot loading I mean that should just
be a given because as long as that meant
as long as that library is memory
conscious and allows the user to pass in
the memory it wants it to use it will
just work with hot loading but of course
most modern libraries are written just
anything-goes let's call malloc
everywhere and who knows where the
memory came from or where it's going and
at that point yeah sure you lose hot
loading you gain a bunch of
fragmentation problems it's just yeah
moderate code that you find an internet
usually sucks and once in a while it's
not bad but usually it's terrible so the
answer to normally does X where X is a
good programming thing work with Y where
Y is a commonly available third-party
library the answer is usually no because
Y was usually written poorly whether SM
s FM L is in that category not I don't
know because I've never looked at it
and by the way the reason I said dx11
and not dx12 is because dx12 is not very
widely supported unless they've changed
things recently if you ship on dx12 you
can only run on Windows 10 so that's it
you really can't use it unless you don't
want to target Windows 7 and Windows 8
which you know it's like 40% of the
existing market I think so
you know dx12 is a ways away I think in
terms of being something you could
cleanly target for it I mean cuz you
talk about 2d game right you know if
you're talking about the latest game
from you know mr. render land or
whatever where it's like requires the
latest possible machine then maybe
requiring Windows 10 doesn't matter
because you figure you you know you know
that everyone has a really new machine
right but you know that that's just not
it's just not feasible for a 2-d 2-d
game wants to be able to run when it
comes to ship time you want to be able
to like turn off features and turn off
stuff and have it run on pretty low-end
stuff right like why wouldn't you
because it's 2d it shouldn't require the
latest possible system you know
I guess that's what I'd say
so yeah so I don't think director well
directory 12 was really a viable thing
to ship a game on right now unless
you're really really pushing people to
adopt the very latest of everything and
a 2-d game really shouldn't probably be
doing that I guess I'd say it in five
years or so I expect that number will
start to drop pretty well so you know
you might be at a case where 90% of the
game community that you might be
targeting market out there those are
probably going to be running Windows 10
you know and at that point it's probably
fair to say look I don't care about the
other 5% of the market or something or
10% of the market I could I can live on
90% just fine
N+ how many games do people with
machines that old really buy anyway you
know so at some point it becomes fine
much like direct that same thing was
true of DirectX 11 right at one point it
was tied completely to you know Windows
7 or something and so you'd be like well
there's a lot of machines running
Windows XP so I'm not gonna do it or
whatever but eventually everyone kind of
finally kind of regretting the moves up
to Microsoft's latest and worst
operating system and then you know you
can use the next revision up and so on
do you have an opinion on si callbacks
and void star user data do you know any
alternatives do you have an opinion on
GCC's nested functions I am fine with si
callbacks and void star a user data I
like them and I would say there are
plenty of alternatives but none of them
are as good GCC's nested functions
aren't something that I've really used
myself so you know I probably wouldn't
say anything definitive one way or the
other I'm pretty early on his dream my
sound was scratchy did you end up making
a separate thread um so we aren't really
super concerned with sound when we go to
actually finish off everything and want
to start doing testing machines and
stuff we will probably do some changes
to the sound but they probably wouldn't
involve replacing D sound for example I
have a Windows 10 machine at work the
only thing that works correctly on it is
direct sound where sappy fails WDM fails
in high-end audio suffer this is reaper
right which is very good at audio only
direct sound works right so I think
shipping on something that doesn't work
on direct sound is a probably a big
mistake because almost nothing ever
seems to work on Windows sound wise they
introduced it you know they took a page
from the Linux playbook they introduced
seven different API is for sound mixing
doesn't make any sense there's no reason
to do that but they did it and most of
them don't work they randomly work they
randomly don't I don't know how you get
in that situation but they do and so you
know D sound and wave out or like the
two things you can count on that seem to
always work
everything else may just fail nothing
about sounding bad I'm I'll just fail
and who knows why I think it has to do
with whether it's the native whether
it's like a modern Realtek shape or like
you could be plug in a USB external
sound thing or something then suddenly
it only has direct sound emulation or
something I don't know and threading
usually has nothing to do with updating
the sound if you need to just add some
look ahead some more padding to your
sound then you won't get skipping right
about hot loading gang code is it a
common thing between game programmers I
would say yes I feel like most I would
say most games need some kind of hot hot
loading so usually games take one of two
tax either the hot load real code or
they interpret script code so that you
know that's still hot loading right it's
just not compiled but you usually I'm
one of the other because the turnaround
time is too slow otherwise for some of
the things you want to do and turnaround
time can get worse - and in certain game
engines take forever to build and
startup and stuff like that so at that
point you really really need ways to
build tiny parts of them and reload them
in you could argue that's because the
rest of the engines architecture is bad
but hey you know unity and unreal or
both giant pigs so you know if you're
using engines like you really need a way
to interpret or hot load code in those
so you can't be restarting everything
every time it's not it's not feasible
stretched di bits has started failing
after changing the resolution to 960 by
540 so stretch di bits is not going to
fail unless something failed earlier on
to get appropriate surfaces so I I don't
think that's what's probably failing I
think you're probably seeing a fail
seeing a failure somewhere else
would you recommend any free windows
debuggers no I would not however I would
recommend going to remedied HIO and
paying $20 for this one I guess I would
say if you cannot afford $20 for a
debugger I guess I would ask how did you
afford a computer very expensive
maybe it was gifted to you in which case
maybe ask whoever that is to gift you a
remedy BG licensed because the $20 is
it's pretty darn cheap and it's been
moving along really really well so
that's what I would recommend there's
still some features and that are haven't
been added to remedy BG yet so it's not
quite as full featured as you know dev
studio is but it's it's way better than
the dev studio now in terms of like ease
of use it's much much faster startup
much much more quickly and refreshes
infinitely faster so it's just more
pleasant to use and at the rate that
development on it's been going I would
say that I doubt you know I doubt it's
gonna be like five years before it
catches up in terms of features to a
visual studio because video so he
doesn't have that many video game
features so I guess I would say it's
probably going to catch up sooner than
that really the thing that's missing
right now is just like breakpoints
support and and mini dumps I guess those
are the two things doesn't support mini
dumps it doesn't support like advanced
breakpoints like data data and
conditional breakpoints
I'm trying to think of other things
Visual Studio can do that it can't do it
but I can't I mean I think that's it
really so it's closed and I don't know
George is on the chat right now it's X
13 pixels I don't know what his plans
are like I don't know when he's gonna
try to go for a feature parity there but
those things do take a little bit of
work to implement but you know compared
to what he's already gotten done they're
not that big you know so I wouldn't be
surprised to see those things come
online sooner rather than later actually
I mean just based on how much has gotten
done in the past you know six months or
so
have you ever used to lemon tree to
bugger if you're talking about Rad's
telemetry it's not a debugger it's a
performance analyzer unless i'm unless
you're talking about you might be you're
talking about some other telemetry I
don't know what do you tell me give me a
link to what you're talking about when I
look for ways of looking at the vision
of objects in a game eg for ray casting
some sort of graph or tree is always for
as essential are there other ways of
doing such lookups efficiently it seems
like an array sorted by distance from
the origin and doing lookups and ranges
so I guess what I would say is
you're always going to have some kind of
spatial partition but the type of
spatial partition is very widely varying
and so the thing that you suggested
which is an array sorted by the distance
from the origin would be totally valid
that's just a spatial partition where
the partitioning is a binary partition
split in rings around the origin it's a
binary tree right of splits where the
split is a sphere centered at the origin
with a particular radius right I don't
know I don't know really how to add
anything else to it
oh wow I'm just looking to chat George
says data breakpoints just got finished
up today really that's pretty huge
because like I was just saying like the
only things you can really point to I
mean someone else correct me if I'm
wrong because you know I don't know
everything about visual studio debugger
but the only things I could really think
of that you couldn't do in remedy that
you could do in visual studio was like
breakpoint stuff and so if Dena
breakpoints are in there then that
really means conditional breakpoints are
the only thing that aren't in there yet
that'd be about it so it's getting close
l space yl how do you run the back
compiler platforms I don't I just have a
build for every platform so I have like
a dot bat and a dot Sh and so on the
sequel says the other thing you can do
in Visual Studio is have your debugger
not work properly correct you can also
have it be very slow and and George
hasn't implemented that either so
thankfully about MIT map generation I
was wondering why you decided to compute
on CPU and not GPU in addition why'd you
decide to go with a simple box filter
and not something smoother or like a
10th filter so there's a lot you could
say about that let me start with the
second point first the reason I don't
use the reason I tend to use a box
filter when computing MIT maps is
because it means you don't have to turn
on trilinear filtering and that's really
it because the GPU when it subsamples
the MIT map it's doing a box filter so
if you don't do a box filter then your
result of decimating the MIT map of
decimating the texels by two won't agree
with the GPUs decimation by two and you
might get some popping there right so if
you choose to turn on some kind of other
filter you have to decide what what your
what your solution that proms gonna be
is it that it's just not gonna be
noticeable enough you know whatever but
I would be worried about popping right
and another way to say it is that if it
didn't pop then it must be close enough
to a box filter to not have been worth
it right I don't know does that make
sense
as far as why I did it on the CPU and
not the GPU just because there wasn't
really a lot of reason to move it to the
GPU everything we move to the GPU takes
time away
from the GPU which we need for rendering
since we have thread sitting around not
really doing anything during load it
seems like they might as well generate
the MIT Maps
all right I'm gonna kind of wrap it up
are
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for the episode a handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
series at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade hero dot-org
it comes with a source code so you can
follow along with it at home that's it
for today I will be back here tomorrow
it'll be early tomorrow
I have something scheduled in the
afternoon so I have to do hand meet here
a little earlier it'll be 10 to 12
instead of 12 to 1
sorry 12 to 2 alright
so it's a little earlier tomorrow that
may make a difference for some people
just give me the heads up as always on
the watch page when we're not streaming
it's got the schedule so you can head
over there if you're curious about it
that's about it for today I will start
trying to integrate our lighting system
into the game tomorrow and then we can
start to move the computation over to
the probes so again it's a gradual
process it'll take us a few begins to do
but then I think we'll be in good shape
because both I think we can both get a
speed improve it there and it solves our
problem of how do we sample all the rest
of our stuff in the game so how do we
light our grass and our entities and
stuff which we need to do as well so I
think that's what we want I think it'll
be good i but it'll just take us a bit
to get there so a couple weeks and we'll
do it that's it thanks for joining me
till tomorrow have fun programming and
I'll see everyone on the internet to use
everybody