hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here on the show we code a complete game
live on stream we are gonna be doing I
think today I'd like to take a look at
some lighting stuff that we mentioned
let me see if I've got it here I know we
did some drawing all right we put a
little multi red sand thing in there
yesterday and we're gonna have to look
at that a little more detail but first I
think I might also address the
stratified sampling stuff just to get
everything in there I'd like to get all
three of these in there probably before
we start going down and turning the
crank on any one individual thing
because one of the problems is that
they're kind of interrelated right I
don't really know how to
compartmentalize them very well other
than saying you know well we know that
each of these might be useful and might
make a difference and so I kind of want
to have them in there as we start to
play with any given one of them and try
to improve the variance I'd like to kind
of know what we're dealing with here
right so I'm gonna take a look at the
stratified sampling stuff today and in
order to take a look at the stratified
sampling stuff I think what we might
want to do is put in a real random
number generator at least a reasonable
one and just maybe get a little bit of a
feel for how that stuff is going so you
know I'm not a number theory guy so I'm
not really gonna spend a lot of time
talking to you about random number
generators in any real depth because
they're not my area of expertise I tend
to just go with the following method
which is that trust that some number of
theory people out there have done a good
job making random number generators but
that I don't know who they are and then
create some kinds of tests that are
representative of how I want to be using
my random number generator and verify
which ones of the random number
generators that they have created work
well with the constraints that I want
right so that's my typical approach to
random number generation is like saying
okay look I don't know how to make a
good random number generator it would
take me some time to study to learn what
I would need to know to really
be good at that right lots of people
have made random number generators but I
don't know which of them to trust so
what I can do is make tests that show me
visually whether or not a random number
generator is doing what I need and it
select one that's the fastest one
probably that satisfies that test that's
all I really need right and that's a
nice luxury that we have in game
development that wouldn't fly in
cryptographic security for example
because there there is nothing to
visualize in cryptography whether
something is breakable or not isn't
necessarily visible to the eye now
obvious problems may be visible to the
eye but non-obvious problems that are
still exploitable may not be and so
there's plenty of fields where you need
to really know you're number theory and
have a really good idea about how these
things work and be very up on the field
in order to make a good decision about
where you would get your entropy from
right game development isn't really one
of them unless you're talking about
securing the channel of a multiplayer
game let's say in which case you're back
to cryptography but assuming you're
talking about what we normally care
about in terms of random number
generation which is visual effects or
gameplay distribution of things right
what you can typically do is just create
some test that shows the output from a
typical run of the NAND emember
generator in the situation did you care
about and then you can usually evaluate
it from that and that's and that's it
right so in our case for example what we
can do is we can look at what the
distribution of rays shot by a random
number generator is and then we can look
to see whether that distribution of rays
is giving us some kind of an unfortunate
clustering that we don't like if that's
the case then we know that that random
node renter isn't quite what we need and
we can use one that's more sophisticated
or different if we aren't seeing that if
we're if it looks like the random number
pattern is pretty stable I'm pretty
consistent then we really just don't
have that problem you don't need to
consider it much further
so that's really that my take on on
random number generation that's how I
typically view random number generation
and so what I would say about that is
that's how we're gonna approach it for
this problem and probably any problem in
handmade Hira and we're not gonna dig
any deeper into it than that because
that's really not my field of expertise
and I wouldn't really have much to say
right I just feel like I don't know
there's some numbers that come out of it
right and that's not particularly
valuable alright so the first thing we
need to do here regardless and this has
nothing to do with the random number
generator this is even just basic before
we even get there we're gonna need a way
to see what's going on because right now
we have no idea right right now all we
know is what we see on the screen and
what we see on the screen right oops is
as follows here we go
so here is our screen and here is our
lighting and what we can see from the
lighting is that we get a little bit of
flicker we would like to reduce that
flicker but we have no idea
beyond that what's actually going on
right I mean as I move around this world
it looks like the lighting is working
relatively well and it looks like it's
fairly accurate so we don't have much
reason to believe that for example our
ray cast is totally wrong but on the
other hand we have no actual hard
evidence that the Ray cast is really
even doing your ray cast we don't know
we're not drawing anything so what I'd
like to start with before we investigate
that aspect of the city of the program
any further is I would like to figure
out some way to draw a say for example
one of these squares be able to pick one
of the lighting points on it and say
let's look on any given frame let's see
what ray directions it is sampling right
just a basic visualization tool like
that would be nice because it would let
us know whether we're even sampling in a
reasonable set of directions to begin
with right I expect to see a nice sort
of random
shooting out of the hemisphere with no
real correlation just some random white
noise there right so if we were to look
down and say this one I would just see
like a bunch of random line shooting out
of it in all different directions but we
don't know that that's what we'd
actually see maybe we'd see them all
shooting one direction one frame in all
shooting another direction on another
frame and that would give us some
information that some of our flickr is
actually coming from just really biased
sampling that we could get rid of with
stratified sampling or a better in a
number generator or blue noise or bla
bla bla bla bla right so that's more
what I want to look at today is just
like let's get into some sort of a
position where we can assess our
sampling method at all then take a look
at whether the random numbers need to be
improved then take a look at whether
stratified means to happen in general
and then we'll we can be a little bit
more satisfied that our sampling
direction is not part of our problem
which right now we don't know it could
very well be all right so if I remember
correctly at one point we did actually
make a way to draw a line I think I
don't actually know if that's true I
think a long time ago we did though so
I'm gonna take a look and see if that's
true
so there is a line segment call so in
theory it seems like we would be able to
have some kind of a of a line drawn in
the direction of sampling so what I'd
like to do here is sort of put this push
line segment call into action if
possible by loading up goop I did not
load up our project file there we go
by going in here and sort of trying to
figure out a way to extract what
directions were sampled from something
and draw them so in here I'm just going
to go ahead and say all right let's
let's take the lighting code and in here
we've got this output lighting points
for curse function what if we just said
okay one of the things that we want to
do in here where we do out letting
points in addition to doing this we're
also going to do something that outputs
a bunch of direct
sampling lines right so how would we do
that well in theory we might even be
able to do it in here somewhere inside
compute light propagation I don't know
how smart of an idea that would be but
for example what we could do is say look
here in sample Hemisphere we get a bunch
of these sample directions what we could
do in here is is try to draw them right
the reason I don't really like doing
that is because we don't know whether
we're set up in here for that and we're
introducing some extra coding here so
what I might do instead is say look
let's put the code for drawing those out
here somewhere right so if I'm going to
do output letting points for curse right
after that I'm gonna do something where
I draw some of these line segments okay
and what I'm going to do is I'm gonna
say alright there's a base P right so
there's a there's a base B here and I
don't care what the color is color can
just be white for now it doesn't matter
and we'll think about that in a second
what we want that to be I don't know
what the thickness should be we'll tune
that later when we see how thick it
actually is but then we just need a base
P plus you know a sort of a draw length
times a direction that's all we really
need we know we've got that white bitmap
situation going on here because we don't
really want to texture these guys at all
and we've got the render group so if I
want to I can do like something here
where I just have debug lines right so I
can do you thirty two debug line index
equals zero debug line index is less
than however many we're gonna do here
debug - right
and I don't know maybe maybe I can even
split this in here do bug line count
something like that and then when I can
do is again just grab these debug lines
out of the solution and and just assume
that they're getting stored right you
know what I could even do is make the
color be something that can be recorded
here as well so that we can record those
debug line colors a little more
specifically right so that's a pretty
good way to
push the debug drawing out of the out of
the part of the code that's actually
doing work and let it get drawn later so
what I could do here is say okay let's
suppose that we've got in this letting
solution just some information about
these debug lines so I can maybe you
just have it here a little struct called
debug line in there I'll have you know
from P to P and a color and and you know
I don't know if I really want to
thickness or not I probably don't for
now that'll probably be hard-coded and
then in here yeah I can just say okay
I've got a debug line it's gonna be
coming out of this array like so I ends
I'll just let this tell me what to do so
I won't even do it that way I'll do it
like this right so then we're drawing
these line segments at the end after we
draw everything else and off they go
so when I do this I just need some way
of storing these and pushing them on so
I can do debug lines and say that
there's you know however many debug
lines there are I don't care can be some
really high number and then I can just
have a debug line count in here and we
can just draw a debug lines to our
hearts content all day long it doesn't
matter so when we come through and we
start our solution we can just set the
debug line count to zero and then when
we're doing anything else we can just
push things on there now I don't want to
push on all of the samples because that
would be absurd I need some way of
targeting a particular sample point so
what I'm gonna do here is just say like
a well okay if the sample point index
for now you know equal sample point 100
I don't know why I'm picking 100 but
we'll want to set that later let's say
then we'll just go ahead and push these
on here so we'll just say push debug
line and we'll give it the lighting
solution and then I'll say well I know
where I'm sampling from right
and I knew which direction I was going
and I can adjust the length here however
I want right now we'll do it a metre
maybe we want to shorter than that maybe
well how longer than that I don't know
doesn't really matter if I can push the
debug line in here and then I just need
a color for now we can just set the
color to be white so that would be it
and it would draw a debug line for every
Ray that shot out of sample point 100
and that would be it right the other
thing I could do is like it's say if I
hit a box I'm gonna set it to white if I
didn't in a box you know I'm gonna set
it to something else so maybe I could
even do green in red so you know let's
say I do a green for a hit and a red for
a Miss and then I can also get a little
bit more information there by just
setting the color to whether or not I
thought I hit something another thing I
could do is draw to actually the place
where the Ray hit now I think about it
that might be kind of nice right so if
the Ray didn't hit anything I would draw
one thing if there we did hit something
I would draw something else and that
seems kind of nice as well so in here I
can recalculate rape Eve if I want to
print so I can do here like end point
equals that and then I can say if a
hitbox end point equals that and then I
can sort of say alright well we'll just
draw out from the sample point some
distance right if the the rate you know
it's the same equation I could simplify
this even more in fact it's really just
this right
where did that code go just that that
was weird all right that was really
strange it's just this right I'm just
saying if there was a hitbox like if we
actually hit something then I want to go
out to where the rate hit otherwise I'm
just going to use that draw like that
stand-in right so you know we take a
look at this and that's pretty
reasonable that'll draw a line to the
point that we actually thought we found
right or that the surface we thought we
found otherwise we aren't gonna bother
we'll just draw some some distance away
some short distance away right and maybe
that maybe one meters too much so maybe
like you know a quarter meters high so
it's a pretty short line if didn't hit
anything right okay so that will do that
pushing for us and all I need to do now
is make an actual function that puts
that on here so in here we'd say okay
let's do a push debug line that push
debug line is gonna have all the stuff
that we just said and what we'll do here
is just say well there's a debug line
that is the solution debug lines plus
debug line count plus plus and again we
want to just do an assertion there that
we're not overflowing the buffer
so we're just gonna say look as long as
you get room just a big line let's push
one on and then fill it out with exactly
the information that we just got and
that's it so that's all I wanted to do
good and now in theory we can as soon as
we debug this we would actually have
something that's gonna draw these little
debug lines for us not in this mode but
in this mode right oh my I guess one
thing I failed to account for is the
fact that that point is gonna move
around that's less useful well yeah
we'll have to do a little something to
fix that shouldn't be too hard but I
hadn't I forgot about that these points
aren't coming in with any particular ID
on them so there's that that thickness
is way too thick that is one thing that
we should fix here those lines are just
are just way too thick let's drop that
down significantly there we go that's a
little bit better I might make that a
bit bigger so that's more what we're
looking for here there we go and
I mean ideally you know I want to be
able to do one close to here so I think
what I'll do is I'm gonna do just a
little bit of cheekiness here I'm based
gonna say like look okay let's do
something that's like debug point index
and what we'll do is we'll say instead
of a hundred I'm gonna say whatever the
debug point is is the one that we draw
right so then when we start out what
I'll do is I'll just do a sweep where I
do a test and you know we're gonna go
over these points anyway and what I'll
do is I'll just say look there's gonna
be like a closest point distance or
debug point distance and that's going to
be set to f3 to max and when I come
through here I'll just say look if this
particular point whatever point we're on
if point P let's do a this distance I
will do a distance square root of the
point whatever point P is and our debug
point location our debug location which
for now we'll just be 0 0 0
I'll just see look if we can find the
point that's closest to the one to where
we sort of want to pick points at we'll
just use that one and that should be
relatively stable so I'll just take the
closest one and go from there its
distance
so that something like this right and
that allows us to set an actual location
and then that location we can move
anywhere we want obviously and it will
hopefully always pick a stable point so
there you go and that does seem to
working pretty well okay so let's go
ahead and increase the resolution here
down to where we're at that is shooting
out the bottom this is the bottom point
here so it might be a little too thick
yeah that's a little bit better so I
guess it depends on the distance we want
a view in front obviously because these
are not screen spaced lines when I mean
to debug view I kind of want to set my
clipping plane too much closer so we can
see things a little bit more easily so I
kind of wonder if again if that clipping
plane also wants to be modified when
we're in that mode so in here where we
do debug camera you can see we set the
near clip plane to three meters right
because it's very far out that was kind
of by design right but if we're in debug
camera almost want to say set it to
something much closer
so like you know normally we clip there
if I switch to a debug camera I drag the
clipping so I can get right in there and
see what's going on so now right when we
when we view one of these things I can
really sort of zoom in and see it much
more accurately yeah if that makes sense
so what I'd like to do is move this up a
little because I'd like one to be sort
of in the region we actually care about
here not upside down so what do we do to
get that is I'm just gonna go and take
debug location I'm just gonna move it up
a little bit I don't know where it
should be exactly but I'm gonna try and
get something that'll be on the up side
so here you go
right and one of the things that you can
see about this so you know if we just
take a look at this in context here and
I'm gonna I I'm gonna basically avoid
doing any work here I'm gonna set up
into debug mode so that the framerate
will be super slow so I can look at this
a little bit more cleanly rather than
adding a pause feature oh well you know
what no I'm dumb why would you do that
don't do that
that's stupid all I really have to do is
this so when we're in this world mode
here we know whether or not yeah inside
the lighting solution we can just have a
thing that's like update debug lines so
what I can do is just say like the debug
lines get updated when the debug lines
get updated and and that's just how that
works I could even make it so that this
output lighting points always happens I
don't know how well I can really do that
let me see if I can so let's let's just
see if inside here inside lighting test
I don't know if I can actually make
these calls here if everything's set up
properly for it
I'm gonna see whether I can yeah so I
would have to well you know what I could
still do that though where's that here
it is
so it looks like I can do that just fine
and so that's kind of nice because now I
can have these going at any time right
and then what I can do is just make it
so that whether or not they're updated
is actually predicated on consuming on
whether or not we're sort of saying that
we should update them right so what I
can do is say all right if solution
update debug lines is active then we
clear otherwise we don't and inside push
we do it as well so now when we run
nothing will happen
right we won't draw any lines because
that flag isn't set to true and then
what I can do is inside world mode here
I can add a key that will swap that in
and out right so what I can do is just
say like okay you know with two keys
pressed then the test lighting update
debug lines just get stalled so now I
can do that and you can see that when I
freeze it we can see exactly where those
lines got shot and who they got shot to
you know I'm saying and one nice thing
about this again is we can sort of
validate whether or not our ray casting
is working correctly or not and so what
you can see here especially is you can
see one of the artifacts of our
multi-resolution stuff so do you see
where this ray ended here it didn't
actually hit anything right and so what
happened there and this is maybe
something again that we want to look at
this is why visualization is very good
because we don't actually know if it
here if I can do it it's hitting this
right
and exiting out early right because we
said that if it went that far it could
that was something we said right yeah so
anyway looking at these looking at these
debug lines here I would also say that
it's kind of odd I would say that
looking at these debug lines I think I
also can see some reasons why I don't
why our spatial partition needs to be
improved for multi rez so one of the
problems is because of the way that
we're doing the splitting we end up with
not very good spatial distributions
right like these things here you really
want you almost want more of like an
octree where you're gonna fill the
entire space whether the bounds of that
thing enclose it or not because for the
purposes of early outing you're ray
casting you want to hit the thing that's
over here sort of probably I don't know
maybe you don't it's hard to say it
might be fine we'll see anyway ignoring
that for now because that's not really
what we're talking about here one thing
you can see just by looking at this
directly is that stratified sampling
probably would help our flicker quite a
bit you can see like sometimes it's
looking over here sometimes it's not
looking over there at all sometimes it's
looking over there somebody's not
looking over there at all so for 16
Ray's spreading them out more evenly is
probably a pretty good idea right just
in terms of how much flicker we're
probably getting from this very
different set of distributions I think
would be good it doesn't look to me
like the random number generator is all
that bad I mean we haven't really tested
it yet so it might still be again it's
not a random generator right now it's
actually a table but it doesn't look
like it's doing anything particularly
stupid it looks fairly white noisy
actually so I don't know that we're
gonna improve that all that much we
might but I don't know that we're gonna
improve it all that much so the
important thing here do I think is to go
with that maybe the stratified sampling
a little bit more and try to guarantee
that we have a little more coherence as
to where we're shooting these rays and
see if that helps our flicker a little
bit so how might we do that let's take a
look
now in this case we're just trying to
get a picture of the lighting
environment that's around us we don't
really have a reflectance function that
we're worried about and so that's gonna
inform the design this a little bit the
reason it informs the line is a little
bit is because if we did have a specific
reflection function that we cared about
or a stratified sampling would want to
take that into account right because if
we know that we very heavily reflect
light from a particular set of
directions and don't really reflect like
much from others we probably shouldn't
bother looking as much in the area that
we don't reflect light from because
there's those samples even if they come
back with light aren't really going to
contribute to our overall look very much
and so concentrating samples there would
typically be a bad idea in this case we
don't really have that the only thing we
have is a cosine fall-off and so to a
certain extent the only thing we really
know is that things that are up here
tend to contribute more than things that
are down out here right so it does mean
that we probably want to take a look at
like this outbound cone here and maybe
sample this more heavily than the sine
cone here for example something like
that right that's just a you know kind
of a vague a vague notion so how might
we sample this well now if we imagine
looking down from the top here and we
sort of have the the idea that well
there's there's sort of you know rough
directions we might sample out right
looking down from the top you know one
of the things that we kind of want to do
is we want to say we want to sort of
look out in all directions a little bit
right so we probably want to ensure that
we're gonna look you know out into the
world in some way that sort of resembles
this
right we want to ensure that we shoot
one array kind of this way one rate kind
of that way right we sort of want to
make sure that we're shooting rain is
kind of out in those directions and then
in terms of the elevation of those rays
we probably want to make sure that we
have some distribution across the
elevation as well how exactly we want to
do that is not immediately clear we'll
have to sort of play around that a
little bit but it's you know it's
something like this so there's a lot of
ways we could imagine doing this but I
think the way that I would probably say
we should do it is with sort of a bit of
a maybe templating scheme to a certain
extent like I might say maybe what we
can do here is have some notion of the
hemisphere where we've pre computed some
of these and then maybe we just blend
between them right in order to at
certain ratios in order to get what we
want right
I'm gonna have to think about exactly
how I want to do this so similarly if
you imagine looking at the thing this
way certain visit we said like stuff
that's really coming in at at a steep
angle there it's not as useful so we'd
also like to sort of be shooting out
more that way more you know more biased
towards upwards and we'd like to make
sure we shoot some in the upwards
direction so we've got kind of a lot of
competing concerns here it's a little
bit difficult it's pretty easy to make
sure that we shoot some in the upwards
direction right because you can imagine
just taking the surface normal of
whatever this point is right and basing
some randomness off of that surface
normal so we could pretty easily shoot
in sort of a square around that right or
a cone and make sure that we generate
like at least four points in that
direction always right so we could
always guarantee that we get some facing
upward and so then the question is just
how do we make the ones that are facing
into the sideways and one way to do it
again might be to take those maybe do
the exact same thing maybe we just have
like a series of sort of of these
vectors and we're going to go ahead and
construct the randomness off of that I
am curious I don't even remember what
we're doing right now
so what we're doing right now is we just
say all right generate something in the
sphere and then if it happens to be
pointing the wrong way to flip it right
so that's yeah
that's pretty basic right one of the
problems that we have here is our
lighting points don't remember their
basis coordinates so we don't actually
while we know the normal we don't know
the x and y axes and that's probably
something we need to actually keep if
we're going to be constructing regular
sampling based on that so that's a
little bit of a tricky situation because
it means we'd have to store a lot more
information on our lighting we have this
information in the box itself and so the
question is yet do we really want to
bloat this lighting point out to the
point where it stores all that you know
and I don't know but so if we had an
x-axis and a y-axis here for example we
would be able to store that here inside
lighting test when we come through and
we write out the normal we can also
write out the x and y axis because
they're actually known just based on the
surface right the surface knows that
information right you could this this
call right here generates it for the box
so we can if we want to just store a
surface x-axis and surface y-axis and we
know the normal points out from that so
that would pretty much be it again it
just costs a lot more to like romp that
information in there but that's what we
would need so then when we go to sample
Hemisphere sample Hemisphere is going to
be a little bit different now so sample
a hemisphere would need so and now it
has all of the information that it needs
in to do constructions of that nature
but it still doesn't have quite all the
information it needs to do everything
it's going to need to do and I'll
explain why in a second so this won't
make any change right if we run this now
we would see the exact same sampling
pattern that we saw before in theory
anyway so that's fine
so the problem that we're getting it now
is like if we if we take a look at
what's going on here we need to figure
out a way to tell it what kind of
sampling we actually wanted here
so we're gonna have to pass a sample
index so it knows what strata it's using
right all right so let's suppose yeah
like I said let's suppose we were gonna
do something along these lines let's
suppose we did the simplest possible
thing first which is to say we just went
okay look if the sample index is less
than 8 or R greater than 8 let's suppose
we split it up into two halves one half
samples upwards one half samples
outwards right and that's all we're
gonna do at the moment that's that's it
right so what we could do here we can
actually do this relatively easily I
think because since we have the complete
X Y and n which is effectively the z
axis since we have the complete axis
system we can construct sort of
arbitrary things here so let's suppose
we did something kind of completely
ridiculous at first just so we can
verify it's actually working what I
could do is say all right you know we're
gonna produce a result here and in one
case what I'm going to do if the sample
index is greater than 8 I'm gonna sample
out the sides of this thing right so
what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna take and
do a normalize
but I'm gonna do it a little bit
differently than we're doing it before
I'm gonna take a random bilateral x the
x-axis a random bilateral x the y-axis
so you can be anywhere in the plane but
the z-axis
which is the normal right the z-axis I'm
actually going to say you only go up
halfway right now on the other hand in
this one I'm going to do the opposite
I'm gonna say you can pick anything you
want but you're gonna have to pick a Z
that's over halfway always and I want
these to be less than halfway right does
that make sense so I'm basically saying
I'm breaking this up and again I'm not
suggesting this is good at all I'm just
showing an example of how we can break
this up don't ask me what I thought I
was doing there okay so now when I run
it I expand and do my my sampling I'm
hoping to sort of get a little bit more
oh wait
alright I'll be honest that's not at all
what I expected
I must have messed something up
well actually no maybe that is sort of
roughly what I expected kind of chaotic
out the sides I expecting a little bit
more sort of distribution there let me
just make this more pronounced to make
sure I'm actually doing what I think I
might do so these should be really flat
out to the sides right so now you can
kind of see that right do you see how
we've got these ones that are shooting
flat out to the sides and these ones
that are shooting up I'm gonna stop
updating debug and just count right
so if you see how many are coming up
here 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 I can quite count 8
there
should be eight can't quite tell if
there are they're all kind of quite
close to each other one two three six
seven eight yes there are you know there
should be eight around the ring one two
three four five six seven eight yep so
you can see that is is working so I'm
not nuts and you can kind of see what I
mean right so now we've got some that
are pointing upward and some that are
pointing outward right and they're not
the same now as I move around you can
actually see that it did change the
character of the lighting quite a bit in
fact because we're biasing our sampling
upwards now you get people who have
lights directly above them finding that
light much more intently intensely right
because it's always gonna make sure that
it finds that light shooting a lot of
stuff up in that direction
however sideways lighting maybe not so
good because now you've only got eight
and they're shooting way out to the side
where they can't really have much of a
contribution right so it really does
change the character of the lighting to
bias the sampling even though the
sampling is still random and possibly
still covering most of the thing it's
not really though because there's
probably a bit in there it's not
covering you can see that it does make a
bit of a difference so it's not it is
relevant how you choose to partition the
space okay but this is not really what
we want to do we want to do something
that's going to give us a fairly even
hemisphere covering on every frame so
the question is how are we going to
break up the hemisphere into pieces that
will work well like that and so like I
said one way I think to do this would be
to do a hemisphere table that kind of
lets us pick a base vector that we've
sort of pre distributed around the
hemisphere and sample off of that the
way I'm going to do that first is I'm
just gonna do none of this
instead what I'm going to do is I'm
going to say all right
when we sample the hemisphere what I'm
doing here is I'm going to take a table
that we have and I'm going to use the
sample index and I'm going to and the
sample index so the sample index I want
to wrap so if you sample more than is in
the table you just go back to beginning
of the table so what I want to do here
is the sample index I'm going to and it
against the array count of the sample
table so ever many samples there are in
the table right what I want to do here
is say whatever hungry samples are in a
table I want to take the mask that would
tell you how many there were and I'm
gonna mask it off now this only works if
it's a power of two right because
subtracting one from something only
generates the mask if it's a power of
two because if it's power 2 then in bits
it looks like one zero zero zero zero
zero something yes it's just a sum set
of zeros right so just to attract one
from it you lose that initial one and
get ones everywhere else and that's the
mask that keeps the thing anding
properly right that keeps the thing
within range
so very simple bit operation with a
constant there to make sure that we
always wrap and then I'm just going to
say this has to be a power of two
so all I'm going to do at first is just
sample the sample table and that way we
can see what the sample table is we're
not gonna inject any randomness into it
now this is a very bad idea for lighting
quality because it means it will just
find an exact as you move around as
it'll just like immediately like have
discontinuous lighting as you move
around but it will allow us to see
whether our sample table looks right if
that makes sense
so what I can do here is you say alright
let's build the sample table then we
only have to do this at the beginning of
the game but I'm gonna do it every frame
anyway because it's gonna be pretty
cheap to build this table we're out of
here nope here we go so what I'm gonna
do here is just fill the table so sample
table what we want to do is kind of
build this table up and we need to come
up with a way to sort of distribute
these points now maybe we don't I don't
know that we really want it to be 16
long and maybe that we want to do 18
long and sample twice from every one of
them for example I'm sorry just eight
long and sample twice for me two of them
that's hard to say I'm not sure so we'll
have to play around with that and see
how how big we actually want the table
to be and that's how many sort of
buckets of the hemisphere we want
because we can choose to have sixteen
buckets on the hemisphere and sample
them all once for sixteen rays or we can
have eight buckets on the hemisphere and
sample them all twice for sixteen rays
right so it's kind of up to us how we
want to do that that's just yeah depends
on what we find to be more effective so
if we take a look at the sample table
here I'm gonna go ahead and set first of
all I want
obviously one that's directly up I think
that's a pretty important thing to do
sample around the
vector I'd like to sample ones that are
close to directly up so I also probably
want to do something that's like four
quadrants around there I'm not sure
exactly how I want to do that but you
know we can play with this a little bit
so this is just gonna be me sort of
randomly distributing these so I have
one up and then like you know four
quadrants around that one up then we
kind of maybe move down to maybe the
eighth wide ring all the way around and
I'm not sure exactly how we want to do
that but again so let's just say we did
something like this two three four five
six seven eight so something like this
where we said all right let's do every
permutation of these so you do this more
systemically so we do
[Music]
so okay we've got negative 5 negative 5
negative 5 0 negative 5 5 so that's all
the ones on the bottom then we would
have those 6 there and then we also
would need
the ones that have zero on them so we
just need negative 5 5 negative 5 0
negative 5 positive 5 5 negative 5 5 0 5
5 and I guess we're missing one here oh
no because we don't need 0 0 so then in
here we just have 0 negative 5 so that's
it that's all
and then 4 13 14 and 15 those are just
random samples around the edge like low
ones we don't really haven't quite
enough there for that so I don't know
maybe the answer is there should be
something here a little bit more
rigorous I'm not sure let's say this is
just something like that and we're and
we're miss we'd be missing one here as I
guess what I'm saying because we really
want one more so what we could do is
just say all right maybe it's more like
this and then we do get that last corner
sample
so that's a sample table right and it's
all good and in theory now we should be
able to see a very regular sampling
pattern so it should be no flicker at
all right because it's OB sampling
exactly the same stuff and that is true
right there's no flicker but it's not
sampling the legging very well because
it just only happens in that one in
those specific directions right okay so
here are those directions I'll be honest
that doesn't look quite right to me does
it well no actually does that's okay
yeah that looks pretty good I think what
what I'm seeing here is these should be
a little bit lower than they are but
other than that I think we're pretty
good so those those mid-range octant
ones maybe need to be flattened down a
little bit so you know maybe these need
to be more like this right
and that looks a lot better to me and as
you can see the lugging still works just
fine it maybe just isn't quite so
accurate in a lot of cases and it has
some weird like kind of jerks on and off
right because it never has any soft
smoothing around those edges but it gets
rid of that and it misses some obvious
lighting things right but again you can
see that it gets rid of the flicker
because it doesn't change per frame it
only it's only when something moves so
that's exactly what we're trying to mix
in here is the fact that a stable
sampling pattern wouldn't flicker but it
misses information so we're trying to
combine the two together to like get the
information over several frames if we
can but reduce that flicker by keeping
the samples stratified in a similar way
so okay so let's suppose we added a
little bit of noise in there now to an
ample sample Hemisphere right we come up
with one of these and maybe you know
let's say all we do is we just perturb
around them a little bit right because
we certainly could in fact we still
leave this in here which I don't know if
we even really need to do that
plissier so if we take random bilateral
so let's suppose we just do pretty small
perturbations for now
you know what let me do it this way so
let's suppose we just said okay you know
we're just going to do a small
perturbation for now maybe a quarter at
most and our results just gonna be
whatever the base vector is perturbed by
that much okay and let's see what kind
of same thing that gives us just as a
start right not saying that's
particularly good but you know there we
go so it seems like that's maybe still a
little bit too much movement let me see
here
combat down a little so there we go
that's that's maybe a little bit more
gentle right
unfortunately there you can still see
we're not really covering everywhere
probably can see these two things don't
quite get together let's let's expand
that out a little bit
their debt now they're now they're much
more able to sort of converge there so
you can see we still get a lot of
apparent flicker there right in terms of
how much noise are you can sort of see
it I'm going to go ahead and see what
the threshold is there
so if I set the ratio to zero so we're
just using completely stable basis so
now we get no flicker right let's
suppose I set it up to put in a little
bit so you can pretty much see you know
the the flicker appears very quickly you
know very little perturbation of the
sampling directions already yields a
pretty reasonable flicker there right I
mean it's not horrible but it's
definitely there so let's say we put in
a lot but it's pretty is definitely the
reduction is noticeable
like you definitely do get significantly
less liquor as you bring that number
down
I also forget how many frames of
smoothing we're doing right now let's
take a look at that number
I don't know where RT Update is there it
is so right now we're doing 20 frames
right looks like a smoothing so 20
frames is at 60 frames a second it's
like a third of a second of lag and the
lighting right so we could do more like
if we wanted to we could we could bump
that up a little bit I'm curious to know
like what the happy medium is there as
well
you know I forgot about that little
thing where you can look over ledges
so I'm not sure how I feel about that I
mean another strategy I could try here
which sounds kind of nuts when I say it
but actually maybe make some sense is if
we didn't use randomized sampling so we
actually use 100% predictable sampling
and just did the samples over the number
of frames we smooth so let's say we say
there's 10 frames of smoothing that's a
hundred and 60 raycast and we just
recast them completely deterministically
over those frames kind of a weird way to
look at it but
I mean in theory it would work so just
like to give you an example of what I
mean by that
you know let's suppose I said okay look
here's how this is gonna go down instead
of having a random series that's stuffed
in here we're just we're not gonna do
that anymore instead what we're gonna do
is we're gonna say look we've got a sort
of a ticker right we've got like a
little like I don't know a counter some
kind a entropy counter so um when you
come through here we're gonna have an
entropy counter and we're gonna say
alright at the end the entropy counter
we add to that and if the end of you
Pantera is greater or equal to the frame
and to pay frame count then it it's
equal to zero again so it just it just
counts around there okay and so then
what we say is something completely
ridiculous which is like alright so then
we say well our T update value is just
one over whatever the that frame count
is so we need it to blend over this many
frames so that entropy frame count is
gonna tell us what that T update value
is our entropy frame count is just
however many we want to blend over right
so I don't know ten or twenty something
like that right let's say twenty because
that's what it was right then what we do
is when we go to seed the series we
don't store the series anymore right
series does not get stored sueing here
instead what we do is we say okay we're
never gonna store the series the series
just gets seated off of the entropy for
this particular frame
so we say okay the the series is just
seated because I think this is how the
service works anyway I don't remember
how we did this here do we have a seed
function there we go
so we just say look you're gonna random
seed off of the solutions entropy
freight counter and that entropy counter
is just you know some nonsense who knows
what's going on here that produces some
value random we stepping value I
produces some value off of this series
right that's that's it that's all it
does and so this way we know that every
we we wrap every end frames and sample
the same stuff again right does that
make sense
so this way we know that our our entropy
is not completely random
it actually cycles so if we were not to
look we should see this looking the same
it should it should be like a repetitive
pattern
although honestly it doesn't look like a
pedicab to me at all
so maybe that ain't right
oh yeah so I guess the problem there is
every individual point is still gonna be
in a different order so this would have
to be per point that we do that actually
so I take that back
this actually has to look since we're
gonna do the random sample here how
often is this serious get used just
there right yeah um so this actually has
to be like that and sorry like that and
we probably would want to randomize it
based on some properties of the point as
well but sorry so this is actually the
stable version and so now it should look
like a repetitive pattern I think
yes and now it does look like a
repetitive pattern
okay so now in theory it's only picking
up you know over the flames where it's
doing the blend now at least in theory
it's it's going to be picking up the
same results every 20 frames right so
it's kind of an integration over those
frames the problem is we're not really
doing a fair average over those in any
particular way like we're not doing
something which allows us to really
utilize all those samples because we're
just kind of blending towards whatever
the latest value is and that's not
necessarily what we would want so the
question is can we do a little bit
better than that by maybe making this be
more of a moving average that would
stabili come out I'm not sure if we can
do that directly but like here's an
example of how we would try so if we
take a look at how we're doing our
lurking right now you can see us doing
this here if instead of doing it that
way we know that T update is basically
the averaging amount so if instead what
we did is just accumulated
trying to think of like how I could make
this into a stable marriage this is
basically like one of those IR filter
kind of problems
yeah I'm not really sure I'm not really
sure we can do much better than that
hard to say here's what I will say so if
we made the period about half so you
know we updated
I guess I want the other way around so
the tea update amount is going to be
about you know half of whatever the
entropy frame count is so we'll update
more slowly than the number of samples
that we take I'm curious to know if that
if that's something that gives us good
result of course I need to probably
change this to be more like that to be a
fair comparison
so I'm not sure how much that really
helps us though
I'm also kind of curious so there's just
so many factors here I'm having trouble
I guess I probably need to like start
concentrating on particular ones with
the other thing I was wondering is how
much of that is from the average
direction to light and how much isn't so
I'm curious like if we were to say hey
yeah the solution average Direction oh
so we're still doing that
this is strictly color channel variance
right this is what it would look like if
we actually used the directional
component as well which honestly doesn't
really look much different in fact it
doesn't it looks a little different in
terms of the lighting solution but the
flicker actually doesn't seem to change
at all
like it doesn't seem to be an
appreciable source of variance for
whatever reason so yeah so I'm not sure
I feel like I'm missing something here
cuz I feel like these should not all be
as similar as they are and the fact that
they're not is a little confusing to me
I wonder if our blending is still not
quite what it should be
um so here's I'm gonna I want to check a
few things here so for starters I'm
gonna try doing a little experiment here
I'm gonna do and entropy frame count of
10 but a tea update of 1 so I just want
to see what happens if we just use its
if we just use the whole lighting
solution every time
because I want to see how noisy that is
right and that's like incredibly noisy
so take the smoothing out of the
equation see how this is doing here
and you know I mean I guess I can
understand why you know because if you
look at what's happening here like let's
suppose I move you know I take a look at
at how the like this this one frame that
we're drawing here for example I mean
this one point that we're drawing here
if I move this cube in the way so that
occasionally it hits it right then
exactly what I expect to happen sort of
happens which is that on a frame when it
does hit the kit when it when it finds
this this cube it'll be bright and on a
frame when it doesn't it'll be darker
right it'll go bright dark bright dark
right and that's exactly what you would
expect from that from the random
sampling so that's like unsurprising
and Sue the ability for those really
bright lights to sort of have that
effect on everything I guess is you know
it's kind of a it's kind of an
unfortunate aspect of that but so let me
go ahead and and play with this a little
bit here so I want to look at the
reframe camped so let's suppose the
entropy frame count was one this pattern
should become perfectly stable right it
does so you can kind of see that that
gets rid of all of the flicker right but
it means that a lot of light just never
picks up the fact that there was a light
near it right which is unfortunate and
again you know that can be solved
certainly and in fact we could even say
well you know maybe the entropy frame
count is a very small number maybe we
only sample like for entropy frames
right and then if the smoothing was over
a much longer period of time maybe
that's sufficient right so maybe if the
T update is back to 20 frames but the
entropy count fin count is only four
then the amount of variance you can get
in there is pretty low right and you can
see from that right that there isn't a
lot of flicker by comparison I guess
although you still get a little bit you
know in and out there
the other thing I could do I suppose is
say well I could actually track all four
like always track all four samples
yeah it's tough to say really tough to
say I'll I try increasing this a little
bit and I'll see what happens
and this gets larger so here we are
running with a lot more of course I
guess one problem is it's hard to see
what the flicker is when you end up
tanking the frame rate so I don't know
if we have to like optimize more I
suppose at that point this is also a
good way to look at our sampling pattern
right so you can see how it doesn't have
enough coverage you can see like where
the gaps are does that make sense
so if you take a look at what this ratio
has to be it's more like that to get
like you know an even coverage
so anyway
I guess I'm not 100% sure on which way
we could proceed at this point we have a
pretty good understanding about what's
going on but what we don't know is how
much better we should get at taking and
using samples before we just go well now
is the time to just try to do the
optimized version of this so we can cast
more Ray's per sample point right
because at some point casting the more
Ray's per sample point gives us smoother
values and maybe you know at that point
we're good enough
we don't really know so that's a tough
call and I don't really know how to make
it
hmm
decisions decisions so at the moment I
don't think there's anything about our
update that couldn't be partitioned so
if you take a look at compute light
propagation for example I did nothing in
here
it all just writes to the output array
based on the sample point index so in
theory we could multi-thread this pretty
trivially so maybe we should and then we
just have eight times more Rea counts
here for free
well maybe not eight at least four so we
could go to 64 arrays pretty trivially
so maybe we just should you know
right so maybe I should just do
something where I say like all right
look we want to work you call back
that's like new lighting work and then
we've just got a lighting work pointer
and and off it goes so then in here we
just say I'm just gonna do it like this
so let's go say all right we've got a
first and stride actually now we don't
we look to a first in the last
I saw just do that and I think that's
all we would need to do if we wanted to
just get it going significantly faster
so we can play around with it so we
could just make some of these and off we
go it would be exactly what you expect
so
yeah
so I'm not actually sure software
rendered commands I'm not sure exactly
where we're supposed to get that
particular piece of information because
we've kind of got these two cue sir I
think we can just use the game memory we
just want the high priority queue right
but I don't know exactly where we get
that so I'll just do this first and
assume you pass that in so inside
hand-made we have that information
inside game update so this right here is
where that that cue comes from I suppose
well world mode uses it to write it was
doing it here but out again know where
the transient state information comes
from right yeah I'd have to get passed
in but I suppose that's fine because
actually when you call the lighting
update function so when you call
lighting test we could just have you
pass it in right so that's actually fine
that's pretty straightforward I don't
mind that at all
so yeah so this is pretty
straightforward I think all you do is
this so you just say alright compute
like propagation and it would say I want
to add a bunch of these entries in here
I'm not sure I remember if we say for
the work you what its distribution
fan-out is necessarily but I suppose we
can just chunk these up in just however
much we really want to so we can just
say like points per work you know and
points per work is it's gonna be well
actually I guess we just want to
distribute this among some number of
things actually so even easier than that
I can just say lighting work you know
however many there's going to be 32 of
these or something probably even less
and then I can just say like alright the
number of points points per work is just
going to be however many points we have
divided by however many works there are
and we also probably want to round up
right
sesame points for work there are then we
would just go like work index Syria work
index is less than however many we have
and then each one of these gets filled
out in series so letting work which
works index and then we just add each of
these on there so we say like okay add
to the lighting cue the do lighting work
function and here's the work so then the
work just needs to know the solution the
first sample point index and the one
past last seven point index so each of
these is just going to be like okay the
first sample point index is going to be
one plus the work index times points for
work and this is just going to be that
and that's it right
pretty sure
and off it goes I'm pretty sure that's
all you need to do and I don't know how
well that'll work but I think that's it
right or at least you should be so let's
take a look here
so there's compute light propagation it
does get called sixteen times so that's
good and so let's see if we can make it
any faster here
well it didn't seem like that went
faster and it should right unless you're
completely memory bound which I doubt so
if we want to do the single threaded we
just do this right
something is up what did I do that made
this so slow all of a sudden because
we're just still doing 16 rays this
should have been exactly the same right
there should be no difference between
those now
what did I do
I've done something horribly wrong I
just don't know what it is
so if I pass those exact values and in
here just curious if in here I say okay
this is one this is point count that's
still slow so why did that magically get
slower
we're only calling compute light
propagation one time and I thought we
were significantly faster than that with
when we were only doing sixteen rays
maybe I'm missing something here
and it could be that this slowed us down
I guess I don't really know this is what
we had before
oops
yeah that's that has nothing to do with
it
so I'm not sure where did we get
suddenly take a speed hit there for
something unrelated to what I was doing
apparently you unless I missed something
that we did earlier that caused that
change not sure what we'd done that
wheres look at our stats here
I guess it's because this world is
larger I suppose that is where we're
getting that speed drop from I guess
that's true so before when we were
running quickly I suppose we were
running on the smaller world either way
let's just go ahead and say when we if
we distribute this work we would expect
it to go faster but it did not go faster
right Oh
I guess it goes a little bit faster but
not particularly much I also don't know
so on the queues how many of these do we
have
so I guess one problem with this is
these are not tuned to the number of
CPUs we have either which I suppose
isn't particularly great we've never
actually did a get CPU call here it
looks like for whatever reason I'm not
sure what's up with that if we take a
look here for the there we go if we take
a look at the CPU utilization here I'd
also be interested to see what that
looks like when this runs so it does use
the CPU use quite handily here
but for whatever reason it does not get
particularly much faster
what if I've split this into less just
curious
strange enough that's worse this is
peculiar actually let's split it into
more
no real change once you get up over a
certain amount now that is pretty
bizarre
let's see how resilient it is to changes
in this so let's say we crank this up to
64 let's see what the difference in
speed is there so with multi-threading
on it's about 170
so you get you get a minor speed-up I
guess I would say so from
multi-threading that on the CPU side you
get a pre minor speed-up the speed-up is
you know about 25% of the total time you
saved back maybe a little less this is
pretty minor for going from a single
thread to many threads that's kind of
peculiar it's possible that if memory
bandwidth is entirely to blame here then
that could be but that doesn't seem
super likely like that that would really
be the case so I'm a little bit
surprised to see that that's happening
now granted we haven't looked at this
hardly at all
so it's kind of hard to make any sort of
judgments about that certainly so I
wouldn't suggest that there's anything
you know it could be some fairly
straightforward stuff is happening here
and we should just take a little bit of
a closer look at it but at the same time
it's just it seems like that should have
gotten faster if your multi-threaded it
naively and so I'm not sure why we
weren't why we're seeing that that
suggests that maybe something weird is
going on and I'm kind of curious to find
out what it is I would like to look
really quickly I'm just gonna take a
quick quick gander here sorry this won't
take too long I just want to take a look
inside this routine to see what's going
on you know what else I would like to do
actually and I think about it I'd like
to time that the overall as well
I just want to be able to see what's
going on there
so it's entirely in compute light
propagation
and there are a couple things in here so
I guess think about it there's a couple
things in here that are problematic so
we are doing a statistics gather which
is bad right and no that's not what I
map
so like this for example is really bad
because that cache line is going to
bounce around so I'm gonna just take
these out for a second just anywhere
that I was changing a value in the
solution itself I just want to get rid
of that all right
so I don't think that was probably
enough but I just wants it so wait a
second am I still casting all the right
yeah okay so that was it right I've kind
of nuts but if you look at what was
happening there the fact that we were
adding a number to a shared cache line
that whole time was enough to drop a
frame I mean let's just verify the test
the case
so there's one put back in there's your
the to put back in I mean look at how
fascinating that is right all I have to
do is add one plus plus I think it's
just one of these this is it right if
you just get rid of this one plus plus
that happens to either of those two get
rid of that and your frame rate triples
more than triples
ladies and gentlemen multi-threaded
coding so right just the fact that we
were operating on a shared variable
there meant all of our threads were just
locking up on that plus plus I guess
right waiting for that cache line to
bounce back between the processors which
is real bad and just that was enough to
totally thwart the speed improvement
pretty cool huh
so yeah so if we wanted to keep those
statistics we still could we just want
to add them into a frame based thing and
send them to the solution and then add
them at the end but that's pretty
fascinating right it's pretty nuts how
stuff like that works so yeah I mean
obviously we've got other stuff like
that that could be in play as well the
lighting points themselves probably want
to be straight about so we don't get
like overlapping there of cache lines
either so that part is a little nasty
and we should probably try and fix it
but that's kind of Awesome and also kind
of nuts so here's the version running
with 64 samples per point and it's
definitely quite a bit nicer it's also
running non stratified right now I think
is that right where is it running
stratified
look it's running stratified yeah so it
may be that we really don't have to
worry about the variants too much beyond
where we're at right now because a
properly optimized version is going to
cast in a phrase to keep this going and
then we just kind of have global
illumination right which is kind of cool
uh so yes so I don't really know what to
make a make of that other than to say
wow that's really cool that that meant
that if you do if you aren't careful
with your cache line ping ponging you're
gonna be in a lot of trouble we kind of
already knew that but it's just nice to
see such an obvious display of it at
work there I'm gonna go ahead and I also
just want to see like if we sort of set
the work point to a certain value and
use that instead of the work amount
I'm just curious here so if we take a
look at the things that we're modifying
we know that we would want there to be
so if there were 32 I'm sorry if they're
4 bytes per float and we're modifying 3
of them at a time for a color that's 12
of those so the problem there is those
are not gonna line very well on a cache
boundary kind of nasty so we would need
to be like sort of fun to cache line
batteries because cache lines about is
it's you know 64 bytes long and so 64
and 12/12 has a three factor of three in
it so I think we would need to do three
cache lines long or 192 right and 12
goes into that 16 times so you want to
do 16 points per if that makes sense
you'd really want to be some multiple of
16 points away pretty much all the time
and to keep yourself from overlapping a
little bit there so I don't know exactly
how we would want to guarantee that but
let's say you want to do 16 points per
work time some multiple so you know
let's say we want to do 256 points per
or something like that and then we would
just do something like this or we'd have
a lot of them and here we would just do
the the loop a little bit differently so
we'd say something like first point
index
you know equals zero first point index
is less than solution point count and
then first point index plus equals
points per work assert index actually I
guess I could still use the work index
here I suppose I could do that and just
break out of the loop once we're done so
I could say work index is less than the
rate count works
let's work index I could still do that
and points per work equals six and so
what I could say is there alright look
let's go through here get the work out
do it exactly we're doing it and if we
want to be run over that's when we know
that we're done right in a sense I still
need to be able to add it to the queue
but I need to break out after that so I
think it's false
Jenica screw it done break so at that
point we're finished and one of the
problems that we have here is again
we've got this offset by one situation
which causes a little bit of
consternation here so what I'm going to
do instead is I'm going to do it like
this and then in here I'm gonna just do
a modification of if work first sample
point index equals zero work for a
sample form x equals one so we'll still
give them out in evenly arranged
tranches like that but we'll you know
try to keep them aligned that way so the
problem here is you know you know we can
do that and and I think that's probably
the right way to do it I'm also going to
put this
at the end we also would have to go and
actually cache line align all the rest
of our stuff - because we don't actually
cache line or keep those cache lines
aligned in the first place so so in
other words the the various arrays that
we're working with aren't necessarily
cache line aligned at their outs at
their start so it doesn't really help
too much to cache line align them there
I just wanted to make sure that routine
was not adding insult to injury
I'm curious now what would happen if we
ran with a lower number of rays as well
so we can we can basically get a full 16
frames a second by using the original
solution now a 60 frames a second rather
I think we could do whereas before we
weren't able to write
so we're definitely getting closer we're
just on the edge of good right we're
just on the edge of good and we have a
lot of options here
we just need to now quite cross over the
finish line because we're getting pretty
close right and we can run this thing
multi-threaded now which is nice as well
and see what the faster version of it
would look like we also could speed up
some of this stuff quite a bit like we
could do a lot better in all these
routines are kind of garbage right they
could all be sped up so we know that
we've got a lot of headroom to work with
there the question is just going to be
alright look what's the what's the best
pass to really finish this up do we go
GPU with it do we leave it on the CPU
side how do we tighten up that variance
there because we're getting closer but
it's like we're still may be wasting our
samples or replacing them improperly so
can we improve our stratified sampling
can we improve the way that we're
blending them together by being more
conscientious about using those samples
intelligently so we've we still got a
little bit to go it's definitely getting
there but we still got a little bits
good I'll go to a brief Q&amp;A here
looks like I got to do it in the other
one can we temporarily turn off turn
down the frame to frame color
interpolation see how much increase
sample account stabilize the solution
yes we can see updates so this turns it
off completely right and where's our red
cap so this was the original solution 16
rays per sample point and here was the
increase train number which is 664 and
it does do a pretty good job of reducing
that flicker but you can see that the
thicker still remains right we also
don't know which of these two is better
for that right we haven't played with
that too much so here is just completely
random you can see the complete random
sampling just does a better job right so
we still have a lot of work to do there
and let's we can look at entropy counter
here as well so if we up the entropy
frame count to a really high number for
example now we get a lot more variances
thing cycle through you could see a lot
more difference in the frames so I don't
know like I said we still have a ways to
go before we could really say that we've
gotten this under control
but certainly we have a lot of ways to
make it pretty good already right
you know we if we jack the smoothing up
you pretty much get a completely usable
solution here is just a little laggy
right the flicker is pretty usable here
which is I guess what like 50 frames of
lag so less than a second at 60 frames a
second of lag on the global illumination
lighting would give us what I would
consider a use usable amount of flicker
above that we start to be bad so at 20
frames you can see the flicker pretty
well right again not necessarily
unusable in a night time game because
the light sources are gonna be flickery
so we could almost excuse that with
fiction so I'm not too worried about it
either way it's just you know I want to
work on it and make sure it's good
before excusing something with fiction
right so yeah and unfortunately the CPU
version because we're not optimized on
CPU isn't really that fast at the moment
so we can't try things like 256 lighting
samples because it'd just be too slow
you wouldn't see the flicker anyway
really right because it just the frame
update is not fast enough right at that
point to really gauge whether the
lighting looks visually okay once you
get up to that number right cuz it's
just you know we don't we don't have an
acceptable frame rate so you can't
really tell you know it's the lighting
gonna be acceptable that frame rate or
not
so anyway that's where we're at
can someone explain why do store and
pass around one past last sample point
index instead of calculating it at the
loop part yes I can so the reason is
because well let's this fits wait you
could do it either way if you wanted to
inside here you could you could add the
number that you that was the fixed
number you wanted to do and then clamp
it to the point count there the reason
that I don't tend to do that is because
since it's gonna have to be computed
either way I'd rather just pass it in as
part of the work unit because then the
work units can be divided up however
they want here and it's clear to me what
I'm sending out as a job to do so if I
wanted to make some jobs smaller than
other jobs for some reason I don't know
why but like you know let's say in the
future we want more sampling and for
some points on others I don't know I can
just adjust how I'm doing it there so I
tend to always build my tiles for work
and record the tile in the work unit
rather than recomputing the tile later
just because it's usually free to do so
and it allows it to be more clear in the
code what you're giving out in terms of
work tranches you know it just localizes
the part that the code to the part you
want to but you could have done it all
you would need to do is pass the first
one right and more specifically you
wouldn't have to do that you could have
just passed a work index right so for
example one way to write this and we
chose not to do this way because work
queues are a little bit more flexible
because you can put arbitrary jobs in
there right
so the arbitrary jobs that you could put
in here can have any data you want and
that's valuable but another way to write
this is to just have a work number so
instead of a queue you just get a work
number and you look at what the work
number is and you generate your work
from that and that's a more specific
type of queue things have to have some
hard-coded Global's in there to
understand what they're working with but
that's it
right and that's a totally valid way to
distribute work and we could have done
it that way you just roll this code into
the part into the stuff that's up there
that would automatically know how to
take a work index out and generate what
the range was from it I just find it's a
little cleaner to do it this way and
more flexible but if you really want to
get it down to the nitty-gritty and not
do any extra work you don't have to
outside you could roll it down to just
one number and instead of a queue you
just have an increment and it's very
efficient we don't need that efficiency
because we're we have large work units
so the overhead is not much but when the
end that overhead gets more substantial
relative to the work amount you know
it's not it's not nothing
well bus why are we not using Atomics
when you modify data on the multi thread
pass because we're never touching the
same data by more than one thread that's
all the the threads are just separate if
we wanted to reinstate these statistics
we wouldn't probably still probably
wouldn't use Atomics here we'd sum these
up per thread and then use a single
atomic at the end when it when the
thread work exits right here to add them
back in so the cache line wouldn't
bounce around given the restricted
number of rays should they be biased
towards directions which are interesting
to us ie not vertically just wondering
as are we interested in the light values
gained from the ceiling compared to that
from services which the player
conversion see on the screen it's really
hard to say right in one sense you're
right because walls and such are only
visible to us if they're around the
periphery and that makes good sense
however you have to remember that
there's things on top of things in the
game world so for example lights like
projectiles that are maybe bright and
glowing will be flying over directly
over surfaces that need
pick them up and so what I would say is
I don't know that we can really say much
about the general bias other than we
want to buy US force for directions
where the lighting contribution is
reasonable and since the cosine fall-off
means that that really sharp angles just
don't add very much it's kind of tends
to be more towards the upward cone
doctors will can the raycast be up as
more yes the raycast can be optimized
dramatically more for starters we
haven't even done simple stuff like look
at the code to see if there's basic
optimizations that need to be done but
beyond that we could sim d them so that
we try to cast for rays at a time for
example in certain circumstances and
other things like that that could be
made much more efficient so yes we
there's no question that we are
inefficient right now in terms of rake s
and could be much more efficient would
increasing the size of the sample table
make sense for going to search for is
probably not I mean we don't want to
stratify too much so probably what I've
got now makes some sense I don't even
know if that's a good stratification so
we may want something less stratified
than that even it may be that this
sampling should really just be more into
like four quadrants or something and
biased slightly upwards you know since
you only use cubes depending on the
height of the light you may know exactly
where to cast since there can be say
only four by four square over you at a
certain height I think could work even
if the lightest place as a wall the
generated table based on height would be
flipped toward the normal
I don't think I follow that logic I mean
does not understand what you're saying
though
aqua xvu less technical question how are
you today I'm alright how are you
uh yeah I still just don't understand I
still just don't understand the question
about the cubes height I mean the thing
to remember is there's no such thing as
the height of the light right the entire
world is a light source it's its global
illumination so there's not like a light
we don't recast towards lights in a bias
fashion right now we could but if we did
that then our scheme gets worse the more
lights there are I don't super love that
because I want like lights to be
everywhere if we want I don't really
want a light based scheme in that sense
but we could do some stuff to try and
you know improve that we could for
example shoot from lights outward more
in fact putting in the bi-directional
sampling will do that automatically
because then when you shoot from the
light you transfer light outward but the
problem with doing bi-directional is
that bi-directional makes the threading
harder right because the the whole the
nice part about not doing bi-directional
is that not doing bi-directional means
that you don't have to you don't have to
worry about mute about multiple people
writing into the accumulation buffer for
the lighting results once you go
bi-directional you do because now you
don't know where you're writing into
that array yes you're you are the only
person who's looping over a particular
block of sample points and writing into
them in that fashion but now anybody
might be reaching into that same array
as part of a bi-directional transfer and
putting it there so the bi-directional
stuff the reason I haven't done it yet
and the reason that I'm kind of not sure
how to do it in a good way is because I
feel like it breaks that sort
unidirectional thread advantage that
maybe is more important for further
runtime overall now that the threading
is working well how does it scale with
more threads we don't have I don't know
why we're doing it this way we have six
and two so we're basically eight threads
I think that's just how we do it so we
don't really scale to any more than six
threads at the moment we just never
launch more than that so you can
actually see that visually in a sense
because you can see that we have room on
some of our threads that we're not
really using there and I think that's
because we don't use all we don't try to
use all eight for high-priority
processing like that
now we could try to do that I don't
really know that there's any point to
this but you know you could say all
right let's say there's eight high
priority crews and again we could go
through and say let's look at how many
CPUs there are and base it off of that
but you can see here if I go ahead and
increase the number of high priority
threads then these all pegg higher than
they used to right so now we're really
sucking up pretty much all of the CPUs
processing time that's available on the
machine for doing your lighting and
there's a little bit that's not used and
that's because again the lighting is not
all of the time so when we finish doing
compute light propagation we then drop
into these other routines that still
need to happen which account for you
know five percent of the time or
something like this and those are not
multi-threaded they're single threaded
so they don't take the time and so when
you then take a look at how much time is
being spent in here you can see that
there is a five percent gap or so up at
the top and that is expected because we
are just simply not utilizing that time
and that's again why you also see that
this number never creeps above 95
percent it stays between 90 and 95
percent because we know that by default
95 percent of our processing time is not
multi-threaded anyway and never is going
to be so we know that there is sort of
an upper limit there that we're never
gonna hit but that's fine that's not an
appreciable amount of frames anyway so
you can see the difference in speed
there here we're running at about 95
millisecond I'll let me launch it fresh
so we have the exact same situation to
look at so here you can see at this
frame rate it's it's doing what 53 54 I
don't think it's gonna change that much
if we knock it down to the lesser
threads that we were using before if I
run it now you can see it's it's more or
less the same it's it's a little bit
higher maybe arguably gets up more
towards 60 there but it's pretty much
similar and the reason for that again is
just because you know remember there's
not they're not eight processors in this
machine there's only four these are
hyper threads so the degree to which we
get more performance is only if we're
waiting on reservation stations at well
the nightclub reservation system reports
it's only if we're waiting on ports
execution ports or memory right and so
we don't scale perfectly with more
threads in terms of the amount of time
we take to display so you know we add
two more threads and we only go up 6%
CPU utilization right whereas if it was
perfect right we would expect to say a
hundred 100 device if it were actually
eight cores that were totally
independent we would expect to go up by
twelve percent utilization for every one
we added in there so if we add two we
expect to go by twenty-five but actually
we only go up at like seven so you can
see that we're not getting that kind of
you that's not the kind of utilization
we're really getting and you can see
that just from this graph I mean this
graph is more or less getting sort of
close to pegging there and you can see
that these two are still working right
so you know
anyway I'm pretty sure that's how that's
going I don't know maybe I don't
remember how this is working in this not
really how that works but I'm pretty
sure that's how that works and off you
go what's the status of using LLVM LLVM
is not something we're using on this for
poor even planning to use on the stream
weird
we just are sticking with VC til we're
you know basically done I don't really
like to switch compilers in the middle
of a process if I can avoid it unless I
have to
how's the light source stored the light
sources are not stored as light sources
or not basically what happens is every
service in the game has emission so if
the emission value is hot is greater
than zero on a surface they need emit
light it emits light that's all there is
to it
no more wrist supports yeah I don't use
them anymore
oh you use the new calculator I'm sorry
Nick see yes I'm sorry I always forget
about it I'm not used to it I'm supposed
to be using this thing I'm supposed to
be doing this
oops can you get an old answer
no it'd be cool if you could get an old
answer like if I had written this I
would put a number besides each of these
that you could then refer to you know
what I'm saying to you
I don't know anyway you know what I mean
are there any ways to make it clear in
your profiler that you are having these
cash issues concerning threads and
shared memory or is this just something
you have to look for a trial and error
experience well so yes
so in our profiler I don't know that we
could write I don't think there's any
way unless I'm mistaken that we could
make that determination however if you
have access to like vtune via the VX DS
that allow you to read the performance
counters in the cpu and stuff which I
don't know what the status is on
Thursday it's been a long time since i
try to write any profiling code that did
like fancy cpu stuff inside the cpu
there are performance counters you can
set which can recover information for
you that have to do with stuff like how
often you miss the cache and things like
this now whether that could ever tell
you exactly this that the problem is
that your ping pong and cache line back
and forth does it say that exactly I
don't remember what the performance
counters are that you have access to so
yeah maybe yes maybe no but what I can
tell you for sure is yes you can get
more information than this you could at
least see information about cache misses
and how much you're stalling on them and
that might give you a hint right now
whether you can actually get a number
that really bull's-eyes the fact that
you're getting into a ping pong
situation where it's not that you're
reading in that much memory but that
you're actually just fighting over the
same line that I couldn't tell you there
might be performance counters that would
help with that there might not be I
don't know so part of its gonna have to
probably experience how much you can
help you with that I'm not sure
few history
hmm so you can insert yeah I guess
that's that's kind of good I mean it's
not what I want I want to be able to
just get it while I'm in here but I
guess going over here and clicking is
okay it's better than nothing does
that's that's probably a good thing
though
alright time shut down alright thank you
for joining me for episode of hand made
here it's been a pleasure coding with
you as always I feel like to a certain
degree the the variance is getting good
like a we're getting pretty good here we
can improve what we've got quite a bit
still I think so I don't think we've
topped out by any means but we've
definitely learned a bunch and I feel
like we're keeping we're making good
progress all the time I think the major
decision we have to make is do we want
to move this to the GPU or not and I
don't know the answer to that question
it's a pretty difficult question
obviously when you move something the
GPU you get a lot of bonus in terms of
good job distribution and very wide
floating point that happens
automatically for you and that's pretty
good but you you do have a problem which
is that your memory accesses are much
more likely to be stalls than they are
in the CPU case because CPU has much
better caching and random access memory
so for something like this where we're
talking about rate rehearsal sometimes
the GPU gets a lot less speed-up than
you would have gotten in situations
where you weren't doing things like
reading out of spatial hierarchy like
that so I don't really know what to
expect
if we move this to the GPU or not and
that's why it's a pretty hard decision
to make so we're gonna have to make that
decision and not sure exactly how but
that's just how that goes sometimes so
we'll have to cross that bridge
trepidatious Lee I don't know and then
the other thing we have to do I think at
this point is just now really start to
coalesce things together and make sure
that we are doing the best we can in
each of the situations that we've got
improve that sampling improve our
blending and just you know get the
variance down to the lowest possible
thing we can with the tech that we've
got right yes it does look good right
now no it's not quite fast enough we
could optimize it more and maybe we can
again reduce the variance using a little
bit more intelligence than we're using
right now I don't know so that's really
again still what we're doing is just
trying to turn that crank a little bit
and make sure that we've gotten it to a
pretty good place but I don't know I'm
pretty pleased with the results and it
looks pretty cool so I'm thinking it's
pretty handy anyway that's it for today
we'll be back next weekend with more
coding if you want to follow along at
home you can always peer to the game at
handmade hero organic come to the source
code so if you want to try your hand at
making some good lighting routines you
could go ahead and do that and let us
know how you do we'll be back here next
week until then have fun programming and
we'll see y'all on the Internet take it
easy everybody