hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream i am going to take a look
at the lighting we did yesterday i think
we actually have our diffuse lighting
sort of working correctly now we may
have some bugs in our four-wide
implementation of it so we may need to
take a closer look at that and there's a
number of ways that we can do that
obviously we can just do some testing in
place to make sure that the four-wide
version works the same as the scalar
version would work but really where
we're at now is just time to start
cleaning this code up and debugging any
kind of lightning bugs that might exist
therein and so I think we're more or
less done with the heavy lifting of
trying to figure out what's going on now
it doesn't mean we're out of the woods
yet because we have to get this thing
running at a reasonable rate certainly
and we've got a lot of work ahead of us
in order to make sure all of that kind
of works well and a lot of debugging
because lighting is notoriously finicky
so we're probably to rig up some test
cases where we can actually determine
whether this stuff is working properly
right look I got to make a fake little
Cornell box we can hop into and just
watch to make sure color bleeding is
happening and you know put some lights
and strategic places and make sure that
they're shining on things properly so
we're gonna have to like go through sort
of the motions here but at least we've
got an architecture in place we can turn
the crank on that architecture and well
we don't really know whether this was a
good solution or not I think weeper you
know we stuck with it right we tried a
bunch of stuff and that is really what I
wanted to show on the on hand made hero
because that's what lighting is you know
there's there's basically members of
triple-a graphics teams who just do this
all day right all they do is work on
lighting algorithms and how to make them
run reasonably how to improve the
quality how to give artists more control
over them all that sort of stuff it's an
entire field right like you can
literally go get a job where most of
what you will do is work on the lighting
for like 10 years right
and that's again because it's such a
complicated problem
while its underlying definition to write
a raytracer that actually rate traces
the world you know quite beautifully but
very very slowly well that may not be
particularly hard to do and you know in
a couple months most people can probably
write one that's actually quite good in
terms of quality by just making sure you
implement all light transfer stuff very
carefully you know test it test it well
and stuff and that takes a little while
but then it would just be right you know
and you'd have a gorgeous-looking
renderer problem is it would take like
three hours to render a scene or
something right and so it's all of that
figuring out how you get from three
hours to 60 frames a second or 30 frames
a second at the very least that's the
trick right and so you know it's a hard
job it's getting easier as graphics
cards get more powerful and Nvidia at
all start to take on more of the work
for us where they're baking into
hardware some of these things that we
used to have to do obviously it's a
nicer world and believe me no one is
looking forward to hardware accelerated
ubiquitous ray tracing more than me if
they can actually make that work that
would be great because ray tracing is
kind of the fundamental operation that
you need to be fast if you want to do
bounce lighting for obvious reasons and
so you know maybe hopefully these sorts
of things will get better and instead of
taking you know 100 hours on handmade
hero to do lighting it'll get down to 20
hours or 15 hours or something right
it'll start to get like less and less
and less and that would be great
you still have to know all these
concepts so please learn them but you
know hopefully like the the
experimentation and the iteration all
that stuff much like rasterization is
now a more or less solved problem in
terms of like if you want to implement
it in your game well you really just
have to learn how to call a graphics
card because it's built into the
hardware much like how that is the case
and you really just have to learn how it
works and then you can go forward you
don't have to spend a ton time
experimenting and oh what's the fastest
way to rasterize this triangle hopefully
some day lighting will be more
like that but at the moment it's not and
it's not gonna be anytime soon like it
probably won't be in the next year or
two right it's gonna be at best
something that's like ten years from now
maybe we can start taking it for granted
you know if we're if we're lucky so you
know oh well you know you can't have you
can't have everything done for you but
you know at least you know it's like I
said it's getting easier not harder and
that's that's nice for a while it was
just getting harder because that's
graphics cards got better but didn't
really have any way to calculate any
lighting things for you it was actually
harder because doing reasonable lighting
became this thing that you kind of had
to just do all these learn all these
crazy hacks and work all these you know
magic things to get some reasonable
lighting in there right and so you know
it definitely was the kind of thing that
was was was more difficult all right so
if we take a look at where we're at
right now were you know I would say look
at like I said I'm not sure we got all
the bugs out of this particular thing
but it's it's not bad right we've got a
sort of specular bounce happening here
but it's specular bounce on diffused
surfaces in a sense so I'm not sure how
to say that exactly weird using the
reflection vector to look up the
incoming light source but we're using
this correctly some light for that and I
think it's it's reasonable right we have
to think a little bit harder about how
we want to actually sample these in the
pixel shader and we also have to do a
bunch more work on what are you know
what do we want to represent these are
in terms of units because you know we
have to do a quantization and also our
stuff so we have we have a bunch of
details to work out but we're more or
less in in a reasonable position here
right now one of the things that we
probably should do relatively soon is if
you look here we can't really view our
profiler right you see how I can I can
open sup we can't really view our
profiler and the reason for that is at
the moment anyway we don't actually have
a way of turning off our like there's no
way to tell it hey we don't want
lighting anymore right like we don't
need that
stop stop having the lighting go so when
we get something like this it's just
like black because it's computing
lighting on something
that can't really have any lighting
computing for computed for it and so
obviously it's just garbage now as we
move forward we're gonna want this and
so one of the things we might want to do
today just as a start maybe the thing we
should do is just go put so that there
can be a secondary pass in here put in
something that allows us to just you
know turn off lighting for our overlay
pass right some we probably should've
done a long time ago but just has never
been a real issue it's finally enough of
an issue that that's probably something
we should do and and you know we can
move on from there all right so I want
to do that the other thing I'd like to
do is we probably should get this thing
set up to do its multi-threading more
properly so I think I might want to do
that first just for fun and you know
just because I I don't like kind of the
way it's sitting at the moment so let me
show you what I mean by that so if you
notice the way we had multi-threading
working before we have this sort of like
lighting computation code and the way
that it works is when we actually do the
lighting computation and we it should be
an end lighting app so in in lighting
what we do is we just say like look
we're gonna build the spatial partition
that happens and I believe that builds
spatial partition isn't threaded I don't
actually yet so build spatial partition
just does its thing right and that's not
threaded at the moment and we compute a
lighting lookup as well we may never
need that well it depends on whether we
end up doing light source biasing so we
may be able to remove that but that's a
separate issue we then go ahead and call
compute light propagation here and
that's a multi-threaded algorithm and
what we've got that nerfed out right now
and we've got test light sphere in there
okay
now compute light propagation is the
thing that actually has the threading in
it you can see this is the thread
dispatch we've got one branch here
that's turned off that does a work
distribution and then we've got one
branch here that we're actually using
that just does it on one and what I want
to do now is move all the code to work
in this line right
so I want everything to work in here and
when I say everything what I mean is
this part too so do you see how we've
got like Z slices Y slices X slices
these slices are independent so for
example we've got 32 Z slices to compute
I could just send one out to each thread
right that would be really easy for me
to do and so I want something that works
more like that and in order to do that
we have one major issue that we would
need to address but only one and that
major issue is when you look at how
compute light propagation works what you
can see here is we have light probes and
those light probes are sort of strewn
throughout the world and the idea was
that previously we didn't really know
how we were gonna sample the world but
we didn't know much about the lighting
we just knew we were gonna have some
light Pro so we actually have these
light probes and they kind of come
through the world you can actually see
them I believe if we go in and draw
theirs we had like some code that would
draw the light probes actually in here I
think it's this code so like these are
examples of I think where the light no
actually those are the voxels never mind
those are the voxels themselves so we
don't actually currently draw the light
probes there let me see if we've got
them an entity so so global lighting
show probes actually controls this that
actually means that although we can't
see it it should be in here somewhere
right
looks like that's actually not not
listed in here hmm well either way it
doesn't really matter because I can just
set it here so global lighting show
probes I'm gonna set to false hmm I
might have to rerun for that but I don't
know yeah there it is
so these are where the light probes are
and these are actually entities in the
world so if you look at them they're
just kind of strewn throughout the world
and the idea here was they were placed
such that they would be like contained
in voxel cells appropriately right so
here's the thing when I look at that I'm
just thinking well I don't know that we
need these right because all we really
need out of this system is to make sure
that for a given cell that we always
take casts at least somewhere that isn't
underground right or contained inside
them so I don't really know that we need
to do anything in particular with these
probes I feel like we could just
actually use the geometry we're given to
figure out where we should place our
probes and cast and the reason I think
this is important is because these
things come in in an arbitrary order so
even if we did nothing else we would at
least have to sort them into say Z
slices to figure out where the heck to
cast right so I'm thinking that we
should probably just try to get away
without them right because I'm not sure
we I'm not sure we're gonna actually
need these anymore since we're doing a
fair lighting interpolation across all
the voxels it seems like we could just
maybe just do it right and when we're
taking our lighting samples we could
just say all right yeah
like take the lighting samples and if
you if the thing happens to be inside a
box just ignore that ignore that box
right and I think that just kind of
works so I'm gonna go ahead and pull the
probes like they're just gonna go away
and we're gonna loop over voxel centers
instead that's that's what I think we're
gonna do so I'm gonna go into the
lighting here and we're we're doing
probes I'm just gonna pull that because
I think we just don't need them anymore
so much like we've got this I'm just
gonna say alright that's gone and then
I'm gonna clean up the code that use
that so you can see here that actually
if you look at where that's happening
it's very limited right there's very
little that actually does anything with
that I can eliminate this for trivially
because all that is is storage here's
the thing we actual in a modify this
part here the work system is just gonna
have to pass something else so one pass
last light probe index what I'll
probably do there for now again just for
now instead of one pass last light probe
index I think what I'll do is send which
slice of the voxel I want to work on
right and this is tricky okay
so currently and this is unfortunate but
currently I think we made a mistake and
the mistake was we made Z be the primal
slice through our voxel so if you look
at the way our stuff is structured Z
comes first so each row of light maps in
our light map image is one sheet of Z
and as we go down the light map we go
down sheets of Z or up sheets of Z maybe
you might say as we go up the light map
we go up sheets and see it's probably
the right way to say it because Y is up
in both cases so given that
it means that if we wanted to do the
most natural thread distribution of the
32z slices we would have each of our
threads work on a Z slice the problem is
there may be nothing on that z slice to
light because a lot of places in our
world just won't have multiple Z slices
that will force all the work onto one
thread and that's no good
so what we'd rather do is have Z slices
packed next to each other and why be the
thing because we know there's always
stuff in Y or X doesn't matter which one
we'd rather have that be the thread
distribution right so in terms of a
locality what we'd really rather have is
one row represent all the X's and Z's of
a particular Y slice or all the Y's and
Z's of a particular X slice that would
be much better than what we've got
currently which is the other way round
so I guess what I would say is I'm gonna
remove this but then I'm gonna assume
I'm gonna first do some testing I'm
gonna assume that the first thing we
want to do is reverse the packing so
that the packing of our texture goes in
the order we actually want to do thread
distribution so when we do lighting work
here I'm going to say that we're
actually gonna have here a voxel slice
that we want it to work on the voxel
slice is gonna be something like oh I
don't know do I want to do X or Y I mean
actually X or Y being the the Sheep
major
anybody got any ideas X or Y which one's
better if the Vox low remains a cube it
won't matter if it gets changed because
we're wider than we are high in terms of
x and y because of the aspect ratio of
the screen that would mean it would
break the work up more granularly to go
by X because X there would be more X's
than there are wise so I'm gonna say X X
will be the major divider in our texture
so X will be a row let's just say that's
true so this is the core piece of
information I'm actually going to pass
when we do light probe count here that's
not what we actually want to do what I
actually want to do here is say now
which voxel thing we're doing and so I
think I want to change this entirely
because this was kind of dumb there was
no reason to do this this way we didn't
really need to do that what we should
have done is just put all the work onto
one person's queue and then call it or
something like that right so it's
unfortunately we happen to do it this
way I'm not sure why we did it this way
to explain a little more carefully so I
think I'm gonna do is delete this right
put it on here
get rid of probes / work and in here
where we say like okay we've got done
equals false this is not actually
necessary either now so all of this is
we know exactly what this is so what we
want to do is say all right we've got an
X index for our voxel well I guess we
can still call it work index that's fine
so we want to do is say how big is the
thing that we're trying to light and
it's gonna be that hot dim right so it's
we're trying to do we don't want to
light the large voxel because the large
voxel is just for storage we
want to do just the hot portion the part
that we actually update every frame
which is a subset of the part that we're
storing so we want the hot dim which I
don't know where that's actually stated
because this doesn't look like it is I
mean it it's it's that but it would have
been nice without stage somewhere else
so we may want to replace that with a
local that comes in here but a separate
issue so anyway we come through here and
we say all right we've got a work index
this is how many work orders we're going
to do we place these work orders in here
you can see here that we've got sort of
a works thing listed in here this and
again this we know what this dimension
actually is right we know that this is 1
/ X right so we don't know if I'll have
to change that in the future but that's
what it is at the moment so we know
we're going to create a series of work
structures those work structures are
going to be based on this we know that
it's basically assigned directly like so
I'm not sure what this was for I guess
this is just to make sure they're
aligned because we didn't want false
sharing of those structures so all right
I'll leave that in we clear it we set up
the information in here instead of first
probe index last probe Elek all that
nonsense all we need is this so that
means this goes away and we don't really
need anything else right because we're
gonna distribute one voxel slice per so
really the big pad is gonna have to pad
a little more right because we're not
actually gonna use that information
anywhere so it's gonna look more like
this and then the big pad will have to
be 36 because we actually have 5 in here
now
so we don't need this all we need is the
voxel X and we can get that directly
from the work index we don't need any of
this
we don't need done we don't need this
and yeah it's like just much simpler
right so that's all we need and I don't
like I said I don't know why we did this
the way we did it we really didn't need
to do that to have the if zero I guess I
just wasn't thinking if you look in here
we're gonna go through each of these
work indexes and prepare it instead of
adding it to a queue the way to do this
properly and I didn't do it I don't know
why is just to use the exact same code
and instead of having the if you just
put the call to do the work right so
right here we just say do that work you
know I'm saying now I don't know what
compute light propagation actually takes
cuz it's one of these callbacks platform
work queue call back it looks like it
just takes a work queue and the data
mm-hmm so basically this queue and the
data that's all we need and then we can
just say whether or not we want to be
multi-threaded by changing that switch
now complete all work lighting cues
should just do nothing if we've never
put anything on it so I'm pretty sure we
can just keep calling that in either
case it doesn't actually matter but
that's a much cleaner way to do the
distribution you can see how much nicer
that is so that's the way we should have
done it it's just not what we did but
we're doing it now so that's okay so
once we have that then we just need to
modify this routine to no longer work on
light probes and so the way that this is
gonna work is this just gonna loop over
the actual stuff we've got right
and here's the real bonus I believe I
could be very much wrong about this but
I believe this will make things a lot
more cash friendly for us because if we
do our casting updates for all of the
Rays that are gonna be cast in
particular boxes so and immediately
after we update the actual in the-- all
of the dependent information everything
stays in the cache right instead of like
scattering all of our probe scattering
our rights to this texture all over the
place then having to loop through it and
grab the information in it again to do
our updating it makes this a lot more
cash friendly now whether we can take
advantage of that cash friendliness I
don't know because that in order to take
advantage of cash friendliness you have
to be able to write your math in such a
way that it's fast enough that it can't
that it's faster than the prefetcher
right but you know it at least puts us
in position to do good work where if we
can figure out ways to make the math
fast enough the memory accesses aren't
going to kill us because otherwise they
would I think so that's kind of a nice
thing alright so how are we gonna do
that well we're gonna do that by saying
alright let's go into our lighting code
here and you need this where's my
where's my routine just got to grab the
lighting competition end yeah so here
we've got the hot dim right and we need
to grab that again like so and then we
need to do this loop
not there right here so what I want to
do is I want to move this loop here I
want to you know with all of this stuff
where does the trance all of that stuff
I want this to move into this work unit
so basically I want this to happen all
of this tap it in here so let's do that
we'll start by putting it down here and
what I'm gonna do at the initial moment
is I'm just gonna do it in a separate
pass here right so basically we're gonna
do exactly this we're just going to do
it in a different location so that that
way it can be threaded eventually right
so again exactly the same thing we're
just gonna do it in a different place
now I'm also not sure why we were doing
these in two separate passes here that
doesn't really make much sense so we can
weld those together as well which again
improves the caching dramatically so you
know we got a ton of fat trim off here
so I was saying like I don't really care
how its fastest running right now that
doesn't really tell us anything we're
gonna have to see how fast it runs once
we get rid of all the obvious cruft and
then we can start actually profiling it
and see what our chances are of making
it run at a reasonable speed cuz it's so
garbagey right now because it's been
through so many iterations as we now
start to clean up this code and like
polish it up a bit
it's gonna get naturally a little bit
faster just from not doing anything
stupid so and then at that point we can
go all right now starting to profile
this and see where what we're actually
gonna have to turn the crank on all
right so when we come through here we've
got the light probes and again like this
is not useful here we've got the probe
the casting that we actually need to do
and what I'm gonna say it's like all
right so here's us going through our our
voxel right and here's us doing the the
transfer on this thing and we you know
as we're doing that transfer yeah again
like I said I'm not sure why this isn't
welded in here so I'm just going to go
ahead and weld
and right now it's no reason not to so
there's our edge coloring so you can see
like right here this is only operating
inside one of these textures so I can
just grab this code directly and in here
after this tx4 update is done I can just
drop that right here right so that's the
thing that ops there's no reason at the
iterate over the voxel twice I don't
even think I remembered we were doing
that I thought we were just doing it in
one pass there's no reason not to but we
weren't so this is what needs to happen
here here's the diffuse right we update
the diffuse here and then here's the you
know right immediately after the fuse
we've got the lighting voxel updates
happening for the edges right so I think
that should just work and that'll
operate here on this thread so then we
just need the casting to be welded in
line with that as well so much like
we've got the light probe iteration here
where we're doing all this stuff what I
really want is to just say oh okay
inside here where we got like Z Y X and
so on when we actually grab out this
cell before we do any of the other work
on it inside that same loop I want to do
my casting so my casting here instead of
looping over a light probe index which
is not actually something we need to do
anymore we're actually just gonna like
loop over array count right so in fact
the Rae bundle this part right here is
really all we need right
so I guess actually it's just that can
go away so we're gonna need some way to
get the voxel location out here but
other than that we're good and so this
code can just operate directly in line
it can update all of the information
that we have we then run through here
produce the edge output and everything's
nice in line and clean right so you can
see how this is going to be a nice
well-oiled machine at some point the
question is is going to be a fast enough
machine we don't know but at least this
all this data can be made to flow
through very cleanly we don't have to do
much and it's perfectly sliced here
because it's not nobody it's never
touching
data that anyone else is touching right
and if we go by rows we also don't even
have any false sharing no other thread
is ever gonna have to look at even this
row because the whole row is ours and so
we'd never have any false sharing either
because the whole giant row we're only
looking inside our own row if we were
doing it where hey this 10 by 10 is
yours and the one right next to it is
mine well 10 is not a cache line size at
all so we would be stepping all each
thread would be stepping all over each
other
right because it'd be 40 bytes per and
they would be fighting for cache lines
because they'd be talking you know
they'd be looking at stuff that's 40
bytes away from another person another
thread and that would just be their beef
all sharing all over the place
so the CPU would keep thinking it had to
send information from one thread to
another to avoid having the cache lines
get written wrong but actually we won't
don't care about that at all because
these two things are never using the
same part of a cache line and so we're
just basically forced to CBG a ton of
work that doesn't need to do all right
so that's roughly what I want and now we
just need this thing to I don't know
what this is here for we don't actually
need this anymore right
so that's not even relevant anymore but
do I need any of that in here I don't
think so
later see like now that's all that's
garbage
so that's roughly what we're looking at
and when we come through here we're
gonna probably need some of this stuff
like you know the information about the
voxel that goes on in here so I'm not
sure how much of this we need but I'm
pretty sure like none of this gets used
in here anymore so I'm pretty sure all
this can move out to the other side of
things so I think all of this can go in
here right probably and then when we
have the random series in here you can
see how this thing was working and
to be completely honest with you I'm not
sure that this is a very good way to do
this in fact I could pretty much tell
you it's not there's no real reason for
these people to be writing to the series
cash line that doesn't even really make
any sense so if you take a look at
what's going on here
we need an entropy source in in this
case right we need an entropy source so
that each of these things when it's
doing its randomization it needs to be
able to do random choices I think I'm
not sure if it actually still does
although if it actually doesn't do that
I guess we don't care
all right so never mind we have to care
about that that's gonna say we need the
random series but we actually don't at
this point um so forget I said that
so now all we really need is just the
location to do our sampling from and we
should probably be good to go all right
so let's get rid of some stuff we don't
need this we do need the commands so
these two things we probably need for
this although the light voxel dim thing
again I think I'm just gonna nerf that
for now I'm gonna say this is actually
gonna be the light voxel dim and I think
we're gonna need to run through this
code and clean up where people are
getting their constants from just
because there's so much of it now and
now that we know what it is we should be
able to do a nicer job on that so that's
kind of a little to do that should be in
the back of our heads
so here's us looking at the light probe
again we don't actually want that so I
think what I'm gonna do instead is just
say all right for the light probe we're
gonna actually ask for we're just gonna
ask for whatever the center of the voxel
is right now which may not be a great
place to ask so I'm gonna put a little
to do here like
so that light propane needs to be needs
to come from somewhere where we actually
know where the voxel is right and test
light square is one easy way to do that
so I think in Vox Center P here so we
should be able to do something like that
now that's not the actual center right I
mean that's that's we need the this to
actually produce the UVW of the voxel
and so on so we don't really want that
we probably want the test castrum probes
so you can see in test cast from probes
right we say in here this cast well no
that's actually also using the probes we
need something that tells us where the
voxel is right I mean that's what we
actually need and so it would really be
this right this part right here so we
probably want to do something like this
where we say all right the Box Center P
is whatever the min corner is and then
we add to the min corner like the voxel
D times the XY of it right and then the
light probe is just gonna be for now
it's gonna be that directly something
like that right yeah we don't do this
light probe index probing anymore right
but we probably want to keep this code
first for some somehow right and so we
probably want to have a way of pushing
debug lines for something what we'll do
is we'll leave the code if zero it out
and in here we'll maybe say like oh if
you know this will eventually do be like
some kind of if we'll do that has to
what we'll do an if here that is based
on which voxel it is or something right
so we'd do something like oh if like x
equals blah and like y equals blah and Z
equals blah then do it right so we will
do something like this but it just won't
be exactly this
you know all right so moving forwards
the der sample index like it's not going
to be a light probe index anymore
because we don't really have that and so
we're gonna need some kind of so we are
using this series up here so I think
this just needs to be sent down with it
so what I'm gonna do is say look those
are the only two places we get it I want
to put those in the work order like so
so we're gonna say is there's going to
be an entropy seed right and the entropy
seed needs to needs to somehow be like a
mud version of something that these
people can get their entropy from I
guess if we only need two maybe I'll
just put them both in there is light
point entropy even used it's it used for
okay well all right let's put the mouth
in there
would love a thing and see we can just
say I want a pad structure here that
pads out to this mini which is not the
same as alignment by the way because I
may want to address that pad in a way
and ask how big it isn't tough like that
and you can't really do that very
effectively with just an a-line thing
anyway
so inside lighting work I want these two
things I'm gonna pull those out right so
I'm gonna do this in the work
distribution I'm gonna get this series
there so we're gonna say this sort of
right get those two entropy s by looking
at the random series in the solution
we're going to pass those down so that
in here where we actually get this we
can just pull them out and that way
nobody is bottlenecking on sharing that
entropy source anywhere right so that's
much nicer then in here we could say
well light probe index isn't really what
we want obviously but we can do like a
you know Z times hot dim plus X or
something like that right so we can look
into the sample index by doing some kind
of a you know weird you know fancy thing
here right where we actually just do Y
where we you know do generate a point
index for entropy sake right all right
so whether we're doing a debug or not
should probably be something that we set
up here so it should probably be like
debug this and we set that in in sort of
a more constant way
like so and that way inside the subway
thing we can look at the same thing at
the moment that's gonna be nerfed out
because again I don't really want to
look at raycasting yet that's sort of a
getting ahead of ourselves to say the
least so let's go ahead and just clean
that up a little bit and see what else
we got all right so we now have to write
out to the voxel C so that doesn't mean
we do need the command structure in here
we need some way of addressing the
texture I don't know that we actually
want to send the whole command structure
down we may just want to send down the
pointers - what - right - so it's hard
to say like I'm not sure which we want
about that so that's a good question
I don't know yeah I don't know exactly
what we want to do about that for now I
guess I'll send it down but maybe I
don't know that we want to do that long
term it's hard to say I don't want to I
don't want to commit so anyway let's say
that we're gonna send it down so that
the command structure does come through
so this is going to be in the work order
so it'll be like here and and we'll just
grab that out so when we set up the work
we'll have to put that in so in compute
light propagation we need to pass that
down so when we call compute light
propagation which by the way we need to
start calling we'll pass that down so
compute light propagation will now kind
of always be called and test light
sphere is actually something that we
would call in a different way now so
test light like this should just always
work this way where we compute light
propagation multi-threaded always if we
want I mean we turn off threading
anytime we want to test it without that
but he's going through that
and so the test lights for your call I
actually want to be inside the thread
part so basically when we do our compute
light propagation we can choose to or
not to do the sphere version as test
code separately right so the test light
sphere would actually go in here right
and be a way of obviating whatever was
happening with the raycasting so for
example it could just look like this
where we have like you know if zero else
test sphere like that that's what we
want to do there so all right we have to
have our game commands our game render
commands pulled out of the work order we
need to set that when we do our lighting
there we don't need this anymore
and let's see got the block copy voxel
begin landing computation I don't
actually know what this was designed to
do
so I'm just gonna remove that all right
so we've got our test cast from probes
that would be another thing that would
happen up in the all of this stuff would
be happening up in here now so our test
lightsphere same thing and let's take a
look at now we've got so in our compute
light propagation call which is now
multi-threaded I think I'm gonna go
ahead and weld that into the other
routine so that we don't like call out
to it for no reason like basically this
is the main workhorse now I'm just going
to put that directly into that other
call so right here there's no need to
call out to a function for that so
instead of calling compute light
propagation I'm just gonna delete that
and have this work distribution happen
in like it's very small it's most of
what we're doing here anyway so I feel
like that should just be directly in
line that's because that's really I mean
that's everything we're doing that's
what this the whole point of this
routine even is so calling out something
to do the only thing you do doesn't
really make much sense so I'm gonna go
ahead and compile that in test cast from
probes you can see us still doing the
probe here what I want to do is just
have this be something that works with
the voxel directly so basically test
cast from probes is going to change to
something else it's going to be
something like this
it's just gonna be test cast and there's
gonna be like a Rey position kind of a
thing
right so you're gonna pass the hoops
you're gonna pass the cast be in there
and this is just gonna do a test cast
like that so if we want to do a test
cast it's pretty easy we just call it
with the casting location so that means
in here right where we've sort of got
our platform work you call back and
we've got various things we can have it
do we want the raycast
to be one of them we might want to move
that into its own routine but basically
what we want to do is something like
this
have a way of doing the actual cast have
a way of doing the test cast and have a
way of doing the test sphere right so we
can sort of define what we want here
like you know which one of these we want
and that's the one that will actually
get done so we can have like test cast
tests fear you know this sort of thing
maybe this something like that and we
gonna switch which ones of these we do
and go from there so then at the end
this one is the actual ray cast and like
I said I might because it's just it'll
get welded in probably by the compiler
anyway and even if it doesn't there's so
much work that it does I don't think it
will matter if it was a call or not
because it's got just a huge crap ton of
stuff it's got to do sadly you know I
wish it was smaller so I'm going to go
ahead and pull that out and just put
that in here and you know we'll see if
it becomes a problem we can weld it in
later and so we just have like really do
a test cast a test sphere or our actual
ray cast
and those are the three things that we
want so then we just need to call them
with the right parameters but otherwise
we're good let's take a look at what
they actually need so test cast just
needs a solution in a cast fee I don't
know that it needs anything else because
it's not actually doing anything else
right so to do the test cast we would
just do solution and that Caspi location
so it is right here and this is kind of
nice too because it means this will kind
of feed forward properly so there's us
producing the centering information so
we're gonna say test cast from the Box
Center we'll say full cast from the Box
Center and the test sphere will do the
same thing all right um let's see what
do we want to do here too much code to
move around and too much to simplify so
when we do these test casts we want
these to just give us back well we
really just want these to just do
they're right you know what I mean so we
want these to do the writing for us this
voxel offset C&amp;D stuff needs to be
simplified and made cleaner obviously so
we want to take care of that at some
point and we'll get there but let's go
ahead and finish up the rest of this so
if I have full cast here this does the
full ray cast set that's going to need
everything that this thing needs so that
needs the lighting solution
it's gonna need the light probe pee
actually so as we'll just leave it that
way
and it's gonna need any of the sort of
dependency stuff so it's gonna need like
the sample point entropy like all that
stuff so I think we probably want to
pass the work down so we can grab that
stuff out like so and other folks might
need that too
we'll see we don't know what they're
gonna require for writing and that sort
of stuff but we'll get there all right
so this gets passed don't know why did
that solution gets passed we don't need
that I suppose technically we don't need
the solution then because you can just
get it out of the work structure so here
you can see us we need this sort of
point index for the entropy and I
suppose we need the voxel location in
general for other things potentially I
guess I'm not 100% sure that we really
need them because we could just pass
down the location that you're writing to
as a pointer which might be smarter and
then you're just gonna do like offsets
of that to think about that
yeah so thinking about that I think we
just need the voxel cell itself for that
for these parts anyway because when you
do like spam voxel is not really what we
want right so if you look at spam voxel
it's doing a bunch of crap that we don't
actually want it to do and so when it's
doing this update step we really just
want that update step to be baked into
here right we want that update set to be
baked in here so from now on this is
really not doing any of this it's really
just gonna do a like update voxel step
it's gonna take the light voxel cell
that you're talking about like this and
then it's gonna blend in the light C and
the light D that you were talking about
right so it's really this I think is all
we're actually looking at now so update
voxels gonna take the cell in question
it doesn't need anything other than just
the information for writing into that
cell and I think we're good right I
might change the order here so I might
just say look give me the information
about writing first and then we'll do
the other part second all right I think
we're good so I think that's what I want
and that means the lighting cell itself
should probably pass the light voxel
cell should come down here right so it
should be like light voxel cell cell and
then in here where we do this we need
that entropy index so I might make that
a thing that we pass down to
something like that
and that'll just be something that we
keep track of for entropy seed in here
and I don't know how exactly we want to
do that but it's like something we want
this thing to keep track of right not
you but you all right so something more
like this so we have the entropy index
the center PE the cell blah blah blah
right I think all that seems reasonable
test cast test fearful cast all right we
got some work to do here but we're all
right still going relatively okay so
when we then go look at some of these
other guys well let me just see if that
got rid of our errors for this what is
this the T update blend yes so the T
update blend hmm I think we're just
gonna want a hard code in here for now
an update voxel so I think that wants to
probably be in passed in like this
so when we do our Jimmy when we do our
voxel updates in the full cast I'm going
to just pass that Qi update blend in
there I don't think this thing needs to
be looking up in the light solution
alright so yeah then we want to call
update Vox the same way in our test cast
or the acht offset and all that stuff
just needs to get rearranged here but
otherwise it's the same we've got the
light see the hit D we've got all that
stuff right so we have all that and we
just need to pass the T update blend
which again come from exactly the same
place for some reason this is out of
order
I don't know why that's the case here we
go let me fix this now what's the
problem I see the problem okay so now in
here we also need to pass the light
voxel cell again and that's again just
because we got to blend in to that
particular cell so we're going to do
that here our entropy index plus sample
point entropy so that really is just for
each individual sample point so that's
actually should be masked where did that
sample point entropy come in it's
supposed to come in right at the yeah
supposed to come in right here so that
should actually I should have cut and
pasted that whole thing out here that's
the complete equation for the entropy
index at the moment all right so now we
need to know where is the moon
obviously something everyone always asks
themselves let's grab that put it in
here because the moon only exists inside
the full ray cast or
what else we got alright so now since
we're gonna run our test sphere through
this particular path I need to make sure
the tests fear actually works and so
that's gonna require me passing looks
like the solution in the group down
right and when I look at that I'm like
no mmm I don't love that I don't think
we really want to do that so I think
what we'd rather do is like you know
take the late lookup voxel dim get rid
of the group do it this way and then
when we get rid of all this stuff figure
out what sort of things were actually
looking up here like Vox in total dim
and stuff like what's fair out why we
need to get that from the setup let's
stop getting from the setup and then
when we actually call that test light
sphere I want to probably do it in a
slightly different way so when we call
the test sphere I don't want to loop
over the voxel this way I want to loop
over the voxel in the outer code right
and just call in here we probably wants
the debug code to get placed into the
routine for drawing so we probably also
want that here right and we have the Box
Center P already so we could just leave
that code in here so this is just if we
want to see those debug voxels so I'm
going to leave that there and and then
work on the this code the test sphere
code up here so we only need to do
looping over the interior texture and
then I think we're good so taking a look
at the equations here we we probably
don't need a lot of this stuff so like
the light uvw is really just mapping the
light in there
I'm pretty sure the in total dim is
actually in the solution itself right so
we have that code don't we I guess we
only have the cell dim but the inverse
Vox will sell dim right like we can
compute both of these things the voxel
min corner is definitely in here so
looking at the way this is working yeah
I think we can just change this around a
little bit let's let's not do this in
light in UV space it doesn't make any
sense
let's just have this past us in the box
Center or P well delete this will come
in here and say okay let me know you
know when we're doing our light normal
we just need to know which direction
it's facing the distance is going to be
a little bit weird here because it's in
gonna be in world space to study of UV
space now so we're gonna have to adjust
the brightness of it but other than that
we should be okay so what we're gonna do
is say alright come through here light P
minus box Center P that's all we
actually need we don't care about the
Vox UV W at all we already have the
voxel cell that we're writing into
because the outer code is computed it so
we can get rid of all of this and Plus
this right here is actually a voxel
update so we could actually just call
update voxel but we're not going to
right now because we're using the test
fear so that's fine but eventually we
probably will okay so now let's clean
this code up from here let's see what
we've got
so here's our T y loop here's our T X
loop and it looks like we pasted this in
a little too early so this was actually
supposed to have
clothes on it like there and then the
these two loops were separate and off we
go
okay so ton of major changes there so we
probably have to do like at least one
more pass on this now to clean this up
and get rid of like stupid mistakes that
we just made but now you can kind of see
we're getting closer to reasonable okay
so let's see what we have here code is
getting smaller and that's very good
right looking much nicer we don't really
have to test if we're inside things
anymore because we only step through
things to begin with that seems good in
fact none of this stuff is necessary
anymore
all right um I'm not sure so I don't
know what this I don't know what this
get irradiance bid is here look up Fox
clamp so I mean you can see like we can
just remove all this code because now
we're just gonna step through the voxels
directly and we never have to ask
whether inside them and that's pretty
valuable right because we can just avoid
a ton of work by just knowing that we'd
never have to actually do that right so
I think we should be okay
Oh mmm I lied so when we actually do the
sampling so that's not true we will have
to where's that clamped we still don't
need this one
but we do need lookup box with lamped so
we still need to get lookup voxel
clamped and we need that for the reason
that we do do the blending in the voxel
for when we have to do our radiance
lookup when we cast rays to see what we
hit right so we do have a little bit
there but otherwise we're otherwise we
could still get rid of the rest of it
and so are we not using the get
irradiance anymore yeah so this was just
us doing that sampling so it looks like
what we're doing currently is just
sampling the light color without
actually doing any kind of bounce
computation so we probably do sort of
want this at some point but it'll
probably just get welded into here so
I'm just gonna go ahead and say this is
an f0 in here and we'll we'll move it
back so sine square root is also not
used anymore so we get rid of that I'd
like looks fishy looks fishy is awesome
all right so I think we're good now so
now we just have to go through and start
debugging this which is going to take a
while right but it looks alright and if
I remove a bunch of this dead code here
we can sort of see it start to take
shape
I'm going to move in it lighting down so
that we basically have our flow here so
we call in it then begin then end so the
last three functions or the functions
people call in from the outside and
everything else is something different
right
our irradiance pack by normal and normal
these are not really used at the moment
and I think they're probably gonna have
to get written differently but we'll
leave them in for now because we don't
know if we might want to use something
similar so we might just keep them we
got the rest of our stuff here spatial
partition all that stuff looks good our
work you call back all of our different
types of updating now got our test cast
our test sphere and then we got our
lookup code looks pretty good I'm
totally fine with that I'm happy with
that all right so now we gotta actually
fix this stuff and get it working
properly I don't know why this is
declared external is there any reason to
do that no I also don't know why any of
this stuff is to clear it up here either
there's any of this stuff necessary to
be cleared up here I don't think so
just see
so I think we're good all right I am now
ready to say this is a light pipeline
that we can start to get behind and now
we just need to kind of like focus on it
and start to turn the crank right we
gotta like get serious here so first
thing let's just fix crash bugs right so
anywhere where we get an assertion or a
crash let's just clean that up first
just to make sure we're working on
something that's actually running you
can see here that looks like our work
size is not correct oh you know what so
I remove the thing where we actually
allocate those I probably shouldn't have
done that we probably should still do
that because we want the alignment I
failed to think about that so in the
init lighting let's continue to allocate
those work units even though there's no
real reason for it let's just do that
anyway so we'll just say look push array
arena light lookup of whatever these
things are lighting work and will align
I don't know what that true is what's
that Oh whether we want it cleared we
don't need it cleared so then we got
some other stuff here we've got an
accumulate PPS we don't need that
anymore
so let's just get rid of this crap we
got memory getting allocated here for
stuff that we don't even do so that
doesn't have to happen right stay the
least
and I guess I need to specify false
there okay back to checking for crashes
and other assorted fun misses so we're
having a really slow run here but I'm
not sure why so something's something's
confused see what's going on there so
we're running the tests fear code yeah
oh I know why sorry
we also now need to stop looping over
everything right so we need to only loop
over one of our of our rows so you can
see here in the work you call back we do
the entire voxel and then we do it 32
more times because we're calling this 32
times from the work queue right so this
needs to get fixed what I'm going to do
here is instead of actually slicing
along X because that's a pretty big
change I want to do that change as a
separate change so I'm going to do it
just fix the the Z to the voxel X since
they're symmetric and we'll just only do
that Z slice again that's not what I
want to do at the end of it all I
actually want to do it along X's but
again that's sort of a separate thing
okay
so again not seeing anything so we've
got some you know we got something
crappy going on here which is fine
because we're going to debug this like I
said but actually it's running okay so
we don't have any issues with that so at
the moment we you know looks reasonable
no crashes just to figure out why we're
not getting a light update there so we
should be going through everything in
order and doing our test spear so now we
have to figure out why would the test
fear isn't writing anything out there
you can sort of see us pulling out the
cell lights here and writing them back
so I'm pretty sure that's happening
correctly or at least should be so I'm
just gonna go to test fear and see
what's up with that because again we
modify this and also like the intensity
might stuff is wrong now and so on so
let's like figure that out in here we've
got sort of our light position I don't
know the in hot dim even used in here no
it's not yeah so if we start to look at
what's going on here I'm gonna also you
know it let's just do this where we're
gonna set whatever the direction is
we'll use that as the light just to see
if that shows up it's a good idea
actually there we go so here you can see
us running the code right and we're
running it the code still running
single-threaded
and we're using the test spheres like
directional clamp so it's just setting
in whichever direction we're going you
know that's that's what we get now
remember we're doing a diffuse sum over
this thing
so what we probably want to do here is
make sure that we set these two lower
values in general because the diffuse
sums gonna put a lot more power into the
system so what I might do is say look
let's actually set this to be sort of a
much less bright debug pattern because
as the diffuse gets blown out we're
gonna get those different colors right
so this is more like what we would
expect right and you can see then now in
the the directional the direction to the
light is getting placed in there now
one thing you'll notice that's not good
is we are running the test fear those
things don't ever look like they're
changing they should be changing and
they're not and so this oh well no
actually that nevermind that's not true
because it looks like that's just based
on where they are on the texture so
that's fine
all right so now I want to see if I can
call this multi-threaded properly
because I think we should be able to
because you know I'm just wanna make
sure we didn't screw anything up there
in terms of the distribution and who's
running to what so I should now be able
to in the letting computation code
switch to adding these into a work queue
and it shouldn't crash right if it does
we've got problems alright so here's
that running the code multi-threaded and
again it's all working nicely the only
difference is now it's like much faster
right so the codes running much better
but otherwise it looks effectively the
same we now don't need those light
probes by the way so I'm going to turn
those the rendering of those off and
eventually we'll remove them and that'll
also save us a ton of work in other
places
oops that was wrong
first the draw the light probe thing oh
it's the show probes okay so now we just
need to since we know we can write into
this thing properly and that our code is
not like totally busted we need to do
something where we can fix the system to
write the test sphere in and verify that
we actually get our test fear properly
right cuz this all looks like it's
working why do we have a hole that that
seems bad I'm not sure why we're not
filling in part of that texture we're
gonna have to debug that that looks like
a bug right
I'm not sure what's going on there our
frame time isn't horrible right now it's
not good but it's not horrible
but you can't see everything is in get
is in the compute light propagation work
function so that's good right that's the
part we're working on so that's a good
thing if we take a look at our thread
distribution you can see that we've got
like six of those fellows kind of doing
their thing
here's them doing each slice of the
voxel right okay so now let's think
about this a little bit more let's go to
the tests fear and try to get that
running this should work we have a
global light position and we have a
center P that's in world space right
so this should all work the only thing
that might not work is this part because
we change from UV W to just using the
center to just using the world space
rather so the light distance is the
fall-off here is probably way too large
we probably don't actually want that to
be the case in fact none of this stuff
looks like it should be the case anyway
this is just um whole thing looks pretty
stupid actually if I'm honest about it
so we probably want to do is say look
the light intensity starts here we're
gonna have a fall-off it looks like that
I don't know what the max bright this
light should be doesn't matter right now
so we're gonna clamp that and then we're
gonna use that to output our value and
what we probably want is this light
distance to have a light fall-off factor
so we we can basically tweak it to
whatever we want so I'm gonna call this
light fall-off
and I'm gonna put that as a multiplier
around the distance and so if we want to
we can say like look the fall-off factor
gets higher as you want the light to
fall off quicker so we'll call it light
fall-off rate and then I think we should
be okay yeah all right so as I suspected
like it looks like our light sphere code
is still fine we just the main problem
was that when we were working with it
before we were in UV space and we
changed it to not be in UV space anymore
so then we end up with sort of this yeah
you know exactly as you would expect the
situation is that the lighting was being
computed with two tighter radius because
in UV space so it wasn't lighting
anything so now we're getting our
lighting it looks right for the most
part I do think we have some work we
could do to clean up our edges a little
bit here you can see our edges are very
vox alized
and i think that's again because we're
not we don't put any negatives in there
so I think that's you know a little bit
of an issue so I don't know like you
know I just want to see sorry you have
to indulge me for a second here if we
just clip the lighting down a little
so if inside the fragment shader where
we're actually computing the lighting
where we do this interpolation I'm just
wondering if we clamp it down a bit if
that will again clean up those edges so
inside the light sampling you can see us
getting our texture sample we sample all
these we interpolate them and then we
output the results basically I just want
to clamp that down a little bit so
rather than falling off at zero we're
gonna fall off at like point one or
something I just want to see what that
does so after this loop where we produce
the s what I want to do here is say that
let's drop that s down so let's say like
s minus equals V for like one
a 100 101 0 or something right so drop
that light down and then clamp it right
so clamp s no if that works it might not
oops so I guess we want that light
fall-off rate to actually be 1 o or not
so you know it's still it's a little
lumpy so me you know I'm just gonna play
with this a little bit
I don't know if there's any amount you
can drop it down by that would remove
the lumpiness but you can see it looks
like way better already right it looks
like way less fox alized
I mean it just looks way better right so
never never ever interpolate to zero
right always bad you always want to
interpolate something slightly other
than zero because you're gonna get
looking nicer result there something I
never really thought of till handmade
hero you know so alright and again we're
still doing that specular sample so I'm
kind of moving around to see how how it
plays it out right so it's like right
here bounces up hits the light source
it's looking pretty accurate actually I
like that results we don't want to
switch that lighting up until we until
we really get to a point where we're
done because again without the specular
bounce it's hard to really see if the
diffuse is working so I think that's
like a little too I think I think we
need more like point two on that
reduction in order to really like clean
up those edges I don't know if three is
the best answer but but I think that
yeah that looks really nice I'll clean
that serious
all right um so I'm going to consider
that a pretty good success story there
because that's actually working really
nicely with the test sphere we can now
try our test cast as well just to see if
that works
might as well have both of these working
because we're probably gonna need both
of them as we do our debugging so let's
go ahead and get that working just gonna
make sure I'm passing the right things
here so it needs a cell in the center
just like everybody else
and and let's see what that does
if that does so oh we got an is test
case what is happening here
[Music]
so is test gateway but his test case
should always be false for his test cast
rather where is the where is that where
was not happening get light leaf for P
oh it was sending down true for that
interesting so one thing I don't know is
it's push debug line actually
thread-safe
so push debug line is not thread safe so
we really don't want anybody to pass
true always look we want to make sure
only one thread is calling that or we go
make it thread safe by just using a
locked increment of some kind but yeah
that was not supposed to happen that way
all right so here's our test shadow code
we're gonna need this light to be a
little bit brighter other than that I
think it looks like it's sort of working
this will be way too bright probably but
off we go
couldn't like a lot of popping there on
the Z like I think we have some weird
like we still have that Z that we're
using for interpolation is still not
stable in the way that I want to be for
the Alpha so I don't see any obvious
bugs in the test caster the test caster
seems to be producing fairly reliable
results you can see that our voxel is
not aligned properly like when we hop
over here we're having some issues with
that voxel like the light voxel is now
in a place where it it cuts off right
here so we're gonna have to arrange
place the light box a little more
carefully we knew that was the case
already but you know now it's you know
pretty obvious because the lighting
works just fine but then the voxel ends
and you don't get any lighting and
that's not good right but otherwise
pretty good looks pretty stable so I
think all of that looks pretty
reasonable to me that's probably a good
place to stop for today honestly because
the next step would be to start working
on the actual caster performance-wise
it's not great at the moment right and
we don't really know why I mean we kind
of us can assume there's a number of
things that are reasons that probably
would be slow especially like you know
all of this code where we're doing tons
of loops and stuff like this so it's not
like it's a mystery as to why it would
be slow but we haven't actually profiled
anything so although we kind of more or
less could guess why it was slow we
probably don't want to just assume so
that's you know the next step for us
obviously would be to start to look at
what we can do to speed this stuff up
Jimmy so yeah but otherwise pretty happy
with that I'm gonna go ahead and go to
QA cuz I don't want to start anything
next weekend would be when we would
start on this stuff I think how come I
can't type what's going on here how come
I can't type into this window there we
go
I do unassigned the clamp of s back to s
oh sorry about that
shouldn't we have seen some artifacts
for that kind of weird that we didn't
due to that I feel like we should have
seen some but I guess I guess not
that's kind of surprising right
shouldn't wall side be in light state
what is light state well I have no idea
what that question means by the way if
we like the voxel eyes light can we keep
it
you mean if you if you like not
interpolating it so meaning if you would
rather do like you mean to say if you if
you just don't want that smooth edge so
you want it to to show the grid like
this more directly like that is that
what you mean I mean you can do whatever
you want man like you know when you
write your own you'd use whatever
algorithm looks best to you
it's your call can you show the
disassembly of transpose in an optimized
well sure I mean the transpose is is
just six shuffles right that's all we
did so it's not interesting it may
require some like we didn't necessarily
do it perfectly like we didn't think
about how it would have to happen in
registers so if it doesn't insert a
Visha it may have a like a problem with
having to copy but that's not an actual
operation so it's fine but yeah sure I
can show that it probably never gets
called it's just in lined right so
remedy probably can't break point on
that
where is it where is it there it is why
can't I
how can I not set a breakpoint oh I
didn't realize I was scrolled over yeah
so I was trying to so you can kind of
see some weird stuff happening here and
I'm not really sure why I generated the
code exactly the way that it did
but it's interleaved these instructions
but if you want to look at where what
happens with the light seed transpose
you can see here we've got the chef's
there they are so it does a chef PS here
and here it clones one of the variables
again this is not this instruction is
free it's just a register rename and
we're not these each take one cycle and
they can they can't be executed in
parallel so this is free it just like
this doesn't count
it just gets executed a simultaneous
with like this in the front end so it's
one cycle one cycle one cycle I don't
know what the heck this is doing
I'll be completely honestly I have
absolutely no idea why that's there it
doesn't really make any sense well you
know what it probably just wants to get
the rights started is my guess so it's
probably just trying to get these stores
started it probably just thinks it's
better to put them up in there I guess
so it's mixed it's taking this code and
shoved it up in there that's fine
anyway here's the next chef free
register rename and the two more chefs
and that's it these are just these
rights from down here I don't know what
that is cuz that's an aligned right and
I told it not to do that so I'm not sure
what that actually is that may be a
different thing it's trying to store for
some other reason there should only be
four of these and you can kind of see
one two three four so these that and
that I don't know what it's doing that's
not part of our chef that's some other
thing
like I literally have no idea what that
is
I'm going to guess because it's on our
SP that what it's doing here is it's
going to use for so it had to spill the
stack there but why it had to do that I
don't know like why it would do that
every time through this loop that seems
really dumb
like it should have done that out here
that's so all I can say is that look
stupid to me
these these look stupid to me these two
right here but they may not I'm a man
analyze this code for more in 16 seconds
so you know take away the grand stuff
that looks dumb those look like they
should be getting done somewhere else
actually because all that looks like
it's doing is just saving its all that's
doing is just saving the the the Const
of those registers and that doesn't seem
like something you would be wanting to
do inside the loop you'd do that outside
the loop right so unless it's actually
using yet no I mean and you should looks
like you have enough registers for what
you know it is what that looks like it's
ill placed to me but maybe I'm wrong
can we zoom out on the octahedral debug
drawing yeah but it's just more of the
same thing why does the clamped light
have a kind of heart shape from those
angle it from some angles with the
sphere lighting two lobes jutting out
behind the hero to his left and right
when viewing from a low angle so I'm not
really prepared to say exactly what's
causing that because we want to
investigate the lighting a little bit
further but I believe that's just
because the octahedral map is on a
diamond pattern and so when you get
you're going to get the interpolation on
diagonals like that so it's going to
naturally form heart shapes rather than
well any other shape
maybe you fix it up already but I think
you might have a copy-paste air in the
border fill if you look at the sphere
test the octal map show weird black line
on each yeah that I mentioned that we
were there I'm not sure what that is how
come this isn't run running run how do I
make this run run why is the program
suspended what's going on there we go if
we try to force ourselves into an area
where we should see some border copies
which I don't know where exactly that
would be
so I'm not sure what I would say is
maybe we should just turn on one of the
tests the test copies like the edge
coloring right so you know we could
force it to do an edge color test looks
like we don't have our edge coloring oh
yeah we do
I guess we don't have a way to quickly
test that I don't really want to look at
that yet right like I want to look at
these more carefully what on on when
we're actually going through and doing
the debugging but I'll make a note like
how will you like the top of the walls
but make them lock light in the middle
so do you mean like like that like this
part of the thing or I'm not sure what
you mean by that
and yet does seem like the walls sides
are the wrong color for some reason
which I'm not sure why that seems odd to
me but I'm not sure where that's coming
from like I said we've got a bunch of
stuff we have to do like test wise I
don't really want to look at it at this
point I think it's probably my guess is
that it's has it's not actually a bug at
all I think the reason we're seeing that
mostly is probably just because of the
way the test cast works so the test
sphere which puts light in the whole
hemisphere that one works properly for
those directions right well properly in
so much as you can call the test proper
so that when you could have seen them I
think it's working like okay right so if
you imagine like where the light
actually is you know it's probably at
least within a stone's throw of correct
although not probably correct the other
the test cast does not it just knows if
it hits the light or not so it doesn't
actually properly tell you any other
direction of incoming light so when you
switch to the test cast it's like can
this wall ever hit the light or not and
the answer is probably like no all the
time right you can even see like it's
not updating any of that part of the
texture because it never takes any
samples in that direction right
so the problem here is it's just it
never note right it's always casting
towards the light it never can find the
light in that direction because there
are no like actual pieces taken for that
direction right so I think that's mostly
what we're getting but again not sure
yet so we'll see when we look at it more
carefully
um for lighting the wooden top I'm not
sure what we'll do about that but
remember the lights may be like up
higher we don't know what we're gonna do
we may like make the walls taller there
there our clue ders may be taller than
they are for example
um in terms of what the next step is we
just need to actually track our light
values all the way through test
everything make sure that with test
cases now in the fused version
everything flows properly and the copies
are proper and like like quantities or
proper and that sort of stuff and then
we switch to the actual ray caster which
we have and make sure that that works
properly and then then we've got just
optimization ahead of us after that
am i planning and putting in tone
mapping I don't know probably nothing
fancy but we might put in some halation
I don't know that we put in any tone
mapping though
does it take a significant amount of
time to switch headspace between
different programming projects for you
and do you have any techniques that you
used to reforming yourselves no it
doesn't really take me any time to
switch the head spaces but what I would
say is I don't really like the fact that
I have to work on handmade Hiro because
it occupies background thought time that
should probably be spent another project
so that's been annoying so basically
means you're spending less mental energy
on your other projects because they're
getting less background time because
Hammond Hiro is taking some of it
all right Matt looks like it thanks
everyone for joining me for the episode
of handmade here it's when it pleasure
coating with you as always I think the
legging is in a pretty good state right
now actually the system's looking pretty
good so I think next weekend we can
start to dive in and just test all the
paths put some debug values in
everywhere and make sure we get out what
we expect basically just run through a
full due diligence lock it down and then
say okay now it's time to get the
raycast err outputting good data and I
think we're we're thumbs up right we do
have some optimization challenges but
even just looking at it now running
relatively fast using the multi-threaded
version I do think that's nice because
if everything's segregated by threads
like that it means at the very least it
will get faster with new chips right if
it's a single-threaded slowness that's a
problem because that doesn't get faster
but a multi-threaded slowness does get
faster with new chips so that's a good
good place to be so I think we're in
good shape so I'll be back here next
weekend to start that in the meantime if
you do want to follow along at home this
series you can always pre-order the game
on hami here or get comes the source
code so you can play around with it
yourself try out your own lighting
solutions if you have got some ideas so
I guess that's about it for this week
I'll see you back here next week until
then have fun everyone I'll see you on
the Internet take it easy