alright hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hero the stream where we
implement an entire game or in this case
an entire lighting system from scratch
and we are kind of getting close to
having good lighting solution I think
actually it's been a bit of a long road
but you know it's converging on what I
wanted
now we today pretty much our job is to
get some debug stuff working drawing
some debug stuff in the lighting
solution so that we can converge on good
lighting right right now I think we're
mostly set up for doing the lighting
that I want but I think we've got a lot
of bugs in there and we just have tuning
to do as well even if we didn't have
bugs so we kind of have to go through
and actually like do that work we also
did the beginnings I trying to remember
exactly what how far we got but we did
the beginnings last week well the other
part of it which is sending down
lighting information separately from
rendering information which again is
also crucial because one of the things
that we need to be able to do since we
are two and a half the game with mixed
mirror look mixed 3d 2d we need to be
able to replace our sprite cards with
actual 3d geometry that can catch light
just simple things like a cube or a
sphere or something like this that can
catch light and so we really want to be
able to keep that in mind as we're as
we're sort of going and we did part of
that work last week we did the part
where we can put in arbitrary lighting
samples per surface so that's half of it
which is saying where we want the light
to be collected we need the other half
of it now which is let's say where we
want our blockers to be we want to do
that in a separate stream from our
actual geometry that gets rendered so
that's really all we have to do so let's
go ahead and get started here today is
day 4:17 so if you're starting with
source code from day 4:16 you should be
able to follow along directly with where
I am and I'm gonna go ahead here and
open up
well I'm gonna wait a while for a visual
studio to open up it's thinking about it
it's working real hard there it goes and
I'm gonna go ahead and load up our
project and build it okay so now I'm
running and we actually found oddly
enough that the lighting solution runs
so quickly at the moment that we can
even run its CPU side now it's very
flickery of course because it's
completely stochastically sampled and we
haven't tuned it at all but you know
even just looking at this what what I
kind of realized you know after we're
gonna have to do work obviously to get
our lighting solution to be nicer and
that's what we're doing the debug for
today because I think we've got some
problems in there but as we sort those
problems out one of the interesting
things that you notice about it is it's
running so fast right now that it even
runs 60 frames a second almost on the
CPU side even even as unoptimized right
it's not even we didn't even do
multi-threaded or Cindy it runs just
fine this way on the small scene as we
improve that that means I think we're in
good shape for it it already looks
pretty good to me like if we you imagine
doing some temporal filtering on that
flicker you know this is really close to
usable so that was a pretty big win for
us and I'm pretty excited about that
because I think it's gonna mean that we
will converge on a really nice lighting
solution here that we can actually use
then we don't have to stress too hard
about because it's like way too slow or
something so on certainly on modern
machines I think we'll be able to turn
on full lighting you know with global
illumination like we have here and it'll
be pretty good now we're not out of the
woods yet like I said there's still a
ways to go to make everything nice and
clean and not flickery and higher
lighting quality and blah blah blah so
we got a bunch of stuff to do but this
is just very promising right and it is
already capturing most of the light
things we want you can see that there's
Bounce lighting happening there these
tiles are getting the blue light
reflected off of these reflectors we're
getting the shadowing that we want so
over here we don't have any of that sort
of light coming in and again we're not
trying to do an accurate lighting
solution here we're just trying to add
character to our scenes by having some
nice global illumination
there so that you can have like stuff
wedding like a projectile goes you get
some nice things going and I don't care
if the lighting is too blocky because
the game is a blot you know it's built
under these little blocks that you're
hopping around on it's supposed to
reinforce the blocky feel it's supposed
to be isn't that minecraft or anything
but it's fairly blocky in terms of the
art style so I don't need these to be
smooth anyway so I don't care how smooth
we get those I just want to make sure we
get some more smoothness in the actual
let examples here that I'm not seeing I
think that's because of bugs that we
have in how we're distributing the light
and tuning we need to do there because
again we are doing sort of a little bit
new stuff now that we haven't debugged
so everything is looking pretty good to
me I'm pretty happy with where this is
going I do think we will probably need
to make a larger scene also we could
slow things down a bit later to make a
larger scene and then as so as we do
optimizations we have something that's
really slow to work on what I'll do is
I'll just turn up the generator so we
generate like a you know big set of
rooms so that we can test you know doing
some of that stuff a little bit more
dynamically but you know otherwise I
think we're pretty good and really the
main things that I want to do like I
said is I really want to get that I want
to get replacement geometry for like the
trees and the hero sprite those sorts of
things with the hero sprites turned off
right now but when we turn it back on
it'll be this big flat card here and
that's no good
so we won't replace the geometry of the
trees and hero sprite we want to get the
lighting tuned and and then I think
we're in good shape to do just like put
it down on the GPU or multi I don't know
maybe multi-threaded on the CPU is the
right way to go I it could be I mean I
don't think it is I think we want that
done on the GPU but you never know it's
hard to say lighting is the kind of
thing that does a lot of random geometry
access and you know sometimes it's just
not the kind of thing that GPUs like and
so I don't really know that'll be in it
that'll really into anything fine when
it comes when we get one that we're like
happy with it'll be pretty interesting
to go okay what's the you know what's
the right way to make this fast and I'm
not sure so we'll have to see when we
have the finished version what what
feels like the right way to go so I'm
going to go ahead and go to the render
group here and and
and what I'm kind of looking at here is
if I remember correctly from where we
left off last week and maybe some of you
remember better than I do because of
course I program all we can a completely
different codebase on completely
different things so sometimes it falls
out of the mental cache but if I
remember correctly what we're doing is
you know we've got this
these extractors here instead of
specifying vertices separately what we
did is we actually just used the same
extractor and place the points in the
same place as we were placing them
before we reduced the subdivision a
little because we were just doing four
points per quad we may up that in the
future you know again the idea is that
you can specify it separately so you
know the generator as it generates the
world can actually be dynamically
deciding where to put these sample
points which is great because it means
we have a lot of freedom to sort of
micromanage the lighting which is what I
wanted because you know lighting like I
said letting is something we just don't
have great solutions for yet so
everything's always a hack that's why
you see all these ridiculous things like
screen space ambient occlusion and all
this nutso stuff going on it's because
there is no perfect solution to lighting
real time ray tracing distributed ray
tracing is the only solution we have
that we know about that would be like a
full lighting solution and it's just not
right it's not feasible it's not fast
enough right so we're always doing a
little bit of hacking and that's just
something that is good to remember when
you're designing a lighting scheme being
able to put in points where you can hack
at it places where you can special case
things places where you can manually
specify it places where it need
improvement all that sort of stuff can
be really helpful because you know
you're not going to get a perfect
solution you just know that going into
it so don't expect it don't expect to
get there right so designing in a little
bit of flex is good so okay here we go
we got our X 7 or Y sub here we're
subsampling the lights we're putting in
these points that we're gonna be working
with and what we know is there are four
points per surface we sent down that
it's hard-coded right now to generate
that amount so what we should be seeing
and the reason I say I want to move very
quickly to a debug view of these because
what we should be seeing is some
interpolation of lighting on here so on
a given surface I should see a color
wash right now what I'm seeing instead
is a solid
color as if each individual one of these
panels only had one lighting sample and
the whole panel was getting lit by that
sample right you can see very clearly
that that is what I'm the output I'm
getting and that doesn't match the
output I was expecting to get and even
though that doesn't always mean there's
a bug you pretty much anytime you get
output that's very different from what
you'd expected you need to investigate
because you probably have a bug but even
if you don't have a bug you at least
have some assumptions that you've made
that are incorrect and you need to
educate yourself what those are so what
I'm gonna do is investigate here so that
I can figure out if I have a bug or just
a misunderstanding of what I myself
wrote because you know these things get
complicated sometimes you think you
wrote something that should do something
you write it correctly and it doesn't do
that thing it turns out to just because
you misunderstood that what would really
happen when this thing occurs right so
you you can have those two paths there's
a bug which is just you failed to write
the thing correctly and you need to fix
it or there's hey this thing doesn't
quite work the way you thought and now
you need to readjust your thinking
because otherwise you can't make the
right modifications to it to get it to
do what you actually needed right
so whichever one it is doesn't matter we
got to find it so let's go in oh and by
the way someone was suggesting that this
on the forums that this sample
hemisphere function isn't uniform that's
correct in fact that's why there's a
to-do on here so I we don't know whether
we'll care about that eventually it's
not that non-uniform but it's a bit a
little bit non-uniform the reason for
that is because it does a cube and then
projects the cube onto a sphere and when
you wrap a cube on to a sphere you you
get bunching along the cube boundaries
right so you will get a cube that's more
densely sample along like you'll get a
hemisphere that's more densely sampled
around the lines of the cube but that
doesn't mean you want to replace it you
have to remember that for approximate
lighting you're you care about speed a
lot and sometimes doing uniform sampling
that's slower connect to be worse than
doing more samples that are biased and
you really don't know till you work up
with it so
don't want to jump to conclusions here
so the person who's asking on the forums
don't jump to conclusions about wanting
to put in a much slower which it would
be if we made a uniform one version of
this because we don't know yet whether
that's a good decision if the time is
not now to look at that all right so
here's our compute light propagation
we're not going to modify that right now
because we want to investigate it as it
is at the moment and so what we want to
do here is we want to have a way that we
could flip between our lighting quads
and our our normal scene right all right
so here is our output lighting car quads
function and what we want to do here is
we want to I think clean up some of this
stuff we kind of want to go through and
just say look I'm pretty sure we don't
want the voxel thing in here anymore so
I'm just gonna go ahead and say look we
keep backups from every day if I need to
go get old code I will so I'm just gonna
go ahead and and get rid of some of this
stuff right we just don't we don't need
this anymore
so what I want to do here is I want to
kind of just sort of start to clean this
up and I want to get a good debug view
in here that we can quickly switch
between it was kind of drinking before
because we never really spent the time
to get it right I'd like to get it right
now and make make this stuff work the
way it should so I'm gonna just trim out
some of this code here right that we
don't need anymore I don't need any of
this voxel filling stuff all of this
stuff that can go away so here's what
we're kind of looking at here and and we
can also clean up some of this the
lighting stuff as well we just don't
need a lot of this stuff right so we
just need to push those lighting
textures it's like the only thing that
we need to push and and they can have
some stuff removed from there too so
again just cleaning this up and then
adding a debug view to it is all I'm
really trying to accomplish right now
and that's just to inspect our lighting
as we can then debug and refine it
because I like the way it's looking
right now and I just now I want to I'm
at the point where I want to turn the
dial and and start improving this scheme
rather than continuing to investigate
other schemes I'm pretty happy with
where this is go so we really don't need
any of this stuff right we're just C and
D are the only two things we're using
right now we don't need my mug off the
table I really don't want to break that
mug because I like that mug it's what I
have coffee in so what I want to do is
just clean that up get rid of it and
remove all the stuff that was dependent
on it right so these things here that
were previously dependent on it I want
to get rid of those I don't want to take
those as function calls anymore
I want to remove anything that was
dependent on it here we don't care about
that let's see what else we've got all
right so that's all good
in the actual thing that we submit I
feel like are we still submitting
that stuff down though where's our red
no there's we need to remove it from
from one of these things as well because
there's a there's an additional lighting
transfer thing here so we want to get
rid of these and that and we just want
this thing this render entry lighting
transfer is the only thing we actually
want and that means we can remove some
of these textures to here like we don't
need to bind this P next texture we
don't need to divine this lighting
lookup either and that's good too one of
the nice things about that is it gets us
out of the 3d lookup space although I'll
be honest we still may need that for the
ray tracing side of things so we may
still and have to have a sort of like
hierarchical structure for that we don't
really know what's gonna happen there
but for the lighting look up at least we
got out of the 3d texture business and
that's probably a good thing because you
know the less you can rely on 3d
textures are better things that grow as
the cube of a size is always a little
bit always a little bit worse than it is
something that doesn't right it's you
would you would prefer to always be 2d
if you could be we also don't need these
light buffers there's a lot once once we
are finished with the lighting we're
gonna be able to clean out a lot of
cruft
which will be nice just things that we
just simply don't need anymore
and that's pretty cool I always find
that to be quite nice those yep okay P
next and look up
and we really don't need to do this
anymore but we'll leave it there because
it doesn't hurt and so now we have to
kind of rebind these a little bit more
carefully here
so technically lighting si will now
become two texts or two I believe and
letting D will become texture three
right like so we we will not have any
other textures in there there we go and
now I need to make sure that those are
still lined up properly in the actual Z
bias shader so those will be in here Vox
Minh corner and just cell dim or no long
getting passed down the peanut sampler
and the look up sampler no longer
getting passed down in there and so
those get removed from here right so you
got the C sampler and the T sampler and
that's going to be it none of those
other folks are there and I don't know
if I've trimmed everything out now I may
have trimmed too much out we'll see in a
second but hopefully well yeah we'll get
some errors here that will tell us what
stuff is missing okay so let's see what
we got here program errors should have
all the errors I think I got a look in
the individual so let's see we're checks
errors Ragman errors look up sampler and
P next sampler are still in there
let's see sampler ah yes so we can clamp
we can get rid of like this stuff like
the clamp locks unbox a light that stuff
can just get removed that's good
and yeah so all of this stuff that we
used to be doing can also get removed
goodbye there you go
and again you can see just even from the
look of it this is just so much cleaner
so if we can make this lighting scheme
work you can just see how much sort of
effort we're saving just in the basic
like execution of the shader will be
simpler there
right Phoenix center is that still in
here oh wait what Oh hmm all right maybe
I was I was a little overzealous there
so we do still need the light position
so so I guess we need to still have one
of these four light positions gosh I
really wish we could have these in a
more compact format than to having a
sample from three separate textures you
know I wish we could just have a buffer
you know we probably could right just
have a buffer that has these three
things in it because fundamentally
speaking right we just want to do a
buffer fetch you know I just don't know
that you could do that in the in the
fragment shader in OpenGL 3 I so you
know what what I'm trying to say here is
just that this stuff is just not really
any of it none of this is F is what we
really want what we really want is just
a lighting Texel like this thing you
know once right now like to UM textured
vertex I don't know where that guy went
here it is
what we really want is what are these
textured vertex things right that's what
we actually wanted and we just want that
to be something that we can specify as a
buffer right I mean we just want to be
able to say here's a position of the
light here's the you know direction of
the light and here's the color you know
that's what we want to specify per light
per light point coming down because
that's what we fetch in here you know
and so it would be nice to go to do one
look up and get all those things back
rather than we sampling from all these
textures which just creates a lot of
overhead but I just funded
we don't know if we're allowed to fetch
from a buffer in a fragment shader
because that sort of thing is a
relatively new addition and I don't know
just a LSL version sample from buffer in
fragment shader so let's see here so
three quick reference card cuz I don't
think you can so I think you know I I
just don't know any other way to do it I
guess is what I'm saying then still
having one I would like to roll them all
into one but I just don't think you can
and I'm not sure so let's take a look
let's see here per fragment operations
that's not so that's
[Music]
I mean because in a sense you could just
contribute as a uniform right as well
and then you just find a buffer to the
uniform but those usually have very like
uniforms oftentimes have very hard
constraints on how long they can be in
earlier versions of geocells well so I
just don't know if that's gonna be
something we can actually if we're
allowed to use right so let's see here
yeah this is one of those questions
that's really hard to answer I wish I
could have done a search on it but it
doesn't look like there's any
information in the search shader access
to buffer
yeah so you can just see like we should
probably stick with textures right
because if you look at it this is what
we want basically I think probably again
I just am not sure what the easiest way
to do this would be but I think you'd
have to be up to version four before you
can really count on this being available
right let's see here
so yes so I'm just I'm just not gonna do
it I'm gonna I'll I'll put it back in
the an array for the position looking at
cuz this is what we want here looking at
that it's like so we've got essentially
two sets of four element wide things but
I don't think again because they have to
be textures I don't think I can pack
those together in any better way really
you know so like looking at this right
these two could be packed together if
they weren't heterogeneous types but I
just don't see any real way to do that
and similarly like I could I could stick
two different color values in there are
other ways to pack this so I don't know
like one way to do it would be with two
V for textures right like one way to do
it would be to say all right we've got a
V for like light zero and a V for of
light data one so two for wide float
textures right we could do that and
these would just be that would get rid
of the concept of max light power right
the light could be any floating-point
number that you wanted and the way this
would be packed would be like pxpypz
[Music]
Direction X and this would be like color
our color G color B Direction Y and then
you just have two textures
they're both floating-point textures you
can now have floating-point color values
right so that you don't have max light
power anymore the power is what the
light is just whatever it is and then
you have the direction X Direction Y you
recover the xethru normalization because
you know the direction has to be a
normal that cuts this down to two
texture
samples seems better than me because we
were gonna need floating points for the
position or the this either way so we're
gonna need a wide format either way
could we could go to 16 bit obviously
per channel so to 32 bit but for now so
I think that's I think I like that
better so I think I do want to still cut
down all of my textures that way - just
- and then we'll send that down that
gets rid of the max light power as well
so it also kind of buys us something
nice there and then we just have to 1d
textures and again those sectors are
quite small because they're 1d so let's
say even if we doubled this and we went
up to having 16,000 light source things
which you know I don't know that we're
ever gonna have that much but let's say
we actually did again they're only one D
so we're talking about eight floats each
one of those floats is four wide that's
only a half mega texture data really not
a big deal
right so again I feel like minimizing
number of textures there's just better
less samplers less fuss seems like a
good plan
well I forgot we have this new oops yeah
we have this new speed crunch thing that
someone sent that's a better calculator
I should probably leave that up instead
so I like that and that way we only have
two textures still and that's good so
I'm gonna go ahead and and try playing
with that a little bit and see if we
can't make that work out and I'm gonna
call these things that we push on here
I'm just gonna call them the same thing
so we've got light data zero and light
data one okay zero data one actually I
guess we probably want that both here
what does the problem cannot grow it
from f32 oh never mind actually made
those type of same alright so in the
decode power function now I guess that
just isn't necessary anymore because if
we look at where that was being used
right decode power was just something
that we're using for decoding the packed
versions anyway so in here this should
be fine so okay in in this we don't
actually have one of these things so
that's fine it's gonna be this and we
did we are not clamping anymore so what
was this doing here output letting
textures this is packing these down and
we don't really want them packed down we
don't want the length this this is not
like we don't want any of this anymore
actually so the incident light is just
the emit see right in fact we don't even
need to yeah this just does not need to
be processed and it's not going to be
packed right so what we need to do here
is we need to grab the location as well
as the average direction and we need to
pack these together so really what we're
doing here is two packs down light data
zero light data one and what I want that
to do again is I want that to follow
this recommendation
that I put here which is pxpypz DX and
CRC GCB right
so yeah let's go ahead and put those in
there I we know that we've got P dot X P
dot y p dot Z we'll have to fetch that
out and then we've got our color so CR c
g CP and then we need our x that's why
it's the only thing we don't have here
is our position but that's okay because
we can easily get the position the
lighting solution has these letting
points in it and it should just be
accessible right off that if i remember
correctly
so where is letting point there it is so
that's all we need right there
it's just that p value and i think
that's it right so that should get
everything at and packed into those
lighting data structures and ready for
submission uh this is no longer relevant
to anybody so it should go away deleting
code is always a good sign in my opinion
and then we need to make all of this
stuff line up with what we said so we've
got light data zero light data one and
these two are now both gonna submit
floats for element floats zero one and
they're both 1d this is all correct so
all of that stuff is fine and yeah off
we go so now we have to modify the
opengl side of things because it's
getting those lighting samples coming
down so we need light k20 and light one
in here to be
our new buffer names and then in here we
need to allocate those properly late
pick 0 K 2 1 0 J 2 1 and again we are
going to modify this because now it's
going to be a 32f texture it's gonna be
a GL float:right so those are just the
same as we were doing before only now we
just got two textures of exactly the
same kind if we could we just say this
texture had eight elements right but we
can't so we just do two that have four
elements each alright so oops gotta do
the bind properly here like two to one
light g20 so we've combined both of
these noob or didn't and now we need to
adjust the shader to account for that
properly so there's like two to zero and
light dataone and those are in slots two
and three so we I should have a slot 0
and 1 and a slot 2 and 3 don't ask me
why I keep typing why so now if I go
back and look at the white see here go
grab this stuff so now this shader needs
to be reworked a little bit so you can
see in here when we do the compile
Xevious program our sampler is well
that's the vertex shader so we don't
really have to do anything there but in
here our samples are C slam 4 and D
sampler so this is like like zero
sampler and this is like one sampler we
need those to be coming through in the
right slots so we've got them here like
stereo sampler like one sampler I don't
know what this debug light P thing is
but we're not using it anymore
that was what we used to have a debug
light that we moved around and all this
stuff like the multi grid up and down we
we just jettisoned all of that stuff
those were experiments that I didn't
pursue past the initial phase so that
stuff can all go to it's gonna be really
nice to like lock this down real
actively soon when we're like ah now we
have our lighting solution and we don't
have to worry about any of this stuff
anymore all right so those are our two
lighting samplers and they're in slots 2
&amp; 3 as they were supposed to be where we
bound them right so they're right there
and then all we need to do is actually
to code those properly right so in here
where we do our fetching here we get out
the light indices we then need to fetch
like a 2-0 light data one and those get
fetched off of these samplers right and
so then what we can do is say well we
can now to code these based on the
encoding that we said before the
position value is going to be light
dated zero RGB the light direction here
which is this value that's going to be
light data ones RGB oh sorry the light
color it's gonna be light data ones RGB
which is in here somewhere we don't need
the max power multiplier anymore
in fact because it's now a
floating-point value so that just
becomes the simple multiply and then we
need to reconstruct the light d
reconstructing the light D is going to
involve a couple steps the first one is
the XY value in fact I suppose we should
say X Y Z I'm here to make it a little
clearer that those are positions going
through the XY reconstruction is gonna
have to start I guess we could actually
write it out this way now remember I
only packed two of the valley
two of the three values I need so the X
Y Z so in the Alpha Channel of each of
these right I packed the X in here and
the Y in here the D value I don't have a
z-value I don't have so the question is
where am I going to get it what we're
just going to do here is the very simple
you know exactly what you would expect
we're just going to go ahead and use
exploit the fact that these are normals
so we're gonna do some z-value
reconstruction here what we know is we
had an X a Y and a Z right and we only
stored these two so we're looking for
this right well what we know is that
since this thing is a normal right since
this is a normal we're talking about
here we know the length of the normal is
1 so we know that the length of X you
know X the length of X Y Z equals 1 what
that means is that if we take the
Pythagorean theorem and say well the
length of something you know he's the
square root of x squared plus y squared
plus Z squared right and we know that
that equals 1 well we should be able to
figure out some way of solving for this
Z squared right so in our case what we
can do is just say well it's pretty easy
to square both sides of this thing
because this side is 1 and has no
variables on it right so that means x
squared plus y squared plus Z squared
has to equal 1 right because it doesn't
matter whether it squared or not the
square of 1 is 1 so that basically means
it's just this without the square root
equals 1 that makes it pretty trivial
for us to go OK Z squared therefore must
equal X minus this quantity right
because this was the quantity on the
other side if we subtract it here we
just get this simple arithmetic right so
the Z value must be the square root of x
I'm sorry of the square root of 1 minus
x squared plus y squared makes sense so
that's just some really simple you know
algebra whatever you want to call it
maths and so what we can do here is say
well alright we've we need to take the
square root of 1 minus like DX times
like we have a square function it
doesn't matter I'll just do it manually
plus light D Y times light
right and now we know that you you look
at this you can sort of say well alright
is this is this dicey right because we
could get a negative value here and the
answer is like not unless something goes
horribly wrong because we know that each
of these values has to be less than one
because a normal can't have any
component greater than one right because
the maximum you can have would just be 1
0 0 or 0 1 0 or 0 0 1 because can only
be one long so if there's a 1 in a
channel nothing else can be equal to
anything and there's certainly no where
to get longer than 1 so something that's
1 or less than 1 squared right plus
something that's 1 or less than 1
squared we we I guess why I say is we
have to assume the property of the
normal that it's length has to be less
than 1 to mean that no matter what these
values are set to be when we add them
together the same will be true right
because remember if x squared plus y
squared plus Z squared has to equal 1
then x squared plus y squared without
adding Z squared couldn't be more than 1
right because the square of a value is
always positive and if we're adding that
and still equaling 1 then if we take it
away
it can only be less right so we know
this value has to itself be either 1 or
less than 1 it can't be more than 1 so
in theory this square root unless we had
a really bad numerical precision thing
happened where we I don't know did it
really bad normalizing somehow had
values that were greater than what I
don't know I don't think it's likely we
could never get anything other than 0
here for example would be the lowest
value we could ever get right which
would be 1 minus 1 right and the square
root of 0 of course is 0 and that's
correct because if we had a 1 let's say
X was 1 we get 1 times 1 and we know Y
would be 0 in that case because all the
values in X we get 1 times 1 plus 0
times 0 right so it would be 1 minus 1
and that would be 0 that would make Z
equal to 0 it's exact what we want
because X is
Z has to be zero there's no more room to
have the normal be anything else right
so that's how we would reconstruct this
and that gives us back all of the
variables that we wanted we don't care
about this at all does render setup
still have a debug light P in it because
if so it does go away cuz we don't need
a debug light anymore all right so now
we got a debug it which hopefully won't
be too bad
Swizzle mask element not present in
operand mmm what what was wrong with my
use of the dot a Swizzle oh yeah sorry
those are from the v4 is not the VIII's
my bad
let's try that one more time
there we go uh so that's kind of
interesting we have now like just by
Rhian coding those we must have had a
bug in how we were encoding them before
because now that we're encoding them
directly we do get color washes now
which is not what I was expecting so we
must have accidentally fixed a bug
unless we introduced a bug that's
generating color washes but the color
washes actually look somewhat correct
here for the sample points that we gave
which are not particularly good sample
points right so that's a little bit
weird but we must have fixed the bug our
wave that we were coding light powers
must have been wrong I'm guessing that's
interesting okay well that's fine
so anyway now that we've got that
encoded what I want to do is what I set
out to do originally but I'm kind of
glad we did that because that puts us in
a much better position Towe don't we
where before what I'd like to do now is
I'd like to go ahead and draw those
sample points have a way of drawing out
the sample points so what we want to do
here again is we want to have ways in
which we can intentionally not draw
lighting for these particular samples
and just output solid color values that
get interpreted directly and remember we
did the work last weekend to make it so
that we could draw things that did not
have lighting again that's why now
remember before it was actually lighting
our text remember that well now we've
got a way to not do that right which is
this and that's really good so I'm happy
about that and we can now leverage that
fact again when we do our debug drawing
because that allows us to
avoid the problem of having what we're
what is trying to be debug display get
them affected by the lighting
computation which is literally what
we're trying to debug so we really don't
want that to be true right okay so now
let's start to clean this code up so
we've got two pieces of the code they're
interacting to create this situation
here so we've got our F key pressed
stuff here so let's take a look at that
sorry I'm a little stuffy today as I
almost always am I went an allergy sort
of person it's not great it's not
pleasant so anyway what I want to do
here is is go ahead and and figure out
how exactly this stuff is gonna work
we're running the lighting every time
now so I think what we want to do is
just sort of change some of these way
these keys are working oh I didn't
realize that the iteration count there
could be beefed up I wonder what happens
if I adjust that whoa that's weird so we
have some weird bugs there oh no that
just reduces it to zero you can see that
we have like a power leakage problem
which I think I know why that is because
we're not being particularly careful
with that but as we increase the
iteration count everything gets brighter
right which is not we don't really want
that we want a solution that doesn't do
stuff like that so this will be good as
we debug this will get much better with
lighting results so there's just a first
bounce
right you can see you don't get any
secondary lighting here's the second
pants and you can see you can see the
blue lighting come in here right can you
guys see that
so no indirect lighting all the light is
coming from a white light source now we
get indirect lighting we get that blue
and you can even see it here like so
what happens is this and this is what's
so cool about lighting right and it's
why I'm really glad we're doing this cuz
I don't I don't know I know there's some
folks who just want to do game
programming stuff and they don't like
this are technical stuff but a fortune
that's not what this series is about
right this series is about technical
minutiae that's why I do it right I'm
not a game designer so I don't care
about game code in the slightest but I
love that right so we're gonna have as
we get this working really well you can
kind of see the kind of lighting
subtleties that this adds to the scene
that are just really kind of nice
so that first bounce gives you the blue
light here it also lights these services
that surface would get no light so if we
just did direct lighting the surface
gets no light now that we do it this
it's starting to get light from the
bounce off of these right and off of via
this and then now it's redistributing
its light to its nearby tiles and now
you get a red bounce light that's a
bounce off of a surface that couldn't
even have been seen itself on the first
one so you just add these really nice
lighting cues right and you can kind of
see as we get this going better it's
it's just really kind of cool I think
what this the character this will add to
the game so if you imagine us just kind
of getting this nicely tuned getting rid
of the flicker and and having those kind
of nice lighting effects in the game as
subtle lights as you move through the
environment as projectiles move to the
environment whatever I just think that
adds so much character to a scene and
just makes it feel so interesting and
reactive and you know I mean that's why
you're playing a game in the first place
right a lot of people don't appreciate
the degree to which audio visuals impact
your gameplay experience but they do you
could just go play a board game if you
didn't want audio visual feedback
immediate fast audio visual feedback the
whole point of playing a video game is
that you have this immediate
audio-visual feedback and that it's rich
and interesting
play a card game or a board game if you
don't want that right it it's
fundamentally not a video game
experience if you don't have this kind
of rich AV because that's what defines a
video game as compared to a a non video
game right so it is sometimes overlooked
everything works together in a video
game there isn't one important part the
gameplay is just as important as
everything else but it is not the it's
not uniquely important everything works
together to create the game experience
and if any one of those things is lousy
the game is worse than it should be
right everything should work together to
form the game experience okay so anyway
let's go ahead and and finish this up so
our submission looks like it's working
nicely here this is some stuff that we
can optimize more for example we will
probably just have this generated on the
GPU in the future so that's what we'll
you know be looking towards certainly
this output lighting call now we kind of
need to make this stuff make a little
more sense here so output lighting and
output lighting textures and all this
stuff we need to kind of clean up the
way this is working so output letting
textures so you can see right here how
this is going this is happening every
frame oops
whether you push f1 or not and so this
is doing the recomputation of that and
it's doing that output every every frame
we could do it only once in a while with
the f1 key if we wanted to in fact I
guess I'll leave you know I'll leave
that in there
just in case we do want to do that but
so this is happening every frame and so
the part that we want to determine a
little bit earlier here right is what
actually is getting output every time
and we don't really need to do it the
way we were doing it here that that
doesn't need to be an if-else kind of a
thing right we can continue doing the
simulation potentially because it
doesn't really matter if that's going on
behind the scenes I suppose I'm not sure
maybe that's the wrong way to think
about it but either way if we decide to
do a if we decide to switch to show
lighting here then really all that has
to happen is that keyboard has to be
here to toggle right so if you hit the
f1 key we have to switch between
outputting the lighting directly and
doing the push lighting here right so
what we want to do is we want probably
at we probably want this to be a little
bit more sensible let's go ahead and
grab this here so we want this output
lighting to be like output lighting
sample or output letting points probably
and then in the future we'll probably
want output letting occluders to also be
in there so we can debug inspect either
of them right so let's go ahead and
actually just make sure that it works
without this first and so now we should
be able to do right is we should be able
to toggle between those two modes at any
time so we're you know we're looking at
the lighting solution here we hit f1 we
look at the debug we hit f1 we're back I
don't know why it flashes once there
probably because nothing's been
downloaded yet to that I'm not sure
let's go look and see if that makes
sense or not but that sets us up to
actually put in something that displays
there's lighting points there
and so what I'm gonna do here is just
going to loop over those letting points
so you know exactly the way we were
doing it here where we output them right
what we're gonna do is we're gonna do
something very similar but instead we're
going to just you know do output draws
on them right okay so the first thing we
want to do here is turn off the the
secondary lighting of that and I think
that happens automatically right so you
can see if show lighting if we're not in
show lighting mode then letting gets
enabled but if we aren't relating mode
then we won't be right and so I think we
could even move that down because
nothing gets drawn up here
I don't think pretty sure so that that
could if it wanted to kind of stay up
here could be moved down I could do that
so it'll enable lighting in this case
but it will enable lighting in the other
case so I think that's all good and then
all we have to do in here is we have to
actually we have to actually output this
for real so we know that we want to
output point count number of quads right
that's what we want to output and then
we want to effectively do what we were
doing here but we want to do it based on
the data we have now not the data that
we used to be outputting right so we
need to figure out how to we're going to
do that we can delete this code here and
we can also make the bitmap call up
there and out okay so we just need to
make sure that this stuff all makes some
sense we've got this UV stuff that that
again is gonna be ignore because there's
no texture on these so we're just
setting it to nothing so all we have to
worry about is drawing the P values and
the C values those are the two things
that we need to output
and we need to figure out good ways to
output those okay so the p-value is
pretty easy we already know what that is
the C value is is perhaps a little bit
harder right now like you can see what
happens here we could just take exactly
what we were taking before where we have
this p value we don't have element
widths or Heights anymore because
remember these are lighting sample
points they know they're not occluder so
they're just out locus so this width and
height we can just call these element
with an element height basically and the
X and Y axis are going to have to be
generated in in asked in a different way
as well so this is this is a little bit
of work here it's not much it won't be
hard but it's just a little bit work so
what we want to do is pick an element
with and we want that element with to
probably be pretty tiny right
we just want little tiny like little
tiny squares that just are at the sample
points so we can see them all we don't
want these like big surface anymore
because they're not these are not the
occluders these are not things that are
getting that are going to intercept rays
that are doing samples these are sample
points they are individual like light
collecting locations that we've
scattered out and that we will use to
interpolate so we just want to see
little markers so we can look at the
lighting of the scene as we go through
right so what I want to do is is just
keep those free tiny will tune those as
we see it maybe we want it to be a
little bigger than that maybe we don't I
don't know don't ask me why that
negative 0.3 was in the area of know
it's probably historical reasons that
have long been forgotten so what we want
to do here is is generate in X and y
axis and the question is how do we want
to generate that X and y axis well we
can just use I think the original
normals that we had in here I seem to
recall us storing that information and
yeah there they are they're duplicated
out from the lighting surface so what I
can do here is I can say that we have a
normal and then what we can do is we can
generate an X and y axis from that
normal the other thing we could do is
look up the surface index in fact that
might be smarter because that actually
has the x and y axis in it so that
they'll be aligned to the sir
just that they were on that sounds like
a better idea to me so hey if it sounds
like a better idea to me let's do it
so solution surfaces I guess we got a we
probably want to grab these actually out
as bullying in Syria so let's let's do
that so we can access multiple things
awesome
oops so there we go
grab the point out and then we need to
grab the surface lighting surface
surface will solution surfaces plus the
surface index so so for now we'll just
grab that out the future maybe we won't
have ax this in which case we'll have to
change and generate them from the normal
which we can do it's not hard but there
we go so we get the x-axis the y-axis
out of the surface we don't need the
normal we do have the emission color and
abstraction alight here we don't
actually we're not going to be actually
using that average Direction annoyed for
anything here because we don't have a
way to really output that at the moment
it would be nice if we did so I'm gonna
put it to do here Casey
draw a quad that extends in this
direction maybe we've got a line segment
call we should probably use it so that
you know let's look at that in a second
get this working first so we've got the
the color value here this stuff we're
not touching so we've got the front
emitter that's like a clamp version of
these so we need to do that again and we
don't have a way of rendering any really
bright stuff so we're just gonna have to
do the standard clamp here we could
scale the values down if we want to but
you know we'll have to see what happens
there so then we got to do these encodes
here the C 0 C 1 C 2 C 3 stuff that
stuff looks like it can all stay the
same to me we don't have a transparency
value anymore so I think this can
literally just be this right that all
looks pretty good
so the emit see here I'll just grab that
the way we were grabbing it there's the
emit see we do in the clamps and put it
into the v4 then we pack it down and
send it into the standard quad pipeline
nothing out of the ordinary there and so
I think that is most of it
[Music]
yeah I really don't see anything else we
need to do there so that should generate
sort of a sea of points for us of course
we may have made some mistakes in there
but here's what we're you know normally
rendering here's our sea of points right
you can see where our lighting samples
are and I feel like there may be a
little too small so I went a little bit
overboard there let's go ahead and beef
them up a little see if that helps
that's pretty good right so here you can
see all of our lighting sample points
and we turn off the simulation we're in
this mode I don't love that so I think
maybe what we'll do is not do that
and we'll let this fall through so the
problem here well hmm so the problem
here is this wants to render in line I
don't know if we can make a trash render
group for this stuff let's see here how
does that work so yeah I mean normally
normally we do have the ability to do a
non sim step right because this is it so
you know we should be able to do this
begins him either way because no
rendering has happened yet so this stuff
really could be
you know where that happens essentially
so what we could do here is say look
this is not what we actually want to do
right we're gonna leave this stuff out
doing it's doing its thing right and
what I'm going to do is going to put
this inside of here so once we actually
do do the do this part of it we'll
switch between which kind of sim we're
doing right so if we take a look here at
who needs the render group it's really
just here and here and the particles are
disabled at the moment so we should be
able to do something where we do like
that I think can the render group be
passed as a zero here probably guessing
it can be because otherwise how would we
do it right yeah these are all optional
so we can pass the zero render group
there which is all we would really have
to do so you know what I could do
actually I can do this really
straightforward I think I think we can
just you
something like this so didn't want to do
that I hit the P key instead of the hit
the wrong key so what I can do here just
say all right
I think that gives me what I want so
what I can do is make a temporary
variable here called use render group
which I can set to 0 if I want to right
so basically what I'll do is if we are
going to output the lighting points then
I'll just set use render group to 0 so
all this stuff when it goes through will
not actually effect it won't actually
affect the render group at all right I
think that'll work
except that that should be their regular
render well that didn't do what I had
hoped and I guess I can see why so the
problem is the lighting will get updated
yeah I see what the problem is
so what I really have to do is erase
what's been pushed so far which which
really isn't gonna work
so I guess we really can't avoid having
it just be stationary which is
unfortunate we would have to do things
further down the pipeline because by the
time it gets to the lighting test here
when it recomputes the lighting test it
will have only had the point geometry
which is not what it needs yeah so
there's no real way to cleanly do that
at the moment unfortunately so that's
pretty much the way it's gonna have to
stay at the moment which is too bad
not the end of the world that's not what
I would have preferred all right so here
we can see all those samples I'm still
going to say maybe even just a little
bit bigger on those samples
so here we can see all of the lighting
sample points that we sent down and we
can kind of see where that light is
getting spread through right and so if I
go through and I take a look at the
bounces so here's the first one
here's the second one you can see
everywhere it ended up spreading out too
and I'll be honest that doesn't look
super correct to me you know I I it's
possible that none of the random rays
that were sent out from say this surface
up here it's possible that none of them
hit these closer to these they only hit
closer to the bottom it just doesn't
seem likely you know and maybe we have
to draw the Rays themselves to really
know but it just doesn't seem likely so
that seems a bit odd just so we're on
the same page there right so one bounce
two bounces now and even now it's still
not still hasn't hit nothing has hit
those so it honestly it looks kind of
like it only ever adds to I think maybe
our pick the way we're picking which
point to add to when we hit the surface
may be buggy that's what I'm thinking
just in my head right now
yeah I mean I think that's oh I think
that's almost certainly the case so I
want to go look at that right now
because even before we get any further
into this letting debugging and
refinement I feel like this part of our
code is busted at the moment so I'm not
sure why but it definitely looks that
way it looks a lot
like this picking process is not working
for whatever reason so you can see
what's going on here we do a test to see
if the raycast that we did hit a surface
when we find the surface that it hit we
loop so the surface point index thing
here we loop over however many lights
that surface supposedly had on it we
grab the point index of each of those
right by starting at the light index
that that service starts at and adding
you know 0 1 2 3 up to however many it's
supposed to have and we have initialized
the closest distance squared to f/32 max
so it's you know it will always be
higher than anything you could throw at
it
anything other value um oh I see exactly
the problem here don't know no I don't
know I take it back no no so then we we
do this light index + or any extra dump
that we do lighting point star hit point
equal solution points plus point index
so that should dereference that
particular point right we then take the
distance between the Rays location which
you know maybe we should verify we
actually are getting that that could be
wrong maybe that's computed improperly
would be one way this could be failing
the raised position - the the hit point
position and we see which one of those
is least I we then record the point
index that that was as the closest point
index and we record the closest distance
squared as its distance now that looks
pretty straightforward to me assuming
accumulate sample works properly does it
it looks like it so I guess what I would
say is also we replicated the surface
end didn't we so we don't actually need
service in here because that could just
come from the point now yeah um so what
I'm wondering is yeah did we some how is
this not the real you know what I think
I think this wood is the so this is the
relative origin I think we don't want
that right so we never actually did
compute that value so I think that's
what's happening I think this is Ray
Origin plus T ray x ray D I think is
what we actually need here and to be
fair since relative origin is just the
Ray origin minus the source P what we
could do too is just re reconstruct it
right it beer AP and we just need to add
the source P back in right so this this
value is missing from that computation
right because it's been subtracted out
here so it just needs to get added back
in so that's the same value with with
one must multiply so that seems good
right but now let's take a look at what
we've got here and already it looks much
more correct right so here's that first
one and hey lo and behold my intuition
was correct these sample points are now
getting lit which they weren't before so
that's pretty good and then if I add in
one more iteration here so there's what
iteration
at a second iteration in now the bounces
are letting up all the points which is
exactly what we would want so that looks
much better
to me right that looks much more sane
and so I think we need to work on the
algorithm now but at least now that that
was definitely a bug and exactly as I
suspected having some debug code in
there made it really easy to find I
don't think we would have found that
without that code right so there's one
bounce there's two bounces not there's
three and so on so again one of the nice
things too about the having this scheme
that has lighting samples that are
basically controllable separately per
surface is that it does mean we can also
over tessellate like we can put more
samples on surfaces that we care more
about and less samples on services that
we care less about now one of the things
that's interesting here is I feel like
we're not probably having enough samples
taken especially because how fast this
is running which we don't really want it
to run this fast I think we do want to
do a thing where we up this rate count
right so I don't know what the best rate
count value is but we want these to be
higher certainly then than they were
before
so here's a slower version that's
running I'm not sure how many bounce
this is so here's one bounce running
with with sort of more samples and
here's two bouncers running with more
samples right and I'm just looking at
what ends up happening with the lighting
on these I'm interested to know why the
lighting is so different between some of
these
and I guess that's just because of the
randomness of how the light happens to
go
yeah so yeah I think the most sensible
thing to do now is just to take a look
at at the lighting algorithm itself and
start to improve the quality of how
we're distributing light in general
right what we'd like to do is try to
figure out some ways to make it more
energy neutral like our ideally what we
would like is some way of saying well if
you run this thing for four iterations
where you run it for eight iterations
you'll still get roughly the same
brightness of light you'll just get it
distributed more correctly than it was
before you know that's what we would
like
we'd like a way of saying that that were
the total amount of light in the scene
isn't gonna just keep going up and up
the more iterations you run Oh we'd like
to be sort of unbiased in sort of the
more sampling meaning of the term where
we converge towards a correct solution
from no particular side like it's just
kind of like generally averages out to
the correct solution so we oscillate
around it rather than something that's
always gonna keep going higher or lower
coming up from one side always right
we'd like something that produces
correct results on average rather than
something that kind of just randomly
bouncing light around and hey we sort of
tweaked it till it were looked okay
right so I think we'd like to improve
that solution as as we can and what I
would like to do is I'd like to make it
possible to run the bounces so in this
mode you know I can continuously hit the
keys to like change how many iterations
were doing there and what I think I
would like to do is I think I'd like
to make it so that we can do that same
key presses in here and so what what
that would require is when I get that
key press run it once with the correct
geometry and then go right so basically
when you hit one of these there's like a
recompute lighting this false compute
but it's true like so and so then when
we come through here we would say like
okay if we're not recomputing the
lighting and we're showing the lighting
then do this thing right otherwise do
the other path and that way we can just
sort of make it really easy to quickly
do that in the other mode without having
to do the little Toggl dance right so
one bounce to bounce three bounds for
bounce right and it just like it does
that quick flash rerender so that it's
pretty easy to do that cycling so that's
that's all I really wanted it to do
and those sample points are still too
small you know I was saying we did wand
him small and it came back to bite me
because it turns out we really want them
pretty big so I keep up in the size here
till we get something that's it's nice
and big
it's pretty good so now we can sort of
see this a little bit better detail as I
kind of go out so there's the first
bounce second bounce third bounce bounce
bounce rate like so and let's take a
look at how that bounce works out when
we're over like here let's say so
there's no bounces first bounce second
bounce third bounce right and you can
kind of see again that these are bounces
off of this colored light source right
that's the blue light so it's getting
pure light on it but when it reflects
light out because remember these are not
showing what the surface will show these
are showing what light hit there so it
was white light that hit here but it was
blue light that hit here right and as
that goes you can see that it continues
to add more light bounce light off of
these surfaces as well you can kind of
see that happening right we need to get
rid of that little snake dude he keeps
jumping around making it uneven for us
to look at what the lighting solution is
all right now there should be no snake
dude um so yeah now so there you can see
a lighting solution in place and if we
look at the bounce sequence here first
bounce second bounce third bounce fourth
bounce right with just bounce and so
that's what we're looking at so what we
want to do here is I think we want to
start to try and get that lighting
bouncing to work better and I think we
want a couple things to do here so first
of all we need to think about this from
we're kind of a weird like hybrid
concept right we are sort of a ray
tracer sort of we're sort of a like
render first lighting model right but
we're sort of half a radiosity solution
as well so we're kind of doing a
radiosity saw because at the end of the
day we're producing lighting samples
that are then used later so instead of
actually producing the light that is
going to be shot towards the viewers eye
and counted like we would be doing an
array tracer we're really using the ray
tracing to produce a radiosity solution
which is just remembering what light was
incident on a surface or an irradiance
cache remembering what light was instead
of surface so that somebody later can
come and use that information to
properly light the scene right so we're
kind of in the middle of those two and
we need to just be aware of that what we
want to do here is we want to
start to think about how we're gonna do
that conservation of energy there so
that we don't just keep getting brighter
and that sort of stuff and and and also
we want to keep in mind how we get a
skylight in there all right so let's
talk about this real quick
how much time do we have we have about
15 minutes I think yes let's see here
one seven oh wait I already did that so
this right here is just
so I'm gonna put that in big ol quotes
the reason I'm going to put that in
quotes is because we're not really going
to be doing anything hardcore here
probably but we are going to start
trying to think about this concept sort
of in a loose sense because we actually
care in this case we're not just doing
it for big technical fun we actually do
need this to be true to make our letting
solution reasonable and what we mean by
this is so the way our current scheme is
working is let's say we have a light
source here that's shining down on the
scene we've got a reflector and another
reflector right ok so what we do on our
iterations is we shoot light and we add
the light to this thing which now can
collect some light and it then becomes a
light itself which can then shoot light
as well and this ven becomes a light
itself which can shoot light at no time
do we diminish that amount of light so
basically the more iterations we run
iteration one right added some light to
the system iteration two added more
light to the system so it's not moving
light around so much as it's actually
adding light to the scene literally
adding it so the amount of light you
have in iteration one is less than the
amount of light you have in the
iteration 2 is less than the amount of
light you have an iteration 3 and so on
and so on so what I want to do here is I
want to have a way where we can conserve
the amount of energy that's in the scene
so when you put a certain amount of
light energy in you get a certain amount
of light energy out no matter how many
iterations you happen to run now the
light may spread out differently
depending on how many iterations you run
and in fact it better otherwise those
iterations aren't doing anything but we
need some way of making the total light
energy to make sure that the total
amount of light energy is not increasing
right
so one way we could do this is split in
half the amount that we send out versus
the amount that we keep on any giving
light iteration for example right so
let's say for example we take a
particular light source
you say okay that light source is going
to emit 50% of its light and it's gonna
keep 50% of its light right in that case
we know that no matter what happens we
will never add more light to the scene
than we had originally this would be a
very simple way for us to conserve the
energy that we have so I'm gonna try
something like that first to see if we
can even out the amount of energy so
that will stay uniform throughout the
process so let's see how we would do
that here we are so I'm gonna take a
drink as my throat let's try it out
all right so what I'm gonna do here is
just going to go into the light
propagation system and I'm gonna take a
look at how we're actually doing this
distribution okay so what you can see is
we're looking for surfaces to send light
from and anything that's got some a
mission to send we're gonna use so what
we do here is we say okay we're gonna
take a sample direction we're gonna
raycast out and if we hit something then
what we're gonna do is we're gonna
accumulate some light into that thing
right and the amount that we're gonna
send is this emit see right here and
this power right how is that power
getting interpolated right here so it's
basically just yeah it's just whatever
the light color we sent down was the
power is is implicit in that so we could
actually like we could if we wanted to
we could have rolled these into one but
it doesn't matter
so we have the emit see right and we
know how much power we're going to use
here the amount of power that we're
going to use here is 1 over the rate
count so if every ray hit that's how
much power we would we would dissipate
the total amount of light from the light
source right but we don't necessarily
want to do that anymore what I'd rather
do is say okay what we're gonna do
instead is we're going to emit only 50%
of the light source this is power let's
say and we'll keep 50% now you can see
how that would play out down here like
right right now we're doing a source
emit see point index plus Destin so
they're just purely summing up how much
light I got this frame versus how much I
had you know and so on what I'd rather
do here is say okay what we want to do
is modify the source emit see probably
by how much ever much light it sent out
and the Destin at sea will get added to
it afterwards right so what we could do
is say okay when we update this value
what we're gonna do is say we've got an
amount
that's coming in so it's like light
absorption right or light retention so
what we want to do is say there's a
certain amount of light retention maybe
it's half like I said maybe it's not but
we'll see so then in here what we're
gonna say is we're only going to
dissipate 1 minus the total the the
light retention factor that we're gonna
keep in this light itself we will only
send out that much light and some light
gets lost right because if a ray doesn't
hit that light would get lost
what that means is we may have to adjust
to only get rid of light that actually
didn't get to that that if it actually
got sent somewhere right because now you
can see we have the opposite problem
which is the light gets dimmer and
dimmer as we go and the reason for that
of course is that it's sending light out
of the scene right so that's actually
good it means we're doing the right
thing here it's just we need a way of
making sure that we keep distributing
the light we have if we can't have you
know how should I say this we yeah we
need that light to basically be retained
if it doesn't have a hit now the problem
with doing that is we don't have a way
of saying oh we need to we need to keep
more of it because we're not writing to
source in it up here but that's ok
because remember the Destin Mitzi is
getting accumulated for this point so
what we can do is we could say all right
let's remember how much power we have
left right
and let's just add that in so what we
could do is we can even get rid of this
plus equals entirely right we could say
get rid of that it's just equals the
desk and what we could say is let's try
to remember how much power we didn't
distribute okay so what we could say is
alright we've got a light retention
value we know that our retained power is
going to be the light retention amount
by default and then every time we miss
array we will add that power back in so
when we come through here and we say
like okay this actually needs to be in
here
so we're deciding that we're gonna take
one of these guys we're gonna update
their emission right so we have two
options two paths we can go down one and
you actually you know what I could do
here I could do this a little bit saucy
ER right I could say also the retained
power I could also make this be
something that gets subtracted from
every time we hit so we could see the
retained power is the full power of the
light source right it keeps all of it by
default and so then when we're done here
what we would do is say okay the
destination the Destiny see right so the
decimate see of this emitter is going to
be equal to its emit C times its
retained power so by default it will
retain everything and just keep a 1
point out so then what we'll do is we'll
say every time we hit right every time
we do an accumulate sample we know we're
passing down this power value so let's
just subtract that out of its retained
power right like so so now every time
array hits we retract that amount of
power out so by the maximum amount we
can possibly send out is the light
retention amount but if we don't send
out that much will still retain that
light on our surface right so we'll
either
send the lights somewhere or we won't
but it shouldn't get dimmer now
hopefully although it does seem to get a
little dimmer we'll have to find out
what's going on there it could just be
that the the light ends up collecting in
particular places now there's something
something going on there you can see we
lose a little bit so we're off by
something in the equation somewhere
there's a little bit of cruft in there
right but we're getting there right so
now we can kind of see that we've got
some some more conservation of energy
definitely that's not quite right yet
still gets dimmer then then we would
like right we also don't know that we
want our retention factor to be this
high like we might want to retain less
of the light right it may be do we want
to send out 75% but of course I think
like I said we've still got bugs in here
so it's hard to gauge correctly at this
point right there you can kind of see
that light getting lost in there right
all right so let's figure out how we're
getting a leakage here look what's
happening there okay
so we're stepping through here and we're
saying that the amount of power that
we're going to send out is going to be 1
- light retention divided by the rate
count right whatever that that rate
count is because that's how many we're
sending out here right per per iteration
or whatever right um
I guess one thing I don't know is as the
rate count drops down what's the minimum
the Ray Kappe it may be the rate count
how does the rate count get modified
if rape count is less it's greater than
eight let's say because it keeps
dropping down with each one and that may
be part of it too alright so there we go
now we know we're always sending out
some rays right all right so we're
losing energy why are we losing energy
it could just be floating-point nonsense
but you know it's probably something
real so I guess one problem is the power
that we add always gets attenuated by
the angular angular fall-off so that is
probably where we're losing our power
right
so in accumulate sample for example and
actually the problem the kumite sample
is that never really worked out to be a
very good out of line function because
it kind of always needs to be in line
which is not great for us but you can
see here that the actual power that we
add is affected by the angular fall-off
so what we might want to do is say well
okay the angular fall-off there is going
to have to be taken into account so
maybe we say something more like this
and we say we don't dissipate that power
we only dissipate power we actually used
right and it's better but it's still not
right we're still losing too much power
there right I don't think that's an
accidental function I think that that
looks to me like we're we're still
having issues right
but that's definitely one source of it
so here is we now know exactly how much
light we're actually adding here and so
we should end up with keeping as much
retained power as we as was actually
kept right we've given away this much we
keep this much retained uhm so yeah what
else happens here anything else so I
don't see so I don't really see a
problem here immediately so I'm not sure
where I'm losing the rest of my power
here so I'm coming through this each
iteration and I've got my power
retention here I'm basically saying that
the power that I'm going to distribute
per Rey is however much light retention
I want it divided by the Ray count right
and I'm saying I'm gonna retain 1.0 of
my power by default so if we never
actually admitted everything the power
should remain the same because it would
always just be omit C times retained
power and power retained powers one so
emit seed estimate C is just going to be
the source of it see oh there it is
reflection color that is the problem
right there
so we don't want to do this how to mark
product right we want to do this
okay oh so close we get out many
iterations before losing power now but
it still looks like that that's probably
not just a numerical precision that
still looks like we've got something
janky happening in there to me I could
be wrong but that looks like that to me
I mean it does take a really long time
before you use it up but I'm gonna keep
huntin anyway just to make sure so yes
so this way we're taking the original
source and we're just saying they
retained power times that should should
be enough to keep us from losing light
because we're adding that power to other
light sources as we go it could be that
we're just at the point where it's you
know it's numerical precision makes it
so that there's not much we can do to
get it something that doesn't lose a
little bit right
and so that light absorption so now you
know what so here's the other thing so
since we are bouncing the light we're
bouncing is gonna be modified by the
reflection color
we're actually bouncing less light than
we originally had so we kind of need to
retain that light in us would be the way
we'd have to do it that's kind of a
tricky thing do you see what I'm saying
so we're gonna send out light that's
been pretty much it's been multiplied by
our reflection color right that's the
light color we're gonna send out and so
that means that by default we've
absorbed some of that light and every
time we send it out we're gonna absorb
it because we're counting that power
against us so we're limiting some of
that power from us that we can't send
out again so what's the best way to
handle that I mean one way to look at it
is to do it more accurately where we're
just actually absorbing that color of
light and so what we're sending out is
the other colors how would this work
the other way is to just normalize the
amount of power and say well whatever
the power actually is that we're sending
out is that much less than what we had
so I can't say I really know the right
way to capture that piece of information
hopefully everyone understands what I'm
talking about namely that the Hadamard
product here is taking whatever the
source emit color is that we have which
is our light that we received we're
modifying it by our reflection color
which degrades its energy right and so
I'm just not entirely certain how to
record that degradation should I just
try to measure that degradation and when
I subtract the power from it modify it
so for example like make a retention
coefficient here the retention
coefficient is going to be equal to
something like the length of the
emission reflection amount and so you
know whatever that length is whatever
the sort of amount of power that is
going to be lost by this we modify the
retained power by that right so when we
when we subtract away that light power
we've got baked into it the concept that
it's the light itself is not uniform I
don't know that that as written is
definitely not going to work but I'm
just wondering if something similar to
that can work because this would have
values that are over 1 and stuff so I
don't that's just going to be a
nightmare I think probably but I'm not
sure
yeah that still gets down to zero
eventually looks like anyway yeah so so
I definitely need a different way of
counting photons right and I may need to
count them on the red green and blue
channel separately the problem is I
don't want the color to shift because
surfaces are supposed to be the color
that they are but I guess in some sense
that's okay because the it's that's
actually correct I mean what a red
surface does is it absorbs green and
blue photons so the green and blue
photons that hit it aren't going to
bounce back out again right but they are
going to stay there so I think I just
need my my retained power to be wide
right I think I just need my retained
power to look like this right
I think so basically when we come
through here and we say source emits e
times retained power I think maybe what
I need to do is just say like maybe just
call this retain color really and say
that we just take the color that we had
that the the the light we had coming in
the literal value of it right and when
we do this retained power here what we
say is like okay actually what's gonna
happen is we're gonna subtract retain a
color and the retained color value is
going to be you know whatever we
actually added right so the result here
is the power times the light color like
so we add that to our desk and we return
it to subtract it away from what we had
right
does that help let's find out again we
get really far down before we start to
really lose power but we still are
losing a little bit of power so maybe
we're close I think it's probably it's
time we're supposed to be doing QA here
I think in three minutes right we're not
in QA are we are we in QA so that's a
lot closer right so this way we start
with what we had right we're then gonna
try to omit some of it this is what
we're gonna try to omit any time we send
light to someone else we subtract that
light from us and we no longer retain
that you know
that seems like it would work pretty
well it doesn't seem like that has a lot
of holes in it I don't think
so I think that may be more what we're
going for here so let's take a look at
our lighting samples right so if I start
out there's our first bounce direct
lighting there's our second bounce with
some indirect third bounce fourth bounds
fifth bounce that looks really nice and
even so I'm gonna go ahead and call that
victory for now because it really looks
pretty good to me I would say
now the problem with it of course is
that you can see the yellow you can see
the light shift because as these
surfaces can only send out those values
their colors will shift towards the
complementary color of the color they
send out right and that's not really
what we actually want to record for
purposes of like things that are in this
area that don't happen to be that color
right we want to use the light color
that was incident on the light so we
almost really need like two like two
values there right so I don't know again
that this keeps the this keeps the power
quite well but it's just not not quite
there so I think we kind of need to
sleep on this we're pretty close though
I'll go ahead and go to the QA
and you know main goal at this point is
just gonna be to start reducing the
flicker I think and then we're getting
pretty pretty good
sudonym 73 Cimmerian am i right in
thinking that you're taking into account
the geometric cosine theta factor on the
receiving surface but not on the
emitting surface yes you are correct in
that thinking
draaga in a tree like blacksmithing you
use your tools to make better tools over
time do you think programming should be
like this where you build tools that you
reuse every project or should you
rebuild most of your code every project
I so I think it's not feasible to
I just don't think you can these days
right
I think rebuilding code rebuilding the
entire code base every project would be
great in a world where you just had a
team your team had 30 amazing
programmers on it and you just had tons
of coding power and you're just kept
refining things and you know the person
who wrote the entity system for last
game writes a new one this game and a
new and the next game a new in the next
game it just keeps getting better and
better that would be a great world right
everything would just be great but
that's not reality right that's not what
you typically have usually you don't
have the ability to usually you just
don't have the ability to rewrite
everything there's too much code in too
little time too few coding resources so
I just don't think it's practical I
think you have to you know first time
out if you're doing a whole new codebase
and yet you got to write what you can
write but I think the next time out you
want to only choose a few things to
rewrite the things that most need
improvement and try to keep the other
things if you have to make modifications
to them make them but don't rewrite them
because you don't want to be your time
as a finite resource and you need to
focus it on where you can make the
biggest differences so rewriting
everything from scratch every time
probably just isn't the best
choice there it's probably better to
focus your resources on doing a really
good job on a few things
and not spreading it out over all the
things so at least for me I try to limit
the number of times I have to rewrite
everything because that's just a way too
much programming especially for a single
programmer to do now if you have a
bigger team and lots of really good
programmers at your disposal that
equation may change but that is just not
very likely plus there are other
ancillary concerns there such as it
sometimes is very hard to redo
everything at once because you don't
have any sticking point right when
you're going to do a new revenging
sometimes it helps to keep the core of
the old engine to have things that know
how things will interact right um so
it's not always possible to rewrite
everything anyway in that sense you may
it may be better the other way around I
I don't know it's hard to say suitum
seriously that may explain why it wasn't
energy preserving is that actually
correct though I thought that on the
emission side you're not usually taking
into account the angle Plus if anything
that would lose us energy wouldn't it
more 85 could you explain the purpose of
multiple pointer levels like void star
star star star star whatever is it just
array of array of array of array I can't
think of a viable example can you give
one of pointers to pointers how many can
you be specific about how many levels
deep you want an example like is void
star star also confusing to you or is
only void star star star star star
confusing to you like is it only when it
gets to five that you're not sure what
the example would be empty s MOX is the
direction of the light correctly
calculated if you only take positive Z
into account magazine is also correct
nor oh that's a very good point that is
a very good point my friend know we
thank you for catching that we do need a
sign here because this
there we go so this right here is
technically positive or negative you're
right so when we reconstruct this we
actually need to do that properly right
and fortunately for us we have a lot of
extra information here at our disposal
which it just happens to be handy but
for example light color what we can do
is pack that into say the r-value right
so what we could do here is say if light
c dot r is less than zero light c dot r
equals negative light c dot R and light
B dot Z equals negative light T dot Z
right so what we can do is encode the
sign of Z which we don't know
unfortunately at this point right we can
encode that into the R value and and
have our cake and eat it too if you will
so inside render group here let's go to
platform so in this light data we will
do like sine DZ times C R right so when
we pack that down what we can then do is
say all right that color value when we
pack it in here what we can do is say
that that's not the function this is the
function here what we can do is say all
right the sine of DZ we'll multiply that
by that they know why we're still doing
that back out isn't for it we will take
that sign and we'll put it in there
right all right so that's we don't have
a sine function so we'll just do if d
let's see is less than zero you got C
times equal are negative du Z see that R
equals negative two that are right so we
just flip the sign of the red channel
and off we go so that that was just a
straight-up bug with the light direction
so thanks very much for that catch
that's like totally just me not thinking
it through
in the case of the red wall only being
lit by the third or fourth bounce
shouldn't the red well not reflect any
red light because the blue wall is
mostly only reflecting blue light well
sort of but not necessarily the reason
is because there's more than just that
that's affecting the red wall so like
all of these surfaces can distribute
light to the red wall right so like for
example here all of these can light this
wall so you don't actually need the blue
wall to bounce does that make sense
if it was only the blue wall then yes
the red wall would never get lit at all
if it wasn't indirect light but it has
these Gray's here
Oh student observant searcing yeah but
think back the original problem was that
the solution was blowing up well yeah
the problem is the original solution I
just constantly a community to light
though so it would blow up no matter
what the light transfer was here I'm Sam
because all it did was add light it
never had a way of removing light from
the system at all so you would always
keep the light you had and add any light
that came in so that's gonna blow up no
matter what right
and we didn't try to do a version that
only sent out exactly the same amount of
light because we don't have a way to do
that since it's not a closed environment
we have to check to see whether we hit
and only subtract that light away
because we don't know how much will
otherwise all of it just goes out from
the atmosphere right at the moment more
85 avoid star starters clear everything
above is bogus so star star star so
triple you'd say was bogus so you're
basically saying void star star star
this is this is the bogus part so
basically you're asking if the address
of the address of the address of a
pointer right I guess or sorry the
address of the address of a pointer and
the answer of course is like you know
maybe so maybe not it depends you could
end up in this situation so what we're
talking about here is we have a location
that's got a pointer in it right so
here's our void star whatever it is so
this is the data that we're actually
talking about here right and so in this
case we may say well all right let's
suppose we had a system where we
modifying ones of these so let's say
there's just an array of pointers going
down right we're trying to modify well
all right let's say we had a pointer
here that points to the one that we're
modifying right now so maybe we're in a
for loop or something right and now
let's say we have a function that we do
with this pointer that advances it and
maybe it advances it it doesn't just go
linearly advanced by something so we
have in advance and it needs to take a
void star star star the pointer right
and it's like you know star a plus plus
to like move this thing down or
something right so it's advanced this is
void star star a or something we say
advance address of a right so you could
imagine a case where three trip stars is
not that bizarre right
sudonym sandy just a suggestion the
ultimate solution might be to use
temporal coherence do one bounce for
frame and use the previous frame
solution for the indirect lighting term
yes that is almost certainly something
we will do the problem that we will have
and we are gonna have to figure out a
good way to solve it it's gonna be nasty
is figuring out frame to frame what
lighting samples correspond and the
reason for that is just because the
environment we could match up probably
by rote but the sprites we can't so I
don't know
we definitely need temporal smoothing
anyway but I'm not sure how we're gonna
do it exactly
Dirk and Dario two weeks ago I asked
about sound input I just want to specify
that I was thinking about the data
structure to store the sound input so
like you have it set up with the
platform layer handling the sound input
and passing it to the game
uh well I think all you really have to
do is the game just provides a buffer or
the platform layer provides a buffer
that's like here's the sound I recorded
last rain right that that should be it
I think all right I'm gonna shut it down
all right thank you very much everyone
for joining me for the upside of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along the series you can
always peer to the game on handmade hero
org and it comes with the full source
code so you can follow along home let's
have a forum site you can go to if you
want to ask questions we have a
contribution page if you want to donate
to projects that support handmade hero
like the episode guide which is right
here or the handmade Network which does
the forums there's also a schedule bot
which tells you I'm gonna be live and a
if you refresh this page a little
countdown timer which tells you we're
gonna be live as well that's it for
today I'll be back tomorrow when we can
try to do a little bit more work with
our lighting solution and start to sort
of narrow in on a good final like
approach we're going to use that we can
start to think about how we're going to
accelerate and to the pseudonym 73's
point at the end of the stream how we
might break that out into something that
is more coherent over time and isn't
doesn't require within a single frame us
to cast the number of race it would take
to make it clean so we'll be doing that
tomorrow hope to see you back here for
that until then have fun programming and
I'll see everyone on the Internet
take it easy everybody