alright hello everyone and welcome to an
episode actually of handmade ray we are
trying to test using 1080p60 today I'll
blog it's really 1080p30 today but it's
the 1080p part we had had trouble with
1080 before it was only capturing in
1080i and we'd been whining for it with
those was going out that I went over the
settings and stuff and went around with
black magic on this a few times it turns
out the card was bad I've switched to a
different one of the same card just a
different card and now we have 1080p 60
capture which means 1080p I'm sorry
1080p 30 streaming should be working
because it should be capturing in 1080p
and then just streaming every other
frame so hopefully that's okay we're
testing it today I'm not doing an actual
episode of handmade error because I
don't want to risk losing one with an
untrusted sort of streaming setup so
here we go we're just gonna be doing
some random handmade ray programming as
you know handmade ray is our little ray
tracer I've built one time it's what we
use when we're testing people had
requested a long time ago that I build a
ray tracer and so I did and you know
we've got it to the point where it's
actually relatively functional it just
doesn't have a couple of things that we
would probably want to do if you were
really playing around the Ray tracer and
so we can add another one of those today
so here it is it's it's handmade right
here I'm going to open up for coder and
I'm going to go ahead and load the
project file for that and build it and
you can see that if we take a look at
the build up bat we were actually
building this in optimized mode and that
makes sense right because in optimized
mode we get a lot better performance and
this is a performance oriented thing so
it makes sense that we want to mostly
compile in OH - when we're actually
running it because otherwise we'd be
sitting around waiting a lot longer for
it to produce images now in the build up
bat it automatically runs the ray tracer
as well we may want to change that while
we're doing some active development cuz
we may want to
in the debugger or who knows what else
but at the moment I'll let that go ahead
and do it so what happens here is when
we run it it's programmed to dump the
output
I believe into the data directory and
you can see we've got sort of our images
here and it's right now set up just to
produce this one image it's not
particularly interesting image at some
point we should probably try to make an
image it's better and maybe we'll do
that a little later today but basically
here is a you know it's a pretty finely
detailed image as you can kind of see if
I go ahead and zoom in on this a little
bit here I don't know if I where's the
zoom view actual size there we go
you can see that it's pretty smooth now
too with that many samples we get pretty
smooth output and so on but you know it
still takes a fairly long amount of time
to do a really smooth rendering with it
even though we're multi-threaded now and
I believe we actually print out here you
can see we print out how long it takes
to actually do something that image
takes about 46 seconds at a really
really high sampling rate now you can do
much quicker by just lowering the
sampling rate quite a bit but I actually
want to leave that sampling rate pretty
high because what I'd like to do today
is maybe work on a little bit more
performance optimization just do we have
a pretty solid understanding of how
we're doing our performance and just
generally what's going on with it right
okay so if we switch back to the code
you can kind of see here how it works
that's pretty straightforward
really all we do is we create a bunch of
tiles that are sort of tiling the image
and we put them into basically a you
know a queue and then we have a worker
threads that come through and take those
tiles out of the queue and they run this
function that's all they do right they
just take this function they go through
look they say I'm gonna take a work
order out of the queue this work road is
just a tile it says where I should
render I loop through and I do however
many rays per pixel I've been told to do
by the configuration settings which it
like it says a Puritan and 1024 Ray's
for pixel and you can see here the 64 by
64 tiles obviously we sort of played
around with that see
which tile setting would be the best I
think that was roughly where the
breaking point was and so you know
that's all this really does and if you
take a look here at what we're doing I'm
gonna move it to the other screen so
that's not where my my head is there if
you take a look at what's going on here
we're just sort of looping over all of
the pixels and for every pixel we're
doing a bunch of ray tests here where we
just take the Ray index and we you know
loop over the race for pixel pick a
location in the pixel to cast array from
cast array out see what we hit and if we
hit anything that's an actual surface we
just keep bouncing around right and
that's really all we do that's it we
don't have anything else and right now
we only really have two primitive types
as well you could see us looping over
them here there's the planes there's the
spheres and that's that's it that's all
we're doing so there's kind of two areas
of optimization we can look into here
one of them I think we don't really have
any real reason to go into yet and that
is the bounding volume hierarchy a
bounding volume Harkey is something that
allows us to not test every primitive
every time you can see here we're
testing every plane in every sphere
every time we do array and that's
actually absolutely fine if the number
of primitives is very low because
anything we introduced that would be a
bounding volume hierarchy here if the
number of primitives is very low we're
actually just gonna slow the radars are
down because it has to do work to
traverse the bounding hierarchy and the
only time that becomes work worth doing
is when we have you know hundred
elements or something two thousand
elements ten thousand elements starting
to push that element count up high
enough that the work done to partition
them into a bounding volume Harkey and
Traverse that bounding high volume
hierarchy that that actually becomes a
payoff by eliminating a large number of
primitives from consideration in our
case the amount of time it takes to
consider these primitives is probably so
low that anything we were going to do
with the bounding volume hierarchy is
going to be more work as you can see
here we've only got like five spheres
and one plane right and so when we want
to start creating a more complex scene
of some kind that's the time to start
looking at an optimization for a
bounding volume hierarchy right now we
don't have that and so we really don't
want to be looking at that so what we're
gonna do today is look a little bit more
at perhaps using some better math
operations here and what I'd like to do
first is just take a look at the
assembly code that's actually being
executed to get a feel for exactly how
bad it is even before looking at wide
operations so I'm gonna go ahead and
open up the debugger and I'm gonna load
hand-made right into the bugger so I can
see what that disassembly looks like now
we're opening Visual Studio which itself
takes about as long to open as it does
for our thing to cast like 8 billion
rays that's just you know Microsoft
quality engineering at work I'm gonna go
ahead and open up that that right here
and this is the this is the Wray program
itself what I'm gonna do is I'm going to
step into that render tile function and
I'm going to just take a look roughly at
what the loop this loop here which is
our most expensive loop right it's
getting executed 1,024 times tremendous
number of times every pixel right so
this is this is the real hotspot here
it's doing just most of the work and so
this is the part of the program where we
really need to find out what's going on
and how to make it faster and so again
before I start anything else out I just
want to get some sense of what's going
on right so we can see a number of
things right off the bat that I really
don't like like all I've done is even
just flip the disassembly and already
we're in trouble you can see here that
when we are trying to produce our random
sort of location inside the pixel to
cast array from rather than in lining
something convenient for generating a
random number we are actually doing a
literal call out to Rand and I really
don't like a literal call out to ran
because as you can see well I guess you
can't see because apparently the C
runtime library source code isn't
installed on this machine but I don't
really care because I don't need it
there we go so anyway as you can see
here the source code to this actually
involves a lot of business I jumped into
the call here we're now calling to some
kind of a CRT internal function I don't
care about this to receive porifera data
this is the per thread data because I
assume it wants the s Rand ran sequence
to be maintained differently for every
thread right so here we go we're calling
into all this stuff look I mean look at
how many look at how many calls we are
deep we haven't even done any work to
generate a random number yet look and
look at where I am right I mean look at
this is the disaster we can't be having
this kind of thing happen in our inner
loop it's absolutely unconscionable and
completely unacceptable so you know why
this is people always ask me why I don't
like using the C runtime library this is
why most of the functions don't do what
I need them to do right not a knock on
the people who imprint to the library
maybe that that was how it had to be
implanted for the spec or who knows what
but for our purposes that's already
totally unacceptable so let me go ahead
and let's start a little to-do list here
so I know exactly what's going on that
we found that we have to replace
so we definitely want to do that we
definitely want to switch to a custom
brand there's no question about that
let's go through and and take a look at
what happens after that I'm gonna go
ahead and do a go to disassembly here so
so that's unacceptable and we need to
make sure that doesn't happen let's see
what other sorts of things we're doing
here a lot of these are single they're
there Cindy instructions the SSE
instructions but they're not actually
using the full width right this is still
doing single scalar at a time which is
fine that's what we expect it to be
doing these all look like reasonable
instructions for what it's supposed to
be doing I don't have a problem with any
of that we do of course have a few
issues like I was saying before where we
want to we want to do wide on these
probably eventually but that's sort of a
separate thing that what I'm looking at
right now I just want to look at any
stupidity that's going on first all
right so you can see here we've got just
our sort of our basic bounce code
looking here use the test and make sure
we exit the loop everything looks you
know at a first glance fine there you
can just really straightforward stuff
happening here nothing weird accessing
these these primitives and doing tests
against them all of this looks pretty
good
nothing nothing too problematic I'm
still happy with basically everything
that I'm seeing here and these are these
are the plane intersections we don't
have many of these anyway we have very
few planes in the world at the moment
yes so I don't know if some of this
stuff could be done better I'd have to
go ahead and look at it in more detail
but I don't see like I'm just looking
for obvious real bad situations and I'm
not seeing anything too problematic here
mm-hmm
it seems to have I think it may have
unrolled this loop a few times I'm not
sure it looks like it did you can see
we're seeing the same thing multiple
times Syria like for example right like
here is some of the plane equation stuff
and here it is again I don't know if it
just reordered it I'm not sure exactly
what it did there I'm trying to find the
sphere of stuff here's the serious stuff
here again looks pretty good let's see
it in lined the square root which is
great that's really good because we
don't want it to I don't know what that
did
what is that button I don't know what a
lot of these new visual studio features
are okay I've never seen this button
before I don't know what it does anyway
so that all looks pretty good so really
I mean besides the fact that we want to
do this wide I'm really just not seeing
too much stupid here so the compiler I
feel like did a pretty good job of a
first pass attempt at making this stuff
work and it looks like really our
biggest culprit in terms of stupid
things we want to really get rid of are
just these r and calls here and that's
fine because we can totally do that
mm-hmm that is not a huge problem now
here we've got our power call that's
gonna do again that's an unnecessary
call we would rather have it do just the
inline sort of expansion serious mansion
to compute power but you know it's
actually okay because that's really at
the very end right that's the end of the
loop there and that's gonna get called
almost never so if we take a look back
for example at where that POW F is being
called there it's in this extract linear
- srgb
and and that sort of stuff let me go
ahead and here you can see here real
srgb color or whatever and then we have
a typo this right here
extract literature linear - srgb
this is
only happening when we finally go to
write out a pixel to the to the BMP so
although that isn't a necessary call and
if that were in the fast path like in
the in the I should say the hot path we
would want to get rid of it I don't
think we have to in this case because
it's you know it's doing ten on ten
thousand twenty four of these loops
before it ever has to execute one of
these this is probably just never gonna
amount to any appreciable difference in
speed for us so it looks like our first
big culprit is ran so before we do
anything else I'm gonna go ahead and
replace rant with something more sane
than Rand now that's a little bit tricky
because you have to know some number
three to do it and I don't but the good
news is there's a lot of people who've
written on this and we can find them now
I we do have sort of a little bit of AI
dilemma here and I'll show you what it
is so I rather like this random number
generator it's made by a person named
Melissa O'Neil I believe yeah she is a
professor at Harvey Mudd University who
I don't think even works on random
numbers or anything like that as part of
her research topic but I think she like
many people who like things to be done
well I kind of got the sense from
reading the paper like I don't really
remember the specifics of the whole
paper but I kind of got the sense when I
was reading it that maybe she needed to
use random numbers for something she was
doing and was kind of unhappy with the
state of how things were and look
decided to look into it and ended up
finding some really good stuff now if we
take a look at this paper as soon as I
find it here there it is paper if we
take a look at this paper it's a really
easy paper to read and I highly
recommend everyone read it it's written
very well it's not one of these math
papers that you have to have a degree in
mathematics to read anyway
it's actually written in plain English
and designed for people who don't
necessarily already know what she's
talking about too
eventually understand it which is great
there may be some sections where she's
talking about things that are harder for
you to understand because you're not in
the field or whatever but you know most
of the parts that you care about in here
it's a long paper it's very well
explained are actually really easy to
read and and I it's a it's a great first
paper on random numbers anyway you could
you could just start here and and be
pretty happy with it so I highly
recommend reading this now the thing
that I was gonna say is these are the
kinds of random number generators that I
like the most currently because they're
awesome for basically everything except
for one thing which is that in SSE
instructions are not the best
instruction set to implement them so if
we were just doing single if we weren't
planning on doing SSE optimization I
would say we would absolutely want to
use these they I can't think of any
reason why you wouldn't immediately use
these because we are using Cindy I've
never really so far I haven't looked
into what the better way to go is like
whether you can adapt these at all in a
good way to sim be that it still has
what needs to happen in them I don't
know but let me go ahead and scroll to
the part that I'm most caring about here
so I can show you yeah okay um so here
is the the problem if you take a look at
how these often work this tends to be
the this tends to be the sort of
structure that these take and the idea
here behind these random number
generators that I you know like I said I
highly recommend reading the paper
because I'm handmade ray we don't go
into detail a lot on all of the topics
like we do on handmade Hira but
basically what she found what she was
looking at these things was that linear
congruential generators which is just a
very fancy word for adding you know
multiplying adding and modding things
you can see let me see here I can show
you
sorry not money adding and multiplying
usually modding as well but here
so it's basically something that just
looks like this it's like you're gonna
generate a new number by multiplying the
old number by something adding something
and then modding by something else right
that is generally what these look like
they're called linear congruential
generators and they typically are what's
used in a very simple and quick random
number generator because as you can see
they're very straightforward this part
the mod part if you're trying to be
extremely fast is often replaced by
something that's not even a modulus
maybe you just do a modulus by a power
of two so you can use an and instruction
for example and then you're just talking
about a multiply and add in an and and
that's a very fast way to generate a
random number problem is they generate
really poor random numbers that's why
people don't usually use them and what
you can see here in the paper actually
well I guess that actually had diagram
right there I don't like that what you
can see probably is that if you look
here we go if you look at what these
things generate in various ways that you
could graph them you can see that you
end up with things that aren't really
all that random they have very clear
defining features in them that you can
perceive and that's a problem especially
you know in game development where
you're trying to create visually random
looking things you can see here you end
up getting stuff that can have really
bad side effects right you know all of
these sort of things like like here's a
example right this is like as good as
maybe you're gonna get with a linear
congruential generator or something and
it still has these really obvious
patterns in it right and that I think is
just a an artifact of the modulus way
that they work they're always going to
have at some visible sort of stride
they're gonna have a sort of a coherent
pattern that emerges and what you're
looking for is something more like this
if you're trying to get a white noise
generator which is what a random number
generator is generally supposed to do
you're supposed to be looking at
something that looks like that not
something that looks like this this is
not what you're looking for right well
anyway what most O'Neill did here was
she was working on
figuring out a way to quickly generate
random numbers that would have
comparable speeds to something like a
linear congruential generator but it
wouldn't have sort of the obvious
drawbacks right that wouldn't look like
so bad there and what she came up with
was the fact that if you were to look at
how the bits were distributed it turns
out that you can mix the the bits of a
linear congruential generator if you
shift them around you can mix them
together in a way that produces
something that actually is much much
more random right and I don't know where
the final graphs are I'd have to look
more carefully at the thing but she ends
up getting stuff that that passes
essentially all of the kinds of
randomness tests that you might throw at
it
she ends up getting that out of a very
very simple thing which is essentially
that equation I showed you before where
it just does a shift and uses basically
bits from the linear congruential e
generated value to you know sorry I
don't know my way around the paper that
much okay here we go yeah back where I
was so this right here is the linear
congruential generation part you can see
state equal state times multiplier +
increment and then here is the part that
she's sort of found is the important
part which is that you need to shift the
state by a value that is itself coming
from the state right so anyway the
problem that we have here is that the
the shift that you're doing here while a
shift like this one is fine because this
shift is by a constant value the shift
here is by a variable right and so what
that means is in order to shift this
value to get the proper output value
you're trying to achieve what you'd need
to do first is you would need to find
out what value was in state already get
that into something in the processor
that allows you to do your share
and shift by it that's fine in x64
normal general-purpose registers they do
have a shift by a register amount
however I at least I believe they do I
don't know I think about it I almost
never use anything like that but Cindy
doesn't is the problem there is no shift
by something other than an immediate in
the sses that we normally use so if we
go to the Intel intrinsics guide for
example and we look at for example we
normally target SSE 2 or SSD 3 but
really anything in the SSE family here I
believe like basically anything in here
if we take a look at a shift left
operation so if you take a look at at
the 128 wide folks here you can see that
all of the 128 wide ones here actually
what's this guy
those are 16s I might is totally wrong
about this I'm so sure you can't do this
she factories by count and count comes
from okay
no nevermind I was just double-checking
so yeah you can't do it right you you
can get a count out of this variable as
a single count but you can't get it out
of of each individual Lane right yeah so
I believe I still am right never mind
for a minute there I was like wait what
Wynwood what am i what am I seeing here
there's been many times when I've wanted
to do that and I couldn't do it but it's
not the case so it looks like right you
you can see here your the the value that
you're shifting can be four lane wide
thirty two-bit right
but unfortunately the shift itself only
comes from the bottom bits of this it
doesn't come from the lanes what you'd
want to see is AJ right or an eye
showing up in this count expression here
so that it would shift by a different
amount per Lane but of course it you
can't actually get that right so
effectively what this means is that you
have to downshift to scalar effectively
in order to do your shifts so you would
like to do four wide random number of
stuff but instead you can only do one
wide because the shift is you can't have
four different shift values in four
different lanes right I and I guess
that's because you know far be it for me
because I don't really know the hardware
design limitations here I assume that's
because the shifter for all these lanes
is taking the same bout so like you know
the register comes in and it can just
shift the whole register by that amount
and then it reads it up in two lanes or
something right so it doesn't have the
ability to shift each part individual
as far as its concerned that's four
different shifts and it can only shift
the whole register so I'm assuming that
there is no such circuitry for doing it
that way now at some point I feel like
they may have added I don't remember but
somewhere way up the chain here I feel
like they may have included a shift that
can actually do variable per Lane at
some point I don't really remember but
the point is nothing on the tart on the
platform's we target unfortunately has
that so that's the real issue that we
run into with these / muted congruential
generators is just that in this case
it's really hard to make a random number
function like this work because when we
go to implement it we have this problem
of just the instruction set not really
supporting the thing that we want to do
but for now let's start with it and then
we'll see what we can do as we go
forwards so let's take a look at one of
the ones she suggests here which is I
believe she recommends using X source
shift
let me see here here we go so you can
see some specific implementations here
right and you can see 32 bit output 64
bit state is probably what we would want
to use because we know we don't need
more than 32 bits of output we're using
floating point values floating point
values can't store more than 32 bits
worth of variability anyway in them
right there 24 bit mantissa only so if
you take a look at this a 32 bit output
with 64 bit state is probably mostly
what we want and what you can see here
is that she recommends basically saying
excuse me using X or shift every time
and then just applying this extra shift
is an existing random number generator
and then applying this every time in
order to get the correct mixing right
and again you can see here how bad this
is and the seamy side of things you can
see that you're trying to perform a
rotate which SSE doesn't do that's okay
can do a rotate in a couple instructions
right you just you just have two or two
bachelors things together so forum your
rotate here and the amount you're
rotating by again is comes from the
state itself so although here and here
your shifts are constant amounts so
those are shifts that are easy to
accomplish this shift is not because
this shift right here for the rotate
thirty-two is a shift that's entirely
coming from the value itself so that's
obviously a problem as well but anyway
if we take a look here at applying X or
shift we can see what that actually is
so if we look at the equation for x or
shift here we have it so here's what X
or if like X or shift is literally just
these operations you can see that
nothing in here would be problematic for
us all an X our shift is to do it's
random number update is it says whatever
the input was I'm gonna do exclusive ORS
with various shifts of the bits those
shifts are all constant so this entire
thing would be totally fine to use like
basically in Simbi right and it's just
the part that improves the value that
isn't so one thing that we could
consider doing for example is just not
using the PCG part of it and see how far
we can get with just an X or shift but
again like you know it's gonna have
artifacts in it and whether those
artifacts matter to us or not I don't
know but let's take let's take this as
our basis because that way we can maybe
then look to a PCG to improve it later
on when we need to and maybe we'll just
try to figure out what's going on there
and I haven't looked at this stuff in a
long time and so for all I know if we
went and looked there may have been some
people who've done some good work on how
to make a sim di is version of this
that's not too bad okay so if we take an
example here of X or shift right
the problem with X star shift actually
now they look at it is this is the
32-bit X or shift and I actually wanted
the 64-bit
sir shift it looks like from what she
was talking about before right I'm gonna
I'm gonna see if there's an X or shift
64 or somewhere here
yeah because I would like to know what
yeah I'm not sure
so I guess maybe it's really just not an
issue because I guess it looks like here
what she's suggesting and again you'll
forgive me for not having read read to
this paper you know in a long time
but it looks like I'll show you
suggesting here is actually just used
the the 32-bit XOR shift which maybe
there isn't a 64-bit extra shift on the
high bits and then you just keep going
right so maybe that's fine
so this one she says it's slightly we're
a statistical performance for slightly
greater speed which may be what we would
want anyway and you can see that this is
a sort of a different equation for the
output version Fred's random stuff
rather than a random rotation so that
would be actually good because then we
don't have to do the rotate implied
fixed shift so this version form slowest
work the difference between the two is
minor and she says this one's probably a
better choice to restate the 32-bit up a
function okay yeah so in either case as
far as I can tell yeah it's a little
ambiguous here just in terms of what the
32-bit it's not explicitly stated at
least right here that X or shift is
being used exactly what it's being used
on right but it seems like that's the
case with 64 bits of state and the state
update would be from the X or shift the
only weird thing like I said is if you
take a look at how this is working I'm
just not sure how the state relates
exactly to this because it looks like
yeah I mean it does kind of look like
she's actually saying you just keep the
32 the high 32 bits I don't know that
looks like what she's saying so anyway
it looks like we're just talking about
this and I should write this down
so in this case if we were going to
update the state specifically it would
look something like this right
and we might want to make this official
by saying something like you know random
series but as you can see essentially
all this exertion does exactly as its
name implies all the extra shift does is
take some random value that you started
with so however you want to seat it you
can speed it with anything I and then
all it does is it sort of shifts the
bits around and X or x' them with with
itself right so just a bunch of X or s
with itself and this apparently again if
you take a look at at the papers for X
or shift there this apparently passes
some statistical tests and not others
right so it's not a particularly great
one but it's extremely fast I mean if
you look at what's happening here it's
it's pretty straightforward right it's
just three X ORS with three shifted
values that's incredibly fast to perform
and what you can sort of see here as
well is that these are constant shifts
so if we wanted to do this operation
wide and Cyndy we would have no trouble
doing so right so that would be pretty
easy as well now the only part that we
again would have trouble with is now if
we wanted to apply the mixing step here
where this where this part would be
applied to the upper parts of the value
then
you know we've got sort of the variable
shift do not contend with but at the
moment here I'm gonna content myself
with just trying this random series by
itself so we know let's let's run real
quick this over here so we can have a a
baseline I'm gonna go ahead and run the
build right
oops so this is gonna go ahead and and
do its little it's a little baked here
so that we can have a timing that we
sort of have on the books for how fast
we were running before we change out the
random number generator and again this
should be using you know a substantial
amount of the computing resources to the
computer we should check the performance
monitor as well at some point to make
sure that we're actually pegging all of
our CPUs we should be but you know just
in case we mess something up and
actually aren't but anyway this will
give us a timing that we can then use as
a benchmark against replacing the random
number generator to see just how much of
a difference it makes having replaced it
maybe it'll make a lot less and I think
maybe it'll make a difference we'll see
so anyway you can see here we've got a
performance number we know that we're 46
seconds there and we know that we've got
us particular per bounce rating here so
there we go alright so now I'm gonna do
is instead of having Rand in there I'm
gonna get rid of that Rand you can see
we've got a random unilateral and random
bilateral so what I'm gonna do here is
I'm going to take this random series bit
I'm gonna move that up to our H file
where we define our structs and then I'm
gonna grab this X or shift part I'm
gonna put it right up above here and
what I want to do is I want to replace
sort of this this bit right here with
our own thing and you can see we've
already got it to do for that so what I
want to do is I want to take Rand max we
know Rand max is now just the maximum
32-bit integer so it's really just 32
max right you 32 max now I don't know if
we ever pasted you 32 max in here I
don't think we did so let's
oops didn't you do that let's grab that
out of handmade code I assuming we've
got it I don't know if we do we do so
I'm going to go ahead and grab that out
of here and I'm gonna put it in here so
there's our u3 to max that's the maximum
value that a 32-inch truck can have and
we're gonna put that right here and then
what I want to do here is put in our X
or shift 32 and what these things need
to do now is they need to take the
random series that we're talking about
now why do they need to take a random
series well as you could see random
numbers come from by having a state
variable that gets per muted repeatedly
over time now what you may have noticed
is the rand function did not ever take
anything there right the rand function
itself didn't take any parameters so how
was it doing it well you saw it when we
looked in there all those calls it was
using thread-local storage which is a
way of like grabbing out a specific
global variable for whatever thread was
calling you and it was doing a bunch of
work to do that we don't want to do that
work so we're just gonna pass in an
address that's like here's where the
state variable is for your thread look
directly at it to avoid all of those
calls right so that we just have a known
location in memory you could just update
immediately and get rid of all of those
thread-local storage calls that were
causing us so much of random overhead
that just didn't need to be there right
so we're going to pass in a random
series for all of those and the random
series will get updated as such and
we'll return a 32-bit value that is at
least pseudo random at this point
probably better than the random that was
in the CRT actually because that was
gonna be a linear Connor grant Daenerys
probably worse then this one was but
then after if we find we need randomness
that's better for seeing artifacts from
that or who knows what then we can try
to improve our random numbers by again
using permutations there cuz we already
started with the random trainer that's
the first step of the PCG so we just
need to get that mixing step in there if
we wanted to improve it so anyway here's
the here's us doing the XOR shift
and then dividing by the maximum to give
us a floating point value random
randomly from a random floating point
value and here we don't need to change
this at all because this was just
working on top of our existing one so
that's all good all right so now if we
want this to work we just have to follow
the compile errors down so when we're
calling these these just need to take
our random series that we want to
operate on and that's really it all
right and I think that should basically
do it so I now need that random series
somewhere I don't know if we ever call s
R and I don't think we do so we never
seeded this random number but that's
okay so all I'm gonna do here where we
call render tile with the work queue
here I need these to have access to
entropy right and so if you take a look
at where we call a render tile render
tile gets called from our our work
threads here or should there we go I'm
like where is it where is the win32 you
can see our render tile gets called here
like so
so what we need to do is we need the
state for render tile you know we need
whatever that state function is there to
have some idea of what the random value
should be and what you can see is the
work queue when when it acts to the work
queue it gets off a work order what I'd
like to do is just have the work order
itself be it contain the entropy that it
needs to use right so what I'd like to
do here is say alright that work order
whatever that thing is that needs to get
done it should have a random series in
here that is the you know entropy so
we'll pass along that entropy along with
the work order so here where we do
random series we will just take the
random seer
in fact we could even just use the
random series that's sitting in the work
order we don't really need it to be that
it could be local to the stack which
might be a little bit more efficient
depending on you know how these things
work out I don't really know but anyway
so if we take this random series here
I'm gonna go ahead and say from the work
order let's get the entropy out of there
and then that's the one that we'll use
right and so what I need to do now is
whenever I pack one of those work orders
up those work orders need to include the
entropy can see us packing the recorders
up here using the tiles and so the order
entropy we need some way here of getting
some randomized value right and right
now we don't really have a lot of ways
of getting your randomized value
unfortunately we would like to have some
way of getting it but we don't really
and so what we what we need to do is
find some source of entropy that we
could actually use to you know to
produce initially random seeds since I
don't really want to do that since I
don't want to deal with that part quite
yet what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna stick
with using our existing Rand for now to
see the entropy and because it's not the
same random function as our other ones
so they won't basically just produce
overlapping random sets and then what
we'll try to do here is replace this in
fact I don't really even need to call
Rand right what I could do is just say
like tile x times something plus tile Y
times something right for now something
predictable so that our images will come
out the same every time but eventually
you probably want to replace this with a
real entry value perhaps even one that
the user can input here that will
somehow do some permutation or something
right so we we want to do something more
real here but for the moment we just
need to make sure that these are
reasonable values so in fact I need to
do it this way Graham series
yeah and I think that's really all we
need to do the random series needs to be
obviously defined before it sees that
since C++ is in ordered declaration wise
and so now we need to see whether this
produces you know usable output right we
should probably have set the race for
pixel down lower well we're doing our
testing here but that's alright
so you know a couple of different things
I want to do first of all we can see
kind of right off the bat though that
there's there was no obvious problem
with our randomness right like it looks
pretty much the same as the other one I
don't see a lot of obvious like things
that are busted with this one that
weren't busted in the other ones so no
huge no huge deal there if we take a
look at the total time however what I
think you'll notice is if we compare
that run with our existing run the
difference is dramatic right so all I
did all I did was replace just that
random number function and you can see
we went from having 0.00025 milliseconds
per per bounce to 0.0009 milliseconds
per bounce it's over twice as fast and
the total time went from 46 seconds down
to 17 seconds right so very very very
trivial thing that I just did drastic
speed up right like way way way faster
it's it's you know getting a 2x speed-up
for just replacing one call to the C
runtime library getting rid of that with
our actual function is twice the
performance plus right and again you can
see why did that it was a really simple
process and I highly encourage you'll do
this looking at a hot piece of code like
that you should not see any calls in it
right like any piece of work that's
supposed to be as fast as possible
should not be calling anything as soon
as there's a call you've probably made a
mistake somewhere and in this case we
obviously did we were
calling out to a bunch of heavyweight
operations when these need to be
lightweight operations inside the hot
path okay so now that that's taken care
of we can look a little bit further and
go okay well can we go ahead and extend
this to be using more of a sim di
structure I don't know how much time
I've got left I think I have over an
hour because I think we started at 1:00
am I wrong about that I think we have
over an hour so I think we could make a
significant dent in that so again let's
see if we can increase our performance
again just a little bit more here by
taking a look at doing our math ops a
little bit more efficiently and now why
am I thinking about that right so the
reason I'm thinking about that is again
I like to guide the optimization to a
large extent by looking at what is
actually happening in the code because
that can tell me where my opportunities
lie and if you just take a quick look
down at all of what's happening here
what you can see in this code just very
obviously right you don't have to really
know very much about assembly language
at all I'm not an assembly language
junkie or anything what you can see very
clearly when you're looking at this code
much like the first time I looked
through it I saw those big you know sort
of warning signs flashing when I saw
those calls
I like why are we calling out something
so that was the obscene to replace here
much like that what I see here is just a
lot of SS right I see a lot of Mullis s
at assess sub SS right everything in
here is an SS call mmm now what an SS
instruction students I call SS
instruction SS instruction is single
scalar right and anytime we're executing
a single scalar instruction we could be
executing something wider than that
right because a single scalar
instruction is telling the you know the
processor to do a multiplication of one
scalar times one other scalar if we
instead of doing mul we're doing mul
pieces which is packed scalars we could
be doing four or
eight multiplications in that same
instruction right so in the same amount
of time it takes to this mole SS we
could be multiplying instead of one
scalar for scalars or eight scalars
right and so what we really want to be
able to do here is we want to be able to
make this function this hot path
potentially be able to do a wider set of
operations so instead of testing one
rate at a time test for raise at a time
right or instead of testing for raise at
a time test eight raise at a time okay
and so that's what we really want to do
there so how would we do this right well
if we take a look at this wimon x-men
stuff here where we go through we've got
this hot ray index here what I want to
do at first because this is what's doing
the majority of the work I'm wondering
whether I could pull this function out
without losing too much speed so what
I'm gonna do first is I'm gonna try
putting this up here and seeing whether
the compiler can handle it okay if I
pull it out right so what I'm gonna do
is I'm gonna grab this loop here the Ray
index part right I'm just going to put
it in here and this is going to be like
you know the sample arrays or whatever
right and so what I'm gonna do is I'm
just gonna pass in and raise per pixel
here is is these are coming out of here
what I want to do here is just have
these be things all of this stuff can be
specified cleanly and clearly and
hopefully everything is relatively yeah
really straightforward I'm just gonna
let the compiler tell me what the stuff
is that we actually need here
looks like you know what can we can we
simplify this a little bit here so I
wonder if this stuff can just be sort of
put into something because there's a lot
of stuff here that we may need I don't
want a huge passing festival but at the
same time I don't know exactly how I
want those to be pulled out well let's
keep going this way I'm just gonna
actually do it this way and we'll just
see what happens so we've got a random
series we've got a film X my
uh yeah and I don't know this may have
to be treated carefully because of the
fact that I don't want it to think that
it has to necessarily reload that guy
we'll have to see how that is there may
be some issues there we'll find a
second-half fix with and half picks half
takes w6h
we've got Film Center man there's just
too much bounces computed is just gonna
be added in locked here right yeah so
bounce is computed would have to be kind
of returned in worlds I assume it's just
world so final color
is just the return value here and I'm
pretty sure that this is all we would
have to do so bounce is computed it's
just going to be stored up in here and
the final color will be put there and
contributed idea of how many of these we
have right yeah one over raised per
pixel yeah
okay so I believe that's really all we
need to do there to get this into place
unfortunate there's just a lot of things
that are getting computed there and so
we may need to pass those in it's like a
struct or something more convenient but
I just try to pull this out into so that
our hot path is as simple as possible
and is encapsulated in a single place so
it's clear what's going on and can be
optimized right so if I go ahead and
paste this in here again we might want
to make that a little bit more
structured but we would just say the
final color here bounce is computed it's
gonna come from there and the final
color is gonna come from there as well
and so really all we have to do here is
just say call this caster that we've got
here and pass all the stuff that you
already computed like so
somehow we ended up changing back to
compiling handmade hero I'm not sure how
I may have accidentally hit a hotkey
let's try that again yeah all right so
again all I'm trying to do here is just
determine whether or not we lost any
appreciable speed we know that we were
getting oh oh nine milliseconds per Ray
before
and we took 17 seconds I just want to
see how much worse it gets so you can
see we do lose a little bit of speed
having it there so the first question is
well why are we losing that speed part
of it may just be because of not knowing
a few things like the random series for
example not knowing it that a few of
these things are localized so it's hard
for me to necessarily say exactly where
that's where that loss is coming from
what I could do is just take a quick
little look and see here if we actually
change something like for example this
random series as it comes through is
being used for nothing really in the
outer loop right so if we wanted to we
could just say that you know order
entropy here is the series that you're
supposed to use we won't use one here
and then instead of passing a pointer
here we'll just use the actual series
directly and restore that address of
right that way it's using something
local it can see that's never modified
outside and doesn't have to worry about
about accessing that at a distance
and again yeah like I said I'm not
really sure why we got a slowdown from
answering that call there
it does get called several times I
suppose it could be actual real overhead
but I don't know so again that's a
little bit better but still not not
perfect right and I'm not exactly sure
why we're sort of getting that as an
issue there so that may imply that we
need to keep it all in one place to weld
it together properly
I could try packing those things into a
struct and accessing them that way and
see if that is actually an improvement
I'm just not sure again it's hard to
know specifically where we lost a little
bit of speed there with the call and to
what extent that hurt us right so let me
try packing and then from there I guess
we'll kind of figure out what happened
so here's the things that we provide
right and here's the things that we need
so if we were to say that well Cass
sampler A's is just going to take this
state and everything that it does is
going to be off of the state we can see
to what extent that that helps us right
so let's take a look here
I also don't know if I could just make
this be grabbed directly I'm just
curious what can I say rid of that I
just want to see what the I want to see
where I can get the compiler in terms of
just allowing us to have this be sort of
isolate it off and right now I'm just
I'm just seeing some slowdown there that
I'm not sure why I'm seeing so I'm just
poking at it a little bit to see if I
can figure out what it doesn't like and
I may have to go look at the assembly
again to figure out what's going on
there so if I just let it grab
everything out like so
I'm going to go ahead and accumulate
these locally so that they don't
actually have to access anything outside
and I'll only write them out here I can
even make that be an ad so yeah that
looks roughly okay to me
and so what I'll do now is I'll just say
alright there's going to be that cast
State I'm going to go ahead and lock
that up here oops
good BH file
like so and then I'm going to just fill
it out so when we go to render a tile
we're gonna have this cast state
function and all of the stuff that
actually gets computed related to that
it's going to go in there right and this
all I'm doing here is just moving that
in to the state itself
I and all that stuff is now ready to go
I think
that'll come out of here that way we
don't have to bother with this and all
we would really have to do here is clear
final color start with nothing and pull
it out right we could even make that a
return value if you wanted to not a
member of caste States so I see but I
would like it to be and it looks like
film width and height don't need to be a
member of it either but again I think I
would like them to be so I'm gonna put
them in there anyway oops ooh sorry
about that
all right so let's see where we're at
here looks like we forgot to set the
world pointer and I think that's it so
yeah again just trying to figure out how
to get the compiler to be okay with me
pulling that code out and not taking too
much of speed it for it I'm gonna go
look at the assembly and see if we're
doing anything particularly bad we may
be doing something particularly bad I'm
not sure okay so there we go
whoa although we've got some that's
interesting that's really cool you can
see some of the tiles are kind of a
little messed up there all right I so
let me just verify that we're setting
everything here I suspect we're probably
not setting everything correctly but
that's really neat
so yeah now I got to go through and just
make sure all this stuff is is set up
properly our final color it looks like
we don't actually have to clear final
color it looks like that gets written
out properly so that's actually not an
issue there we were down to the correct
speed but it looks like we're doing
things wrong so that doesn't really
count so let's see what we actually
messed up here it looks like these are
our base parameters before we hoops
calculate the state so I want to
organize these a little bit here it
looks like do we ever use the worlds in
here at all no we don't so the other
thing I'm gonna do here is just put that
in here like so and get it out of here
so you can see these are the things we
actually are specifying here one cast x
max that's really only used for the
iteration so that's not really used up
here anyway so here we go
let's take a look at all the things we
need to compute here uh so rays for
pixel and Max bounce counts
those are both you know specified
exactly as they appear to be specified
in the queue so those are pretty trivial
and the world is the same so those are
just like straight pass through we then
have let's get rid of this for a second
here we then have the film X and film Y
and the film with thin film height and
those are actually the film X in film Y
are actually specified as you go through
the loop so I'm gonna kick them down to
the very bottom here I and if we look at
like half pix with half pix like that
sort of stuff and the film with the
height that stuff is actually computed
next right I could actually move this
stuff up as well I suppose if I wanted
to we could do that again with that back
kind of where we had it
all right so if we take a look at this
we specify the camera position pur the
camera Z the camera X and the camera Y
we are specifying all of those and it
looks like those are all correct so
that's good then we specify the width
and the height
those are specified here and then we
specify the the aspect ratio correction
which seems all totally reasonable we
then specify the halves for the film and
we create the film center like so and
then we have the half pix width and
height oops that we're specifying here
which again is pretty straightforward
and then we have the random series so I
think that's probably what we messed up
we forgot to set the random series so
let's go ahead and do that since that
comes through since that comes directly
out of the work order again I'm gonna
kind of put it up here because that's
sort of where that comes from
which is a little easier to follow and
we'll see if that helps us at all
all right so that's pretty clean that's
relatively close to the time we had
before so I'm happy with that as a
starting point and now we've got a
function called cat sample race which we
can look at as something that will that
will do sort of all of the heavy lifting
for us right this is where all of our
time is spent pretty much this function
is you know the thing that we want to
make as fast as possible so if we want
to start increasing the width of this if
we want to go ahead and up this to
computing four or eight rays at a time
then what we can sort of do is take a
look at this rays per pixel value and
say well what if we were to just you
know we could sort of do this one of two
ways and don't don't know exactly which
way would be smarter off offhand so one
way we can look at it is let's take the
number of rays per pixel we're gonna do
and let's multiply that number of rays
per pixel out so that we're casting you
know we're casting four or eight rays at
once and so the number of rays for pixel
we cast will be or the number of loops
will be the Rays per pixel divided by
that with four or eight or sixteen if
you have maybe X 512 although I've heard
avx-512 is really dicey right now
look apparently you don't really want to
use avx-512 yet it's just not quite the
chips are not quite handling it like the
i-9s that's why I've heard anyway
just that's what I've heard so yeah
we're talk about four or eight so either
we divide race by race four pixels by
four by eight and we go that's one way
to do it that seems like the most
straightforward way to do it might be
the way we do it the other way we could
do it is cast sample raise actually
takes for film X's film wise and
actually does just a whole loop as if
you were doing four pixels at a time
right so instead of looping over the X's
and Y's as you know as a individual
pixel at a time we loop over for eight
or 16 pixel blocks so a 4 by 4 block a 2
by 2 block that kind of thing or you
know 4 by 2 in the case of 8 something
like that so basically coming up with
some way of stacking that film X so my
and what you can kind of see is that
really this is the only thing that
depends on that so we could load in this
film X and fill film Y could be wide and
then we'd just run and again I don't
really know which of those is best
my gut instinct says honestly that we
should just do it in pixel blocks
but that guidance that could be very
wrong so yeah I'm thinking maybe we just
do that in pixel blocks and I'm just
rying to thinking what the difference
would be so if we did it in pixel blocks
this whole loop this is basically all
exactly the same
everything here is exactly as you see it
except it all gets eight wide if we did
it in rays per pixel instead then we
have to do this eight times to sort of
stack we need to generate eight
different bilaterals there and then
we'll add to a replicated X so we do you
know we do this eight wide like we
normally would this X gets replicated
and then you know we're off off and
running and presumably everything else
stays the same
I don't yeah I don't really think that
there's anything left there to do so I
think everything else should be okay so
I don't know yeah it's a hard call it
doesn't really make that much of a
difference I think at the end of the day
it's so I suppose we can just keep it
confined to this loop for now so if we
wanted to to start with that what we
need to do is take a look at all the
it's the instructions that we actually
need to execute here and try to get
those things working in a way that's
actually going to be wide right so what
I want to do here is just start by
transforming this to something that
looks like it's going to be actually
executing wide so what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna say that there's something
here called width or lane width and I'm
gonna say how many I want there to be
and so I'm gonna start out with a lane
with the four and what that means is
that the raised pixel will be divided by
that lane width so I'm only going to I
guess Lane ray count or something like
that is gonna be this race for pixel
divided by the lane width so that's how
many iterations of the loop we actually
have to do because we're actually
computing more Ray's than one every time
through right
and so this Lane width here oops sorry
Lane ray count is what we would loop
over and we would do you know each of
these only that only that many times now
if I were to run this it would still run
and in theory it should now run roughly
four times faster because we simply
aren't you know we're not actually doing
the work that we said that we were going
to do right I will point out that I
think we have some weird artifact and
going on there right you can see some
sort of weird tile boundary kinds of
things happening there and I'm not sure
if that's an artifact of the random
number generation we'll have to take a
look at it a little bit later but as you
sort of dropped that down to a lesser
number right you can see get the lane
but this one I don't think we see those
artifacts but if the lane width is four
so we're just doing you know two and
fifty six raised instead of 1024 you see
it and I don't know if that's because
the contribution factors like as you
take more rays you smooth over any
errors in your now you can still see him
right you can definitely still see him
there and I don't think those are
present previously right
so here's our second damage and yeah you
know you know you can't really see those
right so my assumption again is just
that that is something so let me let me
crank that let me crank that Lane count
back to four there and let's take a look
if we replace our X or shift here that
we're we're doing a random unilateral if
I was to get rid of that again so here's
a see runtime library Rand I'm assuming
that it's just an artifact of the way
that we're seeding the random number
generator and the fact that our random
number generator is not very random like
I said originally that causes that
problem I just want to verify that yeah
so you can see that that we're seeing an
artifact of that not really very random
random number that's causing it so I'm
fine with that doesn't I don't care
about that at all right now that's again
something that we need to do to take
care of a little bit later on so but
there you can actually see it and this
is exactly I was talking about where
you're your source of entropy matters
right
because if there's a bias to what it's
producing you will end up seeing that
somewhere but that's okay again not
really something that we care about so
really
so we'll take care of that a little bit
later on but for now it's fine for our
purposes because we're really just
concerned about the the part of the
performance and the quality is something
that will prove slowly over time all
right so when we're doing our cast
sampler race here what we need to do is
we need to start figuring about how
we're going to make this a little bit
wider and so if we take a look at what's
going on here some things like this a
lot of these operations can just be done
wide a lot of them like all of this
stuff here could just be done wide right
so for example if we introduced a type
called the lane v3 for example like this
then a lot of these operations could
simply be done as wide operations and
the same is true really of most of these
things where we've got like you know and
that's actually a type that I used in
the real world hence it's built into the
editor highlighting so if we were to go
ahead and just start talking about a
type that was itself actually wider a
lot of the stuff we could actually just
make be wide and there really wouldn't
be much else we'd have to do about it as
we go through these these sort of bounce
computations most of this stuff I think
would actually just work and so we'll
have to see whether we can make that
happen now when we do something like a
bounce computation we have to be really
careful about how we handle this because
we need to know whether or not Alayne is
actually active or not right and there's
this kind of nasty thing that has to
happen here
so we're gonna have to look at that as
well now when we loop over things like
the planes that's all going to work
pretty much exactly as it should but
what we need to do is lock those plane
values out into values that we can
actually operate on a little more
cleanly and for our purposes what we
could do there's two ways we can
approach this and for the moment we'll
use the slower way but we can try using
a faster way in the future right now
what we'll do is we'll use the slow way
which is that every time we iterate over
the plains we'll loft the values that
are in the plane out into actual
replicated values that we'll test
against in the future we could actually
store these probably a little bit
differently and and maybe test against
them in a little bit faster fashion
potentially I it might not really make a
difference that's why I don't want to do
it at first because we may find that
there's really no benefit to be had by
fussing with it but anyway so assuming
that we were going to take the plane end
for example we'd have to put that out
into a wider variable rate erection is
already wide this is a denominator right
and then we get into sort of these if
statements here which are problematic
for our purposes because we need to
compute when we do these ifs we're going
to end up computing something here
that's actually it could be different
for every lane so what we need to do is
we need to basically treat this more
like a mask where we're going to always
be computing these values but then we
only actually use them sometimes right
so what we want to do here is we want to
turn this sort of stuff for example into
something that's an actual mask so we
want you know maybe something like this
which is like our you know our genome
mask or something here this these tests
will produce a mask we can use where we
will have ones in the places where it
passed and zeros in the places where it
failed for each lane right and then
there's no you know there's no hierarchy
to this right because again when you've
got four things happening at once some
of them only true and some of them may
be
false so you have to execute all the
code all the time you can put a test in
so that if all of the things in the mask
fail right then you don't have to do it
but for our purposes there so little
code here I don't know that a jump is
really a good idea so that's hard to say
again you have to test that figured out
so the two things were computing you're
the denominator here and the T and again
this denominator is going to potentially
be zero we just have to allow divide by
zero and the mask will mask it out later
but basically we have to make sure that
the cemg unit is in a place where it
won't fault on divide by zero which by
default they don't think it does so I
don't think there's anything in
particular that we have to do there so
we've got a diene a mask and a t mask
right you can see these two masks about
what we need to do is we need to and
these two masks together and that gives
us our final mask right so our hid mask
is just going to be everywhere that the
denominator mask and the team asked both
past right and where they both passed is
a place where we actually have a T value
that we want to record and so the hid
distance hit mat index and next normal
stuff all of that stuff will be set
conditionally and so what I want to do
is I want to set these conditional like
a conditional equals basically where we
say okay the hit mask is the thing we're
based to say the hip distance is going
to be set if the hid mask is true it
will be set to T right
and that plane we need a couple other
things serious we've got the plane end
put the plane D right so that's a lane
f/32 we've got the plane D here so that
plane D has to come out as well like so
and all of these things are going to get
set in that fashion right so yeah so you
can see here exactly we're doing it's
really straightforward we just need a
middle class conditional assign so
basically like I've set this value equal
to this value if the intermediate and
hit mask is set to one there or whatever
right that's all I'm doing
so then we would want to do the same
thing with spheres right and in this
case the mat index I guess is also has
to be so we have Alain your three two
here which is the mat index claim that
index and that's playing that mat index
and that way we're not referencing
anything we loft these values out into
four wide values or however wide we want
and then we do the operations we were
going to do so then we do our spheres
and we'd want to do the spheres the
exact same way so we'd have a lane V 3
which is our sphere P we would have our
sphere radius
and is there anything else I don't know
that there is find out second here I
guess we got the Matt index so again
nothing particularly odd here
really nothing nothing bizarre happening
all of these things will have to become
lane related but now we've got the exact
same situation as we had before where
we've got some if statements here and we
know that we can't really have if
statements right like if statements
aren't gonna fly not unless there's a
ton of code in them if there's a ton of
code in an if statement then we do want
to keep the is we still have to do all
the code but we want to have the if
statement have a baling condition which
would basically be something that looks
to see whether the the masks that are
computed are all zeros and if so with
bales I don't know that we've quite got
enough code for that we might I mean
there is a fair bit of code here it
could be that we could save some time by
branching around it same is true here
but again don't really want to look at
that just quite yet so here's our root
mask right this stuff all has to get
computed either way here this part oops
is a little bizarre because this is
essentially a thing that's just picking
which of the hits to use so it's
actually a dependent so we've got a
youth playing 32 here which is the guess
the piste pick which hit we're doing so
we've got a pick mask there and then
we're doing conditional assign of T on
the pick mask like so right we've then
got our hit mask
oh sorry our t mask and our hit mask is
whatever the root mask was
andddd with the team asked just like
before and then we've got a bunch of
conditional assignments
that's still a valid complaint so we're
going to leave it all right
so what we have now done like you can
see here is we've basically made these
sort of nominally wide by making some
types that would work if we define them
to be wide we haven't defined those
types yet so this isn't gonna compile at
all so we have a bunch of errors and
then we've kind of sketched in what the
actual operations are we need here we
need conditional assigned we need like
you know inner product we need square
root and so on we need all of those
things we need normalize or zero and all
that sort of stuff right so then we get
to the part where we do our kit maths
mat index here we kind of not have to
deal with this other part where if we
hit something versus if we didn't hit
something we have two different things
to do and that is the part that's
actually a little bit more complicated
that we have to kind of work on right
and so what we want to do here is say
all right let's start with with a couple
things that we need to put out at the
head end we have not done any monster
mination by the way so we need a lane
u-32 here for our bounces computed right
we need that we needed a lane u-32
that's going to be our like active mask
or our lane mask and our lane increment
and what I want to do here is our laning
commits gonna be one across the board
and our lane mask is gonna be you know
that's everywhere so for copies where
we've got the increment and the mask
both in there right and zero for our
bounce computed basically something that
looks like this and what I need to do
now is every time through here where
we're going to compute a bounce I want
to take our bounces computed and I want
to do an ad on the bounce is computed up
by the lane increment right and the
reason I need to do it this way is
because our bounces computed is now
actually not just going to be
the number the width times the the
number of times to the loop right
because we're gonna go through the loop
rays per pixel times divided by the lane
width but we went before so trying to
think to how explain this so before
every time through the loop we knew that
we were only going through here but
until we bounced enough because we would
break out if we if we hit the skylight
and there was nowhere left to bounce we
would just break out of the loop right
so we would naturally not count any
additional bounces there because we
wouldn't actually be executing this line
of code here we will keep going until
all of the Rays have not can't bounce
anymore which means that some of the
lanes will occasionally compute just
sitting there doing computations that
will just get thrown away because their
ray already terminated somewhere with a
bounce and there's nothing left to do
with it yet now in the future we could
get more sophisticated and try to do
weird things like packing new bounce
computations in there or whatever right
but at the moment we're trying to do
just a dumb thing where we just are
doing the same algorithm just wider and
so are in order to properly record the
statistics here what that means is that
when we actually terminate a ray bounce
chain down here I'm gonna have to
actually zero out that Lane in the
increment or so that we don't ever
operate on that again on four bounces
computed right then at the end when we
need to do bounce is computed we need to
just grab out the various parts of
bounce is computed and and some of them
together right so we basically want to
do a horizontal ad here on bounce is
computed to add all the lanes together
and that gives us how many bounces we
actually did how many we did per Lane
sum together is the total number of
bounces right and we can do further work
with that later on
okay so then when we're in here with our
hit mask index
I'm sorry hit art hit math hit matte
index we get back to the same problem
which is that we want to do both of
these paths for everybody so what we
want to do here sort of like with the
conditional sign is we need to do these
operations basically based exactly on
the thing that we were talking about
before where we you know where we do all
of the stuff we're going to do for a
bounce but we only use it if that thing
actually did properly hit something and
if it didn't properly hit something then
we just ignore the calculations we did
and we do something else with it right
so what we need to do here is we need to
be a little bit more conscious of how
we're tracking our materials and there
may be some things that we want to do
it's hard to say whether this is correct
or incorrect I don't really know so it's
worth taking a minute to talk about it
so what we see here is it's gonna depend
on how complicated our material is but
what you can see is that we've got a bad
downshift here we need to look up the
materials for each of these things and
we've got like four or eight lanes worth
where we would need to go look up off of
that material index and what you can
kind of see here is that materials as
they currently stand are very simple
they've got a scatter and emission color
and a reference color and we may really
want to just as we hit things grab that
information out and store it rather than
looking it up after the fact
I don't really know so if we were just
gonna stick with something this simple
we would probably want to just do the
conditional assign of these and track
them as we go however the reason I'm not
going to do that is because I'm going to
assume that this is going to get more
complicated later on and that we're
going to want to not copy it around
every time we do a hit that could still
be wrong I don't really know but the
point is we've now got a really nasty
downshift here not something I really
want to deal with but what can you do we
don't really have a choice so what we
need to do here is we need to pull out
the actual values of these materials and
actually do some kind
of processing that will yeah that will
allow us to do as much wide work as we
can
after loading some stuff so let's start
with the easy part first these things
here where we are doing these
permutations
I think these actually will just work I
guess I need to just set this to lane
here anywhere we were doing a bilateral
that needs to return a wide one we need
sort of a version that does Lane based
stuff there so these would both be Lane
and most of the rest of this right I
think just works so all of this stuff
here just works and so the only thing we
really have to do here even ray
direction I think is probably fine yeah
I really don't think we need to do
anything else I think all of this is
just fine as it is right so I think all
of that stuff is fine the only thing we
need to do is is here where we load the
material out that just that stuff needs
to get get sort of sliced right so yeah
this stuff is basically what we're
talking about so we have an emit color
that we're gonna have to do here Matt
emit color we've got a Matt ref color
and we've got a matte scatter and these
are the parts that we need to figure out
how to load and we'll talk about that in
a second
for now I want to get the rest of this
stuff working like I was saying for we
now have to kind of figure out how we're
gonna make all of this stuff work
coherently but as you can see we sort of
have a couple different problems that we
have to deal with here right so in one
case here we're doing sample Hadamard
attenuation matte color thing sorry
madam it color we've got the same thing
happening down here right from the matte
emit color so in either case actually if
we look at what we were doing in either
case we are doing this operation where
the sample value does get incremented by
that matte emit color so really that
part stays the same right that part
happens in either case with one sort of
important actually says with one
important caveat and that's this break
statement here so every Lane will get
the its material color added to it
unless this ray has already terminated
right so we know that the matte emit
color here when it gets loaded out we
know that that sort of has to properly
get axed as it goes through right so
what I'm going to say though is just
since we're doing a Hadamard product
already we know that if we set the
emission color to zero on the matte emit
color then we would be fine
because it wouldn't do anything so like
must return zero on mask on on Lane mask
right so we need to zero out these on
the on that mask now when we come
through here
the important part is our hit map index
if our hit mat index was zero we need to
terminate that ray but that's really
easy for us to do in this case so we
just need to do an not equal to zero and
if the thing was not equal to zero then
it can proceed otherwise it can't right
so all we really need to do here is
something that will extend that zero you
know this sort of thing so whatever our
lane mask was right and furthermore our
lane increment in fact you know we could
do yeah so here we'll just say okay the
laning current we don't have to store
you know it's just one but it gets
masked by whatever the lane mask is
right so here all we're doing is saying
hey after we tracked that emission color
here we're then gonna mask out anyone
who didn't hit anything is is a dead ray
Lane now that Lane just stops getting
computed entirely right then we just and
that's the equivalent of our break
statement right that's the break
statement it's saying that's it you know
we're not going to go any further in
there furthermore here we can have this
max bounce count we can terminate this
properly we could say that at the end
here right we know that you know if the
lane mask you know if all zero right we
could say if our lane mask falls out so
there's literally no more lanes at all
then stop right so only keep going while
our lanes are you know
you know if we have something that will
check if these are all zeros then we
don't want to you know we don't want to
do it anyway anymore right or I don't
know we'll think about what this
function has to be called apparently all
zeros we want to be able only check like
the high bit probably you do that so
what we probably want to do here is say
if if high bit if all Lane high if high
bit of each lane is zero high bit of all
lanes is zero something like that right
so we can just say okay look if this
Lane mask we know there's all ones or
all zeroes in each slot so look at the
high bit of each or whatever or whatever
we don't even need that it's just we
know that there's one zeros need to one
if something like that
I don't know I'll just call it that I
don't know I don't know what to call it
but point being we know that we have a
mask we know that the mass will be ones
or zeros entirely in each lane based on
whether or not that lane is active so we
just need anything the processor can do
so if it was on arm or sse or whatever
it was on as long as there's something
that can say look to see whether there's
any ones or any zeros in these slots
whichever kind of function you can
support we just need you to do that
thing and when it comes back we'll break
if the mask is like therefore nominally
zero but we don't need you to look like
I just trying to throw what the name
would be for saying we don't need you to
look at each bit because we're promising
you that all the bits in each lane will
be the same value they'll all be one so
they'll all be zeros so you don't have
to check them all right that's all I was
trying to get across with the name and
it was a little bit a little bit
difficult okay so that's what we're
doing there and now we've got our
situation where we sort of have what we
want
sketched out here it's the load that's a
little bit a little bit tricky but let
me finish the rest of this so after we
update our lane then we go through and
we just say here that we need to clamp
these this stuff so we do an inner
product and we want to do a clamp here
like this this I can rephrase as I want
to take the maximum value whichever one
is higher right I either want to take I
either want to take the inner product or
I want to take zero right whichever
one's higher we're going to produce the
new attenuation value by multiplying
these two together and that's all fine
we're going to update the rate origin
this way we are going to then do the
permutations this way and that's about
it right and off we go
so each one of these like I said is
calculating a sample value so at the end
here we're going to end up with the
final color that we need to actually
output that's getting summed and you can
see that now this is sort of wide this
contribs now not really an accurate
value yet because we now have four color
values that are sort of stacked right
horizontally so we then need to do v3 we
need to do a horizontal add on this as
well where we sort of add together those
four different VIII's that we've come we
are however many there are smoosh them
together into an actual final color that
we can then return right I think if I'm
not mistaken this is actually a mistake
in that case because since we're summing
everything together still and the
horizontal add we do need that for still
in there so this contribu is still
raised for pixel I think it doesn't
change right I think that's all the same
now that contribu do the multiplication
down here that sample and final color
all of that stuff is actually laying
VIII's so that I think all of that
actually actually needs to be
contributes to that needs to be Lane b3
s so these are really still Lane V 3s
and bounce bounce is computed here I
think actually comes out here right so
bounce is computed again that's getting
added to every time through the loop
like this so I think all of that is
pretty much right
yeah yeah yeah all right so looking at
how these are happening here where we've
got camera X and all that stuff so all
of these now also want to be lane based
right and they're just lane based
constants and what we need to do here is
just assume that they're just going to
be replicated right there's no these
values can all be just replicated out so
these will just replicate them into Lane
values right so I think now we have
effectively have everything we need sort
of sketched out with how this would be
Cindy eyes right and so what I want to
do now is I want to just do a quick
sketch of making this work one wide so
we did all this work right but I could
just make the lane with b1 and define
all these functions to stub out to their
actual versions that we already wrote
and it should still work and that way we
can debug the like masking and all that
stuff without actually half and use any
Cindy instructions and without worrying
about any of that
right so if I look in handmade ray what
I'm gonna do is I'm gonna open a thing
called ray Lane an h-file that's just
gonna define all of this stuff and so
what I'm gonna do here is I'm gonna say
okay well you know an f32 is just a is
just a Lane f32 in a lane year 32 and a
lane v3 they're all just what they are
already right there there's nothing
special about them at all they're all
exactly what you think they are right
and then I'm gonna go ahead and include
that in here
so in addition to Ray math we're going
to include rail aah
and off we go and so then we only have
just a few errors left to go like
bilateral lane right and that's
something I'll put in here so this is
going to return a lane f32 and all that
is is so then we've got this conditional
assign I'm going to put that in here and
the conditional assign this just takes
you know the various different types
that we've set here we've got you know a
mask a desk and a source and all we're
going to do here is say that desk equals
you know if the mask is one we want the
source to be assigned so we want to do
an end with the source right that will
tell us which of the source things to
come in then we want to take the
opposite of the mask whatever the mask
was we want to flip it so that we now we
have ones in the places where the mask
was not set and that's what would tell
us which parts of the desk to keep and
then we or those two together right so
we're just doing a thing where we
basically we take the mask and we use
the positive version of the mask to pick
up the source the negative version of
the master got the desk and that is what
updates our desk right so that's good
what is the problem
address is a legal right operand right
operand oh here we go
what was the problem there
I don't see what the problem is
oh I do see the problem is okay so this
is just a artifact of C for some reasons
he doesn't let you mask floating-point
values I don't know why so I have to
cast this to a you 32 first right it's
just annoying so these are
floating-point values and I have to cast
them right conversion from lane to Lane
F 32 yes so this will produce an
entirely it's gonna do it entirely new
three twos does the only things that
allow masking an orange together but we
know that this is actually an F 32 right
anyway so once we have that we know we
can do the one for you 32 the one for
you 32 is even easier in fact we could
now just call the you 32 one to do the F
32 one right so you know I'll leave it
like this for now but we could just call
we could just call the you 32 one to do
the F 32 one instead right so in this
case now we don't need the casting
because it's actually just the way we
want it and so we can just do this
directly now because we don't have to do
the reinterpreting all the time we go
right so again if we want to do it this
way we could do in fact me let me know
just do it right so what we could do is
say well pretend this is au 32 you know
pretend this is au 32 right do the
operation and then assign desk to it
or assign it to desk I should say right
so now we have like an f32 version and a
and a u32 version should avoid a
conditional assign oh you know what we
don't even have to do it that way
nevermind because this does the assign
directly so there we go and then finally
we just need the one that works on the
threes and that one is pretty easy to do
because this one will just call three
times the conditional assign on each of
the members right so this will be like
DES Tech's mass source X right this just
this just replicates the function across
the various values right and this looks
like a what is hip distance here hip
distance distance is Alain F 32 and T
there's an F 32 hit mask is au 32 what's
the problem another Rios could convert
the types ah cuz these new addresses
it's fine this is our load that we
haven't finished yet and here's our max
so our max value again this is a kind of
a special version we've got to do here
but that's okay so here's our max that's
going to take an A and a B and it's
going to return whichever one is higher
right that's pretty easy to do if a is
higher than B then return a otherwise
return B right that will return the
maximum value in either case
and then we've just got our last sort of
two here we've got an internal rule
which is mask is erode that's going to
take one of our lane masks and we've
also got the horizontal ad that's going
to return an f32 if you've got a lane of
thirty-two and it's going to return a v3
if you've got a lane b3
so basically whichever one you were
trying to whereas on the lad it will
horizontal ad it obviously this one can
be written in terms of the other one so
the result in this case can just be
horizontal ads on the components right
so we don't really need to write this
when we only really need to write this
one in this case because we are talking
about the scalar version horizontal ad
actually doesn't do anything there are
no lanes to add together so the result
is just whatever the resulting whatever
you passed in right masked is zeroed
same thing we don't really have to check
multiple Maps because we've only got one
so the result is just if the lane mask
is not equal to zero or I should say is
equal to zero right and that's about it
now if we take a look at what else we've
got here a conversion from Lane
thirty-two d'Alene F 32 so we need a a
u3 to version there I guess maybe we
don't actually have any of these other
than used in the v3 one but it's no big
deal I so curiously you thirty-two
version and here's the horizontal ad now
we do have one slight problem here which
is that I we wouldn't be tracking a full
64 a bit so if we turned out we
multiplied - we did too many of these
bounces we could wrap and so I don't
know exactly how we want to prevent that
we won't be having that problem if we
keep the tile sizes small enough but
I should probably put it to you in
because it's a little bit dicey right
and so in here where we do bounce is
computed should probably put it to do
all right so the last thing we need to
do is have some way of loading these
things up here you know hip mat index
again this because of the way we're
doing it we can just make this whole
thing it to do here and and end because
since we happen to know that all of
these are scalar at the moment this can
just be cheesed
by loading out just one but we're gonna
have to load out lane with of those
eventually fear mat index looks like it
wasn't loaded
this needs to be a dot here there we go
all right and so now we've got some
debugging to do and that's probably what
I'll finish the stream with is just I'll
probably turn off the automatic ray cast
part of this here and we'll go debug
anything that we messed up you can see
not a particularly great result there so
so we definitely have a couple bugs in
it but again all we have to do is just
to bug these and then we're in position
to actually next time we do handmade ray
we're in position to kind of you know
move to a Cindy is version fairly
cleanly that won't be too bad right
okay so the first thing I want to do is
in build up bat I don't really want to
be running this anymore I don't want to
- actually I don't want to actually run
the ray caster I just want to compile
because I want to run in
the debugger and so all I'm gonna do
here is I'm just gonna step through here
and see roughly what's going on in the
parts that I think might be somewhat
suspicious right so I'm just gonna first
take a look at like what's happening
like with off x and off-white
oh whoops let me also and our build up
at let me go ahead and change this to be
unoptimized so that it's easier for us
to inspect the values in the debugger
and see what's going on so let's take a
look at what these are oh and one other
thing I also like to do is turn off
threading so somewhere in here we get
core counts we go
and so now we won't have multiple
threads kind of racing through her
making it annoying so here's our offset
X and our offset Y I just gonna look and
see yeah that looks pretty reasonable
one thing I will say is this is we got
some errors in here you know when we
actually go to tighten the stuff up this
this is not the center of a pixel it's
the corner of a pixel so this should
really be a random unilateral I think I
think that's just wrong in fact let me
just change that while we're at it
right I mean unless I'm wrong about that
film X film why are the very corner so
you're only going in so you really don't
want it to be half pix W you want it to
be just pics W and H we could set it to
the center I would be the other option I
mean I could just do this instead I
suppose right where we would just step
into that middle and then that way this
random bilateral maybe I'll do it that
way I mean why not
not a la riesen not to I suppose
oops so just notice that as a stepping
through might as well fix it one there
so now our offsets are properly I think
perfectly set I don't know why yeah I
don't know why we didn't notice that
looks like our state value is zero that
also seems wrong why is our state value
zero
we do initialize these somewhere right I
mean here's where we initialize these we
put it into order entropy when we come
through here and we do render tile we
assign state series to order entropy
so I'm really not sure why that's zero
and I would like to know so I'm going to
step back out here because I'm again
just a little bit weirded out by that so
here's our random serious and there's
nothing in the state value if we take a
look at the work order itself the
entropy value is also zero so I'm just
curious to know oh you know why because
we don't have any offset here the other
thing we kind of need to do and I should
I should probably just do it now as well
I should probably make sure that this
entropy value gets updated per the state
like I think we kind of want to do this
so that we so that we as we step through
the pixels we're using different random
rays because the way we had it before we
wouldn't update it so every pixel would
use the same random series which doesn't
seem like a good idea right all right
that looks more correct to me there's
our film P setting up the origin in the
direction here for this Ray
all that stuff seems right setting up
the sample setting up the attenuation
value setting up the lane mask then we
come through the bounces start enough
our hit distance hit mask all that stuff
gets cleared our lane increment is one
our lane mask is still on so we're gonna
do bats computed should should think up
one we go through our planes we get out
the planes we do our masks right and I
guess one problem you know what there's
our problem right there when we do these
comparisons one of the problems we're
gonna run into here is that they need to
be set to all ones or all zeros and at
the moment they aren't right and so that
conditional assign is gonna break so
that's the first thing you know I'm
thinking Cindy terms and we didn't
really replicate what's gonna happen in
Cindy correctly so what we actually want
to do there when we do conditional sign
I suppose is instead of masking we need
to do it as an actual test because that
mask is not going to be right now the
way I could do that is do a mass equals
mask right so if there's anything set in
the mask it will become all FS otherwise
it's gonna become zero right let me try
that now when we go into the conditional
assign right the mask will be set to all
FS and then we'll do a mask of the
source board with a mask of the inverse
the desk there right and then we should
be set to one of the other so the desk
should now be equal to the source for
example in this case which it is and so
that's a little bit better off all right
let me go ahead and let that run let me
see I don't know I want a picture of
where we're at bug wise
and this is gonna be a lot slower
because we've introduced a bunch of
complexity that didn't need to be there
right for the scalar version in order to
go wide and so you know this is this is
going to be a slower version than our
previous version for scalar for sure
right and you can kind of see it
creeping up there
so let's just take a look at what we
ended up with there so it's not that far
off anymore right we're we're a little
bit closer we're obviously doing a
little bit of our summation wrong but at
least we've got our first emission
tracking properly there so we don't have
a completely wrong image now we just are
not summing quite properly so much
closer okay so let's see if we can
finish the mat and next stuff and just
end up with something that's that's
roughly correct I'm also gonna try to
reduce the ray count the race for pixel
there so I'm just gonna say like a 16
Ray's per pixel right real real tiny
number of rays now so that we can just
really quickly run it and get our output
image right all right so now what we're
trying to fix that I'm gonna go back to
the build that bat I'm gonna go ahead
and make it so that we can still get our
output back so here we go
and now what I want to do is say all
right I want to go see also we're not
running parallel either so that's the
other thing that slows us down we're 8
times slower just from that as well and
that can I suppose I can put that back
in now - all right so now what I want to
see is what am i messing up in terms of
that summation so our final color you
know when we hit an emitter we're doing
the right thing but we're not about
we're not bouncing right so once we do a
bounce
we've got an issue right and we don't
know exactly what that issue is let's
double check that mask is 0 it is not
doing something weird as well so mask is
yard
if the lane mask equals zero then it is
zero so we should break that seems
reasonable lane mask equals lane mask
and hit mat index equals zero that
should in theory work okay because again
it's just using the low bit so I think
everything should be fine there but we
could double-check that let's take a
look at anything else that's weird here
we have there hit mat index we're look
up these yeah I may want to step through
a debug mode one more time and take a
look at what's going on in here
just see if there's anything else
suspicious we're LARPing the random
baths and the sample is always
accumulated with whatever the Matt emit
color is the attenuation value is built
up over time properly so that looks
about right to me and the sample value
at the end contribute I'm sample all of
that looks about right so I'm gonna do
one more step through here in debug mode
so I take it back take everything back
that I said and just make sure that this
works okay again with only 16 rays for
pixel it should be a lot faster
hopefully so no big issue there yeah
there we go and you can see the problem
that we're having here is our bounces
aren't working properly so whatever
emitter hits it works but that's yeah
that's only if it hit an emitter right
off the bat so let's take a look at what
the first hit happens to be here the hit
material index is one that means that
this one should keep going the
attenuation value properly did attenuate
based on the reflection color and the
cosine there and our lane mask well
there you go
our Lane mask is wrong and I'm not sure
why so let's just double check that it
might be a bit thing again like I was
saying let's see what the lane mask
actually is equals F F F that's that's
fine so when we come down here at the
hit material index is one the lane mask
so when I do this and I'm getting
ah that's supposed to be not equal to
zero that's our problem right there so
you see that we've got the lien mask and
this is an and equals really right we
want to produce two mass from this if it
equals zero is just to terminate so we
want to not we want the ones that don't
terminate so we want not equal to zero
is what we're trying to actually produce
here right so that's just updating the
lane mask incorrectly is the only
problem that we're getting there
alright see what kind of image we get
here so that is looking correct to me
again
for the most part let's go ahead and
change this back up to our optimized
version which will now unfortunately be
a lot slower than it was where's our
race for the pixel 1024 right and I
think that's it for today because I
think now we're back to operating
properly with basically Sindy style code
and so the only thing that we have to do
is next session there we go
the only thing we have to do is next
session turn this to actually executing
sim D and go from there right now as you
can see here we're 21 milliseconds to
bounce now instead of oh nine and that's
because again we introduced a lot of
inefficiency here because we are
preparing to do it wide and we're not
actually using any of those nice wide
instructions and so a lot of things that
just didn't need to happen anymore you
know are are still happening let me
double check so we seem to be a darker
as well so it looks like maybe we've got
a summation error in there so we might
not quite be done debugging yet and so
let's take a look at what's going on
with that so if we take a look at this
contribution here that's our problem
so the lane width has to be actually set
properly so I'm gonna go into Ray Lane
here and I'm gonna find this so Lane
width 4 is what we had before but we
don't we're not actually doing that so
the lane width is one in our current
implementation and so now I was
wondering why it was yeah
was it was getting in
speed advantage there because it was
terminating pretty fast and like it
seemed like it was running about as fast
as the old one was but it clearly showed
it was twice as slow per bounce so I'm
like what's going on it's like okay that
the reason is because we actually didn't
run as many rays through it so hey yeah
it was slower per bounce but it was not
running as many bounces right so there's
that so anyway so I think we're good now
probably and again we just have to take
a look so there we go
and you can see that the image is
basically indistinguishable now I
believe probably from the other ones in
that directory let's find out can I flip
between them yeah so you can see those
are pretty much indistinguishable so
those are our three they're interesting
until the only real difference is we
fixed the pixel center so this one has a
correct test fit mem has a correct pixel
center and the other one doesn't but I
think we're good now
and all we really have to do now is
finish our optimization there to see how
good we did now I probably should have
saved one using the correct Rand and for
where you know we could actually
benchmark against that but that's really
all we saved unfortunately so if we want
to in hand in lane now as well what I
could do here say if Lane width equals
one believe I can do that right
in theory if you run this right then we
can you know have lain with equals one
be a case here and then what we can do
is say alright let's put in some other
ones here so there's you know a fling
with equals four then we'll have the
code for that right and if we want to be
super saucy up here we can also put in a
version of it that is eight wide for
example so what we we need to do if we
want to increase oh and also for you do
laymen with equals eight it should say
hey laden with must be sent to something
and so now we're just supporting one or
four and if we were to look at sort of
if I was to sort of sketch out what this
would look like then what we're gonna do
here is say well we've got different
looking things right so if we were
actually going to do a limit equals four
then we have to actually make these
things work so for example Lane F 32
we're gonna have to actually pound
include I don't know what the right
intrinsic thing is anymore
let's see what we did a hand made here
oh it's just always this you know
ridiculous nonsense maybe some platform
yeah so we probably need to do something
here like this depending on which one
we're on we're going to need to have
this sort of stuff at the moment I'll do
one of those so we'll define compiler m
SVC so we'll get that intrinsic in there
and then we can actually use the MM
versions here so like that so I think
it's M 128 again I never use these I
always define my own because these
things are nuts see here yeah M
underscore underscore M 128 so anyway I
we would have to define values for each
of these these are integers these are
not the lane VIII's are just going to
have one of these each for the X the Y
and the Z like so and then each of these
functions has to actually be implemented
for it and a whole lot more the reason
I'm not going to finish this stuff right
now is specifically because even though
we can do these you'll note that a whole
bunch of other things are not actually
set properly so for example you can see
here we've got a bunch of stuff where oh
and I suppose these should also be moved
up in here I might go ahead and move
these into the math so here's the Ray
math stuff right I might go ahead and
and move these into there like so and
then random bilateral Lane I think I
might move into Ray Lane because it's
going to be dependent so this scalar
version is here and the non scalar
version would
in here right and so the way that would
work again is you know we'd need to
create some kind of a right this sort of
thing where we you know and then set a
pi32 kind of a thing and you know this
this kind of nonsense here where we'd
take four of these values we'd read run
the thing for it four times and put them
in here now
eventually what we'd want to do is
actually just keep the state wider yeah
actually you know what that's that's
gonna be the smarter thing to do so
really what we want is all of this stuff
has to kind of be in here probably right
and I guess what we could do is make the
series itself that value could be
dependent on the lane and that might
just work for all I know I'm trying to
think now it might be that we can just
make this all work in terms of lanes
let's let's try let's try that let's try
that let's just see I'm just curious
because that might just work right I'm
not sure if it would if it wouldn't but
it might so let's see I I take back what
I said before and I put one of these in
here and I just say that this stuff
looks like this
and so all of this stuff works on Lena
32s effectively this would go away so
you just have random bilateral like so
and it produces just Elaine's worth of
them and so then the only weird part
here is this has to get converted up so
what we would do here is we'd say you
know this this is returning Elaine new
32 and so we'd want to do something
where we would say you know Lane F 32
from you 32 so we have some way of doing
that cast and you know normally it would
just be something that looks like this
but it would actually be a real Cindy
thing in the future right so I'm gonna
set the lane width back down to one I'm
gonna go into Ray dot H and I'm gonna
take this random series bit here and I'm
gonna just extend it out to that then
I'm gonna look at any where that we use
to call this and I'm gonna take it so
that instead of saying random bilateral
Lane I'm just gonna make it so that it's
always calling random bilateral instead
and then I'm going to compile and see if
it works it looks like it does so yeah
so that way what we could do there is
make that way our random number
generator will also work lane wide
because if you take a look at what's
actually going on in it nothing that it
does is actually not supported in Cindy
so we should just be able to use Cindy
on it right so so that's fine right all
of this stuff
is stuff that we could probably do in
Cindy just fine because there should be
an X or in there and there should be a
shift by a intrinsic value in there and
so those are things that we can just do
and we shouldn't have to worry too much
about it now if i zoom in here one of
the weird things about this is I don't
see the block pattern anymore so I think
the fact that that block pattern
actually wasn't a problem with the
random number dinner it was just because
I wasn't rolling the entropy foot
forward per pixel and had like zeros in
there and stuff so so actually we're
fine X are chefs totally fine that's
good too
we don't really need to do anything
fancier than that all right so that's it
for today I think I'm going to wrap it
up maybe tomorrow we'll do the actual
implementation just to not leave it
hanging and so that we can specify lane
widths that are greater than four so
we'll just say like you know and again
this right here I we you know we can
just sort of also say that you know
maybe we'll do this one too you know and
that would just be that and then I don't
even know if this is supported yet
exactly how hey you know it'll be
supported but I don't know exactly which
of these things you have to include
these days but this would just be if we
were to use the wider equivalents of
these then we could go ahead and use
eight white Cindy as well so I'm just
going to check to see yeah so as far as
I know if we want to we can just use em
256 is as well and that way we can have
an eight y24 wide and one wide path and
we can just compile it however way we
want and there you go so I think that's
really
all we'll have to do and we'll implement
those probably tomorrow let me go ahead
to a brief Q&amp;A here just in case anyone
has any questions about what we did
there and again what you can sort of see
what I did was just a really basic sort
of prep where I said all right I'm gonna
put this code into a state where it
still runs scalar but it runs scalar in
such a way that it can be made wide
trivially and then that way I can debug
it but before it actually runs wide
where things could get more difficult
right
how would one implement something like a
bloom effect in a ray tracer so it
depends exactly what you mean by bloom
but let me go ahead and and sort of
assume I know what you mean by bloom so
I don't know if we don't have an image
processing program installed here do we
we could we could install here and
and I could maybe take a look at at
producing something but I'll just I'll
just see if I can I don't want to be in
Bing wait how come we're not how do we
get end up in this browser this is
Cortana I all right whatever anyway
so what I wanted here was halation and
what I want to talk about here is where
that I think the bloom you're talking
about I'm not sure which bloom you're
actually talking about because there's a
lot of different places that bloom can
come from
but hey Latian is actually the thing
that you're probably talking about and I
don't know whether there's some anime
thing called halation which apparently
could be chit should I get the actual
thing instead of the anime please there
is that not too much to ask so anyway I
there's a couple different places that
the bloom you're talking about could
come from I don't know which one you're
talking about so the answer change it
depends on which one you want but
generally speaking there are two places
where light that can cause light to
bloom so the first thing that could
cause light to bloom and the one that I
assume you're talking about is called
film halation and what that is is that's
when light folk you know photons
entering the lens of the camera
they end up hitting the film bouncing
through the film substrate and hitting a
part of the film outside of where the
film was and the reason that this
happens is because if you have a lot of
light hitting an area but not all of it
will be absorbed by the film elements if
there's so much photons going through
some of them can scatter out to
neighboring parts of the image and
furthermore inside the lens assembly
light can if there's a lot of light
coming in to a particular place relative
to everything else it can bounce around
elements inside the hood or inside the
lens assembly and hit places it's not
supposed to hit so that's one kind of
halation and that's the kind of relation
that you see maybe up in here where
there's just a little bit of blur out
now there's bigger blurs like like in
here for example right where it's really
blew me and that is going to be a comedy
of the film halation itself here's a
good example there you go right this is
the first kind where it's just the film
itself is is blooming because it's
hitting neighboring parts of the film
but there's another kind which is that
basically light can scatter in the
atmosphere when there's a lot of light
coming in if there's any participating
media it can be scattered there and
that's more a principle of like fog mist
atmospheric particles that are
scattering the light before it ever
reaches the lens of the camera both of
these things you could simulate in a ray
tracer to varying degrees and it depends
on how you want to do them right but
both of them are simulated because you
can just do exactly these phenomenon you
don't even have to hack that hack them
if you're willing to just do them
directly you can actually simulate the
potential for something to bounce around
inside the Lema lens assembly you can
simulate the effect of something
bouncing in the film substrate layer and
you can even simulate participating
medium by storing those volumes and
introducing random ray permutation
inside the volume so all three of them
are things you could simulate they're
all fairly advanced right that's when
you're starting to get into like a
pretty physical light simulator you can
also of course choose this you can use
this a ray tracer can do the same tricks
that an on that a rasterizer can do so
if you don't really care about accurate
simulation and you're just looking to
get that effect for cheap you can just
use a post-processing filter that's what
games do and all they do is they take
the final rendered image and they
threshold it to see if stuff is very
bright they just blur it out into the
neighboring pixels and there's not much
more to it than that
right so you can also use the cheese way
and for an effect like this the cheese
way may be fine because there's not a
lot of really important stuff that
happens in halation that you want to
capture if you're trying to do
participating media that's a harder
thing that is less easy to
she's period its lessee these cheese in
a ray tracer and Anna rasterizer a ray
tracer has a bit of an advantage in
terms of reproducing it accurately
because it can just actually do random
rate permutation and yeah it costs a lot
to do that though it which once you're
doing it you're fine
and so I guess what I would say is
that's kind of a six of one half dozen
of the other sort of situation there
anyway let me take a quick look before I
end here by the way I wanted to see if
we should do a capture here so we're
actually a little bit faster even even
though we were much faster and we slowed
ourselves down a little bit so I am
going to go ahead and do a array cast
here for posterity while we're waiting
uh wait first a image second day image
but haven't we done three separate days
shouldn't this be second day image third
day image and anyway it's the 18th
regardless this is the fourth day right
am I missing something
what's going on here
handmade hero zero handmade parameter a1
oh there's no o2 we've said it wrong we
said it wrong oh well let's do it that
way and I'll fix those in a second my
bad sorry sorry everyone just a slight
error there just we'll rename this no
one will be any the wiser anyway so
that's what bloom is hopefully that
helps is the Halton to three secrets a
good way to generate sales positions
I've heard about some people using it is
a low discrepancy series yes so I am not
really an expert on sampling patterns
blue noise and blue noise based sampling
patterns tend to be the correct ways to
generate sample positions in terms of
what is most pleasing to your eye at the
end the Halton series does sort of try
to approximate a blue noise pattern but
it's not as good as blue noise I don't
know you'd have to ask a more
ray-tracing sort of person if it's good
enough right and also depending you know
the the youth scenario may determine
what is good enough and what is not good
enough right let me just take a quick
look here I want to see what these two
things say are these similar I just
wanna see if they're symbol or numbers
yeah yeah there
so I'm going to change the way these are
written here so this is going to be day
zero it's going to be day one
and then this will be zero - all right
so we've got three images here that are
all about the same and I think by the
time we finished tomorrow and that will
be four days of handmade ray we will
have it quite zippy which is nice and
then really we could do a bounding
volume hierarchy and try to push the
sphere count up really high or we could
go down the accurate light range of
things and so yeah we'll see all right
when you learn this way
oh sorry when you learn this way of
doing Cindy I remember in handmade here
when we had optimized to render we use
mm 28 every way so you can do them
either way and so it depends on to the
it's not really a learn this way or not
learn this way it's just a choice about
which one you want to do we did both in
handmade here Oh actually if you
remember and handmade here we've got
this one right and this is all using the
exact same technique that I just did
where you sort of have a type and that
type is a four wide thing right but the
reason you'd use one of the other is if
you've already got a function that you
know exactly how it works like we did in
handmade here where we had a renderer
and like this is a flow needs to do then
I usually just hand code it with MMS the
reason is because the compiler sometimes
does stupid stuff with overloaded
operators if I have a function that
we're gonna evolve over time then I use
the overloaded operator method and the
reason that I do it that way is because
I don't want to lock it down to a bunch
of mm operations until I actually
know exactly what those operations are
because otherwise I'm just wasting my
time
what is your take on anti-aliasing
methods I'm currently looking for one
for my game I see the witness has
multisample and I see a Lee multisample
antis anti-aliasing option only
no FX AAA or TxAA I don't have a strong
opinion on it honestly I just don't have
a lot of experience with those methods
are there any machines with hardware
random number generators that just puts
random values into register with one
instruction yeah x64 actually has one
and we may very well use it for the
initial seed as far as I know there are
no really fast ones though let's yeah so
463 clocks cycles down to 117 clock
cycles so rise in 1200 clock cycles or
2500 clock cycles so you can see they're
slow right so I wouldn't necessarily
call this on anything that you like I
think of as a replacement for a R and a
quick R and because you can do like that
X star shift is gonna be a lot less
cycles lecture system like 10 or 15 16
cycles something like that very low and
so this is gonna be way more expensive
but the Rd R &amp; R already seen part of it
we could use that to see the random
a generator for each work group that
would be a good use of it right so you
know that's that's what I would
recommend and we could easily do that
the question is do we really care enough
to bother and then it's dependent on our
dear Ann's and Bob what we could write
and it would be fine
sudonym 73 it's good to see you
pseudonym 73 I think with our new stream
time we never get see you again that's
good to see you good day a long time in
a stream low discrepancy singers do
exhibit blue noise behaviors you do them
right yeah like I mean that's my
understanding anyway was that that's
what you were low discrepancy sequences
we're trying to basically approach blue
noise but you know I don't know how good
they actually are but their main
advantage he says is that you can access
the quasi random streams in an arbitrary
order not really relevant yet also you
can do better than 2/3 halting yeah like
so for progressive progressive
refinement is kind of probably where
they are most useful in that way right
well you can kind of go like okay I
could just kind of yeah I mean the way
we're doing the rate is right now I
don't know that we care too much about
that stuff but in theory we might just
shade our languages expose things like
conditional assign it's actually more
that they already just do it
automatically so if you take a look at
the way that I wrote this right
conditional assign is what a shader
normally does so in say in GLSL and you
do a equals B in GLSL that's already
conditional assign Lane mask is you know
in the shader you'll do something like
if a is less than B a equals B that's
actually in the shader compiler directly
translated into this
so they're all like the entire shader
thing is all conditional science there's
really no such thing as an unconditional
assign in the shader really I mean sort
of there is in the sense that if you
haven't done any predication yet then it
doesn't need to be conditional but
they're all mask masked laying
operations because shaders always
operate and wide
they're usually 16 wide or 32 wide so
you're never in a situation where you're
performing an assignment that is not
masked per Lane if that makes sense
all right no more cues so I will go
ahead and shut down make sure that was
okay okay right yeah and this all got
set properly looks like right everything
happy there
yeah
sweet let's kind of finish build is set
to optimize till right everything's
right here alright let's just wait for
that terminate rather than killing it no
real reason to kill it there we go and
delete test bitmap since we don't you
know there's our output for the day and
it's all good thank you for joining me
for another episode of handmade ray
today and thank you for testing the
stream I'm gonna end the stream now and
I'm gonna go just after I stop the
recording I'm gonna go talk to the folks
to make sure there were no bugs in the
video but thanks for joining me if you
want to follow along with handmade ray
actually you can preorder handmade hero
handmade ray the source code here it
comes with handmade hero and it's
updated anytime I update handmade hero
so this weekend there won't be an update
to handmade ray but next weekend went up
to hammer here oh all the source code
will get pushed at that time so that's
about it I hope you've enjoyed it until
then have until tomorrow when we'll
finish up that optimization have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the
Internet take it easy everybody