hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show we could a complete game
live on stream yesterday we were in the
process of fixing some bugs just like
bugs that we have on our bug list that I
thought it would be a good time to
finish sort of cleaning those up and I
would like to keep on doing that because
we've got a few more issues on the
issues list that I think are things that
are worth cleaning up now they're kind
of small isolated things that kind of
makes sense I don't like leaving bugs in
the code in fact on handmade hero I
actually am fairly pat usually quite a
bit past my comfort level on that
because typically when I programming I
really don't leave bugs and code at all
but on handmade hero I kind of try to
bundle things up and so go to you know I
try not to jump all around more than I
already have to to just show reasonable
game programming happen so I'd like to
kind of go through these and just get
rid of some more of them that are pretty
reason to get through you know we don't
have a huge bug list or anything but you
know there's plenty things on here that
just really you know probably should be
taken care of so let's go ahead and and
dive in on those today is day 3 23 so if
you're trying to follow along at home
you want to do day 322 source code
that's what you want to start with
because that's what I'm starting with
here on day 3 23 so let's take a look
inside the ye olde project here get it
going just get it on going and hello
hello a visual studio wake up okay and
so my understanding was although we did
a bunch of debugging yesterday there is
one thing that I think we didn't finish
a Kim the guy who maintains I think the
sdl port right now was saying that we
didn't handle the the walking up the
stairs case he was saying correctly when
the aspect ratio changes so you can see
there the the walking up the stairs case
was handled properly in this case so now
let's go ahead and change the aspect
ratio and just see what happens right
and let's go ahead here you know I
you know what I shouldn't be thinking in
my head this is this is the stream I
think out that I'll think out loud later
anyway point being so in theory if we
change the aspect ratio there's
something that we're doing wrong here
with respect yeah and you can kind of
see it doing a pretty crazy flip their
right so we've got some some work to do
here we're definitely not setting up our
render targets the way that we need to
set up our render targets let's double
check to see what happens if we do that
in the software render because I don't
know for broken in both or just one in
this case I assume that we're only
broken in yeah we're so we're only
broken in the hardware renderer which is
what we would expect so let's go take a
look at what's going on in the the
hardware renderer path for that blending
and see if we can't clean that up first
I don't know I don't know if that bug is
actually on here that might not be on
here so this this may just be an on this
is just a bug that's that's not listed I
guess yeah so so this isn't this is not
in there I guess yes I'm just looking
right at it and missing it so anyway in
here we we know what case we're talking
about right so at least there's no
mystery here we know we're talking about
the render entity blend render target
case and we don't necessarily know
exactly what's failing because there's a
number of things that are based like
that are sort of go into making this
work correctly but one thing that I
would point out kind of obviously is
that the the GL viewport is not working
correctly right like I'll just point out
here when I start going up these stairs
here oh well I'm in nevermind i'm
already in the software nurse that's why
I mean the harbor ridge that's fine when
I start going up the stairs you can see
that it pops down to the bottom right
during that transition and so what that
means is is the actual base drawing is
able to draw sort of outside of
where the the viewport region should
even be and I don't have any idea how
that's happening exactly because in
theory that should that when we do our
bind render target right we're doing our
mess our mind frame buffer we're setting
up the viewport and the scissor region
very specifically there now I guess one
thing that I didn't think of is this
scissor here for the clip wrecked I
guess maybe one thing that we're we're
messing up there is our scissor is the
scissor relative to the viewport or is
this is ur not relatively report because
the scissor isn't relative to the
viewport then we would have to take into
account the draw region correctly when
we set up the scissor so that I don't
think would cause the problem that we're
seeing but I do because we're I it's
actually moved down so that's a separate
thing but I do want to just look up GL
scissor on Doc's GL so that I can verify
to myself that those are being called
prepped properly let's see runs erectile
in window coordinates the first two
arguments X and Y so it's a lower left
grandmas with and high space for the
width of hide the box so window
coordinates are those related to the
viewport or not I wish they defined
their terms were clearly in the docs you
always end up having to go look back at
the spec and stop to figure out what
they mean for window coordinates right
is that in the viewport space or that
outside the viewport space I have no
idea right but anyway what's the window
coordinates have integer values at the
shared corners of frame buffer pixels a
last modification of only the lower left
pixel in the window so that that sounds
like you know if i had to guess the
scissor rectangle and the viewport
rectangle are separate so i can set my
viewport and my scissor separately and
they both are in window coordinates
which means that this scissor should
technically be done in the end up buying
frame buffer call or rather I should say
in the space of the frame buffer
right so we really I'm sorry in the
space of the the draw region right so I
think technically what we want to do
here is say that whatever the draw
region was if that if we're in our if
we're in the target 0 we need to
actually you know sort of unify those
clipping rectangles right so we want to
do something like a rectangle like clip
wrecked equals intersection or I guess
is not even intersection it's really
just an offset because we know that the
clip wrecked fits inside the draw region
so it's really just like I need to
offset the clip wrecked by that by that
amount right and I think we might even
have a way to do that right yeah so we
can just say the clip wrecked is an
offset of the clip wrecked right by the
minimum corner of the draw region
because I need to move that clip wrecked
get up in that case so what I could do
here just say well the clip wrecked is
either equal to itself in the case where
the where the render target index
whatever that render target index is
right let's go ahead and get that out
there I or even better this way this
will work in both cases I'll say assume
that's the clip wrecked and then if
we're going to this is kind of a
complicated it because I need to make
sure we work here so I really need to
say if we have a valid render target
index here at right assuming that that's
true at all
wait do I need to do that now I don't
need to do that I take it back
so I guess now that I think about it
there's a couple things that we really
doing here quite right so when we do the
use render targets thing and we do the
if the render target is greater than so
we kind of need I'm just trying to
figure how to handle both those cases
the clip breck things fairly simple
right I can set the clip wrecked and
normally we would just use that clip
wrecked if we didn't have the sort of
problem with with with handling aspect
ratios and all that sort of stuff so
what we need to do is if we know we're
in the space of one of those separate
render targets which therefore doesn't
need to use like the whole screen it's
it's sort of our contained one then we
can just use the clip wrecked directly
but if we aren't doing that then we need
to make sure that we use the sort of
normal space of the clip wrecked and so
what I need to do is say you know if we
are using the render targets right or i
should say if we're not using the render
targets we know we always have to offset
or if we are using the render targets
and the render target index in this case
equals zero in both those cases then i
need to actually make the clip rekt
equal the offset of itself with wherever
the draw region is right and then
regardless of what i do i always do want
to set the scissor right so i think
that's the more correct thing to do
there I don't know whether they're
rectangle two eyes or not yeah they are
so I think that's right and let me look
at rectangle too I hear oops too I so
here we got a bunch of random stuff I'm
going to say that we've got a in line
and I don't know if we have do we have a
v2 I do we have an integer v2 I we don't
really do we we just have regular v2s I
don't think we ever actually talk about
v2 eyes yeah all right then I won't do
that I'll just say like okay when we do
the offset of the flip wrecked
I'm interested to know if get mean how
are we calling offset on a rectangle to
I if we didn't define offset of a
rectangle to I do we somewhere we only
have rectangle to and rectangle three I
guess it just never finished compiling
this thing there we go so it just
couldn't resolve the function
overloading so I was like that seems
really weird okay so if I have rectangle
2i and I want to do an offset call to it
which is what I would like to do here I
can just say like all right I've got an
offset call rectangle 2i and then a SI 2
x 3 2 y and so the result is just equal
to whatever we pass in and then all of
the values right just get added to right
so in this case we've got the draw
region in X and the draw region min Y
and that should give us the actual clip
region that we need so i think that's
correct I think that is is the correct
way to look at the clip region that we
weren't sort of specifying correctly
before and now in theory we are I think
and of course the slight problem with
that is that's going to persist so what
we also need to do I suppose is when we
do our initial clear we would have to
set our scissor correctly as well if
that makes sense so when we do our clear
we have to do sort of a scissor that
allows us to clear the entire region
whatever that is and so I'm not sure
what the easiest way to do that is with
out necessarily knowing what it is so I
think we may have to just kind of bite
the bullet here and say yeah we have to
clear the whole region and in order to
clear the whole region we have to know
the size now what we could do is set the
scissor wider than the window or
something like that too I don't know but
in order to clear everything what we
could do is is is literally just do the
check if it's greater than 0 and C right
so we could say here you know something
like this if the target index is 0 then
we know that we need a frame buffer
that's got the sort of the window width
if you will so you know get with draw
region good height well actually
snotting the drow region it's it's
bigger than the draw region so I guess I
don't know that we even pass that value
down here unfortunately and I suppose we
will have to so we'll probably have to
actually do window with window height
and those are different from the drawer
region if that makes sense let me take a
look at where we use window within
window height here
yeah uh so we and I don't know if all we
use it for is that too I don't know it
seems like if we are trying to do a
particular render size to its feels to
me like these could also just be like
how are we setting our viewport up here
when we set our viewport we set our
viewport based on whatever the size of
these guys actually is so you know if
the target in does grades are we sit so
we are sort of saying let's pretend it's
always the draw region so I guess that's
okay I guess I'm okay with that
and so when we actually go to clear
these we want to set the scissor again
to get with the drawer region get height
of the dro region for these but in order
to clear the whole thing we want to
clear the window size which means when
we actually call this we need to
actually know how big the actual window
is which again we don't really know so
we have to kind of pass this we used to
pass it and then we stopped passing it
it makes me think we want to probably
bundle these because you can see how
they kind of have to cascade down a
little bit like that which I don't love
but you know for now I'm just going to
do the simplest thing until I'm
absolutely sure back that makes sense so
yeah so let's see here I think this is
dimension right let's see yeah so
dimension width and dimension height
should probably just take whatever that
is and pass it down but cannot convert 5
from memory into you 32 * what happened
all right it's right there okay so let's
see here now I reset the scissor anytime
we clear so in theory we should always
clear the entire back buffer which we
are now right because that scissor one
of the problems with OpenGL in the way
that it you know kind of is when you use
the original kinda sits very stateful so
that scissor rectangle that we set will
persist to the next frame and that's why
we were getting some clearing bugs is
because it's whatever the scissor was
the last time through is what the clear
would pick up and you definitely don't
want that right okay so at least we're
setting the scissor now more correctly
which means and now I am getting exactly
what I expected this was the part that I
was trying to fix first now we cannot
draw down here which is what I was like
I didn't like the fact or do I'm like
we're not setting our scissor regions
properly and like now I think we are
right so we fixed that but we still have
one other problem which is that when
we're doing
the split but you can see that the the
actual screen it's part portion of the
actual original drawing is getting
offset downward so it's like it's offset
is incorrect now and so i'm not sure why
we're getting that effect and so we kind
of need to figure out where that's
coming from as well so let's take a look
here in handmade open jail i I'm not one
hundred percent certain how that
displacement would happen because my
feeling is it probably has nothing to do
with this operation meaning I think we
could probably just not do this at all
and still get the problem happening I
because it would have to be something
about setting up the viewport on target
zero in light of that is when is what
has to be happening I think and the
reason I think that is just because I
otherwise how would it get shifted down
because that that operation just alpha
blends something over the top that
shouldn't be sufficient yeah and you can
see it happen there right so it has
nothing to do with this fact I think all
it is is when you are toggling between
those something's wrong with our bind
call so when we do our opengl buying
frame buffer we're not like properly
setting that up i guess right something
is getting set wrong i'm not sure
exactly what that's causing that sort of
jump to occur there so yeah so i'm going
to take a quick look and see what's
happening in the the bind call to see if
i can get any sort of idea about why
that would be happening
I mean you can see that when we bind a
target that's not zero we're going to
make the viewport be the whole size but
when we bind a target that is zero we it
looks like we're doing the proper sort
of min x-men why from the draw region so
i'm not sure why we would be getting why
would be getting that but getting that
we appear to be so yeah i guess one
thing that i ah that's the problem we
also have our transform here i wonder if
our transform is a problem because the
transform has the width and the height
in it now but that wouldn't cause an
offset so what width and height are we
using we're using the width and the
height now that's that should be okay
so here's something that vaguely tickles
my memory so here's one thing that I
would like to try I'm going to move this
opengl screen space call down here so
that we set the matrix every time
through just because i want to see what
happens of course i have to actually hit
my jump alright so good now let's try
this one
alright so still getting the offset
there I feel like there was some thing
that I'm vaguely remembering about
OpenGL we're like the view port and the
scissor or for the perspective matrix
are somehow dependent on each other in
some way that's not obvious I sort of
getting that vague like thing in the
back of my mind hopefully that's not
what's happening here but I'm just I'm
little bit nervous about that okay so
the first question i guess i have is
maybe do we know that our viewport is
being set correctly like maybe i'm just
straight up setting it wrong because it
looks like what's happening is the
viewport is not getting reset when we
switch back to target zero right that's
what it looks like is happening because
we would get the results that we're
seeing that that's exactly what we would
get if the if the viewport was only
changed on if if the if the viewport was
only doing this right and didn't get set
back to this that is exactly what we
would get right so I'm curious to know
how that's happening like why we're not
seeing it gets reset and I suppose I can
verify that I mean not really verify it
i suppose but i can at least test that
by never doing that other view view port
call yeah and then we can verify that
you know the other ones wrong obviously
but ours is not so that's good so it
looks like we're calling that one and
then either we're not calling the other
one and should like maybes for some
reason this call isn't happening which I
don't know why or this call is not
having the effect that the call should
actually have right and i'm not sure why
it wouldn't especially because this is
the call that we actually are calling
right every time right so we call that
for each clear and then we call that to
set up you know this is the call that we
use to set up the frame buffer so i'm
not sure why we would ever why having
its flip like that would ever cause us
to you know why having a second one
makes that occur
I don't know ah but maybe I do so we
would never call it a second time in
here we'd never call it in here right
see that's the thing we would never call
it even one time yeah so maybe we just
have it straight up wrong so here is
OpenGL buying frame buffer right and I'm
going to force it through that's the
thing as we weren't we weren't calling
the right path we were calling this Pat
but we were we had a set of spurious
call there so let's see what happens if
I just do it here
well now that looks that looks right
okay it looks that fixed the bug so just
the fact that we had to bind it it was
using the viewport from the last time
around wasn't it we just were never it's
the same exact bug as the scissor bone
right it was calling GL viewport and
never it was never initializing the call
to GL viewport right because before you
saw what happened there right before I
was only setting the target frame buffer
and I was assuming that we had set the
the viewport up here but we never did
because I took I took that out with the
new viewport setting thing so this would
never actually happen otherwise so you
know what I should do I should take a
page from the PlayBook that we had up
here and say look we've got a current
frame buffer thing happening right and
we're sort of tracking that that current
frame buffer situation and it's and I
guess it's not really current frame
buffer it's like current render target
index we should set it to a bogus value
and we should just that way we know
we're always going through the same path
instead of two different possible paths
based on whether we hit this one or the
one above it right so I want to do that
that way it's all nicely self-contained
and we know that we're always going
through the same path so that's what was
happening we worked on the wraparound
the next time we would draw a frame it
was still using whatever the viewport
was from the last frame now if you never
had more than one viewport well then you
wouldn't have a problem right because
you never have to worry about setting it
to the wrong one and then using it right
on the next train but we didn't have we
once we hit the situation where we had
more than one viewport it was just going
to be wrong okay so i think that's
that's all better like I said that one
wasn't on the issues list but someone I
think Kim had mentioned it so that's
good all right so let's try wrong pitch
probably would have been never has
problem to a president retires for
blender to the pitch to advance a source
has been assigned the value of the fish
need to advances so this was looks like
a typo and they're talking about in here
where we do is the source ray advanced
yeah okay so you can see it here it
would just like some copypasta there
we've got the desk target pitch should
have been the source target pitch right
so I assume that that is the only thing
that they were talking about in that bug
and that wasn't causing a problem
because hey all of the render targets
have the same pitch so technically you
really don't need a multiple pitches but
just in case they ever did it would have
been wrong so at least now we've got
that it's a bug that we don't have to
solve later right so let me try hopping
up the stairs here let's see here
all right um so yeah so we'll try that
and switch back to the issues so let's
see uh what else we got here let's see
so we got a bunch of OpenGL like stuff
here so let's see are from iffy Swiss
check also apparently some cars foot
experience for our from the interview we
fix the typo and we check for the
extension but we couldn't find an
arbiter so we're not to do about that
Minnesota version so this got reopened
here there is no ARB texture srgb
exception because s true beauty textures
move directly the core from ex extension
so determine support for SOA retextures
you need to check if the ex isn't
present or if the OpenGL version is
greater than or equal to 2.1 you know I
really wish people took API design more
seriously I mean really guys really do
you really think this was a good idea
all right so all right so let's go take
a look at that uh now I don't even know
how to check the core version I think
you have to look at what the vendor
version string thing comes back let's
take a look in here where's my info call
yeah so when we get the version
here I I mean are we supposed to parse
the version string is that really is
that really a good idea I mean I guess
we could look and see if the first part
of string is you know higher than to
higher than or equal to 2 and if it's
you know only equal to 2 then we'd have
to look at the point to see if it was
point one that just seems crazy
I mean I don't know what else to do you
know I I don't know if there's an open
gel way to get let me see if there's a
get integer V for it because I'd rather
not have a parser in here just to
determine their like a GL get here it is
yeah so is there like a version in the
GL get into juvie like somewhere version
okay whoo I was a little nervous there
all right uh so at least we could say
after we do this we could say okay you
know GL get integer with GL major
version get into Giorgio minor version
and we could then do some testing on
those that's at least something so let's
go ahead and see get integer V and we
are going to go ahead and pass chillin
major you know and minor will assume one
point 0 because I think windows always
has at least that and so will do the get
integer fees on those and then we can
say all right if the major version is
greater than or equal to 3 right or the
major version equals 2 and the minor
version is greater than or equal to 1 I
guess that's what Martin's was saying is
the is
magic so if we're basically greater than
open Jill you know I guess I could say
it this way to make a little more
current if we're higher than version 2
or we're on version 2.1 right or better
then we know that we have our srgb
textures right so I think that's right
but we'll take a look undeclared
identified GL major version in jail
minor version okay
let me grab that for you so let me step
into that and see what happens here so
we come through here we're going to hit
this we got a major of three and a minor
of zero so that's fine we go ahead and
look here at me say okay the major is
greater than two in this case so we're
going to do this we don't care but
otherwise we would have looked to see if
the major is equal to or the minor was
greater than equal to one right so I
think that's right and then we'll we'll
consider that set but that wasn't the
only thing in this bug assuming that we
got that right so we've got the wiggle
version of the frame buffer extension
has the same problem needs to check our
professor be as well as xed okay so
let's take a look at what's happening in
that one so in win32 handmade we have
srgb let's take a look at that so in
here we've got wiggle through the ARB
framebuffer srgb so it's it's just the
same exact name looks like alright so in
theory we have fixed those and by fixed
as I mean sort of like provisionally fix
them because the people who raided them
laugh to test since we don't really know
if they're broken or not right we're
just sort of hypothesizing that we fix
them but we don't know okay so
so we'll let that be reopened by anyone
who can actually test it for us if it
fight if they find that that's still not
actually doing the checks properly all
right so let's keep going here check GL
and it fall back I can't find it now but
i believe martins posted a control flow
bug with what happens if the ARB pixel
format choosing fails and so let's take
a look at that
here it is small bug when calling win32
set pixel format in the wind 3d opengl
function it is called only for the
modern context if creating the modern
condo sales this function won't be
called and creating the regular context
will fail so yeah so we want to do that
where we do create context let's see so
we do the create context here and we do
wiggle make current this is the
preliminary context where we try to get
the extensions which is not really what
we're looking for we want the actual
Nick call so we say if we've got it we
set the pixel format and we do a quick
context attribs ARB otherwise we do will
create context here so I'm thinking
win32 set pixel format I don't think we
ever don't want to call it right so I
feel like we could just do that you know
here right I mean there's no reason why
we would do it later I don't think so i
think that would then make sure it
always gets called so I'm that was just
a cut and paste problem where we didn't
do that right so okay I believe that's
fixed
so I'll go ahead and put that in here
all right so that bug is in theory fixed
again in theory because we're not really
testing these these are just kind of
preliminary fixes uh and let's see the
necessary described pixel format
so I was not sure about this one to be
honest with you because I thought you
did need to do it but maybe you don't
and so let's see here in described pixel
format when we pass that suggested pixel
format the suggestion was that you could
just not do that right that you could
essentially just pass garbage right and
do this and I don't know whether that's
true or not I'm a little nervous about
it to be honest because I don't know if
if it always is really completely
superfluous so to be honest I think I
might just leave it in there I don't
know maybe I shouldn't let's see I mean
I guess another question is can you just
pass 0 like can you do that
apparently you can so is that an
optional parameter of set pixel format
basically at least on this card
so it's not technically defined as an
optional parameter but it is apparently
only used in a very specific not a case
that is not related to ours right so you
know what I'm going to say though for
completeness that we should just leave
it this way because just because it
doesn't have any effect it's not
technically an optional parameter so i
think i'm going to resolve won't fix
that one so i'll make a note of it but i
think i'm going to leave that in because
i don't see a real reason not to
so I'm just going to close that one as
basically like I'm not going to fix it
okay let's go back to the issues list
getting smaller so we've got not going
to touch that one cuz that's going to
take a while so that'll have to be a
separate one let's take a look at some
of these other ones so use render
targets we still call the writer target
stuff so what I'm going to actually test
that one so that we can actually get
some crashes and make sure that we've
got it so this is basically when we
don't have render targets right so I'm
going to go ahead and take a look at
will get proc address here there it is
so what I'm going to do is I'm just
going to assume temporarily that we
don't have GL ARB frame buffer object in
fact I guess I can do that here
so now in theory we should just crash
because we're not obey we're not
actually doing that check we should just
jump to an invalid location or something
right and yeah and we do so here where
we try to call Geo frame buffers we just
jump into no-man's land so let's go
ahead and now try to make it so that we
do run properly or at least as close
properly as you can without those render
targets and let's take a look at how
that that would go so here we are with
use render targets in use render targets
we wait Matt refer again so you're going
to targets command red mesh or one if
the max render target index is greater
than or equal to the global frame buffer
count how did we get in here
because the global frame buffer count oh
but it's greater than or equal to so the
max render target II index should have
really been zero that's what actually
should be happening there right so yeah
so that's much better okay so I think
then we just have to deal with the bind
frame buffer call Joe buying frame
buffer and in vine frame buffer I guess
we're just going to say well the target
index you know if GL bind frame buffer
chardon x equals zero so we'll just
always force it to render to target zero
in these cases I guess however we do we
may want to just not like you know we
may want to throw away all rendering
that isn't because like weeks since we
can't support it i'm thinking maybe what
we do is say if we r you know going to
do GL buying frame buffer if we can do
it will set the viewport to this if we
can't do it will set the viewport to
like nothing you know I don't know
that's not that compelling either to me
to be honest
I'm not sure what the best way to handle
this is I guess we can handle it
explicitly here by saying if we're using
render targets then we will do the open
jail by and frame buffer there and that
would be fine and then down here when we
would would be doing an opengl buying
frame buffer I guess what we actually
want to do here is say you know if we're
try for actually trying to do is render
targets then we want to bind the frame
buffer otherwise we want to actually
kill this guy if he's trying to draw to
something other than the one that he
needs to draw to write so you know I
guess what I would say is we'd want to
say we'd want to enclose this whole
thing order to issue a continued
basically right we'd want to say you
know don't do whatever it is that you're
about to do if this guy's render target
index is would it be would have been
invalid another way I guess to look at
it would be to actually put it up here
right so we would say you know if
whatever this guy's render target index
actually is I guess we only really pull
it out in this case
and we really don't want to access it
every time probably yeah this is just a
little janky so I mean I guess
I mean I guess the part is I don't
really want to have to do this this is
what the code would suggest that I do is
basically look at whatever the clip
rectangle is that we're getting whatever
the clip bricked is that we're getting
if it's render target index is in range
then we're okay right and so I don't
super love that but I think that's like
roughly correct at least in theory and
then I guess yeah at the end the global
blind frame buffers have to be
predicated on that and then that may be
it and so now you know it's a it's a
really graceful fall back to I guess you
know that that it just pops in now if we
don't have multiple render targets so I
feel like that's okay I don't know if
that's the most efficient way to do this
so what I might say to hear is like well
you know we could say you know assert
clip render target index is less than
equal to maximum target index certainly
but in this case we could say if we're
going to use render targets or right so
essentially saying like hey if we know
that we're in render target mode they
just assume that these that you should
process this so that we won't check
every time if we don't have to I don't
know
so I think that's okay oops and in
theory that should now work correctly in
both cases but let's make sure yeah okay
so I think that's all for that one I do
want to check since we were monkeying
with the blind calls there I do want to
check to make sure that it's not that I
do want to check to make sure that this
guy works okay
and he does appear to so that seems good
all right all right so i think that's
good
what else do we have four issues so
asynchronous textures download we're not
going to do today for sure I really got
what like two minutes left I think so
but we might be able to look at this one
pack entity into chunk list so that
might be good and I think that's the
only one that's really a short one so
let's take a look at that one mocks from
the forums the linked list doesn't
change I believe the pack edited to trim
function is bugging at the code it
creates the first block of Chuck will
also be called there's no room left at
that point the new block should chain
the old block but this is not done this
reference for that remembering it I
think it should become this or something
like that hopefully this will prevent
any future problems so let's take a look
at that that's pack entity a chunk
alright so here is the part they were
talking about first free block is this
one I believe right yeah so he's talking
about this right here and so let's take
a look at what this is doing we've got
if there is no first block or there is
no room right so we have either the case
where we have an allocated a chunk at
all or there isn't any room in this
particular chunk for whatever it is that
we're trying to pack into it then we
look to see if there isn't a first free
block available then we create one on
the free store which seems totally fine
right because now we've just got one
sitting there we take the first block
yeah and we immediately clobber it which
is not good right that is not what we
wanted to do so what we want to do there
is something more like we want to kind
of push that down if there was one there
so we want to do like chunk first block
next I don't even know this doesn't look
this whole thing doesn't really look all
that right to me but anyway so the the
chunking in question here right I'm
sorry the block there's basically you
know there's a new block so look take
that and it's going to be a world-first
free block right so let's just name
these what they're actually to be so
this is the new block that we're going
to use and then world first free block
is just going to be whatever the the
next thing was after that so that just
pops it off of the free list right and
we're saying that there has to be one
because we always allocate a new one all
right so that's all fine and then what
we need to do is we need to actually set
a chunk first block to something Val
it so chunk first block is going to
become whatever the new block is right
but we want to remember whatever the new
block actually we want to remember
whatever is supposed to come after that
block right so we want to take whatever
the first block was and chain that on to
the end of us before we set ourselves as
the new head pointer I think that's
really probably all we needed there I
don't know if that's similar to what he
was suggesting yes but he he did it a
slightly different way but yes basically
so I think that's it and we don't have
much a way of testing that right now
because we don't stress test the entity
occupancy system at all we haven't
really done much with that all right but
I believe that's okay oops
okay so let me just take a quick gander
back of that just to make sure that I I
believe that was a reasonable fix again
we grab the new block off of the first
of the free block list and we advance
the free block point or forwards one we
then say that whatever the first block
is for this chunk we make that our next
pointer and then we make ourselves words
yes so I think that's pretty reasonable
we then clear that block which seems
fine all right so let's go ahead and go
to the QA I think we're done with most
of these
so that's pretty good we're down to not
too many more issues this is not really
an issue right but yeah all the rest of
them are and this one is these two are
basically project things so really it's
this one this one in this one are the
three that we actually have to do
snoring tortoise not sure what the
minimum open Jill version the games for
its but according to https open Jill org
wiki get contacts info the GL major
version jilla minders are only available
in OpenGL 3.1 above oh well that means
we will have to parse then I guess which
sounds awful
I mean that just seems really
error-prone because we don't even know
what the format of that string is right
we have an example of what it is
but if we're not going to do that right
then we would have to actually do like a
you know
it's the name of the what's the version
here let's see result that version so we
have to do something like if at zero
equals dot you know major at equals
minor at equals and something like this
so we could do something well actually
you know what I probably do so we could
say like okay if we found that then we
would basically just say like okay the
dot is a is here and the minor at is you
know one pass here and we break and then
we just say well if we found the minor
at you know I don't know what we'd say
something like the major version the
minor version we assume or one in zero
or something assuming that we found the
minor at we'd say major equals parse you
know opengl parse number a major at and
then we'd say something like the minor
version minor at like that and then we'd
need a little thing here that parses an
integer can't believe anyone ever
thought this was an okay thing to have
in an API but i don't even want to know
and I stopped asking these kind of
questions a long time ago so this is a
like the string
and so then we've got a results right
we're just going to do like a while you
know at is greater than or equal to 0
and star at is less than or equal to 9
we're assuming it's a digit so we're
going to take whatever the result was
and multiply it by 10 right because
we're parsing a string so the first
thing we get is going to see we're going
to read it in and we're going to zoom
it's a digit and then every place we
move over it means that the digits we
saw before hand go up by a power of 10
right so we take whatever our
accumulator x 10 and then we add in
whatever app was right I guess so let's
take a look at that that beautiful piece
of code that shining stellar example
let's go ahead and take a look where's
my open drill there it is I was already
in it well there you go
alright so we're coming here and let's
see if we correctly identified our major
at minor at we did so that's good I
don't know why I guess I don't need the
dot so we can pull that out of the code
and I was thinking I might need that but
I guess I don't so assuming that I
actually caught those out oh and you
know might help if you put a plus in
there somewhere folks there we go could
be in that loop a long time but I want
to actually go see what that did there
we go so major and minor here majors 3-0
so I think we're good so there you go
all right um so I guess that's okay
hopefully that that helps thanks for
pointing that out that would explain why
they weren't defined anywhere
let's see so I'm designing a 3d game
engine and want to first write a
software renderer for it to learn more
about renderers do you think I should go
straight for open Jill or suffer render
and thin OpenGL I'm not sure I
understand the question because it seems
like you said in the predicate to the
question that you wanted to write us off
for render so if you want to write us
off for a renderer then you should write
a software renderer I guess is what I
would say
yeah and insofar as I didn't want to use
scanf because it's just going to be
another thing we have to remove when I
when I remove the sea runtime library so
if it's easy enough to write a parser I
just write it
all right I know speaking more questions
so I'm going to wrap it up all right
everyone thank you very much for joining
me for another sort of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coating with you as
always if you would like to follow along
at home you can always go to handmade
here at work and pre-order the game it
comes the source code so that you can
experiment yourself and you know you can
find bugs and report about the issues
page too so I can fix them a bunch of
those were reported by people who play
with a source code we also forum site if
you want to ask questions we have a
patreon page to my support the video
series a schedule bot if you want to
know what we're going to be live and in
past episodes guide or you can go to
catch up on old old stuff we did that's
about it I'll be back here next week
until then and do you wanna know when
check the schedule bot until then have
fun programming this weekend and I'll
see you guys on the internet piggies
everyone