hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we have to go into the
thick of it today we are trying to add
in some light probes to our lighting
system so that we can give it more
control I we're hoping this allows us to
sample the lighting easily for all of
our sprites as well as our 3d geometry
just because lighting probes make it
pretty clear how you can look things up
and so will we want to implement that
stuff in the shader but we also want to
go ahead now and try to get lighting
computed on the probes which is sort of
a separate part of the problem because
right now as we compute lighting Rho is
computing lighting from actual surfaces
in the world and what we want to
secondly do now is sort of flip that on
its head and say well although the
services themselves allow you to bounce
the light around they themselves will
not be actually storing any lighting
information only the probes well and so
we're hoping this allows us to get
better performance out of the system
because we can sort of use these probes
more sparingly as necessary meaning we
can reduce the number of probes that are
in the world arbitrarily without having
to reduce the complexity of the actual
geometry in the world so meaning we can
leave world's the same but we can change
the number of probes and their placement
to suit our time budget we can even do
things like put probes down more densely
on more powerful machines and more
sparsely on less powerful machines
meaning the more powerful machine you
have the more accurate lighting you get
and things like that whereas for as long
as the lighting computation was tied to
the complexity of the geometry of the
world that would never have been
possible because you would have to
actually just make simpler worlds and
that doesn't seem like a very good idea
anyway we got several weekend's worth of
work to do this lighting is pretty
complicated there's a lot of pieces to
it and so it takes a while to get
through but that's what we're doing now
is getting through it so we're gonna go
ahead and jump back in where we left off
last weekend
the basic idea right now is just we need
to get the plumbing under control so we
can put all of the light probes that we
want to compute into the lighting system
and then we also then need to switch the
lighting system so that instead of
casting from points that are on the
surfaces of the things we are actually
using for occluders we have to change
that to be casting from the light probes
themselves this also involves another
change which is that previously we were
looking at having cubes and stuff like
this that we have multiple points on
potentially whereas now we're just
talking about look a probe just has six
directions and whichever direction you
sent the Ray out in that's where the
summation will occur so that is sort of
a separate part of the of the process
now if we go let's go ahead and and jump
back let's see here - yeah if we jump
back to the handmade lighting code then
the problem that I was sort of stopped
on well I mean that I was just looking
at I guess is one of the problems we're
gonna have here for doing for computing
our lighting you can see we've got a
routine here that's it's not great but
it's not horrible like we did a little
bit of work to make it decent there's a
hierarchical array caster here that
basically ray casts against boxes and
every time it hits a box it looks to see
if there are children of the box and
open looks inside those right now
previously what we were doing is we were
actually going through and for each
individual box we were that we were
going to actually record a hit we would
look to see which surface was actually
being hit like which one of the
directions of the box and if you look at
what's happening here what we then were
sort of suggesting is well alright so we
hit a point on the box and now we're
gonna have to do this this work and
literally as I was just describing it
I thought of a much simpler solution
just literally as I was literally just
talking but let me describe what we were
trying to do and then I'll say well I
think that was probably pretty stupid
and maybe we shouldn't do that all right
so if you look here at the let's go over
this carefully next time part what we're
trying to do here is say look when we
hit a particular box so again these
boxes just to give you some perspective
about what they are let me actually run
the game and just point to what I mean
by a box right and this is the debug
mode build so it's gonna be slow so when
I say box I mean like one of these
things right so like for example if we
were to what's going on here there we go
so for example if we were to talk about
this box here or you know any of these
things they're sort of like almost like
a Minecraft kind of world construction
right except ours don't have to be cubes
they can be like an arbitrary rectangle
but you know we're just placing these
like blocky things in the world they
also don't have to be on a grid so I
guess it's it's pretty different from
Minecraft I guess but you know what I
mean it's the world is supposed to be
blocky
and so these blocks in the world
we're raycasting against those because
they're what form the super structure
and if we want to if we have a large
enough thing like maybe the hero we can
put a block that we don't actually
render but then we use for lighting we
can put a block where they are if we
want them to sort of cut out a little
bit of the light right and we may or may
not want to do that we can try it and
see if it looks better or worse to have
it in there but point being that's all
blocks are there are lighting primitive
basically they're the thing that catches
our shadows and prevents light from
propagating around and so they are the
things that if I put like a light in
here like there is a light here it will
not be able to like shine into this room
because there's crap in the way right
those blocks will stop it whereas in
here these blocks are all low so the
light can hit like this surface and this
surface just fine okay so that's what
we're talking about here
so either actual world blocks or
synthetic invisible blocks that we add
on top of our sprites to catch light
force for the largest rights that we
want that to happen if we ever do which
we may not but assuming that we do we
would be adding like blocks in there as
a as light catchers effectively so when
we hit one of those blocks we don't
actually care where we hit the block
really for purposes of the shadow all we
know all we needed to know was the light
stopped there and so at the point where
we enter this if statement this if any
true here we actually have the
information we need to finish this is
all we really need is to say look we're
doing four arrays at a time so we have
to make sure we only accept those hits
on the Rays that are ones that we cared
about but other than that we're pretty
much done so this you know these two
parts here are all we really needed to
do but we then when we go to process
that hit like after we do all of our ray
casting we're gonna have four hits for
the four arrays which are the closest
boxes that each of those rates
intersected we then need to hand back to
the calling routine some lighting
because when you hit you're sending out
a you know these are light probes
they're sending out rays to see what the
light looks like around them when they
hit a surface they then need to be able
to say what the lighting was at that
service to contribute back to the light
probe now how do you do that well in a
light probe system the answer is you
have to ask the light probes from like
last frame so whatever your lighting
solution was last frame you use that to
light the services for this frame and
create the new lighting and you
propagate it forward right and so if
we're doing that it means we need to
call when we get that ray cast and we
get that hit back we need to call the
lighting function on the points that we
hit and in order to call the lighting
function on the points that we hit we
would need to know the normals at the
point that we hit and since we don't
know the normal
the point we would hit we need to add
some code to do that now this would have
been one way to do it but it's very
expensive right and the question is
because this was the old code we were
using that actually literally came up
with an index zero one two three four
five right
that said which side of the cube you hit
it's not really a cube there are bright
rectangular prisms because they don't
have to have the same dimensions they
can be arbitrarily like long on each
axis but so call boxes so we don't need
that actual information we don't care
which side of the box that you hit we
just care whether or not we just care if
you can get them normal right and the
problem that we have here is we don't
know how to get that normal without sort
of solving which direction of the box
you had however what I was realizing
when I was talking there right is I
think we might be able to recreate the
normal in sort of a more roundabout way
let's see here we go
and so let's let's talk about that here
because if we can create if we can
recreate it in a more roundabout way we
would potentially be able to save
ourselves some time right okay so let's
see
so we have a axis aligned bounding box
or AABB right it's a thing that we know
you know we've kept it simple for
ourselves and we've said look we know
that in our case we have a coordinate
system and our boxes are always aligned
to the coordinate system so you know
they always look like this sort of a
thing oh that's a really bad box there
we go so we know that they're always
access aligned the Y X and z axes of our
box are always the XY and z axes of the
world now it's not necessarily clear
that we really needed that I mean it's
our heart there's a little more
computation involved if you don't do
that
but at the moment that's what we're
doing and we don't really need to depart
from that at all because rotation in
this case it's not particularly
important for us we don't really
anticipate needing that in the game at
all so what that means is we can use if
there is something we can do with our a
a B B's here if there is something we
can lean on for that during this
algorithm we're you know knowing that
the XY and z axes happen to align with
the world that actually can be used to
our advantage potentially all right so
here's what I'm thinking here's what we
know right we know that for our
intersection we're going to come up with
some point on this a a B that's on the
surface of the a a BB and we already
know that information because we have
the Ray origin right so we have the Ray
origin plus T times the raid erection
right maybe I'll do it like this
so we've got a point that we solve for
here during our intersection we will
know the T these are Givens right but
we're basically solving for the T and
from that T we can get back the P
trivially so we always know this number
which is basically like if this is the
origin of the Ray so this is oh it's
this value and this is the direction of
the Ray that's D that's this value so we
know that that is T I guess I should say
D is like the unit vector this way right
we know this distance is T and so we
know that o plus TD is P that's trivial
compute it's just a mad F mad right and
so we can get all of this stuff for free
because just the act of doing the
intersection testing always gives us
this and so the question would be what
can we do what's the simplest possible
thing we could do to get the normal back
given that we know that answer right so
for a given box we know what the center
of the box is and we know what the
radius of the box is right so how far it
is from the center to each side I
believe that's the structure that we're
using right now as opposed to like mini
quarter max corner although I believe
we've already computed them in quarter
in the max corner yeah so you can see
that happening here it does raise the
question of whether we actually would
rather since we have to compute it every
time it does kind of beg the question or
I say suggests the question that maybe
what we should be doing there is maybe
we should be just storing box wing box
max but I don't know as you can see here
we have to like do this every time why
not just do that why not just store box
um in the box Max and I don't really
know why so I might say here to do
KC should we just be storing box men
smacks instead of computing them is
there any real reason to use the radii
the center radius form so you know
that's sort of separate issue but not a
huge impact to time I mean all we're
doing is one subtract one AD per box
check which you know it's not going to
give us the masses food-based boost but
the point is why do something you don't
have to so we should at least check that
for due diligence anyway so we could
really think about having either of this
the two things because we know that our
collision routine currently needs sort
of a min/max anyway right and so we you
know we don't really need to overthink
that so once we get our sort of position
here there's a lot of ways that we could
try to create the lighting normal there
right so if we want to use a completely
flat normal maybe we have to do a little
bit more work but what we could say is
what if we just pretended that this
thing was a sphere right so instead of
or an ellipsoid instead of saying well
you know it's a box what if we just said
that it was a sort of an ellipsoid sort
of a thing right and if we knew a point
on the ellipsoid that we hit right so if
we've done the same thing for the
ellipsoid or the sphere well we wouldn't
really be sitting around stressing about
what the normal was would we because we
would know that the normal is always
going to be just the direction of the
hit from the center right so meaning
whatever the center actually itself is
we would just take P minus the center
that is the direction of the normal
right so this is kind of like our you
know our direction well that the
I use that for a direction solo tile
this is the normal direction and then
the unit length normal would just be
that normalized right so we could pretty
trivially find the normal for a sphere
based version without doing any fancy
work so the question here is will can we
just do the same thing for our box so if
we wanted our normals to be smooth well
we just do that right if we just
actually even even if the box is per to
be particularly weirdly shaped I think
this probably would still work right
meaning let's suppose you were gonna
kind of reach up to that point there
right it's still completely smooth the
whole way around right so when you get
to here you're pointing off that
direction and you get to here you're
pointing off that direction right and so
subtracting from the center just put
we'll put sphere-like normals onto our
box which let's be honest because this
delighting is approximate anyway we
could just use so we could we could if
we wanted to just use P minus C as our
as our normal right and then we could
just normalize it later
that's way way way simpler than what we
were trying to do before and it does
give us a normal for lighting and maybe
a good normal for lighting who knows but
now the question is well what if we
really want to be accurate in this part
of the process and we would like it to
be discontinuous so we would like it to
always point this way all along here and
then always point this way all along
here right what would that look like
well as we usually do in hand-made here
let's start with a 2d case first because
usually in 3d you can solve in 2d and
then that will inform the 3d solution
there are several cases where that's not
true but in this case I don't think I'm
pretty sure in this case since we're
talking about axis aligned bounding
boxes and each one of those elements
that
the Y and the Z are completely
independent in this case and we know the
result will be a one or a negative one
in each in one of those three
coordinates it's pretty clear since this
is going to be a separable problem right
so I think we're not in a lot of risk
here of stumbling into something where a
solution that works in tune you won't
work in 3d but you never know but I'm
pretty sure we won't have that problem
so let's just take a cross-section and
say well let's look at some of these
cases so what we know is that we could
have something that's a fairly well
balanced shape but we could also in
theory because we're not really
restricting our AAA B's in any
particular way here have a very
unbalanced shape in one of the other two
ways which is to say it could be that
like the X is very much larger than the
Y or the Y is very much larger than the
X and the reason that that matters to us
is because you know if you were to just
say like use you know Max or something
like this to figure out which one to do
you can sort of see that for something
like a cube or something that's close to
a cube taking the max is a pretty close
answer because for example here is the
45 degree right and if I just took
whichever the max element was then I
would sort of get this kind of a thing
and that's almost correct right but you
can see that there's a region where is
incorrect
which is here and here because as soon
as we get past the 45 degrees the Y
starts to be larger and when the Y is
larger you you're going to start
thinking that the normal is plus 1y or
negative 1y when that's not actually
correct it changes too early and
therefore you can see why I drew these
two cases with just to underscore just
how bad that is
because in this case here's the 45 right
and so it would really be wrong most of
the time and the same thing would be
true here on the other axis right now
it's wrong most of the time in here
right that's all wrong or that's all
wrong
so it's like well you know that's a bit
of an issue but we can still use it as
an approximate do I love it no because
it seems like it should be pretty simple
for us to do better than that and if you
look at what we're sort of saying here
it seems like there's a pretty direct
way to do it because we know the
dimensions of these boxes ahead of time
it would be pretty easy for us to store
a inverse scale wouldn't it right so if
you think about it after I take this
normals you know this creates a space I
guess it's what I'm saying and after I
take the difference so if I have a
p-value that's here and after I take
that difference what have I done
well the origin of the space after I do
that subtraction is the center right so
I'm now in a space where the center you
know I could redraw this coordinate
system and I'm now in a space where the
center of the box is at the center of my
coordinate system and the normal
direction that I've computed right the P
minus C value this is the P minus C
value here that's pointing off in some
direction relative to my normal and I
know it's on the wall of one of these
boxes so it's inside a coordinate frame
I know the scale of so the question is
why not just store the inverse scale
right why not just store how long the
box is in Y how long the box is an
ex-model about Z that's our radius value
store the inverse radius right because
then what we can do is we can multiply
our point by our start RP minus C value
which is already around the center of
the box by the inverse scale value and
that will shrink it into a unit cube
right
now if we took the maximum element it
would correctly go in that that that
would be the direction that it was
supposed to go right so if we applied an
inverse scale we would get the the exact
answer if we took the maximum element
right because inside a unit cube and it
doesn't actually have to be unit it just
has to be this a cube it just has to
have the same dimension all sides it has
to be one but has to be same dimension
all sides inside a cube what is true is
that any cross-section that we take
would look like a perfect like the
perfect 45-degree switch 45 degrees
always points at the corner which means
that where it would switch from this to
this is always correct right so that
suggests to me that rather than doing
any kind of fanciness to see which side
we hit let's just not care and let's
work it backwards from just the
subtraction right so in here I guess
what I would say is rather than doing
any of this let's just get rid of it all
I don't think we care about any of that
or that or this oops so if we would like
to make this code work correctly now
when we take our selection here and we
select in this mask what we want to now
do is do a result normal that selects in
the normal as well right like we were
doing here
so this this code still wants to occur
because we got it we have to do our
selection but what we want to do now is
just have our normal computation here
right so this stuff doesn't need to be
doing that anymore we'll work it out
so we want to do our normal XY and Z I
don't know if we want to do them like
dot X dot y dot Z but we'll see what
happens to happen here as we go so let's
work it through all right so here's our
normal X here's our normal Y and here's
our normal Z right okay so what we would
like to do here is we would like to
compute first of all our si minus p
value right so we want to be able to
compute you know that that vector to the
point whatever that is so you know this
now we know where the point is because
we have our T value so we know this T
min so the T min value plus so you know
taking the origin of the Ray which is
this value here and multiplying the team
in in fact you can really just paste
this right taking the origin of the Ray
and adding the T min value times the
Raiden that will give us the
intersection point for each four for
each of our four arrays we will have the
intersection point on there the boxes
that they hit now some of them didn't
hit right they weren't earlier hits so
some of them these selects will knock
out later right because we're only
taking the Rays which hit closer but
doesn't matter because we can compute
them in bulk here and then we'll just
pick will only keep the ones we actually
wanted so the intersection P gets
computed here and then after we know
what the intersection point is we can do
our subtraction so this is our you know
unscaled
normal if you will that just points off
the direction or unscaled
direction i don't know how you want to
say it I don't know there's an
for that exactly but it's the
intersection P - whatever the Box origin
is right so this box P here the center P
and I guess that gives us a good reason
why we want to keep doing Fox and radius
right so that gives us our unscaled D
value and then once we have those values
in place we can now go about figuring
out what the normals need to be right
I'm sorry we can go ahead and scale them
so now we want to just take an unskilled
to get our scaled normal here actually
nope we know we need to do that we just
need a hat a Mart product here where
we're gonna use our inverse box scale so
this is something we can pre-compute and
store in the box and then we can have
our skilled direction now I know what
you're thinking you're like well it's
starting to get kind of complicated here
right because we have to compute the
actual point and then we have to compute
the unscaled direction in the scale
direction left but take a look at what
we're actually doing right let me enjoy
the site again if we look
I'm gonna hazard a guess here and I
don't actually know we're gonna have to
try and prove it but if you look here's
the Rea origin right eye and if we took
the Box Center and this thing kind of
comes down and hits this thing here I
guess I need to make sure I'm doing this
in a way that won't pre biases I'm just
trying forever we can get rid of some of
this math there's our intersection point
there's our normal we would know this as
well I think we already actually compute
that right okay so taking a look at what
we actually compute here we know the box
min and Max and then we know sort of the
tee box min tee box max which is sort of
for each individual for each individual
axis that's sort of saying how close is
it to this how close is it to this how
close is it to this right so we know how
far we'd have to go to hit this plane
how far we would have to go to hit this
plane and so on right so the question is
like is there anything we could do here
that would allow us to determine what
the actual normal is faster than like
more efficiently than actually computing
what that point is right then actually I
can do like the eff mad and the subtract
I and to me like I'm just trying to
think I guess we can't really use the
Ray Origin directly because the Ray
origin could really be anywhere I mean
the the Ray origin could in theory be
like right there right and so then when
you actually look at and the direction
could be like straight down right so
then when you look at like
where these things hit like this one
actually hits this side and this
actually hits the top so we can't
necessarily just use like the direction
back to the rate origin for example that
doesn't seem like that would work in any
particular way yeah I don't know
mm-hmm-hmm maybe there is no way around
this I'll leave it like that temporarily
but I'm just i what I do wonder this may
be I have a feeling this is too much
work that we don't actually need to do
it
this single subtract on all the values
and then the Hadamard on all the values
that's one subtract one multiply for
each value so 24 instructions total I
think right because we have to do so
many of them is the problem is to do
them on the X is the Y's and aziz which
is a real bummer right but well you know
they're four wide so I guess yeah 24 is
probably the wrong way right it's
actually 6 but you get the idea so 6
instructions so assuming that we're
going to do these six instructions here
that's not too bad figuring out whether
we could get rid of some of these here
because this is less good because it's
another six instructions but we're
twelve instructions isn't particularly
many to do and what I was going to point
out is at that point we actually have
our answer because the only other thing
we actually need to do with the normal
here is to figure out which element is
the maximum element and 0 the other ones
and change that one to 1 right and the
important thing to realize is we don't
need to do that yet right we don't need
to do that yet at all we can do all of
our collisions and only store this much
because after we've stored this much we
then know
after we've stored this much information
when we oh okay yes thank you
all right fine my brain finally figured
it out
I was like I knew that was too much
information
yes yes yes okay think about the runway
remember we do a bunch of box collisions
right let's say we do like a hundred of
these or something right there could be
a lot of them so we did a ton of box
collisions and then we do like one pro
update with the results so we do like a
ton of these and like one of these right
and so what we're doing here every time
through is we're just storing who was
the best hit and so what we want to do
is push as much of the computation to
the probe update as we can because all
of the box collisions we get a huge
multiplier on those we have to do like
all of this code has to be done for
every box check like all of this code
has to be done for every box check and
all of this code has to be done for
every box hit so as we hit three four or
five boxes and we're just taking the
closest one we're wasting a ton of time
in here if we do anything that we don't
actually have to do well
what's some things we could say about
this look at these equations here look
at what I was saying we needed to do
right I was saying we needed to do
origen plus t direction
right to compute the point we then
needed to subtract that from the center
of the box right and then we needed to
scale that by the inverse box scale so
this whole thing had to have a scale
value on it right but what do we know
about these values that we're looking at
here
you know well this whole equation could
just be done at the end on only the
actual hit so we don't need to do it
every time we could move this whole
computation to the end
why don't we well we don't because it
depends what the sea and the
SR correct you see I'm saying like it
depends what those two values are if we
don't know what those two values are we
can't do the equation at the end so
while we just save those right instead
of computing this equation at all just
save this S&amp;C value and that's it so
instead of doing any computations in
here all we would do is do six selects
and that's the end of it do six selects
to store these values now I don't know
if there's some way to store something
less than six that I don't know I don't
think so
because I think you fundamentally need
an origin in a scale so I think those
selects have to happen regardless right
so we're gonna have to do a lot of
selects that's just the nature of the
beast I think and yeah I don't I don't
see any way around that we're gonna need
to select a color in here as well
probably further reflected for the light
reflection and so you're just gonna have
a ton of selects but that's it you don't
need to do any other math this stuff
doesn't need to happen because it can
just happen outside when you actually
get the result back so like here right
so this is where we can actually do that
finalization work for each individual
array so when we're in here and we do
this any true here really I think this
whole thing can just be like look like
this so instead of normal we just do
like box Center
and like the box in scale and so in here
all we would be doing is just selecting
these out like updating them basically
right and we don't actually need to
compute any values at all so I think
that gets us out of the like expensive
business here entirely which is great so
we already have the Box P that goes in
here I think these are stored like that
right can we select this whole thing can
I do that I don't know if I can do that
or not but I'm hoping if I can't I'll
just write it because it'll be a lot
more efficient to be able to write that
here
well that env radius for now so you can
see that just by doing three selects
here and three selects here I store all
the information I needed I don't need to
do any other computations I can do the
computations at the end on just the
actual like answer that I got which
again eliminates does the minimum amount
of work there I think because that way
we're not computing values that we then
throw away when we get a closer hit so
we're just remembering the information
about the box rather than computing
something and storing that which i think
is better selects are pretty cheap on
modern there's actually a select
instruction in modern X X X 64 I of
course don't remember what it's called
that's called something
it's not called select it's not called
extract oh man blends I forget what they
call it blend blend blend blend blend
sorry about that I just completely
forgot what they called it alright so
let's see where we're at here so this
would be the function we're talking
about blend PS it's SSE 4.1 let's take a
look at where that's at these days
there you go uh so if you take a look at
where that's at
you know 96.5 40 percent of things in
the steam harbor survey at it that's a
pretty solid number you're not knocking
many people out by using it so and
especially about time we ship handmade
here right ammeter is very slow we only
get what four hours of programming every
week by the time we're shipping we could
probably just count on that being
available in most places we're gonna
ship this game uh and so being able to
do blending for either a blend v which i
think is what we actually need because
this this blend this one right here is
an immediate blend which would not
really be what we want we want to blend
based on another value that we compute
and so but this blend v that's like a
single instruction right and it looks
like they don't have for some reason
they don't list the cost of mmm blend v
and i don't know why but that's okay
because obviously we can look it up in
the you ops table so if we do a search
here for that and that's a
I see no what did what did how does this
thing I always get confused about how
this thing works
it's it is SSE instruction though oh
yeah because it's a this is this is not
by intrinsic this is by actual
instruction so we look at the actual
measured cost of this thing you can see
that it's a 2 you opt instruction it
looks like for memory and a 1 new op
instruction regular which is exactly
what you'd expect in our case we would
be in sometimes we'd be from memory
besides we'd be so you know we would use
both of them actually which is fine and
then these are probably fusible to I
would assume I don't actually know I we
look at the actual latency and the
throughput and it's fantastic right I
mean this is like you can issue up to
three of these
per cycle if you want to it looks like
so I don't know how many units they're
on so that yeah you can the issue around
0 1 &amp; 5 so yeah you can these things are
free I guess let me put you that way we
could just do a ton of those so we could
get like 3 of these done in a single
cycle so selecting our box center would
take one cycle right so that's very good
so I think that's all good and we would
just need one thing here which is like a
color value because when we bounce the
light around we want to be able T to
have it bounce around with color and so
that box that we're talking about here
we want to sort of look up in there know
where we actually store those things
waiting box yeah here you go
so the ref see the reflection color
there we want to be able to store that
but that's three cycles in theory right
and you know it depends here whether
these are in the cache or not but they
should be because they're right with the
other information we've gathered so this
is on the same cache line is what we
already fetched so presumably it's just
going to be like
pretty much free to do this this looks
really good right so I think that's
great that would be pretty
straightforward it's simple and it
Whittle that I think that will allow us
to do things much more quickly so if we
got rid of those and we just went with
this I think that gives us everything we
need for our values to come back I don't
know what the hit value actually is
therefore because it feels like that's
something that you could just use tear a
four on the end so I kind of want to say
that that this feels wasted to me right
I feel like we don't need to store this
hit value because at the end when we're
actually using these we don't need a
boolean for the hit value we can just
compare the t-ray and see if it's ever
been updated so like when we plug the T
ray in here when we first started out
right so this thing here when we do our
ray or gin bit right so when we start
the raycast that the T ray it's set to F
32 Max and so all we have to do to
compute our hit value is just compare it
back to F 32 max right so what we should
be able to do here is at the end of this
this is just dumb on our part there was
really no reason for us to do what we
did we just weren't thinking that day
this hit value that we returned can just
be a comparison with F 32 max meaning if
it's equal to F 32 max then it didn't
hit right so what we want to do is just
say something like this
if the tea hit is not equal to f3 to max
then it's a positive right and so that
gets us out of this business here
because I don't think we ever actually
need that right look we just don't care
about that at all so I'm pretty sure we
can get rid of that value and as long as
it's never used anywhere in here which I
don't think it is right then I think
we're fine I'm sorry it's not tea hits T
ray Yeah right
so that gets even less work that makes
even less work get done in here and so
now we're just selecting using that same
selection mask we're just storing the
information and we're letting the
outside code do all of the work for us
right and that's exactly what we want
here now there's another thing we could
do here which is we could just not store
the box Center in the envy radius
because now that I think about it since
the raycast doesn't actually you know we
can actually not do this we can actually
have this come back with the normal if
we want because we could do that here
right so what we could do is is store
like the hit version here right so these
things and what we could do is just say
look these are gonna be whatever you
know and when we come through cure we're
gonna update them like so and then when
we get to the end we will actually do
that computation that I was like we were
gonna do on the outside we could do it
in here and I think that's better and
the reason is because this is the code
that actually knows what it's doing
so it you know the it doesn't have to
return special information back that the
caller has to kind of let go what was
this for again
so we can do this stuff here right we
can just say all right let's do the
computations we computed the best
versions of the box center of the box in
rear a radius right so I guess I'll call
the it's like hit to differentiate them
right like that and so once we get that
information now we can do this stuff
cleanly right we know what the origin is
we know what our result T ray is and we
know the Raider action so we can do all
that strict out across each do we even
need to return the T ray at all I don't
think we do
we could just return the point actually
so I feel like maybe this recast result
could actually also just be this because
that way that's the actual value that
the person wants so maybe we'll do that
furthermore like this result here like
this bit I feel like we just want to now
get this out of here so we would we
would say something like this and
compute that here
so our T ray value it's just a local
right it's not accessing off of anything
and then when we come through here and
we're doing our selection takes on that
we just do this and everything else
stays the same I think that's what we
want
missed one like so and then we just fill
them out here so we fill out the hip by
looking at T array and seeing which ones
with them got updated we fill out the
normal the ref color
and this is just us packing this crap
back up so we just fill these out and we
just need to solve for these other
pieces here all right so let's actually
solve for the dupes for the hit P we
know it's just this equation we said
before that's the location that the
intersection actually occurred based on
our solve again using the T value to
move us from the Ray origin along the
Ray direction to the point of
intersection we then can give youth the
unscaled direction by taking whatever
our hip P was and subtracting the hitbox
center again this is doing this for four
rays at a time so we're actually
creating four intersection points and
doing four centers right we then need to
scale these by the best boxes envious
inverse radius so we're effectively
doing this Hadamard product here to
scale the unscaled result that we get
back and then what we need to do to
select our normal is we now need to use
an element minimum and maximum to
effectively say let's take the highest
whatever the highest one is we'll keep
that one and the rest we want to remove
now this could be kind of painful to do
and so that's why I wanted to move it to
the end I don't want to do it every time
we hit because we might have five six
seven eight ten who knows how many hits
we could have a lot of hits in here I
only want to do it for the final one so
once per raycast and only once per red
cast if we cast ten thousand rays we do
ten thousand of these rather than 50,000
of these a hundred thousand of these
right because it's gonna be expensive
all right so figuring out what we've got
to work with here
I don't know that in sse we would have
the ability to take element mins and
maxes so we're pretty much going to be
restricted i believe just using the mins
and maxes of the like comparison wise
right and so this is a pretty that's why
this is a pretty tough thing to do right
we don't know fundamentally speaking we
just don't know which one of these is
going to be minimum which one that's
gonna be maximum and that's we can't
look inside the elements that's why you
can see here like we had to do this
before right you can see how we had to
do like a series of mins and maxes to
figure out which one was going to
actually be the minimum or the maximum
and we're gonna have to do something
similar here because there's no way to
compute there's no way for us to what am
i trying to say we don't have a single
instruction that looks at the elements
of a particular vector and finds which
one is minimum or which one is maximum
right oh but we're by Ray though so
that's actually okay nevermind we're
four wide by Ray so it doesn't matter
we're actually just gonna do what we
would normally do
alright so that's fine never mind take
back everything I just said we're by Ray
I was thinking we had the x y&amp;z packed
into a single sim deregister where we
don't so we're we actually we planned
ahead all right so what we want to do
now is take a look at that scale D and
what we want to do is say something you
know we effectively want to compute this
right we want to say if the you know if
the absolute value of scaled DX is
greater than the absolute value of scale
D Y you know then
pick X else pick Y right and then we
want to do the same thing again right we
want to do like if the absolute value
the pick thing is creating the absolute
value of Z then you know guess we want
to do that something like this right and
we could change this pretty easily into
something that just starts with the
first one so like it assumes that it's
got you know a particular value and then
just does checks to see if it should
update that value that's probably the
simplest way to write it well write it
that way first and we'll see what
happens so we know we want to compute a
hit normal and what we can do here is we
can say well we know that the hit normal
probably just wants to be set to
something like this I guess we don't
really know the sign of what we're
looking at here do we have sign as an
operator I want to look at where we talk
about these do we have sign in here
anywhere we don't this is a place where
the floating-point format having a sign
bit can be very useful to us so we want
to talk about the sign very explicitly
here because we can get speed winds
there the reason for that is because we
know that the sign bit the high bit 31
bit of the floating-point value is the
positive or negative sign is the thing
that tells us what that is and so we can
make sure that we always just directly
use that instead of having do any
comparisons there so our absolute value
is just going to be an and with a mass
that gets rid of the sign bit that's all
we actually have to do right in fact did
we ever do that
yeah so you can see here our absolute
value function does this exact thing we
just don't have a sign extraction but
it'd be the same right the sign
extraction would be in and with with
just this instead of the notthis right
so be pretty easy for us to copy the
sign of something for example you would
just have you know something like this
right
and so all you're doing there is anding
out all of the data of the floating
point and just keeping the sign bit
absolute values the opposite operation
you're anding out everything that's
you're adding out just the sign bit and
leaving all the data right and so you
know it's it's pretty straightforward
what happens here it's very very simple
but you you can see why we would want
both of them this one allows us to
extract that sign bit which allows us to
or it back in later to create a sign
that matches some other sign and
absolute value is just the opposite
thing it's just destroy that sign bit so
that no one has to worry whether things
are negative okay so what do we want to
actually do here well I guess what I'm
suggesting is we want to do something
like well time here but we want to do
something like this where we have a like
a Y mask or something and a Z mass and
what we can do here is say if we were to
compute the comparison of like the X and
the y right so let's say I was to look
at scaled D itself and say look if you
know the or maybe I wanted the other way
around if the y value is greater than
the x value I want to take the Y value
right and then I want to say well if
this scale D
result value or whatever the best value
was so if the best value i if our Z is
better than whichever one ended up being
greater of these two then I want to mask
in the Z for the normal right and then I
want to take the sign bit and I want to
shove the sign bit in there that's
basically what we're talking about
right okay so how do we do that well in
this particular case for the Y mask we
just need to pick whether we want Y or X
to start with right like which one of
those two do we want to actually use so
figuring out whether you use Y or X is
going to be is just going to be this and
so if I want to do an a select now I
should be able to do that by selecting X
or Y based on that value right let's
actually compute all these so we can see
which one which ones are which and then
because I mean I guess I'm just trying
to work this out in my head and it's not
going well so I kind of just want to
type it out because there's enough of
these in there that I'm just kind of
yeah let's do it like this let's work
backwards from the Select we know we're
going to have to select a 1 or 0 into
each of these right so we've got an X
mask a Y mask and a Z mask that's going
to select into our hit normal either a 1
or a 0 presumably something like this
right I and so if we have to do that it
would look like this
so for each array which that's what our
for white is the channel of the X mask
will be 1 if it's supposed to be 1 or 0
if it's supposed to be 0 right
and so we can select that floating-point
value in there based on which one we
want now it's worth noting that the X
mask will actually just be 0 correctly
and so really you might say looking at
this we don't really need a select
because all we really need to do is
knock out so we can actually do this
with an ending instruction because the
s-max will already be 0 where we need 0
and 0 in binary is 0 in floating-point
so we can just let that clear the
channel for us right furthermore we can
do the same thing for each of these
because they're the same operation so we
pretty much know that all we need to do
is is compute our channel mask and then
putting the one in place becomes pretty
trivial now it's not quite as easy as I
made it look the reason for that is that
these ones are not going in the correct
direction so we do need to or in our
sign bit here to make sure that it
points in the correct direction
now I could or it in on each one and
then mask it out but if we were being
super cheeky right if we're just being
real sly so-and-so's here we could
recognize the fact that for all intents
and purposes what we're gonna be doing
with the normal is just taking a dot
product with it the dot product of any
component with 0 whether the 0 is
positive or negative won't matter
because the 0 will knock out the actual
contribution of that value so I'm gonna
argue that we can actually just take the
hit normal well and actually now think
about it since we'd have to do it for
each one forget everything I just said
we might as well just do it on the one
in mind
because then we're gonna have to do one
or for each channel now that I think
about it so it pretty much doesn't
matter right so what we can do is just
say look sign one value I guess do it
this way there we go so prepare a signed
one value the sign one value is just
saying take the sign bit from our scaled
value because this is the direction we
know everything is supposed to point
take the sign bit from that or it with a
1 value and then that is the thing that
we want to put into our normal anywhere
where the mask comes out in favor of
this particular component right all
right so then we just need to actually
compute our masking values what we want
to do is start by saying look the X mask
is just the combination of you know
these values it's basically saying look
if the scale D X is less than the scale
D Y and the scale D X is less than scale
D Z then it's you know it's the it's the
X component that we want it's less than
both of them and we can do the same
thing for each of our masks so in this
case we just want to do
this all I could do the ex first time I
am yeah like looking at how those are
computed you need to do to comparison
one and since we know these are all
coming out with masks this is can just
be a binary end right it doesn't have we
don't need any kind of logical anding
here so we do two comparisons and one
and per channel that's pretty cheap
there might be some way to make that
even cheaper because when we do these
comparisons we've already got some
information that we could probably reuse
so I'll put to do in here because there
might be but at the moment it's still
really cheap right and since all we have
to do is just this one thing at the end
seems pretty good right so again that
ended up being a pretty nice concise way
to do that hopefully but also remember
we've moved it out of the hot area of
the code so it's even cheaper because
we're just not doing it very much which
is great right what is the problem here
I don't know what the problem is here
probably that
Hiep bucks in scale yep so we don't
store those in radiuses I don't think so
we're gonna have to add those the ref C
is in there but the in radius isn't so
that's one thing that's gonna have to
get in there let's take a look at these
so do we probably don't have a how to
Marge product yeah we don't so we're
gonna have to add a hat of our product
sign bit from is complaining but I'm not
sure why ah so I lied
since we have one per channel right x
y&amp;z I don't know we may have to extract
the sign bit separately from each one
right which doesn't seem great that
costs more to do but I'm not sure
there's any way around it
yeah I don't think there is just gonna
look like this sorry guys
thought I was being clever wasn't really
clever it's always hard whenever I do
Cindy I get confused by lanes versus
elements of vectors my brain doesn't
like that very much
and it makes that same mistake a lot
fortunately it doesn't really matter the
compiler will catch it for you but it's
still kind of annoying right we've got a
unbalanced if zero here somewhere not
sure where
right here alright so let's take a look
at what we actually need here so we've
got a select that's complaining but I
think that's just because in this
particular case the hit ref color like
this select only works on the members of
this so we probably want one that
distributes out to all three but the
bigger thing is we don't have an
invidious right now so basically like
our select function you can see we've
only got this one here what we would
like to do is say can we make a select
function that just goes out on all of
these right so if we have like a v3 like
so and we want to do is select on it
can we just call like this is what we
want here right we just want to do one
that just spams out you know distributed
property to each member it's not really
distributive just per element just spam
it out and do it for us because we don't
want to have to type it like you know
just make it happen for all the elements
and we'll be happy uh so I think that
should be okay
not sure what what is this complaining
about here
it already has a body I thought you were
just complaining that it didn't have a
body what are you talking about huh wait
so why was it complaining that we didn't
have one of those when we definitely did
right have it must have a typo in there
somewhere yeah that's the same function
what the hey
oh so it's not nevermind it's not
complaining anymore
it just doesn't know I guess but it is
complaining about this one what's the
deal
it knows hit ref color I don't know
let's fix the box in radius and we'll
see where it goes maybe this is just a
bad error reporting situation so in our
lightning box we need to put in the
inverse scale so we need an inverse
radius here like that
and you know we could use the reciprocal
here if we wanted to to compute that
inverse radius I don't know that we
really want to do that but we could I
think I'm gonna not do it but again like
it's something that we could consider
doing because remember when you're
storing these loading boxes it cost you
something in fact I think about it
it's just not because less bandwidth is
usually better so instead here let's
just do box in radius we only need to
use it here if we store it so let's
actually let's actually just roll that
into the computation so instead of doing
hitbox in radius we'll just use hitbox
radius like so because we know we've got
that let's do those things while trying
to match v3 for X to do okay I see was
complaining about we need to loft this
box ref C up into a v3 for X right so we
actually need this thing too we need
this thing to take that ref C and get
into that
so that's fine okay so now what we need
to do is this hitbox in the radius here
we really just need to do the divide and
so I'm actually okay with doing the
whole divide so if we take a look at div
right the div PS it's just not that many
cycles it's not great you know don't get
me wrong but if we started doing that
before well I guess everything's
depending on though yeah is there
anything problem is there's nothing we
could pipe line in there so I guess I
really don't want to do the divide I
guess we want to do an envelope lie you
see why I'm saying that because you look
here on skylake for example it takes 11
cycles to do the divide if you look at
all of the work that has to be done here
that would be fine I don't care about 11
cycles because we can do other work in
that time 3 3 puts not that bad but if
you look at what has to happen here at
that 11 cycles it'll hit this is where
we would do the divide instead of a hat
of our product we would do have our
quotient here do divide those 3 divides
nothing else can happen until they're
done right all of this other crap just
has to stall on those divides and I
guess there'd only be a free cycle
bubble cuz if through three of the
divides but it's a little nasty I don't
know it's not great it's probably ok but
it's just a little nasty right whereas
if we did the reciprocal
that's like way less right for cycle
latency it's just very approximate you
know in this case though you kind of
have to figure approximants probably
fine I mean we're not even using the
value that comes back for anything other
than a comparison so like in what world
would it ever actually matter you know
so I'm gonna I'm gonna have to say that
like probably the reciprocals the right
way to go here like probably the RCP PS
Sam and so let's take a look at this
part here right so if you look at what
happens we're taking this and then we're
subtracting the hitbox center off of
that I'm gonna argue that we probably
want to restructure this and say that
the you know the hip P here that we're
computing is I guess well no because we
need that - I was gonna say one thing we
could do is restructure this so that
this this subtraction actually happens
here because those two things can happen
in parallel the multiply and the
subtraction happen together but since we
need the hit P probably not gonna work
anyway while that's happening though the
hitbox inverse radius we can be doing
the inverse on that so the hitbox
inverse radius here can be the hitbox
radius approximate inverse so we need an
approximate inverse there and then we
can do the multiply here right and so
that should be fine the only thing is we
may already have that in here I'm gonna
look to see if we do so I'm gonna just
search through here and see do we have
the RCP instruction anywhere I don't see
it so we need to add one of those and
I'll add it to both you can see we are
using the approximate square root but
we're just not we don't use the
approximate reciprocal anywhere we only
use the approximate square root which
yeah again we don't really care about I
don't think for any particular reason
here all right so let's take a look at
the approximate square root and try to
make it look the same as that because
this is basically the same kind of
instruction so let's do a proc
in yes that and so that's all we really
wanted to do here and so we'll make this
look the same there's the art there's
the reciprocal and there's our view
there
turn that out and so now we're returning
the approximate one over that we can use
for anything we want and so here we can
just say like okay approximate one over
hip box radius that'll give us the box
inverse radius back now remember we want
to be able to distribute this so we just
got to copy this down here and say oh
alright well if you're doing one of
those and you want to do it across all
of your elements we need to kind of just
blow that out so we've got the result
here the result X is just the aprox one
over for the X oops we want to be able
to do that three times one for each zone
and one for each head dimension and then
that should solve our problem now the
Hadamard product I guess we don't have I
assume because we were saying it said we
didn't have it oops
so I guess we never wrote a Hadamard
here that seems really weird
so it looks like we wrote the times
operator instead of the Hadamard product
which seems nuts because I don't usually
do that and you can see us like calling
it here so I don't love that so all
we're really gonna do we don't have to
write it I'm just gonna change the name
of this thing so that it matches what we
were doing I don't know why I did that
I'll have to go back and look at the
video see that's unlike me I must have
had some reason but it probably wasn't
very good one so that's all we should
really need there there we go and now
we've got our ray caster returning
exactly what we want and it should be
actually I think considerably faster
than the old one because there's a lot
less instructions in here right so it'll
be a little slower because we got rid of
this fake early-out case that wasn't
that was a bug in our early one so we're
losing speed there but we'll gain quite
a bit of speed by not needing to do as
much stuff in here I think so that
should be good
and then this maybe isn't the most
efficacious way to do this but it's
pretty good you know it's not the
world's worst and so hopefully that will
be pretty tight as well and you know it
only has to happen after you've done all
of the collision detection for an entire
ray and so it's it's you know cheaper in
that sense all right all right so let's
go in here I don't know how much time I
got left it looks like about 15 minutes
or so yeah so let's just take a look at
this stuff too so when we actually go in
here now I want to say that all of this
should actually be symbolized as well I
think all of this stuff should not
downshift any more and do this these
extractions we don't I don't think want
to do any more so when we get the
raycast back what we need to do here is
determine like for this ray cast what is
the actual lighting value that we get
right and we already sort of sketched
out this routine somewhere in here that
was for our yeah Senor summer where'd
you go
here it is so we already had you know a
get probe lighting for situation and the
kept probe lighting for right now we had
working only on a v3 but I think what we
want to do is make that operate wide you
know I'm saying and it's not great
because the the big thing that sucks
about Cindy and the Cindy instruction
set you know it's really really bad that
they did this because it basically means
that all of your code just completely
falls apart as soon as it has to touch
memory which really just doesn't seem
like a very good idea but I think they
just fundamentally at Intel we're like
look we don't have enough fetching it
stuff here to actually make this work
I don't know so up until avx-512 which
almost nobody has so it doesn't matter
like we can't use it it would run on
like zero machines including this one
this one machine doesn't have it either
the problem is any time we need to go
fetch information so in the case of our
light probes we need to be able to go
fetch what the color values are so we
can combine them together and get like
the results of those colors out so we
can't do that at the moment wide we can
do all the rest of the stuff wide but
the fetching has to downshift and that's
the really really annoying part of it
right and so we could you know have done
this completely wide the entire way and
some all four ray casts at once and it
would have been really nice but we can't
do that and so we're gonna have to think
of another strategy for doing this that
minimizes the degree to which we have to
look at things quote unquote unwind
and my assumption is that that will
probably involve treating the probes as
wide and their raise is not I don't
really know
you know that's that's just my
assumption so you know I think you kind
of need to step through the Rays because
you need to do those those light lookups
for each individual one and you're gonna
have to him separately because you just
can't send me that I and presumably you
know it's also an open question if we
did the right thing as being per ray
instead of for primitive but I think we
did the right thing there just because
bounding volume hierarchies generally
speaking don't really lend themselves to
primitive because you're typically only
testing one primitive as you narrow
things down so typically you want to put
your Ray's in bundles and not your your
the primitives you're testing against
don't typically want to be in bundles
this especially gets true as you go
wider cuz you typically don't want to
test like 16 boxes against array because
a lot of times you just want to test one
box and see whether you should which
side of the thing you should go down you
know or something like that so I would
suspect roughly speaking you know this
is sort of the way it should look and so
when we get out of here
and we end up with the Ray the for Ray
results and we need to then do something
with them I'm pretty sure what we need
to end up doing here is we've got to go
ahead and and downshift to scalar and
then I guess what we can do is once we
take a look at what the scalar stuff
looks like we can put it back into cindy
as much as we can and we might just have
to go cindy across some other thing
because per ray just won't work because
of the lookups really right cuz you know
what i'm saying
I mean maybe because I'll do it per Ray
well we assemble the lookups back into a
4x and go from there I'm guessing but
that being neither here there there I
think I'm gonna call it for today
because basically the next set of things
we want to do is in here so I'm gonna
I'm gonna
say that's good for now and tomorrow we
will go back and into this part of their
team and write this new version for the
light probes and then we're getting kind
of close to being able to debug it at
that point all we really need to do is
go in and make sure that we're feeding
light probes in and then we can start to
actually step through the code in like
debug it and work it through and go from
there but we're getting close so that'd
be good and once we get to that point
then we're pretty happy because then
we're just down to figuring out how to
feed this down to the card in a nice way
which is basically just gonna be like
updating updating a voxel look up and
and setting down the light probe values
which shouldn't be that hard it just be
it's just you know hey it's GPU so
there's a lot of like debugging that
that goes on that's just because you
can't see what's happening and so it
takes you longer than it should
although Nsight has been pretty good
about making those things easier for us
so let's go ahead and go to QA and then
we will wrap it up
origen box Center and hit P are on the
same line no they're not right so I
guess what I would say is I disagree I
think I drew that here
so here's ray origin here's Box Center
and here's hit P they actually form a
triangle and we don't really know
anything about the triangle at all I
guess I would say or almost at all you
know that there really isn't I don't
think much you can say about that
triangle do you believe do you believe
me first let's let's do I need to go
into that in more detail or do you
believe me from the diagram LS r1 send
me a Q : back that says whether you
believe that or not I'll look it up late
coders question in the meantime I've
just added this evil so standard
reference to the issue type name member
named issue I agree it's a stupid
warning but there seems to be no way to
disable it in GCC the rate of bug
against GCC then I mean it's if it
doesn't handle the standard then it's a
bug and it should fix it
but else r1 okay so you believe me okay
cool uh I guess what I'd say is I would
have liked that to be the case exactly
what you said I would have hoped would
be true but it's just not and so the
problem is I can't see a shorter way of
determining what direction that P the
normal goes in other than actually
producing the hit point but I think we
did the best job here anyway because we
need that point later to look up the
light probes so it's really kind of free
you know what I mean I and it's really
kind of free to use it because we knew
we had to make it anyway
which doesn't make it entirely free but
since we were able to move it outside
the code it's almost free and the only
thing we would really save by using
something cheaper would be some of those
selects in there but again we can do
three selects per cycle on a modern
machine so saving them doesn't really do
much for us they're almost free
an entire vector is worth of select is
one cycle right so so I do think we're
we're not I'm not too worried about it
it would have been nice if we could
avoid it certainly because it's always
nice to just do something simpler but in
this case we happen to be using
something we needed anyway and so that's
if you can't get away with the cheat
using something you already needed to
make anyway is certainly the best
secondary option because hey you needed
to compute that anyway so you're
creating it's a it's a chain dependency
which we would hope to not have because
then we can't compete them in parallel
but you know short of that it's the next
best thing because we're not throwing
the we're not throwing it away right
why are the light probe cubes and not
spheres um so they're not really cubes
they're just light probes we can choose
to think of them however we want right
what I did say was that we're just gonna
store one color value per each of the
six directions cardinal directions
coming out of the light probe point but
the light probe is not a cube or a
sphere it's just a point right and so
the only decision we have to make is how
do we store the lighting around that
point you could choose to use spherical
harmonics you could choose to use a cube
map you could choose to use six lights
six directional lights anything we want
right and we may change what that is but
it's important to remember the light
probe is not a cube or a sphere it's a
point and it then the question is just
how do we want to store the irradiance
at that point right uplink coder says
GCC is following standard it's just that
the standard stupid okay so so what
you're saying is the C++ standard
actually is different than the c99
standard why am I not surprised
okay so it's always like if someone's
gonna do something right and someone's
gonna do something wrong C will do it
right and C bus to us will do it wrong
and I guess so
a name n used in a class s so is class
also struct here because they usually
isn't much of a difference between them
or are they different a name and used in
a class s should I refer to the same
declaration in its context and when
reevaluated reevaluated in the completed
scope of s that is not relevant here is
it though
I mean that that doesn't that doesn't
prohibit this we have a type outside the
class and a member inside the class and
that's fine right because the name and
in this case is f/32 or whatever in a
class s so it's inside there I refer to
the same declaration in its context and
when revalued in the completed scope of
s but that's inside the class s right
I guess because inside the class
first of all also is this true of strux
because ass class instructor vary quite
a bit because you write member functions
in a class which is inside the contact
inside the scope of that class but
nothing happens inside the scope of a
struct other than member lookup so I'm
I'm unconvinced this this this wording
doesn't convince me at all let me look
at these other parts here
again I don't so I'm this is not saying
this in my opinion so I maybe they're
trying to say something different here
because maybe completed scope means
something different but do they mean the
scope in which s exists which is not how
I would have said that but in the
completed scope of s no violations Kurt
sure you can't do that but this is where
the error happened here not here right
because this is illegal but that isn't
because you have at no time changed what
this meant in the scope of T it doesn't
mean anything right
so that the error should have been here
the fact that they created an error on
this is absurd because that is never an
error and wouldn't be it literally has
no issues whatsoever this is the part
where you've gone wrong right
the name and used in a class s so I
refer to the same declaration in its
context and when re-evaluating this
I mean I guess the way to read this if
that's what they intended was the name
and in this case is you know if I have a
tight foo and I'm naming a member foo
the name and is foo it's being defined
inside s and we're basically saying that
it can't refer to something different at
that point as later if we were to then
look at what it meant inside s so I
guess I do believe that
I mean that's like the dumbest decision
you could possibly make right I don't
even have words for how dumb that is
because you're basically putting an
error on something that you actually
want to write in code in anticipation of
someone later writing some code which
you could have made the error happen
then C++ is basically just a language
full of people who are absolutely stupid
and have no idea how to program putting
error messages in places because they're
worried that someone might do something
later
that's like 99% of what they did in the
design of C++ it's so freakin annoying I
think anyone who's ever contributed to
the C++ standard needs to have their
license to code revoked it's like it's
the only one thing I can say that is
universally bad that never had a good
idea in it right most languages have a
good idea in them somewhere and C++ is
the only language I can think of that
managed to never do anything right not
even a single line that they made in
their spec he is good every last
decision was wrong every single one is
wrong how do you even do that if I set
out to make a language filled with only
bad decisions I would accidentally get
one right probably because I hadn't
thought it through well enough and and
accidentally made a right decision when
I was trying to make the worst possible
decision I like actually made the
slightly less bad one because I didn't
think of the the ultimate bad one to
make like I never would have thought to
add that in there that's how bad that is
they find things they find bad decisions
no one else would have ever even thought
of I guess that's the best way to think
of the C bozo Standards Committee the
CSS Standards Committee is like a
30-plus year project to see if mankind
can find all the bad decisions it's like
to root out possibility and to leave you
only with sadness right
and congratulations committee you did a
great job
Allen Webster's totally right he said
the good idea and C++ was let's start
with C it's true right C is the only
part of C++ that works
should just change this game over to see
99 at this point
should I work on a game engine in C or
C++ or just put out games and unity
Unreal until J I comes out I mean it
really just depends on what your goals
are right I say that if your goals are
simply to be like a game designer and to
like to ship games primarily you know
just as a as a focus is on the like
production side of games I would say
that you probably want to use an
existing engine right because engine
programming is difficult and takes a lot
of work and if you're not really
interested or if that's not the primary
thing that you want to be doing then it
still does make sense to learn some
engine programming because it will
obviously help you when you're working
on someone else's engine like unity or
unreal or whatever but you don't want to
build your whole engine because that's
not where your tastes lie right engine
programming is for people who want to do
engine programming now it is true that
once in a while and you know I mean this
is I guess an unfortunate situation to
be in but once in a while maybe you're
somebody who doesn't really want to do
engine programming but the engines that
exist can't do the game that you want to
do because it's got specific like sort
of requirements technically or platform
wise or who knows what that just make it
so you can that's a bad position to be
in right and I think you really have to
think to yourself do I really want to go
down that road because if you're not
passionate about engine programming but
you put yourself in a position where you
have to make an engine to succeed that
sounds rough right and maybe you maybe
you're up to the task and you're just
gonna you know grit your teeth and do it
because you want to make that game that
badly
and if you do that more power to you
that's very commendable but obviously
it's a bit tricky right so I would say
most of the time the answer of should I
build an engine or not or should you use
an existing engine should be made more
about what you want to do with your life
and less about if there's a right answer
because I don't think there's a right
answer to that question the right answer
there's a right answer to the question
of what a particular person should do
and it's based on what they enjoy doing
right
is there any reading material you
recommend for more serious real-time
lighting like this papers books even
blog post etc I've done simple diffuse
lighting before but nothing beyond that
so I guess I I don't I'm sorry I don't
actually know what a good reference
would be but I guess what I would say is
the like one possible place to start
might be to just look at the SIGGRAPH
courses so every year SIGGRAPH puts out
a bunch of course notes and they're like
unlike their papers section which is
like here is something state-of-the-art
in theory right it's not always
sometimes it's something stupid but a
lot of times it's like some fairly new
research so you know even if it is
something stupid it's something new and
stupid right but it's more it's more
like at the boundaries of graphics right
like pushing it forwards is what the
papers are supposed to be but they also
have a thing that's like here's course
notes that are designed to be tutorials
for people who don't know something who
want to learn it right and you can even
go look at the ones for artists in some
cases because they have ones that are
introductions like understanding
lighting and BRTS for artists knowing
you can look at some of those course
notes and that would probably be a good
place to start
potentially because it's all
introductory and just kind of gets you
into it right as for actual like books
and stuff I don't know someone in the
chat was mentioning the the PBR book
it definitely covers everything it's
kind of obtuse the way it's written I
would say it doesn't
I don't like literate programming I
think it was a bad idea
and I don't like the way the PBR book
reads I just don't love it all the
information is in there but it's not the
easiest to
distract but hey you know check it out
if it works for you it works for you and
it's it's a very complete reference got
lots of stuff in their spectral lighting
and all that sort of stuff so it has
topics that are more advanced than
things you typically do in games as well
although obviously games are adding you
know more and more complexity to the
lighting year after year as they get
more power so you know eventually it'll
all be in there but I don't really know
what what to say beyond that there's
probably some good online materials for
introduction to lighting I just don't
know what they are right but they're
probably out there there's a lot of blog
posts there's a lot of tutorial material
on the sort of thing there's probably a
good one out there somewhere I just I
don't know what it is because I haven't
read it but that doesn't mean doesn't
exist I just I don't go looking for
introductory lighting stuff very often
so you know so I don't know and then the
other thing you can do which helps I
think is take a look at you know
conference proceedings from game
conferences like you know GDC develop or
I don't know I don't even know what the
conferences are these days all those
crazy conferences a lot of times those
also have them you know and sometimes
game developers put together pretty good
learning materials for stuff like
real-time lighting because you know hey
we're the ones who do it a lot of times
so you know that's that's another place
to look
and Oliver the best cat just to be clear
there are no good programming languages
today period programming language design
is way way way behind the capabilities
of current computing so the reason
everyone's saying that this and that is
terrible is because it is everything is
way behind it we use C++ in the game
industry primarily because there aren't
good languages available for what we
need it's not because it's good it's not
it sucks it's a piece of crap we use it
because we don't have a choice and
that's that's really all there is to it
so it's ok you know lots of people have
done things with poor tools right it's
alright it's not a problem it's just
that's what that's what you're dealing
with right and so it's ok you know I
guess I say it's it's ok we all get by
you can - it's fine the reason we say
everything sucks is just to make sure
everyone knows that everything sucks and
what we would like to have at some point
is better programming languages for
games we don't have them now we'd like
to have them later obviously John is
working on jei which is an example of
trying to do that and a lot of us hope
that it comes out well because hey then
there would actually be a language
written for game programming that maybe
makes it a little bit easier to do all
the things we typically do on a daily
basis instead of having to deal with C++
which makes everything that we don't do
any base is harder than it should be so
that's just the state of the that's just
the state of it
ji demo on macros is in an hour and a
half
oh that's good that's very good
so John isn't it doesn't have a stream
up yet though can we rate because we can
trade him can we
John
I would like to be able to raid John's
channel but unfortunately I can't
because I think he has to be live for
that to happen am I wrong about that I'm
probably not wrong about that so we've
you know we've come to the end of my
stream I'd like to raid John I can't
read John doesn't much matter because
almost everyone who watches this channel
watched a channel 2 so it's probably
fine but you know
yeah all over the musca it's just true
it's true these are really poorly
designed languages you gotta call a
spade a spade C++ is a really garbage
language and I think that will be
obvious you know ten years from now 20
years from now I think we'll have really
good replacement languages for doing
low-level programming and I think when
you look at those languages and you look
back on sleep especially like wow see
this this is a real piece of crap so I
think that will be obvious to everyone
eventually if it's not obvious now so
we're just we're just calling it like it
like it is again you still have to use
it nothing we can do about that but but
that's just that that's just the the
reality of it right
all right um I'm gonna go ahead and shut
down
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for an episode of hand made here oh
it's a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow in
series at home you can always pre-order
the game on handmade hero dot org and it
comes with the source code so you can
play around with it at home and do your
own educational experiments I will be
back here tomorrow when we will take a
look at the outer part of the Ray
casting loop where we update the light
probe information and that I guess will
be the final step in the light
propagation part of the system so we
will probably do that and then start the
de bugging process to try and get our
light probes feeling solid and and and
computing the right answers so I think
we'll try to hopefully that'll happen
tomorrow we'll get through that I don't
know maybe we won't will maybe we won't
and then next weekend we'll finish that
debugging hopefully and we can move on
to the GPU side of things that's it hope
see you back here tomorrow for that
until then remember J a I demo is coming
up in an hour and a half I'm told on Jos
channel that's twitch.tv slash and they
say or 88 right that is this channel
right here so check that out in an hour
and a half and also I would mention
there's been some news
Abner Cowan Bray is running this
conference in Seattle and he just
recently announced that fabien will be
speaking at it if you don't already have
tickets to this or you were on the fence
about it I would say that pretty much
that's an extreme rarity I don't
remember the last time fob Ian's given a
lecture I he's one of the best slow
level programmers that currently exists
in the world I would argue
sorry Fabien if I'm if I'm aggrandizing
you at this point but maybe he's not
listening probably won't hear this so
it's fine
so I would say like that's gonna
be a pretty incredible speaker line up
here and that's pretty awesome that he
agreed to do that so I'm looking forward
to it and I would assume that anyone
else out there who cares about
Louisville programming was is as well so
just wanted to point out that that
speaker had been updated Mike and Tom
had been confirmed before but Fabien
just got added just I don't even know
like two to three days ago or whatever
so that's kind of awesome I can't wait
to see what he talks about
I learned stuff from him all the time
and so I'm looking forward to that and I
hope you are too that's about it for
today I will see everyone back here
tomorrow where we'll start to work on
the light probe updating part of things
until then have fun programming everyone
and I will see you on the Internet
take it easy