hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero show where I code a complete game
live on stream you may be asking
yourself Casey what are you drinking
today hmm hmm and the answer is I'm
actually drinking handmade coffee
the very first coffee to be officially
sanctioned by the handmade hero
television show where can you get some
of this handmade coffee you may ask well
I guess the answer is I don't know it
was actually given to me by a viewer of
the show at handmade Seattle
his name is Arad I don't actually know
if he would actually ever take a coffee
order for somebody cuz he hand roast his
own coffee I think because he is in the
Bay Area and said that he thinks the
coffee there is not very good but I
posted on Twitter a little shot of the
handmade hero coffee and a lot of people
were interested about interested to know
about it that is where it came from I do
not make my own coffee I mean I get
beans
I grind them and I put them through an
espresso machine that is about as
handmade as my coffee gets but I was
extremely honored to be presented with a
bag of handmade coffee and I do think I
have actually the the Twitter handle for
the fellow who made it it's and I will
try to treat that out it's it's at the
Eradicator IRA i ra di CA tio R so that
is where the coffee came from and if
you're interested in handmade coffee you
can you can hit up Eradicator on twitter
and see if he has any tips for you I
don't even know how he's doing it I
guess he must have some kind of a home
roasting setup which I don't even know
do they make like a little roasting
thing I mean I think if you're in the
Bay Area you can't have a house can you
you would have to be like extremely
wealthy I don't know maybe he is but
just seems unlikely right that you'd
have like a big outdoor roaster there or
something like that anyway thanks again
to rod for that it's awesome and yeah
unfortunately I'm running out so left
feed back to the regular coffee probably
next week but until then I'm on the
handmade coffee and it's pretty
delicious this was a this was from
Ethiopia beans t.o.p and beans you can
see it's labeled on the bottom alright
let's go ahead and get this going I'm
gonna switch over to do sorry the new
setup I got a can I still get used to
things
so where did we leave off we've been
since we had I was away for one weekend
and then handmade Seattle was last
weekend so I haven't really been
streaming for a while so you may have
forgotten I mean I may have forgotten
what we were doing so what are we doing
well actually surprisingly I didn't
forget what we were doing we were in the
middle of doing some work with the Ray
casting that we use for lighting and if
I go ahead and do a quick build of the
game here and then launch remedy EPG and
you can see a run of the current state
of things what we had just done at the
end of last name if I'm not in error is
thrown in the Ray caster and had it
basically set the lighting in an area
based on you know to either the correct
radial fallout well correct rid of the
radial test fall off or zero if the Ray
to the light source was occluded and we
got this weird modeling pattern which
was a little surprising at first but
then I realized it may not really be all
that surprising and the reason for that
is because we were just ray casting from
the center excuse me
we were just ray casting from the center
of the voxels of the lighting voxels and
so it's not particularly surprised
that we would get this pattern actually
now think about it because since we have
unevenly the height of our things this
kind of variant if the Centers of the
voxels the places we were casting from
happened to be like sort of along the
bottom here what you would get is you
would definitely get this sort of same
occluding or non occluding behavior of
the light source as you moved around or
other things like that could easily
happen right depending on whether or not
you could see whether or not the
particular ray that was cast to that
voxel center from the light source hits
something or didn't hit something right
so we actually don't really know I mean
although you know it probably is also
there's some bugs in there because we
haven't really done much with that ray
casting stuff but although we don't
really know if there's a bug or not we
just know there might be we also don't
we aren't really doing what we would
want to do anyway
because what we'd like to do is move and
really get started this today I didn't
want to start at the end of last dream
because it's a bunch of work obviously
and kind of moving more towards the full
lighting solution but now today we can
start down that road what we want to do
is use the positioning of these light
probes because that's the whole point of
the light probes right the idea behind
the light probes is that when we build
the level what we want to do is
specifically tell the game here is where
we want you to compute the lighting from
because otherwise we're always gonna
have crazy artifacts that have to do
with the fact that where we choose to do
casting from happens to be like inside
something right so if we actually use
the voxel of the lighting voxel centers
we would be in a lot of trouble because
we would constantly be getting artifacts
similar to these so even if there isn't
or I should say even if what we're
seeing right now is just bugs that we're
gonna go clean up in the actual ray
casting or whatever right we do also
need to address this other potential
source of problems which is the fact
that the precise nature of these
lighting probes
is that we need them to help us not have
weird placement of raycasting
information and that's something that we
have not done yet so we need to do both
of those things both figure out if we've
got other bugs that are in the rake
house is the first time we've turned it
on since we did all the rewriting so if
to fix the raycast or any bugs in there
and then we need to also or maybe we do
this the opposite order we need to be
casting and thinking about the lighting
from the light probe because the whole
reason they're there now they no longer
will even be storing any information
which is kind of cool they're just there
in fact we could we can even say they're
effectively guides there like sampling
guides they're just telling the system
where to sample from they're not even
really storing any lighting information
anymore which is great if it turns out
we can get away get away with that
that's actually really fantastic for a
number of reasons I've explained before
but basically it means we don't have to
track these things through the through
the frame process like we don't have to
go from frame to frame knowing that this
probe and this probe were like the same
probe or anything like that
because all we're doing is throwing
sample points into a system so every
frame we can just throw them in and then
the next frame we can throw in a totally
different set if we wanted to and this
would not affect our ability to execute
the algorithm faithfully that's like
really great right so that's that's a
pretty that would be a pretty a pretty
big deal right so anyway that's where
we're at currently and so we're gonna
have to sort of go through this slowly
because we haven't been you know we
haven't been programming in two weeks
three weeks and so we kind of got to get
back in the swing of things here if you
remember correctly we're calling build
spatial partition for lighting build
spatial partition for lighting is the
thing which basically says okay you know
make some acceleration structure we can
use for faster ray casting we probably
need to do some work on that but that's
what's going on there and then compute
letting propagation as you can see is
turned off that's because we haven't
really gotten to the part where we want
to do secondary bounces that's what
compute light propagation will be for is
for like basically doing secondary
bounces
so what we're doing right now is we're
doing testing and if you remember
correctly what we can do here is we have
some pound affiance those pound defines
determine what kind of lighting test
we're running if I turn to a sphere
based lighting test what you can see is
that we just get the nice radial
fall-off version right and you can see
this has like three separate lighting
spheres I'm sorry four separate lighting
stores because we actually allow four
separate interpolator patterns that
doesn't mean four light sources you can
use an infinite number of light sources
it just means there's four perfect
interpolators in there and so we just
have to output our lighting in a way
that for perfect interpolators could
reconstruct right so it's the same as
sort of saying yeah like if we were
playing say a series of sound effects
let's say right the good way to think
about this is stereo sound right we all
know that stereo sound is sufficient for
playing sound to a spatial sound to a
certain degree what it does is it takes
all the sounds and it mixes them down so
that you put some on the left channel
some on the right channel and some in
both I mean most of them go out and both
at different ratios and that mix down is
basically taking the actual locations of
things trying to roughly figure out what
they would sound like to the left and
right ear and then putting them out
through that those channels right so
effectively you've got tons of sounds
each one has a particular spatial
location and you're trying to mix down
that full set of information into just
two output sounds that will capture what
it should roughly sound like right and
that's exactly the kind of thing we're
doing here we're saying look our output
channel is four perfect things so if we
only add four light sources you could
capture them exactly correctly with the
interpolator but we will probably have
more than four light sources in some
areas or maybe in all areas there'll be
a lot more and in fact really another
way to think about it would be not only
do we have four light sources but
there's all the bounces right so it's a
complete radio it's like a cleat
radiosity solution that we're kind of
gonna have here and so you know
we're trying to do is figure out what
that total lighting solution how do we
best present to the user using only for
playback channels is a good way to think
about it right
so we're effectively trying to say how
do we reconstruct as closely as possible
the lighting solution we want from a
limit that limited number of
interpolation parameters that we have
right but I'm optimistic we'll be able
to do it pretty good right because you
know you can see that it's a pretty good
interpolation reconstructs things pretty
nicely so I think we should be able to
figure out ways doesn't make it work
hopefully all right so that's what we're
working with and so what we need to do
now is start getting the actual lighting
transfer working and what I've did first
is you can see in this this transfer
test I did here what you can see is what
we're doing here is saying look we've
got these voxel cells of our lighting
solution what we're going to do is go
ahead and pack the voxel cells of the
leg solution and send them out so that
basically means that now we're using
kind of for lack of a better term a real
solution right and the real solution is
something we're going to compute up
above right so we're actually now
tracking a solution over time like you
know for reals and what you can see here
is we do have a thing where we're you
know this this is the the actual box
solution here we do have a thing where
we can sort of say what do we actually
want to have happen here you can see the
raycast if I turn off this raycast
so let's suppose I just assumed that all
rays hit and now we're just going to use
the this sort of voxel that remains over
time then what you can see is I think we
I don't think we actually do the copy
the motion copy yet right but what you
can see is other than the frames where
the motion copy would be wrong well you
know what and then it's never gonna be
wrong there's no accumulation this is
just hard set every time so we have to
worry about that what you can see is
this version works just as well as the
other version so we know at least for
our current test purposes there is no
bug in the voxel - voxel thing so the
fact that we've got a stored Vox inline
solution we're out putting that voxel to
the card for interpolation I'm we're not
really seeing any bugs there
right so that's working you okay all
right so what's not working okay is our
rate cast here all we're doing to test
the raycast is just saying look if we
were to take wherever we believe the
voxel center to be right we do a rate
cast on that and where we believe the
light the direction we believe the light
to be in
so we're saying from this voxel Center
we already looked at where the light was
and we did a subtraction to find that
direction right we normalize that and
now we have a unit vector pointing
towards the light source if we call the
ray caster as you can see here and we
look to see is the distance we could get
along this ray less than the distance
that the light actually is if that's the
case then unfortunately we've hit
something and so we can't actually
provide the light in this case right so
it's just a simple shadow binary a
boolean shadow not really something we
want to do in the future because we want
a rich like full bounce solution so
we're gonna use our the stuff we did
before about actually convicting light
around but for testing the ray caster we
would like to just start with a simple
solution which is just like let's see if
we can just say shadow on or off right
and it'll be a kind of crappy lighting
algorithm but it's something we can more
easily visually inspect and what we see
when we turn this on right is we get a
pretty pockmark version of this thing
and so if I run the thing right you can
kind of see now that we get these sort
of weird anomalies and so now the
question is well all right what's busted
right like you know why are we why are
we getting that and our goal here again
is not to make this run because we care
because we don't care this isn't the
lighting we're going to use what we're
trying to do here is say before we
actually get into the weeds of like a
rich lighting solution which we know
will be more complicated in which we
already kind of wrote part of and we're
gonna kind of move into that we're
trying to instead is just test the Ray
casting because since all of our
lighting movement is gonna be based on
doing light tests to see if you can go
from one place to another without
hitting something
we need to first make sure that that's
working and if you remember correctly we
also have this ability to push debug
lines so one things we did at the end of
the last week's last lab close three
weeks ago the last show we did is we
were drawing some debug lines so that we
could actually see what we were looking
at here right and if you look at you
know it's hard to see because the
lighting solution is actually being
applied right but we can pretty
trivially turn that off if we want to as
well but if you look and if you you know
if you look at what we're seeing here
and you kind of look at the at the where
the lines are being drawn the lines that
are being drawn are ones that are saying
that they did hit something so if you
look where the code is actually how this
how this path works out we can see is it
saying look if we are looking at a
particular region because we if we don't
want to draw all the debug lines because
every you know this is a pretty big
thing it's what 16 by 16 by 16 or 32 by
32 by 32 is 32 by 32 by 32 and remember
yeah so it's a 32 by 32 by 32 grid now
32 by 32 when you say that it soundings
it sound pretty small but when you
multiply by 32 again it gets pretty big
right so voxels
are cubic not squared so our intuition
about how big they are tends to be sort
of wrong right you think 32 by 32 bitmap
you're like well that's tiny right but
32 by 32 by 32 well that's quite a few
more right so a thousand lines not that
many lines to see 32,000 lines a little
few too many lines to look at right so
what we wanted to do instead of drawing
all the lines which has just been a mess
of lines and it wouldn't even our boot
overflow our debug buffers anyway
because those don't grow on demand
they're just kind of you know fixed size
or whatever what we need to do is just
you know restrict how big of a region
we're actually looking at there and so
we did here you say okay look inside the
hot corners here we're gonna take the
center we're gonna take minus 4 and plus
4 of the dimension so we're just gonna
look
at a total of like like 1/8 wide bugs
that be 9 wide how do I think about that
I guess it'd be 8 wide because we don't
I don't think we include yeah we did so
right there that's a less than so we're
just looking at an 8 by 8 by 8 right so
we're basically looking at that which is
a much more manageable a number of lines
and they'll only draw when they actually
did hit something so in the case where
some debug line actually hits something
we will actually see it show up here
right so what I'd like to do now is
probably turn off the lighting so that
we can not you know so we don't have to
actually look at that and then dig
deeper into these tests to see are we
seeing something that makes sense
is this Ray Kassar just busted what's
going on so inside our open jail I'm
just gonna turn that lighting off for
now and I think we want this on a switch
I've been a bit lazy and have not been
putting it on a switch here I've just
been kind of doing it this way which is
not particularly good but if you take a
look at at at what this produce is if we
turn the lighting off and run we should
get you know oops one more time what we
should get is something which which
doesn't actually show any of that
lighting it just kind of is a bright you
know full bright thing and when we
rotate around here what you can see is
you should see all of the lines that we
drew that that we're casting lines and
what happened to them right now if we
look and I don't know if we really can
but if we look in here I'm hoping what
we will see yeah um so if you look at
what happens here it kind of looks like
these are correct to a certain extent I
mean some of them at least look correct
because if you look at all of these
lines all of these lines were casting up
and they do look like they stop right
where they would have hit something
right like there's right where at that
thing stops you can see it doesn't go
through it at all right
so all of these
autum pieces Rick all of that you know
those all said look we couldn't you know
we weren't able to hit the thing you
know we didn't Minh able to get to the
light source so all of this shadowing
that you would expect to happen kind of
all the way up through here does look
like it is in fact happening and
furthermore if you look outside here
right you can see that the shadowing
there also appears to be working right
those appear to be stopping right about
at the edge right so all of those appear
to be working now there are some things
at least you know from what I'm seeing
here that look like you know they're not
working so for example right I don't
know exactly where this light actually
is but you know if you look at where all
these things are pointed at looks like
it's right there and that comports with
what we set it to we set it to where
that hero was plus a little bit so it's
like just floating over the hero's head
so if I look you know and I I say what's
going on here you look at these rays and
you're like what did they hit you know I
mean I don't see anything
these lines are terminating in midair
and I don't know what they would be
terminating what the termination is
actually resulting from it looks like
there's sort of a phantom thing here
that they're hitting and furthermore
that phantom thing doesn't even really
look particularly obvious what the shape
of it is almost I and similarly if you
look at like you know some of these
other ones here like I don't know what
that is happening they're just very
strange and so you know I mean I could
convince myself if I was you know trying
to make excuses that maybe like the
somehow we put in a collision volume for
like the lamp and it got output as a
blocker or something but and that
doesn't sound right
and as far as I recall only actual
visible cubes we're getting sent down as
blocker is the last
I'm I checked so to me this says our
rate caster is probably busted and what
we should probably do before we go any
further is take a look at what's going
on here and try to figure out why our
rate caster is so messed up now there's
good news and bad news here I think the
good news is if you look at this rate
casting you know maybe let me go in and
do a slight change in fact I can just
leave it running um let me go ahead and
say when we're doing this casting here
let me cast all the lines really quickly
here and just change the color so I'm
gonna do a line color here and I'm gonna
say that the line color is gonna be you
know this or something else okay I
probably can't do that I'm gonna say the
line color is this and then I'm gonna
draw it always right so what I'm going
to do is I'm going to take this this hit
information here and I'm going to change
this so that we're actually just doing
an f1 so we're always gonna draw the
lines and then the line color is gonna
be based on whether or not you hit
instead just so I can see all of the
lines now so here's the line color it's
going to be set to to this and then if
you hit I'm gonna set something else so
I'm just gonna say like in fact maybe
what I'll do is I'll just do it this way
so we will get like a yellow line in the
cases where we hit something and we'll
get a black line in the cases where we
didn't right and so here you can see
perhaps a more interesting version of
the Ray casting result you can see very
clearly where the actual light is now
right and you can see that it's not the
world's worst solution in some ways
because some of them look very accurate
like
that looks like a pretty accurate hit
test name well actually doesn't know I
think about it that does but if you look
like there's a bunch of sort of in
Congress things happening in the ones
that don't hit as well because for
example you know to my eye I'm looking
at that that stuff in there right some
of these things that are protruding and
if I go inside here you can kind of see
like alright that that does look like
it's hitting they're all stopping like
right at the thing which is even weirder
because that's sort of almost me that
almost sounds like this this part right
here is wrong which maybe it is like
this tear a less than light distance I'm
wondering if that's somehow incorrect
meaning the Ray caster is maybe actually
producing somewhat correct results in
certain cases that we are then saying
aren't hitting you know so you see
there's just a lot going wrong there
it's not good so let's start by going
into ray cast and seeing effectively
what's going on here and what we may
want to do is we may want to sort of
extend out our notion of how we're
drawing these debug lines we may want to
draw these debug lines like in the
actual ray caster itself as well just or
you know output some additional debug
information just while we're debugging
this to make sure we sort of have a
rough idea of what's going on in here
all right
so we're looking here how does this ray
caster work well we start by you know
doing some statistics you can see in
here we count some things we don't
really care about that right now because
we're not looking at performance so we
can pretty much ignore that code you can
see that the way the Ray caster works
it's got a stack this stack is four
boxes that we're going to collide
against and the Box stack is basically
because we have what amounts to a
hierarchy sort of a bounding volume
hierarchy right our BBH that is based on
like you know rectangular solids and
what we do is we start by just putting
the root box which contains all our
boxes onto the box stack and then we
just kind of traverse through it ray
casting going down as we as we go so in
order to initiate our ray cast we start
by saying alright the tier a is equal to
the maximum T value you can possibly
have so that's like saying look let's
assume we hit nothing we just travel
infinitely far along the Ray that we're
given this is the direction this is the
starting point so we're starting here
we're going in that direction we start
by assuming we can go infinitely far
just as far as we want we then say all
right let's load some constants we're
gonna need for some testing I don't know
if those are still needed anymore we can
check to see in fact you know what I
could check right now to see if they're
needed because I don't know we changed a
little bit of house routine works so we
may not need the constants anymore I'm
not sure so I may have def the map just
to see which ones were used here so it
looks like we don't use negative one
anymore but it does look like but you
use one so we then go to let me just
make sure that's true to just want to so
T close enough what T close enough was
and I think we sort of turned this off
and we may want to turn it off again
just for checking but there is
effectively a thing that we would do to
Yeah right here where basically what we
do is we if we decided that this thing
was like too far away for us to care so
you know once we cast array more than 10
metres long we don't go down the
bounding volume hierarchy anymore
because we just assumed look this thing
is too far away for us to really care
and so what we'll probably do is set
this value to something that's sort of a
similar to our lighting fall-off rate so
when we do our lighting like whatever
the actual fall-off is for our lining we
will set that so that at some point we
just don't care about the shadows very
much right we don't care about the light
motion around for things that are too
far away because the amount of light
they're able to contribute just isn't
big enough right so then here we're
going to say look we are going to pre
compute what the inverse ray Direction
is that's going to be used for our box
collision detecting and then we're just
gonna go ahead and get started so we
loop over our bounding volume hierarchy
by saying while there are still boxes on
the stack that we are supposed to be
colliding against we will pull the first
box off of the stack right like so we
will loop over all of the children
inside that box right so like these are
the things that that box contains and we
will then do a collision test against
the box in order to do that we load the
boxes position and mind you all of these
are being done four at a time right and
the way they're being done four at a
time is we are testing for different
light rays at the same time right so
when we say we have a ray origin in the
Ray direction what we're actually saying
is oh actually we're casting for arrays
hopefully roughly in the same direction
and we're going from there all right so
when we come in here we then say and by
the way in our test case we're only
casting one because you can see in here
we just load up the exact same thing
for so we're only casting one actual ray
in here but in the normal case we would
cast four at a time then that's for
speed that's to leverage the semi
hardware so we then compute the minimum
and maximum box locations by adding the
radius of the box right to produce the
minimum and maximum corners we then take
the inverse ray D we basically are
computing the minimum box the minimum
time to hit the box and the maximum time
to hit the box or I should say we're
taking the time to hit the maximum
corner of the box and the time to hit
the minimum corner of the box in each
dimension you know in each dimension
we're computing those by using the
inverse of the Ray Direction here right
so one over the Raider and again the
reason for that is we're trying to do a
fast box collision so we're trying to
avoid doing divides here so we pre
divide that Ray direction and we do the
Hadamard so we just do the you know
vector Hadamard product could get what
we think those T's will be we then take
whichever one of those is the best right
so the one that we would hit first
and that's done by a series of minimum
min and Max steps so we say the minimum
is going to go through here so we take
the T box Minh and T box and we take the
minimum of those maybe the maximum by
doing the P box
min and Max maximum and then we take the
T min and the T max which is the
earliest we hit in the latest we hit by
again taking the maximum of the
components of those right and then when
we're done and we look at like what the
maximum side is we just see look when we
egg you know when we were to hit the if
you think about what this is doing it's
saying we have array we have two T
values one where it enters the box and
one where it exits the box in a sense
right if the place where we exited the
box is less than zero that means that
the entire box is behind where
asking from so we would not that's what
this any true is here for we would not
want to consider this box as something
to rip something that can produce a
usable collision because it's behind us
and the reason that we can have that
happen is because math doesn't really
work particularly well on things that
only go in one direction not the band
but actually just in one direction and
to be honest I bet the band One
Direction is not very good at math
either but in this case what we're
saying is look we need to know the T
values along this line and then what
we're doing is saying if they're less
than zero then they're on then they're
behind us because we're talking about
only one direction so that's what's
happening here
so this is the first test that says okay
we don't actually want to know about
collisions that happen that aren't even
the direction we're looking we then say
all right
now what we need to do is say are we
inside this box and what we're trying to
do here is say look if anybody who was
correctly on the correct side now the
you might say what's this for the reason
we have to do these extra checks is cuz
member doing four raised at a time so
max pass may have resulted in true for
only one of those raise and the other
three may have been false so what we
need to do is say now are we inside
anybody and the way we would know if we
were inside is did anybody pass on team
min right we're team in was behind us
but past unmet on T max so T Max is in
front of us that would bracket our
starting location so the origin of the
Ray would be inside the box that's what
this is saying and that's why it's
called T inside right pretty well
labeled good for us we then look at T
valid and what T valid says is all right
if T min is ahead of us and T min is
less than T Max so it means we're not in
some weird like inverted space where you
know we didn't really register a proper
collision or something like this because
you know one side hit something in the
other side never hit the other thing or
who
what so if we're actually in the case
where like the team is less than the
team acts and the team in is is greater
right than zero this is a real hit
this means we looked at a direction we
did hit something and we now have the
p-value in team in of what the hit
actually was so at team in we hit a box
right the mask is just something that's
telling us whether or not this
particular kit that we found if we found
one right that's why we're anding with T
valid the mask is just telling us for
this particular hit are any of them less
than the actual Rea we found so far
because remember we're gonna test tons
of boxes T ray starts out at f3 to max
so the first time we find a valid hit
that will actually you know be one we
take but then every hit after that we
only want to accept a team in that's
less than the hit we already found
because otherwise we'll actually be
moving our hit further away
right but the closest hit is the one
that stops the Ray so this test here is
used to figure out which one actually
which hits are actually new valid hits
and which ones are hits that happen past
the hit closest hit we already have
close enough again is just saying look
if we have a new closest hit that's
closer than a hit we've already had and
it's close enough that we would descend
through the hierarchy then we're gonna
want to descend right and that's what we
do here box child kind of saying okay
look if anyone is inside this box right
so we're a casted from insider right or
any buddy was close enough hit that it's
probably within our best it's probably
in our best interest to descend because
this box is within our threshold for
where we want to start you know where we
want to keep looking right then we go
ahead and continue down the hierarchy
now to be honest I don't think this is a
pretty this is not probably the metric
that we want the reason I don't think
this metric is the metric we want is
because T close enough should probably
be based on how big the box is
so we probably want to go down the
hierarchy based not on just a fixed
value but on how how much how high up
the hierarchy this box was so I would
probably say something like and so what
this is saying is essentially when we do
this raycast
if we're right next to something
obviously we want to traverse into its
children and see what the specific hit
is but if we're far away from it well
how detailed was this box if this is a
fairly detailed box meaning we've gone
down the hierarchy like one or two steps
if we're you know only maybe 10 units
out
we should probably still traverse it if
we're 20 units out maybe we would right
and then as we go down further if we're
like five steps down the hierarchy maybe
now you know even 30 steps out we
wouldn't traverse it right so I think we
want that you know that level of detail
parameter to be based on where we are in
the hierarchy so that we open up boxes
and look at them more or less as we get
further away more continuously and not
just like all right everything within 10
units gets done exactly and everything
outside 10 units doesn't get done at all
it's not a very good sort of it's not a
very good log level of detailed policy
to me so I think we want to look at that
but that is not probably related to our
problem here because unless I'm
misinterpreting the meaning of 10 units
here and there's some kind of scale that
I'm not thinking about that's actually
in play 10 meters is way longer than
those erroneous ones we were already
looking at which means that our bug is
not really related to this
we have some other bug if I'm
interpreting that right if I'm not then
that could very well be implicated in
our bug but so then we look and say if
we're going to traverse you know we do
right but if we're not going to traverse
then what we need to do is see if any of
these rays actually want to be recorded
if any of the Rays actually did hit then
we're in good shape right we we kind of
know that we want to want to keep going
and what we want to do here say all
right we're gonna accept all of the new
team ins that that passed our mask test
so the valid hits that were closer than
hits we already have we are going to
accept them we're also going to record
the center radius color and emission of
the box in that case so that later we
can do our actual work on it now again
one of the problems here is we're not
really recording them the normal and
that was the problem that we had before
I'm not sure how we're gonna deal with
that to be honest in the future we may
just not where it's mine do I not have
tissues here oh tissue fail all right
it's very sad before I forget I'm gonna
make myself a note streaming setup needs
tissues note to self
good thing it's not allergy season err
that would have been a real problem all
right there we go and so what I'm more
or less doing here is just saying look
take the parts take for all our four
arrays that we're casting accept anybody
who is the new closest hit and you can
see us kind of doing that there and what
we're gonna do about the normals in the
future
I don't know we store those Center and
radius so we can recompute them but it's
kind of hard to recompute and you know
we'll see uh previously in the code we
had how to think here and you could see
me putting it to do in there where we
said look if all if everything in the
mask is true right and what that means
is that this particular hit hit all four
all four arrays at the same thing right
then for some reason we would break out
like we just that would be it
I don't understand why I don't
understand what that was for I don't
even know why you would ever care about
that like I can't even really tell
i I have literally no idea why that
would even be a condition we thought we
should be checking because it's
effectively saying look is this
particular set where we hit all these
things we're leaving the loop here I did
I just have no idea why we thought that
was good you know maybe we were trying
to something like saying look at some
point we know that all of the boxes that
come next have to be further away than
we are right so we can leave the routine
at that point and not worry about it I
don't see how this this condition isn't
that it's not even related to that so I
just feel like this had to be a case of
us being dumb I just you know summer on
the track and tell me if there was some
better reason for it but I think that
was just wrong I can't see any reason
why this would ever produce a reasonable
result and what I assumed was happening
here
is I assume this case was effectively
never occurring because when we would
actually cast for raise we had not
actually put in coherent race election
at that point so we weren't like sending
them out in similar directions at all
either which basically meant that we
would probably never in one hit test one
box would probably never stop all four
race or at least almost never stop so we
probably weren't seeing bugs related to
this only because it never actually did
anything that's my guess so I'm gonna go
ahead and delete that because I can't
see any reason why that would actually
do anything useful but my my feeling on
it is that there could be something done
here where we do actually check I mean
you know for example let's suppose we
took tier a you know here we could do a
check in fact I'll put it to do here
so basically what we could do here is
say hey we know what the T ray values
are so far what we could do is say test
to see whether or not anything in this
parent box could ever possibly be closer
than the close than what we've already
got for our four arrays and and
basically don't don't process it if it
isn't right if this whole box is further
away than where we've already found our
closest collisions we don't need to look
at it right because all we could ever
find is collisions that are too far to
be accepted by our bye-bye-bye this
right
and so I do think that is pretty
important in fact in fact I think that's
something we should just do like in
other words I guess we don't even need
that it's just masks so correct me if
I'm wrong I mean just hear me out here
this really should just be here
like this meaning obviously any closer
oh sorry not quite true so if we're
inside we need to do it if we're inside
or we are close enough and could be
closer than the current hit right so if
there's a child count and we are either
inside the box in which case we
definitely do it or we are close enough
and the the possible closeness of this
thing could result in an actual hit we
accept then we would Traverse now so I
would argue that's almost certainly
necessary because otherwise we're going
to waste a bunch of time processing
boxes that we didn't need to because
they couldn't possibly produce a hit we
would ever actually use right so the
bount when we hit the bounding box of
the parent the parent bounding box if if
that hit isn't closer certainly none of
the things inside it could be closer
unless we ourselves are inside it and
that's a test we were already doing
right so I'm gonna go ahead and say that
has to happen right then we can go on in
here and say all right now we're gonna
do the acceptance test and and you know
record the fact that we used a leaf here
and off we go
so then we come down here and we say all
right now we actually have to compute
what the heck happened we take a hit
position and we compute that by taking
the Raritan adding the you know the rate
erection times the the distance we went
we then do a bunch of work here to try
and reconstruct the normal you can see
that being reconstructed here in a
pretty janky way it's not good
right I don't really know
I mean I don't really know I don't
really know what the best way to do this
is I really don't so this is probably
janky but you know this for our current
purposes we don't have to care about
this at all because the only thing that
we need to know is that the hip key and
the t-ray right those are the only
things we're really caring about at the
moment and so if you look at this
equation here this is the only one we're
actually using and that's the origin
plus the distance we thought we went
times the direction equals the location
we believed to have hit that's the only
property care about the rest of this
stuff is for completing the normal which
we don't actually know it's correct or
not at this point and we don't care
because we're not using it for anything
so we will care eventually about that
but otherwise we're fine
so if you look at what this is doing
here I guess I would say so far you know
walking through that routine other than
the fact that I think there was an
inefficiency there like we should have
added this right but that's just for
efficiency I I didn't see the obvious
bug right look I didn't see an error in
there and so I don't really know what
our issue is and we're gonna have to dig
into this pretty hard I think to find
out what's going on all right so if we
look at what we're seeing here I think
the first thing I need to do is try to
isolate myself down to a raycasting case
that I actually know specifically which
one it is and so what do they do because
I you know this is casting you know
thousands and thousands of rays here
tens of thousands of rays every frame
that is not gonna cut it for debugging
right I have no idea what I was looking
at we've been stepping through the thing
forever it wouldn't help so I think what
we want to do first is isolate a
particular case just one of these and it
just so happens I think there's a pretty
easy way for me to do that I can take a
false-positive so something that that
you know was saying it hits something
and definitely didn't this yellow line
right here
that's not that hard to figure out which
one that is because if you look at where
it is it's on the outside of two
dimensions and it's one down from the
other at the top right so if I was to
pull up into my voxel code where I'm
already trimming the debug lines so let
me go ahead noobs that's not good
let me go ahead and actually jump to
that code that's that's outputting a
debug line and what I want to do here is
change this from doing a region right so
I'm gonna I'm gonna keep this code
around in case I want it later but what
I'm gonna do instead is I'm going to
make sort of a special-purpose version
here where instead of this and I'm Mouse
I'm also going to put this out into a
tester here where I do like b32 is test
cast right and I'm just gonna record a
very specific one of these so what I
want to do here is delete you know the
bottom half of this thing and just look
for one specific one of these and so
what I want I think here is I want to
look at you know the the furthest in
like X&amp;Y and then like not quite the
furthest in Z or something like that
right and then I'm gonna say all right
and in fact you know what we could do to
here is I could make this actually be I
can make this actually just be if is
test cast and then we'll just capture
this range query into this right and so
that way now I have an easy way of
isolating a particular line and the
reason I'm doing that is because I want
to be able to set up you know this sort
of nice yeah I want to be able to set up
this sort of nice test case where I know
exactly
which line it is that I'm looking at so
I can step through it right and so if we
look at the code here and I run this now
I want to go ahead and see oh it looks
like I picked the wrong Y so actually no
it was the it was the furthest back of
the Y I don't know why I stopped the
program I always forget that the hot
code reloading will take care of my nice
time um and so it looks like we be bingo
down on that right so there's a single
test line being drawn and it is wrong as
far as we can tell right that that does
not look valid to me right so now what I
can do is downshift into debug build and
actually step through and see what the
hey is going on there right and so in
this test cast case where we do this
line here I can now do a breakpoint
right before I go to cast I can do a
breakpoint on that test cast and know
exactly what I'm getting so like this I
can just put a line of code there that I
can stop on if I choose and step through
the actual caster to see what it's
actually doing you know what I mean
so as we run and and produce that
erroneous line in the slower build now
you can kind of see this happening right
the rake after is super slow right if
you don't run it in release mode right
because it's yeah it's it's doing 32,000
things so if each one gets a little
slower it it will slow down quite a bit
but I don't care because I don't have to
do anything in this mode I just need to
know about that raycast
so if I now open up the lighting code
here inside the debugger which will be
you there I can go to that piece of the
code and set a breakpoint effectively on
that test which is right here right so
what I want to do now is go all right
stop there and this is in theory our
erroneous test so this is the one that's
gonna think it hit something but it
never actually hit anything right and
the first thing I would like to do is
I'd like to know a little bit more about
the the actual case first so before I
even step into it I just want to look at
what these are right so we have a hit
value of 1 which is what we'd expect how
far away was the light distance right so
in this case it's 6.5 meters away
theoretically if you look at the casting
information and we look at what we're
getting for T ray you can see that we're
getting something significantly closer
than that right it's saying that it only
took four meters to hit something and in
order to get to the light you needed to
travel 6.5 meters right so something's
fishy they're not good now we don't know
much more than that because we can't
really see the diagram what I will say
is 6 meters mmm you know I guess that
roughly comports with I mean that I
think our game skills maybe not quite
realistic in terms of meters so I
shouldn't say meters because it's
probably not really meters at this point
but you know is that completely
ridiculous I'm not sure yet but that's
what we're being told if I rerun the
loop again so did not get step into the
Ray Kassar I'm going to look at what
some of these values are more
specifically so what we're gonna do is
we're gonna start off with the root box
and we would expect to traverse down the
root box so I'm hoping that we hit this
case here and we do right so we push
that box down on the stack and then
we'll have to see in here we we missed
this case
and I'm not sure why let's take a look
at what this box says so this is a this
is a bounding volume used for actually
it is actually containing sub volumes we
rejected it I'm not sure why exactly but
in fact you know what I might do here
before we continue down this route let's
pull those out into billions we can see
you know just so we can inspect them
more easily so if I jump to the right
caster I don't know why I'm not just
jumping directly to it if we actually go
through here and just set up some
billions here now I can see exactly why
we went into this so by looking at the
child camp that any inside the any
closer than close enough I can see
specifically which thing caused us to
Traverse down into it or not right or to
skip that case so let's try that again
and now let's go back
stretch okay so in here i want to break
only on the test case so let's skip
those I'm gonna go into the castor
we're gonna watch ourselves go down the
route box first so that's there then
we're going to go and maybe I'll set the
break point now all right so that one's
failed on Macs pass so that was weird
wasn't it I mean that was different than
the last time oh you know what
hmm so we do have one issue here that is
I guess I don't know if while this
camera moves are we gonna get different
results because is the voxel moving with
the camera at all it might be
[Music]
so one thing that we might want to do is
so let me I should probably verify
whether that's true or not but what I
was gonna say is we might want to make
it so that the camera starts off at a
known good location so that we don't do
that sort of interpolation
I just don't want to have a situation
where we like I feel like we need to
skip the first frame I guess is what I'm
saying so let's do that and maybe I'll
put a piece of code in there that skips
the first frame so we don't have to do
it manually all right now let's go in so
in theory this should be the same as
before
Sumi so there's this going down the
route and there's a skipping max pass on
the next one so this is the same as it
was before so I'm not sure what's
happening there exactly there's all fall
out of scope I wish you could still
inspect variables I know George did a
little bit of work on that and so now
you can't expect variables on the
closing brace but only on the closing
brace all right so we're traversing this
one let me just put these up in here
so you can see like all of them I guess
are close enough let's actually view
these values too so if we actually look
at what these values end up being owing
the mask the easiest way is probably
just to look at like yeah like one of
these
so maybe what I'll do is like Matthew 3
to 0 like so and I don't actually know
how to there we go
I'm like I want that to be in
hexadecimal so it's easier to see so
this value should be just ffffff or zero
right like all these master devalue it
to all ones or all zeroes in general I
believe and so if we look at these like
all of these computations here should
probably be expressed this way so we can
kind of see like what we're looking at
here and then these should correspond
like with it
what is it's not T closer so
so any closer is just a mask actually
yeah all right
um so that's really what we're looking
at here so these should probably be
reordered so we've got any inside any
close enough any closer so you can see
here here's our values and they're doing
exactly what would expect so extracting
the mask out here is working properly it
does exactly what we think it should do
and so nothing particularly weird there
we can also look at the box child cap to
know if this thing is you know basically
a container node and so as we're doing
these collisions here we can also take a
look at the T min value which is the the
primarily important value here and I can
just look at the T min I guess I'll just
do like the dot e zero value there and
I'm gonna look at the T ray as well
which is our current best so you can see
in this case it's like well anything is
gonna be better because currently we
haven't recorded to hit yet so
anything's gonna be better than that
here's where we believe our hit to be um
it would be nice if I had some way of
really figuring out where that was like
but you know this is one of the problems
with with this is I don't know there's
much of a way to do that so I'm gonna
I'm gonna like step through this sort of
gaining a little bit of insight here but
then what I'm probably gonna do is
augment this with some drawing calls
because since debuggers today
still can't do much drawing even remedy
unfortunately can't draw out things for
us it'd be pretty hard for us to know
how reasonable these values actually are
cuz they don't look obviously wrong but
they could be subtly wrong you know I'm
saying to you so here we go again we're
gonna now we're kidding a node we're not
going to descend right so there's two
children and this one and we're not
going to send into it so we're gonna use
it as an actual Collider we're gonna see
here that means that something was close
sir and we're not inside it and it
wasn't close enough to descend right so
if we look at the actual hit it's at
11:00 and so we don't actually care like
that that's not the hit we ever end up
recording we know that that's not the
hit so we don't really have to worry
about that one much oh let me put the
depth up there as well so we're
currently just at the top we don't have
a stack right now there's just this one
so we don't need to traverse that guy
wait in that case how did we if we were
already on depth zero
how did oh because we're still looking
through children sorry so we're still
looking through the children of this and
so this one must actually be what we
wanted so you can see here we're taking
a hit on the T valve there we're getting
sort of a we probably tested two sides
of a split basically and we're
traversing the near side of the split so
we should probably you know we're
probably gonna do that for a little bit
you know we're traversing down and
getting the near sides to sort of get
down to the place where we actually are
here and then at some point we should
actually start hit testing somebody I
know how far down our bounding box our
could goes but it's not a very good
batting bisector by the way
all right so here we're recording
another hit you can see in this case the
the actual hit that we wanted or the
actual hit that we took right now if we
look here this is an actual node it's
not a container so we are recording what
we believe to be a valid hit of an
actual box we think that box was close
enough we are not inside it it is less
than 10 meters which is true it's closer
than our current hit which was also true
of course we just over wrote it and
we're keeping it right that there is the
actual you know that the only thing we
could really say here cuz everything
looks correct so the only thing we could
really say there is either we have put
in a box that is actually here so the
box is erroneous right either we put in
an erroneous box and are correctly hit
testing against it or we did put in the
correct boxes and this this code is
erroneous right this part right here the
computer computes the T because then
this part looks like it's working
correctly this T value is the closest T
value it should have been recorded so
the only way that we could really have
gotten this wrong is if these values
coming in are wrong so this p and radius
are wrong and you know like I said
that's why we gonna have to start
drawing this because if we look at the
box P and the box radius here we're not
gonna see anything right I mean okay
it's a 5.5 by 0.5 by 0.5 box right do we
have any boxes like that I don't know
like a one meter by one meter by one
meter box right has anyone put one of
those in no idea maybe they have I don't
know so we don't really know
but we know that someone put it in there
is that reasonable or is it not we'll
have to find out and then this is the
location of the box again reasonable or
not no idea so I think what we need to
do is draw these boxes okay so we can
see what we actually hit tested against
so what I'm going to do here is inside
the raycast er I'm going to basically
have a toggle run time toggle that's
like debugging or something right so in
here I want to have a debugging just for
our purposes right now I'm going to turn
that on when we're doing just this one
pass and what I'm doing that pass then
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
push debug lines down to show us where
the actual box is right so the way I'm
going to do that is just do if debugging
I want to draw this box I also probably
want to say which kind of box it is
right
maybe I'll do it this way so I'm gonna
take a box if it has children it's gonna
be purple if it's not to me science so
the cyan boxes are gonna be ones that we
actually test against um and I want to
draw these things you know I might even
want to do this a little bit fancier
right so I might want to do a thing here
where we say all right set this box
color up here black and then maybe I
want to actually want to do is just set
the box color inside two different
things so if we look let's say we're
gonna traverse down this thing right
we're gonna set it to a new guess
another color here or if we actually hit
this thing we're gonna set a color here
so if we Traverse down it we're gonna
set it to purple if we don't if we hit
it we're gonna set it to yellow and
maybe we might want even more than that
later but you know for now we'll just
leave with that and then what I'm gonna
do is I'm going to push debug lines down
to just draw the box right so if we look
at the push debug line call we just need
to pass the lighting solution which we
have and then we're gonna have the from
p2p and the color so we know what the
box color is because we already put that
down
so you just need the from P and the to P
right and so to do that we kind of know
we can draw this by just using the box P
and the box radius and we computed the
box min and Max so I'm gonna use the Box
minimax since that's something we
actually have right so Fox min X Box min
Y box min Z like so we're gonna go we're
going to use this
like so and we're just gonna draw the
debug liens that constitute the edges of
the cube so we're well of the box it's
not a cute so if you're thinking about
how to draw the edges of a box right
well we know that we've got six phases
we know that we've got eight vertices
and we know that the edges that connect
them right we have four edges around one
side of the box four edges around the
other side of the box so that's eight
edges and then we have four more edges
that connect those two sides right so we
know we're gonna have twelve lines to
draw right and those lines go you know
between the mins and the max is only but
different combinations of them so for
example if I just wanted to draw one of
the Rings I could say well let's draw
the ring around box mean X then what I
would do is say well you know okay we go
from min Y to like max Y from Max Y -
max Y max Z from Max Y to max why oops
back to min Y is that right yeah and
then back to the man right and so now
what should happen is if I want to turn
this on and what are you complaining
about
none of the over those convert all of
the types oh right so yeah that's a v3
so I need to extract just one component
of this I assume I can do that
just test to see if that works yeah so I
should be good now I'm just gonna go get
out from behind my now smaller head and
I do need to get the push debug line
call up one because we're now calling it
from inside the red caster all right so
now if I run it what I should see is one
ring you know four boxes that I'm
drawing here
I should see one ring I'm gonna skip
stepping through here I just want to
look and see what it draws right I
should see one ring for each box as I
process it if I turn on that debug flag
so right now I'm not seeing anything I'm
gonna go over here I'm also gonna I
don't need to be in debug mode for a
while while I'm looking at these
diagrams I can just do it directly so
we're we call this ray cast function now
not there that's the regular one that
we're gonna try and get to eventually
I'm just gonna pass true for debugging
and so now when we actually build we
should be able to oh you know what I
realized that was wrong way too many
lines what I meant is is test case
because I only want to draw them on the
test case sorry about that
forgot about that I'm just like oh we
want to draw them only wanted wrote on
the test case should there be way too
many um so what you can see here is
we're drawing the boxes now right but
we're only drawing like one ring of the
box right right away you can see there's
some weirdness going on here right so
that's not probably good but you know
let's finish drawing this first and and
we'll go from there
so gonna jump back to the raycast
don't ask me why close the program
doctor we can't just leave the program
running and in here I was gonna draw the
rest of these right so there's our box
min and Max stuff let's draw one more
ring oops so this is just the
corresponding ring so now it should draw
two rings per box and they can kind of
see them happening there right and some
of these make some sense like those look
like big bounding boxes what which is
what we would expect right others not so
much like I'm not sure what that box
could be and that kind of suggests to me
that our box positions are bad because
if you look at what's going on there
like it looks like it's hitting a box
that actually does exist so that
suggests that our box Pease is wrong you
know what I mean like like we got some
issues that's fine we'll deal with that
in a second but you know let's finish
drawing our boxes first so then it'll
come through here I'll draw the last set
and what this is going to be is this is
just drawing between the min and Max X
so that means that here we're gonna keep
the same thing for each of these right
so we're gonna do min min max min Max
Max and Max min yeah sorry min max yeah
and here we're just drawing between the
X rings cuz we drew one ring around min
x one ring around max X and now we just
need to connect those two up and now
we've got a full box drawn so now when
the live code reloading reloads the
changes you can see here now we've got
like boxes and like I said some of them
look correct so like if you look at the
bounds here it does look like we had a
box that contained well you know I'm not
sure
I guess I'm not sure why this region
doesn't look contained so I will say I'm
a little weirded out by some of this
because if you look at what's going on
like some of it looks pretty good so
right you've got like boxes here in here
that appear to perfectly bound the world
the way I would expect but there's
nothing containing this part of the
world over here and if you look at the
lighting bounds anyway
the lighting bounds at least do extend
out to there so I'm not super sure oh
you know what no it's okay it's just
faint so there it is you can see there's
a black bar okay so it is they just
worked reversed so that's fine all right
so if you look at the hits here you can
see we hit this one because it's too far
away we did a hit against that one we
then sort of Traverse down you can see
exactly the pattern here we kept
traversing down we've got people who are
enclosing our light cubes and that
doesn't really make any sense but that's
what was actually happening there this
cube I don't know what the heck is going
on there
let's try to determine which kind of box
that is I don't know where that box is
coming from it doesn't look like a bound
so it looks like a box
someone actually stuck into the system
that's it like just the wrong place yeah
you got me man so you come in here we're
taking a look at this box here what I
want to do is say okay this box color
it's going to come out as zero zero zero
and then when we come in here we're
gonna set it if we're gonna traverse it
to this or if we hit it to this what I
don't like is if we hit the box I want
to know whether or not it was a actual
aggregate box or not that's the thing I
wanted to know so basically like in this
case I want to say if it had a child
count I want to see one thing and if I
if it wasn't I want to you know
so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
set it to cyan in the case where we like
if if the box in question is actually a
container box that we are just testing
against because of the farness or not
for this in this over way and then I
only want to see as yellow so you can
see that happening here right like that
was a box that we just said well it's
too far away so we test against it right
get the but if it's a box that's close
enough to be tested all the way down and
we hit against an actual box in the end
that's right here you can see that
happening so something's busted that's
just wrong
that's saying that there was an actual
physical box placed there by the game
and it is asking us to collide against
it right furthermore our light probes
themselves because they are that would
explain a lot of that pockmarking as
well our light probes themselves are
actually considered colliders that's a
mistake we didn't want that so we should
probably go ahead and eliminate those as
well so like that has to happen so yeah
we got a couple of different things we
got to do now let's start by removing
those from the system and see what
happens I'm not sure and then this will
probably remain and and then off we go
so in the push cube Hall you can see in
the push cube call we're passing this
down here and we don't really want that
like we don't want this thing to be an
actual occluder I don't really know how
we want to handle that I also don't know
what the hey the Z bias needs to be
there for anymore but I guess we were
doing some stuff with that for rendering
purposes but I want to look at the
places we're calling push cube I don't
think there's that many of them and what
you can see here is if I go global on it
the places we're calling it like other
than the render test code right I
inside like yeah inside the asset
rendering and the enemy code you can see
exact where they called I want to know
which ones of those actually want
collision geometry right we don't care
about that you don't care about this
stuff and what I think we might want is
like an actual occluder call here right
yeah I mean I guess what I would say
probably I guess what I would say is
probably what we want here is something
where only you know we can where we only
push occluder stuff on when we actually
wanted to right cuz I can turn that off
but what I really want is like only
these things would have occluders on
them right so when we call push cube
here we would say like you know a flag
or something that says that this thing
is going to be included or you know we
do like that there right because if you
look in push cube this is the only code
that actually cares about it right so I
kind of feel like that code really wants
to be its own path so I think I might do
that so in here we would say like look
get rid of this right have a thing on
here and it's like
like that and this will actually be the
code we care about so we'll say is the
lighting enabled letting it enable is
enabled will you know do what we have to
do here we need to know some stuff like
we need to know what the color is so
that's got to be on there we need to
know what the P and the radius R so
let's get those on there but other than
that I don't think you really need to
pass much and this way we'll only do it
when we really actually need to write
the texture index you don't know if we
actually want to ever use those I'm
gonna go ahead and guess that we
probably don't really I think we can't
afford to do texture lookups in the
right caster so I'm gonna get rid of
that for now and I'm gonna say that we
we just really have that P radius R FC
is all we're gonna actually initialize
right in fact I could leave these in
here temporarily but I think we're gonna
want to get rid of these like so
all right this will literally just push
exactly the same thing right so I'm just
gonna I'm gonna put these into variables
that I can pass to both and then we're
gonna try and figure out what's going on
here so yeah what what are you
complaining about
what is the missions supposed to be it's
not just a single value yeah all right
so render group p value and then it
needs the color and then we're good to
go and now we shouldn't have those
bounce anymore yeah and we don't write
so I think
so I mean I guess that's good in a sense
but I probably need to temper it now
that I have that which I need working I
think I kind of temporarily want to
re-enable it though because I to debug
that sort of bad case right because that
case still looked wrong and I just kind
of need it to still be doing what it's
doing so that I can figure out what why
we actually got boxes placed in those
locations for no apparent reason right
and and I'm not sure yeah like let me
turn on lighting briefly so I can also
just see what our current status is
because I'm not actually sure what that
will look like either but if I go ahead
and and recompile this guy
that seems nonsensical so now you're
telling me
now you're telling me there is no
waiting what am I missing
oh why that's not what it's saying uh
that's just because we threw everything
out so yeah in this case we're not
actually doing the test for whether or
not the thing actually hit so you can
see here we would still need to do this
right
so that makes more sense so I just want
to see what happens so I can know to
what extent we're getting erroneous
recasting now versus not so it looks to
me like we're still getting those
erroneous cases they're different now to
be sure but you know it's still kind of
a little odd right what we're seeing
there so I I could I guess what I could
do is double check now if I can just
switch back and debug a different rate
case so let me look really quickly and
see if I can just do bug a different one
first
because if I can then it's good to get
those extraneous things out of the tree
so I'm not like constantly wondering
like why is there this little box there
or whatever so I would like to see if
there is a way of is easily now without
those seeing the same error and then
picking out a new test case but if there
isn't then we'll just regress to the
previous test case right so let me just
see what's up there
right so I'm going to look at this case
and now we should see another one of
those now we should see another one of
those sort of exploding balls of lines
like radiating outwards like a little
Sun right uh and what you can see here
is looking at you know what we're
looking at here is all of these are
showing up as black which doesn't make a
lot of sense because they should be
hitting something and the fact that
they're not is not a good sign right
so looking at yeah like you know now we
kind of have a weird and and I honestly
I'm not sure why we are even seeing what
we're seeing here but if you look right
you're seeing like some of these are
hitting something
[Music]
and that's very peculiar I'm also not
sure wait are we having some kind of
compile error here like why is the
lighting oh right because I'm an idiot
let's try recompiling that again so if I
look now and I should see more things
getting hit you know I really don't
so yeah I guess looking now I'm having
trouble now seeing error arrays I want
to try and find like errors and if you
look I guess I would say the error now
mostly appears more to be things that
are saying they aren't hitting anything
right I mean a lot of these should
probably there should be yellow lines
coming out in this direction like all of
this stuff should be hitting and isn't
right so if I restart and just look at
this startup location I should be able
to pretty trivially find one that's
erroneous right like one that this
thinks it didn't hit anything but
definitely did right and it's a little
hard to find because it's you've got to
kind of look inside we almost need like
a wireframe mode for looking at these
because figuring out something that's
sort of inside
those look like they're stopping right
there - like like as if they did hit but
they're being drawn is not having hit
very confusing to be honest I have no
idea what I'm looking at right now this
makes no sense to me what I'm viewing I
mean like that all looks correct right I
mean all of those things correctly
cannot hit the light source so that's
not weird but like all of these I guess
are they just happening to coincide with
like oh no they can't possibly I mean
this doesn't even make sense like these
are supposed to be casting from voxel
centers how on earth are we getting
these values like like something sums up
let's take a look
so this hit value here where we're
looking at the T ray value and comparing
it to the light distance that's the
thing that's telling us whether we hit
something or not whether we hit
something before or after the light
source and the way we're drawing it is
we're drawing it from wherever the
casting start was right and then we're
drawing it to wherever it the hit was
reported we shouldn't even be able to be
producing those lines like the lines
we're producing don't even seem like
they don't they should we shouldn't be
able to be producing those Fox
centerpiece in the first place so I'm
super confused right now
and maybe I'm just misunderstanding
something about how sparse the voxel is
but it doesn't make sense like
let's suppose all we did was just share
the voxels so we took the Vox Center P
and we did a push debug line on it and
like I'm just gonna literally say
alright forget about where you were
drawing it to just take the Vox Center
p-value and add some very small number
right like very very small number in Z
and just just so you're basically just
drawing a tick mark right and that's all
I'm all I'm asking for so we're not
actually drawing a recast line anymore
just draw those tick marks right and so
if you look at where the tick marks
actually are right those are the casting
locations and so just based on that like
how are we getting those lines we were
seeing it doesn't make very much sense
if I leave those on so let's do this
here's the tick marks now draw the cast
lines I should only see things coming
out of tick marks right there should be
nothing coming out of a place that
doesn't have a tick mark on it we can
make this a little bigger like so
so you can see that the tick mark shows
me where the thing should have started
right so first of all like total
nonsensical results this right here like
doesn't have any line coming out of it
at all so that doesn't really make any
sense furthermore like there's like
lines that appear to go nowhere like
like that line literally stops right
there right and there is no tick mark
for it period so something is very wrong
here
so the next thing I guess I want to do
is I want to draw a normal so if I go
ahead and take this case here and what I
want to do is say alright like here's
the tick mark that shows where it is
right and then let me also draw like
something that tells me what direction
it was trying to head in so there's this
light normal end right and so what I
want to do is draw a small directional
arrow in the direction of that light end
right so we've got what amounts to let's
see a purple one here I'm gonna go ahead
and put that in like so and I will draw
a small normal in that direction but
something's busted now so we need to
like fix this
whatever we're seeing here we need to
make this congruent first or there we're
not gonna get anywhere so here's our
debug display and you can now see that
we've got like you know which direction
we were casting in and the tick mark and
so I mean this is just a garbage
situation that we're getting here
because we're getting a cast like for
some how we're drawing stuff that's
totally doesn't line up with what we
think it should be right like I mean
these are the locations were supposed to
be casting from what the heck is all
this garbage it doesn't even make any
sense right you know if I if I look in
here we're not even getting a line
that's coming out of there and what's
even weirder is we know that these lines
have to start from Vox Center P so I am
totally confused now
I'll be honest I do not know I do not
know how we're seeing that result the
debug lines all start at Vox Center P
these two are correctly starting there
this one somehow is not so let's go
ahead and isolate one person and find
out what the heck is happening so if I
look in here I'm gonna do the same thing
I did before I'm gonna try and pick
whoever the easiest person is I can pick
and I'm gonna try and figure out what
the heck is happening with them right
and one thing that's kind of nice is I'm
looking at this guy right here right and
there's nothing emanating from him at
all at all right and what I would expect
to see is I'd expect to see the line
like hit this thing or something right I
don't know but not this so let's pick
him out because it should be pretty easy
to pick him out he's on the edge he's
that be plus three plus two plus one so
I should be able to pick him out by just
doing this and changing this to that I
believe that should isolate this dude
right here and then we can just see
what's happening right so here's a dude
who's trying to cast back in that
direction and we get nothing there is no
debug line at all that I can see anyway
for for this for this cast I mean I see
nothing I don't know about you folks
right so there's nothing being drawn at
all and I have no idea why so what I'd
like to know is in this test case how is
it possible that this hit
I'm not this hit this cast tear a value
is coming back so bizarre right and what
I want to do is maybe convert to debug
mode and actually step through this case
and find out like how is it producing I
guess zero for this because the cast B
value has to be producing basically just
the center point again that's the only
way we could see what we're seeing I
think but let's find out
all right so here's us running in debug
mode now we didn't you know we I didn't
do anything we're still in the same
position so what I want to do here is
just say like let's take a look at that
specific case so if I jump back down
here I want to know like first of all
what are those values so if we do this
[Music]
but break on there so now what I should
see is this cast comes back with
something like a zero or or maybe an
invalid value I don't know so basically
this cast is coming back as I didn't see
anything at all right
so I guess maybe maybe that's a problem
is the float max is just overloading us
that makes some sense so let's change
that if we didn't hit then let's change
that cast P to something saying so let's
do it this way
v3 cast P equals getcomponent
let's do it like that if you didn't hit
anything then we know the cast P's
invalid so what we're really gonna want
to do is just do light distance right so
we're going to want to do light distance
times like normal so that was probably
the problem as I was letting those float
maxes flow through there and once you
let afloat max look through there you
know for the debug case you know
anything goes really all right so now
let's try drawing it
and I don't actually see anything so
still not great
oh of course we actually have to use it
all right
so now we at least see the line and that
line is what we would expect right you
can see that it's wrong so if you look
it's passing through this cube very
clearly and so we can actually start our
debugging process right now because now
we also have a case that is erroneously
being flagged as unincluded but it
definitely is occluded so if we pass is
test case here right we should now see
like what this thing tested and it
descended down I guess into the purple
region but it didn't actually ever
record any testing against this box at
all right it didn't traverse this box in
any way and so something is up here
because when it traversed into this box
it should have you would think tested
the children but it didn't test the
children and it's I'm not clear why not
clear who actually caused that to happen
if I go to the raycast code we're
drawing the box in all cases correct
yeah so we're drawing all boxes that we
consider and at some point we should
have traversed down a box and didn't
write like for whatever reason this
stuff didn't actually occur now if we
were to force it through this path right
so if we were to do this and now we will
see all boxes that can be that are in
the system I think right or we should
there you go
I'm not sure why that's taking so long
probably just because there's too many
debug lines I guess I'm not sure why not
sure why this is so slow right now you
should probably take a look at the
profile but like look if that's very
very slow but I don't actually know why
I guess because there's too many debug
lines in the system there but if you
look at what's happening you can see
that when we forced it to consider all
boxes it did correctly intersect with
this dude so there's something wrong
with the way we're checking those boxes
maybe that new test that I added isn't
actually good right and so let's try to
figure that out right so if in here I
said you know restore the test if I got
rid of this any closer version so that's
if any of the mass values were true
there right maybe that was stupid and
maybe that's not actually true so if we
actually do get rid of that let's just
see and then we can debug that tomorrow
if that turns out to be our problem so
now if we let the bounding volume
hierarchy do what it wants to do the
question is do we hit it and the answer
is no so we still don't so is it the
inside clause or is it the close enough
clause let's find out I'm gonna go ahead
and nerf this
and so it looks like it literally like
because that's still not recording that
hit it looks like it's literally the
inside claws that's our problem
I mean maybe so you can see here that
this means that the t max value has to
be in front of us which seems okay and
if the T min value is also behind this I
mean that seems like a correct case to
me I mean I guess I can't say could they
be inverted I don't think they could be
right but it does look like that any
inside is not right and that's basically
saying look if teaming is less than T
Max which I don't even know why we're
testing because it has to be I mean it
could be equal to but that's the only
way right so if the team in is greater
than it's in front of us oh sorry that's
it shouldn't ever mind it's just team X
and this so that I don't even know why
we have this test that's that's weird
just gonna note that so if we look here
and I guess I don't know if max pass is
failing I don't know which one it is but
I can use the color value to figure that
out I suppose or you know what I could
do is just this to see if Max Pass is
failing or if the other thing is failing
although I guess like now I wouldn't
because I it'll fail out on the next one
so I guess I'm not sure right I don't
know I don't know whether the team in is
the problem here or the T Max is the
problem but somebody is the problem
because somehow we're not producing a T
inside value that we should be right
actually I guess that's not true because
since this is an end here its we would
actually need this to be that close
enough case so that's actually not true
either it could be that this is okay if
there's a child count and we're inside
it or we're close enough to it right
[Music]
it's right this way
hmm so I don't know so it seems like
there's something busted about the way
we're traversing there but I'm not sure
what it is and if we just don't I don't
know that the T inside value is probably
what it is because I mean I guess that
might be though because if you look at
where this thing is of course it is
right on the boundary I wonder if it's a
question of like that tolerance value
isn't isn't good enough I mean I wonder
if this is necessary
apparently it was so the problem there I
guess is we were right on the boundary
of the bounding box right let me put
this in here
so now looking at that I mean I guess
that makes some sense why all of these
were a little bit weird let's go ahead
and go back to our normal case I think
we're getting somewhere here we've we've
gotten a few things out now and we're
getting closer so what I'd like to do is
yeah just want to kind of change that
back to this one hoops this one and
we'll pass false here and I just want to
look now to see what is our new pencil
look like basically does it look any
more sane so at least now right so
fixing the flute max bug there at least
we now see stuff somewhat properly a lot
of these look like they're hitting where
they should a lot of these look like it
as well so I'm going to say maybe we've
debunked that at least to a certain
extent now right
so that looks a little more sane to me
so I'm gonna go ahead now and say
alright let's listen like kind of get
rid of the the test drawing temporarily
so I'm gonna introduce yet another one
here where I just turn it off and then
what I want to do is I want to actually
just run this thing and see what it
actually looks like so we'll go to the Z
bias program and we'll leave the
lighting on and then I guess we'll call
it a day and tomorrow we can sort of
dive a little deeper into that stuff and
see and see you know if if we've roughly
got it working and in which case we can
move to casting from reasonable
locations which will make things work a
lot better and then go from there so
looking at like what's happening here
right I don't really know there's if
there's a lot of ways to interpret what
we're seeing at the moment because again
since we're casting from really
erroneous locations I would say this
could actually be non buggy it's really
hard to say now right because what
you're seeing effectively is just like
well you're casting from places that are
kind of right along the edges of these
cubes and various stuff like that which
could just be wrong so I think the only
way to really go forward from here is
now to cast from actual valid locations
and see what happens there which will be
sort of the next step and basically we
want to do it right is we want to cast
from these light probe points but we've
definitely fixed a bunch of stuff in the
casting so we probably will need to do a
little more fixing we've got a good way
to debug it now we can just kind of turn
that on and off and see what's up right
so that seems good if we're in here I
wonder can I now do is there any way I
can do a reasonable test
caste thing rights do this yeah
so looking at that of course it has the
problem where the hot region is over
here so depending on where the hero is
you know I kind of have to hop in the
hot because the hot region is the only
thing that's actually drawing it's debug
lines right and so if you look at what
we're seeing here it looks to me like
you know again just the fact that
there's stuff under the floor that's
setting to zero means you're gonna get
these patterns here so I think the first
thing we're gonna have to do is just
actually we're gonna have to actually
castrum these before we can really get a
better read on whether we've still got
bugs in there I mean we probably do but
I mean you know it's just it's not
possible to call from this so I think
that's the next step and we can do that
tomorrow and then we'll have some idea
of where we're at I'm gonna go to a
brief Q&amp;A now but I think I think we've
more or less gotten out of the weeds on
that
where did you learn programming like
this lighting stuff previously oh um I
mean I guess I'm not sure how to answer
that exactly
I mean I've I've been programming you
know what is effectively game engine
code I mean for I mean I mean the first
thing I made was a game in basic and
that was when I was seven so I mean I've
been programming this stuff for 36 years
or something like that
and so you know so many things you pick
up along the way kind of slowly this
lighting is just an example of some
stuff we're trying I mean this isn't a
known lighting algorithm that we're
using we're kind of rolling our own
because that was something that I wanted
to show how to do on stream you know but
you know all of the pieces are picked up
from places you know ray casting is
something that you learn to do pretty
much any time you start doing graphs
turn your gonna counter ray casting
because it's a fundamental building
block of anything that's a 3d or even 2d
oftentimes game you need to be able to
know can one point see another point or
you know ultimately stated will a
projectile like you know going from one
place to another encounter an obstacle
you know it's just a fundamental thing
you do and so you know ray casting
you're gonna learn to do early on that's
just something you have to you're gonna
encounter no matter what you're
programming in games and then lighting
is sort of like well if you've worked on
graphics are gonna encounter that
because you will have you know lighting
is a fundamental issue in producing
imagery even if you're not doing
realistic lighting you're doing fake you
know something fake with lighting
usually and so you know just years and
years of working with this stuff I pick
up all kinds of stuff and then when I go
to implement something I'm like alright
you know here's my rough approach I
decided I wanted to try this time I
wanted something relatively
straightforward for handmade heroes so
not too complicated but I want
something complicated enough that we
would struggle with it and have to try
out some things do some experiments make
some decisions right like I wanted it to
be real and something that would show up
in a professional level product right
and so I'm just kind of like navigating
it with that in mind like something good
enough that we like the look of it and
that it was relatively tricky to
implement so you get to see me do it but
not so ridiculous that it takes us you
know a thousand hours just to do the
lighting or something and that's just
because of the limitations of streaming
everything means that you know you have
you kind of have a limit on on how much
experimentation and development and
analysis you can do right
which parts of the CRT do you think are
the most poorly designed or unnecessary
and what do you feel is missing well I
mean the CRT depending what do you mean
by that you just mean the the basic C
runtime library like not like STD and
stuff like that I mean I would say the C
standard library look the basic C Center
like F printf and sine and cosine and
stuff I would say you know I'm not gonna
fault them for being poorly designed
because they're so old I think none of
the C library really makes any sense
in a modern context computers just the
basic things you're gonna want to do
have nothing to do with what you see in
the C runtime library so you know I if I
was designing to see if I was designing
a runtime library for today
none of the C api's would be in there
they're all wrong first of all they're
all synchronous by default
second of all they're all based on
synchronous single threaded execution
models third of all they're based on
text data and you know none of that's
true
right I mean how many people have errors
in their programs because the default
way to open a file the C runtime
libraries ASCII with translation of line
endings right so you know there's just
there's a lot of stuff that's it's clear
like UNIX command line utility was kind
of the mental model of like what people
would be doing with this mount with this
library right and that's just not
realistic like no one's writing that
anymore
that's like not an interesting case you
know we're writing it's heavily threaded
heavily Cindy heavily asynchronous like
you know the modern stuff we do just
that just doesn't map to that so I would
say like none of the CRT is appropriate
for today's programming but that's not
because the authors were stupid that's
because they were designing a library
for a different time
right
did you learn new things that game
pregnant while working on handmade hero
if yes but sure I mean the way we're
doing a lady interpolation is something
we made up just recently so you know
anytime you program if you program
seriously if you're taking it seriously
you should learn something if you don't
learn anything
even though handmade hero I'm out in how
many hours it's been maybe like a
thousand total hours or something I
don't know how long we spent on handmade
hero but it's a small number of hours a
thousand hours is not many hours of
programming but it's enough and any time
you spend that many hours programming if
you're doing it seriously you should
learn something I mean if I didn't learn
anything from a thousand hours of
programming boy that would that would
have been a real bummer so we've
definitely learned some things along the
way have I learned as much as I normally
would learn in a thousand hours no and
that's because a lot of things I'm doing
you're like educational things and so a
lot of the time I'm spending is not
necessarily doing things that are new or
interesting to me it's doing things that
kind of just have to be done as part of
a game engine and I'm gonna explain how
they're done rather than just grabbing
some code I already have to do that and
using it right but you know even in an
educational stream like that a thousand
hours is plenty of time to come upon
some new things and we definitely have
can you imagine any debug tools that
would make stuff like graphics
programming and lighting easier to debug
especially for beginners actually I
think you don't even really need to
think about beginners you've watched me
try to debug the lighting today and what
was I doing the entire time I was like
adding debug code to like draw stuff
right I had to make that debug line
system and without it we would have had
no idea what the heck was going on right
modern debuggers don't give you any
ability to do any of that stuff if you
took a debugger and you added the
ability to insert this kind of code so
like if I could go in my debugger and
add this as markup in my code in the
debugger anytime I wanted
- right that would be so cool because
then all of this crap goes away and the
debugger could have all kinds of tools
for like spinning around and rotating
and stepping through and watching the
lines draw right I mean it would be
friggin awesome
right and there's no reason not to do it
it's just I mean nobody writes the
buggers anymore and remedy B G which is
the one I use on stream now was
something that a person did in their
spare time just so we wouldn't have to
suffer with Visual Studio right
I mean Visual Studio is the thing that
people use to debug it's one of the only
debuggers that exists on windows that
anyone even uses there's windbg and
Visual Studio and they're terrible they
don't have any features for actually
debugging code right all they can do is
display a watch window poorly you know
and remedy B G is much better right but
it hasn't had I mean it's a part-time
product it hasn't had years of
development that it would take to put in
all kinds of really good stuff like
viewing images and showing transforms on
them and showing 3d graphics and Rotem
you around it and mint in your code with
3d graphics drawing and explaining what
space things were in and like you know I
mean that's a ton of work right and
that's exactly what Microsoft should
have been doing but you know they're
just I mean the visual studio team isn't
good they have different priorities they
don't know any of this stuff they
probably don't even know how to draw 3d
graphics let alone what you would
actually need and implement it because
they can't even do basic stuff like I
have the watch window update in a
reasonable amount of time right so
forget it like you're not gonna get any
of those advanced features and they're
too busy doing stuff like oh I needed to
make some kind of weird integration with
with Trello or something right like
that's what they spend their time doing
stuff that's totally useless for
actually debugging code right now I'm
hopeful in the future you know remedy B
G is a great addition to the debug
arsenal it means now you get visual
Studios features without having to sell
video studio and they run quickly and
cleanly that is a huge improvement
I know Allan Webster the guy wrote for
coder and Nick silifke they're out cdbg
are now
rad and they're doing a debugger and
it's supposedly coming around pretty
well so I think we will get improvements
but basically it took the program
community going this is absurd these
tools are garbage and a few years ago
right and starting again to get those
projects going and until they come to
fruition we're gonna be stuck with with
none of this right and so it's only
through the efforts of people like
George who wrote remedy BG and the guys
at rad and who knows who else right
it's only through their efforts that
were ever turned out of this pit because
the professional quote unquote
development tools JetBrains and Visual
Studio code and Visual Studio of they're
just garbage they're not made for real
programming they're made for this kind
of like modern type programming where
people just Jam libraries together and
cross their fingers and everything sucks
right and so it's gonna take like some
real effort to make hardcore debugging
tools again and to get some products
alive it's hard because the number of
people who want to buy a fluffy crap
debugger or just download one for free
cuz they're used to not paying for
software like is the case in like web
development right that doesn't provide
funding right you needed some way to
provide funding to good programmers to
make good debuggers and and really big
to thumbs up to rad for actually funding
that project right because without them
we'd probably never get there and you
know in an ideal world enough people
would have bought remedy G remedy BG to
give George the funding he needs to go
full-time that hasn't happened and so
you know I don't know what to say we're
just we're in a bad situation is it
possible to get CXC and msbuild without
installing video studio I don't know
about msbuild because I'm not familiar
with that but CL dot exe comes with the
SDK development tools were used to
anyway so
I wouldn't I would say yes you can how
do you split your time between learning
theory and practice I don't really know
how to answer that question they're sort
of the same thing like when you're
programming you're usually also having
to learn theoretical things if it's in
an area you not sure about and you have
to kind of read papers periodically and
continuously to kind of keep up to date
so I don't really think of my time as
being split I think of that as just sort
of integrated in right how many hours
you expect handmade hero was going to be
at the start I don't know I said I would
do 600 episodes and we'll probably take
more time than that because when we
finished the lighting we will have what
I would consider a fairly complete
engine right
so you know you could hop around the
world you can put enemies in it you've
got full lighting it's got assets and
texturing and all that good stuff and
you can reload the textures and you can
reload things and you can put new assets
into it and do all the things you would
normally do with an engine right but
we're gonna want to build some gameplay
and then test it out and maybe tweak the
engine based on what we build for
gameplay and you know put together a
real game that you know probably won't
be the world's greatest game or anything
cuz I'm not a game designer but you know
we should do enough to satisfy ourselves
that it was good quality code right and
that everything was working well and so
that'll probably take a while so it
looks like we'll maybe do 600 episodes
on making the engine and a at a basic
game right but then you know however
many episodes we want to spend beyond
that to make as much game as I feel like
making I couldn't tell you and I'm not
sure I care like I'm not sure I care how
many episodes it takes
I'm pretty happy with like I think we
did a really good job actually building
an engine on stream it's a very complete
engine as a lot of stuff it can do and
it's much better than what I was
planning to make I was planning to make
just a simple 2d engine but this is like
a full 3d engine with fake perspective
things and real lighting and like you
know a lot of stuff that was kind of
better are you playing through another
series no any plans for physics not
beyond just the basic special-effects
stuff like we already kind of have some
stuff in there for particles which is
basic physics stuff but we wouldn't
really be doing anything beyond that
kind of stuff I don't think all right
let's go ahead and wrap it up all right
thank you everyone for joining me for
the up soto handmade hero it's an
appendage of coating with you as always
if you would like to follow the series
at home you can always peer to the game
on handmade hero org and it comes with
source code so you can follow along into
your own experiments I don't necessarily
know if doing the light casting for
light probes is a good exercise for
folks who want to follow at home might
be a little bit much to do over the the
evening but that's what I'll be doing
tomorrow so tune in for that and we'll
get that going that will put us in a
position to actually be computing shadow
rays from realistic locations in the
scene and spreading that light data back
out to the voxel which is what we want
to do you yeah you probably don't want
to try that as an exercise so skip that
but I'll be back to start that and then
once we get there then we'll be in a
position to start turning the crank on
the lighting because that'll be
basically when we can start to go okay
let's move to let's first of all debug
any ray casting bugs that we still have
in there make sure that works okay then
move up to like okay now let's actually
convict the light around so we'll get
our secondary third turret secondary
tertiary quaternary bounces you know so
that more like light motion and that
will finally give us a way to play with
lighting and the lighting voxel
interpolation fully and we can tackle
kind of what I think is probably the
last remaining problem we have which is
when we have a bunch of lighting
information coming in now how do we map
that down to a for iterator system or
you know do we want to change that for
area system a little bit I don't know so
I don't know exactly what we want to do
there and that's gonna be the last kind
of big unknown for us that we got to
start playing with how do we do that
that down project that's it for today
I'll be back here tomorrow same time
same channel until then have fun for
everyone and I'll see you on the
Internet
take it easy everybody