hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete game live on
stream we are well you know honestly
don't really know what we are at the
moment we have our lighting actually
working and I think mostly what we need
to do now is tune the lighting to make
sure that we're getting reasonable
results for what we want and then after
that we just have to optimize it now we
could also just optimize it now and the
reason that I say that is because
looking at the actual profile in terms
of what is slow right now and this is
doing an entire lighting solution as you
can see like actually this entire room
is lit by the actual lights it's not
there's no cheating here so this is
actually spreading throughout the
environment and so on we can't actually
probably do optimization early if we
wanted to and the reason for that is
just that if we look at what our actual
timings sort of announce as far as I can
tell although we do have some we are
spending some significant portions of
time that we probably would want to
optimize in stuff that's specific to the
current lighting scheme actually the
majority of the time is still in the
raycast so we could just optimize our
ray caster and that would probably give
us a you know a large speed increase if
we you know get a little more serious
about that and it doesn't really matter
like it doesn't have much to do with the
actual lighting itself so changes we
made to the lighting wouldn't really be
a big deal at that point now one of the
things that I'm not sure about - in
terms of lighting is we also never
really looked at the the sort of decay
time of the lighting and I think at the
moment it's something like 20 frames ish
I mean it's hard to say exactly what the
frame is because it kind of blends out
over time which is not really a
particularly specific way of thinking
about it but you know right now we're
doing 95 5 blend so I think you know you
could sort of
that over 20 frames you've got a fair
bit of the new lighting in there and
that could certainly get reduced so you
know that could go down to something
like two and still not be horribly laggy
if we wanted to take a look at that I'm
and I'm like I said I'm not really sure
how we want to look at that but the
update voxel call that we have there is
you know where that happens and you can
see that here wheeler pew zhing this T
update blend function and so whatever we
set the solutions T update blend to
that's really what's going to be
determining that that rate so we can set
the T update blend to whatever we want
and so in here oh wow so this was
actually even more so that you know so
it's really a trade-off between response
speed like this is extremely fast
response for an indirect lighting
solution right which is normally updated
pretty slowly and so if we want to you
know that can drop down dramatically so
here's like a really you know much much
deeper and so you can see if we reduce
the blend dramatically you can see how
slow it is to update right like you see
how slow the high light fades from here
to here but as a result you get like no
noise right and so you can control the
difference between the response rate and
the noise pretty easily just with this
parameter and what this parameter should
be we don't know right like I have no
idea what it should be you can see that
it's pretty usable probably you know at
this rate maybe and so it's still not
too bad in terms of light lag but you
still get a little bit of flicker in
there right you can see a little bit of
that flicker as these change and to be
honest I'm not really sure also about
that flicker I don't know if there's
other things we're doing that may lead
to more of that then is necessary as
well like we don't we haven't really
taken a good look at it but you can sort
of see that that you know somewhere
there's a smooth point for our current
scheme and it's somewhere around the
160th it looks like because I can still
see a little bit of flicker here right
so you know in terms of that I don't
know what we want to do there I'm not
sure what the correct trade-off is for
that and casting more rays would also do
it but we don't really probably have the
budget for it but either way it seems
pretty reasonable so at the moment
anyway I'm not sure we really have to
worry about it too much because it seems
pretty good and furthermore like right
now we're not right now we're not really
we don't do anything particularly fancy
in our actual sampling to try and reduce
the amount of noise either like I don't
know very much about sampling theory I
don't spend a lot of time with it and so
it's entirely possible that that could
be improved dramatically as well so I
think we're in ok shape there so then
when we look at the other sorts of
things that I think you know I'm not
sure about at the moment I think you
know some of the biggest stuff is just
oh what is going on there where is all
this light coming from that seems like
kind of a bug doesn't it like how are
these all super bright so that that's
got to be a bug that looks like some
kind of propagation of like a bad value
like how did this all get bright down
here let me see if I can make that
happen again
I wonder if we have some filling bugs
and stuff like that I'm gonna go hop
over there so I feel like really that
you know again just taking stock of it I
think really what we want to do here is
just go and and pick one either you know
optimize the Ray caster which maybe is a
better idea because then it's faster and
we can make better judgments about it oh
I bet I know what happened I bet it was
the I bet the the the voxel movement
yeah you can see it look at that see how
that's propagating weirdly so
something's something's going on weird
down here like the light I mean there's
I didn't even are is there even a lie
in this room I don't know what's oh
there is a light in this room all right
so something about in here like the
lighting is just super bright probably
because it has a ceiling so it can like
reinforce the bounces the bounces don't
escape right yeah so anyway I don't know
which one we want to do let's go ahead
and say like let's take a let's just do
this weekend maybe a performance survey
just do we have an idea of how hard it
would be for us to optimize further from
where we are and then maybe next weekend
and based on that we can decide where
there next weekend we want to try and do
optimization work or whether we want to
do some quality work first and we can
see so again I'm not really sure about
the current performance state of things
and also I'm not really sure about the
when we're doing the Ray casting exactly
[Music]
how we've been centering this this box
right so if you take a look at this you
can see the lighting domain that we are
currently enclosing and you can see that
lighting domain is pretty wide right and
we may not really want it to be quite so
wide like we may want to shrink this
voxel so that the actual span of it
vertically is considerably less and that
might be a good optimization just right
off the bat because it doesn't really
make much sense that we would be doing
this right it's it's just not a
particularly sane thing to be doing
because we don't need to be simulating
this much levels of light in our game
one or two levels up or down should be
plenty and one or two levels you know
when you when you got up to here you're
simulating like the third or fourth
level I guess I don't know how to quite
out deep these are let's take a look I'm
gonna just stack two levels on top of
each other here so I can see
you know we should probably have a
teleport function in this game you would
think all right so here we have let me
see here I'm just gonna zoom out a
little yes you can see like if that's
the stacking rate you know we how many
we really probably only want three
pronounced so this is probably twice as
large as it needs to be so I don't
really know like one of the things we
should get working in debug pretty well
because I think it would it would
actually make sense to ensure that we're
doing it properly is to just take the
light lookup voxel dimensions and split
this out so that we are actually able to
do us more squat like a voxel that's not
as tall as it is wide and well or it's
not as much in Z as it is in x and y you
know what I mean so if I wanted to do
this first I would like to see where
this is actually getting used so I'm
going to go ahead and get rid of those
two and find everywhere that we're still
using them because there's not a lot of
places that we actually are and so I
want to actually just kind of start to
clean that up so here in the light
lookup voxel dim for the the lighting
solution I think that might be a good
place to start getting rid of this right
so we've got the hot dim getting used
here and really we don't I think don't
want to use the hot dim anywhere here if
I recall the Atlas themselves should
actually have the information about the
voxel dim in them so you can see here
that whichever one we're actually
working on we should be able to loop
just over that foxhole
so the speck atlas is really the one
that we're looping over here because
that's the one that we're updating Molly
the cat is currently digging in a pile
of papers
what are you doing being you looking out
there you have my fun what are you doing
she really enjoys a cardboard box full
of papers so the spec atlas here will
give us the information that we need so
the voxel dim Y there and the voxel Jim
X here should give us what we need and
you can see here that we've got the Z
and that's going in in these slices I
think that's actually fine I don't know
if there's anything in particular that
we did here that was weird
and I guess so if you look at the way we
were doing this it looks like we kind of
assumed that we wanted to eventually do
it in the other direction round so you
can see we were passing a voxel X here
and we but yet we had the Z on the
outside so I don't actually know if
there's any real reason we can't just
fix that so at the moment I'm gonna go
ahead and say let's do that so instead
of this being a Z let's just make that
change as well so what that would be is
in here we would say like okay the X is
gonna be the voxel X and then here this
will be a Z and a Y and I and again I
just I don't think there's any reason we
can't do this but we'll find out right
so if that's our iterators so then we
have the Z and the Y here and then we've
got the X here that also allows us to
balance our work a lot more because
before if we were doing Z slices we
would run it I think we would definitely
run into situations where casting would
be occurring out in the middle of
nowhere for no reason and we're already
doing that a lot anyway
but at least here this would minimize
that quite a bit by shrinking the voxel
down and once we do that we don't want
to assign sheets because the sheets will
be unbalanced right like if we start to
detect that were in an area where
there's nothing we could just not do
casts there and when we do that we would
end up with entire like a thread that
like literally had no work to do because
it was in a slice that you know didn't
actually have any any
geometry and or something right so
that's kind of a separate issue but for
the moment like now if we look here this
should rearrange this nicely and then if
we go to the work voxel X stuff so that
we look at where that's actually being
set we can just make sure that that's
correct and so in here where we sign the
work count you can see all this stuff
happening like this with the work count
we want to make that be the spec atlases
so right here we want the spec atlases
voxel dim Z would be the work count and
we would basically assign out for each
slice of the voxel Z we would assign
that to a different thread right now I
don't know we may need to assign I'm
sorry X naught naught C so for each X
you know each like column on the screen
basically we're gonna be sending that to
different thread and again that's
important because if we're starting to
shrink that Z dimension too we don't
want to only able to slice on our lowest
dimension right and we know our X will
always be our widest dimension because
the screen is wider than it is tall and
so on so once we get in here that should
be all we really need to do
unfortunately the speck out the section
gets pulled out here so I should make
sure that we actually do pull it out
here let me just go ahead and pull out
both because they're kind of things you
want generally speaking so I'm gonna go
ahead and do that all right so as we
start to push forward on that let me get
rid of any places refer to that here
okay so here we look at the speck atlas
stuff and we see the signed unsigned
mismatch that should be fine to just
change these two sign that's that's fine
not really an issue let's do it else we
got here we don't care about that so
here where we create the number of works
that we're gonna do here
this memory arena needs to this needs to
push on however many we think we're
going to have for like the X so I would
maybe make so what I would suggest is
this should probably turned into like a
max kind of thing so here I would say
this should be like a max like light
look
Fox will dim so like look we know will
never allow more than a 64 or something
or whatever I mean I don't whatever you
know whatever we want and that's for
people who want to create sort of static
known buffers they don't have to
delegate them dynamically or do anything
else weird like that although I suppose
in this case there's really no needs
reason not to look you could just use
the frame arena for this so I'm gonna
put to do here because we could use a
temporary arena or the per frame arena
like we have sources of memory we could
just use for this and that just get
flushed at the end of the frame we don't
even have to clean them up we don't
think about it so it would be trivial
for us to do that so this is probably
not really necessary and maybe we should
just get rid of it it's fine for now but
I'm gonna put it to do in there cuz it's
like I don't really know if we should
bother with that and then we wouldn't
have to define this and it would just
make the code you know simpler right it
doesn't have this other dependency
alright so anyway but that's fine
so moving through here those are ones we
don't care at the moment that's when we
want to fix here we've got I think it's
just what spec atlas and diffuse atlas
right yeah so let me just go ahead and
shorten those names and there we go
so now I think we're down to just the
iterator and then the part here where
the Z biased program sends down what the
voxel DIMM actually is going to be and I
think for that that should be pretty
straightforward because it's just a
compile time and this one here is where
it will actually specify it so the only
one we really have left to deal with
outside of the rent the opengl layer is
this one and what you can see here is
really this one is just used to compute
the hot the inverse hot dim which let's
just check out where those are being
used so inverse hot dim here i guess is
not even used is that correct
that's correct so it's really only the
hot dip and that's only used for the
entropy index so I guess we don't really
super care about this even a little bit
that feature is that like that's just
not really used so the entropy index
here I suppose
hmm so I suppose we can just maybe do I
mean I don't really know how we want to
do this but it seems like the most
straightforward way would just be to sum
it up and not actually use the hot team
here at all so we would just say like
you know and I could just do this too I
could say voxel DIMM equals spec Atlas
that way we know what we're dealing with
here delete this and then the Z Y and X
those would just be voxel dibbsy voxel
did Y and to compute the entropy we
would just say well I guess it would be
like you know plus X Y times voxel dim X
Z times voxel dim x times voxel dim Y so
just basically computing like a stable
value there I guess I'm not really sure
and also the sample point entropy part
here I don't know I'll be honest since
that comes off of the work I don't know
why we should just make this be
something that probably I don't even
know if we want to do this way this
could just be something that gets
incremented really I mean can't it be
like where's that even happening the
entropy index itself
could just do this
where we just increment each time we
could think about that a little bit
later but at the moment I don't even
know that we need to bother with any of
that stuff so we'll have to look at how
we want to get our entropy source there
but for now that's probably fine
all right so taking a look at the rest
of this stuff where we've got the
because I mean really this this might
want to add something else I guess is
what I'm saying like you know we might
want to do something like you know you
know that right I mean I don't know but
we might want to strive through the
thing in a weird way because the other
things are gonna be incrementing
directly so we may want this to like
wrap in some weird way I don't know
right we will probably want to do
something saner there eventually but it
doesn't need to be based on the voxel in
a particular way so we're down to just
this part of the code now where we're
going to do the compile Z bias program
and in order to compile the Z bias
program we do need to know what the
voxel dimensions are and furthermore we
need to update this piece of code to
actually be correct and think about what
the voxel addressing is now because I
believe this was like the last piece of
code we had that was still we didn't
ever write it to use a full
three-dimensional voxel dimension set so
if you look at what happens inside it
you can see that it's got like just
voxel dim times voxel dim in various
places I think well no it doesn't take
that back it looks like actually it's
pretty sane so we should actually be
able to just yeah I think we should be
able to just fix these by using
whichever ones yeah so I mean there's a
couple of places like here for example
to me that we're gonna have to fix it
but it's actually not that bad
interesting so I think if light lookup
voxel Jim just got a little more savvy
and we actually made light lookup voxels
been dim B of v3 that's really all we
need to do here so if we take a look at
that so light lookup voxel Jim here is
actually not going to be a percent u
it's gonna be like a v3 with a percent
you present U and a percent u right and
furthermore it might actually be a
percent F in this case I don't know I
mean I guess it's not gonna be pretend F
because it's never gonna be that value
but this right here is probably not a v3
s probably a v3
because it's probably it's only ever
really going to be used for the for
multiplying things out by like I don't
think it's ever really used for any kind
of indexing where we have to have those
be integers I could be wrong about that
but we'll see in a second so I'm gonna
pass the voxel dim in here and then I'm
just gonna literally write it out so
voxel de max voxel Dan why voxel dem Z
so now the light look up voxel dam is
actually a three-wide value and so
wherever we have voxel dim in here in
the future we can we can come up with it
right alright so yeah we probably want
to clean up this shader at some point
cuz there's so much old cruft in here
but we'll do that when we actually do
the quality I'm not going to do that for
now so in here you can see us well wait
a minute am I looking at the right thing
here why is that Oh cuz that's the
exterior okay that's fine so when we
look in here basically this is being
computed based on the dimensions and so
you can kind of see like the Y value
that we're looking up is the inverse of
the voxel dim but this is actually now
just going to be the Z and when we look
at this one we're now gonna have to use
the X and the y right because those were
the the sizes we were computing there
we're for an X Y sheet and just the Z
count right so that's really
all we should have to do there for the
rest of them we just have to look at who
is actually being operating here it
looks like again here we're really using
the same values over and over so I feel
like we should be able to just pre
compute these so it feels to me like we
should be able to say look we've got the
like XY sheet and then we've got the the
Z sheet sizes or maybe like X Y stride
and z stride something like that and
these values once we compute them we use
them in a lot of places so we just need
the voxi stride value here and the vox
XY stride value here and that's really
it I think right so this is like a buxom
squared that's the vox XY stride i'd
want to say again because you're going
sort of across the voxel and then this
one is the Vox Z stride here because
again you're going down the voxel same
is true here I think so this is Vox XY
stride and this is Vox z stride and
that's really all it gets used for in
here we then have one more in here where
we're saying the light lookup voxel dim
Y plus the x times the exterior dim so
so producing the center it looks like
well I'm not sure to produce the
x-coordinate it's multiplying Oh so this
is just the X span of the voxel right
because for each y it has to go one in X
so this is just a light lookup voxel dim
X dimension yeah because for each Y it
has to go one full X you know long right
all right so light lookup voxel dim
where else is it used so just here so to
produce the voxel R in this case this is
going to be one where we take the UVW
and we I guess
blow it out to the like this is the
inverse dim so now we're going to take
the forward dim so that doesn't even
have to change because that's gonna just
be a three-wide multiply now so I think
that's it
actually all right so when we're doing
compile Z bias program here we actually
need to use the size of this thing
as of oxalá that's actually something
that when we have the settings here we
don't actually know what that is because
we don't pass it in here however it is
actually something that we just kind of
know anyway because the OpenGL structure
itself has the spec atlas in it so we
should be able to just say look the
OpenGL Aero spec Atlas here right
speculate Alice voxel Jim is the voxel
dim in question that's what you're going
to use for the lighting so off you go
right so that's hardly an issue so
finally we get down to this and now
we're just at the point where the
setting for the voxel dimensions is
picked here so now we can actually say
we can re introduce this and say here's
the actual light look up voxel dim
it's gonna be 32 and that's just what it
is right and now everything should be
operating on that right and hopefully if
we run it now we won't get some disaster
we'll just get the same exact thing we
saw before right and it looks like
that's roughly what we get so now if we
want to change this to being like XY and
Z we should be able to start you know
debugging that now so if I were to
actually make each of these a separate
value and use them here to you know seed
this with something different I should
be able to tweak those values separately
and as I tweak those values I should get
a different shape so if I look for
example at that I should be able to say
like oh okay
I want to shrink down the Z and we
should be able to try and figure out
where we break right so now if I shrink
by the Z and I and I zoom out here you
can kind of see like that this became
more squat right but it otherwise is the
same and looking at it it actually looks
okay I mean I don't know like it doesn't
look particularly wrong so it looks like
I mean maybe we're still doing it
properly but obviously it's it's pretty
hard to say exactly it does look like
our debug drawing code maybe didn't
quite handle that as well as it could
have but only the debug code the actual
runtime code looks fine and one of the
things that you'll notice is already you
know that jumped us up to a much better
frame rate as well so prior to that
change you know if you if you look at
what we're running at at 32 by 32 by 32
if we run it here you can kind of see
the frame rate 125 milliseconds or you
know there abouts right kind of
oscillating we drop that down and we
immediately get just from reducing the
the footprint of the lighting thus
we go down to almost twice as fast right
and that's sort of what we would expect
because the lighting itself takes a
certain amount of time that amount of
time is based entirely on how many
places we want to sample the lighting
from plus sort of the constant overhead
of producing the diffuse maps which
right now is pretty slow so if you take
out that constant overhead we doubled
the speed of the Interior portion and so
as you expect we get almost twice as
fast right that's exactly what we would
expect to see and so if I go ahead and
hop around now you know it's getting
much closer to a playable frame rate
without us ever actually having an
optimized anything just by saying look
let's not compute the lighting in a
bunch of places that we don't actually
care about right which seems like a
pretty obvious thing to want to do since
obviously you don't really want to
compute lighting in places that you
don't need it all right so I think
that's fine and then we can start to
look at some other things here if you
look at the speed too you can see that
we may want to spend a little bit more
time thinking about how we're doing
these a few snaps as well if you take a
look at that excuse me if we were to
take that out of the equation
temporarily so when we're producing
those diffuse maps here if I go over to
the lighting code temporarily and I
disabled the part of the code which
actually tries to sum up the diffuse
maps properly
so here in the work you call back I say
look just don't worry about that it's
just not you know we're not gonna do
that
no one cares right so if I take that out
of the equation temporarily and I come
back over here you can see that going
away you can see that again like we're
getting a lot faster just from that so
we would get another you know 10 to 20
milliseconds shaved off the time if our
diffuse map production code could be
done more efficiently so that's another
thing that we would want to potentially
think about - although it's definitely
like the shorter and
the stick but if you take a look at how
that's working right now you know yes we
did the nominal we did a nominal amount
of work to just like simplify the way
that was working by you know doing it
for wide but what we didn't really do is
actually reduce the number of
multipliers that are involved here so if
you take a look this is you know we take
a look at our four loops here this is a
two right this is an eight and then you
look at these two and this is an eight
and that's an eight right so if you take
a look at at how heavyweight that
routine is it's just a lot of multiplies
right it's just a lot of multiplies and
we reduced it down from 4096 to 1024 by
making it wide but that's still not
great like we would rather this be
significantly less than it is okay so
let's maybe let's think about this loop
just a little bit and see if we can't
maybe think about ways of making this a
little bit more sane looking back at the
actual runtime itself and again checking
that profile you go ahead and put this
back in you can kind of see that the
profile itself oops sorry
gotta fix the debug we gotta clean up
our debug code one of these days it
annoys me that it can't do the hot
reloading properly anyway so if we take
a look here at at this part of the code
when we if zero that out we don't
actually get much of anything left in
the propagation work why okay so what's
actually the problem here it's using
like a non it's using like a block
that's supposedly not supposed to be
used
for allocating and I'm not sure we have
to go find out what's going on there I
don't know why that's even that's bad
but anyway um you can kind of see here
that compute light propagation work is
drops down to a fairly meaningless
amount of the frame time so this part
even though the fill light Atlas like
these fill light out of order things
those are not really optimized at all
they're extremely stupid right now
but even extremely stupid they just
touch so few pixels
I guess that they're just not
contributing to the frame time so we
probably don't have to worry about those
not for a long time so it's really just
this part right here that's our problem
for that you know for this outer part of
the code and then there's the right
caster so if we take a look at what's
going on here there's a couple different
things that probably could be improved
first of all just the loads themselves
are not great so the offset from Texel I
don't know how good this is doing this
could probably be done better we can
look at the assembly code for it but the
main thing I want to look at first is
just can I take some of the multiplies
out right and so what I want to do for
that is I want to see how many 0 weights
we have like if the weights are all 0 I
want to know that right I want to know
that ahead of time so where we go over
to the build diffuse maps thing which
again this is a good excuse to to make
this code that build a few slight maps
code better because right now it's not
particularly good either so right now I
want to go ahead and take a look at the
performance of this and just figure out
not the performance of it but what it's
actually producing and how that would
affect our performance going forward so
what I want to do here is take a look at
every time this might be zero so I
basically want to say you know 0 W count
and so if we take a look here where this
is you know where this weights that is
happening in fact you know what I can
even just make this a separate thing
so here we are I'm going to loop over
this exactly the way oh you know what I
could even just put it here so right
here so I'm just gonna do this I'm gonna
say how many zeros are there through
each of these when we get out the W I'm
gonna go ahead and say look I want to
know if all of these are 0 that's not
what I was trying to do she's trying to
get that one if all of these are 0 then
we want to know about it no bad cut and
paste and so if all of the weights that
we were going to encounter in the
multiply were all 0 so we basically did
not have to sum this one I want to sum
that I want to count that and know at
the end of this how many of those of
those there were and so I'm just gonna
set a breakpoint here and have it show
me that value the zero count value so
like right here right at fill light last
border so I'm going to go ahead and
change this to a debug build which is
our slow build and then I'm gonna set a
breakpoint on that fill out light Atlas
border so fill light Atlas border where
is the lighting good there we go fill
light Atlas border
where are we where is that there it is I
want to stop like there let's say and so
this way I can just find out like how
many of these multipliers are actually
useless because I don't actually know
right now but I would like to know all
right so basically out of 1024
multiplies right we only actually had to
do 828 of them because the other ones
were zero so they could have just been
skipped right so I don't know exactly
how we want to do this but we could try
and coding this slightly differently
right we could try and coding this as
basically like a multiply skip list kind
of a thing
and I'm not sure like I don't really
know exactly how we want to do that but
if you take a look at the savings there
it's it's you know that's like saving
10% of the work that you would be doing
and that could be fairly substantial
right furthermore there's a couple other
things to consider here the way this
loop is working may be kind of stupid as
well just the way the load is working so
if we were to actually even say look
we're still gonna brute-force this
because we're just brutish like that
yeah so I'm gonna look at a couple
different things so first of all I think
the first thing I want to see is let's
take a look at what the assembly
language code for this actually looks
like now we know how many zeros were
actually doing here I can pull that out
and I'm gonna go ahead and see what the
code looks like here just to see how bad
it is and then I'm gonna see like maybe
about doing the loads a little
differently just to see if I can
streamline it a little bit now if I
don't see anything weird then maybe I
won't do that but we'll see so I'm gonna
set a breakpoint here and then I was
gonna look at the disassembly just to
see what it looks like when we actually
go through here so to make this window a
little bit bigger and here's us you know
stepping through the disassembly here
right so if we take a look at where
we're actually I don't know what that's
doing and then ignore this window for
now so once we get into the actual what
is happening here why are we why is that
jumping like that I think that's just
bad like no it isn't what what is
happening there
none of that looks particularly good to
me I want to find out what the heck is
happening here so I'll set from Texel
it's just supposed to do this oh well we
do have the assert pointer is inbounds
so I may disable that just quickly -
that might be throwing the optimizer a
little bit hold on a second so I'm gonna
do a pound to find here I'm gonna go
ahead and say that there's a light Atlas
check pointers thing and we're gonna
have that in fact you know what I'm
gonna do I'm gonna have light Atlas
assert do nothing and so anywhere that
there was a certain here I'm gonna
change it to a light Atlas assert oops
and the reason that I'm doing this is
just to make sure that I don't have to
pay any price in here when I'm trying to
do optimization work so I can turn on so
basically I want control over asserts in
this particular piece of code right go
ahead and stop that alright so yeah
there was way too much jumping around in
that code and I think that that is
probably because we still had those
asserts in there I'm not 100% certain
about that but let's take a look because
this should flow more smoothly here I
would think what is going on Oh
duh I forgot I don't have a way to
freeze this thread so we're we have to
turn off multi-threading first that I
was like what's going on there yeah yeah
so we still have multi-threading turned
on here I've got to turn that off if I
want to step through this really because
otherwise I'm gonna be seeing multiple
threads stepping through it so that's
yeah less good for our analysis so let's
go ahead to begin lighting I don't it
maybe that remedy already has this I
don't know I've never learned in remedy
hat if you can step a single thread like
step single thread is a great feature to
have Visual Studio I don't even know if
it has it it's a real pain in the butt
in Visual Studio remedy may have added a
better one I don't know but either way
I'm just going to go ahead and say look
we just won't like that's not gonna
happen
so multi-threading is turned off and
then we'll run it now so yep alright so
now running in I should be able to see
this more cleanly so now if we step
through we should just go straight
forward and we are I believe that looks
kind of weird why is it why does it
disappear it doesn't look like the
assembly stepping is working here Georg
help I don't know if there's a newer
version but the assembly stepping
doesn't look like it's working like I
can't actually see I can't actually step
per instruction and it used to work I
don't think we've got X 13 pixels with
us do we help George hmm so I guess I
can just look at this cold though even
without stepping through it so if you
look at the way this is loading stuff
here looks like it's doing some aligned
loads see what else we're doing here
it looks actually fairly good right like
did it actually reorder interesting did
actually reorder the calls did it put
these two wait you can't have done that
where are those two calls or did it
inline them oh please
yeah I can't see where the systems I'm
curious where these calls went because I
don't know if it inline them or what
because I wouldn't thought so so that's
get called twice yes so that's weird so
it actually moved those calls up and the
and it jumps back to them or something I
guess that's just a weird did you notice
how weird that was I mean it may have
just done that I don't know but it looks
like it kind of did something pretty
weird there if this is to be believed
where it it changed where those go oh
you know what it could just be it
actually looks like just the assembly
language here was kind of busted the
stepping was busted now it's working
properly right and now it looks much
more sane because we're actually getting
to this before we get to the call so
maybe that was just a bet that was just
a bad display thing that was happening
okay yeah cuz this looks right this
looks this like I was really confused
about what I've seen there I think
that's because it was wrong so now this
looks totally fine right you can see it
doing a move it's doing a shuff - that's
the broadcast so that's the load of the
of the spectacle value there right so it
doesn't move and then it you know gets
the the value and does the shuff so
here's the mob and yeah you can see it's
it's doing the load one at a time I
don't know what the heck that's doing
what
[Music]
that just doesn't make a whole lot of
sense what I'm looking at here either
well we'll take it on faith if that
wasn't too stupid but it looks kind of
stupid this just looks like way too many
shuffles for what's actually happening
so yeah I don't like the looks of this
at all so I I would say actually let's
let's maybe just clean this routine up
first because it's easier for us to do
that yeah so I'm gonna say look the way
that we're gonna do this is we're gonna
actually load the so the spec atlas
where we're doing the 8x8 there let's
just say we're gonna lock that down for
now and it's got to be 8 by 8 so we're
not going to let this range around we're
gonna hand code this and so it has to
actually be sane right and so if we did
that we would know that we can load
everything so when we're looking at the
spec Texel here right where we know we
could load everything for a particular
spec Texel row with two loads right
furthermore if you actually about how
many there are total so in an 8x8
there's 16 spec texels right so actually
you could put the spec texels themselves
if you only cared about that you could
actually put them in registers because
there are 16 registers she'd actually
just load all 16 if you wanted to now we
can't really necessarily do that because
we need some place to store other things
but it means we could do like 4 at a
time if we wanted to
certainly so let's just write at least
one row here let's write that out
manually and see what happens so in here
I'm gonna say look let's just get where
we would be reading this Texel from like
this and then let's load the two things
we would the two actual values we want
out of there so I'm gonna say alright
you know we've got an
1:28 here that's the you know that's the
first one I guess you know and this is
the second one I mean I don't know how
we want to actually label these because
it's actually the first four and then
the second four so kind of hard to say
but maybe I'll do maybe I'll say this is
zero through three and this is four
through seven I don't know I so when we
look at the actual spec Texel we're
gonna now do like an mm like load ups on
this thing and I'm gonna load an actual
you know text a lot of this so here's
the M 128 respect Texel and the same is
true here only this time the spec Texel
spec Texel value in the light atlas
Texel that's a v3 i guess so
Oh hmm I had not considered the fact
that this is actually RG and B so I take
that back
so this would actually load if it's RGB
RGB RGB which it is right if it's
actually that then there's more per row
so yeah so that explains why there were
more stuffs in there now I get it
I was wondering why all the chef's were
there but that's why they were there
it's cuz there's actually RGB I was
thinking I was doing monochrome but I'm
not alright so yeah if we've got our GB
RGB then so that's three of the floats
times eight so there's actually 24 float
values so there's actually six per row
and this is not the correct way to look
at it right
so if there's six per row it's gonna
look more like this and these are
offsets by some amount right I guess I
should probably just duplicate that line
so those are all the values that we
actually have and we then want to like
process each one right so we want to
actually do the multiply here the
multiply accumulate for each of these
times the correct weight right so we
want to do like a load of the weight and
then multiply it in so previously we
were you know let's just go ahead and
move this out here right so we need to
be able to load these weights and for
each one of like the sy is just what it
is and for each one of these we have an
SX that we need to load and then do the
multiply with right so we know that
we've got something that looks like this
right so we're gonna load the weights
one at a time and then we know we have
to do this as well
right so we can actually avoid loading
the that we can actually avoid like
specifying it that way by just doing
this in the accumulator right so the
light see itself can be part of that
operation and so all we need to do now
is actually get the correct shuffle to
produce the weight value we wanted times
like a shuffle of these things right so
because everything that we want to do
for our for our multiplies is going to
come from whatever you know one of these
six so we should be able to do this loop
cleaner right and make it easier to read
and easier to think about how fast it
should run by just doing those directly
that's my argument anyway so if we load
everything in then we just need shuffles
here right we need to be able to do
shuffles right where we're gonna do like
something like this
know what I mean
and those weights the the weights there
are the only the only weird part about
it is the weights are actually VIII's so
in order to produce the correct v3 we
need basely and it kind of doesn't I
kind of don't know that I really want to
do this in v3 anymore I might just want
to do this in actual like X like written
out manually in XY and Z or RG and B in
this case so they don't have to keep
working through it that way and if we
look at the diffuse weight map here we
can also write this in the way that we
want as well right so I can make this
just be the correct series of things to
load out in in in order so we'll have to
think about how that should actually
work so anyway if we move along here we
know that as we load these in we have
well and now that I think about it it
kind of also seems like I could just
transpose so this bit here I feel like I
could just be transposing on the load as
well right so this kind of feels like it
just wants to be done all this one like
clean routine here so let's just keep
going with this so here's my m1 28 light
CR what's the zero it's like zero PS
there's an mm 0p o set zero that's what
they called it I don't know why they
called it that to did and so you know I
might just even say this is the R this
is the G and this is
B and then the transpose there is this
shuffle here that we have again like
it's just kind of annoying like I just
don't know that I want this in this
struct because once you start to blow it
out it just doesn't you know it doesn't
really make much sense so like doing
that sort of like rapper you know what I
mean just doesn't doesn't make much
sense to me having it in the rapper so
so I'd rather get rid of it so we can
still use the shuffle for X and in fact
I can still I can still do these as has
just our type here which is fine but I
just don't want the v3 version of it I
don't think that's productive alright so
we can leave it like that and that's
fine but then when I think I would want
to do is this transpose here I would
like the transpose to be done outside
right and so this part of the code you
know I would like that to just work that
way just trying to see if I can still
use this type and not be grumpy about it
yeah that especially well yeah all right
okay okay no you know what maybe I'm
okay with that
maybe I'm okay with that it's just it's
literally just three of those I'm okay
with that I can do that all right so we
can leave it that way all right so we we
can probably leave it that way I'm okay
with that I overreacted I was a little
bit grumpy about that but I'm okay with
that that's fine so if these are all
just f34 X's in here
then we look in here and we're gonna try
and do a summation this is the part that
I don't think I actually want to do this
way right so if we instead looked at how
this was working with each individual
element right so you know and you could
think of it more this way as well
so if we were looking at each individual
element here are g and b like so then we
could probably say well alright now we
just need to figure out what the
shuffles are right that produce the
value we need and let me take a look
here but I think that's that's really it
right so I think we can boil this entire
thing down to literally just doing that
oops and then do it all in one go and
and be a little bit happier about it
right and again I'm not sure how many of
these we actually need here so I think
this would just be the original 8 right
because we're summing over 8 pixels so
this is how many ops we need so we have
basically you know 24 multiply
accumulates that have to happen in here
and we just need to make the correct
shuffles out of the original loads to
make that happen right and then again we
can unwind this further by or
simplifying it further by again doing
these loads in a more structured fashion
but for doing one row this is basically
what it looks like and then we can also
prop
look at what this is actually doing to
see whether there's a way to make this
separable as well so we just do instead
of interior loops we just can do you
know row sums and then column sums I
don't know if there's a way that we can
potentially do it that way
but hopefully as we work through this
will we can you know think about that so
anyway taking a look at this if we want
to look at what the shuffle is that
produces the correct values here for
just the R's right which is I guess what
we need to have happen here that's just
going to be the same transpose as this
right so loading these up I think it's
just the same transpose actually
like I want to say that we can just do
that and then call transpose I think so
maybe I didn't even have to blow that
part out so I think I mean correct me if
I'm wrong here but I think if we just
have two of these right and then we load
in or I guess I should say like this
because the transpose is symmetric right
it it transpose is it doesn't it doesn't
care at all whether you started in one
orientation and transpose to the other
or vice versa so we should be able to
just load these in transpose them both
do the OP
I think right yeah oops I and I guess so
well okay so not quite because we also
in addition we need the weights to
affect everyone so the transpose puts us
so that we have all of our ours but we
still I guess that's not that's not true
what I said because we still need to we
would still need to collapse the sums so
this would not like get our horizontal
adds in so maybe I'll take that back for
a second and say maybe we don't do that
because since this is a straight sum
this this just needs to replicate a
particular value right like it just
needs to say look we want to take s 0 r
and we want to just have all of that
right in each case
so since this is RGB RGB I guess it's
it's this right so maybe this is the
right way to look at it you just go by
each of these values yeah so I guess
yeah man these are this is why this kind
of stuff is so annoying right you can
see how long it takes to do code like
this it's just this is why Cindy is not
good right and you usually want this
stuff to be automated and unfortunately
we still don't really have particularly
good ways of doing it because just like
your brain is having to think about too
many like indexes and how things are
sliced up and it just y-you know it's
just like a bad way of designing the way
you're supposed to express things and I
really don't think it has legs you know
you shouldn't be really doing this
yourself
especially now when you consider the
fact that shaders are a good example of
how you can just do this stuff and when
you have properly unpacking loads you
just don't have to think about it
anymore because you just write the code
like you would have written it for
scalar and they can run at that speed
right so anyway kind of a side rant but
it doesn't matter so anyway yeah if we
take a look at the loads here let's get
this back to normal so each of these
shuffles should just now work I think
because again they're just expansions
you're basically just replicating
a particular value out and I think that
should be it
and this should line up exactly at least
a theory oops
and there we go
so I think that loads everything not
sure why this is complaining oh that's
supposed to be an f32
I guess
do we have a load for these somewhere
you would just think that we would I'm
not actually sure we do
apparently not feel like we should have
a load for these let me go ahead and
make one so don't see one
maybe that and this just literally does
exactly what this does
oops
and maybe a little too cheeky love that
caps lock key never want it still
kicking probably should just go hack put
in the registry thing that just disables
it anyway so here's the load for our
data type here and I can go ahead and
load F 32x these and then the nice part
about that is to now then we can stop
with a casting nonsense which is always
kind of annoying
I hate the way Intel designed these
intrinsics they're so bad like you don't
want to have to cast just like here's
the address to load from why do I have
to cast into a float star like that
doesn't really make any sense but
alright so in here where we're doing the
ads let me just take a look so so this
is actually an F 32x
so when we do this multiply here
I guess that we'll just do the f 3/2
times the f32 and we'll be done with it
and that makes sense than I think about
it because it's like you're not gonna
have different coefficients for r g and
b so i'm not sure why i was i was
writing it that way
but all right so where's our shuffle 4x
ah so we kind of set that up so that we
would pass in the two different things
to use in this case it's just replicate
I might actually make a custom one of
these that's just like maybe even just a
function that's like broadcast you know
and I don't know again like it maybe we
already had that but I don't think we
did because we haven't really done much
with these so there's not much there's
not really a lot in them you know what I
mean but I'll just double check to see
if there's a broadcast yeah I don't I
don't see one here so I'm gonna go ahead
and make like a a broadcast where you
just say all right here's the value
that's coming in and here's like well
you know what now I think about it it
does have to be a macro though because
if you want to specify which one you
have to be able to specify that at
compile time it's not actually a runtime
thing so I think it does actually it
would have to be one of these so
broadcast 4x would just say look here's
the one I actually want and here's like
the element index you know and then it
would be a shuffle
[Music]
where we literally just use the same
index each time actually you know and I
can even just you can just even call the
original shuffle so I can just say
shuffle Forex a index index a index
index right and then it should work just
fine so this can just be changed to a
broadcast 4x and then this can just be
done once which seems saner and then we
just change all these shuffle four X's
to broadcast 4x all right and what else
oh not sure out for got in there all
right so let me take a look to see what
the compiler generates now I just want
to see what it generates here if I go
through this code here we go
so here's us doing the loads and then
Bruce doing chef mulch F mole a - f
Malad chef will add much nicer right so
now we're just dumping the chef moles
into the Al use they're gonna have a
party with that and then we're gonna
loop so it should be pretty hard for the
CPU to screw that up I mean you're just
basically giving it a huge bunch of
flops to chew on so I'm a little bit
more comfortable reasoning about what
that's going to do or how we can work
with it so that's fine let's take a look
and see if it's at all sane in terms of
performance I'm gonna have to turn the
multithreading back on obviously but
let's just take a look at that of course
we also may have added a bunch of pugs
there that's sort of a separate issue
about what do you do
it looks like we've got a little bit of
bugging in there looks like there's a
bit of a chromatic aberration right so
think we yet we do have a little bit of
a problem in there but not much let me
just see what that did to it okay so
yeah I mean you can already see though
like unless I unless I accidentally
removed some of the ops you can see that
that actually is a it's a reasonable
speed improvement so I do think that the
way we had written that before was just
a little bit Squinkie for the the
compiler probably wouldn't necessarily
know what was going on there so that's
not not as good so let's take
double-check let me see what I may have
screwed up there because again like I
didn't think particularly hard about
what we were doing here and I don't
really remember if this was going to be
yet an issue there so if you look at how
the broadcast multipliers work here so
we're selecting individual values out of
the out of the spec texels
which I think are loaded out of the
correct place and so if we're getting a
chromatic aberration there again here's
that transpose so that transpose is like
reinter leaving these things right and
that should be fine so
[Music]
yeah so let me just double-check what
we're computing our weights as so the
weights are packed in here
as what
so the weights are just packed in here
as the TX the tech selects is the
element oh hang on a second
so I guess that's fine because that's
just doing multiple of these at a time
which is what we would expect so this is
just figuring out multiple you know it's
producing it wants to produce four of
the destination pixel at once right
so that's unsurprising and so when it's
doing the multiply here it just wants to
broadcast because it's trying to produce
it's trying to take the source and spam
it out to the to the entire side of it
however so when I look at this I'm
trying to figure out where the heck is
that chromatic aberration then coming
from if we look at what's happening here
yeah so this is busted so this is
loading this is gonna go by entire this
is going to go buy an entire vector e is
the problem so this actually needs to be
more like this because that was loading
strided poorly it's supposed to load by
force and it was loading by twelves
right there we go so again we literally
just did nothing there I mean we didn't
even do anything but we got a speed wind
from it and again that's just because we
got rid of some cruft that the compiler
couldn't understand right so literally
all we did was I mean we we shave what
did that got significantly faster I
don't remember what the actual number
there was but it used to be 30 and now
it's ten percent of the time literally
just from rephrasing it right like all
we did was rephrase it for the compiler
and off we went
right so that just dumps a ton of junk
into the ALUs
lets him chew through it and that's a
reasonable improvement for us
what I don't know is to what extent
could we just get rid of some of these s
whys and that I don't know so it would
be relatively free for us to rephrase
this thing so that instead of working
the way that it works now instead what
it would do is it would just tell us
which row to load and so sometimes it
just wouldn't do that just wouldn't load
a road load a row at all right and so I
don't know to what extent we can
actually do that and
and I guess I wouldn't assume that it
would be very frequent but if we kept
our cosine fall-off a little bit sharper
you know we could imagine doing
something where we took the cosine
fall-off and we we sharpen it so that
it's not quite the cosine fall-off or
that it drops down you know it loses a
little bit of energy there or something
and keeps us from having to load certain
rows again not sure to what extent we
really should do that because I also
don't know we can maybe switch to this
to separable blur here and that would
just be way faster anyway because then
you don't have to do sixty-four wide you
just do eight wide summations right
and that might just be the smarter way
to go so let's think about that for one
second if we did want to make this be
something where we separated out those
some values just trying to think of what
the what the cosign actually looks like
in that case and you know could we I'm
just writing it could be switched to
some other thing I don't know how
separable cosign is but you know it
doesn't have to be a perfect cosign so
that's I was thinking like you know a
Gaussian blur is separable and a
Gaussian and a cosine are obviously very
closely related in that way so we could
theoretically just use you know a value
that was going to be separable then go
from there so if we look at like
a cosine curve and like
it's not right
um wait what's the right way to produce
the Gaussian curve I haven't done this
and so long hold on a second gasps you
know distribution is where's give me the
equation please because it's it's you
know it's what I wrote but you gotta
have the right parameters to make it
look useful so it's just the negative
well I guess we don't have to care about
specifically how we put it in there but
it's just that one there but and then we
got to shift it over by something right
because we need to come off of there it
probably isn't a particularly great
approximation for the cosine either way
but X minus B squared 2 over 2 C squared
No
I'm so bad at desmos yeah all right
Decimus is so good is that
it's like we need more parameters than
that a to the e negative X minus B
squared - C squared Oh did I put the
squared in the wrong place though let's
try that one more time there we go much
better and then I guess we also want the
a here can I get these sliders to be a
little bit more these need to be a
little bit more granular and currently
aren't but decimals is just so much fun
I mean look at how nice this is they
deserve some kind of award for something
right when you say
so you know it's not great but it's not
horrible
so if you take a look at how that's
summing up the values there right a
Gaussian is something that we can just
multiply on various axes and it would
produce the correct results and so we
wouldn't have to you know it would be a
shaping curve for this we could also
just multiply this on both axes we could
just use the cosine curve and multiply
that on both axe axes and just say hey
that's what it's what the answer is
going to be
so this is apparently you know just
randomly googling for it
this seems totally like something people
are okay with doing separable so I mean
I assume I don't actually know this is
this is just doing it in in one
frequency domain so but if we were to
just use this I know we can do this one
separable and I assume the cosine one if
we multiplied it would still be okay
it's basically a cosine squared fall-off
at that point I guess you could say not
sure how you would really look at that
but if you imagine the difference
between these two things like you know
would we really care which one of those
we were using you know probably not for
lighting especially because it's just
kind of made up anyway like there aren't
really surfaces that are going to be
reflecting things in a perfect Lamberson
distribution anyway so it's not like
there's something particularly
physically accurate about doing that as
opposed to doing that or vice versa
right so if that's the actual cosine
curve and we compute this as the actual
function for it it seems like that would
be fine you know what I mean like that
doesn't seem like a particularly bad
approximation so that's another thing
that we could do here instead of
actually looping over both of these we
could do something where we produce a
summed Rho value and then we produce
some column values out of those saundra
values you know what I'm saying and it
seems like that would maybe be the
smarter way to go so like we take each
position and we we do the cosine
fall-off curve if you were just doing it
by a row
and then we do the cosine curve if you
were just doing it by a column and we
call that our answer right and we could
leave both of these in place and take a
look if we actually see a particularly
noticeable difference between the
results in here and one thing I can do
is I can again because we haven't worked
on the quality yet I can turn the like
transmission rate of this thing down to
darken these as well if we want to do
that and that would allow us to kind of
see what they look like a little bit
better just because we're not trying to
do any exposure curves here so it's kind
of hard for us to see what are like
octagonal maps look like if they get
even you know to the brightness that we
would probably want them to be actually
we still wouldn't really be able to see
them very well so keeping it in here
would allow us to switch between those
two pretty pretty easily there right
so again just taking a look at what
we're producing for these maps as we go
if we now switch to separable what we
could do is see if there really is much
of a difference between the two that we
would care about for transmission and I
don't really know that there would be
right again these maps on the side here
are the actual light transfer maps and
so this is or rather that what we
actually computed for the lighting and
coming in various directions so these
are just the blurs on those that we use
for diffuse light for diffuse lighting
which also has to account for more
angles right so if we want to go ahead
and change that up if I go back into
this code and say what would we actually
do here to make that happen well in
order to do that we would do two of our
loops we would basically do the loops
twice so we would go down once doing the
rows and then we would go down one more
time doing the columns right
yeah so let's go ahead and put in if
you're around this here and let's see if
we can throw in a separable version of
it on the way out so one of the things
that's a little annoying about this just
looking at the values that are coming in
here I think I just kind of want to
sketch out the routine first so
basically this is this is this kernel
like basically this stuff right here
where we load a spec Texel from
somewhere and then we do the blend on it
I think we're still gonna want to do
this right so we're gonna want to load
the sy tiles and go down the rows and
we're gonna want to do this operation
the same way we're doing it here where
we are summing up four of these at a
time and then we write them out right so
I think this structure actually still
remains this right here so this would
produce the first pass where we you know
we reproduce output values that are sums
of rows right and the difference is we'd
actually write out so rather than
summing this here we would actually be
summing it like here right and this s
why we would also use to determine where
we were writing it out you know
now we probably don't really actually
need to do the transpose there because
when we load it we would because we're
gonna do another op on this right so we
could probably leave it in the form that
it is and then only do the transfer
transpose once at the end but we can
talk about that in a second so this
would basically run through the entire
thing once right and in fact we could
change that sy and and just look at it
as like a tu I as well right so if here
I basically said like yeah we're gonna
use T Y into X here we're gonna delete
the sy version of this thing and so in
here it would just literally be back
right so we go through we load the the
the weights out we would do the
summation here we would output the value
and that would run through the array one
time and then we would then we would
also want our second pass to be exactly
the same only now when we do it we're
gonna be doing by columns right so where
we load values out of the the where we
load values they're going to be from the
diffuse texels not the spec texels right
there like intermediate texels and so we
would get these out of the
you know something would happen here
right we would then load rows of the
inte Texel out so we would be loading
like for wide trying to think of how you
would even do this exactly the for the
the problem with it is you actually the
problem is actually the intermediate
storage so you actually would want to
just be leaving things as ours so I
guess you would just load for wide and
do four columns at once and then you
would Swizzle the four columns to write
them out I think yeah so I think then
what you would do here is you say all
right we're then gonna load four columns
at once and we know there's eight
columns so yet you would load those you
would sum across the column and output
the value right like I have time to
finish this today this will have to be
tomorrow so yes so in order to load the
correct columns here we would probably
still just do the lows manually and
again we're gonna have to pretty much
bake these values like we're there
Lupe's gonna have to be written
customized I think to a particular size
I don't think we can leave it flexible
but I mean it's kind of not already not
flexible here right like this already
assumes a certain number of these anyway
so if we go in here and say all right
for these we'd have to load all eight
columns in that looks more like this
we'd have to do all of the ops on them
and the problem that you would then get
is you can't actually write them out
because they're in the wrong format so
yeah it's just really ugly you would
have to do the ops here so maybe you
would transpose here
let me think about this
so I suppose another way to look at this
would be that if you were going to just
replicate the weights themselves
I'm trying to think of what I'm saying
is true if you were just gonna replicate
the wage themselves could we maybe just
leave this an RGB the entire time
I think we probably could so you know
bear with me for a minute so suppose in
here as we load across this road we
don't actually do any broadcasting right
so what this is doing here is it's
saying well I need to produce the R
value for this thing right
and so rather than thinking of it as
looking as a RGB RGB whatever like you
know what if we've said instead of that
like that's not what we're going to do
so instead we just said like look this
is like RGB like this is you know this
is just element zero right trying to
sketch out what this might look like so
suppose we were just going to start
computing elements here and we said look
this these weights are going to be like
set up so that they multiply this thing
properly and we have like this broadcast
and instead of doing the broadcast we're
just going to say look s zero we know
that we could figure out what the values
are that want to multiply it in to
produce a zero right so we could just
say instead like no it's just that right
so we're just doing the multiply between
these two and then what we want to do is
just sum those up so we're just going to
do like
that so we just have weights for each of
the things that we actually want to load
out I mean I guess trying to think
exactly what this does here so and it
wouldn't be because the weights now are
also not based on oops the weights now
would not be based on anything in
particular because if we're just doing a
row and then column weights we have far
fewer weights there aren't sixty-four
weights anymore right so what we could
do is say look we're just going to
record the weights that we would
actually use for this further multiply
we'll do the multiply and for each
output element that we have for the row
of which we know well and in fact we can
just write it immediately at that point
right it's just a store so we can just
say yeah we're gonna write this thing
out
[Music]
somewhere right and off we go and we
would just do this for each of the six
elements
so like that's one way we could do it so
we just record like what each of these
weights is supposed to be in some kind
of a like weight distribution thing
right furthermore actually like thinking
about this a little bit more it doesn't
really even need to be something like
it's not structured anymore cuz it's
literally just one set of weights and
you would apply it in both cases I think
maybe that's not true
do the same set of weights in both cases
but they might be formatted slightly
differently
so if we actually just loaded things in
multiplied by the weights and
accumulated and that was actually the
value that we stored in there that would
give us you know
so it'd be 36 you know Max or whatever
per row so it would be 288 of those and
then another 288 of those in the other
direction right so it'd be like half the
number and that seems like not as much
as it should be
although that probably was multiplied by
three wasn't it I don't know if we were
looking at that correctly before but in
fact how what is the actual number here
so now cuz then you can see it pretty
easily now so if we take a look at how
many are in here we've got eight times
two times eight and on the interior
there's like what
one two three four five six seven eight
so eight times three so there's 24 max
eight times two times eight times 24
yeah
so it wasn't applied by 3 there was
we've got the three in there so I yeah
if you take a look at the ratio
it would be about five times faster in
theory if we did it this way unless
there's some other like intervening
factor right so you would come through
here you would load up a row you would
compute what the smoosh of that row is
in RGB directly
you wouldn't like unsuited don't know if
I can I think yeah I don't know if we
can actually do this because if you
think about what has to happen here so
in order to get the correct value in the
first slot weights times so0
it doesn't actually have a way to get
that other are in there right like these
don't allow you to do the cross terms
properly so I don't think we can
actually do it this way unfortunately so
I'm not sure I'm gonna save this for
tomorrow I'll get rid of this for now
we'll have to think about how to do it
exactly because it's really just a
question of how do we get that it's just
how do we get stuff in the right spot so
for now we'll just say look we know we
can get that we know we got a good
savings out of it just by making it a
little bit clearer to the compiler how
to do it and so now it's just a question
of can we improve it further from there
but otherwise it seems okay we'll go to
a quick Q&amp;A
are there any caching concerns so I
don't know that there are any caching
concerns with the voxel
[Music]
so yeah so what do we say it's that so I
don't know that there's any cash against
turn to the Vox at the moment cuz it's
so large that we will not be getting
good cash out of it really in terms of
anything other than just regular
streaming performance right now that can
be improved by switching away from float
we would start to get down to areas
where we might actually be able to do
something good there and furthermore if
we wanted to we could get like really
down into reasonable range by also again
reducing the number of stacked voxels
we've got we could also do some things
like play with the resolution in terms
of Y as well so there's a lot of things
we could do to shrink the amount of data
that we're working with the biggest one
would be not using floats anymore and we
could definitely experiment with that
but at the moment yeah we're fully blown
out right now and so we are not gonna be
in a particularly great cash land at the
moment now that said separate from that
I think we have done a good job with
caching concerns in terms of the order
in which we're working on things so what
you'll notice is we very specifically
and I did this 100% intentionally right
each tile is updated by itself so on a
particular thread it loads operates and
writes completely one tile at a time and
the reason for that is that way although
we do have no real good control over the
sampling of the diffuse map which we
randomly have to pull from because we
have no idea like as the Rays go out we
have no idea which one's gonna hit in
terms of the operating on and writing
out of the diffuse map that is done
completely contained and so when we want
to turn the ratchet on that we're in
very good shape to do so and we're
already probably getting four
good caching there because we don't do
anything funky right so that was
intentional and that's to keep us from
writing scattered scattered if we wrote
scattered we would be in big trouble but
we don't do that um I don't know that
there's anything simple you can do to
reduce the amount of flicker if you want
it to be very stable and still be fast
when you update you certainly can but
you're just in the realm of denoising so
at that point you have to have you got
to start looking at your at filtering
right like how you're gonna filter the
results I think probably there's if you
were an expert at filtering it probably
wouldn't take you very long to clean up
these results because there's not very
much flicker so basically what you're
looking at there is just you've got a
filter and that is something that you
you probably want to be more of an
expert on than I am to know how long it
would take you to reasonably build a
good denoising system for this kind of a
thing right
the light series repeating out so have
the light box is it still there and if
so is the de modulus is you know so
that's just because of the textile
lookups so right now we we're at the
textile wraps right so when it does
lighting it's just gonna light outside
of it we don't care about that because
you can never see outside there right
the only reason we're ever seeing that
stuff right now is because we aren't
actually properly centering our so like
if you look at what's happening here and
you pull out right you see that voxel
right now we're letting some some
garbage happen like this should just be
sliding as we move so the place that
you're looking at the camera should
always be in the center and right now
since we're not doing that you know you
can still get times when you will see
across the edge of it we never want to
allow that to happen so we have to fix
that slide anyway and that's just a
question of writing the code that
properly aligns it to with where you're
looking and that's all we have to do so
I don't care that the lighting repeats
out here because we don't we'll never
see it you'll never you will never see
that on the screen so I should be fine
with that
you mentioned something about shaders
being better at this kind of job I lost
your point on that because of me being
for the environment can you please
explain this a little bit more um yes so
one of the things that you'll notice is
like when we wrote our shader code okay
you'll notice that we never had to think
about Cindy at all ever right
we literally never ever ever wrote
anything in here that had anything to do
with Cindy we just wrote this is this
just looks like regular code that
operates on like one value right and yet
when we write CPU code that does
basically the same thing we have to do
all of this mental work ourselves you
know and the question is why is that and
the answer is very simple
the GPU already has in it the proper
memory cross barring on loads to turn
things that are packed RGB RGB RGB into
ours G's and B's and then when it's done
it has the bar to write them back out
that way so rather than us having to do
all of our code that way
GPUs were just like hey you know
everyone needs to store things compactly
as little units that should be packed X
Y Z X Y Z RGB RGB let's just make a
thing that will unpack those into ours
Gees and B's while we're computing them
and then put them back when we're done
intel just never did it they just simply
didn't do it and I don't know why they
didn't do it it must have been too hard
for them to do in the store buffers or
something or the load buffers I don't
know but they just never did it and so
it's all this huge headache when you
want to do something and you decide to
do on the CPU side it's this huge
headache it really sucks
and with avx-512 because that was
designed originally as a shader API so
avx-512 was originally ler Ben I which
was originally for GPU right that has
proper it's called scattered gathers
what that's called it has proper scatter
gather so that actually finally you can
just load and do your Swizzle on the
load and it's free right do your work
and then write it out scattered so it's
the same is true with neon and if you
ever seen that but the arm SSE has that
in it so basically the problem is just
that on the CPU side there is no way to
actually do it clean you can't load pack
day
and get it out into properly aligned
form without a crap-ton of shuffles as
you've seen right and so that's just
it's just a limitation of the hardware
if at some point avx-512 became a
standard feature set which at this point
may like literally never happen I mean I
don't even know if Intel's gonna be
shipping the chips that anyone cares
about anymore like I mean AMD is by far
the performance leader now like I mean
they are just crushing Intel and will
continue to do so like Intel can't even
manage to fab new chips anymore
it would seem so like I don't even know
if we'll get avx-512
it may never happen right it may be that
like you know sort of a marginal set of
Intel chip supports avx-512 AMD never
adopts it and AMD is dominant in the x64
space neon of course is its own thing
and arm you know may become more
dominant as well it's already is pretty
dominant a lot of ways and so you know
it may be that we never get FAS 512 I
don't know
hmm yeah and just to be clear like so
features like Jaso a a OS stuff while
obviously a good thing and you want your
language to make it easy for you to
write things that reorganize your data
without you having to rewrite your code
one of the problems with it again is
that that there's nothing J I can really
do to solve this particular problem
right because the problem is we need
this data in the same format as the GPU
needs this data right and so it ties
that like there's nothing Jay I can't
reorganize that because it has to be in
that format and so there's really
nothing you can you can particularly do
there right now there are things that
languages can do to make it easier for
you to write messed up code like this
which is they can provide tools for you
to ask it to do like arrangement of your
code for you in structured ways someone
just mentioned is PC and yes that's a
very good example of language additions
and then a compiler that backs up those
language additions to allow you to more
easily write scalar code that can be
turned into Sindhi code without you have
to do anything and it will still be good
Sindhi code right so that's a great
feature but again not really present in
much in our tools very much yet right oh
is it in so it says the Intel intrinsic
that is broken
what's broken about it looks fine to me
yeah
maybe you've got a route problem I don't
know it's loaded for me yeah
night isn't a control shift are so that
should load it out of outside of the
cache right that's a forestry load
oh you can't specify architecture so
you're saying you can't like click yeah
it does look as soon as I clicked on
that it broke so it does look like they
broke it yep that is true it would seem
they broke it you can use the you ops
page for this though so that's another
option and that will probably work right
so yeah I'm saying I this this won't
tell you what the intrinsic is so I
don't know I don't know at least I don't
think it will
I'm not sure maybe it will I don't think
it will do but for doing stuff like
finding out what the instruction like
performances this is actually better
anyway so like I would I would encourage
you also to use this as much as possible
and unfortunately doesn't have intrinsic
sin here it'd be cool if they added that
because then there'd be no reason to use
the internal intrinsic guide you just
always use this but
all right I'm gonna wrap it up I'm
really liking this lighting I think it's
gonna be a lot of fun to kind of tune it
up a little bit I think rig is it's just
so nice to be able to walk around and
have that kind of realistic like play
off the walls and everything and I don't
know this is getting really cool
anyway alright close it on up where's my
web browser I closed it that's not what
I meant to do all right thank you for
ready for joining me from episode of
handmade heroes and a pleasure coding
with you as always if you would like to
follow on the series at home you can
always pre-order the game at handmade
hero org and it comes with a source code
which you can use to follow along at
home if you want to try writing a
separable version of that filter
yourself that would be a great thing to
do tonight because it's a pretty
bite-sized problem and you can go look
up separable filters and read about them
before I get into that which I don't
know if we really need to do but I do
think we want to least try it because it
should be significantly less ops and we
do need to reduce the number of ops in
that code so something to think about
alright I'll be back here tomorrow give
that a swing till then have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the
Internet
take it easy everybody