hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero sure we code a complete game live
on stream yesterday I did sort of a i
guess it was impromptu because i didn't
know we were going to go into it and
quite so much death but i needed to
explain some matrix math in order for
people to understand sort of what i was
doing and in a particular part of the
code and so i gave a pretty complete
explanation actually of how to do
matrices work for geometric transforms
and how the inverse and the transpose of
them are related in sort of a bunch of
other stuff that you would need to know
if you were doing 2d graphics work and
needed to do some rather advanced well i
guess not rather advanced i'm going to
use the phrase basic advanced stuff you
know plenty of people write 2d games and
things without really ever knowing
anything about a matrix but as soon as
you want to do something fancy kind of
even that need to know this stuff it's
not advanced per se but it's more
advanced than not knowing i guess not
trying to say that any other way so
anyway we've come to the point hopefully
if you watched the stream that we did
that talked about that now you know that
the only thing we have left to do now is
show how if we want to do a full inverse
of a 2d matrix a two-by-two matrix i
should say how do we do that and i'm
going to kind of show how that works
today and this is going to be not very
much fun for me certainly because this
is the kind of stuff i hate as far as
doing math is concerned oops gonna have
to reboot my Milt in there see here
there we go run
and so here we go on day 3 20 with
inverting a 2 by 2 matrix I was
basically going to show how to do this I
from first principles kind of and it's
just a lot of fussy math we're doing
only a 2 by 2 matrix so it's as easy as
possible which is nice it's a you know a
1 by 1 matrix would just be a scalar but
you know it's still a bunch of fussing
math term so I'm going to do it and
hopefully I won't make too many math
mistakes along the way feel free to use
computer algebra package when you're
actually doing stuff like this but I
kind of want to show how it works out
just so people can see it once all right
so if you remember from yesterday what I
what I said was you know we had an
equation that looked like a P equals P
Prime and we actually wanted to solve
for P so we needed to be able to
multiply both sides with the inverse of
this transform a inverse this guy right
here and so that's going to give us this
equation now we know that a inverse AE
Quilly identity matrix right so this
goes away and we're just left with P
equals a inverse P Prime and this is the
occasion occasion that's good this is
the equation we wanted to solve and so
in order to solve it we obviously need
to know how to produce a inverse and so
that is where we are at today so what we
want to do is say well if I had an a
matrix and let's say it's just a b c d
like so if i have an a matrix and i
would like to produce the inverse of
that a matrix well i've already kind of
shown you everything you need to know to
solve for what that actually is from
first principles if you want to just
work out how to do a matrix embrace
yourself you actually know how to do it
and let me explain why and then I'll
show you how to do it that way and then
we can also see some some kind of
shortcut approaches that you can follow
but let's just take a look at this so
here's my a Maitre
and what I said yesterday in when we
were just talking about what the
definition of the inverse was and what
the definition of the identity matrix
was we said some some very basic things
which is just that a inverse times a has
to equal the identity matrix right
that's the definition of the inverse
that's what we know has to be true and
so if we have this equation you'll
notice that this is a matrix equation
where we have a two by two matrix times
another two by two matrix equaling a
known quantity just you know the
identity matrix is is just a known
quantity it's that right and so if we
take a look at what this is well this is
a equation that has for it this is an
equation that some so has four scalar
equations in it right because a
two-by-two matrix so it's four scalar
equations right one for each slot in
this matrix multiply and we know all of
the values in the a matrix that's what
we're given to start with so we have
four unknowns in the a inverse we don't
know what the members what those four
elements of Andres are we have four
knowns and a four nodes in the eye so we
have four equations in four unknowns
essentially as you'll see in a second in
case you don't believe me which means we
can just solve this right we can just
solve it it may be a lot of fussing but
we have what we need right so take a
look at what ends up happening here so I
have an a inverse matrix I don't know
any of the values of this a inverse
matrix right I have no idea what they
are so let's just say we have X Y Z W
are the the terms of my inverse matrix
right so this is my a inverse here and
then I've got my a matrix right and I'm
going to make my amex just kind of big
because we're going to be room for our
Terms down here right and my my a matrix
I just said was a b c d okay so what are
all the terms of this product here right
and I know again that this equals the
identity matrix 1 0 0 1 0 right there
you go
so what are the terms you know how to do
makeup so I've done tons of times on
handmade hero so I've got ax plus cy in
here I've got AZ plus C W right I've got
be X plus dy and I've got bz plus d w
right those are my dot product terms
right ax cy AZ CW be why ooh I made a
mistake there be why glad i checked be
why DW oh no i didn't know that's that's
nonsense I did it right first time be X
my fine little Mike Ross was just a
little bit off be X dy DZ DW ok so I
produced all of the dot products like I
said matrix multiplication you could
think of was just a series of dot
products every column with every row and
that's what we've got here and so
hopefully you can see now why this why I
say we have four equations because this
is what we are left with right and
obviously if I'm saying that this matrix
is equal to this matrix then each of
their elements must be equal so I
actually know that ax plus C y equals
one right I know they have to be equal I
know that BX plus dy has to equal zero I
know that AZ plus CW has to equal zero
and I know that BZ plus DW has to equal
what right so I know the a's the bees
the Seas the DS right I know the ones
and zeros so I have four equations and
only four unknowns X Y Z W so we can
solve this equation strictly by back
substituting right we can actually just
go ahead and do it like I said it's a
pain in the butt but here we go right
let's just do it grid you know grin and
bear it and like I said without knowing
it without need to know any trickery or
any you know special stuff about linear
algebra just from what I already had
explained
you could have set this up and solved it
right because we know that that's what
has to happen if we want to find the
inverse matrix so yeah let's go ahead
and and I guess use the zero guys first
let's let's start with this equation
here we have BX plus dy equals zero so
it's trivial for us to solve this in
terms of let's say the X variable since
hey let's solve for x first why not so
we would know that that would be be x
equals negative dy right or X just
equals dy over I'm sorry x equals dy
over be right very very straightforward
so now i can plug that in i could plug
that into this guy up here I could say
okay I now know what X is so if I want
to solve for y well I've got an equation
in terms of Y an equation in terms of X
right and you can see how I'm kind of
doing this I'm just saying well you know
really because these don't have any
cross terms I could think of it as you
know as being two equations one in x + 1
+ y I'm sorry two equations in x and y &amp;
2 equation skin Z and W because that's
just how it happens to fall out right
you're only going to have x and y's on
this row there won't be any x and y's in
this row so when I go to solve I don't
have to think about that thankfully
right alright so i've got x equals
negative dy over B and then I can just
plug it back into here where I'll have
only wise right because I'll have ax
plus C y equals 1 well the X I now know
what it is so I can say a times negative
dy over B which is what I solve for
before plus cy there we go equals 1 okay
and so now I should be able to actually
solve for y I would have negative a dy
over B plus C y equals 1 you can see
here that I can pull out the y term
right I could pull out the y term here
and just get c minus ad over B equals 1
right and then I am left with just the
actual
answer for what why is which is just y
equals 1 over ad over B now big caveat
there that's if I didn't make a math
mistake i'm awful at doing math by hand
so you know what i should say is it's
something like c- ad over B modulo the
math errors that Casey probably meant
Casey probably had along the way but you
can see now that you've got a equation
in terms of Y and all knowns on the
other side because these a B D and C
those are all obviously pieces of those
are all things that we knew from the
original matrix right so yeah so let me
just quickly double check that because
like i said i usually make math errors
we have BX plus dy so I just subtracted
the dy to the other side like so and
then I / be so that's where my ex I had
a X plus cy I substituted in my negative
dy over be so at a and a plus C y equals
one there right so that's negative ad Y
over B plus CY and then I just pulled my
Y out I flipped the terms because this
one's negativeness was positive so I put
the sea first and the negative 80 / b
and then I ended up with this term here
right now it's worth noting that if I
wanted to I could sort of i could write
this as a combined fraction or i could
do a bunch of the things to this if I
wanted to like I guess I'm saying is
there's there's other ways I could
phrase this right because you know it's
a it's a 1 over right now but then
there's a fraction on the bottom so if I
wanted to kind of simplify this term a
little i could do so right and let me
just show you what i mean by that so if
I and again this is all caveat if I did
the math right one over this term right
here c minus 80 / be well if i wanted to
combine this fraction right i could
multiply this guy by b over b which is
you know equal to 1
and I could get B C over B right- ad
over be right so I could turn that
bottom into something that could
actually be done as a fraction so it
would become bc- ad all over be right i
mean that's that's just all i'm doing is
simplifying that bottom a little bit why
did i do that because now that I've done
that one over something over something
right I can just flip it I can get rid
of the one over now and just end up with
you know b over b c minus ad right so
that's really a simpler version of that
term be over bc- ad it's a it's a
cleaner version then this is where I've
got the one over there right so b over b
c minus ad if i did the math right as i
said before i now know that that's the
that why element of my matrix so here's
my a inverse I'm just going to rewrite
it here with the one that we know okay
so here it is down here what I say it
was be over bc- ad right so be over bc
oops p c- ad okay i'll make sense uh
okay so let's just continue with the
exact same process again like I said
this is just a lot of of like high
school alger homework I mean at some
level you could say this was this was
junior high school algebra homework
right were in pre-algebra they just made
you like move terms around for no reason
which honestly is what most of math is
before you go to college I suppose so
anyway we still have this equation here
x equals a negative dy over B or rather
I should say we have this equation here
BX plus dy we can plug in our equation
for y to solve for x now because we do
know that bx right Plus D times this
right which would be d b over b c minus
ad right is going to equal zero and
that's all in terms of X as well so if
you take a look at what happens there we
would have be x equals d b over b c
minus ad negated right i'm moving this
the other side and then I would be
dividing by be right so I'd have x
equals negative and you'll notice
there's a bee on top and I'm dividing by
a bee so those go away and I just be
left with d / bc- ad right so negative D
bc- ad now you'll notice something
interesting about that again keep I keep
always at the caveat to the math right i
am not strong with manual computation
but you can see our ex- d over bc my CD
that's really kind of similar right you
can kind of see that that's a pretty
similar term here right bc minus ad uh
it's got the same denominator right
which is kind of surprising a little bit
right i mean it just seems a little odd
so even you know even with my shoddy
math skills we're starting to get
something that looks like it has a
little bit of structure here so maybe
that should give us some encouragement
but you know I'm just saying keep an eye
on that right alright so now let's do
the exact same thing with these
equations now those of you who are
particularly good at math will probably
note that we can probably shortcut this
a little bit because if you look at what
these look like right you can see that
they're essentially the same equations
almost except the ex sorry the AC terms
are the ones that equal one here and the
BD terms are the ones that equals 0
whereas in this one it's the same
equations but the zero and the one are
flipped right so essentially we could
just substitute we could flip the a B
and the CD right and the solutions to
the equations would be the same to see
what I'm saying because it's really just
the same two equations with Z in place
of X W in place of Y right and the zero
and the one flipped makes sense so we
could if we were so inclined jump right
to the conclusion that we're going to
get the same two terms here but with the
opposite set of letters but
I'm going to do it out longhand just so
you can see it like I said we should do
this once I think it's important to just
kind of see everything out once before
you start to do those little swizzles
and stuff so anyway do the same thing
idea before go to start with a0 term so
I've got an AZ plus C W equals zero
right I want to solve for one of these
and so i'll just start solve for the z
right so i'll have a Z equals negative
CW or oops or Z equals negative CW over
a ok so that's my my temporary term for
Z again it's in terms of W so I haven't
solved for Z yet I've just put it in
terms of W but now I could do the same
thing at it before which is my back
substitution right I could take be Z
plus DW and i can substitute it in there
right so i've got bz plus DW and that's
going to equal one right DZ plus two
equals one and so now i can substitute
in my Z term so what I've got here is
I've got be at times my negative CW over
a right that's my Z term plus DW equals
one well now I've got it such that all
of its all in terms of W so again same
exact process coming through so i've got
negative bc w over a plus DW equals one
again i want to solve for W so I'm just
going to pull the W term out i end up
with the D minus BC over a equals one
again like I said very similar equations
because we've just kind of reversed some
terms around but it's basically the
exact same system so it's no surprise
right that it looks exactly like this
guy here only with some of the letters
changed around right so again I can
finish solving for W i would get 1 over
d minus BC over a there's my inverted
term right and like I said before we
want to try and simplify this down so
that we can see the structure in the
equation so I'm going to continue doing
exactly what I was doing before to get
this into the simplest possible form
again x a over a so i can combine these
two fractions well this guy is really a
fraction right but you get my point so
I'd have ad over a minus BC over a that
allows me to combine
terms so that would just give me one
over ad minus BC over a right and then I
can finish the the sort of uninvent no
uncle I can finish the D version of this
by flipping the fraction around just
flipping it over and getting ad minus BC
on the bottom and a on the top right so
I have a with ad minus BC there so let's
see here where my at ya so a over ad
minus BC and that was my was the term
out of solving for that was my w/a over
ad minus BC right so there's my w/a over
ad minus BC right uh and you know just
keep pay attention to this again like I
said you could see a lot of structured
there but it's not quite the same bottom
turn right but you know don't don't
worry about that too much because we're
going to get to looking at the structure
this in a second but just I was saying
like look at the similarity a little bit
there so now we've got our w terms so
let's go back up to the equation that we
didn't use right that we thought we
didn't use but that we used as our
starter I should be circling this one
though we use as our starter here right
where we saw FC the AZ minus CW so if I
start with a Z minus CW again AZ minus
CW and now I substitute in my w I will
be able to solve for Z for reals this
time AZ minus C a over ad minus BC right
and that equals I lost it again it
equals 0 right okay so if I want to
finish solving for this guy I know I
have to solve for my Z well that doesn't
look particularly hard I'll just end up
with AZ and CA minus I'm sorry over ad
minus BC here right so I just need to
dissolve / my a but of course there
already isn't a so i end up with just
see / ad
specie right and that's it so see / ad
minus BC C over ad minus BC right and
there's all my terms now what you'll
notice about these guys is if I wanted
to i'm pretty sure i have a math error
in here somewhere because i i'm
expecting this to be slightly more
symmetric with the minus so i think i
missed a minus which let's be honest is
pretty good for me like i said very very
bad at a symbolic math manually i always
do stuff like that which is why i hate
doing it right i really want the
algebraic blackboard program even for
when i'm working stuff out myself where
I just tell it what math operations I
want to do and it did it I don't know
why that program doesn't exist i've
always thought i should just write it
but does it because i usually don't
actually want to solve stuff for me
because a lot of times i'm working with
things symbolically that it that it
can't solve necessarily and i just want
to be able to manipulate the terms with
predictability and know that i don't
make a kill us error i really wish i had
that anyway um but point being you can
look at the structure this and i'm going
to check the math at second but even at
this point you can see that actually all
of these have the exact same divisor
minus the fact that some of them are
negative because if i wanted to i could
turn this into the same divisor just by
negating this term right if i have c /
ad minus BC right and I want that to
look like c over b c minus ad all i have
to do is multiply it by a negative 1
over negative 1 which is right that's
equal to one if i multiply that i would
just get negative C over negative ad
minus BC which is VC minus ad right so I
can produce this just by doing that I
can regularize it so that it has the
same bottom as the rest of these guys so
I'm going to go see if I can just
quickly find my matter because we're so
close almost had an error-free rum you
might as well go
broke right I mean come on so let's see
here where was I at so let's see we've
got well you know what actually here's
the easiest way to do it i suppose if i
was to convert these all to the same one
let's convert them all to ad minus BC
right so what I would end up with in
that case is I would end up with a
matrix that would look like d / ad minus
BC be negative B over ad minus BC right
and then I would end up with c / ad
minus BC and a over ad minus BC right so
if i take that i should be able to
multiply it if i want to buy my original
matrix and i should be able to get the
identity right if i've done it correctly
right a b c d and i think i have a sign
error so i think this should show us
pretty quickly which pair of terms is
right and wrong or at least get us close
to that right so let's take a look so
say i'm going to multiply this down
right well they all have their gonna
have the same divisor so i'd end up with
ad right plus BC over ad minus BC right
that's what I would end up with and you
can see that this is slightly wrong that
should be a negative there in order to
make this equal one right so it looks
like this term is probably incorrect I
probably missed the minus as I suggested
right if that makes sense the next one
this would give me negative be a right
plus a B and that's perfect right ad
minus BC that's a B minus ay B that's 0
which is exactly what I wanted right so
those two terms look correct right so
these guys look good we know this guy is
wrong so we can just ignore
that for a second here and then let's
double check this guy so if we have cd
times this we would get negative b c
plus da equals ad minus BC and hey look
that's exactly what that is so that's
one so I think we know that these terms
are correct and we just don't know about
these terms here but it looks like this
guy is our error and hey that was I
think the guy that I did last so I guess
I just ran out of steam right this was
this was that guy right there so let's
take a look I had AZ minus C W equals
zero is that correct AZ AZ ah well that
would that would do it looks like you
just copied it down wrong I can't fault
myself too much with that jumping all
over the blackboard here so it's really
a plus AZ plus DW so if we fix that bug
we get AZ plus CA a must be right when
this transfers the other side it becomes
the minus and that's where r minus
that's where we lost our minus that's
not too bad I'll you know I won't be too
hard of myself for that but that's that
tells us what we needed to know and now
we have finished inverting our matrix so
we actually have our matrix here and we
can write this actually in a pretty
compact way if we want to we could
really just say this is 1 over ad minus
BC and the elements are just d- be
negative see a right so this right here
is our a inverse if our a is equal to a
b c d okay that's that's what we've got
and we just proved that worked because
we multiplied it out and got the
identity matrix so everyone's happy
happy birthday everything's great right
well what we can look at when we see
this is you can see very quickly now
that if you just wanted to remember in
your head how to invert a 2d matrix it's
actually pretty easy to remember this
guy right here has a special name that
we won't go into into two
detail but this is the determinant this
guy right here well actually that guy
and the determinant of a matrix of a 2d
matrix is just the product of the
diagonal minus the product of the
counter diagonal right so it's ad minus
BC so it's pretty easy to remember again
if you just want to remember how to
invert one without I can go through all
that it's pretty easy to remember you
take this this diagonal multiply it and
subtract this diagonal after multiplying
it and you get the tournament one over
that determinant and then you just
multiply by the matrix effectively
flipped like counter transposed right
flipping it this way and negating the
the opposite diagonal right so that's
one way you can think of you kind of
like mnemonic Lee remember if you would
like to or you can just do it up by hand
or you can look it up or you can do
whatever you want but point being now
you can see where that comes from right
anyway so that's what we've got and hey
let's take a look at what actually
happens with this matrix if we want to
use it for the purpose that we said we
want to use it for which is computing
the UV coordinates right before we were
doing a transpose so let's actually look
at what the difference is here right so
before we did a transpose and we had our
screen space p right and we were
producing the U and V s right so before
we were we were saying like let's say we
have x and y so let's say we're doing
the vector XY the screen space X Y right
that's our RP so before we were doing
ATP to get our you and v's right that's
how we were doing it and what did that
give us right well that just gives us
the a transpose P right that just gives
us if the matrix looks like this ABCD or
whatever and you know what I guess well
we'll fill in what the values actually
are later I suppose because we know what
this this was the x axis and this was
the y axis of our transform right but
anyway if we have a trance
p and we're doing this matrix it'd be a
be right times X Y so it'd be ax plus B
Y in the top and then we would end up
with C and D for the bottom right CX
plus dy that would have been if we had
not transpose it I guess I should say
and so if we transpose it we're going to
flip those around so we're going to flip
the sea and the B but the A&amp;D stay in
the same place right so that would be ax
plus cy and for the bottom row BD right
so that's going to be BX plus dy so
that's what we would work computing
right if that makes sense and to our
credit we did actually still try to
divide by the length amount there so we
were doing a compensation for the length
of the x and y vectors but that's all we
were compensating for right and so the
length of those vectors hmm we could
look at again we'll we'll take a look at
this I guess we should probably go look
at the code and put in exactly what
we're doing but let's actually just take
a look at what happens when we use our
determinant to do the actual inverted
the actual inverse operation here right
so if we were going to do that we will
be multiplying by this matrix and then
dividing by this value right so our
final values that we would get would be
DX oops minus B Y over ad minus BC and
then negative CX plus a y over ad minus
BC right that's what we would actually
get
all right and if I wanted to flip this
around for just for good measure right
you could imagine I don't know how do i
erase your eraser e I could actually do
it the other way around and say a why CX
right if I wanted to but I'm not going
to do that I'm gonna leave it in the
opposite order okay so this is the
actual vector that we would get back and
if we look at what these are we know
what the ABC and D are right because our
matrix was set up such that this was our
like our UX that the U vector right or
the x axis is X right XX I don't know
how we wanted to write it let's call it
let's call it ux for now and this was
our you why right this was our VX and
this was our V Y right so if i'm going
to replace those then when i get is on
the bottom of these guys my a is UX
right my D is V Y so it's you XV y minus
the BC right so VX you why or I guess we
could write it you y VX right so it's UV
it's like the it's the XY y X right okay
so same thing would be up here v y- you
y VX Zack same product and then on top
we would just have our d term which is V
Y V Y times the input x coordinate minus
our VX right at times the input y
coordinate we get up there and for here
we would get negative you y times the
input x coordinate
+ v x times the input y coordinate so
that's the actual equation now for doing
the reverse mapping that we actually
wanted to do and so if we go back to our
code now we can actually take a look and
be in a position to hopefully fix our
bug so let's go ahead to handmade code
that's in the renderer and that's in
oops draw rectangle quickly and in draw
a rectangle quickly you can see where
we're actually doing this code here so
here's where we're convert well here's
where we're computing excuse me ru and
RV coordinates and we have to replace
this these computations with the correct
ones so let's go ahead and it's me blow
the project file there so let me go
ahead and pop back here
and let's load up already on it there we
go and so you can see that the body is
just doing you know the totally wrong
thing there right it's not like what the
opengl one is doing at all and so that's
the bug that we're trying to fix so if
we come back here and look at what we
were doing well we've got these sort of
n x axis stuff that's happening right
and you we were computing that up at the
top here somewhere and next act there it
is so you can see here that we have one
over the x-axis length squared there and
we are multiplying so we respectively
good / whatever the length of the x-axis
is in addition to doing the basic divide
which I'll be honest I'm not sure why we
were doing let's take a look here I'm
not sure why we're doing it ah ah
because we want to map it into the 120
space right so when we do that inverse
transform their we want to first
compensate for however long the x axis
is but then we also want to divide by
the total length of the x axis to
convert our our length back to be 0 to 1
right uh so in in actuality there's
nothing wrong with with us having sort
of done that done that part either and I
have to think for a second about whether
we need what we need to do therefore
that we didn't really handle that part
in the previous one did because our a
matrix no I guess we did in theory are a
matrix should be taking that into
account now I believe right so I think
we don't in theory if I'm not very much
mistaken and it's easy with this much
stuff to be mistaken I think where we
actually just can do this operation and
and be done
I believe right yeah so I think we don't
really need any of this stuff anymore I
think we can just use the x axis
components and the y axis components and
and do it now here's the interesting
part so what you can see here is the
term that we actually care about here
you know we can we can we can think we
can turn this into essentially exactly
what we were already doing because you
can see that we have our this is this is
our V term right this is the V output
and this is the you output that we were
trying to get so this term is constant u
XV y uy v x that's a constant we can
just compute that ahead of time and and
know and and be done right similarly
this at the top is just a dot product
right it's just a dot product with the
vector negative view y+ VX and this
one's the dot product with v y- VX right
of the incoming x and y so if we just do
the exact same math we're already doing
but just prep our vectors slightly
differently uh we can actually just I
think we can just keep the code
identical right because the n x axis is
is just needs to be prepped in this way
right so first let's compute that
determinant right and that's going to be
our are you a car x axis X right so I'm
just reading off this bottom term here
our x axis x times our y-axis y minus r
x axis y times our y axis X right that's
that determinant value that's under
there and now when we produce these
matrices we want to be very specific
with these we don't want to do that
anymore we want to do ours
cific equation and our equation is for
the for the x axis it's going to be v y
and minus VX both of them over the
determinate right and if this
determinant happens to be 0 right if the
determinant equals zero then that means
that we've got a very degenerate like
we've sort of collapsed our things into
into the same place so I feel like if
the determinant gets too low obviously
we also probably we don't want to divide
by zero so we could just stuff an
arbitrary value in there in that case
but we could also think about what that
actually means a little bit later like
to do Casey just don't draw if the debt
is zero it's close to zero because it
means it would be such a thin thing that
you wouldn't be able to see it anyway
probably but anyway that getting a
little head of ourselves all right so
that NX access again like I said it's v
y so that's the y axis Y component and
it's a you know over the determinant
obviously and the other one is the is
the V axis X component sorry the y axis
X opponent over the determinate and yeah
and these by the way or not need any
more and then similarly down here we
would have a wait a second we missed
something here vxvy
let me read that again DX minus B Y so d
is V and B is you or is also v never
mind this is a and C so that should have
been you and you so these should have
both been you right right I'm not
hallucinating there am I I don't think I
am yeah
yeah alright so back to our back to our
original story so that's going to be
negative x axis x over the terminate and
x axis y the determinant ok so now
borrowing lots of stupid errors that i
may have just made that is what we
actually want to do and then we are
still computing the dot products here
are just we're now just computing them
with different things right we've just
scaled and multiplied them differently
but we're still computing the exact same
equations there's really nothing else to
it so let's just see our first
depressing result because it'll probably
not be right at all and you can see that
it's not so we've got some work to do
obviously there but you know like I said
it you know nobody ever said it was
going to be easy all right so we've got
a couple things to check the first thing
that I have to do is I have to make sure
that I think through whether or not we
need a squared scale in there right like
before I was a little bit nervous about
that because I was thinking about
whether it should be squared not I think
this should take care of it though
because the determinant itself is
effectively going to be doing basically
a squaring kind of an operation there so
dividing by this that seems like it
should do it so I'm not 100% sure that
we would need anything else for week you
know computing those UV coordinates in
theory it should do the reverse mapping
so that it's in the 0 to 1 space janae
um I believe right i believe uh and so
yeah these guys I think are what I would
have expected us to dot with now let me
make sure that I'm not doing anything
weird down here I want to make sure that
I'm computing the right thing so we
musta get are you we mo PS with the N
axis and the py n
what is that p y NX so we do a mall and
then we do them all so that's uh that's
all good i think this why
that looks that looks right that looks
all good to me all right and again sorry
if I'm not talking as much as I should
be we're missing a minus this is
supposed to be minus I copied it down
wrong there we go I copied it from my my
blackboard run alright so debugging this
is going to be quite the pain you know
the fact that we don't see anything yet
suggests to me that we've got like a bad
scalar sewing because we should at least
see stuff that's kind of messed up right
and so you know it feels like we're
super far off or maybe misunderst these
guys got used but i'm pretty sure that
that we're okay there now let me just
make sure they're also not used in any
other place but i'm pretty sure they're
not yes so these are only used for that
process right so that's all good and
we're already subbed out the origin so
we're literally just taking these dot
products here and that's that's
literally it so before what we were
doing is we were taking you know the x
axis and we were normalizing it by
dividing it by its length squared and
that's not that different from what we
were doing here to be honest right
because if you take a look at what that
would have been right previously
effectively what we were doing is we
were saying well okay previously we're
going to take x axis x squared plus X X
Y squared right and dividing you know
each one by its respective one of those
right that's what we were sort of saying
we were going to do and so I don't
really know why we wouldn't get anything
there and I think I may want to go I
guess I can't could step through this
I'm just trying to think if the easier
way to debug this will be for me to go
back up into to go back to the slow code
and draw it there that makes sense just
to see well i'm going to try stepping
through it like this so I'm just going
to I'm going to turn off optimizations
for the moment I'm going to go into this
code or try to anyway here it is I'm
going to step into here now hopefully
we'll get somebody with just a normal x
and y axis one that's very simple and
we'll see right so there's the x axis
there's the y axis and hey they're
perfectly they're going in exactly the
same direction so that's nice and yet
and so hopefully that should that should
give us something reasonable to work
with let's see what the determinant was
there's the determinant
alright and let's take a look at what
hour n x axis is alright so we're
getting much too we're getting much too
tiny it's what i would say at least it
looks much too tiny although it's hard
to say i mean i guess with a thousand ya
know it looks like it's maybe 10 x off
there it's hard to say but yeah so
thinking it through like it would be
nice if we just had a slightly easier
one that was a little bit more
normalized i suppose but you know even
as it goes if we take a look at what the
x axis values are when we dot product
with this it's going to be moving
basically that slowly right so it's
going to be a you know if that was a
hundred pixels let's say to go the whole
length it's actually a little more than
that so if you look at what that's doing
that's pretty close to what I would have
expected actually because if i dot
product with this you know I'm going to
get roughly what I would have expected
and then if i if i look at my n y axis
here
well okay so that's that's kind of
obviously incorrect there because this
means that neither of my axes have any Y
component to them which doesn't really
make any sense to me why did that happen
what's going on there right if you look
at what happens here both of them have
an X and no y component right but my x
and y axes were in different places you
would think at least I would think that
would give me a reasonable result there
so i have y axis y at y axis x x axis x
x axis y you know what I bet I I bet I i
bet i just can't copy y X Y X God you
know usually it's the math that's wrong
but here it's today it's just copying
the math into the code that's wrong
apparently
let's try that again folks okay so now
what are we looking at Hey look so
surprised surprised we did all the math
right apparently but we just typed it in
wrong okay and so hopefully now you can
see and let me go ahead and build in
release mode but I wish I just copied
the math right that would have worked
the first time it would have been great
but of course that I have stared for a
while so now you can see that our
software renderer looks a lot closer to
our regular render in fact it may look
exactly like our actual renderer now
let's go ahead and see if that's true
right I'm going to go ahead and walk
left wise across the screen so there we
are perfect alright so that is that uh
you know hopefully that hopefully if you
take these three days together the day
where we notice the bug they were I
wrote out all the matrix equations and
showed why the bug was happening and
then today where we solve the equation
and fix the bug you know I hope that
kind of gives you a good idea where when
people ask you know if your game
programmer or whatever you need to know
math or what should I do about learning
math um I hope that kind of shows just
how important math kind of is like
trying to hack that to fix that bug
you'd never know you would have no idea
what was wrong right I mean we wouldn't
it would just be wrong you'd be like I
don't even know you know I have noise
but right but when you can go back to
the original Matthew like I've got this
transform I'm trying to reverse it I
know that you know if I want to reverse
the transfer might just solve the
equation for the other term and then you
look at what actually happens to the
math even from first principles you need
to know any tricks right I just solve
those equations you didn't even need to
know what to determine it was right you
just needed to know basic matrix
multiplication and everything else was
solved with with grade school algebra
and boom you type in those two lines of
code and everything's fixed of course
you have type them in right which I
didn't do but if you could sue me you
can copy from your own math notebook
into the code it's perfect right and so
that's just a really cool aspect of
enter and I think a good demonstration
of why understanding math had a pretty
fundamental level at least the parts
that we care about in in game
programming is really pretty important
because you know you can fix bugs really
easily and you know I didn't have to
remember all I did was just invert that
one matrix I could have typed it into
mathematica you know because I knew
that's what I need to do and got the
answer instantly way back my first saw
the bug could just done that looked at
it and type those lines it right so all
the stuff we did it wasn't like this
huge big ordeal all that stuff I did was
just me showing you so you would
understand how it all worked but the
actual process is trivial you just
invert a two by two matrix you could
have mathematically that for you or you
can remember the determinant trick it's
right so this would have been a five
minute fix if I hadn't gone through and
explained the entire thing from start to
finish right so knowing that math and
understanding all of that just allows
you to immediately go oh right okay and
the bug is fixed right whereas if you
didn't know what you'd just be forget it
I mean you'd never fix it right you'd
have to hack something in and hope you
could maybe you know monkey around with
it or whatever um so I guess that's
basically it I'm going to go ahead and
go to the QA because I don't know if
people have matrix Q&amp;A questions here
but like I guess I just say I don't want
to get started on something in the last
five minutes so you know if we don't
have any more cues and we won't but
anyway
me below says selling off topic but any
chance you could describe a little more
what you'd want of an algebraic
blackboard program uh yeah certainly I
could say pretty easily what I would
want so here's the problem i just
described the problem and this is like
why you know why I don't like
Mathematica um so here's what happens to
me when i'm doing math right is i'm
actually not that bad at symbolic math
I'm not good I've seen people who are
good and they're really good I'm not
good but I'm not that bad at that I'm
just bad at me I make mistakes when I'm
you know simple mistakes I don't not
know the right thing to do I just make
some mistakes but I I know a bunch of
stuff i can do to like massage things
into the right forms that i want and all
the sort stuff so I kind of know what
I'm trying to do a lot of the times but
I have two choices right one choice is i
can plug things into mathematica right
and what does that look like well if I
want to plug things into mathematica I
gotta type some stuff and I don't
remember the exact sense been a long
time so use it but you know I'm like oh
ok well here's my matrix you know mr.
Mathematica right and you know then I
say like I've got my P which is you know
X Y or something like that and then I
type you know solve and I don't remember
their syntax for solve but you know
solve a p equals P prime or something
and I i guess i have to put both of
these in here
ap equals P prime you know for 4p right
okay so if I have a problem that's
exactly like this kind that we just used
I think Mathematica is fine right you
can put this in here and what it will
spit out to you is the scalar equation
that solve this so it will output
something that's like a bunch of scalars
here like to you know the scalar
equations for the two things so it'll be
like oh yeah you know u equals blah and
V equals blah which is the exact this
stuff that we just wrote on the
blackboard myself right it'll it'll
output this and that okay and that's
where like most computer algebra stuff
like not just math I'm not picking on
mathematics specifically but good jobs
of general that's where it works okay if
that's what I want but here's the
problem if I don't want it to drop down
to scalar all bets are off so let's say
that I was trying to work out some
really big matrix equation right and
there's you know there's lots of stuff
happening so it's like oh yeah you know
this was you know a pry you know ap
cross a you know some other vector ap
cross B times you know some other matrix
here inverted and that was you know
added to some other thing and blah blah
blah right when I'm going to program
this stuff i don't i'm not going to do
some giant matrix equation in scalar
right and furthermore i may not be
looking for the solutions to these
things i may be looking for insights
into how the problem works so what I
want to do is I want to actually move
these terms around myself without ever
dropping down to scalar using rules that
I know are okay so I want to be able to
say stuff like oh okay you know trust me
on this one PX cross B is equal to zero
or something like this right the zero
vector or something right I don't know
I'm just making stuff up like this
and other things like oh you know like a
transpose B equals B transpose a right
so I just tell it the things that i want
to be true right and then I'm going to
tell you what to do so i'll say stuff
like oh can you reduce this term in
vector notation at all using the rules
can you like reduce it and maybe it
comes out of something or I'm going to
say hey I want to multiply both sides by
B right and so it'll do it and get rid
of that term and put it here right and
so that way I could just I could work
out the equations like I normally do on
a piece of paper but without ever
worrying about making a mistake right so
the computers and let me make a mistake
but i never have to drop down into these
crazy huge scalar equations where I
can't see the structure anymore and and
then our kind of useless to me at some
level right so the more complicated
matrix vector geometric algebra whatever
else stuff you do the more useless
Mathematica typically becomes because it
just generates these huge two other
equations that don't tell you anything
right you're like well that's okay if I
just wanted to solve this one thing in
scalar and type it in for an hour right
but I don't want that i want something
that I can code using my own vector
library using the vector ops like I want
to code this as a cross product I don't
want to have to look at Mathematica as
crazy set of scalars and start trying to
pull out where the cross products are
right so yeah so just an Augmented like
notebook thing where it doesn't have to
be like handwriting I am happy to type
in the equations right I just then want
to be able to manipulate them knowing i
never made a mistake by the rules that i
input
thus Isaac just says q colon whoa that
is not a question and I can't answer it
error if a senior Tory will there be
more things like this that require math
in further parts of the game although it
was pretty basic my math is a bit rusty
um well you know I don't know uh in in
2d games you get a little bit of a buy
on on the math there's oftentimes less
demand for the math the harder core math
in 2d and that's not an accident there's
a lot of reasons for that oh one of them
is that typically when you jump to 3d
now you're doing a lot more real
simulation because since you have full
3d surfaces you can do like things that
more closely approximate what happens in
the real world so you you know more math
comes in there because it's more physics
basically but the other reason is that
three dimensions is more than one
dimension harder than two dimensions I
know that's a very strange thing to say
but for example a lot of things that are
true in two dimensions aren't true in
three dimensions and it has nothing to
do with the fact that you added one
extra dimension right because going from
one dimension to two dimensions did not
change this thing but from true
dimensions to three dimensions did right
and for example rotations don't commute
anymore in three dimensions right in one
dimension a rotation followed by another
rotation rotation A Fella by rotation be
produces a rotation see regardless of
the order so rotation be followed by a
also is see doesn't matter what order I
do the rotations right if I rotate this
far that way and then I rotate this far
that way I get the exact same thing
whether i did this first or this first
right because it's all just a single
scalar it's just it's just the theta of
rotation and no matter what i do i
always get the same no matter what order
i do the terms at 3d not true 3d has
winding and so what ends up happening is
you know if you rotate one
and then rotate another way you'll be in
a different position than if you did
those two same exact rotations in the
opposite order right tons of stuff like
that is true in 3d a bunch of things
that like to apolog-- things break in 3d
things about fundamental geometry things
just become not true in 3d anymore that
were true in 2d there's a bunch of stuff
like computational geometry theorems
that are just like this is you know in
2d we know how to do it we know how to
do it linear time blah blah blah and
they're like in 3d it's unsolvable we've
proved it's unsolvable or stuff like
that right and so there's just these
really bad things that happen when you
come 3d so when you stick in 2d and
that's why what people often ask me I
don't do 3d I am a hero there's so much
more stuff that comes in in 3d I don't
think anyone should ever write their
first game in 3d I this is an awful idea
you should always have to defer stet a
bit of a body on the math a huge huge
simplification on the asset pipeline
blah blah blah blah it's important to
like get your fundamental solid first
and then then go do it the 3d game after
when you can just focus on the new stuff
you need for 3d without worrying about
all the other stuff like how to make an
enemy system and how to do memory
management now too if you're trying to
learn to be an engine programmer don't
try to learn it all at once you'll just
get discouraged right and so what I
would say is to answer your question
about how much more map they'll be
they'll probably be other stuff like
this certainly it's not the only time
that we do stuff like this we've already
done some stuff like this and we'll
probably do some more but it is a lot
lighter in a 2-d game right it's not
quite so much it's not all the time a 3d
game you're doing this stuff kind of all
the time a 2-d game it's less it's less
so
Brian wag do you consider math to be
more of a tool to solve problems or more
of a learning art to be mastered I don't
really know I guess I don't really think
about it in any particular way like I
usually just think of math as a really
good repository of very smart people who
have tried to solve problems before and
this is what they discovered you know so
I guess I think of it kind of like the
tool to solve problems that you
suggested but a little bit more than
just a tool right it's more like a way
of looking at things and a way of
leveraging the knowledge of people who
came before you and what they were able
to figure out which is not really the
same as just a tool right because the
tool to solve problems part obscures the
fact that it's also the thing that helps
you figure out what the problems even
were to begin with like you know I don't
even I wouldn't even know that something
was a transformer that it could be
inverted as a way of thinking about
texture mapping if I'd never had that
basis right so I feel like I feel like
it's like I wouldn't just I while I
wouldn't as I say I'll learn in art to
be mastered because that doesn't really
mean much to me I also wouldn't say that
tool to solve problems covers it perhaps
as adequately or as completely as as how
I actually view it building what I
believe you want to turned up reduce
algebra calm automatic and user
controlled suffocation expressing the
calculus was like wow so someone maybe
has has written it now
possibly I don't know can't quite tell
yeah possibly it's hard to tell from
just looking at this but that might be
not to look at that sim block but I just
wanted to note how your intuition of the
transform seemed really important at
finding the bug way more important than
typing the correct formula no wait I I'm
not sure exactly what that means but I
guess what I would say is I I will state
the thing that I think that is closest
to that which I definitely agree with
and often try to point out especially to
people learning math which is the
important part of math is learning what
all the math does and how right and the
reason for that is because like I said
you know you all the all the actual
solving we could have actually just had
Mathematica do that right you got to
learn the finicky syntax in that but it
could have just produced the right
answer for us right we just put in that
thing right but knowing and this is why
I say hopefully this is kind of like
what you were saying because I feel this
way to knowing what a transform was that
we were doing one that inverting a
transform involves more than just
transposing the terms blah blah blah all
of that is systemic mathematical
knowledge that I know because I've
studied the math right and there's
really no substitute for that you can't
at the moment we don't have like
artificial intelligence of this quality
or anything right you can't at the
moment type into mathematica please tell
me why I'm getting this bug right and so
that's why I think it's so important to
know a lot of that math and I have a
broad math knowledge is because a lot of
times you know if you don't understand
all of these things and you don't have a
way of slotting the problems you see
into a mathematical framework then it
doesn't matter you can't use
math to help you if you don't know which
math is involved right and so that to me
is really the heart of the important
part of a math education is the broad
understanding of all the different parts
and how they work and if you can't
remember how to do them that's okay just
look it up at the time right but you
need to remember that it did this thing
or how this thing does this you know
what it does because otherwise you can't
ever apply it and I actually see this
fairly frequently in programmers
actually and it's a problem there are
people who have a much stronger math
background potentially than I do and and
I'll see them not know how to solve
something that they totally should know
how to solve and the reason is because
they their math knowledge is too focused
on how to actually work out the
equations or something but they never
were able to actually build a big
picture that allows them to do that
slotting that's like oh I I've worked
with this math enough to use your phrase
intuition to have an intuition for it I
know this is a transform I know things I
can do with the transfer my know things
I can do with the dot product I
understand how they work and maybe I
forget I do the math at the low level or
something but I can always look that up
but what I need to have quick access to
and to have instant ability to read is
that am I think am i working with one of
these things is this important here
could I solve this problem used up by
applying this other thing might might I
you know should I potentially try and
all of those things are really really
important so I don't know if that's in
the same spirit of what you were trying
to say but that is true and and that is
really especially when I look at how
math is taught a pre-college at least
and sometimes unfortunately in college
as well but pre-college anyway the
problem is the amount of math that like
we learn in America for example up
through high school at least in my I had
a went to a decent high school I mean so
some people don't but I mean assuming
you went to deuce in high school
the amount of math that I learned was
actually pretty vast but I couldn't do
anything with it right and it wasn't
till after I get out and was working on
programming and it was actually Chris
hecker who i saw doing a lot of math to
solve problems in programming that i
realized that like oh if i just go back
and look at stuff i even already know
there's so much I can do with it but
they never taught me how to look at
problems and figure out what math
applied to those problems right and so
gaining that framework in your brain of
like looking at problems through the
lens of what math is important here is
the very most important part of a math
education no question and the actual
doing of the solving is secondary right
because you'll never get a chance to
solve a math problem by hand even if you
are gues all by hand if you didn't know
that was the problem you had right so
that's totally true and I think that's
very important thing to to remember the
risk oh I actually just learned about
determinants in linear algebra do you
think we will see them later on our
determinants used often i would i would
probably echo the same thing i said
before determines are used pretty often
and they're used pretty often
specifically because they have kind of a
deep relationship to systems of vectors
that you care about and want to do
things with such as invert and other
things like that however we have limited
need for those in 2d so we probably
won't be seeing them pop up like that
frequently but but yes they they are
they're a very common thing that gets
used in linear algebra and and its
applications to 3d graphics certainly
casta 5 do you get annoyed by some
symbols meaning things and different
things in different subcarriers a math
um no I don't really get annoyed by that
because like I said I'm not like a super
strong symbolic math guy and you can see
that just when you watch me do equations
on the blackboard I'm constantly naming
things the same thing you know like I'll
be like oh ok this is you and this other
thing over here is also you and whatever
so it's like I just am NOT rigorous
enough at those sorts of things to get
annoyed at other people not being
rigorous enough of those things so hey
yeah these two branch of mathematics
both use the same symbols and it's kind
of confusing ok I make that same sick
all the time certainly not get get
annoyed might it be nice if it had been
completely regularize the whole way sure
but you know
let me just double check to see if there
are any more q Collins cubic have said
what about 3d with an isometric view the
particular projection that you use for
3d I'm assuming you're relating this
back to the question of whether you know
to 3d is harder than 2d once you're in
3d all of those things are true
regardless of what the projection is
used for your camera the camera
production has nothing to do with it
right it's just whether you decided to
start trying to do full 3d things with
full 3d surfaces in full 3d lighting in
full 3d physics right so you can always
cheese out on any of those that you want
to and still maintain some level of
pseudo 3d ness in various ways and make
things easier on yourself right but in
general you you definitely have the case
where the more actual 3d you want to be
the more strenuous the math will become
and that that's just because 3d is
definitely more than one dimension
harder than 2d as I often say what do
you think of Khan Academy as a math
learning resource um you know I I
haven't used it myself like I've never
gone and said I want to learn you know
differ more differential equations let
me go check Khan Academy what I would
say is I suspect that it probably
wouldn't like it very much and the
reason for that is because I want to
come at math from a programmers
perspective and I don't think they
generally do which is not a knock on
them as a general math resource but it
is a bit of a knock on them for as a
programming resource right and so my
preference would mostly be you know a
programmer centric math learning
resource would be what I would most want
because a lot of times you know even
though obviously math is math
what you emphasize and how you go about
practicing and learning various aspects
of it is definitely different depending
on if you're someone who's you know
trying to learn to solve proofs for you
know the end goal vs someone who's
trying to compute things as the end goal
vs somebody who's trying to pass their
college courses the end goal or whatever
right so thank you / Caleb yeah a 2-d
game that's drawn in 3d is still a a 2-d
game for the most part right but you
still as soon as you even just do
drawing in 3d assuming that you're
actually talking about drawing look
meshes and stuff you know you've got to
start dealing with all of that
additional math now if you're talking
about a 2-d game that's drawn in 3d but
the 2d everything still sprites you
obviously get some by there as well and
every everything you can collapse down
from 3d to 2d saves you some math right
and as we saw on handmade hero you still
have difficulties but they tend to be of
a different kind like our sorting thing
for example is more hacky likes like
programmer e stuff and less rigorous
math whereas the way we might handle
depth stuff in 3d might have a lot more
to do with math right
lq 144 recognizing the kinds of things
you're working with and the kind of
problem you are working on is a
fundamental skill I'm not all that sure
how to teach that directly though beyond
doing something like what you are doing
here and or repeated experience with
solving problems I well yeah I mean my
my feeling on that is just that it's
pretty obvious to me how you would teach
math in in schools if you cared about
the actual useful part of math right and
the way that would work is you would
learn to do any particular thing in math
once by hand and you'd never really even
probably be tested on it you would just
be able to use a computer algebra system
or something to do that work for you as
soon as you knew how to do it right and
then all of your testing would always be
on here is a problem and you need to
figure out what math you're supposed to
use to solve the problem right and then
you can use the computer system to solve
it for you and this is very very
different than the way these kinds of
problems are given to you in school
normally like in when I went to school
the problems were always grouped into
like the kind of problem they were so
it's like we're going to have a test on
UD u substitution so you just know that
every problem that you got is a problem
on you know integration and it's an
integration problem that's going to
involve au substitution so it robs you
of your fundamental practice of
identifying that this is what's supposed
to happen there because all you're ever
practicing is just the mechanical act of
applying UD u substitution which is
something a computer can pretty much do
flawlessly all the time like it's really
not the case that a human is necessary
to do you do substitution like
Mathematica can do that just fine right
well my math mathematic can't do is tell
that what you were trying to do in this
case he
is it integration in the first place and
that you do substitution might be the
way to go I mean mad I can't sort of do
that second part a little bit right so I
really feel like you know the way that
that sort of math should be taught is
the students should never know what they
are being tested on that's like crucial
and then nobody should care whether they
can actually do it by hand or not
because no one ever needs to do math by
hand anymore that's just not a thing
what we would care about is that they
would know how to do it or where to look
it up how to do it that they could get a
computer to do it or write the computer
program that does it right and save that
for themselves right all of those things
great skills being able to like actually
do the equation by hand is like
completely irrelevant like I literally
have no idea why you would ever need to
know it so it's exactly backwards like I
think we have it completely backwards
the way we're teaching it right now
we're teaching it as if we're trying to
produce people from back in the day when
they used to have rooms full of people
like solving equations because they
didn't have computers to do it right and
that's who were like making and we don't
need that person right that that is just
not a skill that we fundamentally need
but what we absolutely do need is people
who look at problems and go oh I know
what math could be applied here I don't
quite remember how to do it but let me
go look it up right and that's a great
skill because you can always go look up
how to do the math if you know what the
math is but if you don't know you'll
never even know that you should be
looking something up right you'll you'll
never even you'll never cross your mind
to go look up how to do interval
arithmetic if you have no idea what
interval arithmetic is and you don't
know that the problem that you're faced
with can be solved by interval
arithmetic right so
so yeah anyway uh but yeah and as an
aside there is handmade hero actually i
think is a good math learning resource
in a limited sense in that way that we
are showing how to apply math to solve
problems but you know most of em here is
programming so it's not that good of a
math learners because most of your time
is not spent doing that you could
imagine a series that was done that was
much more about let's not do a lot of
programming let's do a lot of problem
solving with very simple programming to
actually like implement just the minimum
thing we need to like prove we solve the
problem or whatever that would be kind
of a cool serious like math learning
serious that would be all about like
finding places where the math is and you
know like I said we do do that in Hamid
here I think that's great and I hope
that exposes people to this kind of a
thing but you know if you wanted to
learn math real well you would want a
series that was just like all about that
and all about the math whereas hey
mahira is much more about the
programming than the math and we do the
math when we need it but we're not
looking for excuses to do math every day
which is what you'd want kind of that
you know companion Sirius handmade math
or something right so all right I'm
gonna close Anna closed down closing on
down close it on down here thank you
everyone for joining me for life sort of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along the series at home
you can always p order the game on
handmade here or it comes to the source
code so you could file a long experiment
for yourself we also have a forum site
you can go to if you want to ask
questions a patreon page if you want to
support the video series we have a
schedule bot that tweets the schedule if
you want to catch us live for the q and
A's and just if you just want hang out
the chat and we also have a past
episodes guide you can go to if you want
to catch up on things we did before
that's about it for today I will be back
here tomorrow I do not remember what
time I'll be honest with you I think
it's five
let's find out check that schedule bot
yeah it's 5pm for those two weeks 0 5
p.m. pacific daylight time hope to see
you here for that until then have fun
programming and I'll see you guys on the
internet take it easy everyone