hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete game live on
stream we are I think at the point where
we're gonna try and you know crank
turned the crank on the lighting we've
gotten to the point where it's the
octahedral light maps are actually
working quite nicely there's one thing
in there that looks a little suspicious
to me just in terms the results that I'm
not sure I mean I I don't actually know
whether it's a problem or not and more
specifically I don't actually know
whether it's a problem with the
octahedral lighting or just something
like a problem with our light
calculation in general but there is a
certain quality to the light map result
that looks a bit cube-like and I think
that probably weren't some further study
but other than that I feel like the
octahedral lighting is actually working
quite nicely it was surprisingly good
once we remembered to actually turn on
trilinear filtering
I'm sorry bilinear filtering for the
samples somehow I just when we were
looking at it forgot to turn that back
on once we got everything working and
once we turn that on it was like oh wow
this looks actually really good so I
think what that means at least for today
I think what I'd like to do is start to
tighten up the actual sort of data flow
pattern that we've got in there right
now
and I have a pretty good idea of how I
think I want to do that and I'll kind of
walk through that first but basically
what I want to do is we you know I've
done tons of experimentation with the
lighting system so it's kind of just a
mess at this point and now that I'm
seeing the octahedral of Maps I'm fairly
high confidence that that's what I want
I like the way it's looking what I want
to do now is just kind of take a you
know a comb and sort of smooth out the
lighting system so that it's you know
fairly min
and just doing things the way it will do
them for the octahedral Maps and so the
very first thing I want to do there is
just make sure that I'm writing directly
into the octahedral map at all times so
right now what we're doing is we're
doing a process where we actually create
like a secondary buffer right and then
we put it into the octahedral map I
think we probably want to do something
where we're operating directly in the
octahedral map as much as possible and
you know that's actually a fairly tricky
thing to get right we're gonna have to
spend some time getting that right and
the reason for that is while it will be
fairly straightforward I think to get
our system updating the octahedral map
directly for the actual lighting
computation because it's very simple we
just say look here's where you're
looking in the octahedral map to write
this thing or whatever we do have to fix
the code that does the in-place block
copies so if you remember when you move
around the world we need to preserve the
light Maps so when the center of the
lighting system
you know moves around we need to move
the octahedral map so that it aligns
with the move in the world because we
have effectively infinite sized worlds
for all intents and purposes so we're
never we're only we can only store the
light map information just around where
the character is we can't afford to
store the light maps for the whole world
and I mean even and I mean I guess even
if we did want to store them we would
still need to do something like this in
order to keep track of where each piece
was going to be so we want to do is make
it so that we just update that map the
light map in place right and we've
already got codes that's doing that for
the voxel version of this but what we
want to start doing is just getting rid
of that voxel right because the voxel is
now unnecessary we've got a flattened
Atlas version of this thing that's what
we're using for sampling and since we're
using that for sampling that effectively
means that we don't want to store this
other representation that just costs us
a big copy all the time for no reason we
rather just keep the thing that we
actually care about and make that be how
we get our data right and how we keep
our data preserved so I want to try and
move to that and I want to do that in a
couple steps and then the other thing
that I want to do is I want to start
putting in the actual like light
convection so the actual thing that
actually does the lighting which we have
in there but we haven't actually sort of
hooked up yet and so we kind of have a
bunch of things to do there and I think
what I'm gonna do is since the lighting
looks reasonable at the moment I think
maybe what I'll do is I'll push on the
second one of those first so let me try
to wire up the actual bounce based
lighting see if we can get that looking
reasonable and then after that's done
we'll try to move from that system which
is working directly on the voxel
representation to one that's working on
the flattened representation and that I
think will then conclude everything we
need to do with lighting you know maybe
there's an optimization pass that has to
happen there but pretty much that would
be it so I think we're getting close and
you know that's that's good news because
lighting is extremely hard and takes a
long time so you know it's pretty
encouraging to think that we might be
getting somewhere on it something that's
actually you know reasonably good
looking
let me first open up the game here and
just do a quick run so we can see what
I'm talking about so here you can see
the lighting with the actual diffuse
colors turned off so we're just we're
looking at just the white solution here
and of course our lights currently we
have only turned on one light that we're
looking at as a test it's not doing an
actual lighting computation we're just
testing the voxel the we're testing the
octahedral light maps to see what they
look like and you can see I'm drawing
the octahedral light maps down in the
corner here you can see that they've got
interpolation turned on that's why there
they kind of look you know that kind of
blurry look right we're zoomed in on
just one section of them over in the
corner and so this is just a test of
just a basic light source right and the
light source is like hovering right
about here in fact I think is that it
yeah it's this one right here right and
so you know if we kind of look up here
the bounce that we're getting it goes
like you know it hits here and comes up
towards us so we should always kind of
see it like in in this areas where we
should be seeing the light and that is
where we're seeing it we shouldn't be
able to see it out here because when we
hit one of these light probes you know
the bounce that we're seeing is gonna go
off to somewhere where there's no light
right so it looks relatively correct
there was and the reason I was saying
there was some weirdness here is there's
a couple of things that we're gonna have
to be aware of so one is there's a
definite like squareness to the light
you can see there's like a shadow that
looks like that like a cube shape to the
lighting and I don't know exactly where
this is coming from so that's a little
concerning to me and the reason it's
concerning is not because I'm sure it's
wrong but because I'm not sure it's
right i I really can't emphasize enough
how important it is to you know when
you're looking at stuff like this or
really anything right when you're
programming you always want to assume
that you have a bug and one of the
number one ways you can spot people who
don't really know how to program is that
they try to come up with explanations
for why something is correct rather than
assuming that there's a bug in something
because if you try to come up with
explanations for why it's correct you'll
usually find one right because computers
are very complicated unless there's just
an obvious like the game crashes or
something right
you can usually come up with some
ridiculous explanation as to why this is
okay so you know looking at this thing
I'll be like well you know well it's
because you know it's on a
axl so obviously they'll they'll be some
square artifacts as the thing the lines
with the lock right like I can always
come up with an explanation of why
there's not a bug in the code but I have
no way of knowing if that explanation is
actually true I'm not proving that
there's not a bug in the code I'm just
coming up with an explanation that
allows me to not have to go look for the
bug right and so what I find really
differentiates good programmers from bad
programmers is you may be a good
programmer assumes when they see
something that is just a little bit
suspicious right if there's any
suspicion at all assume it's a bug
and you have decisions here I don't have
to go solve this bug right now I can
still move on and do something else
I can even ship this with that in it if
I want to but know that it is a bug
don't say that the code is correct when
it's not when you know that you have
evidence that's probably not know that
it there is a bug there because there
may be an important quality improvement
that you can make and when you are
making decisions throughout your project
you want to make those decisions
knowing that there might be a bug there
that you can improve right you can
improve the quality of the software
there deciding not to fix something
because it'll be too time-consuming or
whatever else is materially different
than convincing yourself that there
wasn't something to fix right because it
affects the decision making that you're
going to make throughout the project so
I'm not even saying that you have to fix
all your bugs because that may just not
be practical for the size of the project
or the amount of programming power that
you have you know how many man-hours you
have to spend on it or however you want
to measure your project size or those
sorts of things it's entirely possible
that this may be a bug that we just
can't ever fix because we don't have
time or any of those sorts of things
right that's fine but don't convince
yourself that something is working
properly because convincing yourself
that something is proper when you
have some evidence it's not is never
productive right that's just masking a
potential problem that should be weighed
against other things in terms of when
you're allocating your programmer time
hmm
so I'm sorry for that big long
digression but after having talked with
stripe this week and having experienced
what it's like to try and talk to people
who don't understand when they obviously
have bugs in their software and what
they'd rather do is try to convince
themselves that their software isn't a
buggy mess it's annoying
right it's it's really annoying to talk
to programmers who don't obviously
understand that they have lots of bugs
and there's tons of evidence of it
because if they just want to say we
don't care and we don't fix that because
we're an Internet company so we don't
fix bugs okay
like I get it you're trying to make
money not make good software but think
trying to rationalize away obvious
mistakes that are clearly there or that
at the very least you don't understand
yet so you can't say that they're
correct or incorrect regardless it's
just really frustrating and it makes it
very hard to have a discussion with you
right you can't actually get to the
bottom of a technical issue with someone
whose primary goal is to rationalize
away that there might be a bug in there
right so I would really encourage you to
not do that and I would always encourage
you to assume that you have a bug
anytime there's anything suspicious
until you have a complete pathology that
you can 100% point to and say look I did
as much due diligence as I possibly
could here and if there was a bug I
missed it but I didn't ever rationalize
it away I tried as hard as I could to
actually trace through this thing and
find it out and so short story long when
I look at this I know we have not done
enough work to say that that is an
artifact of the algorithm we just
haven't it's very likely that it's a bug
or if it's not a bug it's definitely
true that I don't and you probably don't
either because you've only been able to
see what I've done so far we don't know
what's causing it and if we don't know
we don't know it's a bug it's that
simple so let's go ahead and take a
a look at what we're doing here and I
don't know if we want to take a look at
this bug now but we want to keep this
test case in place because it's a really
easy way to look at the bug right it's a
very simple way for us to immediately
events this bug and so we don't have to
really you know think too hard about how
to reproduce it because we've got one in
here now so what I might do just because
I'm curious and I'd like to know if
there's an easy way to sort of reveal
what might be going on here what I would
like to do is maybe what we could put in
here is some hotkeys for looking at some
of the actual quantities in here like
maybe there's some ways we can make it
really fast to switch between a few
different things in the lighting because
if I could see some of this stuff like
if I could actually flip between you
know show me the normals show me the
voxels and so on I might be able to
pinpoint like where this stuff is
actually changing right so that's one
thing I could do is add some more debug
view to it the other thing that I'm
thinking is as I look at what's going on
here the biggest thing that strikes me
about it right like the thing that is
the most intriguing is that I notice it
moves with the specular highlight right
so this line this fall-off line that I'm
getting here and you know you can kind
of see like as I move around that line
moves like very smoothly right so
remember we're sampling this on a voxel
and if there was some kind of weird
interpolation error between voxels you
know I wouldn't be able to place that
line any anywhere I wanted right so I'm
pretty certain that we don't have an
obvious like discontinuity bug there
because it's actually happening anywhere
you want so it's a it's an artifact of
what happens during the interpolation of
two lightmaps samples let's say that
actually can place this anywhere you
want right it's where the fall-off
actually
ones there and so I'm more looking at
something that's about why isn't there a
like piece of lighting information
happening here you know what is actually
causing that sort of gap in the system
if you will and one thing I might be
able to do to make this a little bit
clearer to me is what if I took out the
height difference because I'm getting
like those periodic breaks because I the
floor is intentionally sort of jittered
around as an artistic thing that I
wanted to do if I went into the room
generator and oops that's no good
how do I I need to unify my key bindings
it's hard for me to do handmade here
every week because it's totally not even
remotely the same key bindings is my
actual editor work so it's like pretty
tough my brain always has to switch so
if I go into the room generator here and
we just want to take out some of that
jitter so I think the peasy offset here
that we've got I think that's the only
thing that's really you know changing
stuff if we take that peasy jitter out
of here I think that would stop our
floors from having any you know
difference and with the floors not
having any difference it should be much
easier for me to see you know the
lighting and the artifacts and the
lighting now of course there's lots of
grass there so actually let me let me
not go there because that induces a
pattern because there's a lot bunch of
sprites laid on top of each other so
what I'd rather do here is just kind of
get out to a flat room so here you can
see what's going on with the lighting a
little more cleanly there right and you
can sort of see right you can you can
see more how what kind of artifacts
we're gonna have and you can actually
see so there's some of the things that
are interesting about it right is you
can see on the edges how we get those
dropouts for like the
where the zeros are for the lighting
there you can see how we get that um you
know you get that stair-stepping pattern
the stair-stepping pattern sort of
appears I guess I kind of want to say it
appears generally to be probably you
know roughly along the voxel everywhere
right so I I see some artifacts of the
stair-stepping I don't know that
stair-stepping of the the voxel based
sampling pretty much everywhere so
that's not really surprising right you
know that's what I would expect I don't
really see I guess I guess I'd to be
honest I guess I don't really see a lot
of evidence that it's obviously wrong
it's kind of hard to tell like I guess I
would say it's a little odd to see two
separate bands moving so one of the
things that's confusing me right now as
I look at this a little more carefully
is I sort of feel like I'm seeing two
lighting fronts at the same time that
doesn't make a lot of sense to me so I
see sort of like there's kind of a hard
edge here that seems pretty consistent
and then as I move this that's like the
specular I wondered so I guess it could
be like a specular versus diffuse thing
are we I'm trying to think about how
we're actually summing this out I don't
think so because we only have one
lighting equation so we are not actually
summing two things right
I don't think so not anymore so it's
kind of weird like I don't know how I'm
getting two separate lighting frontiers
like that right and it's very so it's
very confusing like where that fall-off
clipping is happening right it's just
very it's just very strange I I don't
know how that's happening
and of course you have to remember that
the way we're sampling this lighting is
kind of confusing but if you think about
it what's happening is we're actually
sampling it at each one of these pixels
so at every pixel we're looking up into
the voxel and we're blending between the
eight voxels that are neighbouring and
we're just summing those together right
so I'm not sure how we get like that
hard-edged and then as you do this the
edge a secondary edge wave comes through
like I just don't understand that
fundamentally speaking I don't get it
right and so what I'm interested in
doing to poke at this a little bit to
try and gain some intuition is can I do
some changes can i induce some
structured art into this that allows me
to see what's actually happening and one
of the ways I might start is I want to
kind of look at the renderer itself not
that part so let me go to the Z vias
program here what I kind of want to do
is take a look at how I'm actually
computing this lighting and see if
there's any particular parts of it that
like scream out as I'm looking at them
for if I shoved a particular known value
in here maybe I would get a little more
insight right so for starters one thing
I could do is we're doing a ton of this
like here's a sampling all of the voxel
locations and then we're interpreting
between them right so if I wanted to I
could look at just the base voxel for
example right I could say that instead
of all this stuff just overwrite the
final one with the you know the base
voxel and then if we look at it what we
would see
is what the actual lighting computation
is for these pixels right and so what
you can see now is we get one thing we
would obviously expect which is that the
lighting is now uniform throughout a
particular cube in terms of some kind of
intensity value that we've got there but
then we also have this sort of overlaid
like secondary high light that's the
thing as this fifth I specifically
wanted to bug and that gives me a good
clue which I kind of already suspected
but again I'm trying to actually you
know suss out what's going on here which
is that this is because it changes so
cleanly and and evenly across the things
I'm just assuming that this is the
angular fall-off that I'm seeing here
right and what I'm having trouble
understanding is why the angular
fall-off is shaped the way that it's
shaped right I don't understand why the
angular fall-off wouldn't be smoother
than that why it has such a weird shape
to it but this gives me a very good
indication that it is the angular
fall-off is what I'm looking at there
and so I want to start looking at that
angular fall-off to try and figure out
why it shaped the way it is and either
convince myself through enough poking
that it actually should look that way
for some reason which again I'm kind of
doubtful of which is why I'm doing this
investigation or find the error like
find what I'm doing stupid that's
causing that now we don't really do
anything with the lighting in here that
has an angular component right all of
this stuff is just a direct sample so
really all we do is prepare the angle
where the the vector we're going to
sample but all the sampling happens in
here so the only thing we can really
look at in here is are we doing
something reasonable with this so if you
take a look at this equation here what
we're doing is computing the reflection
vector and storing that in R so we've
got normalized a0 we've got the I minus
2 times inner
I rolled end times world end it's a
standard reflection so this is just
reflecting us about the world normal
right it's like hitting the plane of the
world number normal and bouncing back so
that's all that we're doing here and
then we use that eye vector as part of
our sampling right because we unwrap it
into I'm sorry we called the R vector
after we do that we use that our vector
to do our sampling by basically saying
look unwrap it into the octahedral map
using the you know inverse mapping here
and do the lookup now that could be
busted or it might not be and again I
have I think a good way of actually
isolating that problem when I look at
the game here and I'm moving around like
this what I could do is freeze the
octahedral map so that it's always
getting the same sample out because I
know the normal will change throughout
this thing and I believe we do some work
with the normal here don't we I know
maybe we don't yeah that all looks right
so we're just gonna do the basic
sampling lookup right yeah so all I
should have to do is freeze where I'm
looking in the octahedral map and this
should all stop right it should get the
same result like I shouldn't see this
and if I do see this still then I know
something weird is up right so if I went
and set the octahedral maps XY to some
kind of a known quantity right like and
I don't know where in the octahedral map
I actually have valid data so it's gonna
be kind of a crapshoot to find something
that's not like just black right but
once we get that I should be able to see
very clearly yes so once I get that I
can tell and and should have a very
clear no interpolation as I move the
the mouse around the view around and I
don't
so that's reassuring because it means
that at least there's not some weird
extra term getting thrown in there that
shouldn't be there we are actually just
sampling and off we go so now if I turn
back on the luring of the of the voxels
so I go to something that now should
vary per pixel but will not actually
have any angular component to it we
should again yeah just see a soft
version of this thing and that is what
we see right we see that this blends
together and it seems relatively
coherent so I would say that's pretty
reasonable right like that looks like
what we would expect so I think all of
the weirdness is coming from the actual
sampling of the octahedral map and again
I don't have a good understanding of why
that would be now one reason might be if
there's some badness in how we're doing
the octahedral lookup another might be
if the octahedral map itself has certain
issues right that unwrapping of lighting
is a warp of the sphere and it's
possible that that warp is a problem
right I don't know so it's not
immediately possible for me to say that
this is an artifact of the actual
mapping to the sphere because I really
have no way of knowing so that's a
little bit of an issue as well right but
you can see here that when I've locked
it down that weird sort of sampling went
away now since i when i unlock it right
and i go back to where we were before so
now we're actually gonna do the
octahedral lookup in the correct
direction so now you know when I'm
moving the mouse around I'm back to that
sort of same kind of same kind of shape
so here's what I will say about it
if
look at this actual shape it is kind of
the shape of the octahedral map warping
right and you know what I should look I
should see if I can grab one of our
viewers actually made a really cool
little thing in decimo so you can let me
let me look real quick ha one second all
right so Jeff Knox actually wrote in one
of one of the viewers of the show he
wrote in this calculator on Decimus that
he made that's really a good idea he
basically just made a decimal that would
show the octahedral map which is pretty
great and so what it does and a lot of
bookmark here for it but you can you can
look at that URL it's sa Y ie 6 X bgl on
decimals comm slash calculator so if we
take a look at this and I'll put it in
here as a little like as a little
reminder case we everyone look at it
again if we look at what happens to the
graph of the octahedral map what Jeff
actually wrote is pretty cool so you can
see along the sphere where you are
around the ring of the sphere so if you
imagine the sphere this is just us
walking around the perimeter of the
sphere you know from negative PI to PI
right so just walking around the 360
degrees of the sphere right and then
here's like the Z slice so this is the
middle of the sphere this would be all
the way at the bottom tip and this would
be at the top right and so what you can
see is if we just make a full ring
around you can see that like hey it
collapses down to a point right here
which is what you'd expect and is
roughly a ring of the circle as we
expand but you can see that bowing that
happens there right do you see that and
you'll notice that's a very that shape
you
like really really familiar when we see
kind of this sort of thing happening
here right you can see that we get that
same kind of bowing at here and here
right in two different directions that
curve sort of almost diamond D shape to
it so you know I get again like don't
really know what to make of some of
these things but it's a little bit weird
like I don't know if maybe there's just
a artifact of how low res our map
happens to be that you're just gonna get
some of these weird patterns as a result
again don't know but can't say for sure
so again it's pretty tough to really
understand exactly what's going on there
and it's hard to say like to what extent
that the sampling will have that sort of
a boundary problem but again as you
would expect when you're right on the z
equals 0 it's just a straight line
because that's the definition of how we
unwrapped it right we unfolded along
those lines and again the bowing is the
muck is very pronounced here and like
here right in the map but not here so
again I don't really know to what extent
that is playing a role in this as well
but what I would say is it's a little
bit difficult for me to understand some
of the patterns right so that pattern
for example I guess I could believe that
that pattern has something to do with
the fact that as I'm looking at it there
are like copies going on and maybe like
this pixel is you know not filled in for
whatever reason I don't know again I
could come up with reasons but I'm just
I'm not confident in I don't I don't
have any real way of knowing what's
going on there so what I'd like to start
doing is let's take a look and see what
happens if we maybe play with the
interpolation a little bit and see what
we see and then maybe start stuffing
some specific values some like specific
color values in specific locations in
the octahedral map to see whether it has
to do with where in the map we
r-right because if this was something
that primarily occurred because of some
way of walking through the map we would
expect to see it particularly based on
where in the map you are but if we don't
see that then you know obviously that's
not true okay so let me go ahead and
turn interpolation off and see if I
still see this so I'm going to go into
the OpenGL side of things and I'm gonna
go to where we have the linear parameter
are getting set here so in here I'm
gonna change this to nearest just so I
can see to what extent does this happen
regardless of whether we're sampling
with smoothing on or not right what just
happened why did I not see a difference
there oh wow so wait a minute oh I'm in
the pond I'm in the wrong place
we should delete this code this this
code is not even we don't need any of
this do we yeah and I don't think we
need any of this stuff yeah these are
extra like frame buffer things we don't
we don't care about this that's gone I
don't want to make that mistake again
we should also set a setting like you
can see we've got settings here we
should we should put some of this stuff
back in so the light sampling here this
is the one I actually wanted so you can
see me like moving around it with linear
sampling there here's without the linear
sampling so and what you can see is
actually it's just a hard edge now right
so you can see that it's absolutely
there but it's just a hard edge right so
I think this is great because since we
know that's a hard edge that just turns
into a soft edge later I think this
gives us a great way to start looking at
this right because now I'm SuperDuper
clear on where it is and
what's happening so let's try to figure
out like is this somewhere specific in
the map like maybe we've just done
something stupid at the edges of the map
or something so the first thing I want
to do is I'm gonna go in and start to
knock out certain copy operations we
were doing to see what to what extent
those play a role here right so if I go
to the actual lighting code right and I
take a look at that post pass that
copies the edges in what I'm going to
start by doing is just when we do that
edge pass so this is the edge pass here
what I'm gonna do is anywhere we were
gonna do a update I'm gonna put in an
optional thing that instead of actually
doing the correct rights it's gonna do
false rights so for example if I just
right here I'm doing this sort of Vaught
this copy right and if we look at what
lightbox we'll see is so in the game
render commands right what we're doing
is we're filling out this v3 and then
this V this this D here we're also doing
but I don't care about that because
again we're not using the depth yet so
we're doing this this light voxel see
what I'm gonna do is I'm going to like
have like two values that I copy out so
c0 the first one will be the one that
gets copied into the first location and
c1 the second one will be in the second
location so I've I've done nothing the
copy is exactly as it was and I'm gonna
put in some if zero code here that just
puts in some like hard-coded fulbright
color values in place and there if zero
it out so if I recompile this I should
see no change right and I and I don't
like that's exactly what I expect right
and so then what I'm going to do is I'm
gonna say alright let's actually fill
these in now you can see I'm not getting
anything here because of where I am in
the world let's actually back that zoom
out and let's let's actually see if we
can
get a view of sort of the area that
we're actually in in the texture right
now so at the end of the rendering you
know we've got this thing that puts
those in there right and I guess it's
during the Annette call that we actually
set those up though it's actually this
right here so let's actually zoom this
out and see if we can see a little bit
better what's going on in our texture
let's just see if we can find a place
where it's actually looking at something
and I'm gonna try and find it here
because you can see the center looks
like maybe we're not in the right place
at the moment we gotta like find what
this room where this room unpacks when
we're looking at it here so there's some
so I just want to be able to see like
part the part of the light map that's
actually valid at this point in time so
here we are looking at the light map you
can kind of see like that we've got a
pretty reasonable part of it here right
and as I turn around right this the
light Maps not going to change it'll
change as I move because that moves the
light source but this is just changing
the angle that we're sampling in so this
is just changing where in here we're
actually like sampling that's all that's
happening there with that angular change
so that that's sort of a separate issue
right so now let's take a look at what
we get here if I actually put in these
copy overwrites so now instead of
blending that border we're gonna have
like a red and green line right that's
it there and what you can see as I'm
moving around here is like the red and
green is like nowhere to be found right
like we're just not seeing that like
anywhere in here you know I'm saying and
so you know there's a couple of things
that are kind of weird about that but if
you think about it I guess I'm not
surprised because the edges when we're
not interpolating you wouldn't ever hit
the edges right because we go right out
to the edge here but we never crossed
the boundary so in a sense that's
actually encouraging because with
interpolation off I suppose we shouldn't
see that right I mean we just we
shouldn't see that
difference there right so let's go ahead
and turn interpolation on real quick and
see cuz we hope to we do hope to see
those but that will also tell us are we
at that edge or not cuz I don't know and
we could also poke some structured art
in there to see that as well but you see
what I'm saying right so if I go to the
OpenGL renderer and I look for the GL
nearest here I turn this back to linear
like so and I can now see what you know
is there any red or green that shows up
on these edges right and so there's
nothing there right like it is
absolutely not there you can see that it
is getting sampled but it's absolutely
not in that location right so what's
most interesting about that is it means
that that artifact that we're seeing is
happening kind of in the middle of
things right it's happening like
actually like inside here somewhere and
we don't necessarily know exactly where
yet
but what we do know now is it's not any
of these edge things so if I actually
turn you know I might do this so I can
sort of say you know let's look at the
edge coloring here right and I'll do
that like so so I'm going to do this one
exactly the same way as I did the other
one so I'm just gonna put in a c0 I'm
gonna put in a c1 and then I'm gonna put
the ability to sort of color those
things specifically in the middle and so
now this will also create a border on
the other side so you know just in case
we're getting some sampling weirdness
there we should be able to see that as
well and again like you know looking at
what's happening here just nothing
happening without linear which is what
we would expect if we were doing our
mapping correctly turning linear on we
should see hopefully nothing in this
region and we don't so again that
sampling is is really only out at the
fringes you can see it out here and here
right but I'm not getting any of it in
the actual region that we care about so
again think I think you know to at least
a certain extent I would say the copy
like our copy operation itself doesn't
seem particularly implicated there and
right like like I'm not seeing much of a
you know of an implication that that
this border copy could really be part
could could be any particular part of
the problem so what that you know leads
me to start thinking about now is that
means this seam is something that's
showing up during per pixel
interpolation it's based on the angle
not the location in the voxel so the
lerp is not particularly implicated here
right and furthermore I guess I'm
wondering to what happens if I turn the
loop off now oops so if I jump in to Z
bias program and turn that loop off
again I'm just curious what happens here
I don't quite remember you apologize I
want take a look so if I turn the lerp
of the voxel off now what happens to
that seam okay so this is even better
I've now eliminated like most of the
code right so we're now just looking at
this diamond pattern almost entirely
separately from any other issue right
and what's more is I'm wondering - like
could I just pick a particular voxel out
and stop even go even less far right so
for example if I look at where I am you
know in the world so here we are
we're kind of right outside the hot
region and down so you know the in terms
of where we are in the voxel we're like
dead center
we're pretty much dead center of the
voxel except in Y where we're back a bit
and well I guess even there were more
we're pretty close to the center we're
almost dead center voxel but we're a
little bit forward in Y and a little bit
right in X right so we could kind of
pick whichever voxel we're fairly close
to here and just lock to that voxel and
see the pattern like by itself almost
right now I don't know we care because
we can see it so clearly at the moment I
suppose we don't really care about that
but it's at least worth noting that it
seems like what's in the voxel doesn't
even matter because this thing happens
no matter where we are right we're here
or here or here it really doesn't matter
we're getting this sampling on every
possible voxel cell so it doesn't look
like it matters which cell were on the
only thing that matters is that there's
any light there so we don't see any up
here because there's no light for us to
see but anywhere there was any lighting
at all we get this pattern right so I
think this gives us a really good
opportunity to hunt for the bug right
we're in a really good place we're kind
of like the cat that's sitting watching
the the shrub that the mouse ran into
and we just have to be patient and wait
for the mouse to run out and when the
mouse runs out we're gonna pounce right
so let's take a look at some let's try
and figure out some ways we can poke you
know let's let's SWAT our tail on the
ground a little bit if you will to try
and provoke the mouse to actually come
out so we can pounce it
so looking over here here are some
things that I'd like to see if i zoom in
on some of these voxels I'm you know
looking at this I almost want us to be
able to move around in here like it'd be
nice to be able to scroll this thing
around right well force when we can't we
don't have the yeah we'd have to spend
some time writing that and I don't know
it would probably be worth it but I
don't really know so I'm kind of tempted
to say let's just stay the course right
now because I kind of feel like we're
hot on the trail I don't want to spend
the time the diversion and possibly lose
the mouse right so the only thing I'm
thinking here is like well you know can
we zoom in a little bit more on this
right so oops that's not what I wanted I
wanted that can we zoom in a little bit
more on this and just take a look at
where we are in the in the voxel in the
atlas in the lighting atlas could be
zoom in a little bit more on this and
just see a little bit more clearly like
what what we're looking at there and one
thing I'll note is I'm assuming this
must be the wrong side of the voxel like
if we just zoom out even a little bit
more than this so let's say that I take
that span up a little bit more I'm
assuming that we actually are there's a
brighter section somewhere right because
it just this looks like that looks
really bright and I'm not seeing that
anywhere so I'm assuming this is like on
another z sheet like it's we're on the
wrong z sheet somewhere like these are z
sheets I'm assuming we're on the wrong z
sheet or something or maybe we're on the
wrong y sheet I suppose is the other
possibility so I'm not sure but I'm
gonna hunt a little bit for it just to
see if I can figure out like where the
heck this thing is actually brighter
because shouldn't it have something
approximately that brightness which is
quite bright there we go right I'm like
we should see something more like what
we're seeing here if we expect this to
act
be corresponding right so that's at
least a little bit better so I'm going
to keep hunting a little bit so it looks
like towards the far side of the map
towards the right side of the map is
where we actually see those values right
and let me let me actually go all the
way to the end just to see what we get
there so yeah it looks like it's not at
the very end so it looks like 0.8 was a
reasonable area let me just zoom out
even a little bit more see if we can't
find yeah really just don't don't see a
lot of brightness you can see in the map
right there I can turn off the those
bright colors and maybe we should make
those a little bit less glaring at the
moment but I could just turn them off
entirely because now we know they don't
actually matter right yeah so let's take
a look this should just turn those off
entirely so I guess you know that's the
brightest part of the map presumably I
mean I guess I don't really know we can
take a look at the other side of the map
and see if on the far left side there's
something brighter but it sure looked
like the brightest stuff was it like
point eight and we'll see I suppose we
can also zoom out even more right
here's us looking at the point eight
side of things again so you can see that
it's just like each slice and it's like
this is these are the Y slices right cuz
remember Y is stacked that's why there's
multiple of these and so you know I mean
which one's the brightest one I don't
know exactly maybe this one here looks
like it's getting a little bit darker
over time there but that one looks
pretty bright right there
who that those two look particularly
bright don't they again just trying to
find yeah so it looks like maybe this is
oops looks like maybe this is our Jam
here
just want to get a little bit more zero
it looks like that ones maybe even
better should probably turn off some of
those extra things we're compiling for
no reason now since we actually care
about the compile time in fact I might
just go do that so in here we're
compiling a bunch of stuff like the ping
test the sphere generator that don't
need to be the font the HHA editor like
we're compiling a ton of things so let
me just see if that improves our time at
all yeah I mean that's definitely a
faster compiler right so we should
probably just beyond that all right so
if we take a look at this now we're kind
of zeroing in on a nice bright one for
our current location and if I just go in
here and maybe tweak this ever so
slightly to try and just get that in the
center and then zoom in on it a little
bit I'm hoping that we can get a feel
for what the map looks like in this area
just so we know that we're looking at
the same thing so I'm gonna start
reducing I'm gonna zoom in a little bit
here on it right and try to get it so
we're looking at right in you know right
in the sweet spot here and that's just
again just to make it a little easier on
us so I can kind of see what we're
looking at and you can already see I'm
gonna get some good information out of
this you can see some differences abrupt
differences in the map there so let me
go ahead and zoom in a little bit more
and possibly adjust so I wanna like I
guess I don't know exactly which one of
these I want to look at but we're in a
pretty good area here so let me zoom all
the way into our default zoom now and
we'll take a look so I would say that
actually that pattern right there is a
pretty good indication of what's what
we're seeing it looks like we're
actually writing into the actual map a
very bad
pattern right I'm kind of interested in
that so let me go ahead and go in one
more zoom level here just to look at
that a little more closely and right you
see like we're writing in basically the
same the same exact values in here which
seems really weird that we would be able
to hit so precisely on that so I'm kind
of wondering if maybe we've got some
kind of a weird like bug with how were
trunking our values or something like
that those values should probably not
have those hard edges like they're
having right because anytime you have so
just to be clear on what I'm saying here
it's like anytime you have two
neighboring values that are the same
then when you do that interpolation
you're gonna have a constant value and
then all of a sudden you're gonna start
changing the constant value right across
that boundary and you're gonna your eye
is gonna see that so it's probably the
wrong time to talk about continuities
excuse me
but here's the thing your brain can see
different kinds of continuity changes so
if you want to create a seam that you
can see a visible seam like an edge
there's actually more than one way to do
it one way is to make a large change in
the actual color values or the intensity
your joining what you're doing in this
case we're just black and white so
intensity do make a large change in the
intensity from one pixel to the next
right and that large change in the
intensity will create an obvious seam
and we have interpolation turned off
right now so as the interpolation moves
from one to the other of these right or
from voxel to voxels so from here to
here which it can also do right like
this way a large discontinuous change in
the actual intensity value will create a
seam
that's the kind of seams we're seeing
here so all of these seams are that kind
of a seam and we expect to see these
kinds of seams because we have
interpolation turned off so we should
see them all but the question is if we
now go back in here right and I turn on
interpolation so I say in you know in
here where previously we were doing GL
nearest I go and change this to GL
linear like so now we're doing
interpolation so there will now no
longer be one of those changes anymore
right now again we've locked the voxels
so we're not interpolating on the voxels
so of course that seam remains but where
does that seem come from why can I see
that so clearly right and usually the
answer to how you create a seam when you
have linear interpolation or something
that on is because you've actually
created a discontinuity one level down
so you created a discontinuity in for
example in the derivative of something
so when it is it's going from one rate
of change to another rate of change
right and you perceive that difference
in the two rates of changes as
accelerating right as you see like a dip
right your brain sees that this is
smoothly going at one speed and then
suddenly going at another or something
like that right so I don't really know
if that's implicated here or not right
but it's entirely possible that it is it
doesn't immediately strike me as that
because this is interpreting out to zero
and I would have expected to see an
interpolation across that boundary
creating a problem as well with that and
I'm not really seeing that right so
that's a little bit weird I like how
that we've got a little interceding cube
that was causing me a problem there so
it's a little bit hard to tell about
that specifically but you know off you
go
so I'm not sure why I'm not seeing that
transition boundary but again it could
actually be that I'm on like one of
these voxels where it's almost black
here and maybe so maybe one of these has
it actually completely black and that's
the one we're actually in in fact in
fact where's that edge coloring in fact
KC says yes so in fact if we now turn
off nearest I'm sorry turn off
interpolation and look at the actual
thing
so actually though we probably can find
one of these that does that change right
oh oh never mind
all right I thought I guess that was
just along the boundary so never mind
never mind that Avenue is foreclosed
right it's not that because actually if
you look those were just boundary copies
that we're looking that way so I was
just confused about where we are glad we
have this that helps so I'm not actually
sure right as I'm looking at this I'm
not actually sure where that seam is
coming in right I don't quite get it so
what I want to do now is if I can I'd
like to poke in to some of these here
some structured values so I can see like
where is this coming from how are we
going from a super-bright value here
like that's right in the middle of a
voxel right and I know I'm not
interpolating I turned off voxel
interpolation so it can't be the voxel
interpolation
that's just picking inside the same
voxel going from one thing to another
thing it went from this color to that
color how did it do that right so what I
want to do is try to find where this
actually is right like where is that
actually happening which voxel
atlas in the octahedral unwrapping which
one is one of the I don't care which one
let's say it's this one but doesn't
matter I find any of them
so again structured art to the rescue
thank you Mike Biddle come as we always
thank him for structured art if we want
to take our copy so we're we're doing
the edge coloring at anytime in here I
could also just poke right into the
thing like here's here's a bunch of
pokes right here right we're just like
sticking stuff into the voxel I can just
do this and click some structured art
into a particular pixel so let me try to
find where that's happening by using
like a structured poke here right so I'm
gonna poke bright blue in there actually
let's do a low
I'm a polka yellow directly into the
voxel at a particular location right so
doing this won't do anything because
this will just put it in the corner so
what we expect to see now is a bright
yellow dot in the corner and there it is
right um maybe I don't want yellow you
don't want purple because I'm not using
that for anything else I'll say purple
so I put a bright purple dot in the
corner then what I want to do is try to
find and I have no idea where but I want
to try and find the txt why that would
put me on one of these things whoa that
is not what I was expecting to see but
oh I guess I should have Wow okay so
actually those are just the texels those
are just the texels that's the
interpolation along the Texel right
hmm so basically the problem here is
just the interpolation isn't blurry
enough I mean really that's all we're
looking at these are just the texels of
the octahedral map so I was very right
that the bowing is what those curvatures
are that's just the lat/long curves
along the octahedral map that's just
what we're looking at how fascinating
all right so that makes me want to do
the following test so what I'd like to
do is fill in the nine by nine rooted at
that at three right so I'd like to
basically do this and I'd like to start
looking at our interpolator Wow that was
fascinating do you see what I'm saying
like because I assumed there was a bug
now even if there isn't a bug I learn
something like I now know what the heck
I'm doing right but until we actually
dug in there we really just didn't know
what that was and it would have been so
easy for me to just you know do what
stripe does and assume that you know
what's going on and totally not and just
brush something aside right and that's
really frustrating that people do that
never do that you will learn something
and we just did right like we just
learned something huge and if there's no
question that knowing that going forward
will be very important to us even if
there was no bug here it was really
important that we dug in hard to this
problem and not cheese around right so
let's fill in a very specific matrix
here of like known colors across our
series so we can take a look at that
interpolator and start to think about
how we might be able to improve the
quality for the cranium interpolation
that we're doing here and maybe that
means doing a little more sampling
ourselves which in theory wouldn't be
too bad because again like I think we've
got because we're just sample
from one texture and we'd be sampling
right inside the texture in a very
specific place
we shouldn't be causing much texture
bandwidth there so I think this the fact
that these atlases are nicely compacted
in a way that a graphics card likes to
see things will allow us to do more than
we would have been able to do if these
were spread out and voxel land or who
knows what so if I go in here and look
at what's going on
I just want to spread these out so that
I can kind of get like a better idea of
of what's going on so I'm gonna try
doing like maybe I'll just do like
arbitrary colors throughout so maybe
I'll just do like this kind of thing
right and I'm not really sure again like
what the best way to do this is like I
just I'm just trying to assign color
values that will give me some way of
uniquely identifying where I am in the
map for everywhere around this Texel
right so do you see what I did right I
just put in a 3x3 and I may have said 9
by 9 which I didn't I meant 9 pixel 9
Texel so a 3x3 centered around the
particular one that we were looking at
right just so I can see what happens
with the interpolation right so again we
can very clearly see what's happening
now right we have a way better
understanding of what we're doing here
right we can see that is the sphere
being unwrapped the sphere of lighting
being unwrapped there for us that's what
we're looking at and now what we want to
do is look at what happens when we turn
on the interpolation and see why it is
that we can't like shouldn't there be
some way to smooth out the way that
we're doing this interpolation to not
see those those seams right and so what
we're seeing in the seam is is the
bilinear filtering artifact right so
what we're seeing there is we're seeing
that sort of square based interpolator
coming to bite us right and so what we
could do is try to use maybe some kind
of a radial interpolator or something
right we could try to fuzz those to make
those edges less linear and more for
lack of a better word puffy right we
could try to change those fault change
those fall-off curves and produce
something you know that was a little bit
more diffusing in like us more of a
spherical pattern right because again
this is lighting on a sphere we don't
really want lines so I think what I
normally do at this point is I'd
probably go spelunking for some papers
and I try to figure out if anyone had
done stuff about how do you interpolate
points in an octahedral met or not in
octal map points in a map to try and get
better
sampling than linear that's what I'd
probably do what I'm gonna do instead
just so you know is I'm gonna try and
figure it out myself
and again that's more to show you how
you might go about doing that if you're
gonna spend more time on it so before
looking we're gonna give it one crack
ourselves which we always try to do on
handmade Hiro not because I think you
should necessarily do that in actual
practice I do think you should do that
in actual practice when you're learning
by the way I think you should always
give something one go first but then you
do want to go read about it when you're
actually professional in programming I
usually do the other way around
I usually familiarize myself a little
bit with what's already been done in
that space before I give it a crack
myself because you know I don't want to
go in blind for no reason I'm a might as
well no I try to keep it in mind that
that I should always look for novel
solutions because oftentimes I can come
up with something that might be new and
interesting but I like to know before
going in what other people have tried in
case something seems particularly good
to me or also so I can sort of see like
what are some ideas about directions I
could
go as well you know it helps so let's
take a look at this interpolation here
looking at this right what I'm kind of
interested in is what if I just knocked
out the center pixel so let's suppose
that I wanted to look at that for for a
pixel this one right here and I dropped
it to no light so there's no light
coming from the dead center pixel right
if that happens you can see exactly what
we're kind of getting right like you can
see those lines and these are just
derivative lines weird again it's never
just continuously setting the value it's
just when you do interpolation in a
bilinear fashion you're gonna see these
derivative lines that you get in there
as the change happens you can read them
your your brain can see them right so
I'm trying to think if maybe I could
make something that didn't have that and
I just interpolate in a slightly
different fashion right so if I just
figure out a way to you know produce a
an interpolation that didn't have that
artifact right hmm and so you know
considering it I'm trying to think like
what if I just did a radial of more of a
radial fall-off so what if I just
changed like how I was blending these
two things so that hmm that maybe we
didn't have that particular artifact
right and I think we could actually
probably do this just with by modifying
the UVs but I don't know that I want to
like actually start with that because
that way lies like a very specific
implementation and since I'm trying to
experiment I would want something that I
could sort of screw around with more
like something that I could actually do
more sort of more like so what I'm
looking for I want something where I can
do more experimentation you know more
quickly so what I'm asking here is like
where we're doing this sampling here so
when I actually produce these
values I'm wondering if when I
interpolate the light source here where
I interpolate the place I'm sampling in
the octahedral map I'm just wondering if
I can do my own blending so instead of
this where we do the single look up here
which again we might not want like it's
a little bit hard to give up because
it's nice to have it it's probably much
faster than if I do it myself I mean not
much faster but a little bit faster at
the very least so I don't want to give
that up if we don't get a major quality
improvement but if we got a major
quality improvement again I'm sampling
from neighbors I'm sampling the exact
same samples that the bilinear fetch
probably would have sampled anyway so
I'm staying in the texture cache just
like they want me to and presumably you
know doing the blending myself is going
to add some overhead but wouldn't
necessarily be the end of the world now
because I never remember what we
actually have access to and GLSL three
right I'm on take a look and see what
I've got Oh
got that out hot got that on hockey so
just looking at the texture sampling is
all I was interested in here I just want
to know which samplers I have and how I
and what kind of sampling I have to work
with so if we take a look in here here
we go here's all of our texture
operations that we have is this four or
three three good ok so here's all of our
texture operations and looking at what
we've got here
this operation but probably what we
would want this would allow us to give a
sampler I assume this is just the UV
coordinate right and then I can give a
specific pixel offset so I can sample
the four texels in question there I
assume that's what that would do we'll
double-check cuz again I never remember
what all these crazy things do I know
what I want to do oh actually no I take
it back
that doesn't look like what we want this
looks like what we want because we want
to fetch a single Texel right so Texel
fetch offset is probably what we
actually want this basically says well
or is it because this doesn't do the UV
mapping for us although I guess that's
okay
but what we would like it to do is just
give us the do the UV for us we're gonna
have to produce the fractional part for
the blending anyway so I guess it
doesn't really matter but I guess this
is what we would do so we'd call textile
FETs offset or just actually I guess
test Tech's will fetch at that point
because we we would be doing this
ourselves so we would just say look
here's the offset here's the particular
textile to sample we'd grab four of them
and then we'd do our own blend of the
four right just to see what different
blends might do in order to sort of
change the way that that sample was
perceived right and again this is just
to see if different ways of blending the
lighting would change things so what I
want to do here is I would like to be
able to switch between these two things
fairly cleanly you know ideally so what
I'm going to try here is something I
don't think we actually have ever tried
before but I think it should just work
and that is to say that since if we were
just passing a giant string to open gel
I think once we kind of do some
computations here I should be able to
just do the
right well actually no I guess that's
not entirely true I have to put this in
there oh you know what
no I'm dumb I don't have to do that I
can just using f0 so if I want to write
I can still use if Zi Rui can use if
blocks in my shader is just fine so I'll
just let's do that I don't know why I
did the other thing so what I should be
able to do is do something I can turn on
and off in here so that I can overwrite
this and do our own sampling so let's
say we're gonna return this result and
I'm gonna do something that looks like
this right so if one we do the existing
lookup path right and what I want to do
is pull the a out of here cuz I don't
care about the depth part right now
we're not using it we're just trying to
work out our lighting sampling and then
the death sampling we can work on later
is sort of an extra thing if we even
want it which we might not like we may
decide we don't need that if we don't
have lighting bugs related to sampling
things through walls like right like the
only reason to have the depth is to
prevent you from sampling from lighting
probes that you yourself should be
shadowed by and that's kind of an extra
level of accuracy that we either do or
don't need based on the aesthetics of
the game and what we perceive it's not a
yes or no thing it's a look this is just
hand like sort of an intangible what do
we think would this help or not so if
the results are good enough when we're
done with the color version that doesn't
use depth we just won't use it so I
don't want to do any work on that that's
why it's just kind of been riding along
as just okay we can do a second texture
if we want to and we know we can but I'm
not gonna try and make it sampling good
or any of that stuff so that part is
just a separate issue that we'll look at
later so right now we just want to
update this and basically what I want
here is some way of producing my own
blend value so I want to be able to take
three different samples here of the
color that would sort of be like around
the horn exactly like we were doing
before right I kind of want something
that looks like this where we do four
sample
to get the neighbor you know the four
pixels that are on the sides of where we
are and then I want to just do some
experimentation to see if even without
so we could choose to sample an even
wider region of the tection and texture
and try to do some kind of really much
fancier job on that interpolation but
what I'd like to do here is maybe like
try just doing some radial sampling or
something on this or something like that
right just to see if if changing the
interpolation curves is enough and it
might not be right but I just want to
see if changing the curves is enough and
again I think actually I think we know
we can't actually that doesn't work with
bilinear nevermind actually now what I'm
saying that I think it does so what you
probably would be able to do assuming
we're doing bilinear right I'm assuming
what we could do there is actually just
go ahead and compute the UV coordinates
that are the blend that would be done
radially and then just do the texture
sample I think that probably actually
works and so now I think about it maybe
that's just fine
so let me try to do this a slightly
different way okay so backing this up
here's our sample CUV here I'm guess I'm
gonna take this out entirely and say
what if we just kept even just keep
doing that and the only thing I'm going
to if one in here is the thing where we
take sample see UV and compute a
different value for it right so we're
just gonna change how we're computing
the UV that we're sampling from I'm not
actually going to change the fact that
it's a bilinear sample and let me
explain why
as I get gotta get the owl of shame out
of the way we haven't done anything
shameful yet today alright so what I'm
saying here is if we take a look at what
we're doing here on day five eighty oops
so in terms of I'm gonna call this
bilinear fudge so what we know is that
the graphics card will automatically for
us if we have a situation where we're
talking about four pixels or in this
case texels and I want a sample of value
somewhere in them then what we know is
it will do the bilinear blend for us
which basically constructs these two
values and then constructs this value in
theory but really what it's going to do
after all of that is it's just taking
what the coefficients would have been
and doing a four-way sum right so it's
doing something that basically just
looks like alright the texture look up
at the end of the day at you know UV is
going to be equal to like coefficient
zero zero times Texel zero zero and
maybe I'll write that as a small C
coefficient zero zero times taxol zero
zero plus coefficient zero one times
Texel zero 1 plus coefficient 1 0 times
texture 1 zero plus coefficient 1 1
times texture 1 1 right so it's just
gonna be a summation of this form
regardless of what happens right it's
just gonna take and add up these four
values multiplied each by some weighting
factor so it's going to compute these
and it's gonna compute those based on
the bilinear blend right but we always
know that it's going to come out
with a certain set of values that that
will do this convex combination right
and so all I'm wondering is can I just
adjust those values and I don't
necessarily know offhand so let me see
if I can right so what I want to do is I
want to do something like this I want to
say that the coefficient of T 0 0 right
I want to say that there's something
there's gonna be like a radial
coefficient and the radial coefficient
of like t 0 0 right is going to be equal
to the distance equation from this point
right so wherever I am I know that as I
move away from this point the farthest I
could be away from it in like if if a
pixel is 1 wide like we there's a value
there that we don't know what it is
because we're not actually in UV space
at the moment I'm just talking about if
this if this length was 1 and that
length was 1 so in that space then we
know that this length here would be 1
and this length here would be like root
2 right and so the question is like
alright when do we want this pixel to
stop influencing things and if we were
going to make it be a radial fall-off
right so it looked like that let's say
then what we would do is say like let's
say the radius of this thing is 1 so
what I want to do is I want to take the
radius of this right and so if we
imagined the UV in here right like the U
or the V displacement off of this thing
and probably I should be doing this off
of the bottom one so we're talking this
way right so the U and V displacements
of this particular one what we'd be
saying is that look we're gonna start at
1 so if I'm right on the thing I'm gonna
be full fully bright and then I'm gonna
subtract from there the square root of
the U squared plus the V squared which
is the length of this vector and when it
gets to 1 I want this to be 0 so I want
this to be a clamp right
so this right here is going to be a
clamp meaning I'm not gonna allow it to
go negative right and that will be my
equation so I don't know how to write
clamp in any particularly convenient way
but let's just say maybe it looks
something like this so I want to clamp
this so that it's only gonna go down to
zero and never below right so if we
imagine that I take each of these things
and I produce a radial fall-off for each
one of the points of light here right
then what I'm gonna get is I'm going to
get a series of values one for each of
these where I'm just producing sort of
inverse versions of exactly this
equation because if I imagine that I'm
talking about this square where like
here's T zero zero and like here's T 1
zero or something and here's T 1 1 and
here's T zero one right or something
like that then I know that my fall-off
4000 is like UV right and I know that my
fall-off 4001 is going to have the exact
same V but it's just gonna have like 1
minus u so the r01 fall-off is just
gonna be the exact same value but
instead of a u squared it's gonna be a 1
minus u squared right because the
distance away from T 0 1 goes the
opposite way here as u gets higher my
fall-off gets higher right I drop my
contribution
but as u gets hired here I increase my
contribution so it's just the opposite
value there right I think that's really
all there is to it right so we're gonna
have something that looks like this
oops
so here we have I don't know why I keep
on do that so we're gonna have four
different coefficients each one is just
going to be the clamped version of the
distance equation for that corner right
and the only thing that's a little bit
strange is we know that if we were to
actually apply this literal equation so
exactly what I've written here we would
actually end up with situations where
the brightness was not uniform so the
contribution of these would not sum to
one right so it would produce a radial
blend but it would not produce a
balanced radial blend and that's because
let's suppose we got to a position and I
don't know if like right in the middle
would be a good example of where that
would be but there's probably locations
in here and we'd have to take a look
guys in fact this might be a good case
for me learning to use that Decimus
program we already saw illustrate
something very well once today let's see
if we can't catch lightning in a bottle
a second time so if we go here I don't
really know how to get a new one of
these but I assume I can just do that
maybe yeah so if we were to take a look
at the total power so I'm gonna blend
two lights together right two lighting
samples together and you know in the
actual case we're blending four together
but because I'm just gonna want to graph
one thing here let's just look at just
what happens along this line so from t 0
0 to t 0 1 i could i could do if we
assume that both of these lights were
like full intensity the question is what
would the intensity be along the line
now if they're both full intensity and i
do a bilinear blend I know that's a
convex blend I know that it's uniform
way throughout so it would just be
uniform brightness throughout right
fulbright fulbright and throughout it it
would just be full bright the entire
because you're blending from Fulbright
to Fulbright there's no Delta there
right but what would happen if I blend
these two equations together right so
what happens if I take and I say and I
have no idea how to use this program
guess I would probably do a y equals
does that okay so I do a y equals X is
my variable so X in this case is going
to be u right and I say all right I want
to take one minus the square root of U
squared nope where's that squared yep so
I want y equals one minus the square
root of U squared right and that's my
that's my my distance function there
right and this is gonna be clamped so I
don't know how to clamp this of course
in this case I guess if it's not radial
this doesn't do anything so I guess I'm
gonna have to do something a little bit
fancier aren't I
because if we just square root u squared
the distance is just just along the line
and it's gonna to generate right we
won't any we won't get any of the nice
radial miss there right because yeah I
mean that that doesn't really help us I
suppose I could do this right and then I
would because that's still the same we
don't have to actually do the square
root in that case but again not sure
that really helps us we'll see you in a
second
so if I sum these two together
nope there we go so if I sum these two
together what you can see is the sort of
thing I was talking about right now
we'll take a look at what happens if I
sum them the other way but if you take a
look at what happens if I just sum these
two together even though neither of them
either one right because we're only
looking at this this cube here the 1 0
to 1 neither one of them ever goes above
the actual 1 point right
there's the SEC there's the radial blend
one way and here's the radial blend the
other way and they both stay below the
entire time but because they are
nonlinear through the middle they can
blend together to be higher right and so
if I were to normalize them right so I
would just say look there's the value
and when I take and I add these two
together I want to make sure that I
divide by whatever the total value is
going to be right so I do this that's
how we would get a constant power
throughout right so I would blend this
much of 1 and this much of the other
right and I would I would normalize
those weights by the 1 norm right to
keep us always in line and so if I I
don't know how to graph like other stuff
but you know like if you imagine nope
there we go
so if you imagine looking at the
contribution of this right you can see
that it has a kind of it because it's
getting renormalized by the weight of
the other one you can see it using a
kind of ease in ease out curve almost
now right rather than a line and
similarly if i graph the other version
it would just be the opposite curve
right so if I copy this equation here
again again you'll have to forgive me I
don't really know how to use this
program so I'm kind of making it up as
we go like it doesn't need these I don't
I don't know I guess I did it that way
the
better ways to select and then hit the
divide sign and it knows what you mean
so looks that looks a little better
right so you can see the weights of the
two of them normalized in there now like
I was saying before I guess if I do the
square root here I'm not sure to what
extent that really makes sense but let's
take a look at that so if I were to
duplicate this I guess I just do that
yeah so if I were to duplicate that and
just put in the square root version just
so we can see but I assume that it
doesn't really do anything in this case
because it just turns it into a lion
either way so if I do squirt use squared
like so and then squirt again really
apologize I just I just don't know how
to enter things into this program
properly so it's kind of a learning
experience er right so let's suppose
that I do the Square rooted version so
this is the distance function version
and I don't know how to like turn this
off okay there we go
so there's another version of this that
would show us what would happen if we
just do the yeah the - if we just do the
two opposing ones now that's a little
bit weird to me so I think I may be oh
that's why I'm like it shouldn't those
both be aligned and that's just cuz I've
again did exactly what I did on the
board there we go
no come on make that a squared how do I
make that a squared oh there we go
there we go
so if I actually do the distance the non
squared distance you can see that I just
get the bilinear blend back right and so
what I'm thinking is maybe we just don't
do that so we leave we leave in the
squared term right so we don't square
root we do clamp right we would like to
clamp here and I'm not sure how to get
that clamp in there so it won't look
exactly like this if we clamp because
this I believe would include oh no we're
fine because we can't go over one so no
this is the correct this is the curve
because we're not looking at the
diagonal when the diagonal can get past
one right is where we get a problem
right so like somewhere in here on the
actual queue on the actual square but
this is just looking at one along the
radius so it this is this is exact so
this is what it will look like even with
the clamp in place so if I were to
actually compute these values my
argument is well at that point I know
they sum to one and once I know they sum
to one I should be able to just produce
the UV values I think that would produce
the exact right combination of each of
these things right I mean that's my
thought now I don't know if that's
actually true and the reason is because
there's four things involved here and
having the weights properly sum to one
it may do it in a way I'm not sure if
you can produce all no I should be able
to use all possible combination no
that's not true is it
so I might have to think about that the
question is can I always produce the
correct version of this right now I
don't know is there a way to make this
can we look at can we do fancier things
here I don't actually know like I assume
I can't do 3d graphs but maybe I can I'm
not actually sure it was cool that this
thing just knew that if I used you like
it's really cool that it just kind of
knows it's like hey I looked and I
noticed there was only two variables so
I graphed him this way so what I'm
wondering is if I was to make a 3d graph
would it know what that was like
suppose in here I said well you know
actually what I wanted was V squared
right does it no I guess I guess all it
will do is add a slider so yeah so I can
look I guess I can look at a 2d
cross-section of what's happening with V
I guess that's what I can do
how do I oops
there we go so I can look at a 2d
cross-section of the answer I guess is
how this works by isolating a particular
slice of V right and this will show me
what the answer is specifically for just
that curve right so like I said the
problem with this is unclamped I'm not
sure how this would help us I don't know
if this has any kind of functions like
that I could look I guess
[Music]
maybe here
I don't know where this would be I would
assume that they would have something in
there maybe not I don't know so I'm not
sure if I can actually clamp one of
these values you know that's something
that someone who knew how to use this
program would definitely be able to do
and I don't know how to do it well you
know what did what did the octahedral
one do so there is so clearly like
there's like that's a function so with
squirt so I guess it's just like is
there some way to list the functions
right like how did this and and and this
this is like looks like and define your
own so we could make our own clamp in
fact looks like this is a pretty cool
program it's just like I said I don't
know how to use it so you know like this
part right here is an example it looks
like you can just create your own like I
could create my own clamp you know what
I mean
and again I just don't know how to use
it so I won't do that at the moment but
it's pretty cool that you can do all
that stuff this is such a neat program I
don't know who made this but it's pretty
awesome so anyway and they had to make
all this in JavaScript right like I
think that's pretty good right that's
not fun so if you look at what's
happening here right this is the part
that I'm talking about so the radial
fault I just want to know like is it a
line always or not like but I'm assuming
it's not if we normalize it out I'm
assuming it actually has some shape to
it right
and you can see that if V equals zero at
the v equals zero point it does actually
look like a line which is a little bit
strange because I would have assumed
that it would not since in theory if V
is knocked out of this equation it
should look the same as this one right
so Oh cuz this is the ya no oops so
there we go okay so that's that's
actually more we'd be looking like so if
we use the squared fall-off right so
there's the squared fall-off curve and
again like I think this would be
incorrect because it's not clamping
where it should be clamping right so
when it gets down to zero oh and this is
not right either so when these values as
we do this they're incorrect because the
clamping is not actually in place on the
on either on the numerator or the nut
denominator right so although we're
properly now seeing what happens in the
case where V is not allowing you to push
over zero because when V is zero then
this equation does not need clamping but
once V becomes larger than it does need
clamping and I just it would be nice to
be able to see what was happening there
with the clamping I wish is there no
clamp function so it knows ABS
oh it knows min all right
well so if we took the maximum value of
that and zero I mean if that's actually
working that that's a clamp right
because we don't really need to clamp it
on the high side even if we did we could
choose a min we just need to clamp it so
that it doesn't go below zero right so I
don't again
I don't know if this is right because
I'm not sure how to use the program but
you know we're gonna give it a shot
possibly I mean maybe that worked I
don't know if it did or didn't
so that doesn't seem particularly
logical to me it doesn't look like
that's actually clamping because I'm not
sure where you would be able to get
those those errors in there if I'm like
I shouldn't ever be able to get a zero
should I like that doesn't really make
sense so it's a little bit confusing
like I think I probably did this wrong
oh you know why because this max is in
the wrong place I mean I could do it
this way it'd be a min yeah
so that's sorry that's wrong it's this
way sorry again this is pretty confusing
for me like I don't really know what I'm
doing here so I'm like as I'm thinking
it through I'm just kind of putting
things and I'm like wait a minute Noah
why are you doing that's not the math
you actually wanted okay so if I say
look the maximum of this is zero here
and let me put this one in the same
place so there we can see the
normalization a little bit more I'd
still don't know if that's really
working the way I think it should be cuz
it looks like that I don't know why that
would again create any kind of a divide
error
it shouldn't if I'm doing this right so
we take the maximum value of whatever
this is we want to clamp it to zero so
once this gets above one and this
becomes negative we should be Street
taking zero right and then we've got the
other one in here oh so I guess that's
yeah I guess when we think about that so
when you're doing the V the problem
there is that we now no longer we don't
have the other four we don't have all
four people who should be on the bottom
with a V so that's actually that's what
we would expect because normally now
what we would have is we'd have the
other two in here
right so in addition to the previous
ones we would also have one minus V and
one minus V so it would actually be that
right it's what we would have so yeah I
guess we wouldn't really have that
problem right so that would prevent us
from ever getting a zero I think right
and so that does give us what I would
expect except at the zero okay so at
negative one it's still not giving me
what I would expect there right it's
hard to see this can I yeah I can so at
negative one that would be you know this
this should all I guess always be this
would always be zero right and you know
what V can't I don't know yet so that's
actually just wrong
this can't be negative one anyway so
it's really just here all right
so there's the blend and it looks a
little wonky like you can see that
there's a weirdness there so let me just
take one more look to see if I've got
something that I think is actually
correct now so one minus the this is a
squared fell off here and clamped this
is the squared fall off yep and clamped
this is another squared fall off and
clamped this is another squared fall off
and clamped right I mean so that looks
like it's correct the top one again is
also clamped because we don't want to
consider any contributions that are too
high or too low yeah
so if that's actually accurate I don't
actually need these intersection points
so let's get rid of that and let's take
a look so kind of what you see there is
it's not particularly compelling right
like it's alright and it has some of the
properties that I might want but the
fall-off is not really what I would have
preferred right it's it's kind of got a
nasty like I don't like those
discontinuities like I'd like to see
something that had a little less
discontinuities in it and the reason it
has those discontinuities is cuz of the
maxes right those create sort of hard
braking points so I guess what I'm
wondering is can I make it so that we
actually just maybe make the fall-off
across the entire thing so maybe I just
say look all that work I did to figure
out how to maybe make max work and
hopefully like I'm interpreting this
correctly right but maybe what I should
do is say no let's let's actually not
introduce any discontinuities there well
let me leave this on the thing for now
well actually I guess I don't really
need to so let's get rid of the max not
the Boeing 737 max of course the
wonderful airplane that crashes into the
ground due to software failures let's
get rid of the max so we just had the
turns on the bottom and all I want to do
is say look all right when we actually
drop this down I want to take and I want
to add the route to term in there right
so meaning I want to take out I want to
basically put in a thing and I don't
know if I can do this but let's suppose
I took like like a scale value and said
scalar value equals 1 over square root
of 2 right so basically reducing that a
billet so because I know that that as I
square that
outright like as this squared value
comes out my scale value I know that the
distance the radius that I want this
thing to get to would be root two that's
the distance along the the total
distance around the diagonal of the
square and this is actually the squared
distance here so I believe it would just
be actually the square of this right so
it actually just be like 1/2 right so if
I were to actually put in the one half
term there I'm wondering what that would
do to my equation I mean I'm just
curious right just to see what happens
there
and I guess so I must have messed that
up a little bit in my head let me
actually write that out because it looks
like I'm wrong about that but point
being the scale value like whatever goes
in here I'm just curious what the actual
answer is yeah so I don't know we'll
take a look but anyway that may be more
like what I want right so let me just
get the scale right on that but I think
that may be what I want because then
that way if I actually make these
functions well-behaved in there I can
get a curve and the curve won't actually
be discontinuous I'll actually have one
that can step properly through itself
now one thing I don't love here is I
don't love the I don't love the rapid
fall off here I think I would prefer
something shaped more like that so I
might continue just the shaping of these
here and say maybe what I actually want
to do is make it so my fall-off curve is
something slightly different so what
would happen I really need to learn to
use this because we could probably make
functions for doing this so I could
changes more rapidly but what would
happen if actually I wanted to do like
let's start over kind of into this now
so let's say I've got you V squared here
right and what I actually want to do is
before I was doing the fall off this way
right so we start at 1 and we drop down
like that right and if I do 1 minus like
u squared V squared right you can see as
I do that slice it's it's pretty clean
right looks looks pretty nice so the
problem that I'm getting is when I add
that normalization in there and I don't
know if this thing supports no it even
has undo man this thing is it's amazing
so that a problem I'm getting here is
like if you see what happens once I
introduce the normalization right and it
doesn't matter where the s is in there
or not so no matter what the S is right
so I can figure out what the S is just
by trial and error right and I just need
to figure out what actually that's ok
that's the problem right there
so I should be able to figure out some
way of taking these values and I guess
you know it now I think about it this s
since there's a one - in here as well I
suppose this s even has to probably
happen beforehand so it may not be able
to now but it should be able to be
pulled out hard to say so I need to make
this equation so it operates across the
square so I get an even interpolation on
it but either way once I add the
normalization you notice how I get a
curve that drops off like this and I was
kind of hoping for a curve that dropped
more like that and I guess the problem
is I'm not sure how I would actually do
that in a way that actually has the sum
to one property so we do have a bit of
an issue there and I'm not sure how I
would really go about fixing that but
let's just take a quick look over I'm
going to switch over here and see how I
would get this to come out to be
properly radial so if I assume that I've
got my square here and I want to make
sure that this point right here is
actually the zero point you know what
though thinking about that that doesn't
work right either because if we did that
then we would have to use those values
out here so we pretty much can't do that
we do have to just clamp in there like
it has to clamp and get down to zero I
mean we couldn't use negated but again
then you would you would have the same
problem when you cross this line you
would get a discontinuity so I don't
know it doesn't look like there's any
way to avoid that kind of wobbly shape
to it right and the wobbly shape comes
because when you hit a place you know
you're basically going to have for each
of these you've got a circle right and
each of these circles creates a
discontinuity in the interpolation right
so you have different places where
they're clamping would would kind of max
out
right and I don't really know what to do
about that part right I don't know what
to do to fix that it's a little dicey
right to figure out how we would
actually I'm assuming we would see that
as well so we would we would change the
interpreters to have instead of this
diagonal cross problem we would spread
it out so that it's actually at four
things instead of two which I'm hoping
would give us a nicer interpolation but
at the end of the day there's still a
discontinuity happening there I think
that we would see in the interpolator
and I'm not sure like I'm not sure what
I would do to get around it either way
let me see I'm I want to know if I can
hack something in to allow us to sample
this and the problem is just figuring
out how we're gonna do it so I think
what I will do is I'll use the way I was
suggesting originally just to make sure
that I can play around with it a little
bit easier before I try to do the UV
solving so rather than doing it this way
I'm gonna actually do this right so
we're gonna try and take an RGB sample
and I'm gonna produce that RGB sample by
taking a sum right so I want to
literally do exactly the thing that I
said
I want to do literally this right and I
want these to all be computed based on
the fall-off so I want to do that fall
off and then I need to actually produce
these values these textile samples and
producing the Texas sample is gonna be
the hardest part by far right because
it's a finicky like you know discrete
lookup kind of operation but so in here
I want to go ahead and produce these C
values I know I'm gonna have a UV
somewhere here right that's the offset
and what I need to do is for each of
these I have to produce that UV by
figuring out what the actual equation
would be and like I said what I want to
do here is say I want one - clamp 0 1 of
some equation in here which is going to
be something like you know square u +
square V and so what I might do is
actually to make this easier on myself
just do that okay and so each of these
is literally just gonna be the exact
same equation just with different things
put in here then we're gonna have to
make a denominator right out of these
which is literally just gonna be like C
0 0 + C 0 1 plus C 1 0 plus C 1 1 right
and we're just gonna invert that and we
know that unless we really screw
something up it can't ever be anything
other than a nonzero like this has to be
a number that's either like that's close
to 1 right it's it's never going to be 0
so then we just have to multiply each of
these like so and then we can do our
like conservative interpolation now we
don't have to normalize them to 1 we
could let the powers range and we'll
take a look at what that looks like
right we could try just turning that off
and see what the interpolation looks
like that way if it's not conservative
it's not conservative right we don't
have to make it be concerted but I'm
assuming that will get worse results if
it's not but we'll see right and
furthermore we could conserve it in
other ways like there's other things we
could do to those equations so we have
to play around with it
so for each of these if we assume that
the first value is U and the second
value is V right then in this case the U
is going to be one minus U and in these
cases is going to be one minus V right
but that's it so that's the entirety of
what we're doing we're just taking the
clamp of the squares like so and
producing those blend values so that's
just like a radial fall off on this
thing now what we need to do is say okay
after we do the radial fall off on it we
need to actually have something to blend
here so we need like the basis UV and
then we need the like offsets towards
the other values that we're actually
sampling so we need to figure out how to
sample this thing and in order to do
that we're gonna have to use that
textile fetch function so if we go and
look at here what we want to do is this
textile fetch so we want the one that's
going to take a 2d sampler and a 2d
point right and the LOD is always zero
we're not doing mipmapping here so we
want to do a textile fetch call we want
to pass it the light that we're actually
talking about so light color sampler
that the map that we're actually talking
about we're going to take the I've Ekta
we want a sample into and that's just
going to be like our UV that's our
literal I've X so this is our this is
our UV I guess what we should call this
is our UV I like our integer version of
this right and then for each of these
it's really straightforward because
we're just passing in for each one of
these we want and do we have a v3 you I
don't know what we've got here are v3 s
I don't see that in here so I'm assuming
we have to actually use an I've ech
three so for I Vic three I'm just gonna
say like we've got that four eyevac
three and five ik 2 I'm just gonna say
that that's like v2 s is an i vac to
write NV 3 s is an eye Veck 3
you know I'm saying and the same here
and that will just let me notate it the
way we're used to outside and handmade
hero instead of having to adapt to open
jails like nama clay Chur for no reason
so if I want to I can just say all right
so we've got an offset here that we're
going to apply actually guess it's a 2 s
in this case because we want to do a 2 D
sample I want to do this one right so I
want to take whatever the base is and
here I'm saying that I'm going to do a V
offset carillon do you offset and here I
want to do both so that's fundamentally
what I'm doing here my U and V I know
that I've got effectively a a UV that
I'm trying to sample right what I need
to do is find out how far away I am in
sort of the the textile space right I
suppose this was possibly a bad name
what I want to probably do is like Texel
right or something like that so I
suppose what I want is something more
like that and in order to get a correct
answer here what I want is like t minus
T I like whatever my actual value was so
I want to basically up convert this to
an f32
and subtract so when I have the actual
integer location that I'm sampling at I
want to subtract away however far away I
am from that integer location right so
this is the way that I would do this
blending and in order to figure out what
the heck is going on here right because
we've got so much happening in here I
don't think that I could do and maybe
we'll do is just try to duplicate
everything first
so if I inside here said you know don't
do that let me try to just produce the
linear interpolation values first then
what I could do is actually have each of
these
I could have each of these be the linear
interpolation value that it should be
and I should be able to try I should I
should figure out how to match open
jails result first right so in other
words when I have this set to 0 and I
can pile right unless I have an a bug I
should get I mean what I'm looking at
here right I should get this and so I
should be able to swap between these two
and if I produce the correctly
interpolation values I should get the
exact same result so what I want to do
is make sure I can match OpenGL first so
that I know I'm not screwing this up and
then we can look at changing the
coefficients to see if they produce
anything that's more satisfying right ok
so if we then think about what these
values would have to be so we
essentially have an interpolation across
you and across V and so we know that
each of these is just going to be a
multiplier of those two values right so
for C 0 0 it's just gonna be like 1
minus u times 1 minus V right because if
I met u 0 V 0 I'm just at you know my
current location and as I move away I'm
going to lose contribution in both U and
V linearly right so the same would be
true here except the V is going the
other direction the same would be true
here except the U is going the other
direction and then in this case neither
are going right so it's it's both it's a
different direction both of them so I
think that would be the correct way to
do the the blends on these and let's
just double check really quick to make
sure
so if you think about how this blend is
gonna work you know exactly how bilinear
blend works if i'm bilinear in-between
these and we're saying that this is t 0
0 this is T 0 1 this is T 1 1 and this
is T 1 0 so if these are my points and I
assume that V is going this way and U is
going that way for my two parameters
that I'm blending all I need to do is
say all right what are the bilinear
points that I'm first going to do let's
say along U so if I want to produce
these two points and we'll call these
two points T 1 and T 0 so what would T 0
be well T 0 is going to be 1 minus u
times T 0 0 plus u times T 1 0 right and
similarly T 1 is going to be the exact
same thing 1 minus u times T but now
instead it's going to have this value is
going to be the upper Y right so instead
of 0 0 it's going to be 0 1 instead of 1
0 it's going to be 1 1 right so those
are my two values here and then I need
to blend these two together right using
V so then my final equation for my
texture sample in this case is going to
be 1 minus V times my 2 0 plus V times
my t 1 right and if I now go and look at
what this multiplies out to be I can
just substitute these two values into
here and see what my terms end up being
right so if I take T equals 1 minus V
right and here's my T 0 it's that so
I've got a big friend 1 minus u T 0 0
plus u 2 u 1 0 right and then I add
again now we've got a V multiplying in
here big paren 1 minus u T 0 1 plus u T
1 1 right so if I see now what I get my
terms to be you can
see that they're all lined up nicely
like they each have just a distinct
location I'd have to combine any terms
here so if I want to know what
multiplies t00
well all I have to do is just finish the
distribution 1 minus V 1 minus u t 0 0 1
minus V u T 1 0 V 1 minus u T 0 1 v u T
1 1 and hey that's exactly what I wrote
down right so T's 0 0 in this case is 1
minus u 1 minus V exactly what I have 1
0 in this case is u times 1 minus V
exactly what I've got T 0 1 in this case
which is this 1 1 minus u times V that's
what I've got and then UV which is what
I've got
so again just making sure nothing funny
is going on there this is what I respect
the result to be and so now if I enter
this path in what I need to produce is
the actual input values right so I'm
going to need my T value I need that to
be equal to something right and then I
need and then I need my s my integer
version of that to be produced somehow
right so this is my actual Texel index
which it you know involves actually
knowing the size of the map and
fortunately I think I can get that
without actually having to know what it
is although I think this actually tells
me some of that information right
because I could actually compute the
total size of the map so I guess I don't
need to look it up but hey it actually
it happens to be in here anyway but yeah
um so anyway if I want to actually
produce these these values here if I'm
trying to look at where I was going to
look up you can see that this here was
the UV that I actually was going to use
so in theory I should be able to really
just do see UV x this exercise should
give me that right so actually I could
just use this directly and produce that
value
out of hand right so I should be able to
say look it's the v2 of the texture size
of the light color sampler right and the
LOD level of level zero
that should just give me what I want
also these textile fetchers I guess need
law at level zero in there as well right
so if I just produce that that should in
theory be my T value and then this would
just presumably believe the floor of T
right because I'm assuming that's what
the graphics card is going to do I mean
right it's just going to multiply out by
the size then it's going to floor it and
it's going to use that as its
interpolator so let's debug that and we
may have some errors in the shader now
so we may have to feel that yeah we may
have to field filled some fragment
errors you can see we've got some
implicit cast errors here from vector to
avec - right and so I'm not sure what
exactly we're getting as a problem there
so it could be the floor function is
creating a problem for us they're
looking at the texture size here I'm
assuming that's okay the sample - like
these are all continuous so I guess we
at the very least this is probably not
good so when we do this floor function
we probably have to then convert it to a
v2s I'm guessing but I'm not sure then
also you know what these are all
incorrect as well I guess so that's
probably where that's coming from -
these are producing for wide and I only
want three wide so that's also an issue
so let's go ahead and and stop the
program here for a second do a quick
recompile and see where we're at now for
errors so we have sample RGB s and C 11
so it looks like I just accidentally
capitalized the C value there so fix
that and then the sample RGB we don't
really need that that was a waste of
everyone's time off we go so now I think
we're okay here
not 100% sure let's let's let's see if
this has any any love for us
it does so if I hop over to the same
area that we were in before which is
which is up here in the large room just
we can see a little bit better and I
think I was kind of hanging out in the
middle of the large room so if we look
at that interpolation you know is it
exactly the same as open jails I'm not
sure let's take it let's let's flip it
but it looks it looks closed right like
we're not totally screwed so let's see
what open jail does so it looks like
we're sampling like it looks like we're
just sampling a little bit slightly
wrong like it looks like maybe we've got
a 0.5 somewhere we shouldn't so maybe
maybe we're just a little bit off in
terms of how we're interpreting these
values here I'm not sure trying to think
of what would be causing that problem so
if it's going to do a floor function on
the value it probably does have a point
5 offset in it because it's going to
need to take for the edge so at 0 0 it
needs to actually be sampling to that
value for the entire way so I think it
probably wants to actually look like
points
let me just throw this out I think it
wants to look point five back let me
explain what I mean by that so if you
take a look at the grid right oops
so let's suppose this was our texels you
know what I mean so if this is actually
Texel zero zero or you know what let's
make sure we're the right way around if
this is Texel zero 0 so u goes v goes
that way u goes that way so if this
right here we're Texel zero zero then
actually the bilinear wants to start
here right because it's actually i
believe it it does centers OpenGL x'
Texel ideas are not my favorite
sometimes so i'll say that but i believe
this is how it does it so right or wrong
this is how it's gonna do it and that
means that if you were sampling like
right here you want to start with this
one but also if even if you're sampling
all the way up here but we would start
with that one so I think what we
actually want to do is subtract that
point five point five to drop us down to
the previous one so I think we actually
want here where we do this I think we
want a drop here so that we actually
move back by a half a pixel and well I
guess no that's correct and I guess this
wants to be in there right it's it's not
part of the other branch so if we take a
look now back at the game let's see what
the difference is now with that half
pixel sample so looking at it here this
is the OpenGL when we're looking at now
we're gonna switch to ours and see what
the difference is there and that looks
exactly the same to me right like I
don't see a difference there so
I mean it doesn't I can't even tell when
it changes
that's how exact that appears to be so
I'm going to call that good enough for
government work or stripe debugging and
we're just going to like now see what
happens if we change those interpolation
parameters so here is us playing with
the interpolation parameters just really
nilly right and now we got to change
what's this oh right
sorry about that no stop
all right so in here we've got these
duplicative depth we've got these
duplicated declarations because this was
supposed to be an else and we didn't
actually put an else in there so we
actually need that right
all right and so what you can see is it
did exactly exactly what I wanted right
um excuse me so I was looking for a
radial I wanted a puffy fallout right
that's what I said
puffy fall-off and that's what I did
like I put in a radial fall-off and I
got a radial fall-off right so you can
see the difference very clearly like
right now you it looks more like a light
kind of a fall-off and if I go in here
and I change it back to using the OpenGL
default version which is this you can
see that it gets that line again right
so there's the line now I don't know
which one of those is better like I said
but it was an experiment I wanted to run
so what I want to do now is go back to
the previous way we were sampling these
just to see and you could see like
actually I guess I don't like that right
because that still looks nasty in there
right as those things overlap so when I
actually put real lighting values in
here quote-unquote real lighting values
I don't know what I'm going to find but
I want to know so I'm gonna try turning
off the sort of structured art that I
put in there just to see what happens if
we take a look at the the interpolation
here so if I now go back to the original
and I just turn off the structured art
in the textile sampling so now it's
actually filling in real values so here
are those lights what you can see is
that you know you still perceive them
but I guess I might say I do already
kind of like that interpolation a little
bit better right we might be able to do
better than that even better than that
by thinking about that interpolation a
little bit more but if I now go in and
change my OpenGL
side of things back to linear right so
in here where we were doing our light I
don't remember what we called that
it's like light filtering or something
where did that filter go oh it's already
set to linear never mind what I mean is
in the shader I should stop clamping the
thing so I was in the right place I
don't know why I left so in the shader
if I stop clamping so if I turn this off
here so we're actually interpolating
mm-hmm across the voxels now this is
what we would get right and yeah like
again I don't know I think I would
probably say two things one I'm really
glad we spent the time to look into it
because now we know exactly what's going
on there it's the interpolation between
neighboring octahedral samples that's
producing that result and so we just
need to be aware that there's a cost
there and there's a quality issue there
potentially I do honestly think the
puffy one makes it look more light like
more like lighting so it may be that we
want something like that in there I'm
not willing to call it one way or the
other just yet but I would say you know
it's something to consider so let's go
ahead and add in the full lighting now
so rather than just doing a direct let's
do the mod and I would say you know
we're in pretty good shape like we're
starting to really have something here
right now we have a lot of work to do
because now we got to put in our bounce
lighting right but I don't know I'm
feeling pretty good about it there's a
few things I want to look at but I mean
it's it's looking sweet right I mean I'm
pretty happy with where we're at all
right so let's go to a brief QA
how do I make that happen there we go so
let's go to a brief Q&amp;A I'm pretty happy
with that
ah so deaf signer wants to know why is
the lighting behind the character so
dark so the reason for that is because
right now and this is somewhat
intentional because we're trying to test
right now we are doing specular only so
actually what you're seeing here is only
light that bounces and then hits the
light source right now we can do a
diffuse lighting sample as well and we
probably will want to going forwards but
at the moment we're only sampling in
just that one direction and that's
intentional because I want to be able to
see how this lighting is getting sampled
specifically if we were just doing the
diffuse sample it would be much harder
for us to kind of debug these octahedral
Maps because we'd be taking a sample a
very blurry sample from kind of a much
wider part of the map you know what I
mean and we would be hard to find bugs
does that make sense
for a look at des most decimals
calculator okay we can take it we can
take a look at that huh second so / - ye
x Oh y ZD k 5 so someone has built an
instructional one for us which thank you
very much
you can assign and use functions
throughout the graph the clamp function
uses conditional true/false okay so
basically curly braces are a way of
producing two different things depending
on a condition I guess so if it's less
than zero but zero if it's greater than
one put one if it's if it's neither of
those two things I guess put you right
so it's if if if if and then the final
one is just the catch-all I'm guessing
so as far as oh yeah that's great yeah
that's cool
yeah that's great so perfect I mean
right exactly what we wanted to see so
okay so I get it now I'll do that and
then once I define that function I guess
I can use it anywhere I want is the idea
yeah so that's pretty cool okay so I'm
gonna leave I'm gonna put this here so
the next time I try to do this I'll
refer back to this I can I rename this
probably so that way I can just click on
this and look at this again and remind
myself so I can create those functions a
little more easily so thanks for sending
that in
Cynthia sass how fast this lighting
method was if we compiled in debug mode
probably not very fast but you have to
remember that we the code is really bad
right now we're doing a lot of things we
don't need to do so actually I don't
think this code is gonna be that bad
once we actually streamline it so I
think it will be fairly fast in debug
mode but at the moment it's not going to
be great
Jesse Mayer says I have to say that your
debug videos are often more educational
than implementation heavy ones very
insightful into your process Thanks
yes well I'm really glad that it comes
across because again I think the primary
thing that that you need to learn about
debugging is that tenacious miss what's
actually going on right and and it's so
rare right now and and I'm kind of like
I would say I'm fairly light on that
side of things actually like I'm about
the minimum you would want to be in
terms of that tenacious Ness so like if
anything you should be more like what
you see on stream is the minimum you
should ever do right so if you're
actually a diligent programmer you
should actually probably going further
than I'm going most the time and that's
both because I'm more of a broad
spectrum programmer I don't actually
tend to rathole on things for years
which you know some people might do like
they might be like I'm gonna work on
compression for five years right and
that's great because they will come up
with really cool compression stuff right
but I tend to be more broad I I do more
things less deep so there's that and
also on stream it's limited I can't
spend 16 hours looking at something in a
row which is what I would normally do
right like two days in a row 8 hours a
day or something looking at something I
would do that I can't do that on stream
so I would say the minimum you know what
I'm doing a series a minimum of
tenacious Ness I think you should apply
it's octahedral lighting the only way to
go for what you want I don't think it's
the only way to go it just seemed like
the best one I liked it a lot better
than spherical harmonics as an option
for us we didn't really look at
spherical gaussians but I'm assuming I
would have similar complaints to
harmonics so no it's not the only way to
store lighting diffuse lighting over
time or in I shouldn't say diffuse only
but inbound lighting lote there it's not
the only way to store low resolution
inbound lighting over time
once you take depth samples could you do
bounce lighting by fetching the depth
sample and then moving that far down
than normal to speak directly to the
next voxel you certainly could do
something with that if you wanted to but
in our case I don't think you ever need
to because the whole point is the bounce
lighting is getting rolled into an
actual into the actual probes right the
bounce lighting is going to happen in
the distribution phase the whole point
is we don't want to spend the time to do
bounce lighting inside the pixel shader
right because it's too expensive so
instead what we want to do is just have
the probes over time send the light
themselves around so that we get the
bounces that way right wait there's
something wrong with this no this still
looks right to me
you're saying this is no longer this
isn't the right one I'm so confused
it looks like the right one to me you're
saying it's not the right one so we
actually have to edit this bookmark
what should the bookmark actually be qm
e ph g c1 p5 that looks the same I think
it's fine
[Music]
could you do a stream on wrasse
telemetry one day showing all the things
you can do with it I'm really interested
in the tool but the only good video
source on it is John blow but his dreams
aren't very twirly by nature yeah I mean
I guess the way to think about telemetry
though is you don't really need me to do
a demo it's just you know our profiler
where you can see all the threads and
you can click on the threads and see
what each threads doing and drill down
and do it and all that stuff
telemetry is just a professional version
of that I mean that's that's what it is
so basically like it's a standalone tool
so you don't have to integrate it into
your game like we are write it like we
did and then all you do is in your game
just like we have blocks you put in
blocks for telemetry and it will just
send them off to the tool and the tool
records them and saves them to a file
and you can scrub around in them just
like you can in our tool only with
better UI right and you can do a bunch
of things you would normally do on there
so like they've got more they'll capture
more inherent stuff like kernel thread
switches or like they'll use event
profiling on Windows to like capture
extra stuff like GPU information
so just imagine like the professional
version of what we did that's what it is
so you know if you want to be able to
inspect the performance of your game or
whatever it doesn't have to be a game
that it's just you just buy it and then
you're done right
so Philip judo asks with the octahedral
map with the bilinear filtering and the
puffy filtering seem to have a pretty
quick fall-off between samples would you
consider doing something like bicubic
filtering for a smoother blend um yes
the reason I wanted to not do a cubic
blend is because that involves taking
more samples right so what we could
probably do is take a like we could
probably try taking just three samples
you know what I mean so one way is to
expand it to five samples which would be
a lot that would be a 25 tap to the
texture which seems nuts like I don't
think we're gonna get away with that per
pixel I mean maybe I don't know but
another way we just need to expand it
just a three so instead of a bilinear
filter there's just one more so we just
look on the opposite side as well and
fit the curve through those three that
might work right
and I don't know but yeah look I said
what I wanted to know was what's the
like basically I wanted to know what the
what the artifact we were seeing was and
now I'm like 100% certain I know what it
is and that's good enough for me right
now
I do think we might want to spend more
time thinking about what we should do
about it right because that I'm not sure
about but now that I've played with it
and I tried putting in a replacement and
I saw it change as I expected it I'm
fairly confident that I'm not like
totally clueless about what's going on
whereas when we started today I was I
just didn't you heard me say it I did
not feel like I understood what's going
on and I don't like that right I want to
know what the artifact is do we have a
bug if we have a bug how bad is it if
it's not a bug is it something we could
improve anyway because maybe like in
this case it wasn't really a bug as far
as I can tell right it was actually
operating properly but it's still not
great and now that we know what it is we
can ameliorate it I think we did some
amelioration I think it's actually
better now that it was and it might we
might be able to do even better but at
the moment I'm satisfied just knowing
what that is and so as we work through
the lighting and finish up on the
lighting I'm not gonna have to
constantly wonder what the heck that
thing is I'll always know and I'll know
how it should behave so it won't be
affecting my ability to judge the
quality of the light solution because
now I just know what that artifact is
and I can always just mentally account
for it whereas before I knew it was I
don't know what's going on in there
right it kunos what we're you know
what's why that's happening right so
it's really important to get that
understanding because now I can move
forward without even fixing it anymore
so and it won't negatively impact what
we're doing and at any time we can
choose if we have a good idea or we want
to start displaying around them or we
could always go back to it at our
leisure right
to use an equation for the light density
attenuation um I guess I don't know what
a light density attenuation is do you
just mean the light getting dimmer as it
gets further away or like density is
throwing me off in that in that sentence
do you know if rat has discounts for
students no I don't think they do I do
think they negotiate license prices
based on the customers usually and how
many things they're buying or you know
stuff like that but I think it pretty
much the price is the price more or less
I mean it gets cheaper if you're slight
licensing and stuff but
hmm so synthesis yes there is a distance
attenuation so you can see that we've
got a radial fall-off on the light here
this is not the real lighting this is
just a specular bounce with radial
fall-off that we added in there and
that's all it is right for testing so
because all we're trying to do is
capture light into these probes and make
sure it's working properly and later
will actually do the work of putting in
the lights equation we want because
that's totally separate right the actual
capture and persistence of the lighting
is a separate problem from what you
actually want to do with it and so I'm
not even really considering those at the
moment would you ever go back to red
yeah I love rad game tools I mean if I
can't support Molly rocket from sales of
our stuff it's where I would first look
for a job I mean it's it's the best
place I've ever worked it's also where I
send everyone like everyone I find who's
like a good programmer that I see like
on stream or whatever I send them to
John or to Jeff like pretty much period
so they either go to I know that John
looks for people sometimes so I'll send
him someone or I'll send him to read
just the paper from Nvidia about oxygen
sampling cover the sampling filter or do
they just use linear and bump up the
size of the bitmap to have more samples
so it's funny you should ask that
because I was wondering that myself I
would like to look here's the thing I
remember when we were reading through it
they definitely definitely definitely
did complex filtering on the voxels and
the reason for that is because they
wanted high quality results with sparse
voxels so they wanted to do stuff like
handle like voxel - voxel occlusion and
all this stuff so the voxel blend they
a bunch of stuff I remember seeing that
I don't remember seeing anything about
how the octahedral map gets blended
together and what you have to recall you
have to keep in mind throughout all of
this is they're only trying to solve
secondary bounce distribution because
they are actually counting on you doing
a light map pass first to do direct
illumination right so either actually
ray tracing or doing a light map pass
they expect you to do one or the other
to compute the direct illumination so
they're only concerned about secondary
bounce my assumption is they never would
have seen this artifact because once you
take out the direct illumination and
you're only looking at the secondary
bounce I would kind of assume that this
gets swallowed up in the noise so my
guess is they never saw this that'd be
my guess
now I could be wrong I don't know and I
was very curious myself so I think I'm
happy to go look to see because I do I'm
interested to see what the answer is to
that question
so you can see here like they use shadow
mapping for direct limits so the
illumination is just not in the mix
right
so this is all just about the probes
themselves right
so I don't see any discussion of how
they actually sample the octahedral map
right so I'm gonna go ahead and suggest
that maybe they just leave it as it is
right
so here's the actual sampler and I don't
know or at least might be the actual
sampler no that's not it
so actually no I guess we don't have the
shader here cuz this that's just for
updating the irradiance field right
isn't it
you
so here's them pulling out of a G buffer
this is like a deferred renderer here's
the normal position ray origin
here's the 8 probe cage
so here's the actual sampling so there's
the direct texture lookup right so I
guess I'm not entirely certain it's only
taking red and green out of here oh you
know what this is the depth map maybe
okay so here's the actual color lookup
and that's a bilinear right so yeah
they're just just they're straight by
linear which by the way at when we're
done might be the same for us like I
said we might not need to do anything
about it I just wanted to make sure we
knew what was going on when doing game
logic do you think it's ever a good idea
to write in a sink a wait style and have
that transformed into a state machine
not really I mean not exactly that way
anyway so async waiting kinds of stuff I
don't think is the appropriate model for
game logic and the reason is because
this same reason is you don't really
want to do it for the same for the way
that people do it in like JavaScript for
web pages what if that condition never
happens right so a lot of times when
people write code like that they go like
oh you know I want to write you know the
code for this AI or something and it's
gonna go like Oh chase the player and
when you reach the player then do this
thing and then it never reaches the
player right so just in this weird state
so I think usually what you want to do
are things that can remember state so
they can remember the fact that they are
trying to reach the hero but that every
frame reevaluate whether that's still a
good idea and this
is also why I think most webpages don't
work is there written to assume a very
specific set of things will happen and
invariably those things don't happen
because a packet gets lost or the user
clicks on something in the middle of it
or who knows what or the browser blocks
a cookie and then the code just falls
apart because like six different async
things are all waiting on different
things and none of those things happen
or only two of them two out of the six
things need to happen happen right so I
think you want to be more defensive in
your programming I think you want to
generally assume that while you can
write something that transforms things
into state machines if it makes it
easier for you to program them you want
to program those state machines so that
they actually take into account all the
states that might occur and I think one
of the problems of writing async style
code like that is not so much that you
couldn't write other obviously you can
write either piece of code either way
but you should not be assuming that
things happen in a series of steps that
cannot go wrong right so if you do want
to go the async programming route at
least make there be ways of which the
async thing will have sort of
exceptional things happen to jump you
back to a known good state after a
little while or don't just write it
assuming it will work because it never
does
I don't have much thoughts on the m/l
family of languages I don't tend to like
pure functional
I think functional programming has its
uses but those uses are limited and so I
think it's better to have a language
that supports both procedural and
functional as equal citizens rather than
preferring functional and if you're
gonna prefer something you should
probably prefer procedural over
functional because procedural is more
flexible and it's how a computer works
right computers aren't functional tagged
unions are great I use them all the time
do you know about the inverse distance
way into relation method you think can
be used for games I'm not sure exactly
what you're referring to obviously we
were doing inverse distance wait
interpolation but maybe you're talking
about a specific method what do you
think of C++ 20 modules and separately
of constants pressure
I don't follow supercilious anymore it's
a disaster it's a horrible language one
of the worst languages throw it out burn
it doesn't matter it'll never be good
ever don't it's jump the shark before it
even start before it even got in the
water it's it's over doesn't matter
haven't you looked at them sure they
suck I've only really focused much on
Python and I'm going to learn another
language what do you think of golang
haven't really done anything with it in
particular so I couldn't tell you all
right I'm gonna wind it down
thank you everyone for joining me fit
ups on a hammer made here at Sona
pleasure coating with you as always if
you want to follow along the series at
home you could always peer to the game
on handmade here org and it comes to the
source code so you can follow along with
it at home I live back here tomorrow
when I think I will probably start
putting in the bounce lighting we also
may want to see what we're gonna do
about diffuse so we may want to start
producing a low res map as part of our
down sampling scheme so that we can get
some diffuse lighting in there as well
we have to kind of think about how we're
gonna do that
and but we are gonna want to do that
eventually because we need to have our
services have to have diffuse and
specular component so we have to kind of
think about how that's gonna happen all
right
hopes to get them back here for that
till then have fun partnering everyone
and I'll see you on the Internet
take it easy everybody