alright hello everyone and welcome to
hand made here oh sure we could a
complete-game live on stream yesterday
not yesterday that's a total lie what I
don't mean yesterday at all I mean last
weekend we made it so that we could
reload our renderer all we wanted in
fact we made it so we could really
reload anything all we wanted which is
kind of nice
so our hot code reloading which we made
at the beginning of the project we
eventually lost the ability to hot load
our renderer because our renderer got
cabbed off into a separate DLL and that
dll was not itself reloaded and I think
we also kind of didn't have that
separately I want to say we didn't have
that before because we had welded it
into the platform layer or something I
don't really remember but point being we
had been kind of lazy about that we just
hadn't taken it seriously
and I was like alright if we're gonna
start playing with this lighting stuff
and try to make this final I feel like
we should have that because it'll help
our iteration times if we can just like
leave it up and running and tweak some
things and see the results and so on and
so we did that work and I think we're
more or less at the state where that's
all working the only thing I don't think
we did is we haven't strobed it in any
way and what I mean by that is when we
reload the renderer we don't necessarily
make any special big deal about it
we just reload the code which means that
now the renderer will operate
differently
it's reloaded the code and it will run
the new renderer but any of the setup
work that's been done in that renderer
will not get redone because we haven't
told the renderer that it reloaded so it
doesn't even know that it's setup code
may have changed and so as a result a
lot of the things that we actually want
to do dynamically a good example here
would be if we want to change the
shaders those won't actually change
because even though we change them and
the changes get reloaded nobody ever
sends new versions down to the graphics
card so the graphics are still using the
old versions of the shaders so
we want to do now is just take a few
seconds to make this work it should be
relatively straightforward I think
because all we have to because we not
because it's easy but because we already
did this we already made it so that if
it detects the settings change it
reinitialize --is that got done a long
time ago and so now what we would want
to do is just go in and fix it so that
if you reload the renderer the renderer
gets notified in some way and that way
you can make sure that anything that was
changed actually gets fixed so if we
look at the opengl side of things what
i'm talking about is if we look for
example at the Z bias program here what
you can see is like we've got a bunch of
hard-coded strings that just have like
our you know here's the shader right
it's just written right into the program
we don't load it out of separate file
when we recompile we will get new
strings but this program this compiled Z
virus program function will never get
called because it exists down here in
compile Z bias program the call to Z
bias program here it exists down here in
OpenGL changed two settings which we
like I said conveniently do have the
ability to call again so we already made
something that would do this for us
where we would get everything
resubmitted but we're never gonna
actually do this so what I think we want
to do is in the settings here where
we've got this are equal you can see
that we're doing something where
periodically we check to see whether or
not our settings are equal and if
they're not equal we call this change so
all we really need to do is make sure
that this are equal this check right
here will actually fail when we do a
reload now there's a couple of ways we
can do that but I'm kind of gonna I'm
gonna probably go with a particular one
here I'll explain in a second if you
look at what we do all we're gonna do in
that check is look to see if the memory
for the two of them happens to compare
to be the same so if we changed anything
in the game render settings which is
this right here if we changed anything
in here we would get a recompile now
obviously we could change something get
a recompile like changing whether V
sinks on or off or something but that
doesn't seem like a very good solution
because then we're changing something
that we didn't actually want to change
so what I would ROS is we can just go in
here and put an ordinal in right we can
just basically say like settings ordinal
for something like this or settings
version right and this could just
increment any time we want to force a
recompile and it doesn't mean anything
it's just a value that will compare
differently so basically every time we
reload we can knock settings version up
one and that will force a reload even if
all of these were exactly the same which
they probably will be because no one
probably changed them on the same frame
that we happen to reload the renderer so
I'm gonna go ahead and say all right
look Settings version is a monotonically
increasing value that gets incremented
whenever the renderer gets reloaded or
another event occurs that might want the
renderer to reinitialize without
actually changing any of the settings
above and this will give us an
opportunity to just kind of increment
that value anytime we want and so then
when we look at the win32 side of things
when we go into win32 hand-made which of
course controls is our tire entire
platform layer exists in here when it
decides to do this reload so you can see
you know here's us reloading the
executable here and then we come down I
think at the bottom of this and do the
reload for the renderer you can see here
we know thanks to the way that we
structured this code we know when we are
going to do this so right here we now
know when we do this reload if we just
knocked it up one if we just did this we
would be okay the problem is we're
are those actual settings right so we
got to go take a look at where those
actually are but hopefully those are set
here I believe we just have them already
just sitting in here but again I you
know don't remember this code very well
but I believe those exist in here so if
we take a look at where these come back
you can see us doing a begin frame here
and we've got this stuff if I go look at
that frame right so if I go look at game
render commands I believe that the
settings just exist in here right and
every time that it calls begin frame I
think it gets the settings that are
copied from the actual OpenGL layer I
believe that's what happens now that's a
little unfortunate because it means that
I won't actually have them kind of where
I need them per se
meaning when I come in here and do the
end frame this is where I would probably
want to do the change and I could like
make it so that I remember whether I
changed it on the last frame and then
increment it here or something like that
but what I would rather be able to do is
I'd rather be able to increment it
directly that would be like my
preference and so what I want to be able
to do is have some way of actually
getting at the the settings the previous
settings as they existed because I know
they get copied out into here and then
they get copied over when we go into
this end frame call and so that's the
part that I would like to you know I
would like to be able to increment the
the one that comes out next right and
I'm not sure exactly how to do that well
actually you know what I guess I do kind
of know how to do that I guess I could
just say like renderer was reloaded and
then I guess I could just do if renderer
was reloaded then frame settings
oops I guess I can just do it this way
right so if the renderer was reloaded
then in here I'm going to go ahead and
increment oops that and maybe this
should just be called version let's be
honest it probably shouldn't be Settings
version because Ori in the settings and
then we just set this to false so here
we can just have a thing we remember and
I suppose that's all we really need
right and so in here when we enter our
running loop we can just say like
alright
the renderer was reloaded as a thing
that we remember and our game read
render settings has a version in here
and that's it right like that's all we
would really need to do so unless I'm
mistaken I think that we'll just do what
we needed it to do and now we will be
able to change shaders and other things
I think in there so let's see if that's
actually true because it's a relatively
complicated process like I said so I
don't want to assume that that actually
worked because it may well if not so
here we are hopping around and now I
should be able to change some things in
the renderer and see pretty clearly
whether they take effect or not so for
example if I went into the lighting
system here we've got a bunch of stuff
like you can see push debug box and
stuff like that so if I was to just turn
that off for example this should be an
example of a code change that we should
see immediately so let's suppose that I
just do that and then I'm recompiling at
the bottom you can't see it there but
when that recompile finishes I should
see the boxes go away and I do and now
if I put them back in I should see the
boxes come back and again it's really
just about the compile time which is a
little bit slow right now unfortunately
but you know we could probably speed
that up in fact maybe we want to anyway
so you can kind of see all right that's
you know working just fine so now let's
try and change something in an actual
shader which is the part that's harder
or in some other aspect of the
initialization but shaders are the ones
we're probably going to
and it the most so let's go ahead and
take a look at that so let's look at
compiled seabass program which is
currently doing everything that we that
renders basically everything in the game
right let's go ahead and do something
like lock our values to one so if I went
in here and said all right this is going
to be 1.0 instead of this actual value
that comes out and now I recompile let's
see if we get a surface reflection
change where we get read everywhere and
we do right so I think that seems fine
like it looks like we've got what we
need out of that and off we go so I
think now we can just dynamically change
everything the behavior of the renderer
and the shaders to our hearts content
and I think that's good because it'll
help us you know tune things a little
bit quicker
we won't like if I hop to somewhere and
say all right we're gonna take a look at
what's happening right here we can now
edit that code repeatedly and we don't
have to do any additional work to like
get back to this scenario or whatever
else we might need to do I hear noises
coming from over there I think it might
be the puss I'm not sure you probably
can't hear them but I can all right
anyway so what we'd like to do now is go
ahead and move to like the next phase of
getting the lighting working and I guess
it's kind of a little bit tricky because
like I said we've got a lot of things
that we want to do you can see like I
did the easy one last weekend which was
make this reloadable because that's
pretty straightforward but you can see
here we we listed some things and I
think that you know based on my
experience here I really think that this
part did not
I wasn't encouraged by what I was
looking at when I was like okay what
does it take to do a good flood-fill
here I think we could do flood feeling
maybe on the GPU side of things and
would probably work okay because we'd
have a lot more horsepower there but
just looking at it as like I don't think
this is gonna work it was just a lot of
extra actual manipulation and a lot of
costly lookups in 3d when you look at
the actual number of samples you had to
take to figure out what you were gonna
do even with one cell of the voxel for
filling you typically wanted to look at
a really wide area so like you typically
wanted to look at you know an area that
would be something like 25 voxels wide
right cuz you wanted like two to one
side two to the other and of course then
the one you're on and that's like a 5x5
actually no it was worse than that was
five by five by five right so it was
actually more like 125 samples right
and so voxel filling like that as like
and maybe you could do it by just doing
two passes that each use a three by
three by three so a nine by 27 but a 27
tap filter is still bad right um and so
I didn't really like that idea very much
and I'm kind of nervous about it so I
kind of feel like we don't really want
to be in that business much if we can
avoid it and I think we may just want to
go with something like if we have to
move to spherical harmonics fine but
let's not let's not assume we have to
fill areas that we don't know about
right and it's unfortunate because I
really liked the thing we had where we
sort of said all right so we can
extrapolate stuff outside of the region
and then we can get these nice sort of
fills I don't really know that we're
gonna be able to do that like I we might
be able to do that in a slightly
different way
by saying look when we take lots of
samples inside this voxel area if some
of them are in shadow and some of them
are not in shadow then when we average
those together we could produce things
like okay this is going to be a shadowed
area but it's
going to be set to a particular negative
value to encourage to be interpolated a
particular way based on the fact that we
did see some light contribution in the
area or something like that right
so I could imagine something like that
happening but at the moment like I'm
just not super enthusiastic about it and
so if I think about what I'm gonna have
to do here
the main problem that I see so if we
look at at oops the horrors of having
your keyboard offset if we look at the
spherical are minus basis functions and
I'm just gonna see if I can get a good
image of that here yeah so if we look at
a spherical R minus basis functions
really quickly the thing that I'm
concerned about for the most part is
that if we look at what we would
reasonably be able to store it would it
would be this top tree right so if you
again just to really quickly sort of re
recap what's going on here so if we look
at circular basis functions circular
minus basis functions what these are a
way of encoding functions on a sphere
that's pretty similar to if you were
going to do something like a Fourier
transform to encode things that are not
on the sphere right so if you're trying
to take like a 1d signal and in court
and in encoded with the Fourier basis
functions you would know okay we're
gonna you know take these sort of sine
waves right and we're going to project
the function on of the sine waves and
reconstruct whatever we it was using
sums of sine waves at different
frequencies and phases and whatever else
we you know whatever you want really I
mean Fourier base functions one of them
but you could imagine any you could do
anything you wanted with respect to that
just usually if you want those basis
functional you're gonna end up with a
Fourier transform one way or the other
same ones like the discrete cosine
transform for images or whatever so 2d
you know same thing we're just taking
various oscillating functions and we're
summing them together to produce the
same result as if we had just recorded
the signal manually why do we do that we
do that because it allows us to decimate
the signal right it allows us to say
alright let's reduce the
of basis function we're going to use and
store less parameters to still
reconstruct something that looks sort of
like the function so if we're going to
do that then what happens is when you do
circle basis D constructions of things
you have to decide how many terms you're
actually in the store now obviously if
you wanted to represent the sphere
sampling with perfect accuracy you'd
need to store lots of basis functions
you need to start enough basis functions
to reconstruct the lighting at the level
you actually sampled it right so that
you wouldn't lose any information
there's no way we're gonna store that
many because each one of these basis
functions requires a coefficient and if
you look at how many we could currently
store one texture sample has optionally
up to four components right RGB a which
means we could store basically one top
of a tree one two three four basis
functions right in a single color sample
we could reconstruct with four basis
functions now I know what you're saying
didn't we already have Vox for voxels
each with four colors in them isn't that
16 basis function so couldn't we do 1 2
3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 all
the way down to this part of the tree
yes we could but it would be black and
white right the problem that we have is
we have three color channels if we want
colored lighting as opposed to lighting
that is just an intensity value so if we
want to actually know what the light
color value is we would need to store at
least three different spherical
harmonics one for each of these things
now we could try to do something a
little bit different with that because
there are ways we can cheat we could for
example store 16 basis functions for the
intensity and then some sideband values
that tell us what the color of the light
is overall or something but the problem
with that is if you have situations like
there being a bright red light on one
side of a character and a bright blue
light on the other side of the character
well we wouldn't be able to capture that
the intensity would be stored
differently from the chroma from the
color values right and once we get into
that situation we wouldn't be able to
store lights coming from different
directions very well because different
colored lights because we could store a
single set of colored lights that were
brighter on one side and darker on
another or two different bright high
spot that would all work but as soon as
the different bright spots were coming
from different colored lights we
wouldn't be able to do it anymore so if
we did want to switch to spherical
harmonics the main problem that we're
gonna have there that you'd encounter is
we can only store a very limited amount
of this tree if we wanted three
different colored lights what we could
do is three voxels each with four
components in each voxel we know that's
fast enough for sampling and each of
these things would then have to be just
the top of the pyramid so we'd get just
these four and the question I have I
don't really know is that sufficient
like would that produce lighting that we
care about or not right and I have no
idea that's the blind side for these and
so I guess one thing I would be
interested about would be like spherical
harmonics with four coefficients I don't
know if there's any like thing that
would actually tell us this maybe like
if someone did some tests which I know
people have done in the literature as
well that we can where we can just see
kind of to what extent we would need to
store them
I wonder if DuckDuckGo is good enough at
this or not I've been trying it out
lately and it seems like it's good for
generic searches but I would say for
like technical searches it seems not as
good I don't know if other people have
that experience or not I think
DuckDuckGo needs to work on their
technical searches that'd be my guess
but anyway so in here if I wanted to say
like okay
so these are just the things that I
might try searching for I mean how long
should I boil eggs for seven minutes
you think seems good anyway
so if I wanted to say here okay spiracle
harmonics truncation do we have you know
any any kind of like our example images
of that like what does our lighting look
like as we sort of reduce the
coefficients downward you know what can
we expect right
[Music]
so that's unfortunately just the
coefficient things I think or is it not
what is that can I see this larger they
really don't want to show me that image
apparently I just want some light like
what I would really like is just you
know an object and then and I'm sure
there's a paper what has this it's just
like how long would it take me to go and
find it I just want a paper that
basically has here's an object with some
lighting on it
the lighting is relatively complicated
right here's what it looks like as I
drop the spherical harmonic coefficients
down so I start with 64 coefficients and
I drop to 32 16 8 4 2 1 right that's
really all I want to see so that I can
kind of get a sense of like how bad is
my letting gonna be as I start dropping
these down and I don't this is not gonna
help because I want to see like a ray
traced image like show me what it would
look like if I Ray trace an image with
each of these like how much fidelity do
I lose as I go down the sort of the
pyramid right or as just I should say as
I go up the pyramid as I reduce which
ones I'm actually getting and I again
just really don't know so this is that's
what I wanted to see before I make any
decisions about whether I want to go
down that route
or not
because I don't think 16 per channel is
realistic if we did 16 that's 4 voxel
lookups per gun at 3 guns is just it's
48 box lookups it's just not and I'm
pretty sure at 16 it would be fine like
so the question is just at 4 is it
usable or is it crap right and I really
don't know the answer and it does not
seem like a simple search is gonna cut
it like I'm not seeing anything here
this is just not giving me what I need
to know sadly what's what's this about
that looks sort of render II
yeah again not not quite there let's see
if we can pull anything up let's see
what we've got
I was kind of hoping that maybe there
would be some in some of these papers I
mean you can see here like we'll have
tons of papers to work from in terms of
how to compute the lighting because
there's lots lots of work has been done
on spherical harmonics right and you can
see there's lots of stuff here that that
would give us lots of good information I
wonder you know what so here's like an
example
so Peter Pike Sloane whose researcher
actually knew him back in the day who
did a bunch of work on circle mines kind
of early on when people were starting to
do not early for spherical mass but
early for using them for lighting here
you can sort of see a cube map where you
can see the location of the lights in
the cube map the red versus blue is like
the positive and negative sphere it
doesn't matter which one right but point
being you can see that the two lobes of
the function when you when you're here
it's just an average color so or I
should say an average intensity so that
first coefficient is just how generally
bright is the light and then here you
are adding from someplace and
subtracting from another place so it
doesn't matter which one you
conceptualize is doing that because you
could always negate your components and
do the opposite but the point is just
that like so let's say the red subtracts
and the blue adds or the blue subtracts
and the red adds since this is red I'm
gonna go with blue some tracks and red
adds in fact that's what they did here
blues negative red is positive so it
would subtract light from this area and
add light from this area right and what
you can see here about that is I guess
to a certain extent if you only stored
the top four that's sort of really only
storing one light direction right it
looks like if you wanted two highlights
you would you would be here am I wrong
about that because if I'm gonna add
these together I mean I guess I could if
they if the function happened to line up
just so where the lights happen to be
pointing in these two directions and I
guess I could do something but you know
it's probably not really gonna happen so
it would be pretty hard to encapsulate
or I should say capture lighting that's
coming from two different sides using
only these here and that doesn't seem
great right I mean that doesn't seem
fabulous and again it kind of sways me
from wanting to use these now granted
we're not trying to capture like the
whole lighting like if we wanted to do
highlights from direct lights we could
certainly do that by just actually using
lights on people using shadow maps or
something like if we wanted really good
direct lighting we could obviously get
that in a different way so I'm not
necessarily saying that this has to be
super accurate into terms of the
direction of the lighting or anything
like that but even just looking at this
and going if I wanted to have generally
some blue light coming from the right
and generally some green light coming
from the left Oh or I should say no
generally some white light from the left
and white light from the right I mean
this can't really do it I don't see any
way that's gonna work now once you get
down here I think you could do it but
this this doesn't seem likely
so I guess what I would see here is yeah
it's just it continues to be something
that kind of eludes me how we're gonna
store these and update them and I really
just don't have a strong notion of how
that's going to happen and that's nine
so that's two voxel samples for these
you know maybe nine maybe we could get
nine to work somehow just trying to
think so if we did two voxel samples
each so that'd be six voxel samples and
then a seventh one just for the top
I mean seven voxel samples isn't
completely ridiculous and seven voxel
samples would get us Circle harmonics
down to here right and at that point it
does seem like you're capturing enough
of the lighting to be useful I would say
now again I really like to see some
examples of this okay so this act okay
so this is what I want actually so
alright we're starting to get somewhere
now so here we go these are the images
of the reconstruction of an HDR light
probe into one to six spherical
harmonics right so in other words I
think unless I'm wrong that's saying
rows of the pyramid so one would be this
two would be this three would be this
right so three is all I think we can
afford I don't think you'd afford four
and three is still pushing it but if we
go down here and we look that would be
here's one that's completely useless
that's just a brightness right here is
two and like I said I think two just
captures one directional light pretty
much right and so you look at this and
you go like okay that doesn't really
help us because that's just like you
know it just stores generally the
direction the light was coming from
which is not probably what we want but
you get here and you're like alright
that's kind of like this it's not
perfect but that's something this is
obviously way better as is this in this
but if you gave me this instead of that
or that I'm not unhappy and furthermore
we want this game's art to be kind of
soft we're not going for like a hard
lighting look weird it's where these
soft and cartoony so you know this is
probably not what I want anyway for
incoming lighting because I'm probably
capturing more detail in the lighting
than I need at this point for
nice smooth result anyway this is
probably unnecessary and I don't know
that I would even want it so the you
know I could believe it so I guess I
could believe that doing spherical
harmonics on this would would be
reasonable right
so we could do that I would be down with
that now the only thing that I Bri
probably need to check and because I
don't really understand why is that's
fairly straightforward like and we would
just go read up on spherical harmonics
evaluation and summations to figure out
what we're gonna do in terms of how to
update and compute the lighting based on
these but one thing that I would want to
know first a little bit is just what
exactly what why is it that for example
people are not using these as much
anymore so you know what do they know
that we don't know because this is part
of the rendering literature if if we go
look for example I don't know if you
remember but there's the there's the
paper that I mentioned originally when
we first started this if we go to
Journal of graphics tools that's no no
no what's it called now it's not called
that
[Music]
what so there's there's the thing that
that graphics gems become I thought it
was the Journal of graphics tools or
something like that I don't I don't
really remember and I don't remember
what it's actually called
ah Journal of computer graphics
techniques that's what I meant
so if we actually go and oh maybe we
should read that while we're at it
speaking of things if we actually go
here and look at the original paper or I
was thinking about which was this one
and I mentioned it if we take a look at
the PDF here what I recall from looking
at this paper briefly was that they in
doing their lighting scheme and this is
a very recent paper on this obviously
where they're working with lighting
probes they didn't use spherical
harmonics they used a thing called I
guess they don't say what it's called
but it's octahedral I thought that had a
name but if they just so they store it
in some kind of 8x8 light sample so they
they store 64 values per probe which is
a lot if you ask me but they store 64
values per probe laid out in some way
right I don't know that we actually have
much information about how they're laid
out but I'm assuming they explain it
more
yeah I mean so if you look let's zoom in
here here's a like okay this PDF viewer
is rolling over and dying let's download
this and open it with the real PDF
viewer oh it's already there and by the
way let's download this too there it is
so if we look at I'll load that one up
as well if we look at what's in here you
can kind of zoom in and see this is how
they're encoding it and if you see the
encoding you can see there's a little
8x8 squares of lighting that they encode
and I don't necessarily know exactly how
they're laid out but it's interesting to
note that like they decided to store 64
things pearlite probe right in a texture
that's how they're doing that and what
they actually do which is way more like
a 64 values for a for circle harmonics
would be insanely detailed right and
they specifically decided not to do that
so I'm imagining that maybe they know
something we don't and so let me just
give a sketch of some things they
probably know that we don't
and again this paper is written by total
render expert people right I mean Morgan
McGuire's like one of the most published
graphics researchers I can think of
right so you know this is not this
there's this is no joke so it's not like
this paper was by people who didn't
really know what they're doing and they
just stuff something's like if they did
it that way they probably knew something
we didn't or more specifically they know
the trade-offs very well and know how to
pick what to do and the thing that I
would mention is when we're doing our
voxel sample the reason we're doing
voxel samples is so that we can blend
neighboring light probes together and
otherwise there'd be no real reason to
do that like we don't really need voxels
for any other reason we just didn't know
any other real way of easily grabbing
the nearby light probes that we would
want to use and so I guess what I'm
wondering is how were they dealing with
that part because if we had an easy way
to just know to just do these samples in
some way where we just took samples from
multiple ones of these really easily and
then combine them and it wasn't a big
deal in the shader then maybe we just
would do that and we wouldn't have to
care right so I guess what I just want
to know some more details like how are
they doing this what exactly are they
doing for that part of the process and
and like how are they figuring out how
they want to shade these things right
and so you can see right here in figure
6 they're they're laying out what
happens there they're saying they sample
each probe in the 8 probe cage right and
that is exactly what we want to do and
so I guess how are they doing it do they
have their shader in here I don't know
sometimes they put shaders in the
appendix
so here's some examples of code in here
right so I don't know we could take a
look and we could see what they're doing
because maybe they're just doing
something that's like a really heavy
weight and large and we don't want to go
down that route cuz it's too expensive
or maybe they are doing something much
smarter than we're doing right and and
so that's just the thing that I want to
know so let's take a quick look cuz like
I said they're not using spherical marks
at all and it's not because they don't
know what they are right like I said
these these are experts in the field
they would know if spiracle Harmonix was
really smart in this case and offering a
lot of benefits they probably would have
used it I mean it's possible they didn't
because they find that this way is like
more straightforward and easy to debug I
mean I don't they could have had another
reason certainly but it's not like they
wouldn't have been aware of them or
wouldn't know how to implement them
because they would have alright so if we
take a look here let me load up
maybe notepad and see here
here's the source code for their shaders
I don't know what these are but let's
take a look
so generating random rays this is I mean
it's interesting we should probably look
at it sometime because it's like hey how
are current experts doing there it looks
like they're using spherical fibonacci
all right so you know that's interesting
but not something I actually care about
it the immediate moment in here what we
because we looked at the circle for a
matcha tube if I look in here here's the
code for updating one of these probes
and so you can kind of see the sketch of
what they're doing so they go through
each probe and cast this number of rays
which I assume is just a constant if
they tweak based on how you know good
they want versus versus the cost of the
update and so here you can see them
saying all right I'm going to do a
sample texture fetch on this Ray origin
here right which is the place we're
trying to fetch from and that gets back
a probe location I assume then that this
is saying which probe we hit is based on
a sample that I assume is a voxel let's
take a look
so I guess I'm not sure so what we can
say is these are not voxels right so
these are all two-dimensional look up
tables and and I guess I don't really
understand so yeah I'm kind of confused
so here's the reason I'm confused so
looking up the raid erection by this C
value like these don't mean let's us
because this is the R value for the
array so this is how many rays I want to
cast I would have thought we would have
passed our here oh maybe this is like a
randomizer of some kind or something
like that so I'm I'm passing in which
probe and then the R value and maybe
that is a two-dimensional vector because
I want to fetch I want to do my fetch
based on having different Rea directions
for different probes or something you
know I'm saying you're not totally sure
I get it but you can see that like we're
fetching into a Direction table and
we're using both the Ray number and
which probe were on in order to do that
and so like I said I'm not 100% sure I
know because I don't know exactly what
that table looks like so that's not
great but you know hard to say anyway if
you take a look at these and we look at
these you can see here that we're
basically saying like okay we're looking
at which direction I assumed which
direction we're casting in here where I
say ray hit radiance I don't know what
that would be doing either but I assume
it has something to do with the fact
that we are taking the
Shh no I guess I don't know what that's
doing either yeah I don't I don't really
know what these are doing because I'm
not also not sure what this fetch here
is talking about so is this just saying
that we packed this stuff maybe these
are just storage like is this just we
did the work on a previous time I mean
that could be right
these could just be things where we did
the work and we stored them and now
we're just getting them back by looking
at them up in fact that does look like
what they're doing okay so never mind so
I guess all this is doing is unpacking
them so it's doing update irradiance
probe based on samples it already took
so this is where we're actually doing
the work I guess and we just write it
out into those buffers probably I mean I
guess I don't know but that's what it
seer sort of seems like right so if we
come through here let's take a look and
see if this makes any sense to us right
so if we look at you know this this
looks like something that takes a
direction in and produces part of the 2d
lookup so this like octant code here
look is that do we have how they're
doing the octagonal encoding because
that's pretty relevant to us
I'm not seeing it yes so I don't know
where the octant code code would be
maybe in you till now
so it may be that this is something they
didn't include I don't know
I assume none of this is relevant so
yeah I don't know where that ktem code
function is exactly that would be pretty
relevant I could try to find it
separately but that was sort of part of
the thing I was wondering about right
it's like how are they choosing to do
those and codings and I and I don't
think we really got that answer because
it looks like that's just something that
happens and I don't see that code
anywhere in here unless I just scrolled
by it accidentally and I don't see it
like octahedral GLSL is probably what
we're looking for
I would assume and that's not included
in here now I don't know if maybe those
materials are included somewhere else
yeah well let me take a look it's
possible that this is just freely
available like part of in videos like
thing or whatever see if it exists
somewhere here we go so here's how
they're doing the Achtung code and
decode assuming this is the same thing
Oh in fact it is looks like same authors
- right well one of the same authors
anyway so if we take a look at this we
look at the encoding and decoding of
those octahedral samples this is how
they take a vector and go from where it
would be in three-dimensional space
pointing in direction and then how they
put it into an actual you know 2d square
so first they essentially are taking the
total magnitude right if you look at
this this is like a look at Euclidean
one norm kind of a thing right we're
taking the absolute value of each
component of the direction and adding it
together so that kind of gives us a
value that's like look nothing can be
higher than this right this is the this
is the max value of our of our system
that we're dealing with we then go and
say all right take the XY coordinate of
this so you know this is a three
dimensional Direction so we've got an X
and a Y and then we've got a Z we're
gonna treat those as sort of two
separate pieces so first we say let's
take a 2d planar projection of this
direction and let's make sure that it
conforms to the one norm so we're going
to make this as long as it can possibly
be right such that it's two values such
that if you summed the X the Y and the Z
together you would get one we're gonna
normalize the x and y that way
but we're not actually normalizing the Z
so we're saying that the X&amp;Y oh hey you
know what it actually is called the one
norm I didn't even read that when I said
this is like the Euclidean one norm yeah
it's literally the exam one norm not
only were they taking the occluding one
norm they knew they were taking the
decoding aluminum so anyway so when we
look at this we say okay this is
normally what we expect to see done to
the whole vector if you wanted XY and Z
to sum up to one right
and when I say sum up to one I don't
quite mean it in this case because these
are not positive definite values so they
could be negative that's what this
absolute value here is doing so we're
we're doing the operation that would
make them sum to one if they were all
positive but since they can be opposing
signs they're not gonna do that anyway
and furthermore we're doing something
even a little bit weirder here which is
which we're saying that not only that
but we're only going to do that to the
first two components we relieve the Z
unchanged so then we're gonna do here is
say look let's take a look at what the Z
value is now right so before we touch it
you know before we do anything to the Z
value we're gonna take a look at what it
is and what you can see happening here
is the Z value itself we don't care
about in a sense because you can see
that when we return we just return the
XY so we're basically getting Z out of
this equation entirely so the only
question is are we going to do something
to the Z depending on the circumstance
right
and so what you can see here as we say
alright when we do this in code if the Z
was positive we don't do anything so
we're just going to remember what the XY
plane err version of this thing was
normalized to the one norm and I guess
to be completely honest with you I'm not
sure why we do that but my guess would
be that if we do that we are making
better use of the bits we have if we
truncate this so that it's not stored in
float
so here's the thing I don't actually
know why they're doing that that might
be the reason why it might not be since
they handily presented us with this I
guess I would say let's take advantage
of that so here's our survey of
efficient representations for
independent unit vectors and you know in
here we've got some stuff
here's talking about this looks like a
pretty cool paper by the way never read
it you know here we go we've got some
stuff and here we go for 3d unit vectors
and here's some stuff we could do we can
store three floats that's the complete
thing we could store s norms we could do
a spherical mapping we could do a cube
we can do a warped cube we can do that
long we can do octahedral which is what
we're actually talking about now and hey
this is the one we care about so let's
pause here although here's a bunch of
other things or it looks like actually
not a bunch there's only two more Stern
concentric so here's the octahedral
mapping it basically says all right
let's talk about these as if they were
on a actual tetrahedron
I suppose octahedron so to tetrahedrons
one on the top on the bottom and you
could actually see so this is a great
diagram now I know exactly what they're
doing
and this was gonna be pretty hard for me
to determine and I've think about it a
lot harder to get to here here's they're
doing they're just saying look we got a
sphere let's take each section of the
sphere map it to an octahedron let's
take each octahedral piece and unfold it
into a square lovely that's that's great
I love it
don't ever change
all right so now we can see what the
Euclidean 1 norm does Euclidean 1 norm
is actually the thing that takes this
curve here and straightens it so what
the occluding in one room is doing is
it's this this transform here is
Euclidean 1 norm because the Euclidean 1
norm of a sphere is an octahedron is one
way to think of it right I I want to say
that
I want to say that this diagram is also
almost ACTA this might be a little small
but I want to say this diagram is almost
accurate to scale in the sense that
these points will remain the same so the
point like right here like the point
where these regions meet where the where
you see the cross-sections and the color
change the points where lines meet on
this diagram will remain in place so
from here to here the this looks like
maybe it's like a little bit but other
than that slight amount of shrinking if
you imagine blowing this out so that
just a slight bit so that these points
lined up there there there there and
there right that's actually what will
literally happen because at those points
the one norm won't do anything because
one of the coordinates is one and the
others are zero at those points so you
will literally get the same point back
when you one norm all right scissors
Berg so that's the one norm goes to the
octahedron love it and then the next
step is just saying all right at that
point we're just gonna flatten this
thing down onto the onto the plane by
looking at it from the top down and the
only thing we need to do now is say if
you were on the bottom of this thing we
don't want you to write into the same
location so we're gonna flip you out
right we're gonna take if you would have
been in this part down here right then
instead of writing to here we want you
to write to here so there's gonna flip
you we're gonna unfold you basically
love it
this is great I'm really glad I opened
up that paper that looks awesome
I don't remember where I was looking at
this value I think it was on some github
page somewhere give me that could've
come back to me there yeah so that's
this step right here that goes from a
sphere to an octahedron happy birthday
this right here says are we on the top
or the bottom of the octahedron if we're
on the top of it we're
because this is just what we wanted but
if we're on the bottom of the octahedron
we have to flip you out and the way
they're gonna flip us out here is
they're going to say all right let's
take the absolute value of whatever the
XY that we produced we're gonna flip the
coordinates so the Y goes into the X the
X goes into the Y we're just Swizzle it
right and then we're gonna take it and
subtract that from one okay now what
that we'd have the effect of doing in
this case is as so these values right
what would let me just go back to that
diagram here kind of a bit of a head in
your head you kinda have to imagine
these things happening so if we take a
look at what's happening on the
octahedron here we have one of the faces
of the octahedron we already know that
regardless of whether it let's let's
take these down here or right here let's
do no let's do these two because these
two we can see clearly so if we're gonna
do these and it's got a little arrow
pointed to so you can see this face we
know we're gonna be in this triangle
regardless of whether we're on the red
face or the blue face right but if we're
on the blue face we're trying to push
ourselves out to here but we know that
we're actually gonna be here and and
where are we gonna be on here well if
the Z was one we're gonna be here if the
Z was zero we're gonna be here and based
on the x and y you know we're gonna be
somewhere in here through all of those
you know through all of the in-between
values and so what we want to be able to
do is say all right if we were on this
line so let's say Z was in fact zero
then we're on this line if Z is 1 we're
out here so we know that at Z 1 we're
gonna have to push ourselves out to the
far extreme and what you can see about
that is saying like alright if the Z was
1 then both of
are going to be zero and so hey guess
what we're literally at 1:1 at that
point right so we kind of know that that
will produce the right answer for us
because it's like yeah we know we're
gonna be at 1 1 if this absolute value
here if these are both 0 so now the
question is what do we need to do with
them otherwise well I guess what we're
sort of saying with the cuz this part is
a little confusing why are we taking the
absolute value of those right and I
guess the reason that we want to take
the absolute value of those is because
it's difficult for us we were we're
trying to simplify this we're trying to
make one line of code right that works
by having that will work all in all
quadrants because we could write just
this expression and probably make it
work for any quadrant if we if we knew
which quadrant we were in then we
wouldn't take the absolute value we just
put the correct version of one in here
negative one positive one whatever he
wanted such that when we added this
value it would just continue to push it
away into the correct region so I guess
what this is doing is just saying look
we want to be able to do that just by
doing the sine of each of these whatever
the sign was and reconstructing that
later right
so this basically says let's pretend
because result YX being absolute values
he's saying let's pretend we were up in
this region always right and we know
that at that point if we just negate
these and flip them we can make it so
that we fill this triangle the way that
the way that it would line up normally
right
and I guess on this particular line Z is
zero
you know I'm gonna have to be honest
with you I don't understand why we
flipped the why in the ex
so I literally have no idea why the Y
and the X would be flipped there and and
I just I just don't understand so let's
suppose that I was trying to unfold this
and so I'm you know maybe we're in this
region so this region is down back
moments this part back here right I
would assume that my goal here is that
I'm trying to make it so that the
lighting values like line up along this
line right I mean I want all of these
lines like that I want to line up with
that and this I want to line up with
like this part I want to line up with
that part so along the diagonal if I
want to line up I would think what would
happen is all right so let's suppose
I've got and I step out to like here so
I've got a high Y value and a low X
value like my x value is here and I've
got a high Y value right and then I just
take that one step slightly over here so
does it mean that no I guess it does you
know what it totally makes sense now so
I will have a high x value because I
need to subtract a high value to get out
to here and I'd have a low Y value nope
all right totally fine it's a little it
was not intuitive to me that that would
be the case but totally makes sense
because once you start subtracting the
values and you're trying to make them go
the other direction
that is exactly what happens because
because rather than coming away from
this line I'm going to that I've taken a
90 degree turn so that does make good
sense all right
and then finally the last place here for
sign not zero that's just the quadrant
push as far as I can tell so basically
we're just saying look we're gonna do
everything as if it was up in this
quadrant and then we just need to flip
you to the correct side right so what
we're gonna do here is take the sign of
whatever it was we started with and put
that sign back in right this is great I
never knew this I'm really glad we like
that this is a fantastic encoding I
think that is just absolutely delightful
I mean that that's that's just
delightful I really like that a lot
yeah I mean I mean I have no complaints
about this that just looks that just
looks great the one thing that's that's
that's maybe not the best thing in the
world is that you know you do have a you
do have a extra mass computation in
there that's maybe not the best in the
world but that's okay I mean it's just
that's one test and then that's just
used for predication I mean this is this
is really cheap at the end of the day
you know abs is like it's like one and
four each and then you got the two ads
and then you've got one reciprocal not
even square-root reciprocal but just
straightforward reciprocal one multiply
one test and then a masked a sign of
subtracts another and another and and an
or really I mean that is really cheap
that is really really cheap
um so I'm pretty glad we looked at that
to be honest with you I feel like that
was really educational I've never seen
that encoding before because again I'm
not being a really strong graphics guy
it's not what I spend most of my time on
I don't necessarily know all the good
tricks the latest tricks and as these
sorts of things come down the pipe it's
good to be aware of them right because
some of them can be really helpful
that's a great thing I yeah I don't
necessarily know right now we're gonna
use it but I mean like I really wanted
to know that that's that's pretty great
so moving back now okay so now we know
how to do these octahedral encodings
that's great because that means yeah we
can pack anything in there that means
again we don't really have to use if we
don't want to we don't have to really
figure out much with respect to how we
look at those recordings so this gets us
back to just the next question which is
locates a pose we were encoding those
things we still have the problem of we
need to build the cage and when we look
at what they were doing to build the
cage it looks like someone on the chat
had suggested that we use voxels for the
lookups and so we did end up trying that
but what I had done before then was
effectively build the cage right we did
do this is exactly what we had been
doing we looked at what direction we
were going to sample and we would pick
the we would basically pick which parts
we which of the light probes in the cage
we were gonna sample right so maybe we
just go back to doing that because let's
say we did that if we did that then what
we could do was we could just pack our
samples in using octahedral just like
they're doing here because again like I
said these guys are experts what they're
doing is either correct or at least
correct for in RTX 2080 so the really
only real question is are they doing
something that's just too much for us
like that that's a little too have
high-power so if we want to do this we
could imagine storing octahedral samples
for our lighting on whatever size we
actually decided we wanted right so
could be whatever size we want and then
we just have in our voxel what our
actual light probes are that indexes
into where they would be right and then
what we would have to do is we'd have to
take a look in the voxel we'd have to
use the direction to pick out what we
were going to interpolate between right
so we would have to use like the
direction vector to pick for voxel
samples we'd take an octahedral sample
from each of those four and then blend
it together
[Music]
I mean I don't know man it seems pretty
good right anyway so looking a little
bit further in here you can see that
they're they're actually describing this
technique in detail and if you look at
what they say here I think it's probably
worth just going over each of these
points because like I said we've already
learned something pretty good which is
the octahedral encoding and that seems
like it's really it would be really fast
to sample right because when you want to
take a sample in a direction
all you're doing now is octahedrally
encoding just that sample direction and
then it's one texture lookup to get that
blend because it's gonna place it right
where it should blend now there's a
little bit of of an issue that happens
when you're gonna wrap around the edge
and I don't really know what you do to
fix that but like one example would be
to just turn on rap sampling and use a
texture array I mean right I don't know
do they not do that I don't know why
they wouldn't but I didn't see them say
anything about that but maybe they do we
can go look at their code since we have
it now where was that image with the
things
I was I'm just curious they say whether
they use the texture rate for this so
for some reason they say packing all the
probes in an atlas but I guess I don't
understand why why wouldn't you put them
in a texture array because if you put
them in a texture array then like this
is so what they're saying here is
exactly what I didn't didn't want to do
and this this one pixel gutter border
was exactly what I did not want right so
why wouldn't you pack them into a
texture array because if you packed them
into a texture array then you wouldn't
need the gutter because you just set it
to wrapped sampling and it would sample
the proper part of the octahedron right
so I mean once again the problem here is
if I thought these people were idiots I
just feel like oh they didn't think of
it but like I said these people are
pretty much the most knowledgeable
people you could probably ask for so if
they didn't do it they probably had a
reason so it always makes me nervous
because when somebody who I think knows
what they're doing doesn't do something
it's not really a good idea to assume
that it's just because they didn't think
of it that's probably a bad idea right
so I'm wondering what I'm missing there
because I feel like it's probably
something but I don't know what yeah so
I don't know that's that's an outside
thing I would say my first shot at it
would be do it in a new texture ray
that's my first thought and I I don't
know crap why didn't they do it in a
texture ray
so let's think about this again
so maybe I'm wrong and this doesn't line
up properly let me think about this
octahedron a little more carefully I'm
gonna go to the whiteboard so that I can
see guess suddenly it's a blackboard all
right sue oops
what I need to know here is let's
suppose that I take my octahedron this
is the really bad drawing of an
octahedron and I apologize
all right so here are the faces of my
octahedron and granted they're not great
but let's try to number them so here's a
here's B here's C here's D letter them I
should say right going around the top
and then going around the bottom will
number them again e f a b c d e f g h
right so looking at these it's like that
points that way that points this way
that points this way this points that
way right that's that way that way that
way that way now what we're seeing is
that if we were then to look at this at
the top down right so now we're gonna
like smoosh this into a square like so
then when we look at what these values
are we're we're saying that this was a
this was B this was C and this was D
right and then when we did our push on
these guys we would expect this to be H
this to be e this to be F and this to be
G if I'm not mistaken that's what we're
saying right and so if I look at what
the borders sampling would be if we in
wrap mode what it would be well that'd
be F and that would be G right that
would be H and that would be e right I
mean I'm not doing anything fancy here
where I'm just looking at what would be
on the other side of it that would be G
that would be F that would be e that
would be H right so the question is is
that the correct thing is the border
between F and G and F and E actually
here right so if this was face F like so
and I'm talking about crawling along the
border from B so here's B and I come
around the border this way right so
that's me crossing in here our E and G
on either side of my face and the answer
is yes they are right so I'm
not sure like doesn't that just work
everywhere like I mean is there anywhere
that doesn't work like so here's the H
face it should have a and G on either
side of it and it does I mean it just
seems like wraps sampling just works
doesn't it
what am I missing oh is it flipped
people in the chat were saying that it
was flipped meaning that like this and
this are going in the wrong are going
the wrong orientation so these are like
you know as you go over here it comes
the other way around I guess let's see
if that's true so let's suppose I walked
from here to here in the midpoint right
because we don't really care where that
is and now what we're saying is all
right I'm gonna go to the I'm only gonna
go a little bit in so I'm not going to
go very far down and I'm going to go
over to the G side of the face right so
if I were to walk directly down to that
side so let's say I was to walk here so
I'm gonna cross over on D right so if I
was going to cross over on the midpoint
on D and go to where I would be on H
right then I'm basically saying like
let's say I crossed on this side here it
would be like sort of up there right on
H and so if on here I said I was gonna
do the same thing to try and get to that
point let's say I went to here I'd be
sort of up towards here right and then
I'd cross in on here which at which
point would put me on this face
wait I'm looking at the wrong side I'm
sorry I'm trying to go to gh is totally
out of question so I never mind so try
to go to G so let's suppose I wanted to
walk over to G right yeah okay I see the
problem so this should go to G but
instead it goes to e that's the problem
cuz these are wrong right so as I come
up and and sample outside of this I'm
actually trying to go over here right
want to see something just curious does
this have ducks on the wrapping mode
here anywhere
so it's interesting like if you look at
these so GL mirrored repeat is really
close to what you want so it's almost
like we could have supported sampling
this thing right but you would have
needed you would have needed this to
actually support flipping the Y in the X
U and I'm saying to you so it's kind of
a bummer because it seems like it seems
like you could have actually made this
work anyway that explains why they don't
bother with this right because if you
can't quite make that work then it's
just a it's just not worth it right
there's if you there's no reason to
using a texture array if you can't
actually use the wrap sampling that's a
bummer
because you almost can write it's pretty
close but but no cigar so I guess I
don't know what they end up doing for
that like do they try to add because you
would want the padding in there probably
maybe you don't actually care I mean you
could use clamp I suppose
I want to take before we conclude for
today I think this does give us a good
thing to kind of know what we might want
to try tomorrow but looking in here if
we take a look at all of this stuff this
is the part I want to go through so when
they actually want to sample their cage
what they do is they say all right you
they call probes that lie below the
shading points tangent plane right and
using a soft special that falls off
smoothly as the dot product of the
shading normal with the direction
towards a probe approaches zero that's
exactly what we did - right because you
want to like blend them out as you go
and then here we say we apply a
perceptive based weighting to account
for the human visual system sensitivity
to low intensity lighting in otherwise
dark regions we reduce the graduation of
very low radiance values less than 5% of
their episode according to a montage
using curved profile that sounds like
interesting but not really quite related
to us constructing the scheme that's
like more of a light I mean you can kind
of see for all of these things this is
maybe getting a little too hardcore but
it's ok we offset the shading point
according to a bias proportional to the
shading normal and the direction of the
probes this improves the rest of the
visibility based interpolation weights
by moving away from potential shadowed
unshadowed discontinuities and we then
perform a standard for linear
interpolation based on the distance
between the shading point and the probe
centers using the aforementioned waiting
and biasing factors trilinear
interpolation so what they're saying is
they actually do all eight and they just
wait these less
that seems fine all right so if we
imagine doing eight octahedral samples
you know how much does that scare me
so I'm going to go ahead and say that
doesn't really scare me so let's suppose
that we wanted to do eight octahedral
samples to produce the blend here
if we wanted to do eight octahedral
samples we would take the position we
would produce the value that we thought
we would produce an index from that that
we could use based on the just the
position value right we'd map it into
the voxel and we would use its voxel
coordinate to produce effectively a 2d
index into a giant texture that had all
our octahedral samples right just by
taking the Z multiplying it by the x
times the y to unfold it and then making
sure that we blew out the values by
however big each octahedral square was
right we would do that eight times to
produce eight different coordinates
inside the octahedral sheet so so far
we've taken no texture samples and then
we just take eight 2d texture samples we
then trilinear them together and we're
done traveling in together is kind of
expensive certainly but it's not that
expensive
so one trilinear and 8 texture samples
seems pretty good to me I'm sold I'm
sold
I think this is okay I can do this we'll
do it tomorrow let's go to Q&amp;A
what is tomorrow well tomorrow we got to
go implement this
are you preferring chrome over Firefox
and if yes what's the reason not really
I actually have been using Firefox on my
other machines lately and on my phone
and I guess I've never really bothered
to switch this one over but shake Jess
Scott's question you mentioned on
Twitter you were building you learned
program course can you tell us more
about it yes
so I've got beta testers signed up right
now I hope to start getting the testing
started this week and it'll be a couple
weeks of me giving them content and
seeing how they do with it and then
adjusting that content so it's it's
gonna be a little bit but I hope to have
the course out in short order I'm just
I'm trying to make it so that basically
like it'll be out for you soon it's not
gonna be like a years long development
thing so at the very least it should be
out in like an early access forum like
once I'm fairly certain that it's like
got this it's that it's got all the
videos in it and maybe there's still
some tweaking to do but like it's
basically the course is what it is
you'll be able to get it
it'll be on Steam I don't know how much
it'll cost I think just based on what
I've been thinking lately it'll be the
price of a game or less so it'll be 60
bucks or less probably I don't hold me
to that but I'm pretty sure that's what
it'll be priced so it won't be
particularly expensive it would it would
basically be like a less less than the
cost of a triple-a game basically
how's a sparse energy system been has
there been any drastic amount of
occasion to it no really not I would say
that the addition of an entity cache was
probably one of the most interesting
things that occurred during hand-made
here oh it's something that I probably
will think about every time I do and it
is in the future I'm surprised I've
never seen anyone talk about it before I
think probably because like a lot of
engines just suck at entities and they
really haven't thought it through
but like entity cash I think that's a
big thing I kind of feel like all of my
games in the future will have an
explicit enemy cash model or just like
it just seems really smart I hadn't
thought about it
it just kind of happened we were doing
it and I was like oh in retrospect
if I was smart I would have just done
this I would have thought of it kind of
came out as a just a consequence of the
architecture I really like it I think
it's pretty I think it's really good you
can include the string whack G in a
doctor cookery to get Google really
I only just switch to DuckDuckGo I'm
gonna have to try that so basically what
you're saying is if I say whack G how
long should I boil an egg for some
reason that was something came up before
that's what that will do interesting so
that just shunts you over to Google
interesting all right good to know
there are some certain Amish
implementation on street or you could
look at I don't know something else uh
so I kind of just don't think I want it
I think the octahedral is just better I
really like that I'd never seen that for
the main thing I really like about the
octahedral is it's just explicit right
it doesn't involve a projection on to
periodic basis function and like that
it's just saying look here's a good way
to store spherical stuff because then
you can just visually inspect it too we
just look at that sheet and go does it
look like the lighting right it just
looks it just looks right you know we
don't have to then recompute the
lighting by adding things together and
have a debug visually it's just correct
right
what is an entity cash so the way we
ended up doing it is we just have a
world system which basically says look
the entire set of information about the
universe of the game is stored behind
some like opaque wall that is not meant
to be used when you actually want to
simulate anything or render anything or
do whatever you ask it to give you the
set of entities that exist in a region
what it does is it gives you those but
it gives them to you as basically
pointers into a cache and so if it
already had decompressed the
representation of an entity into like a
simulation version rather than a storage
version of that entity it'll just give
you a pointer to one that already exists
in memory if it doesn't it'll evict some
existing entity and move one of the ones
you needed into it right it's just a
really good way to do things
it's just how it was how a CPU does
things and it just works really well I
really like it a lot
so by the way I know people are sort of
having a DuckDuckGo google chat on the
web so I actually don't care so much
about the other sort of oh sorry so let
me know this was actually relevant so
cash tables I'm not sure what lobbying
calls a cash table sorry let me look
I know so I would say this really has
nothing to do with it
so no this this is this is different so
anyway what I was gonna say about Google
dr. Koh is actually the I wasn't
switching like a lot of people have like
privacy or whatever reason I mean they
have like reasons why they were
switching I actually didn't care about
that my problem is actually that like
you know I find this just impossible to
read i I just I can't read that like my
brain looks at this and it just
barfs so I was totally happy with Google
I didn't have a problem with the search
at all they changed this format and I
just can't use it so I use it if I
absolutely have to if I think dr. Koh
search is probably not good but
otherwise this is just my brain is able
to read these typographically so i can
see where the search results are that's
the problem so i don't care about ethics
of it at all like i am not making a
moral judgment at all between these two
companies
it's a lay out judgment if google went
back to their old way of displaying
information I would just use them again
it's just it's this is some of the worst
typography I've ever seen for a modern
web company like modern web companies
are usually all about typography maybe
not the best as far as information is
concerned but they're usually pretty
fancy right and so I don't know what to
make of this because you know this is
this is absolutely horrid this
typography is so bad that if you if a
typographer was involved with this they
should be fired right my guess is they
weren't because I'm assuming a good
typographer would have told you never to
ever do this right
I mean it's literally like when you look
at what this does typographically you go
okay so this is clearly what creates a
heading so anybody who looks at this
will immediately think that's a heading
so their brain will begin to create the
box for this typography right here it
will extend down until they see the next
one so the box they see is United
Federal Credit Union the description for
it and then this URL so now you think
that United Federal Credit Union's URL
is Waterfront FC you org but it's not
right that's what 99% of humans will do
when they look at this box because you
don't create box based on whitespace you
create boxes based on what you actually
see as headings right there's lots of
white space in here there's white space
there there's white space here there's
white space there and what you typically
do is you process boxes in terms you you
first insert things based on headings
and then you will break up things based
on the white space into pieces so you
know that this and this are not the same
piece of text but you don't know that
they're that this binds with that that's
not a common way to look at it right now
some people may do it the other way
round meaning some people may still use
this white space but that's not a reason
not to do it it doesn't matter if some
people will correctly guess the
typography the fact is the other way
around
everyone will correctly guess the type
like you'd have to be the extremely rare
specimen to not know what the box blocks
were here because both this and the
white space are telling you the same
thing so you really can't get it wrong
right
another way to say it would be that this
is a congruent layout and the other
layout is is effectively conflicting the
white space tells you something
different than the headings tell you
would be one way to look at it so people
who break the tie in favor of the white
space read the page correctly people who
break the tie in favor of the heading
read it incorrectly and that's just
always bad right you never want to have
a tiebreaker decide which way you group
your typography might be a better way to
explain it right all right I'm gonna get
some lunch
whoa oh that's just Milton I'm like what
no it's not was oh it's the game I'm
like what's in the background awesome we
forgot it was running all right thank
you everyone for joining me for the
episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow on the series
at home you can always pre-order the
game on handmade hero org comes the
source code so you can follow along with
it some people were asking about the
courses that will be coming I will put
something up in here as soon as it's
ready for public consumption
it will be purchasable on Steam that's
about the only information I have so far
I don't actually know if we'll be able
to purchase it from the epic store they
don't let you just put stuff up on the
epic store I would be happy to do so but
I yeah that I mean I don't they would
they would have to let me so I'll try to
put it on storefronts at least the at
least steam I know because it's already
I already have the beta on there and so
I'll try to put it on some more
storefronts as I find ones that are
capable of distributing huge files
because a lot of videos so it's fairly
sizable right and we will go ahead and
we will provide more information about
that as soon as we have some until then
I will be doing more handmade hero so
I'll be back here tomorrow same time
same place and we will go ahead and
started playing that letting algorithm
that's about it for today until tomorrow
have fun programming everyone and I'll
see everyone the internet tick use
everybody