to start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade Hero the show we
could a complete game live on stream we
were talking in the pre-chat and I was
just not I wasn't feeling like it was a
good night for it I was feeling chatty
so I asked if people wanted to do a chat
because sometimes we do a chat once in a
while instead of programming and they
said yes and so I feel like this is
gonna be a chat stream and we'll file it
under handmade chat and we'll just see
what people want to chat about we'll
just see what they want to chat about
and we can open up our Milton as well
let's see here
uh-oh did I kill it we're using a by the
way we're using an experimental version
of Milton here it's got a brand new GPU
renderer which technically is not
supposed to work on AMD yet it's only on
nvidia and we are running it on an AMD
card because i want to scare sergio i
guess so yeah expect expect built-in
problems we're not really in a we're not
in the correct we're not where we should
be yeah it's looking like it's having
some trouble let's put it that way but
I'm not a quite sure why it's sort of
working it's you know it's in there I
don't know what I really should do at
some point is switch this machine over
to an Nvidia card probably or at least a
more modern AMD card all right so maybe
we won't do that maybe that's not what
we'll do I take it all back I don't know
if we can launch the old one I may have
to download a copy of the old one we'll
just see if we can load the old one up
here oops
there we go so yeah we'll have Milton up
so I can draw off I want to on the chat
let's see here I'll scroll through some
of the cues let's see so I guess what I
should say is Alan since you
definitively voted YES on the chat did
you have a topic you wanted me to chat
about
I will ask first and then if you don't I
will go through the questions on the on
the stream and select some that I think
might be good and we'll go from there
all right so let's see
oh and Alan asked is Milton successfully
maintaining your data between versions I
guess I don't know but it looks like it
is I mean I I definitely wrote that on
the new on the new one and now I hold it
it loaded it in the old one but I
haven't really tested it thoroughly if
that makes sense
mr. fourth dimension oh shoot that first
question wasn't my questions I think a
lot of people are interested in this you
be business and I am too so let's start
there and see what comes up after ok
well so so the ubii thing is I think I
guess I I don't really know when this
term got coined the you be part of it
but obviously in C and C++ there's the
concept of undefined behavior right
and you V just stands for undefined
behavior for those of you who don't know
what that is
but what undefined behavior means in the
C and C both suspect is just that if you
put in a line of code that does
something that is classified to the
specification as undefined behavior
right
like say dereference a null pointer or
something like this then the idea is
that the specification does not say what
has to happen at that point it instead
simply says that it's undefined behavior
which means that if you write it
anything could happen
right and just to give you an example of
this from the talk in fact even that
touched on this if you dereference a
null pointer on some machines it will
fault because it has virtual memory and
memory protection and dereference
candela pointer will cause an exception
like the kind that we see on handmade
hero if we write to a null pointer
accidentally
that will happen that is not in the C or
C++ specification right the C or C++
specifications do not say that
dereferencing a null pointer causes a
memory exception or a seg fault the
reason for that is there are other
platforms that do support C and C++
compilation which do not have memory
protection and so on those platforms the
reference genome pointer just works you
can read and write from the zero address
all day long it's a valid memory
location right and so what undefined
behavior essentially is in the C++
specification is just a way for the spec
to say we don't know what's gonna happen
when you do this because the results can
vary per platform and we don't find that
it's a good idea to be overly
prescriptive here because if we were we
may rule out c's ability to run on
certain platforms or we may make it so
that the compiler the code the compiler
has to generate in order to in order to
fulfill the behavior definition
specified in the spec is prohibitively
expensive it's too slow right because
you could imagine in that example I gave
with the null pointer you could imagine
if you did want that to always be the
behavior that a fault would happen right
you could still implement that on all
platforms but what you would have to do
is every where in C before the first
time that any particular pointer state
is written to or read from you would
have to manually insert an if check to
see if it was zero first and if it was
you would then have to manually call an
exception raising routine right
hopefully that makes some sense
so obviously the spec writers don't want
to say that they don't want to say
writing to a null pointer is a seg fault
because now all of a sudden these other
platforms it creates a prohibitive cost
if you will for for C to run on those
platforms okay
so that's what undefined behavior sort
of initially was in terms of like how I
would have described it to you before
sort of the nonsense of the past 10 20
years right now what is started
happening unfortunately is as compiler
vendors have been starting to get more
aggressive with optimizing compilers and
that's not a bad thing right we want
them to be aggressive with optimizing
compilers because we want them to
produce code that runs quickly so we
want to we want to be spending time
trying to think of new ways optimize
code certainly what they have been doing
is they've been introducing
optimizations which use the fact that
undefined behaviors are specified in the
spec as being literally undefined to
essentially optimize code to the point
of being what I would call intuitively
incorrect right but technically correct
now I'll just write those two words down
because I'm making them up right they
don't have real words these things I'm
just saying how I would view them so
there's what I would say is there's a
concept of what's intuitively correct in
a piece of code right and then there's a
concept of what's technically correct
right and just to give you an example of
what I mean there right I might expect
in my code for example that if I define
an int right let's say I have an int and
I and the int is currently set to like
two billion or whatever right so the int
is at 2 billion very close to the
wrapping range of an integer right
because you know we've got four billion
values that a 32-bit number can take on
and let's say this is a 32-bit integer
as it would be by default on say you
know the platform's we are currently
programming on if I were to start at 0
and go up to 2 billion well when I get
to like 2 billion in change I'm gonna
wrap around to negative 2 billion and
come back through right on the CPU okay
so that's what's gonna happen on the CPU
if I were to issue an ad however my
understanding and I am NOT a spec person
because I you know I hate the C++ and C
specs with a passion because I never
seem to agree with how they decide to do
things so I don't spend a lot of time
reading them but my understanding is
that an integer when it overflows is not
specified so basically it is undefined
behavior what happens if you took 2
billion as an integer and added another
2 billion to it right now it's
completely rigorously defined what will
happen if you do this with at x64
Edition right if you do a 32-bit ad and
another if you do a 32-bit ad of a
32-bit register and a third another
32-bit register both containing 2
billion it will wrap back around right
we know what's going to happen there
right but as far as the spec is
concerned the compiler is under no is
under no obligation to do that right it
does not have to actually obey that rule
because it is technically undefined what
happens when an integer wraps around if
you or I should say wrapped around if an
integer overflows its value so if an
integer can only hold between negative 2
billion and positive 2 billion and you
go over positive 2 billion the compiler
does not have to make it wrap around all
right now the technically correct thing
here right is anything in that case the
intuitively correct thing would be for
it to wrap around right that's what I
expect that's what the program expects
to happen why because I understand the
CPU I know what the CPU does if you add
two numbers I suspect that if I have 2
billion plus 2 billion that it will wrap
around like the CPU would normally do
because in my mind what's going to
happen as compares going to turn that
into an ADD however the technically
correct thing to have happen as per the
spec is anything the compiler wants to
have happen right because it is
undefined behavior now
start to get into the reason why this
was coming up in the Internet
Chandler careth the guy at Google who
does work on the optimizer for LLVM I
don't know if he leads the optimization
team there something like this I think
is his position he's he's one of the
main guys let's put it that way he gave
a talk that touches on this and I'll
explain why he was giving that talk in a
second so to give you a more background
on it but just to sort of talk about
something that he said in that talk it's
important to understand as well and I
agree with him on this point certainly
that anything here it's not like if you
if you don't really understand this
issue or haven't really seen it before a
lot of times people may joke about it or
whatever and say that the anything like
literally means anything like you could
format your hard drive or whatever and
yes that is technically true because it
is undefined behavior so technically the
compiler could literally do anything if
it wanted to but obviously that's never
going to be true right there's never
going to be unless the compiler vendors
were particularly malicious they're
never going to do anything where they
intentionally introduced a bug into your
program for no reason at all right
they're not like out to get you or
something like this although sometimes
it may seem that way so what does it
mean to say that anything could happen
why would something else happen right
like why would something other than the
intuitively correct thing happen the
reason is because once optimizations are
considered there are plenty of
opportunities for the compiler to do
something more efficient than what it
could have done if it did the
intuitively correct thing for example in
this case where I added 2 billion to two
billion it assumes that I'm using a
32-bit ad right because if I had two
integers and I do a different kind of ad
let's say for example I'm on a processor
architecture where a 64-bit ad is
inexpensive but a 32-bit ad is not I'm
sorry a 64-bit ad is inexpensive and a
32-bit ad is expensive so doing a 64-bit
ad is much cheaper because it doesn't
32-bit it's like an afterthought with
this processor it's used to handling
64-bit native right well in that case
if I want to do computations with this
thing I add two billion to two billion
the compiler knows that if it calls the
32-bit ad it's going to be particularly
slow right so it wants to do the 64-bit
ad because the 64 bit adder is much
faster but when it calls a sixty
four-bit adder it's going to get four
billion right which is not the right
answer in this case and it needs to wrap
the value around right it needs to
produce the wrap or something right
now if it's gonna do a subsequent
arithmetic operation on this thing where
something else is going to happen to it
where it matters whether it has wrapped
around or not or whether that top piece
exists at all right
whether that additional greater than a
signed integer could be part exists it's
going to have to truncate the value here
manually right it's gonna have to like
and out the top part or do something you
know it's gonna have to do some work
additional work and so since this is
undefined behavior in the spec the
compiler is free to do the technically
correct thing which may give a
completely unintuitive result because
the programmer was expecting it to wrap
since he knows there's a 32-bit value
and he thinks three to the values wrap
right but lo and behold it does not wrap
and it gives some very different result
because the processor actually did it in
64-bit right now this is not even
hypothetical even back if we take a look
at something that was before any of this
sort of stuff started happening if you
just take the example of the x87 FPU
right before we had x64 architecture we
had the x86 architecture and on the x86
architecture there was a floating-point
unit called the x87
right and of course they were on one
chip after a while but I think
originally it might have been a
coprocessor I'm not sure I was an amiga
person at that point so I don't really
know exactly what happened for them by
the time I got to the PC they were on
one chip I don't know if they're ever
separate right but the x86 architecture
has the notion of a floating-point unit
in it and it had a floating-point unit
which had
high precision it had greater much
greater than 32-bit I Triple E floating
point okay 32-bit I Triple E floating
point is real weak sauce compared to the
x87 FPU the x87 FPU when you did
operations on it unless you did some
special mode things later on in time if
I remember correctly it added the
ability to you know make the precision
less it would do things to 80 bits this
is my recollection forgive me if I'm
getting this wrong it's been a long time
but my recollection is like it did it
had 80 bit floating point numbers that's
what it did and so you can imagine what
would happen if somebody was expecting
to use I Triple E 32-bit floats so in
their seat code they wrote float X or
whatever right and they did some
operations that they thought would be
32-bit and then they compared the
results of those operations to doing it
on an X at 87 CPU and then compared the
results to doing it on some other CPU
that only have 32-bit floating-point and
what they would find is that their
results would be totally different on
the X 87 because there were so many more
bits of precision you might get totally
totally different results drastically
different in the case of things like
catastrophic cancellation or other sorts
of floating-point operations where the
extra bits of research and make a huge
difference right and so again you can
imagine here if you were a compiler
vendor and someone had told you that the
spec says you have to have 32-bit
floating points instead of saying
something like floating points are
whatever they are right however many
bits they are if as long as it's at
least 32 or something you would have to
insert all this extra code to constantly
truncate these values to make sure that
they weren't doing higher precision
calculations than you were expecting
right so that's what what you know how I
would sort of start to frame this
problem in terms of how to start
thinking about the undefined behavior
issue and now I'll start talking about
what kind of came up recently and sort
of has been brewing over time but that's
kind of the way I think about it is
there's an intuitively correct thing and
a technically correct thing
we might want to use the drop the
correct here if you're uncomfortable but
say there's an intuitive thing and then
there's a technically correct thing
right or spec correct let's say if
you're uncomfortable with that just to
use very generic terminology but point
being there's your intuition of what
should happen and then there's what's
actually gonna happen
according to the spec and sometimes the
spec just doesn't guarantee anything so
the compiler can do whatever is
efficient and that may have unintended
consequences because again it's
undefined behavior you can't count on it
alright so recently what's been
happening is we've been getting a lot of
pretty damaging versions of this thing
right so compiler vendors or you know
looking for the spec they're looking for
optimization opportunities they see oh
okay you know I've got this sort of
wraparound thing that's happening here I
don't have to guarantee that wraparound
so hey guess what I can fold these
operations in and make a much more
efficient execution a much more
efficient set of instructions to do this
operation but hey if the programmer was
actually counting on wraparound you
introduced a bug in their code right now
it's not technically a bug as per the
spec because the spec did not guarantee
the programmer they could wrap the
integer right but it is definitely
intuitively a bug because the programmer
was thinking they were using 32-bit
integers and it turns out that they
really kind of aren't because the C
compiler isn't guaranteeing them that
right okay so that is what's been
happening a lot lately and one of the
big sort of the reasons why this is kind
of getting aggravating to a lot of
people is this can introduce a lot of
fairly serious bugs this can introduce
say very bad security bugs because
somebody thinks they wrote code that if
the wrapping works properly we'll never
overflow a buffer but hey guess what the
compiler compiled it so that it can
actually far exceed the buffer when it
does the offset because hey the spec
didn't say that you had to guarantee the
wrap would happen right
so you're starting to see more and more
of these things where the compiler
vendors are technically within their
rights to do a particular optimization
they do it it introduces fairly severe
bugs in some form or another into
well-known software packages those
people get upset obvious reasons and you
get this like he said she said of you
know okay well just why are you doing
that you're breaking this code it's like
well that's the spec that's our jobs
implement the spec you should have
written code that could form to the spec
you know your code is buggy technically
and then they're like my coche not buggy
you guys just don't understand the knee
what you're suppose to be doing here
that why are you even doing this no one
cared about this updated so you can see
like there would be a lot of acrimony
there right you could understand the
acrimony there and to give a personal
example of this from quite a bit further
back in my programming career when I
wasn't even aware of this stuff it's the
first time I really became aware of this
I actually had a bug exactly this way
and I'll tell you what it was because I
remember it in all the versions of
Granny that I shipped there was a tree
that would do some kind of tracking of
pointers and I don't remember exactly
what it did it for but it tracked
basically some addresses of things and
the reason it was doing that is because
the address was just a convenient thing
that I knew would be unique right
because I knew that each of these data
structures existed somewhere in memory
and I know that no two of them could
access the same place in memory because
hey that's how allocation works you
can't store the same stuff in the same
place and so what I would do inside this
tree is I would just say oh well I've
got two pointers you know a pointer to
foo a and a pointer to foo B right and I
just was like out well I just need to
return the sort criteria for these two
things so it's fine just do like you
know I've got an int or something that I
need to return so I'll just do like a
minus B or something right so if a
subtracted for B if it turns out that a
produces a negative result that's what
will happen for my sort criteria if it
turns a pause result that's what if it's
zero then they're equal it's exactly
what I want and I don't care about
overflowing or wrapping or
anything here because I just as long as
it always produces the same comparison
between these two things in terms of
positive negative or zero I can use a
standard binary tree algorithm which is
what I was using and it will all just
work right okay
problem is that technically according to
the C++ specification if you have two
non care stars so if these are not 8-bit
pointers to 8-bit values right so let's
say struct foo has you know an int in it
so it's it's for wide or something like
this then pointer arithmetic is only
guaranteed to work if the two things
came from the same allocation right so
in other words if I have foo star array
equals you know Malik yeah I don't know
twelve times size of foo right if I do
an allocation and I say that you know
these things have to these things all
came from here and then I want to say
okay I've got my a is you know array
plus three and my B is array plus seven
then technically this is required to
work in the spec it is not undefined
behavior if I remember correctly it is
technically defined to be the distance
between these two things in the array
however if they came this way
so allocated from two different pools
now they no longer have to have any kind
of this doesn't have to work at all so
for example these could be two totally
different pointers totally different
this is still allowed to evaluate to
zero right now you may say why on earth
would anyone ever want that to be
allowed in a specification
right and I would like you to push that
thought on the stack for a minute
because this I guess this sort of
example will be perfect for me to
illustrate my opinion of this whole
subject matter in a moment when we get
to talking about how I feel about it
right which I don't know you know since
it is my stream presumably some button
asks this question because they want to
know what I think about it so I'll tell
you my opinion not that anyone else
cares what that is certainly not the C++
committee but so hold that thought for a
minute but hopefully that's pretty clear
and then just save your bewilderment of
why that would be for later because
there's a perfectly good explanation of
why it would be and also I think a
perfectly good explanation of why it's
ridiculous so I'll give those two to you
and you can kind of chew on them anyway
so mm-hmm now we get to the the latest
sort of thing about this
Chandler careth the aforementioned
google optimization guy in LLVM gave a
lecture where he was sort of talking
about this because and this I don't know
very much about so you know I don't know
if James Whitman's on the stream I know
he's a cpp aspect kind of person he
might be able to tell you more about
this aspect of it
I don't follow CP PP stuff anymore
obviously but I believe there is now
push on the C++ standards committee
called UB or unsigned behavior kind of
they have introduced this is kind of the
abbreviation for it there's kind of this
push to start dealing with undefined
behavior a little bit more to start like
nailing down you know how you sanitize
on a defined behavior from programs and
I don't know I mean I'll be honest with
you I don't really know I don't know why
it became more of an issue maybe because
people have been complaining about it
and they want to see people take more
action about this I don't really know so
you'll have to ask somebody else about
that but he gave a lecture at CB Picon
about undefined behavior and he kind of
gave you know examples of various
undefined behaviors
y-you know the compiler why they
implement certain things compiler that
you know why though some behind apply
and behaviors are happening and that
sort of thing and he also gave the you
know that I think the part if you saw my
tweet about the part I was very
uncomfortable that was for some reason
he called out a lot of game developers
people I respect and kind of the tone
was very odd it was like he was sort of
suggesting they were stupid or didn't
know what they were talking about or
were you know arguing about stupid
things I don't know it was just it felt
very dismissive and I didn't understand
why he was doing that cuz like it was
like Fabien you know who's I mean one of
the most meticulous programmers I know
so to suggest that he would be you know
unaware of the important aspects of this
issue was odd you know or John Blow who
like obviously you know I mean he's
writing his own compiler that's like
better than C++ so why you wouldn't you
know take what he says research that I
know so there was kind of like the it
was a totally weird and made me kind of
uncomfortable to call them out you know
it just felt really odd and dismissive
however Chandler later said on Twitter
after I kind of post so hasn't come
found it he said on Twitter that wasn't
his attention so I think that may have
you know that that may well have been a
case of him you know trying to be more
humorous about it then it came across or
something for all I know you know so so
I don't really know so maybe that part
just was you can just forget about you
know don't worry about that part of the
talk maybe it didn't come across as he
intended and it wasn't meant as sort of
a dismissal of some of these other
points of view I'm not sure but anyway
so he gave is talk about that and you
know I guess what I would say is the
talk if anything I I think maybe the
talk was meant to to persuade people
like me who you know maybe were not
zealots about this issue or hadn't been
involved in the discussion you know very
strongly or something in the past
we're baby to persuade them to not be so
much against the way that the C++ people
do it or I
really no but you know again because I
already know that the tone of the
lecture I misinterpreted I perhaps from
what he had expected I couldn't really
say what he was necessarily trying to
accomplish the lecture because maybe I
misheard him as to but it felt to me
like something where he was kind of
trying to put forward a model of
undefined behavior or a way of looking
at the problem that is in line with the
way the C++ spec and compiler vendors
want to look at it as being a productive
or useful way of looking at the problem
and to not be upset about it or
something like this but I did not find
it at all persuasive in that way and I
guess now I can ping-pong back to my
example and maybe give a clearer
explanation of why I am not persuaded by
that based on how I like to program and
what I expect my compiler to do and so
on
so let's ping-pong back here and see if
now I can sort of tie those things
together so we have a case where we are
trying to do a minus B and we would like
the compiler to give us back a positive
or a negative or a zero and we're
expecting zero to mean that they're
equivalent positive to mean sort one
direction negative to mean sort other
direction all we care about is it always
the values to the same thing and it only
evaluates to 0 if the pointers are the
same right that's what we wanted now the
reason why you do not get this behavior
necessarily when you do point arithmetic
and the reason why it's undefined in the
seats back if they come from two
different memory pools is because
there's ways of doing more efficient
determination of the arithmetic here in
the case where you know that the
pointers must be an even multiple of the
struct size away from each other okay so
if I know that this is four elements
long and I know that a and B are of from
the same pool I know that they must have
the same alignment relative to each
other so if this guy starts on a certain
boundary I know that this guy will be on
the same boundary
four right you you you will never have
them be separated by some other amount I
can't say make a and B be seven bytes
away from each other I could make them
be eight or I can make them before but
never seven right and what that means is
that remember C++ is specification of
the distance between two things is
technically going to be the distance
between the two pointers divided by the
size of the structure right now an
integer divided could be very expensive
so if this was for example not a power
of two let's say this was something like
this all right so it's 12 bytes long
well I don't want to issue an integer
divided by 12 what I want to do instead
is do some shorthand shifty
multiplication weirdness or something to
do a divided by 12 more efficiently than
issuing the integer divide and so that's
exactly what they'll do and they'll use
the compiler will use the fact that
these things are unknown alignment
relative to each other to make it happen
right it can do more efficient
arithmetic that way and avoid the divide
all together okay so you can see that
sounds pretty reasonable right that's a
very reasonable thing for a compiler to
want to do and the reason that they are
enabled to do that was specifically
because this is not allowed in the spec
it is undefined the compiler could omit
working code for a subtraction between a
and B or it can omit completely broken
code for that and in this case what it
decided to do was submit completely
broken code for that because it made the
code for the correct thing the correct
by spec thing to be much more efficient
right so hopefully you can see why that
makes some sense and I certainly don't
want a sir compiler writers under a bus
for doing something like that because
you can see why that would speed up a
bunch of cases in your program which are
based on doing exactly this right but
now let me try to explain why I think
this sort of thing
is really ridiculous and why I don't
like it and why I wish there was a
different attitude taken and more
specifically what that attitude actually
it's so the reason that I think this is
ridiculous is because I think it comes
at the problem from a fundamentally
misguided perspective not necessarily
from the perspective of the compiler
writer but from this perspective of the
specification authors right and here's
why if I am going to define subtraction
between two pointers a and B I think if
I am a diligent spec writer then I have
to choose to do one of two things either
I have to specify an inefficient but
complete option for doing so or I have
to specify multiple efficient options
that are complete this is the way I tend
to look at this sort of problem right
and what I mean by this is if I'm only
going to specify one a minus B operation
right which is sort of what we're saying
because this is the only way I can take
the difference between a and B right
there are not multiple subtraction
operators if I have a pointer a and I
have a pointer B and I say that a minus
B is my grammar for subtracting these
two pointers if I'm only specifying one
it must be the one that always works if
on the other hand I do not want to
handcuff the compiler writers or the
optimizers into a situation where they
cannot write efficient code for things
then that's fine but you then have to
give me options for doing the correct
thing right or you could say multiple
you know options that are complete some
are which are efficient some of which
aren't right and that would look like
this
- be right yields you know is always
correct a you know - /b right is correct
only in the same pool right that makes
very good logical sense to me because
they're what you're doing is you're
saying okay we know that this may be an
operation where people need to write it
in a way that could produce incorrect
results in certain cases so what we're
gonna do is provide two different
operators with that awareness and this
way when the programmer knows that they
are well within the specified usage of
this faster version of subtract they can
use it and when they are not they can
use the regular subtract and ensure that
there will be no gotchas right in my
mind there is no other sensible way of
approaching this problem and the reason
that I don't think there's any other
sensible way of approaching this problem
is because approaching it the other way
requires every programmer that ever uses
your language at any time to be
completely and fully aware of every
corner case in your entire specification
and is that really realistic I would
argue that there is no way that that
will ever be realistic most C C
programmers don't even know all of the
things in the spec let alone their
corner cases I would say 100% of all C++
programmers don't know everything that's
in the spec like there's probably one
thing in the spec somewhere that you
could pick for any C++ programmer and
they wouldn't know it they would be
wrong a little bit or they just didn't
know it was there right that's just the
nature of a 500 page document or
whatever it is at this point nobody's
gonna remember every last little bit and
maybe there is someone somewhere who
disproves that but they're like you know
the autistic programmer a guy in the
basement who just recites the spec while
like you know going like this
okay so from my perspective none of
these things should have ever come up
right there shouldn't be this idea that
the specification can leave all these
undefined things happening where the
undefined thing can be very
non-intuitive right you need to be able
to say that here is a very reliable
intuitive way that this thing works and
when we are going to depart from that in
some way we must make it very clear to
the programmer kind of like a Buy in if
you will that you are about to do
something where you understand the cost
of what you're doing in terms of these
minutiae right because no one's ever
gonna write this if they don't
understand the difference between those
two things and especially nowadays when
computers are incredibly fast
introducing a bug that could be very
problematic that only happens on certain
compilers with certain optimization
settings because you take advantage of
this automatically when someone just
wrote this that's really really hurtful
to programmer productivity confidence in
your compiler ability for programmers to
know that they've written things that
are correct right and possibly the
security of whole systems okay so in my
mind 90% of the undefined behavior
things in C and C++ that I've seen fall
into this camp they are problems with
the specification the specification
should not say undefined behavior
instead what it should do is specify a
reasonable intuitive behavior that can
be implemented on most machines
relatively well but perhaps more costly
and then they should say if we have all
these optimizations in mind for this
thing there will be a faster way of
doing it that you can opt into right
that you can opt into and you can opt
into this in various ways maybe one way
of doing it is changing the type of your
variables maybe you have an int and then
you have an int opt or something that
ops into a few things
maybe it's an operator based thing I
don't know
obviously for different circumstances we
could imagine different things being
more efficient but the point is simply
you should have to buy into these kinds
of optimizations that are extremely
non-intuitive based on what you might
expect to happen in it to a reasonable
programmer that the principle of least
surprise if you will okay here's thing
number two so let's talk about the other
case that I brought up over here so the
thing that I brought up over here was
the wraparound integer case right so let
me talk about that okay
so fundamentally all of there's a whole
family of things in this whole like you
know wrapping sort of family of things
or like you know casting you know
whatever implicit conversion I don't
know whatever you want to talk about
here but but for example in the C++ Beck
you know int unsigned has well-defined
wrapping Wow writing well-defined
wrapping so you do know that if you have
an unsigned integer it will wrap
properly
whereas int does not write so this may
not wrap properly but this I think is
guaranteed to that's my recollection
okay so the interesting thing about
these is this gets at another
fundamental weakness in the C spec and C
the suspect in my opinion which is that
types that generally the way that we
talk about types in C doesn't correspond
to what the processor does in a way that
is useful to the programmer right and
this comes from a fundamentally I think
misapplication or Mis a fundamentally
how should I put this it comes from a
fundamentally different worldview
between the people who work on the
specification from C++ and people like
me now that doesn't mean that that I'm
right and they're wrong but what it does
mean is I don't want to use C and C++
right what it means is it's not a good
language for me and I can say that
pretty definitively right and here's why
when you talk about things in these
sorts of terms and you say that int
unsigned has well-defined wrapping
behavior and int does not just the fact
that you have stated things in this way
completely ignores the fact that
programmers such as myself are not
trying to write an abstract program like
I am NOT trying to write a mathematical
proof in a book I am NOT trying to write
an abstract mathematical program that
can be preserved for generations on a
single piece of paper for future people
to look at and understand how it worked
what I am trying to do is program a
PlayStation 4 right or I'm trying to
program a PC I'm trying to program an
Xbox 360 right that's what I actually
need to have happen and this is sort of
the essence of Mike actin cpp con talk
for example where he talked about this
very civically to the C++ audience I
don't know that anyone found it
convincing but fundamentally speaking
the kind of programming that I do during
the day and that most people in the game
machine during the day is not about an
abstract programming to a language it's
about making something that runs on
actual hardware and in a way that is
specified very completely by that actual
hardware so when I type mmm you know
door PS I'm not trying to say some
abstract thing about how I might want to
write some values to memory at some
point what I'm trying to say is like put
a move ApS in there right I'm trying to
tell the processor what to do and that's
how I generally view what I do during
the day now you might say well why don't
you program in a semi language then
right and the answer is because well
it's vastly more complicated to program
in a semi language I would have to do
things like register allocation I'd have
to do things like think about how to
like put things on the stack and where
they should go right and I don't want to
do those things I appreciate the fact
that I have a higher level language to
do those things for me but what I don't
want my higher level language to do at
all is pretend that I'm on some kind of
an ill-defined system that doesn't
really know whether it uses
two's-complement
or not or whether or not the size of a
register is 64 bits I have no interest
in that because I know exactly what I'm
shipping on and what I want to be able
to do is write code confidently that
translates into well-defined behavior on
the processor I am targeting right so I
don't ever want you to say something
like well-defined rapping or non
well-defined rapping or honestly ever
int or unsigned int because as far as
I'm concerned these things are actually
the same thing they're a 64-bit register
that's going to get operated on and it
doesn't matter whether it's an inter and
unsigned int they get the exact same
instructions generated right for a huge
number of the operations you might do on
them there isn't like going to be two
different types of add for example
there's only going to be one and it
doesn't matter
it's an unsigned int or a signed it when
it starts to matter which one is which
is when I do something like you know a
comparison operator or something like
this when I do something that actually
takes the two's complement and has to do
a different thing for the two's
complement versions than the non two's
competition so it's actually operator
based signed and unsigned is actually
not about this value it's not storing
anything different it's storing the
exact same thing right the difference is
just how I'm operating on it and you can
see this brought in two very sharp
relief when we start switching to the
mmm sort of stuff where we just have
like you know mmm 128 or whatever it is
right or a sorry M 128 you know these M
128 times right well if you've ever
programmed anything with sim D even very
basic step acidity what you realize is
that if you start to do anything besides
floating-point if you do anything with
with non floating-point you are quickly
writing code that treats these registers
as a whole host of different things
right so the problem was kind of like
simple back here and you could sort of
say well there's just two-way street you
know it's an int or it's an unsigned int
so we'll just have those two things
right but when you start writing this
code you realize none and then uh no
registers and pressors nowadays there
can be like 50 different ways to think
about them like oh this thing was like 8
sliced signed values for this operation
and then the operation immediately after
it I was thinking of it as 4 sliced 16s
and blah blah blah right and so it
becomes very very clear very very
quickly is the view of the data in
memory is entirely based on the
operation that you're doing with it and
this in signed unsigned nonsense
is really just some convenience features
that people thought were cool back when
there were very simplistic ways of
looking at values and registers where
hey if I just specify that these two
types then the compiler can just always
infer
which of the operations I wanted to do
in the case where the CPU does have
differing operations for signed races
unsigned right and so I this is just a
complete waste of time like the fact
that anyone's even spending time looking
at that just kind of underscores to me
that I don't think about these that
where they do I would like a different
language I would like it to be based on
how processors work not on how language
designers think about things or types
what I'd rather have is a language that
just lets me say here are a bunch of
primitives they're based on what
processors can do right I can execute
any of them that I want if I try to use
one that doesn't isn't supported on a
particular platform that's just an error
so it's up to me to make different
compilation units or versions of
whatever to support the processors that
I want and then I never want you to talk
to me about spec behavior I don't want
you to specify anything the
specification for the behavior should be
whatever the processor does that's it
right and furthermore if I want some
extra behavior I'll tell you what it is
right if I don't want you to care about
values wrapping I'll tell you right I'll
make my own type and I'll mark it don't
care if it wraps and then the optimizer
knows it can do anything it wants and
doesn't have to worry about wrapping
right I'll tell you but don't
arbitrarily have a bunch of people in a
room decide that in sneed to be
specified is to complement and it
doesn't matter how they wrap someone
define don't do that that doesn't help
me at all that just hurts me right it
slows me down
it has bugs to my program and it doesn't
get me any closer to what I need which
is a more efficient version of assembly
language for programming actual
computers
that's what C is supposed to be right
and so I find this whole discussion to
be incredibly misguided I don't think it
addresses the actual problems it
certainly doesn't help me out and it's
going nowhere good as far as I can tell
right and so you
my preference as how things would go
forwards programming lies is to try and
go back to the original basic idea that
platforms specify their behaviors what
their CPU actually does the idea behind
the language is to allow the programmer
to write portable code when they don't
care by using things which are specified
very concisely and anytime there's any
question about what's going to happen
the programmer makes it explicit it is
not the optimizers job or the specs job
to leave things up in the air so that
random stuff can start happening to make
the code faster like that just doesn't
help me I don't like that I think that
hurts me a lot more than it helps right
so I feel like that is a fairly full
description of the problem I hope that I
hope that sort of clarify as my position
on that subject for anyone who actually
cares
so I think that took basically the
entire hour Allen says he's quite
satisfied and since you asked the
question originally that is good
can I definitely so think about uh yeah
I mean I feel like fundamentally I
really would just like to see some work
being done in the area of let's now that
we know what assembly language actually
looks like on modern CPUs in terms of
their instruction set can we make a
better version of like the original idea
behind C which was like make it easier
to write low-level code cuz right now
it's not really that way you know
so so yeah that's what I would say
that's what I would say and I don't know
like I don't know that would be that
difficult to do you know uh but it you
know it just seems like it just seems to
me like fundamentally not that hard of a
problem to do this part of it and I feel
like with all of the effort that's
expended on C++ spec and compilers and
they never improve the core programming
experience you know they never get they
never actually get down and fix the fact
that it's just I it's this huge
nightmare to program and do basic stuff
like work with you know vector registers
but that's you know that's why people
program in these languages still you
know people people writing web apps
aren't writing them in C and C++ you
know the people still using C and C++
are the people who care about these sort
of things to a certain degree right I
mean I feel like the people who care
simply about using high-level languages
I've got to think they would be leaving
C++ in droves right because C++ is not a
very good high-level language you know
it's not I feel like you could easily
find a better one somewhere else if
you're just if you don't care about the
the low-level aspects of it and pointers
and things like that why are you using
it you know why aren't you using a
Python or rust or go or I don't know
right there's all these other options
out there and the C++ spec is filled
with you know tons of these crazy things
and none of them are particularly you
know easy to use or complete or anything
else right so
let me see it maybe I'll take one more
if it's quick otherwise I think I'm
gonna go
Andrew JDR has one that I can answer I
think pretty quickly but not in a very
satisfying way curious if you've
experimented with different 3d polygons
triangulation approaches and settled on
something that you use under most
circumstances and the answer there is no
because I have not really had to do that
I probably will have to do that in
future incarnations of our engines at
Mali
so maybe I'll have more of opinion about
that five years from now not that it'll
be relevant to you at that point I'm
sure but I mostly I just have not had to
do con like con K you know eat a 3d
polygons is pretty trivial to
triangulate if it's if it's convex right
so there's really no need to get fancy
if it's convex but if it's concave which
is I assume what you're talking about
you know well well maybe you're not
maybe you just mean if you want it up
res it because you said constrained
along de Launay triangulation so I don't
know I guess I should clarify first
though you're just talking about adding
triangles to inside of a triangle that's
already that's already come concave and
convex or you talking about concave yeah
come on okay so yeah I've never really
had to deal with that and I think it
sounds like a fun problem you know I
would like to play with something like
that it sounds fun
but I have it I do know that Sean
Barrett did some work with this because
he wrote a flash emulator for Rad's
called Iggy I don't know if I can
why are you not working streams still
working DNS server doesn't look like
it's working that's not a good sign oh
alright
not great not great anyway there's a
thing called eggy I can't get to the
site to show you but there's thing
called eggy that is a flash emulator for
for games like if people want you know
to play back flash animations and he you
know cuz flash that you do arbitrarily
you know arbitrary triangle things or
whatever arbitrary polygons and animate
them around or whatever and so he wrote
a thing that will triangulate those and
I don't actually know what he settled on
using but you know you could ask him
some time when he's streaming to talk
about it because he probably has an
opinion I mean he probably looked at a
couple different things and picked an
algorithm for some particular reason so
I don't know yeah so I guess only the
DNS server got got whacked right because
it looks like it just can't resolve the
DNS server but it's not a problem
resolving traffic so traffic still going
through but the but the DNS server is
just out right
and let's see
yeah
I think that's it for short questions
think that is it it's probably going to
wind down
all right
alright I think we've got everything all
the rest of the questions look like kind
of involved ones so I'm gonna go and of
course I can't get to the internet so
that's always good
anyway thank you for joining me for a
special edition of handmade Hero for a
chat which we don't often do but we did
tonight I'll be back next week I think
it depends on whether I think I will
probably be moving the handmade hero
machine to the office at some point
because we had to get a static IP
address for the office for various
contractual reasons so although it won't
be plugged into anything I could just
sit the handmade hero thing there and
use that and stream from the office
which I might decide to do if I do do
that will probably take a week off at
the point where I move it and get it
back up and running there but I don't
know if and when that's gonna happen so
as always check out the schedule bot and
and figure out whether whether that
happens by that the handy a sketch with
that anyway thank you very for a free
hat chat I think it will be back next
week if not we'll be back the week after
that one way or the other and that is
about it for now
have fun programming this weekend and
yeah try not to hit any undefined
behavior in your compiler until next
time take it easy everyone and I'll see
you on the Internet