hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here I show recode a complete game live
on stream I think today I'm gonna go
ahead and get started on making some
modifications to our world storage I was
talking about this doing this about two
weeks ago but I wanted to create a
memory viewer so we could kind of see
some of the results of what we were
doing in a more direct way and so that's
exactly why we built the over the past
two weekends we built a little thing
that tracks and shows all of our memory
it's pretty cool actually it's pretty
happy about that
looks nice and it allows us to see
what's going on in there pretty easily
what I'd like to do today however is get
started there's we could there's some
more stuff we probably will do to our
memory view in the end like add some
scrolling and maybe some better display
of some stuff you know it's not perfect
but it's good enough for now I think I'd
like to go ahead and get started on that
modification that I wanted to make let
me just go ahead and show what does that
there we go
let me just show what I'm talking about
here and then what kind of we'll get
started on the new stuff so if you take
a look at the game as it runs today now
we didn't have this ability to before
but now we do we can go in here and look
at things like what our memory layout is
in this case this shows our arena's that
are currently active and it shows you
know who's got what memory allocated
where again this is pretty nice it shows
us how our breakdown is and it breaks
down exactly as I want most of our
memory is spent an asset
caching room that we can use for caching
assets specifically sounds and that's
pretty much what we want ideally we
would have most of our memory taken up
there and the reason for that is because
it's very fungible if we need to run on
a lower-end machine we can always just
reduce the amount of caching we have
there or use lower quality sounds and so
on so seeing your memory footprint end
up mostly an asset storage is kind of
what you want if your game is taking a
ton of memory there's not a lot you
could do about that right and so it
gives you a lot less flexibility to
target lower end hardware if your game
is taking
by the memory well then there's really
nothing you can do you've got to change
you know you've got to go work on your
game code if you want to ship on
something it doesn't have a gigabyte of
memory available for it so we can take a
look at this we also have to build a
debug information on off this is
information that's strictly used to
record things like our profiling in our
memory so we don't really count that
because again that just goes away when
we compile our release version so we
don't really need to see that just have
call sight view that allows us to see
where this memory is being taken so we
can kind of see like specifically in
which pieces of the code or responsible
for the majority of our memory it's
pretty easy to see here who's taking up
most of our space you know we've got a
sort of a 70 Meg layout for our game
mode and 60 megabytes of that is right
here and so that kind of tells us who is
taking the lion's share of things if we
don't already know this tells us pretty
quickly what's going on with that so
that's nice too and finally we have like
our block layout diagram this is really
nice because it's an easy way to
visually see what's going on
and you can see quite clearly here like
here's all the assets or it's just a
giant big block that's just used for
audio streaming it doesn't do anything
else and so that's you know again like I
want to see it this way this up here is
the part that concerns me a little bit
more this is our world storage each one
of these is a chunk of storage in the
world data structs and I don't know if
you can sort of see what's going on here
but basically this is the most recent
block of storage and it hasn't been
filled up yet that's why it's the most
recent one right things are getting
added in there and this is what concerns
me at the moment and what concerns me a
little bit more long-term and one of the
reasons I want to sort of start to work
on the enemy system a little bit now
because we're kind of moving into a
place where that's really the last thing
we're gonna be working on if you think
about it like almost the entirety of the
remaining game implementation we have is
going to be in the entity system because
the entities are what sort of determines
the gameplay so as we're moving
transitioning into working more and more
just on how entities work and how they
behave this concern
me because we really don't have that
many entities in the world right now now
you know I guess that's a it's deceptive
to say that because we sort of do I mean
there actually is if you can think about
the fact that all of this stuff every
last thing here is an entity the ground
pieces are an entity these or enemies
out here that's an Emmy that's an ID so
there are quite a few entities if we
actually zoom out and look at how this
whole world is defined there there's
quite a few actually so it's not like
it's that small of a world but would we
like to support much larger worlds
absolutely and everything else in our
system does that just fine the moment
you know there's nothing else in the
system that's going to prevent us from
creating giant worlds the memory burden
is the only thing that would sort of put
a limit on it and obviously there are
things we can do in our system if we
really wanted to support absolutely
ridiculously huge worlds that are
effectively impossible to ever play we
can only stream to disk and stuff like
that but we really haven't gotten to
that kind of a point with our entity
system I don't think because like I said
there's just a ton of fat in there right
now that I would like to remove and it's
not that difficult for me to go ahead
and remove it so what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna start by sort of talking about
where we're at with that memory layout
and what I'd like to do to fix it and
why so it looks like somehow I got my
shell closed there we go
get that back up here I guess I never I
just clicked on remedy so that's why it
was never open I didn't close it
I just never opened it so if we take a
look at handmade hero what with the
policy we've been following so far is
that we aren't working on the enemy
system that's been the policy I'm
applying so far so what I did was every
entity is just a bag of garbage you can
throw anything in there you want every
entity has everything there's no design
to it and it's fine and that's very
intentional because the last thing I
think you want to do and I've said this
many times the last thing you want to do
when you're designing a system is pick a
design up front it's the absolute worst
thing you could ever do
is the side I'm gonna use an entity
component system before you've even
written any of your game you make this
choice I find that to be an absolutely
terrible way to design code and the
reason is because you're deciding a
solution before you have seen the
problems right and solutions to problems
that don't exist aren't solutions at all
they're just wasted work and so what I
like to do instead is defer my solutions
till I actually have my problems and in
this case what that means is everything
in the game is just a big bag of crap
right in this case until we actually
have some idea of what we want to do
with it right and so this particular
situation is starting to bring up a
actual coherent problem I can talk about
solving and I can see how I would want
to solve it and so now I think is a good
time to add a capability to our entity
system that does address something
that's happening in there that I would
like to solve and can think of a
concrete way to solve it and that thing
is that I would like to start adding
very large elements to our entity system
like these and when they are placed in
here they make the entities too big
right so if I look at how much space was
being taken up you know by this ground
cover for example when we look inside
the the memory view and I did this
before we see how much space that's
taking up relative to everything else
right you can just kind of see how big
that is if I were to change it so that
we don't have storage for the ground
cover just the ground cover nevermind
the lighting Point State which is also
large or any of these other sorts of
things if I run that with you know two
and reduce the memory footprint by that
much you can see this dis creased
dramatically just from that one member
right like if we imagine that our
previous size was like a bound on how
big the world could be just removing
that one member from our entities would
have allowed the world to be twice as
large
and so that's just you know to give you
an idea of what I'm talking about
and that's gonna be true of everything
that we potentially add here right
there's so many different pieces of
information that we might want to start
covering and if you imagine all sorts of
potentially fairly complicated things
that are listed here like path finding
information and lighting and ground
cover decals footprints you know who
knows what those sorts of things all add
up and when not every entity is using
them and you're storing the entire world
with perhaps tens or even hundreds of
thousands of entities in it that
multiplier is just too high so the
question is what do we actually want to
do to address this problem well this
first part of the problem like I said
shows me an obvious way like address it
because I have a concrete problem and I
can design a concrete solution the
concrete problem is that during actual
visibility so when the entities on the
screen lighting and ground cover are
visual effects that need to be
represented and I would like them to not
have to be recomputed every frame right
I would like to be able to do things
like track the ground cover or the
lighting and I'd like them to be stable
across frames and remember information
across frames that's relevant to the
gameplay perhaps even down to relatively
specific things that happen such as how
grass gets trampled down or how the
lighting is propagated throughout the
scene but once I move out of an active
region I don't necessarily need to
remember those things if the user is
actively looking at a piece of terrain
and I don't store exactly how that
terrain got modified they will see the
change occur right like they would
notice a difference if they're looking
at it but if something goes outside of
their view and they go three or four
rooms away
and then they come back to it all that
they really will remember is roughly
what the state of that area was right
was this thing burned was this thing lit
whatever right but they won't
necessarily remember the exact state of
things so I can afford to potentially
forget really specific things like was
this specific piece of grass in this
specific place right and so what I'd
like to do is introduce sort of a second
level cache and I talked about this
again when I was talking about adding it
two weeks ago and this is what I'd like
to add now a second level cache for
things that are purely cosmetic which
can sort of be lawfully remembered so I
just kind of need to remember how much
grass roughly was there on this patch
with maybe like a single scalar that
needs to get remembered but what I don't
need to remember is the exact
arrangement of the grass on this patch
that I can just get rid of and
regenerate it later when this thing
comes back into view and so I'm looking
at a way of sort of taking the ground
cover field or the lighting field I'm
looking at ways to essentially compress
that down and store it in a small
permanent way when I need to and then be
able to decompress it later now because
of this sort of how should I say this
whilst thinking about this so while
that's kind of in your brain right and
you're thinking to yourself about the
ramifications of making such a change
well I've always since the very
beginning of the new system suggested
that we would probably have something
like this where we compress entities
down into something that only remembers
the things they actually use and these
are sort of related in a sense right
meaning storing sort of lossy versions
of certain visual elements is very
similar to compressing entities down
based on only what we actually care
about remembering and so for example if
you imagine an entity that doesn't have
hitpoints well we don't really need to
store hitpoints for that entity right
and so these two things are actually
kind of they feel the same right these
two things feel very similar in that if
you have a set of entities that want to
be compressed based on usage and also
lossy storage that might want to happen
it sort of gets me thinking about
alternative ways of dealing with our
entities in general and let me discuss
that with sort of giving you what I'm
thinking and I hadn't really thought of
this when we first started typing in
entities so it wasn't something I was
looking at again it's in that kind of
comes organically out of how you end up
building the system so consider this we
want to be able to work with entities in
a in sort of what I would call their
full form and that is something that
looks a lot like this sort of bloated
entity structure that we're talking
about here bloated in the sense that it
has a ton of stuff in it that we don't
actually need in a lot of cases but it's
very easy to work with like that why is
it very easy to work with like that well
it is because there's no restrictions on
what we can do right any piece of code
can just write to any piece of the
entity and add capabilities to it
willy-nilly right there's no hard
constraints on what an entity is or
isn't and so it gives us complete
flexibility and furthermore it gives us
that complete flexibility with no
runtime cost at all at the moment right
for the routines are actually operating
on it because we don't have to do things
like searching a list of properties to
find if it has one that we're talking
about we don't need to allocate
properties on-the-fly to attach new
properties to things none of that has to
happen in our system and so the runtime
cost that we are paying right now is
actually just strictly a memory cost
it's a memory
and with cost so instead of having a
computational cost and a memory
bandwidth cost that's just less of
looking through things like saying and
the component system might do or some
kind of a system that had any properties
attached to it or suffering the
restrictions that come from a thing
where entities are sort of fixed in
their conceptualization and like this
entity is this kind of monster and only
stores the information for that kind of
monster so it can never get any other
things applied to it right instead of
having that for question restriction or
the restriction of having to have all of
this busy work where things are finding
or you know on every piece of on every
single time anything happens with the
entity we sort of have the best of both
worlds here and we pay the cost only at
the time when we actually need to
consider paging memory around right
because that it's like the cash cost is
the only cost for paying and so far it's
unclear that we're really paying much of
that cost right and so the question is
is it perhaps possible to retain the
usage of the bloated entity structure
such that we really can keep using it as
arbitrarily and as flexibly as we watch
perhaps even going further and allowing
sort of arbitrary size lists in here and
stuff to even write like perhaps even
more bloated than it already is can we
do something that supports that and
potentially gets rid of the memory
bandwidth costs of packing and unpacking
storage for these sorts of things and/or
the bloated memory footprint cost of
just storing them at all right and what
I started to realize was that well
here's what we're doing we have a begin
sim call and if you remember the way
that begins sim call it works is it goes
through each of the world sort of
buckets we have
essentially amounts to a sparse voxel
storage for our world right I all of our
entities are just kind of binned based
on where they're located and when you go
to simulate a particular region of the
world what you're doing is you're
gathering all of the buckets that might
contribute to that region of the world
but that's all we're doing fundamentally
and so when we call this begin sim call
here what we do is inside begin world
change we we sort of unpack all of our
entities into like an active set and we
set this up because we thought someday
we might want to do that unpacking in a
real sense but right now all we do is
actually go in and grab that for it here
yep we thought that someday we might
actually want to do that decompression
so we do actually have a step here where
we're like hey let's actually unpack the
entities that are that are involved and
I believe we do that right here right we
take this destination we say you know
this should really be a decompression
step and we copy it right and then when
we do an end world change we copy it
back right so you can see us doing that
here and we have a little bit of packing
that we do but a very little bit right
it doesn't really there's very little to
it it's it's really just that right so
now the question is you know
if we're paying this cost here to like
pack and unpack entities we have to ask
ourselves from one frame to the next how
much difference do you think there is in
terms of entities that we've used like
that that we unpacked last frame and the
entities we need to unpack this frame
right and the chances are it's almost
exactly the same as the user moves right
a few thing a few new entities might
page in on the side like maybe five to
ten percent of our entities may page it
on the side and maybe five to ten
percent of our entities pay will page
out on the other side right but like
other than that there's really very
little going on in terms of the packing
and unpacking we literally packed all of
our entities last frame up only to
unpack them all again this frame so this
got me thinking well why don't instead
of us thinking of simulation as
unpacking all of our entities simulating
them and repacking them why don't we
just assume instead that the simulation
just works on unpacked entities and all
it really does is ask the world storage
to make sure that any entities it's
going to touch are unpacked but if those
were already unpacked from last frame
they just stay unpacked that system
could then pack only those things that
are no longer being used by the
simulation and unpack ones that are but
essentially act as a rolling cache that
doesn't require any packing or unpacking
at all most of the time does that make
sense what I'm saying I hope it does but
we're gonna go ahead and do this over
the next few weeks and so hopefully if
it's not clear what I'm saying you'll
a couple chances to sort of see what I'm
talking about here and so fundamentally
there's a couple wait phases in which I
want to you know sort of make this
change take place and what I'd like to
do here is say okay let's start by
assuming that this is actually just a
reference table so when we say begin
world change what I'd like to do is say
that the sim region entities here this
thing right here right so that where we
sort of say look we've got some number
of entities that we're gonna unpack and
we need to store them in here
excuse me what I want to do is make that
set of entities there I want this to be
a reference table basically so instead
of referring to entities directly these
will just be like pointers to entities
or something like that right and
furthermore if you look at the way we're
doing things
right now we've got this entity pointer
here in our entity hash what it makes me
think is well maybe actually the entity
hash could just be the only thing there
is so meaning this doesn't actually have
to be there anymore and we just walk the
entity hash to do stuff right now why do
I want that well I want that because if
we just start using entity pointers
everywhere and don't ever look at some
like compact array that implies that we
could just point into a cash held by the
world for each entity that we know is
stable up until the time when we stop
our simulation for this block right so
we can start the sim use pointers into
the world sort of l2 cache of unpacked
entities simulate them all be done tell
the world now is a good time to pack any
these that you think need to be to stay
under a particular memory limits for how
many unpacked entities we keep around
for example and off we go
right make sense so that's really what
I'm thinking and so the first thing I
want to do again I'm just going to start
to explore to that change the first
thing I'd like to do is change this
entity structure to be something that
will generate an error everywhere it's
used and what that's gonna allow me to
do is just inspect my code to see what I
think the impact of this change will be
without ever actually doing any code in
the first place right so what we can see
here is there's a connect entity
pointers call and what that's doing is
really like sort of Swizzle enough the
Swizzle hangs around word its connecting
up entities to other entities in the
system right and I think that that is
something that will probably have to
always happen when we at the beginning
ending of simulation and the reason for
that is those pointers that we're using
if we you know maybe we will stop using
pointers all together and we'll just
always use hashes to connect the thing
but regardless because when we do a PAC
on things we can't necessarily know who
needs to be who needs to be updated to
not have a pointer we don't want
pointers sitting around inside the we
don't want pointers from entities to
other entities generally to persist
outside of the simulation right so when
we start the sim inside there you can
have it pointers enemies pointing
enemies all you want but when you finish
you want to get rid of those right now
again I'm not really sure that we want
that in the first place because I'm not
sure we really want to I'm not sure we
really need entity entities pointing to
other entities instead of just using a
hash by like their ID
so I'm not sure we really need to do
that and we may want to look at just
removing that and using the hash instead
that's sort of a separate issue right
but anyway so that's fine we could just
loop over the the hash there or whatever
like we got plenty of yeah there's
really there's really nothing weird
going on there what by the way is this
entity hash occupants are used for you
know what hold on one second I want to
see what that's used for before I do any
more of this I don't really remember
what we're doing with that
so it looks like that is literally just
to speed up clearing so that we can just
clear that field it's what it looks like
so I'm assuming we yeah we literally
just added that to speed up this clear
so that instead of having to clear all
the entities we just cleared or it so
the instead of having to clear the
entire entity hash table we just cleared
the occupancy table I think
I mean looking at that's the only thing
I could think that that would be doing
right um and I don't see anything else
that that's good for so that's we don't
really have to care about that that's
totally fine and would not be affected
by this change at all really okay just
want to make sure I knew what we were
doing there looks like that's just for
accelerating that clear all right so
this is us just allocating the array
again that's nothing and this is us I'm
talking into the array again totally
fine here's us packing back up here's
this adding an entity again none of
these things really would be implicated
there I don't think this is testing all
of the entities in the system to look
for a camera here's us looking for
traversable x' and again we want to do
these by spatial queries anyway so again
this is really totally fine yes so like
all of this stuff I would say
all of this stuff I would say is really
not not a problem so so I think this is
pretty trivial right I think we could
really like we could pretty much just
get rid of this as something that anyone
ever used right and we could pretty
easily move it out into out into the
world structures so if we go into the
world structures here right we can see
is here's the world and here's where
everything is stored it's in this chunk
cache here and this I don't know what
we're gonna do with this is just for
maps and stuff so that we can ignore for
now that'll be something we look at a
little bit later but if you imagine it
here inside this this world part here we
had something that was literally like an
entity cache so in here we've got like
like this and so we've got this unpacked
entity cash and the unpacked entity
cache just kind of tells us like kusu
and why and where and what's going on
for unpacked entities we would have
essentially the same thing that we have
inside the sim region right this would
be there and the difference is this
would just persist from frame to frame
and when you went to like you know
unpack things or you know as you were
unpacking things this would keep track
of who was unpacked and who wasn't and
it wouldn't have to redo work that was
already done right so if you unpack a
bunch of things on frame 0 on frame 1
you then try to unpack most of the same
things you don't do any work you just
get pointers back in here of the already
unpacked entities and that way in an
infant in fact I'm trying to think so
you know in this world chunk here where
we've got this world entity block right
I'm not sure why this is if a pointer
would be better here because it is a
pointer I think we previously did that
at the Donmar so the answer is we are
doing that in here in this world chunk
we would just say oh you know we just
need some way of saying whether this
thing is in the expanded set or not
right and so like maybe something like
this
you know I'm saying so we have something
like this we've got like an unpacked
world chunk and in here we would say
like alright we've got an entity array
that's you know keeping track of what's
happening inside you know the unpacked
version of the world chunk and then when
we can have is sort of the same thing
right and this one can probably be
significantly smaller right because
there's not that many world chunks that
are unpacked anyway so you're not going
to have to look through a whole heck of
a lot of them unlike this which could
have lots and lots of chunks in them
like this has like thousands of chunks
potentially or even maybe tens of
thousands this has a hundred or
something right and so you really don't
have to make this particularly large in
order to avoid long change so if we have
an unpack hash there and we imagine
something like this the only thing that
makes me nervous about this at all is
just the fact that I don't like having
to have entity Headroom in every one of
these entity arrays I and so that part
is maybe a little less good than it then
it should be maybe um and so I think you
know it's hard for me to say but I think
the way I would like to handle this
in fact yeah I'm pretty sure so if you
think about what happens here right
we've got these different world chunks
and when we go to pack a world chunk
back up what we really want to do is
pack all the enemies that might have
moved into that world chunk so storing
that like this isn't really what I want
right all I really needed to do was
store whether it was unpacked or not so
honestly I think maybe it's okay to just
say was this thing unpacked or not right
so in here you know we've got this thing
where we got the XYZ coordinates for it
and then we've got some additional
information this is already unbalanced
so if you look at how this is structured
right you really want it to look like
this anyway there's already effectively
an unbalanced earth this is eight we've
got eight there's eight and four right
so it's already a little on the line I
don't feel too bad of just having at
least at the moment it can just be as
ab32 but we could make this flags if we
wanted to in the future just say is it
unpacked or not right look does it exist
in the unpacked set or not I think that
might be better and then we could say
there's a giant list of entities in here
that we pack and unpack into and then
that's like it right that's all we do I
think that's probably best
something like that
and so if we do something more like that
I think then we're in much better shape
and we don't really have to do any
additional work I don't think when it
asks us to unpack a chunk all we do is
we do exactly what we're doing before
but now instead of always adding the
things from the chunk to the entity
array we instead look at the unpacked
value here and if it's already unpacked
we just don't do anything right and
that's it later when we go to pack up
all we do is say if we were going to
pack a particular chunk that we've
determined isn't being used anymore well
all we really have to do there is loop
to the entity array packing up entities
into that chunk that belong in the chunk
and marking them is no longer in our
unpacked entity set but that's it really
and I think that I think that works
pretty well right I think that's good I
think we're good to go at that point the
only thing that I'm not sure about how
we would do and maybe I'll to start
typing in the actual routines and see
where it leads us but the only thing
that I'm not sure about here is I don't
know how to detect which world chunks
should now be packed right and so that's
why I kind of think we need some sort of
a list like an LRU sort of a list here
that just says here are the chunks that
I did unpack and now you are gonna have
to pack them back up again at some point
right
and that part I don't really have a
coherent idea for you can think about
what the codes gonna be in your head
right so you're gonna do a sim step and
maybe like at the end of every frame who
knows or maybe at the end of every sim
step you're just gonna make a call it's
like hey PAC the least recently used
chunks as necessary right so if you've
got a bunch of world chunks sitting
around that haven't been used in several
frames pack them back up because they're
probably not needed anymore and the
problem is how do we know right it's
pretty easy for us to store in the world
chunk like instead of this unpacked
value we could store a like how like a
timestamp like when was the last unpack
of this thing that's pretty easy for us
to do but what's not so easy for us to
do is to know without looping through
literally all of the world chunks in the
system who's the least and so we kind of
need some secondary right you see what
I'm saying we need some kind of
secondary structure here and maybe we
just store like another list of that or
something that we cycle through I don't
know and like I say I just I really just
don't have a solid idea for exactly how
that should work so let's start by just
doing the initial pack unpack stuff as
if we knew so I'm just gonna pretend
that I can loop over those at some point
and figure it out and then we can after
I'm done with that change figure out how
the heck we're gonna do it right well
well after we get everything else done
which is plenty of work to do for today
then after all that said and done and uh
tomorrow or sometime then we get started
to talk about all right how do we
actually know which world chunks get get
repacked right how do we know who's the
ones to do and we don't have to do that
right away we could just pack
everybody back up right as a start but
but yeah all right so let's see here you
know what else
unpacked may be superfluous because if
first block is zero then you are
unpacked right so we may not even need
this I'm gonna get rid of that for a
second just to see if that's true
because I think it might be so we'll see
all right so anyway let's go ahead and
make this happen if we can and and go
from there
all right so when we're doing connect
entity pointers again for the short term
what I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna step
through the entity hash cure and use
that as the way we loop over all
entities if that makes sense so in here
where we do connect any pointers and we
call that on the sim region I'm going to
introduce basically a helper here and
that helper is going to be something
that allows me to sort of easily iterate
over all entities so something like this
right
and I would say like iterate all
entities I passed the sim region in and
then I would say something like this
right so basically just a thing that
allows me to loop over all of the
entities and then this here is the only
part I think I would have to actually
replace right something like that I
since this is a thing that essentially
only loops over a pointer we could
probably also just do this right that's
probably fine too and so in the interest
of keeping it simple maybe we'll just
say that and that way we can basically
turn all loops into something that looks
like this what I'm going to do ahead of
time here is actually just sort of
define this as a stub so that I can
compile and see if everything works and
then we can kind of go from from there
so we have an entity integrator that
gets returned from iterate all entities
that needs to take the sim region went
and we would also have an advanced call
which takes this iterator and that would
really be it that's the entirety of it
and so I think if I then compile I'm
hoping that that will give me an easy
way to replace the routines I was using
with a utility function right so here is
an example of me sorry not that one ooh
create under you don't care about right
now so here's another example of
something that that loops over all of
them right and so again I'm just going
to do the same thing this time we wanted
something called test entities so I'm
just gonna make it test entity but
otherwise it's exactly the same here is
another one right and so we'll go ahead
and do that
same exact thing and again a lot of
these want to use a facial partition so
these will get a lot of these will get
replaced anyway again which is good
because it means that we really don't
care how inefficient this is because
we're not really going to rely on this
in the final product anyway so this is
just a stopgap measure and we don't have
to be too concerned about that all right
um so yeah looks good to me
let's clean up the compilers from that
and then look at the places that we
can't replace with that particular thing
so there there there and there this is
just a different word it's not called
sim region it's just called region I
should have I didn't really mean to
recompile there but I did oh well
did we not replace this guess we didn't
get that far I don't know what the sim
region is in this case oh it's just
called some region so that's pretty easy
and it's like one more
okay so that allows all of our
iterations to work and we can just
implement this when we're ready and so
now really what we got to look for is
the rest of this stuff
I think the way I'd like to do this now
is just by actually not doing anything
other than moving exactly the thing that
we previously had into the world code so
if that makes sense like I'm not
actually going to implement any of this
stuff we talked about I'm just gonna
change the location of the way it's
currently working to work inside the
world struct that's all and then we will
progressively sort of add features to
that until it becomes what I was sort of
talking about alright so in here we're
gonna need something that does this
right like obviously that needs to
happen because we need space to store
this stuff and so we can have that
happen as we go in here where we're
doing sort of this dest bit here this
unpack that's occurring right here you
can sort of see the identity the hash is
something that wants to probably remain
inside the sim region side of things and
the DEF P plus equals chunked out the
stuff that has to probably keep
happening to I would suggest because
[Music]
every frame the entities have to sort of
be centered around our simulation origin
so I feel like that part is gonna have
to persist right like that part's not
really gonna that that part we we have
to always do so we have to look at that
these two things is always having
happening
this part yeah all of this stuff this
all looks like you stuff it would
normally happen right
so here where we do the remove world
chunk right we're pulling this chunk off
we're doing all the work to it what I
can't quite understand here though is
where the copy happens oh no I can't
right there we already looked at it so
there it is so again looking at this
stuff here this is all stuff that's
really simmer sim region related but
everything above it's sort of isn't so I
feel like a lot of this stuff and let me
look at that identity the hash yeah so I
feel like if we kind of group this stuff
together here we can kind of see what
we're dealing with right in terms of the
stuff that's getting unpacked that seems
like all of it and then this stuff just
has to happen on everybody anyway so
that's the tack I'm gonna take again
this is fairly subtle code so you can
see I'm being careful trying to think of
three relatively carefully here to the
extent that kam and so really what I'm
looking at is this entire preamble
really all the way down through here
because I think what I'm looking for
right
that's pretty deep a lot of loops there
a lot of loops a lot of ifs so that's
that's the like three dimensional loop
over everything removing those in there
and similarly the add to free list part
of things
so after this chunk is is removed right
like when we grab it out here we do want
to do this part as well I'm gonna try
and get all this stuff out here not sure
what this was I think just a guard
against the enemy count being too high
but I think
I think that should be fine and so
coming through here looking at what's
happening this is going to be a four eye
loop here over all the entities in the
system and then this stuff is going to
happen as before so connect entity
pointers and why would say is that if
you look at how this is actually
happening here since all of the entities
you know if I look at connect entity
pointers in fact if I look at where we
are calling connect any pointers you can
see that it's sort of just a one-off I
think I might make that just part of
this routine directly so I want to get
this sort of out of here and in some
region where that happens I think I want
to just make that be something that
happens right because I think we want to
do this all in one loop now that makes
sense so I'm gonna get rid of this
that's gonna go away and in here where
we sort of do this stuff
I'm gonna say let's do this all in one
pass right oh well but adding to the
hash has to happen before we can do this
sadly so it still will be two passes it
looks like that's too bad just I think
it's too bad so this is a two pass at
which I don't love we could maybe look
at that a little bit
and to me that sort of argues again this
like traversable reference nonsense I
feel like maybe those just need to not
be pointers anymore anyway and they need
to go through the hash table because
again you can see like I have to do a
second loop because I need to do one
loop to fill the hash table and you
another loop to connect them up it just
seems kind of bad especially because
like we don't even know if anyone's
gonna need these right we're sort of
freed assuming that we're saving time by
converting those ID reference by ID to
reference my pointer but we don't even
really know that we are and so I
suspected that Smith might just be a
waste of time
and that's pretty high on my list of
things to look at after we're done I'd
like to make sure that that we do that
the right way because I think probably
this is the wrong way all right so I
think I think everything we need is
right here I think that's all we needed
to really do so if I go ahead and sort
of change desk to be entity here
I think that's just true everywhere
right because all this code came from
the same interior so it should just be
dust everywhere it wasn't two different
parts I think that was the same part all
this looks the same to me so I think
that's all good so we've got the this
loop here and I'm hoping maybe we'll
just get rid of this loop so we can look
at that a little bit later on but for
now it basically looks like this and so
what we need to do inside the world
struct itself right is this call here so
we've got this this happens on startup
but but this call here where I'm going
to like unpack world region maybe I'll
call this ensure region is unpacked
something like that that's gonna pass in
the like min chunk max chunk positions
that you're trying to use like so and
then obviously we need the worlds that
you're unpacking and then when we have
that map into sim space call with the
sim region that part I don't think I
want to actually pass the sim region in
here for any particular reason because
we don't eat it anymore so what I'd like
to do is that map into sim space when
you look at what that's actually doing
you can see that it's just doing a
subtract on the the origin right so what
I'd rather do is I'd rather just have
that origin this this part here I'd
rather just have that be something that
that gets passed in right and so when
we're doing that I'm sure region is
unpacked
I feel like this allows us to
essentially take that map in the same
space bit there and just make that
happen directly so on here we would just
say all right the chunk position that
you're talking about
we're just gonna
do that subtraction in line here and off
we go right now the other thing we could
consider is we again when we're doing
that that chunk dealt dealt a bit here
that's the part that we need to add to
these entities right in order to get
them centered properly well you know
what now I look at it okay so we don't
really want to do that
we don't really want to do that do we
because the well yeah I don't know
so the problem that we have here is the
world position of entities is it's just
a vector right and it's stored relative
to the chunk when it's packed and it's
but it's considered relative to the sim
origin when it's not and so I'm not sure
how to that's the one piece of
information that's a little bit
ambiguous as to how you would handle it
here right because since you on when you
unpack this the sim region itself is not
going to know whether someone's position
has been adjusted yet right so it
doesn't really know what to do
it doesn't really know what to do about
that
I mean if we're more explicit about this
then what you'd have to do is something
more like this so if you look at kind of
what has to happen if we were to do like
a literal translation of what would go
on then you can kind of see it's a bit
nasty if the entity was already unpacked
it had a previous simulation center that
it was stored around and we need to
update it to the new simulation center
because the simulation center may have
moved right but if this entity was
unpacked fresh then it was stored around
its chunk in which case the updated
actually needs is the difference between
the chunk center and the simulation
center and that's that that's this chunk
Delta right and that's like really kind
of subtle and error-prone you know it
just doesn't seem it just doesn't seem
like a good idea to me
[Music]
so I kind of feel like as much as I it's
not my favorite thing in the world it
seems like it kind of argues for the
entities to generally look see here
you know it kind of wants them to know
what their origin was you know what I
mean is the is like the sort of least
error-prone way to do that is anytime I
update an indie I just store like what
was its P around and then when you you
know go to you know start using it at
the start of simulation you just say
well I need it to be centered around
this so is it or isn't it right and
and I guess I don't know it's not a good
idea
it seems very wasteful because you only
really needed one bit to tell you
whether this thing was stored relative
to the previous simulation center which
you could store as well so let's do this
here's what I'm gonna say and I don't
know if this is good or bad but it's
sort of seems good here's what I'm gonna
say I'm gonna say there's an unpacked
origin right and I'm gonna say that the
this doesn't happen here ever in fact I
kind of like this I'm at I'm happy with
this so what we're gonna do is we're
gonna sort of create a origin update
which is like when Electronic Arts
System downloads updates we're gonna
create an origin update and that's gonna
be the update that's necessary to take
the location of the new origin and move
us from our old origin to there right so
if we said we're gonna go from the
previous unpack origin to the new origin
that gives us the flow or the D unpack
origin right
like what's the Delta between those two
and then I can just go ahead and set the
world unpack origin to be the new origin
and then when we go through the entities
what we can do is during unpack of
entities we can just add the chunk Delta
like we were going to write so basically
we know we're unpacking around the
unpack origin so it looks like that but
for any entity that or that existed a
priority right so that one that was
there beforehand what I can do is first
loop over those and update
those so I'll say all right you know
entity index from zero to over many we
have just do that one piece of
bookkeeping and off we go
so in here we would say that the
unpacked entities entity index plus
equals D unpack origin and and there we
go that's actually much cleaner I like
that a lot better so we do one pass over
the entities to adjust them to the new
location and then we do it now again I
don't love having to make all these
additional passes over to the entities
it's less good and we could save time by
not doing that so I I don't love it it
makes me think that probably we want you
know this stuff to be done sort of in a
welded way like this stuff should
probably be handled in here and this
stuff cached as well
you know and it seems like since we're
doing that loop over the entities there
you know why wouldn't we just update the
hash table and all this other stuff you
know there and I mean I think we just
should right and so if you look at what
would happen this call can just happen
inside this loop and inside this loop
right so we can have two different calls
to that same bit of logic that's
happening here to make this stuff work
that can just could have just happened
in here and so you know it kind of
suggests to me that we I don't know it's
a little tangled but if we did take the
sim region here then this piece of code
it could be called from both places you
know I'm saying to you so you can see
why this is a lot more efficient and it
makes me think I kind of want to
structure it this way it's it's exactly
the same code it just doesn't need so
many loops which it generally means it
would be better and so then in here we
just do the same thing the nd gets
registered in either case that gets us
out of this business entirely and since
I want this to go away
that would just have one clean pass
where you get everybody registered as
you sweep through them the first time
that just seems better so even though
it's a little tangled I think I prefer
for now and we can untangle it by
pulling the sim region apart into two
pieces if we really wanted to I don't
think I do want to but you know we could
write it's certainly possible to do so
let me take a look at where we're at on
compilers here this just needs to be
placed out here in the create world call
like so
[Music]
this no clear doesn't actually need to
be and no clear
we can totally clear it now because we
just allocate that the thing once and
these have different names that's max
unpacked entity count that's unpacked
and accounts and unpacked entities and
this arena is like this thing which is
you know wherever we're storing the rest
of our world garbage
it's there alright so yeah we got a
bunch more work to do here but I think
this is on the right track for doing the
isolation that I wanted
this right here needs to be off of the
world but otherwise that looks fine
keep forgetting that's called unpacked
uh and so I think yeah that just leaves
us with these two operations that we
were doing and so really the create and
be call would be exactly the same as
before
that's pretty easy to handle both
creativity and delete entity are just
fine there and so if the sim region you
know it's got the world pointer in it
and so really what these are is they're
just thunks to the world code because
the world code is the thing that would
really be handling this and so I think
what you want there is just in in this
case it really doesn't need to do
anything it doesn't this this is really
a call on an entity it doesn't need a
region and probably never will because
it's just going to to make sure that
it's marked as deleted but we're not
actually do anything with it so really
this is the only call that we're talking
about here and so it's really just this
part that we would be forwarding so what
I'm going to do here is in the world
code I'm gonna have an internal call
carrier which is like create entity and
that's going to be effectively the same
thing but it's going to just take the
world's actually and probably nothing
else so it's going to do this parts like
that and then it's going to return that
result
and so this part here is just a thunk
it's gonna say I'm getting my entity
from the world that backs me into that
be a stretch these days a world that
backs you so once we get one of those
then we proceed to assign it an ID which
is and then add to the hash and that
stuff is done on the actual sim region
right so I think that probably takes
care of all of this this that null
entity should should be moved to like
this gonna be oops move to the worlds
and these just get changed to they're
unpacked versions because you always add
unpacked and then pack you don't add
packed in and unpack right we add to the
unpacked set and then it gets packed
down later on okay so now and I guess
this is fine like that too I'm gonna go
ahead and make that be just a thing that
we hang off of ourselves
and there we go so that should be fine
and this is all off the world that's
doesn't matter this is the end world
change stuff and so that's the last
thing that we should have to do I think
and it is so now we have to deal with
this situation here and so if you look
at what's happening first we have a map
into chunk space and sort of doing the
the the storage of this stuff with the
exception of the packed reversible
reference which kind of has to be done
every frame the other stuff is stuff
that we only do when we actually pack
something right um and so if you look I
don't know what this stuff was for oh
this was breath testing where the things
moved I guess this is gonna be out of
date now so I'm gonna get rid of that
because we have we would probably have
to write that again later if we actually
wanted it so what we want to do now is
when we actually end when we sort of
like you know we pack and B's as
necessary or something like that you
know what I mean uh we're just gonna
basically call this and say hey like
we're gonna repack stuff now by the way
just so you know you know do whatever
you want and this here I should time
both of these functions by the way
because they are
doing a lot of work so this guy should
get one of those as well so when we do
ensure region is unpacked the
corresponding thing is repack entities
that's necessary and that's just going
to pack stuff up to ensure that we don't
waste space now again the thing that I
said that's a little bit Squinkie is
these packed reversible reference
nonsenses here and again looking at one
of those things I'm just not sure I like
this stuff anyway
it just looks crappy in general like if
we have IDs then like just use the ID
right and and so I just kind of feel
like we should just use the ID
everywhere instead and and I feel like
that just makes this code work better
and so I kind of want to do that and
just say that those reversible
references just have to be by index now
because there's already you know a call
that gets that for you and so I don't
feel like we really need to do that
it just seems stupid so I may just also
say that we're going to get rid of that
I'm not gonna literally get rid of it
right now
and the reason for that is just because
I don't want to introduce more changes
that I need to in one step so I'm going
to let it sit just for the briefest
moment and then we're going to get rid
of it so what I want to do now is
instead of judiciously repacking we're
just going to repack up
right so this stuff at the moment and
world change is just gonna call repack
Kennedy's as necessary on the world and
all of this stuff is still going to
happen because all of it can happen
right so what we're gonna do is we're
going to go through all of the entities
that still exist in the worlds like this
actually that fit today and as we loop
through them we are going to put them
away exactly the way that we used to put
them away and then what we're going to
do is we're gonna set our nd count to
zero and that's that right um so I think
that's really all we need to do that
could go away and hopefully this will
sort of work we may have a little bit of
dignity but hopefully it won't be a huge
deal when we're doing this remap here to
remap one of the entities positions into
chunks based based on an origin again I
sort of you know presciently although we
knew what the code was so it wasn't
prescient that's what compression
oriented programming lets you do is
appear like you know everything when you
take your design because you do I stored
the unpack origin so we can unpack and
repack based on that that origin and be
correct
right because that is exactly what we
would expect to have happen here when
we're doing this packed reversible
reference stuff we need to know what the
sim region is because we need to
actually do we why when you do pack in
any reference
where is the same region used so if the
what is this about
so if this thing doesn't have a pointer
but it does store an ID then it says if
I get a hashed pointer I don't actually
know what get Hashem ID does let's just
quickly take it look at that
so it's saying if there was a lane 4th
this thing what
I don't quite understand what this was
meant to do
hmm we're basically trying to zero out a
reference to something and we're trying
to zero it out in the circumstance oh I
see what this is trying to do it's
trying to say if someone zeroed out the
pointer they're trying to tell us that
yeah okay so you can see this this just
sucks
so yeah we definitely don't want this
right it's just bad because look at all
this garbage you have to go through
because if you if you just set the index
to zero instead setting the pointer to
zero here we have to do this extra work
to determine that that meant you were
clearing it and not that it was a
reference to something that isn't
unpacked in the same region right now
right yes so that's just stupid
I don't like anything about that at all
that's just bad that's just bad in
general so that yeah I mean this is just
further reason why we want to get rid of
this code so sure for now what we're
gonna do is let's just say that the
region gets passed as zero and we'll
deal with the bugs from that at the
moment and then we're just gonna get rid
of this this is gonna go away completely
cuz I don't like it and it's bad alright
let's see what else we got here this is
not found pet reverse-flow reference so
we'll just kind of make it found here
temporarily
all right and that just leaves us with
this which is a really simple thing we
had to implement here where you loop
over the hash table which is really
pretty straightforward but let's go
ahead and implement that so really all
we need here is just some way of knowing
what we were actually iterating over and
if you look at the way this works the
entity hash table is an internally
chained hash table so just looping over
it is sufficient as far as I can tell to
visit all of the entities because if you
look inside the entity structure itself
we don't have like a hidden pointer
there that change these things as far as
I can tell right there isn't like a
entity star yet so that there is no way
to change these together so basically
looping over the hash table all we're
gonna need for storage here is the hash
index and so when you do iterate all
entities all we have to do here is say
well I guess we need one more thing
which is the point of a sim region
although I suppose we don't really even
need that per se I mean we could just do
this right and maybe that makes more
sense that's it all right
fine
let's just say it's that I don't know I
don't think about too hard because I
don't really care about this piece of
the code all right so we're gonna make a
iterator here and this iterator needs to
store the sim region it needs to store
the entity that we're pointing at and it
needs to store the hash index that we're
at right and so in each one of these
cases we sort of need a little helper
function here oops
and we'll talk about that in a second
but effectively what we're doing don't
ask me why these didn't have internal
before them just because they didn't I
guess in here we're doing the same thing
we're just gonna bump the hash index
here right and so in each of these cases
what we need to do is scan the hash
table for the first time that we see a
for the first time that we see one of
these filled one of the hash table slots
filled with an actual pointer and so we
need like find next entity or something
like that right that's gonna take one of
these things and find it so we first
started to 0 then we say fine next
entity and we say you know go go to town
here we would increment it right and
then say fine next entity to go to town
I think that's all we really need to do
here I would like to assert that there
is one because you should never call
this function if you're the if with an
invalid iterator I just want that to be
an error for now and so here where we do
find next entity we just need to scan
through the hash table looking for a
valid one right I'm also gonna start out
by making this equal to 0 just in case
well no you know what no I'm not I'm
going to do that actually here so we'll
start by assuming that we couldn't find
one we're then gonna loop through all of
these by saying start at the hash index
that we're on go until the sim region
was it
- go until the end of that table looking
for one and then well we don't have to
do return anything and then return so
since we know this already starts here
and this is the actual thing that we
want to increment I can also just
instead turn this into a while loop that
kind of just looks more like this right
and so this way we can just loop through
these incrementing as we go and all we
have to do is say look if the entity
hash that's at this location actually
contains something we want to stop right
and furthermore this pointer here is the
actual pointer we want so we can say
this and remember it which is what we
want as well I think that's all we
really need to do to iterate over all of
these but we can double check that by
stepping through it in debug or make
sure we didn't forget something okay
that's supposed to be an arrow because
this is a pointer so I'm not sure why I
wrote it as a dot that's just the way it
goes sometimes and also obviously this
needs to return the thing that we
actually made okay I think that's
everything this is the actual hash index
of the iterator that we're incrementing
there and off we go
yes so now it comes down to debugging we
need to actually make this stuff work so
let's get started on that I probably
want to make this easier on myself I'm
gonna go turn this into debug mode so
that we don't have to do too much work
to decrypt what Visual Studio well what
the PDB is telling us so let's go ahead
and get that going here where we do
let's see where we are in the call stack
first of all so we have some idea what's
going on you can see in here we're in
begin sim
we're looking for our entity this way it
looks like maybe we didn't when we did
our unpack we didn't like hash
everything that we should have hashed or
something right so let's just take a
look at what's going on in here oh well
actually you can see that we just forgot
to call the function so that's that's
what's so we have to actually call our
functions if we want them to do things
that's the first rule of programming
they have to actually call your
functions if you want them to execute
just thought I would let all of you
novice programmers in on a really big
secret that those of us have been in the
industry for a while have learned it's
like a really you know closely guarded
secret if you don't call a function it
doesn't do anything that's a that's a
big one you know some of you may not
understand what I'm talking about there
I know it's pretty advanced stuff but
that's actually you know if you think
about it
that's actually what happens shockingly
all right so let's get this going like
that and now let's try to plug it
because can't really debug code that
doesn't get called other than to say
that it should have been called all
right now we're getting somewhere
okay so first of all what we're seeing
curious we're blowing out our entity
counts so the oh wait what sim region
did we forget - oh all right sorry we
forgot to delete some code as well we're
not quite done that needs to go away
entirely and we need to change that that
reference to it this is supposed to be
world unpacked
unpacked entity account and this is
supposed to be world max unpacked
account see what else we got there and
this debug value here where we do the
entity count I suppose we can do that at
the end of this where we just say what
the entity can
currently is running of the or what the
unpacked end account if the world is I
guess it's fine all right back to the
bugging what else we got so it looks
like here we did blow out this number
I'm curious here though let me just make
sure we're not still on our kind of
junior programmer streak here of
forgetting to call our functions no so
we are actually thankfully calling
repack entities as necessary I was a
little bit worried there that we weren't
so yeah off we go and at the end of this
we are correctly zeroing our unpacked
entity count which should mean that we
can do this as many times we want and so
when we're going through and doing this
I think if I'm not mistaken yeah I think
if I'm not mistaken that this should be
a real check now and it should have
gotten initialized properly right yeah
so I think that's all okay so let's
actually start debugging this that that
looks like that is now an actual valid
error hopefully we'll see but let's see
what's going on alright so I'm going to
check the world here and it's at least
correctly like barfing on this right so
that's good let's see where we're at in
our we're coming in here to our inshore
region is unpacked call with our min and
Max chunks there and one thing I would
like to do is let's let's just look at
what happens to the world itself as we
come through these calls I just want to
make sure this is generally working at
all so here is us trying to unpack one
min max chunk here right
I and it looked like that literally
unpacked nothing coming back through
here we got 90 109 and see us unpacking
various regions so that seems to be
working fairly well so far right so I'm
not sure which what we're getting in
terms of bugs here and in terms of the
call stack this is all inside the world
generation right you know what I might
want to do to let me do one more thing
that we've I think we've never actually
done we add one more thing to before I
get too deep into debugging that I that
I would like to have we want to make
sure you can only unpack once before you
at least call to say that you want check
for repacking so so I want like a thing
called unpack is open here that when you
call unpack we set and then when you
call repack we unset so like in here I
want to say that you've opened up your
unpack and then in here where we do
repack I want to say okay you've closed
it right and so when you call this I'd
like to assert that the unpack is open
although technically that's really not
the part I care about what I care more
about because you could call this as
many times you wanted so that's really
not the issue what I want to avoid is
multiple people calling this before they
call the other one right so what I want
to do here is assert that it's not open
before you open it and then here I want
to assert that it is open before you
close it just for the moment right and I
want to make sure that there are no
balance calls but otherwise I think
we're okay so let's take a look at where
we're at here unfortunately it's a
little bit behind my head but that's
okay
so if we look in here it looks like
we're actually in the simulation part of
things now and so what I'm wondering is
just the first time that we're
simulating something let's see if that's
true so for whatever reason and I'm not
sure how we introduced this error
exactly but for whatever reason we seem
to introduce an error we're generating
our world doesn't cause a problem for
packing and unpacking it all seems to
work but when we go to actually do our
first simulation that does fail right
uh and who knows why right we have no
idea why but we're going to have to
figure it out right so looking at this
particular part of the code as we come
in here right if we look at the world it
is correctly re initialized right so it
doesn't think that anything's unpacked
and so when we come in here what we're
saying is that we effectively get
when asking for this region which is not
exceedingly large right that's totally
reasonable it's not some weird crazy
like number that doesn't make any sense
when we go to unpack this this obviously
should never execute currently because
there is no time when these things are
actually stored there this part
supposedly just unpacks like infinity
items let's skip to like maybe here or
something so how many entities are in
this block three hardly going to break
the bank there
so is it pulse
are we getting like some kind of a
what's going on here are we getting some
kind of like an infinite looping chain
or something it would be nice to be able
to tell if that were the case here's one
of the thing I'm gonna do just as a
check so in here where we do this sort
of like first block block next sort of
thing so you know we're pulling this
stuff off of the set where we remove
this chunk and now we're gonna like do a
bunch of garbage with it right what I
want to do is I want to
I want to check to make sure that this
isn't like an infinite loop and so the
way to do that although this isn't quite
good enough is I'm going to assert I'm
gonna create like a synthetic checker
here right and what I'm going to do is
I'm gonna cert that my check block is
never equal to my block right and what I
want to do is I know this is ridiculous
well we'll sort of talk about what this
is well I'll just talk about right now
so suppose I want to look to find out if
this linked list has a repeat summer in
it so if the entire list repeated then
it would be sufficient for me to just
take the first pointer to something or
really any pointer to anything in the
entire list right and assert as I'll it
loop through the list that I don't hit
it right because as long as I never as
long as I don't hit that one I know that
the entire list doesn't loop around
right and I can't really do it here the
first time right I would have to do it
one past the first time look I need a
counter which is what I was I was about
to do but there's another reason I'll do
it but we'll see this
we really want this so what I'm trying
to do here is basically say all right so
suppose I have I want to check to make
sure that this thing doesn't contain any
cycles well this is gonna loop through
the entire list and if there was if the
entire list was just a circular list so
I'm just running around in circles and
I'll never terminate then I can just
check to see if I hit any one of these
blocks more than once so the easiest way
to do that is to just say well the first
time through I don't want to assert
because obviously I'm gonna process that
first block but every time thereafter I
could just check to see like set it
equal the first block and check to see
whether they're equal at that point
right and that would work but what I
want to add is another case here and the
reason for that is suppose the linked
list was like a list of like 50 things
and then just the last like four of them
were in a cycle right so there's a bunch
and then there's a cycle at the very end
right well what I'd like to do is be
able to find that cycle at that at that
tail as well and so the way I wanted to
do that would just say look if every
second time I move my main pointer I
move if I have like another pointer that
moves half as fast no matter where the
cycle is in the chain eventually I'll
it'll catch up right eventually so I
should be able to do something like this
and I could make this really any number
I wanted this could be 5 10 100 doesn't
matter and so all I really want to do
there was like check to see if there
were cycles and that's
way to do it's not a very good way
necessarily but it is a way to do it
right and so I was just curious if we
found any cycles I don't know that
that's actually what's happening here
but I'm just curious to know so we
didn't see any there I think I wrote
that code correctly but it's a little
bit subtle to be fair also that supposed
to be outside technically I guess could
be there
alright so assuming I wrote that code
properly then we didn't have a cycle in
there and it looks like I did right
we're decrement in the counter if it
equals zero then we advance our check
block and reset the counter OOP nope one
more time
all right
so let's say I checked that properly but
let's be honest I didn't do a
particularly thorough job there but
let's just say that we assume that we
don't have any cycles and I the reason
I'm kind of only vaguely checking for
that is because I'm not sure what we
could have done that would have added
cycles so I suspect if we did do
something wrong here
really what we're finding is something
either we're like over adding entities
in some weird way or what we're doing is
when we're packing our entities back up
we're like packing them all at the place
where we start instead of where they
should actually go or something like
that right I think that's sort of more
what's happening it's a more likely bug
and so I'm gonna look for that a little
bit more aggressively instead so yeah
so looking at how this code is working
right we're mapping something into the
space of the chunks by taking whatever
the entity pointer was and saying we
want to make it relative to the unpack
origin which is the origin that we were
told to unpack with the last time you
started a sim region which is being
stored here and I think is what we
expect so you know just to kind of look
back here if we look at when we're doing
that begin world change you can see us
storing the origin here and so when we
call this I think that should be correct
and should be sort of you know what we
would expect to see you know I don't see
anything odd going on there
similarly this code doesn't really touch
those positions at all so it's really
just going to be this one here that does
where we update the desk P here
shouldn't really matter
I think that really shouldn't matter so
this right here where we do our
subtraction we take the chunk position
and the unpack origin there that seems
correct as well right and that Delta is
going to get applied to the entity as it
comes out and I don't think anything
bizarre happens in register entity
I mean nothing nothing really goes on
there so this code here where we're
coming through and you know removing
that world chunk there I do let me see
so this part where we add the fruit and
why we have a mutex for that I guess
because we allowed like multiple people
to access this yes so that that really
could be made in line to what we're
doing here as well which I would prefer
but again not really germane to this so
you know looking at looking at this I
think we want this code to just be in
line here oops sorry
this code rather and that ticket mutex
should really just go on the unpack
right
and that just makes a lot more sense
than having to take it each time through
there just doesn't really make much
sense but um getting that really that
relevant though so I'm trying to think
of an a way to approach this debugging
wise and I can't really think of what to
do other than maybe to take a look at
the packing calls to see who is getting
packed and why so like I want to see
what this value is a lot of the time do
I think it's repeating and necessarily
I'm not really sure what the most
expedient thing is the only things I
could think of are now sort of involved
right so we're just gonna have to do
something involved there's no shortcut I
don't think so I'm gonna take a look at
the NTP here for the packing and what I
want to do is set the breakpoint here
I'm just looking at these values
and I'm just looking at the spread of
these values by the way using remedy
here to do something that you literally
can't do in Visual Studio which is watch
values change as you run visual studios
lag on the watch window makes this kind
of debugging actually impossible it you
just can't do it you used to be able to
in the old days and then they made it so
slow that you can't anymore
all right so let's step through a couple
more times and see
so it does seem like they're it's like a
suspiciously large number of entities
packed into this one particular cell and
I'm not sure whether that's to be
expected or not in terms of the overall
size of each individual chunk I'm not
sure how many things you would expect to
see in any one of them overall though
you know again I'm not seeing any kind
of really sort of ridiculous like oh my
god like how could you possibly ever
imagine having this many of the same
chunk value you know it looks like
they're spread there's entities spread
out among the chunks like you would
think and they have various coordinates
throughout the you know negative 10 to
10 range on everybody which is you know
what I would kind of expect so I'm not
really sure again where this like
difference is coming from we're you know
we we should have had the same exact
number unpacked before we made the
change as after we made the change and
yet we don't and so where that's coming
from
I really am Not sure I'm gonna go ahead
and look now towards this set of code
here so I'm gonna let it fail first of
all and in here oh you know what there
is something I just thought of that
maybe would be related which is that
where we sort of do our our looping if
this
was broken which it might well be
because we never tested it then some of
our stuff that probes for nearby
entities would fail and that could have
caused a problem let's take a look I
just need to get to one of well you know
what I'll do let's double check that
code alright so in here we start off
with an iterator and it you know didn't
find anything let's try that again and
step into this there we go so let's see
what we've got
here's our entity hash right we're going
to loop over this and see what we can
find
so while we're inside this array bonds
we look to see if we find one we just
loop over everything in here and then
let's see if we find anything so we are
finding stuff
right that does seem to be finding stuff
um so I mean I'm not seeing a lot of
reason to be suspicious
that all looks fine to me
you
so yeah and I'll see I don't think
that's probably our problem either so
I'm going to let this run to the crash
site I'm gonna set a breakpoint on the
outer piece meaning this part right here
and so we know that after the world gets
created which all seems to work without
having to unpack a region that has too
many things in it the first time we try
to do one for sim is when we fail so if
I look through here I just want to look
at what the pattern is of things that
get unpacked in terms of chunks see if I
can see anything that's a hint there as
to what we did wrong so when we go into
insure region is unpacked here what I'd
like to do is say if you know we take a
look at where the majority of these
entities are coming from so like like in
here for example right if I just go
ahead and look at this block stuff here
I want to look at who is responsible for
the majority of blocks
so like negative one negative one zero
zero negative one zero
[Music]
how many entities if we've already added
that's an incredible number of entities
you can sort of see like yeah like
what's going on there so it also almost
feels like I wonder if somehow I when I
did the transformation on that code I am
leaving the blocks in there somehow so
they don't actually get removed but
remove world chunk right like should do
that and so after calling this there
should be no way of like it shouldn't
ever like duplicate those entities out
unless I'm missing something
you know which maybe I am but
I really don't see how so another thing
that I could do here actually is track
the pack unpack level so for example and
I guess we sort of already do that well
no so in here we have last used entities
storage index and last use any storage
index anytime you create an entity right
if we look at that call when we do
create entity and we pass it into the ID
let me just go ahead and look at the
places where this is called yeah so
allocate entity ID is just gonna
increment this thing so that's how many
entities we think we made if that makes
sense
that we actually asked for and if we
track our pack unpack count what we
should see is that the number of total
entities that we've packed - the total
number of entities that we've unpacked
should always like equal that number we
should never have we should never be
able to have like a higher number than
that right so what I might do is say
let's see what happens if we track that
so in here I just have a like that's
like well I don't really I can just feel
like a packed or entity total deep packs
- unpacks right
and I can even make that in s32 so that
if it if you know we do have an error
there and it goes negative we can see
that it's negative right so in here
every time that we go into this call to
do this this is an entity unpack so we
would we would deck down the number
right I and then any time that we go in
here and push it into the in we'd up the
number right and so what we should see
is those numbers should equal each other
out right the total number of allocated
entities should match the total number
that we've packed and so I'm just
curious to see if that actually happens
or if we've got any issue there right so
let's take a look and just see so
looking at these there is a discrepancy
between those numbers and I would like
to know where it comes from but the
discrepancy isn't large so even though I
think we should track that down because
maybe we allocate some IDs for entities
like reserved space or something
what is the discrepancy actually so 2142
1 4 9 2 - oops - 1 5 2 3 so there's 31
entities unaccounted for there right 31
allocated IDs unaccounted for and so we
do want to take a look at that but again
not really gonna explain where our
entity where extra entities came from I
don't think so all right so that means
the total number of entities that we
packed into the system was 21,000 the
total number we created was twenty one
thousand five hundred and twenty three
how we create identities and never
packed them I'm not sure right and so
that's what we want to go
cat but if anything that would mean that
when we were unpacking versus packing we
like didn't pack as many so that should
actually have be that's the opposite
problem as to what we're seeing with
this bug so again not really sure where
that's coming from
okay so we know we haven't hauled the
packing routine like too many times and
ended up like duplicating entities or
something like that that doesn't seem to
be happening but again what we don't
know right is we're sort of where we're
getting sort of this this extra entity
throughput so one thing I'm curious
about is visually can we get a clue if I
was to go into the system and start
expanding that number out so like what
number would we need if in here I said
the max entity count was something more
right congratulations you can unpack
four times the entities that you thought
you could right does it keep like will
it still have a problem is there any
amount of headroom that would prevent it
from from being the case or not right
and that's what I want to see it looks
like this blows out the hash storage
which is I guess what you would expect
so I suppose that would have to be that
size would have to be increased as well
and maybe like I said maybe we do that
and so in here let's make this a dial
because I would like to be able to run
with different numbers and see what
happens so in the same region I'm going
to define a thing here that's like
or like Maxim region empty count will
just be something that I'm going to
define and so I'm gonna define that to
be four times eighty one ninety two and
then everybody else can use that so the
entity hash can do that and we can do
that here and I don't actually want it
to be that big I want to be
significantly lower than that I suspect
but like I said I just want to see what
number are we getting so like what is
the actual number of things that we
unpack because I have no idea since it
just crashes out and says hey we don't
have room for unpacking that many so how
many would you unpack if you could right
so the answer is fifteen thousand three
hundred and eighty-three is how many
would like to unpack right which is
underneath the total number that there
are so we don't have a smoking gun that
says hey we're obviously unpacking wrong
but it does seem ridiculous that somehow
we're unpacking fifteen thousand in
these now but we haven't done anything
to the code other than just change where
we're unpacking them so we shouldn't
have been able to exceed the number by
such a crazy amount in code that should
be doing literally the same thing so all
right next question if we draw this junk
do we see anything that would give us a
clue
now one thing I'd like to do is maybe
disable lighting for now because again
the lighting storage isn't gonna fit
with this much stuff because the way we
send these these pieces of light
information down obviously into the
lookup table is a fixed size so that
light data width
isn't gonna cut it if you look at where
that's specified you can see we only
have so many and we
I'm currently a fairly poor system for
managing the lighting so that's just not
gonna really work uh so I'm not sure
exactly what to do about that I could
make this larger temporarily I'm not
sure I really want to because I'm not
sure that that that will actually work
through the renderer but we can do it
temporarily just to see I suppose
because I just want to see what the
screen looks like you and I'm saying how
many of these do we have I'm pretty sure
we can't even do this because we
wouldn't be able to submit these
textures they're gonna be too large
right so imagine just disable lighting
temporarily while we take a look at this
that's nuts all right
so how can I turn lighting off kind of
permanently while we look at this
because I really just don't want I think
the easiest way would probably be to do
something like this so if we do letting
enabled here and set this up where we do
enable lighting I think I might be able
to just do that I don't know what this
does
[Music]
it looks like that only changes the
enabling of the lighting there we need
to kill switch for lighting I just don't
think we've ever engineered one
oh is it enabled lighting never even
called alright even worse so we don't
really have a way of killing this and I
would like one to kill this because I
don't really want to have to update it
so maybe inside the lighting code where
we actually you know where we actually
do this work maybe I can just add a kill
switch in there we don't care about that
so much so we're we're actually doing
all of our like compute like propagation
is there really no switch that turns us
on and off because I thought we kind of
did that at some point we had a switch I
guess that switch got illuminated
I mean we have an if zero here but it's
not really what I had in mind
so inside handmade world mode where we
actually do the lighting does that
actually have anything now it really
doesn't so it looks like we just don't
have a way to really do much about this
we've got an updating lighting option
here and but it's kind of janky right
we've got updating lighting and show
lighting and in terms of these getting
set yeah this is all just kind of like
old code that's kind of just gone now
how are those getting set at all there
right now
like if these these must have to get set
to something at some point right in
order for those in order for lighting to
actually get enabled so I'm just
wondering how that is happening
yeah I don't I don't see it
so in terms of calling output lighting
textures world mode updating lighting
should have to be set to true somewhere
right but if it's never set anywhere how
is that possible
oh so it did how did it not find that
when I looked for it before that's lame
anyway so inside play worlds where we're
setting this here I don't know to what
extent I can do this and have that mean
anything but we're gonna try at some
point I guess when we do our lighting
pass yeah so it looks like this just
always gets called like when we're
pushing the cube Stefan right every time
we push one of these cubes on it needs
to allocate one of those lighting points
and I guess the light store is so this
part here where this is getting pushed
on though if lighting was not enabled
then I suppose that would actually allow
us to prevent that part from out
flooding so it does seem to me like
somebody like in here when this render
group gets set up somebody has to start
having the lighting take effect right
somebody in here this part
that has to actually occur so who is
doing that and could we make them follow
the same flag so that we don't have to
worry about it so if this is render
group letting enable to 0 and so right
here I guess is where that gets set to 1
so when we actually put those on there
right and so I assume what we want to do
is don't push those down in that case
where where the lighting is not actually
happening right so inside world mode if
we did just check that flag and not set
up the lighting was that called push
lighting this part here I assumed that
we can get away with that
I don't really know but we'll try
interesting so we got by that part okay
but now when we're doing sort of load
traversable x' here
and this is the neck this would be the
next time through so we made it through
the first loop fine but in here where
we're looking at this entity reference
it looks like for some reason these are
not being restored to zero properly in
this case I mean that is one change we
made the one change that we consciously
made was we just passed zero for the sim
region could that really have caused all
of this problem I doubt it but maybe it
did if you remember in repack enemies as
necessary this I didn't pass the sim
region here so you know really this code
was supposed to look like this and I
didn't want to deal with it right now I
want to deal with it later but maybe we
need to sort of analyze it first this
way and make sure that we haven't messed
up anything before and actually go ahead
and do the change I said I was gonna do
first how could that really be the
problem though doesn't really make sense
but either way
okay so yeah that's not the problem this
is like a separate issue
good cuz I was like that shouldn't have
done anything what we're doing there so
I'm not sure what we're getting a
problem with here but again it's
probably all stems from the same bug
that we have that we just don't know
what we've which problem we've
introduced here but as we're looping
over the entities in the sim region here
oh wait I totally screwed this up okay
so this may actually explain things and
I had the information necessary to do
the right thing and I just didn't we
don't clear this array when we start the
entity hash occupancy table tells us
whether there's something there so
actually my iterator is total garbage
right now oh wow
okay Wow all right did you see that bug
that was a pretty stupid one on my part
I feel like that may be a foolish thing
cuz I literally looked at it at the
beginning of stream and I knew that I
needed to obey that hash occupancy I
said that and then I proceeded to
totally ignore it right I mean you
remember that happening I assumed so
yeah I feel like it's my can't even
really see that that's on my head I need
to like adjust this so you can there we
go
so I think what we need to do here is
say add that occupancy check back in and
that honestly maybe all there actually
was to it so what we need to do here is
check the hash occupancy of this
particular entry right and then we need
to go ahead and get it so like get hash
from ID not that one okay so this call
right here where we do like is empty
that I think is what we actually need to
do and weren't doing so we say for this
hash index if this thing is not empty
then we can get the pointer but
otherwise we can't right makes sense and
so we were looping over a bunch of false
entities
no wonder they all like got confused and
and perhaps remapped in weird ways
because that that was just total garbage
so I think that maybe all the problem
there was there's probably other bugs
let's be honest if I missed that one
which I literally said we had at the
outset of the entire thing then the
chances are high that I've done other
stupid things as well okay let's take a
look at what's going on here so
let's start by seeing what our profiler
is telling us it's going on here I'm
gonna switch this to release my just for
a second so I can see what's going on
but yeah that was really stupid I don't
know why I did that
I was just quite dumb all right so if
you look at what's going on here we can
see there's some weird like there's way
more Arena occupancy than there should
be
so we're getting bugs we definitely
still have bugs in there and if we look
at the profiling spending a ton of time
in this repack which we wouldn't expect
so we've still got some pretty bad mojo
happening here so why what's what's
going on right and and I have no idea so
we're gonna have to figure it out all
right so back debug mode for now I also
want to look now to see if that changed
anything about our pack unpack although
based on that I guess it didn't so this
was an unrelated problem that also that
I just also had that was separate right
so what I want to do here is let's set a
breakpoint in begin sim
and in here I'm gonna look at the world
structure and I want to see how many we
get so yeah this was an unrelated
problem so that was just also a problem
and so we're right back to square one
now we did have to fix the other problem
so it's not like uh-huh it's not like we
didn't need to find that bug but it is
the case that we really have no idea why
the change we made would have affected
the system the way that it did
so we're still just as in the dark as to
why we're getting such an unusual
behavior out of this
it would seem like you know my
expectation would be that we're handling
the positions incorrectly in some way
because that's the most subtle part of
this system and I'm not sure what else
really could be going wrong there
because it's the thing that determines
where you get packed as well so that's
the thing that I would have most
suspected to be wrong would have been
that and if you look at how the entities
are working in here I honestly can't see
what the problem would be there because
they seem at least to be doing seem to
be be doing it up Wow
so this is just gonna overwrite this
right here so why that is above the copy
I have no idea this was just an owl of
shame day it seems like we got all the
hard stuff right perhaps and like two
really stupid things we got wrong but I
guess that's just how programming goes
sometimes so what are you gonna do you
know there's not much you can do just a
reminder of how bad our lighting is did
you notice that although our world Jen
is quite slow this is a debug mode when
you're not running with lighting on
right and so kind of ridiculous right
how much like our entire frame time is
completely dominated by lighting such
that the debug version of the game runs
pretty much at speed
maybe not 60 but at least 30 just fine
and that's kind of absurd so that just
gives you an idea of just how much we
need to improve the lighting because
it's you know pretty much makes we could
just be running their game at debug if
we really wanted to if it wasn't for the
fact that lighting is
is you know it's there one thing I might
do just based on that is to say look are
we building in debugger nuts you know
and maybe set this based on on that I
don't know that's a tough one to say
anyway I think that means now we're fine
and if I do sort of build in release
mode here we go
I think we should be back to normal
looks like we are
alright so I'm gonna call that a day and
I think that sets us up pretty well
because it looks like yeah if it wasn't
for those two pretty stupid things that
I missed I everything seemed to be fine
and so all we really need to do now is
take the next step tomorrow of not
always repacking and then we're and
that's basically the only thing we
really needed to do and then then we're
good right and we're ready to make our
packing function actually throw things
away if it would like to right so I
think that's all we really need to do
here and that puts us in good shape for
tomorrow I'll go to a brief Q&amp;A in case
anyone has any questions about that and
I'll readjust my head my camera here a
little bit
well the pact entity be a separate
struct and what is the plan of adding
removing data so basically what I'd like
to do there is at first we will probably
not make it be a separate struct because
I don't care enough about it at the
outset so we'll leave it as a struct the
way it is now but what I'll do is I'll
add a watermark to the struct and we
just won't save the back half of it
right so all the data that we don't mind
throwing away and that can just be
reinitialized later during unpack we'll
just stick that on the end and the
reason for that is I just don't want
people's lives to become more
complicated right but at the sort of
more towards the end of development when
I'm pretty confident of how I want
everything to work I will make two
totally separate data stores one will be
the entities truck that's gets used
during simulation and that's in the
cache area and the other will be some
kind of a like hand-tuned packing of
that probably like almost maybe even a
compressed representation so we may even
do something where we like sort of just
have like encoding of what's in here as
like a flag array or something or maybe
even a tagged thing it's like here's the
tag that says what's here and then the
data for it what's here the data for it
what's here then the data for it so that
we don't really have to store anything
that wasn't relevant to that particular
entity something like that but I will
let that play out I don't have a
particular requirement for it I'll let
that play out as it wants to as we go
I had a question regarding the arena
graph in the profiler that may have
changed as episode and you may not be
able to display it in its current state
I it was about why there was separation
for the ground chunks
the first group all were green but every
X amount there is a gray value of
separate them what was the separation
yes so that's a we want to look into
eventually actually and I'm not 100%
sure what it is but I will explain
what's going on there so if you look at
what happens in the allocation so if I
use what is used
chunk space so inside use chunk space
you can see that what happens is it
looks for free blocks that can store
world data and if it doesn't have one
right so even if it has no free space
left then what it's going to do is it's
going to allocate space for a new one
right
looking at the way this is written it
looks like this right well okay so even
just looking at this I can tell you what
the problem is so what ends up happening
is every block is allocated as a one
megabyte block because that's just what
we set it up as we can change that to
anything we want
but blocks get allocated as one megabyte
the world entities get packed in
granularities of 64 K that's one shifted
up 16 right that's 64 K of data so the
question is how many of those can you
fit in a 1 megabyte block right I don't
know 1024 x 1024 divided by 64 divided
by 1024 well I should get exactly 16 of
them right but lo and behold when I look
run my application what do I see
one two three four five six seven eight
nine ten eleven twelve thirteen fourteen
fifteen and uh right so what's going on
here well I was gonna say we have to
look into it more but even just looking
into it in the ten seconds I took me to
explain it I can tell you what the
problem is so world entity blocks are
the things we're storing there is 64k of
data in the block but then a bunch of
crap
there's an entity count some low entity
indices I don't even know what those are
right this stuff that's been here since
time immemorial
this stuff adds to the 16k right and so
what we end up with is I'm sorry
as for the 64 K so we end up with is
something that's 64 K plus a little bit
and that little bit adds up over the 15
that we put in there such that when you
go to put the 16 one well if there's
even one byte more used you can't put
one in there because 16 fits exactly
into one megabyte so what we'd rather do
is have the entity data size actually be
64 K minus whatever this nonsense is
here right so let's just do that now cuz
you brought it up we might as well do it
and so if we go in here and say what
slow entity index right here's my
compile I just want a first seat as does
anyone use this and if so what do they
use it for right so if I come in here
and just say that's a new thing that's
got an underscore under it does it still
get used and if so who is using it
please tell me right so no one's using
that thing so that can go away does
anyone use entity count I assume they do
because they would need to know in order
for the entity size so I assumed these
two values are used here but let's just
validate that fact so I'm going to
compile it without that low entity index
stuff at all right
um here's me running everything seems
fine right no issues and then the data
science presumably still needs to be
used nd counts is it used I think it is
yeah now we probably don't need to use
it because this string could probably
impact as it is I don't care though
because this is fine
that's a pointer it's 8 bytes long at
most these are both 3rd 4 bytes long so
2 of them is another 8 so really we just
need to say hey we need at least 16
bytes of headroom to store a crap so
just leave it leave that room right now
when we run we should pack optimally
hopefully if there isn't another problem
besides the one we just addressed and
hey look we pretty much do although it
looks like for some reason there's still
a little bit of leftover space here on
some of these where they can't I don't
know why and so that would require us
looking into this a little bit more it
may have to do with entities being too
large to fit or something well and then
that shouldn't happen so I'm not really
sure why there's empty space on those
but now you can see we're filling some
of them up properly why is there extra
space on any of these now though I don't
know
that should have either filled all of
them or none of them and so the fact
that it did neither of those two things
is certainly odd
[Music]
so that's a puzzle
I do suppose that since we are sharing
this arena with other people that may
have something to do with it because if
anyone else tried to allocate something
during that time we wouldn't place it
there it would get placed somewhere else
so if this if the world arena were used
in some kind of a temp storage fashion
that could potentially explain it but
I'm not sure what we could do is make
the world arena isolated for now and see
so for example if we did want to do that
what we could do there is just say so
inside here if I look at create world so
in here where it gets past this parent
arena if instead what I wanted to do was
just have this thing be a self-contained
arena right I could say that and get rid
of this and in that case this would
become a bootstrap you know I'm saying
mm-hmm
and so in that case it would be this
right and then what we would do is
anywhere in here where we were looking
at the arena we just need an ampersand
on that but that would allow it to keep
its own separate arena for memory and
and track separately and then we can to
ensure that none of what I just said
is happening there so world chunk
so that's where the extra memory is
coming from you can see it right here in
get world chunk you are having an
allocation here to you're having an
allocation there that's keeping the
headers and so anytime you allocate one
of those again you cannot fit optimally
in there if we can fix that and we
should I think right I'm just going to
show this now I think we do not need to
keep it as a separate arena so I
probably will just back that change out
but I just wanted to see so you can see
here if we did that we'd have a separate
arena here and you can see the storage
works out to base to the same though
right so I'm not sure if we want that or
not
it's hard to say when you we would have
to then track this memory separately and
I'm not really sure I want to do that so
I think I'll just go ahead and back that
out but it is pretty simple to do there
all right so the question is how do we
avoid this problem right because you can
see what's happening there and by the
way this is just another reason why
visualization is so good it shows us
exactly where we're wasting our space
right and that's pretty cool so anyway
you can see what the problem is when we
do get world chunk in here we end up
with a situation where we need to
allocate this sort of header that goes
on the front of things and what happens
is that header is just not very large
right if you look at a world chunk it's
this tiny little thing and so we're you
a little bit extra memory in those
blocks that have every time we have to
okay if the header that means now we
can't fit that 64k in on the end but
remember we've got free lists here so
what we can do instead is say when we
when our free list gets exhausted don't
let's not do this where we push a single
thing on the free list and take up a
little tiny chunk in our arena let's
take up a whole 64 K why not right so
instead what we can do is say all right
hmm
let's make a chunk array and let's push
a whole array of these things on there
like this and the number that we're
gonna push on let's say we made this
more systemic and say the world block
size is this well now we can do is we
can create a number which we can call
mmm chunks per block or something like
that or chunk count per block and we can
take the number of bytes that are in one
of the blocks that we use for storage
and just say how many of them would fit
once we do that so we can allocate
exactly that many right and then we just
loop
shunk index is less than the count per
pluck and we just push all of these onto
our free list right so in here where
we're going to we were previously gonna
like sort of initialize this thing like
like this what we can do is say well
let's push for each one of these let's
take the chunk array plus our chunk
index right let's make that be the chunk
we're working with right let's set the
world's first free chunk to be that
chunk but the next in hash of this one
to be whatever's in there right so we're
just kind of daisy chaining these on you
know I'm saying and we could do that
even easier if we wanted to but that but
basically what we're doing is just
pushing a whole bunch of these on at
once and then we'll just pull out of the
free list from then on out right now I
believe if I did that correctly and of
course I didn't
just make sure I got that right now
first you're trying let's allocate this
many of those we're gonna go through
each of them here and we're going to say
that
oh no that's totally wrong sorry it's
new chunk next in hash is whatever their
current think is on the top of the list
which is nothing refers to it and then
that's the new top guy so we just puts
them all on the free list and other than
that typo I think we probably did that
properly and now by allocating them in
bulk we should have a perfectly packed
in memory structure and as you can see
we we definitely do right and so that's
just the next unused block there right
and what you can see is now this right
here is all of the world chunks actually
got allocated like right here and then
from then on we were fine for the rest
of the way however you can see we lose
we lost some here and I think that that
is because this doesn't fit evenly so if
you look the tote the total number of
these doesn't quite add up the way that
it should
I would assume let's well actually no
you know what that's not the problem
nevermind that would leave a sliver in a
different place what that actually is is
the first time out there's people who
have used this arena for other things
right and if we could zoom in there
which is something we want to add
eventually I think you can see it's
handmade world up CBP taking up that 5k
that's what's offsetting us so that we
can't fill up that part so that's always
gonna be the case because that's the
world structs itself that's sitting in
there causing that problem right so so
that's fine
but then yeah now everybody will be
perfectly packed from now on and off we
go
did you ever figure out mem Lord pages
for virtual Alec is that what you're
talking about no men large pages for
virtual Alec is just if you want to use
two Meg pages right I think so
enthusiast says how did people do memory
management in the era of Commerce 64
that is so luxurious nowadays with all
these amounts of memory we have our
machines yeah well in the Commodore 64
days while you can look at it two ways
one obviously they don't have the luxury
of doing all this crazy stuff we're
doing now it is because computers are so
amazing we have so much more horsepower
but we're expected to do a lot more with
it right and so it's kind of a
double-edged sword in the counter
sixty-four days there you really weren't
you didn't even have to think about
memory management as a thing because
when you only have a 64 K buffer total
that you're ever going to do stuff with
the things you can do it with that are
so limited that you can plan them all
out ahead of time right and so you're
not gonna do memory management like
Noah's gonna allocate things really
you're just gonna plan like here's the
buffers we use for each exact thing and
here's where they are and in different
modes of the game we use different
layouts and that's it and everything's
hard-coded directly to that there's no
like variable allocation kind of stuff
that happens there for the most part
that's my assumption anyway the the
place where that doesn't entirely happen
is if you did one of those interpreted
systems like maybe scummvm or the
infocomm z machine those may have sort
of did it did it a little differently
because they are sort of virtual
machines so they may have been able to
do more of a memory paging kind of a
thing but at the same time they really
had nowhere to write the memory to so I
don't know to what extent they really
did anything like that right
all right so let's go ahead and close
this down for today thank you everybody
for joining me for the episode a hand
made here it's been a pleasure coding
with you as always if you would like to
follow us at home you could always go to
hand made here org and pre-order the
game because it comes with a source code
which I update every night so you can
play around that at home and do your own
experimentation with it I'll be back
tomorrow when we will take the next step
which is to try and keep edit ease
around frame to frame as a cache and
then if that works out well which we'll
see whether it does or it doesn't you
know we'll see how much work we have to
do for that but if we have time and that
works out well we'll also take the step
of packing entities in a limited sense
during that sort of phase so that's
we'll be doing tomorrow hope see you
back here for that until then have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the
Internet take it easy everybody