hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete game live on
stream before we get started today I
wanted to mention that we have created
two discord for Mali rocket which can be
used for handmade hero and things
related and so I just want to point out
that's available now for your use it's
open and you can join it the address if
you want to type it in and will probably
provide links to it there's actually on
the twitch page itself there's an ask a
question via discord button that would
catch you there but it's really just
that standard discord GG link if you
just put in Mali rocket that will go
directly to our section of discord
there's already a lot of people on there
so please go ahead and join we do unlike
twitch chat or other places that are
kind of a little more wild Westy this is
actually monitored by us at fairly
regular intervals and we do maintain
some pretty strict rules on there so
basically there's no politics allowed
whatsoever and no outrage allowed
whatsoever so it has to remain civil
discourse and completely apolitical or I
will happily ban people all the time so
keep that in mind but anything that you
would normally use the twitch chat for
on handmade hero like asking me a
question can be done there and there's
even a special pound live channel you
can go to that I'll keep up during the
streams that I can read so that's a
great place to just ask questions if
you're tired of trying to use the twitch
chat which I realize can be kind of
annoying sometimes alright that's it for
announcements let's actually talk about
the show what are we going to do today
so we kind of left off last time with
getting our situations squared away for
communicating with the 3d hardware a
little more cleanly and we actually
learned something really valuable now
that we got both render dock at the end
of the show actually and n site working
and
eh turns out that both of them are now
working very well originally when we
tried render dock multiple years ago I
think like a long long time ago it
wasn't able to actually work with the
graphic setup that we have but it is
able to work now and it's pretty good
so actually we can use either one of
those tools and maybe we'll try using
render dock a little bit more now
because render dock I believe works
across multiple configuration so it
might be a little bit more applicable to
folks out there who are following along
at home because you don't need to be
using an nvidia card specifically it
already use it I think insight this
won't work on like an AMD card for
example for obvious reasons and videos
not exactly in the business of providing
debugging tools for other people's
hardware right but render dark dock is
designed to be a sort of more
general-purpose
cross-platform debugging tool for
graphics and so we might try to use that
a little bit more if we assuming we
don't hit any like snags with it
obviously so anyway we found out
something really interesting actually
when using it which I'll recap now which
is that actually the slowest part of our
frame render time at the moment if we
turn off some of the inefficient things
like right now we don't have very
efficient ways of sending down ground
cover but if we assume that we were to
speed that up using some fairly obvious
ways we would do that one of the things
that we see is that actually we do spend
quite a lot of time in our multi sample
results like a lot of time in our multi
sample results so much time in fact that
without ground cover it massively
dominates the runtime of our game doing
those multi sample results now will that
change as we turn the ground cover back
on add particle systems you know
generally stress the renderer more
absolutely because the multi sample
resolved cost the same amount no matter
how much we draw to the screen and so it
does stand to reason and obviously makes
perfect sense that as we scale up the
graphics for the game the amount of time
that we spend in our multi sample
resolved will go down proportionately
because the
the time for the rendering is going to
increase whereas the multi sample result
time will be the same as it is right now
however that said what we do also know
is that that time is not insignificant
and so it may be something that we want
to think through because there probably
are ways that we can restructure how
we're doing our rendering such that we
don't really need that kind of detail on
the multi sample resolve and the reason
that I say that is because the only
thing we actually use multi sample
resolve for is cleaning up the edges of
our like geometric primitives so when we
put sprites on the screen for example we
don't actually care even a little bit
when we put sprites on the screen we we
don't have any need to know what's
happening in the multi sample buffer
right those could be done completely
separately if we didn't have geometric
primitives that have actual hard lines
in them we would not have to actually
use multi sampling at all so our sprites
don't rely on the multi sample buffer to
get high quality we've gotten high
quality just by being careful about how
we draw our sprites so it's worth noting
that the multi sample buffer is just
there because we're trying to smooth out
those lines that are on the edges of our
geometric primitives now those geometric
primitives are essential to the game
certainly but we may be able to figure
out a way to draw them such that we
don't require multi sampling to be on
for the rest of the cycle right
for example the depth peeling that we
use to make sure that we can do or order
independent transparency we could just
say that we don't want to do that for
all of our geometric primitives because
they won't need it since they're solid
and don't have transparency right and so
if we you know a priori just said that
pass that involves the the geometric
primitives themselves that pass is the
only one that actually has to go through
the multi sample buffer well that's a
pretty
telling argument just in terms of how we
might go about speeding up this process
so let me show you what I okay that's
not what I meant to do let me show you
what I mean by this and that may be what
we do today is just get that one last
little thing done before we put the
lighting in because the lighting is
gonna add a bunch of stress to the
system and I'd like to have the system
working well without that so this and
maybe the other thing we could do on
Sunday again in preparation for adding
the lighting stress on is we could clean
up our ground cover submission process
so again we could maybe take some of the
load off there so there's things we can
do to try to improve the way our
rendering is working right now and I
just like to get those out of the way
and then when we start to add the stress
of lighting at least then we're only
fighting that one thing at a time so
this is render doc and what I'm gonna do
here it's going to go to launch
application I'm gonna do load well
actually go say it's already in here my
last settings gonna do load last
settings here and you can see I didn't
have the working directory set properly
that's why the reason we were getting
crashes in it before I'm gonna go ahead
and make sure I set this working
directly directory correctly and that's
what we need to be set to now so I'm
gonna save those settings into this
render doc handmade render doc cap thing
here I think that's how it's supposed to
go let's just say that it is I don't
really know
there we go and let me do load last
settings and see nope okay so clearly
that's not how that works I'm not sure
how that actually works then okay there
it is no maybe I have to just do this
close it I don't know how to get it to
remember that no idea maybe those are
stored in some other file or something
but I don't know fur for the time being
I'll do it this way cuz that's what
seems to work so anyway if we run the
game from here you can see me doing it
here is the game running and you can see
the ground cover is turned off as I said
as I hop around
you can see the game running as normal
with some debug points in there for
where the lighting probes are at the
moment if I hit the f12 key it will do a
frame capture I can then look at that
frame capture if I close the application
because I don't really need it running
anymore we can just pop back here and
what you can see is this is the capture
of one single frame you can see it
drawing the color passes here and it's
it's actually a little bit easier in my
opinion to use then insight for that
purpose because here's you know you can
kind of see me just quickly going
through and seeing what got rendered in
those different passes it's just it's a
little zippier I don't know it feels a
little bit easier to use personally just
you know just personal preference
probably there but anyway what you can
kind of see about this in in general is
that if I want to I can go to this clock
right and you can see the clock timings
that are really not correct I don't
really know to what extent these can be
relied on but there are some kind of
approximation to how much time is being
spent and they do agree with the insight
ones at least in terms of ref proportion
what you can see here is something like
this where I get the color pass which is
a clear plus draw elements and then
another draw elements right you can see
that that entire thing which drew all of
this that whole thing took only on the
order of 331 microseconds but here you
can see that this single resolve that's
just one fullscreen quad running the
multi sample resolved shader that took
three milliseconds so it basically took
ten times as long to resolve the multi
sample buffer as it did to draw the
buffer in the first place so that shader
code that we're executing there and more
importantly probably than the shader
code although who's to say but more
important than the shader code the
bandwidth of pool
the entire multi sample buffer in the
whole thing may be really cost us a lot
and the reason that I say that maybe is
because I don't really know what the
gratis cars doing but just to give you
some perspective the reason a multi
sample buffer is a multi sample buffer
is because the graphic card itself is
allowed to optimize how it chooses to
allocate those samples so for example if
it wanted to it could keep just a
regular color buffer for the multi
sample buffer along with a flag that
says whether it means to actually have
any multi samples right and then have a
backing buffer for the other 15 multi
samples if a particular pixel needs them
right it could just implement it that
way there's no rules about how the
graphics card treats a multi sample
buffer so what that means is for 90
percent of the pixels on the screen like
you can see here most of them would not
need to ever touch the deep part of the
multi sample buffer it's just one color
written by one triangle that covers the
entire pixel right and so the only
pixels that actually need to talk to the
multi sample part of the multi sample
buffer are the ones that actually lie
along the line of a geometric primitive
such as right here and that is
drastically fewer pixels drastically
fewer pixels then the entire multi
sample buffer well unfortunately as far
as I know and I even asked us on Twitter
to see if anyone out there who's a GPU
expert maybe had heard of something or
knew anything about it I even asked them
is there any way inside a standard kind
of shader to ask the graphics card on a
particular pixel while doing it resolved
is this thing completely covered by one
color or not and if we could do that
then we would be able to put in a warp
branch kind of inside our shader that
would probably optimize it quite a bit
that just said if there's only one color
don't read the other 15 multi samples
right because all of that extra
bandwidth of reading all of those extra
sand
apples if in fact the graphic card has
optimized them which this number
suggests to me that they have the fact
that it's so much lower because remember
it had to touch all the pixels right it
had to read it had to read and write the
entire multi sample buffer just like
this has to read the entire multi sample
buffer right
this had to do all of that but the fact
that this was able to do it so much
faster than ours unless it's just
because our shader is super crappy or
something which it could be but the fact
that it could do it that much faster
suggests to me that it was probably
hitting a fast path where most of the
time it didn't actually incur the memory
bandwidth cost right that's what that
suggests to me now again I don't know if
I'm right because I don't have any way
of really intergrating the graphics card
in in any way that could tell me but
that that seems to me to be a likely
candidate right so so what that tells me
is that if we could write the best
possible case for us would be if we
could do something where the the the
multi sample resolved that we're doing
like here could be done in such a way as
to not require the depth peeling so that
we don't have to do it four times right
that would be the best possible case for
us now the problem with that is that
right now we sort of do use the depth
peel to handle something that involves
the geometric primitive that something
is when we have to Flora stacked on top
of each other and we alpha the top floor
out we are currently not guaranteeing
that we draw that in any particular
order we just draw it in any old order
that happens to come in and we don't
ensure that floors that are higher up
for example get drawn before floors that
are lower down and so we do currently
have unfortunately a restriction that
doesn't really let us do anything
intelligent there right so now the
question is is there something else that
we could do like is there something we
could do that would allow us to do this
result or to get that like anti-aliasing
that we're trying to get there
is there some way we could get that
anti-aliasing in a way that allows us to
drop the number of these resolves down
to just one so we only pay you know this
like two millisecond cost here or
something but don't have to pay the two
to three millisecond cost three more
times up here in these other resolves
for no reason that's the question and
the answer is probably yes
but I'm not sure I necessarily know why
so I have to kind of think it through
let's pop over the white board or black
board as the case may be and see what we
can figure out also while I'm at it
does anyone know if Milton ever got
fixed to fix the bug that they
introduced with the fact that the
smoothing looks really bad now does
anyone know I'm not sure like if if that
ever got you know cuz we we got this
nice like grid feature in there that
someone added but in order to get the
grid feature we had to upgrade to a new
version and that version seems to have a
weird luck bug where the the smoothing
is all messed up it's very like rough
now and has a lot of weird like small
errors and stuff like that I'm not sure
so it would be interesting to know if
anyone ever figured out what was going
on there I would certainly like to know
and put perhaps upgrade to a new version
if anyone knows the answer that question
so let me know in the discord or
something if that's the case because it
would be nice to get that sorted out at
some point in the near future okay so
here's the problem that we currently
have we have our sprites and our sprites
are like a okay right these don't need
multisample
at all but these do so they don't need
another sample they do need depth feel
then we have our geometry and these do
need multi sample and sort of need depth
peel and so what do I mean by that right
what do I mean by sort of need epi oh
well like I said sometimes we may want
to use the ability to alpha blend floors
in and out and so they kind of do sort
of need depth feel to a certain extent
but what does that really mean do we
really need depth feel necessarily like
is that actually something that we
really need to have or is it not so
necessary right because remember the
reason that we needed the depth peeling
on our sprites is because we want to be
able to draw all of our sprites with no
sorting and just have the z-buffer
figure it out and in order to do that
and have the Alpha values still
composite properly on top of each other
for partial alpha values we need to know
what order they come in and that feels
really the only way to do that right
well my question here is well hmm for
alpha blending do we really need to like
fur when we're doing one floor on top of
each other that's not really as hard of
a problem as just a crazy crap ton of
sprites just thrown together and
expecting the graphs it's hard to sort
them out
we're def feeling was maybe a little bit
more warranted if we're just talking
about alpha blending out at a certain
range that's you know like a fogging
distance to us that seems like something
that we might be able to handle it a
different sort of way and let me sort of
say something else about that while
we're at it if I was to run the game
here again
let me go up into well actually let me
just run it as I normally would in
remedy so let's launch the debugger here
let me go to loading there we go so if I
was to run it here what you would notice
is that as I do start to use that
feature of alpha blending out a floor
that's on top of the floor that we're
currently on what you'll see is I go
down these stairs is that as I get lower
down into and you know the camera starts
to move down is that the alpha blending
when I blend these out does some
somewhat undesirable things actually
what do you hope you can see there is
like when I blend out that floor I
actually sort of cut away the floor and
I can see like the inside of the cubes
right now we may decide that that's fine
like maybe that effect is just kind of
nice and we don't you know like maybe
it's just a nice smooth effect right um
so there is something to be said for
that but at the same time there is a
separate issue there which is like well
if I really wanted this to work more
artistically we probably wouldn't alpha
blend out the floor that way what we
would do instead is we would alpha blend
out like this rendered image in a sense
and we wouldn't allow you to see like
the backs of cubes or something in there
right and no matter what we do if we
just use the alpha the way we're using
it now you're definitely going to see
those because even if we turned on some
kind of a back face call that would
remove these interior facing polygons
here which we certainly could do we
would still end up in a situation where
these cubes here we would see their
sides which we were not previously able
to see
and so there is a certain amount of like
me looking at that going oh I don't know
about this right and so when I think
about that what that strikes me is you
know if I was gonna like play around
with this a little bit that strikes me
as something where I may want to say
well for multi samples we can do better
than that to multi sample resolves I'm
sorry four-month ISTEP results we can
definitely better than that to multi
sample resolves I don't know to multi
sample resolves might be necessary and
the reason I say it might be necessary
is because what I might want to do is
just do two depth peels of the geometry
one for things that are past the Alpha
plane and ones that are thick for things
that are before it and then blend those
out in a cleaner way that doesn't
involve that kind of sort of seeing B
you know seeing the seeing how the
sausage is made might be a bad bad way
to say it but you know what I mean right
like seeing an element of geometry that
really has nothing to do with the
artistic intent of the game it was just
something that happened because these
things happen to be drawn as cubes and
we happen to be setting their alpha
value down but but no one really wanted
it to look like a hollow box there we
just kind of wanted the floor itself to
sort of fade out and you know and then
instead we got this right so the
question is like you know can we do
something with that is there some way
that we can maybe play around with that
and so what I would say is if we just
assume here that we take the sprites and
we were to say let's do these in a
separate pass right so there's a
separate pass that deals with sprites
and that pass is going to be somehow you
know removed from a pass that involves
geometry and perhaps the geometry for
example is just rendered
to a temporary buffer that gets
composited in with the sprites during
that depth field process as if it was
just another sprite a sprite that
happens to be the full screen or
something right and so if you imagine
doing it that way what you could imagine
doing is just taking the geometry run
dirt rendering out the geometry in the
multi sample buffer resolving the multi
sample buffer to a full screen quad and
then when we actually do our sprite
resolves we just mix it in as one full
screen quad pass that means that the
depth peels themselves never need to go
through a multi sample resolve they can
just be used as is with multi sampling
turned off and then the geometry part
which does need the multi sampling well
will turn it on for just the part that
computes the geometry pass which is then
composited in as if it was a full-screen
sprite with its own depth buffer right
so that's a relatively easy way that we
could do that process and I think that
would work just fine the only thing that
it doesn't do again is handle alpha
blending out that those floors that were
too close to us and so that's the part
where I say we may have to do a 2x of
the multi sample result the reason I say
we might need to do a 2x is because when
we're actually doing the rendering and
we do that multi sample rendering it
seems like something where I don't know
even if we're doing 16x multi sampling
if we do do a screen door transparency
kind of thing for the blend outs on
those things I think maybe that wouldn't
quite be smooth enough I mean I don't
know right so maybe it would be fine and
then you could just get away with one
but I just don't know and so to get the
full you know 8-bit at least
interpolation of that fade what we would
have to do I think unless I'm missing
something when I what I'm thinking about
it in my head here I may be missing some
other way of massaging the problem but
what I'm thinking about is we need to
introduce a plane that's like here's the
Alpha cutting plane right everything
behind it gets generated in one pass
through the multi sample buffer which we
then resolve and then everything in
front of it gets generated into a
separate
buffer and then resolved right and then
those two get out put on top of each
other based on depth right and I can't
really say that I know what else I would
do and yet so if we wanted to do it in
just one multisample pass then what we
would presumably do is we would just
yeah I mean I'm sorry but I can't I
can't really think of any way to do it
in one multi I'm pass other than just
using screen door transparency for
things on top and the reason that that
doesn't really thrill me either
is because if you think about what
that's gonna do doing three screen door
transparency and especially when you've
got like a whole floor that's getting
blended in on top like that that means
for that whole screen basically like the
whole screen because most of its gonna
be filled with that upper floor that's
in your face that whole thing is gonna
have to touch a large amount of the both
our sample buffer because the screen
dark transparency algorithm that would
be used there would be to say look
what's the Alpha supposed to be let me
cover that many of the 16 samples with
my coverage information and that would
again put it on the slow path for multi
sample meaning as we go into right a
pixel it's gonna have to write to all 14
50 15 multi samples sometimes even 16 if
it's a big fair right uh so that doesn't
seem good either and so just I don't
know I'm not thinking of a way to be
able to blend those floors in and out
with without to multi sample resolves
want to resolve the underlying floor
geometry and want to resolve the
geometry and he look huge in the upper
area right I can't really think of
anything else we can do there
so that's currently that's the best I
think I can do I don't really think
there's much else I don't really think
there's much else in the way options
so I'm gonna go ahead and assume and
this assumption may be very incorrect
but I'm gonna go ahead and assume that
we need to use at least two multi sample
resolves to get high-quality results
there and support all the features we
want to support it may be wrong about
that and if I am then maybe we can
figure out if someone has suggestions
about how we would get that number down
from two to one
but either way going from four to two
still basically is a is a species of
speed doubling right for multi sample
resolves costs twice as much as to multi
sample resolve so it's still even just
doing this one refinement would
potentially save a lot of would
potentially save us a lot of issues
right so I think we probably want to do
that and the only thing that's a little
bit tricky about it is it does mean that
we have a little bit harder work to do
in terms of how our geometry gets
segregated in two sets so if you look at
what's happening right now we have a
geometry buffer and we fill that
geometry buffer up with geometry and
then we render it and the nice thing
about that is that at least so far we
haven't really had to think about much
in terms of what's going in there other
than the fact that the game is bracketed
by two markers that say everything
inside here goes through four def peels
whereas the part that comes after it
basically I think says look you don't
have to because it's like a debug HUD
overlay or something so there's a little
bit of optimization inserted with
respect to that but in terms of the
actual game like the stuff that gets
outputted for the game image there's
nothing in there in terms of like logic
right it's just a render buffer that
just has a bunch of quads in it some of
those quads represent sprites as some of
those quads represent geometry but we
don't actually do any work to keep those
two things separate and so the render
itself doesn't really know which ones
are which and more importantly they're
not batched up in any way that would be
conducive necessarily
to making sure that we can render them
quickly because for example if geometry
and sprites want to be rendered
separately we would like all of the
geometry to be in one batch and all of
the sprites to be in another batch or
something there abouts and currently the
way that we record our render
information is we put geometry and
sprites into the same buffer so we don't
actually know at any given time which
one of the two we were using and even if
we marked them so we said these ones are
geometry these ones are sprites they
would still be interleaved in a way that
is very inconvenient for us to do it in
a single batch because a batch wants to
take a contiguous range of things
whereas we may have cases where we're
just doing like a cube and then a spray
and then acute cubes and then two
sprites and three sprites and then a
cube right and each one of those things
if we were actually doing some kind of a
split render to different render targets
would incur a render target switch and
we would just slow things down to a
crawl
so we definitely don't want to do that
which means that the one thing we would
have to do to improve this process if we
did want to stop depth peeling our
geometry and go slightly different
direction with it is we would have to
start segregating sprites and geometry
into two separate buffers so that when
you actually push a sprite onto the
render buffer it goes into one channel
and when you push a cube on those quads
go into a different channel and that way
they stack up into separate buffers and
remain contiguous the entire time which
isn't particularly hard to do but it
does introduce a little bit more
overhead in terms of us during setup
having to create multiple buffers that
we fill with differing information
basically right so uh I'm not really
sure again you know just thinking that
through it seems like the right thing to
do to make that change
but the reason I'm talking it through
extensively and a little bit hesitant is
it does sort of start to degenerate the
renderer a little bit right right now
there's not
much stuff in a renderer that's super
specific to and made hero right really
any things could sort of be dumped in
there that's a game built out of quads
you know and there's not a lot of stuff
you have to worry about in that regard
but this would definitely make a
difference it would basically say we do
need you to think about what things you
have that have alpha in which things
don't and we do need those things to be
segregated at the head end right so when
they get fed to the renderer they have
to go into separate buffers at output
time and you've got to keep that under
control right so that's the only thing
that gives me some pause apologize for
the autumn cut tired today
it's normally I do this in the morning
return it at night so that's really the
thing that that gives me some pause not
the good kind of pause like a cat has
but the bad kind of pause like when
you're not sure if it's the right
decision but it does give me some pause
since I'm like well alright you know
maybe the right answer there is to just
not go that extra mile
leave it going the way that we're going
now because it's a little bit more
general and look you just turn off multi
sampling if you're on a lower end Kravis
card and you get some crispy edges on
our geometry and you know that's just
how life is for you right so that's
certainly possible let's think about
what else week so so let me again let me
just brainstorm a little bit and think
to myself what if we wanted to turn off
multi sampling entirely like is there
anything I could do that would allow me
to just not have this problem at all you
know what I mean my guess is is the
answer there is no of course but you
know what's what's what's the options
right and so there are some things that
you know maybe we you know maybe we do
have going for us I'm trying to think
but like for example one of the things
we know is that we could produce a multi
sample buffer entirely separately if we
wanted to right we could render a pass
that just produces a multi sample buffer
it doesn't do anything else it's
basically just a multi sample depth
buffer or something I mean I don't know
exactly but just you know some kind of
multi sample buffer and so we could
produce the edge information as a
separate piece of information right I
mean we could do that if we wanted to
and so you know that would work right
like if you look at what's going on here
and you want to look at like where we're
getting you know this sort of effect so
if you look in here you can see how nice
and smooth that edge is that's what the
multi sampling is giving us right there
that particular edge right so like edges
like in there it's not has nothing to do
with because that's inside the texture
so it's by linear filtering that's
keeping all of that working properly and
mipmapping and so on that's what's
keeping the results high-quality all
inside there but anytime you see the
edge of a primitive that's the multi
sampling in action there where it's
basically getting those nice smooth edge
effects right where those things meet
because it's allowing it to record who's
getting covered in which cases right and
so that's really the thing that we're
trying to recover and the problem is you
know I could produce that edge
information in a separate pass that
would only really need one pass and
wouldn't have have to be depth filled at
all I could produce the information of
where the edges actually are
unfortunately I don't think there's
anything
I can do with that information
[Music]
so yeah I mean just thinking it through
I just don't see what I would be able to
do even if I read from a buffer that
gave me that information the problem is
if you think about how this thing is
rasterized I don't really know I mean I
don't know to what extent I could turn
on something like conservative
rasterization and just to give you some
perspective on what that is if you look
at one of these lines that you know is
drawn like this
what multi sampling requires is that you
effectively have conservative
rasterization or rasterization that
considers pixels that are mostly outside
the primitive but still slightly inside
so you can kind of see in here this
pixel right here is mostly inside the
primitive and of course it gets assigned
a correspondingly high alpha value as a
result so you can see you know this part
here that's being drawn on top of the
floor it's blending in mostly this and
only a little bit of the floor right and
so if you look at what's actually
happening this is mostly inside most of
the pixel is covered by the primitive
and as we get further up less and less
of the pixels getting covered what that
means is that if you looked at a pixel
that was like this one where you can see
that almost none of it is probably
covered so it's just at the very edge
right so only maybe just a little corner
of this pixel was actually covered by
this primitive over here if you think
about what's going on there it when you
actually switch away from multisample
rendering you're never gonna call the
pixel shader on this actual Texel I
don't I on this actual pixel because
it's not having its Center covered by
the primitive and so to the extent that
I could turn on conservative
rasterization
right meaning if I could tell the
graphics card which I never tried to do
before
but if I could tell the graphics card
look any time you would have covered one
of the sixteen multi samples in a multi
sample pattern I need you to actually
invoke my pixel shader even though there
is no multi sample target bound right
if you imagined doing that then in
theory what you could do is you could
say well if I store if I run a multi
sample then I look at the resolve of the
multi sample and I store out which
primitive was the one that was the high
coverage and which primitive was the low
coverage and what their blend ratio was
then what I could do is something where
I just take the color and I say whatever
I would have written to this pixel if
I'm the high primitive I write it in as
the term that matches that amount of
blending into the pixel and then if I'm
the low one I do the the inverse of that
right and that recovers this blend for
me without actually ever having the
multi sample there at all anymore
right so what that would allow me to do
is render one pass into the multi sample
buffer resolve the multi sample buffer
into what is basically an edge smoothing
buffer and then when I render do the
blend without actually having to have
multi sampling on at all right
I mean
it sounds like something that probably
wouldn't work and the reason is cuz I
don't know how widely support there is a
thing called conservative rasterization
that probably would do what we need to
do there but I don't know how well
supported that is like I could do a
brief search for it but I'm not super
confident that we would want to be using
something like that as a core aspect of
how we do our anti aliasing right like
that just sounds like maybe not such a
good idea for a number of reasons right
so I don't know I'm pretty apprehensive
about that
and now that I think about it another
way of looking at this problem is that
if we turned on I think I mentioned this
too back when we originally did it if we
turned on conservative rasterization
because we're currently like we are as
we speak we are we are already doing a
depth feel the depth peel would handle
the multi sampling for us so because
it's already gonna blend things on top
of each other according to their
coverage alpha values all you have to do
is just write the coverage value into
that pixel so I want to almost say that
all the crap that I just said actually
isn't necessary at all all we really
would need the thing to do is to do the
conservative rasterization and then give
us back that value like we just need to
know how many how much of this Technic
cyl was covered just give me a number
between 0 and 285 right we just need a
coverage to alpha so let's see if we can
do that right because if we could do
that multi sampler resolve is gone we
just don't need it and we'd still get
perfect anti-aliasing if we could
actually get it to do that I'm gonna
give it one more shot and I feel like I
already look for this so I'm a little
bit apprehensive about it but I'm gonna
give it a I'm gonna give it a shot
um oh great because apparently patented
always good to know probably not what
we're doing but you know I love those
pads so again this is it kind of nice
separately even if this is not something
that we can actually end up using but if
you kind of look in here this is exactly
what I was just trying to say so this is
an example of a primitive and you know
you can see how this pixel is almost
entirely outside right of the try of the
primitive that's being rasterized
nonetheless because conservative
rasterization has been turned on it
still gets covered right and that's what
conservative rasterization means it
means let's include more pixels than we
actually would would need to you know so
we're not being like aggressive right
and so you know that is precisely what I
want to turn on and so you know at least
we know somebody oops did I there we go
at least we know somebody would allow us
to do this right I it looks like
maybe these are some hold links all
right so this is how it would be done in
d3d
we could look in open Jill so here it is
so there is this conservative raster
call right and this conservative raster
call would would probably be all we
would really need to do to get started
right so let's see here
[Music]
so I'm not sure exactly we'd have to
look at how to set these up properly
because there's a little bit more to it
than that I'd have to read exactly what
those crazier but you know point being
it's it's all kind of what I respect to
see in here yes so we would just enable
this we would set some bias information
as necessary and then the only question
is inside the shader do we how do we
know how much coverage we would actually
have
um yeah so I don't see I don't see any
information you can actually use to know
how much you you've covered like what
the actual coverage is there so that's a
little bit a little bit rough and I
don't know
so you can see here it's talking a
little bit about I'm gonna read this and
see exactly what it's talking about here
but it says open ela runs a fragment
shader once for each pixel covered by a
primitive being rasterized when using
maltose sampling the outputs the
fabricator broadcast you know right what
we expect and we can also run the
fragment shader once for color sample if
we want to actually do it and then it
looks like you can also do some sort of
nonsense here where you control that a
little bit more I don't we don't really
care much about this I just want to know
if there's something if there's
something that gets passed to the shader
right
so you can see here
they are talking a lot about stuff that
interacts with the shader but I still
don't see anywhere where it actually
gets passed right you know I'm saying
so what about this
again still not seeing anything about
the shader per se right all I really
want to know is what the coverage is
this is actually saying that we would
call which we don't actually want right
and we don't want alpha-2 coverage we
want the opposite we want coverage to
alpha right we want to take however much
of the pixel is covered and we want to
get that as a value
but again just not seeing it
hey look it's the witness so I'm not
sure I am not sure what to make of that
let's see what this has to say
so these are some built-in uniforms
childen um samples is sort of saying how
many samples were covered there what is
this step modifies the fragment alpha
and coverage values based on the values
of sample alpha 2 coverage sample 51
sample coverage sample coverage value
sample coverage invert again I just want
I just want you to tell me how many
would be covered if we were multi
sampling I don't want to actually have
to turn on multi sampling right
and again I don't really see much like
GL sample mask again would just be you
know I assume only set if we were
actually in if we were actually in a
multi sample buffer and I'm assuming
that in something like you know the
conservative rasterization they're not
going to set those pieces of information
but
well this is kind of a bummer right like
I really only just want just this and I
just want to know how much was covered
and I mean I could you know if I was if
I was really gonna get ridiculous about
it I could just pass down the edge
functions myself and try to compute the
coverage directly by intersecting them
with the pixel area but I don't really
need to do that or want to do that
anymore
like I I really just need to run the
multi sample code and get that value
back right I mean maybe it is better to
do it analytically in which case yeah
what I don't have to do is send those
four edge functions down for every quad
or whatever right you just send down the
four edge functions you would intersect
those edge functions and see how much of
the pixel itself was actually covered
and I mean technically it's really only
two edge functions because for any
triangle that's in actual geometry the
only two edge functions you need are the
two that don't share an edge with the
with the other triangle of the quad
they're not making this one easy on me
are they they are not making this one
easy on me at all but in some sense I
could at least turn on conservative
raster and then in theory I could
compute the value myself
but it's a real bummer
let's see what we've got
in terms of of coverage for that anyway
like is this even an avenue worth
pursuing or not let me see here
extension search serve it is raster
hello that seems like less okay there we
go so if we take a look at what's going
on here you can see there's not a lot of
goodness here right like the number of
people who could actually benefit from
using GL &amp; GL and be conservative raster
not great right so it does seem like
we're still kind of Sol on that which
leads me to ask sort of a related
question which is is there any way to
run the hardware in multi sample mode
without actually having a multi sample
buffer right
I mean fundamentally speaking that's all
I actually really need I don't need
conservative rasterization I'm fine with
only 16 grayscale levels that's probably
good enough so if you were just to run
the multi sample routine but instead of
actually ever writing to the multi
sample buffer you just told me how many
samples were covered which you do
actually I believe that is in the
fragment shader is there any way to
enable that and say please render
everything as if it was 16x multi sample
but just don't actually waste the memory
because I don't care right is it
possible
like for example if we were to turn on
GL multi sampling but we didn't attach a
buffer that actually had multi sampling
would we get those III really don't know
we don't care about any of this by the
way
let's take a look at this multi sample
coverage the our pampas M extension
provides a mechanism for anti-aliasing
primitives the method allows this
mechanism allows an application request
additional buffer an application can
request the number of samples for
fragment rendering bla this told us yeah
coverage sample anti-aliasing is an
extension to multi sample and to the
other thing the technique separates
samples into two examples color samples
or samples with color depth and stencil
information whether messing up over
coverage samples includes with color
samples and additional samples that only
provide pixel coverage information
this extension follows the example of
the env framework for multi sample
covered extension which adds csa support
for frame buffer objects the base
description of model example rendering
is written in terms of coverage samples
and color samples the window system
ocean of samples is layered on top so
this is interesting and I have never
read this before
yeah this doesn't quite look like it
either
[Music]
we it's so close to being something we
can use and yet it keeps just slightly
evading us why can't we get that
information because it doesn't matter to
that part of the pipeline right like
there's absolutely no difference like
the part that invokes our fragment
shader absolutely does not need to know
that there is a backing store for the
samples right all it's doing is taking
and segment positions sixteen of them
actually and running the edge tests on
all sixteen and seeing which ones passed
that's all it's doing right and so we
just need that information which it
could have just done and if we can't get
access to that information we could do
it ourselves but man that's a lot more
work because now we have to pass that
transformed version of the edge
functions down into the rasterizing
stage so the fragment shader that has to
do that we have to do that in fact a
turret shader ourselves for those
sixteen samples it just seems like they
should be able to give that information
to us because they were gonna give it to
us if we would just attach that buffer
right
I mean the other thing that comes to
mind that just sounds absolutely bananas
is can you attach a multi sample and a
non multi sample render target at the
same time right because that would be
another way around this we would attach
a multi sample buffer literally for no
reason other than to force the shader to
tell us what the information was and
then we wouldn't bother to right hum to
the to the multi sample buffer right
that's another thing we could try
again it sounds absolutely ridiculous
very frustrated right now
so is there any way we're not looking is
there somewhere this could be that
actually is in there and we're just not
thinking it through right let's do one
more thing well you know what we could
also even do it here too
but well you know what I'm gonna do it
in here so if we go and we try to get
like a header file right like the gxh or
something like that right you know this
is a giant header file that in theory
just has like every possible extension
that you could possibly want in here as
of like 2018 right hopefully and so if I
was gonna search through here let me
just see if there's anything that sounds
like it might be relevant in terms of
things we might be able to enable we
know what that one was didn't really
help us those are the same versions just
ARB
again not really we there's it's gives
us a lot of opportunities for the other
direction so if for example we are in a
multi sampling mode and we want to take
our alpha value and translate the Alpha
value into a coverage against the sample
mask that's available but wait a second
that's sort of what we want right
fragment coverage to color
get that up in the in the hot seat there
let's keep on going
I'm not sure what a coverage modulation
table would be but this looks like some
way of monkeying with the samples
themselves I don't see much here that
looks like we probably care about it
though we could read about that just for
good measure
I'm interested in this since I can't
tell exactly what that's saying I am a
little bit interested to know what that
is so I want to get that one up there
too there might be something in there
that we actually care about I'm not 100%
sure so I'm gonna check it out
mm probably not
so this just looks like the standard
stuff we use I don't see anything in
here that's specific to this this is
just for when we create textures that
are multi sample textures so none of
that looks interesting so I will say
this this looks interesting
is it this one no it sorry it's this one
this one looks interesting I mean both
of them I want to read but this one
looks interesting I
it basically says like whatever the well
that isn't like that useful though
because the the kind of way they did it
looks a little bit different so it looks
like the fragment coverage won't come in
as part of the shader necessarily there
five Mikoto has enabled or disabled with
the generic attainable yep
what disabled skipped when abled the
coverage treated as an integer bit field
is substituted for the red component of
one of the fragment color values the
fragment color value updated with the
coverage mask is specified using this
that works right like it's kind of a
wonky thing but if we turned on
conservative rasterization and this that
would work that would do it and then we
wouldn't have to worry about multi
sampling at all anymore
right
but I'm just assuming this this looks
like some pre shader stuff right like
well no it's 2015 all right so I don't
know maybe I mean now let's take a look
at at whether that exists anywhere
really
so it kind of looks like basically these
Nvidia extensions just never got picked
up that's unfortunate
yeah I mean I'll double-check but just
looking grim here folks I'm is just
gonna be a sad episode I don't really
think there's much we can really do
about that it's really sad too because
basically like we don't need anything
other than just a little bit of
information would be sufficient but we
just don't get to have it unfortunately
and I'm not sure what to do about it
that it's not it doesn't like seem to be
much we could really do let's take a
look at this extension here post depth
coverage
I mean I guess another thing I I don't
really know is does GL sample masking
just maybe just work even if you don't
have multi sampling let's take a look
maybe there's some way to nudge it so it
says yeah unfortunately the the docs
just straight up right off the bats of
GL sample masking is a fragment language
that indicates this set of samples
covered by the primitive generated
fragment during multi sample
rasterization which suggests to me that
if we're not doing multi sample or
asteroids asian well we probably just
don't get a value as a sample bit said
if and only if the samples considered
covered for this fragment the array has
seal s over 32 elements where s is the
maximum number of color samples
supported by the implementation
yeah
so I I don't know man
this by the way is what we're doing
someone else on stackoverflow already
had to do it apparently right so
unfortunately again like this is
assuming that they're actually want to
use MSA which the entire point here is
we don't write we don't actually want to
do this because we don't need it
once you have order independent
transparency you don't need MSA
you just need the thing to do a
conservative rasterization pass this is
really disheartening to me because this
is clearly the right way to do it and I
think the GPU could just do it but
unfortunately it won't and that's always
what's so frustrating about GPUs you
know I don't even think the chip
probably would have a trouble doing what
I'm saying it's just you can't get at it
and so as a result that doesn't actually
help you right well that was a colossal
waste of all of our times so I guess I'm
gonna go ahead and say that I'm gonna
have to make a friend at Nvidia and be
like hey man why can't we have this is
there a reason we don't have this why
can't we have a handmade hero extension
that's just like when you turn on
conservative rasterization you can say
to set the sample mask to like whatever
the number of samples you want like look
just pretend there are 16 samples I
don't care that there aren't just
pretend there are you know like what
what's it to you man
that seems like the most sane thing to
do because I don't know what else to do
but really there's no reason for our
code to be doing stuff as crazy as it's
doing it really just does not need that
even a little bit I should
well the render buffers for ad they're
not gonna help us
so really we should spend the rest of
this handmade hero like rendering us
frowny face because I'm pretty sure that
we're just totally hung out to dry by
our GPU friends here I don't see any way
to do the obvious thing that would be
fast here and unless I'm just not
thinking of how to trick the graphics
card into doing what we needed to do it
just there's no way around this we're
forced to spend a tremendous amount of
memory and bam for absolutely no reason
just to smooth out these lines when our
def PA would have just worked
all right
so is there anything else is there
anything I'm not thinking of I don't
think so um so yeah I guess that's all
pretty sad so let's do one more thing
while we're here
wallowing in sadness um one of the thing
I did want to do that's you know and I
guess I you know I shouldn't maybe be so
disheartened because you know now I
think about it you know maybe there is
one kind of less good case there which
is that the triangles that form like the
quad in question they're like you know
where the two triangles touch if you
don't use a multi sample buffer then how
would you know that those two triangles
are actually like coplanar and shouldn't
have like a seam so you know like I can
sort of see why you might care about
that part of it at the same time it does
kind of seem to me like that's really
not that big of a deal for us to fix
because we know that they're always
coplanar at that point so like hey man
for optimization purposes I still think
we could have done a much better job
there but anyway since I'm sad and I
don't care anymore I do want to do one
more thing which would be to say that
when you look at how our death peel is
working currently one thing that's not
particularly good is if you look at the
difference between these color passes
what you can see is that we are doing
one thing that's fairly smart right
which is that we're doing our color
passes in the order in which they would
be seen by the viewer so color pass
number one is the things that are
closest to us color paths number two are
the things that are behind those things
Clark Pass number three is the things
behind those things and color pass for
and so on right and so the only thing
that I think we might want to change
about this is if you think about what's
going to happen as we add lighting in
here when you look at this and you think
about how many lighting calculations are
going to occur well they're going to
occur for every pixel in the entire
buffer which may be fine
maybe we subsample it who knows but
point being something happens here and
those lighting calculations are
expensive if we then go to this next one
here then what we would find is that
actually a bunch of these things can't
be seen so if you look here right like a
lot of the stuff that we depth peel away
can't actually be seen and when we buy
the time we get to here we just most of
it can't be seen right there are things
that are just like too far behind other
objects and finally get the things that
probably aren't seen at all so the thing
that's that's not good about that is
that once we start to increase the
pressure on the pixel shading by
including all these complicated lighting
calculations we're going to start to
tank our frame rate by 4x because what's
happening is we draw the entire screen
and spend a ton of time lighting it and
then we draw the entire screen again
it's been a ton of time lighting that
right and that means that we're gonna
spend four times as much as much GPU
resources lighting our scene than we
actually needed to because we only
probably needed to light the things that
are closest to you and maybe one thing
behind that but oftentimes not even that
for many pixels in the scene because
most of the pixels of scene are a pig
right so one thing we might want to do
is augment our actual color past shader
such that when you actually go to draw
something you only draw something if the
previous pass didn't have something
opaque in that slot in other words the
alpha value that's actually in the slot
when you actually get there if the alpha
value that's in the slot that you would
need so you know I draw the first pass
and I've got a particular pixel
I know what the both the depth value and
the alpha value are for that pixel when
I go to render the thing behind it if
the alpha value was opaque I don't want
to render this thing at all right
that's just fundamentally not what we
want now in order to do that literally
as I just said it we would have to read
from the color buffer as well as the
depth buffer because the thing I just
said was we need to see if the alpha
value is opaque but at the moment we're
only reading from the depth buffer so
one thing we could do is start reading
from two buffers at the same time when
we do that render pass we read from the
depth buffer and the Alpha buffer and we
see if both of them are what we need
them to be but with a little observation
I think we could easily figure out a way
of not having to do that but getting the
effects as if we did and what I think we
could do is say look we know that what a
depth field does is on a depth peel
reads from the depth buffer from the
previous pass and it says I'm only gonna
render things that are further away from
the viewer than what's in the depth
buffer for the previous pass there by
peeling away the scene one layer at a
time that's why it's called death
peeling that's what it does so what that
means is that for any particular
location on the screen I can prevent
anyone from drawing on any pass to that
location by simply putting a value in
the depth buffer that is further away
from the camera than anything else could
possibly be which is basically the
highest possible depth value or lowest
possible depth value depending on when
you whether you want to think about
things is getting higher as they go
further away or lowers they get further
away right but either whatever way you
think of it whatever the one that
represents things for this from the
camera stick that value in nothing will
ever compare favorably to that and so
nothing will get drawn from then on
right and that's an if statement we can
do around the entire shader nothing at
all needs to execute if that
doesn't pass and so what we could do is
save all of that potentially expensive
lending calculations only for regions of
the screen that actually have a 4 by 4
block that are actually going through
that because remember the if statement
doesn't save us any time if we don't
actually get all of the pixels in a
little chunk to go through that same
route of the if because much like we did
in our actually no we didn't did we used
RGB I think so nevermind but point being
they work on sets of say 16 pixels at a
time sometimes more and so if all 16
pixels don't go through the same path on
it if you don't really save any time but
for our case because oftentimes they
will
I think we'd save against the whole
amount of time now unfortunately like I
said we're saving time in this place
here that we don't really care about as
much but I think it's worth doing that
anyway because even though these numbers
aren't high they're about to get high as
we as we start to increase the amount of
work the shader has to do to do that
lighting so if we wanted to do that
again I think it's a pretty easy
modification now we're in GPU land so
there are no real easy modifications
it's always more complicated than it
needs to be but it's at least one of the
simpler of the hard modifications that
you might want to make so if I pop over
to our OpenGL obsess the wrong one open
jail code here what I'm gonna want to do
is I want to go ahead and look at our Z
bias program and that's not the one I
want alright so here in the Z bias
program where I'm doing this compilation
what you can see here is when I go
through this particular section of the
code the fragment shader which is the
bottom one here which has the letting
disabled at the moment because we
haven't put in the full new lighting
what we're going to do is when we enter
the main program if it was a depth peel
you can see us doing a discard right
away and that discard operation will
prevent
anything else from occurring for the
remainder of the shader what that means
is that I can pretty simply just add to
this structure here anything that I
might need to do as long as I end up in
this discard path I won't pay any more
cost if if all of the pixels in a warp
happen to go through that that same path
right so you can see here we've got a GL
frag cord Z and a clip depth the clip
depth is the value that we're reading
out of the depth sampler which is the
previous frame that's why the first
frame the previous the previous peel on
this frame what that means is that if we
set this clip value to something so here
we got this GL frag cord Z right and
we're checking to see if it's less than
the clip depth right if it's less than
the clip def it will Dakar discard what
that means is that if we just set the
clipped up clip depth to basically like
the far clip plane right as far away as
a capacity B we will discard everything
right so all we really need to do is in
here where we're going to write to the
depth buffer and don't ask me what that
else discard is there I guess it's
probably for the Alpha huh yeah
you can see here we've got an alpha
threshold where we just throw things
away if they're too low so the alpha
threshold that we come up with we then
would discard here we basically just
need a similar one of these that will
replace the depth value with something
high in the case where the alpha value
is really like very very solid right so
we here we would just need something
like look if blend unit color a equals
one right so it's basically the highest
possible one there is no transparency
whatsoever if we want to just specify a
fully opaque pixel at this point then
all we would have to do is basically say
like whatever we write to the depth
buffer here which I believe is a
constant we can just set it I'm not a
constant a pre named variable I believe
we can set in open jail
whatever we want to write to the depth
buffer here we just need to make sure
that it's very very high right so
something that that would exceed pretty
much all of our anything that you would
ever want to write to write so for
example if we look at our fogging here
right we got our fog distance our clip
distance all this stuff we actually
already have a bunch of information here
like our fog and distance that says
where the fog cuts out for example right
so we kind of already know what this
stuff is and in theory we may also I
don't know if we get access to the far
clip plane but we can actually just pass
down an f32 here if we want to however
in this case I may say we just won't
bother like maybe we just set this to
some very high value and call it a day
now when we do a right death buffer here
that's some nonsense I mean up we
actually need to go look up what the
GLSL output name is for the depth buffer
so forth and in fact actually though we
already know that actually right it's in
here isn't it don't we output to the
depth buffer maybe now no we don't we
only because we don't need to keep it
well no in the multi sample resolve we
would though right so in theory we
should have already had to have looked
up what the heck you call it in the
OpenGL Naumann clay Chur so when we do
the resolve and here it should do it
right so that right that's it right
there
yeah
so if we then go back to our compile Z
bias program in here if I basically just
say alright when we are going to come to
me when we are going to write an opaque
pixel we also then tell the wheel I
basically and say look pixel shader men
this is like this super far away value
that we're going to put in here right we
could do that um the problem with this
approach and why we'll have to do
something once that clever more clever
here right is that if I were to do it
here the problem we would have is our
depth sorting wouldn't work anymore
because we're relying on that GL frog
depth to be written properly in order to
make our depth sort work for this peel
itself so I can't really do exactly that
but luckily for me since we're already
going through a multi sample resolve and
of course we have to go through a multi
sample resolve because as it turns out
there doesn't seem to be any way to turn
that off and still get smooth edges even
though I feel like we should have been
able to do that and that was very sad
earlier inside the multi sample result
we are done computing the fragment
depths right this is the final fragment
depth that we're actually going to use
and the final blend unit color we're
actually going to use for that depth
peel which means that after we do
whatever the heck actual stuff were is
we're going to do right and we go down
to the end of the shader I can't at that
time doing here right so if that blend
unit color the value that we're actually
writing out there is going to be a fully
opaque then I can just set the GL frag
depth to be something incredibly large
and that's the end of the game right so
I think that should be all we really
have to do the only thing I'm not 100%
sure about there is she
frog depth is you know probably ranges
from negative one to one would have been
my guess so I'm thinking that really the
maximum value wouldn't have to be in
world space it would probably only have
to be in fragments in you know clip
space so I'm thinking that probably 1.0
is a high enough value because that
would be the maximum that you would ever
hit right but I don't actually know
right like I don't remember how we set
this up that's one of the problems of
handmade hero being such little chunks
over so long is my brain doesn't really
keep track of what we did you know six
months ago or something right and it has
to page it back in which is annoying but
point being it's some value who knows
that we set it up it's a floating point
depth buffer I assume the values would
be between negative one and one that may
be erroneous assumption I don't know I'm
not a GPU guy it's not my job anyway um
so I'm gonna see what happens in that
circumstance right can I basically blot
out those pieces and stop having to
spend time on things that really
probably shouldn't have had time spent
on them right so if I go ahead and
launch I'm not gonna save the capture
for any particular purpose if I go ahead
and launch here
you know the game stills rendering okay
so we can't have broken anything to
catastrophic aliy and we could say also
see whether or not the depth sorting is
working you know I mean it probably is
cuz everything appears to be deb sorted
properly so we again I don't think we
could probably have broken anything too
badly and the Alpha is working there too
so let's suppose we hopped up on here
and then took one of those captures and
just see did I actually change anything
right because I don't know if I actually
did and then we look it on here so
there's that full screen and here's what
happens on the first color pass exactly
as I suggested previously when we were
talking about how so much stuff gets
covered you can see the basically like
the entire thing is almost completely
opaque like there really isn't a lot of
deaf people and going on here there's
some little stuff probably happening in
there
that's really basically it so in this
next pass yeah
so this worked perfectly exactly as I
hoped right so this next pass you can
see there's almost nothing rendered and
that's exactly what I wanted
we're only rendering pieces of the
screen that actually needed to be
rendered which is pieces that were like
behind some partially transparent piece
right and then in the final one you can
see us getting even more interested
minutiae of things that were alpha on
top of alpha and then finally in the
last one there should be almost nothing
right it would have to be like where
multiple edges of multiple things
intersected and so that again has the
potential of it's not going to be much
of a difference now but if you look at
these numbers in the future since I can
easily turn that piece of code on and
off I think as these numbers start to
grow larger I think we will start to see
we'll start to see those become relevant
right now there's another thing we could
do potentially as I'm saying and I'm not
sure if we could actually do it but you
know point being death that's what
exactly what I wanted to have happen and
hopefully you understand what I did
there right it's it's pretty
straightforward use of the shader result
so another thing we could consider doing
there is if you look at how the resolve
itself works when we're resolving what
we're doing is we're reading we're
basically blending values together right
we're saying we're gonna take in these
values of these samples and we're going
to blend them together and then we're
going to output the results that's the
notion of a resolve right and the slow
part of this is the fact that we have
this if true here right so this if true
this is basically the thing that is
saying do I actually need to resolve
this pixel that's the thing I wish I
could not have to do right if I set that
to false so we just don't do multi
sampling anymore then what happens when
I launch this application no I don't
want to save this capture and you know I
do the the nonsense here get a look at
what the timings quote-unquote are even
though I don't really think they're that
accurate what you can see it's just
representative wise these draw are eight
calls that don't you know everything is
the same we're still attaching a multi
sample buffer we're still using a multi
sample rendering we're doing everything
exactly the way that you would expect so
nothing has changed all we're doing is
that when we go to resolve it we just
don't read from it right we just take
the first color sample and the other 15
never touched right just that is if
these timings are at all accurate which
we don't know if there are but let's say
that they were at least proportional we
saved like 10x right it's not 16x
exactly but it's close right it's
getting up there so you can see just how
expensive that resolve was and that
prompts the question is there some way
that we could simulate that if statement
and even though we're not getting any
help from the GPU here as much as we
would like is there something I could do
that would solve this problem for us and
what you just saw was a good example of
perhaps how that problem might be solved
right there's two things we could do
that would fix this right thing number
one would be what if we just read from
the previous depth feel when we do this
resolve
and if in that slot the the depth value
suggests that we've already made this
opaque or we read the alpha value let's
say so we basically know the alpha value
we're not going to use this value then
we just don't resolve it just leave it
blank right I mean we don't even need
this the else Clause goes away right we
literally just just leave it garbage
because no one's ever gonna look at it
right so that's one thing and then the
second thing we could do and this is if
we were feeling like a real saucy
so-and-so is we could try to construct a
buffer that would have that information
in it separately right and the way we we
do that is what I was suggesting before
we would basically do one render of an
actual multi sample target resolve it
and then the only thing that we leave in
the color channel is like a 1 or a 0
that is should I blend this right as I'm
saying that I don't think that actually
works because you need to do it for
every peel so I take that back that's
not really true yeah so I don't really
think that that's that's accurate I lied
there so the first one I think is true
right and the second one is false right
but I do think that yet if we wanted to
right we could say fetch the color or
fetch the depth our choice but basically
it would just look like this Texel fetch
from basically like a mask sampler same
set up is everything else and instead of
sampling it multi sampled which we're
doing with the other one we would we
would not
we would look at the Alpha Channel and
we would basically say if the mask value
that you see here is less than one right
then we know that we will actually be
blending so go ahead and compute
whatever that value is right and then
when you're done right that I was normal
otherwise just don't do anything right
like this doesn't have to happen so
that's one thing we can do right and
that would probably help us here
I want to say there's another thing we
can do here and we probably should which
is that while we're doing that we should
just build the output buffer right at
the moment we have this nonsense right
so at the moment we've got this nonsense
happening here where we do a final
fullscreen quad we take for depth I'm
sorry for color samples and we blend
them together using their alpha values
using this equation right so we take the
final one we then blend in the one on
top of it the one on top of that and
then the one on top of that right but
actually there's no reason why we would
need to do that I don't think we could
just treat it as an accumulator probably
I'll have to work out the math to see
whether the coverage makes sense there
or not but honestly like
you know right it seems like saving up
for copies of the screen and then
combining them with that equation I mean
can't we just do it incrementally and
only keep one buffer around it kind of
seems like it right and so I do feel
like maybe this is a little bit long in
the tooth and we should probably get rid
of that as well so we'll think about
that maybe that'll be Sunday what I want
to do now is again probably do that
hookup that I just said so basically if
I was to jump back to that Z by shooter
here and we take a look at this so when
we go through here and I'm sorry not not
that I meant the resolved
I meant the resolved where's that
resolved so if we go to compile resolve
multisample so really I think you know
this does make a lot of sense let's
fetch that mask and let's only resolve
these samples if we actually have to
it's not as good as what I would have
wanted which is some way of knowing
whether we need to do this even on the
first step feel but at least this might
speed up the second third and fourth
theft feels and that's not nothing
taking something that takes four times
the time to taking just one times the
time hey man that's a huge improvement
even though it's not the perfect
improvement that I would have hoped for
it's not bad
right so if I said here there was
another sampler 2d for the mask sampler
there and we went to compile peel blah
blah blah right when we look at open
Jill create program and Link samplers oh
nope sorry result - am I on the wrong
road again too many samplers yeah if you
do open gellick samplers on this one you
could see here we're even it's this is
old
we were even asking for some other ones
here that we didn't actually even need
so that's kind of a waste of time there
but anyway point being we already had it
set up to be doing more texture samples
anyway and now we actually will so now
we'll get the mask sampler out there now
when we run this we won't put anything
in that channel and so actually I think
it won't do anything at first because
there won't be anything enabled in that
texture channel so at first I want to
say and maybe everything will just come
crashing down now but I want to say that
at first if I just run it without
actually doing the any work that we
should actually see just what we know so
there is an error there so it doesn't
like the fact that we're not binding
that mask that mask sampler I guess or
there's a error in this code which may
also be the case so let's go ahead and
run it under remedy so we can actually
see what there is and I can read it and
fix the code so if I go in here and look
at what the they are there's vertex
errors it's probably a fragment error
right because we weren't editing the
vertex shader so it's unlikely right but
let's see what it says of course they
don't think remedy has a way to do this
but it's on line 83 unable to find
compatible what unable to find
compatible overloaded function ah yes
sorry this is the fact that it's textile
fetch but that's not what we would
actually use because textile fetch I
think is only for sample index so I
don't think we want that although we may
still want it with just a textile fetch
of zero so let me see which one we
actually want to use because yeah okay
so now we do we just want to pass the
zero right so we do want this we want a
sample at zero which is you know the
only one that that texture pass because
it's not a multi sample touch so let's
try running it again there we go so now
I'm not sure again whether or not we
broke anything with that because during
that resolve now we're
looking at that mass value and it's not
guaranteed to actually be anything valid
right so let's look in here and see what
we're getting in terms of yeah it's it's
looking a little busted right I think
like I don't know why I'm getting some
I'm getting some garbage in there so I
think it's I think it's a little busted
right which is what I would expect and
let me just verify that that's true if I
were to comment this out right so I
would say that this is just fifth one
right and so we're not doing that mask
test we still do the fragment fetch but
we don't actually use it right let me
just verify that that actually produces
oh well okay just a cast sorry if true
so if I run this again just making sure
again I I want to make sure that those
artifacts are gone so that I wasn't are
you serious what is the problem
syntax error unexpected dollar sign end
at token yeah what the heck what are you
talking about can't just do if true did
I accidentally insert some kind of
garbage in there
not sure what that's actually
complaining about I mean correct me if
I'm wrong but all I did was change that
part right so if I compile this you're
saying it's fine maybe it's not true
some other thing I thought it was true I
thought it was just TR Yui was what it
wanted for those things not sure I see
what the problem is there so that works
fine but for some reason that like
doesn't work
I don't know anyway I want to go see if
this artefacts are still there I'm just
going to go ahead and here and just
verify that they're not and you could
pretty much see that they're not so I am
correct in thinking that that all seems
to work just fine and so now what we
need to do is actually hook this up this
mass sampler here and feed the color
buffer in for example right and so if we
wanted to feed the color buffer in what
we need to be able to do here is do this
only when we are actually depth feeling
is the only thing and so that makes it a
little bit trickier than normal because
we wouldn't necessarily have a color
buffer to feed this thing but we might
be able to trick that out right because
we'll we'll see when we get there when
we're actually setting up our depth
samples I'm sorry we're actually setting
up our peels whether or not that that
actually happens so let's take a look
inside here where we've got begin peels
right so you can see it's setting up the
color buffer there normally we clear it
to zero zero zero so we could actually
also clear the resolve target and feed
that in probably let's see so when we do
a resolve multi sample here right so
this is the the one right and so when we
bind the textures here we bind the the
thing we're gonna be sampling for for
the color tubing I'm sorry for it for
the depth and then we do the color here
and we only I don't know why we have
multiple color channels at the moment
actually because there should only be
one probably right but
yeah so we only have the surface reflect
so this stuff with things for thing for
when we were doing fancier stuff and
we're not really doing that anymore so
we don't really have to worry about that
but basically what happens is we're
gonna bind the DEF handle then we're
gonna bind the color handle and when you
look back at the code there where is my
there we go we look back at the code
here we want the color the depth and the
mask and honestly the fact that these
coming in the opposite order that
doesn't make a lot of sense to me I feel
like the way these are bound is like
depth and then color and so the fact
that they're opposite each other I don't
understand how that works right
I guess they must be specified in the
opposite order in the compile depth so
that's 0-1 and yeah they are all right
so we should probably be a little more
consistent there so depth first then
color then mask same here
depth color mask okay so in here if we
wanted to bind these right we would just
do this and in that texture slot there
we would want to put whatever came from
the previous depth feel so the previous
depth feels color result like resolved
color is what we would put in here and
since we don't actually know that in the
case of the first step feel because
there isn't anything there we would want
to be able to stuff that value with
something that wouldn't get looked up or
use a different shader depending on the
circumstances and you know depending on
how we want to do it but if we take a
look at how this would work we would end
up in a circumstance where when we are
doing this resolved here we would want
to bind the previous peel so let's take
a look at resolve multi-sample
so in here where we're going to be doing
the peels you can see us saying we're
going to go from this thing to whichever
one were on right and what we want to do
is say well in addition to that we've
also got the mask and that's going to be
this right but obviously we don't always
have that so what we want to do is
probably say well the mask
buffer is going to have to be probably
the to buffer itself and will probably
have to clear it in the case where we
can't do this right so we want to do
here is say look if we're on peel index
zero so we're actually like just peeling
the you know we're doing the first
render pass that isn't really a depth
peel in the first place then there's a
couple of different things we could do
certainly but the simplest possible one
I would suspect is to just say look in
that case the mask is whatever we're
going to and we'll clear it right so
that's what I would suspect we probably
would want to do right in the case where
we're not on the first depth peel then
the mask actually is a valid resolved
buffer and it's this one right it's the
one that came prior now the issue here
again and you know honestly maybe you
I'm thinking about it maybe we don't
even want to do that maybe there's just
a stuffing value that we throw in here
right and the stuffing value it's it's
just always zero so what we could do
instead is say yeah okay so in our
OpenGL right where we've got whatever
the heck happening here we know we're
gonna have stuff like a standard texture
that's just all-white that we like stuff
in there sometimes and maybe we also
want a texture we stuff in there that's
like always all black right so we can
basically just like pick when we don't
really actually want supply a legitimate
texture to something we can just have a
solid color texture sitting around and
we we hand that instead right and so
what that would look like is we just say
okay
there's a single pixel that's just all
black right and maybe like maybe that so
it's not it's not actually that it's
black with a 1 in the Alpha Channel it's
actually all 0 so it's really no color
at all right it's like completely not
there it's invisible right and we just
set that mask up and then feed that in
and run the resolved multi sample as
normal right I think that's all we would
really need to do and so it's not too
bad if we look I don't know whether
we've actually got this in our bindings
currently to create some textures like
that but it's not too hard for us to do
either way and so if I look I'm not sure
so here's an init function right and you
can see that here doing this creating
this sort of white value to pass down
just don't know if anyone actually ever
uses it but it's basically what we want
to do for the all zeroes value right so
what we would want to do there is like
yeah again to prepare that texture I
don't really see much we can do there
but so let's just do this right or seven
all zeroes value we say look give me one
of these things
wouldn't I call it again so we have one
of these things we generate one of these
single pixel all zeroes texture right we
then do a text image 2d and we just say
like look this thing is just going to be
this all zeroes right and so it's gonna
be a 1x1 I don't really remember the
parameters of Geo text in which 2d you
know sue me
oh it's right there nope nope no so we
pretty much don't ever call that do we
look all right so if I just go ahead and
oops if I just go ahead and submit this
one down right so we know it's a gel
texture 2d I don't know what the format
is so we'll have to go look that up but
the width and the height are 1 it's you
know the same as everything else we go
down but it doesn't really matter so we
could just use this and leave it at that
and then we just pass it all zeroes
right and so then all we really need to
do is just fill this out and so I can
actually look at what we were filling
that out as well so I don't actually
have to look at the GL documentation so
that format value here is what passed in
just kind of coming to dare it is so I'm
going to do a frame buffer text image
[Music]
just glr gb8 probably right
so that would create that special
texture for us so it would do a gem
textures to get one and I'll need to
actually put that in here so there's
just a you know we went for that so we
generate the textures and we'd have a
happy times for that oh and this buying
texture here just needs to actually have
masks it's not a frame buffer per se
though right or is it yes so we actually
want to pass the specific color a handle
so what I actually want here is I want
this so I really just want to bind that
mask texture directly and then when we
call resolve multisample I'm either
gonna pass it the color handle of the
frame buffer that we actually used or
you know I'll
yeah and that these are the multi sample
buffers right - so this we actually
don't even want that I just want the
depth field buffers right so I actually
want I just want the DEF peel resolve
buffer and in that case like I guess
they just don't have those filled in but
either way so in here where we get the
mask it's not bad right
it's actually this
right something like this and so then
we're saying look just stuff it normally
and I got actually past that stuff it
normally with just you know whatever the
previous color channel was and then in
circumstances where we don't have a
previous channel because it's the first
step feel fill it in with all zeros
right so we can see if that does
anything good it might not but we'll see
in a second let's see first if we're
getting any actual artifacts here
can't quite tell I'm not convinced yet I
didn't break it
I think it's still broken I feel like
that's not quite right
yeah I'm definitely seeing a few
artifacts in there so I think it was a
valiant effort but we're still a little
bit off right just a little bit but
we're close anyway if we actually take a
look at what happens now we're we're
passing a mass value and we use the mass
value determine whether or not we should
blend set that mass value in such a way
that we at least hope that the Alpha
Cham tells us what we actually need to
know and in fact if we look here we can
also see let me just verify in resolve
multi-sample
let me just verify yeah we're we're
using from color handle this is the this
when we do an open gel begins screen
fill it's gonna use that frame buffer
and that frame buffer would only have
just the color buffer if I'm not
mistaken so I think that's fine so let's
take a quick look at that and render
dock and then we'll call it a day but I
think we do have a bug in there so I'm
gonna have to be a little bit more
careful and look through that with more
oh sorry render dock
all right so now looking through here I
just want to verify that it does what I
think it should do and let's see so yeah
not really so these are kind of semi
nonsensical results that I'm looking at
here
all right so when we first do this it
looks like the mask is never succeeding
did I like screw up that change I don't
know we can look and see if I screwed it
up if mask is less than one from the
thing that you put well so I mean
correct me if I'm wrong but if I had
actually succeeded in stuffing it with
all zeros then this mask value should
always be less than one right it should
always be zero because no matter where
you sample it or what channel you pull
hero is going to get zero right so that
seems a little odd to me
but let's keep going so if I were to
look at this particular pass we know
this is probably correct because we
haven't touched the color pass we look
at the drawer rays pass I just want to
know what went in here right so what am
I actually getting when that was kind of
a nice little mesh view there anyway
what am I actually getting when I look
at the fragment shader what's coming in
here right and so if I look at the depth
sampler I can't actually tell that's
what I expect to see here I'm not sure
why I don't see a depth buffer properly
but maybe I've got these things bound
backwards that would make a lot of sense
right let's look at the mask I'm not
sure how to use render dock really I
don't know how to look at these things
so texture 51 like I should shouldn't
there be something that says like how
big it is I guess that one by one is the
thing zero by zero zero by zero doesn't
seem right so that seems a bit bad okay
let's take a look at the color sampler
if I'm doing this right that's what we
would expect to see there and then
finally the depth sampler oh you know
what I'm thinking the wrong button that
there it is okay
those all occur to the only thing that
looks busted to me is it I don't
understand what I'm looking at there I
may have submitted this texture wrong so
let's take a look I made that it's easy
to do that let me just it's probably
some typos nonsense so oh yeah
fantastic so that may be the only
problem there oops
alright so let's see if that's any
better because what I was doing is I
wasn't actually initializing that
texture actually set the wrong value
there so let's try that one more time
see if this changes the perceived
results here at all all right so if I go
up here like I was doing before and kind
of look at one of those edges to see
what I can see and again it doesn't look
right right I'm getting like leakage
there I think so I still think we're not
not getting it right maybe we're a
little closer but not right oh you know
what I do want debug that though because
that was very handy so let's take a
screenshot there f12 and then close it
so looking through here let's take a
look at this pass again right and so
here's the first drawing Clark pass
here's the draw arrays illness this time
it's not all black so it looks like it
did properly pass right to me so that's
good right you can see that resolved and
you can see furthermore that it looks
like it did anti aliased properly right
so the first pass now looks good it was
busted before it looks like it's less
busted
now the second pass as you might expect
is rendering kind of where we would I
guess expect it to because that's where
two primitives are meeting and fighting
for supremacy potentially right
I don't want to know why that's purple
but maybe it's a lighting probe and then
when we draw a race here we're actually
resolving it that seems like it could be
fine I mean I don't know that there's
anything particularly wrong with that
what I would say is it looks like the
depth is ah yes we do need to save the
depth buffer yes because it needs to go
in to the resolve for the depth peel so
we do need to write one piece of
information in there which is to say
that we because we're not rendering the
same depth buffer every time we do need
to when this doesn't work we do need to
at least write out the depth that does
have to happen so when we do this else
we do want to do that I don't know that
we really need to output a color because
if we're not going to use this color we
probably don't need it intended ly we
don't eat a frag depth either
so these fetches probably aren't
necessary so I want to say we can
probably do this right and then just set
the GL frag depth to be like stop right
don't depth peel anymore I think that
might be a little more correct let's
find out so if I now go to the launch
and get this going here no I don't want
to say the capture uh oh that's probably
just us crashing and not having a set
this correct
we probably don't write to blend unit
color alright so we need to write some
of the blend unit here probably I would
guess just to avoid any issues so we
probably need to write some black
channel out we could change it to like a
purple as well so we can see it but you
know either-or so we do need to write
something of the blend unit color
probably I'm guessing or the compile
will fail we can go look and see if
that's actually it maybe that wasn't it
there we go let's take a look
syntax error unexpected and at token it
keeps giving me that what is it talking
about I have no idea what it's actually
complaining about they're like none at
all it seems like very unhappy but I'm
not sure about what so let's suppose we
just did this see if that makes it any
more happy and actually now
I really don't know if that's part of
the problem of this like embedding this
thing in the code if it's getting
confused or something but I don't see
what it's objecting to because the code
looks fine right like I don't see I mean
we didn't do really anything maybe we
get rid of a couple of these cases here
but I want to keep that Multi stamping
debug in there you know I'd like that to
remain in there
yeah I really just don't see what the
what the crime is right so basically
what you're telling me is previously we
had this and that was fine
right like everyone loves that no one
has any problem with that that's
fantastic the shader compiles like yes
really good how's that and that's fine
everyone loves that everyone thinks
that's really good that should also have
fixed the bug by the way so meaning I
would expected that too but actually
doesn't look like it did weird that's
all this disheartening Jimmy but then
apparently like if you commented those
out that would be like horrible like you
can't definitely can't do that or
something nope still okay
I have no idea what this is doing I have
no idea why I didn't like this
all right well I don't know and I don't
want to know I'm just gonna set the frag
depth to one and since that seems to be
okay who knows maybe we'll have to do
something a little fancier there with
how work oops with Howard submitting
shaders so that we can put them in
separate files I don't know but anyway I
would have thought that writing the
fragment depth there would have solved
the problem but it didn't solve the
problem and so that suggests to me that
I'm not quite sure still what is wrong
I've got it I've got it wrong I've got
it wrong in my head not just in the app
so if I take a look at this right again
that looks like a pretty good resolve
they're kind of what I would expect
there's the initial pass these are multi
samples here if I then do this resolve I
expect it to get smooth right and it
does now if I do this I expect to see
places only where primitives overlap I'm
not 100% sure that that's okay but I
think it probably is because those
primitives do occupy potentially the
same location right and so then when
that resolves we get that then we do the
next pass yeah I don't know why we're
really getting those cracks let's take a
look at that when I if I don't use the
mask input right but by the way also
when we look at this here if I actually
try to analyze how what the speed is
like I'm not sure if these are actually
representative actually looking at that
it looks kind of semi nonsensical
actually but anyway if you believe this
wildly now different set of numbers
possibly because we moved the camera
you can see that the original resolve is
expensive these are considerably less oh
right
and if that one is very expensive and I
have no idea why like that doesn't make
a lot of sense either does it so I I
don't know we're still a little bit
busted here we're kind of over time so I
should probably wrap it up but point
being I do think we should probably go
ahead and and push forward on that and
make sure we get that working because I
do think it would be fairly substantial
savings again if you just change this to
always being true so basically this
which of course it probably just
complained that for some reason now
we've written a completely ridiculous
shader that doesn't work but if we just
set that to always being true when we
run the application no thank you
that is so frustrating is that a problem
with for coder or a problem with I don't
know what that's problem with like it
really just doesn't make any sense
how about that we have not had this
problem before I wonder if it's because
of virtual white space actually in for
coder I'm not sure but we can take a
look
yeah I mean that's just garbage I mean
that's just total garbage
so I don't really know what to make of
that it could because of virtual
whitespace I'm not really sure it's
super annoying and really stupid and the
kind of thing that I hate about
developing software ever because it's
like it should not be something that I
ever have to think about what I'm
actually working and yet it's like 50%
of what I have to think about so I just
want to switch this off for a second and
leave it that way because I'd rather
come back to tomorrow knowing that it
wasn't broken in some other way right
that seems to be a hugely impossible
thing to ask of see and/or for coder I
don't know or perhaps just OpenGL so I'm
not sure why I can't you know it could
be that if I changed these let's just
hypothesize here if I changed all of
these comments to only be comments that
were C style then maybe it since it
doesn't matter where the line breaks are
at that point maybe that works because
it could be that what it was doing was
interpreting those comments as going
longer than they should have gone you
know what I mean
so I'm wondering if I just do this does
that solve the problem
nope so yeah I mean I have no idea what
it doesn't like doesn't really make any
sense to me it could be again pound
defiance probably wouldn't work either
in that case or pound ifs as well so if
it was getting confused about where the
line breaks are for some reason that
could be what I could do is look at what
the code is actually on disk that's
probably a good idea so if I come in to
remedy let's see what remedy thinks that
parse is like because it's not using the
virtual whitespace thing so if I
actually went into that code shouldn't I
know if I spelled it spelled it wrong
why did I get them I couldn't actually
get in there oh it probably just didn't
lined it no worries I'll just look at it
this way
so here's compiled resolve mother
example as it was written to disk here
is the fragment code right
you know it looks normal to me firm
pretty much all intents and purposes I
it doesn't look like for coders doing
anything weird there to me the error
output by the shader compiler is
horrible like it doesn't tell you at all
what's going on so I'm not sure I'm
grumpy but I'm not sure so I don't know
I also did that it didn't work I don't
know what's going on there I really
don't that's extremely frustrating and
it makes development that's almost
impossible so I'm gonna have to I guess
that's what we're actually doing Sunday
since there's no chance I can possibly
keep going with it just randomly failing
like that for no reason but I guess
that's where we're at so if I go through
here and when we do the Texel fetch I
just need some way of nerfing just this
one line right and so what I was trying
to do before you say well I would like
to set mask and maybe I just do it
without a carriage return I don't know I
would like to set mask to zero if
possible you know just to make sure that
it still works if I do that
all right and so then if I look in here
I'm just curious can does there still
have a bug so the bug is still there
even with that not happening so maybe
it's a little overblown maybe this
happens always so if I was to remove
that code entirely like we're just not
doing that anymore
so it only does the full the full
resolve and there's no checking
whatsoever right we just have that bug
like we've had that bug for the entire
time apparently and it just doesn't
really matter because you have to like
get up so close to see it or something
it does appear right like it's there
so I don't know unless we just
introduced that in some other way it
does look like actually this just worked
so I guess I can't leave that in because
it looks like that I didn't actually
introduce a bug now I still would want
to be a little more careful about that
but it does look like on the whole I
don't know I'm seeing artifacts that I
didn't see before though so I'm not
willing to believe that yet I still feel
like we've got issues here is it back
where it's just doing the the composite
at all times
and you know I don't see anything
everything looks nice and smooth so I'll
see any artifacts there put this back in
you know it does you know what artifacts
I actually am seeing it's just actually
anisotropic filtering on the MIT Maps
that's what I was actually seeing which
is new relatively speaking cuz we only
added MIT Maps recently probably to fix
this all right so maybe they weren't
Jenny all right so if we do actually now
finally run the game one more time to
the capture close it and look at the
timings now we can see we've done a
pretty good job it's not fabulous for
these two it looks like so maybe there's
some ah yes so we almost finished but
not quite we really were able to make
this be almost free right which is great
so but the other ones are not free so
this one in this one why because they're
not reading from the correct place
really this textile fetch is gonna it's
gonna be whatever this alpha value comes
back as right but we're not writing out
a alpha value that would indicate two
for the next step peel when we block it
we're not plugging up the value for that
depth peel right so what we actually
want to do is when we know we're
completely occluded we want to set our
blend unit color as well we want to set
that to have an alpha value of one right
so we want that is what I think we
actually want to do right now of course
I won't be able to do that because
heaven forfend I'm able to compile a
shader in 2019 but that's what we
actually needed right and so I think
that now if we actually take a look at
that it through via render dark doc as a
performance profile now I think we'd see
a pretty good
a pretty good improvement there right
so now if we take a look at the actual
times like now you can see these things
are minimal right this first resolve is
hugely expensive but all the rest of
these are almost free right and we
haven't really given anything up I don't
think I think we maintained all of our
all of our quality basically and man
just look at how much freer that is
right
like our render time went down by a
factor of almost four right so that's
really really good
and and I'm pretty excited about that
and I think we are still at exactly as
high quality as we were but now we just
take drastically less CPU time to do it
no I'm saying and let's just double
check double the test or double check
rather little check yeah let's just
verify that everything's still kicking
seems to be just fine
so that's good so not bad for you know
like we didn't quite get what I wanted
which is to not have to use multipling
at all but hey our multi sampling is now
really really cheap which is about the
next best thing right and I don't see
any artifacts in here other than maybe
some MIT mapping problems probably needs
them up and isotropic on those really
steep walls but other than that I think
we're good to go
oh my exceeding the size of the buffer I
could be let's find out
I should have actually said we're going
Q&amp;A but it'll also get fried good so if
this is like four thousand something
then maybe
um yeah that's going to optimize
doubtless let's just do it this way
that's close enough I mean it could be
right I would be willing to bet that
it's a good guess unfortunately I don't
quite remember exactly how much is in
there but yeah maybe with that comment
in there right so like yeah again I
really wish the it's nuts that I have to
do any of this it's ridiculous it's just
for some unknown reason and I don't know
what the reason is we can't seem to get
past the fact that we have all these
different compilers like all I really
want is to just have this in my code
right but instead I've got all this
janky it's like super janky how these
things are going through I'm not
surprised we hit that and there's really
not much I'm gonna probably do about
that either because it would you know
again it's just a pain and I also can't
even read these things right cuz they're
like not formatted properly because
they're formatted as a third string it's
just it sucks right but I don't know
sort of actually having a more developed
environment I don't know that there's
really much more I can do right because
it's like I don't the next step which is
the correct step is to be able to just
write the shaders directly into your
program as code and then when the
compiler pass goes over it extracts
those out using all of the correct pound
defines from your standard build and
everything and they just go into the
shader instead of going into your actual
executable right but that's something I
can build like you know when I'm doing a
full code base but on handmade hero I
just have to use the crappy tools I have
right and so is this a good way to do it
no do I want to build out the correct
solution no cuz we just don't have that
kind of time you know I'm saying
so unfortunately I think we probably
just keep stumbling along on it but
thanks for that cash because I was like
what the heck what's going on there
guess 4,096 isn't as big as I thought it
was that's crazy that that's a 4k shader
but it is
makes you appreciate why shipping
shaders as a as source it's not great
either right because that's actually 4k
and it hardly does anything all right so
we have zero questions it looks like
that makes it easy
couldn't you just not um no I mean that
would be nice right but the problem is
that we actually stick crap in there so
like we actually dump in the max multi
sample count and so unfortunately we
have to specify a size at a time again
this is stuff that is just because of
the limitations of the crappy language
that we use but you know why can't you
just run the pre-press around the
shaders though well I can't like so
there's a couple things I could do right
but again there's really no way to do
this kind of operation so what you want
is you want this sort of stuff to be
what you want to be able to do is you
want to be able to do something like let
me go through all of the max multi
sample counts I might use let me compile
all of the this shader multiple times
into multiple buckets and then pick the
right one based on that that would be
very easy to do in a meta programming
environment right like it'd just be
trivial really but the way that modern
like C++ and stuff works they don't have
any of these abilities in them so as a
result what we're doing is we have to
basically do a printf or you know choose
any other string operation to produce
the fragment code and insert dynamically
at runtime which one of these settings
happens to be true
right so as a result we have to pick how
big the things gonna be even though we
really don't need that because
technically what we could do you know
technically this is just going to a
shader compiler right which firstly we
don't have access to but even if you
were like going to use an intermediate
representation or something right then
there would be no need for any of this
because you could already pre the
compiler could already have taking all
of that and converted it to the toe
and then all we were doing is replacing
a constant in there with the constants
we wanted right but none of that is on
the table because like development
systems are so far from being anywhere
near being able to do that that we just
have to kind of like clunk this stuff
together and it's not good and if you
really wanted to solve the problem well
you wouldn't do what I'm doing here
right but you always have to make a
trade-off like am I going to spend a
bunch you know several weeks making this
system that does all of these fancy
things or am I just gonna get by with
having to deal with the occasional bug
because like this buffers gets truncated
or something right
now that I know what that error is I'll
just know to increase the buffer size
but I was just could not tell it was
very confusing what it was trying to
tell me all right so there's a little
too cryptic
let me try to see if there's any other
questions alright so that's it
do you have any concept of life
stringbuilder that you could use with
your format string function to have it
pass you back a string allocated from
temp memory is a small thing but you
wouldn't need to think to worry about
that anymore
um I do have that when I'm actually
programming like in my code base we
don't have that on hand made here oh we
we probably could make one without too
much time because we do have a streaming
buffer like we do have this right so we
could probably do that
maybe but again it's just probably not
worth the time to make it right because
we don't really do this anywhere this
would be the only place that would get
used so
let's see someone was suggesting dual
depth peeling
they have not enabled multi sampling
however I think it's possible to work uh
so but but what we were working with was
specifically well they're sampling I'm
not sure I could look at it though it's
this it
SDK 10 of Virgil screenshots samples yes
we can just take a look let's see
yeah so that does sound at least
interesting just kind of reduce the
number of depth field passes I'm not
sure I'd see what they actually do here
though
so here's the money part we solve this
issue by working on a sliding window of
two consecutive layers I'm not sure what
that means
we essentially turn off the hardware
depth buffer and use blending to perform
the read-modify-write part of our custom
depth test the peeled fragments from the
front layers need to get mMmmm I'm less
enthusiastic about that though because
that may get off certain fast paths that
are about depth testing is the only
thing
I mean maybe it's fine
so yeah I'm not sure about this I would
have to digest it a little bit more and
think about whether there's anything
from here that I particularly wanted but
I'm not sure
I'm not sure I get what they're saying
but I I'm a little nervous about the the
fact that it's not using hardware depth
testing I would want to hear from
somebody who actually did the
performance profiling on a modern
hardware card that that was okay before
I actually spent the time to implement
that you know I'm saying
so I don't know I don't know how I feel
about that
have you considered using render talk
directly to recompile the shaders at
runtime during rapid development um I
haven't really but I probably should we
can actually recompile the shaders I
think ourselves on the fly like in other
words the act of recompiling them in the
game is pretty easy I think we can just
do that like if I go in here and want to
change the color of something like you
know I think we just can and then when
you recompile the game I think it
reloads maybe it doesn't oh you know
what it might not because we don't
reload the graphics driver anymore you
used to do that but I guess we don't
anymore so that might be helpful we
could also just re-enable that meaning
re-enable the ability to reload the
graphics driver at whenever it changes
we just don't do that in the platform
layer right now so I don't know which of
those two things I'd rather do we
haven't spent that much time working on
these at the moment so it's not that bad
but when we do the lighting that may be
helpful so it's hard to say yeah I mean
I can't see some episodes ago you said
you didn't understand why John credit
your unbraid since you didn't do any
work on it uh well no that that wasn't
what I said or at least hopefully that
wasn't what I said I mean go check the
video what I said was I'm not sure why I
was credited so prominently in fact I
specifically think I said it would have
made more sense if I was just listed as
like additional programming or something
but instead I got listed like as a
special section like right at the
beginning of the credits that was like
rewind evangelist very prominently and
while it's certainly nice of John to
give me credit for something it really
probably wasn't super earned is all
because
I was I didn't come up with any of the
sign for braids oh I I was he who said
that because of a baling list post I've
made that was just talking about how the
players time is valuable on the so if
you're going to make them do something a
second time you should make it be
worthwhile and games that aren't gonna
do that you just have rewind so I can
just like correct my mistake and move on
right because that just seemed natural
to me so he gave me credit in the game
because of that mail but the mail was
just complaining about something else
right so it was really the entire idea
was John's idea not mine it's sort of
like if you gave someone credit for a
game you wrote because like you thought
of the game idea after reading like a
short story or something even though
that short story does not appear in the
game you know and so it's kind of just
like giving me credit as being a source
of inspiration for something which again
is very generous it's just probably not
deserved it's like if you actually were
there and saw the connection it was very
tenuous and the entire like goodness
that came out of it was because of John
having a whole suite of ideas that
really weren't contained in that mail
and honestly we're very tangentially
related to that mail you know what I
mean
so again love to have the credit and
it's super nice of someone to go out of
their way to credit you especially you
know circumstance like that where you
really don't deserve it you know but
that's why when someone was asking me I
think they asked me why I was credit is
rewind evangelist I was just trying to
be honest by saying like if to be frank
like really honestly the only thing that
I contributed to braid was the like code
for rounded rectangle
collision detection because and it was
because John was like I have to be
sitting at the same table as him with
laptops out one time and he was just
like this is stupid thing that's in here
it's not smooth I'm gonna replace it
with something good and I was like oh
I've got this like one fly like this you
know literally one file that's a rounded
rectangle overlap tester you know
that'll give you the rounded rectangles
you want go for it right that that was
the sum total of like my contribution to
braid you know that and playing the game
in beta but I don't even really know if
I ever I don't remember what feedback I
had on the game but I don't I don't
actually think I really had any valuable
feedback either so so it was like it was
the the the the level of billing I got
in braids versus the level of
contribution in braids are not related I
got much higher billing than then then
my contribution by far
how would you implant in debug systems
the way of changing also v3 v4 values
don't we as we we have that don't we
though don't we have a thing that adds
beat like we have that in like the they
like placement editor right
I just watched the video about sub-pixel
sampling for peace our diocese thanks
for explaining it was really good I have
two related questions though when you
viewed the spritesheet you noticed this
not alpha premultiplied and kind of
mentioned that it might be a problem I
was wondering why the reason why is
because premultiplied alpha is the only
way to make sprites sample properly
using bilinear filtering using hardware
bilinear filtering or maybe I should say
the default way that hardware does
bilinear filtering so if you have non
premultiplied alpha then your bilinear
filtering
will be wrong unless you actually pre
multiply first and then bilinear filter
right and so all I was saying is that
using bilinear fetch won't work at the
places where the alpha is not 1 or 0 and
so they kind of set us up for failure
even if we had been able to place a
shader we would got some black fringing
around the edges of things when we tried
to use bilinear to to filter that's all
as for number 2 which is you mentioned
that they don't use maps and you're
saying how should we produce nips for
pixel art assets box filtering would not
works it's made for bilinear so I guess
what I would say there is just that when
you're making something when you're
minifying something like that so you're
taking something that was previously
what you know that would be when you
shrunk it all the way down so that your
pixel art is one pixel per per screen
pixel one texel per screen pixel right
so when you do that what ends up
happening is you by the time you've
gotten down there when you want to
shrink it smaller bilinear is probably
fine because the pixel art is too small
at that part point to look like pixel
art anyway
probably should just by linear filter so
Minah fication filter is fine I think it
should be just fine
magnification filter is the only time
when you can't just turn on by linear
and forget right so the MIT map should
just be fine I think
and I guess I haven't thought about too
hard but you may need to put an if in
the shader that just says look if I
minifying don't just dudes regular by
philipp bilinear and forget about it
right Ciara as he says you're right but
I think you need to point something yeah
so for point sampling then you don't
have to worry about it right so the
reason that they don't also have
premultiplied alpha the reason why they
don't also have black fringing on their
sprites magician to all the other visual
bugs they have is because since they're
not properly filtering using any kind of
blending they don't have to worry about
the fact that they're not premultiplied
alpha but once you actually do the
correct blending for pixel art you are
using the bilinear Hardware you're not
just using it the same way you would be
if you didn't adjust your UV coordinates
but you are using it right and at that
point you have to then again make sure
using premultiplied alpha because if you
don't then bilinear filtering doesn't
work right I mean it works but it
produces subtly wrong results the alphas
not correct right serious this is thank
you rich for the skinned mesh video I
still have to watch it what you haven't
watched it yet I specifically made that
video for you you have to go watch it go
watch it alright that's it for questions
it's time for bed
what's the problem here you'll
accidentally insert something I don't
think I did
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for the episode a handmade hero so a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with the
source code at home you can always peer
out of the game on handmade hero dorg
and it comes to the source code right
away so you could play around with it
even while it's still in development
again as I mentioned at the beginning we
now have a discord as well I'm probably
gonna put some links on here so you can
click and go directly to it but while
we're still working out the kinks if you
do want to check it out
it's just discord GG slash Molly Rocket
and that'll go straight to our discord
if you're on discord check it out
there's plenty of fun discussion that
seems to be going on there it's it's
been pretty good so far
so give that a little look-see if you if
you're interested in chatting about the
series or game development related
things or just interested in checking
out some of our other projects that
we've got in the pipeline at market
that's it for today I'll be back here on
Sunday for I guess at that point we've
pretty much done everything we needed to
do so I think at that point maybe we
don't really need to do anything other
than finish up the training on like
ground cover and getting that flowing
faster through the pipeline and then
we've got a pretty good performance
oriented profile on our GPU at least for
this stage of development I think
certainly so I think then we're good to
dump lighting in there and see how much
worse it gets
alright that's about it for today I'll
see you back around Sunday until then
have fun programming and I'll see
everyone on the Internet tabes everybody