hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show where we code a complete
game live on stream unless we are an RSI
break which we are right now so we're
just doing q and A's because the right
hand is fine and so they can draw I got
a question from Andrew JDR on the twitch
chat wanted to know about SG X which is
Intel's new thing in X 64 processors
coming down the road which basically is
going to be like DRM you know squared or
maybe even two - the DRM power so yeah
if you're one of those people out there
who likes being able to control your
computing devices that those days are
probably pretty numbered and I suppose
on the slight positive side if you're
somebody who is worried about your game
being pirated well that might never
happen again after this so there's that
too but we'll save the philosophical
part of it for a little bit later and
I'll just talk about the general concept
here because this is actually not
something new this is actually something
that other computer systems I want to
say that Silicon Graphics or Sun I don't
remember who one of those to have had
had this a long time ago actually and so
this is actually not particularly new
old SDX is a whole family of things and
some of that things in that family sound
new to me I had not heard of them before
so the DRM part of it is not new but the
other parts are you know I don't know if
they're new because I don't study
hardware that often but they definitely
were new to me like I haven't seen it
before for whatever that's worth
alright so how do you make unbreakable
DRM right how do you do that well the
answer is that really doesn't take much
so the way things currently work on a
CPU right is it looks something like
this I have a
ooh here it is right and mr. CPU is
connected to a network card right some
kind of a thing that goes out to the
Internet and that goes out to the
internet and it talks to let's say valve
right and valve sends back through this
Internet card something that the CPU
then probably has to interface with but
eventually it writes it out to your hard
drive okay and it is the executable
right it's the game writes the game it's
got the egg Z it's got the data all the
stuff is here on the hard drive okay and
that's just how everything works right
now right you you go out you you buy
something on Steam the network card
talks to valve it downloads a bunch of
stuff it writes it to the hard drive and
now your CPU goes and it plays this
right and so let's just put ourselves in
valve position again I'm not trying to
make a philosophical judgement here
let's just assume that we think that DRM
is a good idea all right
and certainly valve takes a neutral
stance on this which I commend them for
it they do not force DRM on their
customers so basically it's the
publishers decision on like when you're
on Steam the publisher decides whether
something is DRM door not so valve to
their credit does not force DRM on
anybody right it's it's like if the
publisher wants to do it they do it if
they don't they don't
but plate being let's say your valve and
people you know are like hey excuse me
this is this is you know what I'm gonna
draw a publisher here so they're gonna
be like big and fat and they have like a
tie on like a pinstripe suit right and
they're probably on just like tons of
money
there's just probably this like huge
pile of money like these are little sacs
of dollars here right so this is like
mr. Electronic Arts or whatever and he's
like excuse me mr. valve but people are
pirating my game and I don't like it
right this hair is probably slicked back
here I'm guessing and he's probably
smoking a big old fat cigar that the
cigar probably cost
more than most people's computers so
this is probably like a $5,000 cigar and
he's like excuse me but you know people
are pirating our game you need to do
something about this right so what can
Val do in this scenario so what Val can
do in this scenario and what they I have
done and to be fair I haven't looked at
Val's DRM but so I'm just I'm making
this up here's one example of what they
could do and probably roughly what they
did what they can do is say well okay
every instance of this I know that you
know this CPU and this NIC and this hard
drive are in a user's machine and I know
that user has a steam ID right so I know
that when a user buys a game I know who
that is and when they talk to me they
have to tell me who that is because I
won't give them the game unless they are
logged on right you can't just ask Val
for a game and it gives it to you you
have to prove that your customer so you
have to have credentials and all that
stuff right so they know the steam ID
and the steam ID goes across the network
so what valve could do for example if
they want to is before sending this back
to you they could make some changes to
the game package itself such that your
steam ID is inexorably linked to it
right so there could be some
modifications to this data this data
here could have your steam ID baked into
it in some kind of way right like for
example let's say I run some kind of
encryption on it where I use the steam
ID as encryption key or something right
so now whenever I go to launch this game
the steam launcher tries to launch the
game it has to use whatever the steam ID
is or something like this to decrypt the
game right or maybe something else maybe
it's not the steam ID maybe it's like a
key that gets comes back from valve and
then it decrypts the game and runs it
right something like that makes sense
right this is reasonable DRM it probably
stops the number of people but obviously
if you are a pirate or shouldn't say
fire if you're a cracker someone who's
going to try and crack this to produce a
version of the game that can be
distributed external to Steam and
without Vericut verification well it's
not impossible for you to do that
because
when this comes back over the nick it
gets written to the hard drive you can
now observe this and furthermore when
the game is run you can observe the game
running right so you can figure out
especially by looking at two different
people's installs and looking at the
difference between the two packages for
example you can probably determine after
some amount of work what the changes
have been to this and you can undo them
right you can turn it back into an
executable that does not depend in this
way on on something unique to the user
right so now instead of something which
has to be run under the guise of a
particular user steam ID because the
game is actively trying to like decrypt
itself using that as a key or
something's happening it will use now
the key and if you don't have that key
it won't work right they can just turn
it into so that it always runs with that
key and just knows that or it's been
decrypted and they just distribute the
decrypted version right so you can
understand that there are many ways in
which this might depending on exactly
how it was done because they can watch
it all happen and because they can then
undo it
because whatever the CPU was doing to
run it in the first place they can
obviously undo right it's no problem
okay
so how do we make something that does
not have that problem right how do we
make something where it's simply not
possible for anyone to ever break the
DRM short of say the NSA or something so
how do we do that well what we do is we
modify this diagram a little bit so
before we had CPU Nick and hard drive
right and we're still gonna have those
but now we're gonna add something very
specific because here remember this was
our weakness the steam ID or whatever
you know whatever is based on this login
credential thing whatever valve sent us
back with this a steam ID or a
decryption key or whatever it is is in
the system and visible to the attacker
and as long as that's true they're
always going to be able to break the DRM
because as long as they can view what
that is there's nothing you're going to
be able to do they'll eventually if they
really want to crack it and you could
make it harder and harder and harder for
to untangle all the stuff that you did
based on this but if they are willing to
spend enough time they will always be
able to do it okay so what's the problem
what's the problem
the problem is that right so how do we
fix it fix it well what we do is we put
it inside the CPU right so what we do
now is instead of making that key
instead of making you know this is
effectively our key that the whole DRM
is based on instead of making that KB
something that's out in the open
we just bake the key directly into the
CPU okay so the keys inside the CPU
still got the NIC still got the hard
drive right so now what happens well
what we do is we use for example let's
say we use something like RSA encryption
right some kind of public key encryption
okay and for those of you don't know
what public key encryption is public key
encryption is encrypting there's two
different keys it has a public key and a
private key and these things go together
and the idea is that the public key is
something that everyone can observe and
stealing that key or that key being
exposed is totally fine it's expected
that everyone in the whole world could
be given this key and that the private
key on the other hand will be kept
secret and what public key encryption
allows you to do is to use a public key
to encrypt a message okay so basically
if I have some message if I have a
secret I can apply encryption to it
using the public key that produces an
encrypted secret that only someone with
the private key can decrypt so anyone
can encrypt anyone can turn something
into a encrypted secret with the public
key but only the person with the private
key can decrypt it nobody else ever can
the only way they can is by cracking the
actual encryption which you know as far
as we know to this day mathematically
speaking requires actually doing brute
forcing with like a
giant you know computer array and
granted depending on the particular
public key scheme like RSA certain
things have been cracked in
ba-ba-ba-ba-ba so you probably would not
pick RSA but point being you'd pick some
secure public key scheme elliptical
curve cryptography for example blah blah
blah okay so do you see where this is
going
inside the CPU we store the private key
and it is baked into the CPU such that
nobody literally nobody can access it
it's built into the circuitry of the CPU
and the only way you will ever get it
out is by doing some kind of crazy crazy
hardware hacking on that CPU which I
guarantee you Intel's fab technology is
very very very very very very very good
so I strongly suspect that this is
something that only like a state actor
probably will ever do although you know
who knows never count out Europe
sometimes like hackers in Europe have
leaked skills and crazy hardware but
point being probably not going to happen
right because it is baked into the
hardware ok so since we have this baked
of the hardware okay we've got the CPU
it's baked in the hardware the private
key and then it also has its
corresponding public key which anyone
can see ok that's actually just exposed
in the system so now what do we do well
now what we do is we say ok you know
we're running we're in our in our
situation where we're gonna buy a game
we say hey valve we bought this game
please give me the game they say no
problem give me your public key your
public key goes across the network valve
takes it they encrypt the entire package
with that public key they send it back
right and here we write into this into
this into our into our hard drive we
write the encrypted game now remember
nobody can possibly decrypt this game
it's not possible to decrypt it at all
unless you have the private key so the
only thing that could possibly decrypt
the game is this is the CPU right now so
then you use Intel's STX instruction set
to say I would like to load a neck
cute and encrypted package please and it
uses the private key that's directly in
the CPU to decrypt the game code and its
accompanying data if you wish and the
CPU is set up such that no one can ever
observe it that's what the SGX
extensions actually allow you to do all
of the memory is protected no one can
actually access it so it is completely
isolated so literally you know this
creates you know unbreakable DRM in in a
very specific sense right unbreakable
you always have to quantify because you
know is it really unbreakable well
nothing's probably actually unbreakable
right but what it means is that it is
not software breakable meaning nobody
will ever be able to break it in
software like they do now what you would
have to do is actually reverse engineer
a specific CPU with the game on it and
then you would do this process right and
that would be a thing that I believe
would require hardware and like a lab
that's so expensive that almost nobody
has access to it so will certain you
know will will the NSA be able to crack
Steam games yes will will China be able
to crack them their equivalent of that
yes because I guarantee you they've got
such hardware and are probably using it
will hack sorors who post a Pirate Bay
probably not right so there you go
that's how that works
and I see you could just give them
another public key that you have the
private key for so that part of the
process obviously is it's to use a bell
ring it's it's Turtles you know all the
way down at that point right so you have
to imagine if you really want to make
unbreakable DRM you do this for
everything so the valve executable that
gets installed is also only installable
on you know the Windows machine which is
also only installable on the hardware
right it's like it's it's a trusted
platform on the whole stack if that
makes sense so presumably if you really
want to actually do the whole thing then
all the code has to be trusted and
signed and you know will they do it I
don't know you know they may not want to
they may maybe eval doesn't want to do
this and or stop or who knows who else
right so I don't know you know whether
they were live whether they won't it's
already the case right that Windows kind
of has a little bit of this stuff built
into it that used the trusted platform
module and so once they have this
presumably they will just make sure that
you could just have the concept of a
signed executable and off you go because
once you have the concept of a signed
executable it means that all valve has
to do is say I want proof this is thing
called attestation right which is also
part of the SGX thing which to be honest
I didn't read yet so I don't know what
scheme they used for it but there's a
thing called attestation which is a way
that you can prove to the outside world
that the thing you're running is an
unmodified version of something else
right so I don't actually know how the
signing process works but the answer is
the reason that you can't intercept the
public key and send or send some other
public key that you want to come back
you know something that you have the
the key for is because presumably if you
actually decide to implement an
unbreakable DRM scheme you will use
attestation to make sure that everything
on the machine is signed and I'm not
sure what they decided to do for that
because it's there's a whole chapter on
it
oops there was a whole chapter on it but
I don't actually remember what they said
I wasn't paying very close attention
because they were just like well we've
got it and I was like alright I trust
you probably implemented it properly but
yeah so let's see here where is the
attestation section control structure is
Enclave signature structure
there it is okay let's see okay so I
think what they do I'm not gonna read
this right now but I'm just guessing
based on what that said so I think what
they probably do is they sign that as
well so they sign the public keys
themselves are signed with a key that
only Intel has so basically you can
verify that Intel signed that public key
which means it's a public key that they
have not you so basically I again making
this up because I didn't go read the
document very thoroughly
but basically what they do is they say
okay you know here's my CPU here's the
private key right and here's the public
key I'll give this one out this public
key is not just a raw public key it's
actually a signed public key in some way
which means that for example at Intel HQ
right they have a private key and a
public key right and they have used that
private and public key to generate some
attestation data that goes with the
public key so here's this public key
right and what they do is they create a
signature right of some kind which
anyone can with the public key can
verify the signature but only someone
with the private key could generate the
signature and then you send this whole
thing to valve and valve can you know
everyone has this so valve has it they
can go is this public key actually Ali a
legal CPU public key and Intel says yes
it is or Intel you know public key they
use it to decrypt it it says yes it is
and there you go right so yeah still
unbreakable and actually now that I
think about that actually doesn't even
involve any signing at all right so that
actually means you don't even need any
of these to be signed the valve the
Steam client doesn't be signed
windows can be completely exploited it
can be you know
whatever and you still can't decrypt the
game because the only way that you could
decrypt the game is with the private key
that's in here because you can't send
some other key because you don't have
Intel signing keys does that make sense
that's the em wrath what about the above
see area where there is no internet
connection how would run runs of suffer
in offline mode this does not require
internet connection the internet
connection is only there for the time
that you download the game once the game
is downloaded it is encrypted on your
hard drive with your private key that's
in your CPU so you can always run the
game on your CPU it never has to go talk
to valve ever again right never again so
when it's on once it's on your hard
drive you can play it anytime you want
the only thing you can't do is copy it
to someone else's machine and expect it
to run there because when you copied
someone else's machine that CPU has a
different private key it will try to
decrypt the game with that private key
and it will just get garbage sudonym 73
so the NSA doesn't have to crack it they
just have to rubber-hose intel yeah
you're correct actually yes that's
correct
so yeah the NSA and and probably you
know other state actors potentially will
probably just all get copies of that key
right because they'll you know like who
knows but the NS yet the American
governors go to in towns like give us
the key we have an army what are you
gonna do right
so yeah trust me it is not breakable
right software-wise not breakable
hardware-wise
if you can get into here then yeah but
no steveod 1990 can't this be broken
using emulation nope can't be broken
using emulation and the reason it can't
be broken using emulation remember so I
just wanna I'm just going to go over the
steps one more time step one
send public key to let's say Orage let's
say ëi say Electronic Arts origin right
step 2 ei encrypts SimCity 12 right step
receive SimCity 12 encrypted in-store on
hard drive right step 4
this is actually the part where you want
to run the game step 4 CPU the crypts
and runs
using private key okay so in step one
when you send the public key to ETA
origin they know that not only is this
public key valid because it's signed by
them but emulation like you said you're
asking if emulation solves this no
emulation doesn't solve it at all
because this public key can be verified
by origin as one that came from an
actual Intel CPU and emulated Intel CPU
will have a public key private key pair
in it that Intel didn't sign so they'll
just say no I'm not sending you the game
so you never get the game right so that
Avenue of tack is gone so you can't
attack step one step two encrypt SimCity
12 well if you could break into
Electronic Arts you could attack that so
hey the DRM is breakable here in the
sense that hackers who hack into EA
could break it right but hey that just
means they got access to the original so
in this case the DRM didn't fail it's
you know it's social engineering and you
broke into EA right but that's obviously
neither here nor there that's that
obviously you break into yeah you could
physically go break in the EA and steal
their hard drives and then you've got
every game that you want right so yeah
so that's that's not really breakable in
any case that we're actually talking
about in this context step three
there's nothing to break because all you
received is it encrypted executable so
you haven't you can't do anything with
it you can't copy it to someone else's
machine
you can't inspect it you can't do
anything it's a meaningless series of
bits as far as you're concerned right
and step four where the CPU decryption
runs it the SDS extensions ensure that
no other process other than the one
that's actually running can actually
look at it and since the process itself
is actually being decrypted with that
private key note you can't fake it and
give it some other thing that's gonna
inspect the memory so step four is not
you know none of these are attackable
right and it doesn't matter if it's
running an emulation because if it's if
it's a if it's running an emulation this
will fail right here already and so the
only way you could ever get to here in
emulation is if you've already Hardware
hacked and Intel CPU and got a real
private public key pair out
and that's why I said it's not soft for
a breakable the only way to break it is
through a hardware hack which actually
retrieves the private public key right
Maciek can't they just figure out
Intel's key generator and make a key
generator for it
well prison again that's that's only if
Intel is fantastically sloppy right I'm
assuming that Intel's key generator is
not predictable right I mean if Intel
really wanted to they could collect
neutrino hits in an underground lab and
generate completely random nade late
data or something right or they could
have it hooked up to a seismograph or
who knows what right they could like
they could actually generate completely
really random stuff when they you know
that they feed into the fab right so who
knows so yeah could they attack Intel's
key generator only if Intel screws up if
Intel actually follows good practices
for their key generator it will never be
able to be cracked it unless someone
hacks Intel
Steve void so even if the emulation
contained a valid key from a registered
copy it couldn't be cracked
okay so again I just want to underscore
there is no key with the registered copy
the game that comes down is encrypted
and it's encrypted using a key that's in
your CPU right so it doesn't matter if
you have a valid copy
everyone's copy of the game will be
different because each one will be
encrypted with their CPU and only their
CPU will be able to run it so there is
no such thing as a registered copy of
the game in that sense meaning that
there's some key in the game the game
contains no key it was encrypted without
putting anything on it or in it that
identifies how to decrypt it the
decryption key is stored in your CPU and
your CPU alone and you cannot access it
with any instructions because it's
actually baked in the CPU so the only
thing you can do is Hardware hack the
CPU you have to actually get out an
electron microscope or something I mean
I have no idea how your hardware hacker
CPU but you know you gotta use some kind
of a hardware attack to get it out but
you can't do it in software andrew JDR I
assume this breaks certain features of
the windows API since the memory is
protected global hook dll's for example
I don't think you would even probably be
able to use these extensions until a
future version of Windows enables them
is my is my assumption actually if that
makes sense so so I feel like I feel
like I feel like I saw a thing in there
that says that you have to enable it
when you start up in some CPU thing so I
don't know that I guess the point is I
don't know that these will be usable in
Windows
that's not designed for it so I'm
assuming you'll have to wait for Windows
11 or whatever and then it will have
this enabled so I'm assuming that they
just take care of it and when you run
something in this then yeah those
executables running under SGX will
not have any of the other stuff that you
would expect like like DLL injection
won't run there you know II junkie 64
what if the CPU fails or you want to
upgrade again it's not a problem for
someone because they'll just re log into
steam and it'll redownload all their
games right so you know for most usage
scenarios you it's just a little bit of
time for that to happen but otherwise
it's fine long boolean would intel
create a different key for each
manufacturer CPU or is there only ever
one key no it's a different key for
every CPU and it has to be because if
every CPU had the same key then you'd be
right back to where we are now and there
and it would be trivial to circumvent
because my executable would be encrypted
with the same key as your executable as
your CPU could read so I just I'd give
you the encrypted executable and you'd
be able to run it so the only reason
this scheme works is because each CPU
has a different key so when they go to
launch an executable they decrypt with
different keys so only things encrypted
for six CPU will run on that CPU that's
crucial cracker door but this means you
lose control of your own system since
only Intel can perform actions yeah
basically I mean thankfully it's not
required to have SGX meaning you can
still write code for a computer that
doesn't have to be signed for now but
yeah so you know this is only for people
who want to use the DRM you won't have
to get intel's permission to run
something or cpu yet you know and
hopefully that would never happen famous
last words
how susceptible is the locking of
portions of memory CPU cores to
malicious encryption programs that
simply want to screw your computer over
I don't think they'd probably put that
not not particularly problematic because
it does not privilege escalation at all
it's running in its phone it's running
in its standard ring level so the
operating system can still just kill the
task trivially yes and and it you just
can't see you kids can't get or access
any of that memory but you can kill a
task that was running it and the memory
you know gets gets freed or whatever or
whatever has to happen there right
happens but you don't it doesn't prevent
you from from terminating the execution
ratchet freak if the game is sloppy and
ends up allowing arbitrary user code
execution then the code can be leaked uh
I don't actually know about that part
because I haven't read the SGX stuff
carefully enough it may be that the CPU
will never execute any code that isn't
encrypted with the key so that might
also prevent you from ever having
arbitrary code execution right pragma
script if anyone ever leaks intel's
private key SGX on all those CPUs would
be explored yes correctly the correct so
if Intel if anyone ever gets the Intel
signing keys
it's that only the CPUs that would be
exploitable because the CPU isn't
exploitable the CPU is the thing that's
providing the protection so there's no
exploit on the CPU in fact all this
stuff is not a privilege escalation
that's the whole point it's a user mode
thing that prevents code execution
without without the correct key so
there's no XY on the CPU but if anyone
leaks the Intel's signing certificates
right the signing Keys then that means
the DRM is going to be broken because
then that means the thing that someone
suggested earlier where you just send a
separate pot a public key that you have
the private key to you lie and say this
is the public key and my CPU now you can
actually do that because now you can
make up a public key sign it with the
private key and send it off right
popcorn oh nine why don't they use this
system for banks something that's worth
protecting
well banks probably will use this system
now right obviously this this system
will have benefits right so you'll be
able to get better security in other
arenas because of this the problem is it
also means you're going to lose even
more control of your computer than you
already have which is already quite a
bit quarter Tron can you think of
awesome usages for this like optin anti
cheat so the server would know everyone
on it had no aimbots or whatever yes so
basically like like I was saying before
so the problem with this
basically that it takes control away
from the user of the computer much like
you know the constant thing of like oh
you know your government keeps you safe
from terrorists you just have to you
know surrender all your freedoms or
whatever it's exactly that trade so will
you get things in return yes are they
things you want in return are they worth
it no I'm on the Ben Franklin side like
you know people who sacrifice freedom
for for safety deserve neither or
whatever he said I I'm on that side it's
like I don't I don't feel like
sacrificing the freedom to control what
your machine does your machine should
never be able to hide something from you
that's just that's just the fundamental
principle of computing that I will
always stand by I just do not like the
fundamental concept is the users in
charge of the computer as soon as you
reverse that I think you're in a world
of hurt and we're already halfway down
that with the trusted platform module
and with SGS it's now gonna be it's
gonna be times 10 so pretty soon when
you live in a world where nothing in on
your computer at all is under your
control you don't be surprised because
that's exactly what will happen because
remember corporations never want you to
control anything right they never want
you to be able to do anything other than
exactly what they say so the consequence
will be primarily used for your benefit
is you know is laughable it will be
primarily used for their benefit and to
the extent that that helps you you will
get helped but that's about it
and so yeah corporations don't want
viruses running on your machine for any
particular reason unless they made the
virus right so yeah that won't happen
right but you know you also will be very
constrained with what you know you are
actually able to to decide to save you
will not be able to backup software that
you run anymore ever you will have to
obey all of the things they want you to
do to be able to run your software when
they tell you you have to upgrade you
have to upgrade now like full stop right
because they'll be able to completely
dictate what it is you can and cannot do
rfh 666 let's see will this constant
decryption used while running a game
have an effect on performance I'm
assuming not but I don't know again I
haven't read the abstract stuff
carefully enough to know but I'm
assuming they took care of that so if it
is the performance that I'm assuming
it's a negligible one Rob Robbie once
the keeper is known everybody could use
it and equip the game with it through
valve leaving valve encrypt everything
with the same key for different users
well fail on the way very fast I'm not
sure what you're saying what do you mean
what's a keeper is known but yes if like
I said if you if you have the money to
mount an actual hardware attack on a CPU
then you just have to try and convince
valve - that - you know by every game on
Steam or whatever before they catch on
and then you can decrypt them all and
then you can you know post them to
pirate bay or whatever if that's your
goal right so you could that could
happen but if they ever catch on they'll
just stop issuing for that CPU so you
can also imagine a scheme where Intel
issues revoked certificates where
they're basically like hey everyone who
uses our service here's a big list of
CPUs we found that we no longer don't
let people run code on right I mean you
can imagine a world and this is a
trivial imagination just using the STX
code as it is right a world where they
decide that you are untrustworthy user
and now you can't run any software
commercial software at all because they
sent to Adobe and to Microsoft and to
valve and EA and everyone else they've
sent a list of certificate revokes which
basically say all these cpu public keys
don't trust them anymore and yours is on
there and now you can't buy anything
your machines are brick effectively and
the only thing you can run is open
source stuff
right trivial a imagine like takes no
effort to set that up it's a trivial
example of something that would be you
know not only would I say it's trivial I
guarantee you that's what will actually
happen
there's no quit there's no question in
my mind that's what they'll do
q4k labrie downloading games sounds bad
for SSDs not really because again you
never have to redownload the game unless
you upgrade the CPU which happens how
often right once in a very very long
time
Master Yoda isn't it expensive for intel
to print a different circuit for each
CPU I don't know I don't know enough
about their fab technology right so I'm
not sure sudonym 73 does FGX sound like
a great place for a rootkit to hide or
what um I guess I don't know probably
yeah because I guess there's no reason
it couldn't run it ring zero as well
like I soon the sjx decided to just work
I don't know ratchet freak doesn't that
also prevent no because you
could also I'm assuming because I looked
and it looks like it's page based so
your executable can also JIT stuff
that's you can write to a region outside
and even inside so you can get to
something inside and then run it if you
want right but if you were actually
allowing that I all excited soom you can
do that maybe you can't I don't know but
at the very least you could get to
something outside and then so the only
thing that would leak is the jaded code
which you just have to make sure you
keep that to a reasonable level so that
that doesn't allow piracy right but it
wouldn't because all the data is not
pirate of all so you could just get to
outside and so people can copy the code
so what they can't get in the data so
the game's useless without the data
right so you could still actually get a
fair bit outside and be fine
outside the wall
now shield isn't expensive for intel to
print a different circuit for each CPU
and maintain a queryable database for
each client 24/7 considering its key was
generated using quantum measurement okay
so just to be clear
Intel does not have to maintain a
queryable database they in no way have
to do that
none of this involves communication to
Intel and like I was saying even if they
want to do the nightmare scenario which
actually I think is probably a likely
scenario where Intel or you know what it
doesn't even have to be Intel now that I
think about it in fact Intel doesn't
have to do this right anyone can
maintain a black list of users now just
there could just be a service called
evil corporation incorporated and you
know Electronic Arts and ooby soft and
Microsoft and Adobe and all those guys
could just subscribe to their service
which is the blacklisting service and
that service just sends out which public
keys are known to be pirates right and
hey if you happen to get on there even
if you were in a pirate you get on there
by accident tough you could never get
out right there's no way to you there's
nothing you can do about it so Intel
could actually be a totally harmless
actor in the scenario but because they
created the technology a third party can
now lock you out of your own computer
like basically making it so that you
can't run any commercial software I'm
totally plausible scenario I would
actually say likely scenario it's
exactly like credit ratings are now
right there'd be a thing called like
Experian and it would be like is your
software credit rating okay right and if
it's not you can't buy anything anymore
you have to go purchase a new computer
in order to be able to do so it's ugly
Andrew JDR have you heard any word on
whether AMD will be employing this I
have not Huber Caleb isn't dear I'm good
if you want to prevent people from
freely redistributing your software so
the problem with DRM is not that you
know it's not that software piracy isn't
harmful to software developers
potentially right that's not the case
right if it's not the DRM is is is
somehow not a useful thing for a
software developer who wants to try and
prevent any - wants to absolutely
maximize the profit that they get off
something DRM could be very valuable to
that right the problem isn't that the
problem is the is the sacrifice in order
to get that we give up control of our
computers and that's not acceptable
right it's simply not acceptable and so
I've always been very against these
sorts of concepts because I feel like if
you make that trade then you've lost
you've lost essentially the spirit of
computing it's gone and you can never
get it back so yeah okay maybe now
instead of selling a hundred thousand
copies of this game you'll sell a
hundred and fifty thousand copies of
this game or two hundred thousand copies
of this game was that worth it right
last I checked games are making billions
and billions of dollars a year so to the
extent that piracy is a problem it's a
problem of not making quite as much
money as they were making but not a case
of all game developers are going out of
business right so as far as I'm
concerned until like the you know until
the game industry basically collapses
it's really hard to make an argument
that users should give up control of
their own machines for the sake of us
making fifty percent more profit I mean
does that really sound like a good idea
does it sound like a good trade for all
the users of the world to give up the
ability to control what their computers
are doing so that game developers can
make fifty percent more money
it's a recreational activity
Rob Robbie how you draw the future of
restricted hardware I should start not
buying hardware like this right yeah the
problem is what are we gonna do right
this is the problem when you have
monopoly on things what are you gonna do
not buy a CPU I mean
AMD will probably do the same thing but
even if they don't Intel makes the
majority of chips so most laptops you
buy most desktops you buy especially
laptops because you don't have the
ability to build your own of those very
easily it's harder to do a good build
your own laptop build your own desktop
you can do easily right but it's like
it's pretty nasty right it's pretty
nasty Steve Ward 1990 I imagine this
would be great for use for Hardware
banning from games yeah maybe maybe not
I mean the thing that's kind of tricky
about it is just that it's it's per
Hardware not per user so users can
always get more hardware and then
potentially circumvent it right but yeah
it does make it a lot stronger it means
a user can't create another account and
and now go do whatever it is they're
doing that they have to actually get a
new machine m4 TPM 53 as I'm still
learning a lot I always look at old code
in my project and want to rethink the
architecture of it oh this is a separate
question let me see if there's any more
on the DRM nightmare since we're kind of
getting that all into one stream here
which is good
Rhodey g.e let's say a revoke
certificate is issued for a compromised
CPU and valve at all no longer issues
new software why would your system be
bricked since you already have an
encrypted version of the software on
your HD how could they still prevent you
from running the software that's already
installed they couldn't so you can still
run old stuff but you will never be able
to purchase anything new again right so
it's not bricked in the sense that you
could still run the games you already
already played but you can't and but you
couldn't get online with them right so
that wouldn't work and
you certainly can't ever buy another
game so you'll never play another game
after that and you won't be able to play
online anything nor will you'll be able
to get updates to those games or DLC or
anything else right
Godfather since the key is on the CPU
couldn't you just buy a new CPU if the
key gets blacklisted instead of a whole
new computer yes you could buy a CPU and
you could save the graphics card right
which is the only other major expense of
the computer so but the CPU is is the
big big part of it right CPU is 400
bucks whatever if you buy a nice one I
mean heck it could be 1,200 bucks to do
about it really nice 1 mm v 94 won't
that generate a huge mark of computers
that have been blacklisted or so so you
mean like a people selling their old
CPUs that have been blacklisted well the
problem too is now you've got this
problem where someone's selling computer
you wouldn't know if it was blacklisted
so you'd have to somehow have an escrow
where you could determine whether the
CPU you were buying was blacklisted or
not it's gonna be kind of a nightmare
but I bet it's gonna happen I'm a shield
it feels like it is just a matter of
time until someone somewhere breaks the
scheme and it is just a massive waste of
time and resources for everyone am i
right
well best-case scenario you're right
right best-case scenario yes because
that means now we don't have to live
under that scheme under that control
scheme where other people are making our
decisions for us about who can and can't
buy software right but you know will it
happen I don't know I have no idea
ezo audio rear is isn't it to your M
that is the primary driving force for
piracy in the first place uh I don't
think so
in fact I know it's not right because
I'm pretty sure the witness was released
with no DRM and it got pirated a
tremendous amount apparently so
I don't think that DRM has much to do
with piracy Qbert Caleb I think it is a
bigger deal for companies like Adobe and
Autodesk both of which have suffer with
insanely high piracy rates maybe I don't
know MMB 94 when big companies start
locking out people from using their
software the people will start looking
for software from smaller companies that
won't use this technology how are you
gonna do that how are you going to not
use Photoshop right it's already the
case that you could go to a small
software company for something right but
they don't make anything that's
comparable you know it's really hard to
find alternatives and plus what will
happen then the big company will just
buy that small company and that's all
over that's what happens lots of times
right it's like you know how many small
things do you know of well okay flash
used to be a separate company owned by
Adobe now right like a lot of a lot of
things are acquired and sort of smushed
up right premier was this was made by
like a college thesis or something
that's part of Adobe right I mean they
things things get accreted they just
they just buy a smaller company so if it
really created a problem they just buy
them that's what Autodesk does they own
Maya they own soft amaz they own 3d
studio right like you know basically
between the foundry and Autodesk there
isn't a 3d package in existence that one
of the one of those two don't own right
hi I do you think that there's a chance
that the smallest trend of drm-free
games will counteract this sgf stuff in
any significant way I I have no idea in
my opinion these things we just
shouldn't be doing them like we
shouldn't give
we shouldn't figure out what the future
looks like when companies control what
you can and cannot run right there has
to be a balance there you know and I
don't know I mean all I can say is it
like how many people out there learn to
paint in Photoshop on a pirated copy
right and now they work at a company
that actually legitimately pays for
their Photoshop as an artist was that
really that bad that that's what
happened you know and I don't know right
I don't know and sometimes yeah I mean
there's you know sometimes companies do
try to do things fairly and they have
like a full-featured educational version
of something or whatever but you know I
don't know it really depends I think on
on whether you how much you trust
companies to do the right thing and most
the time I find they don't you know
wherever every sad the entry costs and
fabrics are so high else I would find a
Kickstarter soon to some fantastic user
owned CPU architecture yeah it would be
nice to have an open CPU architecture
someday like I think there's some people
who started an a competitor to arm
that's like an open source New York -
sure maybe someday we can just get on
that and then forget all this stuff but
I don't know the fab technology is
really hard to come by and you know I
don't know how that happens could this
be taking a step further if they start
putting the key on the motherboard
instead of the CPU that's less
replaceable no I mean the motherboards
often much cheaper than the CPU actually
the CPU is often to three times
expensive is another board so putting on
the motherboard doesn't really doesn't
really make it any worse
and juju tiara so apparently QEMU a VM
hypervisor has support for emulating SGX
how is this useful
uh well I'm assuming and I could be
wrong but I'm assuming that as long as
you're running on an X 64 processor with
SGX then it would just work right cuz
you just the the emulated processor
would just use the actual processors
public and private key and if you didn't
want to do that you could make up your
own public and private key and still run
just fine
you would just wouldn't be able to
actually you wouldn't be able to attest
to anyone outside that you were a
legitimate Intel CPU but that may be
fine too right maybe you're not trying
to do that
so the SGS extensions for security would
still just totally work under emulation
and if it's an actual xst for a
processor with SGX that's running it
they would actually work for attestation
as well because all the VMS would all
attest as that processor correctly
so I sauce the kid for businesses
wouldn't just tech be good for the
consumer I would feel more comfortable
if my bank had my encrypted data as
tight as possible so the problem is I
don't know that this helps banks really
all that much beyond the current though
because as long as as long as some
customer service personnel can access
your account then hackers can write the
fact that SGX is keeping like some
process from accessing it potentially
doesn't necessarily help you because
they won't attack hackers will attack
that point they'll attack the customer
service gateway or something right so I
don't really know how useful this is for
a bank it adds a little bit of security
potentially from virus attacks on the
bank maybe or something like that maybe
but it I don't know that it really
prevents hack Soaring assuming that the
bank has remote customer service of some
kind or even local customer service to
that for that matter
you look at one minute left so I must
see if there's anything else
keeper caleb has rad ever had problems
with people pirating their suffer or
people releasing the source code yes
they have and you know they just they
deal with it on case by case basis messy
old oculd encrypting each 16-gigabyte
gain download using your s Jeske be
prohibitive costs for a company like
valve how likely would it be for valve
to refuse doing such a thing
so valve you know has a mixed record I
would say as far as as ethics in that
they're not like ei which is strictly
like seems to have only their best
interests in mind like valve does
occasionally do things that I feel like
are not so great but often times they do
things that are pretty pretty ethical or
pretty fair to the consumer
I feel like valve does so it's entirely
possible that like valve might not do
this right you know they might decide
that this is too dangerous or route and
they don't want to do it so I don't
think they would be patient zero
like EA's origin service for example
would probably be the much more likely
one to like adopt this sort of thing
first I would say as for whether
encrypting the game download being
prohibitive it's not prohibitive at all
the cost of encrypting the bytes of
something is so cheap that the data it's
the bandwidth cost that's expensive
having the CPU as it shovels something
out the network port apply encryption to
it is is practically free
Rob Robby I am less afraid of price can
price control with DRM strong as this
one I'm more afraid that the OS of the
future will block software that hasn't
been signed that is scary yes and you
should be very afraid of that because
that almost certainly will happen I mean
it's it's sort of already is happening
on the iOS right like you can't run
software on your own iPhone without
signing it full stop and so I think that
sort of thing will only get more
prevalent and yes I am very much against
that and I think it's a huge huge
problem very very bad
a valley a would the entire time need to
be encrypted or just the executable part
um I mean basically the part that you
don't want to be pirated has to be
encrypted so if you don't mind all the
art getting pirated but you just want to
have the executable not get pirated then
yes you could just encrypt excute Abul
so it depends probably for most games
it's sufficient to just encrypt the
executable you probably don't need to
encrypt the art because if they can't
have the xperia but whether they going
to read Plymouth the whole game probably
not right so it's probably sufficient to
leave the art unencrypted
Godfather since valve need a big push
for Linux I'm willing to bet that they
won't chip on the sjx train since it is
a possible limit to consumers
s3x works on Linux justice fine just as
well as it will work on Windows it's a
CPU thing so cubic Caleb what is code
signing anyway code signing is again
just exactly the same thing as what I
was talking about here with the keys so
basically it's it's like this sort of
thing where there's some concept of a
certificate that you use to sign
something so so they can prove that you
that it's that's valid so I'll give you
an example of what that is all right
all right so the basic idea of public
encryption I already said what it was
right the idea is that you you generate
a pair of keys a public key and a
private key and and you give this one
out to everyone this goes out to the
world and this one is a secret and no
one else knows it but you okay that's
how that's how that works and what
public key encryption allows you to do
is basically depending on how the scheme
is set up it allows you to pass data in
either direction here such that you can
for example encrypt something this
direction meaning I could encrypt
something with the private key and then
everyone the public key could decrypt it
and know that I was the only person who
could have encrypted it right because
I'm the only person with this or you can
go the other direction which is to say
that I can encrypt some of the public
key and know that only people with the
private key can decrypt it right so what
you were asking what code signing is
code signing is the thing that goes in
this direction right if I'm Apple I
retain this secret key that all iOS
devices have a public key baked into
them that is the pair for it but only
Apple has the private key let's say so
you submit an executable to Apple right
they encrypt it with the private key or
in this case they probably don't encrypt
it they just sign it which means they
take like a checksum of it or something
and then in and then just encrypt the
checksum so they don't need to click the
whole external because we're not trying
to protect the executable they're trying
to just prevent it from running right so
they just encrypt some measure some
approximation like a hat like a hash or
or a checksum let's say but if we wanted
to be paranoid we can encrypt the whole
thing so let's just say we did that we
encrypt the whole executable with the
private key right and now all the iOS
devices all have the public key on them
already and everyone has that so it's
fine and so when they go to run
something they only run things they can
decrypt with the public key so they
decrypt and run so obviously since no
one else has the private key no
when else can actually take an
executable and produce something that
when decrypted with this public key
actually produces a working executable
right because if you feed in if you took
some other private key and feed in the
executable equipped Dex control with
that and feed it into here you'll just
get garbage out right it won't have it
won't look anything like that suitable
you put it there just kind of completely
meaning this bit stream so that's what
code signing is it's the operating
system having a public key and the
vendor having a private key such that
only people who pass their executable
through the vendor for signing can
actually run on the on the end device
nestled acacie would you consider
prioritizing developing for os's which
refused to use SGX
I mean sure but I doubt any will that
make sense
Steve boy you should do more streams
about this kind of stuff it's really
interesting when yeah I mean when it
comes up I mean like I said I'd wear
since we're on RSI break we - let's chat
about everything Rob Rob ad room like
this is sad
can you please choose a happier topic
for the next chat I can try but
unfortunately this doesn't go away that
makes sense
all right so I think we're pretty much
done anyway we're out of time here on
the stream so I'm gonna I'm gonna wrap
things up
that was that was yeah I'm breakable DRM
in a nutshell sad but true
coming down the pipe and probably not
gonna be stoppable
yeah what are you gonna do if only
people were nice and actually cared
about like progress and happiness and
things instead of money wouldn't it be
great but that's not the world we live
in so well anyway thank you very much
for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero chat we will probably be
next back next week for some more chat
until then I hope you guys have fun
programming I'm sorry that DRM will ruin
all of our lives eventually that's just
the way it goes maybe we'll be able to
do something to stop it who knows but
for now that's just that's just a sad
state of affairs yeah so go ahead and
everyone go cry under keyboards I will
as well and maybe our collective tears
will short out the world and it'll be
some kind of grand protest thanks for
joining me everyone I will see you back
here next week don't forget to check the
tweet bot on handmade hero org to find
out what the schedule is until then have
fun coding and I will see you guys on
the Internet