hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show where we could a complete
game live on stream we are probably
going to since we sort of started it
yesterday we are going to take a look at
allowing multiple sim region
computations per frame just to sort of
get an idea of what it what it would
entail and we're just not going to worry
too much about the overlapping
boundaries problem what we'll do is
we'll just try to make it so that if
multiple sim regions would overlap we
just go ahead and overlap that merge
them together and simulate a bigger sim
region that's probably not going to be
you know the final way to do it we may
have to get more creative and try to
hack things together in order to make it
work I don't know just because I'm
worried about the performance
implications of merging regions together
you know like i said i don't really have
a good feel for what's going to be
required there but we're going to give
it a shot and we'll just see what
happens at the very least we know that
we can do a reasonable job anytime some
regions aren't overlapping so you know
when in doubt at least implement the
thing that you know you can implement
and then you know will at least be in a
better position to have some kind of you
know guess about whether or not we'll be
able to do something smarter than just
merging the regions so today is day 3 49
so if you would like to follow along at
home please start with de 348 source
code that's what I'm starting with today
oops and I'm going to just go ahead and
do a quick build and run here so let's
load up the there we go let's go ahead
and run this so we are basically back to
normal behavior here for the most part
everybody is kind of just hopping around
doing their random thing that they do
and so I really just wanted to make it
some way of sort of having a bigger
world
that's getting simulated by different
people and different at different times
and stuff like that and and so as you
can see I've had the world generator
generate us a fairly sizable at least by
our current standards sighs you can keep
walking around this world for a long
time and there's just lots of random
junk happening you know we don't have a
very interesting world generator at the
moment so there's nothing interesting to
see in this world but it's definitely
got plenty of rooms and so what I want
to do is just get it to the point where
maybe we've got to simulation regions
happening if you remember we've sort of
have this ability to zoom out on the
debug camera and if I do zoom out on the
debug camera you can kind of see what's
getting simulated at the moment and it
kind of reaches back just to write about
their right you can sort of see that
anything in this boundary here is sim
and anything in this safe region here is
is pulled in as well although not
simulated at the moment and I can sort
of come back here this way and activate
those things you can see how they become
active when I come in there but if I
leave that region well I'm not doing a
very good job leaving it if I leave that
region then things that are outside that
boundary generally I think go back to
sleep right I don't actually know if
that's true to be honest with you I
guess I don't really know what we ended
up deciding to do there in terms of
checking people's active flags because
we have some weird stuff that's
happening whoa so this is pretty
interesting here I guess what that means
is because like this guy was still
obeying collision and everything so I
guess that means is we're not rendering
anything out there but we are actually
simulating it properly which is
interesting so the simulation battery
must go out to their remember we have a
weird thing that we did which is that
any time any part of a creature is
inside if that is a multi-part creature
it will bring in the rest of the
creature so we also have kind of an
interesting thing going on there we have
to look for but anyway if we take a look
at what's going on here we definitely
have a big enough world to make multiple
sim regions because for example you
could imagine
having say for sake of argument down
here there's definitely rooms we could
have a second sim region down here
simulating those rooms right so it would
be nice to do a test here where we could
have that extra sim going on so we could
verify that we can sim and that we can
also send this other area over here
right so that's really it uh by the way
those of you who are wondering where the
black dot is the black dot is we've
figured out what it is the black dot is
the cursor for some reason we're drawing
the cursor we're not drawing it in the
right place I don't even know why we
were drawing it or when but you can kind
of see it moving around there randomly
you know I'm saying that's pretty weird
so yeah I have no idea why that's there
but that's what that is somebody must be
drawing the cursor I've no idea why I do
not care about that at the moment I
should probably add to the Duelist
though like say why is somebody's still
drawing mouse cursor and drawing it
wrong like no idea when that got put in
one hour night it's kind of hard to
remember what it is that you have and
haven't done and why all right so anyway
I'm going to recompile here at that I'm
going to go ahead and switch out to a
handmade world mode and in handmade
world would be already sort of started
to play around with this you can see I
have an update and render sim region
call and what I did was I made it so
that right here we just you know do that
call which updates and renders the same
region and so in theory we could call
this twice with different sim bounds and
do a second simulation but things are a
little bit dicey ER than I would like
them to be because if you go and look at
what happens in the update and render
sim region call because it's update and
render are baked together we definitely
have some situations where if we wanted
to do an update without doing any
rendering it would be a little bit
unusual right and similarly there are
some things in here like this which are
sort of what happens with the player
input right but we don't really want the
player input to be involved
here you know we don't necessarily want
player input to be getting considered
every time we update a sim region
because we only want to do that for the
for the sim region that the monitor is
actually viewing because if you you know
you're not supposed to be interacting
with any of the other sim regions that
are getting simulated off-screen which
are just to like allow MPC's to do
things or to allow game events to happen
that are you know sort of happening
without your participation so they
certainly shouldn't be checking for any
kind of player input at that point ooh
hmm yani okay so let's take a look here
and and just see what we might want to
do about that so again we've got a we've
got some sort of issues here that we we
kind of want to think about specifically
when we do updating of the world we
don't necessarily want to split update
and render into two separate parts right
because if you think about what happens
here the natural thing for us to do
would be to say well we want to be able
to update the sim regions and we want to
be able to render the world but we don't
want to have to render every time we
update because we may want to update
things that we don't render their
off-screen so it may be tempting to
break update and render into two steps
one that does updating and one that does
rendering the problem with this is it is
inherently slower to do that usually the
reason is because when I have to update
something I have to pull of its data
into the cache and I have to work on it
right so it's live it's there it's in
the cash ready for me to operate on it
it already got dragged in to you know
from main memory into the processors
cash so it's usually pretty free at that
point for me to then just use that data
that I've already pulled into the cash
to produce a render command for this
thing that will properly reflect where
it is in the world and what if it Maps
should be and all those other thoughts
of things that I need to
look at the entity's data to be able to
determine how to do that right so if I
fundamentally split up update and render
into two pieces then I have this problem
where I'm pulling everything back into
the cache twice right the first time I
pull it in to do the update the second
time I pull it in to do the render and
that's not probably going to be a very
efficient way to do things so it depends
largely on whether or not the update
needs to fully complete before the
render can happen is really the only
reason why I would probably split them
up and what I mean by that is if for
example update needs to operate in
several passes like for example all
objects need to be I'm sorry all
entities need to be moved in the world
and then they need to have some like
collisions reconciled after their
movement or something and then and only
then after all that's done can I
actually issue render commands for them
if that's the case then splitting it
into update and render makes reasonable
sense because I already know that I'm
not going to get that cash win I have to
wait until things are done and pull an
entity back into the cash to render it
anyway so at that point I'm not worried
about making an architectural faux pas
by splitting up these two operations
however if I don't think that I'm going
to do that if I think that in general
i'll be able to just step through each
entity allow it to run a simulation step
and then retire it and say this is its
permanent location for the final frame
for the next frame rather at that point
it really doesn't make very much sense
for me to split them up what I would
rather do is just make it so that I do
them both together and there's just have
a branch that's like if I'm rendering do
the render work otherwise don't write so
I think at this point in time it's too
early to make a definitive statement
that i know that splitting update and
render is a good idea i think that it's
possible that keeping update and render
together is going to be smarter and more
efficient in the end it certainly has
the possibility to be so and so what I
would like to do is keep it
that those things are still welded but
they will essentially work they will
essentially work in a way that allows
you to turn off the rendering when you
don't want the rendering to occur now
I've got some situations here where like
I don't super understand a couple things
like for example I don't know why the
render group okay as that's why it is
because it needs to reserve sort keys I
was like I don't know why the render
group needs to get passed down to
something like the brain who's really
tired easy to adapt it's nap time and so
yeah in in this case where we've got the
sort of always behind always a sort of
it's having to pass the renter rip down
to this thing so yeah in this case with
the render group reserved sort key bit
this would just be something where the
render group is only getting passed into
this thing for that one purpose and it
makes sense why it has to happen but I
do wonder when we move to a z-buffer if
maybe we can get rid of that I hope that
we can I'm not sure because it'll depend
on how we choose to make things work but
it's entirely plausible that we could
just sort of structure things so that
maybe that works I don't know well I
guess we'd have to because we won't have
the ability to do a sort key of that
nature inside the z-buffer really i mean
we could implement something like that
in a crazy sort of depth control
situation but i don't know if we really
want to go that far so anyway yeah this
render group situation is is not my
favorite and I do wonder so if we do
that reserve sort key thing here if I
wasn't going to do that always behind
always in front of I assume we just get
the head passing in front of and behind
the body at the moment right because
that's all that was for also I believe
we're still in debug I mean I optimize
build which I don't really need to be in
at the moment we're not doing any kind
of performance testing so I'm not going
to bother with the logger build times
that come from that
so yeah you can kind of see how the head
like flashes because it doesn't have do
you see how it kind of goes behind the
body occasionally there to see that
happening so that's what I'm talking
about that's what that code was in there
for so I'm going to go ahead and say
that while we're doing this for
architecting since I already said that
we're going to go ahead and put in the
3d stuff and I don't think that sort key
situation is really going to be able to
work i'll probably just pull that and
then we won't rely on the render Bruce
that's the only reason it was in there
now it's worth noting that I'm not one
hundred percent certain how we are going
to address that problem but I think it
wouldn't really matter that much because
as long as the body and the head when
they when they tilt are tilted the same
way I think we'll probably be able to Z
buffer will be able to take care of that
for us we'll just have to layer things
properly so I think that'll be ok I
think that that won't be something it
will still require a little bit of
finesse but I don't think it'll be too
much of a problem so I'm going to go
ahead and remove that for now and then
we can get rid of the render group from
here because that's the only thing that
it was actually necessary for so what
I'm going to do now is I'm just going to
take a pass through this code and I'm
going to try and isolate the stuff
that's actually working on the render
group and what you can kind of see here
is that there's really not that much
stuff that's happening it's mostly in
pass-through calls and a little bit of
debug stuff here so this debug stuff it
doesn't really matter when i call this
debug stuff per se because since it is
sort of put in the world in a sort any
way or in a z-buffer later on i should
be able to do something where I kind of
move this stuff down into a more
aggregated place so for example if I
wanted to I should be able to come down
here
and yeah let me just see if that still
works reasonably well get the debug
camera there yeah
so that's still totally fine and so what
I want to do is I just want to kind of
calves off this part here because all of
this stuff and I guess is this raft
outline mouse p nonsense this looks like
the stuff this is the person who's
drawing the mouse isn't it goodbye to
you sir I don't actually know is this
necessary that orthographic change there
I don't think it is yeah so if I take a
look now at what's actually happening I
can pretty much calves off this entire
section as being stuff that's only there
if we're rendering right so for
rendering we need to do this and then
really there's only just one thing that
I need to be aware of which is that it
update and render entities right that
actually does need to obey the same sort
of protocol where you have to be able to
test whether you're going to render or
not so that you can optionally not
render but now we're definitely in a
case where we don't have to render if we
don't want to and similarly I can come
in here and I can sort of start to act
get these things sort of place in a more
reasonable fashion we could sort of say
all right maybe like this let's say we
could sort of look at these and go you
know we know that at least these things
here are optional right we don't need to
pass any of this stuff if you wanted to
do a sin step you could and all of those
things could be left 0 right now what I
don't know is for background color I'm
assuming that's just a pass through to
the render edit e and I'm correct as far
as game state is concerned that's only
for input I think or yeah because
basically controlled heroes is the only
place that that really is ever used so
that's really in some sense probably up
optional as well so it would kind of be
nice it'd probably be
nice if we had some way of making that a
little bit less sort of weirdly
intertwined so for example if I went out
to let's say uh maybe rain and just
looked at it yet you can kind of see the
only reason that we need this is again
to get at that controlled heroes array
so you know that's another one that's
really only necessary if we have input
so technically even that is is kind of
optional so you can just kind of see
what i'm doing here is kind of looking
at really what what's actually necessary
for this code let's take a look at
screen bounds so screen bounce is
interesting in that screen bounds is
really something you know this this
render code this code for the pushing
the outline here this stuff could really
be moved one level out if it wasn't for
this this sim region bounds part here
and uh so I mean really that's the only
thing and so if we wanted to we could
probably get away with doing this a
little bit cleaner I'm trying to think
of how exactly that would work because
you can kind of see the problem is that
we don't get information about the
camera until later and so then when we
come through here we would mean that we
need to know some of the stuff like the
screen bounds and that sort of thing in
order to just do that debug rendering
but yeah again that's like all see your
sim bounds should be used yes for this
so it's really you know even screen
bounds here is a totally optional thing
right it's not necessary so you're
really looking at very very few actual
actual pieces of information there I'm
interested to know in update and render
entities because I'm not actually sure
I'm interested to know what the
transient state is used for in there so
inside update and render
which is right here I kind of want to
know what trans States used for I'm
going to switch screens because I can't
see behind my head there so tranh state
is also just used it's just used for the
asset system so really the trans state
itself is not necessary at all that
could just be the asset system that's
getting past there would be the only
thing that action news happen and that
only needs to happen because of the
rendering so that again is totally
optional so you know we sort of have a
thing that's like game assets here and
the trans state is really not necessary
it's really just that one piece of it
right and so when I call this you know
I'm really only passing that is the only
useful part of the thing that I'm
actually passing so yeah again kind of
getting it a little bit more little bit
more figured out here so yeah so trans
state is getting past with that reason
but now we sort of got an idea that
really if you were going to simulate you
would only need these three things
that's all you actually need and then if
you want to simulate an render at the
same time then you need to deal with
this stuff right here
so I think that's mostly it I just want
to know if I can maybe I I would be
interested to continue fussing with that
a little bit more to kind of get it more
condensed down into a cleaner state I
don't need to do it right now but it's
on my mind because you know maybe sort
of reorganizing how some of these
structures work may be thinking of
things in terms of a context that we
could construct there are ways we can
sort of architect around that a little
bit and so I do wonder if maybe that
isn't something we will want to do in
the future I'm going to go ahead through
here and do the exact same
reorganization mouse p i think was used
only for debug picking if i'm not
mistaken but we probably still want that
to be happening so we're going to leave
all that in there we've got some stuff
here like dt is going to be necessary
and camera p is really only necessary
for rendering obviously so a lot of this
stuff i think pretty much everything
after here is probably also optional and
so now we just kind of have to take a
look at what this stuff is doing or when
it's doing it so you can kind of come
through here and see we're computing all
this stuff like the camera p on all this
like fog amounts and that sort of stuff
we don't care what those come out to be
if all we're doing is simulating so it
doesn't matter you could pass like zero
for the camera P and that would be fine
I also don't know if this stuff needs to
be done at the top I think it might be
able to do it sort of well no it needs
to be done prepped so that each entity
can hand of have it happen but this is
obviously something that doesn't
actually need to be inside here this
could be done above this could be done
in the outer layer code and passed down
as sort of the fog cam rail arrays or
something like this right and these clip
Rex could be set up that way so this is
actually something that we could pull
out and probably should pull out into a
separate piece of code so that's just
worth
thinking about there because for example
these like push clip threat calls those
are something that we only would be able
to get if we actually had a render group
itself so you know we're really looking
at something more like this where if
somebody told us we were going to have a
render group then we could do something
with it but otherwise we can't so
looking at this rendered group there's
some usage of it the next time we get to
it we come back down in here where we're
sort of doing this entity transform
stuff and my assumption is that all of
this can be sort of removed because
remember this is all just like for
sorting and for you know aggregates and
all that sort of stuff all of this stuff
is just for drawing there's nothing else
that happens in here at all as far as i
know so really all of that stuff can
just be kind of moved inside of a giant
if statement that says don't do any of
the render work if somebody isn't asking
us to render at this time and the same
thing would be true down here right so I
think that's pretty much all we would
need to do let me go ahead and
reorganize this particular call to have
the update and render entities to have
the order of parameters reflect the new
order of parameters where I just kind of
was arranging things there so we've got
the dt comes here then we've got render
group camera p draw buffer background
color assets mass p and the same now is
true for see here update and render
world is calling update and render sim
region which is right here that's going
to translate this world mode and the sim
bounds those are the things that are
actually passed then we have the render
group screen bounds the game state the
background color is actually before that
so background color screen bounds game
state input render group and drama fur
so there you go and now if i run this I
should get exactly same thing I was
getting before and I believe if we want
to we could turn off rendering so let's
just try that and see if we can do it so
we'll just call update we know we only
need these things so I'm just going to
call like with nothing for the
background color with rectangle I don't
know well I mean I guess it doesn't
matter what I pass here but you know 0
for the game state 0 for the input 0
under group and 0 for the draw buffer
now there is one place we're going to
have to fix and that is that I inside we
have to if on the input inside the brain
because we didn't in here there is one
person who does that you can kind of see
that we have this place for the game
state and the input get hughes and so
that part is not going to work anything
that references the input is not going
to work so if i take a look at ups
that's not what I wanted if I take a
look at where controller is being used
at the moment I think it's really only
in just this one preamble where we set
everything right and I think we can
probably just do an if around that and
have that go away now granted I don't
know that we really need it too because
you know this is only going to happen in
a circumstance where you're simulating
something that should be allowed to be
controlled so you know we could just
always pass the game state and the input
I
that's a tough that's a tough call but
i'm going to go ahead and do it anyway
because i think we probably want to
eventually get it kind of separated out
so i'm just going to go ahead and try
that all right so we want to d sword why
do we clear d sword if it's already
cleared like it's cleared here it
doesn't get set to anything so I have no
idea what that's for I don't pretend to
know old code so I'm going to do if
input around this and then I'm just
going to kind of go through here and see
if I can move all of this stuff in word
so that now it's not actually able to
access it and it looks like we've got a
couple things from the con hero that our
control information and so yeah so I
think for those I think we just want to
sort of nullify them out right I mean I
think what we want to do here is we've
got a handmade h oops
for this sort of thing I think we just
want to go like hey all right there's a
cleared one of these that you can use
that just has everything set to nothing
and then when you come in here will
actually set it if there actually is one
you know what I'm saying and then
everything else can proceed as as
planned I think that should work all
right so now in what we're going to do
now is just kind of go through and clean
up anything where we were referenced or
something we didn't have so in this case
like we've got the mouse p situation
happening so that's in here and what I
want to do is just say well okay you
know don't set it to anything if you
can't write if you don't have an input
then you don't see if we got anything
else
um what there I was like that's a weird
place to give me that error because
that's actually where the error is but
okay so here's an input dt4 frame is
getting called here and of course in
updating render sim region that input
dt4 frame is not something that we
actually have because so what we really
want here is we want that DT for the sim
to be passed directly to us oops because
we don't know if we have an input right
and that way we can kind of get rid of
this and then down in here when we
actually call it will just pass that
along
so now I think we're in good shape
because right we shouldn't be seeing
anything right because we've passed 02
the sim but it still should be
simulating everything in theory
unfortunately I guess does that mean we
exit because we didn't set heroes exist
to anything yes I suppose it does so we
will automatically exit because it never
triggered the like add a hero piece of
code uh well so that's okay I mean this
is just for testing purposes so in
theory that's all fine so now all we
have to do is simulate some other region
that is not the same region that we were
going to simulate before so you know now
we've got two sims that are happening in
fact if we did this the game should run
at double speed right if I simulate it
once and then stimulate it again I
should get a double update so everything
should move twice as fast in theory
right or something weird like this
should happen weirdly enough I i I'm not
even really sure what that is doing
can't say I know whether that's what I
would have expected or not because I'm
kind of just doing something random here
but I would have expected it to simulate
them again and they didn't look like
they were going twice as fast which is
weird so I'm not sure what happened
there that seems a little odd doesn't it
I mean it seems like that should have
the little hopper guys should have
hopped twice as fast I'm not surprised
that I can't move because I would be
getting cleared so I'd only be able to
do a little bit of motion before I would
get cleared by the next pass through who
didn't have an input call but yeah it
seems like those guys should have been
hopping faster I guess let's double
check something does this play twice as
fast yes it does so we do know that our
dt per frame can be doubled and we'll go
twice as fast so I would have expected
if I did this that I would end up doing
two sim steps which should have made
everything run twice as fast but it did
not do that at least not that I could
perceive Oh although since we're running
too slowly with two of the sim steps let
me see if this makes a difference there
we go alright so it did do it did do
that disaster narrowly averted so I
wonder what is actually why it was
running so much more slowly when we ran
it twice let's take a look in D because
it doesn't run that it doesn't really
run much slower when we're not when
we're in a release mode I'm curious who
is taking up that time Oh get closest
reversible of course the UNAC celebrated
N squared disaster of it all some point
we're going to have to do something
about that it's an easy thing to do
something about but
alright so I think that's really all we
needed to do to do to sim things for
frame we could also choose if we want to
to do sin without input so I could avoid
passing in the input but still do a sim
and a render I think and if I do that
what I could say is like okay when we do
an update and render sim region let's
give it a sim bounds that's not the sim
bound we're currently at so let's call
this sim bounds to write and i'm going
to go ahead and say that sim bounds
drive an offset call
mmm yeah I do I'm going to offset the
sim bounds by something so let's say
that I'm going to offset the sim bounds
by like you know 100 meters in that
direction for some reason don't ask me
why and then I'm going to go up here and
I'm going to say all right a mr. camera
person let's use the debug camera let's
zoom out a ways and I really need this
debug you I do not be quite so bad as it
is but now we should be getting in there
we have it is to separate simulating
regions that we can see both of right so
there's one region that's being
simulated and here's another region
that's being simulated by the sim call
which is exactly what I wanted and so
you can see that this is relatively easy
thing for us to have work it's it's
pretty straightforward but I like I said
it gets problematic when these things
overlap and maybe there's things we can
do to kind of fix that I don't know we
got to kind of think about it a little
bit harder but at least for part of the
way there now so yeah I think that's
about it all I want to do today we're
going to start in on some more heavy
lifting on that front next week so let's
go ahead and go to the QA
f1 aw did you make that debug you by
yourself yeah that's why it's kind of
clunky like we didn't when we made it we
were kind of playing around with data
structure stuff a bunch and doing some
things you know that are cool and all
but we didn't spend any time on the
actual widget miss of it all so it's
kind of super lousy and it wouldn't take
very long to go in and fix it and I
probably should budget a couple days
just go in and make some nice widgets
you know for it but
Nicola have you thought about
refactoring your brain code to make use
of virtual method switch statements on
type is basically replicating the type
system a bit of the code smell so I mean
as you may have predict I strongly
disagree with that opinion my opinion is
that virtual methods are the one that
smell and that switches are correct the
reason that I believe that is twofold
one is because I believe that if
fundamentally speaking C++ as virtual
system and inheritance are designed and
properly so even if you were going to go
that route you would not want to do it
the way that they do it and the reason
for that is because the identification
of a type as being the type that it is
is a first class citizen in programming
and also in actual math in like group
theory and stuff c++ fundamentally
doesn't allow that they have a very like
shoddy rtti system that doesn't even
have your you are not even able to
define what the values are four types so
you can't say this particular derived
class is considered type you know 37 or
something this but that's critically
important it's critically important
because you need it in order to be able
to do save and restore and communicating
between your program compiled on one
compiler and another version compiled on
another compiler like let's say ps4 is
llvm and your pc version is you know
msvc there are TT I wouldn't necessarily
even have to agree with itself although
i don't know maybe these days they
expect it to do so in the old days it
didn't but even simple things like that
just don't work right so first of all I
I think yeah virtual methods are the
ones that I think are really
questionable I don't like them at all
secondly switch statements are actually
way more readable in my opinion because
they put the code that does the same
thing for each entity in the same place
which is what I find more valuable than
having the code for an entity included
all the different types of code for
entity including one place the reason
for that is I don't tend to change
entities in ways or I don't
to change subclasses in ways that are
super unique to their layout very often
what I tend to do is change the way
methods work very often so for example I
may change the way that rendering is
happening that means that typically what
I'm doing is I'm changing the render
call of all of the entity types or
whatever it is at once so I want all
that code in one place so I can pull out
shared pieces really easily just by
cutting and pasting it up to the top
rather than having to factor that out
into a virtual base function which could
call the derive functions and have to
make sure that that always happens blah
blah blah blah blah so I would like
strongly challenge anyone who suggests
that switch statements have a code smell
to them that to me is very dogmatic I
don't see any factual basis for making
that claim it's just it sounds like one
of those things that C++ programmers say
but they have no data to back that up
right there like I don't know of any
actual evidence that suggests that
somehow a virtual function is cleaner
than a switch statement because all the
evidence that I've ever seen either
suggests that their equivalent and just
have different sort of code layout so
depending on what you might be doing one
may be better than the other right or
did a switch statement is strictly
superior because you have a well-defined
type you can use that type in other
places right so yeah
do you use keyword only at your day job
are you faster without the mouse um yeah
I don't really like using a mouse very
much but I sometimes have to and
sometimes you know a mouse is useful for
like picking entities and stuff like
that and a lot of times I don't
necessarily have good keyboard UI and
things like unfortunately it tends to be
a cheaper sometimes to do stuff like
coming through and making a quick mouse
you buy for something is actually easier
than making a good keyboard you I so
that's unfortunate but Nick see i missed
the reason the two areas on the screen
are discontinuous are these two sim
regions of a larger world yes so
essentially what we're doing is we're
stimulating both of these regions I just
said simulate a region where the where I
am right now and then stimulate a region
off to the side so if I was let's say
let me build in a release here so we're
not paying the the the cost there and
let me go ahead and pull this guy out
for the love of God man I need to fix
this somebody really github bug
alright so I'm going to start hopping
along right and hopefully you can kind
of see that that simulation region down
at the bottom there is just going to
keep simulating some part of the world
that's kind of like just off to the side
right that's all it's doing and at this
point now there's nothing in that same
region because it's you know there's no
part of the world that happens to
overlap that for whatever reason and now
I've gotten down at this point to the
area that we were seeing in the same
region before i'm now in it right and
i'm hopping along you can see me doing
it right so hopefully that'll make sense
and yet if it will only actually see
anything in the sim region when there is
part of the world that happens to
overlap it which is not necessarily
always I can't really see where my guy
is at the moment
oh no that's not good look at what
happened to my poor hero he's been sort
of stuck he's been stuck in a tree in a
horrible accident I assume this is
probably because I hit one of those jump
pads which we have not really
implemented yet I think I slammed him
into a tree but anyway point being that
is all the separates in region is meant
to be doing
what do you think about changing float
values in the debug system by the
distance you drag example longer drag
distance equals bigger increments
decrements of the value shorter drive
distance equals smaller increment so
you're talking about basically
acceleration on it meaning like if I
move it a lot I don't just move it by
that much more than the little amount I
actually moved by like an exponential
amount more if I'm understanding
correctly I I don't know I I guess I'd
have to play with it probably
and yeah I definitely don't like see
make see make is is real problematic
especially on windows it's a little bit
better on unix I think probably because
it came from unix I would assume I don't
really know where it came from but I I
believe that the sort of Windows version
is a bit of an afterthought it doesn't
work very well it's got a lot of
problems like I had to edit the source
code to see make in order to get llvm to
build properly because see make itself
didn't have any way of specifying that
you didn't want to use dynamic libraries
it was hilarious it's like hard coded
into the source it's like ok so there's
a bunch of stuff like that likessee make
is way worse than just using a batch
file in my experience I'm still open to
the possibility that like there is a
make system that's good or something but
I've just never seen it is the problem
they all seemed like way worse than just
writing in the batch file that does the
build
what books you recommend for c
programming you know i mean the only one
that I really remember is the actual one
that's like the C programming language
the original one the white book by cover
I mean there might be good ones these
days but I don't know what they are it's
been 25 years since I learned see so I
have no idea
how about for learning open jail so
those arcs synthesis tutorials are
pretty good I mean you know there's not
a lot of great resources on learning
modern graphics API is unfortunately but
like it's definitely the case and I'm
going to go ahead and here and rid of
that for now
handmade network oxus somebody posted
here you go so this this thing here is
pretty good I the the the Ark synthesis
tutorials were like a website that was
like a dopo gel three-point Oh tutorial
site that was that was pretty good like
it covered a lot of stuff and like
showed how to do it in fairly modern
open jello with like shaders and you
know was as good at anything that would
be like here's how to write something
that isn't super antiquated I don't know
what else there is available and for
some reason the arc synthesis tutorials
got taken down but thankfully somebody
had saved them I guess and now they
exist here I don't know if this is the
person who actually did it or not but
whoever did it I'm glad they did because
it's something that I thought was pretty
reasonable when I looked at it and it
was a bummer that they kind of went away
but
soy sauce the kid by the way I would
throw in a pitch for n site if you
haven't already taken a look at it this
thing if you're having OpenGL problems
and you have access to an nvidia card of
some kind this tool is really good it's
a little crashy and for understandable
reasons because they're doing some
pretty unholy stuff with the graphics
card to say the least but this thing
really will help you with OpenGL
debugging like I would highly recommend
using it because it allows you to do a
number of things that you can't normally
do in any real easy way in your own code
so for example you can step into shaders
and actually inspect variables right and
it kind of works you can look at
textures like for it given shader
invocation you can actually look at what
textures were bound and what their
images were so you can even see if you
like your textures are messed up and so
like there's a ton of stuff that
typically you had to do yourself to
validate these sorts of things when you
were doing graphics card debugging in
the old days and this stuff is really
helpful so if you do have access to an
nvidia card it's pretty great if you can
run something like this because then you
can at least validate your OpenGL code
is working properly on a known platform
and then at least you can know that when
you're going to run it on whatever L
because you know maybe the bugs on AMD
or something right at least then you've
taken out part of you know we least you
know it works on something because
you've debugged on something and then
you're only talking about bugs in that
specific Hardware whatever you've moved
to right
I've never tried render doc uh is it
good
it looks like sort of the same thing
which is cool
it's cool that it supports all three of
these ap is what version of OpenGL does
it support hmm so this would not really
be something that I could use because
that's a kind of an old version of
OpenGL to a certain extent but but it
would certainly work for what you were
talking about which is OpenGL ES oh wait
no no immediate plans so no it wouldn't
nevermind all right I'm going to wind it
down here but yeah I haven't tried that
one but that's cool if that works too
you could try either one of them right
like whatever one works because they
probably both show similar information
alright thank you everybody for joining
me from the episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
series at home you can always prayer to
the game on handmade here org it comes
with the source code so you can play
around with it we also a forum site you
can go to if you want to ask questions
we have a patreon page and go to France
fourth the video series we have a
schedule bot who treats the schedule at
you and we have an episode guide you
could use for catching up on old
episodes i will mention i have been
thinking about switching up the format
of handmade hero uh to be in longer
chunks I've been thinking about possibly
instead of doing monday through friday
one hour stream a night with usually
like maybe one day off on the week you
know I typically do some days I do five
but oftentimes I only do four so it's
about 44 hours a week on average right I
was thinking of actually doing on
saturday and sunday to to our blocks so
that there were longer continuous
programming blocks especially when we go
through and do the 3d stuff because
that's definitely going to be something
where you know maybe we want a little
more concentrated time to kind of talk
about the math and then implement it in
one episode which would kind of be nice
so I don't know I have been thinking
about that that may happen if that does
happen then probably what we would be
doing is next week we wouldn't do any
broadcast during the week and then the
Saturday into Sunday we would do two
hours each what on each day to our
Saturday to our sunday if that makes
sense
but don't quote me on that I haven't
100% decided yet but it seems like what
I may want to do to do sort of a thicker
block if that makes sense
all right uh so that's about it I will
sign off for now and like I said maybe
check the tweet bot for more information
about whether we're going to switch to
it switch up the schedule for a little
while and try it that way and see how it
goes or whether we won't that's about it
for today until I see you all next time
have fun programming and i'll see you on
the Internet take