hello everybody and welcome to handmade
hero today we have um
kind of just an assignment from our past
self uh we have to figure out some good
way to rebuild our
uh sampling
tables our sampling tables for lighting
we found were actually broken um they
had been broken for a while it seems so
that was an issue
but they are especially showing uh
they're especially causing a problem now
because we're trying to debug uh the
simplification to the lighting that we
did
and in so trying we discovered that
like the rays we're casting are totally
not distributed the way that we thought
they were
so uh what we're trying to do at the
moment is oops this is actually debug
builds which i didn't actually mean to
do
let me go ahead and do a release build
there
so
there we go
um so if we run uh our lighting as it is
currently it actually is it's pretty
good uh we're we're not really um
we're we're in a very good state the
problem is there's this weird like sort
of color bleed that happens
and so we think we have some problems
with just like maybe the apron and stuff
you can see when it starts up it
actually looks quite nice
um so we're pretty close i don't think
we're like super far from
uh having it work but you can see that
we've got sort of this weird like color
bleed problem usually those feedback
problems are from like we're sampling
off of the apron or something is like
over getting over added or weird things
like that
um and so we need to debug that and as
we were debugging it we realized that
like as we looked at the raycasts the
ray choices of rays
there were like all of these rays
pointing straight down
right um
and it turns out that our our sampling
table
um if you go and look at it is just not
correct like there actually is
um
a
uh a situation where like every so often
like you see that zero zero
uh one
zero zero one zero zero like
there we should never sample sample the
same ray twice right i mean we never
want to do that um and yet here we are
doing that a ton of times right
and so we clearly have a bad
distribution that we're that we're
putting in here that's not good uh and
we really want to be able to fix that
but while we're doing it uh we also
probably just want to rebuild these
sampling tables to be a little bit more
uh sensible anyway right
because now we know
that we're actually just sampling the
whole sphere every time like before we
were doing sort of an overtime sampling
because we were trying to sample a lot
more probes
now we just don't have that problem
uh because we've got a lot more
horsepower since we've reduced
we're not using z anymore
um
z stacks
so there's just a lot fewer probes we
can cast a lot more rays and so and we
also optimized the raycasting to be very
fast so it doesn't take very much time
to do the samples anyway
so we probably want to do something
where we just like create a sample
sphere that's pretty reasonable with
respect to um
you know just chunks where we have
16 rays or so going out of one face and
16 rays going out of another face 16
rays going out of another face
um
we kind of want these like i do think we
want these to be a blue noise pattern
blue noise sampling is always better
than white noise uh for you know because
uh white noise is
very uh is is going to over sample some
areas and undersample others whereas
blue noise is always like fairly
distributed
the problem is how do we generate a blue
noise sample that has exactly 16
points
in the
[Music]
in the region of the face
the the octahedral face that we're
sampling from
and
you know
that's a that's a tougher question
i can think of sort of ways we might do
it like for example if you were to make
a dense
blue noise pattern on a sphere
and then you just like scale that up
over like you just searched for a scale
factor
where it as you scaled it up you would
get uh only a certain number like you
basically like restrict the size
of the stuff on the sphere until you get
ones that are yeah but even that's not
going to be the same as for distance
it's a tough problem like i don't know
exactly how you do it
like i don't know how you do a blue
noise pattern where you basically say
look we're going to divide the sphere
into eight
uh you know octants and we want each
octant
to have 16 evenly distributed sample
points that are like you know
uh
sort of like equally
you know spaced out or whatever
i don't know how you do that um
i would also
ask is it just per pixel should we just
do it per pixel because this is another
problem so let's think about this real
quick
um
so if we were to look at the the map dim
right the octahedral map is eight by
eight
so there's there's 64
um
there's 64 like taxels that we're
filling
right
um and
let me run speed crunch oops
let me run speed crunch here
if there's 64 texels we're filling
um and we are actually for each one of
those texels yeah so there would be 16
samples per texel
is that correct
because we write out a row at a time
um so there's eight
yeah so i think that's what we would be
doing it's 16 samples per textile right
so i think what we actually probably
want to do is just generate
samples in the texel
probably
um
and best tardis we don't have
any temporal
uh variance anymore i mean we could add
some more in but at the moment we are
just sampling a fixed set of rays and i
know there's like issues with that but
the idea is to be dense enough that we
don't care because it seemed like we
were we will be able to do that
um
possibly
so
yeah like
maybe the right answer is we generate
blue noise a blue noise tile
for
the texel
and then we just compute the directions
out of the texel
so because it's not that hard to make
blue noise where we
uh generate 16
points in a
in a square
it it is and in fact we could even use
sort of something that's not quite blue
noise like something that's like
pseudoblue noise sampling pattern that's
you know because we don't need it to be
exactly blue noise it could be
sort of like
blue noise
light like um
you know what i mean
uh
so we could do something like that
we could do something like that
um i'm just trying to think of what's
the most straightforward way to do it
uh
like
the other thing is i guess we could just
tune the parameter manually
so we can just tune the blue noise
distance parameter so that we know that
it's like roughly correct like
you know this gets 16
and it's like a little sparse but it's
you know it's good enough or something
um
so yeah so let's take a look at hh
sphere uh and let's just try to rewrite
it to something else uh let's also get
it so that we can draw it so like if we
look uh inside handmade lighting
there's this like sphere drawing thing
that we have um here right so this thing
draws the sphere and so what we could do
is try to get that working in some way
where we can see uh the light
uh
values here
um and if we run that we should see like
a sampling sphere sitting there right
and the point of this there's not a
whole lot of point to this at the moment
but what we can do is
we can
verify
by modifying this routine
we can verify that this
comes out looking evenly distributed
somehow right like um
we can adjust this drawing routine to
draw like the each patch
in like a different color or something
uh and
from there we can like we have this get
debug color four right you can see this
part here so we can do something where
we basically rebuild the table
then we draw the table here where we
show each patch and we can sort of
verify that it's roughly correct
right
so i think that's mostly what we want
um so in hh sphere
what we would like i think there's like
a fair bit of cruft in here now um
so like things like interleave
directions like we don't actually want
this anymore
um
i don't think
like
like we don't want some of these things
anymore like interleave directions
we don't want to actually do
um
we want to generate
we want to generate things differently
than that
i also don't know like why
do we even want those at the moment
that's kind of a good question
light sampling
sphere float table do we use that
what is that used
for there's a light sampling so the
sampling spheres
are here
and the directions
like why are there two like
we haven't done this in long enough that
i don't
remember why it's doing it this way i
also have like no idea why there are ray
bundles per sphere this way
um
is that because we load them as 4x
values
like what do we do there
uh when we load this end do we do some
kind of
so we use something called ray d single
which is a sample ray direction pulled
out of
the light sample directions right
so
it's just it's just that
so what do we need
what do we actually use
the sample spheres part of things four
like does anyone use
this
was this just for back when we were
doing other things
um
because i don't know right so like do we
ever look up a light sampling sphere at
all
oops
like i don't think we do so let's remove
this because that may be another source
of confusion is that we're generating
these two things because we used to use
one of them and we don't anymore and
just like getting that out of there will
reduce the chances that we do something
stupid like are looking at one like
because we're drawing one and like using
the other right which is really bad um
that could be
making us think like something right so
this is why i say like you know doing
this pass to clean up the code is very
important because we've done all these
experiments and now we need to condense
down to just like
just one so that we can focus on getting
it right
um
and nice and shippable right like anyway
so uh if we just take the sampling
spheres out of here who complains
right
um
let's find out so
i don't know what rays per probe is
there so if we get rid of this what else
we got this i don't know what that is
um and this is just drawing it so like
if we turn off the drawing
um
is that it
so yeah so none of that was getting used
none of that is getting used
so so that entire thing where we do like
the interleave values like that whole
thing just doesn't even matter
so this like we're only using this part
of the entire thing so presumably if we
went to this this part here
so we've got this like light sample
direction presumably if we just deleted
like the rest of this stuff
like this
um
it would be fine
like i think we just left this in here
because we were using it but and now we
don't so let's just get rid of it and
see what happens like if i get rid of
that entirely does anyone complain
okay
so basically like we've we know now that
we're actually down to just the table
that actually we care about which is
good
um
so that means we can also delete all
this other stuff right so here is the
only table this is the only table we're
actually using
was is that
we don't care about any of these they're
not relevant so they can all go away
um and that means that the sample
direction
like bundle thing
doesn't have to happen so it's just the
raw directions that we need
and if we look at the raw directions
oops um
i'm not sure where these are actually
defined uh probably
somewhere sphere store
so where is sphere store
okay
um
so the sphere store here the raw
directions is really the part we
actually care about and that's just the
v3 the sphere store i don't think we
actually need
so if we look at spheres
in theory that should just be like not
even a thing
anymore
it's not used in the output
is it used in here
i don't think so
so yeah i think like basically we can
remove interleave directions we can
remove
i don't think cube store is used at all
so we can remove all of these
and i think we're good like uh we can
just really remove all this stuff
uh are we compiling this though
that shouldn't have compiled so i think
we're just not compiling hh sphere so
let's
make sure we are
there we go
okay so if i remove
uh
this stuff so we remove that we remove
the
the use of spheres everywhere
so we just have like
generate some stuff for us
and store the raw directions no more
spheres
right no more sphere stuff happening
i think
then we're good so we don't need any of
this
and now like our
our program is vastly simplified
right and we're all good so that's all
fine
so now all we're doing is calling
generate octahedral lighting pattern uh
and we have a thing that outputs that
here
which i think is correct i don't think
we really need to modify it particularly
much
the raw directions though need to
actually be packed in a different way so
we want to like change the order of them
um so that in here like we're gonna want
to have
uh for
we're gonna want to have this load
properly
so that you
do the casts in like the right order
right
um
and that's easier said than done because
it's kind of complicated to unwind in
your mind
if you look at the way that it's working
now
we have like this octahedron index and
it loops over and you do eight ray
indices right you can see them happening
here
um
and i don't think we actually want to do
it that way
i think what we probably would rather do
is
build the ray
build this one do the loops the other
way around
if that makes sense
so in other words
we would pick
we walk the table in order we do eight
or sorry uh however many light sampling
octahedron counts there are we do that
many in a row on the same accumulator
then we move to the next
texel
right
i think that's how we would do it
um
yeah
um so if we're doing it that way
then we know that this output right is
just going to be the this table of light
sample directions
uh
the light lighting octahedral map
dimension
is fine as a pound defined output we
need to know that right
the
light sampling octahedron mask is not
going to be a thing anymore
because we don't step through them
unpredictably
so that would go away
the
light sample directions for octahedron
um
i don't
think
i don't think that would actually ever
be used
so really all you need is
the map dimension
and the
count of the rays coming out of a single
texel
so it would be like
you know
lighting
uh
octahedral
samples per texel or raise per texel
right
and that number is actually a parameter
we could generate like more or less of
those depending on how much cpu power we
want to spend versus the quality of the
sampling right
um so instead of raised per octahedron i
think what we want here is raise per
texel
and that would get printed the
octahedron count would not be a thing
because we were that was sort of a
surrogate that was actually what raised
protection was
but i don't think we want that
and so then the total count which is how
many of these we're going to have
is just the dimension squared
uh
times the
um
the raised per texel
right so it's
it's
bat
and since i don't know if square will
evaluate fairly
i'll just do or like a compile time
right i'll just manually do it
like so
so that's the count and that is just how
that's how many will be in here uh and i
think what we'd rather do instead of
putting this in there we should make
that be a automatic compiler-sized thing
and then we should just like assert i
don't know if we have a ct assert
um
we do
uh we should ct assert that like these
come out correct because we want we want
this number
to always be the same as the number that
we print out and if they aren't rather
than
forcing them to be we would rather print
out an error message it's like hey by
the way
this totally didn't work uh right
so we probably want to do a thing that's
like hey uh assert that the array count
of the sample direction table
is equal to the the amount that we said
we were going to do
and that way we we rather than force it
uh we will yeah we'd make it do
make it do the thing
so
uh raise protection is here
so we have
um
square the octahedron dim i don't know
if square we should probably do it this
way because like i said i don't know if
it's that that may be
not for integers may only be for floats
i don't remember
okay
so i think that's everything
that we need to do to print out the
correct thing like to the file
right
we then just need to
think about how we actually want to
sieve these properly and you can see
like we've got some kind of a like
we
we put a bunch of directions out on this
thing
and then we sieve them
right uh into like
ones that go
you know i don't
it just doesn't seem like a very good
way to do this
i mean maybe it's the only way to do it
i don't know
but
because like it so here's how we did
this right
so we allocate some space
uh for this thing
for where we're putting
for we allocate some space for like ray
directions on a sphere we randomly
initialize them to white noise so we
start with white noise
um then we use basically like energy
repulsion like we basically just like
look
and
repulse points based on how many things
are
close to them
you know what i mean
um
and
we stop when we are within like
a range
uh
right you can see here
we try to get the
the distance
to converge to some arbitrary thing we
picked right
and that's how we produced our sampling
sphere
like i said the problem with that
is that we don't guarantee we'll get
enough uh
actual points
for any particular uh octahedron
so what i propose we do now is i pros we
don't actually modify this algorithm at
all i propose we run
this crappy one
go do a visualization of it so because
remember we were drawing the wrong thing
um
so we don't really want that right
so uh go fix the drawing of this down in
the sampling spheres drawing thingy
uh to actually draw them and colored by
texel
right
we do that
and then we
should be able to visually see that the
result is bad
and
then we can pop back to h8 sphere and
try to fix it
so if we have it all
um
if we've
go ahead and do uh redo this
loop
where we loop through the texels i guess
like this
um
i don't even know that we care so much
about
these but
um i'm gonna i'm gonna do it this way
for now so so
all right
so we loop through t y and it's light
sampling octahedron map dim
light
lighting sorry
uh octahedron map dim
uh so if we loop over
i don't know why that's indented further
that doesn't seem to make a whole lot of
sense but okay
why is that who is indenting is it this
is there something like a hanging indent
above here that's causing this to be
busted
apparently so what's the what's the
problem for code or why are you confused
there must be like something if zeroed
out up here that's like
causing some
weird
like everything is is one over from
where it should be
why why is that
anyone want to guess
it's this isn't it
okay
better
so if i loop over
these
txty values
like so
um
i should be able to
then
for each one of these loop over the
total number of rays
per texel
um
and pick out like each one
from the sample direction
the
these things come from a table
that
will have been
loaded here
um
and
we're really just going down these in
order so meaning we would start by
saying like rader equals the first one
in the table i guess we
need to look at sampling direction so
um
so sampter equals you know whatever the
the first thing in the table is
and then each time through here when we
draw a ray we want to go to the next one
um
the position of this thing
is
looks like we're just kind of hacking it
um
so we can literally just say like okay
the sample directions uh i don't
remember what the actual name for this
is it's ray d i guess
um so the ray direction we get out of
here then we draw this thing
and what i want to do is make the color
of it
um
just be something that only gets updated
uh as we go through the
texel area
so so there'd be like a color index here
and the you know what the other thing we
could do is just actually cut
we don't even really need to use the
debug colors so
what we could do is say like
this is checker
here we could make just a checker board
right where we do like um
either
white or black
i don't know if we have the ability to
turn lighting off easily
for things i don't remember how we did
that but it will make it kind of harder
to see
uh in that sense but we could
like
do these debug things i don't remember
how these debug things work so i don't
know we'll have to play with that later
but
um
the checkerboard pattern would be like
just the bottom bit
if the bottom bits of x and y are
different then
we use one color otherwise use another
you know what i mean
um
i feel like that's probably all we need
so like you know you start out txt why
they're equal if you step one in either
direction they're now not equal you step
one in the other one and now they're
equal again right so it should that
should produce like a checkerboard
pattern which is all we need to see
i think
um
so i think that produces a drawing of
the actual thing uh that we want so now
we just need to like run the actual
program
have it print out the directions and
call it a day uh unfortunately like i
said this program i don't know that this
is actually outputting the correct order
i'm not sure
um
yeah so this loop is kind of busted uh
so we probably want to fix this loop
um
to look like this
right like this wants to look like
i think
like this
um so that we loop over the txty
uh with the map
dim uh
we don't really care
about
that
so it's this is
this is the dimension right
this is the oct map dim here
so we loop over the ocmap dim
and then we've got rays per texel
uh and the total number of directions
here is
is this
oct map dim squared times the rays per
texel
um
this
is like
hard coded
so
that to me suggests that like like this
shouldn't this should be
like these are all like totally
hardcoded it looks like for some reason
um
which doesn't make a lot of sense maybe
we'll do v2s
um
or do we have a u okay
maybe we'll do v2u of ocmapdim so that
in here we basically say like look the
dimension of this thing
um
for the light atlas or whatever is just
going to be the oct map dim plus two
which is what it should be
and then instead of having that dxdy
there we're just like look we loop
through the x's we loop through the y's
uh and we have arrays raise protection
right
um
okay
so
you can actually you can even see how
this is obviously wrong like you can
even see where the bug is coming from so
we compute the total direction count
like we were doing that before we were
computing it differently but it still
was like how many of these do we want to
put out right
and then we're asking for a poisson
distribution that's the exact number now
a random distribution over the sphere
is going to on average give you
1 8 of the
rays on each texel
well not each textual 164th of the rays
on each texel if it's eight by eight
right
um
but the problem is
uh if you if you actually look at any
given texel it's gonna be off by one
like in either direction because it's
random so there's there's gonna be some
that have like one less or one more on
them and so when you then go to output
exactly 16 or something
from that square you're not gonna get 16
right that's not going to happen
you know what i'm saying
i'm hungry and i need some crunch i i
feel like i need the little i need some
little chicharrones i feel like we need
to take like a 10 second chicharron
break
uh to try and get downstairs and get
some chicharrones but that's separate
that's neither here nor there i suppose
all right anyway
um so yeah this was kind of busted and
now it's a little less busted so um but
this is still a problem so i feel like
we would have to increase the total
number of directions we ask for in the
distribution
like this total direction count needs to
be like higher because when we pull
stuff out of the thing
we gotta have more there has to be
proportionally more
uh random points than we need otherwise
it's not going to come out to 16 per
it's just not going to happen right
and so
i don't know the best way to do that
but
you know um
i also don't know how this thing knows
how many directions there would be
that's a little bit weird as well so i
feel like this is just kind of a little
broken
and i don't love it
this is fine in that you ask it to do
some number of directions and it
produces like a bundle right
um but i think we want something maybe
like storage for this that takes with it
the size
so
like
something like
uh direction builder or i don't know
direction gen you know
so that you know how many of these you
generated
uh i think you want that
you know what i'm saying
uh
so generate poisson samples here
nobody calls
we call generate poisson
distribution
but nobody calls generate poisson
samples
so let's get rid of it
focus on what we actually have
nobody calls test funk either
okay
um so when we call
uh generate poisson distribution here
maybe we give this uh like hey
[Music]
you know return us one of these
direction gen things
um
and
it looks like it doesn't care like this
displacements is just the thing
that it uses like internally
it seems
so we don't have to return that
um
what is this used
dur index equals false
what is that for
that
doesn't seem to
be a thing
like like that's not actually a thing
so it seems like this is
bogus
i guess
i don't know
um so anyway uh if we take a look at
this direction gen generate poisson
samples thing if we imagine that this
was going to return us
uh a result here uh the result
directions in fact i guess we can just
move it down here because i don't care
um the result i don't know why there is
a printf but i guess it's just because
it prints out a status
right it's like it's printing out a
status with a backslash r so this just
advances the line
um
whatever
so directions equals directions whatever
and result equals result and blah blah
blah
so
if we want to
uh
if we want to in here take the
total direction count
that was requested and save it
now we can do that and at least now
we're passing around something that
has a size because we're going to need
that uh
eventually
so
we've got that now
um and that's good and so when you do
like a generate uh poisson
lighting pattern or whatever i guess we
don't care about this one because we
don't use poisson lighting pattern
anymore right
so when we do generate octahedral
lighting pattern
like we do here
um
somehow the oct map dim doesn't have a
plus operator you're kidding me
like v2u plus v2u isn't a thing
that can't be right
can it be
have we literally never had to add two
of these together
also we do have a v
oh no that's v3s never mind
i guess we don't
i
i mean
it ain't there
so i guess we just never needed that
we've only ever added operators that we
actually use
and i guess we never used it
i ain't seeing it
um so v2u just doesn't seem to have much
any in general like there's hardly
anything here for it
um
is there even a v2u operations section
there isn't even a section for it
so i guess we want a thing here for
b2 operations
not a lot to see here but
probably something we want
right
okay
uh back to our story so the poisson
distribution will now return like a
thing that actually keeps how many there
are
right
so
this way we get uh input directions
uh we'll just call that input for now
so we generate poisson distribution with
the total direction count
uh and this is like
uh the total direction count would be
saved in here
you know what i'm saying
i feel like that's better
and we probably have
sort of like
a
a uh
outputter account
and an input dirt count and they're
different because of that scaling
difference that i said like we know that
we have to generate more a denser
covering if we want to be able to
extract
points from it
so the input direction count is going to
kind of be like this
times
some extra
you know what i mean
like
um
i don't really know
how to sensibly
figure that out but it's gonna have to
be like oh you generate 20 extra or
something right it's a 20 denser
distribution
or something right
so it'd be like
hey uh yeah take the output count
and
you know we're gonna multiply it by some
scaling factor that we we just randomly
have to pick
um and then we ask for that number
right
and the output direction count
uh is
is actually going to be a different
thing right
i wonder if we
direction
array let's call this direction array
so that way like we can be a little bit
a little bit better here where we say
like okay we get an input direction
array back
um from generating the samples
and
we can allocate one of these
we could also have like a thing that
allocates these for us so that we don't
have to have all these mallocs around
like we could do this
where we just say hey how many of those
did you want right
and we don't really have to care about
this code at all because it's just some
offline tool we run it can be as crappy
as you want but i'm just trying to make
it easy to read and simple right
uh because we have to debug it so i
don't want it to be like it can be
somewhat horrible but i don't want it to
be like excruciatingly horrible right
um
so okay we can allocate a direction
array uh and so now we can sort of do
something more like this where we say
okay the result here
gets allocated up at the front
where we say okay
the result is allocator array of the
total count
there's we can also use this to get the
other thing which is like
displacements um
and
we could also make these be e
right
just simplify that a little bit
like the elements of it so it's just
like a little bit cleaner
not cleaner simpler to read
so we allocate a direction array
for each of these the results and the
displacements
um
now that gets handled automatically then
we just have to change this to like in
fact we could even rename this
directions then it's even simpler so
it's just directions dot e
is the direction itself
um and then the displacements would oops
displacements will also be e
but otherwise the code remains the same
okay
so that's pretty easy and then these for
the outputs would do the exact same
thing so the direction array for the
output uh would also say hey i need
um
an
allocary
like so
and off we go
so
that's the basics of what we're doing um
this here
is
not useful this is so raise protection
goes on here
um
we've
have it all
so we have our tx already set up and our
ray index also
uh but now we've got to actually write
this internal
bit to work properly
we also need to return the output
here
so
and then we have to look at how this
thing actually works so
all we're doing here is searching like
in an n squared slow way
this is just searching to find
um
in the inputs right
it's like we search over the inputs by
the way i need to fix that like you
can't see the semicolon with the cursor
the way it is in for coda right now
that cursor probably needs to be
a little bit different i have to
remember to try to fix that
um it's like too fat you can't actually
see what the thing is underneath it
um anyway uh so input directions
just called input right yeah
so we're looking over the inputs to find
one that is pointing in the direction we
actually needed to assuming that we find
it we
assign it to like a value that we know
marks it as having been used so we won't
use it again
and then
we output it as one for this thing
right
we then probably want to make this
really harsh like we probably want to
just like
print an error if we don't find one
so so basically like
if
like
it'd be more like this
if we find one great if we don't we're
in trouble so like if we don't find one
we like print out an error like that
this is really bad
like for this texel we could not find
um
enough
like we we just ran out
right
and we just want that to be an error
because like basically like we need to
go fix the code like it just it's not
good enough at that point right and we
need to we need to fix it
um all right so then we have
our direction array
uh that we get back from this
and
uh the things that we're now reading are
we have the octahedron dimension that's
correct
um
and we have the rays per texel
right
so
this is really octahedron side
uh and so the v2u for the octahedron dim
um is going to be the
side like twice because we're only doing
square right now although we you know
can change that but at the moment we
don't have any plans to
and the raise for texel is just directly
in
um i don't know why these are out of
order
so you'd think you'd write it like that
like how many rays how many things maybe
you want it more like that um
so
let's do it this way
i don't know uh
octahedron texel
there needs to be a better word for when
you have a square texture
you're saying one of them
um
something like that it's really really
cumbersome
but um
oh well uh and then here we have raise
for texal
right
so
and then the destination file of course
which is a separate issue
um so we get the octahedron side we get
the rays per texel
and we pass those in
uh and then later when we do outper
output sphere inl
uh we just pass the same things again so
actually it's not a huge count sorry
it's ox dim
so we'd pass the same thing
so i think that's okay
uh
and then the output sphere thing just
needs to change slightly
right to be a little bit different
this is going to be one of them arrays
right
so this is
a direction array
we output
the
sample direction thing we output the map
dim
the rays for texel
and this is going to be like a only one
of them at the moment because we don't
support
rectangular
output
even though we would properly handle it
we just don't bother i guess
um
we then have this thing here do exactly
what you would think uh the total
direction account goes away because i
now pass that through properly like i
wanted to before
um and
off we go
okay
so now i think we've got it all we've
we've have it all
and i think the whole process should now
work barring bugs which there are always
are
but i think we're more or less good
right like that should output the thing
and
i don't i don't think we'd need to do
anything else i mean we have the kind of
bs constant of 0.2
or 1.2 i should say
but you know
what can you do
so uh if we've
built it
um
we can now run the h8 sphere
program
and we can say that it's like eight
uh and that the raise per texel is
16 which i think is roughly what we were
targeting
uh and then the destination inl is like
i don't remember it's like sphere
samples or
hh lighting or i don't even remember
what the heck it's called
um
handmade sampling spheres
handmade
sampling spheres
and so let's like
kill this
buffer
let's run this program
and
and who knows what it's going to do i
certainly don't
um
and
i think when this gets below 2-5 if it
ever gets below two five it might not
no it did
um
so you can see here like it it
definitely has a problem it can't find
enough texels
right
um
which may be due to bugs i'm not sure
um but anyway
that's the program running we have to go
make it work better than it does
but
if we now
look at the sampling spheres what we
should see
is because we're flooding the if we
didn't find one
then
output zero we can now much more easily
see
who
was able to fill
their uh quota like and who wasn't
right
now we also should be able to uh
like our lighting will be totally borked
because it's reading the table wrong now
oh what's this this is good our this
this is saying that it's not
enough
things right oh no it's not it's just
saying that it
it's missing
a
parentheses before semicolon is that the
total light did i print this out wrong
this number
oh yeah like
why is that word wrapping
i guess because this is an inl file
but anyway you can see it's missing
the closing paren
so
um okay so now we can change our stuff
to read from this properly and draw it
but it's going to be wrong um so that's
fine also i don't know what this that
says there's a missing
a pound if
that's hanging here apparently
so i don't know what that's about
but
did we accidentally
that all looks right
that looks right
i will say i don't quite understand what
that if is for so uh you know what we
this is what happened
we forgot to remove this when we
commented this out right so that one it
shouldn't be there anymore
that was the only weirdness
okay so before we do anything else let's
go back to h8 sphere and put in the
missing
closing paren because the next time we
run this program it's going to output a
bogus file if we don't do that um so
then we can go through here and fix this
stuff so
uh the ray weight here is now just
always going to be we know that it's the
the uh raise per texel because that's
that's always going to be
the number that the the ratio that we
want to use because we're always going
to be summing
over that many right
um when we loop through here we now know
also that this is not really ray index
so this is
like
there's two things now there's a ray
index and a texel index and right now
ray index is actually also texal index
so if you at least i think and that's
wrong so we don't want that i also don't
think we need to keep this around like
we're not going to be doing it through
that
um
so uh
the transfer pps pulling out of this ray
index here that is actually not correct
if that makes sense
so we need to do a slight modification
here which is to say that the transfer
pps value there's really going to be a
different way that this works so the way
that this will actually work is more
like this we will have on the outside
where we're looping over the actual like
um
the actual texels one at a time
and by the way we need to make sure that
this is actually looped this way yeah it
is
um
what we need to do here is say the
actual that actually transfer pps is
going to be
summed
for by an accumulator so whichever one
we're on right now
we're going to have a transfer pps
accumulator which is just one
vector that we sum into over and over
for each ray and then the texel index
that we are actually advancing across
that is going to pick out which transfer
pps value we're actually targeting
so these right here are going to be
transfer pps accum
like so
and you can see we already have a to do
here to fix this because this is not
really necessary to do it this way right
we could make that better
so when we do that accumulation
we actually want to have both of those
and so now we've got two things we've
got the ray index as it moves through
the table
and we have the uh texel index as it
moves across
right
so this right here is texal index is
less than um
this value the octahedral map dim
so we're stepping across those
um and while we're in here we have this
transfer pps a cube value
and that's going to be the thing that's
actually zero this doesn't have to get
initialized because it will get written
each one of them will get written to
because we're going across this eight
here right
like so in fact you could actually just
say this is array count
of transfer pps
like that
so we're stepping across um
each one of the tr each one of the
texels that we're going to have to write
we're accumulating across all of the
rays
that we're going to do and that's going
to be in here and that's going to be
over the rays per texel
value like so
um and that raised for texel value i can
probably make this a little bit easier
to read by doing that um the raise
protects the value
uh we're just looping over these picking
out different directions to cast out of
the same texel
um and then when we sum it in at the end
like we sum it in right here
so we we just we we like accumulate
accumulate accumulate on the same texel
write it out once
to that texel
then at the very end we blend that into
the texture map here after we've done
all eight we load them up and blend them
in one wide operation
so now we just need to be able to step
the table properly
and stepping the table properly just
requires us being on the correct row
so when we look at this like direction
offset this whole nonsense we don't
really need any of this anymore um so
really all we're doing is setting this
once
there's like basically like a
uh
how should i put this
um
we'd be setting this once and it would
just advance each time um
so
[Music]
the walk table offset here
um
i would say probably all we really need
to do is
at the outset
just set the sample
dir to the correct thing here
each time through we just do the sample
dir ray d and the sample dir
um walk table offset we load those up
and then at the end
we just each time through the loop uh we
increment the sample direction
probably
because there's so much float work going
on in here we probably can just spare
the extra add and then you don't have to
do any kind of addressing so it seems
like that's probably the right thing to
do is to just step it
um
that'd be my guess
so at that point we're left with um
we no longer have octahedral
indexes we just have like
a
texel index
and
ray index right
so
um
for debug sake the debug pic value
it's really just txty and ray
so
it would be
it would be texil index
is the thing that equals debug pick tx
oops
like so
and array index would be debug pick ray
index
um and again like at this point it
becomes kind of weird that we don't just
do the while loop in here as well
because there isn't really any reason
not to do that
um so you probably like this
should probably be renamed instead of
taxel index it should just be tx because
now it actually is tx
um
and
eventually we should just make that loop
over ty as well
one would assume
you know what i'm saying
so for sample directions really this
part just needs to
be set to the correct place in the table
and in order to do that we would need to
know what row we were on
uh so this sy right is the is the thing
that's telling us that
so it's again kind of annoying it may
make more sense again to just like
push that in
like
to just start at the root of the sample
table and just go through the whole
thing by having the ty loop here
it's unclear why we wouldn't do that so
i might just do that um
because you can see here now there's
just this extra nonsense for no reason
right like like it's unclear why we
don't just have
um
it do the entire
chunk at the same time like why does
this happen we don't know
so it seems like we probably would want
to just like
take this loop
and move it out so grid raycast rather
than passing an sy
just passes the light probe p the spec
atlas uh the spec texel a just gets
compute would get computed
uh directly in the thing what about tile
that the tile i suppose
we would need to pass in now right
so
instead of spectexel a you would just
pass the tile
um and then the rest of the stuff is
exactly as it is
so
this loop would come
out
ingrid raycast
and we would take
this part here and make this be the ty
loop
right and
the cast initiated part
is really just a statistics gathering
thing for us so we know
what this is
uh it's just gonna be the total it like
we do them all
so it's literally it's literally the
entire table
it's it's literally
total light sample direction count
right
so then we do
um
[Music]
the sample direction just starts at the
beginning of the table
we walk the table
uh pulling out the
the correct tile each time
and that's
our loop
so i think that's basically what we're
looking at here um
the
that's there's no such thing as sy
anymore it's just t y
um
and the tile is going to come in
as inst up here instead of sy
right we're not passing that anymore
and instead of spectacle we're passing
the tile
i don't remember what that is
it's some kind of tile thing
or not
so what is that value
we just saw it what is the name of the
type light atlas texl oh it's so it's
just light atlas texl tile
i guess
um
i don't know what that was for we can
put it back in if we need it someday
um so
yeah
this is tx
and the spectacle is now
um not a it's just
spectacular
the
[Music]
the sy needs to go away
and
this ray index needs to be
clamped
to
i guess i don't know what atlas index
means here
atlas index is just the global
uh enumerator i guess
so uh yeah so basically like
this is kind of just not
necessary anymore this can actually just
be moved out like we don't have to call
this again
right
we can just call
uh solution debug
here
like so
meaning if we're debugging then this
just happens
and i don't even know that we need to do
that
because this stuff can now happen
inside the old version
so
like we can just pass down
we can just prep and pass down a thing
that checks the atlas and off we go
i think
so in grid raycast here
where we pass this debug pick
um
debug pick enabled
would just be
uh we would just expand the check
in
where did you go
here you are
we would just expand the check here to
check against the t y value as well
and
so then we just do if the atlas index is
equal up here
so this entire thing would just be like
we could we could keep basically exactly
this
um get rid of the sting that calls it uh
that calls um
grid raycast twice
and just pass
true or false based you know that the
solution debug pick
we just pass it if we happen to be
the correct value so debug ray pick
pick equals nothing
if we're equal then it equals the debug
pick
right so that will pass down
so that leaves it off
in the case where it's not the
particular atlas and on in the case
where it is
the ray index has to be clamped now
to
whatever we called this value so
the per texel
and now i think we're good
so a lot of reorganization but getting
closer to a reasonable thing
okay so that should now
i guess we should like debug crashes
right because we're going to be like
wrong we're like stepping too far along
something or who knows what right
um so the first thing we want to do is
like debug crashes in what we just did
because again this is really like
aggressively optimize code so we've got
a lot of like you know
hand tuned stuff that is
is going to have a lot of like
fragility to it right
because this is like the most heavily
optimized thing we have in the entire
system by far
um
so that looks like a legit
that's not an unaligned that's not on
the line that's actually just off which
is good it's easier um
so
it looks like we're stepping too
much
here there's probably like one of the
things on the interior is doing like a
uh
is is
counting on something having been set up
and walking through it only once
although that's
just looking up into the table
so that's like a problem with the walk
table
probably
let's take a quick look
at walk table
hmm
solution
light sampling
walk table quadrant index
starts in a reasonable place
uh
sampleder
walktable well actually just show me the
whole thing
oh
right
yeah
hmm
so a zero zero zero will make it so that
it's yeah like
i mean we sh this should still not crash
it should be we should make it so that
this works fine but when it gets to
something that's zero zero zero it will
never step through the table
so
i don't know what we want to do about
that
um
maybe just special case it in the walk
table build
so like
like if we can
i'm trying to think of like how you
would build these tables so that that
would still work
so when we compute the walk table right
you can see what would happen here is it
never really would hit
uh the padded max cost per
ray um
you still would i mean shouldn't you
march
i i like i guess the problem would be
maybe if t terminate is picked
incorrectly
which it obviously is and how is t
terminate set in the case where it was
going to be zero like that
t terminate is zero
t terminate
gets updated by t best
and so in v the problem here is that nv
ray d
right
envy ray d is
is wrong
so we probably just need to like
actually do a safe divide here
because if all of these are imph
because they're all zero so nobody like
they will all be imp and nobody will be
picked
it will be forced to pick a random one
effectively
um if it's not random it's predictable
it will pick you know the last the first
one i guess right
but that will be inf
so we probably want to do something like
comparing it and making sure that if t
terminate
is
too high
if it's in you know then it gets clamped
something like that because
my recollection is it needs to sample at
the terminator and so the problem is
that if you never leave the square if
you have no way of ever knowing where it
should end up
then what's going to happen is that t
terminate value is going to be infant
here
and
you can see when it ends the probe
sample piece single
is then going to be
a completely out of bounds value
when we then do the sample that's what's
going to have
this texal pointer because the base
offset that we compute right
is going to be out in the middle of
nowhere and it's going to load a
completely bogus value so it's a very
predictable error
the problem is like what do we set it to
it should never happen
so
i
we only care about it while we're doing
this debugging process of making sure
the table doesn't have zeros in it but
we want to be able to run while that's
doing that so i think we just want to
clamp it
like look you know clamp this between
you know
zero
um
and
some
large value right i don't know what well
you know maybe we just want to do like
if it's inf
do we have an ism
you know like some really large
this is terrible
um
it can be used
but if it's not um if it's this if it's
a bogus value
um we probably want to add an is in
for for this very purpose um
because we we we do have a case where
that is what we need to know what is
this what is complaining about
fatal error
why can it not open handmade hero
why are you not
stop
stop debugging
it cannot stop
apparently
folks debugging cannot be stopped
why can't it be stopped we do not know
can we be billed
now yes
um what version of remedy am i using i
may have to update
three five oh yeah um i should probably
update that at some point uh because
that's
it's a bit out
of date right like
the uh
the actual current version is like
three six three and i'm on three five so
we're pretty
we're gonna
have to remember to do that we're like
way
way out of date
okay
um
so we need to fix that bug uh so that
this doesn't happen on load on like out
of bounds loads basically
um and so we have to figure out like how
we're gonna make that happen so now we
fix the t terminate to be zero uh which
is good i think
um but we're still having like a let's
look at what the
so when we compute the diffuse atlas
um
base offset here
i mean no
like just not an acceptable value in
case anyone was wondering
how did this happen
if it's zero how would we does this also
use an inverse
it may be that like there's no way to
run zeros through this thing because
it's you know simply not built to have
rays that don't march right race
they're expected to be normal
right
so yeah i'm not sure
why we're getting that but you know
broadcast
one norm
one over one norm for iuv
yep so this uses an inverse as well so
so i think basically like i don't think
there's any way to
um
i don't think there's any way to shove
zeroes through this thing unfortunately
because everybody expects you to be able
to
un do the rate the ray is supposed to be
a normal
you know what i mean
um
so i guess we can't do that
so i guess um
if we
want to do something like this we have
to output something that is at least a
valid ray direction and we can still
make it be like 0 0 1 so it's very
obvious that it's wrong and of course we
also print out the values so but i guess
we're going to have to just do
cast straight up
if you don't know where to go right
because we really can't like none of
this code it all assumes that because
they're coming from a table they all
have to be valid you know
normal
they can't
be garbage right
so let's try remaking our sampling
spheres again
um
you know what this is going to run
really slowly because we're running it
in debug
although i did want to go get
some snacks so
there is that i wonder if that's like we
should run it in debug mode so it's slow
and then i run and get snacks
okay
so in theory
if i build now
um
we should not have those so we shouldn't
get that particular bug we may have a
different bug but we shouldn't get that
one
um
can i revert this buffer
no
so here we are and you can see now that
like our zeros have been replaced with
ones in the z column for bad for like
failed
um
outputs and we compile just fine
uh now we can go see what happens uh
when we actually run
all right so actually that's better than
i would have expected so we're in good
shape
um i would like to know how to properly
draw this thing like i
why our debug lines
are are
i don't know why our debug lines
are like not lit properly like you can
sell like this is sort of wrong
at least i think it is maybe i'm i'm
incorrect about that but it looks like
the fact that
these are
in the wrong place means they're not
getting drawn in white and black as they
should be
i'm not totally sure about that though
that could be incorrect
so
let me take a
look so for example when we draw
diagrams
um
how does this stuff work
is there anything that says what makes
things emissive i don't know
so it looks like enable lighting
is
like is actually still on for things
like diagrams so
i don't know it might be that there is
no way to do that like i haven't really
looked to see if that's something we we
really do
um
but
so i'm not sure but i'm gonna go into
the
lighting drawing thing and just see what
happens
if we don't move these up as high
yeah so it's just it's just like
lighting like they they get lit and even
though i i don't really want them to be
we don't have a super good way of
avoiding that so you can see the
octahedral map pattern here um and
unfortunately there's like too much
other crap in the way
but you can see it
and you can also see like
where the stuff is missing
right you can see the gaps
and those gaps are almost certainly the
places where it you know couldn't find
um
values that fell within the texel
because they happen to be like slightly
on the wrong side like towards one of
the other
tiers or something
right presumably that's what's happening
although we don't really know
but it's still a reasonable sampling
streak it's not horrible at the moment
it's just not good
you know what i mean
um okay so now we have to figure out
what the heck is going on of course
so there is that
so we're not out of the woods yet uh but
we're getting closer slowly
uh because we're obviously still not
some summing these things properly uh
but at least now we're not doing
completely ridiculous stuff like we were
before where we were crashing because
we're sampling out of bounds
so uh if we now look and see what's
going on here i i guess we have some
questions to ask ourselves about
whether or not we're stepping through
the texels properly and all that kind of
good stuff
um when we
work on rows here we create this
accumulator
um and basically we're going to be uh
that ray the weight that we add for each
ray right is going to be based on
um
the inverse of however many rays we cast
for every texel
uh when we step through these
i feel like this should just work like i
don't feel like we should have to do
anything special here
um and after we sample
um right we just
we're just summing the the accumulator
over the rays
ah
that is a problem
so it's not a summation there it's just
setting it equal is all that's happening
so
there we go
um
so now at least we're stably
we are stably evaluating the lighting
we're evaluating it in the correct order
um
and we now just have to figure out like
why we're getting
first of all we have to fix the holes in
the sampling sphere which you can see
here again
so we want to try and fix that so we're
not
sampling down all the time and then we
have two more problems one is we're
getting that light flooding and we don't
really know where that's coming from
uh but the other problem we have is also
that uh
there's when we move
there's some weird like on movement we
get
some dimming artifact i have no idea
where that's coming from
doesn't
stand to reason that should be happening
so i think that's just a bug
uh that that is happening
with how we're accumulating or something
something bad is happening there
right
um like it's like it's being cleared or
something which is totally wrong
but we're pretty close and if you look
at sort of like if you imagine you got
rid of that dimming effect
this would be pretty stable pretty good
lighting right it's it's pretty close
it's not that far from what we actually
want so we have some weird things we've
got like the the green
bleed um we've got the the weird dimming
as we move
but we're pretty close to good and we're
we're very respectable frame rate wise
even with all the debug stuff on we're
we're well above 30. so i think we're
probably uh able to do this at 60fps as
well right i think we'll probably be
able to
to um
button this down
and this is on an old machine too right
like this is not on a new machine
okay so
first questions first how do we fix our
sphere to not have this problem with
being unable to find stuff do we just
need to make it denser
do we need to change the way we're doing
this like maybe this is just a bad way
to do it unfortunately um are we picking
wrong i don't know
so octahedral from unit vector
so this will be correctly using the plus
one offsets
that all seems fine
and
so i don't know is like 20 like like
let's let's check by using a massively
over sampled sphere
so this is twice as sampled right
and i guess we might say
this this might not converge though
because this is an arbitrary this value
doesn't mean anything
um it probably needs to be scaled like
by the total direction count
uh in some way
so like you know it would have to be
increased or decreased correctly
um
so like this value probably needs to be
lower at that point right this needs to
be like something else and i don't know
for 2x we should probably try to figure
that out
what that should realistically be if
we're gonna use this repulsion but you
know that might also be an argument like
i said for like we need to do something
that's not repulsion like repulsion is
just too sloppy
it's not looking good
well we'll leave it at that difference
for now
that's just the difference between the
maximum distance and the minimum
distance so it's the variance on the
sphere so you know in some sense
it's not entirely implausible where did
my command go
i don't know what happened there
it's not entirely implausible that you
could continue to use it that way but
yeah
um
so 8
handmade
sampling spheres
um so we'll see if we massively over
sample the sphere
will that like let it pick enough
for each texel if it doesn't that
suggests maybe we've got a bug where
it's actually not picking properly
because with twice as many you'd think
there would be plenty in any given
section of the octahedron to get the
number that was necessary right
and this doesn't really look all that
much different right
so it kind of feels like it's just
broken
like
you know what i mean and it's it's it's
really weird that that would be the case
so i think like this may just be broken
like this is not working properly or
something
because if the total direction count um
if the total direction count that you
ask for
is
twice as many as you need
then how would you not and they're like
point repulsed so they're relatively
well distributed
how would you not get enough
like something is really off about that
but i don't know what it is is it
because our get octahedral offset
routine is busted or something
like you can see how this is working
it's stepping through the tx and tys
and then it is for every
ray that it needs to output
it does raise per texel of those for
that tx and t y by just looping through
like literally n squared just looping
through
looking for something that matches
and it just doesn't make any sense
that you wouldn't have
enough in in it like how would that be
possible i i'm trying to think if
there's an error in my reasoning but
it doesn't feel like you could possibly
have
so few
on the sphere at that point
um
that you couldn't sieve them
it just doesn't stand to reason that
that seems like
obviously has to be wrong
so
[Music]
now that's what it did look like
and honestly it really doesn't even look
different
despite asking for twice as many points
is there something like that i'm missing
here
like we call generate price on
distribution
with input duracount
so like
hmm
what am i missing
i'm definitely missing something
i feel like we're going to need a snack
for this
we definitely want to solve this problem
and we need a snack for this so i'm
going to call break time
and we're going to get a snack
and then we're going to
check it again we're going to figure it
out
that's my official call everyone takes
snack break
do it
i'll be back in a moment
[Music]
foreign
bye
[Music]
so
[Applause]
[Music]
do
oh
uh
[Music]
bye
all right
so
we have two choices here really
one is we just abandon the scheme a
priori
and say look we're gonna generate them
in a different way that doesn't involve
picking the other is we debug the
picking because it must be broken
unless somehow
generating twice as many points in the
sphere still somehow doesn't have enough
on each octahedral point
which doesn't seem to make sense
to me
16 was raised for texel
so we're generating 32
times 64.
yeah we generate 32 choices
per texel
and then when we go to look for 16 of
them we find that there supposedly
aren't 16
in some of the texels
right
supposedly
that's what we are told
and if we look
at the inl
you can see that it's like very specific
like it's not like everybody is missing
one or two
it's like there's very specific holes
like a giant hole in one of the things
and then another one hat is completely
full
which makes me think there's some kind
of bug
either in the repulsion so that it's
like repelling things more at that point
because of some way that we wrote it
or something else
i'm not sure
but
we should probably try to
debug the octahedral map thing a little
bit
because i don't know maybe that routine
is kind of busted
as well look we don't know
if that routine is right
it may be totally wrong
you know what i'm saying
oh and if you wanna know the indexes
here's the indexes like zero zero
like
it's right on the edge right so zeros
threes fours fives sevens the
the middle numbers like two two that
sort of thing never shows up here
right
um
so it seems like maybe the um to me that
it's possible that the thing that's
doing the classifying is classifying
wrong
maybe
i don't know there is one other
possibility
which is that
look
an octahedron
by definition warps a sphere
in the place
where it is warped it will be hard for
that texel to find anything right
because it's covering less area of the
sphere you know what i mean
so
you know i could believe it
um
which is why also i'm wondering like
okay
what's next uh cheat your owns
not enough i should have gotten more
i need like two bowls of chicharrons is
what i really need in life
the more bowls of chicharrons you have
the better your life is
i mean i think that's just everyone
knows that
we don't need to labor the point
okay so
i guess what i would say here is i do
think we may have to change the way this
is working
so i might not bother debugging this
part because
when i think about the fact that the
octahedral map is by definition a warp
of the sphere
then to me that suggests that i am going
to have like i'm not going to get a
choice i'm going to have to
distribute points in the actual texels
and make them be evenly distributed like
in textile space because otherwise
you can't evenly distribute things in
sphere space or like
you're like that's not going to work
because the octane doesn't pull evenly
from those
so it kind of does feel like i i need to
do something slightly different here um
and i don't know exactly what that thing
should be but maybe that what that
should be is we try to do more blue
noise on like inside the texel
but as far as like textile to texel we
don't try to evenly distribute those
across the sphere because
like it wouldn't help if we did
or we try to do something else where we
just like seed things
um
okay here's the thought here's a thought
here's a thought
what if we
[Music]
here's my proposal you ready for this
hold on to your mankas
what if we
seed
the number of rays per texel that we
want using white noise
inside each texel
so we start with something that is white
noise
with 16 rays
coming out of each texel face on the
sphere
we then
run
the distributor
but
we refuse to let
any texel
leave
the octant that it is in
what do you think
anyone
anyone want to weigh in on that
so we we start with 64x6 you know 64 8x8
so 64 texels
octahedron we generate white noise
shooting out of those texels
we then run the sphere repulsion
but we don't let texel we don't let any
rays leave the texels that they're in so
there's always exactly 16 per texel
but they can repulse to try and get
themselves spread more evenly apart
right
won't you get clamping on the edges
well
i mean
yeah
you can't move past the edge but the
point is other texels should in theory
other samples that are in the
neighboring texel should in theory push
you
still right
now the fact that it's a warped space
you know
is a problem but
i think we should go do something like
that though because we can start by just
doing 16 rays uh randomly generated
white noise out each texel and that's
some place to start anyway
and then the repulsion just has to try
and improve that slightly right like
we could just use the white noise
directly but it's not the best sampling
pattern because it's going to be a
little clumpy
so we could just look at it that way
so maybe let's start with that
um
because we can start by using the white
noise directly without actually having
any repulsion and then we can
turn on the repulsion and work on that
separately so let's suppose we uh
basically nerf the propuls the repulsion
part
right
um and we're just going to seed the
directions um
out of the texel
so we use the like octahedral
to
offset something thingy right
um
so
this unit vector from octahedral
[Music]
will
give us
a sampling
so the oxy coefficient is going to be
like one over the value right so so
as long as we
put these into uv space basically
unit vector from octahedral
from octahedral should give us
everything we want
right
um
yeah
so i think
that would do it
because that's a zero to one value
right
um
so let's let's see what happens
let's see what happens i'm going to call
unit vector from octahedral so so inside
hh sphere what we're actually going to
do is not this we're going to seed these
differently right
so in this place points on the sphere
poorly thing and we're going to change
this to place points on the sphere
um
randomly
per or not 16. uh
raise per texel randomly
uh per texel
so uh when we call this we would no
longer be able to tell it how many we
wanted we would have to specifically say
like what's the oct dim
um and how many rays per texel we have
we would then have yet another of the
exact same structure of loop like
everything basically just looks like
this in these routines right
so we basically just go through and we
say all right um the total direction
count is now
uh as it was before it's always going to
be
um
octave x times octave y times rays per
texel
uh and then we're going to seed them
by
uh doing this nonsense
uh and maybe i'll call this seed der
index just so it's not confused with any
variables below that we might use
um we're going to call unit vector from
octahedral and we need to basically have
this direction that comes back
um
we
when we do generate octahedral lighting
pattern this now no longer has to happen
so the
things that come back from generate
poisson distribution are just going to
be correct there's no actual work that
needs to be done so this pick would go
away
and you would just call
generate poisson distribution right
so in here we just say generate poisson
distribution
um and
it would just give you back the actual
answer right
so
what we do need to do here though is
generate random unilaterals that would
give us the correct offset so basically
like the v2
um this is like the the uv coordinate
right we would generate white noise
by uh
you know generating a unit vector from
a portion inside the text the texture
that represents one texel the specific
ty tx texel here
so we would essentially do like there's
there's going to be like a u
like a u span like how big is is a um or
like
text dim basically or like a uv dim i
don't know how you want to say that i'm
not sure what a good name is for it
but it would be
a uv dim
times a unilateral so we're going to go
like some
distance like you know
uh
some random distance along the the uv
dimension
um
like so and uh
the so the uv dim is like the oct map
dim one over the octa-map dim right so
it would be like tx plus
uh some random unilateral
so we start at like
whichever texel we're on
we add some
fractional value to it and we multiply
that by whatever the uv reciprocal is or
like you know i don't know uh
in oct
jim something like that
that seems about right
does that seem reasonable
uh so
we would have
a inv octam which is like one over the
octam
uh and that way like it steps through
correctly and uh yeah is that just is
that it
oops
um and then we just like write those out
uh in order
um
so is there really no inverse operator
there i guess there isn't that's fine
uh and so maybe that's right we don't
know
uh so let's try hh sphere
we disabled the rest of it right yeah
so maybe that's right we don't really
know um but we can
look at what it made
and see how bad it is right
so
you know they at least look
semi-coherent so it's not entirely
fictional what's been written here but
you know we have no way of knowing if
it's if it's really correct um
right
so
let's take a look if we now uh com
recompile we'll be compiling with those
new values we can at least look at them
in
um
on the drawing
like and see what we have
okay so something weird is happening
we're only getting
one
like we're not actually moving all the
way around did i did i mess up my for
loop there
oh are these uvs actually is that is it
not actually uv
is it actually positive negative
okay so actually it's negative one to
one
right
um so that's why we're not getting yeah
so it's actually negative one to one
these are so
the uh
the division of that well
so does that mean it's like
negative four
like negative one is the zeroth texel
and one
yeah i don't really know
so
i guess that's fine that's pretty easy
to to fix if that actually is all it is
it would just be
you know two times
uh the value and then you bias it back
by one right
um
so that's not really
a problem if that's all it was i'm not
sure though because it's been a while
since we worked with these octahedral
maps
so i don't really remember oops i have
to actually run this again
all right
um so there's our sphere
right
and you know it's kinda sucky like it's
clumpy
exactly as you'd expect
but it's a sphere
and
you know
and it's a sphere i don't know what else
to say
um
the copying artifact thing is still
definitely there so we should like
totally unrelated to it it seems that's
just like stable
um and the green bleed is there so those
are separate bugs presumably
i think we're getting closer
so let's try now to
uh like
if we did want some repulsion here
i'm trying to think of like how we would
actually do this so
[Music]
so if we were doing some repulsion
i'm assuming what we would mostly do is
just say if the displacement would take
you
would change your texel index
then you can't do it
probably something like that i don't
actually know
uh look i'm not sure how plausible that
is it's an actual algorithm right
you
i might try it just because why not
so effectively what that would look like
is when you have
one of these so you're calling
unit vector from octahedral
uh we would just call octahedral from
unit vector
and then
clamp
right uh or
quantize
um
we could also just call get octhesial
offset which already does
that quantize
so
maybe we just do that so in here we say
all right we turn the repulsion back on
we go into the update step which is this
i think
and where we would update the direction
which is here we only update the
direction
uh if it would stay in the same quadrant
right
so we basically say like
if the octahedral uh if they're not
or if they if they are equal
we can take the step otherwise we can't
so if get octahedral offset for
the
direction that it was and the new
direction are not the same
um
and the octim coefficient
is whatever the light atlas would have
said that it was
so i think that would just require us
doing this
it has the padding around the border
right which is kind of annoying but
that's just how
that's just how computers have to work
i'm afraid
um
so the atlas has the octim coefficient
in it and so we can in theory just make
it so that you can't push it in a way
that would upset that particular apple
cart
right
and i think that's all we need there
so
uh
[Music]
we have these for other things but not
this particular one
so i think that would work although it's
you know i don't really know that's kind
of clumsy i don't know that we have any
reason to believe that such a a
particular repulsion thing like this
would actually work
in this regard uh this criteria probably
won't be correct either
so it's a bit dicey but you know
and you can see like it quickly locks up
not being able to really displace
anybody
it looks like
so i'm not sure where to end this it
looks like
the difference here is quite substantial
right like like it's like
that's how far it got
which is not far
so
again it and the problem is since the
thing is warped you can't really compare
i guess you could compare distances in
uv space
but like
probably not good
so i don't know not sure how useful this
really would be
like again it's like not horrible but
it's definitely not like good
so like it might make more sense to try
and do this like on the uv map and let
the sphere be warped as a result i mean
it's not as good because you're trying
to sample in the sphere space but i
don't know
i'm not really sure what else to do this
isn't my area of expertise so i don't
really have a lot to draw on here like
sampling is not my strong suit so i
don't really have much to say
um
about like how that should
be structured right
um
but either way like let's say that
that's good enough for now and look at
some of the other bugs because really
this is probably not our problem at the
moment like the fact that this sphere is
not great
is not what's causing our more severe
artifacts so we can probably afford to
start looking at those now
since we know that the tables are at
least not completely messed up at this
point
um
if that makes sense so you know we've
got like our ray
cast now that we had um from before here
and
these should now be more sane
and you know the i mean the raycasts
themselves look fine
right
i mean it looks like it's actually
correct and like i don't see
you know i mean i i just don't see a lot
of evidence of bugginess going on there
that should be minus one
and it's not
that's gonna bug me so i'm gonna fix it
even though it doesn't really matter
um
so yeah so i guess like our next
question is like where are we getting
this weird green blur from
um that's probably the hardest one to
solve unfortunately because it's going
to be very weird to try and
determine what the heck that's coming
from i suppose
um
but the only other one we really have
now is that dimming
that happens when you move so the the
light leakage here seems like probably
the most important thing to look at
um
because like where is that coming from
i guess one question i have is are we
doing more adding than we should be able
to
are we adding more frequently than we
should be able to and that i don't
actually know
it's just a linear blend though so
that's not true so i don't think we're
at risk of of doing too much addition
because we sum by the inverse like
the
the ray weight here
is correct in that it prevents you from
summing up more than what you started
with right
um so that seems fine and the transfer
pps values are blended right they're
they're
one minus
that they're
lerped
together so you're not adding any energy
there
um
so i don't know how we're getting this
sort of
i don't know how we're getting this
energy bleed
hmm
um i'm curious like
it's definitely just like a very clear
energy bleed like it's like you can see
it happen right like in fact like i
don't know if i can
turn off the scaling there
um
the light map
debug buffer
so
let's take a look at what we're putting
in there because i think the light map
debug buffer basically gets like some
garbage values put in it yeah you can
see here for like filtering out like
looking at particular textures
so we could definitely change these
values to something else to look at um
i mean it seems like we probably just
want to do this so if we want to take
the uv min
and the uv max and just set these equal
to like zero and one
would that just show us the whole map
uh maybe i'll look at slightly less of
it just to see
oops
wait shouldn't that have that should
have done
[Music]
uh i guess it's just it's really that
tiny i guess
that that looked counterintuitive to me
what i just saw but i guess i'm wrong
like it looks like the stretching like
in
i don't get it
oh is that because we currently stack in
z only yeah okay that's probably because
these are stacked oddly
which is probably also something we
would want to fix eventually
now that i think about it
because they're only stacked too high
which don't make a whole lot of sense
you know
um
stacking them too high is kind of dumb
like they probably should be
uh
you know x by y
and then just two copies of that
you know for the z or whatever so that's
probably a mistake
uh but oh well you know we're probably
not going to fix it right
um
so
it does look like a pretty consistent
light bleed where it's just you're
getting energy added to the system and
it just spreads throughout the system
and the question is where is that energy
getting
uh
where is that energy coming from
you know
like
it's coming from somewhere
but i don't know where
and like there's very specific places
where it's unstable is it because it's
sampling from an apron in some way
that it's not supposed to happen like
like is something weird happening there
like it's very clearly like
only
possible when certain areas are
available
which is odd
and the fact that the copies are wrong
as well is it's so weird like it's very
strange what's happening
like ha
that i can't even come up with an
explanation it's one of those times we
have them every so often i am here i
can't even come up with an explanation
of what's going on there like if you if
you ask me to write this exact thing
what i would have to do
to make this happen doesn't seem
commensurate with
what i would expect now
i want to go look at the copy
because it's obviously wrong with start
there
i'm going to kill this
buffer of values
the copy obviously doesn't work because
we're getting that weird like
uh
on every time the voxel slides the
values are all wrong so the part where
we actually copy the voxel is just
totally busted
um
so this block copy atlas thing is
totally
bogus and doesn't work
why that would be i don't know because
in theory it shouldn't really have
changed much but i guess it's because of
how we
um are are computing like the offsets of
these things because we did sort of
change
how they were sized
you know we obviously screwed that up
so i'll start with
with uh first things first here and just
say like z doesn't matter
anymore
um so we should be able to assert that
the d voxel z value is always zero
and if it's not
uh that could be one of our problems
right like if the d voxel z value is
wrong
then uh that would explain a lot
so maybe that's the problem
uh but i don't know
doesn't look like it
so d voxel z is correctly staying
at zero which is what we would expect
so then the question is are other d
voxel values somehow wrong
um
so the way we're doing this
is we're taking
the origin value
and we're looking at the delta between
them
we are then trying to move
so every time
every time the origin moves by some
number of chunks we assume that the
number of chunks
is
aligned with our voxel cell dimension
evenly
which could be completely wrong
but b even if it was completely wrong
i'm not sure i know why we would see the
behavior we're seeing
i guess we would see that behavior if it
moved too much
so if the invoxeldim
cause the multiple to be too high
that would do it i guess
hmm
so i kind of want to know what these
values are
like
so
in normal operation at 60 fps these
should always be
like one or less
right
and so i'm kind of wondering maybe if
they are
um
if they're not
looks like we don't have an abs for ins
um
[Music]
fine
um so i'm just kind of interested to
know uh i guess the problem is i have to
kind of enable this later because
on the first time through
it's not going to be the case because
you're
moving to
[Music]
um
you know a different one but
some kind of garbage like this
so you know the first time through fine
get it set up but the next for from then
on we should never see any sliding right
it should always be like one tile at a
time
all right so it's correctly only moving
a single tile at a time
right
um
and yet somehow
we're getting this weird uh
this weird difference why are there two
copies of block copy atlas
oh it's just a yeah
you
so i mean that all looks pretty sane
like i don't really see
what the problem would be there
so it could be something slip we'll have
to look at this more carefully
i'm going to turn off those overlays
because i don't really need them at the
immediate moment
i might also be interested in in a very
slowed down version just to see
what's happening
i mean it's unmistakable on the copy it
everything gets dimmer for just just a
brief flash so the copy is just wrong
but i do not know how it's wrong
here's another question for you suppose
we were to turn off interpolation what
would it look like
so if the t update blend
were just one
so there's no interpolation anymore we
just see the whatever happens on this
frame is what we see
right which is this
that is just really weird
so i do think we're probably going to
have to construct some test cases here i
don't think there's any chance of us
debugging this in
in situ
right
um
[Music]
what we can debug
uh
we have
i think so i think we're gonna have to
create more test cases
and you can see like so whenever this
thing moves
you know that it has changed the
placement of the lighting you can see
very clearly that it blinks
once for every move it is clearly on the
copy so the copy is just wrong
but we have no idea why the copy would
be wrong it doesn't make sense for the
copy to be wrong
what is validate texla atlas
interesting
hey so what if we turned this on
wonder if we get any traps we don't
we should though eventually as we like
right that's just saying that we don't
have super high values i guess
not super low values it looks like
so it does eventually trap
it just takes a little while
but that feedback eventually hits
um
so you get you get out of bounds values
like right away
and it's from the raycast because it
can't be from the copy since the copy
validates on either end
right
so you get like out of bounds light
values right away
um
and again we really don't have any idea
why that would be
i'm guessing we should probably call it
a day for today uh because this is gonna
be really involved right we're gonna
need at least another four hours
just of set up time to like track this
down
because we we definitely have problems
with the light atlas now that have
something to do with how we you know
simplified it down
and we're going to have to go through
the whole like re-approval process like
to like narrow it down right
and again this is just this is that's
just how it is whenever you try to do
extremely like optimized code like this
where you're pushing everything into
like these extremely like special case
ways of doing stuff
your bugs are very hard to track right
there's really no way around that it's
why we don't normally write this code if
we don't have to right like
um
modern languages don't make it easy to
write optimize code
so uh it's kind of what you would expect
because there's probably some rather
obvious stupidity lurking in here but
it's just very hard to see because we
have
turned the crank so many times on it to
get it down to something that will run
fast enough
uh
that we don't really you know we don't
have the luxury of a simple
walkthrough right
um
adding some
opt-in bounds checking in here would
probably be a good idea right
like
validating that probe p single is in
bounds
would be good like we can add some
assertions here that are relatively
uh unobtrusive you know they'll get
compiled out
when we turn off
asserts
um
we could put some things in here that
would probably be okay
um
that would help us know that we're not
doing something weird like that for
example that bleed could happen from
things like fetching out of bounds or
something like that it could happen
so let's take a quick look so uh probe p
single
didn't i just look at it
probe sample piece angle
we could do some assertions here
and just verify that this is okay so
basically we'd say
okay
um
pull out the base
location
like so
and assert that it's not like out of
bounds or the thing that we're looking
up in which is the diffuse atlas
um
so like
assert that this is in bounds of well
does the atlas do that for us
so it would be nice if this
had a way of just telling you if you
were inside or not
but it doesn't actually seem to
so you can see here that we actually
have
the thing
that we want
which is this test but we don't have a
way to
[Music]
access it outside
so we could do that right we could do
like a vector is inside
or whatever
so we could do something like uh like
voxel index is in dimension
and
put this in there so that the checks
for each one being inside
would
be something you could call elsewhere
so then we would just do voxel index is
in dim of the light atlas we'd assert
that
as probably like
this would be an index
so
if we just pass the xyz to the
function here as our assert
then people outside can also call that
assert which is what we want right
so here we would just say assert that
voxel index is in dim
and there's a few at diffuse atlas and a
place that we're trying to check
um
and
that would in theory tell us
although i guess probe sample piece
single
still has to be converted
so we still need something that maps
into there which i guess we don't really
have
right
okay so we would need to actually divide
by the
um
by the cell dim i guess
so i guess we actually kind of did have
what we needed because although you know
although we probably do want this
function as a separate thing
i guess we actually can just use the
grid
so we'd say get index for p and then a
certain bounds
right
something like this
so when we're debugging at least this
would tell us if we ever tried to fetch
out of bounds and i don't know if we
quite did that correctly but
you know
maybe
so let's let this trip a few times in it
no
uh in a debug build and let's see if we
can
see if there's anything particularly
squinky going on there
okay
so
there's the actual sample point we're
trying to take
that is obviously wrong
it's not only wrong but it's weird
um
so you can kind of see like basically
these all have the exact same pattern
they are all like
totally bogus z values there are some
x's that are off one
apron wise
but the z values are just complete
garbage
right
so i don't know if that's because i'm
doing something wrong here but that
seems bad
so what what would make
us happy here
so
the total bounds let's look at this sp
right
so the total bounds like how is that z
value how are we getting that z value at
all
i
okay yeah i
i get it i get it
i totally get it
here's what's happening
okay
so in compute walk table
we don't anymore bother to check
z values because there is no z
voxel
anymore
right we we only have
an x y
sort
of the things
that's all we have
right
so when we step through the spatial
partition and and i i don't remember if
we're drawing this or not um
i guess i'd have to turn that off but
this is very good like so this this
answer is a big part of our question of
why we're why we're messed up right
so this is very good this was this was a
very important i'm really glad we just
added this
um
this was this was big
this will help us tremendously okay
so what's happening here uh if we
if we've have it all we gotta update our
remedy we need to be able to to kill our
app which we can't anymore it looks like
that stopped working
um
but
we
i
let me
put this in o2 and
simultaneously
uh let me go and draw the actual
cells again
so that we can see them
which you know we don't need this right
now
spatial grid
that's what i want draw spatial grid
so debug draw spatial grid
will step over each of the grid
areas and it will draw the
bounds of them
right if i do that
this will just draw just the boundary
box so this shows what grid cells there
are
in this
spatial grid right
so
i gotta i gotta turn off all the
validation that we were just using
so that i can actually look at it
okay
so here are all of this the grid cells
right and you can see that it's just a
two-dimensional array of grid cells
and so what we're doing with the
marching table
is the marching table
that we use to to
find out where we're where we are
if you were if you're
normally casting inside the actual
geometry it's totally fine because
you'll always hit something
as you're trying to go up or down right
but the geometry is incomplete and like
in some places like there's like we
don't have anything there array would
just go and it will go forever right
now before that wasn't a problem because
we actually had
an apron
for
stopping like we do right now where
there's an apron along the outside where
if you hit that apron you stop marching
but we don't have that for z anymore so
what happens is you just go as far as
you go in z which can be infinitely far
doesn't matter right
and then you try to sample and you
sample complete garbage out there
so whenever we do that sampling we're
going to have to clamp
right we're going to have to say like if
you would leave
if you've left the area
if you've left the bounds
then you stop
uh and you you know you you wouldn't
sample that ray
right you wouldn't download a ferrari
and you wouldn't sample that ray
that's almost certainly where our bleed
is coming from we're sampling completely
out into garbage land and then that
contaminates everyone
that also explains why you only get to
bleed sometimes because if all if you
move to a place in the world where all
of the lighting computations are being
done in places that actually will hit
something
then you will not get the bleed
right
so i think that totally explains this
problem the question is just what do we
do about it
i also don't know why we were getting
like negative one
in x that seems broken
so that may be like a legit rounding bug
or something that we have in the walk
table or like it's hitting the apron
wrong
right
so i'm not sure what we want to do about
this
one thing we could do about this is we
actually just
when we sample we clamp the sample to
the cage so we just clamp it to a valid
value
that has the bonus of working for
everything that would be outside so that
might be the best way
um the other option
would be that we
we discard so if you are outside you
just don't sum that one in it's just
zero
um
[Music]
in theory this should never happen in a
improperly constructed environments
so i think it probably we should just do
whichever one's more efficient because
we won't have to care about the quality
of the result in those circumstances
because they're only there for catching
bugs and like numerical errors and stuff
um it's not actually there to do any
kind of like
real work
that we care about
so it probably is just whichever is more
expedient like throwing it out or clamp
clamping
probably clamping is easier because that
way it doesn't introduce any kind of
branch it just kind of says all right
the mixes will at least now always be
valid
it's just you may end up fetching
something that you probably shouldn't
have bothered adding or something right
that's my guess
[Music]
so yeah
so here where we end up with a probe
piece single and then you can see here
what we're doing is we're we're um
producing
here with invisalign and total bounds
this floor function here is what's doing
it
um
[Music]
so yeah so you can see us actually we
are clamping
right here
uh to
okay so we already are doing this
clamping so i guess i i spoke too soon
this won't actually solve our bug
because we are actually doing the clamp
it looks like
but that doesn't quite add up now does
it because if that were true
if that were true
then why
why when we ran this before were we able
to sample out of bounds for zero for
rays that were equal to zero
i get is that just because the clamp
wouldn't work
on like in for something
like something still seems a little bit
fishy there
yeah i would have assumed that if would
just be fine in that comparison right i
mean i'm always a little hazy on on
what cindy will do
but
you know
if and negative imp should just compare
as would a large number in that
direction
so you would think that clamp would
correctly clamp it down
so that should always be clamping so how
the heck did that ever actually sample
outside of where it was supposed to
sample
like that doesn't make a lot of sense
that just does not make a heck of a lot
of sense like we should be able to set
that value to whatever we want
right
so i wonder if there's like a subtle bug
in here somewhere where there's some pla
way we can actually
sample outside
so yeah i don't really know what's up
with that
um
i don't know what to make of that
i'm pretty confused
so you can see like the general flow of
this code we start by producing the
coordinate
by flooring the
this is basically the voxel lookup so p
right is the is the place we're going to
sample
we subtract the minimum value
um which is exactly what you would
expect
we then multiply by the inverse cell
dimension which is the same as dividing
by the cell dimension we then floor that
that gives us our voxel coordinate
our uvw is where uh the fractional part
of that which is what you'd expect right
um
we then say okay
the maximum
place
that you could sample on this vauxhall
the like the maximum address you could
use is the dimension of the voxel minus
one one one right like it just subtracts
one from that
we clamp between zero and that maximum
value
the base chord and the bass chord plus
one so those are the two corners like of
the voxel
that we'd like that we'd like to sample
right
we take the difference between them
which is our way of saying if we
flattened up against an edge we don't
want to step in those directions at all
right
um
and then we produce the base x y by
saying okay whatever the minimum is that
we're going to sample we multiply that
by the stride
um and then we also add here like
whatever this nonsense is which is
basically like the roast ride for z i
guess
tyleros stride
times t x y
okay so that's that's the offset for the
specific va like the actual texel
right it's the xy offset of the texel
um
and then you just sample that thing
which is exactly right yes so i don't i
don't see how that was i don't see how
that was screwing up exactly i wonder if
it's we kind of need to go look at that
code again
um
maybe to provoke that
crash that we had um
with the zeros in there
to see what was actually happening so i
kind of want to do that so i think i'm
going to do that before we call it a day
here
so in our walk table like i'm pretty
sure all we have to do is just load this
up
and spam a zero in here
i'm pretty sure that just makes us crash
right
yeah
so if i look at those values i i just
want to get like a good understanding of
exactly
why that particular piece of code is
crashing i could have understood other
pieces of code crashing maybe but now
that i've looked at this if it's all
clamped how is that happening right
um
so here let's examine these actual
values so we can see what they are so
we're gonna take an f chord here
um
right and it's just all garbage
which is what you would expect
right
well you know what those are actual
nands though
so that might not clamp
in fact it won't
um
you would have to actually nand check
that so that
would explain it if that's actually
what's happening
so that actually looks fine though like
i would have thought that nan's wouldn't
clamp but they did
uh
like i said i'm always a little hazy on
what cindy willer won't do there
so these all actually look correct
the min and max are both zeros and the
delta is zero
so
so it does it does actually clamp nands
so that's great
so the question is
why did base offset end up being so
busted
which is the actual value that's
offensive
so base x y z
is min x y z times stride x y z
which is right
and min x y z
is zeros
i don't follow so
if
if base offset is computed from base x y
z
right
then we know that it's wrong because
base x what the reason this is messed up
is because base x y z is garbage values
base x y z is min x y z times stride x y
z
that should just be zeros
right
plus
this
line here which
should just be correct is t x y
so t x y is broken
so it's t x y that's actually the
problem
okay
so actually
i misinterpreted what was happening
before
really it's just the fact that it can't
invert that value is producing a bogus
txy fetch
so when i thought this has something to
do with the actual grid cell it doesn't
that's a lie because that always gets
clamped
so it's just the txy that was actually
causing it and that comes from r
which we do know would be wrong
so i guess like surprise it turns out
this wasn't actually a problem
oh well
um
that's a little bit of a bummer
but
what can you do because that would have
been nice if it turned out that you know
if that had actually been happening then
that would have probably been an easy
fix but no such luck
okay
so let's take the bogus value out
and put it back
to where it was
all right well
um
i guess we got to call it for today and
we're gonna have to
um pick this up back up next time when
our goal will be to
look at these last two problems here and
probably have to dig in pretty hard i
don't know where they're coming from i
don't have any guesses at the moment
so we're kind of just gonna have to
go through
slowly but surely and eliminate
sources of problems
it's too bad because
uh we're really close to good
it's too bad about this
because
it's very close to being
a really good lighting actually
but we're obviously just sampling really
weirdly we have a weird thing too where
the light you can see um
as it goes through because we have this
weird problem
that's a separate problem
of uh
the
the lights as they go through
other like
lights themselves
are occluders in the system right now
and we don't handle that properly
so uh you get this weird thing too
that's a separate issue that's what's
happened when you've
moved through things separately i would
also ask what the heck that is
oh that's the light yeah so in this case
you can see like this our light is
actually moving through another light
right it's this light here
um
we can actually probably see it if we
change
the uh drawing area
why is that only drawing sometimes
doesn't that seem bad
what's up with that
so you see how y
seems like it mostly correctly works
although it doesn't work right there
oh that's just because it's inside
something that's why never mind
yeah i mean we just we have some really
weird problems right and i i think we're
close
but it's gonna be a real grind to get
down to zero right
we're close but it's gonna be a grind
unreal engine 6.
all right i'm going to call it for today
uh we're going to have to look pretty
carefully at this stuff this that's
going to be a real grind next weekend
unfortunately but that's just where
we're at
um so
we will do it
uh so i'll be back here next weekend and
take a look at that until then everyone
have fun programming and i will see
everybody on the internet
take it easy everybody