okay so it's a little late start here
523 so we're going to go to 623 all
right hello everyone and welcome to
handmade hero the code or we code a
complete game live on stream we are now
in the position to start playing with
like some UI stuff a lot of people have
asked about you I stuff before probably
because of my reputation for IM gooey
things we get that question a lot and
honestly handmade hero is not really a
game that involves any kind of you I in
that sense there's no buttons or widgets
in the gameplay for handmade hero you
are direct control of a character and so
the early isn't any particular reason
why we would be implementing any real
sorts of you I in this game but since we
do have debug code in the game now and
we do want to be able to use that debug
code effectively that tends to be
something where you I wants to be
available to the game right and so what
we're trying to do in this circumstance
is we're trying to make user interface
like UI code right whose goal is very
specific normally if you're trying to
make end user facing UI code what you're
trying to do is make it be as usable as
possible for the you know for the
customer right for whoever you're
shipping this to whatever that that is
right if it's a game than the player if
it's you know some business software
than whatever right the person who's
buying that thing but in the situation
for you I in this case what we're
actually concerned about since we're the
only people using the UI we're only
really concerned about two things can we
use it quickly enough to make it be
usable for the purpose that we need that
we need it for and since we wrote it we
know exactly how to use it doesn't need
to be discoverable it doesn't need to be
easy to use it just needs to be
efficient enough that we can use it and
then the other thing and the most
important thing is that it should be
extremely low implementation costs
because we don't want
to be spending a ton of our programming
time building UI or fussing with you I
that nobody is ever going to see except
us we don't care how janky it is because
we're the only people are going to see
it so any time that we spent making me
why like prettier or fancier or more
functional or any of that sort of stuff
is probably wasted we have to have some
kind of a good case for spending any
time on it so what we want to do is try
to figure out like essentially the
highest leverage way of implementing the
UI in any particular case what is the
way that we can write the minimal amount
of code into the game and get the
highest number of debug UI features out
of it right that is what we're trying to
do so with that in mind you've kind of
already seen me sketch out a little bit
of that we implemented some stuff last
week just a little light stuff like
being able to hover over things to see
what they were doing and also to be able
to let click on things too like drill
down into them and I don't know if you
noticed but of course when I implemented
those I didn't do anything unusual I
didn't create some giant you I hierarchy
I didn't go cutie on it and have 800,000
classes just to implement a button all I
did was I put an if statement into the
code that said if you are hovering over
this rectangle right now and you you you
know it becomes the like hot rectangle
and if you click the button then it
executes some action on that rectangle
right that's all I did and that is the
attitudes I think you want to take for
making debug you I in the game you want
to make the thing that is the easiest to
implement that doesn't cost you any time
that doesn't lead to let code rot or
anything that just you know is nice and
tightly bundled with the actual output
code so at the rendering and the UI line
up nicely and if you so that you can
expand on how you're rendering things
and trivially have the UI kind of follow
along with it all that sort of stuff is
really what you should be shooting for
and that is exactly how we are going to
continue progressing down sort of that
path of of implementing this debug you I
up to the point where we feel like it's
good enough for us to use on the project
so we're going to take a slight step
back from what we were working on last
week because like I kind of just shove
some things in at the end because it was
kind of wrapping up we could take a
slight step back and what we're going to
do first is say all right we need a
little bit of debug you I hear the very
first and most obvious thing that we
should probably do before we go any
further he's have a way of turning this
profile view on and off right because
right now you know the if you if I run
the game right let me just bring it up
here we now have profile bars all over
everything and we were playing around
with those and that was all fine but the
problem with that is that we can't see
the game right so at the very least we
are going to obviously need some way of
saying whether we want to draw any of
this stuff or not because if we are in a
situation where we're working on the
game and don't really care very much
about seeing profiling and detail or any
of that stuff then either a we want the
profiling to go away completely like
just gone or you know we also probably
would want to consider something like a
collapsed view that's just a very small
sort of extremely small debug monitoring
monitoring version that just sits in the
corner end is designed to only draw
whatever is necessary to alert us to a
potential problem that we might have
missed so for example frame spikes or
things like that just show the total
amount of time for the you know frame
retirement maybe goes in there so we can
say oh wait we saw a you know something
weird happening there so that we can go
grab it right something like that
so that to me is more you know what we
want to focus on so I want to start
putting in a more solid concept of the
debug rendering stuff so that we can get
to the point where something like that
is as nice as Eva believe a solid story
for how adding things to that you I kind
of like comes in and you'll notice up to
this point in handmade hero when we had
debugging features and things like that
that we wanted to implement you'll
notice we also kind of have this problem
of they just kind of always had to be
shoehorned in there and we never really
had a good way of like turning views on
and off now that may not be such a big
deal actually if you think about the
fact that we have live coding ability
but there is a problem there is a short
comment coming with live coding ability
while live coding ability does totally
solve our problems in terms of like
tuning a particular piece of code
because we're working on that particular
piece of code that particular piece of
time at that particular time and it all
makes sense live coding doesn't help us
if we have a number of different debug
like visualization kind of things that
we might want to turn on and off for
example if we want to draw like entity
bounding boxes right yes I could make
that be just a live code editing thing
where I just go back into the code right
I change the entity bounding box thing
and then I come back that's a totally
valid way to do that but that's a lot
slower and less convenient than if we
just knew we had a list of things we
could turn on where we could just
quickly go click on them and say I want
Andy bounding boxes on right now right
so there's this concept of like
collating that stuff into one place and
so there's a couple different ways we
could do that but it's a very least even
if we decide we don't necessarily want
debug UI for it if we want to have it so
that it still goes to the live code
editing then what I think we want to do
is that the very least make a file
that's got all of those debug switches
in there in some kind of like way that's
easier to to deal with right so that
they can all be kind of scene and and
touched quickly you know what I mean
so I feel like that's just kind of a you
know kind of an obvious sort of thing
adjunct thing that we want to do so
let's start working on that again I
don't have anything in particular in
mind I'm just going to go ahead and
start doing some code transformations
that I think will get us there because
you know I know roughly I need some kind
of some buttons or something I need some
way of starting to interact with this
thing so let me just open up handmade
debug again as I should I should mention
its day 1 90 so if you did a pre order
on him my dear org you treat you want to
follow along at home day 1 89 source
code is the source code that i'm
starting with here on day 1 90 so unpack
that into a directory if you want to be
lined up with us alright so in handmade
debug first thing i want to do and i
said i wanted to do this originally is i
want to get rid of these global
variables here because we just kind of
threw them in there when we were kind of
working with it before we already have
the concept of debug state now we really
don't need these global variables for
anything so I feel like now would be
probably a good time to sort of clear
that out right to sort of stop dealing
with any of those global variables
because we did the work already to have
debug state that's stored so I'm going
to go ahead and get rid of those and
also if i remember correctly I feel like
the fact that we were using those global
variables also meant that our loop live
code editing would break the debug
system right I I don't really remember
if this is true but I feel like it
should have been true because the local
variables would not get reset properly I
don't actually know if that's the case
but here I'm going to recompile yeah so
when I recompile right the debug system
gets hosed right and so that's not a
good that's not a good thing so again
that's another reason we want to do it
even if just not to just get the things
out of a global scope so we just don't
have these names floating around to the
global scope for no reason besides that
is just pretty easy for us to do so the
first thing I'm going to do is I'm just
going to go ahead and move these guys in
here and go ahead and do a kill wrecked
on that and then move it over okay so
now I've got these guys in here and now
what I have to do is come through here
and make sure that everyone who uses
that stuff which is all going to be a
compile error is
I'm going to have some kind of ability
to call through the debug state now i
guess i have a problem which is that the
font ID defines are not above the sky so
they can't actually be used i'm not sure
what the most effective way is to to
deal with that but i assume that that is
in the file format stuff and the file
format stuff doesn't have any code in it
so it's pretty free i think for me
probably to put it up there so now i
hear what we need to do is we need to
make sure that we can get at the debug
state so i'm going to go ahead and grab
that out there we go there's that debug
state I don't remember what I call that
down these other things so I call that
debug state typically I do so I'm just
going to call it debug state here as
well and debug state now just kind of
needs to store this sort of stuff we
don't really need to call it global
anymore but I'll keep calling it that
for the temporary time being just when
I'm doing this port and then we can
decide if we want to change the names of
some of those things in the future right
so I'm going to go ahead and and change
these guys here debug render group i'm
not sure where that's coming from that
must be defined elsewhere us we should
also probably make that be something
that click that pulls inside as well so
we'll handle that in a second so there's
that left edge there's the font ID
there's that font scale so i think most
of that is probably okay let's let the
compiler guide us through the rest of
this year okay so debug text out at
let's see
so I feel like in general the debug
state probably doesn't want I feel like
the debug state pointer is probably the
one thing that we're going to want to be
global there right because what happens
here is the debug state global is really
just the game memory global you know if
you have the game memory global than you
know what it is and so every time on
entry into anything as long as we make
sure that that gets set right when we do
debug global memory equals memory this
stuff right here having debug global
memory is all we really need in order to
make sure this stuff gets processed
correctly all the time so probably what
I want to do instead of having this past
and now that i think about it right
because I probably want to do something
where I always just get from the debug
global memory I always just get the
debug state out of that right so I
always just have a thing here which is
like you know get debug State you know
or debug get state something like that
and then that function is just a known
in line that doesn't take anything and
uses that debug global memory there to
get the debug state so what this would
essentially do is just say okay as we
saw down here right oops wrong place
where is it where is it here it is as we
saw down here right if we know what the
game memory is then we know what the
debug storage is so it's always pretty
free for us to just say anybody who
wants to can get it like this and we
have the debug global memory and so we
can access it off of that right and that
will always give us that debug storage
so that is the easy way to make sure
that that always works and then we only
have to make sure that one global
variable is updated on entry into the
game system which is pretty pretty easy
to ensure and then we know that
everything else will work as long as
that's the case and then everybody else
should probably do an if on it so if
there is no
it's running without debug services it
just won't do anything right and that'll
be fine so I think that's sufficient at
least I assume it should be and I think
that's all we really need now the debug
render group I feel like the debug
render group should also be should be
something that's actually just done a
little more directly I'm not sure where
that's actually getting to find I don't
remember where we put that it's been a
while so it's right here so I feel like
that is something that we want to just
go ahead and pull inside as well so i'm
going to go ahead and finish this stuff
but then i want to make sure that we we
address that other one as well because i
want everything to go through a single
sort of uniform path that looks like
this everywhere always right so i really
want it to be like that and then instead
of having an if debug render group will
just get rid of that and it we assume
that once we get the debug state we have
the render group if that makes sense
okay so if we have the debug state now
we should be able to get all the rest of
the variables debug state font ID month
ID lot scale scale same thing here every
town and again i'm not really doing
anything other than just moving these
global variables into things that are
referenced directly so that we know that
it's all kosher there we go let's see
push font again same thing here we've
already got in the debug overlay we
already have this information so you
don't actually have to query it although
it does mean that debug overlay doesn't
actually need to take game memory for
any particular reason actually what we
can do instead is just do this and then
we know that that's just going to use
the exact same path that everybody else
does and i like that a little bit better
so we just do this and then we'd you
know we do it this way
okay so that seems fine and debug state
left edge there yeah and debug steak
little tight okay debug overlay the
function yes that's true do you look
overlay does not take that anymore thank
you for mentioning it that is just this
now and now we're done okay so i think
we should be in reasonable shape and so
yeah nothing has been altered at all so
now we're just operating without the
global variables i don't actually think
however that we have fixed the problem
quite yet because if i was to recompile
the debug render group will go away
right so that's why i say that's we also
want to fix that one so even though we
moved the rest of those variables in
those were not really the entirety of
the problem we need to make sure that we
don't use anymore global variables so
that we don't have any complex with that
so that's okay this stuff is totally
fine here all we really need to do and
we can get rid of that to do as well is
make sure that our debug state stores
that stuff as well so we have a render
group in here and we'll call you know
that that will will use and we'll just
make sure that that gets initialized in
some kind of reasonable way and so I'll
pre declare these guys since we actually
use them in the debug system and then
we'll go through here and try to figure
out what the best way is to organize
this so that we know that it gets
initialized properly and so on so you
can see in here inside the the render
group allocation and everything else we
allocate stuff out of the transient
arena for the debug render group that
doesn't really make a whole lot of sense
it's not a particularly useful thing to
do I don't think so at the end of the
day I would rather not I would rather
not do that I'd rather have that pull
out of the debug memory it's
health and so in order to do that I
think we want to move this out and we
need to get the asset information in but
i believe that debug reset actually does
that right it gets past the game assets
already so what I think we should
probably do is just move this out
entirely and do that allocation in the
debug reset and the debug reset will
just if there isn't one yet it will just
make sure that it does it at that time
so inside debug reset we have the
information that we need so in here I
feel like we could do something where we
just say okay you know if the debug
state render group does not exist we'll
just create it at that time using the
resources that we have you know what I
mean because we know that we're
initializing things at this point and we
should be fine if that makes sense that
seems like a reasonable thing to do I
guess I don't know for sure but it seems
like a reasonable thing to do so if we
were going to delegate this this here we
would pass the assets and then we would
need an arena and again we have an arena
in here but it's the collation arena at
the moment so again this debug state
kind of wants to make sure that the
debug state is is more of a real thing
right and so I think what I'd also like
to do is make it so that it doesn't
really matter what order you call these
functions in I'd like to make sure that
no matter what order you call them in
you can still make sure that this stuff
kind of works properly and so in order
to do that I'm going to use another
thing another little common convention
that I often use which is that what I'd
like to do is every time you go to get
the debug state it'll just quickly check
to see position size it's not initialize
it will initialize it that way everyone
who does this will always get the the
debug state will always have the ability
to do the initialization right so I want
everyone to come through here if that
makes sense I want everyone to always
check all of the stuff that we might do
we'll look at this in a second I'm just
throwing everything up there and what
kind of then organized in a minute and
you know I want everyone to kind of go
through there so inside debug game frame
end you know that's a that's a thing
that actually doesn't use the global
memory because it has the memory passed
into it right
and so what I might also say is like we
could just double this up so that
actually there's one that takes a void
and the one that takes avoid all that
does is that just does a debug get state
with the global memory like so but if
you happen to know what the game memory
is then you can just call it directly
and that way we can also do things like
have if we if we have more information
about what the memory is we don't have
to count on the global being initialized
which might gives us a little bit more
flexibility depending on the
circumstance right so yeah in that
situation here we would just call diva
get state and then we would pass it the
memory like so and now we have a little
bit more insurance there okay so let's
well you know what this I guess there
there's some things in there but before
I I go back to that what I'd like to do
is just make sure the initialization
code works relatively well so what I'd
like to do here is say that we have a
debug arena and I'd like to kind of get
that arena into more of a sort of the
standard way that we've been doing
things where we kind of have a tiered
access so in here I'd like to have the
debug arena something like that and I'd
like to initialize the arena like so so
that we use the whole thing for this
debug arena and then the collation arena
can just be a sub arena out of that
right you remember we had the concept of
the sub arenas here where I can just say
okay I want to reserve some of the
memory from it I'm going to go ahead and
say that you know just got to move out
as well we go so I want a collation
arena and I'm going to have some kind of
a size to that but it's going to be
allocated out of the debug arena right
it's going to have a size that we
prescribe which I don't know really what
we want it to be and I don't care what
the alignment of it
right although maybe you know what for
this in this case for collation I don't
know that we would want the alignment to
be 16 so maybe we want the alignment to
be for 16 may be a little aggressive so
you know we've got this guy we're doing
the the arena collation here and how
much do we want for that I don't know
maybe we just give that 32 megabytes of
memory I'm not sure again I'm not sure
what we want to do about collation in
the long run so for right now we'll just
leave it at that okay so when we do our
the rest of our stuff here that'll work
so then what I want to do is move this
up here and say okay we've got our
render debug group I'm sorry debug
render group what we want to do is say
okay if we're not Alicia lized than we
need to also initialize our render group
now we know that this is the first time
we're doing anything so we need to
initialize it we could say how many
megabytes we want that to be we can say
that we want it to come out of the debug
arena right and and yeah that's really
all we need to do I think so now when we
do this stuff I don't really know it
kind of feels it kind of feels like this
stuff wants to be kind of wrapped inside
the debug code you know it's kind of
weird that it's sitting out here for no
apparent reason so I kind of feel like
we we want these to be just debug begins
and ends you know what I mean we want
this to just be like the debug render
group this stuff that's that's happening
right here I feel like she just kind of
be wrapped in up in the debug CPP you
know that just seems like just the
logical thing to do to me I don't know
how you guys feel about that but that's
kind of the way I feel about it you know
and so debug reset I think should
probably just be should include this
stuff right so you just you just call it
and you don't have to check you just
call it and this thing you know knows
that this is all set up
right I feel like that's just fine I
don't feel like anything weird I don't
think that really makes any sense to not
do right so then when we get to the end
this where we do the debug overlay let's
just go ahead and put debug overlay
let's let's put that in here so debug
overlay this can just be a time function
right instead of a timed block and then
let's just make sure we actually do this
stuff you know in here so we'll just go
ahead and make sure that stuff actually
happens that way we can just say okay
debug overlay and it does its thing I
don't know that there's any reason why
we can't just do that so I feel like
that's what we will do alright hopefully
that all makes again I'm not doing any
I'm just consolidating things like I
said this week I want to do you I work
so I was trying to clean up how this is
working now that we kind of have it all
organized so that i can make sure that
there's nothing weird happening right
okay oh so yeah we got it we got to
figure out how to get the assets in
there reliably hmm that's a little
harder and to be fair one of the things
about the the debug assets it's kind of
annoying is really we don't necessarily
want to have to use assets in the debug
system because if like the asset system
is broken it means that we wouldn't see
our fonts at all you know what I mean
which is kind of a bummer so oftentimes
the way that you actually do this is you
wouldn't have the assets be used in the
debug system at all what you do is you
make a little thing that like packs up
some font into the executable itself
that you can just load out of a static
array right and so you know that's
something that probably would be nice to
do but in this particular case I think
we're going to struggle through it this
way anyway just because it's probably a
lot of extra work to go ahead and do all
that stuff for for that purpose but
we'll think about it
okay so restart collation debug and
debug get it for an up-down that's true
that has not been found I feel like this
stuff is is stuff that really we're
going to be getting rid of soon anyway
because we want it the frame processing
to be more incremental but for now it
should be okay so if we're doing restart
collation here then we know that the
current event array index is actually
going to always be 0 because we just
started so we know that it's that's
already 0 so we really don't need that
particular piece of information for all
intents and purposes I should think
hmm i say i need to think this through a
little more about exactly how I want to
do some of this stuff but for now I
think this is this is fine for
restarting the collision that's probably
fine and yeah so we're just the assets
that's a problem there so for right now
I think I want to defer that because I
want to think about that a little bit
more so what I want to do here is just
go ahead and port the rest of this stuff
so debug state render group that doesn't
need to happen see assets we start
collation render group debug state
render group oops and same thing here
yeah
last one well not really trance state
high priority queue that is true we do
not have the high priority queue so we
would have to get past the high priority
queue there that is that is definitely
the case let's see debug state debug
render group alright so I think we're
all good there so now we just gotta we
gotta think this through a little bit so
we need to be passed some other things
here we need to be passed what what we
need to actually accomplish that
information now although I guess I don't
know now that I think about it let me
take a look here game memory so actually
we we do have that information right
that's just in the global game memory
there so we actually can just use that
directly because in here we know that
we've got the debug state and we know
that we would have right the high
priority queue information already set
up so if we want to we can just do this
right where we do handmade H oops we can
say that we just kind of grab that out
you know of this thing move this down
here so the high priority queue
can be set pretty much any time so when
we do our initialization we can just say
oh yeah okay the debug state high
priority Q equals whatever the high
priority queue was there and now it
knows right and then I think the only
thing we would have to do is get past
the draw buffer that we are compositing
on top of that's really just about it so
let's take a look at what draw buffer is
find as is it just an image it's a
loaded bitmap so really all we have to
do is say okay we've got the draw buffer
here so debug overlay needs to be given
the thing that it's supposed to overlay
on top of or on top of which video is
supposed to be overlaid and now we just
pass it in there right so now we just
have this this issue of the assets and
i'm not sure what I really how I'm not
sure how I feel about this I'm just not
sure
it's a bit of a conundrum it's konnen
drama chol in that sense again because
the only real reason that we have the
assets is for the fonts although to be
fair maybe the debug system wants to be
able to draw like textures and like a
little viewer so you can see what they
look like or things like that so I guess
it's not that unusual that the debug
system would want access to the asset
system but it does mean that we have
this problem of we don't really know
exactly when the debug States going to
be initialized so what we could do I
suppose is force the debug state
initialization to happen at a known time
when we know the assets are configured
up but that's a little again it's a
little janky especially in the cases
where maybe we start to have situations
where there could be you know threads
involved I don't know but but thinking
it through a little more I suppose
everything goes into buffers for the
debug system so far and we could just
assume that things generally are going
to go into buffers because they have to
be thread-safe anyway and so at that
point it's not such a big idea big deal
to say that things have to happen so we
could still leave we could leave this
essentially the way it is we could do
something like this where we say okay
there's like a debug initialized call
that has to happen and you know it does
something like this like so and when you
do debug get state actually what happens
is it just asserts that nobody ever
tries to do that when the debug thing
has not been initialized yet you know
what I'm saying so basically debug
initialize just takes the game memory
and maybe that can actually just beat a
call that actually sets everything up in
terms of the debug global memory as well
in fact we could make it so that the
initialized state kind of runs off of
that
in some way we think about this a little
bit more so if you take a look at
handmade hero dot CPP the way this is
working is at the top of it you know we
assign the debug global memory like this
and so I feel like at that point you
could really just make it be that that's
the best of debug initialize call right
I assume although well if it's got to
get past the assets right the assets
don't get initialized still down here so
technically this is the earliest that
they could actually be initialized in
that sense right is after these happen
so I don't know that's kind of a little
bit tricky but we could make it so that
we call debug initialize here right and
you know maybe i'll call this debug
start in debug end or something as well
just for fun down
and you know if I'm going to do that I
could just say all right debug start is
formally is actually going to be this
guy right here all right something like
this and it will be the one thing that
doesn't go through this because it's
allowed to be uninitialized if that
makes sense delete that and so in debug
start and we got man we got 20 minutes
right because of the late start today so
we've got another 20 minutes to go even
though it says during a begins now it is
not true so if we're in here we know
that we can get the assets now we know
that that initialization would happen at
a good time for us we know that we kind
of set all of our stuff up and that's
kind of nice right so if we are to go
that route yeah if we are to go that
route then I think we should be in good
shape and when we do our debug start
debug and the weird thing about debug
end is it's not really debug and frame
it's just the part where we draw you
know so it's the sort of the debug
drawing and so it's a little bit of a
misnomer there but that's just the
nature of debug code it's kind of a
little nasty how it integrates in
because it's kind of trying to like
capture as much as possible that makes
any sense so yeah so I think that would
probably be okay let's take a look at
where that gets us so far okay so we've
got to buy start to bug and that's all
fine in here when we call debug start
this could also take the game memory so
that's not a big deal either although it
doesn't well it doesn't really need it I
guess because it's but we know that the
cave of global memory has
be set every frame anyway due to the
live code editing so that's fine this
guy is all good you just got to grab it
out of there see same thing here and
then restart collation just needs to be
predefined so that it can be called up
there to initialize things and like I
said that's something that I think we
want to kind of improve a little bit the
way that works anyway so debug start and
debug end just need to get pre declared
because they replace these two guys here
we go okay and I think that's just about
get so hey we're still drawing we got
the deep the fonts working in debug and
all that stuff seems to be fine so let's
see now if we can get our loop live code
editing working if I recompile this now
I'm totally fine so that's great we can
just keep going with that now so that we
don't have to worry loop live coding and
debug services will be nice and
harmonious with each other and that is a
good thing right that's all all nice and
dandy and in fact exhume we could
probably even just do this and and
doesn't even bat an eyelash so that's
all pretty great that is what we want
that is happiness and goodness so yeah
so I think that's all fine let's go
ahead and keep going with that now that
we've got those things kind of
reorganized a little bit more let's try
and make something let's just let's just
try to get our UI story a little bit
straighter right so again just a little
bit of baby step what I'm going to do is
I'm just going to make it so that the
the profile view
can maybe can maybe happen can maybe
like be resized or something right I
just want that those profile bars I'm
just going to play with that a little
bit so let's say for example that we
would do something like rectangle too
and we wanted to make like a profile
wrecked or something something like that
so I'm just going to make a rectangle
and I'm gonna say that the rectangle is
supposed to go that's where like the the
profiler stuff is supposed to be drawn
so if i do that if i come into our debug
and you can see and in fact i just got
some residual coding here that we may
want it well I guess we might want some
stuff from it that's why it's still
there so you can see when we do this
drawing stuff right we have a bunch of
information about how this is going to
be drawn and we've got some like scaling
stuff and all that sort of thing in here
what we could do presumably this I can't
think of any reason why we can't do this
is we push an orthographic transform on
right like there's our orthographic
transform it seems to me like we could
pretty easily just make that
orthographic transform be something that
actually happens kind of like in the
middle of the actual code so you know if
I'm if I'm in here and I'm like
rendering this stuff you know I could
say that i'm just going to before i do
before i draw this stuff you know I've
got an orthographic transform that gets
kind of stuffed on here right so in
theory i'm just going to i'm just going
to see what happens here in theory i
could do something like this
well actually let me just do it this way
to make sure it works first but I could
just do some like this where I push an
orthographic transform on you know and
here is me just like setting up the
exact same transform so in theory I
should just get like exactly the same
what does it complaining about
conversion from ro32 in 30 I love how
like visual studio doesn't even tell you
which argument like they couldn't even
figure out which argument it was that
had the conversion so you have to guess
it's like thanks guys from our 3 to 2 in
32 so didn't we just copy this whit what
do we what are you talking about where's
the where's the sure so it's int
int real so what oh so I should not have
done that that was a mistake so these
really it's really the other way round
soaps so in theory if i run this should
run and it does and that's good but now
i'm going to just see what happens if i
just say oh yeah won't you just make
that be like half the height that it was
or something right oops put that here
why does that take integers because that
doesn't really make any sense I feel
like that's busted in my opinion oh and
I guess I see why so the orthographic
thing I probably just forgot how we
implemented this so pixel width pixel
height and then meters two pixels the
scale is actually baked into here so
that makes sense so really we don't need
to do any of that we can just do this
and I just make it half the size like so
right okay so that makes that guy
smaller right and in fact I can
presumably just make him as small as I
want right like if I want to make him
even smaller now he's even smaller right
because since the renderer like has
everything going through a transform
it's really not a big deal to have that
happen now the problem that we will have
and you can actually already see it is
that we don't actually transform the
mouse into that space at all so we have
the mouse position we just use the mouse
position directly to check for like hit
testing and stuff like this and that's
not useful right that's not going to cut
it we need to like figure out where the
mouse would be in the transform space so
that's another thing that we're going to
have to watch out for but at the moment
i'm not going to concerned about that
i'm just going to focus on sort of this
other separate part okay so transfer
minus we can pretty easily transform
this guy by using the orthographic
transform to change his shape as well
and we can also leave to shape the same
in addition like we can do something
like this leaf is shaped the same but
also control what what his actual
placement on the screen is right so I'm
going to go ahead and do that one we've
got like the chart left and we've got
the chart bottom here somewhere chart
top right so if I want to have some way
to move this around I can just make it
so that like I said I've got like a
rectangle here or whatever that i've
defined called profile wrecked i could
just make it so that the data actually
comes from there so you know somewhere i
set the profile wrecked oops min x or i
guess i could just do profile articles
recommend max and i can just set this to
something you know whatever i actually
want the min-max to be you know maybe i
want the thing to be 10 f 2 200 200 so
like a little 200 x 200 square up in the
corner or maybe it's a little bit
further down something like that I can
if I want to just get all of the
parameters out of that for this
particular thing right so how would I do
that I guess I would just go the chart
top is going to be whatever this profile
wrecked says it is oh and I guess I
shouldn't say if it so if it's actually
5,200 it's actually going to be down at
the bottom corner always going from the
top down that's that's just an old
school program or problem so the chart
top right is just going to be whatever
the profile wrecked max why is that's
just going to be the top and then the
left is going to be whatever the min x
is right so that would start with that
recommend max no overloaded function
right got to put some v2s in here got
about that
there we go yeah yeah okay and so if we
take a look at that right and again it's
actually like that's these I always
forget our court assistance from that
from the center in this case so 5050 is
actually going to be like up 50 and over
50 from the center in theory right
pixels so I'm not sure if that's exactly
yeah so that's probably about right it's
hard to say it looks like it's a little
off but yeah that's basically the idea
and then for the scale right we could
also say like okay whatever the scale is
our chart with of a thousand we could
just use whatever the width of this
thing is whatever the width of our
profile wrecked is to scale but since
this chart already got the scaling built
into it right oops we don't have a
getwidth function on our and our wrecked
and our rectangles that's kind of crazy
get min corner match-winner let's get
dim so there's the width
and so now right like yeah the thing is
is super tiny because now we've set the
width to be only however much we
specified in there and that's all fine
but we also have the problem that we
don't respect the height of this thing
right so again if we wanted to operate
kind of in a box that we could control
the size of we would need to like shrink
the width and the height of things in
order to fit into the box so that's
another thing that we have to do i do
want to know though I'm a little bit
confused is that really 200 pixels worth
of width it seems a little bit not so
much oh right because it's actually only
150 because this was wrecked min max
yeah so you know how it is anyway so
yeah that all looks fine so if we wanted
to change how the height got interpreted
we know that we have a certain number of
lanes and we also know that we have a
certain number of frames that we're
going to draw so if we just go ahead and
back solve for how many of those we want
to have right if we just come up and do
something like this we now know what the
max frame count is and we know what the
lane count is so assuming that the max
frame you know we could do something
like this where we just go okay we need
to know what the lane height is right
what we could do is say all right the
lane height we're just going to assume
that the lane height is zero and then
we're going to do assuming that the max
frame count is greater than zero so that
we won't divide by zero we'll just say
that the lane height is going to be
whatever the max frame is times the lane
count
right that's how many lanes we have to
draw and then we're just going to say
that however big that that's you know
how many total we have to draw so
however big that actually is going to be
well I guess we also have this space and
concern here right so we have lain
height x laying count and we've got this
this sort of spacing that produces the
bar height we've got this sort of
spacing here so as a constant of for
that gets added in here right so we want
to discuss by that as well so we want to
talk about basically like you know bar
spacing equals four point 0 or something
Laura spacing so this is actually like
bar plus spacing like that so this is
plus bar spacing but we want to do here
is back solve for bar height right or
rather I should say backs all four lane
height so we know how big the lanes are
so to do that we know we have this many
of them we know that for everyone well I
guess we also we kind of need to do this
in two stages we know we have this many
blocks right and we know we have a the
get dim of the profile wrecked we know
we have this much total space right
that's the entire height of the chart so
if we divide that by max-frame now we
know how big each block of bars could be
but we have to then say ok the bar
height itself we know their spacing in
between them so we would need to
subtract away right the bar spacing from
that result because each one of those
bar blocks has this extra mount there
and then that total amount that we have
left over and there's a little bit of
there's a fence post thing we could do
there because it's not in one hundred
percent correct but we can talk about
that a second if we then divide that by
how many lanes we want that would give
us that would give us what we're looking
for for the total a hang
so yeah yeah so now we're getting a
little bit closer to what we where we
want to be but we kind of have some more
work to do here but point being where
you know we're getting there slowly so
what I want to do now is I want to start
debugging this and then also have a way
that we can sort of test moving it
around what I'd like to do is I'd like
to draw whatever the rectangle is so
this rectangle right here I'd like to be
able to do like a push rect outline on
that or I guess I don't even really have
to do a push back to outline I'm just
going to do a push rekt first before we
draw anything else I'll do a push rekt
of this guy so when we do this push
wrecked here's the render group let's go
ahead and do push wrecked so when we do
push wrecked I need to pass it to that
group I need to pass it the rectangle I
need to pass at the Z and then I need to
pass it a color and what I'm going to do
is I'm going to pass it just like
essentially a sort of a black overlay
right so there's our our supposed
rectangle and this confirms what I
thought before which is that our
rectangle is kind of busted so I don't
understand like a rectangle min max if
if that's actually correct I guess well
you know what I guess it could be is 50
pixels only that many all right so I
guess that is actually correct that's
that's that may actually be correct so
we're all good here the only thing
that's a little janky is we go outside
of the rectangle because our current
definition is we don't actually sort of
stopped anyone at the moment from you
know if you if you take more time than
you're supposed to we don't stop you
from drawing outside the bounds which I
don't know that I necessarily even want
to fix because that's kind of something
I wanted to see there but we could try
to make it a little bit more prettier
later on so that's also totally
reasonable what
that is super weird oh wow so we have a
bug we have a total bug there that's
pretty interesting you can see that we
like when you click the button when we
do resetting ah look at that check that
out remember I was saying that you find
problems in debug stuff I just want to
show you this so when the left mouse
button goes down mouse but when we do
refresh collation we had this like giant
spike happening in the frame thing right
oh well I guess it's not a bug now I
think about it's not even really a bug
that's just what would happen right so
if you take a look at what happens here
when I click the left mouse button it
Rico lates all of those frames right
because that's kind of the way we have
it set and you can look at you can see
it taking all this time to go Rico late
the frames which pushes out the time
when it does the render to one whole
frame afterwards basically right that's
just kind of that's kind of cool all
right so let's let's try to solve the
one obvious bug that we do have here
before I guess we're almost out of time
we're not drawing high enough so I just
need to kind of like get my math in
order here for the max frame situation
okay so we have our max frame thing here
this is how many frames were going to do
we have our lame cat our lane count her
Lane count like that so we get how the
total width we have and we know that we
have this many frames that have to fit
in there so we find out how much this is
basically this divide tells us how many
frames how many pixels per frame we have
we then subtract away the bar spacing
from that because we know that we're
going to put that much space in between
them so we only have the residual of
that left and then we divide by the lane
count and we get the lane height so pro
Lena that then we come back through here
we say okay we have the lane eight times
the
in count that's how big each individual
frames but you know the S we called that
a bar for no real apparent reason that's
how big those should be and that you
know that looks pretty okay to me I'm
not sure why short height bars plus beta
times do a state frame that's actually
wrong I don't know if we actually ever
used chart anywhere do we yeah we don't
really ever use it anywhere so it's not
actually important but that's actually
wrong this is actually max frame here
right cuz that's how many we're actually
gonna draw that's the chart with which
we knew that's the chart top which we
also knew that's the scale which only
affects the left right so yeah I'm not
sure I'm not sure I understand exactly
so I'm just going to go ahead and break
this out and just take a look so if we
do get dim dives Mac frame look there
this is basically pixels per frame plus
facing then we have pixels per frame
which is that minus however much there
is in between each bar and then after
we're done with that we have the lane
height itself which is just the pixels
per frame / the lane count and I'd like
to just I just want to go ahead and see
you know what what what what happens
there this is bars the spacing spacing
bar height plus bar spacing and that all
seems Lane height x lane count yeah I
mean that seems reasonable alright so
let's go ahead and take a look I'm just
going to step in there and see if I
could see what the problem is before we
go to the QA right
let's go in here pixels plus spacing is
15 pixels per frame so what is debug
State profile wrecked so what does this
say it basically says that we've got you
know we should have 150 pixels to play
with right and whats max frame max frame
is 10 so 15 pixels per bar does sound
right we then subtract away the bar
spacing and we get 11 pixels we then
divide by the lane count of nine right
and we get 1 point 2 pixels per let's
see what we do here we then say the bar
height is 11 which is correct bars plus
spacing is 15 right which is correct so
the chart height total is 150 so that's
actually computing it correctly are we
drawing it wrong so let's see how we
draw here bar spacing times 4 ah so
that's the problem we're just drawing it
wrong we change the meaning of that and
I didn't propagate it down so it's
really just bars plus facing just needs
to be propagated down like so bars
facing is that not in there yet there we
are and so now we've got our stuff sort
of sitting in a little window which is
cool and yeah I'm going to go ahead and
go to the QA if that makes sense and
take some questions here because we did
plenty on this dream and feel like I
said we're kind of in that mode where
we're going to kind of over the course
of this week drive the debug system into
a state where it's more of an actual
little kind of UI system that can sort
of place things properly and not be
quite so ad hoc because we kind of know
what we need now in the structure is
there so we can just kind of start
placing things so if you have any
questions about what we were doing go
ahead and cue it
midlo I appreciate that there are more
robust ways of implementing such things
but would it be practical to use the
debug data to drive some of the game's
visual effects EG fire or more likely
some otherworldly magical entity or the
display on an in-game computer maybe it
could be sort of an easter egg for those
of us who know how the games made well
the reason that i would be less inclined
to do that is because it's going to take
a big chunk of memory and it takes a
bunch of extra cycles and stuff to
collect this information so the idea
would be that when you ship the game
it's compiled out so presumably it won't
actually be in there but maybe you know
maybe that's a bad decision and maybe
since this is a project that's about
education we should have a way for you
to get at the debug code in the game to
try and encourage people to play with it
so you know if if that's the route we go
then yes we certainly could tie it to
something let's see Elvin there are
magenta spikes in the debug graph that
happened so fast we don't have time to
click on them how do we plan to catch
those having the ability to step frame
by frame could be useful another idea is
to have the debug text left off at the
last repetition we hovered well don't
forget we can always pause it and
although we only see a few frames here
we actually have 64 of them so what
we're going to be doing with this debug
you I is will be able to just kind of
grab this and scroll back to the one
that was a spike so anytime we see that
spike will be able to just go like that
and grab it right even if it went off
because we've got a pretty big back
buffer and we can always make those back
buffers arbitrarily bigger on a machine
that has you know a ton of memory
because like if you're dead machine
that's like 32 gigs of memory because
it's like some fancy dead machine or
whatever you can just dedicate like you
know twenty four gigabytes to debug back
buffer and you could store every frames
all the events from every frame for the
entire game in there if you wanted and
scroll back as far as you wanted so
there's no like limits on that we can we
can have a party
any other q's
numark to use there's no more accusers
no more q's
alright well no Marquess we will wrap it
up doo-doo-doo oops okay thank you
everyone for joining me for another
episode of handmade here it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along the tour
code at home you can always pre-order
handmade hero the game on ham a hero org
and it comes to the source code which I
update every night so you can always
stay up to date with what we're coding
and play round source code at home so as
you can do your own experiments and
learn things we also have a forum site
you can go to if you want to ask
questions or if you want to look at an
antidepressant ain by the community we
have a patreon page if you want to
support the video series you can put you
can subscribe to that we also have a
tweet bot which will tweet the schedule
so you could always make sure you're
catching the stream live if you want to
be you'll know when it is up so
definitely check those out if you're
interested I will be back here tomorrow
5pm pacific daylight time for those of
you interested in seeing the debug
system become something more you I
friendly that is what we will be doing
this week and so it should be pretty fun
so tomorrow we'll kind of get some
little kind of windowing stuff happening
in there and we can go from there so
hopefully I'll see you back here from
that for that until then have fun
programming and i'll see you guys on the
internet take it degrees everyone