hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero sure we could complete game live on
stream today i want to take a little bit
of a look at the collision detector uh
probably this in like two ways last week
i
did some diagrams on the board just to
sort of talk out like how do we want to
approach this for
what will be our final collision
detector that we're you know
we need one that we can ship now so this
is not like a prototype thing anymore
this is actually we want one that's
going to be reliable
um and so what we need to do here is
start to go down that route
and what i sort of said was look i
probably want to do something
that's actually not that dissimilar to
the one i made for
the witness because actually i do
want something that's going to have the
same kind of robustness to it i don't
really like shipping code
that's super janky so i would like to
have something that i have some
confidence
that it's actually been architected well
from the standpoint
of knowing that things can't get stuck
or things like that so on the screen
right now we have uh the blue
lines are the collision boxes and
currently this is running through a
super crappy collision detector that i
think we wrote in like somewhere in the
first hundred days
that really doesn't do anything smart
uh and so now what we're gonna wanna do
is start replacing that
and so like i said what i'd like to do
to that
if possible is i'd like to
have the um we can go in here it's
called move entity
so in here what i'd like to do is i'd
like to have a collision
routine that in general works
in the positive sense rather than the
negative sense so
rather than something which looks to see
where you can't go
and stops you i'd rather have something
that
every frame looks for where you can go
and puts you there
and the reason that i want that framing
uh is because
numerical precision is a very difficult
thing to work with
floating point is not a precise way to
do calculations
it's floating point for a reason it only
handles a certain amount of precision
for you
that's just how uh fast computations
have to work
they have to be limited in terms of
their accuracy
or their preciseness um
and as a result of that we we don't
want especially in a game scenario where
hacking things is important because you
want to constantly
do random stuff based on arbitrary game
design ideas you might have
or your designer might have the last
thing you want to do
is make it so that you need to maintain
extremely rigorous definitions of
numerical precision throughout large
swaths of the code base because that
will just immediately drag
everything down to a crawl um because
you really want the ability to just move
entities around and
and slap you know different velocities
onto them or doing all sorts of things
that are just based on making the game
feel good to play and game design ideas
people are exploring
so you really want that underlying
system
to not really care about how crappy
the inputs were you want it to take very
lousy inputs that might be
interpenetrating they may have been
teleported from one frame to the next
they may have very high velocities very
low velocities they might be really
close to each other really far apart you
wanted to just be able to take
whatever random crap the game designer
or designers
randomly did and you want it to produce
the best possible outcome
so you want to try and make a routine
that on every frame
is trying to help you rather than trying
to screw you
up right uh if you've seen glenbary glen
ross
you know what i'm talking about if
you're going to make something up make
sure it helps
so we're going to take this in two
passes
the first pass is going to be to try to
change the move entity routine
as it exists currently to one that is
simply
trying uh the opposite way around
instead of
taking a motion and seeing how far the
motion
we can go before we hit something which
is it was kind of doing like that sort
of a thing
we're going to change it into a routine
that just goes look i was here
a straight linear extrapolation of the
path that the
game design asked for would put me here
what's the closest place to that that i
can put myself
right and still be in a valid location
so changing it from a let's try to go
somewhere and see where we stop
to a different thing which is let's look
for valid positions to put myself and
we'll just pick
whatever one we can find that's closest
to where we're going but we
always will never be doing numerically
inaccurate things like doing very small
motions or anything like that we're just
going to change it the way we look at it
to looking through space for some place
valid to put people
we're gonna do that first and then the
next thing we're gonna do
is if we get that working nicely and
we're happy enough with it
uh next week or two weeks or however
long that takes
then what we want to do is look to see
if we can upgrade this routine
to being more about simultaneous motion
so we take all the entities see where
they all want to go
and then only resolve problems that
actually occur when entities collide
with each other and the reason that we
might want to do something like this
is because if we keep a system in place
like the one we have now
where everybody moves incrementally so i
move entity a then b
then c then d then e right then
two entities right next to each other
who are both moving
in the same direction will not both be
able to move sometimes
if the one that's further back tries to
move first
it will be disallowed because it can't
move into where the other entity was
and then it doesn't matter that that
entity happens to then move
out of the way on the next frame right
now this is a fairly minor issue because
then on every subsequent frame it will
be
basically correct so but you can produce
some little micro stutters and stuff
like that
so we might want to try and get rid of
that if we can not a huge deal because
again that doesn't really affect
robustness it's just kind of a nice to
have
so we'll look at that but we don't care
about that until we get
this part right because this is the part
that really can ruin the game
if you have a collision routine that can
produce inter-penetrating objects or
things that get stuck in walls or those
sorts of things
like the one that we have currently
would totally let you do
um that's just a horrible experience for
players and we want to take that out of
the equation
there will be enough bugs in any
sufficiently complicated game
to worry about without having the
collision detector producing crap like
that
so that's our goal is to get rid of that
here and to try and move towards
something
that's trying to help us every frame
it's trying to put things into legal
positions
instead of generating problems for us
every frame which is potentially moving
them into illegal positions
right so that's what we're going to try
so uh looking at what we've got
here in the move entity routine you can
see that right away
we know we already are computing the
thing that we actually care about which
is the desired position
if we just turned off uh the entire loop
right if we just said look we're not
going to do
anything this loop is not going to occur
right
so this loop goes away and instead we
just said okay the entity's position
equals this desired position
that would move everybody to where they
want to go
with no concern for collision right
so if we did that then all entities and
you can see it's like interpenetrating
uh anytime it wants to right you can see
that like if i wanted to go over here it
can move straight through a wall for
example like that right
so we know starting out we have two
things we have where we were
and we have where we would be if if we
did not collide
right and we can verify that by doing
what i just did so we know this desired
position
is the correct thing based on whatever
the random physical requests are that
for acceleration and velocity and crap
that the gameplay code wanted to do so
that's a separate piece code we'd have
to care about we just know that it's
going to set those things
we can produce those things here so we
do right
now
i suspect uh first of all
i'm going to get rid of that because i
don't care about that at all
but i would suspect that this should
probably move
of this routine and be in
some requested physics stuff
and we just take the desired
point here so really what i want the
screen to be and you can see
so this is fine we can leave it here for
now we don't care but eventually what
i'd like to do
is i'd like to make it so you just pass
in desired position so you just say look
i'm going to do whatever i'm going to do
gameplay wise maybe that has some
physics in it like acceleration or
velocity
maybe it doesn't maybe i just have other
ways that i'm going to move things
and when i call move entity all i really
want to know
is where should this thing end up on
this frame
where do you actually want it to go and
then we're just going to go from there
and say
now let's see if we can make a routine
that puts that somewhere
you know that puts it into a legal
position
that is close or as close as possible to
that desired position
right um now if we look in here we can
actually uh keep some aspects of this
routine because
in a sense we do uh want to have
something like
iteration because we probably will need
to do a few
tries for this um we don't really know
exactly what that would look like yet
but we probably will have a for loop
here
and we're probably going to try a few
subdivisions of things or something like
this
so uh we might leave that this stuff
is not this is not gonna happen anymore
now
this uh right here obviously will
replace
because this is now n squared for every
entity we move we have to test against
all and
other entities uh and this is not quite
n squared
uh in our particular case
it's actually way way way faster than n
squared
because there are very few entities who
actually move
so the reason that this isn't
already tanking the frame rate is
because although we have to iterate all
over
you know thousand two thousand entities
however many are in the active set at
any given time
although we're iterating all of those
entities we don't actually have to test
uh uh we don't have to call move entity
on most of them
so every call to move entity would
iterate over all the entities in the
active system to see if they have
collision volumes
terrible waste of time very inefficient
but the reason it doesn't because
become n squared and blow up the
performance of the system right now
already is because move entities only
called on like
six people it's like the floating heads
and the glove and that's it so we do
also kind of get a benefit here that
actually this routine probably won't
have to be that fast in practice because
the number of things that actually run
through the collision system are going
to be actually fairly small
but we probably do want to fix this
either way because a simple spatial
partition even a crappy one would speed
it up tremendously because rather than
stepping through all the things
you'd only step through a little region
of things and that seems like it'll be
much better so
a two-phase pass through would probably
be a better idea so we probably want to
replace this with a space partition
either way
but the reason we're not seeing that
need yet the reason we're not
actually caring about that is because
move entity is probably only called like
10 times a frame
right so it just it it doesn't go n
squared because rather than calling it 2
000 times a frame we're calling it
you know 10.
so inside here
uh we've got volume uh stuff for
everybody
now we know that the entities collision
volumes doesn't change
so i'm just going to move that up to the
top not because the compiler won't do
that for us it will hoist usually
things out of loops more just so i can
see it more clearly
i prefer to see the stuff up at the top
that's
you know my constants for this entity
these are things that
you know aren't going to be changing
here uh and then
i should probably get rid of this
because we're not doing that yet um
so i want to hoist those out and that
way i can see okay these are the ones
that i'm actually using for testing so
these are certificate to the entity
now if we look here you can see we're
computing them in casket diameter
this is for dilation this is so that we
can test the entity as if it's a point
right um and against the things that
we're moving
i don't know that we'll actually need to
do that
in practice because we're going to be
sort of changing the way
uh that we are looking at this to be
different um so i don't actually know if
we really want
this per se uh this may not really be
um this may not really be what we want
but that's okay um
yeah uh but we'll see we'll leave it in
for now
uh so anyway you can see us here uh
doing some nonsense
where we then do some testing that is
totally ad hoc it looks like testing we
did
for like corners of walls it looks like
and uh
furthermore this looks like this was
only in uh 2d
this is when we wrote this so
i mean that's probably fine for this
game if we really
asked ourselves that question um
but if you look it's just like i mean
why bother like so this
this was old 2d collision code i don't
think we care about this at all
uh so i'm just going to go ahead and say
that this is going away this this is
just this is just lousy and we don't
need it it's not going to do anything um
that we care about uh and for that
matter
neither is any of this stuff uh it looks
like we've got handle collision and
speculative collide
uh and again um
i don't really know that we care about
this yet so when we go to speculative
collide
you can see here that it's just sort of
um
it's just really more of a canvas
collide
so speculative collide is probably not
the right term
um we probably just want like
a does this collide and this is
uh this has nothing to do with collision
detection this is just now us thinking
how do we want this like integrated into
the game design part of things so
there's a couple things here first of
all we
want to know whether or not this thing
collides
uh from the standpoint of
do we test against it and then there's
probably
also one which is do we stop
when we hit it because you can imagine
us
wanting something that that does a
trigger when two things
collide but that we don't actually stop
them
and at the moment we don't really need
that very often
but but like um
the way to think about it is this we
have an opportunity here to unify more
of our systems as well i guess what i'm
trying to say
so right now we have some things like
which room are you in
we do that check it's a separate check
we have things where we test
like uh are you in a place where the
camera
should zoom in here right i don't know
if you remember but there's stuff in the
game
um from a long time ago that did this
sort of stuff right so we come up here
and we're gonna hop um over to like
uh you know um
yeah like the cat right so we hop in
here
and and it zooms in right to look at the
npc
that we're that we're talking to or
whatever so we've got some
markup in there that's like where um you
know where
where the where the pus is you know you
you zoom in
on uh on npcs if there's these are
actual people
um not puss but you know they same thing
zoom in right
uh and so what we want to be able to do
uh in those cases is we want to be able
to
um
want to be able to know are you standing
in this particular location are you in
this particular region
blah blah blah we could then
make the collision system just output
that information because since we're
already doing all these checks and we're
already going to have that system in
place it we might as well piggyback on
top of it
so like i said we probably want a thing
here that tells us these collision flags
and probably what we want to do is just
make them direct flags we can test
so i don't think we really want things
like speculative collide to be happening
that doesn't sound like a very good idea
so probably what we want to do and we
removed the other flag which is the can
collide flag
which i do think is a good idea to
remove because i don't think it's what
we actually want
but i do think we want some actual flags
here um
and so what we probably want to do is is
make these
be something like this
where we have uh an entity flag
for whether or not collisions
are triggered so like whether or not we
will
report uh so like reports collisions
uh and then another one which is like
uh prevents motion through or prevents
motion
on collision or something like that
right
uh event on
[Music]
collision
and prevent motion on collision
now we don't actually have to do both of
these
because we could choose to have the
event
thing be actually what determines that
so we could say like oh
events get generated on collisions and
then there's motion that's prevented on
collisions
or something like this and the reason
that i'm not necessarily psyched about
doing that
uh sorry should say that the other way
i'm not psyched about the idea of when
two things collide
i fire some event handler and the event
handler tells me whether or not motion
can proceed
obviously that's the most flexible thing
uh and the reason that's the most
flexible thing is because it means
there's procedural stuff in play that
can say like oh yeah allow this question
or don't
based on who knows what like we check
some things about the entity and how
many hit points the player has and
whether or not they're doing a
particular action at that
time and what i think i would like to do
is say
no i don't want to do that let's just
assume
that we're never going to have anything
that needs that level of
tweakiness to whether things can
interpenetrate or not
and the reason for that is i think it
will just simplify writing the routine
we'll be able to make a more performant
more streamlined routine if it doesn't
have to go
out to some other piece of code right in
the middle of trying to solve for these
collisions
to ask whether or not it should allow
something to go through
something else or not right so what i'd
rather do is say look entity system
unless we actually can point to
something eventually in this game design
where we're like we need to have this be
completely dynamic
and there's no way we can set flags
ahead of time that would say it
um because remember you can always clear
and set this flag so you can always have
things that like turn
on prevent motion and turn off prevent
motion that's fine it's only just like
do you need to actually take two things
and compare them in some complicated way
to determine whether motion can
can pass i mean we can even have things
like
different prevent motion flags that you
know if you could just set entities up
so that they have a flags
a mask that would work too so
i'm just going to assume that no matter
what we want in the game design we can
make something like that
but in general there's always a way to
know without
calling out to a gameplay routine
whether or not two things
can coincide or not in space so
that i just want to make that statement
up front and so what we have here is
two flags that control what the
collision sector's behavior can be one
of them says whether or not you want to
be notified
when two things are overlapping uh
and the event on collision thing will
just be if either of the two things has
that flag
right so if either of the two things has
that flag an event will go
into some log somewhere for processing
gameplay purposes or however we want to
do it doesn't matter
uh that system will just end up getting
notified out of the pleasure system at
that point
if we have prevent motion on collision
set then
the anytime there's a question of that
form whether there is an event generated
or not
it will prevent motion through there so
those are the two things that i wanted
to have there
and we're not going to call things like
speculative collide that's not going to
happen
right okay
so we don't care about any of this i
don't care about any of this stuff
or this stuff like literally none of
this stuff right
so more or less all we're going to do
here is we're going to want to have
this handle collision call at some point
but
what i'm going to try and say uh like i
said before
is i want to try and have that on the
outside so we're in here
uh in the the the for loop situation
whatever
i want to make handle collision in so
much as i can
uh be something
that is called after the fact so
basically like
we do all the work we
will stack up like who is gonna get
notified
and those are just gonna go into some
like ring of things to get processed
later or something like that right
now fortunately for us we don't even
have to do that right now what you can
see here is we didn't
have anything in that routine and
similarly like can overlap
doesn't look like it was used either so
hopefully we can just get rid of most of
this stuff
so um in can overlap
which we now have a uh boolean for i i
could
keep that routine around i'm not sure if
i actually want to or not we'll see in a
second
uh whether i do um but if i just do this
and get rid of can overlap it should
just be removed yeah
so maybe i want to keep that routine
around round and it just does that flag
test i just said
but maybe i want the flag test welded
directly into here so we'll see
whether i want to pull it out later i'll
just assume for now that i don't
okay so taking a look at what's going to
happen here
now what we need to do is say all right
how are we what's our strategy
for determining whether or not we hit
things and if we hit things
determining whether or not we need to
actually stop the motion
uh one way or the other right
so
let's do um a
trying to think of how i want to do this
here
so let's do something
because i think what i'd like to do is
is again do something where i kind of
subdivide
space a little bit and search i don't
want a line because a line doesn't allow
gliding along walls and it also wouldn't
help us displace ourselves
out of inter penetration so we want a
search over some space right
and we know some things about
the size of the delta so whatever this
is i don't it's
player delta is a dumb word because this
is not the player
um so this is really just delta p here
right it's not
it's not like have anything to do with a
player because this is moving
any entity not just the player so when i
take a look at the delta p
um in this case can we also just
take a minute to reflect on the fact
that that purple
color is absolutely horrid um
we don't know for a fact that ryan
fleury is colorblind
but it would seem that he may
in fact be colorblind uh if that was the
default color
um let me take a look inside here at the
themes
this is the themes where what is that
color
uh is it is it token highlight
um
you know what i'm saying like that is
just a horrible purple
um
2f2f37 no that would be like a blue
right am i am i wrong about that
so that's actually this underline here
so it's like a different it's like a
it's like a token highlight for other
places
that aren't there or something
does anyone know what that is offhand
because it's really
it's really aggressive that purple
a little bit too aggressive you know
what i'm saying to you
anyone know what that is
anybody
purple means it couldn't find the
variable okay so basically there's
some variable we're not setting um
[Music]
you know what i'm saying uh
oh terrius python but is there a way to
just set the color
but can i just set the color is there
some
setting for the color
minor highlights okay minor
yeah that's just not set so let's just
set that and then we can just
just have it right it's it's not an
issue um
if we just set it to a color that
doesn't kill it that isn't
a horrid right um
flurry color token minor highlight
uh and
minorly
we don't know who's responsible terry's
python
terrius python says uh that that's the
case
so if i just do this um
do we do we now believe
that this will be fine that everything
will be fine
move entity let's take a look
oh yeah thank you tarius python
for saving the day because that was that
was pretty garish
you know if you don't mind me saying so
just a garish purple
um so yeah
we could make that a little brighter too
if people are having trouble seeing it
but
i don't know how much i care like i
don't usually need to see that that well
um but you know at least now it's kind
of like
okay not too bad all right
so uh at this point like i said what i
need is a way to
go through and test space in a way
that lets me figure out uh where i could
put this thing that's close to the place
it actually wants to go
and i think the way i'd like to do that
again is just to break down space into
some pieces
and so maybe what i'll do is just kind
of look at it
like a uh
like kind of a subdivided grid probably
so what i may do
uh is something like
oops uh did that just
yeah deleted my stuff um so maybe what
i'll do
is something like this i'll do like
subdivision
levels here uh
or something like this
and for each subdivision level i will
look through
uh some level some number
of
i i may even want to stack so
for each i i want some way of like
subdividing space and i could do this by
just doing a blanket grid in fact you
know what
let's do it with a blanket grid first so
just a fixed size grid and it'll be kind
of crappy
right but let's do it with a fixed side
grid first
and then we'll add subdivision after
because that'll just
make the problem a little bit simpler
you know what i'm saying to you
so let's do it with a few for loops here
where we just
take and we we do like a
um a dimension here where we say all
right we're just gonna look
through like a four by four by four or
something
um and we're going to see uh
which of these cells is
available to place the
uh entity in
where is the best place we could place
it in this series of cells
right so starting from the location
and moving outward in a radius that's
roughly
the size that you want to move um we're
going to see
to what extent we can like break the
break thing down
uh into pieces and we'll see what
happens right
and what i might do is say look this
thing is going to potentially
have to run multiple times as well so
what we may do is make like kind of a
little bit of a kernel here
um that's maybe something like uh
move entity small or uh
move n and c locally like something
that's just a very small perturbation
uh and then this code here is going to
be something that happens
only on like a small movement
and so here what we may do is say well
if this move is too large so if if the
actual like the the length of
most of the motion is too large
for uh what we're doing we're going to
break it up
into pieces you know what i'm saying so
we'll just say and this is why i didn't
care about that to do from before we had
to do that was like
cap the maximum velocity i don't think
we want to i want to just
take whatever velocity you asked us to
and split right
okay so if we're going to take the
velocity and split i need
like uh some total motion and again you
know what
to do subdivide motion
into max size steps
again i won't bother with that yet i'm
just going to call move entity locally
first and we'll do that
subdivision there is a separate step as
well
so off we go and what we want to do here
is
call this function uh
with the entity who's moving and
the desired position of the entity
um so where you're actually trying to
put it
and i might even say like something like
that
so we want like a v3 from
and a v32 uh so this is where we're
coming from this is where we're going to
this is guaranteed to work as long as
these are fairly small motions
and then we need to pass the region and
the entity
because we need to know the entity's
collision volume we could
if we want to just pass the collision
volume
i'm going to pass the unity for now
we'll think about how we want to do that
later
so we're going to do this which gives us
information about that motion we're not
going to do the subdivision yet
um i might want to make this a little
easier on myself for iterating
um we've never made a voxel iterator
here
so maybe that's not a great idea uh
but um you know
the index to the voxel we would
basically do something like you know
while
voxel i z is less than the dim z
you know off you go uh and then at the
end you do like a voxel
i x plus and you say if voxel i
is uh less or sorry greater than or
equal to
the um
the voxel dim
this is just a standard way to do the
iteration right so if it's
greater than equal to voxel dim then you
do
your other increment
and in here i would also do voxel i
x equals zero and then the last one
voxel i z
oops y greater than nuclear voxel dim
y voxel i y
zero plus plus x light z
so that's a simple way to just do one
for loop
well it's not a for loop but you get the
idea one loop
uh that is going to do
all of the squares of a voxel right all
of the indices of a voxel
uh and then in each one of these i'm
just going to go ahead
and
[Music]
test so this allows us to do our
sort of our breakup right our our
discretization of the space
and in each one of these i then uh need
to
put in like the cell dim so here's the
cell dim
this is going to be how big that voxel
is and
again i think
i think the way that i want to do this
uh like i said is i want to break out
the space in a way that that ensures
that i'm looking at
the place that i was at the place that
i'm going to
and some reasonable apron
around it again the reason for that
is this is not trying to be an accurate
physical simulation
at all because this is a game we do not
care
fundamentally about the accuracy of the
physical simulation
what we care about is that we recover
from screw-ups gracefully so
if the game design code that like does a
bunch of random crap
ends up sticking to objects inside each
other right or like one side another
we want to be doing searches outside of
that space
to try and ensure that like we'll get
those things will separate
at some point right so what we want to
do is we want to try and
look for places we can put things so
that they will split in those cases
now the only thing that's a little bit
dicey here
is you may want to do something like you
check to see whether or not you're
currently interpenetrating at the start
of a frame and if you are you search for
a wide
you search over a relatively large area
to try to get yourself
out of that location i don't know to
what extent we want to do that it
probably depends on just how bad we
expect
the gameplay code to be doing things
like that my hope is is the answer is
not very
right um
so yeah uh
so i think that's i don't know this
part is not that important because we
can't always pick
larger ones later but what i want to do
here is basically say okay
we've got from p and 2p and those are
going to be like the corners of this
voxel
and then we're going to extend it by an
apron right uh
so we want to do like a total voxel dim
and the total voxel dim uh is going to
be
uh like and in fact i guess we could do
we have a rectangle three
uh wrecked min max
right so voxel bounds maybe is the right
way to do it
so we do voxel mounds uh and we say we
want to go
from the from p to the 2p right
and
the problem with this is we want the min
and the max i don't
do we have a min and a max for vectors
like we want this right
you know what i'm saying to you looks
like that works
so basically we want to take the entire
span of the move
like whatever that is um
what the heck is this
this is like the this loaded this is
like the c
tray i don't we don't need that i don't
know why that's up there
um so this is the total bounds of the
move and then what i want to do
is i want to do like an add radius too
um and so i want to make sure that
however big that is
we also look at some region or some
small region around it
that's like the epsilon and i can call
this the apron
um size or something
and again i don't really know how big
that should be uh that's that's a really
tough call
because i don't know like how much space
we want to look
uh at but it's going to be something
right and we're going to want to tweak
that and hopefully we can maybe draw
some of this stuff
so we can see it and make some more
informed decisions about it
we know that 1.0 in this game
is a fairly large distance right that's
like the distance from like
one square to another uh on the hopping
or whatever it's like
you know about one or something like
that so
we know that like point uh this would be
like 1
100th of that distance which would be
pretty tiny
uh and so like i said i don't know what
we want this apron size to be
it's it's tough to say but it'd be
something in this range you know maybe
it's that maybe it's this i don't know
we can play with it
so from there we would say okay the
voxel dim is something we know that the
voxel bounds
divided by the voxel dim would be the uh
actual
thing the actual dimensions of each
individual cell
and i don't know
why this is
that i suppose another way to write this
would probably be this
um and
[Music]
why am i getting grumpus why is it
grumpus here
all right so here
we have the voxel bounds and the voxel
dim we want to do a divide we don't have
a divide
for vectors um
[Music]
for no real reason we probably should
uh because sometimes you want to divide
right
um and so i'm not sure yeah i'm not sure
why we wouldn't
uh i guess this is actually
do we have a hadamard divide
so we call that hadamard i probably
should have just used multiply
it used to be that this was rare to see
a hadamard product written as operator
times
uh but now it's not because shaders do
it
and so now everyone's used to just
writing times for this
so you know um
i think i may just cave on that and say
look man
hadamard is just times now
because it's not doesn't really make a
lot of sense
uh all right so anyway let's suppose
this is operator slash
from guns and roses and then we'll just
you know do the divide here and really
this should probably be operator times
you know that should probably be that uh
and
you know we should probably just change
that right so
in here where we had these uh we should
probably change those to something else
and you can see
like just trying to look at how many we
have
uh it's not even that many
you know so i do think maybe we we do
that
um let's let's maybe do that as well
just get rid of those
because i don't think it makes a lot of
sense
um honestly anymore
to bother with that like this is in in
in game parlance nowadays
operator star is pretty much what it is
uh
and and so it's you might as well get
used to it because that's what it's
going to be
in basically everything you do um so
seldim
times whatever this is here
right is all that's going to be
same here
there's that super aggressive token
killing for some reason
um does anyone know that answer targus
python
do you know how to get it to like
actually just delete a token
when you do that rather than deleting
two tokens for some reason
right like it for some reason deletes
way more than
a token even though i thought i bound
that
to delete token but
maybe not um i don't know
we'll have to look maybe that's in the
uh yeah i don't know
something something's weird i'm not sure
like what that is but it's it's not
great
um so anyway looking at this
again all looks pretty straightforward
why is that say hadamard when there's no
hadamard there
is that
is this that
that's a bit weird i don't want to know
what was going on there
we won't ask these questions um
all right there we go
and oops yeah i would really love to get
that fixed it's one of the only
remaining things that super bothers me
uh in in this editor right now is that
weird like super aggressive like when
you hit
delete it deletes like everything and i
don't know why it does that because i
thought i bound it to just
the token delete like if you look
at the bindings file
so this is what they're bound to um
[Music]
which is obviously not right or
you know maybe it is maybe the only
thing that there is but
is there like a thing um
that's better like something that would
not
do that that would just delete one token
at a time um maybe it's white space or
token boundary or just
backspace token boundary
anyone any guesses for coder experts out
there
there's that and there's also the other
fact was that like the weird like when
i'm opening a file
it deletes the whole thing like only
deleting just
characters at a time in that thing up
there those are the two things i would
be very interested to know if anyone
knows the answer
uh alright so
doing some stuff
getting rid of the hadamard thing
um because i think it's pretty standard
now
these days that times times
had times has had a mard product
that's just what happened i don't know
why
um you know they could have picked dot
product they could have picked cross
product
they could have picked hadamard products
the powers that be picked hadamard
product so
at this point i don't think there's much
point in
differing about it um
[Music]
uh
it's really weird too it's like not even
symmetric right
like if you're here and you hit delete
it deletes the parentheses
and the hadamard if you're here and you
hit delete it just deletes the hadamard
so like it'd be it's really hard to even
wrap your brain around because it's
using
it's doing like all the alphanumerics
and stopping
when it hits white space or a symbol
which is not something that your brain
does very like it's not an operation
your brain would normally think to do
you know what i mean or that it wants to
do
like or naturally you know i feel like
so it's kind of like always confusing
victor c minus says that there are some
things i can try
so we're going to try them because the
way it is right now i don't like
so it can't be worse backspace
token boundary
is it actually d-r-y or is it d-a-r-y is
it actually spelled wrong
i guess we'll find out in a second uh
part delete token boundary
okay um so if we do that and then do for
red
[Music]
let's take a look
at what happens
ah yes
much better thank you ryan and thank you
victor c minus
so yeah other only other question is is
there a way to stop it from doing that
like when you do this is there a way to
make it only just do
a character at a time does anyone know
that'd be another nice thing to have
um so we're getting down to things where
there's not too much
problems at the moment there's the
indentation is broken
which is just a bug i don't know how
long it's been in there
a long time so that's unfortunate but
hopefully that
that's just a bug that will hopefully
get fixed at some point
all right so that's all good
and this just needs to be
like a v3 a fide version
um so voxel bounds
uh so we can divide those two
right uh and that will give us the
dimensions of each individual cell
which is good so we have those um and
then we should be able to
uh construct the positions from there
oh cool more infos
someone says that in the config file
if i set lister whole world whole word
backspace
yes
wait but that's set to false
isn't that isn't that what
lister whole world whole word
backspace when modified is already set
to false
is the only thing which
does that mean it just doesn't work
anymore maybe
or do we set it to true for some reason
um
which
try true now that's confusing
but we'll give it a shot
yep that was it wow okay so that may
just be a poorly labeled parameter
i guess but hey man i don't care as long
as i get as long as that gets what i
wanted
i don't care uh okay so now
uh we're compiling again with the
hadamard product let me just test to
make sure i didn't break anything with
the hadamard product
so that's all good uh looks like
everything's fine
so let's go back to trying to help these
little fellows move
uh how much time we got here we have
like one hour probably i don't really
know uh
so if i go back to move entity locally
and we take a look here
um you can see that i've got my voxel
i'm stepping through and at each point
in the voxel stepping
what i want to do is determine um
whether or not i could
stand in this place on the voxel
and what i might do is just look to see
uh
what i might do is just look to see like
what the corners of the vaxlar that i
can stand on
you know what i'm saying uh
and
i'm trying to think if i'm actually over
complicating this by actually bothering
to step through a voxel at all
because what i was thinking is can i
just start at the place i was trying to
put myself so the 2p
can i just look around there to see if i
can place the player anywhere and if i
can't
i just move outward from there
i'm just really not sure about that
so here's what we're going to do for
starters just because
um because i don't really want to think
about it too much
until i actually have something working
i can play with it
so what i'm going to do first is i'm
just going to say okay there's a voxel
dim
here uh and
and it's maybe more like this
uh and i just want a voxel occupancy
like uh
a thing that basically says like could
you stand here or not right
so there's like a uh
a vacant you know what i mean
um and i want that to literally be
whatever the va to be voxel addressable
so we just have a little thing that's
going to say where everything
is or isn't right so when we come
through here i need to first
say like hey uh this
better not be the one i'm actually on
so like test entity had better not be
equal to entity
right but assuming that they're not then
we'll go through here
and take a look at them you know what
i'm saying
okay uh and then what i wanna do
is for each of these we're gonna take a
look and we're just gonna test
the place in the voxel that we are so
wherever the voxel location is we're
actually at
we're just going to test that voxel and
i want to
make this an iterator so like i want a
voxel
iterator um here actually
and so i want to make this thing be
something like that probably so that i
can
roll this in so there's a thing that
looks
like uh
iterate foxhole um
this kind of thing you know i'm talking
about
so all i want to do is exactly this so
i'm going to grab
the while loop condition and i'm going
to make that be the thing i return
uh and i'm gonna return the
this condition as whether or not we're
still iterating
for advance it's literally just this the
code we already wrote
right um and then for
starting and this is all just
you know
oops
uh and all this is just going to be
whether it's the i or the dim
right so here we've got you know the i
is the thing that's in each of the left
sides and the dim
is the thing that's in each of the right
sides
now we don't actually need this thing to
record the dimension because it's
duplicative
so you could choose to just not have
that right
and to do that we would just say
something like this
which seems plausible to me so that now
it's just that
um and
that seems fine you could even go one
further and say we don't even have a
type for it
it's just iterate voxel and it returns a
v3s
right which would be kind of nice um
[Music]
but who knows like i don't know maybe we
want this to be fancier so for now i'm
just going to do it this way
and be fancy but we don't really need
that so
i don't know if we'll you know i don't
know if maybe we'll simplify it
later on um okay so
supposing we do this uh the voxel this
part here
is just literally just dim uh
and zero we can have an offset but i'm
not going to have one at the moment
uh so here we're just gonna say iterate
voxel and you pass in the dimension it
remembers the dimension and sets the
initial thing to zero like this uh
and off we go so that's the voxel
iterator and in here
we would now do a for loop voxel
iterator vox i equals
or voxhitter or something iterate voxel
it's going to take the voxel dim and off
we go now
also those are all s's right yeah so
we pass that in there and then we just
have an is valid
voxitter and an advance
or next in order maybe
maybe it should be
um and so this is just we'll march
through the voxel in order
and do what we wanted to do so
i think that's all we need
uh and now we're iterating over all the
pieces of the voxel and
we can then say that as we loop through
here
what we could do is say that the thing
is uh and you know what maybe we'll do
occupied instead
so everything it defaults to not
occupied uh if we find somebody who is
occupying it in here we just set that
right so if someone's occupying it
um we would set voxiter uh
i z it doesn't really matter which way
we do this
but you know x y and z
so we want the occupied uh to be set to
true
and we can also stop because then we've
found
out that you can't stand there right
so i want to do something like that uh
where we test
and and here is where we would do the
test so like if
you know the overlap test uh
on this piece of the voxel corner um
off we would go finally we will step
through the voxel a second time
so just a two pass algorithm where now
we will look to see
and uh what i want to do here is
step through the voxel at one less
dimension
so what i want to do is i want to step
through the voxel dim
minus one right
uh so i'm just gonna now so so before i
was looking through like
voxel positions right uh and now
i want to so like one way to think about
it is i wanted to step over
vertices here and now i'm stepping over
cells here so i want there to be one
vertex
on like the other side of what i'm
looking at right
and so then what i can do is i can just
see uh
are is this voxel completely unoccupied
and if it is
i'll just take the closest point inside
it and treat that as a new valid
position
and if not i won't right and that's all
i was gonna do
someone on the chat asked can the amount
of time the entering second hour notice
be displayed
can it be adjusted um yeah
it can be adjusted in c tray right i
think
um
to be honest i don't really remember
anything about this program
when i wrote it but
uh it it does have a
thing in there that that determines
whether or not it's going to show that
um
so it looks like it displays it for one
minute
so if you wanted to change you know
if you were building this program
yourself and you wanted to change it
this else statement uh would be what you
would change
right and arguably if you want to start
doing cool stuff here you could just
make an array of ranges so rather than
doing in minute you could do something
like is it between here and here and
then you just make like a range and you
know set whatever you want
so you can fuss with that if you want to
you can also just change this routine if
you want everything to display
longer you can just change file time
minute to two times file time minute or
ten times file time minute or whatever
however many
minutes you want display for you could
do
so so there's that uh but yeah anyway
um so back to our story
um yeah so
in here what i want to do is just say
look if all of these are
so so if i were to just like take all of
the occupieds
um and just do a big munge so like
if not
uh
[Music]
like so
and i said like vox spitter i
uh z
[Music]
bloop bloop um so if we were to just
check like all of these booleans
and and again there's gonna be like a
better way to do this um
then we're doing it but again i'm just
sketching out the routine
i'm not thinking about optimization god
i wish the indentation in four coder
would be fixed
i do not know it used to work it broke
and it seems to not be like
going to be fixed for some reason which
is weird
because how that doesn't drive people
crazy i have no idea
um so looking in here
like if we look at what's happening we
could just like
smush these together um
there's going to be eight of them right
because it's the vertices of a
of a cube well it's not necessarily a
cube it's a vertices of a
of an axis-aligned uh bounding box
effectively
uh but we would gather up a bunch of
booleans and smush them all together or
uh and we would then know like look
if there's nobody occupying um
this whole set so if nobody's occupying
anything in here right
uh then i'm free to place the player
at the closest point uh
in this in this region
and
this function is the is what would do
that
right so if we said what's the closest
point
to the thing in this box well we can
make the box
uh and we can get the closest point
which as you can see is a trivial
operation right you're just min maxing
it right
um and off we go you don't have to
virtual white space neighborhood or is
that the way
yeah i couldn't really get virtual white
space to work right when i tried
so i just gave up on it like it had
trouble with like comments and it had
trouble and i had trouble with a lot of
things so i just like forget it
um but
uh so i'm just using the regular but i
but i would like indentation to work
properly right
um if that makes sense
uh so all i want to do is say get
closest point in box
uh to to this so
i want to put it in the 2p place
so i want to get the closest point in
this cell
this voxel region and
uh that's going to be my test point
and then i just want to do like look if
the
do i have a distance squared yeah or no
i don't
all right so if the distance between
um the test point
and and i guess what i should probably
do here is just have a best distance
squared so now i think about it up i'll
probably just do this
like a test dist squared so if i take
the squared length
uh from the test point um
to where i'm trying to go which is the
2p that's
that's the like i'm going to say how far
is it from
the point that i'm actually trying to
get to
if my best distance squared so far is
greater than that
then i want the new one so i want my
best p
to be test p you've seen me do this type
this code a thousand times
so we'll just keep that one as our new
best point
so here we're going to have our best
distance squared our best distance
squared
um from the test point is going to be
our
current point probably i would say right
well that'd be only if it was in there
so no i'm just going to say this is f32
max for now
uh and then i'm going to say our best p
is where we're standing
right and so and and maybe we should
change this maybe we should be like if
you can't find
anywhere to put the thing then the
player just goes wherever they want
right you can see why that might be
safer
like if the player just gets stuck in
some crazy out of bounds scenario just
let them be in god mode
so they can get themselves the heck out
plus speedrunners
right this is the stuff they live for
you know what i'm saying um
so yeah so maybe we default to saying
entities can do the move they were
trying to do of course this doesn't
really help them
well would help for the glove i'm
thinking like the player moves on the
squares they can't they don't run this
through this routine but
you get the idea so uh speedrunners
you're welcome so this will be like if
we
can't find any legal place to put you
in the vicinity uh we just let you do
the move
and that way you can't get something
stuck uh permanently
it'll it'll be able to get out somehow
right
okay so we go through here we test we
see if we find a place if we do
uh then we use that and then at the end
we just say all right so the result here
is that the entities uh gets placed at
the best location
that we can find and you continue onward
right so very straightforward this
is complaining i don't know what it's
complaining about
to be completely honest with you uh so i
don't know what's going on there
uh oh that is wrong uh
so i'm really in the habit of typing v3s
because of starcode galaxy there are no
floating point things in the beginner
course
so i'm very used to it's like my brain
is not thinking of v3s at all
um so we just need to produce this cell
and
that's not particularly difficult
obviously
because we know that that's just going
to be whatever our voxel bounds are
plus an offset right so the cell
in this case uh is
just gonna be a rectangle three
um which is a rectman dim probably
where we take them in we offset by
the voxhitter eye
right um and
times the cell dim and that's just going
to place us in the right place
and then we have the cell dim itself as
the dimension
so the cell should be pretty easy to get
and off we would go this is supposed to
be a minus don't ask me why it wasn't
and now iterate voxel seems to be
complaining what's it complaining about
we have a voxel dim here which is a v3s
and we're subtracting one one one from
it i'm not sure
why that would be complaining um
it returns a voxel iter so that's a
little bit weird what's the actual
warning
oh what
is that just because of this
okay so the fact that there was a
placeholder in there was causing the
compiler to not realize that this
had been closed at that time so it was
thinking i was like voxitter only exists
inside this for loop scope it's
definitely not being shadowed
but okay so if we basically say that
look
we're going to run this in a not really
real way
but i want to test it in waves because
we've got a bunch of complexity here
this is going to test all the voxel
cells and it's going to put you in the
closest point in a particular cell to
where you were trying to go if that cell
was empty
what i want to do is just leave all the
cells empty right now so it should in
general
uh just this should
we want to get this working first
because if this doesn't work we already
have a bug before we ever do any
collision detection right
we're we're just trying to say like you
should be able to move inside the cell
that you're in um and whatever and so
you can now see like okay
everyone's moving freely which is what
we would expect they can penetrate
directly through things they don't have
to stop which is exactly what we expect
because we're not testing anything
so that means this is probably working
okay we don't know for sure but at least
i'm just you know bringing it up in
waves
so that we kind of have a reasonable
idea of what's going on
one step at a time so now all we have to
do is test these corners
so we can you know determine whether or
not something's in there or not
um uh and so this should be pretty
straightforward it's just a point test
so it's just a point in box test
we are going to grow this uh minkowski
diameter here
and see like can can the player's cube
or can the collision cube standard now
this is going to get more complicated
and the reason that this is going to get
more complicated is that in the future i
think we probably want cylinders so
we're going to have more of a cylinder
cylinder
uh collision test here or you know other
things like that
so we're going to want this to be more
uh flexible than it is because we're
going to want at least a few different
permutations
cylinder we're probably going to want
cylinder cylinder cylinder box
and box box
right
so that's presumably what we're going to
want there um
okay so here's us taking
here's us doing stuff for no reason
uh is what we're actually doing
you know i might take a quick break uh
actually because we've been going a
while here
we've been going god how long have we
been going i might get some more water
well this is actually lemonade full
disclosure uh
i'm gonna take a quick break i'll be
right back
oh
[Music]
[Applause]
be
foreign
[Music]
all right
water has been refilled so we started it
like
started two and a half hours ago
i gotta talk more quietly so i don't
don't get my voice too going all right
okay
um hopefully everyone enjoyed that brief
peppy peppy song
all right um so this all seems fine
and so all we really need to do now is
to just do an overlap test here
where we take a look at that collision
volume
and we make sure we know what's going on
here so you can see here we do a
relative like
nadp volume p test volume p nonsense
this is simpler than we're making it out
to be i think probably
all we really need to do is go if the
person was
standing here and so on so if we look
at the collision volumes the collision
volumes are presumably yeah i don't even
remember
not that
there's a collision volume thing in here
somewhere there it is
so these are just offsets from the
position
of the entity so in theory i think
all we really need to do is say look we
know where this
rectangle would be so uh the test
rectangle
is just going to be uh
whatever the test entity's position is
plus
uh like as an offset right um
of the test entities position and the
test entities collision volume
produces the rectangle in question uh
the rectangle
for the uh vox
like where the player where the
mover would be so like mover wrecked i
don't know we want to call that
is just um taking whatever the
base voxel position is so whatever this
position is on the voxel
and offsetting uh the collision volume
of that now i don't remember much about
the offset function but it looks like
yeah so you just take so it's the volume
first and then the position so it's it's
really it's really that way around
uh and none of this matters that's all
gone so then we just do like
uh inter section
we just use our intersection call to see
whether or not the rectangles intersect
here
uh so presumably we can just call that
on these two so the mover rect and the
test rect
and presumably we can just go from there
so all we need now is to know
what is the base voxel position and
again i think that's
pretty much straightforward it's really
just whatever the vox
it's this right here uh that we were
going whatever we're going to use is the
position
uh from before right
so i'm pretty sure that all we have to
do is take the entity's collision volume
and offset it there and now what we've
done is like point sampled
this collision function um to see
which uh vertices of the voxel
you could place the player on or place
the mover on
and then we just use whatever the
largest
whatever the closest open voxel is and
we place you in there
right and that's all we're doing um
and so that should maybe start to
actually work now
uh but i don't actually know it doesn't
look like oh um
[Music]
i should make sure we're actually
setting this properly so
recommend diminished cell dim closest
point in box
if not occupied this
does offset rectangles intersect then
it's set to talk about okay so this
should
now be working although it doesn't look
like it was so now we have to actually
start debugging it
um like
right because i can punch i can still go
straight through that wall right which i
should not be able to do
um although actually
i guess
yeah so we're actually doing this right
like everything is actually
happening we're calling move entity
locally
we're doing in here we're saying
uh you know place these two things um
all right so why aren't we working we
have voxel bounds min plus oxygen so
that that's the corner of the voxel
uh
that that would be the point where the
player would be standing
so that seems right we're placing the
collision volume there
this is placing the collision line
wherever this entity actually is
right which is what we would expect um
so yeah i can't say i see
why that's not working what i would like
to do
so i'd like to step through here so i
can watch the only problem is
like i'm not sure there's much i can
really
like we kind of need to set up a case
here
[Music]
um
because this is just going to be if we
try to step through it in the real game
it's i think it's going to be too
complicated
right
so there's two different things i'm
thinking one
is i could draw this
which i think i probably want to do
um
[Music]
but the other is i kind of want this to
be something i can test i just need a
case i can step through
where i kind of have some idea of what
should be happening so i can watch
carefully
what actually goes on um
because yeah it sure seems
so let me see i'm curious is this just
always failing out or something too
would be the other thing so
if i prevent motion in the case
so speedrunners you're not welcome does
that stop everyone from moving
yes so basically what's happening here
is we're never actually getting an
unoccupied one of these
it looks like right um
[Music]
appears to be the problem
so if that's the case maybe i can just
step through it directly if it's always
failing i should be able to just look
and see uh
i should be able to just look and see at
that point
what's going on because this should set
this
should be it should be relatively clear
what's going on
at that point
so maybe i just do that um
and we just see what we can see oops
uh entity
and
let's take a look um should be
like in here somewhere right
or does it not i guess it's in the
sim region code i don't know where we
actually put this thing
here probably
yeah uh so
let's just take a look uh at what this
looks like i i should probably be in
debug mode because
we we don't really want to have to deal
with all the
nonsense can't inspect any variables in
debug mode because how would you ever
inspect variables that's just an
unsolved problem in computer science
it's not like the cpu ever computes
those variables or anything
so if we go ahead and look here
to see what is the stuff that's
happening
so from p and 2p so this is an
actual move right which is good that's
what we want
um and if we look at the apron size here
and set up these bounds let's let's take
a look at what the bounce ends up being
um so that's seems fine
like doesn't seem totally ridiculous to
me
uh so the cell dimension what is it
uh cell dimension quite small which is
what we want
uh we're trying to do small
small stuff here so let's see what
voxitter says
voxiter is exactly what we would expect
um
we are going to iterate through these
things here
and see you know we're we're definitely
not getting
like it's not like everything is
suddenly intersecting
oh duh uh
forgot soft bean
yeah yeah yeah how you doing bean do you
wanna say hi
say hi say hi to the camera
no okay don't say hi to the camera then
what are you doing puss
i just i just was to tell people that
there was a bug in here
um did you want to tell them did you
tell them about the bug you can tell
them
you can tell them about the bug you know
okay here tell them about the bug
tell them about the bug
tell them about
you know what it is right do you know
what it is
you already know what the bug is here
come up come up you can come up i know
you want to hang out on my shoulder come
on
tell them what the bug is don't keep
them in suspense
don't keep them in suspense bean
you already know what the bug is don't
you
you're one of the best programming cats
i know
you always know what the bug is you
don't always tell me because you just
all you do is muse sometimes
but you know what it is i bet you do
that's right
here you go tell them what the bug is
can you tell them what the bug is
hmm what do you think
you want to give them a hint
all right that's okay i know
i know everyone needs to learn on their
own if you just told everyone what the
bug was all the time
they would never learn so that's fine
i understand your pedagogical methods
all right you want to sit in my lap what
do you want to do you can't be on my
shoulder for the entire time because i
can't type but you can sit on my lap
if you want to so
that will work if you want to give it a
shot go right ahead
okay so what i was going to say is i
forgot we we literally said this at the
outset
so the problem here is that we have
things that are not
actually motion preventing elements
right
so what we want to do here is say look
we don't actually we don't want you to
actually
prevent motion or collide
if the thing that you're colliding with
doesn't have a flag set that says it
stops motion
right uh so you gotta
we gotta test those flags in here
otherwise you're always gonna be hitting
something like you'll always be hitting
at least the room
boundary marker right um and so
you know that's that's just something we
have to deal with
so what are you doing
what are you doing what are you doing
what's going on
oh come on come on okay
all right
you just want to cuddle you don't want
to do any programming you just want to
hang out
did you just eat your oh you know what
you just ate your dinner didn't i mean
your lunch didn't you
your automated feed or go off you just
had your dry food your today's
your lunch dry food is that what
happened
yeah that's a good girl
that's a good girl
that's a good girl all right
oh you're gonna eat my hair now okay
well
i don't know that we really need you to
do that though
so maybe why don't you just sit there
and i can type in the flags code how
about that
what do you think does that sound good
at all
um okay so yeah
i don't know how we want to do this
exactly because most things that have a
collision to volume probably want to
prevent motion
and it's probably the rarer case that
you have a collision volume that doesn't
want to prevent motion
so i don't know if we actually want to
do the flags the way around that we did
them
we probably want to do it the other way
so that we specify
things that act that don't um or
something like that
you know what i'm saying uh so
you know if if we look at the flags for
entities
i'm just guessing that that's what we
would want to do so maybe like
um maybe this should really be more like
a louse motion on collision that's a
good puss okay puss has settled down now
she's sitting on my arm
which is not the most comfortable thing
for me but it does allow me to type
which is really the important part
so what we'll do maybe is set allows
motion on collision for things
like the room so uh if we look for where
we create the room by tommy wiseau
uh we can set for those types of
entities
things that say look you can just walk
through these right they don't
actually stop you well not walk through
them but you can
uh move smooth movers through them
obviously walking is is done by the
the actual transactional motion system
so it
doesn't care um about these settings but
when we set the thing like the room uh
boundary stuff that would actually do it
so in here where we do add entity
uh right here you can see this
right um what we would want to do is say
like
cam room flags or equals
entity flags allow motion on collision
so that we know that this thing won't
actually stop
other stuff from going and we do have at
least one other one of those
uh so we might as well set that one now
as well which is when we
create things like a conversation
section so like when you go
uh somewhere that you're going to like
um
someone hops onto it uh and and
oh gosh okay you all sat there puss what
are you doing
puss is wrecking havoc uh so
conversation stuff when we add one of
those
those also would like those would not
stop you either
like the glove should be able to move
through those uh cleanly
and so on all right so let's start with
with
those and let's see if that maybe
doesn't change
what's going on in the system at the
moment uh so if in here
um i go ahead and
i test now so in the vox iter stuff
when we when we're going to do these
testing
i'll just do if test entity is not equal
to entity
and uh if there's
not a flag test entity flags
and allow motion on collision because we
we don't want to prevent the motion we
want to potentially trigger an event
in the future so that's the thing we
might want to do
um but we don't actually want to prevent
um the motion when we have those
those hits uh and so now let me just
quick let me run this again to see
whether that changed things at all
um first
uh okay so people can now move as we can
see
and so uh now we're back to actually
working on
uh oh by the way you can see why
proportional derivative controllers are
bad
do you see it how low like at low frame
rates the glove just
just does weird stuff that's because the
there's like the
the weird thing we slapped on there is
like under damped so it's just gonna go
nuts
right um as it keeps moving around
so uh now we get more what we would
expect
uh which is you know we're we're moving
stuff around and we're not getting into
the situation where everything says
that it's occupied so as long as it
doesn't have that allows motion on
collision test
we will allow sorry allow motion on
collision flag
as long as that flag is not set we will
do
a test and we'll set occupied to whether
or not the rectangles intersect
right
okay so now
uh we have to figure out why we're not
getting any
actual stopping of motion which is more
what we would have expected to see so
when nothing moved that was like how
that was kind of weird because it's not
the bug you would expect and it turns
out like well okay yeah that's because
this was always triggering on like the
rooms
boundaries and stuff like that so we
know that
this code at least sort of does
something because it means that when you
do have a large collider nothing was
allowed to move
but it appears that this doesn't really
prevent you from moving through things
for some reason
so we're not quite at the point where
we're actually doing what i think we're
supposed to be doing here
which is preventing motion uh at least
small motions which
you know something like the the floating
familiar head
uh would be doing so we kind of need to
know like what is the deal here like
why are we not um why are we getting an
entire
box that is marked as as movable
in a way that allows you to move through
things like what's going on there
and looking at this i just want to make
sure that this is testing what i think
it's testing
i think it is
also i would note that this is actually
just to clear up what's going on this
only actually gets used in here
right so really all we're doing is we're
just testing these flags
and we're saying all right if
all of these are not occupied so we or
them all together
which means if any of the squares are
occupied
it will be one and then we're knotting
it
so basically all eight corners in this
lookup
have to have said that they were uh
that it was possible to move there right
and so this looks pretty reasonable to
me so i guess i'm
not sure why we're getting nothing
we'll have to step through it uh but
again i'm not sure how to set up a
scenario that will actually produce
um what we want to have happen there so
i kind of want to see do we ever hit
it doesn't look like it really it looks
like you can just punch straight through
so it doesn't really look like it's ever
actually preventing
any types of motion there um
so why would that be why would we not be
seeing at least
some uh
why would we be never seeing any uh
change there right
um and just to make sure i don't
actually know what this
rectangle's intersect thing does but i'm
assuming we're already using it
so we know that it's not completely
busted or something like that as well
which i suppose this thing but let me
just verify
looks reasonable so yeah
not sure what i would most like to do is
draw this out
um so i'm wondering if maybe i just will
so basically like
a way that i can draw out a thing that
shows me
the voxel that was used on a particular
move
um and i can see like
whether what the actual occupied status
is so
for example like if we go
into the uh
entity code and we've got you know
something that push
down uh some of this debug stuff
like push volume outline
and i put one of those in here
for uh the voxel for example
and the problem here is we would need to
actually send down
a render group to this but i'm okay with
that for now
for debugging purposes i also don't know
like we don't have debugging
maybe we do
i'm assuming we don't have any drawing
here
yeah we really should have the our debug
system sucks
frankly um it's one of the worst things
we did on handmade hero
uh just mostly because of focusing on
the wrong things i think
but what are you gonna do um
so anyway what we would like to do here
is the render group
uh if we pass down the render group here
and i just take a look and see like
uh
about pushing down some of these guys so
if we have a rectangle
and we want to draw it uh what i can do
is just draw which cells it thinks
are open for now i don't have a better
idea right but we can just do this and
say look
um go ahead and draw the cells
that you think are open and maybe for
now i'll move this back out here and
we'll just draw them each time
so we would basically do like you know
a cell color equals you know
uh maybe maybe you know green
um and then set it to red or something
like that
if it can't be moved so so like red is
can't go
green is um and then we just do
some nonsense like this
where we
[Music]
you know you know we do that and
i don't know
what's it complaining about um
cell color is the wrong
type and not only that but i'm so in
star code galaxy mode right now
i just have not been thinking um in
terms of floats
the brain just goes in in a direction
right um
so i'm going to pass the render group
here
for debugging and again we just want to
pull this out later
after we're done uh because we don't
actually want
any of this stuff uh to be in there
but for now we want to just do some
drawing in there and so we can just we
can see what what the heck's going on
right
um and so uh my hope
is that like if we zoomed in we could
sort of see like
because i can right you can see it right
you can sort of see
it drawing now those this green streaks
right
um and so like as it moves
you can sort of see that like it's all
green in there like there's no
red even when it probably should be
right so if i
um for example if i place
myself oh so there's actually some red
right there in fact
so it's actually got
that's weird it actually
looks like it's correctly
it actually looks like it's correctly
denying those motions
but then they're still happening
i mean it could be because we're just
not actually subdividing the step and
it's able to tunnel through but it
doesn't look like it like the
the hand is appearing inside here so it
seems like
maybe
i must be thinking through this a little
bit wrong
somehow so
again let me try switching to preventing
moves in the case where nothing is found
weird
so that actually makes the collision
detector
work
right which
makes no sense to me whatsoever
um
because it should always be able to find
its existing point
i guess not when it gets close enough to
something
interesting
i mean
i'm not sure what we want to do about
that
when we add subdivision it may take care
of itself
um but i don't know
that actually works remarkably well now
uh and see do you see the tunneling if i
get up enough speed on this thing
i can tunnel it through which we're
allowing right now because we don't we
never subdivide the move at all
so if the voxel can span it will allow
you to tunnel
which is by design um
that's what we would like it for it to
do
so that's great i mean i'm just testing
this here and it works really nicely
right because i can
so these guys the these things
don't obey any collision detection right
and so you can get the gloves stuck into
it pretty easily
um and uh
so that it you know goes through there
and
and it gets stuck on on stuff which is
what i wanted and it comes back
out which is the main thing that i
wanted to make sure was always happening
right
so you can see now with like really
large
motion steps you can tunnel through
things you can get out of things which
is what i want
right that's what i wanted to see so
that's good
actually um but now
we have to actually go in and say well
okay
but so if i subdivide
uh to to only relatively small motions
the tunneling won't happen anymore and
then we would be left with
basically a correct collision detector i
think
but the only problem is that i kind of
don't like the fact that we default to
non-motion
so if we start subdividing i'm wondering
if
we will be able to do something where we
can fix that
so that we default to being allowed to
move but i'm not sure
but already very promising i really like
what i'm seeing so far
and that's because i can get this thing
stuck by putting it in a place
where it can't move anymore and it it
always comes back out and that's the
main thing i want
um is to make sure that it's that we're
not going to get stuck
right um and so i think that's okay
but like i said i'm nervous that if i
then go to
the subdivision thing so that it can't
take large steps anymore
if the default is can't move then it
might get stuck again
right um so i'm at least a little bit
worried about that
it's it's not it's not
wouldn't be my first choice right um
so i don't know i don't know what to do
about that let's start adding the
subdivision
um i guess
for now um
[Music]
and maybe we'll just call that good
enough but i don't know i may want some
more i just don't know if that's
sufficient
right
um i i just don't know if this is
so so i'm i don't know what i want to
say about that um
that worries me a little so we'll start
though by just doing this
uh desired subdivision part here so
basically we just have a t
value
and all i want to do is i just want to
make sure that we subdivide this
into a reasonable number of steps
uh and so if it's too large
i want to subdivide it i want to like
basically bisect it
uh so that large motions get bisected
into smaller motions
until we get down below um a particular
threshold
and so you know
something along the lines of
let's suppose that we have a
um
a total length
that's whatever the delta p was right
and there's some stuff we want to do
separate from this that's like reverse
engineering the acceleration and the
position
there's this other stuff we wanted yeah
we probably want to be position based
and reverse solve
but that's a separate issue for physics
purposes that
it does nothing to do with collision
detection it's just what we will do at
some point
don't remind me of that we'll take the
total length here
uh and what i want to do is like a max
or like a a step length right
and i want to say that look i don't want
anyone moving more than some
amount whatever that amount is um
and this is probably like some
fundamental constant
like you know uh
physics or like uh
motion displacement size or something
like this
where we say when we're doing this
we've got some fundamental constant
that's like
you know 0.01 or something
and the apron that we use
you know and and maybe it's more like
that
and so the apron that we use is like a
tenth
you know of the motion displacement size
or something like that
i don't know um and then the motion
displacement size
is is this right um
and so we want to do is say how many
steps are we going to have
so we would say like you know the step
count here
is going to be the total length of the
thing
divided by how many steps there should
be
and we know that we want at least one
step count
so however many there are uh we know
that there can't be
less than one step
you know what i'm saying
all right
fine just fine whatever
be that way no one cares about you
uh okay so we're going to go ahead and
say produce a step count
it has to be are you kidding me
there jeez
um so it has to be at least
one and it will be up to
uh the total length divided by the
motion displacement size so if there's a
longer one
like someone's trying to move an entire
unit in one frame we'll actually do 10
subdivisions
that's probably too much so we're
probably gonna make this
not be that large as it is right now
but you know that's a constant we can
tweak based on what we want
um our largest things to be it's so it's
sort of a separate issue
right we don't have to care about that
right now
all right so looking in here where we
get the step count
we would then just say look we're going
to do our step index
and we're going to go through the step
counts
one by one and for each one of them
we're just going to produce
a new desired position and attempt to
move the entity locally from its current
position to
to wherever that is right
um and
i mean i guess we kind of just want to
stop if it can't
so i i mean i guess we kind of really
actually
want to just stop if it can't so we want
to do like
you know we may just want to do
something like this
so we would take the desired position
uh would be
would be the entity's uh original
position
right so so
like
before anybody moved it um
it would be the original position uh
plus the step index over the step count
times the delta that we were trying to
move
right um
[Music]
so that much of the thing we like add in
each time
you know what i'm saying to you uh
so like if the step index uh
and and it's it's gonna be like plus one
because the step index starts at zero so
we wanna
start if their step count was one we'd
wanna move it the whole way
because we're only gonna try once if the
step count is two we wanna start out at
and then try to go to 100 right so we've
basically got a t
on the uh like on the step so we can
compute that
like so and then use that to move
our saucy gentlemen whoever
they are and then what we want to do
is we want to let move entity locally
tell us if it
succeeded if it didn't succeed
then we don't want to keep trying
because there's no
uh point in doing so uh so in here we
just want to say
look if we never hit a positive case
then just give up uh and stop trying
because you're never going to
uh ever get anywhere
um uh beyond that right or you could but
you might tunnel so we don't even want
you to try
might be the better way to say it
um so i think that's what we want there
uh
that is missing a parenthesis i think is
it no it's not i take it back
um what is the problem here
missing but oh yeah well okay i'll give
you that
i'll give you that one uh
so for reasons unknown
that seemed to allow those two to move
on to each other
which is very strange so that actually
seems bad what i just did
and also the glove can't move but the
other dude can
which is very strange oh i guess because
it sunk into the floor
is the problem there
so this is why you can see why i
i wanted that to accept the 2 the 2p
value right um
hmm hmm he says so i'm curious about
uh
other kinds of motion you can see it
having
it's struggling a little bit
so you can see like this dude is
properly not allowed to move
right
and if he were a cylinder he'd glide off
that edge which is why
we want that right
so he's he's probably not allowed to
root you can see the subdivisions
actually chugs the frame right there
right but the problem that we're going
to have here
is just like okay so at that point
the subdivision for the motion is
down to a level where it really doesn't
allow
the glove to like get out of
interpenetration
so i don't know what we want to do about
that
[Music]
um
that's a tough one
i'm also at least a little weirded out
by
how many steps that seems to have been
taking
because this really should not happen
that much
in my opinion
because people should not be moving that
fast
um i'm going to get rid of the push
volume outline there
uh since that is generating a bunch of
stuff but like
it's really kind of remarkably
hitting performance i wonder if i did
something weird there because there's
not that
many like there's a lot of chugging
going on there
right which suggests that we're sort of
subdividing this thing a lot which
doesn't make a whole lot of sense to me
like you see how harsh that is
right um
so that's a bit strange and i'm
wondering why there would be something
trying to do that much
like like what is this step count
actually getting up to
such that we're seeing that now granted
like i said there's no spatial partition
so
it's looping over all the entities for
those collision detection cases so it
should be slow
but i mean look at that
look right off the bat it hit one
where it was trying to take a step of 10
right um and motion displacement
size is 0.1 so
that's suggesting that on on one frame
right it was trying to go a distance of
one unit on that frame alone
which seems a little bit broken um
and so i'm just curious to know like who
is that like who is doing that and why
so let me go ahead and see maybe i've
got something stupid in the code here
um also i think we're out of time so i
should probably stop because
we did mostly we want to do today which
was rewrite that routine to get us into
a better position
for doing stuff but yeah it's kind of a
separate issue
um so let's see like what's the step
count here 15
uh oops so it's trying to move 1.5
which is nuts
um that's just nuts we need uh it's it's
a floating guy so we need some
limits on how much these people are
supposed to be moving right that's just
really crazy um
and you know we could artificially cap
it so we could just say
look the step count here is
you know
is only five uh and so we'll just say
like to do casey
uh look into capping
more directly
right because we don't really know how
we want to do this but but
that is way too much and so that means
someone's asking for unreasonably large
moves which makes sense because we just
slap some springs on some
like you know it makes sense that that
kind of nonsense is happening
but let's just take that out of the
equation for now
um so we'll see uh
we'll see if that's any better and now
but
you know we still don't have any any
real plan and so this is our thing to
think about for next week
how do we want to start progressing a
little bit better on this routine
for how we deal with the like startup
and shutdown cases there because
since right at the moment we're only
doing that still seem too slow
um yeah there's still way too much
lagginess there
which granted might just be because hey
it loops over all the things
um so it could just be because hey this
doesn't have a spatial partition
we need a spatial partition so you know
it could be that
um
but we'll see sorry
uh let's go to brief q a
why would you cpu absolutely the render
is done by gpu uh it's lighting
is the is the main link the reason um
we do the lighting on the cpu side right
now
if we didn't do that if the lighting was
disabled
so like if you know if we went into the
lighting and just say you don't have to
do lighting
so you know um
so in here somewhere we just said
you know like that um
then we would we wouldn't have to worry
about it uh
i hate unreachable code warnings because
they
i want a way to just say like returning
yes i know
like i know it's a re it's
yes like like we all know it like thank
you so much for your help
um but you know they can't do that or
whatever
so
here
so if you like nerfed the lighting um
and so you were just doing this right
uh then if we
switch this to debug mode you you
wouldn't probably have
a whole lot of need for it um but
you know i don't know we'll see so
uh or not
so it looks like we still are pretty
slow i'm not so i'm not sure where
that's coming from
we could run the profiler and see
[Music]
so what's the actual slow part uh
it could be also in our debug our
super crappy debug system which i
suppose is also an issue but
um let's take a look
at who that is
so here we are um
[Music]
so update and render entities
is the other big frame time
uh and i guess we don't really know it
could even be the thing that we just
wrote
that is the problem there but who knows
so
if we took out some of that stuff we
could we can maybe start to see
like maybe i can go in there and to move
entity and say like is the stuff we're
working on now
which is crappy um you know
is that something we could uh that is a
problem
timed function
isn't that supposed to just work what is
the problem with timed function
all right um i don't know yet to what
extent move entity is now a problem
uh because we're doing all this voxel
stuff in there but we can take a look
yeah so it's it's what we're doing now
is part of the problem although
update and render entities is also kind
of slow
so all the crap that's going on in there
is not great
um so like if you imagined
uh you nerfed this out so you just said
like
ndp plus equals delta p
and this went away
so you don't have that loop over all the
entities anymore
then you run in debug mode and uh
now we're down to just the updated
render entities call
i think
compute light propagation work i have to
turn off
um and so now like our update and render
entities call is still kind of crappy
right um because you can see like here's
us not calling that
and we're running along at 60 frames a
second right
and then uh as soon as we actually start
in the game though it's it drops down
quite a bit
so you can see here like you know
this is totally playable though you
could play at this frame rate
and be fine um
so actually yeah like it's it's mostly
just the lighting and the collision
now the collision will get much faster
as we work on it
so that we could probably just define
but the lighting there's nothing
like the lighting is what it is so that
as long as the lighting stays cpu side
we need optimization there
and there's not much we can really do
about that right that's just how it is
um so yeah
doesn't the orig p need to be updated
each step
um no i don't think so
so if you look at how this this loop is
working
it basically says look i'm gonna go from
where i was and i'm gonna move
the percentage of the requested delta
that is the step i'm on
right so it's always starting at the
start point
and moving some percentage of the delta
going from zero percent
well going from some fractional percent
to one
to one hundred percent over the course
of this loop
right um and i did it that way on
purpose i didn't wanna
keep adding small vectors together
because if you do that you may end up
again in numerical precision land
where it doesn't actually work correctly
so