ok hello everyone and welcome to hand
made here on the show we code a complete
game live on stream no engines no
libraries we cover at the complete
complete range of game development here
nothing is left out of the process so to
matter what part of game development you
are interested in we will cover it that
is a guarantee that is just how we do
things here and right now we are working
on sound mixing we have already written
our sound mixer we have already written
some features for the sound mixer such
as sound streaming we have already done
volume interpolation we've done a lot of
stuff in the past week it's been it's
been a whirlwind it's true but what we
have not done yet is allowed the person
playing the sound the person requesting
or cueing a sound we played to be able
to set the frequency of that sound right
so what we would like to do is we would
like to have some ability for the
frequency of the sound to be changed
dynamically and let's talk a little bit
about why you might want to do that so
if you think about what happens in a
game right so typically you know this
this is sort of here we are on day 143
so let me just put a little title up on
there so if you think about what happens
in a game a lot of times what we're
talking about when we're talking about
playing with sounds is a lot of times
there are sort of triggers or events or
periodic ambient events even that are
trying to create some kind of an effect
to reinforce an activity or an action
right in a game and so examples of this
might be you know I've got a little dude
you know and the little dude is running
around and whenever he jumps up into the
air you know we want to play a jump
sound or something like this or whenever
his feet touch the ground we want to
play a footstep sound right and so we've
got all of these things that
are being sort of fed into the sound
system and the sound system is supposed
to play sounds that reinforce these
things that are going on and it's true
even in ambient sense maybe you're in a
place you know with with a tree or
something like this right you know kind
of the world's worst tree here all right
don't plate okay you know what just
forget there's not a tree I lied about
that there's some kind of ambient thing
going on I was gonna say like branches
crackling or something but the tree was
so ugly that I felt I had to come back
from that you know what here we go let's
let's let's go with a pine tree that
should be a little easier on the on the
art skills there so you know we've got a
little tree here and the tree is going
to like sway back and forth and so we
want to do is place them like branches
crackling as well right so that's not
really an active thing that's that's
necessary happening but we've got like
sort of this forest theme and there's
going to be some branches crackling
branch and sounds or something right so
all of these things are going into the
sound system and of course in a perfect
world we would just have some way of
generating a footstep sound all the time
that was unique and different and
interesting and all these other things
but the reality of game development is
it often times there's a fixed budget
and that budget may be determined by how
much you can afford to pay to have the
sounds created that budget may be
dictated by how long it takes to process
the sounds and put them into production
use or something like this it may be
based on how much room you have on a
console for storing the sounds it may be
based on your download equipment there's
all kinds of reasons why you can't just
have eight billion footstep sounds
unless of course you're the witness and
dedicate your entire budget footsteps
downs but most of the time you talk
about limited space so maybe you have
five footstep sounds let's say right for
running on a particular thing like grass
right so I have grass footsteps and I
have five grass footsteps well if I have
five graphs footstep sounds and I play
them over and over again so as the guys
running he's taking you know you know at
least two or three steps a second did it
right i am going to hear the same grass
footsteps sound many many
times a minute right and that that sort
of repetitive nature of that sound can
get very grating especially in a
circumstance where you're trying to
create a realistic sounding soundscape
as opposed to perhaps a gamey sounding
soundscape like you know if you were
trying to evoke an old arcade game this
would not be concerned because they were
supposed to have repetitive sounds if
you're trying to evoke a realistic
outdoor scene of some kind or some like
this not so good right and so one of the
things we could vary would be the volume
certainly because our mixer has the
ability to vary the volume so at least
then we add a little more variability as
the footsteps go there's some very
instant volume so addition to five
different footstep sounds that might
trigger on this grass we have some
volume but what would be nice is if we
had a little more range to play with
there and so that's really where
frequency modulation I'm pretty much is
good frequency modification comes in
where we can sort of pitch shift our
footsteps a little bit up you know a
couple half steps or down a couple half
steps or semitones as they're called not
talking about huge frequency shifts here
but we're just talking about if a sound
is a particular pitch maybe pitch
shifting it up a little bit pitch
shifting it down just a little bit right
we'd like to have that in there as
another way to get variability out of
our sound state and in some cases we may
even tie that variability to something
in the game that the player can proceed
so for example maybe you know a boss
monster as you hit them and they take
more damage the frequency of the impact
goes down or up so you can hear a little
bit of feedback as to how you hit them
or who knows right you can think of
reasons why in addition to just creating
a less repetitive soundscape that
frequency can be a nice easy way for you
to put more interactivity into the
soundscape than if all you had was
volume right and so these two things are
pretty nice things to have in a mixer
all told and they're pretty easy things
to add so that's why I focus them on
them as things that I think if you were
talking about a sound system it's
probably worth your while to implement
these because you'll get a lot of
mileage out of them that other things
you might not get very much mileage out
of such as like all kinds of advanced
filters or something like this because
you may just not have a lot of cases to
use them but I think almost every game
pretty much uniformly can get a lot of
mileage out of volume and frequency to
be sure so I guess what I'm saying is
there bang for the buck is pretty high
so okay so if we have a sound right
we've talked about how the distance
between peaks in the sound right so
basically this wavelength here right
this is the wavelength of the sound if
you will this sort of peak to peak
measurement you could also think of a
half wavelength as being like peak to
trough or something the speed at which
that is occurring in time right this is
time determines the pitch of the sound
right so it doesn't really even matter
what the crazy waveform is it's the
speed of the oscillations contained in
that waveform and there may be many of
them overlapping right we discussed the
fact how they add but those overlapping
oscillations are what your ear perceives
as pitches each individual one having
certain pitches and there's pitches that
evolve over time and so on so what we
want to do if we want to change the
pitch of a sound is we want to speed up
or slow down the rate of those
oscillations so the distance between
these two things we want in time to
become shorter right or longer and if it
becomes longer that will shift it down
in pitch and if it becomes shorter that
will shift it up to pitch that's just
fundamentally how the sound worked as we
discussed on the episode where I
introduce sound a couple days ago so as
I said on that episode and I'll just
remind you quickly of it won't belabor
the point here there are a couple
different ways to do this some of them
are very very expensive and they're
designed for purposes where you're
trying to do large-scale pitch changes
without changing the amount of time the
sound actually takes right so you have a
sound that's one second long in duration
when it's a certain pitch and you want
to shift it up in pitch but have it take
the same amount of time okay that's a
fairly complex operation
there's multiple ways of doing it the
traditional signal processing ways and
wavelet ways are kind of crappy there's
newer ways now such as like cylindrical
resampling and stuff like this that are
way way better but sort of less
well-trod but point being they're very
much more complicated they're much more
involved than what we're doing they're
not prohibitively so but they're much
more involved thankfully you don't
actually need any of those for the kinds
of pitch shifts we are talking
about we're talking about just minor
pitch changes and for minor pitch
changes we don't care if the sound gets
a little longer a little shorter because
it'll still be roughly you know if it
took a second now maybe it takes 1.1
seconds we don't really care we'd only
care if the footstep sounds sounds a
little bit longer right because you
really won't perceive that difference in
practice you'll just hear the pitch
being a little bit different so for that
what we're going to do here is totally
fine which is just playing the sound
itself back faster or slower and so
fundamentally the thing that we have to
do is you know we've got a sound that's
represented digitally so you know we're
saying that this move wave form but
actually right we only really know about
the waveform as a series of sample
points where it crosses fixed slices
oops in time right and we're sort of
thinking about it just as these samples
these are the samples of the sound right
we have a sample buffer right it's
filled with in 16s those in six teens
are encoded by thinking about where a
waveform passes through vertical lines
and time instants in time at this
instant in time where would the waveform
be those go into our sound buffer that
is our sound we play back what that
means is that if we want to play back
the sound at a different rate we do not
have the luxury of simply resampling
this curve at whatever rate we want
because we do not know what the curve
actually is we don't have the curve we
just have samples
those samples do not represent an actual
curve they represent just a piecewise
linear sort of approximation of that
curve right if we looked at them this
way it's only once they are
reconstructed by a speaker that they
turn into something that approximates
the actual oscillating sounds and there
are artifacts even that happened when
you do that given the fixed sampling
frequency and that gets into a lot of
signal processing kind of nonsense that
we probably don't need to cover here and
I'm the wrong one to talk about it
anyway because I am far from a signal
processing guy but the point is looking
at this function right all we really
have is this piecewise linear version of
it that's all we know and so you know if
we wanted to do a smooth resampling of
it as if it was a curve we'd have to try
and guess about what that upsampling
might look at and there's actually ways
you can do some things because it is
sound where you can up sample in
slightly better ways but since we are
pitch shifting such a small amount it
actually is fine for our purposes to
assume that we have this piecewise
linear version and just resample at the
peace lies points now I know signal
processing people are probably horrified
at that because it's not really the
signal processing Lee pure way to do it
but again for small pitch shift it works
really well it's very very quick and
easy to write the code for it so it's
good for a real-time mixer that we don't
want to spend a lot of time we don't
want to take a lot of CPU time doing its
work it's pretty handy for that so what
we want to do now in the code is rather
than playing back sounds by just
outputting those fixed slices in time
like we were doing before we would like
to make something where we can actually
do a lot basically the same thing we did
with the bilinear filtering in the end
images like we did for our rasterizer we
want to do the same thing here only
because we only have one dimensional
data instead of two dimensional data
instead of a bilinear filter it's just a
straight linear filter so you remember
for pixels we were trying to interpolate
between four corners right we were
trying to say like we want this and so
what we did is we interpolated to here
and here
first and then we interpolate it between
those two to get this that's why it's
called a bilinear filter right is
because there's two right there's two
steps first we do a filter to produce
new points and then we do a new one
right it's like it's two stages of a
linear filter rather than a single stage
this we only have two things to begin
with so we're just talking about
straight linear filter we're just doing
that first one and you remember I said
at the beginning of the series I'll say
it again that you know p prime equals 1
minus T p0 plus tp1 that Universal blend
linear blend equation that comes up over
and over and over again i think i said
something like if you only had one
equation that you could take with you to
a desert island for programming it is
the one because man it is just the
building block of everything in games
that we do because it is a perceptive
medium and linear blending does so many
important things for people's perception
of what's going on so you know that is
that is really the thing it's going to
come back here because we're doing
exactly that same thing that first step
this blend right here we're just doing
the same exact thing for sound so what
we want to do is be able to produce a
floating-point version of where we
believe ourselves to be in the sound we
want to do the exact same thing we were
doing with the bilinear filter where we
floor and ceiling it to get the two
locations that we would like to talk
about right we will then figure out what
the samples are at those two locations
and interpolate between them based on
the fractional amount that's left over
after doing that that floor operation
okay so that's really what we're talking
about that's all we're trying to do and
so what we want to do is make that
happen and again nothing at like
literally zero nothing that we do here
will be different from what we already
did in the rasterizer it's just a
simpler case because now we're instead
of having to do square blends we're
doing just lying blends
so once we have that once we have the
ability to take a sample at an arbitrary
place in a sound rather than having to
only take samples at these predefined
points then we have the complete freedom
to change the speed at which the sound
plays back because instead of doing
something where like T plus equals one
sample right basically every time we can
just do t plus equals you know X samples
where X is any value like 1.2 0.9
whatever we want right and so that will
allow us to change the pitch of the
sound by changing its duration and again
if we just keep that to a pretty limited
range of pitch bending then we won't
really hear any objectionable problems
to that because the length of the sound
won't be changing appreciative
appreciably all right so let's get
started again today is day 143 so if you
would like to follow along at home with
the source code if you have pre-ordered
the game on handmade hero org you should
be able to download the source zip
inside there is all the days and so day
143 is what we're on today unzip day 142
as the source code and that is what I've
got here so if you want to match up with
me that's what you want to use okay
let's get rid of that let's get a
command prompt up here and all right so
let's go ahead in here and start by yeah
loading up our audio mixer and taking
stock of where we are at so the first
thing we could do right to get started
with this is that if you remember what
we did in the case of the violin you're
blending for rasterization you remember
the first thing we did is just not do it
instead of doing bilinear to make that
nice smooth effect that doesn't so you
don't see the oval crispy little jumpy
lines and stuff we just first started
out with saying you know what doesn't
matter let's just do a point sample
we'll just sample it at the nearest
place
and we'll just use that to get things
started and then we implemented by
linear to make a nice smooth clean
version after that so we can do the
exact same thing here what we can do is
we can start by actually writing it so
that we do use the floating point
location in the sound to pick where we
are reading from so we can change its
speed overall but we will just pick the
closest sample rather than actually
interpolating and that should in theory
anyway lead to some objectionable
artifacts that we could hear you know
maybe it will maybe well it depends on
the sound certainly but hopefully we can
hear them and then we can implement the
linear filtering which will take them
away okay so let's go ahead and do that
let's go ahead and take our handmade
audio here and say that a playing sound
sample played first thing we're going to
do is upgrade that instead of being an
in 32 which is the sample count we are
actually going to make that a real 32 so
it knows kind of where it is in the
samples more specifically right so let's
go ahead and fix sort of the the
warnings that we will get there so in
terms of samples remaining in sound all
we have to do there is do our round real
32 2 in 32 right in this place which
will round out that samples and then the
same thing would be true here right i
drowned it out again there we go and you
know I could do something as well like
first sample oops s32 first sample index
and that sample index I could just take
this way first sample index like so and
then down here first sample index and
since it only gets updated at the very
end right it should not be a problem so
samples played is never touched anywhere
else right so it should be all good
right
and this guy needs to use it as well so
okay so if i do that nothing should
change we should still have the same
thing we had before right oh good so now
what we want to do is say all right
let's allow that to be modified by some
other amount than just one person so if
we do that what we need to do in here
right we can no longer just say sample
index and this for I loop obviously is
going to look a little bit different
right so we actually want to do here is
we want to say that the sample index now
is actually going to be a real 32 right
and what we want to do is just go ahead
and take that out now I guess I probably
should have not actually pulled it out
here I thought I was doing a helpful
thing that doesn't look like I actually
was anyway we have real 32 the sample
index we want to go ahead and make sure
that that stays kind of looking within
bounds there so we're going to still
clamp it that way and then when we do
our sample index what we'd like to do
here is we'd like to do an accumulator
I'm going to move it out of the for loop
just for now I'm going to put it down
here so when we can see that we do
volume we can also do d sample right and
then d sample is something we can just
set for the now to equal to 1 point 0
and that should be good so now what we
need to do is figure out what sample
index were actually on and so this is
going to be something more like this is
like a sample position really right it's
not really a sample index anymore at the
sample position and so the sample index
is actually going to have to come from
doing that round right and then we
actually have a sample enix that we can
use to look things up now oops get that
there so now if I play again hopefully
it's the same
and you know what I wonder if we can I'd
like to have the sound keep playing for
now at least while we're in debug mode
when i switch back to the editor because
since we have live code editing it's
it's I want to be able to hear it when
we change things I wonder if we can just
tell windows into platform layer to not
maybe do that you know as as much I'm
not really sure let's see about the
primary buffer what we what did we say
in there I guess is there some way to
set it to a cooperative level you know
maybe this this could be set to
something else I feel like maybe that
has something to do with it I don't
remember this stuff off hand but let
boobs that's not what we want ah let's
see let's see let's feature so that this
this is not so you'll be muted with this
level sir but yeah so so this is not I
wonder what we can say to just have it
play a little bit more nicely with what
we're doing because I would like it to
to not keep forcing us to shut forcing
our application to not output sound in
the case where you know it wouldn't work
I don't know let's see if we can see
your direct sound output when not
focused let's see let's see yeah yeah
it's looking like it might take a little
bit more while or I could go read some
of my own source code to see what
actually happens in there I guess that's
not to be done right now because I'm
afraid that I'll just be a rat hole that
will go down so maybe what we can do is
let's just say i will try also i'm
wondering if i should try just setting
it to normal for now just to see what
happens nope so it has nothing to do
with that anyway so yeah so we'll have
to take a look in DBS caps global focus
I wonder why we've got it to do on that
was that like a hint to our future
selves
let's see and I'll continue to place
buffers if the user switches focus to
another application even if the new
application uses direct sound so DBS
caps global focus it looks like we did
kind of do a hint to ourselves about
that so I wonder if we want to to do
that well doesn't look like it worked
anyway so that's that doesn't perhaps
matter as much but yeah because this is
a oh this is the d/s buffer oh but
that's not
no it is it is it is that I assume
create some buffer set format just gives
current position so that's but that's a
buffer description so I wonder if maybe
we can take a look at it a little bit
more specifically here let's take a look
at this structure Jamar guess we'll have
to get it off Google servers their flags
yeah so so that should have done it i
guess but it looks like maybe global
focus what does it say here the one
exception is if you switch focus directs
on application that uses the dsl right
primary flag in this case level sounds
for lockers will not be audible so it
sounds like that should have worked
right with this flag set and application
is rex on kitty to play so i feel like
that should have worked maybe we need to
set it on the secondary buffer as well
but I don't that seems a little odd but
I mean we could try that as well and
then I guess we'll just give up for now
and take it offline
aha so I guess setting it on the
secondary buffer works i wonder if i can
remove it from the primary buffer then
we can all right so i'm going to go
ahead and say that right here i'm going
to say to do in release mode should we
not specify that so that we don't play
sounds unnecessarily i wonder if we
should do that in fact what we could do
here is something like pound if a
handmade internal right and in the case
where we know it's an internal build we
will go ahead and order that in so that
we can play sound all the time alright
so that didn't take too long sometimes
windows things could be a bit of a rat
hole certainly but yet
alright so since we have loop live code
editing we can kind of play around with
this stuff I guess since it's sound we
don't even have to see it so maybe
that's fine too I don't even need to
play with the play with be a vmax window
to get into position so let's go ahead
and and take a look at what we need to
do here to be able to change d volume to
something else right so the problem it
here that we have if i want to change
this let's say I want to change us up to
double speed right one of the problems
that we have with changing it for double
speed is samples remaining in sound is
not going to be correct anymore because
this assumes a particular rate right so
what we really want to do is we really
want to do this math in in a little bit
a little bit different way like you know
sample time remaining or something like
or float sample remaining and sound or
something like this right where we first
compute what it would actually be if
they were playing one at a time but then
we take into account the D sample so how
long you know will it take given how
fast we're moving through it to compute
a different amount because this loop
will be incrementing by D sample not by
one so we want to go ahead and divide by
D symbol to find out how long it will
actually take us to go when we get our
sample remaining right and then we can
round that up to figure out what that
would be an actual term sample space now
there's some edge condition stuff that
we're going to happen think about
but after the moment we don't have to
work that too much right define an r32
by the way I'm really digging this new
more concise version I for people who
don't like it I'm afraid it's gonna stay
I think it's going to stay I've been
liking it at work I've been liking it
here this set right here is way better
than my old set so I'm feeling I'm
feeling it that makes sense it's always
so funny uh-oh it didn't like that so I
oh you know what um so here's an
interesting thing that we have not
addressed yet and we should probably put
this on the to do this we really don't
have to worry about it now but I wanted
to mention it so one thing that we
haven't done with the loop live code
editing is now that we have multiple
threads working those threads are in the
dll that's going to get unloaded and so
we have to make sure all the threads
have spun down before we reload our live
code which we are not currently doing
and so that's you know again doesn't
create a problem for the game because
the users will never experience a crash
because of that because they're not
developing the code and live editing it
but we are and so one thing we might
want to do here is put in something like
Mick you know blush all thread queues
before reloading DOL right and that is
the thing that we will hit occasionally
we haven't hit it very often but you
know it's totally plausible
so yeah so let's take a look here and
here my audio let's slow this down a bit
so that sounds a little bit wrong to me
even modulo the artifacts that will come
from not sampling so I think we've got
some bugs in the computation here so I'm
just going to go through this a little
bit carefully before we move on to the
linear blend that's just intuition on my
part it just sounds all more wrong than
I'm expecting it to sound from having
done this sort of thing before so that's
there's really no way otherwise if you
were drinks for the first time you
wouldn't know you could be like well
maybe that's for the linear blend and
then you put in labor and anyway be sure
but uh so if I take a look here we've
got the sample position it starts at
samples played and the sample position
that gets added by D sample every round
right we round it in to figure out we
round what the sound position is there
oh but our update also has to take you
to do the proper thing here for sample
position so samples played should
actually be set to sample position right
at the end of the day so what we
probably want to do here is do something
more like this where this is a while
loop right and they go through the
sample positions like so and now when
we're done with that loop we can just
use sample position directly so that
will be correct
you
so still a little bit odd like it has
that very odd breaking point up around
1.4 where it starts to be more than one
sample so I feel like we've got some
kind of a nasty like I don't think I'm
quite still doing it right right right
around that rounding threshold so we got
the D sample let's let's walk through
the code once and see what I'm missing
and if we can't see anything that we're
missing let's drop down to the bugger
and step through it and see if we can
see what's going on so uh right now we
make sure that samples played has to be
greater than or equal to 0 because we're
not allowing pre queued sounds yet but
like we said in the future maybe we will
first sample index is just something
that we're trying to use to figure out
how many more samples we have to go so
we're taking a sample count- that for a
sample index since that's not a reused
value I can actually go ahead and and
now make that be something that just
happens in line here like so so that's
good get rid of that so we start out
thinking that we're going to mix all the
samples in the buffer we then say how
many samples are there left in the sound
will the number of samples that there
are left in the sound is going to be
however many samples are actually left /
how fast we're going through them right
so you know if it was 2 point 0 that
means we would get through it and twice
the time so there'd be half as many
samples remaining to actually pull from
right we would then round that to figure
out what the actual number is in the
future we'll probably it you know do
something a little more fancy there
because rounding is not really super
appropriate necessary haven't thought
through what happens at the end
condition there but for now it should be
fine we then say if the number of
samples that we were going to mix is
greater than that number we use that
number as the
were to actually try to mix the volume
we're not actually interpolating yet so
this should not be having any effect and
furthermore it is doesn't run on the
sample clock anyway it has its own d
volume so in theory this should not be
really related at all right meaning we
should be able to ignore that loop
pretty much completely we then go ahead
and check the sample position again we
say let's start where we thought we were
going to start let's go until we hit
samples to mix more samples ah that's
not that's not correct though right
because that's the place that we would
get two samples to mix has been pre sort
of determined that's not actually what
we wanted to do right in fact we could
just use the original value there if we
were going to use that what we actually
want to do here right if sample position
is actually getting updated in in its
own space so if we wanted to loop over
the number of samples we were supposed
to fill I would need you know I would
need a different value so it's almost
just a pure loop index at this point
which kind of suggested me maybe I've
architected this loop a little bit wrong
you know what I mean but who knows
alright so let's say we do that plus
plus loop index like so so now we know
we will actually go over the number of
samples to mix and then again we're
still using sample position each time
and we're updating that by d samples so
all that is the same but we're just
controlling the number that we're doing
so then after we get out of that we
update the volume obviously which is
fine and and check to see if we have to
stop any volume ramping then we update
the place that we are in the samples
played by you know using whatever the
samples thing was and we then remove the
number of samples that we mixed from the
total samples and we continue on our way
so let's take a look at that and see if
that's a little bit more sane
right pretty good right alright so again
not particularly complicated allows us
to change the pitch we can't change the
pitch without changing the speed but we
don't really care about that too much so
we're pretty good there there's not
really a lot more that we need to really
address the only thing that I said I
think we might want to do is get the
bilinear filtering in there just in case
I'm sorry the linear filtering in there
just in case that smooths out a bit as
you could hear it really was didn't
sound all that odd even just with the
rounding so we're not really in a
position to be super concerned about
that but since it's pretty easy for us
to implement maybe let's drop it in and
how would we do that we do that exactly
the same way as we were doing it before
right all we're going to do is say when
we actually do this here let's go ahead
and floor assume we have that in our
thing right floor real 32 so what I want
to do is I want to floor that sample
position right to get the sample index
is and then what I want to do is take a
look at that fractional part 2 right so
we've got the fractional sample position
that's going to be whatever the sample
index was that we actually computed out
here it's going to it's going to be the
original sample position minus that so
that'll give me just the fractional part
right that fractional part will now be a
number between zero and one that we can
use to do the bilinear sample so what we
can do is we can take a look at both
sample index and sample index plus 1
right and in order to do that we just
need to say okay you know we've got two
samples they're both s sixteens right so
we've got sample zero and we've got
sample
and which is the exact same thing just
plus one and once we've pulled those two
out really all we have to do is up
convert those two real 32s and then so i
guess i could probably just do it like
this write-up convert them from essex
teens to real 30 tues once I have them I
just need to blend them together by that
fractional position and we've already
we've done this a million times we know
exactly how we would do that right in
fact I think we even have a linear blend
in our math thing that we can use if we
just want to use the exact same thing
lerp right here it is so if we want to
lurk between those things linear
interpolation here we go let's take
sample zero let's go the fractional
distance to sample one and that will
become the sample value right and so we
can even make this be kind of like an a
you know an if sort of thing right we
could do something like this where we
still leave in the old paths as well so
you know if we want to be able to a be
compared them just for our own
edification at any given time we could
do that right so here we are playing
sounds let's say we're going to play the
sounds that some reasonable Delta
something like what we might actually
want to do not something super
ridiculous
of course that's going to rear its ugly
head occasion
you
I'll be honest I can't tell the
difference I cannot tell the difference
between those two uh yeah I don't know
that's uh that's a tough one so you know
we could do it we could not do it I
can't really hear the difference we may
need to get two other sounds at some
point to actually be able to tell the
difference I don't hear really any
artifacts in the other one either so
that's that's kind of rough but it may
just be because it's the wrong sound for
it honestly so there's that but honestly
that's just about it right that is
pretty much the end of it in terms of
capabilities that we really actually
need in the sound mixer this d sample
here we can read right out of our out of
our sound so one of the things we
probably want to do is have the sample
be in here on the sound so that when you
play a sound you set that D sample to
whatever speed you want to actually play
the sound at we could also have that be
something that you know you could pass
in here as well but you know not just
just not a little just really not much
that has to happen there so we've got
change pitch and we've got the audio
state the playing sound it would just be
basically like a deep it d sample or
something like that for now maybe we can
come up with a better way to phrase
those in the future but you know really
they're talking about that right so
that's mostly it like honestly they're
really just isn't a lot more to it
there's maybe some edge case stuff that
we want to look out there when we drop
this down to Cindy and we can like just
make sure the I's are dotted in the T's
are crossed but again that's the code
for a real-time streaming sound mixer
with pitch shifting and volume animated
volume right not a lot of code just not
a lot of code it's a very very simple
thing
so that's really all there is to it yeah
so I don't think there's really anything
else to do there we've got about 10
minutes left so I think maybe you know
let's let's just ute since we were
getting to that point where we want to
use the live code editing and it feels
like the fact that that's going to cause
problems with the threaded reload could
could easily make us grumpy right I'm
wondering if maybe now would be a good
time for us to to make sure that that
flushing stuff actually works right so
if we have the thread props here we know
what the cues actually are so what we
could maybe do is do some kind of a
win32 complete all work to force the
cues to flush themselves out entirely
before we actually do anything else
right let's just take a look at that
really quickly right so when i do the
load the load game code right let's see
and through the low income if compared
file time so win 32 unload game code i'm
just going to go in there to win third
you unload game code and i'm going to
say that maybe when we do the unload
game code we well and I just I don't
know is the right thing to do to do it
in there probably not maybe that's a
stupid idea so maybe what I want to do
here is say okay right here we do the
flush right so we've got the 2 q's right
we've got the Q's right here so maybe
what we want to do is just win through
to complete all work on the high
priority queue win32 complete all work
on the low priority queue and and see if
that helps our situation right
so here we go I let's go ahead and
change these values like we're looking
for okay so that did not help us let's
take a look at what we're getting here
as a problem so the problem is that it's
having trouble okay so this is actually
just a string this is actually just a
string problem right this is actually a
problem that has very little to do with
with what I was just talking about I
guess we were being kind of overly
overly cautious there so the problem
with that is that file name was invalid
right and we already talked about this
when we implemented the LiveCode ending
we said that file names wouldn't like
strings that were embedded wouldn't work
right so when we actually build up this
asset table normally this wouldn't be a
problem because that would be loaded in
as data which would persist it wouldn't
be part of the code but our test code
here actually has the problem because
the test code itself right has the
strings in it so it's not a problem that
would actually hit us once we get our
assets as I'm working but until the
asset system actually I'm sorry not that
system obviously asset systems working
at what everything's going through the
asset file actually defined and using
the data from it these strings will be a
problem so what we can do if we want to
write is we could just say that those
things are going to get loaded that are
going to get copied into our arena right
so wherever we have a care estar here we
could just go ahead and and copy it
because we've got the the two places
where it's used add sound info and an ad
bitmap info we those are the only places
that we would really have to deal with
it right so when we set the info file
name we could just have like push string
right in fact we already write a push
string
we did not write a push string so here
we go beeline void ops are in line Cara
star push string like so and then note
Casey this is generally not for
production use this is probably only
really something we need during testing
but who knows and here is the string to
push and then we just need the memory
arena that you want it to go into right
and so what we'll do here is we'll just
say that you know we've got that assets
arena right we've got this one here so
we can we can say that we want to use
the assets arena to push the file name
and then that would take care of that
problem because now they would be stored
in our datastore rather than in the
unload of all section that Pat gets
reloaded so when we do our put string
the only thing that we need to change
about the way we were doing things we
can just do a push size right to get the
string that we actually wanted so we can
actually just say okay we want to push
something of the string length size
right and then we want to or I shouldn't
say string length but I should just I'll
just say sighs and then the alignment
can remain the default alignment and
then what we would do is we would just
copy the characters right so we would
say like care index equals 0 care index
is less than string length you know or i
should say size plus plus care index and
then we would just do this guy right
here is the desk string this would be
the source the desk gets pushed on and
then we just do desk care index equals
source / index right so all we need to
do is determine this size and the size
obviously is of a null-terminated string
unfortunately there's no way to get that
size without looping through it now
if this were production if I was
anticipating actually using this guy
more there's actually a trick you can do
here to avoid the double loop i'll
mention it briefly so if you look here
like we've got this thing passed him we
want to know how long it would be so
what I what I would actually typically
do is you know something like this right
terraced are at equal source well it's
not know we loop over and for every
character there we add size to it and
and obviously we also want to include
the null terminator so we would set the
size to always be one at the start to
include that in el terminator but what
you would do if you wanted to be able to
do this without the two loops because
you know you're pushing into a memory
arena in the single threaded context
what you can do is just start actually
pushing the characters into the arena
right um ah what the heck do you want to
do it I don't know maybe we should just
do it now it's it's not worth it hey but
point being the memory Tory sitting
there so you can just start copying it
in and then you can avoid the double
loop that's that's all I was going to
say right so hopefully you can see why
that's interesting potentially in some
circumstances right so yeah so anyway
that's all we really need to do there I
think we should probably test that
routine for spring but when we come in
here
hey what oh why did we never call push
string did I not an asset call it did I
not it's called right there why is it
knocked oops I mad I was still thinking
of the old naming skirts okay let me
come in here we're doing tests here I
shot a bitmap right we loop over this
and we just count what the size is we
get there we say it's 26 characters long
so we pushed that is it let me call
school in 25 characters long correct
strangling doesn't return the length of
the null terminator so we have the null
terminator in there so we go ahead and
allocate that much we then go over that
mini and copy it in there and then we
finish let's take a look at desk make
sure it's right it is so that is
basically that and while we are running
let's go ahead and do a little bit tests
of changing that right again
I
kalari loads in there so hopefully that
took care of that problem again it's one
that we said would be with the live code
loop live code editing stuff is just
that's one thing you can't do is is have
data that's in the code block and we
should be able to avoid that most of
time because our strings will all come
from the asset file so we really
shouldn't have to worry about it too
much but we have to worry about it
temporarily while we have test code
that's just one of the costs of having
tesco but test code is almost always
worth it to get things right so it's you
know better to spend a couple seconds
debugging some things than to then do
not do it so let's go ahead and go to
the question and answer if you have
questions or answers about the stuff
that we did acid a stream please put q
colon in front of it and ask it now so
that I can answer it abner combrer you
said there were newcomers in coming
yesterday but then the questions were
all pretty normal actually so I don't
know we'll see see what we get certainly
maybe the newcomers are all super smart
and ask really smart questions and they
just look like they were people who've
been watching the stream the whole time
but that's just because they super know
what they're doing you never know they
could have fooled us
how would you pay in a sample slightly
left or right in volume well when we do
the change volume right we have our
change volume call in there you would
just decide how you wanted your volume
to behave if that made sense so uh well
lets you know what let's just let's just
do it so you can kind of maybe hear it a
little bit better you know what I could
also do here is I could maybe
all right can you guys hear that better
now
is that too loud
I'll let you guys catch up for a second
but what I was going to say is I think
we do have a debug mouse position right
we we passed the debug mouse position to
the game right so what I was thinking is
if we went into handmade CPP we could
start playing with the pan stuff pretty
easily by doing something like in a you
know maybe in the game state here where
we start looking at the input you know
what we could do and by the way I guess
we should we could reenable that Thun
now that our ground buffers recompute on
the fly it's probably pretty easy to do
well I guess I don't know because we
don't want to touch ones they're in
progress so maybe I won't do that yet
maybe I'll just leave a note to do re re
enable this but make sure we don't touch
ones in flight so when we come in here
to do all of our controller stuff maybe
we want to do something well we'll do a
change volume of that that playing sound
that music test that we were doing like
so and what we'll do is we'll just have
a music volume value that we set so
let's let's see your game state audio
state is that the correct call there so
now music volume what we'll do is we
will set the music volume to be
something that pans based on the mouse
position right so will essentially say
well you know I I'm going to make a
music volume I'm going to set the zero
element of the music volume to be
whatever the mouse position is and maida
let's see here
and made platform mouse mouse X it is
right so we take a look at the mouse X
and we'll say that we want to take the
mouse x / you know the some kind of
dimension right whatever the dimension
of the of the drawable buffer is is
probably what we would want to use I
would think for that so maybe we'd say
what is that output buffer called let's
see see here render where is our render
render render there we go so we could
take a look at that that drama for stuff
the buffer width that's what I want so
if we were to do it by the buffer with
and this is just some absolute some temp
code here will do actually we can do a
safe ratio zero so to make sure that we
don't accidentally get anything bad
happening there so we can just make it
so that you know the I guess would be
the right volume the further you move
the mouse to the right the more right
volume you get and music volume for the
left will just be whatever the inverse
of that is right so it's it's however
much it would take to add back up to one
right and so again we can sort of decide
how we exactly we want that to work but
so if we do that then we should be able
to micro pan it around pretty much and
then we also you decide how fast you
want that to happen and I guess we want
that to happen pretty quickly right so
yeah okay so let's go ahead and what
does this thing do you have V from v to
2k so that's good second there we go
let's play it
can you hear that
right so that should give you some idea
of how you can value slightly if we this
is using point five point five so half
volume in either speaker when it's right
in the middle it's using 1 point 0 in
the left speaker right or 1 point 0 and
the right speaker and 0 and the other
speaker when it moves to the extremes
and again this is exactly that same
thing that linear interpolation is
talking about basically your talk about
going from 0 to 1 on one speaker this
way and you know one you know what I'll
just draw it on the whiteboard huh as I
draw since we don't check to see if our
apps active it pans as I draw ah I'm
gonna leave that on for a sec because
it's so darn ridiculous so basically
what I did there right is I said okay
I've got from zero to width of the
screen right and i know that i get a
debug mouse position because we were we
sent the debug mouth position from the
platform layer a long time ago saying
well you know maybe someday we're going
to want to have some HUD stuff that you
can click on to the inspector debug mode
it's a the game is not playable with the
mass amount of mouse game but we'll just
shove the mouse in there anyway so i was
like well it's in there we might as well
play with it so what i was saying is
okay i can produce a value between 0 and
1 by just saying wherever i actually am
the mouse x-rite divided by the width
will give me what percentage of the way
i am there
so if I a third of the way there it
would give me point 3 333 right as the
value so if I set that as essentially
the right speaker then as I move flush
with the right speaker it gets closer
and closer to 1 and becomes full volume
in the right speaker then what I can
just say is well 1 minus whatever that
is is going to fill me back up to a sum
total of one volume so that would be
whatever the left speaker should say so
as it gets you know closer to 0 on the
right speaker by moving closer here it
gets closer to one on the left speaker
right so I basically just did you know a
standard thing which was right volume
equals mouse over width and left volume
equals one minus right right hopefully
that makes sense
with this pitch shift be animated as
well like you enter a time dilated area
and pitch shift in a second or as you
cross a barrier I don't think we really
need that for anything in particular so
i would say probably best to leave it
out of the loop in because the pitch
shifts are fairly subtle that we're
aiming for we're not set up to do big
pitch just go like i said the time
dilation would get you there and so when
you're talking about subtle pitch shifts
there's really not a whole lot of point
in doing the that ramping because you're
not talking about changing between two
large things where you get a lot of
audible payoff from doing like a ramp
right so typically we're just going to
play sounds at a pitch and leave them
there as a way of getting variety but
we're not going to do a lot of ramping
if you wanted to pitch if the music
without changing the speed couldn't you
just do a quick and dirty linear
interpolation between the current sample
and the next sample that is what we are
doing that still changes the speed
because the whole reason that it's
getting faster is because you're moving
the basically the play cursor at a
faster rate than one to one with the
output so it the linear interpolation is
just to avoid artifacts it doesn't
really do anything special garland Oh
bloom can I ban everyone of course you
can you're a moderator you you have the
power how many years did it take you to
learn how to code that's a little
off-topic let me look to see if there's
let me go there's a lot of questions
here I'm going to stick with on topic
ones until I can't see anywhere on topic
ones uh let's see let's see me below
said it clips now meaning when I turn
the volume up on the audio it was too
high is that what you're saying what
what are you saying clips a little loud
though because I'm quieter than it okay
so let's let's tone it down a little bit
from there and maybe find a happy medium
because since we're working on sound I
kind of want it to be somewhere there so
maybe we'll do it at sixty percent or
something let's see how that is and I'll
play it back at its normal normal amount
there so it's playing at D sample oh so
it is already playing at the right sound
level
let's see did you ever cover what would
make a good test sound file for this
type of mixing word no but if you really
if you're trying to do some very serious
finally of your audio a pure sine waves
tend to be pretty good actually you can
you can hear things in pure sine ways
pretty reasonably do you ever use mem
copy from the C standard library no
I mean sometimes on the stream we have
because we haven't gotten around to
writing our own CC enter library yet but
no in my real life no I don't use my
copy what's the yellow rectangle now the
yellow rectangle was a placeholder
because we don't have art for stairs yet
so we were testing some zooming code
just it again this is all just was test
stuff that we were playing with and so I
don't know why it's a yellow rectangle
don't don't ask me we've got a bunch of
stuff we're playing with that we're
going to wrap up relatively soon so
there's a bunch of weird test stuff
floating around in here that you know as
you can imagine is a bit odd
you
what kind of sound options do you plan
to include the game like will the player
be able to pause the game and mute the
music but keep the sound effects or is
it going to be a fixed thing like before
settings it'll probably be a fixed thing
I would imagine but I don't know like I
don't I don't really like the whole
customizable thing that much as I've
said a couple times before because you
know like you make a movie and you watch
the movie you don't go I'm gonna replace
the soundtrack to this movie maybe it'd
be a better world if you could so I
don't necessarily want to say that
that's a bad thing to shoot for but it's
definitely not my preference I'd like to
experience the thing that was made and
so typically you know I kind of feel
like the music is part of the soundscape
and should be part of it that said the
whole point of handmade hero is to hack
on it so every copy the game will come
with a source code so for people who
want to replace the music I've actually
rather than giving them a menu that does
it I'd rather encourage them to learn
enough coding to go in and build the
game and take out the music because
that'll be a great project for somebody
to just want an introduction to
programming to go in and just just take
out the one part that plays the music
that might be kind of fun kind of like
the controller setting stuff I kind of
want to give people reasons to to mod
the game themselves because it's
supposed to be an educational project
wouldn't you want to use the alternate
way of animating the volume for this
feature by setting a rate not a length
of time feature meaning that what the
pan left to right assuming the pan left
to right know that that's the exact kind
of thing that I don't want to set a rate
because what I want it to do is track
the mouse exactly so I want it to
basically ensure that on a given frame
it will go from its current volume to
its new volume but I don't want it to be
a pop so I just want to interpolate over
some reasonable number of samples which
is what I said to set it to do right
with a player running would you connect
speed of the player to pitch or look to
add more sounds ie more steps in grass I
would add more sounds for the footsteps
although the speed that the player is
moving at depending on the circumstance
could very well change the pitch as well
depending on the surface they were
running on so for example if I run
faster I'm probably hitting the ground a
little harder or doing other things so
pitch could vary with speed as well but
it wouldn't be the primary thing to vary
the frequency of actually triggering the
footstep sounds would be the primary
thing you'd very first once you release
the source code this will allow people
to build upon edit and make their own
games correct yes so actually the way
that it works is the source code is
already available if you pre-order the
game you can already start hacking on
the source code you just can't ship it
you can't like use it to make a
commercial game because there there's a
time lock on it bass glaze but that time
lock expires two years from the ship
date of this game and at that point it
will be you can use it for making any
commercial product that you want
you may have already covered this but
does the OS alone allocate threads to
run on each core so it is impossible to
force a single thread to run on its own
unique core actually those are not
mutually exclusive so yes it is the OS
alone which decides what core of thread
runs on so you are correct in thinking
that you do not get to choose what core
a thread runs on however because that
can be important for performance
oriented programming due to the fact
that certain caches are local to certain
core is and other things like this and
who knows what else right there's lots
of reasons you might care most operating
systems and windows is one of them
provide you with ways of actually
telling the operating system what Korres
you want your threads to run on so even
though if the operating system that's
doing the deciding and you are not
writing the code that puts things I
different course you can actually make
calls they're called affinity masks and
things like this where you can call and
say I want this thread to only run on
these cores or this one core or whatever
right and then well I don't actually
know if it's a hard guarantee meaning I
don't know if windows actually
guarantees that it will only run on that
core it will create a strong preference
in the scheduler Atlee at the very least
so that when the operating system is
scheduling the threads it will try as
hard as it can to run that thread on
that core and I'm sorry I just don't
recall whether windows scheduler
guarantees you'll never run on the other
core or whether it just is a strong
preference but either or the point is
you do have some control their
indirectly and that so so you can
actually maybe not force a single thread
to run on its own unique core but you
can certainly try I mean you can
certainly do something like set all the
other threads to have affinity to other
cores and set your thread to have an
affinity to your core and set the mask
so that your
can't run on the other cores or things
like that you can try to set up the
circumstance so the scheduler just will
actually do that thing so so you
actually can do that and there's other
things Windows has like a user mode
scheduling thing and they've added other
stuff too so you may have even more
options than that but at the at the very
least for for all of which you know for
for quite some time windows has had the
ability to articulate to the scheduler
what it was that you expect to happen in
terms of distribution of your threads on
the the computers course
is programming just you remember a whole
bunch of commands and putting them into
sequence um I probably wouldn't quite
describe it that way but it's not far
from the truth I mean basically what
happens is more like you build a mental
model of how computers work based on the
kinds of computers your programming and
you know you have a certain set of ways
you can affect their operation and then
it's you trying to figure out what set
of those things you can do will produce
the outcome you're actually trying to
produce so you know I mean I don't know
how you want to phrase that exactly but
that's that's you know the rough idea
let's see looks like that's the end of
the auto question so we're kind of
getting we're running out of time here
does anyone else have any top questions
about sound I should answer before the
time runs out of the street
anyone anyone maybe garland abloom
already banned everyone and so at that
point it's true that we couldn't get
very many questions but
is it too complex to add low and high
pass filters via code no you know I
don't have a lot of experience with
sound coding I'm not really a sound
coding guy so I suppose I'm the wrong
one to ask but I believe it's pretty
simple actually it's just a thing you
know when we're out putting those sound
samples it's one of the filters you
could run that's sort of just a in place
pretty simple filter that just as you
output each sample you do a little bit
of math on it and you use like
accumulators to keep track of some state
so there's a little bit of bookkeeping
involved if I remember correctly because
you have to sort of know there's sort of
the concept because it's a filter it
needs to have a window of samples to
look at because it needs to know what
the oscillations are that it's trying to
filter so there's a little bit more
bookkeeping that goes on if you try to
start adding filters that's usually the
majority of the pain involved in
imploding filters is okay now you've got
to have a bunch of extra bookkeeping for
them but once you do then it's just a
simple set of math ops that hopper eight
on the bookkeeping and the new samples
coming in and it's really that's really
not that much more than that so if you
know if you really wanted a low-pass
filter for some reason it's not a huge
deal to put it in
if a tree falls and the hero is not
there to hear it will it make a sound
well I guess it really doesn't matter if
the hero is there or not it matters
whether the user is there or not right
because the sound is going to come out
in their world the hero can't hear any
sounds because the hero is in a world
where there is no such thing as sound
really all of the sound comes out in
your world even though it's happening in
his so yeah I would say that the sort of
the Buddhist conundrum or whatever it is
is actually very simplified compared to
what we have here because our cone is
something like if a sound happens if a
tree falls in your world and its
vibration is reproduced in another world
but no one in that other world is there
to hear it did it make a sound
soy sauce the kid asks is the next thing
you're going to do put the sound code in
simdi yes I think probably what we'll do
is we'll just lightly you know we won't
really spend a lot of time optimizing
but we'll just translate it to Cindy so
we can make sure that it works wide and
then we'll probably call it good and if
we ever want more sound processing stuff
we'll revisit it way later in the game
development cycle when we know exactly
what sound features we don't have and
want but these are the the only ones I
really know that I definitely will make
any use of so we probably won't go nuts
on adding sound features beyond what's
here until we actually have some
indication of exactly what we would want
them for so are you going to use complex
numbers I heard they're useful for sound
processing uh so yeah I mean the whole
complex number system thing is if you're
into digital signal processing which is
where a lot of sound stuff comes from
then that all of that the basis of all
of that ends up being in sort of this
complex number basis where because of
the way the Fourier transform works and
all these are the sorts of things you
get into places where it becomes
convenient to think of things in terms
of complex numbers honestly I don't love
digital signal processing I feel like
it's kind of cheesy so you know your
mileage may vary but if you want to
implement the traditional sound
processing code in the traditional way I
yeah you would want to go read about
digital signal processing which is based
on complex number usually uses complex
numbers to talk about what it's talking
about that is really mostly for doing
filtering sorts of stuff you certainly
don't need it for any of the stuff that
we just did like unless you're going to
fourier transform something to do some
processing you probably don't really
need to worry about it so all right i
think i'm going to call it let's see
here because we're about out of time
let's go ahead and
close close it down alrighty clothes
clothes okay thank you everyone for
joining me for another episode of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you want to
follow along at home with the source
code when we are programming on the
stream here you can do that if you
pre-order the game on handmade hero org
it comes with the source code every day
I update it nightly after we're finished
coding so if you want to play around
with it at home and just experiment and
try to learn from the series it's a good
way to do that we also have a forum site
you can go to to ask questions if you
have questions about working with the
code and stuff like that it also has the
annotated episode guide for catching up
on past episodes things like this it has
ports to mac and linux as well by
members of the community that can help
get you started if you want to work on a
different platform besides window so
that's helpful too we have a patreon
page if you would like to support the
video series we very much appreciate
subscriptions and we also have a tweet
bot which will tweet the schedule at you
if you want to catch the series live
that is the best way to find out when
it's going to be so if you're interested
in catching more of these dreams that's
the place to check out for now i am
going to sign off but i will be back
here not tomorrow because tomorrow's a
day off but friday 5 p.m. pacific
daylight time same time same place on
friday and i will probably be doing some
work on changing the code over to Cindy
so that we can make sure that our that
nothing that we did with the sound code
is going to be confusing and Cindy and
we can make sure everything lines up
nicely and just you know get everything
kind of nicely button down and be sure
that architectural e it all works
properly so we'll go ahead and do that
and then we will kind of be able to
check sound off our system off of our
to-do list until much later if we decide
we want additional features so that's
pretty good pretty excited about that
and we can go back to buttoning up the
asset system which is basically just a
memory man management some of this time
so we're about to check out some pretty
big to-do items and that's pretty great
that would allow us to move on to some
of the final stuff that we have before
we can do game coding so pretty excited
about it things are going pretty well I
think and yeah
I'm pretty happy with with the progress
that we've made so give yourself a pat
on the back and I will see you guys on
Friday have a good thursday if I don't
see on the internet until then happy
coding everyone