all right thank you everyone for joining
me for another episode of handmade hero
you know I've been doing this yesterday
and today I sort of started with the
same thing I normally close close with I
think I normally say welcome to handmade
hero the show where we code a complete
gave live on stream I don't know why I
switched it up maybe this weekend it's
just backwards weekend it's hard to say
anyway it's lighting time we actually
fix the lighting yesterday to not have
some obvious bug finish that it had when
we had just kind of splattered it in
there so we we have a lighting solution
now that while it's not particularly
interesting it is actually usable at
this point right like we're getting to
the point where we could actually use it
and it's not good like it's not what we
want because it's pretty boring it's
pretty basic in terms of what it does
but it's getting there right it's like
it's not completely messed up anymore
and so that's a good like place to be
obviously but that just means our job
for today and probably next weekend as
well before we decide to sort of get
this down to a more optimized thing that
we can use and put it on the GPU which
is going to be kind of the final phase
of it and that phase is you know going
to be pretty straightforward but but you
know annoying because it involves GPU
programming before we get to that what
we want to do is you know it's push the
quality level a little bit here and
there's a bunch of things that we
probably want to fix in terms of quality
that I see right so looking at it at the
moment you know we get this kind of
situation where if you take a look at
what's happening there are some basic
things that I would like to try and
improve on so the very first one
obviously is if we take a look at how
these lights are distributing you can
kind of see how this light for example
propagates basically symmetrically
around where we're going like for
example if I stick my my guy right up
against the wall there you can kind of
see how this square which is too away is
lit basically the same as this square
over here right there's there's
really not a lot of difference between
these so you can put a light right up
next to a giant litter and this is the
only light in the scene remember and it
will just lead right through and why
does it do that well the reason is it
does that is because we don't really
have any notion of shadowing in terms of
light source direction so I don't love
that aspect of what we're not really
doing that in there which is which is
bad so I think we want to try to improve
that and the other thing is that you'll
notice like I'm not getting as much
color bleed as I would like and so you
know if we take a look at what's going
on here where we've got this sort of
lighting where we're lighting some of
these panels up like right here you can
see you've got a lot of light shining
off of these red panels and I see almost
none of it coming up on to these ground
reflectors there's maybe a tinge of it
in there if you really wanted to see it
you could but you know in terms of if
we're being honest about it it's really
not there in any appreciable way if we
take a look at the reflectors and what
we're seeing it's just it's they're more
or less it's like those red ones aren't
even there and that's not what we want
either so that's that's really what
we're talking about here and so we need
to sort of look at that and so the two
things that I would like to do is to
push forward is one I would like to
start getting some directional shadowing
in there I don't like the ambient
occlusion path it's turned off right now
if I'm not mistaken let me see if that's
true before I say that I'm pretty sure
it is I don't like the ambient occlusion
pass we kind of got it from the the
paper the the friction lamps paper I
don't like it
it's not not doing it for me maybe
that's because we implemented it poorly
I don't know I mean it's hard to tell
without a reference implementation
obviously but I don't really like it and
III want something that's that's going
to be better than that
for shadowing so you know if I turn that
on here here's the shadowing
not a lot of difference and you can see
we get some weird behavior too so we
might have some bugs in there we could
take a look at just in terms of the fact
that you know you get this sort of black
pure black shadow where the light gets
you know clipped out entirely and you
know I guess that could be theoretically
correct I mean in a certain way because
you think about it this guy right here
really has no one he can get light from
there's nothing to bounce off of
oops
there's nothing for for that light to
bounce off of that like nothing nearby
for it to illuminate so when it gets
shadowed it can be shattered entirely so
that you know I don't necessarily think
it's wrong and when we put together a
more realistic scene that had you know a
ceiling or a skylight you know I think
you wouldn't have that problem happening
as often but the thing that I would
point out is I'm less inclined to go
diving into the ambient occlusion path
and try to find if there are bugs in it
because I don't like it to begin with
because as our shadow it you know if
that's our solution for shadows well it
doesn't work and is it going to work
because the thing about ambient
occlusion is it doesn't have directional
shadowing information in it it doesn't
know if you're on one side of a wall or
not and so the problem that we will just
have with it whether or not it's working
well is that it will never produce the
actual shadowing results that we want so
at best that ambient occlusion thing can
only really be part of another algorithm
that would do the other sorts of things
that I want and so I'm less inclined to
really deal much with it at this point I
would probably just say that we're going
to leave it kind of off on its own and
we'll revisit it if we feel like we need
what it does later on so what I'd like
to do now again is yet start to focus on
trying to improve the quality there and
I think what I'd like to do is maybe try
to focus on that shadowing quality it
does bring up one question of whether or
not we need to make the heroes not
interpenetrate with really tall
wall I don't necessarily know if there's
much we can do with that it's a good
question yeah we're going to have to
soup I swore on the train we're
going to have to mess with our Z bias
that's like the fifth one man I tried so
hard to not have any curses on the
stream and I fail so anyway here's what
we need to do we need to start looking
at improving that lighting and what we
want to do is focus on either the shadow
or the light bleed part I think both of
them are fixable and we can sort of
start to play with them what do I think
these are coming from well first of all
the shadow Park is really obvious where
it's coming from
it's a lack of something right now the
light just propagates light between
surfaces without thinking about whether
there's something in between the two
surfaces that are trying to provide
light right so what happens in this case
what we get is a situation where each of
these reflectors and again I guess I
should go back to the reflector views
you can see it each of these reflectors
is transferring light between every
other reflector right and we will do
something that reduces the degree to
which we N squared that in the future
but for the moment it doesn't matter
because we're actually even doing it N
squared and that's fine what we're just
for testing we're doing it N squared so
when we're doing this N squared
transference the problem that we will
run into is that if we are just testing
you know each one of these reflectors
against each other reflector right then
we really don't have any way of knowing
whether or not that reflector can see
the other reflector we know if the
reflector is too far away right so when
we're moving the light around we do know
stuff like oh okay
you know this reflector isn't getting
much light from this light source over
here and the reason is because it's too
far you know so that's a pretty easy way
for that to be rectified and and yet you
know that sort of information about
light and fall-off into place what we
don't have is a way of knowing well you
know this can't really see this because
there's stuff in the way right and so
the amount of light that comes back here
should be lessened that's just a basic
part no matter how we do our reflectors
or how they're shaped that's something
that is is we just need some way of
taking into account so what I want to
know is is there some way that we can
take what we're doing right now and
change the basic idea so that we end up
computing something that has a little
bit of shadowing in it and I guess I
might suggest something really
ridiculous at this point I which you
know I I guess I it's one of those
things where you never really know till
you try but if we imagine that every
reflector was actually going to sort of
keep a little bit of a pseudo pixel
render kind of a thing going on I know
this sounds ridiculous and yeah I know
this sounds absolutely ridiculous but if
you imagined that we just sort of took
every reflector and looked at how the
other reflectors mapped onto its
hemisphere that is sort of the complete
picture of how the light comes in to
that reflector right because the thing
that we're not capturing now that we
need to capture is the fact that
reflectors overlap and so if we took you
know almost a render
of that hemisphere then we would get you
know that information that we needed
right however that's like pretty cost
prohibitive to produce even if we were
on the GPU you know if you imagine that
we have something on the order of five
files and abuse reflectors eventually
rendering 5,000 cubed Maps or something
is probably not a very good idea even if
we were to do it sporadically and even
if we're doing it just with flat plates
like this five thousand times five
thousand in terms of the render load
isn't necessarily that bad for a GPU
right like if you're trying to think
what would that be so it's 25 million if
your translate 25 million primitives
well honestly since their instance
because you're rendering the same 5,000
just rendering them five thousand times
it's really not that bad in terms of the
number of rooms you're trying to sink
the problem is the number of destination
cube maps there and the setup involved
in switching render targets five
thousand times
sounds dangerous so in terms of actually
rendering all the reflectors in that
sense I don't know that sounds pretty
rough so you know the question is is
there something we can do that's more
straightforward than that that's simpler
than that
and I don't know but let me just sort of
give you an idea
no time
all right so here is the problem
and I'm going to draw it right here so
the problem that we have is we've got
these reflectors and we want to take a
look at you know some other set of
reflectors that are coming into it right
and what we'd like to do is we'd like to
be able to say well okay so you know
this one is basically entirely behind
these other two so anything coming from
this one just isn't going to be seen
whereas the only way you're going to see
any contribution from this one is if it
like secondarily bounced off something
else you can see like maybe something
over here or something like that but
you're never going to see any light from
this guy right here reflected onto this
one it's just not going to happen so the
reason we're not getting that right now
is because when we consider these two
all we look at is the distance so the
fact that this one happens to be that
far away is the only thing that
attenuates it the fact that these two
are in the way doesn't really help us
right and similarly if we take a look at
the ambient occlusion pass the ambient
occlusion pass just looks at how much
these other things shadow the hemisphere
of this guy it doesn't tell us for which
person it doesn't tell us that this one
is shadowed more than this one which is
the information that we actually need
and so from this reflector what we'd
like to do is we'd like to actually say
well tell me about what all of these
reflectors would flatten onto if I was
to draw this hemisphere in here and
again what we could do right like I was
saying is it could take a cube map and
we only need you know slides of the six
sides the cube map obviously this
backside here is not relevant but you
get the idea if we were to look at this
cube map its table what's coming in on
the cube map what's coming in on the
cube map would tell us this information
because each of these things would
project onto the cube map and they would
be Z sorted so the Z buffering of the
cube map would take care of that piece
of information for us that we actually
need to know the problem of course is
that we don't have probably the
resources to render an entire cube map
for each of the five thousand reflectors
that might be in one of our scenes now
maybe that's a stupid statement maybe
the real statement is no
of course you can do that welcome to the
new GPU land just of course you can
render 5000 Tube maps a frame if that's
the only thing you're really doing go
nuts you're right because again we don't
need to send out any additional
information for this because all 5,000
primitives are the same every time right
they're the same set of reflectors
they're just being viewed from a
different viewpoint so it's really not
that big a deal I don't think that's
really that faint I'm saving to make the
reason is because again the cube map
itself is actually five faces or going
to have to render running five faces of
the cube app needs actually five render
passes
so in effect unless we actually try to
do it a little bit more straightforward
where we actually set up multiple render
targets which we could probably do and
then render everything to the cube map
internally in that way I don't know it's
kind of a nightmare right it's not great
so what I'd rather do is try to think of
some scheme that we can do that's not
quite so bad as this right it's not
quite so bad as this but maybe does
effectively sort of maybe a little bit
sort of kind of sort of maybe a little
bit kind of the same thing and there's a
pretty straightforward way we can
actually do that and the only problem
with it is it's probably a little too
artefact program a little worried about
how you would get rid of the aliasing on
it and so I guess we could just try it I
don't really see why not there's not a
reason not to try it I guess but it's
definitely one of those things you look
at and go well okay but yeah how am I
going to get rid of the aliasing on it
and I don't know the answer to that
question maybe well maybe one will
present itself but here we go what if we
were to say okay we know we want to
render effectively a hemisphere well
what does rendering actually do for us
what does render a cube actually do for
us and at this point you can see by the
fact that I'm just doing badly that the
coffee has kicked in a little bit too
too much that's one of the the cons of
drinking coffee on stream is you
definitely elevate the energy level to
it uncomfortable amount but sometimes
programming requires elevating the
energy level to an uncomfortable amount
and that is where we were at right now
so I apologize an explanation of a
little bit too excited that's just what
happens with caffeine actually it's more
sugar it's really the sugar the caffeine
is maps are related this is actually one
of those
Starbucks beverages it's mostly sugar so
the sugar is definitely helped anyway so
looking at this what I would encourage
you to think about is what actually
happens when we render why does render
even solve any of these problems at all
well the thing that solves the problem
is actually the z-buffer right the
z-buffer is the thing that actually
solves the problem and it's no accident
that the things we want to do with when
rendering solves our problems
rasterization I should say solves our
problems the z-buffer is really this
thing that takes care of it right
because if we were to render the cube F
in here the thing that's telling us that
we're going to have these things stacked
on top of each other and that this one
is going to be seen where than this one
is the z-buffer occluding per pixel
those primitives right that's what's
actually happening there and so the
thing to remember in that case is that
the same is true for the lighting as is
for the rasterization of the sprites and
everything else the z-buffer or that
depth or is what is making this work and
so for example even when you when you
look at doing things that have nothing
to do with radiosity red stuff that
we're playing with now if you look at
how people do shadow mapping for example
the same thing is true it's basically
using the Z buffer as a technique to
produce what a light source can see for
example and so rasterization the key is
the Z buffer the Z buffer is the magic
that's the thing that's actually
producing the information we actually
need out of this process and so the
question is to answer selfies can we get
the magic of the Z buffer in some way
that doesn't require setting up a full
render worth a full render from a cube
map no less which is obviously not what
we want because it's even more expensive
than a regular render path and that's no
good for our purposes well the answer
here I think is yes we can and the
reason I say that is because a z-buffer
is nothing more than a check per pixel
to see whether or not the Z value of a
primitive along the Ray of a particular
line of sight happens to be in front of
everything else that has previously been
seen all it is is one it right that's
all it is
you can tell how far away something is
you could do an if statement and say
replace the current one with the new one
if this one if the current one's closer
right that's all the z-buffer is
actually doing for us we don't need to
do anything else
in this circumstance so what I would say
is what if we just emulate that ourself
so suppose we took and we said here is
our reflector we would like to measure
and maybe I should draw this in three
dimensions just to be clearer so suppose
I I have my sort of there we go
something like this suppose I take my
reflector and I say I am going to sample
this reflector on along some set of
angles just you know I'm going to
randomly pick some ways around the
hemisphere to sample I say randomly I
don't mean that we're eventually going
to use a random number generator to do
it or anything like that what I mean is
well that's left is something to figure
out another day right so they'll just
say we figured out the way that we want
to sample this probably using something
actually fairly structured because we're
going to want to make sure that it's
clean so it's probably going to be
something like a blue noise pattern
across a hemisphere that we control
actually fairly tightly for various
reasons that's something any more you
think about right now so let's just
assume that we've done some work to
figure that out and that that work will
get actually done in the future we've
got some series of rays coming out of
the reflectors that we want a sample
effectively we are ray tracing at this
point right and now we're going to turn
that z-buffer around and say well if we
were doing a ray tracing approach right
you're just doing this V buffer but sort
of doing it along array so instead of
producing all the privilege or a pixel
you instead are casting your ray out and
saying what is the rate hit right it's
basically just ray tracing at this point
and it's pretty messy buffer around well
if we were going to do that we could
certainly Ray trace our rays against our
reflectors if we have a definition for a
reflector that allows us to intersect
array with it then we can do this
operation fairly trivially right there's
nothing magic about it
so we can effectively raytrace even on
the GPU we could rate race fairly easily
by just you know switching around the
way the primitives work we're saying
each primitive is actually going to do a
rate rate in the buffer to figure out
what's going on for that particular
pixel right there's there's ways we can
set this up on the GPU to work so we
don't really have to worry about the
fact that it appears to be something
that's that's rate racing because GPUs
is a programmable now we should be able
to convert the algorithm over so if we
think about this is more of a rate
racing kind of problem and we sort of
averted invert it and think of it as
looking outward we can pick arbitrary
directions and we can pick a very small
number of them potentially right we
could say let's suppose we've got you
know eight directions or sixteen
directions or something like this that
might be enough to give us a reasonable
lighting solution while still not being
too many for performance purposes right
I don't know it's just a suggestion
right and furthermore we are really only
doing this to capture shadow information
so we are still taking into account the
lighting from every reflector that we
can see we're just doing a set of quick
checks on each of them to see whether or
not we should maybe discard part of or
all of the lighting information that
they're in right okay the other thing
that we can do here is take a page from
the PlayBook of the original algorithm
and say well what is instead of doing
that we actually consider them to be
solid angles instead so for example
let's say we wanted to do something
where we have this reflector like I say
and we want to do a cap outwards and we
actually consider each of those tasks to
be more of a cone so what we're actually
going to do is sort of take a look at
how much of the cone is include occluded
by each of them right and so we can sort
of talk about how much of the cone has
been restricted at each individual place
or how much of the
is being seen by by one thing or another
you know that sort of a thing and we can
come up with some kind of ridiculous
algorithm potentially that you know
tries to weight contributions of things
along the cone right so that's that's
just my thinking of how we might be able
to improve this algorithm you know maybe
shoot out eight shoot out four shoot out
16 I don't know how many of these how
much is too expensive
I'm not sure what I do know is that if
you take a look at the way GPU works or
a CPU and that for that matter the fact
that they tend to be wide often means
that you can figure out a way to do
things so that you can get 16 things
done at a time if you have the same
inputs to them so for example if we're
going to do the same 16 rate check
against a particular incoming primitive
that's probably as cheap as just doing
one it you know you can get that
parallelism out of it and so if you're
doing some like ray tracing it actually
removes you to do 16 primitives at a
time if you can and so you know there's
a certain degree of leverage we might be
able to get there in terms of getting
back to something that's more like
rasterization in terms of it
it's Lane utilization anyway so maybe
that gives us some some options too so
this is what I would like to explore the
reason I would like to explore this is
because I think the only way we're
really going to get better shadowing in
there is to start thinking about
directional occlusion rather than just
thinking about general ambient occlusion
because Direction occlusion is the only
way to get sort of the knowledge that
something on one side of a wall can't
collect much information for something
on the other side of the wall not a very
controversial thing to what but just a
difficult thing to get so if we come
back to sort of the more pragmatic side
of things here and just say how are we
going to actually implement something
like this
well the brute force
and really straightforward method is to
just literally have some way of
intersecting our line with our
primitives right now this just comes
back to another ray playing intersection
which we sort of talked about before but
what we know is that each of our
reflectors is actually in a plane right
whether we choose to do a disc or we
choose to do a sort of parallelogram or
square of some kind in the future one
thing we do know for sure about them is
that they are only is going to be in a
plane and if something is in a plane we
know we've got a plane intersection if
we're trying to see where along array a
particular one of these reflectors is
well that's pretty easy to do all the
attitude is is do R a plane intersection
which we've done before and one of the
things that's really clear about R a
plane intersection right I can derive it
for you again it's very very
straightforward it's a very simple one
to do if you have an origin point right
here's p 0 and you have a direction
normal we'll call that n we'll just
assume that it's normalized if I know
that I want to hit up well I guess I
shouldn't call that n let me call that D
for direction because I'm going to want
to call the planes normal and if I then
have a plane somewhere out here which
has a normal n right and and a
particular origin point here that's
described as the distance along here you
know I'm picking really bad letters
today that's all this are for Ray how
about that because this is going to want
to be the D value as well there right so
what we knew about this is if we have a
plane somewhere in the world described
by our standard ND formula and remember
a plane is one of these equations right
ax plus B y plus cz plus B equals 0
right this is an assigned plane this is
a linear plane right here in a fine
plane plus D so this is the standard
equation for a plane we've seen it
before if you haven't you're going to
want to use the hand made hero episode
guide to go back and look at where I
talked about planes and how to describe
this right here is just the normal
times the incoming point so this is
really just n x times PX plus NY Times
py plus NZ x pz plus the D value for the
plane equals 0 right so this is the
normal to the plane in here this is the
point we're testing on the plane this is
the D value for the plane right
hopefully this is all coming back I
should probably look at the chapter
right now to see if everyone's like wait
a minute I totally forgot how planes
work hopefully that's not true but maybe
it is anyway so we thought this equation
for the plane and really all we want to
do here in fact I could even use just a
straightforward equation for the plane
if we want to just this right here all
we need to know is where does this
equation right line up with the equation
for array and remember the equation for
array is just going to be and I could
take furthermore the simplification of
this p0 point can be subtracted out so
we can make this be 0 0 just by
subtracting away transforming the the
plane to the space with array even we
can make it even simpler ourselves and
just say look the array is just a
t-value
that goes out along the Ray it's just PR
X T ry t RZ is just the the point right
that's that's the point along the Ray as
we go out along T so if we walk along
this proportional to t t RX t ry t RZ is
just a point that we would end up on
right again this should be all review so
I'm not going into it in too much detail
the point being if we just want to solve
these equations we're just looking for
the equation that solves this for T and
it's a pretty straightforward thing to
do because if you take a look at how it
works we would just substitute this
point in to this equation and we're
basically done so for example if we just
substitute in a t rx plus a coops BT are
y plus C T or Z plus V equals 0 what you
can see here is that the team pulls out
pretty straightforward right I just end
up with
a RX + b ry + CR z + Z equals 0 and if I
want to solve for this well it's pretty
straightforward again I'm solving again
for T which is the length which is the
distance along the Ray I've traveled so
far I just get T equals negative D over
R X plus B or Y plus C R Z right and
that tells me how far I had to step
along the Ray to get to the plains right
so again it's a very simple substitution
we have an equation that tells us how
we're moving along array we have an
equation that implicitly tells us
whether we're on the plane or not so we
just substitute in the equation for how
we move along the Ray into the equation
for when we're on the plane and out
comes the answer as to when we would hit
that plane now you will notice that
sometimes we won't hit the plane how do
I know that we sometimes won't hit the
plane well first of all it's pretty
obvious if you think about it if the
plane is facing this way and we're
pointing that way well we're never going
to hit it we're just going to go forever
and we're never going to hit it if
you're pointing slightly that way we
would hit it if we're pointing slightly
that way we would hit it when we go
backwards right
but it's reporting directly
perpendicular to the plane normal we
won't hit it
hey big surprise that's exactly what
this says this is the denominator of an
equation we know that the denominator of
an equation can't be 0 that means a our
x + BR y + c RZ cannot be equal to 0 if
we want this equation to hold and so he
cannot have any valid value if this were
to become 0 when can this become 0 well
those of you with special eagle-eyed
vision who've been watching hand-made
here all the time should know what this
equation is does anyone know what this
equation is please tell me someone those
those Creationism not even look at the
chat because I really hope that someone
knows what the equation is
hopefully you said that this equation is
the inner product or dot product because
that's exactly what it is it's the X of
one thing times the X of another the Y
of one thing of the while the other to
see is one thing the Z of one thing
times Z of another what are those two
things lo they're the N and the point
right so a B and C are like I said the
top n x and y in Z right and rxry
RZR the points of the Ray so if I have
the points the x y and z of the normal
the XYZ of the Ray I'm dot park them
together what do we know about the dot
product the dot product is length of a
length of B cosine theta when can the
dot product be 0 well only if the length
of these two things are 0 we know
they're both not or if the cosine
between them is 0 when is the cosine
between two vectors 0 its 0 when they
are perpendicular to each other right
because the dot product of this and this
cosine between those two angles is 0
because of course right we know as it
kind of comes up the cosine starts at
one comes up up up up to 0 right at 90
degrees which is exactly what we'd be at
if they were perpendicular or negative
90 degrees as well right so negative
ninety or ninety is going to be 0 in
both cases if it's perpendicular cosine
is 0 what did I just say we're never
going to hit it if we're perpendicular
to the normal here's the raid erection
here's the normal dot props together
they're 0 done deal
right so effectively all we're saying
here in this equation is just yes you
will hit the plane eventually this is
when you'll hit the plane if you happen
to pick a direction that's perpendicular
to the plane surprise surprise you won't
kid it shouldn't be shocking okay anyway
all that stuff is review you should have
had that from earlier in hand-made 0 so
I'm not going to belabor the point if
you haven't I highly recommend you
consult the Oracle whose name is midlow
and he will do his episode guide tell
you the the place you can learn more
about Rea plane intersection but once we
have a ray plane intersection what we
can do is we can say all right for all
of those reflectors if we're looking at
one of these and we want to take a ray
that goes out into the world if we want
to figure out where the ray chip things
what we need to do is take those
reflectors and we need to figure out
when we kiss the plane right we will
know that will produce a p-value like I
said in the previous equation that will
produce a p-value that tells us when we
have hit a plane in the world right when
we've hit a plane in the world that
tells us we have hit something
in the plane of a reflector it doesn't
tell me tell us if we've actually hit
the reflector and in order to tell us
whether we've actually hit the reflector
we need a model for the reflector now
the way that we've currently been
modeling the reflectors is effectively
as disks I don't know that we really
want to do that anymore one of the
things about the you know the only
reason we picked this in the first place
is because we were using this sort of
disk to disk measure of size we can
still do that we can still use the disk
as the way of computing how much light
is transferred I don't know if we really
want to use that for shadowing the
reason I don't know that we want to use
it for shadowing and we really don't
want to use it for just for a transfer
either so we made switch to something
better for transfer the reason you use
it for transfer is because it's
symmetric and easy to compute but it
tends to uh under count our squares
right so we could either over account or
under counter square as I'm not sure
which one we want to do but you could
think of either one as being bad
specifically for shadowing if you under
count then you're going to let more
light through than you should if you
over count you're going to block out too
much light so it's not those you want
either those things the important part
here is just for the shadowing part of
this equation with what we're talking
about now when we hit a plane that has a
reflector on it up right because that's
the test that we can do we then need to
know is did we hit the reflector itself
in Tunis this is much easier to see if I
again look and I say here let's say I'm
casting along this ray out from this
reflector well when I hit the plane I'm
going to get this point back right and
what you could see from the diagram is
that point doesn't actually coincide
with the reflector at all so technically
that's not a kit we would say that that
ray misses the reflector it doesn't hit
the reflector right so again we have a
number of ways we could do this when we
reduce that point what we could do is we
could use again if we let's say we stick
with the disc formation for now again it
does provide some nice simplification if
we have the disc formation what we can
do is just
well what's the distance between those
two points if the distance is less than
the radius well then I guess we hit it
we're inside if it isn't less than the
radius we dip right so again all we're
saying here is there's a nice implicit
function that will tell us whether or
not we're inside the disk or not inside
the disk that's got some nice
attractiveness to it why does it have
some extract to it well a it's just a
very simple expertise for less than R
squared kind of a situation so that's
kind of nice so you know we we've got a
nice way of testing whether and find it
the other thing that's nice about it is
it composes really well if we actually
did want to do cone tracing of some kind
now we can't do exact own tracing here
in the cheap way but we could do some
fairly free country singh that's sort of
approximate how would we do that well if
you think about this is tracing out a
cone what's pretty easy to do here well
we've got a key value that tells us how
far out we've gone that T value can be
directly proportional to the cone size
right so when we get the T value back
that says here's how far you went along
the Ray to get to the plane when you go
that far along and you get to the plane
and you're there you then have a team
value can use to plug in to say what's
the size of my cone at that point right
because I would know how big the code
would be proportional to T that's a
pretty easy thing to set up right we can
just say how wide our cone is and then
we can compute just based on similar
triangles how wide the code would be at
that plane is that correct not exactly
because in the plane that plane may be
very may be kind of a oblique right the
angle might be kind of sleep to it so
it's hard to say how you really want to
do it you may want to take that angle
into effect by dot product thing these
two together which you already have to
do for the pleasure anyway and and
project the cone distance but each
regardless of what you do you can still
end up with a radius value that's a
complimentary radius value to your disk
radius so what you end up with right if
I shoot out from here and here's my
other plane I hit this plane I know I've
got a reflector out here I know that
reflector has a radius will call that
radius of reflector I know that the cone
also has
- radius right so I can also compute a
span here on the actual plane that is
sort of a radius of the cone right and
the radius of the cone can tell me if I
overlap as well so what I can do is say
if the distance between these points is
less than the radius of the reflector
plus the radius of the cone then they've
overlapped right and furthermore I could
see how much overlap there was by
comparing the distance to that so it
says set me up for doing some cone
tracing as well it's not as easy as I
made it sound because it's again if you
want to take into account the fangled
you have to actually project the cone
onto the line which takes more work
because it's not symmetric anymore you
have to come up with sort of the new
span in that way so it's again it's a
little bit tougher to project onto it
and furthermore if you don't if you're
doing it in 3d it becomes an ellipse
right because the you know a conic cut
by a plane is an ellipse of some kind so
it gets more complicated than that as
well and so I guess I would say you know
it's not it's not like really free but
you could cheese it out like you could
you could do something where you just
kind of roughly attenuate it you always
you treat it still as a cone not as an
ellipse but as a truncated cone always
and you just pick the cone sort of size
to roughly match the angle of the plane
you know there's some hand waving there
we can do is my point so yeah that's
that's an option right it's something we
could think about and I do think the
cone tracing might be interesting to a
certain degree I'm not sure how good of
a results it would really give us but
it's something to think about as we go
forward
all right so maybe blue - where do we go
from here so what I think we want to do
here is I think what you want to do is
pick a particular one of our reflectors
right and what I think we want to do is
pick one of our reflectors and do this
computation for it now why do I think we
want to pick one of our reflectors well
if we take all of our reflectors through
this fork we're just contented with a
nightmare first of all we're going to
have to optimize the thing well enough
to make sure that it runs fast enough so
we can see it operating on five hundred
reflectors again on the CPU
single-threaded that's not great we go
threaded nan Cindy that's not great and
I'd only do that right now
second we're not going to be able to see
what the heck is going on what we want
to be able to do is draw some lines or
something we want to be able to draw
some debug information here so we can
have some idea of where this thing is
working or not and whether or not we got
any bugs we're about to introduce a
bunch of weird like Ray intersection
sort of stuff here and we want to make
sure that we've got it right if we can't
focus on one reflector and see is it
actually doing the occlusion that we
think it should be doing we're going to
be I think in a world of hurt so I think
what we want to try and doing here is to
just go okay let's try taking one of
these reflectors let's do the one behind
the wall for example let's see whether
we can get that one computing sixteen
rays out from it for rays out well first
we'll start with one and we'll see if we
can get that behaving properly once we
have that behaving properly then we can
sort of take that and move that into the
space of doing all of them and we don't
really care how fast it runs because
again we're just on a CPU we just want
to see if it produces pleasant results
so we'll try to get it running as fast
as we can in terms of seeing you know
how it does and then we'll go on from
there and that will give us the
information we need as to whether or not
this is a fruitful thing to pursue or
not and whether or not we can produce a
relatively artifact to the artifact
artifact free version of it and off we
go so what I'm going to propose at the
start is that so anyone who's not on
board should make their opinions known
unfortunately the way you would make
your opinions known is by putting them
into the chat
I don't read the chat during the stream
so it is effectively a democracy where
no one listens to you which is we have a
term for that
it's called democracy so basically what
we want to do here is have everyone cast
a vote to make them feel like they're
having input in the situation while the
effective aristocracy just makes the
decisions for you just like every
government in the world right now I am
that government and you are being
oppressed so there you go that welcome
to welcome to the real world
so off we go what I need to do now is
figure out which one of these I'm going
to do I think the easiest way to figure
out one of these is to just pick a sort
of debug value we can put in and we'll
adjust that debug value to pick a
particular reflector that is like the
closest reflector to that point let's
say and that will allow us to I'm going
to pull one out effectively this is the
one that's going to be the reflector
that gets that gets chosen so we'll call
this like a rifle pic or something and
why am i doing it this way instead of a
quad index remember this is actually
coming from the render so all of this
information is still coming from the
renderer we haven't cheated it all here
we're using the full pipeline
effectively we've just asserted
ourselves in and we're looking at all of
the things that are coming in and doing
a lighting sort of debug test on those
things what that means is they're in
that community particular order right
the game frame-to-frame sends us totally
different orderings for the clause even
if they're the same set of quads because
something clearly different order so
picking a particular quad bike index
giving going to help us here what I want
to do is pick a particular quad by world
space location because that will be
relatively stable frame-to-frame at
least for our purposes so what I want to
do is make a wrestle pick value here
that basically allows me to say for a
particular placement like let's say 0
negative
- maybe I'll say actually 0.5 or rather
I want be 0.5 on the Z so for something
that's like actually - something that's
too uplands and 0.5 off the ground I'm
trying to pick something kind of over in
the wall area it's probably more like 4
up I don't really know what the court
excessing are I'm going to start with
that and what I'm going to do is every
time we go over this I'm just going to
have a like close pick value and I'm
going to start that maximum what I'm
going to do is I'm going to take the
distance from just an arbitrary sort of
location on this thing we're already
picking sort of a center point so I'm
just going to say let's look at the
center point of the thing and I want the
length squared of the element I'm going
to I'm going to call this closed x
squared + post pick index post pic just
squared so what do I do here is I want
to take a this thick squared distance
squared I want to take the length from
the element to that pick point and what
I want to do is I want to see if this
one is the best so here's the Vista
Cristen squared what I want to see is if
the best one this is a standard format
for this loop you see me do it many
times
every time we loop we're just going to
compare our current distance to see if
it's closer than the closest one we've
found so far so if the close pick
distance squared is greater than this
one then we'll use it right and our
close book index becomes whatever one
we're on so that lets us know which one
of these it is what I'm going to do is
after I find that out I now have a close
pick index value assuming I didn't mess
it up I'm going to have a close pick
distance value that will tell me which
one of these quads was close as the
closest one to that input point that I
gave when we do the future passes what
I'll do is when we go to render
that particular reflector what I want to
do is I want to highlight it somehow so
you can kind of see there's our lending
equation here's where we copy it in what
I'm going to do here is say oh okay
let's actually hijack that that process
of coloring it in the case where the
quadrant X happens to be the one that
we're picking out let's go ahead and set
the front emit to some very obvious
value like bright yellow my favorite
picking value looks like that close pick
index so I put it in the wrong place
there we go and I don't know what I just
hit I must have hit some kind of search
all of a sudden anyway so if I run this
now what I'm hoping to see is that if I
view the reflectors I should probably
turn this in fact let me just go ahead
and turn this on permanently because I'm
going to want it on all the time there
we go oops so what I want to do here is
I want to figure out a way to get one of
these these soft Oaks to to highlight so
what you can see here is is we do have
reflective thai lighting it's this one
here right right there and so it's not
it's almost north place it's not quite
back far enough it's not quite up high
enough so all I'm going to do here is
I'm just going to change that value to
be up higher and back further right and
so hopefully we can pick there we go and
so now we've picked you know one of
these squares maybe I want one of the
ground tiles here let's say might be a
better way to go let's say as well I
don't know if I don't know which one of
these would be best I mean another one
we could do is one of these but let's
let's do a ground tile let's do a ground
tile so that we can see that it can't
reach the light for example because it
hits one of these or whatever
all right so if I want do the groundhog
just pull it back a little bit probably
maybe 6.0 let's say see if that's right
not quite enough to switch it yet I
point out and we can prove account a
little bit
all right so now we're picking that one
right there I guess I should probably
have drawn this point but I haven't
drawn the point yet so we're almost to
the one that I wanted let's pull it back
slightly more and let's move it up
slightly more and see if I can't pick
that one okay so now we've got a weird
little debug procedural way to isolate a
reflector and keep it stable across runs
so that we'll just run it and it'll pick
that one automatically we don't have to
like pick it with a mouse or doodle
around weather or anything like that um
so now we've got a particular reflectors
that we can pick there and what we can
do is send that ones lighting through a
different path right so we can still use
everyone else going through the old kind
of crappy lighting path but when this
one comes up it you know it can do some
kind of nutso situation right so we know
that that ones being highlighted now
what we can do is get rid of that the
highlights because we don't need to see
it anymore and we want to actually just
see the color that it actually shows
obviously so that's that's good so now
we look at this and we can see that that
reflector is getting you know it's
created exactly at everyone else even
though we've got you know these these
light sources that are right there you
know being blocked by the by the giant
wall it still gets a pretty much direct
contribution just like it would if it
was on the other side of the wall and
that's the thing that we want to start
taking into account so now if we want to
we can again isolate that that fell out
here when we come through to do the
compute lighting you can see when we
sort of have our iterations we go
through the destination I don't know why
total photons receive is still sitting
next we don't do that anymore
but anyway when we come through here and
we're doing our our computation I can
just pick that one out and do a
completely different lighting pass on
that particular on that particular
individual and what I can do if I want
to here is I can set it again do exactly
the same thing as a good to verify let
me see if this is actually how is this
so I actually want this as well in the
else clause there we go
so in order to verify that this is
actually doing what I want what I can
also do is say well the accumulation
here the death visibility we don't care
about but this is what's going to get
set to the new color value for this tile
let me set it to yellow here as well
that this with a v3 or v4 yeah so what I
can do here is say all right if the
destination index equals the the one
that I'm trying to do such a laying on
then what we'll do is do a special
letting path for right now we'll just
set it to yellow again this should show
up as the same highlighted square right
and it does so that's good that's
exactly what we want although I think
that's actually what would that mean
that everyone else will get lit by a
little bit of yellow in theory should be
it doesn't seem to be though
anyway ignoring that fact so once we got
that right I'm wondering why I wonder
why is that doesn't put any yellow light
into the scene something weird has
happening there wouldn't you say
hmm I mean correct me if I'm wrong but
if I'm setting this accumulator value to
be bright yellow then on this path each
lighting path it will take the front
emission color which is the thing that's
that pulled in for lighting for you know
as using it as a source from then on it
will take and use that as you know as
effectively an emitted yellow light or
it should anyway I would argue but it
doesn't appear to be I mean what happens
if I just crank that value to an
absurdly high amount I mean I should see
something right okay so it's really just
a question of power and we don't get
very much bleed I guess from one of
those if it's just one if it's just set
to one you can see how much fun this
lighting is going to be when we're when
we get it all nice like it's so cool to
have an environment where you can have
like multiple light sources and they
sort of create this nice sense of space
right like you can see already how this
is going to be fun you know if you have
a game and it's got you know a little
fire back there or something in it and
you know you kind of got these this sort
of nice space being created by the
different pools of light especially so
if we start getting it again so it
properly doesn't transmit a new light to
surfaces that are out that are big
shadow or whatever anyway so we know
we're picking the right one and in this
regime what we now need to do is is
implement this loop differently right so
if we imagine here we've got this this
forest index
sorry I'm stinking so anyway if you can
we got the source index we're going to
loop over all of these and we know we
don't want to test against ourselves
obviously so this equation still more or
less does what we expect it to do right
so so we want this to basically be the
same we're going to take the light that
we know is incoming we're going to take
the vector to the light we're going to
see it's got to be in front of us
basically and it's got to be you know
some reasonable distance away it can't
be zero can't be right up against us and
then what we're going to do is take the
two light this is that that
normalization so two light is
effectively the Ray that we would be
searching along and what we also would
find at this point is that we we can
take again that clean equation we know
what that is as well because we know
what the source normally is so I can
actually compute this fairly directly so
if we want to look at that like that
some inner product and again this is
inner product we're already doing for
lighting you can see right here we've
got or well know maybe it's not I don't
know if we ever do this one for lighting
edge so I guess but if we were to take a
look at what the the sort of the inner
product is with the direction we're
searching along and oh right now so I
didn't get back because that's the one
to the light source that's not the
direction we're the Ray we're searching
along so I take it back I think I take
it all back
I forgot we need another thing in here
because we're not just doing one search
we're going we're not just searching
along our with our main normal we're
actually going to search her along
potentially more than one of those right
so if I say the in here we're going to
have like a ray index equal zero ray
index is less than
however many raise there are so what I
want to do here is say okay let the pose
that I just have a bank of rays that I'm
going to cast along so I just have
multiple of these right at first I'm
just going to try passing along I guess
a single one of them probably so we'll
just say you know there's just going to
be one ray and maybe that ray is the Ray
that is the reflector ray so we will
actually treat it the same so we'll just
say I've got the reflector that I'm
computing I'll just cast out straight
out from it because we know we're
probably going to do that one but then
we probably want to add a few more in
here that are going to capture the light
from sort of other directions as well so
we'll start with that ones we're going
to loop over the Rays here we're going
to say for each ray we need to figure
out sort of the normalized version we're
assuming this ray is normalized so
assuming that the life is not too close
to us what we're going to do here is
sort of collide against against the
light itself so I take it back we don't
probably need this so much if we take a
look at that ray value can say all right
the Ray that we're shooting along is
going to be raised ray index we want to
now figure out whether that ray and the
weather that ray will ever intersect the
light the plane of the of the of the
source and so the way that we would do
that is again by the inner product like
I talked about - the inner product of
the Ray and the source normal that gives
us an idea of ray source and that gives
us an idea of whether or not there's any
chance of hitting about what we want to
do is avoid anything that's too like
oblique to us so if something is real
Leon the edge like we really only want
things that are that are going to be in
the reasonable hemisphere around this
point so we want to look to make sure
that there's a reasonable amount of
approach to that so we look and see this
again this is that cosine term here that
I talked about here that's this term
right here
so we're basically saying okay we're
casting out from a reflector we have a
plane
so this is our Ray this here is the
source then we're taking the inner
product of these two things and we want
to see that they have a regional
approach now I guess now I think about
it though we want things pointing in the
opposite direction to us
glad I just drew that diagram so really
we want this to be negative source then
if you will we want it to be pointing
back towards us not away from us and so
we wanted to get that sense right
because we are doing the diagrams this
way we want the normal point towards us
so we want the dot product if we're
looking for it to be positive we
actually want to be kind of coming out
this way here right the other way we
could do that is to just invert the
sense of vist right we could instead say
well it goes from zero to negative one
there some like that but it seems easier
to just invert it there I don't know six
one half dozen to the other right
similarly speaking I suppose you could
just negate it on the way out or you can
just negated here if you want to it's
going to be the same either way right so
you can you can just the negative will
distribute over over the left on so
anyway this is the the value that we
want to know in terms of how aligned
they are again if there's zero zero
they're perpendicular if they're 1
they're directly facing each other and
everywhere in between is OK with us we
want to compute our AP value so that
that value that I said before which we
computed over here this stuff where's
the actual here it is so it's the
negative dar XB ry c RZ so what we want
to do there is you can compute it almost
directly but not flight because you
don't actually know what the D value is
but we can easily find out what the
value is fairly cheaply I'll show you
how that do that second so you know if
you want to do the tea rate computation
what we do is we say all right we've got
a RX b ry c RZ again the a b and c are
just the normal two that are just at
that source normal and again we want to
probably use the same source normal that
we were using we need to use the same
one that we use for the inner product so
since we're negating the inner product
here again we need to use the same one
in both cases so you know what we could
do is say racehorses then we could leave
it this way again and do something like
that which maybe we want to do so that
the source sentence will use directly
then we can use the source then directly
here for the inner product so you can
state source then well actually I guess
we just did the inner product so
racehorse then this is that inner
product of race or sin right nxr are x
and y are y and z are Z and that
negative D needs to be on the top so the
problem here is what is negative D right
we need some way of computing that
negative D so in order to compute D what
we have here is d is supposed to be the
AR x BR y plus Z or Z plus D equals zero
for the plane equation right that's what
we're supposed to get and we wanted to
Center it around the race so again despi
has the origin of the Ray has to be
where that's centered around well we
know that despi you know the location of
the source producing a point on the
source relative to the destination is
pretty easy
we know that the relative source P could
just be found by subtracting the despi
you know the source be subtracting away
the destination D from there that
produces for us a vector that goes from
the destination to the source pretty
easily where where is my diagram of what
we were just drawing didn't we have
thought I was drawing something else
here okay I drew it right here I guess
for some reason all right
we can't produce this value pretty
easily right because this is our
destination reflector this is our source
reflector right here we can produce this
arrow pretty trivially because it's just
a source position - the death position
problem is we want the D value of the
plane so how do we get the D value of
the plane well we can actually just
reverse solve the equation to find that
out right we know that we've got you
know NX px + NY py + NZ pz + D equals 0
we want to solve for Z we know all of
these things right so all we have to do
is just put them on the other side and
we're done right in terms of figuring
out what the D value is the D value is
just going to be negative NX p x- n YP y
negative n Z PZ what are what is that
it's just the negative dot product right
of n transpose P that's it so we can do
that very simply by just saying negative
inner product of N and P right so that
gives us that D value that we wanted and
now we have our intersection point right
very very simple nothing to it so
there's our test for how close our
intersection is what we want to do now
is say well okay I needed a bigger one
I'm out what I want to say now is like
okay if I've got that I need to have
some understanding of whether or not
I've actually hit it and like I said we
can do that with a pretty simple check
again we can produce the like the raid
point if section essentially by taking
our starting point and adding the Ray
times the distance along it right if I
start where we started where the Ray
origin is if I add however far we went
for the intersection times the Ray I
should step out to where it is now I've
got my
points at the intersection plates I can
then take the distance and figure out
whether or not I intersect so the
intersection is just going to be you
know rape and I can hear discs squared
is just going to be rapey - source P
well actually relative source cream got
to keep them in the same space right so
I know if I take the rate the location
where the Ray is going to be oh and
actually I guess I don't need to do that
right if I take the location where the
Ray is going to going to be relative to
the you know the destination P I think
where I would actually hit the plane I
subtract away where the source is in
this space I end up with a distance
squared right and then I can say whether
intersects by just saying if the
distance squared is less than the square
of the source radius right so if the if
the distance a way of the point again
I'm just doing exact one thing I said I
was going to do if I intersect a plane
let's say here's where the reflector is
this is the source reflector here is the
destination reflector I come out here I
find my intersection point and now I say
how far away am i from here to here
right how far away am I I'm going to get
a value out all I want to do is compare
it to this radius if it's more than that
radius I didn't intersect if it's less
than I did that's all I have to do right
so I take the length squared I can
compare two squares just the same as I
could compare the non squared version
doesn't change the direction of the
comparison at all so I can just say if
the length square to just avoid the
square root
it's a length squared of these is less
than radius I intersect it otherwise I
didn't that's all there is to it all
right and in fact I can just put that
inside here I don't even really
to look at it right so there you go so
if I intersected then I know that I've
got a new intersection value and an off
we go
so that's effectively the code for doing
the shadowing along the Ray and what I
can do now is just say that outputs a
value per source that determines whether
or not I actually want to be polite what
I could do is still use the exact same
lighting transfer that we're using
before just by nesting these down so
what I could do is say all right let's
actually just make this whole thing
[Applause]
actually just be a preamble that happens
right so what I can do here is say all
right let's just get this whole thing
going right and all I'm going to do here
is what do I have to do so this is the
destin'd mixer did I keep that in the
right line that's a tune yeah so all I
have to do here is just say all right
for each of the sources I'm looping over
I got rid of the other sort of version
of the loop so instead of this here I'm
just going to say for each of the
sources I actually wanted rid of this
stuff and say for every source I'm going
to do exactly what I was doing before
but if it happens to be this one special
one I was trying to look at specifically
what I'm going to do is compute a
shadowing value for this source I by
using my ray information right that's
that's all it was going to do now I
think I guess there is a problem here
which is I kind of do have to do it
beforehand because in order to do this I
have to
so I have to compute the shadowing
information before going further I guess
[Music]
so this is going to be a little bit
tricky but so if you take a look at what
happens here where normally we're
summing up all of the accumulators right
and so what I'd rather do here is I
guess what I would rather do here at
here's here's the way we can actually
test this a little bit more carefully
let's actually put it in here so after I
do the light contribution before I do
the accumulation what I'm going to do is
say if it's you know give it to the
normal case where we're not the special
reflector that we've picked out then we
just do the summation is normal
otherwise what we're going to do is
we're only going to use let's say the
light that is the closest one that we
hit just for starters so the way I'm
going to do that is I'm going to say all
right let's introduce a value which is
close to fit I'm going to call that
value 32 max here so you know it starts
out being nothing when we come through
here I'm going to say all right we test
against our rays and you know what I'm
going to have the closest hit I'm going
to click this Ray's definition up at the
top as well so I'm going to say we've
got you know here are arrays and we've
got our closest hit our closest hit is
also an array there array an array which
is one for every ray right so when we
come down here what we can say is for
this particular ray if this was a hit
first of all we can say before we do any
other checking we can just say if key
ray is less than closest hit or
something like this we can do that here
before we bother computing whether or
not we actually have to think because we
don't need to bother checking this if we
aren't even going to be the closest hit
yet but any way we can do is say alright
we've got a particular ray I want to see
whether or not it's the closest hit or
not so I'm just going to say for this
Ray index was this ray closer than the
closest thing I've already evaluated
if it's nothing I'm just going to ignore
it if it is then I'm going to go through
and see if I actually if I did hit
I'm going to make this be the new
closest hit so this just gives me a way
of saying which light source is the
closest along the Ray and what I'm going
to do is I'm going to step the
accumulation see to just be whatever is
the result is just the long just that
one ray right so so that's the end of it
right now what I'm assuming will happen
here other than having six compile
errors what I'm assuming happy here is
this should make our square be black
probably if we did everything right
which we probably did oh well it is
black of course there's other ways it
could be black that part that I don't
have anything to do with that but the
reason I say that is because if you
think about what we just told it to do
we said only use any thing that's that's
directly above you know it's doing a
calf straight out the top only do
something that's straight out the top
now we could see if we're working at all
by moving over here I'm seeing if we
ever get consuming right on top of it
and it looks like it does work if we do
that right if we're right on top of it
you can kind of see that we do get a
well actually knows but you know what
would happen there is if we're right on
top of it what's happening there is
we're actually picking a different
closest point let me get rid of the Kuro
sprite again because that's just
creating again too much of a problem for
our test case
all right let's try that one more time
if I go ahead and move up here let's see
whether we can ever get so it doesn't
look like we're actually able to get
that to hit even though we should
probably be hitting it as we pass
through there so that would suggest to
me that it's not really working properly
now one thing I can do let me just make
it a little bit easier for us here which
is if I go to handmade world mode I
thought we had a way to add the lighting
in here
oops that's not real mode that's world
[Applause]
let's push life that's what it is so
when you put the light on here
let's give it a much larger radius so
now you can kind of see that we've got
if I come from the perspective here so
now we know that if we debug this
routine we should a lot the race should
be able to hit this emitter here and it
should actually work right so now we
should be able to get sort of that that
information going forward so that's good
right that's what we want all right so
what we should see here is we should be
able to go back to our code we should be
able to debug it now so that we actually
do hit the light that's coming off in
fact let me go ahead and just actually
step through it there because we should
have in this case a an intersection here
for the light and it should be able to
transfer that that light that's above it
should be able to get a hit on it so
let's go ahead and see
do I have a way to get into Rendon nope
okay so let's go ahead and see what
happens if I go ahead and step into this
and what I'm going to do here don't try
this at home
I don't actually know if it work is I'm
going to actually try on the fly getting
this to go into debug mode so this is a
release build and I'm just going to try
compiling debug mode with hot code
reloading which apparently just worked
which is awesome and then I messed up in
here so it's effectively what I'm trying
to do here is figure out why we're never
getting inside here or to see whether or
not we're ever getting cider so we are
are we ever getting inside here we are
so it looks like we are making it all
the way in - in fact it looks like we're
actually we are actually getting a hit
ah but there is our problem so or at
least one of our problems so one of the
things I neglected to do here is clamp
the Ray - it's allowing tips that are
behind it right this tear a value is
going to cast out in both directions
effectively there's nothing to prevent
it from shooting backwards so T ray can
come out negatives and it's always any
negative values are going to be less
than any values that are positive
because negatives always less than
positive so it's always going to pick
something behind us which is it
emphatically not what I wanted it to do
so what we really want to do here is say
if t ray is greater than 0 and less than
the closest fit right that's actually
what we wanted it to do
that's the more that's the more fruitful
approach so let's try that and go from
there
all right so what we can do now is is
rerun and
and start to bugging this new not so
busted version alright so what we see
now actually is it appears to be working
more correctly you can see as I move
over the top of it I actually do once it
moves into sight I actually do hit it
and when it moves out I'm no longer
hitting it right so that's actually
quite nice that's actually exactly what
I wanted to have happen so now that's
perfect because what that means is that
if there was something in between the
two of these two things we would
actually get the shadowing happening
which is exactly what I wanted and off
we go so we could run this on everybody
of course it's expensive but we could we
could run this on everybody in fact
let's go ahead and do that just
temporarily yet to see how slow it
actually is the problem is we're only
casting at one rate right now when we
start to cast out more rays it'll become
a lot more expensive and probably won't
work but I can obviously do that fairly
straightforward all I have to do is as
we you know as we go I just you know get
rid of that if statement right well in
order to do that I have to get rid of
the bottom miss as well you know let's
just do it this way let's just say if
one so it will always pick that pattern
in all cases so this is going to be a
lot slower now presumably and what you
can see here is it's it's also got
obviously the problem of since it's only
casting out in exactly one direction
almost no lights ever hit any other
surfaces right and this is exactly why I
say you need to have a lot of different
directions that you can cast out and
find other like other sources that you
want to hit so it's exactly working
properly we don't really know it's
working entirely properly yet because we
haven't really done much testing other
than to see that it's sort of look like
it's working if we now start casting out
in different directions that would give
us something potentially usable this
raise value is obviously kind of a
constant thing that we can do let's go
ahead and cast out some other rays right
just some some other rays and other
direct
right so if we want to cast up reason
other directions we need some way of
figuring out some stuff some other
directions to test right and the problem
is this is that's easier said than done
in our particular circumstance because
we don't really have very much
information to stage to figure out where
that should actually go and you know
what I'll do here is I'll just put a
bunch of these in that there we go one
two three four five six seven eight nine
ten eleven twelve thirty forty fifty all
right there we go
don't ask me how I had ended up picking
exactly 16 there I don't know but what I
want to do here is say okay for you know
each of these rays I want to have some
other possible rays to cast out and what
I'm going to do is I'm going to do the
stupidest possible thing this is really
bad don't do this at home and we'll
definitely need something better later
but what I want to do is I'm just going
to create a trays here for the time
being just by perturbing each of these
by some value right so I'm just going to
return each of these by something I
basically pretty random right at nothing
particularly smart here I'm just picking
random rays
oh never mind this isn't constant what
am I talking about this is per
destination yeah I'm just thinking
random reason I'm not picking them in
any sort of smart way I'm kind of
surprised at how fast that actually was
running but what you can see now is that
we now have more chance of picking
things up right because each of the Rays
that we capped out effectively has you
know it's got eight chances of being in
the direction that will actually hit the
light source and that's great but again
you know not good enough and if I went
and picked those rays better we would
get more intersection certainly but what
you're seeing here is specifically the
sort of thing I was talking about before
where it's like casting out raised by
themself probably isn't going to cut it
the number of rays you would have to
send out is just going to be too high
and granted when we start doing this in
a multi resolution fashion which we're
going to do eventually it will be better
certainly but it won't still probably be
good enough so that's why I was thinking
what we probably want to do here is make
something that's going to be a little
bit more cone based so that it can pick
up more ships so if we want to replace
something that's going to be a little
more cone based what I can do first of
all is let's switch back to this so I
can verify that our cone base tracing is
actually doing something what I can do
there is expand the radius of the cone
as we go out in a really like I said
very cheap and cheesy way and so what
I'm going to do there is say okay let's
suppose that when you cast the r8 out as
it gets further out it gets wider so
this distance here where we look at the
distance square is less than the square
of the source R what we actually want to
do there is take a look at if it's
actually the source R plus the plus
whatever our cone radius is
and our cone radius in this case is just
going to be proportional to tear a tear
a is the thing that kind of goes out and
what we can say is for every certain
distance that it goes out it gets a
certain distance wider now what we could
say is that it could be exactly even at
this point it could be that for every
for every unit that goes out it gets one
unit wide that might be a little bit too
wide but for now we can sort of just say
that's what that is right and so now
what we should see again is a much
smoother like you getting you can
actually see it here quite good quite
specifically you can see that you get a
much wider pickup for all of these
lights and so even though now we're just
casting one ring you get quite a bit
bigger pick up if you're casting out a
cone because it makes it a lot easier
for them to be seen now the problem that
we get well I do think we might have a
bug in the cast though because that it
doesn't make a lot of sense as to why
that would be the specific area that
this would pick up if this were casting
out a cone it should pick up this as it
gets further away it should be picking
it up right now in fact oh well you know
what but it's making other things are
being closer in the cone so that's
actually not that that's actually not
that unusual yeah that's fine
so yeah as you can see if we make it a
wider cone we can pick up more things
the problem with this is if we only take
the closest hit that means that our cone
is not going to be doing a very sensible
thing for us in terms of Stan's wing so
what's going to happen here right
imagine if we trigger for tracing out a
cone in this way right then our problem
that we're going to get is that
something that's in the cone like this
but maybe there's a giant reflector
right here that's what we should mostly
picking up some little thing that's in
the cone right here that's going to
register as the first hit and we're not
going to get any contribution from this
at all and so what we want to probably
do there is say let's take a look at
when we hit something
I how close it is we kind of want to
know something about how these values
should be composited together right and
so we get into sort of the same problem
we were having with the DEF peels before
it's almost we kind of need to know you
know for the cone radius we kind of want
to know how much of the cone you're
intersecting with and how much of a cone
you're dissecting with should sort of
make you have more or less contribution
to the thing that we're to the lighting
solution right and so things that only
intersect the cone a little bit we don't
want them to block out things that are
very heavily in the cone so yeah again
we get back to that sort of same problem
now if we wanted to do something created
there like I said there are things we
can kind of do if we want to we can try
to make these be a little bit more
extensible in terms of how they're
picking up what's left in the cone for
example what we could do is again pick
sort of that multi sampling take sort of
that multi sampling approach in the cone
we could say something like the overlap
amount is going to give us some
indication of what's happening we could
try to sort along the T values I don't
think that would be particularly good
idea necessarily though so again yeah
I'm not sure I'm just really not sure
what we want to do once we've produced
that value certainly what we could do is
take how much in the cone you are and we
could say something like
we could have some heuristic that we use
it's like how much in the cone you are
versus how far away you were or
something like this I don't know that's
ever going to produce a particularly
good value
so here's what I'm going to say I'm
going to I'm going to step back from
this slightly because we're coming up on
the end of the stream so I'm going to
leave this for now we're going to think
about that a little bit more but I'm
going to leave that for now what I'm
going to do is that we do something
really ridiculous because why not
and what I'm going to do here is going
to say all right let's suppose that we
we take our raid our bank of raised here
and I'm going to do this in a very
different way
so what I'm going to do instead is I'm
going to say let's take let's take some
ridiculous number of raise here because
we can let's take some ridiculous number
of raise and let's just generate raise
at the start that let's generate 32 of
these guys that aren't based on any
normal yet so what I'm going to do is
going to say for you know one two
however many of these I want to do and
close this hit I guess we can also do a
read count phrase
so this will initialize to any number of
raids that we want for the time being so
what we're going to do is we're going to
start by saying all right each of these
Ray's is going to be equal to a random
value for now all right so what I'm
going to say is I'm gonna say we're
going to do a normalize of 0 and we're
going to pick literally a bunch of
random values where's our random so we
want a random bilateral so we want two
random bilateral on a random series so
here's our random series and we just
want to take basically a random
Direction not a pigley good random
Direction by the way we're gonna take a
random direction we're going to take 32
of these rays here we're going to
generate thirty two random rays sort of
cover a sphere in them when we come
through here I'm just going to loop over
them I'm just going to skip any rate
that doesn't point out in the direction
of whatever the element is so what I'm
going to say is if the inner product of
the Ray and the destination normal isn't
is greater than zero we'll use it if
it's not we won't so now I'm just kind
of bloomin out along along a bunch of
different directions here and it's going
to be slow right it's going to be very
slow because we've got too many rays if
that makes sense and I just want to see
how many of these it would take to do
anything interesting
it looks to me
like it's not still enough let's see
what we have to crank this number to I'm
just curious
so it's still not really able to pick up
what I've expect I wonder if I've got I
may have some this is not a very good
test because I may just have some really
bad bugs at 256 it should be pretty much
taking up most things and just be
incredibly slow right
yeah so if I look at that
it's still so I think we may have some
bugs in there at 256 it should be
roughly good although to be fair these
things are are not as big as they
probably should be because the members
were sort of sub Stanley I do wonder if
maybe we did something where we overfill
a little bit like sort of got kind of
this minimum spanning here if we did
something where we actually tried to
overfill that a little bit if we did
something more like this
I'm wondering if that is more
representative as well just to get their
reflectors so that they cover the scene
better right and
you know eventually that does seem like
it's kind of working maybe a little
better but honestly still not really so
I think we've still got some bugs in
there let's take a look what how much
time we have seven minutes not really
man
so let me take a look I think we've got
some bugs in there at the moment
unfortunately because that doesn't seem
quite right to me so I would like to
have a little bit more information about
what's going on here and and why so
presumably if I set this down again to
some relatively low number it should be
plenty fast and of course it is but
again you're only getting raised in
certain directions there and in theory
16 rays should have been roughly the
same speed as before because that should
be the same as casting a trays because
some of those rays you know half of
those rays wouldn't be used right but it
doesn't look like that's really the case
necessarily so I'm a little wondering
kind of why that's why that's true maybe
just because my wife's source is getting
picked up twice there we go so that's a
little odd I guess there's just a few
more inner products and that does seem
maybe like a problem but still
so yeah what I'd like to do is I'd like
to look at those let's take a second to
just look at what those rays actually
are is there a reason that none of my
windows ever stay open by the way like
what do I have to do to make it so it
doesn't clear all my windows I have no
idea what I'd like to do is I'd like to
see what those razor right I'd like to
just see make sure that they're picking
sensible rays I don't know if I might
have to compile and debug them to see it
that doesn't look that um
that doesn't look great let's go ahead
and step in there shall we
I'm going to
that made you spend an artifact of me
getting the wrong breakpoint okay yeah
this makes this looks much nicer
so yeah that seems reasonable and again
I think if we step in we should see that
when we go to test these rays we only
test about half of them which you can
see happening here and that looks about
good right yeah so if I am to do yeah
like I said kind of a lower number of
those and I don't know like I mean I
could do a lower number of rays and
conical this is something I think we'll
just leave till next weekend to think a
little bit more about but I'm just kind
of playing around with it a little bit
here so maybe this grows at a rate of
like two meters at 0.25 meters per meter
gone so there's the cones or narrow eye
and we'll take a look here just to see
[Music]
so if the distance squared is less than
source are in the con r so this is the
cone version of that and yeah it just
looks it just looks buggy because you
know the one that's underneath it I
guess it could be never shooting out
anything in that direction maybe we just
need to be a more sensible about picking
the directions and that's fine too I
guess we can try that really quick if we
were going to pick directions a little
bit better how would we do that
obviously we don't really want to do the
random stuff quite yet so so if we Randy
something more like that we just do we
just do something that was based off of
the destination and so probably here we
just say just and what we want to do
here is take the destination normal and
offset it by a certain amount those
amounts want to probably be in the plane
of V they want to be sort of distributed
in that Hemisphere relatively well
that's a actually surprisingly hard
thing to do there's actually quite a few
people who have written things about how
do I quickly generate you know given a
normal how do I quickly generate good
directions to search along and we should
probably take a look at some of those I
don't recall all of them at the moment
but basically what we want to do is
something cure that would
give us the ability to to base our
search directions off of the normal
right and probably here I guess this is
probably sufficient
it's still not great it's not it's not
good let alone great but it might be
good enough for us to test here
so here's one that has a more reasonable
search direction it looks like the speed
of this is pretty bad in terms of I
don't know if it's because of the number
that there are I will say that this
check can go away because we're now
pretty much exclusively producing ones
that are going to go in that direction
we could also only do this check if the
resulting light was actually going to be
seen as well because right now we're not
doing that either but yeah that's a
separate issue so let's try that again
and one thing you can kind of see here
although it's still not really very good
solution yet
one thing you can kind of see though is
we are getting a real solution now like
you can see that as I move around the
wall I'm lighting up what's behind the
wall only when the light forth is
actually propagating and so that's kind
of nice right that's a lot more usable
of a solution if we take a look here
you
we really need to stop having the head
be on an unstable spring to say that to
say the least but you can kind of see
like this is starting to be a more
usable basic lighting solution as we go
right like that's actually pretty good
it's a little bit buggy because again
these reflectors are not I like how much
the spring is wigging out that's a very
satisfying we should we should just fix
that in brain there's all this crappy
head code
so this stuff here you know we can
choose this out pretty easily by just
saying like okay you know the the head
GDP equals GDP this code right here I
believe is really all the entirety of
our problem
what I'm assuming is that if we were
just to clamp this we would be okay
so if we did something like if the
length of this particular vector is you
know greater than you know some some max
cap value we'll just say that we're
going to multiply it by the inverse of
that value so effectively just saying
that if this this length is greater than
if it's greater than 0.1 then let's just
you know make it equal to 0.1 I think
that would do it looks like 0.1 is not
quite large enough give it a little more
than that
and so there you can see like I just
basically clamped that spring down so
that even though it's still a really ill
behaved system it doesn't cause any
problems now because it can't get
unstable enough to lose to lose control
right so again yeah just looking at the
lighting solution now you know not good
yet but getting better you know as we
move the light around you can start to
see that it's you know pretty reasonable
so I guess I know the thing I would be
interested in checking it I guess we are
we my mind the Q&amp;A now I don't even know
where I'm at
let's see if we're time nine minutes
into the Q&amp;A okay
so if I take a look here and say all
right the DDPs clamps so we're happier
now if I go into world mode and I wanted
to create sort of another give myself a
little bit more to play with here in
terms of of of occluders when I do add
standard room if I want sort of you know
in here play around with with what's
going to happen what I could do is say
you know if offset y equals two or off
at y equals you know negative two or
something like this and in that scenario
now when I've got sort of these light
lighting quarters on both sides
basically let me just go ahead and and
turn off the reflector view so now if we
take a look at what happens when I'm
moving around
you can really see the shadowing start
to be you know somewhat reasonable right
again not not great but it's getting
better and so you can kind of see that
we're we've got the surfaces behaving a
lot more sanely where you know if you
take a bird's-eye view of this and
imagine we smooth it out and stuff when
it's on the GPU you can start to see how
this would be a plausible
you know lighting solution right let's
take a quick look at what happens if we
change the number of iterations on this
I so if I come through here and I change
the lighting iteration count down to one
oops
and so here is just one pass on the
lighting in terms of light distribution
let's crank it up to three here's three
iterations of the lighting
so another thing I should in seeing also
is what the emission amount does two and
three don't seem to do very much I don't
know why that may be just a balance
issue like to look into that but the
because yeah the difference between two
and one is pretty noticeable I'm
wondering if am i doing something wrong
there like a fool baby I wonder if I'm
doing something wrong there it might be
so I still think there's some bugs in
there that doesn't feel right to me
so we're yeah we're we're still a little
bit of ways a way I think from actually
having a bug free version of even the
basic thing that we've sort of
constructed so far what I do want to do
to here is I'm going to do a quick
change here of making two different
colored walls as well so we can play
with that next weekend - let me just
actually I'll make that wall blue
so here you can kind of see two
different wall colors now solid blue
ball and a and the red one and you know
what I'd like to see eventually what I'm
not seeing yet right is I'd like to see
as we do more I'd like to see more
bounce lighting happening I feel like
right now it's really not you know I
feel like this wall should be spreading
out some more light there maybe these
there should be some mutual amount there
I'm understanding in increasing the
emission amount to I want to take a look
at that real quick but I think we just
have a some debugging to do next weekend
to really take a look more carefully at
how that's working so here's the the
emission values what I want to do is if
we assume that one is the highest
emission value and zero is the lowest
emission value what I'd like to do is
like max emission I'd like to introduce
the notion that there's some like there
so there's a maximum value and the
maximum value is you know 10 or
something so a light of 1 is actually
that way we can still transmit them more
directly so if you look at how much
lighting is coming in now right it's a
lot brighter the light source is and
like that blue light is like that blue
surface there is really bright and I
would expect to see potentially some
blue light kick out onto like these
surfaces and I am seeing a little bit
but but only a little bit there and so
I'm interested to know why I see so
little in
terms of that right and ni and I'm not
sure so I do wonder like okay so if it
could say if we increase the lighting
bounce right I would expect to see that
smooth out and it doesn't really so I do
I do think that we're not really
sampling very well you know we're still
kind of just kind of crappy in terms of
what we're doing here and the reason I
say that like I said is just because the
difference between our first bounce and
our second bounce is is like nothing
right so you know looking at this here
this is with no bounces it's just direct
lighting and when I go up to one bounce
of lighting I do get you know a
noticeable difference when I go to two
bounces of indirect lighting I see
almost nothing different about them
right there's like no increase like so I
do think that there's a little bit like
we need to start thinking about our
sampling and probably tighten that down
more before we go any further forwards
could do or their engine features or
ideas that emerge during the handmade
hero streams and that you since back
corded to the 1935 engine not that not
in terms of actual features but I but
there is one thing that happened on the
animator gyro stream that I had not
thought about before that I do use it's
the counter trick so if you look back at
handmade hero there was a thing on
stream that I realized where I was like
oh wait if you are only using one
compilation unit then underscore
underscore counter the preprocessor
macro is unique for all the lines in the
entire program normally it's not because
normally it's only unique per file but
in this case it's actually unique
through the project which means that you
can actually just know that every
location where you use counter has a
unique index into a table and I do use
that in the 1935 code base and I'd never
thought of that until handmade hero it
just happened on screen one time I've
never seen anyone even think about that
I've never seen anyone mention it I've
never seen it even discussed is the
first time to my knowledge that it's
ever had been done was on the stream not
maybe someone had done it before but I'd
never heard of it and I use that now
midlow for the random series you picked
at random munted before could it have
been could it have made any sense to
pick three sixty four three two sixty
degrees or would absolutely any number
do oh wait is there a problem with the
stream no dropped frames here I think
maybe someone else maybe
unfortunately the stream got got toasted
someone else's maybe Internet had a
problem or maybe twitch other problem I
don't know but anyway the what's
happening there remember is that's the
secede value so in the random series we
haven't really done any random number
generation so right now we just have a
random number table and eventually we'll
just produce will replace this with an
equation that generates pseudo-random
numbers right so all that that was it's
the seed value so remember we have an
index into the table we just are seeding
into the table at that location you
could just as easily a big zero or
something right any number will do it's
just where you start in the table and so
because I didn't care what the new
random series was I that's why I picked
a one two three four right but you could
have picked anything
I wonder what happened did twitch go
down or something because my internet
connection does not seem to have dropped
anything like there were no there was no
loss to no BS at all so it doesn't think
it missed anything
yeah I'm guessing that it was just like
trich and just got toasted or something
on the route got toasted I don't it well
but then I should have seen dropped
frames so right because it doesn't
doesn't OBS report drop frames if the
inject server knowingly rejects them or
it gets you know it doesn't get act so
so so something happened in between
twitch receiving it and it going out I
guess is what I think I think of because
it couldn't actually be a route being
down because I would have seen the drop
frames from that I think right I don't
really know but that's my function
and yes I did see the tip on visuals
video that that wasn't exactly I was
talking about I know you can do that
but that's a thing that just saves one
window I thought there was a way to make
it so that in general it just kept all
the windows that you had open but it
doesn't seem to be the case and I don't
know why it's probably something in here
I guess
yeah I don't know where it went to
yeah I don't I don't know how you make
it do that but like at least on the one
at work it's in a state where it just
keeps all the windows open which is what
I want whereas this one is now in a
state where it automatically closes them
[Music]
and I do not know how to make it stop
doing that
so tools options environments tabs and
windows tools options vironment tabs and
windows a lot of folks are ok so this
preview tab thing that's what we don't
want let's see how that goes there we go
perfect yeah because that was what was
happening was coming up in that weird
preview tab thing and I don't want that
thank you very much thank you big fella
ho that is exactly what I wanted
so I'm not related to lighting but I've
been catching up with the multi-threaded
sim region's tonight and notice that we
never unset the entity active flag if an
entity is not contained in the updatable
bounds so I don't know what the status
of that code really is at this point
because it's a little bit Murphy we
never really quite figured out a way to
keep those regions working when they get
close to each other so that was a little
bit of a bummer but so I assume you're
talking about do we still have that
I so it looks like
if it looks like this should probably be
from what you're saying I think you're
right it should probably be flipped
right it should be probably be something
like this yeah where we say clear the
active flag if it's you know if it
doesn't overlap I guess the question I
would have is when does this part happen
where mark brain actives so that happens
after it's unpacked so yeah so that
should still work if we just clear it
out that way I think
we do have one problem here which is we
have nobody who's really active at this
point so let's see here I think our
world is too small for these things now
though so many problems they won't fit
they'll be they'll be crashing because
they'll just be in the middle of
geometry or something right I think
so what we can probably do we probably
can get the snake in there so let's see
so if I said if I said something like
this that'd do it
there is a snake
hello mr. snake
don't know why snake has stopped oh
because it got locked up with its own
tail as as is the snakes way let's make
the snake a little smaller
there's many copying around
and I guess the other thing we should
probably do because if we're going to
put the snake in there sometimes we
should probably have a way for the light
to be for there to be light in there I'm
just thinking out loud here so you know
if you imagine that you want to have
these things have some sort of a
emission possibility here so I guess
we've got I'm not sure how is that they
were doing an asset hi
let's take a look at entity visible
piece so if see visible key I has one of
these things here we could do like that
right and we could say in here is that
whatever the test is for these we could
do that as well so I could say like all
right put the light on there
and I don't really remember what the
values are for this but let's take a
look so if I look it to the render group
under push light you can see we've got
the render grouped the P plus the offset
got the radius so we'll just use that
the color and the emission which I guess
here we could sort of do though we
haven't really talked much about how we
want to do these pieces here so you know
the emission can just be begin why I
guess in this case because the dim line
is not used for anything else so we'll
just sort of cheese bad at the moment
and and do it that way so if we want to
we can now have lights on our enemies I
guess so if we make that happen
what we should be able to do then is
when we create construct these entities
to add a snake segment I what we should
be able to do here it's we want to have
them light up we can for example I could
just say that there's going to be a side
and add piece call for adding a light so
[Music]
I could just do it this way say it's add
piece light
the asset type idea at that point is
irrelevant
and we just end up with the radius the
offset B emission the color right and so
I think what we would get there is we
end up with for the pieces we've got a
piece of pipe light we've got the color
value just ends up being the v4 of color
in 1.0 the offset is the offset the v2
for the dimension is the radius in the
emission and the asset type is probably
zero honestly I think that's mostly what
we would need subside Jim offset color
and flags that should be everything
there what is the problem
trying to match argument list of entity
asset type oh that's an asset header
type sorry asset type ID
[Applause]
so in theory I think that would work
I don't actually know but you can try it
so let's suppose that I just for sake of
an argument could add to flight here and
did an empty and I said that it was that
you know zero zero zero I guess or maybe
it's slightly up from wherever the
actual bitmap is and then yeah I've got
the color let's say if the yellow light
is why not I and we got the emission
value well you know what else I need to
I need the radius so and then we have
the emission value mission values can be
work fairly weak light maybe yeah
all right so we've got radius offset
emission color so that actually goes
here and so in theory these snakes would
have like a little lights attached to
them now maybe yeah so that's good and
that light probably wants to be up a
little bit higher but yeah that's the
basic idea so we find just take this out
there you go so now you know if I move
away and and we're just looking at the
lighting from the from the snake it's
kind of life itself up and we get into
some of the problems that we're going to
have as well when we look at this
because you can see what there's some
bad we're probably going to have to
treat sprites especially right even in
the future when they're a little bit
better but if we take a look at what the
reflectors look like here
you can see that it's kind of a problem
because the sprites themselves little
snake sprites are these huge reflectors
that are it will shadow stuff underneath
them unnecessarily so that's definitely
going to be a problem that we'll have to
deal with kind of going forwards anyway
[Music]
let's see here so all right so I think
we're basically done I'm just kind of
screwing around at this point and see
here yeah
and one of the things that I guess is
pretty nice right and as we kind of go
forwards this is why I want a solution
that kind of works like this is you'll
notice that it doesn't really even
though our lighting is it's pretty slow
right now it's happening entirely on the
CPU which is not you know what's going
to happen in the future and we're doing
a bunch of sort of arbitrary stuff if we
can just spend another weekend or two
getting the quality up to a good
reasonable point we're still new scheme
that doesn't care how many light sources
there are and I like that aspect of it
so like adding the snakes light sources
even though there's three the the number
of light sources went up it's four times
what it was before it doesn't cost
anything more to do because generally
speaking it's just the cost of the total
number of things in the scene is the
cost of the algorithm it doesn't have a
multiplier per light source and
basically any global illumination scheme
is kind of that way because global
illumination is kind of assuming that
all of the things in the scene are
lights in a sense right so that's good
too so basically yeah like where we're
at right now is is a you know yeah you
get the idea I have well we're in the
hacky but I've decided I'm kind of
enjoying hacking on this I'm curious to
to know what happens if we turn off the
rate of texting on after a certain
iteration so what would what would
happen if we said that we allow light
bouncing with no occlusion after you get
to a certain point so the first like to
bouncer so like if the iterations is
greater then you know the the the first
erase the second duration happened with
ray occlusion
if you get past that you then are into
just straight accumulation mode at that
point so you know what does that look
like so you know here's here's what it
looks like to just not have any any of
those happening right the the number of
bounces right now is stays within there
you 0 and 1 and then you stop and now
what happens if we add a diffusion pass
after that right I'm just curious to
know what that looks like so it's it's
interesting it does send a lot of light
around if you ever have a pass that that
doesn't do the shadowing I guess because
at that point it's still able to take
take light from from the actual light
sources themselves
so you definitely you know you
definitely leaked a lot of light at that
point
all right I just want to know for my own
edification all right
all right I think I'll end it now let's
see here
Brian apps see trade license question
make it to Utley update my github branch
of your timer code from handmade hero
until you say otherwise meaning you're
apparently giving me unlike the folk
domain to any further code in that
folder would you prefer I ask the return
permission so you don't need to worry no
yeah you can just I'll let you know if
for some reason I ever don't want that
code to be copied out but yes the C tre
code you can copy out to your github
branch for sure all right let's close it
down thank you very much for joining me
for other sort of handmade here it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to following
through it at home you can always peer
to the game on handmade hero org it
comes with a source code so you can play
around with it maybe you can play around
the lighting and find some interesting
ways of solving the problems that we're
trying to deal with right now we also
have a forum site you can go to as well
ask questions the patreon page transport
the video series the schedule bot if you
would like to know one we're going to be
live and an episode guide you can use if
you want to catch up on old episodes
that's it for this weekend I will be
back next weekend I believe I do have a
move to do that may affect whether or
not I can stream I'm not sure but
probably be back next weekend if not the
weekend after for doing some more
improvements on the lighting quality
we're getting there it's starting to
feel pretty good actually it's just not
at our good quality level yet but it's
starting to feel like we you've got
options and we just need to start
getting a little bit more serious about
some of the ways in which we're
computing the letting transfer and we
maybe can make this work so that's
pretty exciting that's about it for
today so hopes to you all back here for
an extreme until then have fun
programming hoop and I'll see everyone
I'm going to take it easy everybody