hello everyone welcome to handmade Hiro
sure we could a complete game live on
stream we are in the middle of our
campus lop series very very many streams
this end of this month and beginning of
next month we have done all the work to
edit attachment points we I want to say
are pretty much ready to start going in
and getting all our art assets lined up
placed and so on so today on the stream
we want to do is start that process here
are the things that we've got to do
number one we've got to actually start
respecting these alignment points we can
edit them now we don't use them right so
we got to go into the code the entity
code now that we have all this
information about how stuff is going to
be aligned we need to actually use it
right so implement that and that's gonna
require some thought because now we've
we've got stuff we didn't have before
right we now have this this idea of
these pieces that can snap together and
we we more or less have an entire kind
of skeletal system almost like we can
snap bitmaps together kind of
arbitrarily and we can define new ways
that they snap together to we don't need
a lot of that for what we're doing but
it does mean we kind of to think a
little about it like how do we want to
do that okay we got like bodies and
heads so at least we know we want those
points what does that look like inside
the entity startup code and so on right
so we want to go do that so that's what
we're gonna start on today because in
order to even see that things are
working in that our editor actually does
what we think it does we're gonna need
that number two we want to then start
saving those once we can see that
they're doing what we want and we can
actually build the snap together pieces
the way that we want them built we want
to take that and be able to save it and
load it from a intermediate
representation that we can use as a
permanent storage format so just a text
file we kind of talked about this
it's a simple text file format so that
way we can save this along with our
actual input PM G's so that we have a
definitive reference of like here's what
you import to rebuild the hhas from
scratch right so you want to do those
two things and then finally what we'd
like to do is implement that Save button
so that when you hit the Save button in
the editor it updates your hhas
automatically and saves the C the C
style like text thing that that puts
that data into the HHA that you know
that you use as the source file format
so we got a bunch of stuff to do over
the next week and that's what we'd like
to get to because once we've gotten to
that point we should have all the stuff
in the game right then we we should have
all the different characters can be
sitting around or hopping around we can
place them in there we can start working
we can start looking at adding a ground
cover system if we want to because now
we have the ability to like place
alignment points on all of the like
little grasses and things so you know if
you want to think of this in terms of a
tech tree getting this feature done
unlocks a whole set of things we can do
to decorate our world which is really
what we want to be doing is is having
the freedom to decorate our world
however we want to and right now we did
the work to loading all our art assets
but we just been stymied by the fact
that we can't mark them up well now
we're gonna have a lot of opportunities
to mark them up and in addition to
having the opportunities to mark them up
we will also be able to use the editor
code be write to anything else we want
because that editor code is very generic
we could add any kind of editor there
that we wanted I don't know of anything
offhand like I I'm not anticipating that
we need to use it for a lot more stuff
because is a procedurally generated game
so it's not a lot of like editing of
actual levels or anything right so I
don't know that we're gonna need to lean
on it much but I did show you how to
write an easy quick generic UI system
and we used it and so now anything that
we want to edit we can and so we come
across something we were like we'd like
to edit this aspect of our inputs that
will just work because we can slap it
together really simply right so that's
where we're at it's a good time to be
handmade heroing I think because we've
got a lot of possibilities on the
horizon and that's where you want to be
so let's go ahead and take a look at
what I mean when I say that we've got
the editor going but we don't use it and
we'll see what we need to do to start
using it so if I run the game as it
stands right now one of the things you
can see here and you know another thing
we might want to do today I've mentioned
skill times is I want these things to
snap automatically like our debug stuff
that we have here it needs so it could
stand a little clean up but what we have
the ability to do now right is we can
select anything in the world that we
want to look at right and when we select
things in the world what we can then do
is we have a bunch of editor types of
things we could throw in here right now
there's only one thing we edit which is
alignment points we can get a list of
those alignment points here and we can
then manipulate them however we want so
for example I can set this information
so on now this information isn't really
being used although to a certain extent
you could argue that it is so if I go
click on this for example I think that
if we edited some of these things maybe
they would get used I don't know maybe
they're not gonna use it all I really
couldn't tell you it looks like maybe
not I'm not sure so I feel like the
default one maybe would get used I don't
know let's let me let me look in there
and see not sure which one we're
selecting at the moment yeah I don't see
any movement on it so maybe we're not
actually using one of those let me let
me go look at one that's more specific
and let me see so here we're looking
specifically at the cat right
it's kind of ridiculous all these weird
things we've got hopping around here so
if I'm looking at this cat specifically
which is let's see this right here so it
doesn't look like that's even getting
used even as the initial alignment point
now I'm not sure why that is because I
thought we were still using just the
initial alignment point but nothing in
here is actually responding as far as I
can tell and so one of two things is
true either we're not using it I don't
think that's probably true we probably
are using it or it actually gets
mirrored out and I think it's probably
the latter that's happening I think it
kind of gets mirrored out right so what
I'd like to do now is I'd like to go in
there and actually get all of this stuff
hooked up properly first of all we
probably don't want to mirror it anymore
and second of all we probably want to
start looking at ways of well there's a
couple of things we wanna do in fact
this is a good example of why oh saying
we might be the editor to add some
things when we select here you'll notice
it becomes pretty hard to select these
two things separately and like I select
something and I'm just getting a
particular bitmap index but it's hard I
can't really pick from multiple of them
right so another thing we might want to
do is have a list of what the bitmaps
were that you had clicked on so that you
could be more specific about which one
you were editing because there's two of
them right and so that's another feature
we probably have to add to the editor
and again I think we've set ourselves up
to do that well by baking the editor UI
stuff really generic we should be able
to throw that together in no time right
so a lot of stuff there that's what we
want to attack now get these things
actually working that will also allow us
hopefully to import a bunch of other
things into the game so that it can be
more populous right okay so let's take a
look at how these things are actually
being used right now so inside there are
file formats we've got the align points
here's how they're defined we've got a
struct align point it has some members
in it that allow us to say
a percentage alignment feature a size
for the thing like a scaling value and
the type typing to find in one of these
things what is it a lining for example
top of head base of neck or just default
to world things like that we want the
ability to use these things they're not
being used at the moment and I think and
I shouldn't say not being used you can
see that they weren't being used as we
edited them I think the reason for that
is that our current way of using these
align points is fairly anemic I think
what happens in the asset system is when
that gets loaded up so when we actually
go to bring something in what happens is
this loaded bitmap structure here right
you can see that it kind of mirrors a
lot of stuff you know this this thing so
we end up with stuff like the width over
the height the width and the height the
align percentage right that the the data
that was in the bitmap gets lofted up
into here and is generally incorrect
right because if we go back and edit
some of this stuff this becomes wrong
you know I'm saying and so what we
probably want to start doing is not
using this loaded bitmap as that you
know we want to just use the data
directly so I think that will probably
simplify things for us quite a bit now
if I go look at where this sort of stuff
happens you can see in here that we we
have some use of it in the asset system
this is a Dib that's that's our render
of test code and here's the asset
builders hasn't matter if we look in
here that's all if zeroed out code right
that's not relevant and so we come down
here we finally get some information
where we're actually using it it's
pretty straightforward stuff right so
just looking looking at a lot of this
stuff I don't think we really need most
of what's in there so I think what we
want to do is we want to look at now
pairing that back and having people
actually reach in and get that stuff
from the assets a little bit more I
think that
probably more what we would want right
okay so let's take a look at what we
want to do there let's start by seeing
what we can do for some of this stuff if
we got rid of the pitch who would
complain right like who's gonna get
upset about that looking here we've got
the bitmap pitch gets put in there right
it looks like we create the pitch when
we do make empty bitmap I'm not sure
anyone actually calls that who cares
about it let's see here we've got make
sphere normal map we're not using
anymore right so some of this stuff is
just old right sphere diffuse map so I
think these are not add pyramidal right
so these are these are not real things
we're not using them anymore let me look
at make empty bitmap and see if anyone's
using that no one is so I'm just gonna
get rid of these because these are just
old residual code we don't need anymore
if I go ahead and recompile we should
now be at a place where nobody cares
about the pitch at all and so we've
successfully got rid of one of those
members and let's keep trying to pare
that down some more so in terms of who
uses the width and height or the width
over height or the align percentage
again these are things that we could get
by reaching back into the asset the void
memory part here again a lot of this
stuff it's remember we wrote our render
originally to be a soft writer we move
to 3d so now we've got kind of too much
we we support a lot in here because it
was spanning different kinds of systems
we've now got the idea of textures which
means that even in the software renderer
the software renderer would now be a
thing that's that's keeping that texture
memory around so really this stuff as it
stands needs to be changed fairly
radically right and we want to start
looming this up
let's see who's doing what with memory
because I'm not sure I'm just gonna look
through here so you can see that the way
that it works is it uses that as sort of
temporary storage if you will right to
load that to load that stuff in here
rather than just loading it into the
texture and being done with it I'm gonna
let that stand for now but now I know
that that's
true I'm gonna put two do on here it's
like really we only need texture buffers
now because we can really update this
system to basically use just transfer
buffers that we use to shuttle things to
the card and we probably don't need
backing store anymore like this that's
probably just irrelevant for our
purposes so let's keep going when we've
got this width over height and width and
height I want to see who's using I just
want to learn everyone who's using this
stuff so I can have a better handle on
how that's working so let's see what
we've got here you can see here when we
create the texture handle we would have
had the information here so it's really
not that necessary the way that it's
working there so we probably can get rid
of that as well let's take a look width
and height there that actually can come
off of the texture handle now right so
bitmap texture handle would actually
have that information in it so the
texture handle bakes that in and and so
again it's really duplicate information
I'm gonna go ahead and see to what
extent I can really push that like if I
was to get rid of these two what could I
do they're like like can I actually get
rid of those entirely as I go also does
width over height actually need to be
there anymore again since the texture
handle has that information could we
just you know lean on that entirely one
of the things I'm looking at here is is
it possible to really get down to the
fact get down to the point where
renderer texture is all we really use
and this stuff isn't really used at all
anymore like it's loaded bitmap can that
just be render a texture now that's what
I'm looking at that's what I'm aiming at
I don't know how far we'll get we'll see
if we can get there so if we want to
look at the bitmap with bitmap Pyke here
I guess what I would say is we can
actually instead look at that texture
handle right so this texture handle here
where we actually see what the texture
handle is that we're looking at
now this is a renderer texture this is
the texture handle I can actually get
that with them height out myself so if I
want to get the width out I can I can do
that I don't remember exactly how that
works but I'm pretty sure it's pretty
simple yeah it looks like you just pull
it right you just pull it out so another
way you do that actually it would just
be to say texture handle dot width right
and height we just have that baked in
there and so that means in here we can
just say look if the bitmap within
bitmap height that's the same as what we
were doing before and we shouldn't need
anything else same happens here right
this is the same thing
we know what the bitmap width and height
is there because it comes out of texture
handle we don't need not to get it
somewhere else
excuse me
and this now no longer has to happen
either we just know what those two
things are so anyone who was doing that
can just look at those directly and
again that gets baked into the texture
handle which means that we don't need it
there so basically all of these things
can go away right alright so that was
actually very simple getting rid of the
width and height so off that goes
consuming so now we're really just down
to some of the base values in terms of
the align percentage again we want to
start reading out of that array that's
gonna be the most complicated to change
I'm gonna go with over - ow if I compile
without that we'll see who's actually
using it and then we'll see how to
replace it so if I come in here and look
at with over height what we can see is
when we get the bitmap dimension that's
really where that's getting used and
we're using that to just multiply out
when you say how big you want the height
to be we're just using that percentage
here we can reproduce that percentage
pretty easily using some kind of a safe
divide and I think most of time we call
get bitmap dim we've already guarded
against that here in terms of divides by
zero so I think that's probably okay
looking through here we're dividing by
those things anyway so really I think
because we're doing that kind of
prophylactic use it
case I think we can probably say that
this stuff is okay to use in general now
I can probably take that a little bit
further I can look to see who's actually
doing get bitmap Tim just so we have
some idea of who's in charge there you
can see it getting called so right on
push-fit Matic it's called who else is
using it you can see it's use it here
it's being used to get the the XY and
the size there went to make that
rectangle right that's where that's
being used primarily and then in the
debug code it's actually being used
there as well okay looking at how that's
being used though just you know in terms
of figuring out what's going on there
and the bitmap scale and that's where
stuff it's unclear to what extent we
really need that entire call it's a
little bit it looks a little bit
Squinkie in that and then I'm not really
sure to what extent it really needs to
to occur let me let me just check what
it's actually doing yes so looking at
this it's just a way of reproducing
these these sorts of things here the
basis P - to what extent this basis P
get used I'm gonna I'm gonna look at
this a little bit more closely in terms
of of what's happening there so basis P
does this part of the object transform
is that all that's happening who who's
in charge you're like what's going on
with basis P are people using this value
it looks like the min P is getting is
there is anyone else using the basis fee
and furthermore why are we doing it that
way I don't really know let's take a
look so if I if I go out and find the
bitmap that bitmap dim stuff let me go
figure out where that actually happens
bitmap used a bitmap damn looking here
you know what happens if I knock that
out cuz I'm not sure I really want that
to be in there anyway who's actually
using it so you can see it being used in
one place only so we're getting it rid
of that because again I'm trying I want
to compress this code down because a lot
of the stuff is reserved
a lot of it's vestigial remains so you
look at what's happening here this
object transform offset P Dimpy stuff
right you see us doing a vector ad here
why we're doing an XYZ manually if
someone wants to tell me why this isn't
written like this I would love it
because I mean can you see a reason why
I assumed it was because we used to be
doing different things there and now
we're not because we're in 3d that's
totally reasonable but what that means
is that this really should just go down
in here right so that is how we're
getting that basis P out right we're
taking the dim P and adding the object
transform offset so we don't really need
that furthermore it means the object
transform coming in here isn't used
anymore you can see the fact got
eliminated right that was the only place
that that particular thing was actually
being used so once we get to that point
we can be pretty sure that this is
really all we're talking about here that
means this goes away and we're left with
only this it also means that these
things that are being used here we can
be a little bit more careful and take a
look at how they're actually being used
and we might be able to simplify that
down a bit more to but for the moment we
know that that's all we needed for this
so let's go ahead and take a look at
what the other places that we're using
that were and we can go from there
so here's another place that's using the
that get bitmap dim so it doesn't need
this transform which is great because
that was just being created as a dummy
transform there anyway so that
eliminates that piece of code which was
ugly no transform being used here again
same thing where is that no transform
just defined so yeah no one wanted that
in the first place so that's another
great removal against simplifying the
code and getting rid of some stuff that
really shouldn't have been there in the
first place as things got simplified
down it just naturally removed which is
what you want any time to get the weak
key it's a good day so here's our width
over height getting back to the thing we
were actually looking at removing before
so looking at that value this get bitmap
dim as it's being called I think now you
know just looking at what's happening
here we got the the Texel U and V stuff
that's happening down here needs to be
guarded by a bitmap with an bitmap
height call here because we want to make
sure that divide is safe that's the part
that we would have to duplicate in here
so I'm not sure to what extent we want
to propagate that outwards if I look to
see who else is using that get bitmap
dim right we saw where that was
happening when people are calling that
the other places are not guarding
against it what I want to know here is
when we're doing that stuff when we look
at get dim size we're just looking at
doing that multiplication it's it's
basically it's definitely the kind of
thing we're checking that at the outset
makes a little bit of sense because
don't have to do it if every time but I
really don't know that it's worth
storing the value and having to have it
duplicated out like that it just doesn't
make a lot of sense it seems like better
to just do the divide every time because
it's really not that expensive to take
that reciprocal and it can be a fake
divide it could be a reciprocal so you
know for example if we go to the Intel
intrinsics guide here you know divides
traditionally we're very expensive and
so sometimes you get in the habit of
trying to avoid them but if you take a
look at the cost of them here so if I
want to do a divide you can see
generally speaking actually the
throughput it's not that bad especially
on sky like the latency is only 11
cycles really not that bad and
throughputs very good actually but
furthermore reciprocal where if you want
to do a poor-man's divide for example
here you can see here on skylake you've
got a pretty good throughput on there as
well the latency amusingly enough is
actually not that much better than the
regular divide right on the the div PS
it's it's you know 11 versus 4 it's
obviously bad but neither are good right
so if 4 cycle is is still you know
forever latency but that's ok because
you know our bread and butter things
multi s there for cycle latency as well
so generally speaking you know
reciprocal not that bad
I guess it's all I'm trying to say it's
it's really not that much different than
then a basic multiply it's it's gonna be
about the same only instead of issuing 2
per cycle it going through 1 so I
that divide really not that bad so maybe
again at the just for simplicity's sake
I feel like it would be nice to make
that be something that you don't have to
worry about anymore and this this
wouldn't have to be stored anymore
mm-hmm and so that's what we're really
looking at here now what I'm thinking is
that when we go to do a get bitmap here
and we look at the and we do the get
that mapped in here
here's it see if I can find here's the
other place that we use it and what you
can see there is it's actually using
some slightly different things it's
taking that bitmap scale and it's using
it to compute the full dimensions so
it's more doing the full push bitmap
kind of a call to draw it here it's it's
mostly doing the same thing that we were
trying to do before so yeah like it
looks like the get bitmap Tim stuff I I
don't know I'm really having a hard time
deciding how I want to do this I'm
almost thinking that you you know you
want to kind of make this I'm just
trying to think if I want to anything
else
fancy here or not I I'll leave it how it
is let's just go with it for notes let's
just go with it for now so if I want to
recreate with over height here the
basically what I'm do is say look let's
assume that things square for now what
we'll do then is say okay if I can like
if it's okay to use an inversion right
so if it's okay to look at that that
bitmap with then then I'll do the
inversion and if not I won't so in here
you know we need that in here when we're
looking at using the texture handle I
think we want this kind of call to be a
little bit more specific about how it's
doing that texture handle because you
know this code will execute whether or
not how
texture handle yet or not maybe that's
not a problem I don't know hard to say
what I will say also is how we're
assigning texture handles is probably
broken right now too
because nowadays we could assign a
texture handle immediately even though
there's no texture backing the texture
handle and we would want to do that
because we eliminate a lot of
complexities in this call for example
just to give you a little bit of a taste
of what I'm talking about here if I look
at the asset system and you look at get
bitmap here where you're calling this
get bitmap and you might return to zero
you can see it returning a zero here we
could change this into a render to
texture call where you actually always
get the texture back every time you call
it because it always allows you it would
always allow you to pack a texture
handle back with the width and height of
that bitmap right and so I feel like you
know this code really could stand some
improvement we haven't done it yet but
it really could get simpler than it is
right now it could get a lot better than
it is right now but I'm just gonna I'm
gonna always assume that the texture
handle is valid because it always should
be valid in the future and even if it's
not valid the computation won't fail if
there's just a bogus width and height in
there you'll just get the wrong with an
height through bitmap but if it wasn't
loaded you won't draw it anyway so it
doesn't really matter so I'm going to
assume that we can get that information
out so I'm gonna take the texture handle
here and I'm gonna say that we can get
that out of it here's that happening
right here I'm gonna say if that texture
handle has a width that's valid then we
can produce a width over height that's
valid because we can save the texture
handle and you know what looking at it
here it's really only the height that
needs to be valid right so I'm not sure
really why we're doing that but so there
we go
that's what we actually want to test
because we don't care the width could be
zero and that's totally fine
so this is how we would produce that on
the fly you know and our fallback will
just be one because then it'll just well
if the height was it doesn't matter
one it could be zero either either war
will produce the right result here
because either we'll take one and
multiply up by zero or I'm sorry either
we'll take 0 and multiply it by 1 or 0
multiplied by zero but either one it's
gonna produce a 0 so it doesn't really
matter what it's set to right so that
would solve that problem and then we
don't have any accessing of that
particular piece of information anymore
actually anywhere I suppose so let's
move forward a little bit on that remove
that now and you can remove this
entirely right okay so the bit met with
my height stuff that happens here that
all flows properly now let's make sure
we can run still so then screw anything
up just make sure all of our bitmaps are
still there they all are and they all
look right and so now let's finish this
off by saying well we're down to just
you know we want to get rid of some of
these things we're gonna leave this one
in for now but but we're pretty much
want to get down to just passing the
renderer that texture handle there so
now we're down to the one that we really
wanted to work on in the first place
which is a line percentage and that's
gonna be the hardest one to work with
because now we have to have to think
about where that's gonna come from for
real so you can see here when we call
get bitmap in we're going to need to
pass in that a line percentage and
you're gonna see as we look through here
we kind of have some special-purpose
stuff going on when we do load we're
calling get P percent on one of these
line points or to set that a line
percentage up the problem is now this is
not the place to do that anymore why is
it not the place to do that because our
bitmaps have multiple attachment points
we cannot assume when we load a bitmap
that we know which attachment point
people are going to want to use because
you're gonna want to use multiple of
them depending on the circumstances for
example if I have a head that's loading
in midair I might use a different
attachment point that if I have a head
that's attached to a body blah blah blah
blah blah right so we want to be able to
have different line points furthermore
we need to be able to access alignment
points that are not necessarily related
to the attaching of things maybe there
are just points that we specify in there
they're used for a spawning special
effects things like this so that needs
to be a more general purpose thing and
you can see our to do right there I'm
gonna start by just nuking it it's like
goodbye it's gone so now we're gonna
force everyone
who was looking at that to do something
better that's gonna force it up the
chain of command and we're pushing back
who needs to think about a line
representation that will complicate the
outer part of our code but that's what
we actually want now because that outer
part of code needs to actually be aware
it needs to think about how it's trying
to align things and it needs to actually
work at a higher level and that's what
we're trying to do so it's gonna make
our little hour cob day but we need it
to be that's the point and so that's why
I'm pushing this up the chain of command
that's intentional right so what we see
here is in order to do this alignment we
are gonna need some alignment percentage
what we need to do is again push it up
the chain of command say look when you
pass this in instead of passing us a c'
line now which is just a constant
multiplies what you are trying to align
pass us the entire alignment right so
give us this alignment percentage as an
actual v2 that we will apply and you are
responsible for figuring out where
that's going to come from it's not a
default parameter because his groin
Eve's husband in every single bitmap you
need to pass it in to us so when we get
down here you can see again it's just
gonna it's just bumping up the chain of
command the people out sign of push
bitmap calls now need to pass this in as
what is the actual alignment that you
want you don't have the option anymore
of lollygagging on that it's going to
have to come in that means we're gonna
move it up past the color which is
something you didn't have to pass in so
these default parameters here that we
will still allow to be default the
aligned percentage is no longer one of
them that means that's gonna get passed
through here instead of see line there's
the aligned percentage now everyone who
calls that push bitmap call which is
only the one that's used for sprites has
to know what's going on that's totally
fine
that's what we want so it's all good we
look in here and we see again we're just
bumping it up the chain of command
here's that see line again it was the
same call here we're just gonna go ahead
and grab that and I'm gonna push it back
behind the rest of the default
parameters so that we can actually have
it passed from the the outermost scope
of the code right because that's the
part that needs to start thinking about
those alignments
just and that's the part that's gonna
get more complex now that it has to
think about that okay so let's see who's
actually using that or at the align
percentage is in the wrong place got to
be over here now we've got our push
bitmap call oh you know what let's use
that flag let's use that flag someone in
the pre stream told us about minus WL
let's use that flag to get rid of oh
look at it look at it look at how much
nicer it is thank you
visual studio team for having minus WL
thank you that is very nice okay so
here's the push bitmap call where's it
happening it's happening in a particle
system right so one of things we don't
want to do it apart though system is
have a lot of cost per particle this
call will probably become simpler in the
future I don't care about the particles
right now I'm just gonna sub that in as
a v2 0.5 0.5 that may just be fine for
most particles anyway and so we'll just
leave it at that
um what did I do wrong there is that the
see aligned value that's the see aligned
value so that needs to go away as well
so it actually needs to look like that
probably what's the render group of
transform bitmap ID
[Music]
what's that real 32 I don't know
all right so look in here we've got oh
its height that's what it is so we do
need that one point now in here so we
need the P we need the one point O then
we need the color and that should do it
so I think that's all we really need
there is there something wait I not get
them all there's the group there's a
transform there's the bitmap
oh that's bitmap IDs sorry it's this one
bitmap ID there's the height the offset
we don't actually need so I'm not sure
what we were doing there what was
getting passed there what was what were
we passing here what was the call 1.0 P
and C okay too many parameters these
render functions that's how it always
does render functions unfortunately all
right so moving forward here's another
one of those calls there's the color
right this is the stuff that's going to
need the actual alignment point so I'm
gonna say like a line percentage here
and I'm just going to come out here and
say there's the align percentage and
that's what we actually need to set at
the moment I'm just going to set it to a
bogus value but this is the place where
our code will become more complicated so
in terms of that I think we're good to
go
we need this to take the alignment
percentage in the right place I thought
it was a line percentage color I'm just
having trouble remembering that function
for some reason so spit meant by D
there's the height there's the offset
there's the align percentage there's the
color we don't need that anymore
and next this is just our basic layer
rendering stuff so yeah that actually is
just needs to have the alignment point
specified here again that needs to be
looked up in here somewhere so we'll put
it to do in there there we go and
honestly those don't really need to
probably looks up because we don't edit
those those were always always those
were always set to just 0.5 and that was
it so you know unclear whether we really
care about that or how much we really
care about that but you know whatever
ensuing here we can sort of get the
first align point one of the things we
could do is just for fonts we could just
say it's always the first alignment
point you know what I mean so when we
actually have the bitmap info in
question the bitmap info we could just
say like get default alignment or get
you know first align or something like
that so we could actually say that we
just get that here and it can happen off
of the bitmap info and that also could
be something that we just do in the
cutscene so that we don't have to care
about it right so maybe that excuse me
maybe that's what happens here
right and so the bitmap ID in question
for this layer image that we just want
to put on there maybe that's just how we
how we get that ahead of time right so
then we don't have to think about it
again and so if we want do that inside
the asset system there should be pretty
straightforward how we would get that
right if I wanted to throw that in here
if we want a utility function for how we
would get this
all we have to do is look back at the
file format and you can see that it's
got the align points here so all we
really need to do is get P percent we
just need to get that on the bitmap
infos first alignment point so if we
know that we've got some thing that
always works
like for fonts and stuff like that
that's how we would do it
and we can put that inside here as well
because it's actually part of this whole
suite of things sort of so that could
just come in here actually and and
operate on one of these because it's
actually valid everywhere right it
doesn't require anything else all right
so moving through here what we can see
is it looks like that one point oh is
that the see line value I think it might
be so I think we're really looking at
this maybe yeah and I don't know where
we're passing the align peak here cuz
that remember but I can look it's right
before the x-axis y-axis so it's
actually what's the one point oh it's a
co line value so that's good alright so
that should get rid of all that and this
one needs it too
bitmap scale bitmap offsets color um who
else so inside here that part we don't
care about it all this bitmap Tim we
don't need any via line at all so I
think here we just could just do 0-0 I
think I don't know what we would want to
be I think we ignore it when we draw it
anyway I think so that should presumably
not be irrelevant let me see what goes
on here line percentage is the last
thing so I think that's about it
so now a line percentage has been pushed
up one in the chain and everyone pretty
much has to know what they're doing here
you can see us actually doing it here
there's us not using the align
percentage so I think that's it I think
that successfully pushes everything up
to the top so now everything that we
draw is actually not using an alignment
point at all actually except for the
things that are we know that they're
baked
so like the alignment points on the font
so you can see are all still working
because again we know that's just the
zero slot because we make those
specially those aren't edited by an
artist and we can look here I think the
cutscenes are probably also correct so
let's take a look we should we should
implement the title screen at some point
now that we have a title cutscenes look
pretty good everything looks right there
so I think that's also fine right so in
terms of yeah in terms of where we're at
I think we're in good shape now so that
brings us to the actual entity rendering
part of things where we can now start to
use these alignment points so the first
thing we'll do
is just the basic test of is any of this
stuff working at all
so if I take this a line piece here and
say get first a line on whatever the
bitmap is in question here so remember I
have the bitmap info and I said get
bitmap info for this bitmap ID right
when we do that and we get that bitmap
info back then inside this first a line
thing I can actually just ask for oops I
don't why that's lowercase I can
actually ask for the actual light point
that comes from the first one of these
which means that once we come down here
and actually use it we can use the first
one the only reason I want to do that is
I want to see if we can get it working
with the editor right so I want
real-time editing of that a line point
right so when I come through here and I
select this thing and I go to edit one
of these aligned points right there we
go
so it's it's it's taking that alignment
and and and working on it right and so
that's what we wanted we and that's
that's what I wanted to see and do see
right so that's all really good that's
all happiness and sunshine flowery
nonsense right uh so the scaling value
we would like to use - that's gonna
involve a little bit of fancy footwork
on our part because right now we have to
go we don't really think about how the
scaling flows to the pipeline we're
gonna have to do a little bit of work
there to make that value be rigorously
defined so I want to stay away from that
just for a second while we work on the
rest of the stuff about how we pick
these things right so now we need to do
is we need to start thinking about how
these scaling values are actually set up
so it's not very much alignment guys are
set up because we need our align points
to snap together right
we need that sort of we need the reverse
lookup part of this right we we need to
sort of say
hey go get an alignment point out of my
previous person and put it in me and all
those other sorts of things right so if
we look at how our file formats define
it's gonna be a little bit difficult but
we can probably figure something out
right if we look in here we've got these
entity pieces right they're sort of the
the pieces of the entities are sort of
like built up out of multiple pieces
what we need to figure out here is how
do we we need to figure out some way of
of connecting each piece with its
correct alignment points right so the
way to think about this is we have a we
have a set of definitions of what these
alignment points mean so we can tag each
alignment point with what kind of
alignment point it is and then we just
need some way of saying well you know if
this thing wants to be matched up to
this other thing we need to know which
kind of match up it's supposed to be if
this thing is saying that it should use
like head alignment so I'm trying to
align like top of neck to base of head I
need a way of Unknowing that's the kind
of text I'm going to do looking for
those two you know looking for the
correct one in each of them and actually
applying it right so that's the crucial
part we're trying to do here and what I
want to do first is I'm gonna write a
crappy version because I don't want to
try to accelerate this thing I mean
you'll notice we do this a lot I don't
want to try to make something fast
before I've made it at all because if I
do that what I risk run the risk of
doing is over optimizing something that
we will then later change so since we
haven't worked with the system at all I
don't want to think about the speed yet
because I'm nervous that I will have to
change it a couple times and then the
optimization for work will go away right
I'm not that nervous about overcoming
the code I don't get that nervous about
optimization stuff premature
optimization is a root of all evil
that quote you're taking with a bit of a
grain of salt but the part of it that's
really true is trying to waste time
optimizing something that you don't
abusing that's definitely true right
because that you know if I then change
the system then all the work I did to
optimize it is probably useless right
and so that's the big thing we want to
watch out for okay so let's get going on
that let's take a look in here I when
this this code executes it's got this
notice this notion of any visible pieces
in here so any given anity can be made
up of several different pieces and that
makes sense because you know there's
there's sort of a two-tiered approach to
this kind of thing there are enemies
that are worked together so you know
maybe I've got two different pn amis in
a room that are controlled by the same
logical brain we have a system for
handling that that's the brain system
and it controls multiple entities right
but there's another concept which is
just like I have to have a single entity
but we just want to animate it with
multiple pieces those pieces don't
disaggregate like you're never gonna
have those pieces come apart right but I
just need to build it up out of multiple
things I don't want them each to be an
entity because they're not really
entities they're just different pieces
of the same entity that get animated
separately from each other right so it's
an animation conceit not a gameplay
conceit that's what these visual pieces
are each one of those visual pieces
needs a way of sort of understanding how
it is stacked like how it is snapped
together that's what needs to be
authentic in here in order for this to
work so if you look at the end of it in
any visible piece thing what we want to
do is you know here we've got a cube
layout for cubes for example right well
I might want another thing here which is
like let's say we've got you know an
entity or a so what I'm looking for
a bitmap or whatever right like so if
this thing is actually going to be a
bitmap piece so it's not a cube or a
light then it might have additional data
there right so if this is a bitmap piece
so I know I can do this if I want so
this is like the bitmap info that comes
out of here so in here what I could do
is I could say all right I know I build
up this set of visible pieces what I
could say is tell me which visible piece
you need to snap onto and which thing
from that visible piece you're trying to
snap to right so what I could say is
look here's the the parent piece
effectively right so which one in this
in the set of visual pieces which one am
I actually snapping to obviously I could
make that smaller it doesn't need to be
particularly big and then I could
furthermore say what's this what's the
type and so in here you know one of the
things I like to do sometimes let me let
me add this to our system I don't think
we have that nasai yeah we do okay
nevermind um so one of things I like to
do sometimes is be a little bit more
explicit about what these types are C
and C++ suck at this they're very bad
but you know we can be a little bit more
rigorous ourselves just just because we
can be so what I want to do here is say
look I've got an enum 16 so it is a you
16 I'm going to tell you what the type
is here it just so it's a little bit
clearer to a meta processor if one was
going to read this or just a programmer
later this is a 16-bit value but it's
storing one of these right and I think
they finally added that C bus plus some
time I think suppose was 17 finally
added the concept that an enum could
have a type 30 years later they thought
maybe a programmer should be able to
specify what the type of a variable was
revolutionary concept for the late knots
anyway let's go ahead and try and get
this into production here again
implementing it in a particularly smart
way so if I pop back over to where we're
actually creating these entities I
believe that's in room Jen where stuff
is actually getting generated
ventually will probably have an entity
gin but at the moment I don't think we
do so I don't know where that stuff gets
set up maybe it wasn't in there let me
see let me just see where add piece is I
don't know where that where it is oh
it's still in world mode okay yeah we
there's so much stuff we got a we're
gonna have some fun with the generator
once because you know after that stuff
all comes together here so anyway I
inside like add player for example so
here's the piece of that I'm not gonna
do that player because the players kind
of not the concern right now we need to
decide some stuff about how bodies are
handled before we do that I'm gonna go
look at the cats right because I let
cats better than humans anyway so I'm
gonna go ahead and do them first
so let me find our where's our add cat
here yeah here we go so here's how we
add a cat and you can see us adding the
pieces here we say look a little bit of
the bodies ahead and you can see that
right now it doesn't have any
information about what's going on there
right and so what I'd like to do there
is kind of have this notion that when
you add one of these pieces and again I
don't know if that's in a world Jen I
guess a piece where where is I don't
know where that even is add piece where
where where was it tell me where add
piece gets done I have no idea we need
to clean this stuff up so I know where
any of our functions are so it looks
like add piece is in entity okay I
already made an enemy Jen nevermind
I guess I did clean it up so I shouldn't
have been complaining about myself maybe
I was smarter than I thought I was
that's always a good day because usually
it's the other way around so anyway if I
go back to our our AB cat call here and
I want to look at this this bad piece
here any visible piece comes back as a
pointer in case you want to edit it
and what what I'd like to really do here
is just say when you actually add the
piece I'd like you to be able to add
that bitmap information to it right and
one of the things is you know you see
that we need this piece index here it
would be nice to get that back right so
that we have some way of doing that
reference so when we do that you know
this energy is a little piece pointer
that comes back it turns out you know
that is good enough because since we
know that we're doing this construction
in a local setup we can do differencing
on that array we know they come from the
same place so that's not actually
dangerous in that case so we can't
actually make something a little bit
more expressive here when we do that
asset basic category what we can then do
is say look we can connect pieces
together you know and in here I can just
say all right here's the entity that I'm
talking about here's the visible piece
that's the parent here's the entity
piece that's a child so we're going to
connect those two together and what I
want to say here is all right what's the
thing on the child I'm connecting from
and what's the thing on the parent I'm
connecting to probably what I want to
say they're right I sue so if I come
through here and say all right what are
one of those look like I know that
inside the file formats I've got the
list of things that they could be right
so I kind of want to say look for the
parent I'm gonna connect from the parent
type that parent type to this child type
okay and then inside the entity you know
I'll need to record those pieces of
information like so and then I've still
got to use sixteen here that I could use
right
and so we've only taken up it's only one
64-bit value and we could even make it
smaller than that you know these could
be um eights there's not going to be 256
different kinds of align points right so
we could even get a more aggressive I
don't think we need to for any
particular reason but we could so we
want to really
if we really want to compact us down
even more right you could do something
like this and be really super aggressive
with it we certainly could do that and
maybe we just will and then if we ever
need more space we can always expand
that out in the future and and go from
there
right so we can we can be more
aggressive there and then we would just
have a one more here and that makes this
only 32 bits total to specify the
complete alignment thing which keeps
that nice and compact I don't remember
what QV q UV layout is but I think it's
also like a 32-bit value so it keeps
this a very small this set of stuffs a
bit picky here we could start working on
getting that down more to but that's
just a you know we'll cross that bridge
when in if we need to cross it at all so
there's our bitmap piece specifications
stuff there and that's all we really
need for that so if I now want to define
one of those I can specify that on the
bitmap piece so when we do this connect
on the entity what I need to know is the
reason that I need to pass it in the
first place
is this this needs to be an index into
this array right like so the entity has
an array of these right about here right
so it has this list of pieces and it
needs to know which one I'm talking
about in that array but I'm passing a
pointer so in order to get which one it
is out of that pointer I just want to do
some math there right so I've got the
entity pieces there's little pieces what
is it called I just looked at it but of
course I wasn't paying attention to that
just pieces um so I know that's the base
so if I subtract the parent if I
subtract that from the parent I get how
many array slots it is to get to the
parent which is that index that I want
right so this in this case is the parent
index and I can assert here that I could
truncate it so I could do a safe
truncate to you 8 here and say look a
if you ever for some reason have more
than 256 of these because I'm not
certain that 26 pieces is not allowed in
the system that would be an entity with
so many pieces that you really should be
representing it as multiple entities I
think at that point this is this game
does not want that it would be
impossible to even see what was going on
there so we're not gonna do that just
right off the bat so anyway we can save
truncate these as well and then that
allows us to set the entire thing up
right so all we need to do now is say
all right actually what we can do here
is just say well we know that we're
going to have one of these entity we
know what we're setting is one of these
bitmap piece things so here's the bitmap
piece it's gonna be off of oops off of
the child I can assert that the child is
a bitmap type right so that it's not any
of these things so I can I can I can
assert that we're not trying to set
something that shouldn't have one of
these in the first place so I can say
you know assert that the flags and you
know what I could do it even right here
I could say like look there's this
concept that a piece is a bitmap and all
I'm gonna do there is say that the flags
had better not have either of those two
things in it right so peace cube peace
light
are not allowed so if I end these two
things together what I'm really looking
for is did anything get set so if
nothing got set here then we're good to
go
if something got set here then we're not
so that's all we need there I can assert
now that this this is it bitmapped piece
which is what I wanted
I can then access this member of it with
the confidence that it should be
accessed at all I can then set up the
pieces that I want by just setting the
values to the what we had the person
passing they should be and then we're
done
so that's how we would connect two
pieces together right that means inside
our add cat call where we're actually
trying to add the cat right here is
after I do these I am now I can say like
visible piece I can store each of those
and now I can connect them so I can
connect the body in the head like so I
can say I want the body because we again
inside the file formats there we know we
have top of head and base of neck so I
can say that I want the top of the head
to connect to the base of the neck or
whatever right actually no sorry the
default because again there is no base
of head so it's just whatever it's
default one is I want that to connect to
the base of the neck right and I won't
so line those two pieces up okay all
right so I've got to do a couple of
things here
um eight needs to be defined so inside
types we need again that full set and
I'll just make sure we have all of them
cuz they're all good and again C++ did
finally add these but I you know I'm so
done with C++ at this point I don't even
bother using new features because it's
just like waiting to find some special
you know anti programmer mind the C++
committee has left in the fee
so that it ends up being terrible and
you wish you'd never use it which is how
every literally every feature I've ever
tried if C++ is um so I would recommend
not going down that route but you're
welcome to go you're welcome to have a
party there bring your minesweeper you
know bring the canary down the coal mine
make sure when you see it die stop using
the future so here we have the the
errors for the connect base function
that we just did we don't have we
actually don't have a that safe truncate
feature yet right because we've only
ever done I think the safe truncate to
you 32 so what I want to do is make sure
that we've got the other ones of these
so you can see they're really simple
functions all they do is they really are
just a cast but they're a way of just
making sure before you do the cast that
someone would have would have complained
it you know in debug mode someone will
complain prior to doing the cast if it
couldn't fit right oops that's so that's
really all I wanted to do there don't
ask me why I forgot your name function
but that's all we really need and now
inside here we've got the parent piece
I'm gonna call that a parent piece
instead of parent index because I don't
know I like that better I guess good
good call either one let's see from n64
what
okay so I think that's all we really
need to do we got the alive type here
specified I think that's it and so now
we can specify how the cats are supposed
to be attached up right unfortunately it
won't do anything why because if we want
to do anything we have to actually
implement code that uses that shouldn't
be too hard right
because inside here it's pretty easy for
us to figure out where our pieces
actually are and then do sort of the
retcon on it now one of the things that
we have when we do the on top versus not
on top this is no longer true thankfully
cos 0 is the most on top and it's most
on bottom not true anymore
right so what we want because we just
sort so what we want to do here is on
entity visible piece what we want to do
is specify parents must always come
before children and I'll show you why we
need to do that in a second
but what I want to do is rigidly enforce
that rule it's gonna make our lives a
lot easier as we can oh we can do it in
one loop instead of doing it too so in
here what I'd like to do is enforce that
rule you can see how I got my index
before what I'm gonna do here is add
another assertion which says that let's
make sure that the parent piece whatever
that was is less than the child piece so
whatever the child's location in the
array is had better be greater than the
parents and so what we'll do now is
we'll run the code and we'll make sure
that that passes and if it doesn't pass
then we know we add them in the wrong
order right so for example if I had in
that jet you know that add cat thing
where is that oops
and cat so in the end cat thing what I
wanted to do here is say well let's
suppose that the head was defined first
well now what should happen is we should
get an error it should actually stop us
from creating the cat and there it is so
that's just a layer of protection to
make sure we don't accidentally be that
wrong so now we can do is inside the
entity rendering code so when we're
actually doing this what we can do is we
know there's a fairly complicated set of
code as you see for figuring out where
each piece is right this is relatively
tricky here we're doing all kinds of
deformation whatever nonsense right so
at the end of the day we finally find
out where the heck this thing goes right
we would now like to be able to specify
some additional information about it
right we want some kind of information
about where the thing went and this
actually becomes even trickier than we
think it is because we're gonna have to
do one more piece of of rather tricky
work here to make sure that we can even
know where each individual piece ends up
now why do I say that I see that because
you'll notice what happens inside push
bitmap is we pass down an aligned P but
we never find out where the bitmap
actually ends up right so if you look in
here when we do that thought get bit
mapped in this is the information we
actually need on the outside and we
never get it right we never get it so
what I'm almost gonna say we need to do
here is I think what we actually need is
we need to move this code to the outside
as well
now all the places that we're calling
this suggest to me that we probably want
to leave it in place but we want to
provide a version of just this interior
bit that you can call
like I think we want this here right we
want this to be actually something you
can call directly by itself so with all
of the other information you can
actually proceed from there makes sense
and so if I call this function I need
all of the information that comes with
it you know from from all of this stuff
so I'm gonna copy that in like so but
what I'm gonna do here is say instead of
the object transform which I don't
believe gets used anywhere does it no it
does mine so in addition to the object
transform I guess then I should say I
guess it's the height maybe it's not
years no everything's used you are
expected to pass in the used bitmap damn
right so you've got to actually use that
and again we may want to simplify that
part of the code in the future because
at this point now that we kind of see
how things are going it's probably
probably not really passing the right
set of stuff that makes sense so I want
to pass the dim in there and then
everywhere here that was using the dim
which is like actually just that those
two places right
all of that stuff is now captured inside
this routine so that we can do it in two
steps if we need this information and we
do because we need to know the actual
dimension and size of this thing if we
don't know the actual dimension in size
of this thing and the placement of it
right we won't be able to properly
attach things to it because we won't
know where it is if we just allow the
thing to automatically move it for us
then we don't really have any way of our
cells using that information later so
now what we need to do is do this in two
steps right we need to first do this
step here and we can do that up above
here if we wanted to I guess but I can
say I guess we have to make sure it is
actually a bitmap first so here we would
do you know the bitmap tim-tim and we
pass all the same things we were passing
here and then we just passed them again
so inside here what do we need we need
the bitmap the loaded bitmap so we don't
really need the transform we just need
the bitmap we need the piece to mention
why we need the offset we need the
alignment percentage we need the
excesses and waxes we don't need the
color once we have that we can pass it
in and go from there
we don't want to use this one anymore we
want to use this one directly so we need
to pass the bitmap itself not the idea
anymore we need to pass the height
that's good the offset is good the align
percentage is good the color of the
excess relaxes okay
so that is what we need to do for making
it into a two-stage function call and
where does that come out here
and again I think like this code is
really overbearing now so I feel like
we'll be able to simplify that down in
the future but that's separate issue so
alright so inside here what we need now
is to get that bitmap so when we you
know loaded bitmap bitmap equals get fit
map and so on let me see where that's
actually being used it doesn't get used
till they're just looking through it
here yes so I feel like I feel like this
stuff can just happen down here probably
right
looks right so that looked good so yeah
if we got this bitmap and we look up its
info and so on right yeah
then we just need to make sure we
actually ever got one and furthermore we
don't really need this lookup anymore
because the bitmap info is just pretty
sure it's just that right
that not true so where's the loaded
bitmap all right well never mind I'll
I'll use the get call still I don't
remember it comes from okay so I think
we're done with that and now what we
need to do is actually utilize that
information let's make sure we're still
actually getting any bitmaps here okay
so we're not so we're not quite getting
this right so I think that may be
because inside get bitmap here I think
you have to cue a load bitmap on it if
we can't get it yeah we do so you can
see here what has to happen there so I
need to cue that in order to to force
the thing to you know to ask for it
right
so here I'll actually do that and again
I think we want to clean this stuff up
so because we really don't need to be
doing it the way we're doing it we can
simplify that a lot but anyway so moving
along the bitmap ID we know so that's
pretty easy
that's the render group so I think
that's fine that'll looks good and off
we go so we should now have all of our
stuff rendering as it was before and we
mostly do except this part of the code
doesn't thunk through so I didn't quite
finish in Asset rendering this has to
call push bitmap with all the with all
the junk
and you can see why I say this is
overall they're just too much garbage
happening now and a lot of this stuff
could be simplified down and should be
eventually alright so now we're back to
where we want to be and it means that
now inside the entity we can actually
track where things really are what that
means is we can look at what the entity
piece count has to say so if I go back
to the entity structure we can see that
we've got like a set of entity pieces
and what I want to do is I want to be
able to have a set of like a set of
rectangles that tell me where the people
were who I was working with right so if
I take all the rectangles here this will
allow me to capture where I drew things
so I can then essentially solve for
where each went where any parent was
right if as I step through the array
drawing each individual piece I say
wherever this piece was I'm gonna right
back where I thought it was when I
finally put it into world space and
started to draw it if I put that into
the rectangle knowledge here that will
allow me to then take alignment point
information that I get from the snapping
information right that connection
information I can look up where things
are in two piece rectangles and know
where the parent was right I'm trying to
think of what exactly I want to store
there
and I'm thinking what I really want is
maybe just the x and y-axes because I
think that tells me everything I need
right I just need like the transform so
I basically need a three by three matrix
right I just need like I need like what
the origin point was and the X&amp;Y axis
because I need to then be able to like
move these things out along those like
that's basically what I'm doing here
[Music]
and that pretty much tells me how I need
this thing to be aligned so you know
thinking about it a little bit more
specifically here again like this could
probably be simplified quite a bit if we
look back at our math code and we we
look at what we actually I don't
remember what we had stored in here in
terms of like matrices and things like
that see did we actually have any way
down well we do we have M four by fours
so looking back at what we have here
right we've got em four by fours they're
over specified for what we need but we
could use them just because we already
have them like we don't need a full 4x4
because no projection here but maybe
that's fine so
if I look at the piece transformer right
here then I can sort of say well alright
anytime I'm going to update a piece on a
produced a transform for that piece and
then I'm going to use that to align
anyone else who needs to get aligned to
it right and since we produced these
axes here you know thinking it through
we may now want to sort of pull back a
little bit and have that have the
alignment points just be things that
work sort of like a skeleton here
because again now we're sort of giving
the point where it's really not
necessary the stuff that's being done in
there and you really just want to split
it into the font rendering code which
uses the alignment points at a very
fixed way and doesn't have to do
anything interesting with them and then
the actual in-game sprite code which
wants to have a fairly complex
relationship right I'm gonna start by
not doing that and then I think what I
want to do is go clean up that code so
that we have a much more straightforward
way of writing all these things in right
so let's go ahead and do that here's the
piece transforms in question what I want
to do is say for each piece index we're
gonna write that transform out so in
here what I'll do is say well when we
get all this stuff right all of this
information we then have the ability to
write in a matrix that would have the
pieces we need we know we're not going
to have any rotation but we are gonna
have translation and we might have axes
that we put directly in so we're not
going to call this X this X rotation
stuff but we may slam axes directly in
there at some point as well right so
we've got some stuff that's going to
happen in there for sure okay so if we
want that to work how are we gonna do
this exactly
you know yeah I'm just not seeing a way
to do it other than to actually really
start pulling this stuff out into here
because if you look at how this stuff
works right we've got stuff that
modifies how the axes actually actually
work you can see that's us generating
these up right transform axes here right
and so for anything that was actually
doing that upright transform we need to
actually have that work inside here and
last up I just I feel like a lot of that
stuff is gonna end up being you know
that stuff really has to be done in a
more we've got to start making this
stuff a little bit more coherent so I'm
gonna go ahead and say let's just do it
how much time do I have left what do we
got like 25 minutes I don't know it's a
very good question how much time we have
anyone any no much time we got anyone
nobody knows it's alright the stream
thing will tell us I think but I think I
want to I want to kind of push through
that so if I compile this first let's
let's make sure we're still compiling
here because I don't think we are I just
need to not that out okay so what we
want to do now is we want oh and you can
see here like this stuff this stuff is
actually gonna be getting done all of
this the part of that that was relevant
is now going to be actually happening as
well which is nice okay so what I want
to do now is I want to actually go
through and figure out who's calling
push bitmap and why and I want to clean
that up so what you can see here is that
we've got the debug code calling push
bitmap here we've got the dev UI calling
here at the cutscene the particles so
there's a Codel of five people calling
it debug system dev UI cutscene
particles and entity I want entity to
now basically be just doing its own
thing almost entirely I know that the
deep obsessed with WI the cutscene the
particles they aren't using the more
complicated stuff there right so I think
and I could be very wrong about this but
I think in here I I don't know who's
actually using this up right transform
information or why but what I want to do
is move that out so only the entities do
it and it's a specific thing that they
do right so there it is in the push back
push it's in the push bitmap called
there does anyone else use it so that's
just a generic call yeah so I think what
I want to do here is get that up right
idea I want that up right idea to go
away entirely so we're gonna start there
so this is going to go away the object
transform will not tell you that
information and then I'm gonna fix it so
now these are both the same okay so they
can collapse down to just be default
transform
that's fine keep going that's fine
all these are fine what else we got okay
so now we should essentially have only
one person who cares about this upright
flag and it is the push bitmap call that
we were using here right and that's to
get this like up right sprite stuff
happening so what I want to do there is
and what is the push up right so that
actually does this thing here which is
different from this it's actually a
different way of doing it right
not sure either where this is coming
from so it's actually getting computed
outside of push-up right interesting so
I think what we could do here is again
start treating push bitmap a little more
harshly and force the people who call it
to do something more specific so first
of all we could start by doing this
which is not what we're going to finish
with but we can do this right and now we
could sort of see who's actually calling
this and why and from where you know
what I mean I would be interested to
know if anyone's actually doing this and
furthermore since I know I guess I know
nobody really needs this up right path
mmm pretty much anyway so I think we
could just say like look it's false
right
and so then the only person who cares is
here and so the upright transform stuff
is just whether or not this entity is
supposed to be upright or not here and I
mean and so I don't actually know where
we were getting them or how we would get
that information otherwise I guess we
just always assumed it was upright I
guess which is not something we
necessarily want to assume but that is I
think what we were doing so really now
it just looks like that right oops
okay
so I think that's sufficient for how we
were doing it before right see there's
all of our rendering still looks fine
here right all this stuff works
similarly I assume that the yeah this
all works just fine too
and all of this stuff should work just
fine yeah so everything still intact no
issues there and we're good to go
now if I go through now and actually try
to simplify down what do those people
actually need to call I'm gonna start
with the cutscenes which are the most
basic thing right and you can see what
they pass default transform here does
not get modified other than to give an
offset to the thing which could just be
specified as a position and so what I'm
gonna news I want to figure out if I can
just get rid of those entity transforms
I don't like them they're stupid they're
just nonsense that you could have just
done yourself right you could have you
could have handled these separately so
let's find out to what extent I'm right
first thing is get rid of scale does
anyone actually ever set it to anything
No so scale is irrelevant completely
irrelevant right there's no scale
happening so if I just get rid of scale
we're down to the fact that this is just
an offset right and that's the end of it
it wasn't used at all so now if we just
get rid of object transforms period I'm
just curious to know what do we actually
get as a result
all right so if we do get render entity
basis P it just adds those two things
together it happens only in push rect so
literally all that would be doing is
adding whatever the object transform
thing was so what I'd rather do here is
say look that's just the p value that
comes in right so we're done I don't
want to know about any of this you can
just do it yourself so don't bother me
right and so if I wanted to do that that
way what I could say is well the P and
the basis P right the offset comes in I
just do the thing with the dim this is
just an add of these two so really basis
P is just P at that point P itself it's
never used only basis key is right so
what I could do then and say all right
basis P is this
done our now our push shrek call is much
simpler and off we go
similarly here we wouldn't need the
object transform for that we could just
use an opposite there I'm not sure how I
want to do that one exactly because it's
not taking it to you think I don't even
know if I want that call any works I'm
not sure what a 2d rectangle supposed to
be doing in that case but we can figure
that out a little bit later alright so
this called just I'm just want to get
rid of that call it doesn't belong so
now we have I'm gonna put a volume
outline there's a rectangle 3d all that
happens there is like the object
transform was just an offset that got
added on so again not necessary right
and I'm just pulling this out because
like I said don't like it don't think it
belongs there
so there's rectangle to there's out
transform don't want that no no bad
goodbye
okay continuing through to transform
again don't want it so really all it
happens here is we just don't do the
transform same thing here don't do the
transform so people just pass in what
they wanted in the first place
same thing here don't do the transform
there we go so all of these things where
we're just talking about a bias there
that has to be added I'm just going to
call that a v3 like so because all
that's used for a sorting in the first
place let's take a look at push bitmap
it takes a knob to transfer I'm here I
don't want that so I'm gonna get rid of
it let's take a look at where object
transforms being used it was being used
here to specify that piece which I don't
want the same thing here let's get rid
of that all these things can go and
again it's just overdue clean-out right
we just want to get rid of these things
that don't do anything so that we can
simplify how the render is working and
make it clear we don't need any of this
we don't need any of this when we do
push the stick push rekt here we would
need an offset so we kind of need on
carriage it's a thing that's like where
is the entity probably I don't know that
draw hit points actually gets called
anymore so there it is
and so the entity transform bit here
what we really want to do is just have
this value right so we would just pass
that in because that's what it was
actually getting so it needs it up in
here like when we do draw hit points it
would need that ground point and then
when it's you know every time something
in here happens where it's gonna draw
something like in here these are always
going to be like ground P plus the thing
you know alright so moving on debug pick
entity is not really a thing anymore we
sort of implemented that directly like
I'm just going to get rid of this
we did a better version of that already
inside object transform now this part
again just got removed so we can
eliminate entirely this anyone who's
using this is now just doing entity
ground P that's all that they're doing
there right that's entity ground P and
that's all that's happening so that
really doesn't need the entity transform
same thing here right this location that
it's being specified that is just enemy
ground P so none of that ever needs to
happen anymore and you'll see why I'm
pulling this out as I bubble it up
you'll see why I want to get rid of it
because we actually don't want that we
don't want those transforms happening
down in the render it was a bad place
for it we had reasons at the time those
reasons are gone so yeah this again is
just entity ground P we're not actually
calling these anymore but if we were we
would you know not want to call that so
here we've got another situation where
we do want an offset P in this case of
course we could just do I think we could
just roll it all into the computation of
P by itself but in order to you know not
have bugs that I might introduce by
doing that since I don't care in this
case I'm just going to go ahead and put
it in here and then when we actually go
to do the the rendering of this thing
I'm going to go ahead and say that the
you know the way that we compute this
stuff is just like kind of convoluted
and strange but oh well
so it's offset P
you know what why isn't soapy why hold
on a second so looking at this we don't
actually use py except in here Wow so
this is like so P is actually not used
only offset is that's kind of nuts so
really I don't know for whatever reason
we ended up writing it this way so we
actually don't use P we just let it flow
through that way and we use that I guess
is fine I think that's right I'll have
to test that because I'm not sure I
understood that quite right but you know
hopefully we did all right so here we've
got our shadow transform and our text
transform and so then down here when we
actually use our shadow transform in
text transform it's really just this
right and we don't actually need to do
anything else there because those are
just things that offset the Z for
rendering purposes sorting purposes here
when we do know transform well know
transform is pretty easy because that
just means we delete it which is exactly
what we would like to do with it
and then we've got the backing transform
for the box so in here we'd like to do
is we'd like to offset that box by this
Z value and so I think that is the Z
value so I'm pretty sure that that is
what that would do you know I mean
inside that push rect we may want to
just take an offset here in general so
you know I might argue that the better
thing to do there for the 2d push rect
call is rather than specifying Z specify
an offset and that way in here what
would actually happen is you would say
oh okay so when we actually push this on
we we pass down for the for the rect
outline stuff when we do the offset we
just say that it's this you know what I
mean
and again this could stand to be cleaned
up a little bit too but all right so
then the backing transform just comes on
there and that's good
same thing here so there's the tooltip
it goes in oops goes in there yeah
what's the problem oh I know what the
problem is oh no I don't know the
problem is so push rekt in this case
what's what's the deal the bounds
renderer push 4x
I thought I'd just changed this oh it
was wrecked out line but I changed I
hate that too there we go alright so I
think that's all good now it's gotta
clean that up a bit
so here's push rekts it doesn't have an
offset so that's the zero offset there
so you know so that's all well I'm good
same here I guess it doesn't care where
it's pushing that same here
all of this stuff is just initializing
these VIII's so since they would all be
cleared initially I believe we wouldn't
really need to do this right that's not
actually necessary but I could just do
it anyway there's a tool chip transform
here's the text transform here's the you
while I transform here's the shadow
transform and there's
all right um what else we got so doing
our push tricks here again we have the
UI transform stuff we knew that doesn't
actually happen anymore so what is the
base Z that's happening here okay so
this this is some kind of a sorting
thing we're doing for like letting our
profile bars beeping so I do want to
effectively have like an addition that
happens here right so this this wants to
be a real thing so we're gonna say all
right take the UI transform in this case
and add some to it to get you know keep
the sorting happening the same way as it
was happening before in here again same
thing so in this case we just need to
add the song where we've got the base D
not attacking itself on there and that
should be it ya know transform is good
because no transform means we don't care
what it is
no transform there we don't care as well
the UI transform in this case just comes
right in there and this is a 1 so that's
a UI transform plus onesie and well what
else you got for me
Pilar right we don't need that anymore
what else we got
no transform backing transform that here
and off we go
pretty simple pretty simple all right so
it looks like we're out of time
I'm just gonna go ahead and finish this
up and then we'll do Q&amp;A I would like to
run it once though and do any light
debugging while we're still here and
then I'll in for the day this is just
added to our position right yeah there
we go
okay sorry there's so many changes here
vacuum transform in this case so get
clipped rekt and I'm not sure what we
decided to do forget cliprect let me
just look at that one real quick so it's
just the Z value that comes in there so
that's just this and that still works
actually just fine so no no issues there
same here
that's all easy this get cliprect
similarly wants to be like this what
else we got
no transform that's good with the melts
all right so let's just see what we
broke looks like we've got a entity
placement break although only for those
bitmaps so it looks like that one bitmap
broke that one kind of drawing broke but
nothing else did looks like I'm gonna
get rid of this stuff anyway eventually
um so I think the only thing that I
broke was inside the entity stuff in
here so I guess for some reason when we
were doing our push bitmap here I didn't
add the offset and actually you know
what you can see that's 100% true
actually but that's fine because that's
the code that I'm gonna want to start
off on tomorrow anyway and because
that's part we're gonna be rewriting all
right so that was pretty easy change to
make actually I'm happy about that that
went really well so now we've got rid of
that and again we're simplifying this
code down which I want to do for sure
right like I want to keep making this
less and less complex use bitmap dim
we'll probably now bifurcate that out
and so they'll just be two calls one
that happens for the font stuff and one
that happens for the entity render stuff
and it'll get pushed into that actual
routine so as we progress down that road
I think we'll get even cleaner I'm gonna
go to quick Q&amp;A now and then we'll wrap
it up
questions questions questions
[Music]
Oh any news about me Oh hash yes
actually there is some news let me ask I
have been too busy to post a new version
but actually we have a stronger version
of male hash coming that runs about as
fast as the old one it's only slightly
since that little teat slower but it's
actually a much stronger hash but I
haven't had chance to post it yet ooh a
good pro tip from long boolean not
actually important but Krampus related
the Lau F in krampuslauf is pronounced
more like ooh in the words out o so more
like owl or couch in German the a in
Krampus is more of an off so Krampus so
it's more like Krampus Lau is that right
Krampus Lau long building can you tell
me how close I'm pronouncing it now
Krampus Lao is Krampus Lau better
Krampus Lau is the pee hard or soft is
it
Krampus Lao or krump a Slough like or
which is happening there
let me go ahead two three I forgot why
sorting was necessary couldn't we just
send it all to the GPU and have the
depth other sorted out uh yeah that's
that is what we do
but we used to sort because we used to
not have a depth buffer we decided after
testing that we really wanted it so
that's why we don't the sort anymore
if that makes sense when I said I wanted
these sorted in order of parenting that
is not Z order the reason that I want
that here is because we're gonna want to
go we're gonna want to do a single pass
through the list and children need to
look back at where their parents were in
order to place themselves in the right
position so I just want to make sure
parents always come before children so
that's a different kind of sort
it's not about Z order right can you put
the shadow offset in the shadow
transform now probably I don't really
remember where that's happening
I don't think we're doing that anymore
yeah I don't think we are I think it's
just it just is that transform that's
all the only thing we've got at the
moment when do you feel that should be
the game I'm looking forward to playing
it oh well we've got a while we we don't
do that many hours of programming each
week so it's gonna be a while we're
mostly done with the engine but we've
got a bunch of gameplay code to do so
you know you're looking at well I also I
said I would do 600 episodes so for 294
so we've got 106 episodes before we
would ship it just just on principle
alone my particular reason to use
Windows or Linux yeah you can look at
the episode archive if you go back to
handmade hero org watch the watch page
you can search previous episodes for
things like Linux and we talked about
Linux a bunch of times in various places
here this so if you want more
information you can or you know another
one would be why windows let's see I
don't know if there's a way to search
for why not Linux so you might search in
there a little bit to see the more clear
answers but the basic reason is just
because games ship primarily on Windows
that's why so handmade hero is made to
be portable and in fact already runs on
Linux and Mac in a number of places
because community members supported it
we have not done the porting on the
stream yet because that's the thing I
said I would do later on so portability
is very important because you know you
want to have multiple platforms a lot
times you watched upon ps4 Xbox one and
Windows as a minimum you know of what
you'd like to target usually and then
depending on your game you know Nintendo
switch Mac Oz Linux potentially as more
like just finishing to
get all the platforms if you've gone
that far the reason we do Windows is
because it's the easiest development
environment that everyone can have
access to right like if I pick ps4 for
example you'd have to be dev you'd have
to be members of the development
community they're like you have to have
Sony approve you to get any left I'm a
dev kit right so I can't really do that
so I have to pick something you know
that's commodity available you can just
go out and buy it you don't need to get
approval you don't you know and it runs
on a regular computer so Windows and of
Windows Mac Linux by far like almost all
games on the PC are sold the Windows
version so I just went numbers wise
right and so you really have to have
windows be your foremost platform
something that may change but right now
Linux and Mac just don't account for
very many of your sales so Windows is
where you need to make sure you're good
because that's where most of your sales
would come from it's your most important
platform and then Linux and Mac are like
what you port to right
how much time do you think games I
should spend refactoring code compared
to running new features I often find
discouraging when I spend too much find
refactor the code without I think adding
anything new for a while um you should
never refactor anything that you're not
refactoring to do something new I guess
is the way I would say it so the answer
is you should never be spending time
refactoring code if you're not doing it
to add a new feature or to improve its
performance like refactoring should only
be done to as something you do during
improvement and it should be relatively
obvious at the time to an experienced
developer what sorts of refactoring I'm
not really a fan of that term
what sorts of restructuring might have
to occur in order to move the code
forwards and that's something that you
can only really learn by experience
because sometimes it's more efficient to
simply modify the little piece of code
you need to add the feature you're
looking for other times it's clear that
in order to do that you want to fix
something right and so that's I guess
what I'd say is the only piece of strong
advice I have there is never spend time
restructuring code without an idea of
why you are doing it so a lot of people
preach too much puritanical sort of
things about code code that works
properly is good and code that doesn't
work properly is bad and that's pretty
much the end of it so when you look at a
piece of code and you're going should I
be restructuring this code someway
never just restructure it to restructure
it you should have an idea in your head
of why what am I getting am i getting
increased speed am i getting less bugs
am i getting new features and if you
don't have one of those strongly in mind
then you're just kind of wasting your
time lungful you're dropping the app oh
okay so when you said that you
pronounced the Krampus Lau the AO you
still you didn't mean get rid of the f
you just mean don't say laughs say
laughs is that what
so it's Krampus Laos crawfish love
off-topic do you have any tips on
parsing academic math papers no they're
written by people who seem to be unable
to communicate with humans I don't know
why you just have to grind through them
it's terrible I know I don't know why
that happens I don't know why every
single math paper I've ever seen after I
spent the time to actually understand it
I could have explained it crystal clear
without all of the ridiculousness
for some reason they just don't do that
I don't know why I have no idea why I
really don't just bad convention I guess
okay so Krampus Lau is bad
Krampus Laos is good so Krampus loved
Krampus laughs no no no it's conscious
laughs we are going to see if the
changes to the scale alignment point
back to the file they are coming from
yes we're going to be doing a couple
things there yeah in the tech stop it
still offsets the text sorry what is
that but that's good right
I mean what why is that bad
I mean look looks looks right to me
could you be more specific
off-target I've heard you mention other
memory management techniques than the
arena's as used on handmade Hiro sure
there's lots of memory management
techniques but arenas are a very
powerful one and pretty important the
ones we use on handmade here are really
the bread-and-butter once I think you
should use most of the time so there's
hand the the arena's and then there's
free lists which we use those are two of
the most powerful simplest and gets you
almost everything you want memory
management techniques but there are
obviously more so you try to use
multi-threading which is possible or the
other way around or does it just depend
a lot so here's what I'll say I've done
a lot more multi-threaded programming
recently even than I had done when I
originally started handmade Hiro you
know multi-threaded programming is very
very difficult it's far far more
difficult than single threaded
programming so much more difficult that
I think you really want a lot of
language features to help you do it
properly which don't exist in C++ and
that's an issue
anytime you can get away with not
writing a multi-threaded code you should
because your code will have less bugs in
it however it is increasingly becoming
the case that almost all code needs to
be multi-threaded in order to run on
modern systems fast enough because
modern systems just aren't getting much
faster single-threaded they're only
getting faster multi-threaded so I guess
what I would say is there's no good news
yes try to write as little
multi-threaded code as possible no you
really can't limit how much longer to
code you're running unless your games
are very simple and yeah C++ is a
terrible language for multi-threaded
programming it has literally zero of the
features that you would want and so it's
just bad and the more I learn about
multi-threaded programming the more I've
developed my own multiple printing
techniques the more I realize just how
hard it is so hard in fact that I
actually think that it breaks a lot of
things to that other people are relying
on like garbage collection just doesn't
work for multi-threaded programming
either it's just completely wrong
because it's based on the idea of global
visibility and that is so not OK right
so you then have to develop really
complex techniques for garbage
collection to work properly like you
have to defer all of this things to luck
known sequence points or things like
this it's bad right and so I feel like
we're still also in our infancy in terms
of really understanding the proper
memory models for multi-threaded
programming and I'm not an expert on
that either so ask me again in 10 years
can you show John below how to compile
from Emacs to the keyboard shortcut he
maybe he doesn't want to I'm sure he
knows he can can you go into a bit of
detail about what these memory allocated
alligators and management techniques are
it's not right now I mean we've talked a
bit about the LAN stream but I have
Pasadena you would never refactor code
just for code readability no definitely
not
I mean I try to keep my code readable at
all times to the extent that you can
but but no readability is not a valid
reason to refactor code in my opinion
because either if it was written
incorrectly and is should be written in
a different way in the first place for
readability then you probably should
have been able to have some other
argument for why you were gonna rewrite
it not just the reusability I'm not just
the readability there should have been
like it's too hard to call or there's I
want different ways of calling it that I
can use outside of it differently or
it's slow because it's written in a
contour did way that could have been
improved by reorganizing or something
but just like an abstract subjective
opinion about how readable the code is
not a good reason in my opinion
no we are not planning on having script
support okay puss in Krampus is like
puss in pussycat
so Krampus Krampus laughs Krampus mouth
Krampus laughs Krampus love Krampus
laughs Krampus louse
I just discovered dual quaternions are
they used in game programming
I imagine someone probably used dual
quaternions I can't sorry I can't name
anyone offhand who does but probably
someone does Oh could this be in shadow
transfer so this right here no no I
didn't do that I could I think you might
be right but I don't know that's a good
question
I'll put it to doing for you
what are you thoughts an is PC for
multi-threading sim D is that that
Intel's paralyzing compiler that they've
got there are you talking about this
thing well let me see
yeah um my thoughts are it's good I
don't have a lot of thoughts other than
that one sad sad thing I learned
recently doing meow hash was that
dropping down to Assam actually gets you
a massive performance winning me a lot
of cases still uh so I don't know I
don't know what to say
compilers are still bad they just they
haven't gotten very good I'm gonna I'm
gonna go ahead and shut down stream or
get a little over getting a little over
time here getting a little over time
alright let's wrap it up hmm thank you
everybody join me for an episode of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you want to
follow along series at home you can
always pre-order the game on handmade
hero org it comes with the source code
so you can follow along every night with
what we're doing
I'll be back here tomorrow when we will
start to try and make a little skeletal
transform code in that entity stuff so
that we can start to use those snap
points and have those work reliably for
us that's our big next to do that's will
be doing tomorrow PC backup for that
until then have fun putting everyone and
I'll see you on the Internet take it
easy everybody