hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here the show recode a complete game
live on stream we got another bonus
weekend sorry weekday stream in honor of
krampuslauf which is coming up you don't
want to get caught behind Krampus
Krampus obviously very dangerous for
children likely to dismember them and so
you want to be out in front right you
don't want to be caught you don't want
to be a laggard during the Krampus run
that's just not a safe place to be so we
want to try and be out ahead of it so
that's what we're doing here and we've
got some stuff on handmade here that we
want to finish up that we did a bunch of
the work on yesterday actually which is
just giving ourselves some editing
interfaces to play with just basic debug
interface for editing and we got that
working actually and so what we need to
do today is just kind of clean it up and
wire it up to the actual functions and
then we can start playing around and see
where we're at maybe take stock of what
we need to do from there so I'm going to
go ahead and launch what we had
yesterday again we just barely we had
finished like sort of extracting the old
debug UI code that we had that we still
use for for this sort of stuff for
example and you know again like these
things are they're kind of janky but
they get the job done we could clean
some of these up too while we're in the
process but basically what we did is we
allowed that user interface to be used
for other purposes and we just kind of
this is a simple rendering of the
interface that we had kind of talked
about before and so what I'd like to do
now is kind of like get into this a
little bit figure out how to make this a
more proper thing and get it actually
working because now that we've got it
all like compiling such that you can
call the user interface stuff either
from the debug system or from this kind
of like impromptu editor stuff that we
wanted I want to kind of just get that
going for real because it's just it's
only just barely in there now it
at the end of last stream so that's what
I'd like to do today and I'd like to
also use that as an excuse to test we
actually made the editing functionality
for the attachment points that we needed
we just you know didn't have an
interface for it so it didn't actually
do anything so I'd also like to you know
start looking at that code and see does
it work you know do we need to debug
that because we we wrote it and we don't
really have any way of knowing if it
works or if it's any good and so that
will be another place we can start down
if I finish what we're doing here so
what we sort of finished up on was the
notion that now you can use this WI
system and we now have sort of all of it
pulled out in here we have this WI
system and that allows us to access all
the stuff that we had written for the
debug system now there's a number of
different ways you can write user
interface code obviously and we've shown
some of them on the stream and one of
the things you can see here is if if I
wanted to and I don't know that I
necessarily do but when I sketch this
out I kind of did the more immediate
mode graphic user interface style where
you just say that you want a button and
then you put the code for emulating the
button right inside there and there's
there's good and bad reasons for doing
that there's there's pluses and minuses
to it I guess is what I would say and
the plus is that it gives you a
convenient way of keeping all the code
localized right it means that the same
code that says how to render the button
is the code that says how to operate on
the button and it's all done
procedurally so that you don't actually
have to create a standing structure
anywhere to process this it's entirely
ephemeral which is can be really nice
because it cuts down on a lot of bloat
in the code and a lot of state
management that you just don't have to
do because you're never creating
anything so if you want to save button
on one frame you just say there is one
if it disappears on a subsequent frame
it just does you don't have to worry
about oh wait
is there a save button object that I
created and do I have to delete it and
all these other sorts of things it just
kind of simplifies matters for the
person using the code and that's nice
what we don't necessarily get out of it
is a lot of flexibility in terms of
externally implementing things that can
operate on stuff that's on the screen so
in other words it by the it the strength
of it being able to bind these things
closely together being convenient for
the programmer it's also in a sense of
weakness because it means that you have
a preferred way of implementing one
thing that you could do here and it
makes it harder to separate out code
that's gonna operate across multiple
things on the screen or different ways
of operating with the same things on the
screen and so you do have kind of like
pluses and minuses but it's really up to
you a lot of times to figure out what
makes the most sense for what you have
to be doing now in our case
this is just our debug at-at UI so you
know you probably don't want to optimize
for really unusual esoteric use cases
because I'll do those up and probably do
come up in some kind of a professional
tool you know I would use Photoshop as
an example but I said professional tools
so you know maybe not but like being
tools that have complicated UI
interactions you know sometimes you have
to think more carefully about how these
are going to work for a number of
reasons one of them being say for
example you need to do things like
scripting or other stuff like that these
sort of things stop making very much
sense and the reason that they don't
make a lot of sense is because if the
only way to actually access the code
that does something is by going through
the code path that actually displays the
button well that produces a very
unwieldy workflow right it means that in
order to do scripting you have to also
call the renderer to execute the script
somehow or unit right there so once you
start getting into more advanced API
stuff that you need your UI to be able
to support typically you need to take a
step you took you can still use an
immediate mode paradigm for rendering
your layouts and for responding to them
in some ways but you need to start
having a cleaner separation between the
the act of using a particular UI element
and what that thing does if for no other
reason that there are more other people
in the sphere of influence there that
need to be able to access those same
functions so that's why you typically
get into situations where you need to
kind of have okay save actually doesn't
do anything itself
it just has an ID that's like this is
the save operation and then somewhere
else there's a thing that implements all
of your operations and the reason you
need to do that is because if you didn't
do that you couldn't have things like
scripting or user bindable buttons as
easily right because you need that layer
of separation there and again there's
nothing too
do with retain mode or immediate mode
graphic user interface API design it's
just how the person implementing the
actual back end like the Edit operations
how much they can push those into the
actual implementation of the GUI really
depends on that and so what you're
looking at here is you're looking at
trying to make a clean decision about
what you need right because you don't
want to go implementing a bunch of stuff
you don't need because then you're just
wasting a lot of time now on handmade
hero we could do that because as an
educational series so if we were like
look we want to show how to do this even
though we don't need to totally valid
and we sort of did that like we didn't
really need these to do separate
interactions for the way we did them we
could have done something more quick and
dirty like this but we did kind of show
how to do a separated UI as one option
right but if you're in your own code
base you don't want to be doing things
just to do them because you actually
know exactly what you need and you're
not trying to teach anybody anything
unless we're trying to teach yourself
which of course is a reasonable option
as well
so in our case we don't really care and
you can see that this was a pretty
convenient way to write this so you know
least for the time being maybe this is a
good way to do it and what's kind of
nice about like the way that we've
implemented it here is that if you do
support in a basically an iamb GUI style
for your thing it allows you sort of the
best of both worlds because when you do
want to have things be interactions in a
table by ID or something like this you
can but then you can always have one of
those interactions just be immediate
right so for example in this case what I
could do is you know have a interaction
like you know immediate button or
whatever right I can make an interaction
that is that thing and then I can write
some interaction code that is as if it
was an outboard thing as if it were a
separate thing for all the tables and
stuff but instead of actually doing that
all it does is feed there is
it's back to code like this to execute
on the fly right so let me show you how
to do that now and again that's why I
see can't get the best of both worlds
because we can for any given operation
we want really just have either one and
our architecture doesn't need to change
because it's flexible enough that it can
do either those two things and that's
kind of nice right so what I want to do
there is just say all right there's this
immediate button thing right and what I
want to do is all of these buttons that
I've got here right that were you know
immediate I just want them to go through
that path so when inside the dev UI
you're gonna make one of these things
right so you know we've got the button
thing here when they're doing their WI
interaction in there couldn't you know
constructing that what we want to do
there is just have a way to construct
one with this immediate button bit right
and then what that's going to do is it's
gonna create one of these WI
interactions it just has some way of
remembering what it was that you
actually clicked on right and there's a
number of ways we can do that and I'm
gonna probably do the cheesiest one but
you know whether or not you want to do
that one is kind of a separate issue so
what I'd like to do here is say okay you
know I want to create one of these
things I know that I need to construct a
dev ID and then the rest of this stuff
is kind of just dirigir meaning once I
know a dev ID for this thing I'm kind of
done because if I have a dev ID I can
uniquely identify which button was
pressed without any storage right I
don't need to remember anything other
than just that dev ID I don't need an
instance of the button the ID will
disambiguate it right so if I assume
that when I'm pushing this button
somehow I'm able to get a dev ID here
and we'll figure out how that's gonna
happen in a second but if I do that then
creating this dev ID
interaction is pretty straightforward
right all I really need to do is say all
right look when I create this
interaction I'm gonna set the ID to
something and we don't know what that is
but the rest of it is just merely a case
of saying that right and the rest of
these things like the target can just be
left null because we don't actually need
any more information right we don't need
any other there's nothing else that goes
on there when we look down at the WI
itself and we're actually processing
these things so we've got the
interaction the hot interaction the next
hot interaction that sort of stuff um we
really just need the knowledge that
something is being executed and as long
as we have that knowledge we can
basically finish off this loop so all we
really need to do here is say look
there's gonna be a dev ID you that we're
just gonna call you know execute or ID
to execute and all we're gonna do here
is see if the ID that we were going to
use is executed that gives us a result
of true otherwise because it results a
false right so hopefully you can see
when I'm starting a sketch in here we
need a damn ID we'll figure out how to
make one of those in a second once we
have a dev ID we can make an interaction
that is called this a media button
interaction it will be a thing that just
allows buttons to be clicked right and
then once I know that that's happening
if I click on a button that interaction
will just set the ID to execute to to be
our ID and once we know that we know
what the result is so once we know that
we know here that the result in this
case is just whatever the UI says the ID
to execute is we just want to know if
it's equal oops having some capslock
issues I don't mind telling you we just
want to know if these two IDs are equal
so if the UI says that we're supposed to
execute a particular ID and that's also
the ID that we have then we're good to
go so it really just ends up
how do we make this dev ID right how do
we make this thing and that's all we
would need okay I don't remember what
the actual equal like equivalence value
is for dev IDs to completely honest with
you
I know it's I know we made a function
for it
it's this I guess and so I want to
change that to dev IDs or equal and
honestly I think just are equal it's
fine with me so you know you're passing
it to typed values so I'm just not sure
there's a lot of risk there in over
naming so I'm gonna go ahead and change
that over as well and then in here we'll
just see the IDS or actually just a
party cool or rather we don't know what
that is yet and in here we'll just say
debug IDs are equal will just be are
equal and there we go so really again
all I want to do now is just make sure
that that stuff is reasonable so just
fix that last one I just want to go
ahead and make sure that that all this
stuff is implemented and then we'll look
at how we might want to create one of
these IDs all right so what you'll
notice is that we didn't actually do any
sharing of the user interface execution
code and that's kind of intentional and
I think we may just let that live for
now and I'll kind of show you what I
mean by that so if we look in terms of
when the debug system itself when it
goes to do an end frame
where's where is that at there is when
it goes to do an end frame what it does
is it calls its debug interact function
and that's the thing that actually does
the updating you know of what's going on
with with you know any UI interactions
that might make sense here right so you
can kind of see that sketched out here
like you know if you're not interacting
with something then we do some of this
stuff and in blah blah blah blah blah
right we see whether or not you're gonna
interact with these various mouths mouse
buttons we actually
we do the interactions which is
interesting so we actually we actually
handle multiple clicks inside a single
frame which is a bit aggressive but you
know all right that's fine
and so this code here you can kind of
say some of it is like share ish and
some of it is it write this kind of code
we may just want a lot of this stuff
like you know just just looking at it a
lot of the stuff is probably just best
saved for in the debug system like it's
just it looks better inside the debug
system there's not a lot that we
probably want to save here because all
of its pretty specific you know this you
know maybe is stuff that could be shared
and if we wanted to share it we can
always add defaults and here that call
sort of a WI generic processing loop so
we can choose to pull things that we
want to share out but just looking at it
if you look at how much is specific it
really just doesn't look like the kind
of thing that needs to get shared and
the reason that I bring that up is just
because I think what that implies for us
is we don't really want to call the same
function so inside our editor here which
is using the UI system and so on right I
think what we want to do is in our you
know in the in the main gain area that's
actually doing this stuff the in-game
editor right I think what it wants to do
is it wants to handle this UI stuff
itself not as a part of a shared
operation with the you know with the
debug system this is a little
questionable I don't really know to what
extent we want these things shared this
way I'm gonna leave it that way for now
and I'm just gonna call here after that
end UI frame I'm gonna follow the debug
system
lead on how this was working and just
say look what we're gonna do is we're
gonna insert and interact call here and
and say like this is you know editor
interact or whatever and we're just
gonna pass exactly the same stuff as we
were passing here and I'm just not gonna
think too hard about it otherwise right
so we're just gonna do exactly this and
go from there now when we actually call
this I'm gonna pass that WI as well
through here because I think that's
probably what should have been happening
here too that's sort of a separate issue
and I'm not gonna pass the mouse P and D
mouse P because those are part of the UI
now so we're just gonna like do this in
a slightly more modernized way than what
we were doing before now that we kind of
have a better picture in the system but
otherwise it's gonna be basically the
same so if I go ahead and grab this
editor interactive bit here and place
that in side the the editor proper and
just write that in we have our in-game
editor here and I have our dev UI here
I'm gonna actually stick with just
calling that you know and then we have
the input and so what I want to do is
during editor interact again I'm gonna
follow the lead of the debug system but
I'm gonna write some pretty different
code in here probably or handle some
different things and then if I end up
deciding that what we've got you know
really should be shared I can share it
right and that's the part I want to
emphasize here right is all of this
stuff if I do decide that I want it to
work the same way
will merge them later so what I want to
avoid is sharing for sharing sync I want
to see myself write the same thing twice
in the same way and go okay I see that
these things are really going to be
pretty much identical so let me go ahead
and and deal with that and merge these
two things right so I'm gonna start by
looking at the skeleton of this
and editor interactor team care and just
look at what we've got so inside here
you know this obviously is not relevant
I also don't really think this is
particularly relevant so I think we're
mostly looking at you know I guess
really just in here that one that we've
just that we've described so if we're
doing a particular interaction here I
mean you know now that I think about I
don't even really know which one what we
would really even be caring about very
much in terms of implementing this
immediate button part here but you know
this is the only one we would really
care about so when we're looking at this
UI interaction type if we say okay you
know here's what we're gonna do that I
also think since we're switching on that
value I guess what I would say is if we
want to handle the none case I don't
know why that wasn't just one of the
cases right so that's yeah I don't I
don't know exactly why we weren't doing
this possibly because well I mean even I
guess it's maybe because this click
interaction the way that it works is it
needs to call end and then begin maybe
is the reason so they want to share you
know they this wanted to get shared
couldn't really tell you I mean that
looks like the only real difference
between these two things
right is is that is the toggle so
between begin and end and that doesn't
seem like a particularly good reason
especially doesn't feel like pretty good
reason because that's something we could
have done with a function pointer and
just swapped so I don't know that that
seems like a bad excuse for it
so I'm less inclined to maybe copy that
sort of version of events over here but
we'll see so I guess what I would say is
yet you know looking at these then we
have to think about whether we want to
copy that sort of beginning and interact
paradigm in the first place and go for
there so let's take a look inside the
debug system at the like begin interact
and interact so the thing that we're
most closely going to be related to here
is just I mean probably like the the
button version that we use in here it
didn't really even need any processing
so it was really just you know this this
is what happened on begin interaction
you know when you had a transition this
is all that we were doing is that
whatever the interaction you were over
becomes like the sort of active
interaction right I and that was that
was it so I don't really know we don't
at least for this so far we don't really
need much more than that that would
really be all that would be going on
here and we just need to be able to
process every time we sort of stop
interacting with something we just need
to be able to process whatever the stop
whatever the end of that interaction was
so again looking through here I'm just
not super sure we really needed to do it
this way it seems like we could have
done this all in just one routine
I I mean just even just looking at it it
just really seems like this something we
could probably condense pretty cleanly
and actually just make this a much much
simpler version mm-hmm
for example right you can see here what
we're doing let me just try to make this
a little clearer here so you can see
here what we were doing is saying all
right
there's this concept that there's some
number of transitions that a mouse
button has gone through right so you
know on a given frame if that were zero
so you know however many transitions
there are if that were zero and again I
have no idea why we felt the need to
count backwards for example right
because this loop fundamentally speaking
is just as simple as saying well you
know we need to count up to the number
of transitions right so I you know want
to do this and if the number of
transitions was 1 we didn't want to do
any right at least that seemed like what
we're doing if the half transition count
was 0 it's greater than 1
yeah I think if so in other words if it
was 2 we would do one time through the
loop if it was 1 we wouldn't do any time
through the loop so I mean it seems like
really all we were doing was this you
know so I I don't really know why we
were going to talk sort of walked that
backwards again really kind of a little
bit confusing you can see here right
because let's say this was zero then we
wouldn't do anything right if it was 1
we wouldn't do anything and if it was 2
we would do once so that's the same loop
is this I mean am I missing something
there I I don't know what the rationale
was for sort of this rather obtuse
for this rather obtuse way of doing
things similarly you know you look at
what's happening here and really that's
just going through this loop for the
final time and it's just this thing
that's different there so you might also
say look you really wanted to do that
but what you didn't want to do is call
this right on the on the final one so
you're almost you you know you're almost
just saying look if we were gonna bottom
out here don't don't do it right I mean
that's all we were doing there and then
that you know it's presumably something
you could still check right so sorry it
looks like I've got the wrong one man
there we go so just looking at what was
going on in there it was something like
this
and so again just trying to create
something here that that you know that
makes sense in terms of doing begins and
ends I just want to see if we can
simplify that down to something less
crazy so that we don't have to
constantly be be you know I just feel
like there's a lot of nonsense going on
in there that maybe doesn't make a whole
lot of sense right so let's say that we
hoisted that up here
and I guess what I'd say is let's see if
we can make it so that we can just have
a loop and all of the code is just
contained in here for what we want to do
write something a little bit more like
single switch statement that just
handles everything so you just put the
code in that you wanted for whatever it
was gonna happen here so rather than
having to have different functions for
each of those you could just implement
what you wanted to have happen inside
the switch statement or you can call out
to a function if you'd rather implement
there but make it so that it was easier
to do that so when we're looking at
what's gonna happen here when we go to
do our interaction we're gonna look at
how many times the clicks happened even
if no click happens we want to give
people a chance to process what
effectively is a mouse move and so maybe
we just say look you know there's mouse
move and that's transition index 0 so at
the first time through the loop you were
gonna get the ability to a mouse move
there's gonna be a like Mouse down and a
mouse up right and those are these
things so in terms of whether this is a
mouse down or a mouse up event that
you're supposed to be handling on these
transitions I feel like we could
probably make that be something that
just happens in here so basically saying
okay you know we know whether the thing
ended down or not and so we can just say
maybe we say look
if the transition index is and in fact I
guess the other thing I'd say is this if
the transition index equals zero or not
that tells us what's going on so the
first time through we just process the
mouse move the next time through that
loop we just say well it's gonna be
either mouse down or mouse up right and
oops sorry and the question is just
whether the ended down like whichever
one this is if it ended down then we
know that the transitions are going to
be opposite what they would be if it
ended up in a sense right so the I mean
I suppose it would be nicer if we knew
well I guess even just the transition
counts parity tells us that right so if
the transition count is even then it
tells us one thing if the transition
count is odd it tells us another great
so we kind of have like the ability to
reverse engineer that part of it as well
in in the loop I want to get rid of all
of this stuff here and I guess what I
would say is at the end of all of this
presumably what happens here is this
this code here when we find that we
don't have any current interaction if we
are in a mouse down then we would have
one right so you know we are generally
speaking if we don't have an interaction
we will take hot interactions from then
on and if the mouse goes down then we're
gonna create one of those right and
that's pretty much what's gonna happen
when the mouse goes up we probably just
have to end our interactions but I don't
know like you know maybe that's not
always true I don't know it seems
probably safer to assume that it is true
all the time but I don't know so I guess
you might say look if we don't have one
here then if the mouse goes up then the
interaction gets cleared I'm not sure
how are we doing that before I guess we
were doing it right here right
so we were kind of doing this before I'm
not sure we might want do that a little
bit differently but it's fine
and so you know something like this so
then when we have immediate button then
we kind of know what's going on right
you know we have mouse if the mouse goes
down if the mouse goes up and here I
kind of want this to be sort of a
clearing operation that we would just do
because this is I don't really want that
to be something that people have to call
separately so in census this should
probably be like clear interaction and
that just makes this happen
now we could that's really just a zero
struct call but I I'm just gonna make it
a little bit more systemic systemic here
because I don't really want it to be
ambiguous what's happening there so I
want this to be something that you can
call and just know that whatever was
supposed to happen it will happen and
you don't really need to know what that
is so if this is a dev UI interaction
here then I can I can clear it that way
right and this I'm going to cut and
paste in here and just say look that's
something that everyone has access to
the debug system will call it will call
it here and multiple people will want to
call it so anyone who sort of like ends
the interaction will do it here and when
we do this Mouse up right the we sort of
set ourselves up here and said well we
know that inside the WI we want the
ability to say that there that there's
an ID that we're executing in this case
and so we're gonna go ahead and put that
put that up so that it will get executed
before we clear the interaction now you
could argue and you wouldn't necessarily
be wrong that this should possibly live
inside the editor again I'm proceeding
cautiously with these and I'm not sure
how much they're gonna collapse
I'm allowing there to be a lot of
flexibility here I'm not trying to
create any walls between these systems
I'm like letting them be fully as
spaghetti E as they want to be until I
have a really clear idea of what I want
to happen right because I find that it's
usually the opposite way of what most
people think like usually I don't find
it best to keep things rigorous at the
outset because you end up spending way
too much time usually what you'd much
rather do is keep things fluid at the
outset let them be mangy and weird and
then when you're really sure what's
going on then you start to get rigorous
and draw those boundaries and that's a
much better time to do that because
you're not wasting a lot of time on
things that really shouldn't have
happened because you didn't realize what
was actually going on so if we look at
what's gonna happen with the immediate
button stuff now we're not gonna see the
mouse down here really so you know
really what's happening here is is that
interaction is gonna start here so
really what we're gonna see here only is
Mouse moves we would never see Mouse
downs because Mouse downs are gonna get
handled by the none interaction in in
our case right so we rolling a see mouse
moving mouse up and for us Mouse up is
the execute case Mouse move he's really
just something that would the only thing
that would really do is it would recheck
the for lack of a better term like the
the Box region that we were clicking in
and so you know one thing we could do is
inside this WI interaction we could have
a rectangle there and we could use that
rectangle to see whether or not we
should be highlighting ourselves or not
but we really don't need to so I think
honestly the entire code for this thing
comes down to something like this and
and that's it right so now what we
really need to do is say well how do we
actually set these things you know which
house this what's this actually going to
look like
and so what we need to do there is is
come up with a scheme for figuring out
from which transition you're on whether
the mouse went down or up right and we
know which one it ended I don't know if
we know which one it started on because
I think we passed a rather minimal set
of things here which means that like
ended down is probably all we've got
yeah so you can see we only get that
that's the only actual input we get
there is whether it ended down so we
kind of have to walk it backwards from
there that's not that big a deal right
so what we can do is we can create some
sort of thing that's like mouse button
and we can we can set this based on the
transition count so and I guess we could
all set it for this right so we can say
look the mouse buttons if it ended down
it's gonna be true right but then we
want to not that if the transition count
was odd essentially right because it
will not have started that way if the
transition count was on if it's even we
have the same amount but so what we want
to do is say if the transition counts
mod two right so if it was odd you know
I'm saying meaning because the
transition counts going to be a number
like 1 1 mod 2 would be 1 meaning true
if it's a 2 mod 2 would be 0 meaning 0
if it's even so if it is odd we want to
flip it right then each time through the
loop we just say mouse button equals not
mouse button and that's all we have to
say about that and so this is the state
for this and we can also furthermore
kind of go through this and simplify it
by saying well if that's what it looks
like then really all we're saying is
Mouse down equals mouse button and Mouse
up is not mouse button
right so we're really just saying that
and so that I think is a fairly concise
way of coding everything into one loop
and that's really pretty brief right so
we're just gonna handle all the
interactions right there and off we go
so now if we debug that and get that
work cuz I threw a lot of stuff in there
it was fairly subtle code right so I
don't want to pretend that that was
simple but it is concise and it is not
very intricate there's not a lot to it
right and so really what we want to look
at here is just figure out okay what do
we need to create an ID that can
uniquely describe one of these buttons
because that's really the last piece of
that puzzle let me see
where are our our equal pit part went
wrong here
dev ID as you know what it's probably
fine it's but I just took it's just
probably that the ID was not defined
almost again and I need to actually pass
that
let's see cannot give her argument three
from debye DWI interaction that's a good
point
UI is an undeclared identifier that's
another good point anything else that is
also true it's the UI interaction that
we're talking about here so I think
that's everything we needed so that is
pretty much the complete the complete
solution we just now need a way to
actually create an ID and then I think
we'd be good to go so you know if I well
that was interesting
so it actually speaking of debugging
that code it actually returned true for
this oh you know why probably because
it's set to zero right so in that code
we should probably do something here
where we say that this dev ID if this
dev ID is valid right so we probably
want to do something more like this
something like this I don't know if
we've gotten is valid for that but you
know that's like if you're saying it's
equal you kind of got to know whether or
not it was ever set to anything valid in
the first place and that's not something
we actually know here so in this case
what we want to do is say all right I
need to compute something that says
whether this thing's valid so what I
want to do is to say if either of these
two I don't know why I put about that
way if either of these two things is set
we assume that it is if if they're both
zero then it's not right I can make
these a little bit more full there I'm
gonna pull these out and just see if I
can get away with putting them in here I
don't know if I can I'm gonna try yeah
so now I think we should be able to
launch the editor and not only that code
will run but again we cannot check our
buttons even though the code is now in
there to do so because we don't actually
have any way of telling if they're
accurate or not and furthermore you can
kind of see how everything lights up at
the same time the reason for that is
because they all have the same ID which
is nothing and so they all light up
whenever you hover over one of them and
so what we want to do now is figure out
a way to construct an ID that's going to
be valid in you know in this case so
when we're gonna do the button here now
there's a lot of ways we can do that we
played around with this a bit in the
debug system because we wanted to be
able to create unique settings in our
case here we probably can do basically
the same thing it probably wouldn't be
that hard to just make a macro here that
generates a unique ID in this case and
you know I don't know whether we want to
do that or not it's annoying this should
be a simple matter right in other words
what you should be able to do is inside
the definition of a function if you
let's say look I just need to have the
file on line number like tell me who
called me right pass that along should
be really trivial to do C++ makes it
almost impossible you have to use the
macro browser to do it so you can no
longer overload functions and you can no
longer have name resolution it's really
bad but you know that's what we would
expect from C++ so what we want to do
here is decide whether we want to do
that one simple way we could do it is we
could just use the label text that's
passed in now there are reasons why that
works and reasons why that doesn't work
basically what it boils down to is does
the compiler do string pooling or
doesn't it and so what you can see here
is this compiler does string pooling and
I'll explain what's going on here in a
second and so you can see the actual
activity occur which is the undo redo
and delete which are unique words all
work properly unused
does not
right and the question is what's going
on there well what's going on there is
if I was to use the pointer to the
string as the debug ID or developer ID
here in this case then that only
uniquely identifies the button insofar
as the text itself is unique because
when the compiler goes to build the
string table what most compilers
nowadays will do if assuming
optimizations is on they might not do
this in other cases I don't know but
assuming you're creating an optimized
build at least what many compilers will
do is they'll say well if you have the
same string I'm not gonna put it in the
data segment for this executable twice
right I'm just gonna put it in there
once and then everyone who needs to use
that string I'm just gonna point to that
right and that's a much more efficient
way to do it unfortunately it breaks
anything that was counting on those
strings being unique so what we would
rather have in this case is something
that allows us to uniquely identify the
place where this button is being used
maybe or you know something right we we
want something more and because we want
something more there I'm just gonna
suggest that probably what we need to do
is have this passed in so the we don't
know how to identify your button because
again it's just a little too
unpredictable to use this due to string
pooling it is a shortcut we could take I
just don't think it's feasible in this
case let's just say you've got to make
your own okay you've got to pass your
own one in there that's just what you've
got to do okay um so if we want to do
that what we could do is say well in
that case we know that we could make a
unique ID here a lot more easily we
could for example try doing something
where we try to think of what the
easiest thing to do is like we could do
something here where we use the point
index because we know that that's unique
and
and or you know what we could do just a
pointer to the point right we know that
that's completely unique in this case
nobody else is using that to create an
operation in this context so it should
just be fine you know what I mean so
that's one thing we could do we could
also create some IDs for operation types
that would also work just fine all of
those things would be fine so trying to
think of how we want to do that
I think really all we would want to do
here is just maybe use the line so I'm
gonna I'm gonna introduce a concept here
I think it'd be fairly straightforward
and that would just be like you know if
we want to make a dev ID we could do
something like this where we just say
all right if we're gonna get a pointer
here that's gonna uniquely identify the
thing we're editing you know so this is
like the pointer you know maybe we've
got some magic sauce that occurs here
that tries to give us more than that as
well
right like and so you pass us the
pointer we then say like you know dev ID
we have some function that that builds
these I think we've already got some of
that so I'll go look for them but we're
gonna pass like whatever the pointer is
that you wanted us to use and then we'll
pass you know maybe like the line number
from the file so that like all of these
things will be unique just based on
because they're calling location would
be unique right and we did more of that
in the debug interface stuff right we we
got pretty crazy with that here insert
of some annoying ways but like unique
file counter string right you can see
this thing where we just said we need a
name for this thing and it's like did
all this stuff right and so something
similar to that would also work for us
where we could have four things that get
concatenated
together to make a string that's
definitely gonna be unique you know what
I mean
and so we could even pick you back on
top of this if we were to make you know
and I'm just gonna take a look at where
that's actually used one two three four
right so it's only right here we could
just make this be a macro that's just
like hey compose all these things
together for us please right so looking
at this you know we've got this debug
name and you pass the name in here we
don't actually ever use the name that's
kind of just you know historical
nonsense there right the the D the you
know this doesn't actually ever get word
in I think there was some reason we
couldn't do that I don't really remember
exactly what it was to be completely
honest with you yeah I don't really
remember there was some kind of platform
we were just with that so you know this
really is just a concatenate call that
concatenates three things together so we
could just make that be what we wanted
there right so for example in this case
what I could do is say look let's just
make this this okay and make that work
and then we can make this a more generic
function right so this thing here we
could just have be like so we just have
this is a thing that concatenates three
things together
and then we've got this right
similarly what I can do here is say like
file I'm string and I guess you know it
could just have its unique thing at the
end too so it's got like the file the
line and the counter
it needs the pound after each of these
four line encounter so I guess we
probably would want a similar thing here
like on cat to
like that and so now these are
presumably just utilities we can use to
do this call now the fact that that one
gets a pound we probably need to name
these little more carefully because
they're not generic so maybe I have to
do like something more like that so this
is just file in line your end I mean
that seems fine to me and then I'll pull
that one out and that one we can use for
whatever else so here there would just
be a thing that's like file and line and
you don't have to pass anything and that
just calls filing line underscore with
file @y right um that all feels pretty
good to me and you know this maybe is
better served than at that point sort of
being a little clearer that it's just
for this and we'll just leave it at that
right I think that's good and then
inside you know maybe inside our types
here we can make this pound of fine so
people who need to use it and so what
that lets me do is inside the WI stuff
then we can make this be really clear so
if we do dev ID from pointer then we can
call file in line here and get a string
that's actually like what we want so in
addition to the pointer to the thing to
edit we can also unique based on that
and that gives us a pretty powerful way
of generating locational code locational
things that will be what we want right
and so then inside the actual code for
that it's quite simple the dev ID for
anything of that format
in this case - I want to make sure we
cast away Const there cuz C compilers
love to make strings constant nowadays
which I hate I cannot stand that I hate
Const in general and so I would have
preferred it if that was something that
I got to the side because some people
like it and they're welcome to use it
but I don't and don't want to have to
use it but you know they force you to
use it it's really annoying anyway so if
we're gonna do it this way here's our
results and in this case it just looked
like that right so you just end up with
a pretty easy way to you to make those
things unique so at that point I think
we're more or less done with a good way
to get those we can just say dev ID from
pointer and we can say look here's the
the point that we reading and each of
the buttons is now pretty trivial it can
pretty trivially do that it's so can all
of these editors as well which is
probably what we'll want to do as we go
so that gives us a good way to make
those unique in here it's a little bit
trickier to do but because we don't have
a point that we're adding but it's
crucial to remember well that's okay
because actually just the editor itself
is plenty because these are unique there
they don't get replicated multiple times
there's only one save only one revert
only one undo and one redo so really we
can pass any pointer here I mean we'll
pass the editor but we could just pass 0
and it would even be fine because we
don't need to do anything else there
right we don't need to do anything else
to make those things unique so now all
of our pointers should be unique and not
dependent on string pooling anymore
because we're actually creating strings
that are themselves unique for the
location that they're being used and so
now if I go over things I get a nice
clean interface exactly the way that it
should be working and that pretty much
concludes what we have to do for that
part of the process right
okay so let's move on now to some things
that are a little bit more specific I
also I don't know if this actually works
now like if I click on this so it does
so our interface is actually sort of
working now right like if I click on
this thing can see that I've added I can
add points to it I can also probably
delete points although you know you can
kind of see the next part of the thing
that we have to go through to do that is
actually working on the selection stuff
right so let me quickly do that but you
can kind of see that we have you know
we've got our interface working now so
we can start to debug this stuff right
I'm not sure what happened here what did
we get why did we get a bug there with
uh with our with our undo Sentinel oh I
do believe we never actually created
those sentinels during in it so actually
all of this stuff kind of has to be set
properly and we we didn't do that
so there is an initialized editor and in
the initialized editor one of the things
we need to do is just make sure these
sentinels are linked up and so you know
in order to do that we need to do this
code right so we want to kind of have I
don't know what you want to call this
but like it's just points itself
I don't know what to call that
but it's this and what we need to do at
the beginning is our two sentinels
actually need to be set up to point to
each other it's the one really annoying
thing about doubly-linked lists
implemented this way it's unfortunate
because clear to zero is pretty much
always the right solution and it's it's
one of those unfortunate algorithms that
is nice in all other ways but that way
not very much you know what can I say
not everything it doesn't all work the
way you might want so yeah that should
do us a little bit better there when
looking at this here so let me just go
ahead and like do some of these and then
try so undo and redo look like they're
not available right now for some reason
not sure why that is so undo available
and redo available
if this is not empty and that's an empty
that's correct is empty is set to result
this next equals list that's correct
so for some reason we were not it looks
like we were not pushing on a change
there is that correct you allocate the
edit now and we did not push it on right
because we've got all this stuff here
and we just didn't simply didn't do it
so here's like all of that list code
right that we're using here and we
simply did not do a push first which is
what we should have done right so we
created the edit but we never actually
stored it so you know we want to do a
push for us gonna be edit and I
presumably I have to here say okay and
and actually now think about it when you
allocate it editor edit it probably
should always go on there right I mean
it really probably should just do that
right here I would think it's hard to
say because maybe you want to make one
of these sometimes when that's not true
but not sure when that wouldn't be the
case so I kind of think that should
happen here and I think that's probably
yeah what I would prefer
um we really don't need to sentinel eyes
that either cuz if you look at what
happens inside push first I don't think
we really need to do that because it
when you call link on one of these
things you can see that it just
overwrites those two fields immediately
so really this doesn't need to do that
it can really just be be back so I think
that's all fine and we'll give that a
shot as well now okay so looking through
here now if I do this we can see what's
going on I did a pop first on this and I
didn't get back and edit for some reason
oh I know why that is true so another
thing that we didn't yet implement is
inside the dev UI when we are done so
when we end a UI frame we need to clear
out anyone who is executing so the ID to
execute has to get cleared at the end
because that's no longer happening right
so it would have just kept trying to
undo forever all the way back to the
beginning and eventually it will run out
of links and correctly hit the assertion
that says why am I being told to undo
right now there is nothing to undo the
user should not have been given that
option right so we gotta figure out
where that's Oh
[Music]
on endui frame it's actually going to be
inside it's gonna be right before that
that I need to execute got set so it's
really actually a little harder to
figure out where that would go
right because we need that to be
happening in the pin that pass so
I don't really love the idea of having
this have to be like stratified but you
can see what happens there right even
though it's ID to execute needs to last
one frame and one frame only so after
you're done executing it once you need
to go I can't do that an end frame
because it needs to go to the next frame
to do that you know what I mean and so
it's a little bit janky there how that
would really work
you know it's very much like this so
it's almost like you need to do this
right so it's like yeah on mu I frame
you know this becomes that and that
becomes that you know which isn't great
I don't know how I feel about that it's
not my favorite thing in the world
um but hey you know it works just fine
for now and are like undo/redo and
everything is good and off we go so
let's take a look at revert there
because we've got sort of we've got sort
of another thing that that's just
incorrectly Emma so I think our revert
may also pretty much be implemented okay
know what that's doing there when we're
doing this we want to pop back to
whatever we thought are clean undo
Sentinel was our clean undo Sentinel
therefore has get initialized at the
beginning as well so right now what it
would be is whatever you know the undo
Sentinel itself is so I think that's
just probably all we really need so in
terms of reverting to the state of the
code at the beginning I think that's all
we really need so yeah so I think like
if I do a bunch of these here and then
just do revert that should work right
yeah so basically the entire editor is
now implemented and working properly it
looks like and so what we really need to
do now is just work on the UI part some
more I will say deletion doesn't appear
to be working so that is one feature
that appears wrong because I thought you
could delete and I'm not seeing that
happen so I would be just going to know
why
delete didn't work you can see the Edit
align point thing happening here and it
should be setting that a line point to
none mmm but it doesn't seem to be for
whatever reason so something's going on
there let me see what's happening in
edit align point so it's gonna set the
type here it looks like let me see what
set a line point has to say
so the two-parent filled if that's set
to true what did we well even if it
isn't it doesn't really matter it's
still gonna be the type Ord with that so
in theory this should just work unless
we screwed up like the get type call or
something which does it look like we did
how much time do I have by the way does
anyone know when we start 12:45 so I got
what like 45 minutes something like that
I don't know I might assume I got like
45 minutes
so anyway inside here where we've got a
set a line point I I don't know if we're
just like like what's going on there but
we'll verify that it gets called because
you know maybe it doesn't get called for
some reason but and you know maybe the
UI is busted somehow I'm not sure but in
terms of what's going on here oh I see
why it's it should be doing that that's
the problem there also when we do this
this delete should set that to false
probably I would think and probably all
of this stuff should just be set back to
the default you know so that should I
think that was just a case of us calling
with the wrong things and also this was
a bug it should be type because
obviously you could still have that to
parent flag set and technically it's
still in an uninitialized point okay so
let's see now okay so now I can delete
which is good right
so everything looks pretty clean there
right and this allows us to do
everything that we wanted to do so what
we're really talking about now is is a
little bit more UI work because all of
this stuff now needs to actually be nice
and usable which means tracking whether
we're selecting something or not because
we need to do that and then actually
providing these some way to edit these
in a way that is usable right something
right we got to have something there and
I'm not sure what that what that's going
to be
I guess I would say that I guess I would
say that the most pressing concerns are
we'll start with selection we'll put
that in there
and then we'll go to putting this in a
window and placing it somewhere on the
screen that's not right here because
then it's pretty usable for the creation
and deletion and then we'll just work on
getting these interactive so some way of
adding those those are all the things I
think that I have to happen and then
we'd be done with the UI the final step
is then implanting the save features so
that when we save it writes it back two
different things right I think that's
really all we need to do all we need to
do it's fair bit of work but you know
all right so I think that's good so
moving forward I want to do something
here we say all right you know looking
at this we've got this active asset
index so we've already sort of set
ourselves up for success quote-unquote
because what we what we do have here is
just that the highlight right I mean you
can see here the highlight asset index
in any particular case is it's set to
the active one already and that's the
one that we edit so really in here where
we do should hit test and we come back
with one of these things and you know
whatever else that's really the place
where we can we can control when we set
these things so inside the hip test here
what we want to do is say don't don't do
this operation like this is not what we
wanted to do if we were in the middle of
actually editing something so what we
want to do here is say something like
that something like that and robably we
want to wait for mass down so in here I
think I'm not really sure what I want to
say about this it's a little squeaky
let's let's um think about this a little
bit more broadly so inside handmade hero
the main loop right here you can see us
doing our hip test and then we end the
hit test here and then we do our UI
stuff I think what we want in this case
right is we want to be able to defer any
activities till later so I think what we
want to do is say okay when we get this
hit test back don't take any action let
the action get taken later on so in the
code that actually is processing the UI
will deal with it there so in here when
we get the hip test back and that hip
test is just pointing to this right so
we have we don't need this piece of
information at all really so honestly
this is just it doesn't matter I don't
think so we can just get rid of that I
think
and so I think the right solution is
just put that there when we actually
have the the code to do stuff for editor
interactions what we'll do here is say
look when we are done with all this
stuff if we were gonna click on things
right so we come through here and we say
you know all right we're doing we're
doing our clicks if there was nothing to
interact with you know we can we can
look for this stuff here if when the
mouse button goes down we look for an
interaction and there isn't an
interaction to use then we can do the
asset pick right so meaning another way
of saying it is the interaction is the
asset pick interaction would be another
way of saying that so you know we could
even make it so that here what we say is
look if if the next hot interaction was
not said anything set it to something
that will do that pick I guess it's how
I would say it so I'm just integrating
these two things together in what
becomes a fairly clean way I think so
you know if the UI next hot interaction
isn't isn't a thing then what I could
say is well alright if you know what
what the if what we were going to do I
guess it's just I could even just set it
blindly to be the hot you know pick pick
the hot item right so to do this thing
right so then we would just have a thing
that's like case W I pick entity right
or you know pick asset and it just does
this and instead of getting up off of
that it's going to get it off of the
editors hot group
like so and so we just need to make this
thing be what you would do on Mouse down
so if you you know if you were gonna
pick one of these you would just it
would just do it and I guess more
correctly speaking it would be on Mouse
up so the mouse goes down and my mouse
up you picked it right I think that's
all we really need don't quote me on
that but I think that's really what
we're talking about here so in this case
we would just say alright you know we've
gots WI has another function here which
is wouldn't I call that pick asset and
so I just want an interaction that is
that interaction you know and I'm saying
so I just say all right next tide
interaction type equals pick the asset
that's all we really needed to do and
now I think that gets integrated in I
think don't quote me on this because
that may not actually be true and also I
don't know how we have what do we have
currently for checking these things but
I guess we don't have one of those
things so I'll just put one there
so that should allow these systems to
merge in a nice clean way so I want what
is the question here oh so I don't have
to like have them to go she ate with
each other they'll all just go through
the same system which i think is much
better right
and that way negotiation about who's
picking what and when just kind of all
goes in in a nice sort of clean and
obvious way so when I'm in this this
mode here you know I I pick stuff and it
won't change right and furthermore any
time I'm over these things
I'm not picking right at least that's
what should be happening I would argue
so if I'm over here right I shouldn't
actually be able to change the selection
the highlight part is sort of a separate
issue but we'll see so for example if I
was gonna do this it would click on
another one when I clicked on used it
shouldn't do anything and it doesn't
right I now need some way of getting out
of that interaction and yeah you know
like I don't know if the Escape key
maybe is the most same thing there or if
just clicking on anything else should do
it it's probably fine
probably fine as it is yeah um so anyway
let me just kind of play around that a
little bit more so when I'm actually
picking these things what I probably
want to do here also is kind of invert
the way that that is is happening so in
terms of the highlight the way that the
highlights going there so we've got the
WI you see highlight here there we go
that's not what I want it I wanted in
game editor I want this so when we're
doing this highlight here I don't know
exactly how I want that to go
so I think we want to be a little more
specific about which things are in the
picking set here so when we have these
dev IDs that are getting pushed on here
if I look at the editors test stuff
right we've got sort of the hit test
that happens here and we've got these
asset groups I do think we may want to
push on also some kind of an ID so that
they can be used for highlighting more
because otherwise it's just a really
kind of squirrely like you know like
this so that when those things are
getting pushed on and you push the asset
key and the you know and that stuff
I think this wants to take an ID that
can be used to control that I just think
we're gonna need that and so when people
call add hit they should pass a
something we can use to identify that
again and that's not so hard right
because if you think about what an enemy
has in it it already has an ID that is
used to identify it uniquely right it's
it's got a 32-bit value right that can
be used there and so when we are doing
the hit testing and we're gonna put an
ID on there I think it should be fairly
straightforward to just use that that ID
and go from there that's my argument so
I think we should be able to do
something like you know
you know something like this and what we
need is some one of these that works on
on you thirty twos basically right we've
like the Peace Index as well so I think
what I want to do from it's something
like this where we say like okay you
know here we've got one of those and
it'll use the value and the Peace Index
in this case to create the dev ID and in
the way that we would do this is say
that if we're doing hit testing you know
we'll create one of those things right
and I don't really want to be creating
it all the time so it would probably be
better if we place it in here so that's
a little unfortunate and we'll have to
see what we want to do about that but in
this case we're we're checking like the
bitmap buying stuff we would no longer
do this at all
instead what we would probably do is say
well ok if the dev ID and the hit test
highlight ID you know if these are equal
then draw the thing that seems more
likely I feel like that's kind of okay
and this here
is basically the same thing so it's just
another way of doing this code where we
say alright like build me some unique
thing out of this and so in order to
reinterpret that I think we have a we
actually have a ummm sort of like caster
thing here like for for pointers yeah so
in this case you know we've got a way of
converting these things and
unfortunately we can't really take to
you thirty twos and combine them into a
pointer if we're not on 64-bit right so
that's a little Squinkie
that's a little Squinkie and I'm not
sure what we want to do about that I
don't really want to support 32-bit
platform super much but you know who
knows if we have to for some reason so
since there's not a lot of places where
we would really need to use that it's
kind of hard to say whether it makes
sense one way or the other to required
or not you know what I mean for now I'm
gonna say we're now I'm gonna say we
kind of want to do yeah like I'm really
conflicted about this because I don't
really feel like we need to do much
there well you know what so here's one
thing we could do we could do something
like this and I think this would be
reasonable right so if I said instead
well you know really for the dev IDs
maybe we don't do it like this maybe we
do it instead more like this where we
say like okay so there's you know
actually like this right then it would
be like okay even on a 32-bit system we
actually have 64 bits there so you're
always allowed to do SiC up to 64 bits
worth of ridiculousness in terms of
creating these debug IDs right which is
what I want you know I want to be able
to do arbitrary ridiculousness there I
don't want to really be super
constrained by that stuff and so then
that maybe makes a little more sense
because then what I can do is say all
right when we're looking at these things
like this like you know are equal
whatever we can just look at the 64-bit
version of it and know that any other
types that we're in the mix will just
work right I think that seems reasonable
actually that seems like a reasonable
compromise because then we can still do
shenanigans but the shenanigans will
work on 32-bit as necessary because
these are not things that get used in
the gameplay part of things are only
used in like dev mode stuff so I don't
really care if they're inefficient I
just want them to but I don't
necessarily want to preclude them from
ever working so there's that right so I
think that might be a better way to go
if that makes sense and so that seems
good to me
furthermore yes so I think also another
thing I might do there is say well you
get two of these if you want because you
could fit two of them in there right and
so then what I could do is say okay good
now when I want to do this like and say
you know value zero you three two zero
equals a B and then the void is this so
then that lets me create kind of a more
explicit thing there you know that feels
a bit better so when we create one of
these what's the problem there partner
that's the problem
all right all right so that seems good
and then what I want to do is I want to
change that code in the in-game editor
that was sort of saying there was this
high light asset index that we're not
going to have that we're just gonna have
like high light ID and highlight asset
index is not a thing and what I would
then do is say well when we do this if
we're doing an edit mode asset if I want
to do a highlight asset index here what
I can do is say well we've got an active
asset index that's what we're heading
but we can also set a dev ID that's like
what we want to highlight and I'll just
copy that in and we could set that
whenever we really want to you know I
think that's better and that way when we
pick one of these things we can you know
take them both
seems better to me or at least you know
slightly more reasonable so I think
that's good so then in these when we
were doing things before all of this
should still work anything that was
pointer based you'll you know it just
you just make them out of void and that
just works and then in here what we were
doing when we were trying to get ID
values out of this again you 32 from
pointer we really didn't need to do it
that way we can just use the Union now
so in here we do you three for pointer
and we ask for this value and we do a
shift down by two I don't really know
that what the you 32 from pointer part
really was doing there little on a
second let me make sure yes it was cast
on you through two anyway so really what
we can do here is just not do that and
instead just take the bottom you 32
right and and that gets us out of the
casting business there entirely and just
lets the Union do to work in that case
which seems reasonable right all right
so now we want to do is figure out some
way to get this high light stuff working
a little bit better the first thing we
need to do there on the second is inside
the entity code so we only want to do a
push volume outline when we find that
these IDs are equal right and so in
order to do that we need to get them
from the NV ID and the piece index that
should be unique and then we need to
push that on when we hit which we do and
really we don't want this anymore
the highlight color thing is not really
a thing so really I think we just want
that to be this and so now we just have
to make sure that dev ID part works
actually correctly and then we can go
from there so highlight ID yeah what's
happening with active asset index it
should only happen there yeah which it
does alright so now let's take a look at
what's going on and we'll try to clean
that up a bit and figure out what what's
going on there so if I click on things
so I don't get it why is why am I
getting everyone highlighting there that
doesn't really make any sense because
we're explicitly comparing just only one
set of debug ideas there so we must be
building those debug ideas poorly like
like we're doing something weird there
right like something something really
strange is happening so for some reason
for some reason that that ID set is
being as being Squinkie and I'm not sure
why oh well that would do it you got to
build the ID properly if you want to
actually have it work it's shocking I
know
alright so now we have a more
traditional kind of selection based
thing here right
if I clicked outside in there wasn't one
we should probably clear it so like we
probably needed another way to clear
that as well but if the mouse went up
and there wasn't anything here so so
nobody was actually you know nobody was
picked by the hit test then we probably
just want this to be cleared right I
mean that's what we actually want to
have happen I can't remember I thought
there was an actual thing like that well
no there isn't it's just for
interactions I guess but you know we
want that where we just clear it out
right and similarly the asset index
would be cleared as well that should
give me some some sense of like common
editor feel to this right and it does
now right so I click on these you know
and if I click off they're done it also
gives me a fair bit of fidelity about
the selection so you can see here like
you see how it intercepted and it didn't
reap ick so it integrates these two
systems really nicely too so they're
just totally unified and don't step by
each other's toes which is really nice
as well I will say I'm not sure what's
going on there that looks like a picking
error of some a different kind like I
don't know why I can't really pick that
see I'm having trouble picking that
particular entity
and so I don't know if we maybe have
some bugs in how we're picking or
something
it just feels like the sort okay oh yeah
so it feels like the sort is not working
properly and it may well not be we
should probably go take a look and see
if we're doing that that sort
computation correctly so when we do Ray
intersects box what are we doing here
are we passing so we are passing the tea
hit it it just doesn't look for whatever
reason doesn't it doesn't feel like it's
really actually taking the close side it
looks like it's taking Mik like the far
side or something
and I'm not really sure what's going on
there
so it's doing the T step to get to each
axis separately it's like how far do I
have to go in access right I have to go
and why am I fired I have to go and Z
and just taken whichever one gets there
fastest
right
so I feel like that should be giving us
a point that point but I'm just not
seeing it it doesn't feel to me like
that's working properly and you know we
are drawing that box in theory and it
sure feels like it's working
and interestingly enough it sort of
seems almost like a little steep driven
like correct me if I'm wrong but like
let's say I click on this one and then I
go and I keep clicking and I don't
change over until I get to this one
right but if I'm on this one and I start
clicking I don't change until I get all
the way there so it's almost like what I
have selected actually has an effect on
whether or not I can select the other
one which seems busted so that may be
part of just the UI code so let's try
this that may just be that the editor
hit this stuff is wrong I mean it may be
that this code was borked there so when
I come through here and I'm looking for
mouse up
I mean what I could do is just say look
why don't we just set that to like
whatever and just verify like just see
if it's working
and it's sort of isn't sort of isn't
right
so it's just really weird like I don't
know what's determining when it works
and when it doesn't work
that's frustrating
we definitely set the highlight a tee
every time we go to do a head test we
don't really
yeah we don't really I mean what if I
set it somewhere else is there something
to do with that particular thing this
has just happens every time now
you see how weirdly sticky that becomes
such a super bizarre
so I'm gonna need some debugging I mean
cuz I don't have any theory about that
but it looks like it really doesn't have
much to do with this it looks like we've
just got some more like a more deeply
rooted bug there that is not really so
related to how or when that gets updated
so it's it's sort of like this it's
somehow dependent on that in a weird way
like I don't know I guess we could also
draw that picking rake and you know we
were drawing the picking ray back at the
beginning something like that we could
try to draw it to make sure that it's
still getting updated right like the
clip space Mouse pee part of things I
mean could be getting stuck and not
updating or something I'm not sure why
you know that would happen but um I
don't have a lot of ideas here we're
copying it every time you know so again
not really sure why would we be getting
an odd result there
so one more thing let me just try one
more thing because there is sort of
another way this could be failing I
guess and let me just try to eliminate
that first and that is in here where we
do the Equality testing let's actually
just do it here so instead of doing this
I'm gonna go ahead and just not ever
highlight what it tells us to highlight
and instead I'm just gonna highlight
what we hit so anytime we hit something
we're gonna highlight that and I'm just
gonna see if that ever gets stuck just
to make sure that we're at least
considering the set of objects we should
be considering and that that seems
pretty tight to me so I could believe
that this had something to do with like
our sort routine being screwed up or
something right like because this always
seems perfect like I'm not getting any
like that just seems rock-solid
right
so I feel like we're pretty clean on
that so the question would be maybe like
is the hit system is the when we're
actually putting these things in is that
actually what's causing the problem
right this could be the dev ID it could
be us right we we don't really know
who's who's you know at fault here so
let me go ahead and and do this even
more directly we'll drill them at the
same time so now we can see what our
hits were and then who we actually were
told to highlight will be done
separately right
so that's kind of nuts right like here
it's like we're getting we're being told
to highlight okay no that's fine so
we're seeing that those are all the
possible hits and we're just being told
to highlight that one so that's fine but
that's not right so now we really aren't
probably being told to that let me let
me change the width of these so that we
can also see more specifically what's
going on there so we'll make this one be
a little bit more will make one be wide
and one be not wide hopefully that makes
it easier to say hopefully so you can
see like a thin little yellow line so
they're like that's not even in the hit
list but it's the thing that we're being
told to to highlight so it's definitely
the UI systems fault that this is
getting screwed up right somehow so I
probably just messed up the it's
probably just that sort routine when I
went in there and added the dev IDs I
probably just screwed it up or something
but so that's good so we know it's not
that so we know that basically our
problem is we we screwed up the the hit
testing here so let's go ahead and look
at that real quickly before the streams
over and hopefully that's our only real
dumb maneuver yeah okay well that was
easy
once you know where the problem is it's
not so hard to fix it so now I think
we're totally good yeah so all I need to
do now is just undo the change I did
before
that made us always update the asset so
really we just need that and now now
I shouldn't be having those same
problems that I was having before now
we're good
okay um there's probably more stuff we
want to do there but I think that's it
for today we will or at least this
stream so I think what we will do here
is just leave it at that
and what I want to do is come through
and now start working on this part of
the UI because I think we're pretty
clean here now on all of this stuff we
have undo redo revert we can click on
things we can select objects it's pretty
reasonable now so I think all we really
need to do is like box that I put in the
corner make these little buttons work
and then I think we're off to the races
we can get back to just the basic hij
stuff we wanted to do like saving to and
from a text file and stuff like that let
me go ahead and go to a brief Q&amp;A here
so we can't see if anyone has any
questions on what we did
any questions
how long do you think it would take to
get to this level and the product if
you're working on it eight hours a day
um well it's hard to say but obviously
this you know you could just take the
amount of time divide it by eight and
that's the maximum because you knew I
you know I did do it in that number of
hours so I don't know how many it is
it's probably like eight hundred so
eight hours a day that be a hundred days
so it would be if you assume like a
five-day workweek probably 25 weeks does
that make sense
so not not very long I mean 25 it's like
half a year six six months so pretty
pretty brief you got to figure you'd
probably get a pretty big bonus not
having to wait like multiple days in
between our along streams or stuff for
two hour-long streams so I don't know I
mean I would think that would help but
you know you never know maybe it doesn't
plus you can get rid of like there's
tons of stuff in there I'm just
explaining things and not actually doing
any programming I'm just trying to
explain something on a whiteboard or
whatever so you know that goes away so I
would I would think it'd be less than 25
weeks probably
see voucher is there a reason for making
two lists for undo redo rather than one
I didn't I didn't have a reason I just
did them as two stacks because I thought
that would be them clearest in the code
and it's pretty free to do so like you
don't really cost you anything to do
that so I thought that would be clear
but you certainly can implement them
with only one so I didn't I mean I
didn't think about it too hard I don't
think there's a reason to prefer one of
the over the other I think it would just
be whichever one you prefer
probably
I guess all I can really say is I can't
think of a strong reason to prefer
either so I just did the one that I kind
of you know the one that made me feel
more comfortable when I was typing it in
but you know I I didn't have a strong
reason for that and I can't and I can't
think of a strong reason now either big
engine support multiple render paths d
3d opengl but why do these engines don't
use only open jules 233 that's cuz open
gels are very well supported by candy 3
on windows d 3d runs much better it's a
lot less bugs especially on certain
drivers you know like maybe nvidia has
very good OpenGL support but you know
AMD and intel typically don't depending
on the day depending on the year so you
know OpenGL would have been great if
everyone had bought into it and it had
been meticulously maintained it wasn't
it's kind of a sprawling mess right now
and while there is a subset of OpenGL
that if you just consider just that to
be OpenGL that would have been a great
API I kind of wish they had done that I
wish they had said ok OpenGL 5.0 is this
subset and that's all we're doing then I
don't think you would have needed Vulcan
or any of this other stuff you could
just been like AZ do open jail that's
what we're doing that's open till 5:00
and off we go right they didn't do that
unfortunately so it's still a giant
sprawling mess and that's just how it is
so on Windows you pretty much want us to
ship d3d
you know that's what you want to ship if
you're shipping something else you're
probably in danger of hitting a lot of
extra core driver bugs that you didn't
need to ship and so most graphics you
know backends use it by default if you
boot up an engine like you know like
unity or something that supports both
OpenGL and D 3d on Windows which I'm
pretty sure they do they're gonna
default to be 3d because there's just
less bugs and that's what you care about
you know when you're shipping a PC game
you care about less bug reports you know
less users who are upset because they
can't run your game is what you want and
and that's not you know that's not open
jail which parts of CPU do you use a CBP
rather do use I use operator overloading
for math operations and I use function
name overloading just in general other
than that I almost don't use anything
there may be some places like for timer
code that we use constructor destructor
pairs to make sure that you can open
something at the beginning of a block
and automatically closed at the end of
the block that's about the only place we
use constructor destructor so we could
just make it pretty easily get rid of
that so I think mostly what we use is is
the operator and function over function
name overloading we don't really use
anything else
follow-up question regarding a bejeweled
can you name some of the stuff of a
subset they should have marked as open
jewelry 5 yet look basically a-z do like
env command list a Z do you know if you
took a game that was using exclusively a
Z do and env command list and you said
what is that that is pretty much what
should have been b5 and they should have
been like everything else is deprecated
you can't use it right so if you oh if
you initialize OpenGL v5 you could only
use a CV oh that's it and if the car
doesn't support it it doesn't support
OpenGL b5 so you can put the sticker on
the box right
do you think Vulcan would not have this
type of problem with bugs because it's
more low-level no I mean low level
versus high level really isn't the
source of bugs the proliferation of
configuration possibilities usually is
what leads to bugs and so to the extent
that Vulcan may have limited the number
of configuration options it can probably
have less bugs in open jail but you know
I'm sure Vulcan has tons of bugs already
I mean the other way to say it is like
testing is really the thing that makes
things not have bugs and Vulcan is not
particularly testable I wouldn't say in
a way in any way that's more than other
things are testable I think that to the
extent that Vulcan was sort of designed
with a particular snapshot of hardware
in mind it will probably become
increasingly buggy over time would be my
suspicion so as graphics cards no longer
need you to do some of the things that
Vulcan requires you to do those things
will become emulated effectively inside
the driver layer it's actually already
going on with a number of things in
Vulcan even today those things will
become bug year in bug year because you
know they are now implementing the
driver to try to emulate behavior that
actually wasn't required it doesn't
exist anymore and then you just lead to
drivers having to have accurate
emulators which you know may or may not
be the case and the degree to which the
driver team is able to robustly test
those set of configurations you know is
implicated as well you know and I really
know how to how to say it any more than
that as for switching 2d 3d before
shipping the game I don't know if we
will or not we're in the position where
we may not really be pushing the
graphics hard enough to care like we may
not have enough craziness in our
graphics layer to need to switch to
something like D 3d to have better bug
levels like you know the degree to which
you exercise the GPU and its API largely
determine the degree to which you need
to worry about those those bugs and with
handmade hero we are I mean yeah we're a
little more complicated than a typical
2d game that's true we're certainly
doing more than that but the question is
are we doing enough more and would we be
able to just kind of at when we go clean
up our OpenGL code in the end or
okay this is all we're doing we're done
you know the game runs as we want it to
run and we have no more features that
we're trying to add in 3d when we clean
that up and look at it it is it likely
you know like if we do like a test run
on with people trying the hardware are
we finding a lot of bugs or or are we
just not and if the answer is we're not
then it's probably just not worth it
right because if it's working it's
working right however for finding that
we are kind of hitting OpenGL nonsense
and like it's not running on Intel
hardware for various reasons and we
gotta go through you know then you might
be like yeah I just switched to d3 d12 I
mean not eleven right because that works
pretty much everywhere that we would
care about
can you program can you program shaders
and assembly on Vulcan or any other
graphics API you you can't invoke in so
I guess here's what I'd say let me try
to explain the situation with that I got
to say that I am not enough of a grass
burger to know the answer the second
part of your question which is are there
any graphics api's that lets you program
in assembly language because that's a
very difficult question to answer and i
think you have to be a graphics expert
who's keeps up to date with all of the
GPU stuff to really know the answer to
that question what I can tell you is
there is a assembly ish language that
direct3d exposes and you can program in
that so if you want to you can use a
assembly like language the problem is
it's not necessarily related to the
assembly language of the actual GPU and
for good reason Nvidia and AMD have
different assembly languages and so you
can't really write a single assembly
language that would work on both in a
complete sense right not to mention the
fact that different cards may have
different instruction sets even from the
same vendor Vulcan I don't recall
defining an assembly language of any
kind so I think Vulcan is just a
straight-up no they define a thing
called SPI RV which is basically like a
intermediate representation so it's not
really an assembly language it's more
like LLVM IR like it's like a single
static assignment form kind of a thing
right if you know what that is it's it's
more like that it's more like here's an
intermediate representation that's not
assembly language because we don't know
what the actual machine code is we're
targeting until we run the
cuz we need to see what grabs card we're
on right so we don't really know so
instead we're gonna ship the IR that you
would probably start with to assemble to
like generate the code on the back end
so you know they've got that on Vulcan
and you could certainly choose to
program to that directly if you wanted
to because as far as I know they don't
try to prevent you from doing that
the specification for SBIR v is
available you can write your own
assembler that would output to it there
may just be assemblers already that
output to it I don't know because I've
never looked for one but I would assume
someone's done that it wouldn't be hard
right creator Lord doesn't that same
problem ApS growing old and unsuitable
for current graphic arts also applied to
X 12 it doesn't it doesn't so the thing
to remember is the thing that makes
things not have bugs is the testing as I
said before so the thing you have to
remember with Vulcan is nobody's testing
it right like Microsoft does not care at
all if Vulcan runs on Windows as far as
I know right like it does not matter to
them because they're like look we
provided you with DX 12 that's the thing
we're gonna test that's the thing that
Windows runs on that's the thing that
all of our stuff is using so when we do
compliance testing to figure out whether
dx12 is properly working on this range
of desktops in our testing lab that's
what we're testing we do not fire up
Vulcan and we don't care if it runs
right that would be my assumption about
what's generally going on now I don't
know maybe they're like we love Vulcan
and we run Vulcan all the time and we
actually don't care if TX 12 runs and so
we test Vulcan all the time I doubt
that's what they do
but you know there you go so yeah I
wouldn't say that the API changes at all
meaning I don't think dx12 is somehow
better suited than Vulcan to be bug free
and to that matter OpenGL is the same
way I don't think they're necessarily
better or worse suited right
it's more what I was trying to say in
the previous part was that they're not
better suited for it right so Vulcans
not better suited than anything else and
it will have bugs just like everything
else does because as it goes forward it
will atrophy so what you really want to
do and the reason that I said
specifically I and I don't know that I
said this on this episode I've said it
before the reason I don't think Vulcan
is very interesting unless you're an
Android programmer is because Apple is
testing metal and that's what they care
about if it runs Windows is testing DX
12 and 11 and that's what they care if
it runs anything else you use you're
just stepping on the third rail right
you're basically saying like look I know
that the platform vendor for this
platform isn't keeping this thing
running I know that they are not making
sure it works so I'm just rolling the
dice and hoping that Intel cares enough
to test Vulcan on their latest chips or
old chips to make sure they run ok with
it right so what's the point right you
don't it don't matter you know what you
need is reliability out of these api's
and using an API that is strictly
available on a vendor whim could be
useful but the only time I would really
say it's worth stepping on that third
rail there is if it was a really good
API and Vulcans a crap API it's not good
right it's very poorly designed so
you're just inviting a world of hurt by
using it there's there's no point to it
right you're just waiting for the other
shoe to drop while simultaneously doing
a tremendous amount of work to use an
API that wasn't well designed so if
you're going to already go through the
trouble of using ap is that aren't good
why not just use the two AP eyes that
aren't good that the that the actual
platform holders are guaranteeing will
work at least the extent that they can
right that's just basic you know herd
mentality strengthen numbers I'm gonna
cut right it's like just
use the thing that's getting tested by
your platform vendor because you know it
works right because you know it works
and and these other things who know I I
don't even know how long Volk and I'll
be around
you know it'll probably end up just like
OpenGL something that kind of works most
the time if you want to use it you can
its unwieldy and doesn't particularly
match anything particularly well anymore
right it's gonna be just like that like
Vulcan is just OpenGL v that they just
rewrote everything and said here's
another here's another one and we have
no coherent story about why this is
better it's not a better API it's not
more convenient to use it's not
guaranteed to be better to map to
Hardware forever and ever more anything
right it's not tested by platform
vendors other than Android probably in
the future I'm guessing so we can't
guarantee that for you oh and also by
the way we don't really have any
commitment to anything else about it
like we don't have a giant testing lab
guarantee you know that certifies these
things or ain't like like none of that's
true right so you're just basically
saying I'm using it because I like the
name you know I like being associated
with with a curing process for rubber I
don't know right
in him a hero there I saw this concept
of begin render n render I believe it is
called which reminds me of a fixed
function open Jill Jill begin Jill and
can you say how these functions and HH
roughly work or what is the constant
find it yeah they're not really similar
to the open GL ones at all what they are
used for is bracketing what has to
happen in the render because our
renderer does some things that need to
repeat sequences of events and also know
when a frame is done and stuff like that
so they're really just a way of
bracketing two so that the renderer
knows what isn't what's inside a
particular frame right because it needs
to do work with that
lo4 D says shouldn't these graphics API
is be made by GPU vendors or can they
not do that um I would vastly prefer it
if that's the route they had taken
meaning if Intel AMD and NVIDIA had just
released raw api's to their cards they
said these are the things that we
support I would love that that would
have way better unfortunately that's not
what happens what happens instead is
each platform vendor defines her own API
so Apple to find their own that's metal
Microsoft to find their own which is
direct3d and then vendors instead of
finding their own all get together and
define multiple of their own so now they
get together as a consortium with
Microsoft and apples feedback by the way
to all define Vulcan and all define
OpenGL which basically leads to a Vulcan
and OpenGL that are good for nobody
right because they're just this giant
mush of stuff that's not really under
anyone's really coherent
well-thought-out plan and without any
hardware target because everyone's
hardware has to be targeted it's got to
be maximally inclusive in terms of what
it supports because of that which means
that you end up in the lowest common
denominator denominator kind of
situation right so it's just it's just
really it ain't great right I'm sorry uh
I don't understand the question part I
mean current API is I know dx9 supports
it up to three point X or four point no
I'm not sure what you're referring to
case of aeschylus is what you expected
to learn from this series other than how
to make a game um actually I wouldn't
necessarily say that what I expect to
learn for the series is how to make a
game there's a lot of ways you can make
a game and you know you could you could
download an engine and use that or like
game maker or something right or RPG
maker so making a game is like a
different thing what I expect people to
learn from this series is sort of the
basics of like direct programming so
like learning how to make actual code
that does engine style or low-level
style features themselves so knowing how
to directly do a lot of stuff like
you know creating their own threads and
their own work queues and dispatching
work to those queues and programming
with Cindy and like all that sort of
stuff that you would never encounter if
you were just using someone else's
engine or you know programming at a
higher level or in JavaScript or
something like this right
so that's what I focus on in this series
not how to make a game per se because
making game is a broader topic and
there's a lot more things you might want
to think about if your only concern is
that you're trying to make a specific
game not you're trying to learn how to
be an engine program or a low-level
programmer right do I think the next
generation of consoles will adopt
retracing extensions I really don't know
it might be a little early for the next
generation of consoles remember we
haven't even really determined that the
current crop of GPUs that just came out
can really do ray tracing all that well
to begin with let's to see how that goes
it's it's gonna be an ongoing process
you know Nvidia might take a couple
years to really give us a card where the
ray tracing is really obviously great
so consoles probably aren't gonna get
there in the next generation because
remember that could be like next year
right it's been a while since the PS 5
Xbox one sort of style consoles came out
so expecting the next generation which
could be really soon depending on when I
don't know when platform vendors are
gonna choose to pull that trigger but
that could be pretty soon I don't think
it's safe to say that rate racing will
be ready by then the next next meaning
the PlayStation 6 or something that
sounds likely cuz five years from now
six years from now whatever that might
be that's given you know Nvidia and
probably AMD as well a lot of time to
like bolt on tons of ray-tracing power
into these chips and get it working well
and prove that it's useful and then
that's probably a more more reasonable
time for it why are most Triple A games
still running on dx11 is dx12 too new
and that well supported it's probably 6
or 6/1
dozen the other they probably don't want
to be locked in Windows 10 and I don't
think dx12 goes back to Windows 7 which
is still a platform they need to support
I suspect that's most of it
the other part of it maybe they just
don't really need the stuff from dx12
dx11 is pretty good and it's not clear
that you really need a lot from dx12 all
that much really so it's probably just
that that trade-off once it's clear that
everyone has a machine that can run dx12
that's probably more of a attractive
option right what would make a graphic
api great a grabs an api is great if it
contains a well thought-out model for
articulating from the game to the
graphics card precisely those things
that the game is trying to do and no
more your summative 5 5 5 how often do
you read other people's code bases
Chevie recommendations are good examples
of well Kobey's it's learned from these
days not too often I don't have a lot of
the recommendations but I would say the
in code bases are probably good ones to
look look at they have released a number
of them and those are you know we're
groundbreaking engines that you can go
read the source code so you know that
how they chose to do things was if
nothing else revolutionary in a sense
meaning you could say whatever else you
want to say about any of its engine code
they were far ahead of everyone else at
the time more or less so they were
programming in ways that were great by
definition whether you think their code
is good or not there was really
irrelevant the results speak for
themselves
so those would be good to look at just
in general I would suspect to understand
how that happened because it was very
remarkable but it did doom and quake
were both very very impressive things
technological artifacts for their time
was opengl 2.1 a great API mmm
probably not is there a good API for GUI
application of Windows that you would
suggest I don't know I've never really
used any of them modern ones I can tell
you QT is terrible so there's a negative
recommendation like don't ever use that
I do know that some people like I am GUI
I have a dear I am GUI I haven't used it
myself
but you know that's one to look at maybe
yeah so there you go all right I'm gonna
wrap it up we are done with questions
all right thank you very for joining me
for those sort of handmade hero sort of
pleasure coding with us always if you
would like to follow the series you can
always peer to the game on handmade hero
org it comes with a source code so you
can follow along with what we're doing I
will be back here at some undisclosed
point in the future because we're doing
surprise streams for Krampus loft this
week and probably next week too so I
will see you sometime soon check the
Twitter feed the handmade here on
Twitter feed or just this watch page for
more information thanks Jamie
I'll catch everyone next time