hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream you know what I forgot
someone asked a question or the pre
stream and i forgot to close down the
windows so I apologize for that uh we
are finishing up some code changes that
we made we did the work yesterday
actually of finishing the concept of
brain code which is like essentially a
sort of self-organizing controllers for
our entities and we just need to kind of
finish porting some old code into that
structure and then we kind of need to
play with it some more and see if it
really does what we want because you
know we have one use case which is the
hero and we need to kind of build some
more use cases to see if it holds up
because you know we just we just don't
really know we're in that stage where
we're trying to sort of make sure we've
got a solid entity system so we're kind
of doing passes over it to sort of get
it into a state where we believe that
most of the things that we want to do
are well accounted for so yeah today is
day 2 89 if you are interested in flying
along at home unpacked a 288 source code
into a directory and that's what I'm
starting with now I'm going to go ahead
and load up our handmade project
handmade project I don't know what that
was supposed to be um let me see here
there we go
share adjustment as well so all right
here is our handmade project and we got
our brains actually working which is
kind of cool so we know that everything
was correct what we didn't do is finish
porting the hop controller but for
example the facing direction and stuff
like that is set properly now by the
brain and it sets it for both things
which is kind of cool and so now we
can't have to do is go through there and
now that we know that the structure of
the brain is as it is we need to start
cleaning out that code so that
everything else flows naturally from it
and the stuff that should be in the
brain is in the brain and the stuff that
shouldn't be in the brain is not on the
brain right which is kind of a good rule
of thumb for regular brains one might
argue so anyway let's take a look at
handmade world mode dot CPP ok so in
handmade world mode CPP we have we have
essentially three parts to this code and
we probably you know it stands to reason
that we might want to make these a
little more isolated as well so for
example we could pull out all the brains
into their own file so they're easier
for us to know where brains are and
similarly we could pull out you know
rendering or whatever that's our stuff
so we may want to start kind of pulling
these out so it's a little easier to see
and like a lot of people ask me we get
this question over and over how do I
decide when to make new files it's
literally just when I for visibility
like when I want to see two things at
once that kind of indicates to me that I
want them in separate files purely an
artifact of the way everything has to
happen has nothing to do with the
architecture of the game at all and
really just isn't very important but
that's you know it's it's entirely
personal preference and and you
shouldn't feel pressured to split files
in any particular way I would be very
suspicious of somebody who told you that
there is a right way in
wrong way to divide up your code into
files because that just kind of isn't
true so anyway I'm going to go ahead and
make a new file here let's see I'm going
to make a new file for handmade brain
brains brain or brains brains brains
let's call it brain so I'm going to make
those and then I'm going to go ahead and
and open those up so oops code and made
brain alright and let me go ahead and
stick the little header in here case
people are using source code control and
want it labeled which I often do so okay
we go ok so now I've got my two brain
files and what I need to do now is I
need to start pulling some stuff out
into them right and so I have my entity
eh I could certainly put the brain stuff
in here probably without really causing
too much of a problem because the brain
stuff doesn't really rely so much on
anything else it's pretty isolated for
the most part and so I can sort of just
grab these and put them out here and say
here's what a brain is and really all it
needs to know is that there is such a
thing as an entity and you might point
to that entity but I don't know that we
really need anything else there so if i
go ahead and compile that what does this
thing oh let's see here yeah so i just
need to now go in and add that those
files in so that they can be so that
they can be accessed by the rest of the
code so handmade entity why isn't it
here oh it's here okay well that's fine
and made brain-dead H so we'll go ahead
and build that and then we also need
handmade brain dot CPP to be included
oops
so that's that's all there is to that
and now I can start pulling out brain
code into its own section so if i take
the world node code which is what we had
before and I pull it out into the brain
section what I should be able to do is
just kind of jump down to where that's
actually happening here let's see run
all brains right so in here where we've
got this sort of brain execution layer
what I should be able to do is just take
this switch statement out and I should
be able to dump the switch statement
just as a whole I think directly into
this file right so I should be able to
do a thing where this is just like an
execute brain and I don't know if the
compiler will actually in line this but
I hope it does because it's only ever
going to called in one place this is I'm
moving this out into file just so I can
see it more easily at the same time that
I look at the individual entity update
pieces of information right so this is
going to take a brain it probably also
needs a few other things as you can see
it needs like potentially access to the
input controllers it's going to need
access to the sim region as well so
there's some stuff in here that I also
need to do like sim region and then I
can go ahead and and make this go there
we go so we'll see what else it needs
i'm just we're now going to say execute
brain brain there's my sim region when I
build this you can see we need the game
state and it looks like mostly mostly
just those it's like the game states and
the controllers and I don't think I
don't think we really need much else so
we're also going to need it looks like
we need a DT so we need a DP value like
how much we're going to update by we
need that game state
and I don't know what we actually need
for I guess we just need the game input
and we could do something here where we
try to be a little clever and we
actually only do that input part if we
know it's one of the ones that takes
input I don't really care about that so
I'm not going to bother with that point
being once we've got that we can go back
to World mode and set that correctly so
here is X cube brain and i'm just going
to pass it the stuff that we know it
needs there we go so heroes exists is an
undeclared identifier which is true it
is an undeclared identifier the question
here is how we want to deal with that
and I've never been particularly good or
I shouldn't say feel good I know
perfectly happy with the way that code
has been working it's kind of janky and
what I would rather do is instead of the
heroes existing I'd rather have it so
that we have a notion a strong notion of
the world mode having been exited so I
think what I'd rather do is say down
here you know we get to throw to the end
of this situation and you can see here
we have a not heroes exist I think what
I would do is say something more like if
world mode exit or something like that
then we would do play title screen and
overwrite it so yeah I don't know
exactly what we want to do with that yet
but you know you get the idea so in here
we've got the play title screen a switch
essentially let me see what that's
actually going here exit seems
reasonable and we could do exit to title
just so it's clearer what it actually
means why is that it's not saving my
position in that file at some point I
have to look through for coder and find
out there's a lot of like stuff that
slows me down a lot which is
I can't switch between buffers very
quickly and for kodir it always puts me
in weird places or doesn't switch to the
last buffer I used your stuff like that
I need to like make that more solid at
some point I just haven't had a chance
to do so because I noticed that too
that's it's much slower for me to move
around than it used to be and it's one
of the things that I find like that an
indentation are the two things that have
been problematic so far and I think
indentation is already getting fixed or
partially fixed so it's mostly yet just
one of those little things that I feel
like I could probably fix on my own too
so all right heroes exists is not going
to be set to true anymore and then what
what I'm going to do is instead of
having that concept of it like a Deadman
switches kind of thing there when we do
an exit right what I would say is let's
just go ahead and keep track of how many
heroes there are in art right and and so
these brain IDs we could just say okay
any time we exit any time there's a hero
who leaves or you know I guess what we
could even do is just loop over and see
if none of the controller heroes have a
brain right we wouldn't even have to do
any more than that so we could do
something where we said okay you know
what we don't even need exit to title
all we really need to do is just say
that the heroes exist thing that we use
the dues we'll just set it by looping
through the controllers
and so we can also look to see how that
did that see that's the thing right it
totally loses where my place is like I
used to be down at the bottom of the
file and now I'm I don't know where I am
I'm nowhere this is where I was so okay
so in here I've got handmade world mode
and I want to look at handmade H to see
where those con heroes are being stored
oops aah and they are getting stored in
here we go this I believe we can now
replace as well with Max controlled
controller count and so yeah and here i
can just use the array account of this
of games state-controlled heroes and for
each one of these i can say the controls
hero i guess i can even just do if game
state-controlled heroes con hero index
dot brain ID value here is exists equals
true break I heroes exists needs to get
this needs to get here quick Wes good
does that do anything okay oops I think
we're all good now okay and this is
still running for some reason even
though I would have accepted the crash
because we change the data layout but I
guess it just wasn't because we just
added something in a place that it
didn't matter it was fine anyway so now
we kind of have the brains pulled out to
a separate file and here is that file
and you can kind of see that we've got
stuff in there that we need start
working on and then down here we have
what is now sort of becoming the physics
part of things so here's all of the
controller logic so this is like if we
have anything that's thoughtful at all
so a monster or you know monster AI or
any of that stuff can run up in here so
we've got this we're going to run the
brains we can then say like okay you
know now we can come in and deal with
all the entities these entities should
have had stuff set on them and you know
we yeah you get the idea we have the
notion of updateable which we can still
avail though I think that might that
might be something we eventually can get
rid of now based on the fact that we're
room locked and not free scrolling
anymore we really just have to worry
about this one little part of the
boundary which we can talk about some
time later but assuming that entities
are updateable we can kind of see what's
supposed to happen here and so what we
want to start doing is cleaning up this
code into something that works reliably
for all entities that need to you know
be updated now here in this post physics
entity work side of things you can see
that all of this is actually just
rendering right like this is this switch
statement does nothing but render a dude
right that's all it does
and so I don't really know exactly how
we're going to handle that we're going
to have to look at that in a little more
detail very soon now but basically we're
going to have to start wondering about
how entities are how entities look and
that's going to have to be derived from
their properties in some ways that are
complicated right because like i said
before we kind of want to have the
ability for entities to be fairly free
form into kind of morph into various
things and that's going to put a bit of
a stress on the way that we match you
know figure out what bitmaps to draw
because obviously we only have a finite
number of bitmaps so we can't just
create bitmaps whole cloth if everything
was completely procedural we could but
that's not really feasible for the case
of a sort of hand-drawn look kind of
game like this maybe someday in the
distant future it will be but not today
so yeah so I don't know a lot a lot of
this stuff I don't really know if we
want much of this in here I feel like
this kind of needs to get moved out of
here so it's not bothering me anymore
see here put this damn in here yeah all
right and so we can kind of see how this
works all of this stuff is
simulation-based we and we have these
sort of separate waves and each wave
corresponds to something that we're
trying to do we have the brain phase
which goes through decides what to do we
then have like a physics phase which
moves things around and then we have an
entity phase and I don't know that I
care super much about this timing block
so I'm going to go ahead and flatten
this out again I'm just trying to
flatten this out and start to think
about how it's working and simplify
things are possible so yeah so here
we've got run all the brains and I don't
really need this common anymore to be
quite so big if you run all brains and
this is
simulate all entities all right so now
what do I want to do here well this
stuff is sort of a mix right its a mix
of rendering and simulation you can see
that it does a switch on the entity type
here and it does the actual movement
code set up and then it does a switch on
what the movement type is and does the
movement sort of separate from it
doesn't matter what ND it is it'll do
the same movement code regardless and
then it comes down and finally does the
rendering right like essentially this
should not be called post physics entity
work it's really just rendering because
that's the only thing it does at the
moment right you can see if there's
really nothing else that's happening
here besides that let me delete all this
we don't need this anymore yeah so this
rendering code is something that will
get to later so I guess I don't really
have to care about that too much at the
moment but we're gonna have to start
thinking about it soon so I'll leave
that for now and we'll just focus on
this will focus everything up to this
point ok here is the move entity code
does the code that gets called whenever
an entity has to actually go somewhere
or do something I don't really know if
we want this movable flag anymore i
suspect we probably don't want the
movable flag anymore and the reason i
suspect that we don't want the movable
flag anymore is because the way that
we're doing in an emotion now is much
more semantic and i suspect that pretty
much you could just have your movement
mode be set to on not moving and that is
good enough like we shouldn't need a
flag in addition to an enum that says
how you're moving one of the ways in
which you could be moving could be not
moving right so I suspect we could get
rid of this flag pretty soon as well and
that's something I'll probably be aiming
to do in a second here but what I'd like
to do is go back and take a look at some
more of these things and just make sure
that I kind of know what's going on here
so you can see that we've got DDT Bob
and we've also got a DDP or the two
things we're setting I'm going to go
ahead and say that this right here is a
paired thing it has to do with the head
distance from the body and so
in my mind this is a brain operation
right this is an operation that has to
do with things when when something's
planted stretching towards it's like
related entity right and so what I want
to do is say well if the movement mode
is planted and if there's a head then
we're going to sort of you know have
this this notion that this stuff is
going to occur right and the difference
here is that when we compute this DDT
Bob that's going to be the DDT dub for
the body we're going to write that into
you know into the DDT okay because
otherwise we sort of we do have this
other notion of what the DDT bob is
right we have that being able to happen
in other ways right it can happen inside
one of these sort of hopping movement
things and so I'm just going to say that
that's something that that happens as an
accumulator right and then later we
apply what we need to apply to the DDT
Bob and and then we you know we would
zero that out on packing because it
would get it would go away during
packing right so essentially i'm doing
the same thing I did with DDP there's
now on the entity there's the notion of
acceleration stored on the entity but
only during the time when it's actually
stimulated we would never actually store
it right it's not something we would
store and keep around so here's my DDT
Bob and again this is probably not
singing will keep but we just want to
we're going to have values like this and
we would have if probably just not
called DDT Bob but we would have this
notion that you know certain bones have
some springiness and other things like
that right
okay so what we need to do in additional
as an additional step here is things
that we don't want to pack right we want
those things to not persist to the next
round to the next update cycle so inside
world when we are actually packing
entities what I'd like to do is just you
know sort of prophylactically so that we
don't get in the habit of keeping them
around or aren't confused when they stay
around i'd like to go ahead and clear
the things that are not supposed to be
stored okay just to keep that going so
now in here yeah we don't really have to
worry about a lot of this stuff because
now we know we've got two things both
the head and the body so in this case
here i could say like if I've got the
head then I know that my head distance
is going to be that length and it's the
length between the head and the body and
that gets rid of all that complexity as
well okay so now I think we're still in
good shape again we haven't fixed our
GDP yet but we're starting to clean that
up so I think that's the last thing
we've got to do is actually get the DDP
part correctly which is what allows
enemies to move around and what we have
here is we have this notion of this
movement spec and while the movement
spec is not necessarily a bad idea i
think it is a bad idea that's not stored
on the entity and the reason that i
think that is because again much like
the DDP it's something that a bunch of
people may want to feed into and operate
on so what we want to do is we want to
have some notion of how this movement
mode stuff works and and so let's take a
look at that oops i'm actually up here
so you can see what used to happen when
we would set this these these movement
modes we had this movement spec that was
here it was getting is getting set this
way I strongly suspect that we want to
kind of clean up how this movement spec
thing works at all anyway like the speed
and the drag and this crap I don't know
that we want any of that anymore I
probably I would be shocked if we really
want
I this to work exactly the way that it
is working but you know that's all right
for now not a huge deal the point is
what I'd like to do is take a non packed
movement spec and add that to the entity
so the move spec here that we've got
where we do default moves back what I
want to do there is say okay the
movement spec on an entity you know
there's going to be one put it in here
for now we'll just say there is a
movement spec it's not packed for now
and so what happens when we go to update
is instead of getting the movement spec
from here we're not going to do that at
all instead we're going to get the
movement spec out of the entity itself
and so later when we come down into the
movement stuff and we say let's go ahead
and move it what we actually are going
to do is we're going to get that out of
the entity so if I go back now and look
at where we were actually signing that
there were two places we were doing it
one was for the head one was for the
body oh well that's not true looks like
one was for the body where was the head
did we never do the head do we ever even
use this we don't use it i'm just not
even going to bother with it for now
because i don't care about the familiar
at all right now
hmm interesting so in here so I guess we
never really used it for for the head
which doesn't make any sense because we
would have had to use it for the head in
order to make the movement work so i
must have just deleted the code that use
that or whatever anyway I don't really
care about that because I want to apply
the I want to I really don't want this
to be doing anything fancy anyway I
guess is the point so you know we'll use
this for the moment and we'll just say
okay here a body I don't care about but
hero head right so if there's a hero
head I want it to I want it to use
whatever this spec is let's say so we're
just going to go ahead and say head like
so I don't know where that actually gets
to find here it is but that's gonna I
think we're gonna I don't like that
system at all i don't really like that I
think it's not gonna scale well like
having this movement spec concept I
think we want to make it a little more
of a functional thing I don't know maybe
I'm wrong maybe it'll be fine but I'm
not super not super confident in it
let's put that way alright so the
familiar I'm just going to throw this
out because we haven't we talked about
the familiar much all right so let's
take a look at what this is starting to
look like now and let's see if we can
get so I'm not getting any DDP in there
let's see if we could figure out how to
start routing the DDP into it so here's
the brain code and in the brain code you
can see me setting the DDP here right
and that's sort of the controller's
requested DDP we then take a look at
what that is and we were sort of we're
doing like some kind of a
the fussing on that I guess would be the
way to put it and then we're adding to
the heads velocity just just straight up
right the heads velocity is just kidding
getting added directly which is kind of
a little bit weird yeah this is what
happens when you have to make too many
code changes at once and you have to
spread them over weeks of time because
you only probably on our program an hour
today you kind of forget exactly why you
were ever doing something one way but
that's not it here another excuse me
okay uh so if we're looking at if we're
looking at the hero head to me it looks
to me like since get closest reversible
will always work in the case that we're
looking at now it seems to me like the
DD the head DP should always actually
have a value added to it right and this
doesn't really look like what I would
have wanted to do so I feel like I'm
just going to stop this from happening
entirely because basically the heads DDP
should be equal to this acceleration
that's what we wanted to do is set an
acceleration for the head and that's
just what we're trying to do so now I
want to kind of figure out why are we
not getting any sort of movement here so
i just want to see what happens and i
should probably also come in here and
say let's put that in for now i want to
make some major changes to this code but
we don't have to do that right now and
so now when i'm pushing on things i want
to know why i'm not getting any any
actual acceleration there which is a
little bit harder to do so what I'm
going to maybe do here is maybe I'll
just add a force so that it's like
permanently pushing to one side so that
I don't have to try and hold down a key
and then hit a break point or something
like that right
i guess i can use was pressed ah i see
what the problem is for some reason we
have was pressed and that was down right
so we actually were using this as a
state thing we actually were storing the
controller state in the con here oh
right I forgot about this we were doing
some stuff to make it so that you it
would it would remember what the last
direction you had pushed was alright I
like that I felt like that made a good
difference when we were I felt like that
made a reason alone I'm sorry playing
around before so i think i may leave
that there if that makes sense i think i
may say like okay that's a reasonable
thing to keep in the controlled here was
like what the controller state was
supposed to be and so i guess maybe
we'll call this controller door or
something like that I don't know GDP
makes it easier to type even though
that's not quite what it is so I'll
delete this one here and I'll say dd p
equals clown hero GDP and we're gonna
have to figure out how we want to do
analog stick motion as well right
because I don't know if we want to use
some like some cross like make a nice
cross shaped dead zone pattern or
something so that you kind of its locks
into whichever one you're pressing more
into I'm not sure but something like
that probably has to happen at some
point if we want to support analog
sticks as opposed to just d pads so
let's see here so going through we've
got a length squared con hero DDP
and I think that's all we need oops what
happened I don't know what I just did oh
right I change the data layout so we got
to restart anyway all right so now what
I'm going to try doing is I want to I
want to make sort of a pass through the
code to find out exactly why we're not
getting the DDP I want to find it i want
to step through the code and see how the
DDP is ending up getting set and i just
want to do that before i start factoring
this code to make sure that we don't
have any other bugs well I'm almost
certain we do have other bug so I'm
saying get rid of those before I start
playing around with the code all right
so inside brain which is not here
unfortunately open-file brain does it to
be all right so what I'm going to do is
I'm just going to set a breakpoint on
move down or I you know what I'll do
move left all right so the x equals 1
the easiest case to look at so here we
are in that piece of code visual studios
thankfully picking up a key press that
went to another application and starting
to insert characters it's almost
certainly what you want the middle of a
breakpoint and here we go looking
through here looks like we don't really
have anything particular to care about
here but here is the code we actually do
care about where we're sort of looking
at this DDP okay so if we take a look at
the con hero GDP we see that it is x1
which is what we expect we come through
here and you know we should theory not 0
too much of it at our GDP too ah well
that explains that
because that's not correct at all our
GDP to never gets set here right and it
should so DDP to actually should be
equal to this directly I think is what
we should have been doing right because
we should have said it to what the
acceleration is so I think that's the
mistake or not
right because this is clipping out the
elements of it if you know when there's
no push happening but otherwise it's
passing it through which is what we want
it to go to head DDP right and we're
using that DDP are we not or are did I
never do that either which would be yet
another thing that we didn't do when we
were fixing up the code yet we didn't do
that either that's got to go away so DDP
for any type familiar this can be the
entities gdp for now we're going to
probably move the editing familiar code
over to a brain though obviously right
and so that'll be fine just ended a DDP
all right so we're not really in a
correct state yet we still got a bunch
of stuff to do but at least now we're
back to being able to move our head
around in the way that I would have
expected so that's nice uh all right
sorry I've got itchy eye it's a bit
allergy ish in Seattle these days for me
i don't know why i don't think the
allergy season is really that high at
the moment but plants all right
so now we need to do is start to kind of
clean up this code a little bit more you
can see that entity type is now starting
to get very spare which is what I wanted
right because I don't really want
anything to have to do with the env type
anymore so one thing we could do is now
say that the hero familiar code moves
over here as well and so I don't know
that we really want anything in
particular to be called hero familiar
yet but I'm going to do that for now
just so we can sort of see that well
whatever it is that has that sort of
stuff related to it it's going to be
over here right so all of this stuff is
going to be over here and so now and
then in theory that floaty thing for now
code would I guess also be a break a
piece of brain code right that was like
moving things around so even this would
be a brain floaty thing for now because
anything that's like a behavior is going
to move over here and they might not be
specifically brain IDs they may be like
it may be like the brain ideas like an
animated piece of scenery is the brain
type and then there's properties of the
entity that sort of tell it how it moves
render things like that if that makes
sense so now this this entity type stuff
is not going to be determining that
anymore and maybe we use this and maybe
we don't
and now this goes away and we really
just have the movement code right which
is have entities move and then the
rendering code I'm going to go ahead and
grab this and put it down here alright
so now we've got to actually define
those rains which is fine and then
anyone who was previously using the ND
stuff you know I should probably I need
to start keeping track of the four coder
things that we that we run into because
I don't ever keep track of them like
buffer position laws etc etc I got a
concert making notes things don't get
better if you don't make notes alright
so in here we've got this editing stuff
I'm not going to port the familiar just
yet although we probably do want to do
that soon see here all right
okay so let's go ahead now and start to
think about you know what I'd like to do
is before we clean up this this brain
code anymore what I'd like to do is
actually come over to the entity stuff
and see if we can now consider a way to
I'd like to figure out some way to get
rid of that entity type right cuz like I
said one of the big things I wanted to
do was not have entity type be a thing
anymore like I don't really want that
right and so I would rather have ways in
which an entity itself just says that
it's made up out of some pieces and so
when it's created it can just be made up
out of those pieces and then off you go
and there's really not much more to it
than that right and so you can see that
that wouldn't be probably that difficult
because you can see that all we're doing
here is like pushing bitmaps on for like
you know we're just doing some asset
matching and then pushing some bitmaps
on it so it seems to me that we should
be able to have a way to make that work
without a whole lot of you know of to do
about it and I feel like probably we
could say that you know in general
things are made up of a couple pieces
and that those pieces you know have sort
of an own way they get rendered and that
we don't need to base it on the type at
all right that seems reasonable to me
stairwells are not a thing anymore those
just don't exist so I don't really want
that we can get rid of that entirely
Monstars are a thing that would exist
but they're going to be a brain probably
let's see here so we've got the Monstars
and a Monstars was really no different
than a regular hero but just with a
torso that's all it was and presumably
we'd have other stuff in their floors
and floaty things those are like just
solid pieces that are on the ground so
again I feel like all this stuff let's
just let's just do it let's do it i'm in
the mood to get rid of this i don't
really want any of this crap here
anymore so here this is just debug code
right so so this can just be anyone can
have this drawn right anyone can draw
their traversable xin their collision
Rex so just let's just do that right
let's do that and so that just should be
like a bunch of yeah there's just few
bunch of squares on stuff right yeah
there you go and so we'll just make a
debug switch or something that controls
that and then we don't have to think
about it anymore right so that's fine so
now we don't care about any of these
entity types at all and then the rest of
these like I say most of them are just
like okay do I have a shadow and then
I've got some luck do I have to any
springy parts that are sort of
associated with each other it looks like
it shouldn't be that complicated to me
right
seems pretty straightforward
yeah alright so in here we've got I
don't know what why color I guess we
just have because we were doing some
kind of bouncy offsets for the heroes
body so what I'd like to do is just
let's just take this code and just make
a sort of a smush down version that
every entity could use right and so the
enemy familiar where the head bobs up
and down right thats can still be the
same as as how like the as how the torso
Bob's up and down right those can all be
essentially the same because the torso
already has this notion of that it can
come up up and down I'm sorry the cape
can come up and down based on the tea
Bob so really these are the same if that
makes sense and we don't really need
them to be dealt with separately so for
you know if this was something that
we're going to be animated then that can
just be something that gets generically
animated and it's not really a big deal
so we'll figure out how to do that the
Mon star is completely the same that as
the hero just didn't have a head right
drawing hip point seems like something
that everyone could have happen and then
if they just don't have hip points then
we just don't draw it so I feel like
that's also something that could come
down here and we just make that a little
bit smarter to just look to see whether
there's any hip points lots and if there
are we don't draw them in fact it looks
like that already works right because if
you don't have hip points you don't draw
the hit points so now anything could
just get hit points all of a sudden if
it needed to and that would work which
again is more keeping with what I want I
don't really want things to have types
that define these things I just want
them either have it or they don't and
then not have really any cost to just
making something suddenly have them all
right so the hero head if I was to sort
of add these together let me see what
happens here right the hero head again
could just be in place of one of these
guys so really this that concept of a
composite where we just have like a
shadow a thing and the thing on top of
it would draw everything
we have at the moment so we could just
do that I don't know what this 2.5 so
these are the heights right so let's
just make this a property of the entity
so in here we've got them this entities
and you know maybe we've got sort of the
notion that each entity sort of has a
component right and I don't know what
we'd call this but like like a visible
piece right and this visible piece would
just be I've got you know essentially
the things that I use to call this
bitmap call is what I actually want
right I have like this sort of stuff so
I need to know what the asset type is
like what is the asset type that I'm
grabbing for this thing I need to know
like I suppose what the Alpha value is
for it and maybe I don't really want to
know that I'm not sure but you know
probably I do i need to know the scale
of it so how big it is probably right
just this way like height basically and
I guess we could just call that height
so I need to know the height and I need
to know the color I could just say v4
color right
and then I need some information about
how they're going to be matched right
because like I guess I could just put
the direction facing direction in there
and then you know well I guess that's
really all i would need is just to just
throw in that yeah i mean i don't know
that i really need to keep an entire
waiting vector in there I think we get
you to get by with this just for now and
probably most of these things would work
ok right and so then you here I can just
say well I've got a few of these visible
pieces right and you know at the moment
we're basically saying you know we can't
really have very many of those and I
think I don't ever probably want to have
too many of those because you know
really this is just if just this is just
for animation purposes if things were
actually moving around very distinctly
then they should be separate entities so
this is only like four animation these
are animated pieces of this thing and so
for now it would just be something like
that right now possibly in the future we
may need to do something where these are
shared and in fact you know now I think
about that might be that might be
something we would want to do in general
just because we don't really need to
store them if they're usually the same
but I don't know I i think i'm going to
leave it this way for the moment yeah I
think that's I think that's probably how
we're going to leave it all right um so
if we have these these visible pieces I
and then I'm going to draw them you know
I could basically turn this thing into a
loop that works that way right we've got
the entity x-axis the y-axis and the
floor display stand that stuff we can
essentially use this thing and just make
a loop that would look this way and we
would just need some extra information
how much time do I have not a whole lot
of time I really just need a little bit
of extra information to do some of these
more advanced things so I'm going to
leave the hero body out of this for now
and I'm going to do the rest of these
because they're a lot simpler for me to
start with and then once those are
working we'll figure out how to back
into making the other ones work right
okay so let's start with the most the
easiest one which is the wall so if we
imagine how this is going to go I can
just say ok there's a piece index equals
zero peace index is less than your way
account of the env pieces Peace Index oh
wait no it's not I guess I can just say
piece count because it has less than
that number often and then I have an
enemy visible piece and I'm just going
to do that that drawing so i'll do a
push bitmap and i want to do a get Beth
Matt a get best match here and so I'm
going to do a get best get best match
for the bitmap ID when I do the get bet
get massive get best matching bitmap I
need to take the piece asset type
man I can't actually get any more room
can I that's unfortunate the asset type
the match vector and the weight vector
right once i have that bitmap ID that's
the one that i'm going to be passing
here i know that the piece height goes
here i know that the the piece color
goes wait no this is the offset I guess
right which we haven't really done
anything with yet so then I would have
here I'd have the piece color like so
and that be the simple version right so
that's pretty good so now I just need to
actually set one of these and so for
example for wall I could probably make
this happen right now so if i go up here
to where we would create a wall and add
wall oops
yeah I can go ahead and add the entity
piece here that that correctly
represents this thing that I'm trying to
draw so here's me doing it first without
that is asset type not known at this
time somehow does any of you come before
asset that seems weird but possibly true
let's find out because file formats it
would be in file formats right and
entities way down here its asset type ID
that's the problem so now when I run the
game I'm not gonna see any walls right
so I know they're there because their
collision volumes are there right but I
don't see them so what I need to do now
is I need to actually get one of those
and you actually make a piece for the
you know that says a tree has this one
component that's the tree and you should
draw it right so if i go to handmade
robe mode us to BP and inside add well
what i need to do is do an ad piece
command which will create which
basically says like hey it's going to be
an asset tree it's going to be a 2.5
tall and it's going to be well we don't
have an offset yet I suppose I should
have probably put an offset in there but
it's just going to be white right it's
not going to be tinted at all okay so
hopefully you can see what I'm doing
here I'm doing a very straightforward
process to get this started I'm just
saying ok let's make a sort of a data
layout that just mirrors what we were
actually doing so that I can make it to
the entities prescribe in the actual
the exactly what will happen when they
go to be rendered so that each entity
can have a unique way in which it gets
rendered as sort of like it's only it's
basically like taking and it's almost a
mini scripting language kind of approach
right when you do this sort of thing
you're saying I'm going to add a bunch
of Records which say the functions to
use basically and they just happen to be
based on very specific parameterization
so it's a very limited way of scripting
it right so you're basically compressing
some some ideas about what code you
could call into just a few parameters
and then unpacking them that way all
right so in the ad piece called you know
right pretty easy how this works I just
say alright I've got an entity the
entity has an asset type ID I'm sorry
the piece has an asset type ID it's got
a height and a static color and that's a
simple way to add a piece we would
assert of course that the entity piece
count was not too full
and then we would just say fill out
exactly that piece so entity visible
piece and then the pieces plus entity
east count + + piece asset type ID
that's a type ID at peace height equals
height and peace color equals color so
that is all we need to do to add a piece
and in theory now also we probably can
render this right what is it it's not a
member
probably don't ed idea okay all right
we're at the Q&amp;A but hey you can see
that we've restored that functionality
so now we have trees and of course since
we are now doing that it also means that
if we wanted to write we can use the
world modes random series which I
believe is in here right so we could use
like effects entropy and I'm not really
going to do this but you know you could
imagine doing it right if we wanted the
trees to have a random amount of red in
them right we could do random your
lateral on the effects entropy and now
every tree would be like a different
color right at least they are or not I
would have expected each tree to be a
different color we are using that are we
not
we might not be I think about it please
can't now we are so we're passing the
color here why are we not seeing that
beat it oh because there's no red in it
yeah that's good point if there's no red
in the tree you won't see that so let's
take that again and say a random amount
of green in it that's probably a little
bit more obvious oops yeah so um you
know even just so you get some idea of
what's going to happen there you can see
why we might care about this just even
right off the bat because we're going to
want to have lots of different trees in
the game but they don't have different
entity types necessarily and so you know
having the ability to just say like this
is what we're creating it in the here's
how it behaves on what its stats are but
it's visible representation might be
slightly varied just so that things look
slightly different all the time right
you can see why that might be important
and so there's a lot of things like that
that we might want to do and this is
just one step towards doing that and
yeah so like I said just kind of a nice
additional thing now I actually want to
do that right now but I just wanted to
point out how that changes things
alright let's go ahead and go to the QA
uh that's funny it's like yeah it
doesn't matter what the red channel is
on the trees there's literally no red in
those trees so you can knock it all the
way to zero and you're just removing
stuff that wasn't there
any questions
looks like Reno got no questions which
is okay if we don't have any questions
then we will end the stream it's coming
along pretty nicely I think there's only
one thing I'm slightly nervous about and
that is how we're going to do boundaries
of the simulation region everything else
is pretty nice recently came across this
read the abstract and tell me what you
think
programmer is hoping to achieve
performance improvements often use
custom memory allocators this in-depth
study examines a top case to use custom
allocators presently 46 SF because the
state of the art general-purpose
allocator the douglas allocator performs
as well or better than the custom
allocators the two exceptions use
regions which deliver higher performance
proved us up to forty four percent well
obviously I probably agree with the
results because like handmade hero uses
regions regions also reduce / programmer
burden and eliminate source of memory
leaks exactly what I would say as well
however we show that the inability of
her mr. free individual obviously
regions can lead to stantial increase in
memory consumption that's generally true
if you you know depending on the type of
application it is whereas this
limitation precludes the use of regions
for common programming idioms reducing
the usefulness that I don't know if I
really agree with but ok for their
generalization of general purpose in
region based lectures we call reaps your
star combination of regions and heaps
providing a full range of region
semantics with the addition of
individual object deletion we show that
our implementation of reaps provides
high performance at performing other
allocators of region like semantics we
needa case study demonstrates the space
advantages and software engineer
benefits of reaps and practice our
results in Kate the perimeters eating
fast region should use reaps and that
most programmers Christian customers
should instead use the Lea allocator so
I guess I'd have to read what their
implementation of reaps quote-unquote is
but for the most part I agree with the
abstract because in general like that is
why i use regions as well I find them to
be faster and less error prone than then
allocating and freeing individual
objects I find that I just use free
lists when I need to recycle objects but
certain applications that are not video
games have more strenuous need to free
things in that way and so it may be that
they've done something interesting here
with how they do it or it may be that
they're just doing something that's like
exactly what I would do or that is a
free list essentially and so I have to
like read to find out if it's something
to talk about that second
tournament does that help
is there a limit to the colors you can
have uh well I guess that I'm not sure
what you mean by I'm not sure what you
mean by limit there's not a limit to the
colors you can have in terms of sending
could you be more specific I guess is
what I'd say because there's a number of
ways I could answer that question and
the answer is yes in some cases and no
one in other cases and so I want to kind
of understand what question you're
trying to ask before I say things that
may be further confusing maybe more
confusing than than helpful long billion
will you have to have an entity type at
some level like when generating the
world placing trees and whatnot I would
say that I don't know if we'll have an
entity type per se but when we're
generating the world will definitely
have ideas about what we're placing and
that might come from a type but it may
instead come from just the structure of
the code right like this thing is going
to go place trees and it calls the place
tree routine which knows it's placing
trees and so there was never may be a
need to have a phenom right um so I
guess what I'd say about that is I don't
know whether we'll ever use those enums
again we may delete them and then never
come back or we could you know if they
end up being something we do need to use
in in the generator side then that's
fine I don't mind them in the generator
side right I just don't want them in the
runtimes don't think they're the right
level of control
waiting for a clarification on that
limit to the number of colors question
in the meantime I'm going to see if I
can quickly look at this reaped paper
and see if I see what what their
structure is for heaps
oh wait um
so I guess what I would say is what
they're describing in this paper does
not sound all that different from how I
structure things in like my code at work
except for the fact that they seem to
have added a lot more overhead than I
would then i think is warranted because
i find that most of the time I feel like
they were probably trying to target a
lot more oops key code than mine is and
so they probably were trying to
accelerate cases where people were doing
a lot more malloc and free than I ever
do in the course of a running program
and so they were probably chasing after
performance in areas where I just don't
need it and so I feel like they add a
lot of memory overhead here that I don't
think is necessarily warranted now that
said I haven't spent a lot of time
optimizing memory performance in my code
because it's almost never an issue so if
someday I actually took some harder look
at that just because hey it'd be fun to
try and get it more optimal just as an
exercise I might have a little bit of a
better idea as to whether i think that
level of overhead they're talking about
is warranted which I don't really know
okay so clarification was colors of the
trees the hero enemies etc again I
really just don't understand the
question like what do you mean to say is
there a limited number of them do you
mean does the game design have a limited
number of colors the trees didn't heroes
are supposed to be or i'm sorry i think
i'm missing like the sort of place
you're coming from ingeniero I've been a
little lost the last few days would you
mind giving a brief recap of what you're
trying to do to the entity system now uh
yeah so the the overall idea here is to
split out the parts the things that make
an entity actually appear on the screen
and do stuff to split those out into
reasonably separate elements that can be
recombined very fluidly right and so
some things that I wanted to be able to
do for example I was say oh if I have
like a hero head in a hero body I want
to be able to write some control code
that can make the hero head and body
move around but I don't want there to
have to be an understanding that heroes
are always constructed of a head and a
body and furthermore I might want to be
able to like put different bodies on a
hero or you know do stuff like that
dynamically without like having to sort
of copy things between Andy I want to be
able to swap in a new piece and have it
start working furthermore I'd like to be
able to do things like cast a spell and
make a hero behave a different way and
then later behave you know or whatever I
want to sort of have a very rich way of
doing all that I don't want to have
heroes always have to look the same way
I want to be able to have like different
outfits on or stuff like that
potentially blah blah blah blah blah
right and so the way that we implemented
it in the beginning because we were just
sort of getting things working and you
know we're coming back to revisit it now
and I'm trying to do the real version of
everything the way the meat in the
beginning as we just said hey energies
a type and whatever the type is that's
what determines everything right and
that type there was basically just some
switch statements that were like
whatever your type is that's what's
going to determine the code that we call
to control you it's what we're going to
use to can determine how your rendered
it's what we're going to use to
determine how your physics operates
right and so I'm just trying to get rid
of all of that and say no there's just
an entity and an entity has lots of
little pieces of information that sum up
to reproduce all of that stuff that was
previously hard-coded to an entity type
but now you can mix and match so if you
want something that's being controlled
like a hero but that looks like a tree
and blah blah blah you can do that right
and be the reason I'm doing that is not
because I think there's some inherent
important beauty in writing an entity
system this way and if you have entity
types then that's bad or something it's
more that this particular type of game
is sort of a generative sort of
exploration ille adventure a rogue kind
of a thing and as you know from having
played the good ones of those they're a
lot about having rich permutations and
interactions between things and so I
really don't want to have hard edges in
that space where it's just like thing is
either an A or a B I want like
everything in between a and B to be fair
game and so that's sort of what we were
trying to do there right
thoughts on avoiding denormalize
floating point on console platforms do
they all have minus f fast math uh well
uh so I guess what I would say is it
depends on what you mean by console
platform but if what you mean is X bone
in ps4 then an exponent a ps4 are x64 so
they operate through the SSE unit for
doing math which means you can just not
have D normals at all so don't really
have to avoid them they just won't
happen because you can always have the
SSE unit just never duty normals
handling to be honest I don't even know
if the SSE units on consoles do handle t
normals they may just always be normal
to you normals go to zero I mean I've
never looked niche sir my apologies yes
limits in the game design yeah so the
game design definitely will want to have
specific colors that mean certain things
obviously in various places but small
variation in color will probably be
something that we would actually use
just to add a little more variety to
things so we probably wouldn't limit
that we would allow things to sort of
have color variation
anonymous 519 can you explain the
difference between how you manage memory
at work and how you're currently doing
it in handmade hero uh not really
because it's kind of a long story will
monsters and other things be able to
attack each other like a witch
accidentally shrinks a goblin or
something yes probably to be honest I
don't feel comfortable saying yes or no
till we actually let it happen and see
if it's too chaotic but I certainly
would default to yes in that case would
we do anything differently if we wanted
to have HDR capabilities in the game we
would probably have to add a few values
in some places to allow colors to be
more powerful than they currently are we
could just say that colors can be set
more arbitrarily but typically you don't
quite typically you might do things
where you have like a power value and
then a color value so there's some
things you might do but but not really
no most of it would just be that the
renderer would would be taking tone
mapping would be doing tone mapping and
taking that side of things more
seriously
realest 01 can you answer our offended
people would like to see your priest on
YouTube I've answered that so many times
by now but I'll answer it again the pre
streams are only for people who watch
the string that's if you want free
streams you gotta watch the show they're
they're not they're not for posterity
let's see
now it was 519 the reason i ask is
because i really like the idea of
allocating upfront and managing all
memory myself as in him a hero but i'm
not sure if I'm just shooting myself in
the foot by not using malloc and free so
I guess what I would say about this is I
you should be able to think this through
relatively straightforwardly right so in
handmade hero you know that everywhere
that we're just doing a push and we
don't have a free list there's no way
you would ever want to use malloc and
free for that right because you never
it's never freed it just gets push push
push push push push push push push push
push which is essentially an instant
operation that Malik can't even come
close to being as fast as right because
it doesn't do anything it just it's an
ad right and then free just goes ok we
just reset the point so you know that
anywhere that your stuff looks like that
you would be crazy to use malloc and
free because that is just clearly always
a win once you start having a free list
so now you don't know right and I should
add one caveat there typically what you
would do in a more general purpose
scheme is you don't allocate everything
up front you just allocate when you
overflow so you just push push push push
push push if you're about to go over the
end you just get a new block and keep
pushing right so that you don't use more
memory than you need right so that's
what you would do in the case where you
have a free list it should be relatively
easy for you to think through in the
places where you have a free list is
this faster with Malkin free or is it
faster doing the free list approach and
you know what don't hurt yourself
thinking about it just do an f0 just put
an ifdef in there make it so that you
can call Malkin free or your free list
version and see which one's faster
that's it right you won't have that many
free lists in a program it's not that
hard to test you could even make a
central
thing part of your alligator could just
build in that switch and then just turn
it on and off done deal right it's
always free to switch back to malloc and
free right the only thing that's hard is
if you're counting on that region free
and I don't know how you really solve
that problem if you're counting on the
region free switching to Malik free as a
little hard cuz you don't clean up but
you can still at least test it and then
you don't get the freeing so you can't
really run the thing indefinitely but
you could at least test it to see if you
got a performance win there and then if
you did get a performance with malloc
and free that you thought was important
you could then go back no okay how do I
deal with the fact that I've got it like
free this stuff manually now
alright
all right i am going to wrap it up all
right thanks everyone for joining me for
another episode of Hamming here it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to follow along at
home you can always peer to the game on
handmade hero org and it comes to source
code so you can do whatever it is that
we're going to do so you can play around
with it basically and see if you you
know anything that you want to try and
it kind of helps learn along with the
series we have a forum site you can go
to ask questions we have a patreon page
you can go if you want support the video
series we have a schedule bot that
tweets schedule when I remember to
upload the schedule which I didn't do
this weekend so I apologize for that
it's a I did upload it yesterday so now
it's correct and of course we got this
little countdown timer here that tells
you as well and then we have a past
episode guide which you can use fun to
catch up on old episodes it's pretty
cool and our very own did blow has made
it so that it's got all kinds of time
links in it so you can jump around and
like go where did-- case you talk about
this thing or whatever it's pretty cool
that's about it until tomorrow at five
p.m. pacific daylight time when i will
be probably finishing that sort of
moving the rendering out to a more to
that sort of peace based creation time
system until then have fun programming
and i will see you guys on the internet
take it easy everyone