hurting hello everyone and welcome to
hand made here of the show recode a
complete game live on stream yesterday
we took the bold step of deciding to
actually initialize the hardware a 3d
hardware acceleration because I kind of
got tired of not having any vsync in our
game and I don't really know of a way on
Windows anymore to actually get somewhat
reliable vsync without going through one
of the 3d api's the in the old days
there was like a direct raw API that you
could use to get these things separately
from you know separately from the 3d
driver now it's not so easy to do that
that's kind of all very legacy stuff and
I don't know if you can really count on
any of it anymore so we initialize that
and today we have to do some work well
we may have to put the work off because
let me tell you what happened
I found the HDMI capture card here it is
this is the one we bought for handmade
hero and I've been meaning to switch to
it so that we could not have that we
could have a separate machine that
streams so that we wouldn't take up any
system resources with OBS and have a you
know cleaner way to look at profiles and
stuff right but when I went to plug into
this machine I discovered that this
machine's graphics card is so old it
does not have an HDMI output it's got
DVI and DisplayPort so I need to get an
adapter but I get an adapter or a
different graphics card I guess once I
do that then we will be able to do it so
maybe I'll try to
I might have one at the office I don't
really know I'll look tomorrow or I can
order one but it means that that's a
little bit of a problem and I don't
really know any way around it now it's
possible that OBS for all I know might
have some way of me being able to do
some kind of a game capture thing here
that would allow you to see it but I
just don't know so unfortunately we may
be a little bit blind because as you
know when I run the game if you were
here yesterday you know that what
since when I run the game now is when we
start drawing it OpenGL I can see it and
you can we made a thing that just draws
a pink screen I am seeing the pink
screen you are not seeing the pink
screen right now apparently so we're
gonna go ahead and just do what we would
need to do anyway and and I have a bunch
of white blackboard stuff to talk about
today anyway so that'll take up some
time but hopefully we'll be able to at
the CAPTCHA card working and then we can
just go with that from now on if not
we'll just start fussing with OBS to try
and make it so it both captures the game
OpenGL and the desktop either one of
those two separately works okay I just
don't know if there's a good way to make
it so that you can fluidly switch
between them unfortunately so that's the
part that I don't actually know so let's
go ahead and do a brief recap of where
we're at and then I'm gonna go to the
blackboard and kind of give you the
overview of how 3d Hardware works
because nothing I do with it will make
any sense if you don't have a solid
grounding of how that's actually
supposed to work so okay if you remember
from yesterday here is win32 handmade
and we basically just went ahead and did
a initialize opengl with 30 to
initialize there it is and you remember
the stuff we had to do is we had to set
up a what we wanted sort of our our
drawing format to be we had to tell
Windows GDI that that was what we wanted
our window to be set up as we then had
to create an OpenGL context it's
basically saying that sits on top of a
Windows Device context that allows us to
access OpenGL through then we set that
up is the current one for our thread and
then we were done and so then the only
other thing we had to do is actually use
that code somewhere and so we had just a
very simple thing which set a drawing
region it set what color we wanted to
clear to and then cleared the color
buffer to that color we then called swap
buffers to present the drawing that we
had and that was it right that's the end
of it so hopefully that was all pretty
understandable and now we need to take
the step into actually calling the 3d
graphics hardware in some way that does
things we actually want because clearing
the screen to pink is
nice and all but it doesn't really help
us get our game on the screen right okay
so let's go ahead and see what day today
is day 236 yeah let's talk about GPUs
all right so what is a GPU you all
basically know what they are if you've
ever played a game before or your gamer
in any way obviously you know about them
even if you've never done any
programming you know about them and we
talked a little bit about them yesterday
about how they sort of came out of the
old concept that there was a graphics
workstation which this is a computer
that had dedicated hardware in it that
was designed to do graphics operations
and eventually those things became
daughter cards to put into pcs with
companies like 3d effects and Nvidia
sort of bringing that to fruition and
now that is just a standard expected
thing to have in a PC to the point where
they now are basically the same as those
workstations back then they're much more
powerful than the workstations but
they're basically the same conceptually
in that now it's basically not even
possible to really buy a PC that doesn't
have a dedicated 3d hardware
acceleration part on it even if you
don't buy a big beefy desktop style one
then your CPU now oftentimes has a 3d
accelerator built into it right like
intel oftentimes now ships the cpu is
you know 30% of the dye and the GPU is
70% of the dye so a huge portion of your
actual physical chip that you buy from
Intel is actually just a GPU on there so
in in pretty much all respects now
anything that you buy even a cell phone
these days often times looks a lot more
conceptually like an old silicon
graphics workstation in that sense that
there is dedicated hardware for 3d
graphics built in just and it's expected
so that's the world we live in now but
we did not grow up that way we did not
start out in that
you know with that basic design and so
it's really kind of uncomfortable the
way that the system is architected for
CPUs and GPUs it's kind of a very legacy
very clunky way that these two things
work and so let me give you a little bit
of a background on how that works so you
know very much about the cpu now if
you've been watching handmade hero we
know that basically there is you know
main memory right it's a big old chunk
of memory you know this is often times
something like 16 gigabytes today right
and then you've got a CPU this is like a
core i7 or something over here and
there's a little bus right that allows
the chip to access this memory and to
put things you know send things and get
things back from this main memory right
everything's grant and then there's some
like IO ports or who knows what else is
happening on here and and maybe some
other people are viewing this memory
like you know maybe the USB controller
can look at it who knows if it can maybe
it talked about the CPU I don't know
doesn't matter we don't care about any
of those things the only part we care
about is this part right here which is
to say that this is what we've been
working with almost entirely so far and
with this particular system the way that
it is right now with this diagram
there'd never be any way to get
something on the screen right the
screens over here here it is right and
somehow handmade Hiro's been showing up
on there there about but we don't even
really know how and the reason that we
don't know how even though this is like
we've been doing things as low-level as
we possibly can on a PC the reason that
we don't know how is because at some
point the memory that we're trying to
display actually can't live in this main
memory anymore
on this particular machine and the
reason for that is because the actual
memory where the display actually lives
is over on the GPU so here's the GPU and
here is its memory right on the card
this is actually physically on the GPU
card right and this is something you
know often times like one gigabyte it's
smaller it's almost always smaller than
this right now what has to happen and
the reason this has to occur is because
the physical plug
like literally the like the cable the
HDMI cable or in our case the DVI cable
he's connected to this memory right like
this is the card this is the thing in
the computer that has the plug on it
that connects to the screen so if you're
going to show something on the screen
that something has to be in this memory
so what happens is at some point windows
right Microsoft Windows running on the
CPU when we have asked it to has been
moving our bitmap right this bitmap that
we drew has been moving it silently for
us over to the memory here and then this
GPU the card has been transferring it
over the HDMI cable to the screen where
it is displayed and there's actually
Hardware in here that's designed to read
out of memory like this and encode it
into an HDMI signal and put it out the
thing like that's on the that's actually
part of the GPUs chipset right there's a
little chip in here that'll do that or
something it used to be called a DAC
right a digital analog converter because
the signal that was going out was analog
but I don't think they really call it
that anymore I don't know maybe they do
because it's still sort of an analogue
thing but since HDMI is digital it's not
the word DAC is a little ambiguous there
but I don't know I'm not a hardware guy
I don't know the terminology they use
for those sort of things but that's
what's happening okay so what we've been
doing so far is we've basically just
been asking Windows hey look here's our
bitmap that we made ourselves we we have
it in a particular location in memory
and you remember where this was
happening this was happening where we
were calling stretch di bits or anything
like that so right here
yeah win32 display buffer and window
this call right here for this call right
here depending on which branch we were
in that's what did that we gave it the
address of where this was we told it how
big it was and then it moved it over to
the GPU and the GPU displayed it that's
what was actually happening okay now on
some computers that doesn't have to
happen if we were in a situation instead
where we had a CPU GPU combo right
so let's say this is a sky like part
right so the latest Intel chip it's got
one of these on it they have a shared
memory architecture potentially which
means that that picture that we drew
with the CPU is actually in the same
memory as could get scanned out right by
that HDMI cable essentially the HDMI
cable or the DVI X cable in our case is
actually plugged in to the unit on the
computer that has the main memory and so
it's not always the case that this
transfer has to happen it's only the
case if the GPU is on a separate card
and in this machine it is so this is
like a stipple desktop setup but a
typical mobile setup right might look
more like this where there's just one
shared bank of memory okay
so let's talk about what this means for
how things have to happen all right
because this is the diagram that
concerns us and the reason that this is
the diagram that concerns us instead of
this one is because on the PC you are
often on a high-end gaming machine
looking at this so when you're talking
about optimizing you're usually talking
about optimizing for this because this
is the thing where the you know Broz got
to GeForce Titans in there or whatever
so there's actually more there's more
than one of these right so this is the
thing you're looking at for the really
high-end optimizations right this is the
thing you're looking at at the lower end
but because this is the worst-case
meaning this is the most disconnected
things can be and it's an important case
this is the one that everything's
designed around for the most part this
is the this the worst case is this where
we have two different sets of memory and
so even though they're playing machines
out there that just have one unified
memory bank for everything we have to
deal with this diagram so even when you
program this guy you're still
effectively programming it as if it
looked like this and the reason is
because you you know you're trying to
ship one game that runs on several
different types of GPU right and so if
you pretended everything was always in
main memory it would come to a
screeching halt when it tried to run on
one of these so this is the diagram that
concerns us which means what we're
looking at you
is something that essentially looks like
this so here's the CPU and here's system
we'll call the system Ram here is what
we'll call
oops graphics RAM and here's the GPU and
these two things are connected by the
PCI bus right that's that slot that you
plug things into right where you plug
the graphics card into so the GPU has
fast access to everything in here the
CPU has fast text everything in here but
everything that's not right so if the
GPU wanted something from system RAM or
the CPU wants to read graphics Ram it's
got to go over the PCI bus maybe again
if it's a skylake chip if it's a Intel
integrated graphics part something like
that it does not because it's all system
Ram but assuming that we're talking
about something that's like oh this is
an nvidia part and this is an intel part
well then there's this bus and so
there's a speed hit that you take
transferring these two and oftentimes
the speed it isn't so much about
bandwidth in that way that memory
bandwidth is often very good it's it's
rarely about how fast you can transfer
things it's more about the latency it's
more about how long it takes from the
time you start to the time you finish
right it's kind of like a very very big
pipe right that's very long so it's once
you know you're gonna send something you
can send a lot of stuff down it and it
all gets there to the end quite nicely
right but the distance scott traverse is
quite long so from the time you start
sending it if you gotta wait a while to
get it there right and that's pretty
important this is a this there's a lot
of latency in this in this part right so
you got a lot of bandwidth you can send
a lot of stuff down but it takes a while
from when you decide you're gonna send
it you you it's it's not like it normal
memory it's it's you know quite a bit
more so anyway this is the diagram that
we're concerned about and let's just
talk briefly so that you kind of
understand in fact I don't know maybe
since maybe today might be a good day to
just get all of us out in the open so
you kind of have a good feel for it
since we don't have the capture card
anyway maybe we'll just do all
blackboard
who knows I'll go in
as much the detail as I think is
warranted as we kind of go through here
all right so what is the brick like what
what are these things why do we even
have them right I said I used terms to
to explain sort of where it comes from
and implicit in those terms are a whole
bunch of decisions and reasons that we
haven't really stated explicitly so for
example why do we need this DP you like
like why can't this CPU just do the
things that we needed to do like what
what is the idea behind it like what's
going on here right and so the reason is
because these two devices are designed
for very different purposes and they
make different trade-offs both in terms
of their memory architectures and in
terms of their instruction set
architectures so they are getting closer
together but they started out very far
apart so I want to sort of draw a little
bit of a faux diagram here I don't mean
for this to be highly technical but I
want to say something like this is a CPU
in 1999 and this is a GPU in 1999 okay
so before just before the turn of the
millennium and I would say that right
here this might be the just we'll call
it the PU the processing unit of 2030
let's say I don't know maybe who knows
essentially what has happened over the
years is CPUs and GPUs kind of move
towards each other if that makes sense
so they started out very different and
they're becoming very similar so part of
the understanding of why we have two
different types of chips is not as
readily apparent if you look at what the
chips look like today but it's much
easier to understand if you look at what
they looked like a long time ago so a
long time ago what was a CPU well a CPU
was something that was mostly operating
right single instruction single data you
might say right remember we've talked
about Cindy right which is like single
instruction multiple do those those big
why
vectors it was mostly something that
looked more like this where it was like
saying oh I have stuff like you know a
move instruction I have to move like one
32-bit value you know out to some memory
somewhere I'm gonna pull another one in
I'm gonna look at its contents I'm gonna
do a branch right so they tended to be
things that were built for serial
execution right so fast a single thread
you know single line execution so
basically you know CPUs what they tended
to look like is I'm trying to do a
series of operations as fast as I can
those operations operate on one thing at
a time and they're very varied it's a
very random heterogeneous right
instruction stream there's no rhyme or
reason to it it's just whatever okay
meanwhile a GPU is an incredibly
incredibly specific thing and what that
is trying to do is just trying to take
blocks you know and it's trying to fill
them in with pixels so it's just trying
to figure out what on screen is supposed
to fill with pixels and I'm trying to
fill them with predictable linearly or
sometimes perspectively
interpolated color values right so most
of what I need to do is I know I've got
basically these things called textures
which are like images I'm pulling from
very regular very predictable parts of
them right like I'm pulling from
specific coordinates to kind of map them
into here and I'm filling them out sort
of stretching them a little bit just
like we wrote exactly like the kind of
code we wrote but even a little more
primitive than that if that makes sense
and it's very predictable this texture
stuff this is read-only you never write
to it this is basically right only for
the most part but it does have blending
right it's got the ability to like kind
of blend on top but for the most part
you never even really read from this
thing right and that's sort of where
things were you know I don't know the
exact dates here but you know pre
millennium okay and so this thing had a
very specific memory usage it was try it
did very few right
to the texture area and almost
exclusively tons and tons of rights to
this stuff it always kind of read
because of bilinear filtering it always
read and like little quadrants it knew
that it would it would tend to read
little sections out of this right it
would rarely would it read like a whole
row of a texture it much more often
reads like a little chunk of a texture
for whatever part was on the screen it
knows when it's filling it's filling
like generally these little regions
about you know the size of what a
triangle should roughly be on the screen
and so and so forth right very very
regular so these things looked very
different back then as they started to
become more general-purpose here and as
CPUs started running into like heat bear
you know barriers are of how fast they
could run single pieces of code these
two have moved much closer together so
over the years when we got you know to
say where we are right now where it's
like you know it's 2016 and here is GPU
2016 and CPU 2016 these things look
remarkably remarkably similar right the
CPU has either an 8 or a 16 wide right
Cindy unit we talked about this
GPUs actually look a lot like this they
have either a 16 or 32 wide Cindy unit
usually and there's been you know now
there's so much stuff that happens with
shaders and you know we added shaders
which are basically programs the GPU can
act execute we added unordered access
views at compute shaders that could
write to anywhere in memory can read
from every memory basically what
happened is a huge amount of
general-purpose stuff crept into these
and a huge amount of like perf specific
stuff crept into these and so you
started seeing them converge to
something which both could do both right
both the CPU and a GPU are now sort of
set up to do both things and there's
just some because of their legacy that
they do worse than others on either side
okay and so you know a lot about this
architecture we've talked a lot about
this and so what I'd like to do is kind
of give you a perspective of like sort
of what this architecture tour sort of
looks like to have at a very high level
because we don't even really know like
Nvidia won't tell us exactly how their
chip works internally right so we don't
necessarily know but we can give sort of
some examples of sort of how it works
all right so now instead of a device
that's purpose-built for just doing this
like filling triangles in exactly this
way and reading from texture memory and
doing a very specific set of operations
on them all that's out the window
because now we've got shaders on our
backs to do all these things so now what
a GPU actually looks like is usually
just a ton of al use right there are
these these are the arithmetic logic
units these are the things that do like
remember when we did our renderer these
are the things that do like the
four-wide multiply remember when we did
these things are like mm mul PS right
those instructions and they take two
components like an A and a B and it's
like it multiplies a zero times B 0 a 1
times B 1 a 2 times B 2 a 3 times B 3
right you know that
well that is basically what a GPU is a
GPU is a giant one of these so instead
of a four wide one or an eight wide one
with which like the Intel desktop chips
now have eight wide for these they are
more like 32 wide so they're more like
saying hey you know what
or I guess like 16 wide like I said is
another one I think in video 16 wide and
AMD straight to what I don't really know
I have no idea nobody tells me these
things I don't even know might be secret
for all I know anyway they're basically
these giant 16 wide or 32 wide al use so
they basically take in you know some
giant number of floating-point values
right something that looks like this
with literally that many floating-point
values in it and they do some arithmetic
ops on them typically one might be a mad
like a multiply add so it'll take like
an A and
B and a C and do a times B plus C right
it might have that kind thing so a big
old arithmetic operation it can do in
there and they're just set up to do tons
of these and what you see so I don't
know if you guys ever looked at this
maybe you wondered what this was but if
you do like lists and video GPUs or
something like this or you look at how
they quote their numbers you'll see
stuff like a core count or something
they'll list on there right so we come
in here and it'll say something like
let's see processing power band with
transistors I don't know where that is
where is it
they have those you see see if they list
these on if not we can just go to two
and video it's like let's see Nvidia
Titan number of cores okay so this is
what they say right they say CUDA cores
2880 right now you think about that and
you're like well how many cores does my
CPU have any like oh maybe it's got four
cores and you go oh well how many cuda
cores does this GeForce have it's like
2880 it's like oh my god it must be so
much more powerful in a CPU well as you
expect in anything with marketing this
number is completely ridiculous right
what is a coup de coeur where well a
coup de coeur is actually the number of
GPU cores right times the width
oops of the ALU times the number of
values on that core right and again you
know I don't know a lot of the specifics
of these things so I'm just giving you a
baseball park here but if the ALU is 16
wide right then this number is 16 and if
it has say 4 al use on it then this
number is 4 right so the actual number
of cores when they lift something like
this is actually quite a bit lower than
what they're actually saying it's as if
in
divided multiplied the number of cores
by eight because they can do eight wide
instructions and if they have to execute
you you nuts that can each do one of
those right on each core then they would
multiply it by two again so it'd be like
16 times or something right the actual
number that of course that's actually on
there yeah so it'd be something more
like saying oh you know take this number
and divide it by by something big and I
can't they might even do a little bit
more than that like they it might even
be like if they could how many they
could issue I'm not sure it's something
ridiculous but point being this number
is very is has nothing to do with what
you might think an actual core was if
that makes sense I wonder if we can find
some work if someone out there knows
definitively how Nvidia computes their
core account feel free to post it on the
stream because it's it's an equation
like this where the actual number of
cores actually works out to be something
fairly small I don't know let me see
here so twenty eight eighty divided by
64 is 45 right so yeah in this equation
let's say we did this right then the
actual number of cores in this thing is
45 right so yeah it's a lot of cores
potentially but it's a lot less than
twenty eight eighty sounds like right so
just something to be aware of anyway so
what these these things are again is
their cores just like a normal CPU core
as you would expect but and there's a
lot less of them than you think there
are when they write the thing down but
they're simplified so they don't have
nearly as complicated as an instruction
set as an Intel CPU they don't
necessarily have the same kind of
caching or those person because they're
set up for different four source stream
more streaming operation but they're
basically the exact same thing so they
have like all the instructions you
expect to see like a mall and a div and
an ad and whatever they have all those
things although sometimes they're all
done with the same thing so sometimes
you may have something like a multiply
add well if you have a multiply add
instruction you don't need a multiply
instruction or an add instruction you
can just do a mad zero
in one of those places and you end up
with whatever you want or a mad with one
whether it's placing about whatever you
want right okay so that's what a GPU
core actually is and the way that the GP
GPU core works is a lot like what we saw
when we did our rasterizer remember how
we didn't we said oh we can do four
pixels at a time right so what we did is
we said let's do a B C and D pixels at
the same time and well that way we can
fully utilize that system that Intel has
for doing for wide multiplies right well
a GPU does exactly the same thing it
just does it wider now you might ask why
doesn't you know does it do 16 in a row
no and the reason for that is that most
triangles are fairly small right the
higher res the the higher definition the
game.the the more detail the models the
smaller the triangles get triangles
don't usually fill that much of the
screen right they tend to be kind of
tiny and so when you're doing pixel fill
operations it's you kind of want them to
be more square right you want them to be
shaped more like you know like this and
less like something like that because
the time triangles don't tend to look
like that they tend to look more like
that right so what they do instead is
they just add a vertical component to it
instead of just doing four across like
we were doing they do four across four
down so they do sixteen they do them
this way so they basically take you know
pixels they take pixels that look like a
pattern like this and they just unpack
them right you know and well they don't
definitely know unpacking per se but I
mean they just kind of like think of
them this way right so then they do
these giant operations on those and off
you go
okay and they do exactly exactly exactly
the same sort of stuff we did the
triangle probably only touches some of
these pixels they mask just like we did
we had our mass where we were like
writing and we didn't want to write the
final one so we masked it out same thing
it's all exactly the same so the way we
wrote our rasterizer is very very
similar to what these things are doing
internally
right okay so these GPU cores you know
it's got a bunch of those cores and
they're designed to just basically take
share code right that's that shader code
that you write when you see like a
DirectX shader or whatever that kind of
thing shader code which is very much
like CPU code now and they're designed
to execute that 16 or 32 wide that's
what they're trying to do I don't know
if any are 64 oh I don't know how wide
they get but that's what they're trying
to do and so that's why shader is not
quite the same as CPU code and the
reason is because you have to remember
an Intel chip is highly optimized for
executing basically straight-line CPU
code that's got a lot of branches in it
right
it's got jumps branches it's got random
memory access all these things well GPUs
aren't set up to work with that right
they're not made to do this they're made
to do much more coherent code and so one
of the reasons you can't just take CPU
code and shove it into a GPU in expect
that they do faster is because the
degree to which a GPU could be faster
than CPU is entirely dependent on
parallelism and it's dependent on two
kinds of parallelism one utilizing the
fact that there are more cores on GPU
than a CPU you know maybe there's 10
times more cores and utilizing the fact
that the ALU is much bigger maybe it's
twice as big maybe it's four times as
big maybe it's three times as big
something but it's got a boost there
what that means is you have to be able
to go 16 wide you have to be able to go
10 way parallel you have to be able to
do those things with this code if the
code can't do that it's inherently not
gonna get any faster on GPU in fact it
probably will get slower because GPUs
tend to run at slower clock rates with
worse support for arbitrary stuff okay
so with that masking part in mind
remember I talked about the masking here
with that masking part in mind let's
talk about how those ifs work right so
in a CPU you've seen how this works we
say if X you know
do this right maybe let me do something
here y equals 5 if X y plus equals 7
okay so in a CPU what we expect to see
here is something like taking you know
the location of Y so here's the place of
restoring Y we take the 5 in this
instruction and we put it in there
we then load in X so whatever is in X
may be in X is a 1 we load that in we do
a test instruction on it right to see
what it see if it's equal we do some
kind of comparison of some kind and then
we do a jump and we do a jump based on
the result of the comparison so either
we skip the jump doesn't happen and we
do this piece of code or the jump does
happen and we skip over it if we do get
to this piece of code we're then going
to take 7 and we're going to write it
back into here right we add we do an add
instruction and we overwrite the 5 with
5 plus 7 which is 12 right or we don't
so we're used to thinking of code in
this terms where we where we go ahead
and say oh okay do a test jump over so
we think of it as doing like either/or
and maybe there's an else clause here
right so we think of term of code in
terms of either or either or right
if this do this otherwise do that that
is not how anything works in the world
of wide instructions the reason for that
is if this is 16 wide well what does it
mean to do an if we've got 16 different
things here some of them will be yes
some of them will be now what that means
is that in the wide world in the GPU
world all branches are always taken
basically right so what happens is when
you get to an if statement in shader
code what that actually compiles to is
not an if statement at all
it compiles to both branches but with a
mask so it first does a test here to see
which slots of the 16 wide Lane are
going to do which branch right and it
produces a mass that's like oh these are
the places that need to do this branch
then it computes fully the result of
this branch computes fully the result of
this branch
then uses this mask too and them
together and an or you know mask and or
them together to produce the correct
composite result so to the extent at
which this if ever actually happens with
a jump is only if all of them have the
same value basically ifs with a jump are
now just an optimization in GPU land
they're a thing that if you happen to
have all the same value and know you can
skip one whole side of the branch maybe
it will maybe a GPU smart enough to do
that maybe it's not but that's all the
jump is now the jumps in optimization
but it's not the actual control flow the
control flow actually always goes
through both branches conceptually
speaking and the only time that it won't
is if all the values happen to lie in
one side of the other the branch okay so
when you think about how GPUs execute
you have to kind of change your mental
model a little bit into more of the code
is all straight line there is no such
thing as a branch not taken unless
you're optimizing a particular case
they're all taken how does this work
with loops you've seen loops right same
thing loops they loop until the very
last guy no longer tests for the loop so
even if everybody else all the other
lanes had finished and they only need to
do like five loops to this thing but
this last guy at the end he's got to do
like a hundred iterations because that's
just what his lane was set up to do
right you do a hundred iterations on
everybody and every time through the
loop you just throw away 15 years 16
caps and you are sad right now again
that's the basics of GPU
I'm sure GPU vendors do all sorts of
things to try to improve performance
here like maybe they they notice when
you end up with a 4 or 4 split and try
to merge in some other work from
somewhere else you know I have no idea
how sophisticated they try to get with
some of these things but that's the
basic idea and that is why you'll often
see things like they'll talk about a
warp there'll be things that refer to
like everyone in the warp
or something well that's what a warp is
a warp is 16 or 32 guys who's very knit
together and they're gonna take all the
branches and all the loops together
until all of them agree and so the only
time when they actually do any branching
or any terminating of loops is when they
all agree otherwise they're all going
through everything every time always
right and you can see why that's
important to understand from forests
vector because if you write your code in
a shader thinking that it works the
other way you're gonna make very very
different decisions potentially than if
you know that this is the basic way that
it works okay so that's the the basics
of how the GPU execution works the part
that I don't know very much about
because I've never seen any Declassified
stuff about how this works is that's a
part of the GPU that's that's that's all
those a lose that's like you know we
have 48 al use on here or whatever what
I don't know very much is the how the
bookkeeping part of the GPU works
because obviously there's all this
dispatch that has to happen here like
hey go do the transforms on this vertex
buffer hey go fill these pixels hey do
whatever right that part I don't know
very much about and I don't know how
much you can't even know about it if you
don't have some kind of nd egg to
classified information but this is how
those cores work and this now because I
like I said GPUs have gotten so general
this is actually just true it's really
just this no matter what you're doing if
you're filling pixels it looks like this
if you are transforming vertices it
looks like this if you're executing a
tessellation shader it looks like this
it all looks like this now because
shaders have gotten so the ability to do
so much general-purpose stuff that they
really can't design CPUs to take
advantage of any specific thing anymore
like they used to we're not here we're
here so it's really just big old al use
that could basically do anything running
fairly generic code right at a
relatively low clock rate compared to
your GPU the CPU but very wide and with
a lot of those alias right so a lot of
floating-point operations that it can do
all right so that's what a GPU is that's
really what it is and there's some still
special purpose hardware in there for
example there's usually a mem
a unit that's very good at fetching
textures so there's like a thing that
can go fetch and do like a DX TC you
know there might be like a DX TC texture
compression a thing like it hardware
just to get textures really fast there's
usually a texture cache that sits
somewhere in here that's like faster
than the graphics Ram so there's a bunch
of complexity that comes in here to try
and make the GPU fast but at the end of
the day it's just something that's
executing code very much like we see on
the CPU side only instead of having a
lot of like branch enos enos to it it's
it sticks to be very wide very masky
kind of stuff all right so where does
that leave us we're gonna get into some
of that so I want you to kind of be
aware that you have understanding we'll
revisit it later because when we
actually do our GPU code for drawing
anime hero we you know I'll be remanding
some that stuff so keep that in mind but
right now what we have to do is look one
step removed from that basically we have
to worry about how we're actually going
to get the GPU to start doing the work
that we want that's the work that it's
actually gonna do for us right it's got
all these alias it's gonna do all this
stuff for us right but we have to figure
out how to actually get that happening
okay
so this is the diagram that concerns us
what tends to happen the way these
things usually work is there's a concept
that memory is mapped and what that
means is typically some portion of the
system Ram will be mapped such that it
lines up with a portion of the graphics
Ram and so what will happen is the CPU
will say I would like to put some stuff
in here so it will write into memory
that is mapped and that memory will then
get transferred over the PCI bus to
essentially you know fill in what it
needs right that's the concept of mapped
memory and that's just like when two
devices want to have some shared memory
- you know they can map it so it's
mapped in one space mapped another space
now as you might imagine that could go
both ways so the GPU could write things
in here and then I'd see it over here
and again that touch gets transfer to
the PCI bus when there are changes here
they show up here with a change here
they show up here and that's a coherent
like map
everything and you can you know it's a
thing that exists but nowadays as you
can imagine the the graphics workloads
are so heavy that you you typically need
to be a little more aggressive with
things like the way that that works so
what happens now is oftentimes GPUs have
essentially DMA transfer controllers
that they call it copy engines
oftentimes which are parts of the chip
that literally do nothing but sit there
and take instruction from you about
where to grab stuff and they're just
sitting there grabbing things and moving
it into their memory right and I don't
know but I don't think they actually
require much in the way of mapping other
than just it has to be in a part of
memory that the DMA controller can see
and so the mapped concept if you're
actually talking about what happens at a
lower level oftentimes doesn't end up
meaning that we're actually trying to
mirror memory between these two things
what map ends up meaning most of the
time when you're using a GPU nowadays is
just that you put something somewhere in
a range of memory that the GPUs bus
controller copy engines can see and get
right because in general I don't know
the specifics of the PCI bus I was an
amiga guy so I don't know I don't know
PC bus sorts of stuff at all but
basically my understanding is the PCI
bus you know devices have to have mapped
regions that they're allowed to read and
I don't know to what extent they're
actually allowed to read any given
memory but even if they were allowed to
read any memory in the system you have
to remember that the CPU has virtual
memory right we talked all about this so
you know your application sees some
virtual memory space you don't even know
if that memory is all stored in actual
memory right now someone might be paged
out to disk whatever so this guy
the actual GPU when he comes over to get
memory it had better be in physical
memory at the very least right because
if it's off on the disk forget it
he doesn't know anything about the disk
he doesn't know how to access the
harddrive right
that requires CPU intervention and so
what actually needs to happen here more
importantly than anything else is this
concept that we need to map the memory
or whatever we need to lock it down it's
one way to think about it we need to
pick a range of physical memory and
actually say we're gonna leave this in
here and we're not going to let it leave
or get transfer it out or swapped or do
it or anything else until this guy
finishes getting it and we receive
confirmation from him that he no longer
needs it right and so again so this
concept of mapping memory or thinking
about memory that both the CPU and the
GPU can read it tends to end up being a
lot less about thinking of it in terms
of shared memory with like
synchronization between it and more
about transfers where we lock a piece of
memory on the system Ram side and then
we tell the graphics chip either put
some stuff in there please or or move
some stuff out of there please into your
memory okay and so you can kind of see
where I'm going with this that is
exactly what we need to do if we are
going to actually send our image or a
bitmap down to the graphics card so
we're gonna need a way to do that right
but before we can do that even before we
can do that we need something else which
is we need the way to tell the GPU to do
anything at all right because we you
know we could lock down a piece of
memory and put some stuff in it but how
are we ever gonna tell the GPU hey come
get it the GPU needs some way of knowing
what we're even trying to tell it to do
okay and so what's that that's a thing
called a push buffer now you'll notice
we have a push buffer it's the thing
that tells our renderer what to do well
guess what that's modeled exactly after
how the GPU works so what basically
happens is you start off by taking some
chunk of your system Ram you lock it
down and into there your put actual
commands which are like I shouldn't say
commands but basically like an own
binary structured
thing just like our push buffer that's
got like stuff aren't like do this do
that do whatever that has pointers to
other lockdown pieces of memory and the
graphics card is instructed to read from
the top of that and do what it says
right so it grabs that push buffer over
here to its memory presumably starts
executing off of it does the things in
it and in there are things like hey go
grab this other chunk of memory bring it
in here draw these triangles do whatever
load the shader set this state blah blah
blah so the the model of execution you
have to think of in terms of to actually
going on the system is well it looks
kind of like this here is us Chris
handmade hero right and we've got it a
little CPU and the CPU is executing in
handmade hero and that's all great at
the top of our address range right the
OpenGL 32 DLL code the system drivers
and stuff they got mapped in and so once
in a while and handmade hero we got to
do some stuff with the graphics we're
gonna call out to something out here
these are functions again right that are
mapped into our address space when we
load it in that DLL we're going to call
some of these and what they're gonna do
is they're gonna prepare in in some of
our memory right they're gonna prepare
some of this push buffer data right or
something like that
all right they're gonna prepare us we
don't know we can't even see because
this is again in videos code whatever
there to prepare some of that push
buffer data in our memory this is our
memory by the way this is our thing
right hand made here right this is our
code and here's I push buffer here's
some more code from the operating system
whatever this is our main memory so the
CPU is gonna do that the CPU will
prepare this push buffer right and then
at some point and this is entirely up to
the driver and how it choose to do
synchronization whatever at some point
it's gonna take and I assume this has to
happen it's gonna take what's called a
ring transition now you don't really
need to know very much about what that
is but point being CPUs have the concept
of rings there's like typically
ring to ring one ring zero ringing - one
yes that's a real thing and what these
are they're basically privileged
privilege levels for what you can
execute we're just an application we
have essentially no privileges we can't
do most of the things that the kernel
can do of the operating system we don't
even know what the memory map is like we
see a virtual address space right so we
don't even know where the actual
physical memory is we got no idea what's
going on right but the colonel knows all
that stuff and it could do all that
stuff and part of the reason for the
separation is obviously for security and
for stability you don't want like one
errant application to crash your whole
machine if you can avoid it so basically
these rings of privileges obviously on
the CPU I think we've talked on the
before helped to ensure that happens so
at some point after we've built up
something and we need it to actually go
off will actually take a transition into
the actual driver code which is actually
in ring zero right so we happen on some
other ring right that's higher than
moving zero that doesn't have those kind
of privileges then we go to the actual
ring that can actually talk to the
hardware and in here there's like
something that is going to kick off our
push buffer right so this push buffer
might have had like our memory it may
have mapped it to a physical thing this
is our virtual address space right it
may have already been locked a physical
in which case the kick off can kick it
off directly transfer and kick it off
directly it may not have been in which
case what it will do is actually do a
copy first I don't I have no idea that
happens in our our ring or in their ring
I have no idea right but at some point
inside the ring zero at least I assume
you softly ever exerted this maybe
they've changed that who even knows but
at some point it will do what's called a
kick off which is basically saying this
push buffer with all the stuff that you
told the graphics card to do now is
ready to go so start executing it on the
graphics card and that will trigger this
transfer and the GPU will get that and
start working on it right so the mental
model that you should have is looks a
lot like this it should be I've got
stuff in my memory space that I'm
building up with calls to OpenGL and we
can't build it up manually the reason we
can't build it up manually is because we
don't know the format it's different for
every graphics card we don't know what
the push buffer command buffer
stuff has to look like right we have no
idea these are often called command
buffers by the way not just push buffers
we under the format so we got a call and
open jail or again direct3d or mantle or
anything else we have to call into that
to construct these things once we have
constructed them then we at some point
trust that the driver will take a ring
transition kick it off and the GPU will
start doing it right and that's what
happens so it's a very very buffer
driven it looks a lot like our renderer
looks right now you build up buffers
then you say hey go render this and it
does the only difference is instead of
it rendering right then on the CPU it
gets handed off over the PCI bus over
the graphics card where the graphics
card will do it while we're doing other
things we don't wait we just kick it off
it goes and does it and later we get the
results right so that in a nutshell is
what we're going to be doing and so when
we call our OpenGL calls they're
somewhat high-level right cuz they're
their card and mastic so they just kind
of have some basic ideas of the things
that grass don't need to do and then the
driver will take care of translating
those somewhat high-level things into
whatever the actual push buffer stuff
was you need to do now if this were a
locked machine meaning we knew the exact
hardware configuration of it and we had
all the docs and everything you could
imagine doing the low-level version of
this code like on a Raspberry Pi or
something where you know the format of
the push buffer you know how to do a
ring zero kick off of the thing or
whatever you know all that you could
write all this yourself there's no magic
to it it's not like we couldn't write it
ourselves the problem is on a PC
there's no way to write it yourself you
have to run across Walter grabs cards
you have to run on graphics cards are
completely undocumented and that you
don't know the pushover format for so
yeah good luck you got a GeForce Titan
in there you'll never be able to talk to
it with your own code because they won't
tell you how it works right so so
basically what we're doing is we're
calling through OpenGL to do those
operations that we know we could
conceptually think of how to do if we
only knew what the grass art actually
did and we
could abstract across multiple ones
right but that's what's going on so the
thing that we will try to do tomorrow
probably because I'm going to go to
questions here the female will try to do
tomorrow and maybe we'll even have HTML
capture card if I'm lucky the thing
we'll try to do tomorrow is we will try
to do the very simple operation that is
as follows we have our main memory and
we have our screen display
we made this with our own renderer right
what we need to do here's the GPU mem
actually through that a little further
away right what we need to do is we need
to take this and we need to put it into
the GPU memory so that has to happen and
by the way it's this is a bit of a lie
the reason this is allies that GPUs
oftentimes don't store things as
continuous linear bitmaps like we do
they also store them with a thing called
Swizzle
that's designed to optimize the memory
access you don't have to worry about
that right now but just so you know this
is a bit of a lie this might actually
look more like this totally
discombobulated version of that guy so
we need to move our image over right so
that's step one move over I should say
let's just say step one transfer our
bitmap
step two we have to then tell it that we
would like to draw that bitmap to the
screen right so step two is we need to
take the screen and fill it with
probably what will end up being like two
triangles right because GPUs are
optimized for drawing triangles so we
draw like two triangles that encompass
the whole screen okay so we need to draw
two triangles and those two triangles
have to map to our bitmap so we need to
use textures right to grab this part of
this triangle and put it here and this
part and put it there right that's all
we need to do and we just need to do
that with a direct copy right we don't
want no z-buffering we don't want no
shading we don't want no nothing we just
want to be directly written to the
screen and then three we have to display
it and we've already got that right
because you saw us clear the screen and
we did the display so this is all we
have to do it'll take us a little bit of
doing to do it because it's a little bit
cumbersome to do these things because
again once you start talking about going
through api's and there's two separate
sets of memory and all these other sorts
of things things get a lot more
complicated when they're just on a CPU
it's one of the reasons that I really
just don't like the idea of GPUs I wish
that we just had super beefy CPUs the
world would be such a nice better place
be a lot more reliable - but we haven't
ever gotten there someday I hope we do
I'm gonna go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A so
if you have questions about how graphics
cards work or what's going on they're
ones that aren't too Hardware specific
so that I can answer them because I am
NOT a hardware guy so I can't really
tell you some of the real nitty-gritty
stuff but if you have those questions
please go ahead and send them now with a
Q : in front of them and I will try to
give them an answer
ratchet freak you can instead of two
triangles use a single triangle twice as
big it avoids the overdraw at the
diagonal sure yeah you can do lots of
things
you also can just not do a triangle draw
at all right because sometimes they
actually have the constants constant of
AB lit so if you're worried about the
actual speed there's a lot of different
things you can do but I would I would
try to very strenuously point out the
fact that you really should not be
thinking about that in any way at this
point right like literally I have no
idea why that would even be entering
your head at this point because you have
no idea if this would even be slow in
fact I can guarantee you that it won't
be slow the diagonal is so few pixels
that it's literally completely
irrelevant right most of the time you
don't do that operation for speed the
like giant triangle thing this thing
most of the time you don't do that
operation for speed anyway the reason
you actually do it is to avoid that if
it's something that needs to do like a
operation that at at those points if you
operate on them twice you would get an
incorrect result right but the speed
difference between those two is like
really just not very very not important
quick see for you a question all it does
on bare-bones physics level is run
electrons through if statements right go
left go right etc with transistors so I
I think I would say although I'm not the
right one to ask because I'm not a
hardware guy I think I would say more
like it's either go forward or stop
because I believe a transistor usually
is like something like this right where
there's a there's electrons going this
way and there's a thing that will either
stop them from going or let them go so I
don't think they do left or right they
either go or don't go so I don't know
but maybe you're right maybe it's left
or right maybe maybe it's forward or
into the sink right so they do go in two
different directions in that sense I
guess but I don't know I'm not a
hardware guy I know nothing about
hardware can't you run a Xeon Phi as
your main processor or did they make
them dedicated only not like
price-performance makes sense there you
can run a Xeon Phi as your main
processor with the second one I believe
but I you can't quite so the problem
with that is they nukes the texture
units on it otherwise that pretty much
would be exactly what you would want
right but it used to have texture units
and now it doesn't and I don't know if
you can really do high-performance
crafts without texture units I'm not
sure kronole dragon what barriers are
there currently from just using the cpu
as a GPU there aren't any it's just it's
just cost right
so if Intel wanted to like the person
who just mentioned the xeon phi
you know the xeon phi is like faster
than GPU add a lot of stuff big big
computation stuff so you know there's a
few things that GPUs do better based on
how the you know like I said texture
fetching and stuff like that but there
it's just cost its like Intel doesn't
want to sell $2,000 CPUs to everyone
because they know no one would buy them
because I can't afford them right and so
you know at the moment it's mostly about
cost where I shouldn't say cost I should
say margin maybe like Intel wants to be
able to sell chips for $100 or whatever
and make $70 off it or whatever you know
who I don't know what it is they want a
fairly fat Marg in there right they
don't want to do something that's like
$700 that they make six the word they
have to pay $650 in that is cost or
whatever right so like Nvidia and those
people like their margins are I think
much lower than the margins that Intel
has four CPUs and so it's really just a
cost thing I think Intel could make you
know they could make something that was
really fast and was just a single one
that did it but you know a slim seer can
we make a first-person 3d mode of the
game just for education ho keeper Caleb
where does the ps4 exponent processor
lie on the CPU GPU spectrum it's it's
basically like thing it's like a lot
like skylake so where did I draw that
guy I don't know where I drew a lot of
drama game so basically like you know if
you've got like a skylake chip it's
something like you know
get something like this I don't know if
it's actually that way it's I think it's
70% not quite 75 so this might not be
quite right but it's like that and it's
just one chip and then you've got your
memory right and the same thing is true
basically for the AMD like bulldozer
line of stuff right which is like the
expo and the ps4 are basically like you
know we can't know exactly what they are
because they don't let that out of NDA
but you know they're basically like an
AMD bulldozer kind of a type of thing so
it's basically the exact same thing
right it's like oh there's some CPUs and
then there's a big old GPU on a die and
it looks like that or whatever right and
not much is really different it's
exactly the same you know you can
because you that the big difference
really is that because you know that
they're both on one chip you can execute
you can short-circuit things to the GPU
really quickly so you can you know kick
off computation so cheap you're the cook
away you know it's on the same die like
that and so there you don't to worry
about that PCI bus transfer nonsense and
they all got shared memory so it all
just kind of parties out of here it's a
better architecture right like this
would be the best possible thing would
be like if Intel and NVIDIA got together
and just well them together until just
decided to like make some
thousand-dollar chip that had like a you
know 40 cores you know 40 40 I don't
know not 40 I suppose more like 256 ALUs
or something on it or whatever that I
don't know that would be the best
possible thing for sure
Quarter Trump says Intel has killed off
many projects that made good money but
had bad margins yeah exactly I mean one
of the things you have to remember is
that it's a little bit of a problem
where you know when Intel's
when Intel comes out with us with a GPU
and it's not very good or something
right the temptation might be to think
that like oh they just don't know how to
make a GPU as good as in a video or
something right but the reality is that
that's just not the case it's usually
more like they had a very specific price
target and margin target they were
looking for and this was the chip that
fit in that target because Intel's fab
technology like annihilates in videos
fab technology to say the least so you
know if they wanted to they could fab a
pretty amazing GPU I'm quite certain but
that's just not where they're gonna make
their money and so you know if there was
a market for $2,500 GPUs in in enough
quantity
I think suddenly you'd see it Intel one
right and the other problem is software
Intel can't write drivers to save their
life right can't do it no idea how to
make software Intel's never know how to
make software I probably never will
they're getting better than they used to
be but they're really bad and so a lot
of the finesse in getting games to run
well is also at having a well
functioning driver cuz they're very
complicated they do a lot of back behind
the back optimization and a lot of like
you know complex stuff Intel as has
traditionally had a lot of trouble with
that and so that's another big stumbling
block right that has nothing to do with
being able to make a fast heart piece of
hardware so
long billion I've been told that lots of
graphics drivers optimize for specific
games at the driver level how does this
fit into the equation
how did this optimization make some
games run better so what happens with
that is exactly what you would expect
this process that I just talked about
right it's over on the side here
somewhere right so this process where
we're building up the push buffer what
happens is the driver writers will look
and they'll say oh okay you know we we
have our driver fully instrumented so if
we want to we can go and we can run you
know battlefield or we can run Grand
Theft Auto and we can look and see how
it's building up the push buffer is like
what kind of calls is making and what
it's doing and since we know how our
chip works best we can look for ways in
which they could have done what they did
more efficiently and we can make that
happen
right we can it's sort of it's a lot
like a fuzzy match kind of a thing right
it's like oh I know that like in GTA it
does like this command this command this
command this command this command or
whatever right and I know that if I just
did this earlier and switch the order of
these two it would render much faster
right so the driver just does that
behind your back before actually kicking
this stuff off the GPU similarly they
can tune all sorts of stuff about like
how often they kick things off how big
the kickoffs are what they wait for
where the sync points are there's like
all these things like with that sort of
process of managing where the GPU is and
what memory goes where when all of that
obviously what you could imagine is very
complicated there's tons of asynchronous
stuff there they can tune all of that to
the game and make it run better right
and so that's why they do a lot of
detection to see when people are doing
specific stuff and they do that based on
the game often times are like oh I know
this game when it does this thing it's
safe for me to perform this operation so
I do
SSS in the graph why does everyone good
that works at Intel Kate Intel yet
simultaneously Intel's engineering is so
far ahead of everyone else's it doesn't
compute well I mean if you want to make
chips you need that kind of a fab
investment and there's not very many
places very many places that have it so
if you're a very smart hardware designer
where are you gonna go so you may hate
the bureaucracy or whatever else but at
the end of the day if you're gonna do a
lot of chip design stuff I think that's
where you end up right Carrie Johansen
what did you think about Larrabee I love
it I love it love it I wish that Intel
hadn't essentially killed it with bad
software practices I mean that's that's
the long short of it I wish they had had
I wish that's what I was for going on
right now
I wish the xeon phi still had texture
units does Vulcan fix the problem with
opengl of not being able to transfer
buffer objects between processes with
separate address spaces transfer buffer
objects between processes what are you
trying to do that are you talking about
like a chrome style security system why
are you trying to transfer buffer
objects between two processes and no I
would not be allowed to say either way
but I'm curious why you want to do that
not that I think it's bad for it to
support that story I just I just I'm
curious Angus folder Intel's compiler is
meant to be really good right yeah so
apparently like one guy wrote the IPC
thing or whatever the the auto
paralysing one that's supposed to be
pretty good and it's like some guide
wrote it who was really good or
something like that right there are
normal compiler stuff in the past have
not was not that good
let's see can you give us some insight
without breaking any NDA's how different
from open jail console graphics API is
our well yeah I mean so I think the
right way to think of it is more that
none of this stuff really matters at all
it's more about just whether or not you
can count on certain things so the big
difference between programming on the
console and programming on a PC in terms
of how you deal with the graphics card
is not that OpenGL is somehow so much
different the concepts are all basically
the same the stuff is all the same
sometimes you can even run the exact
same shaders right the big difference is
that you can count on stuff like I know
that this chip takes this long to do
this thing I know that this memory is
shared between the CPU and the GPU I
know that the CPU can directly call the
GPU to do some operation right and so
you can bring those things into the code
and use them and those are very
different from what you could do on the
PC because on the PC you could never
write that code it wouldn't run up
abstractly on all the different pcs out
there so that that price you pay for
having a heterogeneous computing
environment is simply that you cannot do
those things you can't do on a console
but nowadays that difference is it's
very small sometimes because a lot of
times now you know you know Sony doesn't
want to tell you how the thing works or
Sony wants to reserve one core for their
operating system so now you can't even
count on using all of the cores of the
thing I read it right it starts to look
as these things become more like
livingroom pcs and less like quote
unquote consoles it's a lot more like
the PC everyday and so the degree to
which you're doing mr. fancy-pants stuff
when you look at like the PlayStation 2
for example versus PlayStation 4 night
and day the PlayStation 2 is like
crazytown and the ps4 is like it's based
like programming PC with some extra
stuff you can do because you know
chrono kun sharing objects weaving
applications without CPU overhead yeah
you got to tell me why you want to do
that I don't know what the use case is
explain to me why two applications want
to share an OpenGL object again not
saying you shouldn't be able do it I'm
just I'm just curious Kaneko's why do
you think there's no games about
programming hardware history of PC
hardware it's the domain is unimaginably
rich I don't know I mean Tia T is 100 I
guess was sort of like that people seem
to think that was sort of interesting on
the other hand it's not like a huge
seller so it's probably like cuz the
markets not that big might be one of the
reasons right
how does G DDR Ram for GPU or concept of
memory chip design specifically for GPU
enter into this picture well it's it's
actually relatively important so again
I'm not a hardware designer so I'm not
gonna try and tell you specifically why
it's important because I'd probably just
be wrong right but let me give you the
gist let me give you the gist of it so
let's take the instruction set designed
by Intel for Cindy and I'm going to show
you something we already did in handmade
hero right in handmade hero we did a
thing where we computed for addresses
for textures because we wanted to do
bilinear filtering right
and I'm sorry because we were operating
for wide I should say right so we had
four pixels now each of those pixels
wanted to look up right into some piece
of memory and grab what was there but
even though we can compute it for wide
we then had to downshift by extracting
each one individually executing a scalar
like a you know you know this is this is
Cindy for wide scalar operation to go
fetch the thing then stick it back up
into the sim D and we had to do that
four times right that's a classic
example of how the architecture of the
memory system is not supporting the
architecture of the computation what we
want to do is have four addresses and
then issue one operation that's like go
fetch them all and it gets them all
right and so what should have happened
and you can see this here see these
fetches see this this nonsense right
here look at this right here's all this
code that's doing four pics of the time
all of a sudden we have to do it
manually right to see how we have to
blow it out - everything is now manually
done four times four times four times
four times always four times right and
that's a classic example of the memory
subsystem not supporting the AL use and
so I imagine and I don't know but I
would I would bet your bottom dollar on
the GPU
you don't see anything like that I bet
you've got a 16 wide fetch that does
full scatter gathers so it just takes 16
addresses it goes out and gets all 16
and brings them back furthermore I bet
that's a texture unit so that those can
actually do the bilinear sampling in the
memory so I bet the memory never even
has to transfer that stuff it probably
can grab up a bilinear sample in like
one go or something right and again
that's all because that memory is
designed fit I just think that's what
should happen with memory like we should
just have that with memory on the CPU -
I would like to see it go that way
because like I said I just want CPUs I
don't want GPUs in the future I just
want a big old beefy CPU but you know
probably not gonna get it
could you one day maybe do a pre after
stream short summary about your thoughts
on os design and what you would do
differently given current hardware
that'll be something I'd probably talk
about in a more formal setting at some
point but it's not gonna be anytime soon
probably in about a year or so I
mustered up one more how come the
witness has four gigabytes of RAM as a
minimum requirement I don't doubt it has
great optimizations as John is an apex
lab programmer is it because nowadays
everyone has four gigs at least and they
thought it's unfeasible or too limiting
to go below that what can be the design
behind that requirement so I feel like
it's probably not really my place to
answer that but the answer in you know
in sort of the abstract sense is that
actually the witnesses memory the way
that their architecture works in the
witness is actually not great for memory
so it does not have great optimizations
for memory at all it's it's it's it's
not prickly good at that and I can tell
you the reason why that is and the
reason is because when they started the
witness John was thinking that it was
going to be a game that would be like
you know 5,000 entities or 6,000
entities to make up the island or
whatever the actual count is like 65,000
I think and it ease and so the game grew
from a code base and never was really
redesigned it grew from a code base
where it just can't really handle paging
very well it has sort of asset streaming
shoehorned in and not a particularly
good way and and the actual footprint of
the game itself just it's not really
designed to to use small amounts of
memory
that said does it actually require four
dicks to run I don't know I'm not really
sure it does you know I think they
probably picked a fairly high number
just cuz why not like any machine that
can probably that's probably fast enough
to run it probably has four gigs of RAM
or something because it's a pretty
graphics intensive game right so I don't
know but yeah it's the reason that if it
does actually take four gigabytes of RAM
and I don't know if it actually does but
the reason is very simply because it's
not designed to be memory optimal at all
it's not even it's not even it was never
even a goal of the development process
to keep that number low I guess is what
I would say so like literally you know I
don't want to say literally but almost
no engineering effort was ever expended
by anybody to to make sure that happened
Elven why does it always seem like PC
games claim that they require much more
hardware power than they need do they
want the extra power just in case
something goes wrong or what well a lot
of the reason is is to cut down on
support right you know you don't want to
necessarily come out and say this is the
absolute bare minimum that my game could
run in because then like some user like
is running like 12 things in the
background and has like their World of
Warcraft game open like doing something
and then you try to run the game and
they complain to you that it doesn't
work on the minimum systems back or
whatever right and so part of it is just
like you don't want to set your minimum
systems back down to like the most rage
of things so if the witness can actually
run in 3 gigabytes of memory they might
not have an incentive to say that they
might be like 4 gig you know make sure
you know don't let's not push it right
and so I think most games probably
followed that better to be safe than
sorry a little bit you want some margin
for error because it does lead to more
support hassle when people because once
you say this is the minimum spec people
are going to expect it to run on that
spec and you're going to get people
complaining if it doesn't so you want to
make sure you don't cut it too close to
the wire right
question having OS level support for GP
resources for computing graphic so that
3d graphics tools can interoperate
efficiently eg in VFX production where
you have lots of tools using the same
data I see so your paints are talking
about you know and this is probably not
quite right but like I've got Mudbox and
I've got Maya and I want them to just
share the same vertex buffer so they
don't have to transfer back and forth
that's a really reasonable I have to say
I don't actually know I if L can does
that or not but I wouldn't be able to
say even if I did I don't think but I
honestly can say I don't remember it was
not a usage case I ever looked at long
boolean what would be a disadvantage of
having a big beefy CPU or are there none
well I mean the disadvantage is the
price
have you seen that guy that is going to
recreate quake and handmade hero style I
I haven't actually watched the stream
but I some handmade gerra people did
tell me about it
which sounds cool I think that's a
really good idea
pumpka pumpka
how long do you expect this project to
take i think i ballparked fairly
consistently that would be something
like 600 episodes and right now we're on
episode 236 so two more years I don't
know at an hour a night it's pretty slow
right and a lot of stuff is like this
where you don't even get any work in a
day because you're explaining things so
what I get fall out for just allocates
itself an 8 gigabyte block that seems
fine to me
I mean if they actually need it if
they're actually doing something with
that I mean you know
quick question about strictly a listing
due to your forum posts not defending it
but how would you propose compilers to
understand that pointers do not overlap
to optimize loads and so on not sure how
we could improve generated code without
having that kind of guarantees assuming
we need to still support old code
I don't want compilers to do that I
don't want compilers to do that when was
the last time in handmade hero which by
the way is doing software rasterization
where we were like oh no we have to
start compiling this in optimized mode
at all no where it's only the pixel fill
right we're not even compiling with
optimizations on the game ran at 60
frames a second the old the pixel fill
is the only thing right so if you just
write relatively same code you don't
need the compiler to be doing these
things for you and so all I really want
is the ability to tell the compiler when
I care these two things don't alias
that's all I need and that's in there
restrict I can tell it that the two
pointers don't don't conflict right so
it's it's it's bad programmers writing
bad code and then compiler writers
deciding to try and optimize that code
for benchmarks or whatever right and
like that that is not how it should go
that is really bad and you end up
costing good programmers the people who
don't care about these things a lot of
time because you introduce bugs in their
code because you choose some strict
random thing in the spec that no one
should ever care about it shouldn't have
been in there as a way of rationalizing
some stupid optimization that's there
for somebody who like instantiated
30,000 levels of templates and was like
bummed that their code didn't run fast
it's awful awful awful awful I hate that
stuff it's bad programmers costing good
programmers Thai and I hate it
and room two out of curiosity back then
when it came out was GDI just a wrapper
for OpenGL do you mean the other way
round when it came out GDI was GDI there
was no such thing as open jail
GDI was Windows as graphics interface
when OpenGL first got introduced into
the windows ecosystem which I believe
was empty 35 1 what it was was a
rendering library that sat on top of GDI
and it was a software renderer so it
rendered in software and output to the 2
GDI so it was literally just a software
under that sat on top of it later as
Hardware became available it started
being able to accelerate and at the time
there was an one like one silicon
graphics card I think you could get to
plug into a very expensive plug into a
PC that did some kind of acceleration I
remember those being around back in 92
or something but I don't I never
actually used one I saw them sitting on
the shelves at Microsoft Qbert Caleb
restrict doesn't seem to work with vs
2013 2015 I don't really know much about
that like I haven't I haven't spent too
much time with it in 23 2013 it used to
work no read isn't restricted like
stupid limited though and you don't have
a leus one that's definitive at least no
mister it doesn't I've never really had
a problem with restrict I mean yeah be
nice if there's a better one that said
like these two pointers don't don't ever
collide whereas this one might with this
other one or something but I've never
really found that to be a problem
why is it the games get more difficult
to play as widows us get more advanced
well it's because the people who
designed the platform's are getting
worse honestly if you're talking about
why they're less likely to run
originally it was just dll's that was
the only thing that couldn't be broken
then you started getting into these side
by side assemblies manifests registry
all that stuff was just really bad ideas
bad design on the windows architecture
and so now it's almost a given that if
you take a game executable it won't run
there's no question they've taking a
modern Amos doodle and try to run it it
won't run you have to install a bunch of
prerequisites first right I think that's
about it we are out of time so I am
going to wind down save this off so I
will hope that I can find some kind of a
Divi Divi a DisplayPort to HDMI
converter or I guess a DVI x2 the slave
port converter either one would be fine
actually maybe well maybe we'll find one
maybe I won't so hopefully tomorrow
we'll have a way I'll do the coding
either way but hopefully I'll have a way
for you can actually see that the
results work so that I'm not the only
one that see but whether they work and
at some point either way I will get the
converter working so that at least by
next week we'll be able to be doing
OpenGL that can stream properly either
way so anyway thank you everyone for
joining me for this edition of handmade
share outs when pleasure cooking with
you as always if you want to follow
along at home you can always pre-order
the game on handmade hero org and it
comes to the source code so you can
follow along we also have a forum site
you can go to ask questions a patreon
page you can use to support the video
series and a tweet bot which tweets the
schedule at you so if you want to know
where we're gonna be live that's the
place to check but I will tell you right
now it's tomorrow at 5:00 p.m. Pacific
Standard Time unless I post otherwise on
the three pot so that's it for today
until tomorrow have fun coding everyone
and I'll see you guys on the Internet