okay hello everybody and welcome to
handmade hero the show we code a
complete game live on stream we are I
think at this point we're sort of ready
to begin some lighting stuff in earnest
because we kind of debugged all of the
crazy things that we had to deal with
getting GPU stuff to work now there will
still be a little bit more GPU debugging
in our future because we've got to
figure out how we're going to compute
the lighting not on the CPU side of
things so we do have a little bit more
unsavory work to go certainly but we at
least got sort of our our basic
framework stuff for the lighting working
so now when we run lighting code in
theory we can have weight or not
did I leave this not actually rendering
any lighting I thought we left it what's
going on what's happening did I forget
where we left this oh oh I don't know
what this is saying my evaluation period
has expired
I never know I was in an evaluation
period well that's unfortunate anyway
let me continue what I was saying before
we deal with Microsoft's the disaster
there I so I thought we had left this at
normal lighting but it looks like we
didn't do that and I'm not sure why so I
take it back let's go ahead and find out
what's going on with that let me jump in
here
oh I remember what nevermind I do
remember I lied we were trying to add
letting direction that's what was
happening so we stopped we had just done
this D bit here so let me quickly
uncomment that so that you can see what
I was about to try and say lighting wise
and then we can go and do that get it
actually working so in here we've got
this this inner product between the
light Direction RGB in the world and
that's actually the part that we haven't
done yet so that's that was why I guess
we did leave it intentionally that way
so this was where we left the lighting
and we were about to put lighting
direction in there the point of lighting
direction was we're now now that we have
something that you can sort of see is
starting to resemble a lighting solution
although isn't quite there yet you can
kind of see that it's like yeah okay you
know I could believe this will someday
compute some lighting it sort of looks
like it's actually working per pixel and
kind of relevant to where the lights are
and all that good stuff but when you
take a look at it you can kind of see
that the surfaces themselves don't know
where the light is coming from right so
if you see like around here that should
be a hard edge this is two sides of a
cube right so it's this but instead of
being a hard edge it's just sort of this
gradient wash and the reason for that is
because it has no idea where the lights
coming from so it doesn't have the
ability to attenuate lighting reflection
or change lighting reflection in any way
based on the facing direction of the
surface versus the light source because
while it does know the facing direction
of the surface it does not know the
facing direction of the light source so
it can't do the standard reflection
computations that you might want to do
to improve the quality of your lighting
and take into account surface direction
which is a pretty important lighting cue
for people now maybe you want lighting
that looks like this and that's fine
there's nothing wrong with that but it's
just not probably what you want because
it's pretty far from the way lighting
would actually work
so what we were gonna do is we're gonna
go ahead in here and put in a
contribution from the light direction
and that's what we ended with last time
that's why it was black because here we
have doing the dot product with the
lighting direction and the surface
normal of the surface and the problem is
just we have not yet set down the
lighting direction right so what we
wanted to do is now be able to send down
the lighting direction which might sound
easy but it's actually takes a little
bit of work on our part the reason it
takes a little bit of work on our part
is because when we compute our lighting
solution remember we're computing an
aggregate lighting solution for various
places in a voxel right we're using
these light sort of reflectors to
compute an approximate lighting solution
for the scene and we're kind of eyeing
getting that down to the GPU at some
point so we're kind of doing we're
certainly not doing anything like ray
tracing per pixel anything that we're
doing sort of some loose ray tracing for
some sort of sparse elements of the
scene to try and create something we can
use to approximate the lighting
everywhere to sort of a low fidelity
result and in doing so we don't actually
know where the light is coming from
because we're not tracking that
information yet so in here where we pack
these values together you can see this
where we packed down the color we also
want to be able to pack down the normal
and so in order to do that we need to
get it from somewhere you can see us
getting like stuff like the emission
coloring out here what we need to be
able to do here is also get the D value
out and so what I'm gonna do is say I
think we already put it in here actually
here's a lighting element and you can
see that I put in sort of like this
situation here that's sort of what we
want to get out of it we're gonna ignore
incident light for a moment we're just
gonna use average direction to light and
that's the thing that I need to fill out
so for right now we're gonna do that and
we're gonna have to track that value so
as you can see that hasn't actually
helped us at all right we're still gonna
be black because we're not filling out
average direction to light but that is
our goal for today is we want to start
filling that out so here we are in
lighting test I don't know why this
ambient inclusion crap is still in here
because we don't use it anymore and I
don't think we're gonna so I made just
nuke it it's it's just bad it was just
in our way what I could do is just do
this that way it's not in our line of
sight anymore and here's our compute
lighting function you can see us doing
some iterations here we then do ray
casting so on and so forth
and so now we restructured this loop at
the end of last week to not be so weird
it was kind of weird because we came at
it at a weird angle so it wasn't really
written as a straight forward ray cast
now it is written in a straightforward
ray cast you can see that there's some
number of iterations that are gonna be
done in average together there's a
destination index which is to say each
lighting element we're gonna step
through in series and do a bunch of ray
casts together lighting from it again
this is not intended to be a final
starlit style loop it's just intended to
do something that we can practice with
to get our lighting solutions to
someplace we want and then we'll worry
about optimizing them later so then
here's our ray count we're going to cast
a trays at the moment but that's an
arbitrary value can set to whatever you
want just makes it more accurate and
slower as you increase it we then go
ahead and go through it's an N squared
algorithm we go through every that's why
I say we're gonna have to optimize it
eventually it goes N squared is the slow
thing we're gonna go through all of the
sources which are basically the other
lighting elements in the scene and we're
gonna cast rays to see whether or not we
can hit them whether or not we hit them
whatever the closest one is that we get
right we then say that's the one that
would contribute from this ray and so
here is the case where we did hit
something right because you might hit
nothing and we might want to have
something that happens when you hit
nothing as well you might get incident
light from say skylight at that point or
something like that like an ambient
light okay so once we get in here you
can see us taking a look at what the
light is I don't think we really need
this light distance thing but it's fine
to check anyway if two things were right
on top of each other for some reason we
just want to avoid doing anything stupid
so here where we've got all of our
lighting stuff what you can see us doing
here is computing the the lighting and
accumulating the total light
contribution what we really want to do
here is start to expand this tracking to
yeah you can in fact you can kind of see
here you can kind of see here we have
some weird remnants of stuff and like we
should just clean this up a little bit
so that desk visibility isn't really
being used anymore if I remember
correctly so you can kind of see this is
a thing that gets computed in this
ambient occlusion stuff I just don't
like this stuff this is we kind of we're
looking at an old paper and we did some
of the stuffs in there I'm you know it's
just bothered me so it's just gonna go I
mean we have a github and we have the
old source zips if we ever need to grab
it out again we can I don't like that so
I'm gonna just start simplifying this
down cuz I just want to get rid of
things that I don't want in there where
is that there it is so in the lighting
element I'm gonna say we don't have this
anymore this is not there anymore that's
going away the static information is the
stuff that comes in so that's all fine
the reference color the transparency the
radius the position in the normal right
so now let's start to try and work with
this other stuff and let's try to make
something reasonable so we have this
front emit color in the back emit color
at the front emit color and back
macclare are how what kind of light were
shining out on us
and that is all well and good but the
problem is we've sort of got to again
we've got to sort of things and I'm
comment this as well should we do at the
same time we sort of have two different
things that are happening here right one
thing that's happening here is when we
want to we want to collect the light
that's coming into a surface and then we
want to reflect it out on other things
as we do our iterations for a rate for a
ray casting right so we kind of have
this sort of dual problem there's a
couple of different ways we can look at
this one way is we can not convict that
light around you know let me just draw a
diagram because this is this is
complicated enough that I feel like I'm
gonna have trouble explaining it without
a diagram
so we've got a couple of different
things but think about it this way so
let's say this is an emitter so this is
set to actually radiate light outwards
and let's say this is just a standard
reflector so it doesn't have any
emission but it does reflect light and
here's the person we're computing okay
so what's gonna happen here is we're
gonna start casting rays out from this
thing now one of the Rays might hit the
actual emitter and when it hits the
actual admit err that's fine we know
exactly what's gonna happen here right
whatever the emission is of this it's
gonna send that light to this surface
and that lets us know some incident
light so if we wanted to store if that
was the only way we were sending if we
wanted just to store the incident light
and the average direction that that
light was coming from we know exactly
what it is it's however much light this
is emitting and whatever the Ray
direction was right that's all there is
now let's say there's a second emitter
this is emitter - and one of our rays
also hits that so we catch two rays and
we can hit both of them well what we can
do is just add the incident light
together right so we can have incident
light you know from one plus the light
from two right so it'd be like emit one
plus admit two for both of these right
and then we average the two directions
together to get an average incoming
direction and again not a perfect
legging solution but in terms of just
figuring out what the average is there
we go now we could do a little bit
better than this
if we want to because we can take a look
at the magnitude of each of these so if
this was really bright and this was
really dim we could wait the normal
towards the bright one because that's
gonna give a more accurate reflection
since the majority of the light is
coming from emitter one if the normal
was more bent towards emitter one we
would end up with a better approximate
lighting solution by saying that the
average incoming light Direction is
actually that way not halfway in between
them since not very much light is
actually coming from inner - right
again none of this is perfect and again
this is also where people start getting
into a lot of crazy stuff if you want to
try and do better approximations to it
this is where things like spherical
harmonics come in basically there are
other ways I've mentioned this in the
stream before I'll just mention it again
there are other ways of encoding light
that get increasingly more complicated
sometimes they're good sometimes they're
bad they have drawbacks for alarm onyx
in particular has drawbacks of there
being very hard to transform and stuff
but if you become familiar with a
particular representation such as severe
achill harmonics you can get pretty
facile with it and figure out how to do
things that will lead to good results
that aren't too expensive to compute so
there are other ways of trying to encode
more information than just what the
direction is on average you can try to
encode information about how it varied
as well
right so if you want to try and get a
more accurate lighting solution you can
try some of these things so anyway so
that's pretty straightforward and that's
something that we should be able to
that's something that we can mimic
pretty easily right
not much there's not much fanciness
there I think hopefully everyone sees
how we could modify that loop to do that
but the other thing that we might want
to do is do this in an iterative fashion
that's more like radiosity than it is
like ray tracing and what I mean by that
is now let's take into account
reflectors this is pretty
straightforward because it's just ray
casting to admit errs so there isn't any
ambiguity about what we might want to do
once we introduce reflectors which are
things that don't emit which is most
surfaces but that we do want to bounce
light to us so we can have some indirect
lighting which we would like to have
because direct lighting is not
particularly interesting once we want to
have indirect lighting we do have a
problem about how we're going to compute
that so one way to compute that is you
always do the Ray casting again right so
we do a ray cast out to here we find
this reflector and then we say okay well
let's cast another ray and see if we hit
an emitter right the reason that that's
particularly problematic is because it
leads to having to do a lot more ray
cast
than you would like so what we would
rather probably do is allow the emitters
to spread out to the reflectors first
instead and then when we hit a reflector
we know to grab it back right so the
problem here is that it's like we may
want to do some amount of forward
propagation and then do our gather and
so it's just like with anything else
it's just a question of how we want to
do it and I'm not sure exactly what the
right mix is one you know one way to do
it is to always just do ray casting the
entire time that probably will be pretty
expensive for us so the way I was
thinking of doing it is more like where
we spread things out so what I think we
might want to do here is create a simple
final gather loop that literally just
casts out rays from this surface that
we're computing and it just averages the
results it sees probably based on
magnitude so it a ver ajiz the color and
then averages the normal weighted by the
magnitude of the color that is probably
what we should do and then what we'll do
is split instead of having that pass
also be the thing that propagates light
instead what we'll do is we'll make it
so that the emitters we do one phase
where we let emitters spread out two
reflectors and then emit reflectors will
propagate out again so what we'll do is
we're here we've got this iteration
going on we will now have that Globo
rendering lighting iteration count that
will only be for spreading out emission
and then at the end we'll have the final
gather right sue me for one second I
still can I did unlike normally when I
just have screwed over any nose I think
I am coming down with a little bit of a
cold
it doesn't actually bother me much but
does make me stuffy
okay so that's what we want to do and
that's why I say we kind of have some
other stuff here so like incident light
an average direction to light will be
the things that we will actually encode
and then like front emit see and back
emit see would be the things that we
will want to those will be the things
that we'll just use for that propagation
pass now the structure of this is
rapidly turning away from the original
structure that we had but that's okay
like I said we didn't know going into it
how are we gonna do lighting lighting is
one of the worst problems in computer
graphics everyone does it differently
it's always a giant hack and the reason
is because hey it's really really hard
the real world happens to do a really
really good job of lighting by using
massive route force it just sends
billions and billions and billions and
trillions and trillions and quadrillions
of photons all over the place and it's
really hard to match that it's hard to
match it with you know like when
typically when we have something like
that like a situation like this where I
have like a rigid object yes
nature uses billions and billions of
atoms to encode what's happening to this
thing fortunately for us they all stay
in a very rigid lattice structure most
of the time and especially to our eye
just look like they're all moving is one
giant piece or two giant pieces in the
case of the pliers which is why we can
do such a good job approximating those
things lighting not quite so much
lighting actually propagates all that
information all the time using billions
and billions and trillions and trillions
of little pieces and approximating that
is just really hard for us that's why
everything's always a hack so again
moving away a little bit from the scheme
we had before but that's quite okay
because like I said this is
retort process if ever there was one and
we're just kind of flailing around to
try and find something that works well
with what we've got set up that isn't
too expensive and will possibly be
gpu-accelerated
in the future so that we can kind of
move everything down there in a couple
weeks when we have something that we
think looks ok and then we can just sort
of have an okay lighting solution that
our game can run through so all right
what we want to do then is is split into
two phases I think and I'll just
separate these into two functions so we
could see them a little bit clearly here
so what I'm gonna have here is I'm gonna
have like a light propagation function
and then I'm gonna have a final gather
I'll you know I'll stay away from the
turn of art for now I'll just say like
I'll say gather final lighting this is
called a final gather because in in the
rendering literature and maybe not so
much the running literature in rendering
practice I guess I would say that phase
at the end where you say all right I've
done whatever lighting computation I'm
going to do for figuring out the
lighting of the scene but now I actually
want to go back to all of my surface
points that I care about and compute the
actual lighting for output that thing is
typically called a final gather and you
can see why because it's like okay I
push light all through my scene however
I was gonna and now I'm gonna like grab
that lighting in for any given point
gather it up and compute the lighting so
final gather typically is that phrase
I'll stay away from it because it's no
kind of a weird way of saying it so what
we want to do here is we kind of have a
little bit of annoyance we've got
something that essentially is completely
we've got two passes are very similar
they're both going to do that ray
casting and I don't really want to
duplicate the code for it because as we
change these you know as we as we
how these lighting elements are computed
or stored I would have to change both
functions a lot in identical ways which
seems annoying so I also need one more
function here that these will both call
per element that they're computing and
that will probably be the raycast right
so this part here that we've got this
ray index part here something like this
is going to be sort of pulled out right
so we're gonna have a thing here that's
like our ray caster and so what I want
to do here is I want to have a way where
I can just say like all right we've got
some number of rays we're gonna cast at
the moment again that was set to eight
and that's fine for now but that's
something you know a value that will
actually think about a little bit later
and what we need to do here is probably
abstract out this ray Direction bit in
fact we may want to just call this ray
cast multiple times I don't it's a
little bit hard to say but yeah I think
we probably want to call them all the
time so maybe we want to stop it more
like here right
so we're gonna come through here go
through all of our source indices we're
gonna see whether or not we should skip
it
so we'll probably still want that skip
index in here because if you're casting
from a particular element you don't want
to test against that element because
it's there coincident and you may record
a zero interaction that's right there
and so you just want to make sure you
skip that so they don't mm-hmm if we
loop through each of the lighting
elements in series and we get what we
think is the the source normal and we
check to make sure it's actually
pointing back towards us I guess is what
we want to do there yes so that's just
avoiding the case where we wouldn't
intersect and also making it so that
we're not casting against the behind of
things that's not really correct in this
case so what I would point out there is
since we want to use front and back you
meters because we have a lot of things
in the scenes we have a lot of like
cards in the scene so although it's more
expensive I think what we want to do
here is actually have a like I think we
actually want to have something that's
like front or back right
so we'd set it to like one if it's front
and zero if it's back so I think we want
to do here is say something more like we
we will you know we'll return a boolean
that says whether or not we hit will
encode a result that says you know
here's whether or not it was the front
or the back of the thing and here's what
the source was right the other thing we
could do is just put the source
information in here so the other you
know the other thing we could say is
like well here's the like we could copy
the information out right
maybe let's maybe let's do that
so maybe what we'll do there say alright
we've got sort of the the thing that
comes back in fact we could yeah yeah we
could do that so what we could do is any
time we're gonna raycast we could
basically just say look let's just
return whatever the
you know the contributing color and
direction you know the direction that's
the ray direction so maybe we just say
what the contributing color is because
we're only convecting light around here
so we could do is say look there's a v3
that comes back that's the color that's
all we're gonna do right and that seems
reasonable enough because we can
actually yet we can handle everything
else from there I think and it should be
okay I think yeah all right so if we
loop over the source sources we do our
tests we see whether or not we hit
something
so in this case we suite what we want to
do is say did we hit the front or the
back right so what we're looking here is
we're looking to see whether or not
whether or not we hit the front of the
back like so it would look like that
right so we don't need to know whether
we hit the front or the back or nothing
and the way we're doing this is saying
well if the normal is pointing back at
the Ray right so if the normals pointing
back at the Ray here's the Ray here's
the normal if the normals is not
negatively with the Ray we know that
this is a service that's aiming at us
right but if the opposite were true if
it were pointing this way right then we
know we're hitting the back of the
surface so we have both cases and we
need to handle or want to handle both
cases right
so what we need to do here is say all
right if we hit the back of something or
we hit the front of something we need to
know which one we did and we need to
propagate those properly and again we
don't have to use vacuum ition we could
try just using front and I'm just not
sure let's think about this as well so
what we could do is we could say that
when you have a surface that's got two
sides to it we actually put two emitters
in there and the reason I'm thinking
about this and I'm sort of stopping
myself and going hey maybe I want to do
that is because we do have things like
the cubes where the back faces shouldn't
be considered right we only want to
consider the outward ones so I'm
starting to think to myself maybe what
we want to do here is say that we only
have one direction the band One
Direction like I actually want the band
One Direction to be a in the game on
every surface we'll just text your map
like their latest album cover
I don't know what that would look like
so we'll just take this right here this
picture I and and we'll text your map
that on all of the surfaces right in the
game and that'll be that'll be perfect
that'll be great all right so we want to
say that there's just one direction for
lighting element right and we'll put two
elements together if we you know just
sort of slightly separate it if we want
to start simulating things that are
two-sided like the cards as if they
actually are two-sided right which we
may very well want to do like I said
that may become necessary to get some of
the lighting effects that we want in the
game so but I just don't want to
complexify it by saying everything's got
two sides because if I do that then I
have to pay for both sides of lighting
even for all the cubes which there are a
lot of that don't actually have two
sides right and so we don't want to do
that for everything so I'm gonna say
let's keep it like this and that there's
only one you midsi so I'll do it so loop
over the source is gathered them out if
I when I do the raycast if I happen to
be facing this side of it so it could
potentially be a hit I care about do the
actual intersection we want to only
compute this if it's the closest hit
that we got along this ray so this part
should still be in here don't we have an
r32 max
we never changed the name of this did we
oh it's you know what that is the new
name nevermind
they can pick an old-school all right so
we got an f32 max we pick the closest
hit and when we find the closest hit we
just need to store the color right so
all we need to do here is say well
whatever the source was let's store that
color so I'll do results equals source
emit color we don't need to record the
hit the which one we hit anymore at
least not for at the moment
and off we go so that raycast will tell
us what the color is that we're getting
back and that's all fine I don't know if
we need this acumen see anymore we may
not depending on how it looks down below
but I'm pretty sure we can actually
simplify that as well all right so this
recast will take the closest thing and
it will give us whatever the emission
was that was coming back along that Ray
and that's exactly what we wanted so
then we come down here to compute like
propagation and we know we can use this
ray cast to do it now I'm gonna skip it
for now and instead I'm gonna go right
together final lighting reason I'm going
to do that is because gather final
lighting is actually the thing that we
want to is the one that's close to what
we're already doing so I can basically
just take the COBE ad before and and
sort of use the raycast function to just
do exactly what we were doing so this
whole thing here can just come through
and and be done right the other loop is
gonna be a little bit little bit
different well it's not gonna be that
different but it's fine
all right so here's our gather final
lighting code I still would like to do a
ray count here this ray count may go up
because for gathering the final lighting
we may want to cast more Ray's for
gathering final lighting because it will
not have any iterations right so it may
be that like you know compute light
propagation looks like this and casts a
trace for propagation it may be that we
do like double the ones here and there's
no iteration at all because we only want
to go through the lighting Alice wants
to do our final gather right so we'll
come through here so this part again
would only be in here potentially but I
don't even know if it's going to quite
look like that so let me gather the
final lighting we're gonna go through
each of the destination things here what
are we using the two camera for oh
that's the look direction for the action
that's fine that's when we actually
compute the how the light is gonna
bounce back so so yeah and that's we
don't even want that because then
that'll get double counted so we don't
even need I'm pretty sure this is not
necessary because we're only going to
compute what the lighting incident on
the surface is we're not going to
compute the reflection so there's two
camera part where we would be doing
where we're looking at it from that's
gonna happen per pixel later so we don't
even want this anymore right that goes
away all right so we go through our
array indices here we compute the rate
erection by getting a random number
which we want this closest hit stuff
source element nonsense blah blah blah
that all kind of goes away because now
that's in a function right we've got a
compute whoops we've got our raycast
function here now what we can do is say
we could have an actual boolean that
comes back because we actually know
whether or not we hit anything or didn't
hit anything but I'm just going to
assume that we always hit something and
the reason that I'm gonna assume that we
always hit something is because we
always do in the real world we always
will hit something and in theory there
should have been light on it the chances
that the light will be zero somewhere
should be like non-existent so we're
always going to assume that we hit
something even if it's a skybox or a
very dim thing corner of the world most
of the time we hit something so I'm not
gonna try to optimize the case where we
don't because that's a case we actually
don't want we don't want the game to be
pitch-black anywhere unless it's like a
level with no light in it where you're
you know you shouldn't even really be
there because you don't have a light
source yet or something like that that's
not something we need optimize for
because most of our scenes will have
light everywhere so we need it to run
fine when there's light everywhere so
optimizing for that cases is meaningless
right so what I want to do is I want to
call our ray cast and I realized I
didn't actually pass anything to the Ray
class yet so lighting oops
bang solution
what we're gonna skip and then the Ray
direction and the Ray origin I will need
as well what did we call that in here a
relative source key is source P and s P
so okay so we just have to replace death
P right wheezing despi there that's
gonna be ray oops origin so there's our
Ray origin and Ray direction it's gonna
do a light cast from there and that
should be all the information I think
that we need right I don't think there's
anything else so that's the the function
we're gonna call here is compute light
propagation which we're skipping for now
and so then I'll do here is call bar ray
cast I passed the lighting solution to
it we know we're gonna skip destination
index because that's where we're casting
from and we don't want to do that one so
we have our ray direction and our source
location here's the raycast
here's the incident color it's coming in
and what I'd like to do now is go ahead
and do some computations with that
result that we get back and I'm gonna
ignore this accumulator for now so as we
gather the lighting we're going through
we're gonna get a bunch of incident
colors back one for every ray that we
cast we now know two things about it we
know the color that was coming back from
that ray and we know the raider action
itself that we use to gather it right so
now what we want to do we don't need
this in fact I don't even know why we
were calculating it to begin with again
this is just sort of the fact that this
was kind of old code we must sort of
massage it a bunch of times in order to
kind of get like you know in order to
sort of put it into the final form we're
constantly trying things and
experimenting so stuff gets in there
that doesn't really make any sense we
don't need to compute this cuz we know
what this is this is the Ray direction
right we know that this was the
that we were you know gathering light
from so that's really not important to
have there right okay so when we're
gathering this up we don't really need
to know any of this stuff it's just not
important this is what we actually have
so now we've got sort of our light color
this is the incident Co that's coming on
the surface this is multiplied by the
reflector we don't want that right so
that multiplication by the reflection is
something that's going to have to that
wants to happen out here instead right
that's something that's gonna happen on
light propagation not something that's
gonna happen when we're gathering now
why is that again that is because what
we're trying to compute here is the
incident light on the surface because
we're trying to collect information
about incoming light so that per pixel
in the pixel shader later we can compute
what the actual reflected light is from
a particular surface element and in
order to compute the reflected light
from that surface element we need to not
have taken into account any reflection
here because it will be wrong right so
what we're trying to do is just gather
the light that comes in and save just
what came in and then later we'll do the
reflection computation okay so we've got
a distance fall-off here and these are
always the kind of things that are a
little confusing in a since I'm not a
ray tracing guy it's something I always
have that kind of scratch my head about
in general light along array doesn't
diminish right so I don't actually know
if this fall-off really should be here
the inverse square law says that it
should right but the fact that we're
casting Rays as samples into the world
would automatically do that so it's kind
of right it's kind of
difficult to wrap your head around
sometimes for this sort of thing where
the different lighting aspects come from
but if you think about what I'm saying
so let's say I want to know how much the
light from this emitter contributes to
this surface right well we know that the
inverse square law says that as the
light comes in this direction it gets
dimmer proportional to the square for a
diffusive mitr right for I'm sorry for a
diffuse reflector right and the reason
for that is because as you know however
many photons are coming out of here they
get sparser and sparser the further out
they go right if I'm emitting photons
from this thing then these two right
here you know might have hit a surface
that was this far away that was this big
but if I move it this far away all of a
sudden this photon hits and this photon
doesn't right so as you get further from
the light source the number of photons
that are going to be the density of
photons in any given area diminish
because they're getting further apart
they're separating right but we are
casting Rainey's out from the surface
that do exactly that
right the Rays themselves are separating
and are less likely to hit anything out
there that that we encounter so I'm
gonna say in my non render guy way that
may very well be wrong that we don't
want to include a distance modulation
here because the raycast
itself already has that inverse-square
gather built-in and if we were to on top
of the sampling itself including the
fact that it will be less likely to hit
surfaces based on direction if I were to
go ahead and put that lighting distance
consolation in there I might
double-counting right so it's a really
tough thing to call it may be that this
is not enough raised to really
incorporate that effect sufficiently I
don't know so you know this is the kind
of thing that I would go study if I were
doing this for reals reals like if I
really wanted to get to the bottom of it
it's also something that we could ask a
hardcore rendering guy about they would
know the answer to this problem
pretty cold because it's basically a
question of whether you're sampling
already takes into account a lot of fact
of the lighting or whether you need to
take into account it it into account
yourself right so right now I'm gonna
leave it out it may be that it should
have been kept in as this number gets
high enough I'm pretty sure it needs to
be taken out cuz as that number gets
high enough the sampling definitely
includes this information right I mean
at the limit if you imagine casting
billions of rays out from the surface
the inverse square law would then
naturally be applied because the
averaging that occurs over all of those
incident lights will naturally produce
an inverse squared gather from the
surface so my only question is when this
gets down to low is that now the wrong
way to think about it I don't think it
is I think it still is it just means
your lighting solutions kind of been
accurate um but that's just true I mean
what you know oh well so I don't think
adding in a term that would diminish it
is gonna fix it right I think you just
need to cast enough razor to make it
work all right
so as we go we have our reflection
normal again that's not important we
don't need any of this stuff the
specular power distance fall-off none of
that stuff is getting included in here
at all although you know what I should
probably save a lot of this stuff
because for the gather stage this stuff
is possibly important so I'm gonna move
that stuff out here
all this stuff like diffuse inner
diffuse contributes to pull use some of
it we won't let me just go ahead and cut
and paste it all up here so that we can
look at it again final Gallic summits
gonna go there but most of it is not is
gonna stay in in the in the propagation
routine and won't happen the final
gather so we'll get back an incident
color that's what's coming in I we still
probably want to do the cosign so I
think we even don't want to do that I
think we just want to do a straight-up
we just want to straight-up some these
guys based on their intensity I think
that's all we really want because stuff
like this diffuse inner product to
figure out how much contribution the
light has to the surface I think we
actually want to save that again for the
pixel shader because that's where we
would use that information based on the
surface properties of the thing we're
lighting so I think none of this stuff
wants to happen I think that's all stuff
that has to happen up here in the light
propagation and not mmm I think none of
that wants to happen in here so I think
everything is just going to be we get
back an incident color we do none of
this all we're going to do is say okay
when we get back the incident color we
first want to find out how much incident
color there is so we want to do like a
waiting and
so we want to get back to waiting and
that's going to be based on how strong
the light is that comes in we then want
to accumulate this value so we've got
two values that we're accumulating we've
got the incident light and the weight
and really if we want to we can do these
in place but I'm not going to so we've
got an incident that we've got the
incident light accumulation and we've
got the weight accumulation so they can
divide them out well you know what even
that I guess we don't really have to
well yeah all right so I'm gonna take
the incident light that comes in I'm
gonna multiply it by the weight that we
compute right oh sorry no I'm not
that's what okay yeah God will could use
there it's the incident direction that's
the one I wanted so I'm going to take
the incident color and just sum them
because all of the stuff coming in is
will count for now
and I'm not sure how correct that is but
I think it's roughly correct it's hard
to say so anyway yeah I take the
incident color I'm going to accumulate
that I'm going to take the incident
direction and I'm accumulating that but
I'm going to accumulate that based on
the weight so that the stronger the
light is the more it contributes to the
normal and I guess then I think about it
I don't even need to accumulate the way
because I'm just going to normalize that
direction at the end so I think this is
correct right I think that's really all
we're doing we're getting back an
incident color and we're accumulating it
we're getting back a sort of weight that
we use from that that we're going to use
to sum the directions and then when
we're done we just soar these back so
then we take the destination I was
correct in that this is not necessary so
then we have an incident light here and
an incident direction
oops caps lock
and that's just a normalized version
right because we know the length since
we know this normal has to be a normal
it has to be length 1 normalized
normally what we do when we sum up
things that are weighted is we record
how much weight we had so that we can
normalize at the end right but in this
case we don't really have to do that and
the reason we don't have to do that is
because we know the normal just has to
be a length one so at the end whatever
direction it's pointing we just make it
be length 1 in that direction and we're
done so yeah the weight doesn't have to
be tracked like we normally would so
this is a pretty concise easy to
understand loop now I don't know how
great it is but you know it is what it
is we're basically just casting out as
many raises we decide we want to to do
our our final gather we sum up all of
the incident colors so that's the total
amount of light hitting the surface is
stored in the surface and then we just
average the normal in a weighted average
based on how intense the light is and we
don't know what this value should really
be right now it's the what's called the
two norm right it's the length of the
vector of color which is a reasonable
approximation but it might not be the
one we want we may want to use squared
like length squared we may want to use
the sum of the lighting values there's a
lot of ways we could do that right and I
don't know what the best way to do that
would be but there you go
so there's our gather
I'm pretty sure that all we really want
to do here is say okay when we do gather
find the lighting it's like this is
probably gonna want to do this in both
cases we're gonna do gather final
lighting on the solution and that should
just work so now we just have to focus
on the propagation phase compute light
propagation and taking a look at this
function mostly what we're gonna have to
do is readapt it and sort of clean it
out but it's mostly get this this is the
function that's going to have to do the
actual light computation to figure out
how things bounce around the scene right
so this was gonna have more lighting
actually in it so compute oh and this no
longer happens oops
so we extract our reflectors we compute
the propagation between those reflectors
and then we gather the final lighting
and that is what we will send down to
the graphs card for use of per pixel
alright so for computing light
propagation again same basic idea but
this time what we're sort of trying to
do is do some series of iterations that
bounces light around the scene right and
this we could do in a number of
different ways but I think what we want
to do is kind of switch around how we're
looking at it
[Music]
because I think we can optimize it quite
a bit by doing it from emitters forward
instead of doing it from reflectors
backwards right and here's why so let's
suppose I do it because there's two ways
you can do this right
one way it can do it is I can loop
through all of the reflectors and do
raycast
outwards to find emitters right the
other way I can do it is loop through
all the emitters and project outwards to
generate new emitters with every one I
hit the reason I like going through the
emitter is better is because there's
only very few emitters when we start
each scene may have like five thousand
reflectors and only like ten emitters or
something right
twenty emitters who knows how many but
there's a lot less services emitting
light than reflecting light so on the
first pass we can just not begin to skip
anybody who has no emission value right
so I think that's what we want to do
there and I guess now that I think we do
need that a qmc I was premature so we
are still gonna need that because we
don't account for it in one pass right
although I guess we could so here's an
interesting thing so we could if we
wanted to allow people to propagate
within the same frame I shouldn't say
frame within the same iteration we could
allow people we write to later to
actually continue propagating that light
onwards I'm not going to do that and the
reason that I'm not going to do that is
I'm gonna say that we want to prepare
this sort of to think about we're it
working in a very parallelized way and
so what I don't want to do is ever write
to any value I'm reading right I want to
have like a strict input output buffer
kind of a thing so I want to be reading
from the emission color and outputting
to the accumulation color and then
swapping the two who basically is what I
want to have happen right so maybe like
you know we could even call this like
send color and receive color or
something like this or you know this is
the color that's emitting now and this
is the next emission color or whatever
so it just kind of gathers them up as it
goes all right and so yeah I mean I
don't know right like but that's that's
the idea so as we come through here
we're going to do compute light
propagation I'm gonna say like okay you
know let's let's leave through each of
these saucy gentlemen here and what
we're gonna do is say much like we did
before
oops we're gonna raycast this so for
each of these destinations we're gonna
do a bunch of raycast here I don't know
how many we're gonna do but a couple
right
previously we were doing eight so maybe
that's how many we're still doing or
maybe maybe reduce that because we want
to have more iterations and less raise
or who knows what but something like
that's gonna happen right so we're gonna
go through and we're gonna say instead
of dest index here I'm going to change
this to emitter index because that's oh
I said I kind of want to loop over the
emitters here's the emitter and what I
want to do is say you know if the
emitters emit color is greater than zero
then it's something that we will
actually raycast from otherwise not and
the other thing we can do here is this
could be a you know another value so if
we wanted to we could say look if you
don't have at least you know a little
bit of light coming out of you we're not
gonna we're gonna assume you can't
really contribute to a propagation phase
so that value is tunable right I you
know down the line so when we come
through these emitters we're gonna say
if this is somebody who needed to emit
we will raycast
at that point and we'll say that you
know we want to skip the emitter itself
because obviously we don't want to hit
that but we want to recast and we want
to see who we hit now we do have a
problem here which is that we didn't
actually we want to write to that person
who were who were targeting and our rate
cast again like because it's nice and
simple for the final gather
unfortunately we don't have the ability
here to know who we actually hit right
so we would need to expand this to
include that as much as I didn't want to
have to do that
we do need that right so we'll send the
index and the color back I so we'll set
the color to zero we'll set the index to
element count and then off we go
so in here that's all we really needed
right is just to remember that then when
it comes back both of these guys get
what they want so cure when we have this
rate cast we don't care what the index
is so we just use the color in here we
care about the index so we just use the
index and off to go so here in this rate
cast we want to take a look at what the
index is so here's our hid index like so
if the hit index is less than the
element count value right here
we know it's valid and so what we want
to do here is just take this and add the
light that we are trying to send
basically we're the emitter we've found
somebody we should transfer light to so
let's transfer that light and that's all
we're doing so
I believe
to think about this now
I believe this is the place where we
should in theory be able to take into
account the inverse square law more
directly so we can we're just looking at
the transference of surfaces here
surface to surface so I believe this one
would work the only thing I'm not sure
about is we can hit the same surface
twice and we don't really want that
[Music]
so the kind of convoluted way we had it
before we actually looked at each
individual surface to see whether it
could see it so in this case what we
want to do is sort of prohibit ourselves
from writing to the same person twice if
we happen to hit them more than once and
I don't really know the best way to do
that right which suggests that maybe the
emission process also wants to just be
kind of stochastic and not take into
account things like light distance
fall-off and so on honestly
yeah so I'm not really sure about that
one
that's a little bit tricky because
essentially there's two ways we can look
at this one way is we can look at this
as a complete N squared problem where we
want to consider every emitter and every
receiver and see whether or not we can
see each one from each other and do one
light transfer per round the problem
with that is assuming that our raycast
we start optimizing the raycast part
because that's the expensive part of
both of these we really don't want to be
in squared anymore we want to just be
able to do a quick rate cast that uses
some kind of acceleration and then
determines who we hit so it almost makes
me feel like we really just want to do
this maybe we really don't want to do
the emitter-base thing at all maybe we
just want to do stochastic samples
always I and that's and we just run them
repeatedly
I don't have a strong opinion one way or
the other but just thinking about this
it really does kind of seem to me like
we want to you know we we want to have
some we really I think we really do want
to stay stochastic and accelerate the
rate count you know just try to be able
to increase the rate count and so on so
yeah I'm gonna say I'm just gonna say
that that's what we want so there'll be
a weight and a color here so as we go
over these when we find an element we
hit like we'll take the next emit color
and we'll basically compute whatever the
lighting transfer is gonna be from the
hit and then we'll wait it up and at the
end we'll normalize those weights into
the final value I think that's what we
want to do all right so now we actually
have to figure some of this stuff out
how much the emission how much you know
emitted light there's going to be and
that sort of stuff right so we're
turning this this surface into sort of a
virtual emitter if that makes sense and
again this isn't accurate
because we're not doing full scene ray
tracing so per pixel we just have to
have an idea of how things are sort of
bouncing around the scene so everything
is kind of a chalky reflector for
purposes of this propagation pass
there's not going to be a lot of like
focused light reflection and caustics or
any that stuff we're not going to
capture right
so specular surfaces at render time we
can do but at bounce time we're not
going to be supporting really okay so
now what we need to do is figure out
alright how much light is going to come
in
here and so what we know is we're
starting we have our emitter and we know
what its emission color was right so
we're starting with that now we do want
the incoming direction to vary by the
cosine because we're storing up the
amount of light that hits the surface
that we're going to then send back so we
do have an inner product in here right
so we do want to take the inner product
of the REA direction so the direction
we're casting out which again we're
gonna have to yeah what you're gonna
have to compute here so from the emitter
for each ray we have to take the
emission normal and we're gonna take the
Ray direction-- here that's gonna come
out from the emitter right we could call
this more specifically the emission
direction and of course we know it's
coming from the emitter origin there we
go so we do that ray cast out when we
compute the light color we take the
inner product of that emission direction
and we need to clamp it
with the surface normal that we hit
right now we want this to be one when
the emitter direction was directly when
the emitter could be seen directly above
the normal exactly and remember the
emission direction is coming out of the
emitter so we actually need to negate
these right because what they're facing
opposite each other right now the
emission direction and the receiving
normal are facing opposite each other we
would get a negative one in the K in
that case and we want the opposite
Dmitri we want one in that case we have
to flip the sign of that around so that
it the cosine fall-off works properly
right so that's the amount that's going
to come in here but then we also want to
take the Hadamard product let me I'll
pull this out here so that we can
alright I guess we'll call this angle
and Euler attenuation okay so there's
the angular and attenuation and then we
also want to take the Hadamard product
here with the reflection color because
whatever the thing is that I hit its R
if it's gonna reflect that light out by
multiplying here now what you can see is
that's wasted work because this
reflected color is going to multiply
every attenuated incoming light so what
I can do is instead wait till the end so
after we've done everything wait to the
end to do this right
so if I sum up all of these only using
the angular attenuation then at the end
what I can do is I can loop over and I
guess to start this needs to be inside
the iteration obviously is when I run
through everybody again at the end I
will look at all of the reflectors and
again this is really just nominator of
how I'm thinking of them I'm thinking of
emitters here I'm thinking reflectors
here but they're the same elements right
when I come through here what I want to
do is I want to say all right the emit
color is going to now have whatever that
summation was it's going to be
multiplied by the reflected color to
sort of take all of the incident light
we summed up there was in this that was
going to bounce off the surface it's
gonna get modulated by the reflected
color because you know if this is only a
red surface we should knock out all the
green and blue light there or whatever
right but again I just pulled out that
would have been a common term across the
entire summation and then I also want to
average over the number of samples that
got hit here so I want to say okay in
addition to that I need to take whatever
that lighting cap was there and I need
to do one over the lightning camp right
so I need to also multiply it by that
next limit C needs to take the next emit
W and multiply it over it's alright so
one over get next emit W
like so now we don't need to do that in
the case where there is no no hits were
recorded right so we can do that
comparison continue so that's fine and
we may want to store this as an integer
for that purpose in that case because
we're just sort of counting up but
that's neither that's not super
important that's like a fiddly detail at
this point so after we do all of these
we know how many hit each individual
reflector we're gonna go ahead and
correct for that weighting factor there
right so each sample that came in we're
gonna correct for that and then we're
also going to knock out the using the
reflection color we then need to clear
everything out right so this clears
everything out so that we can then do a
summation another pass a summation and
this stuff I think we don't really want
any more right we just don't need this
this is stuff for computing the final
lighting and it's just not something we
need so if we go back and look at the
OpenGL code right dumi and look at all
of this stuff this is stuff that we then
eventually want to put in there right
like all of this stuff right here is
sort of stuff we want to put into the
fragment code
in the future this summation is not
necessary anymore because we're kind of
doing it here so I think that's really
all we need
that's the mote that's that's pretty
much it right and here honestly we could
just do this per channel as well we
could just say if emits c RM @ cg m @ CB
right you know something like this right
we don't really need a length squared we
just need to know if any of the channels
summed up to it right so I think that's
roughly what we want there we now need
to set sort of our initial stuff where
we do our extraction because we have to
clear this stuff properly and make sure
everything's set right so when we do our
extraction you can see I would set these
things here we've got front emit C and
vacuum it C and nonsense like that so we
kind of know we're not doing that
anymore
right we're not doing a back emit see
we're just doing a regular emit C and I
think do we clear these normally I don't
know if we actually clear these yeah we
need to actually clear these in here so
we need to take these two values and set
them properly right so we need to say
like next emit see oh no y-you set those
both there we go
right so it looks like we want it like
that so we have our omit see our next to
Mitzi and our next omit W like so so we
just get those set properly I don't
think we need incident later average
direction to light because those will
get set directly and they don't need to
be cleared to anything in particular so
the same thing has to be true in this
function as well because we have two
different ways you can strike their
vertices right now
so again looks like this is not relevant
so we have an omission here we have a
next limit C 0 and a next image W at 0
as well right and those two are just you
know sort of ad hoc extractions that we
were doing um I don't know why we pulled
elements out there doesn't look like we
really need to so may be able to do this
no no no I like it up let's do it
let's let's get down all right so this
has to actually return a raycast result
now I didn't actually change their turn
value even though I read in the function
to have it it's just a weird typo there
no I did that okay and let's see here so
now we've got sort of these old output
letting quad stuff so we don't really
have this visibility value anymore so
I'm just gonna get rid of that entirely
and these are just gonna be our omit C's
I think what we really want to draw now
is that incident color but we can leave
this as a Mitzi's for now we probably
want to be able to drop both of them but
the emit C's are the colors that we
actually were sending out from those
surfaces which is the information that
we probably want to draw but we really
want to see both we want to be able to
see both the emission color and the
incident light summation because both of
them are relevant so all right so now
when we're packing things down again
that color now wants to be the incident
what is the average direction to light
oops that's d sorry I was just this is
incident-light so this wants to take the
incident light not the front emit and
that's gonna pack that down so now we're
storing the incident light in C and
restoring the average direction to the
light in D which is the information we
wanted this is just some debug code but
we'll keep it working for now because
why not and then inside the shader now
so this is actually now more correctly
stated so this is this is the light
color and this is the light direction
right and we're sort of taking a look at
all right so how what is this code doing
so that's a distance fall-off which
seems okay
because we're not sampling multiple rays
so we kind of have to do that and then
we've got a inner product between the
light direction which we want and the
world normal seems correct so I think
that's all correct now we just did a ton
of new code there so we're gonna have to
do some debugging which means probably
how much time we have left in the stream
probably I will leave it for next time
because this ain't gonna produce much
wow that was actually better than I was
expecting
doesn't look correct but I was expecting
just like complete garbage or something
yeah all right well that was more than I
had hope for it it's kind of trippy and
kind of cool actually and pretty fast
oddly enough as well so yeah that means
a lot closer to done than I was
expecting
[Music]
we're getting there folks the long slow
struggle of lighting but yeah it's not
great yet I also don't know why we're
not getting any yellow light
transmission here so something bad is
happening they're like why why there's
no pickup from the yellow light on this
I don't know I don't know if it's
because there's some too much shadowing
happening or something and also like the
red blue light transmission here is kind
of out of control so we've got a bunch
of stuff to work on but I'm pretty happy
with that what I would like to maybe do
is take out
some of the additional emitters here so
if I go into for example world's mode
I don't remember how we were setting
these emitters here but like snake
segments for example and piece of light
so if I were to take out the ad piece
light for the snake I think we're
probably gonna want just this one light
source in here right so that way we can
sort of see man that is just getting
this is starting to be kind of cool like
as the as you move around and the
lighting changes on you like it's kind
of all busted right now so it's not
really good but it's like it's just fun
when you get into those sorts of
situations right like when you can see
the lighting sort of start to change in
or whatever I don't know starting to
have sort of almost a real render not
quite but almost um so yeah like I
wanted to take out the I wanted to take
out those additional yellow lights
because when we first start debugging
this we're gonna want to look at just
what happens with one light source so we
can have a better feel for what's going
on there
right so that's what we'll start working
on next time and I'll try to get visual
Studios registration stuff straightened
out so we can debug I'll go to some q
and a's now as well
please increase the fontsize individual
City for debugging the font size is
pretty small
it's not the same as for it uses uh
problem is of course I can't do that
today because Visual Studio is doing its
thing
I wonder free to just make an account
try to remind me next time tomorrow I
could try to make a note of it too here
I suppose I don't know if I spelled
commensurate right
we're visual to do yeah uh so I don't
really I don't use the I don't use the
shareware version of Idul studio I still
use I bought the professional one that I
use at work I still use 2012 but I used
the shareware version on the stream
because that's what everyone else is
gonna have to like I don't want people
who are trying to learn to program to
have to go by the professional version
of Visual Studio especially cuz it's not
worth the price yeah I do have an
account I just don't I got to go look up
what the password is I don't know what
it is so I'll go look it up and then
I'll sign it in after the stream is done
and yeah and the reason I didn't use for
our coder I ran notepad detecting them
to do is because I want it to be a
window like a separate window that I
have that I won't close right I cuz I'm
gonna close for a coder in a second and
it's gonna be you know I want some myths
stuck up there
yeah no malicious intent understatement
I just find it funny how expires are
three days without your giving them
customer did it yeah so there's a couple
of different things about it right that
I don't like about the visuals of your
thing first of all like I think it I'm
happy to pay for software you know I
like paying for software actually and I
miss it and so when I when a piece of
software package has two things going
for it I'm pretty happy one it does not
have DRM so I can just take the
executable package and whatever check it
into source code control pay my money
whatever the price is and be good that's
thing one and thing two is that it the
price of the software is roughly
commensurate with what it does and that
it does the thing that I want right so a
Visual Studio kind of fails on both
accounts to a large extent I don't use
Visual Studio because it's good or that
they even are attempting to have me as a
customer I just use it because there is
no really other debuggers right now
right there's really almost no
competition in that space there's
competition in like the reverse
engineering space like there's AI 2 Pro
and stuff like that but you know not
really in the just regular source level
of debuggers for people who wrote their
own program not who are you know trying
to inspect some else's program so like
good examples of software packages that
I love paying for Reaper the audio
package priced very reasonably for what
it does did no DRM at all you can just
check it into your source code control
there's just a registration key you just
save the registration key and you're
good to go it's targeted at the people
who is targeted at like that's like hey
this is for recording professionals
every change they make is for recording
professionals like I it's great it's a
great software purchasing experience
example of the worst possible starving
experience anything from Autodesk right
massively more expensive than the value
it gives you because usually they're
targeting like thousands of different
use cases only one of what
is relevant to you and you're paying for
all the rest of them extremely intrusive
DRM even installs like rootkits on your
machine more or less right cannot be
checked into source code control right
cannot be efficiently distributed
throughout your team it just and
Microsoft has sort of gone from being in
the first camp when you used to buy
Visual Studio you just got a CD you can
install it on computer there was no DRM
you could check it in the source code
control it just worked you paid your
money you had it all the features were
geared towards you right professional
developer programming and see now
they've gone well 100 percent Autodesk
tons of features for everyone in their
grandmother most of them are relevant to
you last time they cared about game
developers was you know 1983 that's a
joke obviously it was more like 1995 and
you know the price is astronomical
compared to what you're getting for it
there's it's DRM all over the place even
the parts that aren't dear m'd you can't
even check in the source control Chris
are 8 million weird like side-by-side
assemblies installs and blah blah blah
so you know nowadays I tried to purchase
as little as possible from Microsoft
because they went you know they
basically went from selling software the
way that I purchase software and and the
way it makes me effective to selling
software the way that just makes my life
miserable
did you try Connie moon instead of stock
command prompt I loved quake console
effective deliveries I don't spend much
time in the command console so I don't
go I don't complexify my install by
using custom one if you're someone who
spends a lot of time in the console and
writes lots of stuff there then you know
that that may be a good idea final space
is the good times for paying software
and our hat for paying for suffering are
happier totally over yes there's like a
few very specific software packages
where you still pay your money and good
service in return there vanishingly
small Reaper is like one of the last
remaining examples right
couldn't thought for long time you've
done something with automated unit
testing are you playing - no we don't
really have much that needs unit testing
in this package in the in this program
so there probably won't be any automated
unit testing there might if we want to
get saucy we might do the game industry
version of unit testing which is because
generally except for some core systems
unit testing doesn't really buy you
anything in game development because it
only finds your really easy bugs the
really hard bugs are the ones that come
from things that evolve over time in the
game but there is sort of a game
development equipment that and that is
sort of like randomized input testing or
even structured Impa testing where you
basically write sort of a bot almost
that tries to run your game in various
ways and sees if it can break it right
and this is great like this it is sort
of the equivalent of unit testing for
like web stuff unit testing is good at
finding like server bugs because servers
have well-defined inputs and outputs
that you can run unit tests against unit
testing is crappy for finding game bug
because it can only find the easy game
bugs like bugs in your memory allocator
bugs in your asset loader like okay
great like yeah maybe that's worth a
little bit something and if you have a
summer intern have them write them great
go for it but the problem is they're
really hard bugs in game development are
the ones that come from odd interactions
of the game over time and unit testing
does zero for this so but that doesn't
mean that automated testing is is a bad
idea for games it just means that you
gotta use it's not unit testing it's
it's actually sort of more constructed
randomized input testing and it and it
works very well so so we may if we get
saucy at the end of the project we may
try to do that because you do find a lot
of bugs you would not have found if you
do put stuff like that in there
all right um I'll just quickly answer
this last question how do you keep your
motivation grand long-running products I
don't really have a lot of troubles
keeping mood keeping motivated to work
on stuff what I do have the two problems
I tend to face are just a getting too
stressed out because I'm fine like I
could spend ten years working on a
project but nobody wants to pay for that
right and so I get really stressed
because I always behind because I'm
always like looking into things or
experimenting with things when I
probably should just do something stupid
and move on
so that's more a problem I have I don't
really have the problem of the
motivation I'm I'm like usually my
problem is the opposite I'm too
motivated to go solve some problem that
really probably shouldn't be looked into
at this point right that's why I'm kind
of more of a research coder than a
production coder I'm like on the
research side of production is where I
tend to be more successful and straight
production I'm actually much worse
because I want to go look I want to go
look for new ways to do things I'm too
motivated to do that and what I almost
need is a decrease in motivation I
almost need to like I would be better
off if I just wanted to get things done
quickly sometimes and just wasn't
motivated to go do more work on
something right so there's that and the
other problem that I tend to have is
what was I going to say
all right I don't know what it was sorry
what was the other problem
I don't know yeah I don't know but yeah
that's typically the problem I'm the
main program problem I have is wanting
to go solve problems that don't need to
be solved right now and I don't really
think of that as that much of a problem
as a requirement right it's like that
basically means that when I'm taking on
stuff I need to do stuff that benefits
from research focus because otherwise
I'm just going to take way too long to
do something that doesn't need you know
I'm gonna spend time improving something
that nobody wanted improved right all
right I'm gonna wrap it up close down
everything
thank you everyone for joining me from
UPS on a handmade Hira
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with a series you can always go to
handmade hero org and if you pre-order
the game on hand me here org it comes
with a source code so you can play
around with everything yourself and do
your own experimentation with the source
base as it is maybe you can fix the
lighting before tomorrow and you know
you can debug it before I do I we also a
forum site and go to forum I ask
questions a patreon page you want to
support the video series and mostly that
patreon actually goes I dispersed it out
to people who are making stuff that
support the stream such as the fabulous
annotations done by mid low or the
handmade network that runs the forums
among other things so really that's for
us the whole community we've got a
schedule bot which tells you are going
to be live if you want to subscribe to
that such as a Twitter bot that will
tell you when we're gonna be lives you
can find out when episodes going and we
also have an episode guide you can go to
if you want to catch up on old episodes
of this series that's about it I will be
back here tomorrow when we'll start
debugging the lighting and trying to get
it to produce good lighting results it's
starting to look kind of useful so that
should be fun
hope see you everyone back here for that
until then have fun programming I'll see
everyone on the Internet take it easy
everybody