alrighty hello everyone and welcome to
handmade hero the show recode a complete
game live on stream we have some work to
do today because we wanted to finish our
bounds checker we basically implemented
our own memory bounds checker that
allows us to know if we ever overwrite
blocks of memory that we've allocated
but we haven't quite finished it we we
sort of got the basic version working
yesterday but in order to finish it up
we kind of have a couple more things we
need to do and so that's what I'd like
to do today and basically there's two
things we need to do one is we need to
manage our headers a little bit better
and the other that we need to do is
implement something that that shifts
memory up towards the end of blocks so
that we can do overflow testing as well
as under flow testing right now we're
only doing under flow testing so let's
go ahead and get started since there's
really not much to explain its all the
same concepts it's yesterday but we're
just finishing up so today days is day 3
46 you'll want to do day 3 45 source
code if you're going to be following
along with me so let's go ahead and
build and run the program there we go so
all we're doing right now is we're doing
the like I said we're doing the
underflow testing let's go over here
platform allocate or try to add platform
allocate so all we're doing right now is
we're doing underflow checking and we
did something interesting here in fact I
never really did this before i'm not
sure why i never did this before and I'm
thinking that I probably will I might
change the way I do things now that I've
done it this way here on handmade here
I'd never really yeah I just never
really thought about it too much and
probably I should have let me open up
Milton and just briefly say what I did
yesterday in case for those of you who
missed it it was just kind of weird um
let's see today 346 teh 346 my tablet
seems to have no longer is no longer
treated as a tablet perhaps by Milton or
anybody else by the way I'm not sure why
that started happening it happened after
I did that thing with the I accidentally
let the program run and use up all
available memory I don't know if you
guys remember that so I'm not sure if I
should try to get the wacom drivers to
go back into some state that makes some
sense probably I should do that after
the stream but we'll try it really
quickly now just to see whether that
helps it doesn't help a wacom driver how
are you doing the tablet driver was not
found so you know not great no tablet
driver and so Milton is uh yeah Milton
can't really access the tablet if
there's no tablet driver to say the
least so i guess i'll have to reboot the
machine at some point anyway ladies and
gentlemen the robustness of windows day
346 let's just go ahead and mention here
what was happening so what i did was i
needed to make a page of memory for the
allocation and we don't really know how
many pages that is that could be any
number of pages right so this is like n
pages here because if the allocation is
you know 36 k then we need at
least to fit the the 36 k we would need
well I probably should have picked
something a little bit less convenient
as L oh no that's fine I take it back
let's do 34 k so we know that we need
things in 4k page clumps because the
operating system only manages pages in
4k about clumps so if I was to divide 34
k by four I would get eight and then I
would have a remainder of 2 K right so I
know I have eight full pages but then
I'm going to essentially need nine pages
I don't know why I put that there so I
need 84 k pages to fit the 32 k and then
i would need at F to K leftover and so
what I need is I need nine pages total
one of them will only have 2k in it it
won't have the full 4k right so I need
essentially nine pages for let's say
that allocation so in this case n would
equal 9 and then what I need to do is I
needed to basically put guards on either
side of it and I should stop saying
guard page because not really what i
mean but dead pages fault pages I need
to put one page so this is a 4k page
this is a 4k page right that are marked
as like do not write to these so that we
can get checking on either side we can
only get perfect checking on one side or
the other because again if the
allocation turns out to be not rounded
to a 4k boundary then we're going to
have some blank space somewhere and we
can either put the blank space at the
beginning and have it end right at the
upper end or we can put the blank space
at the end and have it end right at the
the lower end but we can only
fundamentally check for underfloor and
overflow perfectly in one direction at a
time right we can only do one of those
at a time but those so if we're doing
this it also points out the fact that
it's unclear where we put the memory
header we can stuff the memory header
into this unused location if it happens
to be big enough but what I did which is
kind of fun is I made one other 4k page
that's just for the memory header over
here right so there's a page beyond the
page that's there for overflow detection
that's just
for that purpose and that seemed kind of
interesting and I liked that that was
that was kind of a cool I don't know I
thought that was kind of interesting so
what I might do is just double down on
that I think that's kind of neat so I
think I might just go with that and and
make it so that that's actually how this
works in general and what I mean by that
is currently what we're doing if we kind
of go into our our memory system here
currently what we're doing is when we
allocate memory we put that we put the
size of that block we put that into this
to the chain right I'm sorry we put that
into the allocation the size of the
memory block chain we're doing that
outside in the platform independent
layer right when we're saying hey let's
go ahead and and have the memory
allocator here that's actually doing
reallocations every time it needs to get
a new block from the system it's adding
space for like a little chain thing of
its own but what I'm thinking is I
wonder if it wouldn't make more sense to
actually have it so that the operating
system allows us to get or we like share
that thing with the operating system if
that makes sense and there's two ways we
can do it one way is we can have the
operating system put it in a special
location like it was doing before the
other way we can do it is having it be
part of the block that this that this
thing manages and I don't know which one
of those is is the best way to do it
what I do know is that we could
essentially change the API to the system
and I kind of like the idea of doing
that I kind of like the idea of changing
the API to the system so that people who
allocate memory from the system actually
understand the the fact that you're
getting back a thing that has a control
block in it right and that you use that
control block for storing your
information as well if that makes sense
and so what I mean by that is if we look
at the platform layer and again I'm just
kind of experimenting with this but I
could I just like the idea when we say
that we want to do a platform allocate
memory right now we're just getting back
a void star which is like a pointer to
the memory
and when we free it we pass in a void
star you know and we also pass in
whatever the flags were and again the
reason that we had to pass in with the
flags were is because fundamentally
speaking the operating system doesn't
have any idea how the memory was
allocated in the first place so in order
to get back to its control block it
needs to do work so what I was thinking
is really we don't have to do that if we
don't want to we don't necessarily have
to even deal with that particular
situation because what we could do
instead is actually have the platform
memory header or actually have the win32
memory header be like a real thing that
you get back and that you can see right
so if you imagine we take a look here
we've got this sort of win32 memory
block thing and just what I'm thinking
is we could make you basically get back
you know a pointer into a part of this
or into actually this right so for
example we could say like okay you know
what is the portion of this that should
be visible to the application and you
know if we take a look at it it's like
well it's probably you know something
like this right these things are pretty
much stuff that only the win32 side
cares about but these things are things
that the application would potentially
care about as well right the flags are
something the application was having to
pass back into us that it could keep the
size is something the application wants
to know about the memory that it
allocated right because it's trying to
track that as well the base pointer is
the thing that it primarily wanted in
the first place was where the memory is
and then we've got two more things here
that are you know sized appropriately to
actually have them come back to us as
necessary and so what I'm thinking about
that again is just that hey it would be
cool if we could make it so that this
was effectively some some you know
struct platform memory block
where we just said all of these things
are actually in here or maybe that I
don't know something like this I have no
idea what should be gang block maybe um
so anyway inside there I have no idea
select lock button mmm I don't know
anyway point being the the memory block
sort of exists inside there and so you
know when we allocate one of these we
could pass the operation we could pass
the call the person who's calling us
back one of these things so for example
we could then make the allocate memory
and deallocate memory stuff actually
work on one of these platform memory
blocks and return one of these flat for
memory blocks and so then what we could
do and also that would alleviate the the
need for us to deal with that then what
we could do is sort of see how that
would work out in in our scheme so when
we want to do like the allocate memory
and we're trying to freeze something
right we would pass it in the memory
block that we actually cared about right
the the the blockade or so when we say
get footer or whatever what we need to
do here is figure out for arenas and
stuff like this we need to figure out
where these blocks exist right and in
order to do that I think what we could
do I don't think it'll be particularly
difficult I don't know yet though what
we could do is say alright so the block
chain is gone we'll just say that the
block chain is something that again is
now lofted up into here because it
already has most of the data right we
know where the base pointer is here is
the base pointer we know what the size
is because there's the size we don't
know what they used is and we don't care
about the pad so really all we're
talking about is this
right because those things were almost
entirely storing the same information
which is why I kind of wanted to
collapse and dash didn't make any sense
to have both right so once we have that
platform memory block then that means
that all we have to really do like we've
got get footer here on the arena the
memory arena where it's got this this
base pointer what I want to do I think
is in addition to the base pointer I
want to store what the block is what the
platform memory block is that's the
pointer to the previous platform memory
block right and we can chain these
backwards because we only ever go
backwards through them so we also should
be able to say like okay platform memory
block arena pre or something like that
right so we should be able to chain them
backwards that way inside a given memory
arena we can just say like okay there
should be a memory block that is the the
memory block that we actually are using
currently and we just remember what that
is right we just remember whatever we
wanted that to be and so that would be
you know something like that right
now there's a bunch of stuff that's kind
of ee stored here and the question is
just I don't know if we want to double
chase the pointers or to keep them
copied out like we kind of were before
if I because if you take a look at what
happens here we obviously have and I'm
going to make that a you ate from that
we obviously have base stored in both
places we have used stored in both
places we have size stored in both
places so we don't actually need that
data we could just always use it off of
the current block itself but it does
require us to say well if we have a
memory arena instead of looking directly
into the memory net we're kind of
looking into some side buffer you know
to every time we want to do an
allocation and I don't know how I feel
about that so I'm going to do it that
way because I think it will be easier to
make things work properly at first but
it may be the case to do k see if we see
/ problems here maybe move a used base
out to avoid that sort of double in
direction that's going to happen right
so I don't know you know memory
allocation is not something that happens
that often inside handmade hero so it's
possible that it isn't really relevant
but you never know so I'm just going to
like sort of mention that there is
potentially a problem there and we'll
see what happens when we get to it so
okay that would be sort of the new way
that things would look and then you know
when we sort of when we sort of need to
do stuff here what we can do is say okay
where's our push size inside our push
sighs when we do our sort of used plus
size greater than size stuff obviously
this would require that we have a
current block right so if we have a
current block and then we're just going
to say alright the current block used
current block size right and you see
what I mean about the Dublin direction
so you can kind of see how that's I mean
you know it's not great right it's not
necessarily what we would want to do
there and it really just depends on the
circumstances whether that would be
problematic or not so anyway let's take
a quick look at the other way that this
stuff would work you can see here like
these guys would also need to have it so
yeah you know I mean you can just see
why I'm like a little bit nervous about
why having that constantly be the case I
also don't know when we do get effective
size for that's one of the problems that
we have had and will and still have at
this point is get effective size for is
not going to take into account the fact
that we may allocate a new block of
memory at some point so get effective
size for is only useful in the case
where we know that our base pointer is
actually that we know that we're not
doing our like overflow checking and so
on so that's a little bit squirrelly as
well because yeah I don't know I guess
it doesn't really matter because we sort
of rectify that later on but still it's
just a little bit weird anyway so when
we call get effective size we also have
this problem but again we can sort of
say we can sort of make that be a thing
where if there wasn't a current block
this would be if not currently if there
wasn't a current block then we wouldn't
do it so we could also do a thing that
was more like you know if arena current
block do it otherwise don't and so on so
anyway if we know that we don't have a
current block then we know we're going
to have to do that if we don't if we do
have a current block then we just need
to see if it has memory once we get in
here then we're going to go ahead and do
everything pretty much the same way we
used to do it let's go current block
here firm blah
and then I think we're all good like so
and again I'm going to want to revisit
this a bit just until I get it down to
like a place where I'm happy about it
but anyway so that's the basic idea
there and what we're going to need is
when we actually do this sort of
allocation you can kind of see we do a
memory block train save here that would
now go away because we wouldn't be
dealing with that anymore and so then
what we would do is say all right we
know that we don't need to do this
anymore so really the only thing we're
doing is making sure we never allocate a
block size that's too small we then go
ahead and say let's take we don't care
about any of this no that's going to get
filled up for us by the platform layer
so now our current block or I should
probably say Rena and block good block
that we're now going to have a platform
memory block where we do a platform
allocate memory and we felt till at the
block size and the flags that we want to
to use for allocation that's going to
get us back a new block that's going to
be completely initialized and and yet
that's about all there is to it we no
longer need the block count because the
block count was strictly there to
prevent us from unwinding too far in
this case we now know that we won't have
to worry about that I don't think
because we will have the back pointer in
our in our heading so we will know when
we've rewound too far so once we get a
new block we need to arena we need to
set the arena breathe what should we
call that
we're going to prove we need to set the
arena prieve to be the block that we're
currently on and then we set the new
block to be the one that we're currently
looking at right and that's pretty much
all there would be to it we don't need
the footer stuff anymore we don't need
any of that because we're assuming that
we're just going to use the one the
operating system laid out for us and so
I think the rest of it kind of is the
same as it would be again the this stuff
here has to now have sort of a
block-based thing here and all of this
is how it is I don't know who is still
calling get arena size remaining
only the person who prints this thing
out so I think that's not going to be a
thing we do any more would be my
assumption so I think we're just going
to say let's let's nuke this and then in
our memory system here we can just say
that's not a thing anymore alright so
let's see arena has room for and that is
also not being used anymore nor is get
footer so we can just simplify that
stuff down a bit all right when we do
the begin temporary memory I believe
that there isn't anything in particular
that's going to be happening there that
that needs to be special I think it
should be pretty basic yeah so i think
when we do begin temporary that's all we
would need when we come back here to you
know i'll be honest
yeah ok so the when we were doing the
the blackout thing we were just doing
that so we could clear memory so again
yeah we definitely don't need that
because all we have to do is just keep
walking back so all we have to do is say
as long as there is that we just say
while there is a current block all we
have to do is just do free last block
right that that's really it and so that
way when we do free last lock we just
say like okay the thing that we're going
to free platform memory block is the
current block we're then going to
deallocate that memory right whatever it
is we don't need the flags anymore and
that then that's really all there is to
it before we do that we for we free it
we need to get the arena the pre vat of
it so we can move back one block but
that's about it and that's all we should
really have to do I think I mean I think
that's really it so yeah we could also
make this a little simpler and say the
base part here could actually just be a
block it's like what block you were on
instead of what base you're on so we
just need like the block we could do
like that and then that way we can say
well the current block is not equal to
the block that we were on before I think
that's really all there is so that way
the temp men would not be storing a base
pointer it'd just be storing a platform
memory block right and i think that's
that's it uh did I type it in a row yeah
I did what there we go uh so yeah I
think that's good what else we got here
so sub arenas I don't know that we're
using sub arenas anymore let's let's
double check because I don't think that
we are so let's just get rid of those
all right and when we do draw a Rena
occupancy that is not even something
that we're doing anymore but it's um I
think at some point we will want to
enable it so I'm going to leave that
there all right so now let's get down to
the win32 part of things right so now
what we need to do is take a look at how
I specified this on the platform side we
moved those flags into the platform part
of it that part of the flags anyway so
we just need to take a look at anyone
who was using that the base pointer was
also in there but I don't really
remember how we're writing this out yes
that is how right so we always want to
access the platform block for these
because these are these were all things
that were in there and let's take a look
here so allocate we're going to want to
rewrite now and deallocate as well let's
just make sure okay so let's go ahead
and rewrite these now that we know
what's going on so in this case we're
going to take a win32 memory block that
we have allocated in addition to and
we're going to set up the values in it
you can see here we're setting up some
of those values like we're setting up
block base right but we're not setting
up some of the other values like block
used and so on those I guess can be
cleared to zero I suppose so maybe it
doesn't really matter that much they all
should be set to zero but let's assert
that they are so when we set the the
block let's just assert let me go ahead
and set these here equals
cannot convert from the three-member
luck to you 8 sorry about that again and
there we go so now I really want to know
all I really want to know now is what
exactly Jimmy is what exactly those
other values are virtual Alex should set
them to zero but I want to make sure so
these two should both be set to zero so
I want to do an assert that my block
values here are always initialized I
believe they should be but I just want
to ensure that they are because maybe
they aren't when I return the value here
I actually am not returning the win32
block I'm returning that sub portion of
it right because i'm not actually
telling the platform layer about the
win32 side of things I'm just kind of
returning it a little baby piece and
then that should in theory be all we
need to do for the allocation when we
deallocate now we know that it's
actually passing us in a block right so
if we take a look at the deallocation
call which would be here we should be
getting now a block pointer back instead
of memory right so now all we need to do
is say well ok we know that what they
gave us was like a plat block was the
platform part of the block so i need to
back up now to get to the correct part
to get to the win32 part of it right and
if I want to I can make this a little
easier on myself by just using sort of
the the standard subclassing way that
that things work in c and c++ which is
that if you have a pointer to something
if you put something at the top of it
you can treat that pointer interchange
lee right this is how c++ implements
there you know sort of light
polymorphism that they have when you do
inheritance or stuff like that I you
could just say oh alright well I have a
memory block I want to sometimes treat
it as a as just a regular block so I
don't want to have to do the pointer
math to move like I could write if I
left it down there I just when I want to
go back to a win32 I just have to know
what to move back by a few pointers
right by 3 64 bit values but what I can
do instead is just use it this way and
then casting just work so you don't have
to do any arithmetic so since there's no
reason for me not to do that I suppose I
might as well just do it that way it's a
little more efficient so I can just say
like okay like so now in this case I
don't have to do this check anymore
because I know that I'm actually getting
back the actual block itself so really
all I have to do is use this to check
the looping flags and see whether I
needed to do anything otherwise I'm
pretty much done right I can just free
the block as I normally would free the
block that's really all there is to it
so I think there really isn't very much
to do their hoops that's really all
there is
and i think that's it okay so let's see
that's supposed to be an or not an and
so that's not going to go well to say
the least you can't just you know or an
and not interchangeable so if we have
the current block and we're saying that
it's not set to anything that means we
automatically have to take this path and
allocate some new memory for ourselves
right but otherwise then we want to
check to see whether the current block
has you know room or not all right that
does not look good at all what's going
on here
well in this case I can just step in so
I'm gonna here we go so let's see we
have a current block oh wow that's great
I don't know what's going on there
obviously when i get the size i had to
set it to this I when I cut and pasted
that was a little bit of a bug there I
meant to still set the size equal to
that that was just a total typo okay
alright so now let's see what's going on
here we're doing a begin temporary
memory and I guess we aren't properly
handling a case where we don't have a
current block where the arena hasn't
been used at all because we're looking
at that used pointer which is not
correct right so i suppose what i should
do there is make sure that we handle
that correctly I don't think there's
anything I can do I probably just have
to check to see if there is one or not
and then when we do the rewinding in
theory that will just work but we also
again we can't do these assertions here
so what we would have to do is that say
if arena current block if weary rep
rewound all the way we don't want to
touch anything right alright so now in
theory we're running okay and we're
running entirely in underflow checking
mode right now I believe because we kind
of did a little thing in here where we
I'm sorry overflow jacking mode we stuck
a little thing in here but at the moment
although that we will do this part
properly meaning will will force
allocations to all be every time you
call it it'll do a separate virtual a
lock and create the pages we don't
actually support underflow I'm sorry
overflow checking in here so for example
we've got underflow checking support
here but we don't have any overflow
checking support so we want something
we're
are going to do like platform memory
overflow check right and this gets a
little bit tricky because now we can't
just do the basic thing that we were
doing before where we sort of allocated
the memory and then push the pointer
forward a few pages that's not going to
work because now we need to make sure we
line it up at the end of a page not at
the beginning of a page now I believe we
should still be able to say yeah I think
as long as we allocate those two extra
pages I think we'll probably be fine
because the allocation that we get back
I mean we will let's put it this way i'm
going to do the math out properly even
though i think we may be able to cheese
it just because we know the a persistent
is only is going to allocate on the 4k
page boundary anyway but we'll ignore
that for for a moment okay so if I have
this under float check on I know you
need to add two pages if I have the
overflow check on obviously I still need
two more pages one is for that the page
that blocks access and the other is for
the page that stores the header part and
in this case what I have is I need
additional some additional space to
effectively like align the other part of
the allocation so that it can end on
that boundary what that means is I need
to know how much extra it would take to
pad the size that I wanted right in fact
now that I look at this too since we're
doing two times page size this is not
actually correct this should have been
this
right because we don't need to account
for the win through to memory block
anymore when we're doing this stuff duh
because we're making a whole extra page
for that thing anyway so what I was
saying is now ok we do the underflow
checking it just works this way we do
the overflow checking now what we want
to say is well we don't really know what
this size is quite yet we know we need
the two extra pages we also need this
size to be rounded up to the next
boundary of pages right so we need to
sort of say what is that rounded up
version and we also probably want to do
a thing here where we're like okay a
base offset and what we could do with
the base offices say well if you look at
what happened we'll start it out at zero
if you look at what happened in the case
where we have the underflow checking you
can see that we did the base we added
two times the page size to it so what we
could do there is say well when when we
actually set that base pointer right
like right here we don't really have to
do that here we could do that up here
and so when we set the base when we set
the base pointer we could say like all
right wherever that base pointer is
going to end up is now going to get off
set well I guess hmm ya know that just
works so what we'll do is here in the
base of the base offset we know that if
we aren't doing any kind of overflow
tracking it just has to move past the
win through to memory block right so
again that would just be here's the the
the you eight of the block and then
we're going to add to it whatever that
base offset is right so we're just going
to move it past the header however in
other circumstances like in the one
where we're doing the underflow checking
then we know that we want to move it up
by one page size worth right this thing
here or a two page size worth rather one
for the for the header page and one for
the page that
marked as don't touch this page right so
in here we just have the base offset
equals 2 times page size right so that's
all there is to that now in the overflow
checking case we now know that there's
going to be a base offset that's used to
slide this up to align it and so we have
to do is compute both what the total
size is we need to allocate and what
that offset is to put the actual base
pointer at a location that will make it
so the end of the allocated space lines
up as close as possible to the the end
the the memory endpoint right okay and
we do have one other thing that we have
to do that has to do with alignment that
hopefully a lot of time to do after this
but we'll get to that a little later so
anyway what we need to do is say if this
size was going to be padded out to a
full like basically the entire 4k pages
worth whatever it would be will round it
up right so I basically need to round
this up to a page size rounding it up to
the page size is you know rounded size
or size rounded up just means that I
have to essentially take whatever
whatever part of it was not it I don't
know why my brain is explaining this
poorly remember we have this guy a line
pao2 right where we basically just we
add in 1 minus the entirety of the thing
we wanted to do to sort of move it up to
the next value and then we get rid of
anything in the bottom it's it's
essentially just saying draw this out
because I'm my brain is for some for
some reason too tired today to give a
good verbal explanation of this so I'm
gonna try and say it a little more
clearly so you know in in integer space
right we've got something that looks
like you know like this it's like
you know 0 1 1 0 1 or something like
this and we know that what we want to do
is we want to round up to the nearest
thing on this side right and maybe
there's even some stuff over here right
so we want to round up so that we know
that we're not using any of these bits
right so what we do in order to do that
is we just say well if we added this
number right if we added all ones down
here then we know we would produce a 1
here right and carry forward if there
was any bit set down here at all and
that's precisely the thing that we
actually care about right is if there
are any bits set down here because if
you think about what happens if i have a
number i said like i want to align it to
a 16-byte boundary right then it doesn't
matter whether i have 1 2 3 4 5 6 any
number other than zero right in that
bottom part in that bottom 0 to 15 which
is what this would represent write any
number in that bottom part is too much
we will need to go up to another one if
it's all zeros I wouldn't need to go up
to another one but if it's anything else
I do so we want to add essentially one
you know just the number whatever we're
wrapping 2-1 to do that bump then we
clear out the bottom bits at that point
because we know we've got the rounded up
value so this is all I'm trying to do
and so I'll do my align power too and I
say the value that I wanted was the size
and the win32 page size is the thing
that I want to align it to now I knew I
have the size rounded up so now I know
that the size i'm using is sized rounded
up plus 2 times the page size the base
offset is going to be first the page
size to get me past the header part
right then I'm going to add the size
rounded up which would get me to the end
of the memory block and then I want to
go back however much I was actually
trying to allocate so I start in and
right at that ending point right and
then all the rest of the stuff should
work the same now once I do the
underflow check or over
so check think here then what I need to
do is the exact same thing that I would
have done in the underflow checking case
but what I need to do now is say instead
of block plus page size what I actually
need to do is go up to and you know what
i could do actually now think about it
if either of these are set what i could
do is just say protect offset right i
could just do exactly the same trick and
say alright there's going to be a
protective set in the case where we
doing underflow checking to protect
offset is just the page size right in
the case where we're doing over overflow
checking it's going to be the page slice
plus the size rounded up it's going to
be all the way to that that final page
and then it just runs this in either
case since I suppose since the protect
offset itself is set to zero when there
isn't anything in particular that's
being protected I suppose we could also
have done this by just saying if protect
offset but this is a little bit more
correct at the moment so I'm going to
leave it that way all right so in theory
that will do the overflow checking now
but I'm not entirely sure and hey it
looks like it did because remember we
inserted this line as a bug yesterday to
say when our overflow checking worked it
will catch this error and it caught the
error right remember that was just a
silent bug we inserted that we never
would have known was there until we saw
some bad behavior when it over wrote
something and now we actually know that
we can catch it so that's pretty that's
pretty awesome right there let's go
actually remove that because hey we
don't want to leave the bug in that we
inserted intentionally but now we know
at least that our overflow checking will
catch overflows okay so where did we add
that guy all right there we go and now
we're good so if i run it again now we
should be just overflow checking our
actual
code now and like I said before I think
I had a question yesterday on the QA
where someone said they were asking why
are we adding overflow checking if it
hasn't come up yet and I believe that my
answer to that hopefully is prescient
here assuming that we're actually doing
it properly is that we don't actually
know that we don't have any right the
whole point of overflow checking is not
to catch overflow bugs that you are
having currently necessarily there to
find any overflows you might have that
are not causing obvious problems yet
because typically the most difficult
underfloor overflow bugs to catch are
ones that don't immediately manifest
themselves the more immediately the man
SSL is the less likely you are to need
overflow or underflow jacketing to
actually find them so in this case you
can see we're getting an actual thing
here it suggests that we may just
actually have a bug here now we haven't
really debugged our overflow checking
itself yet so it's a little bit
premature to suggest that we know or
don't know that something like that is
happening but let's take a look and see
what is happening here I'm not sure this
doesn't look but in particularly onerous
so maybe that we're right because this
this looks roughly correct to me I so
i'm not sure why we're getting a why
we're getting one there I wonder if we
are slightly off on the way we're
passing back but you can see here yet
you can see our ass getting the desk
pointer out of out of this push we are
pushing one more than we need which is
what we would expect we're then going
through the characters for that and
we're putting them on there it looks
like at the end when we do desk length
which we should be able to do right that
it's thinking that that's an overwrite
on that but I don't know why that would
be an overwrite let's take a look
because now also one of the things we
can do is we know that that best pointer
is actually like an individual
allocation because when we're running in
overflow checking mode we know that each
of them was allocated will be basically
on a page that we can then look at so we
should be able to take a look at it here
and see
there it is and we should be able to
figure out whether it actually gave us
the page boundary minus the amount that
we requested right so length plus 1 in
this case was five so we should know
that there we should be able to get five
things we should have been able to get
five spaces before the end right it
should have given us back five spaces
before we would overwrite and and have a
problem and let's see if we did so we
can see here we've got FFC so we could
trivially do the subtraction here and
see how many we actually got right and
that's definitely not the right number
of of characters to be able to write
because we should have been able to
write to five locations and in this case
we're only going to be able to write to
four locations perhaps a more correct
way to have written it so you could see
that was this way and so we we have one
that's missing there and exactly as we
would expect because our bounds checking
is protecting the page immediately after
it as soon as we try to right there
we're going to have a problem so let's
take a look I don't know if the first
time through this happens it would be
great if it did it does so now we can at
least debug what we're doing in our
allocation that's making that not work
properly let's take a look so we compute
our effective size for the effective
size for in this case is five so that's
fine that's what we would expect to see
and then we're going to say what's the
block size that we allocate the block
size is going to be five again totally
fine so let's go into our memory
allocator here where presumably we're
having our problem we can see our page
size is 4k the total size that we need
to allocate is going to be 69 bytes
because the size is 5 and then the side
the one with 3des memory block of course
being 64 because its cache line size we
have the base offset is just going to be
that which we're not going to use
because we overwrite all these same with
them protected offset we don't have
underflow checking on we do
have overflowed checking on so now we
take a look at what our size rounded up
is our size rounded up is 4096 that is
correct because if we're asking for five
we know we'd only need one page
obviously the store five so then we take
a look at whether our total size is our
total size is going to be that one page
there's going to be three pages right
which is what we would expect so if I do
total size divided right up by 4096 I
should get through pages than I do so
that's nice similarly eight eventually I
can do it this way just to make sure
it's not a rounding thing you can see
it's exactly what we would expect so
then we take a look at what the offs
that's going to be it's going to be one
page forward then it's going to be
however much the size roundup is minus
that five okay and so what that should
give us is it should give us you know
I'll put it Oh leap out and then come
back a little bit right although the
page boundary but coming back a little
bit so that isn't really what we were
seeing and so we'll have to go take a
look at why but it could be that we're
touching this somewhere a little bit
further up but let's double-check so if
i come through here and look at what the
base offset is the base offset is eight
one eight seven so if we were to take a
look at what we would expect that to be
8187 you can see that it's putting it
exactly where I wanted it so that seems
to be correct and if i look at block
block base you can see that that's not
see it's B which is what we would expect
so where is that plus one coming from is
what we need to know we do the virtual
protect that's what we think we should
do so that's fine we come back we get
our block and now let me just see what
we're doing here in terms of getting the
actual memory
get alignment offset may be our problem
aha yes so this is actually I guess the
thing that I said when we went back a
little bit beforehand where I said we're
going to have one more thing to do with
alignment well this was the thing I
wasn't sure if we'd ever hit it but it
looks like we will hit it because the
default alignment of four is in effect
even on things like strings which can
have odd alignments like that so the
problem that we have here is basically
that we need to make sure that the size
we passed down to the allocator is
always aligned to the size we expect to
align to afterwards because otherwise
when it does the back up it's not going
to work right and so I'm not sure
exactly the best way to do that there's
two ways we can do it one way is we can
modify the size first and then pass it
down and the reason that we would do
that is because if we want to make sure
that we are always clean in all the
circumstances we can do that the only
reason not to do that is if we do do
that padding it means that if the next
allocation was something that didn't
actually need to be aligned itself
because it's an alignment of one or
something else then we shouldn't have
done it because we're wasting a little
bit of space I'm not sure I care about
that too much but yet it's a little
subtle let's put it that way so let's
take a quick look here what we would
probably have to do to make that work
okay and I think that's the last thing
as far as overflow or underflow checking
is concerned I don't think there's
anything else in particular that we need
to be aware of but so if i come through
here then essentially what's going to
happen is once I do this allocation I'm
going to get back something that's been
slit up to the to the end of the
boundary at that point because we split
it up to be right before the battery if
it what if its size wasn't aligned to
this the size to the alignment that we
wanted we're effectively doing that
sliding up is going to unaligned it and
then
we're going to try to alignment by
applying the alignment offset and that's
going to make it be in the wrong place
right that's that's that's going to ruin
that's going to ruin our fun so again we
have two choices here one is we can make
sure that the size is always also
aligned that way when we go down to the
subsystem the win32 subsystem it will
leave us aligned because the size itself
will have been aligned the other thing
we can do is pass the alignment down to
the win32 subsystem so that when it does
the adjustment it will back align will
it will move it back up the amount that
it needs to for the alignment ah yeah i
think what i'm going to do is just say
let's go ahead and and do let's go ahead
and align it to the alignment that it's
asking for that just seems like maybe an
easier thing to do and so i'll just say
all right you know initialize to the
size in it if we're going to be in one
of these overflow or underflow checking
scenarios then what i want to do is say
size equals a line pao2 and we'll pass
in a you know itself and then whatever
the alignment is that we're currently
using and now we shouldn't have that
problem right in theory now when we do
this and we do the allocation in theory
now the pointer that we got back where
is the point that we got back there it
is should be properly 4-byte align and
you can see that is it left eight
characters right and so as you can
imagine it's kind of annoying because
now we get worse we always will get
worse bounds checking but there's really
nothing we can do about that right uh we
can only get as good a balance
checking and still maintain alignment we
can't get any better Bow striking and
still maintain alignment right if that
makes sense and alignment is like a hard
requirement it's in a lot of cases all
right so hey sadly for us it looks like
I mean maybe good job for us I don't
know which one to say but it looks like
there aren't any particular overflow
bugs to catch that we had in our code at
the moment so hey I guess we did a good
job on that before but we do now know
that we can check for them right and so
that's all well and good what we want to
do now to is make sure we don't have to
check for that right we can always turn
off our bounds checking and then run and
we should be back to our nice it be
frame rate because now things are never
calling the allocator which is what we
want so that's it for for the sort of
debug allocation stuff there's I don't
think there's anything else in
particular that we want to do let's make
sure that we can still do loop code
editing let's see here that doesn't look
good source block size how is it getting
set meowzers that's just ridiculously
big let's make sure because like I said
we want to make we don't want to we
don't want to break anything so let's
see what happened there we've got block
size what is
where is my buck it's right here so how
did that sighs get set to a new unusual
value what happened there let's well let
me take a look closer look at it first
before I try to figure that out so we're
looping through here and I guess I would
say this this looks very suspicious I'm
not sure this is valid at all in fact
it's definitely not right you can see
this is kind of nonsense here so let me
take a look at what happened there let's
let's jump in here so there's our
Sentinel and you know here's our blocks
I will say not encouraging looking that
one looks reasonable this one does not
look even remotely reasonable none of
this looks at all reasonable it's quite
ridiculous quite whereas these all look
very reasonable so it looks like our
next pointer is having some issues there
let's take a look at why that might be
happening oops
so here is our 1 through 2 memory block
when we are passing in this block we're
passing in that right there we've got
the next in previous pointers we do the
free memory block on this guy which is
what we would expect so that all looks
relatively good to me we no longer need
this page size in there so that's good
too and presumably this can now move
inside here also so there we go so what
we want to do here is just figure out
who is is making our block act weirdly
you can see here where we're setting it
we always set the next point or equal to
the sentinel we always set the pre
pointer equal the sentinel prieve I
don't think any of these things these
are ticketed here I don't know if
anything else would have to be ticketed
it doesn't look like it would be because
that's the only thing that actually
touches part of the linked list as far
as I can tell none of these other ones
would really be involved I don't think
so that all looks pretty reasonable I'm
going to take a look and see if I can
spot we'll leave it for tomorrow if I
can't spot it but I want to take a quick
look just to see if there's an obvious
reason why that's happening let me take
a look at the first time of lock is
freed just want to see what the the
values are here
so here's the first time I block is
freed and you can see that I assume that
this is the Sentinel here in fact you
can tell it is because here's the hard
address for it so it's actually
obviously not a dynamic allocation so
the next one here is the Sentinel and
you can see there's quite a few
allocations already on the table before
we actually free one of these
allocations but at the moment anyway if
you look at the Sentinel it's not wrong
like it looks just fine so we take the
mutex we set the next and previous and
then it still appears to me like
everything is relatively good right
look I don't see anything particularly
unusual here going on so i'm not sure
where that corruption is necessarily
coming in but let's go ahead and keep
running here there we go and so for
whatever reason when we actually get in
here now if you would think that we
would have seen some error by now in the
usage but for some reason we don't but
then if we take a look now at the
Sentinel we will see I think that that
next pointer is messed up yeah so I'm
going to leave that one because that
might take a while to track down so
let's go to the Q&amp;A first and then we'll
check check that one data then I think
we're done loving that Q&amp;A session
repeater thing
it looks like hmd bot is doing it now so
it's not in in so but oh no I see in
sohbat replicates the QA and then hmd
bot prints out the actual information
can we just talk about how in so bot is
like a national treasure International
treasure at this point really that is a
great question in savate just asked
bashing Tim berners-lee inventor of the
outer loop from zero to free everything
it's kind of like in so bot is is sort
of like the beat poet of our generation
there was a great cartoon from a long
time ago called technological threat I
don't know if you ever saw it but it was
basically like a this like office that
slowly got replaced with computers or
whatever and it reminds me of what's
happening in the chat with all these
bots taking over from script maybe set
the default alignment to one winning
memory checking mode yeah that does seem
like a good idea we would require a
pound to find for that let me put this
in the to do list maybe we'll do that we
did this set default alignment to one in
overflow underflow checking nodes
because that's not called on the arena
we could maybe make that work though we
could maybe make that work and also
debug loop or mmm block list there we go
I know this is a little off topic to
what you're currently doing on streaming
but what role does a software driver
play if any at all to what are you
referring when you say software driver i
guess i would i would say the reason
that that was a that phraseology was a
little confusing is because all drivers
are software so do you mean a driver
like a software rasterizing like out
like a software opengl driver as a boat
like one that does the rendering and
software instead of you know driving a
graphics card or is there something I'm
not sure I understand the question
to anyway no you can make a c+ project
that enables you to use resources that
you can't use in user mode in the
colonel ah I understand I think what
you're saying so what you're talking
about is installing something at the as
a driver that exposes something to you a
that you would normally have to be in
kernel mode to access so that is
definitely something it depends largely
on the operating system when you need
that and when you don't so for example
on windows file systems have to have a
driver right in order to be a file
system you have to be a driver so you
can't just write an app that you run in
user space that implements a file system
so one of the things that people have
done is made a driver that all it does
is forward all of the driver calls out
into user space so that you can
implement user mode file systems right I
guess what I would say is I don't have
much to say on that topic that is
generally just something that has to do
with what your operating system
considers privileged and what it doesn't
and certainly anytime you want to access
something that is relatively hardware
related such as implementing file system
or accessing performance counters of
some kind that may be protected
depending on how your operating system
works you may have to implement a driver
in order to get at that stuff because by
default the operating system is not
going to run your application in a way
that it can get it sometimes that's
because of protections so sometimes
that's like I want to access something
on the hardware that it's the operation
through prevents me from doing so if I'm
not a driver other times it made us be
because that's the way the operating
systems API is set up so for example
with the file system stuff it's not so
much that the operating system is trying
to prevent a user space application
from accessing something like us us sdd
drive it's because the fundamental
infrastructure for how hard work like at
sdg drive or something is implemented in
Windows is that it all stays in kernel
space presumably for performance reasons
right so you just have to be down at
that level if you want to interact with
the operating system that way but
there's nothing inherently stopping you
from just forwarding those calls out to
a user space thing and then processing
them there it's just that the operating
system doesn't do that by default
because it wants to be more efficient or
something right so you know that's
usually how those sorts things go but
you're you're doing it usually for one
of those two reasons either you're
trying to forward operating system API
stuff out to the user level and that API
stuff really only exists at the kernel
level or you're trying to access
something that's protected so that the
user it's not something that the
operating system set up an API for
necessarily but it is something that the
application can't get at because it's
walled off and the only place the
operating system allows you to get at it
is if you're in kernel mode
what are we doing here people there's no
more q Colin's there's no mark your
clones I'm done I get some time
alright thank you everyone for joining
me for an episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to you know
follow along at home with series you can
always pre-order the game on Hammond
organ it comes with a source code so you
can experiment yourself we also have a
forum site you go to want to ask
questions a patreon page to wanna
support the video series is scheduled
about the tweets scheduled at you if you
would like to know one we're going to be
live and an episode guide that you can
use to catch up on past episodes that is
it for today and for the week tomorrow
is no stream I will be back next week so
do check the tweetbot for more
information on that until then have fun
programming everyone and I'll see you
guys on the internet take it easy
everybody