hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero the show where we code a complete
game live on stream we today have to
start the process of actually using
light probes in our game we are
switching to them because we wanted two
things
out of it one I wanted a more convenient
way to sample sort of ancillary entities
so I wanted to be able to light
everything in the game kind of easily
and have everything go through a
lighting pass more easily hopefully and
so we want to take a look at that but
the other thing that we want to be able
to do as well is we wanted to be able to
reduce the number of light samples that
we take and because we had previously
locked the number of light samples to be
roughly the same as the amount of
reflectors that pretty dramatically
affected our ability to place samples
only where we actually needed them or
wanted them so what we're gonna do today
is we already did a bunch of the work
for this like yesterday but what we want
to do today is to start the process of
actually feeding like the lighting
system with light probe information so
we can start debugging and tweaking that
process now our goal for today and
probably next weekend it's gonna take it
like I said it's gonna take a while
because lighting is hard mm-hmm there's
a lot of stuff you got to do our goal
for today and probably also next
Saturday or something is we want to get
to the point where our light probes are
working but nothing else so we're not
going to try to change how the world of
getting lit right now we're just leave
that exactly as it is and what we're
gonna try to do them is we're going to
try to get our light probes working so
that we can draw all of our light probes
and see that their light the amount of
light they claim is coming from each
direction
looks you know roughly reasonable to
sort of a cursory inspection that's the
first step in getting our light probes
working and for obvious reasons I want
to go there first rather than try to get
everything working all at once because
what I'm trying to do and you've seen me
do this many times on handmade hero is
anytime you're working with a very
complex system especially one that it's
very hard to test right this is a very
visual approximate kind of a part of the
code right especially when you're
working saying that's pretty hard to
test and and pretty hard to know really
you know what you would put through it
to say yes it's working no it's not you
want to try and find verifiable way
points in that process so that you can
do a small chunk debug just that part be
reasonably sure that it's okay and then
move on to the next part that way you're
not just blindly looking through in a
giant pipeline for where the bug might
be and so rather than try to debug
things by doing the whole thing and then
looking at why the lighting is wrong and
having to just go I don't know is it
because the probes are wrong is it
because the shaders wrong is it because
bla bla bla bla bla what I want to do
instead is just go alright let's try to
get to a waypoint first which is can we
see light probes drawn in the
environment do they look like they're
drawn roughly correct so if I move a
light around do the probes near the
light seemed to be getting brighter and
furthermore is like the up Direction
brighter than the down direction if I if
the probe is high and if the I mean if
the light is high and if the light is
low is the down Direction brighter than
the top right and so um that will give
us a way of sort of verifying that our
lighting solution is pursuit producing
usable results in the propagation stage
before trying to move to the stage where
we're actually lighting the things in
the game and that way we can be more
effective right we can we could have
more effective
bugging so that's all we're doing but
like I said lighting is complicated so
it takes a while even if everything goes
well there's just a lot of code and and
so that's just how it works
I maybe someday in video we'll just
solve this problem for us if they get
ray tracing good enough you just make a
call called GPU turn ray tracing on and
you'd have all your lighting done I mean
I realize it sounds ridiculous given how
much work lighting is but if you think
about it that's how much work
rasterization used to be and nowadays
that is literally what you do you make a
call that's like hey here's a million
triangles draw them and it just does
right you don't do anything else that
would have been a ludicrous idea in you
know 1991 when you know the people that
looked when Chris green was writing a
texture mapper for Ultima Underworld or
something right if you told him like oh
yeah like well she was earlier than that
it's like 1990 probably right if you're
like oh yeah the you know in in six
years you'll just it'll just be like you
make a call and the PC does all of that
stuff for you it'll be just like it
looks like an SGI workstation right
anyway so you never know right you never
know eventually we may not have to deal
with this stuff and that would be great
because hey that's just more time you
can spend on doing something else
because it's not like we don't know what
we want to have happen with the lighting
we do it's just we have to make all
these approximations because it's too
expensive to try and compute real
ray-traced results every frame let's go
ahead and open up our lighting system
and see how we might proceed like I said
yesterday the biggest thing that we need
to move towards now is if you look at
how our lighting is working we have
these light probes here that we need to
operate on and we don't actually send
any down right so that's really the
entirety
of the issue for us is we're not we're
not getting any light probes so before
we can even start we wrote a bunch of
code yesterday before we can even start
testing that code and seeing if that
code works or drawing the results of
that code or doing anything right we
have to get light probes in here so it'd
be pointless for me to go take that code
we did and try to like start moving
light around through it or something
right because it just it doesn't make
any sense we don't have any light probes
to start with so the first thing we need
to do is get the actual light probes in
here this is a plumbing problem and so
we're gonna go ahead and and try to
address that now if I remember correctly
we left ourselves I think I don't
actually know if this is true by the way
I need to update my remedy don't I oh
yeah we're way behind hmm can I do that
here I may not be logged in I'm not
logged in well sorry about that we'll
get a new remedy soon because there's a
much updated version although maybe I
think George said he finished data break
points recently so maybe that version
will be out soon it will update to that
I don't think there's anything in
particular I need right now so I'm okay
using the existing version of remedy
here but point being we're a little
behind here sorry I'm so sorry about
that George I gotta pick this machine I
I update my dead machine at work all the
time but I sometimes forget to update
the Hameed hero machine all right so
here's the win32 handmade our-our ubg
i'm gonna load that up here and if we
run it I think we just turned lighting
off right and yeah it looks that way so
you can kind of see here like lighting
is off entirely right now I also don't
know is this a debug build or a regular
builds I'm not sure about that part
either it looks like it's an optimized
build I'm gonna go ahead and turn it
into a debug build and then what I also
might do is I might I might go ahead and
and turn off whatever slow about the
lighting for the moment as well so that
up there so I believe if we take a look
at what's actually happening
in the game here if I take a look at the
profile you can see the compute light
propagation is still getting called even
though I'm not actually doing I'm not
actually applying the lighting because I
turned it off in the shader so what I'd
like to do now is I'd like to go into
the lighting because we don't need it
anymore at the immediate moment right
and compute light propagation here I'm
just gonna get rid of that so this this
function is just gonna go away for the
moment and we're only gonna actually put
it back in here until I we're only gonna
add it back in once I've done some work
with the light probes and we actually
want to run it and so now if we run our
system here we should see some speed
increase there although okay when I said
we should see in blah blah blah what I
meant was if you actually compile
properly that's what's supposed to
happen there there we go so compute
light propagation also it's remember
it's threaded we do our light
propagation on multiple threads because
it's an expensive thing alright so let's
try that one more time
all right so here's our actual speed of
the game in debug mode which is good
much better than it was and now also as
I relieve I mentioned this kind of if
you watched the whole series you saw me
say this two weeks ago or something when
we did ground cover you can see how
expensive this stuff is getting so
render ground cover it's very expensive
in debug mode if I actually change to
release mode obviously it gets a lot
faster because it's just math ops that
get optimized there so you know if we're
actually compiling in full release you
will see that that gets dramatically
faster why I didn't just recompile it I
don't know I always forget that we can
just recompile handmade hero and have it
replace the thing but obviously it gets
a lot faster if I compile it in release
mode but even so you can see that
render ground cover is pretty
significant there right it's more
expensive even than than gathering up
all of the debug information that we
spew into the log for processing which
used to be our biggest amount of time
spent so this right here this render
ground cover as you can see is like
really really expensive and that's to be
expected but also something we could
dramatically improve so if you go to
like the entity side of things here and
we look at how the render ground cover
section here it is you look at how
expensive the rendered ground cover
section is you can see why it's so slow
there's especially this part here right
where we're getting these texture
handles back it's just really you know
well here show you get assets so well
actually this was that part's not that
bad cuz as long as it's valid I guess
it's probably okay this is a bit fussy
so that's not great but then if you look
here right the amount of computations
necessary for this stuff are kind of
ridiculous right you can see we've got
to go through all this nonsense here
there's this ridiculous garbage here
right all of this stuff has to happen
and then we've got this stuff here again
just really ridiculous just just way too
much code right and so all of this stuff
here could have really have been cached
you know I'm saying like the only thing
that we might not have been able to
cache is the bitmap part of things the
texture handle part because we're not
you know we have to maybe make some
extra affordances in our renderer for
being able to say that I want you to not
evict certain bitmaps because they're
used in high volume scenarios or
something like that that you know
shouldn't get thrown out away until I
can tell you definitively that I'm done
with them
so there's definitely like you know a
bit of this that that maybe can't be
optimised away as much as it should be
but everything in here like this entire
set section in here all of that could be
cached and would only have to update
when the texture handle updated right
and not only could it be cached in terms
of not having to have the CPU compute it
but it could actually be cached on the
graphics card right so all of the data
that you would need for drawing the
entire thing all of that could just live
on the graphics card and we wouldn't
have to do any of this and we wouldn't
have to send it down right so it's just
worth recognizing that there's a ton of
work we could do there as well that
we're just not doing right now
and so that's again we're in a good
position the part of our game that is
slow in debug mode actually doesn't need
to be slow anyway we can improve it
pretty dramatically and that's pretty
great alright but let's continue on with
the lighting because like I said if we
want to be fast we can just compile in
release mode right now and we're very
fast anyway
you know we're hitting 60 frames a
second and not really any issues I don't
think although well there are some the
renderer does need to be optimized a
little bit you can see we're not quite
hitting it reliably we should be way
under that I think probably most the
time although I guess with vsync on is
vsync on or off right now and actually
no-fee sinks on or off
we don't have a thing for that doing
let's take a look so when we want to do
our request vsync here by default it
looks like it's it's requesting it
now why aren't we
why isn't that actually something that
we provide for switching because you can
can't you
I don't know maybe you can let's see
here not actually sure so if I wanted to
can I turn vsync on and off
one more time
there yeah all right so
so it's a little bit hard to say I'll be
honest I'm not sure I understand exactly
I'm seeing there it might be that vsync
request vsync is not actually doesn't
actually update when you change it there
that's what it looks like to me it just
seems really unlikely that that would
actually happen so let's take a look at
that sorry to kind of get off-track here
but I'm just curious I want to know
what's going on with there so in here
we've got change to settings and here is
our platform OpenGL set vsync thing so
if we look at OpenGL set vsync it looks
like that should be calling the correct
thing but maybe it doesn't I don't know
let's take a look so if I do platform
OpenGL if I basically set a breakpoint
at this function what happens
looks like it's not getting called for
some reason although that may just be
that the breakpoint isn't triggering
because of some kind of thing Burke got
optimized out let me just see what
happens in a full debug build do we so
do we not call it there either
okay I do think so I don't know that
that does seem like maybe they're it's
weird that that didn't have a breakpoint
set properly I wonder if we should
mention that to George because it
probably still should have set a
breakpoint somewhere but yeah anyway
let's see what happens here
so we're actually making the call
properly vsync enabled should be true
right now so it's going to call a wiggle
swap interval X with one there so that
that's what that did and now we just
have to kind of see okay if I jump into
the render settings and I ask it to
change vsync do I actually get in here
so if you think enabled there is zero so
it should pass zero so it sure looks
like we're setting it properly I mean it
could be that you know it's certainly
possible that we are asking for vsync
and getting it and then asking for
nobody sync and getting it but we just
happen to take roughly a sixtieth of a
second to render but I don't know man
chances seem pretty low that that would
be the case so we know that we're doing
the right thing here's our frame time
it's you know 118 roughly kind of has a
hiccup in there
based on the frames lay so that's
happening and then if I turn it to true
that that seems like I don't know that
that just seems like we're getting vsync
no matter what we do to me so I guess I
don't know why we're seeing that
particular behavior that's a bit strange
it may be that for some reason we're
just not able to call wiggle swap
interval but I'm not sure why let's take
a look at wiggle swap interval
I mean it seems pretty straightforward
I don't know I don't know why that
exactly would be failing
I don't know
so that's a bit of a puzzler because it
looks as if we can't request no vsync
and I'm not really sure why that may
just be luck that that's happening but
I'm not sure so we may want to put to do
in here I don't know if we've got the
issue list and I'm gonna just put a note
that we should figure this out at some
point because something is off there so
I'm going to go ahead and do a new issue
here I'm gonna say are we actually able
to turn off vsync and I'm just gonna say
cursory inspection seems like we aren't
able to turn off vsync we need to look
and see if there's
so I don't know might not be anything we
may look at it later and determine that
it's actually fine but it does look a
little bit wonky so I just want to flag
that as something we should take a look
at all right back to light probes so now
what we've got we know we were drawing
in purple there where all the light
probes where we placed all of our light
probes and so now we have to do is
actually take those light probes and
feed them forward into the renderer so
that on any given frame the renderer
knows what light probes are actually in
the mix and which light probes aren't
right it needs to have some idea of what
the light probes are or aren't and
what's interesting about that is if we
go to the world's cache you know we've
got this notion in here where you can
see when we unpack entities right when
we're doing our our entity unpacking we
have this notion of entities coming into
the working set and he's going out of
the working set and since our light
probes themselves are entities it seems
like what we probably want to do here is
start to think about the lighting
solution as something we just want to
manage as part of the world cash in on
cash so if you take a look at how its
currently working its kind of stupid
right we have this entity structure and
we're you know and we knew it was stupid
the time so not bad on us it's just
we're delaying till we were gonna
actually work on it but you can see we
got this ridiculous lighting nonsense in
here as part of our cached entities but
we don't really need to do that anymore
what we can do instead is every time an
entity gets unpacked that has that's
that's one of our light probes we can
just add a light probe to the probe set
in the lighting system and every time
and
gets repacked that had a light probe we
can just pack that probe back up and by
pack it up I don't actually mean pack it
up I guess I just mean discard it
because we don't need it anymore right
it's it's fallen it's gotten too far
away to be relevant right so I think um
I think we should be okay with that you
know where my little basket is basket
come to me come to me waste basket there
we go all right so I think that's more
what we want to do so I'm going to start
down that road and that'll be how our
light probes like kind of work in terms
of coming into or out of the active set
and then what we can do is we know that
if we render them as entities we see
them we could do a secondary render that
shows us not only where our lighting
probe entities are but where our light
probes are and we can verify that that's
correct so as things move in and out of
the set that we're getting a correct
result there right so in here where we
have lightning point state with lighting
here like this what I want to do is just
start by eliminating this so that's
gonna go away entirely and one of the
things about that going away entirely is
that we'll pull a ton of code out of our
system right it's going to go away so
now when we look at things like push
light right and this sort of thing
the lighting point state light store
stuff all of that is going to get yanked
out and the reason that it's going to
get yanked out is because we no longer
actually need this information to be
present at all right
not sure what the right way to say this
is so the lighting Point State was a
cache of light information in the system
and we don't actually need that there
right we do need to be able to push
lights into the system and we may want
those lights to be special in some way I
don't know but we don't need to have
them have these caches anymore because
the light probes themselves will act as
the caches I guess it's the right way to
say it this is actually really good for
us because it eliminates a bunch of
bookkeeping that had to happen during
render time and that bookkeeping is
expensive so getting rid of it will also
sort of speed things up a little bit if
that makes sense so I'm gonna get rid of
this and this and we're just gonna kind
of slowly work our way through there
and you know this probably is a bit of
it to do here where we're basically to
say look
I don't actually know exactly what we
want to do here it's kind of a little
bit confusing but it's probably
something like we want to just push a
special-purpose light probe in that
emits this light I don't really know it
may be that we to be to be honest now I
think about it we probably don't want
that we probably want to keep a separate
list of lights
they don't really need their data cached
so I think maybe we probably just need a
separate list of lights per frame that's
probably what we want
so anyway I'm gonna get rid of this also
when we push cubes pushing an emission
value onto a cube probably isn't is also
something we don't really want to have
happen anymore so getting rid of that
emissive value I think probably we want
I it's a little hard to say
I'm not really sure exactly how we want
to deal with that part because we do
want to be able to have emissive values
I guess in a sense so I guess I'm gonna
leave that in now to think about it
because maybe that's actually fine
I don't know we're gonna leave that as
an open question but I'm not gonna pull
the emissive values yet I am however
going to also get rid of the lighting
Point State thing so this nonsense here
that's going away and I'll just
eliminate it everywhere cuz that'll
generate errors for me in all the places
that we're using it and so on all right
lighting box will also probably go away
as well so here's our lighting point
state with our light store in it that's
gonna go away there all of this stuff
where we're doing this push cube here
the lighting part of things needs to go
away so the lighting enabled stuff just
just goes away
so all of this light count light index
you can see how much code was in here
too
right look at all this stuff this is all
gonna go away it's just gonna be
happening inside the pixel shader the
lookups will be happening there so all
of this stuff can can sort of get
cleaned up and I like that a lot like I
said it's all good it's very good when
we're pushing quads here the emission
for the quads oops again I don't think
we actually want what we really want to
do is just when we put the cube down
there we just want to store the fact
that this cube needed to be considered
as part of the lighting system but
that's all we really needed it to do and
so that stuff goes away I think also
this emission value when we push a quad
down with an emission value there I
don't actually know that we need the
quad to know about its emission value
it's possible that we do but I'm not
actually sure if we do or don't so if we
take a look at here like where that
emissions getting used at the moment
yeah you can kind of see it's just not
relevant right and I think we want to
just get rid of this because the quad if
you want to encode if you want to encode
the emission value so that the quad just
appears very bright that might make
sense but I really don't know again not
really sure so I'm just gonna leave the
emission in there and the reason I say
that is because although in here we
don't really need the lighting value in
that sense meaning we don't actually
need
we don't need the quads to have any idea
about lighting at all anymore they're
just render primitives which is what we
want and that's good but for a parameter
like emission when we have a quad that's
supposed to light up right so this quad
is supposed to be lit and bright when
that happens we want the face itself not
to like be shadowed or anything right
it's emitting light so we may need to
encode in into our like color values or
something we may need to encode the fact
that this is not reflective it's emits
emissive with a certain level of
emissive color so even though this thing
is not being used right now at all I
think I want to keep it in the pipe
because I think eventually we may need
an additional value here at least one
floating-point value that just says how
bright the quad should be of its own
accord so I think we can't get away with
eliminating a missing Commission
entirely and so I'm going to leave that
in there on as a sort of proactive
assumption that that you know that will
have to change at some point for render
clarity right alright so looking at
textured vertex here we've got a bunch
of stuff we've got a normal perfect that
says it doesn't need to be pervert X I
don't know if I necessarily agree with
that we may Bend that so I'm gonna
actually get rid of that notion
these don't but they're going away now
light UV not sure what that's supposed
to be don't have any idea what that is
if we look in here at like things for
lighting UV I don't know does anyone use
that nobody does so who knows why that
was there
so we're gonna get rid of all that stuff
all that's gone we're just gonna have a
point a normal a UV and a color which is
a pretty standard layout for a vertex
and off you go
okay so Jimmy
so moving on we've got the vertex at rib
pointers here for textured vertices that
are sending down those light indexes we
don't want that anymore so that's gonna
go away again just pulling stuff out of
the pipeline here those don't need to
get sent down at all
similarly when we're doing our push
quads here anybody who was passing
through light information that can go
away as well let's take a look at the
debug light store here okay so in here
where we're storing this light for our
debug light again that doesn't need to
be there either because again those
things don't have to get cash anymore
you can kind of see that assuming we're
able to make all this work getting rid
of all this code is also great right
this is all code that was costing us
time before and now we don't have it
right so that's all very good oops
so hopefully you know that's all like
gonna be a plus again just pulling out
the vestigial remains there you can kind
of see in here we've got the storage for
our you know where where we were putting
the information we don't need that stuff
anymore
[Music]
that's just blending the old light
solution in so again to get rid of that
and this stuff is all gonna get nuked
anyway where's our letting Point State
there it is so when we're doing this
sort of like yeah this part where we're
working the lighting point States back
up again again don't actually need this
for anything so I'm gonna just walk
through here and pull it out so box
store direction
[Music]
so the problem with this code is we may
want this rough code because we are
gonna be updating like we may want to
keep how this is sort of working a
little bit so I think what I'm gonna do
right now is I'm just gonna if zero this
guy because I want to look at this code
later when we implement the frame to
frame coherence of the new system so I
don't really want to get rid of it just
yet right okay so let's see here here
we've got our lighting push again that's
pushing on stuff it doesn't need to same
with here
so I'm just gonna gonna get rid of those
and leave them like this and that again
just cleaned out like a ton of stuff
right which is good
same here we don't need this don't know
where else we might have code of that
nature some push cube stuff that doesn't
do lighting so there we go and so now
again that sort of pulls the lighting
out of that sort of specific part of the
code and allows you to just run directly
now inside the actual renderer we need
to pull out the part where we're
actually doing that lighting as well so
if I go and look at the Z bias program
and we look at what we're actually doing
in there I want to get rid of the things
that expect to receive that so the vert
light index in the texture vert where is
it
well I guess only the vert light index
is getting past them I don't know
exactly what's going on there but the in
the the vert light index can go away and
so the frag light index can also go away
those two things wouldn't be passed down
anymore and so where that was getting
sort of sent through we can just get rid
of it right and then inside the actual
sampler here we don't need the light
zero sampler or the light one sampler
anymore but we're gonna leave those in
temporarily can get rid of the frag
light index and so in here I think all
that stuff gets if out on on lighting
enabled you can see here it just this
was the part we would have been looking
at that fried frag index and doing
something and so now we don't have to
worry about that
right and so here we're doing our
textile fetches from the light
information we're gonna want to keep
that so I'm gonna do an if lighting
disabled here and then I'm gonna do an
else and I'm just gonna get rid of all
of this stuff and we know that lighting
is in fact disabled at the moment you
can see it here so I think we're okay
mostly with what we're doing now but we
may have to fix some errors in the
shader right so it'll report those to us
OpenGL will or should okay so we're
almost there but you can see we're
missing our quads and so we probably
have some vertex alignment issues or
something who knows what we've got but
we'll we'll hunt it down
so in here we're not doing lighting so
we wouldn't expect there to be any
problems with that in the shader but let
me just make sure that we don't have any
of that oh you know what I just realized
actually
this this was our problem here we still
need this this texture index right so I
accidentally removed that one but we
still want that one right so I was just
being a little bit overzealous there and
forgot about that part of it but inside
the textured vertex yet we do need we do
need this just to tell it which texture
to grab so there is I guess still a
there is a thing that's you know we
don't really need to send this down
every time right if we have a quad that
consists of four vertices actually we
only need to tell the graphics card once
which texture index it is because you
can't change texture indices per pixel I
mean we could but why would we there it
literally doesn't do anything for us so
we're just kind of wasting space at that
point which kind of sucks this does
bring up one particularly interesting
option for us you can see this vertex is
highly unbalanced this point it would be
sixteen bits off but as we already said
you know right
we could put some emission in there
right probably not that would have to be
per pixel so I don't know so we know we
at least would like an emission level
right and it could be a 16-bit emission
level if we really want to and so that's
kind of a cool that's kind of a cool
option to sort of pack in there we
basically have sixteen bits that we
probably want to use up just to make
this thing be four four byte aligned so
I feel like that's a pretty clear option
of where the emission would go maybe we
want something else in there too but I
don't know at this point all right um
let's see how we're doing there so I got
to go we if out that part of the shader
though - sorry about that so like I said
we do want those texture indices to to
be sent down and then in the Z bias
program I want to make sure that that
lighting disabled stuff is still
learning disabled so this frag Boop's
this frag light index here doesn't need
to be there the same thing is true in
the shader itself so that frag light
index goes away I'm gonna go ahead and
put the if I'm disabled in here else and
then this whole part can also go away
and then this part should already have
the letting be completely disabled which
is what we want so I think we're pretty
good here
okay so now we just have to fix whatever
bug we introduced here where we're you
can see what's interesting about this as
you can see that for some reason solid
cubes are working so it's only things
with a texture on them that aren't so
I'm not sure if I did something weird
there with the with the Texel fetch but
I don't think so
so the frag texture index that's coming
in there the invert texture index there
oh you know what it may have been that I
forgot to delete that reference to the
in that could have been in actually
nope so we're still getting some kind of
a problem where the texture probably
with the texture index is not lined up
properly or something right so let's
take a look at what happens in that code
and just see if there was something
weird going on there we should just get
rid of this light index nonsense here
the vert light index stuff so I'm gonna
go into the prog system they're not
Prague the city but but Prague the the
structure so we've got this vert light
in next I'm gonna get delete that
because it might be that someone's using
that and we're creating an issue right
like this for example so I want to make
sure that that's not happening anywhere
and that's completely removed like this
there we go
and I don't know if there is anywhere
else we might need to fuss with it we'll
see in a second here but just kind of
starting to trim these away and then we
can do is we can open up insight and
take a look at what we're sending down
just make sure that we've got everything
before we start a little more hardcore
debugging to find out what went wrong
there but we're mostly good now I think
she's got to figure out where where we
lost our texture index there
[Music]
I'm gonna scan this really quickly and I
would like it to not be behind my head
so just looking through here at vert
texture index
it all seems pretty good I'm not seeing
anything weird
the lighting stuff is all more or less
gone
[Music]
then I'll seem fine
so that all seems that all seems fine
you can see here the sampling from the
frag texture index which is set there
but oh you know nice realized when I was
being overzealous there I probably
forgot to fill out the texture index
yeah so you can see here I totally did
right you can see here that we're just
not filling it out so this is supposed
to have a texture index right and I
totally I totally got rid of it right
cuz every time you do this you're you
know when you call right quad you're
supposed to be writing the quad with a
particular texture index in mind and I
just totally got rid of it let me just
verify that that's true but I'm pretty
sure that's what we did right yeah so
that's just stupid I don't know why I
did that but again I think I was just
for some reason thinking there were two
lighting indexes for every vertex I
don't know why I thought that but in my
head like I just I was I was just being
too crazy with it I'm not sure why
that's just what happens sometimes
all right so in here this this this code
is for whatever reason I don't think
we're actually calling it though right
so it's actually the other one like the
the other code I think that was the
problem there but you can see here like
right quad was supposed to be supposed
to be called by somebody and never was
right I don't know if we like thought we
were gonna speed something up and then
didn't I'm not sure but push quad which
is the one we actually call this one
here push quad is gonna have the same
problem right so we probably get the
texture index we're supposed to use and
then yet you can see we never actually
fill it out here right and if you look
we never passed it down so it's not it's
not as big of a piping problem as we
have in the other one where I
accidentally deleted it from being
passed in but basically in here we've
already got the texture index right
there we're just not filling it out so
that's just a case of again overzealous
deletion we still do need that even
though we would prefer to not actually
need it and to have done it per
primitive in this case we can't can't do
that because we haven't ever set up a
primitive thing for our quads uh so now
we hopefully are piping that through
properly
which means our vertices actually
correctly have their texture in them and
it looks like that was the only thing we
were missing so now that lighting stuff
has been pulled out of the lighting path
entirely right and so we should be good
to go here now what we need to do inside
the shader of course now is we need to
sort of pull come to me inside the the
actual pixel shader we need to pull from
the lighting probes that are inside the
voxel right and so we want to have some
way of doing all those lookups I don't
know how much time we have but it occurs
to me that maybe I could do this in the
opposite order we thought we were gonna
do it in meaning I could if we wanted to
actually not do the light propagation
first I could do the lookups first and
from there now I don't know if that's
actually something we want to do but
it's certainly something we could do
right and so meaning I could send down
light probes that are fake
we just set them to whatever we want and
then verify that the pixel shader
actually pulls from it correctly right
and so that would be an interesting
thing to do I don't know if we want to
do it that way but we certainly could
all right so let's think um I think I
still want to do the light probe pushing
pass first that still seems a bit better
to me and in terms of lights themselves
that part is a little bit more Squinkie
and so I'm not sure that that parts a
little harder to say anyway I'm gonna go
to render commands here and if we take a
look at what we're keeping track of my
question is just like how do we want to
get these light probes passed down to
the lighting system right so if you look
at what's going on in here you can kind
of see that the the push buffers for our
game render commands the lighting
information actually doesn't get pushed
on there right you can see this pretty
much just takes quads and that's the end
of it right
there's the index array there's the
texture array and there's the vertex
array so the way so all of that stuff
moving down through the system there
makes good sense when we were pushing
lights in here right what we were sort
of expecting to do I believe and let me
just take a look at the render group
yeah so what we were expecting to do is
sort of push lights on separately as
part of this pass here right and we've
got two sets of things we need to send
down we need to send down the boxes that
are used for college like ray casting
right so that we can track what's
hitting Ray's and what's not and then we
also need to track where the lights are
that are actually flooding in a mission
to the scene because those are you know
again also something we want to keep
so if we look I guess what I would say
here is we can probably keep this pretty
similar and just sort of change lighting
box
so I guess the thing that I'm not sure
exactly how we want to do it
yeah I'm not sure exactly what we want
to do here but I think we want to keep
this stuff relatively the same the only
thing I'm thinking is that maybe
emission wants to only to be a separate
thing like we want our lights themselves
to be stored separately but otherwise
this looks fine the light index seven
part of things that part that part I
want to look at a little more closely so
let's look at where that's being used if
I can pile right now
with that out who actually gets upset
with me
yeah so those light indices were just
where we were storing light information
for the faces of the cube which at this
point we're not doing anymore those are
going into our light probes so the
things that we actually hit and bounce
light around on those are actually not
it doesn't matter right we're going to
gather the lighting from the probes at
that point so I think that just goes
away it's just not a thing right so if
we take a look at that lighting box that
doesn't need to be there now the child
part of things probably does because
when we do our lighting box computations
we're still gonna need a spatial
hierarchy and so I feel like the thing
we use to like build up the boxes we're
probably still gonna need for ray
casting would be my guess I don't know
that that's true it may be that
brute-forcing it actually would be
better given how few of these boxes
there actually are but I don't want to
pull out code that I don't know if I
need so for the moment I'm gonna say
we'll leave these two in their
transparency I don't know what to make
of that I don't know that we really want
to model transparency inside the light
convection I'm assuming that if I get
rid of that nobody complains because I
don't think anyone was probably using it
yeah that transparency just wasn't
actually used in here so I'm gonna get
rid of that I'm not gonna have that be
recorded and we're just not even gonna
pretend that we're gonna do anything
with it so I think we're down to just
this stuff I think this is pretty
accurate with what we would need and
then these two pieces of information
here we're going to leave on there
because they
are part of the spatial hierarchy thing
but because all of the actual reflectors
themselves which are at the base of the
hierarchy don't need a child count or a
first child index I'm not 100% sure we
actually want to put them there because
we may want our spatial Harkey to just
be something else that has nothing to do
with these lighting box structures to
themselves that's sort of a separate
issue and we can take that up a little
bit later on so so we'll see I don't
know where that's going to go exactly
but we'll we'll sort of play that by ear
in terms of emission I don't know what
we want to do about that but I think
emission itself is probably something
that we would want to like I said I
think we might want to put lights in a
separate list so that we're not really
looking at them like this but I don't
know so that's something we'll have to
think about a little bit more carefully
as we go further down as we as we sort
of get deeper into the system all right
so let's take a look at this lighting
index nonsense this stuff I don't think
we need at all so this extended light
point count and the lighting to see I
don't think any of that stuff is
important so I'm just gonna get rid of
that
[Music]
yeah and I don't really care about any
of this stuff at all so basically what
we're gonna do is we're just gonna get
rid of the accumulated light information
here so this stuff here where we were
kind of where we were doing that that's
just gonna go away and what we could do
is use the actual look when we're doing
the ref see here we could do something a
little bit more specific with it
but I think what I'd rather do just
trying to think for the child indices
yeah so what we could do for that is
just say where we get the the ref see
there
yeah none of this stuff needs to happen
where we get the ref see there we could
just sum up just from the children right
so I'm not really sure how that wants to
do its thing but it seems to me like it
maybe wants to do this not sure but
basically like the length difference
here I suppose
oops yeah like like the point we don't
really care about the point we just care
about where the lighting box itself is
did that stuff already get set in a
different path by the way
I'm not sure I'm you know what I don't
really want any of this stuff so I feel
like I don't I just want this stuff to
go away and later we can sort of figure
out how we want that stuff to propagate
down but I'm just I'm just gonna get rid
of this stuff
we don't want this stuff at all it's
just let's just do good all right so
here where we actually in here we're
doing the looks like we're doing the
thing that actually builds the box
surfaces here and again I don't think I
want any of this stuff really this is
this is again for sort of treating the
boxes as if they were things that we
reflect around but we're not really
gonna want to do that so I think this
stuff is just not yeah just not on the
table so I'm gonna go ahead and get rid
of that
here we have this is just the lighting
output here it looks like this was stuff
for
you know I'm not sure what this is stuff
for oh right
so this is just stuff for storing the
averages over time all I really need to
do there is just again if death a little
bit more of it out I wanted to look at
this code because our averaging seemed
to be working pretty well and since
that's a fairly fuzzy thing to do I
wanted to be able to reference what we
were doing already all right so as far
as lighting point
output goes yeah so like this stuff here
where we're looping over these again
this is I'm just gonna go ahead and if
zero this out where we're outputting
this lighting because we're gonna be
outputting probes instead and so it's
gonna be pretty different
by comparison so I'm just gonna go ahead
and do that okay
so we're now still sort of technically
doing some stuff with the lighting in
there but it's not stuff that is
meaningful anymore right so we kind of
nerfed it and now we can start to build
the actual lighting probe system on top
of that and we still have I think we are
still going to be able to have the where
we put these lighting boxes that are
used for computation we're gonna still
be pushing these down we're just going
to be pushing them down without the sort
of light information in them it's just
they're there as blocks to sort of take
rays that hit them and stop those rays
from propagating right so it's the
collision geometry for our array caster
but that's all and so that's sort of
what we're what we've pulled out is the
part where the lighting information was
welded into them
which we didn't want so when we actually
do a push cube here what we want to do
is say whenever you're doing a push cube
whoever pushes the cube if the lighting
was enabled
we push just the cube data on to the
lighting system right so basically what
we say here is if group lighting enabled
then what we want to do is in that
render group we've still got this idea
that the lighting boxes get pushed on
here so we would say all right give me a
lighting box like and fill out
interestingly enough I suppose even this
could work with the entity cache because
we could actually do a thing where we
just don't even have to build the
spatial hierarchy every frame like if
you think about it we could just insert
and remove things from the spatial
hierarchy that tends to be hard
incremental e updating spatial
hierarchies is a lot of work so I don't
know if we really want to do it but it's
worth noting that like we sort of could
because we now know when entity has come
into her and out of that cache yeah it's
worth thinking about anyway in here
we've got the lighting box we need to
grab that from the render group where it
should be and so that would be in light
boxes plus whichever one were on right
now so light box count right and before
we do that we just want to assert that
we haven't blown out the total list
so you want to assert that that lightbox
count is less than the maximum so
somewhere in there we've got a maximum
lightbox count
although I guess I don't know where
let's take a look so we push light data
widths
worth of light boxes on that doesn't
really make any sense anymore so I think
we kind of want that to be a different
piece of information the reason I say
that is because our reflection geometry
is no longer coupled with our lighting
output the number of light probes we
take so we really want like a light box
like a max light box count kind of a
thing right
and so this right here which is the
would be the number of light probes it's
gonna probably reduce dramatically and
this max light bat box count here is now
what we're using for our actual for to
determine what the maximum number of
actual colliders we can have for our ray
cast right so that's it's pretty
different then the old system used to be
where those two things were locked
together so if we take a look at our
light boxes now when we get one of those
out we don't need to fill out hardly as
much information as we used to it's a
lot simpler than it was if we go back to
the lighting box and we look at what
goes in there now we just have like the
child count probably have to get
initialized to zero but that box P is
just going to be the actual location the
box radius this is going to be the
actual radius and the ref P this is a
bit of an issue the ref P actually needs
a little more information than it quite
has the renderer texture in question we
kind of would like to have sampled from
that texture that's kind of the crazy
part right is that when we're doing this
sort of ray casting we almost want the
cubes themselves to have an additional
color that's information about it that
lets us know how we want to bounce that
laying around and that would normally we
would want that to come from this
particular from this texture right and
so we sort of have a latent to do in
here which is that the texture should
have the information in it about what
its reflectivity is and currently
doesn't and so that's a little bit of an
issue if we go to render or texture we
have an index in there that tells us
which index it is on the graphics card
and what we probably need to do is have
the asset system also be able to look up
the general reflectivity of whatever
that texture is so I'm gonna just
proactively save because I can and am
going to that we're going to store the
texture index into the lighting box
structure now so that we can add texture
lookups in there in a sane way if I just
imagine this happening right that would
store the information in question so I'm
gonna go ahead and do that as well and
that's just this right alright so the
reference color can just get passed as
the actual color the emission is the
emission and then that's the full thing
like there's nothing else to fill out we
can get rid of the first child index as
well but we don't really need to so it's
unclear to what extent this actually has
to happen these here all of that stuff
is probably fine let's see we missed one
color we just need that
all right so now we're sending down the
light boxes and presumably the system
can still continue to function pretty
much the way that it was and we can
still raycast against those light boxes
the only difference now is that when
we're a cast against those light boxes
we're not storing the information
anywhere like we're not actually doing
anything with it right like if we go
back and look at the at the lighting
system when we actually were doing the
light propagation mm which is here if we
actually reenable the compute light
propagation stuff oops that's not the
one I was talking about that's not the
worker thread where's the worker thread
here it is so when we were actually
calling this what you can see here is
what we do when we actually you know we
cast array what we actually do when we
cast these rays is the result of the
Rays was getting distributed out to the
lighting points that from whence we
emanated the Ray right we're basically
doing like a transfer and energy
transfer there and that stuff just wants
to go away entirely right we just don't
want like this surface point stuff just
needs to go away entirely and what we'd
like to do is we'd like to have this ray
tracing process have built into it that
it's sampling from a particular point of
the light probe like every ray has a
destination it's supposed to write back
to and when it hits something it just
writes it back to the correct location
and again that's why I said I think we
can speed things up as well because once
we are once we're actually using boxes
more intelligently we shouldn't have to
worry about that
that Finnick enos of like which point
specifically we were looking at right
so that's one thing another thing we
could consider doing here and I do think
this maybe would make things easier for
us is if you take a look at what happens
here look at how much work we're doing
for looking at box surface indexes on
collision right and so if we actually if
the textures actually got like let's
suppose like in here when the textures
are getting rolled in here if instead we
just said the color of the box here we
pre compute what the texture modulated
box color is and we just use one color
per box right so we don't store colors
for each side of the cube that seems
kind of compelling right that way when
we do our hit test this crap doesn't
have to happen right there's just a lot
of work going on here you know
good and I really don't know if we need
that to happen
now we do have one problem which is when
your raycasting against boxes you do
have to figure out which side of the box
you hit right and we could argue that
maybe what we want is not really boxes
but we actually want our quads to just
be the primitives we've rate race
against but I don't think so because I
think that's gonna be more expensive so
it is true that yeah in general I
suppose when we're looking at our
masking operations there it does kind of
look like you know this box surface
index this part here we could save that
and that does save three instructions
from each of those passes right
although looking at it here that mask
does the selection hmm actually it looks
like I'm wrong about that it looks like
actually we can remove the whole thing
because it looks like we only update the
the distance based on a select with mask
which we already computed so again yeah
like if we were to do this right all of
that computation would go away like all
of that and that's pretty compelling
because that is a huge amount of work on
every ray hit that we would no longer
have to do you know I'm saying so that's
pretty compelling that feels pretty
compelling to me
that feels pretty compelling to me that
seems like that saves a lot of time
right and since you know basically all
we would have to do for that is just say
look boxes just have one color so if you
want higher fidelity lighting the mat
you got to add more than one box right
what you can do if you want to you can
break a single cube up into multiple sub
boxes that have different colors in
different locations you could do that
and I think for most of the time since
you're usually only bouncing lighting in
an important way off of one of the
phases usually like is used to create
like the world and I don't know that I
don't know that we really need to do
much more than that
so I'm thinking that probably should
should get removed and box surface index
which you know is is the stuff that
needs to sort of operate off of all of
this that seems like something we would
like to just get rid of uh so that's
good I mean that would really pretty
dramatically reduce that count there I
don't know why this is still compiled in
in like this this should be an if
developer kind of a thing for sure but
that looks pretty good
I mean that looks like it saves a
tremendous number of operations from
every race hit now granted it doesn't
really save any operations in the case
where you were testing a like a route a
interior node a non-terminal so when
we're walking the bounding hierarchy
doesn't really help us because we never
get to that part we weren't looking at
which space of the cube you hit when you
had children
that you should have gotten down to a
lower level of so it doesn't really
speed that up but it does speed up the
case where you were hitting boxes at the
low level and since the lowest level of
the tree is where most of the boxes are
that's probably nothing to sneeze at
right there probably was a lot of time
being spent in this box surface index
retrieval like or computation I should
say so yeah you know I'm gonna say
that's possibly good possibly important
yeah I'm gonna say that's that's pretty
good now one of the things I'm not 100%
sure about when I'm looking at this code
is we do say in there if all of the so
that you can see this line of code here
it says if all of the mask values are
true that means if every Rea this is a
packet tracer right so it's tracing for
rays at a time if all of the four rays
that it's tracing at a time all were
I guess further away
let's see T valid and T min is less than
result T right no sorry they're all
closer so if everything if all of the
rays in the entire packet hit this box I
guess
then it stops looping but I don't
understand why like is that actually
valid or it's not just a bug
I don't see it do you guys see it so we
have a Rea origin in a raid errection
coming in here and we're basically
telling this thing here's the lighting
work structure right we're basically
telling this thing hey we've got a stack
of boxes here and we're taking a box off
of the stack and we're going to test all
of that boxes children so we loop
through the children right I mean this
is what we're fundamentally doing and
we've got a mask that we're testing here
to see whether we can stop and stop
considering children so what are we like
how are we making the determination that
we don't need to test any more of the
children here we're looking to see
whether or not the the hit value right
whether the hit value is valid and less
than the closest hit
and I just don't see why that would be a
termination condition I can see okay so
like if I I don't I don't kind of see it
look you have to test all the children
right
I mean III don't I don't see how you
cannot it just it just doesn't make any
sense
I mean does anyone out there I guess
I'll ask the chat I have a box it's got
some number of children inside of it
when I'm hit testing I don't have any
real way of knowing those those children
in there aren't sorted in any other way
right there are just boxes there inside
this box so I don't know and I'm not
like sorting them by the REA direction
or something in here so I don't even
know which direction I'm passing through
this box so I can't know when I'm done
testing children because the children
could have been anywhere so just because
just because I had all of the rays hit
one of these things why why does that
stop the traversal
anyone is this just a bug that we've had
in the lighting system anyone in chat am
I being stupid here but I don't think I
am I think that's just wrong because I
don't see how you could stop iterating
over the children of the box until
you've tested all of them they they all
might fail I'm sorry they all might
produce a better hit so any kit you have
might not be the closest and at that
point you're kind of in a situation
where you're not returning an accurate
lighting result here
so saying that everything is true in the
mask so what like why does that that
doesn't help you look I don't see how
that helps you at all
that just seems like garbage I'm gonna
put you on this
but this is just gonna have to go away
entirely and in terms of total partition
leaves used I assume we might as well
still tract that piece of information
because you know if we were trying to
count that is accurate right but I just
I don't know I don't understand why that
was in there and I also don't understand
why like I don't understand why this was
only counted during an all true case
because the total number of perdition
leaves that you used is actually 100%
dependent on any one of those lanes you
used the partition if any of the lanes
hit it doesn't matter if you only hit in
one you don't hit in all four to use the
partition so this code just looks like
complete crap and I think we just had a
bug in there which probably contributed
to our noise so that that's not good
like that was not good I'm pretty sure
that was a bad situation that shouldn't
have been happening I'm pretty sure but
we'll see when the vod's go up for this
and some people take a closer look at it
you know maybe someone be like no no no
no go back to when you implemented it
here it you had a good reason and it
works okay I'm like all right but that
just looks that looks like crap to me
it's there
there probably are ways you can early
out of this loop but they're probably
not related to that because they would
have to have something to do with
whether or not you could determine
definitively that you are never going to
hit another box earlier than this box
like for example if you determined that
the hits were all at the min value of
the parent cube
then you would know that no other child
could be could have been closer anyway
and so that's an early out condition
that would be valid I don't think it's
one that would happen very often so I'm
pretty sure you don't really care but
you know if we had been testing that I
would have said sure but we're not we're
testing just strictly whether or not
we've got hits and hits are not really
dispositive in this case so that doesn't
seem useful so anyway if we were to
assume going back to what we were
actually working on here if we were to
assume that we were to eliminate the box
surface index and so the only thing that
we really know when we get back a
raycast result is which box index it was
I when we hit it and if we hit it right
that's a more sane way to do the raycast
what I don't necessarily know as far as
the box service and next part of things
goes is when we do this rate cast do we
actually care about that or do we just
want to know what the color was right do
we actually need to store a box index
here or can we just send back a color
value like an RGB and use that right and
it may be that it's just more efficient
to like return back the index but I
don't think that it is because that
index is like a split lookup thing that
has to happen which is not great you
know what I mean and so I kind of think
that you know modifying this raycast it
would be nice to sort of change it to
something where it's like if the raycast
never needs to look at who calls it if
the raycast never actually needs the
sampling out of it so this is alright so
first of all this is only place we call
it so if this thing never needed to do
all this garbage right this is really
expensive and it's crap right and the
reason that it had to happen was because
we were casting off of
boxes and we had to see like whit when
we hit a box we had to see like what the
color was at that point on the box we
don't really want to do that anymore so
I'm imagining that probably the right
thing to do is to is to do the right we
what we want to do here right is we want
to do the lookup of the okay yeah as I'm
saying it I can kind of see why this is
a problem so we definitely don't need to
send back the box index
I don't think all we need to know is the
point so we just need to know the
location where we hit and we already
have that it's this right so then what
we actually do need to do is based on
that position we then do need to do our
indexing into the voxel and to produce
the averaged color based on light probes
so we do actually need to know at that
point when we shade that location on the
surface we would need to know that so we
do need to know I'm normal I guess as
well if we're trying to shade from that
surface and so although we don't need to
risk record the box surface index one
nasty part is that does mean we may need
to still do a little bit of work to
determine which direction we were facing
so I think we may need that
unfortunately as much as I wish we
didn't and so if we go back here and
take a look at that piece of the code
right you can see in here where we're
sort of like alright this was how we
were assembling the box surface so next
before the question is is there any way
that we can get without having to go
through all of that garbage that we can
get the shading normal out
right and you can kind of see here where
we've produced the information for the
hit we did it by kind of going through
and selecting yeah so when we kind of
come through here the problem that we're
gonna end up with the problem that we
end up having is we do want just the
normal to be stored and we don't really
want to have like this information tells
us which box surface we were on so
obviously that would tell you the normal
but it would be nice if we could figure
out a way to get the normal out better
right something that didn't require as
much work because you can look in here
when we determine whether or not we hit
the box just using that team in T Max
value there
it feels like there should be some way
of doing the same process
you know what I mean
we create the tee box men and tee box
max by taking the Ray direction and
figuring out how far we have to go to
hit this close side of the box and how
far we have to go to hit the far side of
the box right
and then using min and Max we determine
which one of those will occur first and
second you know that's all we're doing
I guess what we could say this is a
tough one I guess what we could say is
that the comparison between t-box min
and T Box max would tell us which
it would tell us which one of those two
we were doing and then I hmm we're gonna
have to work out some math for this one
I think this might have to wait until
next weekend but I'm just thinking about
it and I'm like it feels like we should
be able to get that directly so that
when we get in a true hit here it feels
like we should be able to do something
here that allows us that allows us to
compute this without actually having to
compute the index of which face was hit
you know what I mean
it it feels to me like there's some way
we can do that and if you think about it
we know because we know like we can do
this comparison ourselves if we want to
write meaning we can do we still have t
box
minty box max right so we can do this
comparison we can say produce a mask for
me that tells me where you picked the
minimum and where you picked the maximum
right you know which lanes hit on the
men and which lanes hit on the max when
I know whether you hit the min or the
max right when I know which one you did
then I know I have information about
where the Ray was coming relative to the
box so I know whether it's hitting am
inside so a negative facing normal like
if you hit the tee box min right then
it's a negative facing normal if you hit
the tee box max it's a positive facing
normal
right so I know whether it's a plus one
or a negative one just by this I think
and so then the only question is which
of the three sides was the one that you
hit was it X Y or Z and so how are we
determining that here
ah okay so it's this process here that's
determining that right whether X Y or Z
was least that's what's determining it .
so in theory at least
in theory it would look something like
this so T min equals T min X you just
double-check my assumptions here so the
team in here right
which of these three it equals that
tells you which axis it is right and
then whether or not it this right here
that would tell you which whether it was
positive or negative
so with those four comparisons you
definitely have all of the information
you need and so you could use a select
at that point to produce the normal by
doing for comparisons and a bunch of
selects on the results of the
comparisons that might still not really
be what you want but it's a start and it
is cheaper than all of this probably
substantially actually because first of
all none of this is serially dependent
so all those can issue at the same time
and then you can the select you're only
going to select that normal so if we go
look here write that normal you're
setting four of those the X the Y and
the Z sort of separately this f/32 for x
of the normal it's it's really a Veck
three right so it's really a v3 for X
that we're talking about there it's this
you know I mean so if we were to
actually be doing the normal there then
presumably we can set each lane of the
normal as a select itself so I think it
might be something close to as simple
as this so when we do the positive or
negative part of things right we're
gonna figure out which one of those it
actually is this is sort of a separate
thing it's like the positive or the dirt
normal der normal sign right something
like that and the normal sign is just a
flip between like 1 and negative 1 so
it's really just like look it's one if
the min was less than the max then it's
negative 1 you know I'm saying so we
would determine the sign of the normal
here and then in each of these I think
you just select between the zero values
so there's nothing in that channel or
the sine value if it is actually the
thing that's in that channel so I think
it's this or close to this right which
is to say that we need for tests and for
selects which is a lot cheaper than this
probably I think because this has you
know I don't know 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
11 12 I mean there's probably 30 plus
instructions in there and this would be
like 8 if you have select like more like
12 if you don't
on the platform so I think that's a
pretty significant savings this could
probably be done better though all right
so I'm gonna leave that temporarily and
yeah I don't know if we have a like a
one or a negative one in here anywhere
so we have a zero it's just that so
that's fine so I can I can actually just
do this I suppose I guess another way to
say that would be it's just an and
because when it ends it'll just end out
to zero so I guess we don't need to
select because if you happen to select
with zero you're in a good place so you
should be able to actually do this I
think that actually makes it even
cheaper oops
right so that's the actual value that
we'd be selecting and I guess since we
have to mask these in here though I
guess we do have to do this
so it is a little more expensive than
I'm claiming or was thinking right
because you do have to do the Select in
there so it's only really two
instructions to compute the value but
you do have to select in which is kind
of annoying selections are cheap on some
platforms on more modern CPUs they're
very inexpensive but on older CPUs they
become less expensive big sorry them
more expensive because they don't
actually have an instruction to do it so
it becomes multiple instructions it's
two hands in an or usually so ant one am
not one or and one end kind of a thing
it's not great so anyway yeah looking at
this I think this means it's for selects
for comparisons three ends not great we
might be able to get it down less than
that though and you know we'll see but I
think we do have to do it that way and
that selecting is annoying but I think
that's just how it has to go all right I
believe that
we don't have a 1 and a negative 1 in
here so I think I'll just make one right
now and that can be that what does
select complaining about though here
I'm not actually sure what what it's
grumpy about
I mean that looks pretty reasonable
right but it doesn't like it
now the Tuileries Kabuto there could be
v3 for X what does select want
it's a F 3 to F 3 to F 32 it's trying to
F 3 to V 32 what
I see I see it I see so we probably want
more like that
let's take a look is that actually gonna
be accurate though so when we did these
comparisons we then took the minimum of
those two to produce team in three and
team X 3 and then we collapsed them down
so the problem there is again yet we
don't know which one we used so we need
to go back and figure out which one we
used there and
ugh yeah all right we're gonna have to
do this next time this is gonna be
pretty complicated I think we can do a
good job on it but but figuring out that
normal is gonna take us some work let's
go to a brief Q&amp;A here that's gonna be
that's gonna be annoying
we're gonna have to work that one out in
the blackboard by the way
generally tips for how someone would go
about moving an existing code base from
object oriented programming
assuming you're in control of it by the
way thank you very much for the series
I'm learning so much that $15 doesn't
even begin to compare with the value of
providing at the fact the series is free
is even more awesome well thank you very
much I guess what I would say is moving
an existing code base from
object-oriented programming to for lack
of a better term programming usually
involves a couple different things you
have to do I would say you probably want
to start by looking at the objects in
the system and their member functions
and I would start picking apart the
places where people have placed member
functions into objects that clearly
shouldn't be member functions there's
usually a lot of these I typically so
just to be clear I you've got to sort of
competing ideas there's the concept that
someone is doing something to data right
so I'm going through a list of
instructions I should do to my data you
know move it over here add 3 to it do
whatever right and that's procedural and
then over here you have a different idea
which is that data is does something to
itself and you are just asking it to do
something to itself and that's
object-oriented programming right so the
problem is when you're thinking about
the object-oriented programming and this
is especially bad if the people who do
the auditory and programming are
particularly far down the rat hole what
they'll do
is they break up a single procedural
notion which is here's the things I
wanted to do in the order I wanted to do
the man into like tens or hundreds or
sometimes if you're really unfortunate
like a thousand little functions each on
an object and they all sort of conspire
to do this one thing that was actually
pretty clear before so what you want to
start doing is going where can I start
to pull out procedural things that
happen in this code base and remove all
those little weird like member functions
that do tiny bits of things and how can
I pull them into a coherent single
procedure of blocks that do an operation
that's the first thing I would start
with trying to highlight the places
where I can create real procedures that
capture the meaning of the program
properly and disaggregate those from the
objects that be to start right and as
you turn that crank and focus on doing
that more and more your objects should
start to become just structs and then
you can stink to start to think about
merging them as necessary or splitting
them as necessary into smaller data
chunks or larger data chunks as is
dictated by the procedural code that's
probably what I'd say saw a gaming s I'm
only on episode 81 so excuse the new
bean is I've created different modules
in my code that store different data for
my entities physics render AI etcetera
would it be silly to create an anonymous
module type that unions these different
modules into one generic struct meaning
I can put them all into one array and
pass it around no that is not at all
silly so
in general what you have to remember is
like polymorphism in the object-oriented
world how they say that is just one
flavor of a broader concept which
actually has very little to do with
object-oriented programming and has more
to do with code reuse when a CPU goes to
execute a particular piece of code that
code always has to be the same so when I
create a chunk of compiled code in my
program it's gonna execute the same and
the question is how many how much
leverage can I get out of that one piece
of code right because there's reasons I
might want to do that first of all code
has a cost it has to be decoded two has
to live in a cache somewhere it costs me
to execute code
I don't want an arbitrarily large amount
of code right but also it just it's less
things to write if I can write one
little CPU routine to do a bunch of
things and I reuse it a bunch of times
hey that's good on me I didn't have to
write too much code right and so
sometimes what you would like to do is
reuse a piece of CPU code to do two
different things because those two
things are closely related and so one
thing you might want to do for example
is reuse like some allocation and this
can have benefits even beyond just
reusing CPU code it's also reusing
memory potentially right so sometimes
what you want to do is say look I've got
two things they're actually totally
different but I want to treat them the
same in some parts of the code so I'm
just gonna Union them together that
means that when I create one of these
things I can use it as either thing and
just depending on who uses it later down
the pipeline they're gonna decide what
to do with it in one way or another
right that can pay dividends by not only
compressing the code down so if you have
less code necessary to do the same
operations but also it allows you to
avoid things like memory fragmentation
because it means if like one of those
things was six bytes larger than the
other one
it doesn't matter
right you're you're wasting a little bit
of space in your memory sometimes when
it's one type of set of the other but
you're gaining a regularity that's much
more powerful and so it's always worth
noting that combining things together
and treating them uniformly can have
benefits that have nothing to do with
the traditional audit oriented sense of
polymorphism right you can get benefits
there that are real procedural benefits
that have to do with saying the CPU
actually does and that's valuable so
don't shy away from it just because it
might seem a little object oriented II
it's not it seems that tracing raise to
collect like is a heavy operation if
ray-tracing supported GPU Hardware most
common would it be fair to say that you
would prefer to move the lighting
computation to the GPU entirely yes so
if you were targeting like a brand new
GPU like an RT X card or something like
that you would just do it entirely on
the GPU but ten years from now this code
will be on the GPU for sure because
everyone probably who's buying games
will have a card that can do the ray
tracing efficiently right
talking to graphics folks it seems that
shader permutation management is a real
pain point on the other hand you have
titles like doom that use a
significantly smaller number of
permutations and pipeline states or are
you saying significantly smaller or
significant I'm not sure what you're
talking about saying what about doom
there sorry in a more complex 3d title
what's your take on GPU complexity
management how do you design a solution
that scales um well I guess what I would
say there is typically you have to
remember that the GPU code itself also
has a cost for having too many things
you don't want to have to change shaders
like all the time right because all the
same things that apply in a CPU usually
apply on a GPU as well like I mean I
don't keep up with GPU stuff because I'm
not a rendering guy so I'm kind of the
wrong one to ask
but as GPUs have become more complex
they do a lot of the same things that
CPUs do they cache things a lot and so
typically speaking if you're just
dumping 10,000 shaders onto a GPU and
just being like hey good luck pal
you know um I don't really know if
that's a particularly sane way to go
about managing the complexity either so
I would say you know my first thought is
yeah I would try to architect my system
so that actually I don't have that many
kinds of shaders and that I can use a
smaller number of parametric shaders
rather than a higher number of like
tightly optimized shaders because most
of the time I think you'll end up
actually probably winning out by going
for less things and you can always spot
optimize if you see that one particular
shader is used a ton and you want a
special case just that one set of okay
when this particular shader is used with
these
particular parameters I see that that
accounts for like a lot of my fill time
then write a highly optimized version of
that one that seems fair but the like
approach of let me generate like every
possible combination of every fader I
might use that doesn't seem that smart
especially when branching isn't that
expensive in a shader if all of the
branches take it
so like nowadays branching the shader
isn't that bad if it's if it's not per
Lane so something like a constant that's
loaded in that's part of the material
that can be pretty cheap so again I
would say like my first thought is I'd
try to get the shader count down
honestly III I would I would try to move
towards a couple basic shaders that do
all of the kinds of things you want to
do and focus on getting that to work
well and then I would just IIIi would
only break out into more precise
permutations when I thought I needed to
for performance like it really was
necessary a real production related
question in hand-made here we have a
general idea of how the game should look
and feel like mechanics art direction
etc we're tackling engine problems
because they're interesting and I'm very
good for you're doing it how will the
process of tackling things and exploring
the engine design would look in a real
production environment based on your
experience say maybe based on your
experience working on the witness with
John Blow um it's really not different
honestly you always have some idea of
what it is that you're trying to do and
you're basing your engine work off of
that and so in our particular case in
handmade hero we're like look we want to
look at these things because they're
interesting or we know we need them for
specular game design so we're spending
more time on those and we don't spend
time on things that I don't think I want
right that never changes even if the
answer is we're making a generic engine
well that's your driving function you're
like should we explore this case I don't
know does it allow us to expose a
feature on the generic side of things
that people can like turn on and off and
use
if the answer is yes we go down that
route right and so typically you just
always have some function in your brain
that's like should I start doing this or
shouldn't I and that can be as simple as
I asked the producer on the project
where the priority is for this thing or
it can be as complex as I sit down and
figure out how many different ways I
could use this thing in a generic
version of this engine that we're gonna
expose in a UI right but you're always
doing that you know you always have some
function and the function just changes
but the output from the function is
still what you use to determine where
you spend your time tips on reading
academic papers is about graphical stuff
I always gonna get lost in the technical
jargon and don't really get anything out
of them a good example is your video
about you decaying actual paper yeah
skin papers to learn what they've done
and what's possible and don't push it
any further than that until you actually
want to really do something with some of
those papers and then sit down and
actually implement them like work it
through line by line and make it
yourself that's the only way to really
learn them because yeah there's too much
jargon
there's incomplete explanations bad
explanations math that's written as math
instead of code for no reason just
because it's convention for them or it
makes them feel better about themselves
I don't know but you have to sit down
and really work it through because you
can't just read the paper and learn it
it's not written well enough for that
right most papers are not written in a
clear and concise fashion
sadly all right let's wrap it up
thanks everyone for joining me for the
episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with a
series at home you can always go to
handmade hero org and preorder the game
it comes with the source code so you can
play around with it yourself we will be
back here next weekend to work on the
lighting somewhere again like I said
it's there's so many things involved in
lighting and it has to be high
performance so it's always takes a long
time so it'll take us a few weekends but
we'll get there that's what we'll be
doing hopes to be back here for that
until then have fun programming and I'll
see everyone on the Internet take it
easy everybody