hello everybody and welcome to handmade
heroes show we code a complete game live
on stream we are in the middle of
updating our debug code so I'd like to
get right into that and if if you want
to follow along at home you can of
course pre-order the game on handmade
hero org which if you've done that you
want to download a 248 source code
because that's what I'm starting with
today all right moving on let's see
where we left off if I remember
correctly there was something that I
kind of want to do at the end of last
stream and I put a little to-do in there
for us so maybe that's actually the
first thing that we'll do but let's just
mention where we left off we were kind
of starting to try and finish this stuff
up and I found it was kind of in a state
that was actually relatively usable so
we're able to sort of go in here and and
use this to create various systems but
there's a couple of things we had to
kind of clean up first of all we get
this weird thing where all names are
always forced through the hierarchy
system so it creates these dummy nodes
for things even if we didn't actually
necessarily want that of course in this
case we kind of do want that and so we
have to kind of decide how we want those
to go do we want to just always have
data blocks for that purpose or how do
we want to do it so we got that other
thing we want to do is turn back on the
profiling and make the profiling more
usable since we're recording profile
information but right now we're not
really using it for anything and so in
order to do that what I would like to do
is just have a way of adding profilers
into our into our sort of set of things
here and doing that should be relatively
straightforward because since we have a
way of talking about these things so
I'll just go ahead and load up handmade
here I believe what I did was inside
handmade dusty peepee I had a debug
block here and what I want to be able to
do is sort of just say okay whenever we
have like this sort of stuff in like a
debug block like this I want to just be
able to say okay let's create a debug
profile right here let's you know put it
in this debug lock and what I want to do
is just say what function
I'm trying to profile let's let's just
say so this is a time function right
here and so what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna say hey let's go ahead and get
that time function let's just have game
update and render be timed and putting
this profile so that's what I'd like to
do of course if I compile that it's
gonna be a pretty significant error
because debug profile is not actually we
have we have ever defined so I need to
go into the interface and add the
ability to sort of put that in there and
so I think all that really has to happen
is we just have to mirror exactly the
way that we were doing these other
things so when we say like the bug value
or whatever that's really all we
actually have to do I think so all I
want to do is just have a pound to find
here for debug profile I want to have
the like function name that we're trying
to start at so like where we are on the
on the on the profiling and and so all
that's gonna do is this I think
oops this exact thing so it's literally
just going to record you know this in
here although like I think we'd probably
want well I guess since it's already got
an actual name here I suppose I can just
say hey the function that you're trying
to profile is this function right now I
feel like that's pretty much all that
should have to happen and so we can just
pass here that what I wanted the type to
be was that sort of trace type that we
had right because we've got this this
notion it's an interface we've got this
notion of the counter thread list or
whatever so we can say what we actually
want that to be what I think I might do
here is introduce another type which is
just to say like I'm not gonna say
specifically how I want this thing to be
profile necessarily
well maybe yeah well I don't know let's
let's just say let's rien a belay
counter function list and let's just say
that that's what we want so we want a
counter function list we want to say
that this is the function name that'll
be scoped to and so when we record that
event it will go into the stream and
that will allow us to pick it back up on
the other side when the debug system
encounters it and so when the debug
sister encounters that written in there
then all I need to do is tell it which
is it's going to be in here right so
we're going to come through here and
we're gonna get down to the part where
we you know we're inside a data block or
something like that and we we see it and
we would store that element here once we
store that element inside the data block
we should be able to encounter it when
we are iterating over the elements and
so all we need is something that can
output that function list now I don't
actually think we still have any actual
drawing code for that you can see here
where we've got this kind of like debug
type counter thread list thing I feel
like I feel like this calls debug draw
event always it does not call debug draw
element and so I don't really know I
don't really know if that's a problem or
not
like I don't really know I guess
I guess what I would say about that is
maybe that doesn't really want to be
part of the actual data blocks I don't
know
so the reason that's a little bit
confusing is because we have a notion of
two different things there's debug
elements which can actually exist in
sort of multiple hierarchies we can have
like lots of those and then there's
debug events which are things that came
to the stream and that we're trying to
record and so I think that maybe now
that I think about it actually we may
just want to make that create a debug
element to not actually have it have to
think about data blocks at all right so
like you know when we're running through
here and we see one we could just make
that be its own element right so we do
these these event types and we see the
different kinds PM block and block open
data block close data block we could
just say oh okay when we see debug type
what was that guy's name just like fun
function dude right so counter function
list when we see counter function list
as something that we are going to add
what we could do is say well whatever
that debug element is because we've
already got one for ourselves right
we've already parsed out an element for
ourselves it's this guy right here let's
debug element what we could do is take
that debug element and use that debug
element as the one that creates the
profile that might happen automatically
now that I think about it so I don't
really know that there's all that much
you would have to do here
so I'm going to start by seeing what
that actually does some curious
all right so what did we call that we
called that guy a game update and render
but I don't see him here which is a
little bit odd because I feel like it
should I've created a game update and
render I guess because it's route it
wouldn't that's actually okay so that's
actually true so I suppose what I
actually need to do is I need to
actually do something that fit takes
that does that insertion into the group
so inside here debug CDP so inside here
where I've got my Ellen from event when
we do this sort of thing and we do add
element to group this is the part that I
guess is not really happening right it's
getting a parent group but there isn't a
parent group to get a della meant to
group I want to see what what does that
actually program to do so it shouldn't
turn it the route I must set I want to
set a breakpoint here I think I want to
see what happens when we get this when
they get this dude mark debug value is
that mused anymore either
speaking of cleanup do we need that
still I want to take a look at what
happens if I just get rid of that I
don't think so
so that's going to
all right so yeah I feel like that
should have inserted it but it didn't so
I'm still a little hazy on on why so
what I would like to do is say okay when
we hit this because you'll note right I
mean the reason I say that is because
everyone else gets their stubs and I
guess it's just because it only creates
people in the node it only it only does
the precursor so it only does global
renderer and camera it never does the
final one so for example I guess just to
double-check that my understanding of
that is correct you can kind of see here
if I was to do something like this or
that would it create the foo and my
argument is yes it would create the foo
and it just doesn't create the other
part if that makes sense yeah so it does
actually it so it is actually inserting
it it just doesn't we don't ever
actually see it because we have not
actually done anything with it so I
could do something like this where I say
do you buy profile game I've eaten
render the thing is I need to say where
it's going to go and so I I would need
to sort of expand the call to have some
notion of what the function name was in
addition right because we we need sort
of like where does it go and what the
function name is and so that I suppose
is a good argument for the the data
block that seems like a reasonable idea
and I don't know if we support data
blocks inside data blocks
does anyone know if we support that I
wonder
I'm very curious to know what happens if
we do that really hating the OpenGL
startup time man
it's brutal so it looks like the answer
is no right because there's profile so
it created a data block but it does not
nest it right so I guess what that means
is if you wanted that's that you would
actually have to do that
yeah interesting so I think I'm sort of
getting where this is at now and it just
needs a little it needs a little bit of
a reorientation of its thinking right
because you can kind of see how it just
nothing ever quite works right the way
that we might want it to so I'm going to
stop for one second and just say well
you know what let me finish getting the
let me finish putting the the actual
profile in there first just to have it
displaying something and then I'm gonna
try to focus on cleaning up that
interface a little bit so we know
exactly what we're actually gonna say as
the final debug you know debug interface
that that that all the codes gonna have
to actually use so in theory all I would
really need to do here is is that that
function list that guy has to actually
appear when we do a draw element so we
do a debug draw element call we actually
need to have this occur debug type
counter function list and it would have
to do this so I'm just I'm just gonna
grab this so it's just gonna draw the
exact same thing as the thread list so
it's not really gonna drag draw func the
function list at the moment but you know
that's no biggie so let's see here
I do not see my function list see if I'm
actually oh and it is inside a datablock
there right so technically it has to be
up here
so I do not see it but I don't know why
so I'm gonna check to see whether we
actually is that just because it never
gets stored inside the data block
because of the interception call like if
I take care of that so it gets through
the other one I guess that is what would
add it yeah there it is
all right so okay
so I mean I roughly get how it's all
working now and so now we just have to
decide how to make this this stuff a
little cleaner right because we're sort
of on the cusp of it but it just it
needs to get smushed down it's - it's
just - all over the place at the moment
and that's not gonna I'm not gonna be
happy with that at all
so let's bounce back here and let's just
take a look at the interface stuff real
quick and let's just decide or try to
like play with the actual code that's
being called and say okay if this is all
that we're gonna have right this is
everything's going to go through this
from now on this is what we get how is
this going to work we know we've got our
timed function stuff and that's all fine
so I feel like the time function stuff
doesn't probably need to be touched the
timers are probably okay and so all we
really need to do now is figure out how
to make sure that our data stuff comes
out okay and let's think about how we
want that to work right so if I'm
constructing like a menu thing here that
I want to have happen I probably want to
do something you know where the end data
block maybe the end data block is
actually just implicit right so maybe it
looks something like this right so maybe
we just don't do begin end at the moment
maybe we just do debug data block that's
the data block right
and these debug values
I guess they can just be named these are
just named weird because they used to
have to have the underscores and I think
we want to just say like that's just not
we don't care about that anymore right
and if we want to we could do this right
and now these that that debug data block
would be automatically closed like we
could just make a little struck that had
a constructor destructor pair like we
did for the timed like we did for the
time function so we could do that it's
not the prettiest thing in the world but
it's okay right and same thing if we
want to do here like so and that seems
ok so you know we can't do something
like that and in this case the question
is just how do we want to indicate the
hierarchy do we want to use the
underscores like we were doing before in
this case since the data blocks these
are just straight-up actual names we can
actually just make these V strings
first of all right we could just make
this piece something like that and so
here this way we could use underscores
if we wanted to be able to talk about
things underscores we could use a slash
to sort of do a path like syntax right
so we could do something like this and
then you know we need this sort of debug
pointer ID and the debug pointer ID
thing is again it's just we need some
kind of grids there right - we need
grids so that we can recognize these
data blocks uniquely across multiple
runs of the program and there's two ways
we could do that one way is with this
with this string and the other one is by
using the pointer the reason I'm not
sure about using the string is just
because I may want to talk about
multiple debug blocks that all have the
same name so for example if I'm talking
about an entity I don't know like
there's two different sort of notions of
that and like the selected entity it's
like there's the entity that's selected
right now that I might be talking about
or I might be talking about the
concept of the selected entity and those
are actually like two different things
so I'm not really sure how that shakes
out exactly and I don't know which one
we would want to do I guess
in the interest of making it a little
bit again to reduce the complexity one
way to think about reusing the
complexity would just say well this is
the simpler of the two and it just has
to hash the string right in order to
figure out it just have to use a hash of
the string to look that up and you know
maybe that's the best maybe that's the
best option right that might be the way
to go because again just simplifying
things might be nicer than not so if we
were gonna do it that way that's really
totally simple we can just say there's a
debug dative lock and then everything
that we say after it kind of goes under
it as a hierarchical element and we can
add like slashes and stuff so that it
can you know expand out into something
that we can view easily that seems good
enough debug value seems pretty
reasonable and I don't think we need to
edit that much so I feel like this is a
pretty reasonable way like is there
anything in particular that we would
have been wanting to do that we couldn't
do with that without you know that this
would be a problem for I don't know
let's take a look at what would happen
if I actually want to make this work
without these word names though right if
I was gonna actually have this kind of
come through I would have to do like
okay this is debug renderer camera I
guess is what that is and then I have to
close this debug block and then I'd have
to open another one and say like oh this
is game ground chunks right and then
here I'd have to say like oh this this
data block is a renderer I guess this
isn't
global something like that
I don't really know there's that crown
chunks you can kind of see what I'm
doing here right so there's the renderer
probably would put that up here this way
I can even kind of see it a little bit
clearer right it's like a submenu and
let's see globally I familiar follows
hero so that's in AI and I guess it was
an AI familiar even and this is in
particles and this is in simulation
right that's that's basically what we're
looking at here so yeah so if you assume
that this was like you know if that's
reasonable then we would be you know
that's that's not too bad right I mean
we can we can handle that that's not
that's not too too messy to work with I
think it seems okay so yeah so let's
assume that that's okay if that's okay
then let's just kind of clean up a
little bit of how it's going and I guess
we just need to have a way for that grid
to not be weird right yeah so if we come
back over here for debug data block
here's our begin data block in our end
data block what we need to do here is we
just need to make bound to find debug
data block with the name of the data
block has to basically be an
instantiation of like exactly it has to
do exactly the thing that we were doing
here where we got a new timed block you
can see how we did that it was it was
this sort of thing which unfortunately
means we got to do the ridiculous macro
expansion that I hate thank you so much
C++ for that so if we go back here to to
data block we have to essentially copy
the exact same thing so this is going to
be like debug data block yeah debug data
block although actually no we don't
because you can only open because the
way we're doing it here you only open
one and you've got that you've got to
have the bracket so that it'll close it
when you're done with it so maybe we
don't really have to do that what we
could say is just like since we know
that's the pattern we're using we don't
have to worry about the time
black thing that is potentially
compelling right because so we could
actually do debug datablock like so
something like this and that would
presumably just work because since these
are always at us at the top of a scope
we don't have to worry about you making
that name unique like we did when we did
the time block because we wanted the
time blocks to be able to work inside so
that's maybe what we should do
I just makes the laser on us so here we
would just have a set of beginning to
the block end of a if we just we just
have debug data block I don't know if we
ever did begin array an end array it
looks like that never actually did
anything so I don't actually know if we
were expecting that to do something
maybe we were I don't know but if we
have this for begin data block now then
we just need this data block to actually
do something so that is just going to be
something which automatically opens and
closes it so the constructor
has to do this on end and this on began
oops
except I don't actually want to be a
macro certainly and so I think that is
just through what it should be so debug
data block there's all that stuff so
when we do in an open day to block we
now know what the name is because we
said the name is going to be passed in
so that's easy enough we don't actually
know we don't actually know some of the
rest of this stuff and I guess the
question is since this is in a macro I
also don't know if we need to pass in
some of the other stuff like the grid I
don't think so really
but like we would have to pass in all of
this stuff like right because we'd want
to know the the file and the line number
potentially if that stuff ever gets
saved I don't know if it does I guess it
doesn't really get saved for just a
generic debug event all that happens is
just you get the event type in the block
the unique file count or string stuff I
don't know that we I don't know that we
use that too much in fact I would like
to know a little bit more about that
what does good actually get used for
let's see I can't actually see that
because it's behind my head let's see
do you bag ID from grid
where are we this is an open data block
so if we're an open data block we
basically go through and we try to
determine what the idea is from the grid
so I don't really know like I feel like
again I feel like this could be
simplified down from where it is right
now but I see why that has to be there
right we do need some way of talking
about particular data so unique file
counter string right that sort of means
that for any time you use record debug
event since unique file counter string
is going to be happening where the
record debug event call happened you end
up in a situation where like you can't
actually in fact like in this
circumstance this is just wrong right
because this record debug event won't
actually get a grid from here so you
pretty much always need to have this
pass-through get thread ID is fine event
type is fine ret I see all of these
things are fine event table stuff all of
this stuff seems fine but unique file
counter string I don't think can
actually be there
I think record debug event kind of needs
you to pass that grid in you know I just
feel like that's got to happen that's my
guess anyway and so I don't know what
the best way to do that would be but I
just think that for example when you
call into one of these things like n
block I think it's got a it's got to do
that I feel like that's got to happen
because otherwise these aren't going to
be correct so I don't know if you could
do unique file counter string here like
so what I probably could do is say well
unique file counter string obviously is
going to produce a string so what I
could do is
you know whoever calls timed block here
has to pass that in which isn't my
favorite to say the least right you can
kind of see why I'm not thrilled about
that
what does begin block do it records you
so they both they both record a debug
event and they would end up recording a
debug event with this is the location
you know with that as the grid and
that's just not what you would want so
I'm not sure how to really get around
that correctly and also there seems to
be a pretty big proliferation
of things here as well
so I feel like maybe this should be cut
down a bit and the other thing that
could be plausible here is that if the
time to vlog just remembered what these
were it could remember the file name and
the line number in the block name that
came in here and if it did that then
what it could do is say like oh okay if
those just are stored as part of if
those just come in to the time block
here as part of it then they could be
passed through as the grid yeah yeah so
really what I have to do is untangle the
stuff again not particularly glamorous
but yeah this is why if you ever wonder
why I love meta programming so much it's
because you never have to deal with this
ridiculousness I mean all of this stuff
is completely unnecessary work it's just
because C++ doesn't actually support any
of the features you would actually want
for marking up your code you will note
that John showed the trivial meta
programming example the other night in
his programming language where you can
just say hey if there's the part where
I'm going to profile this function how
about you insert the profiling code at
that location write C++ status committee
30 years hasn't managed it it was too
hard for them but what are you gonna do
all right so anyway working around that
I just got to make it so that this stuff
gets passed through so I think I'll keep
this this notion this grid thing because
it sort of smashes everything together
into one piece which sort of seems like
a good thing I suppose to just only have
to record one pointer to one string and
get all of that information and I also
wonder if perhaps that isn't something
that would be would be something to take
to like the nth degree
like if we know that this is always our
format so we have a
with pound B in there which is the
number and then the block name we could
also say that this is going to be okay
then there's like a colon and after the
colon then we have pound or then we have
the name or something right and name
could also be there like so so if we
were to do that then we could get rid of
block name right and we would only have
like one thing which is just like what's
the name of this thing right and it's
the full name and has everything in it
that you might want stored once and that
way you just have just that one string
pointer you also have so we'd have the
clock the type the core I want to look
at see what an event has in it here
here's to do but I'm at the clock so
this looks like we already had to do to
remove it now we have I guess I'll keep
it named quid just for now because that
way we have less compile errors to fix
so we've got the grid we've got the
thread ID the core index and the type
and so that's 264 's looks like we're a
little unbalanced here you would think
we would want a few more of these but I
guess that's not in the mix right I mean
we're we're missing some stuff here so
that's a little odd but whatever so
anyway this is still relatively small so
that's good this is a little bit too
much of a payload for it I would think
so we probably at some point would want
to make these not be quite so for a post
if we were worried about it but I guess
we're not so anyway this is fine that
should give us all the information we
actually care about and then we'll just
count on parsing it after the fact so I
think that's really all I want to do
that seems reasonable
and so in here the block name no longer
has to get passed in it's just what type
of event you're recording and the grid
that you're recording there that's the
only thing that you need to tell it so
now when you have something like this
that just sort of works actually
shouldn't say grid this is actually just
a name right oh no it is grid so
something like this where you want to do
a frame marker or you do the counter
what you need to do here is just say
like I guess we should call debug grid
or something like this debug bug yeah
not sure about that so in here what we
would want to do is have this maybe be
something that's a little easier to type
so we can call this you know that's a
debug name something like that that's
use anywhere so here I can just say like
record debug event and then I just say
here's the debug name and that would
wrap that up in all of the the niceties
I believe so now we would get you know
like the file name the line number the
block name and then finally the I'm
sorry the counter and then finally the
actual frame marker part so that seems
fine all right so let's pretend that
that's good let's just pretend it's good
I'm not saying it actually is let's
pretend I also don't know what int
counter equals counter is that some kind
of flow-through thing where does the
counter what what what is this what does
this do does anyone know
is that some kind of I don't think that
does anything
I think that's vestigial remain so I
think we're literally just talking about
this now right
does that seem reasonable so the frame
marker is just record this debug event
and set the value to whatever the second
two laps was that's our you know that's
our frame counter and then we've got
this record debug event where this is
the thing that will actually do the work
for us and you know off it goes and
that's all fine and yeah and counter is
just not used in there so I just don't
think that has anything to do with
anything I think we should ignore it so
in here we've got our time to lock our
time blocks like I said are going to be
calling out to this guy right here I'm
gonna move that up so I can actually see
it here well actually I guess it's got
to be below this call the macros so
maybe I won't but anyway in time block
that's gonna have to produce these grids
now because everyone who has a record
debug event now has to pass a debug name
at the end so something like this where
we have the begin block it's not going
to pass this stuff anymore
it's got to just pass the grid in
directly right so any time you do that
it's got to be this that's the only
option and the same thing is true here
so when you do a record debug events I
don't actually know what exactly that's
gonna do but it would have to take a
good as well right so something like
that again not sure what the deal is
with the counter I guess this was
something that we were using before but
I do not know that must have just been a
completely vestigial romaine from back
when we were manually inserting the
slots
because now that we just do the atomic
add to get the the location of this
thing it just doesn't matter
right so that's all there's just a ton
of code I'm glad that we're cleaning
this up because there's a ton of stuff
here that we experimented with that we
just don't need right I mean we just
straight-up don't need it so so yeah so
that's kind of good to know because yeah
none of this stuff is necessary at all
in fact I don't even know why we have
two of these now to some degree because
I mean I guess I can sort of see why we
might want them just to make the
beginning end block thing work properly
but really now all this is going to be
is when you pass the name here it's just
gonna call begin block with debug name
and the name you passed it I mean that's
all it has to do right and the same is
true of this guy really really
straightforward so that kind of cleaned
that up pretty nicely which is which is
kind of cool I'm glad about that
but anyway so now if we get into here if
we get into this bid this here this is a
little bit tougher course now we don't
even have to store counter which is
great because we don't store counter
than this struck now is free right it
doesn't take up any room on the stack if
the optimizer is not smart enough to get
rid of it it's never asked to take up
any room on the stack which is kind of
great
and so now if we've got the time block
stuff here when we do this
initialization of the time block you can
see the stuff that's passing we don't
want to quite do it like this anymore
what we wanted to in sit said is just
say that well whatever our block is that
we were trying to do it just has the
grid and that's it right we don't need
anything else because the only thing we
need to do is call begin block with that
grid that's there is nothing else to do
right I mean that's that's all there is
to it really straightforward so if we
call begin block with that grid we can
eliminate all of this stuff I guess we
got to leave the to-do in there because
we never actually do that we never
actually did the hit count
backing right I don't know if we care
about that or not but we might want to
at some point maybe when we get to the
end of this and then when we do this
this end block here I'm gonna just call
this like a x block like that so that it
can just say okay it's gonna you know
that's gonna be the closing one that we
don't care about it having unique grid
we only care about this one we only care
about the opening having any quit
because that the closing can just refer
back to the opening to know what it's
wid would have been so that's pretty
easy so that's time to lock in a
nutshell there then when we get here
we're like time function and all this
nonsense right now all of this stuff
should be actually really really
straightforward in fact I don't think we
need any of this because now that we
have this function for doing stuff I
feel like we should be able to just say
oh okay
if you're gonna call if you're gonna
call time block or a time function then
then all we need to do is just create
one of these guys right actually
before I say that now I lied so we still
do need it for a number because we need
to append a number on here if we want
multiple of them so not quite a homerun
we've still got to have this ridiculous
macro for no real good reason but what
you gonna do so what we can do here
though is say alright all of the other
stuff with the line and all that stuff
that at least can go away because when
we do this here all we really have to do
is when you call time block and you say
I guess name then what we call through
here is just going to be debug name that
name and similarly with the time
function I think the exact same thing is
what we would do we would just say that
we would have debug name of a function
like so and and then this stuff doesn't
have to happen right and so the same is
true for all of this this all goes away
you don't need the counter of the file
or the line or the block name we're just
passing the grid and and then that's the
end of it so I think that's like well
basically does all the same stuff so no
differences but at least now it's much
much more straightforward and simple so
we don't have you know sort of arbitrary
nonsense happening in there that just
makes things we're complicated for no
reason at all alright so we now have I
think all the stuff we wanted from here
so that's all really good let me give
that a quick compile and fix anything
that's busted a syntax error string so
end block is not happy with my string
for some reason but I'm not sure why
because begin block apparently was fine
so what did I do wrong there begin block
underscore is record debug event it's
this call right here and
that all seems fine end block is pretty
right do it in block I'm not sure I see
the problem let's take a look so in
debug name
we've got unique thought counter string
it basically just passes four strings
right file line counter in name so ABC a
name which is F what we thought and in
fact I guess I could more like this
like so
I don't see the problem here
I don't see the problem to be completely
honest with you so begin block works
fine but that's what we would expect
it's only when we try to actually create
one of those debug names that we are
unhappy OOP that's not what I'm going to
do when it creates that end block it's
unhappy of course it won't show me the
expanded macro so I can't debug it of
course
because that would be way too easy I
could run the preprocessor on it and
just look at what it expanded to or I
can try to work through it here so I'm
gonna pass name in there we're gonna
call a debug name with that string so
it's gonna be passing four strings here
I believe at least that's what I was
hoping it would do and assuming that
file works then that's definitely the
case so I'm not sure what the problem is
with that let's just try this
missing before identifiers pound to find
debug name it should be yeah that should
be that's exactly what we would expect
so it's literally just this one it's
only end lock that's the problem so
debug mean by itself is not a problem
it's only end block that is the problem
and end block is a problem for reasons
that I don't necessarily understand so
let's try just for sake of an argument
let's try expanding this out a few times
to see what actually happens so if I was
to grab this so now instead of calling
in block I'm going to call in block I'm
gonna call em lock underscore and I'm
just gonna pass time to block to it oops
and just make sure I get same error and
I do so n block with the debug name of
time block is a problem for it clearly
so just calling debug name with time
block I'm wondering if that just by
itself is enough
and it looks like the answer is no so if
I don't call through the macro then it's
not a problem if I if I do call through
the macro than it is a problem meaning I
cannot do that for reasons that I am not
sure what they are probably due to the
vagaries of see macro expansion which
are absurd just my guess so what is it
that it doesn't like about that because
it allows me to pass the file just fine
here so is it just the fact that it's a
parameter that's the problem for some
reason I've got a B C and D those all
look relatively straightforward assuming
that D is an actual string which it is
and that should be fine
and passing record debug event that grid
shouldn't have been tricky either so I'm
not sure what the problem is they're not
sure that's a good question I wonder if
I can just be processed this file and
see what it actually expands out to be
that's always a little bit dicey of a
proposition certainly let's take a look
I might as well give a shot so let's see
just I think less is on this machine
less just gonna type it to less groups
and then I'm gonna search for
pre-process to standard out or
pre-process to file so /e should be what
we want and people I send out with no
line directors probably want so slash EP
is probably my best bet would be my
guess
right so if I come in here and do a
slash EP of handmade CPP and I pipe that
to pre-process temp or something in
theory I should get you know again
totally in theory I should get a file
that shows me something of what happened
in the preprocessor Oh fabulous and it
includes all the blank lines of course
well alright it doesn't matter we can
still search for tilde timed lock
presumably
maybe not
kind of need something I guess we need
something that actually will have used
it but shouldn't I see till the time
block I mean shouldn't I be if if it
actually pre processes it shouldn't I be
able to see till the timed block summer
feel like I should it's a bit weird some
see runtime library stuff getting
include it into our our code so like
it's time to block that in here at all
it does appear not to be in here at all
which is kind of odd
it should not have gotten removed ah yes
it should have you know why because I
did not specify the pound defined so all
of our debug code got removed that's
fine
easy enough to fix with a minus D and
made internal or actually how many
switches do we need to turn on debugging
just handmade internal and made internal
plus one now if I load pre-process now
we should get to time block there it is
alright so let's see what we actually
end up with when we pre process this
monstrosity I'm going to go ahead and
make these into separate lines just so
it's not too heinous to read there we go
oh wow okay that's kind of funny uh yeah
okay
so it looks like it actually inserted
this after thread ID equals uux and gets
ready it did event grid equals grid I
just was too dumb to do like this as a
separate thing so it just inserted
yeah it just insert it replaced that
with the actual grid kind of silly so
hopefully that's it then which means I
can just groups switch back to this I
would think that's that's eliris I like
that yeah I'm a fan I also think that
maybe if end block if n lock never
really cares about what its grid is then
really it should not need a name so this
is probably best to just do like you
know some generic name that we don't
care about because that way you know
nobody who actually ever calls end block
should care if they don't care they
don't care so you know forget about it
so that seems reasonable all right so
that was easy enough and hey you know
what i should mention something as an
aside here that is yet another bonus of
the unity style build like the order we
call it a single compilation unit build
i guess whatever you want to call it
single compilation unit build a scub
doesn't sound that good but single
compilation unit build if you want to
pre-process a file that's all you have
to do and you can pre-process the whole
thing normally it can be kind of
confusing if you want to pre-process a
file because you have to go figure out
how it was built in some big build
system and then just get the pre process
of that thing or whatever it's kind of
nice when you know that you can always
do a separate compile with different
switches as a pretty tree
thing to do alright looks like we're at
time so I'm gonna take a quick look here
at what we're doing before moving on
debug ID debug point or ID what is the
same for debug point or ID debug ID is
not defined is that true
it's right there what you complaining
about
oh it's you're just complaining about
something that we did up here probably
missing semicolon before or so what's
the problem is it just our data block
situation yes it is that's just that
there we go so we haven't done this the
stuff is not finished yet block name
unclear data for our time function let's
take a look at that so time function so
in time function where is block o so we
do time block with the name and we wrap
up the debug name so really this this is
not supposed to be it should just be
that right
and actually I think furthermore it
probably should just be ya know it cost
you so it should be that so it's that so
what's the problem their block name we
changed it we changed it to grid that's
so that's it okay so now I guess that's
about all there is to that these kind of
have to be fixed up so what I'm going to
do I guess because I don't really want
to go too long on that I'm just going to
go ahead and make our build up at not
run internal that way we'll still be
compiling I think all right so wait but
that's is that because we didn't pound
to fire those or something begin block
and block
where's the data block stuff so it
should have done this right if you did
but debug data block ah it's because we
got rid of these and haven't really done
anything with them yet okay so we have
to buck data block and that is that
let's connect to the Falcons being used
when in the process alright and platform
controls this is also a date block here
alright so I'm going to leave it like
that for now we should be okay just
running without made a debug information
and and then tomorrow we'll pick back up
and finish that clean up good deal
looking for cues John is struggling with
fonts alright
it can be kind of a chore to install
fonts on windows sometimes that is true
one time I could not figure out why a
font wasn't slowing it turns out you
cannot install a font from a substance
keep your Caleb how the heck do you
quickly get back into some obtuse code
that you have looked at in six months
well you saw it's kind of slow going
right it's like I got a kind of page it
back in a little bit that's okay there
isn't much to probably ask questions are
about the minute like we're at the
moment it's not a very complicated thing
so we could just end it early and that
we ever go watch John which seems like a
very good idea to me especially if he
needs to install fonts or something
maybe someone can help him who knows
font things Oh in sohbat
all right so um so I'll go ahead and
wrap up all right thank you everyone for
joining me for an episode of handmade
hero it's been a pleasure coding with
you as always if you would like to
follow along the series at home you can
of course pre-order the game on handmade
hero dot org and it comes with a source
code so you can download it and keep up
to date with what I'm doing and play
around with it at home we also have a
forum site you can go to ask questions
we have a patreon page can you support
the video serious we have a tweet bot
you can use to follow the schedule and
if you would like to use the editor that
we use here on stream it is actually
made by someone on the chat it's been
progress it's in development as we speak
it's called for coder you can type for
coder like I did into Google to find it
and if you pledge to support the project
you can get a copy early which is what
I'm using that's it for today john is
streaming some ji development stuff
right now so if you would like some more
programming in your evening I highly
recommend checking that out and taking a
look at where he's at with his
programming language development I will
be back here tomorrow at 5 p.m. Pacific
Daylight Time if you would like to see
us finish up the debug stuff so until
then have fun programming I'll see you
guys on the Internet or perhaps on John
stream take it easy everyone