hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete game
live on stream we wrote the Katy tree
traversal code yesterday the actual code
that we think we want to start debugging
and so today our job is to actually put
our Katy tree into the format that that
code wanted it was a bit of a
snuffleupagus oriented programming
situation which as you know I highly
recommend where we basically said let's
write this routine imagining that the
data format was exactly what we wanted
to make the routine fast or at least as
fast as we could think of at the time
and so now our job is to go actually
make it in that format so I'm gonna go
ahead and get started on that because
until we have a routine that builds the
tree we can't start debugging and
unfortunately yes this does mean we have
to debug two things at once because we
both have to debug the tree build and
debug the raycast
but you know at the very least we should
be able to get something running today
where we can say all right you know it's
not debugged yet but everything's in
place for both the build and the and the
testing now and like you know it doesn't
crash and so on right so we'll have like
a working model but then we've got to
actually debug the logic of it because
there's probably things that we didn't
think of or got wrong since it's a very
delicate situation we're dealing with
here right we're trying to get this
squeezed this down to the smallest
possible size and instruction count and
I think we did an okay job but like it's
not horrible even as it stands before
we've really taken an acht optimization
knock at it yet so I think you know
compared to this guy it's probably going
to be better but you know like we never
know so that's why we're gonna have to
see through actual debugging and running
of it how it actually performs all right
so what we need to do is we need to
produce a version of split box and I
might just leave the existing split box
in place
at the moment and just write a new one
so like this is gonna be called like
split KD or whatever and this one will
just do it's gonna be substant Li the
same routine but I just don't want to
have to deal in line with making both of
them and so I want to leave the old one
just for reference purposes so we can
still run it and then later when we
actually have this one debugged and
we're happy with it if it is in fact
faster we'll just vape the old one and
use this one but I don't want to have to
have them both operating in place that's
not my idea of a good time at this point
so we're just gonna do this and so we're
gonna come through it's gonna do exactly
the same pass we're not really gonna
change how we're building the tree yet
because I don't want to change the
metric yet so I just want to isolate
like it's like just to put everything
out there we don't yet know if we could
do a better job dividing our boxes up
into Katy trees too so that's a separate
thing we can improve but right now we
just want to improve for a given KD tree
how good can we test that tree that's
what we're trying to do now so I want to
leave the metric exactly the same I
don't want to change anything about that
what I want to do instead is just go
ahead and try to divide everything up
the same way and see what happens
based on the splitting okay
so one of the things that's a little
weird about this
weird about this though even as I'm
saying that is we can't really do
exactly that although I guess we sort of
could depending on how we want to
restructure that routine so hmm so
here's an interesting thought one of the
reasons like one of the things we were
doing before is we were allowing
overlapping rectangles and I hadn't
really thought about before because if
you look at this here
we don't go out of our way to ensure
that we actually split anything right so
we may have a place where we cut a box
like literally in half so it would be on
both sides of the thing and we could
just include that thing on both sides if
we wanted to but again that gets more
expensive so we could also do something
where as we go down the KD tree we just
let the thing test each time in other
words if we wanted to when we look at
the actual hit testing so this this here
what we could do is just make this be a
while loop and have it happen every time
you know I'm saying so we could actually
do that and then this would just be an
if its own if that's totally separate
right and I guess I don't really know
what to make of that
that's a really tough call because we
probably would need to test it both ways
to really know which one we should do
because in one case any time you split a
box you are adding a check to either
side
but on the other hand if you do it this
way you're doing leaf checks possibly
much earlier than you should and so you
may be wasting time with those checks
when you would have found a much closer
hit and never had to do them if they
were actually placed into the tree so
that's a tough call
gosh that's a tough call and I'm not
sure which way I want to do that I mean
my gut instinct says look you probably
don't want to proliferate boxes so maybe
you would put this up and just always
have the ability to check them so
they're basically loose bounds and
anything that can't be sorted into one
side of the other comes up here you know
that seems reasonable on the other hand
there's a certain purity to saying look
we only do this side of the branch when
we get down to the bottom of the tree
that implies that like hey a lot of the
time you you have less unpredictable
branching perhaps right because now
instead of this unpredictable branch
happening every time you walk down the
tree it only happens that one time so I
guess you know honestly I guess I might
say like let's just split the boxes I'm
really torn like the other reason I
don't like that idea is that I don't
know if there's really much of a bound
to it
like you know how many times are these
boxes gonna get split up right so let's
see I mean let's just see what would
happen here if I was going to change
that aspect of it right so let's suppose
that I did this so in here when we come
through this part of the routine let's
suppose I did something more like this
so I said like all right while leaf
index is less than one past last leaf
index then do the thing right oops
so you know maybe it goes through and it
does that so that everyone if they want
to can have leaves in them and then in
here we would just say okay if we cannot
you know if we cannot go any further
down the side we're going down then we
you know we stop and that would just be
something we would test
I guess separately right so I'm trying
to think how we would want to do that
exactly because it means we would
probably want to store one additional
bit right that just says do you keep
going and we would look at that so we
come through here we do this loop on all
of the things we test all of the things
we have to test right to produce a new
hit for this region and then when we get
down here we would do a we would just
need to know if this thing has sides
right if things this thing has sides at
all and I guess what we could say is the
sides if a side is literally zero then
it wouldn't then it doesn't exist right
so we could just test that right we
could just test that in other words if
whatever the Kati thing was for this
when we look it up like we're gonna go
grab the curse tack value here right
so you know what no because we we stuck
the curse the app so no that won't work
the reason that won't work is because
the curse act value there is what use is
what is used to determine the leaf index
in the case where we I mean here we go
we actually just used the same index
right because either it's referring to
Lisa or it's not so that wouldn't really
work and to be fair we probably could
make it work because we have room and we
know you you have some extra you know
we've got first leaf index in here and I
think we're currently not using it right
so we could use first leaf index instead
and I almost want to say that's not
actually used anywhere right like in
other words if I compile this code let
me just get rid of split KD here there
we go um so if I compile this code and
and I were to remove first leaf index
right so that goes away nobody's
actually doing anything with it right so
we could actually encode the leaf and
leaf count in there directly and so we
can do it the other way it's just yeah I
really wish I had an idea about this I'm
just really I'm just really not sure
which one to do and I don't really want
to have to write both but all I can
think of is it seems like you'd have to
like it seems like you'd have to write
both and just see which one was faster
because I don't see much way of not
doing that I mean right so I want to say
that what we probably let let's I guess
let's do it let's just do it this way so
let's let's do it this way let's say and
here what we do is we say all right so
there's a separate thing called leaf
index right and what we do is we say in
here we're gonna do the leaf index from
up to the one past leaf index by
doing the leaf index leaf count bit
right and what we could do is just have
both of these things be values so
presumably we could do something where
we just say all right that's what we've
got here we don't save the leaf count
because nobody cares what the leaf count
is and then what we do is in here we
just do a while leaf index is less than
one passed laughs last leaf index then
we do our loop and then in here where we
do like curse stock value stuff right in
here where we do that and we do our well
depth bit this is just gonna be a
different if statement this is gonna be
if the leaf index is zero right or sorry
it's the opposite way round I guess
right so well no actually cuz that's
just it's just whether you wanted to set
it has nothing to do with the leaf index
at that point I guess so
yeah in here the leaf index one passed
last if index is just unpacking these
first leaf index
because at this point we still have it
right yeah so I guess the problem but
the problem we would have here is when
we pack that we would have nowhere for
it to go so we'd end up looking at the
KD again all right all right I give up I
give up
I'm officially just going to say look
you can't do that you have to split
boxes just with them if you have to it's
not my problem anymore
right what was that if zero okay okay so
I'm gonna say yeah we're just because
there so there's just not enough room on
the stack at that point and I can't
think of anything obvious to do there I
think we're just gonna leave it this way
cuz it's fairly compact this way and
doesn't require re looking up anything
so I'm just gonna say that's what we're
gonna do for now and then we'll look and
see if maybe we need to do something
else later but that just that was enough
for me to say okay we're gonna start
with the we're gonna start with one that
that isn't allowed to do that all right
so let's go ahead and do split KD and
what that means is if you split a box
you've got to split the box in half
along the KD axis if you can't figure
out a way not to and we can make this
routine smarter so it tries not to do
that but then it sends it to either side
right so that's what's gonna happen so
yeah and again one of the things we
should keep in mind here too like I said
it's that like this is a totally stupid
in fact we should even put this here
like to do Casey this is a pretty stupid
k/d splitter we should look for better
fast metrics for picking the split plane
right
um so yeah I think I think we now just
need to rewrite this routine and make
sure that this thing splits in a way
that we we like I'm going to probably
rewrite this slightly and the reason
that I'm going to rewrite this slightly
is because I want everything to be
handled sort of in a more logical place
without having to be sort of partially
in line and partially not so think of
the first thing I want to do is say all
right there's a KD index and what I want
is the KD index to start off be ito it's
it's an axis I want the KT index to
start off saying no split so the KT
index of three is like it's not split
this node is not a splitting node right
then what I'm gonna go do is say in each
of these we're just going to record what
the split actually would be and then
we're going to do the split later right
so in here whatever this you know
whatever this classifying is here we're
we're gonna let it happen twice for now
and again this is just to try and keep
the complexity down for a little bit and
we can worry about building these
quickly later on so I'm not sure
I'm not sure if we really need to do
much other than say okay so this yeah
alright so going through here you can
see the counts an account a and count B
right
and in this case we're basically saying
look if this was a split that we're
going to use then we'll just break out
and I'll call the KT index so I'm like
I'm literally just gonna copy this this
exact thing and say for now we're just
gonna do it this way if we found a
reasonable split we're gonna split and
we're gonna record which which one it
was right so here's the dim index right
and we're just gonna record that dim
index right and that's the one we're
going to split on then in here we can
basically say okay if the KT index
equals three then we know that we did
not split right so this is actually
split false and otherwise we know that
we did actually split and we can also
assert that the KT index is greater than
equal to 0 and the KT index is less than
or equal to 3 sorry - when we get in
here because it has to be one of those
it has to be one of the dimensions we
actually know about so next we would
basically say okay let's move into the
into the body of this the thing that
actually does the splits so this is
going to be in here and this part here
is the nan splitting part right and
these will have to get rewritten because
they're not doing what they should be
doing at the moment so we also would put
this in here
okay and so now what we need to do is
think more about what the actual stuff
we need to write into these into the
sides section actually contains so we
don't really know how that's gonna work
yet and the only way we can know is to
go back and reread our routine and see
what is the actual information it wants
encoded in there specifically so when it
comes through and tests one of these
things what it's going to do is it's
going to push on to the KT stack some
piece of information that it received
right and then it's gonna unpack things
like the leaf count and like the node
index like that sort of stuff that it
needs it's gonna unpack that and things
like the plain D that sort of thing so
inside those sides we need two things we
need to pack our plain D and our KD
index and then we need to pack our
child's node index and our child's leaf
count and our the node index will
actually be the leaf index if this is a
leaf node right so what that means is
that this routine definitely gets a
little more complicated because what
will actually happen here is this KD
tree node for the sides that needs to
not be passed in anymore so what's
actually gonna happen is when we do this
whole garbage experience we don't
actually want to create a container node
until we actually think we're gonna
split this thing and then once we
actually split it we need to see what
the what the sides say we should pack
right but we don't actually want to have
one of those at the start because if we
don't so if we if we're on this side of
things then all we want to do is pack
these up like we're doing here and then
ignore all of this like none of that
wants to happen and instead what happens
is we have like a result parameter that
we pack back so we're gonna do like a
pack and we're gonna send back to the
other side right so here you can see us
passing back the plain D and then the
sides information right so what we
essentially want and now you can start
to see the shape of this routine more
clearly is there's going to be a return
value here that's like oh and actually
split is now irrelevant there's gonna be
like a pack value right and the pack
value is going to get returned to the
parent because that's what they need to
put in their side in their side array
right so now it seems pretty reasonable
like this all seems fine to me
so in here you can see what we would
need to pack is we need to pack the leaf
count and the node index and the
obviously we're always packing in the KD
index pattern and the plane test pattern
so the Katie index pattern and the plane
test pattern always get packed in by the
parent so in here we only need to pack
the leaf count in the node index right
yeah
so since those packs will actually
always be the same I want to say we can
probably do this a little bit
differently which is to say that in here
we can produce the pack value in one
stable location and then we can deal
with the like we can deal with the
packing by saying look here's the note
index to pack here's the leaf count to
pack right and so in here we know it's
source count so leaf count equals source
count ah so we know there's a safe
truncate to u8 so we're gonna source has
to be packed because we know that if
it's greater than 4 we're gonna try we
want to watch to make sure that we
actually split anything I guess I
suppose in theory I wonder if this is a
problem because in theory we could get
into a situation where we actually can't
split and I don't know what we do about
that if you have a thing where there's
actually 256 things that cannot be split
along any dimension but how would that
ever happen I don't think it could so I
think we're okay with that but we would
want to know right the worst would
happen is to get wrong rate casting so I
think it's okay but anyway so in here we
would say all right we've got our our
leaf count all set up so this whole
thing will just work and the node index
is just whichever the first one is so I
guess I shouldn't I was a little hasty
there where is that - is that bit in
here somewhere
Oh what am I thinking we have this
routine copied just right above so where
is my split box there it is so we want
to do this
as well right so this needs to happen to
add the box storage and then we need to
know what the node index was because
we're gonna pack that right so there's
our entire set of information along that
path I think that's just correct right
so this looks fine and yeah and then
we're all good it's just this is known
index now and then we're just down to
the other side so when you here where we
actually do need to we need to add a KD
node in this foot in this case and then
we need to go through and actually do
the classification and this is going to
be a worse classification actually we're
probably going to need to change exactly
how we do this like I said so we're
gonna change how we do that but for the
time being we're gonna have to add a KDE
node here right and then we're gonna
have to construct the the KD nodes
contents and the difference here is I
mean we're still effectively doing the
same thing but the difference here is
we're gonna have to have a thing that
splits boxes in half and puts one in one
side and one on the other so that's the
real like the main difference we're
gonna have there so we probably will
still have something that looks roughly
like this it won't create child boxes so
this part is not this is not gonna
happen right so none of that happens the
KD node gets added here and
I guess we want this to be also like a
note indexes we're gonna need to know it
so our Katy note index here or this
index this note index I guess we'll call
it maybe we're gonna add one to that and
then we're going to go ahead and we we
don't ever add them anywhere else so
actually what a more but probably do is
say this note index equals solution Katy
node count plus plus right and what we
have to do here is say like look if the
solution Katy node count is less than
the total number that we can ever have
right and we don't know what that is
then we can do this otherwise we just
return two packs value of zero because
we would have to because we can't build
anymore of the tree and that's fine it
just means inaccurate lighting for that
frame so that's good because we don't
want like crash if the lighting can't
happen right we just want to have bad
lighting so that is also good if we blow
out the bounds at all right so I think
this is what we do we'd say all right
let's get a node count here update then
let's grab that particular node so
that's this node I might change this and
say this is the PAC node index although
there there are the same so no I guess I
would just call this node index and this
is what it is it's what we're gonna
return right so that's the node that
we're actually gonna use the next time
around and then when we get down here
like I said we sort of have a little bit
of work to do with the splitting so in
terms of splitting this all needs to get
rewritten but what we do know is that
we're going to effectively have a pack
value so this is side zero pack so what
we're gonna do here is I guess this
right so this is like the positive the
negative sign pack and then we're gonna
have the positive sign pack
like this I guess I mean it probably
should correspond to the bit so maybe
it's the other way around I don't know
that part doesn't really matter because
we can choose whichever way we do that
we just have to make sure that we're
picking the sides the same way in both
places so which way do we do it up here
would be the next question here we go so
up here we say let's move the mask in
terms of what we saw and then we're
gonna say descend down the start side
bit not the inverted bit so I guess it's
like positive would be zero right and
negative would be one so it's the sign
bit is what you use to address into
there right so then in here this part
again is not really relevant to us so
I'm guessing we would do something
because like if you look at what's in
here we need to know the plain D it's
right so we need to know this and we
need to know the sides we need to know
the first leat well no we don't because
that doesn't exist right so the first
leaf index
so now and I think about it actually do
you need any of these things though cuz
to the sides just always tell you that
like couldn't we have just packed that
into the sides
I mean yes so I don't think you need any
of this I think this is all a waste of
time right so I don't know that we need
any of that for anything the first leaf
index the leaf count the KT index can
all be packed into the side because by
definition it has to be because we then
count on it being packed into the side
later right so I mean if I look I think
it's just literally like you set the
plane D here and the plane D is set to
whatever the heck the plane D was set to
so it's like this thing right the
classifier distance so this is the plane
D here and if we go down to this we
would just say all right that so once we
set up the plane D here all we would do
is say that once we know that we don't
have to do anything anymore it's
literally just this because everything
else we would pack into these sides
values right
so yeah pretty sure so I would probably
prefer to do it like this where we we
accept the node in next leaf count pack
back like so and then we or in like
what's the stuff we need the index and
the
just the index right so we pack in here
our KD index
so this is our like KT index pack value
and that's just this thing shifted up
right and so thinking about that like if
I'm thinking about that which I am the
way that we decided to pack the KD
indexes into this thing is they were
just shifted up by 28 right so it's just
like slammed on the top of that thing
the plane test pattern and I guess we
could we could put the plane test
pattern in there as well because it
needs to be right so the plane test
pattern is just whether it's the
positive side or the negative side oh
and that's different on either side so
don't know why I would do it that way so
this is the positive side and then this
is the negative side right so the
positive side plane test pattern and the
negative side plane test pattern are
these things they are 24 bits up right
and what I need to do is just have
whichever pattern corresponds to the
correct side now if those are the sign
bits then all zeroes is the positive
side so it's actually just zero and if
it's negative then it would be all ones
right so we have all zeros are all ones
as what we would actually use for oaring
things in and that's it because the
plain B gets put in separately at push
time because there's no need to store it
since when we push it we have it so we
can just you know get that we don't need
to store 64 bits it just floats the
structure the KD Index gets packed in
here the plane test pattern gets packed
in here and the leaf count and the node
index get packed right here so the node
index or a leaf count all we need to do
is shift these up so it looks like the
node index is shifted up by nothing and
the leaf count is shifted up by 16 right
so that's the complete pack like like
that's it so what I need to do now is
have some conceptualization of the
maximum number of these that you can
actually have right and I guess probably
will just make it be the maximum that
there is so basically like will allocate
a full complement of that because that
space is pretty cheap for us if you
imagine we have 65536 of these struts
that are 12 bytes each now like it's
less than a megabyte of scratch space
which these days you're lucky if you can
get like the DLL for one entity in your
unreal game to be less than one
megabytes so like
I'm assuming we can probably just say we
can afford maximum scratch space there
because I don't care and we won't touch
it it won't be cash pollution if we
never touch it so only if you actually
stressed it to that level would you ever
actually pay for that so I think that's
fine now the problem that we are going
to have immediately hereafter is that
now we don't actually know
looks like also next dim index so next
dim index is actually something we would
have to produce outside as well so in
here I would say we probably just do
that and that I don't know if this is
actually a good idea anyway but
something like this okay so yeah so now
I think we're all good here
Katy node count Shh
should be fine there what's the actual
problem what is that actually
complaining about No
Oh previous decoration yes sorry thank
you compiler that was not intended so I
think now we're more or less this
routine is more or less correct and what
we need to do now is write the code that
will actually break like that we'll
split these things up and I'll be honest
with you I don't really know what we
want to do here so I think I'm like I
think this is an open area of research
for us that we want to probably play
with later to see what the way is to
build the most most balanced KD trees we
can and we weren't doing that previously
right I'm going to keep like I said
before the way we're doing it now just
because since I don't know and you know
what let's just pass a rectangle three
since I don't know yet how I want to do
that and I want to compare apples to
apples as much as possible we're just
gonna keep doing it the same way we were
doing it before so here I'm gonna say
like look let's do a get center on this
thing so we'll just use the total bounce
center here which is what this was
computing and then we're I think the
classification system would just work
and then when we come down here this is
only this part actually has to get
redone and the reason this part has to
be redone is not because we couldn't
just use these counts that we produced
up here but rather because we actually
need to look at the splitting properties
of this right so yeah like I said not
exactly my favorite thing in the world I
don't care about ref see a ref see B
those are not relevant anymore those are
color of color approximator z' we were
using for long distance ray casting and
we're just not gonna do that anymore I
don't think so and we can you know and
it's cheap to add it in either way we
wouldn't do it here
so in here what we want to do is we want
to do subsidy the same thing but now
what we need is something that's more
like if it's clearly on one side we do
one thing if it's clearly on the other
side we do the other thing if it's split
down the middle we add it to both sides
right so this like check approximator
thing is fine we can leave it that way
but then what we need to do here is when
we do this sort of when we brush through
here we would need and bounds a and
bounds B by the way or exactly what we
would pass to this and this and let's do
positive bounds negative bounds and then
like negative count that way we can see
what those are we don't have to remember
what's a and what's because you know you
could see screwing that up pretty pretty
easily
so we'll just do positive counts and
negative count and we'll do it that way
all right so I think that's all fine and
[Music]
all we need to do now is in here have
this bead like three ways so this is
gonna be like if add a or is add
positive and if add negative right and
we might sometimes set both of those
things that to true so we would do this
and this and here we'll just say
positive counts here we go positive
count negative counts and here we would
do
the negative cap right it looks like
we're doing a backward a forwards
backwards build there right and so here
again just changing the names of these
is going to be positive bounds and
negative bounds and this will be
positive bounds and negative bounds
negative positive when we do the rectum
in max here that is just weird no we're
going to need it so we might as well do
it here as box bounds and we probably
just should have made that be a
rectangle it doesn't really matter about
whatever so then this is positive count
plus plus and this is negative count
plus plus and now we've got a proper
summation for these and so this is going
to be like an else if else kind of thing
now where we do like add positive equals
add negative equals true and here it's
gonna be like add positive equals true
add negative equals true right and so
what we need to do here is we're gonna
do exactly the same thing as before
it's just instead of classifying the
center which is what we were doing
before we're gonna classify whichever
dimension of the box was the one that we
actually need to check right so if we're
checking for adding to the positive side
what we want to see is is the minimum
one higher than the class distance right
so when you subtract away plane D right
which is what we're doing here right
if you subtract away the plain D from
this thing then what actually happens
right and
I don't know why we're even doing it
this way this seems dumb I mean it's
that doesn't even make sense
I don't even know what the heck plaster
is therefore this is just a yeah that's
just alright whatever so I mean this is
just this right I mean that's that's
what we're doing so if it's greater we
add it to the positive side if it's less
we added to the Oh actually wait no we
can just do this directly so what am I
thinking
add positive is just a boolean value in
fact we don't even need to store it
right all you actually need to do is say
look is the maximum value the farthest
it could be is that on the other side
then you're going to do this branch and
if the minimum value is on the other on
the negative side of the plane then
you're gonna add the negative branch and
we don't need to do any of the stuff
that I was just saying so ignore all
that as key and peele said forget
everything I've set up unto this point
so I think that's actually all we needed
to build the tree properly and why the
heck this thing was written this way I
have no idea because there's no need for
a dot product I guess we were thinking
maybe we would use other kinds of planes
at some point but this is stupid and
we're not gonna do it so like this yeah
it doesn't really make much sense to me
right look why why wouldn't you just
have done this here I'm saying
so it really doesn't make sense why we
would do that and yeah I just don't get
it so in this case if we wanted to do
this check still the same way as we were
checking it before we can just say that
we're gonna actually multiply it by this
thing e right and and then we just check
it so no more inner products being
thrown around for no reason when we can
just do an offset load yeah doesn't
matter alright so this thing will build
our KD tree now so we can just call it
and the problem we're gonna have is we
have an allocating space for it so it's
just gonna crash immediately because
we're sending it off in a null land
right and sending it off into no land is
not a good plan so we're gonna need to
allocate some space for it but let's at
least verify that that does happen and
hope that it crashes because if it
doesn't crash that means it's not even
running which means we've failed quite
hard whoops
so anyway in building partition for
lighting you can see here where we've
got all this kind of crap happening what
we want to do here is do a split KD on
this thing and what I'm going to propose
here because I have no real better idea
about what we should do is I'm going to
propose that we now add a global control
switch that basically says look you
build one thing on one path you build
another thing on the other path right so
the root box index can still be used
it's not really a root box index anymore
but you know we don't need this we don't
need it but what we're gonna do here is
say alright there's a there's a control
thing here and this thing is going to be
like lighting
use old KD and that's going to control
both things so you know you get
whichever tree it is that you thought
that you wanted when you set up the
lighting system and if this one turns
out to be demonstrative Li like way
better then we just go vaporize the
other one and if it doesn't we play with
it for a little while to see if there's
a reason why it isn't that is obvious
and if there isn't then we just walk it
back out and go back to optimizing the
other one right okay so light use old KD
blah blah blah whatever and so on we're
just gonna define this to be 1 and we're
just gonna verify that we can still
build it that way the box that Katie
stack garbage can also happen the same
way so we can do this right where we
define those two and actually is that
doesn't actually make any sense what I
just said this is only used on this side
of the branch now so probably the right
way to do it is just put it here hey
this is only used here right so yeah so
that seems better and you know I'm I'm
happy with that
so now what we should see in theory
anyway
is if I run this under remedy we should
be able to run the old way and get it
okay that's the wrong I loaded the wrong
program so we should see the same
results that we had been seeing which
right that that does look right and then
if I run it the new way it should crash
like I just said because we didn't
actually give it any space to work with
so I'm assuming it will just you know
just die this needs to
look like this and we need to pass the
total bounds here that was my little
foot stamp did you like it when we
passed the total bounds here we need to
pass the occluder bounds and then we
need the solution root box index to
equal the split Cady but we don't want
it to have the leaf count in it which
should actually be fine because it can't
write it can't be a leaf at least I
don't think so well no it could what if
you just had very little yeah so
actually it should just be that honestly
so that's the split Cady and where's the
parameters that thing so it takes the
solution the box count the source the
dust the dim and Oh accidentally to
leave the dim index and we want this
thing I'm gonna just call this like root
K T value and just then put it in there
cuz you know honestly it needs to be
there um and so then when we do the box
at the start what we actually want to do
is just unpack that index that way it'll
work even if we have some weird
degenerate case where there's like
nothing to light so what we really want
to do here is this right so these two
values the leaf count and the curse tack
value those actually want to come out of
the packed value here which is the
solution root KD value yum Santiam
that's not good thank you compiler
that's a good catch all right
so that's everything we should now crash
the first time we try to write one of
these things oh and you know what let's
compile in debug mode because obviously
the release modes not gonna show us much
we should crash like right when we first
try to add one of these things so we'll
try to add it and it should just crash
cuz none of that stuff's initialized
right and that's exactly what we get so
that's good news at least we got what we
expected so now let's go in and actually
add the scratch base in so that we have
some space to do these so that's gonna
be an HH light prof in the same place
where it just allocates scratch space
for everything else I can see here right
we can allocate space for this so in
here I can say and I don't know where
all this stuff needs to go so it's Katie
nodes right and I mean I guess I could
just put like 65536 in there and call it
a day but I'm not sure if that makes the
most sense maybe it does maybe it
doesn't for now I'm not gonna do that
so for now I'm gonna say all right let's
get those Katie tree nodes in here we're
gonna malloc a UN sixteen max times the
size of one of these Katie tree nodes
and off we're gonna go now that's gonna
be too much space at first I believe
I'll so let me just run this and see
what happens to us so it looks like we
spiral out of control
so just stack overflow they're not the
website but an actual stack overflow so
we're not getting Kate Cady index equals
three hardly ever it looks like for some
reason and I'm not sure what that reason
is but I guess we'll find out in the
future
so we'll look at that later what we're
gonna do now though before we do that
any before we do anything else there
there was one of the thing I wanted to
do and that was remove the craft that
was in this so I want to say all that
can go away now right am I right about
that so if we want to get rid of that
Cady index which we do we need to
remember it right so we would need to do
this
[Music]
um just want to make sure I'm thinking
about this correctly
so I'll be honest I don't know that I'm
right about that so when you first test
the value right you need to know what
the KD index is of that thing that
you're testing and up here where you
where you push on the opposite side you
need to know what that KT index would
have been so you would need 2 KD indexes
here right because only the plain D is
told so you'd need the KD you need your
KD index and you would need the KD index
of your of the next person down now
honestly that's probably fine luck you
could do that it would look like this
right yeah so it would look like this
and it would just unpack whatever the KD
index was and at that point I think we
actually filled the entire 32 bits with
stuff right and so if we wanted to do
that I mean I guess we just can this is
kind of a ridiculous routine and I don't
know if I'm being smart or stupid
usually it's very difficult to tell the
difference between the two until you
have runtime measurement of something so
I am totally unsure about which one I am
at this point so there's that
I got nothing that's just what we're
doing this may be fantastically stupid I
need to work in I don't even know if I'm
in the right ballpark here of stuff like
I'm I'm like I'm really surprised by how
that lutein routine looks and like I
said either it's very smart or it's
really dumb and usually you
unfortunately it's the latter right
usually if you're trying to be too
clever you are trying to be too clever
so I don't know we may have to walk a
little bit about that back as we start
to step through it and realize Oh duh
that was really stupid but I mean that's
just that's just the way it is nothing
ventured nothing gained you know what
I'm saying to you so alright so now we
should be able to start debugging this
thing and the first thing we need to do
bug is our split node like this thing
because that's not correct now right
this is also smaller now so I don't know
how we want to document that cache line
size because 64 divided by 12 is a weird
number right so I'm just gonna leave
that off and pretend we didn't think
about it and just say it's 12 bytes
aren't you happy
I think we're all good there so let's go
ahead and debug our split Katie node
thing it just just let's double check
that it's actually even plausibly doing
something so here we're counting values
by saying where is the total bounce the
bounds that we're looking at here what's
the center and let's go ahead and take
the counts of each of those right now
what I would say about this is we
probably want to just record the best we
probably want to do like something like
picking the maximum minimum sign like we
want to do something where we actually
test all three because we don't just
want to pick one that happens to have a
count but I don't know
I mean well like we might as well pick
the best one because we're doing a
second pass over it there's no reason
not to do that right
hard to say
anyway so the dimension yeah that like I
guess I would say like you you want the
you want the lowest maximum is that
right you want the lowest maximum value
let's just do that oh wait no don't do
that yet because I said I wanted to test
it apples to apples so pick the lowest
nice but I will do that next
after we debug all this crap so the
Katie node here we basically say like
look if we can add another one then we
do and we add the node count here we
we get the plane D we classify
everything as to whether it's on one or
the other side of a plane Oh
although I guess we should also assert
that both sides got something because
they should always presumably well
that's a really matter we pack those up
and then we're off right note index leaf
count stays zero in that branch
yeah so I would have thought that would
work it obviously didn't so we're
testing to see whether the element is
the maximum side of the box is on the
other side of the positive flame and the
negative side of the Box on the negative
side of the plane
I guess the problem there is eventually
you get down to something where you're
not yeah so I guess the problem that
we're gonna have is I can't not change
this because if I don't change this it's
just gonna always keep splitting
[Music]
potentially although since it cycles the
dimension each time still should have
been okay I'm gonna go ahead and just
step into this I'm not really sure why
that's failing so let's watch it fail
because I don't feel like I really have
a handle on it honestly so let's jump
through here and I guess what I'll do is
let me just let this thing go a bit for
a while so maybe I'll just like watch
this part I assume it breaks the first
split it breaks like right here right
okay so no it doesn't actually it has to
actually get down into a cycle at some
point by the way in case you're
wondering some things that don't work
with visual studio is what I'm doing
right now like I love that thing where I
was like wow visual studio is really
slow and everyone was like why do you
need to be fast can't you just use the
data break point no like there's more
things in a debugger when you want to
watch your program run I have so little
patience for modern programmers they
drive me nuts their standards are so
incredibly low it's like it's just it's
infuriating how low their standards are
right it's kind of like you know they
just
they build like a house that's like four
two by fours that are kind of all wonky
and then like a you know a a piece of
canvas across the top that they like
nailed in and they're like it's a house
and you're just like what are you
talking about
have you ever seen a house before like
no it's not but they're like now that's
great why would you need anything else
if it's raining you just go into the
canvas part unbelievable so this is
we've gotten into the loopback state now
right because I could see the stack kind
of proliferate so I'm just want to look
and see what's going on now so that I
have some understanding of of the
situation so here's the positive bounds
the negative bounds the positive count
and the negative count and
so I wonder what the Box bounds actually
are so I'm gonna step through here so
let's take a look at box bounds here is
box bounds oh so by the way here is I
think x3 I think I saw X 13 pixels out
there and I was just lauding his
debugger for saving our us all from the
collective disaster that's Visual Studio
I wanted to throw out a feature
suggestion that I find I have a problem
with a lot and there is a thing in
Visual Studio that sort of tries to
solve it but it sucks it would be cool
to have one in remedy and it'd make it
good so when you have something like box
bounds what I want to see is just a
quick summary of what the thing is over
here and I feel like there's a lot of
ways you could implement this feature
and I don't know like what the best
possible way to implement it would be
but there's like some suggestions right
so I think the ultimate suggestion is
can you just make a thing where in the
executable you can just define like this
like
and then like the name of the thing so
it'd be like that sort of thing you know
I'm saying so like basically there just
be like a function and then in here I
can just serialize this thing like out
to remedy dude I'm talking about does
this make any sense
so remedy just looks when it loads the
eggsy it just looks for any symbols that
are like remedy watch and then if I have
that I can just there's like a button in
here like a preference setting or like
probably a button probably a setting
like right here where it's just like do
you want to call those or not cuz
sometimes you want that turned off
because you're like you don't want to be
like reentering that code because you're
like debugging something in there but
then like other times you just click it
and it'll just call you and you print
out the thing does that make any sense I
don't know how achievable that is with
the current way that like remedy works
necessarily but just a thought because
then if you could just get that working
you could do like anything you want here
and I wouldn't do this by the way I
would probably actually do this I'd make
an H file that defines this thing right
because then you can also do stuff like
you know requested size and pixel buffer
and I don't know right like you could
imagine doing stuff where people can
dump images out to that and we
forms and who cares right and like that
would get you entirely out of the
business of even having any of those
features in remedy if you just have the
ability to take like bitmaps or strings
and they get dumped out to remedy and
then people can just write these and you
can even then have people share them so
they can just share all of their remedy
watches and you just like you would end
up just doing this at the top of your
program and then never think about it
again right I think that would be like
an awesome feature and unlike the stupid
crap like Visual Studio makes you write
a plugin that you have to install is
it's like there's already an executable
like you've loaded my executable why do
I have to build a plug-in right it makes
no sense but it's like that's where
their head is that they're often you
know they're often we don't know how
computer works land which so whatever so
I don't know how achievable that is but
that seemed to me like the shortest path
towards a really baller watch window and
you wouldn't even have to then do most
additional features cuz that watch
context could even pass like parameters
like you know you got like the string
thing in there where you do like string
count those could be things that get
passed to this watch thing too so the
watch struct can just add things on to
the bottom over time and you know old
stuff would still work cuz it doesn't
mean if it doesn't ever touch lower down
it won't break right so you just keep
adding stuff to that struct and it's
just like a giant context you hand to
the thing they fill it out and back it
comes and now you're you know you're in
baller town right so I don't know that
seemed really simple I wanted to throw
it out there because I was holding off
on suggestions like that because you
know remedy was kind of just like
getting started and adding like the
basic features but remedies getting to
the point now where it has all the basic
features so I thought now might be a
good time to think about like what's the
easiest way to add like features that
are just ball
they have nothing to do with basic
debugging they're more like hey this is
cool and most of our girls don't even
have this right anyway that's all okay
so let me go ahead and try to figure out
what the heck is going on here but I do
think that that's a problem again
because we're never gonna maybe get out
of that split I guess it is kind of hard
to say like whether we will or won't but
yeah all right hold on a second
okay so taking a look now if I I'm in
the like bad part so let me take a look
at what those box bounds are and you can
see why I'm like motivated for that
feature cuz like I just want the box
bounds to show like these three values
these three values and then the
dimension so the subtraction of those
values right and that's a really easy
piece of code for me to write in my
thing but it'd be really hard for you to
add that because you'd need to have like
a scripting language or something that
like let me tell you what I want to see
and some of those things have to be
expressions just like it just doesn't
seem like a good path to go down like
having a scripting language in a
debugger
because you've already loaded my actual
code so calling my code seems like the
easiest way because then the debugger
don't have to do nothing you know so
anyway so in the Box bounds here where
we've got like these values I guess the
answer is we're not splitting because
why tell me why
I guess because some of these are just
right on top of each other yeah so I
guess the answer there and I'm not sure
if this is the right answer or not but I
guess the answer there is like if it
gets down to a degenerate case where you
cannot split then I guess what we do is
just treat that as a leaf right so so I
guess like where's my split Kitty here
it is so I guess what we would do is
like try to do this thing first and if
the count on either side is equal to the
source then we just don't split right so
I think it's this
so we'd come through here and we'd try
to do this we would see whether or not
we could do anything about it if we
can't do anything about it then we
meaning if this split doesn't work so if
we'd say like if positive count is less
than source count and negative count is
less than source count so if we're
always if we're always passing a lower
source then we do this if we can't right
then we're gonna set the KD index
backwards right so we're gonna say hay
bale this is now a leaf right and so
it'll it'll change those now we don't
want to actually add this thing until
then so I would say that this stuff
actually only happens like in here at
that point and so we have the ability to
bail if the actual split procedure fails
how does that work wait aren't we
supposed to stop somewhere
well I guess that succeeded then okay so
now I'm assuming we're gonna have the
problem of now we gotta debug our are
actual like ray cast routine and that's
fine so let's take a look at at that
okay so here we're gonna push this onto
the stack the start side bit and here
we're going to push we're going to load
out the packed value right and we're
gonna do the next split and we're
splittin and here we're doing an actual
leaf okay
so this says it had to check the other
side as well
what's the stack depth at this point
seven so I'm just going to watch what
happens here
so it's sort of working let me run it
for a while and just see whoa
access violation writing location really
hold on a second
so this does not bode well like I said
so I'm assuming there's a bug in there
or are we really screwed up somehow
because even in debug mode that first
ray cast pass should not take anywhere
near this long right
hmm so what's going on here if I do a
break we're in here the depth is only
for weird are we just oscillate Alou
pier where we oscillate it looks like
that's exactly what's happening
but let's verify that
I mean it's hard to say I should
probably print out the log also I'm kind
of curious how many of these did we make
not very many so even if we were to walk
them all so our walk must be screwed up
right because even if we were to walk
all of these things then you wouldn't be
able to spend this long testing them
right it's just not I don't think it's
theoretically feasible let's see whether
or not we get caught in an infinite loop
by going into a build that probably
could test everything if it wanted to so
let's do a release mode so it it does
complete so it's just like a very bad
walk I guess and it doesn't produce a
similar result although I guess we don't
really know for sure because we do have
error in the system in general but yeah
so like it seems really bad I mean I'm
assuming that it shouldn't be that bad
no matter how we ended up doing it it
shouldn't be as horrible as that right
so I'm not sure I'm not sure we'll see
so let's see I think we're almost done
about 15 minutes left so I guess we'll
just try to do a little debugging here
and then next weekend we'll try to
actually get to the bottom of everything
so yeah that just takes that's that's
just really weird
hmm all right so let me also check to
make sure that this finishes in a
reasonable amount of time if I actually
turn on debug mode in terms of that
initial first one because I'm assuming
that it does but actually guess I don't
know so I'm gonna go into debug mode and
I'm gonna make sure that that initial
thing should check complete in a
reasonable not time right yeah so we
should expect that roughly we shouldn't
expect our routine to be that much worse
that it couldn't you know get at least
that far so let's take a look what's the
problem and again we don't really know
if the tree is built properly so we may
want to actually go through and work out
by hand to what extent the tree makes
sense but if we take a look at the the
new routine you can see us doing the
testing here and again that's producing
the T ray stuff which is what we
actually need it to produce right and
then we're doing the testing on the KD
tree as we go down and yeah we just know
whether we can whether we need to test
the other side by using whether we get
on the other side of the plain D right
[Music]
so I suppose one thing we could test is
just to see how long this thing takes
assuming that we only ever go all the
way down one side and that would just
look like this right and we would expect
that to be basically instant right and
it like totally isn't so it seems really
weird because that doesn't have to do
like anything right it's only gonna
descend down like the briefest set of
things and then it's gonna like be done
like it shouldn't I don't know why it
would be having that why it would take
that long
[Music]
I'm just trying to avoid starting a full
debug pass on this thing because we
don't have time to actually do it so I'm
thinking we gotta wait till next weekend
but it's like yeah I mean something
seems really wrong here so let's take a
look at some of these count values so is
it possible for me to just get that
information out so like this should tell
me right we have a thing that tests the
walk I want to say so if we look at I
just want to see like how many these
things were tested so it says like that
the well I guess we don't record
partitions so we should do that right so
total leaves tested is here but
partitions tested isn't so we need like
this here to do the partition test right
okay
so yeah I just don't really know so
let's take a look at what these numbers
compare to be so if I set the lighting
to use the old KD what's what do those
numbers look like versus the new one so
[Music]
I mean the answer here is that the
number of leafs is wicked high right
because this is how many leaves were
tested with the new system this is how
many leaves were tested with the old
system and we're not even doing the walk
so something is really broken there
possibly because of the way that we're
actually doing the dividing it could
just be that our tree is that bad right
so I don't know so let's take a look and
see what happens if we try to upgrade
this a little bit right where we just
spend more time building the split box
and we see if we can do better than this
super super super crappy version because
since now this one actually has to
divide the boxes up and put them on
either side it creates a constraint that
the tree build has to actually not be
super sucky
so maybe what we'll do is say okay if we
take and do this check the same way that
we're doing down here so we're gonna do
this right we're gonna do this I don't
actually know why we're bothering with
this because we don't need that right so
this code is just doing account a count
be like that's all this thing needs to
do right and this doesn't need to be
there at all
so all we need to do is sweep through
here and see like using the classifier
the exact same thing we were doing
before to see what would happen in these
cases and then we'll just pick the
lowest min value right so we'll say so
when we come through here we'll say that
if count a or I should say min count min
count equals min count a count B right
and then we'll say if the min count here
is less than the lowest min count or I
should say if the lowest min count is
greater than the min count then we'll
say that the lowest min count equals the
min count and take take it
right so this is how we'll pick our
class we'll say whichever one is I'm
sorry maximum so whichever count is
higher we'll take that and what we want
to do is minimize our maximum count
right so it's just a min max 3 at that
point and I don't think that's gonna do
it because I think we've got other bugs
but you know we'll find out right so
we'll see assuming that was that a
release build yet was I was like if that
wasn't a release build then that was
actually improvement but it's not so at
this point I might want to actually
start printing out the tree as well just
so we can see what the tree looks like
at least the top bounds of it maybe I
could also try dumping out the like well
yeah no no
let's take a look at HH light prof and
see what that like the total box count
and stuff is after we're done so here's
the box count before we do it right or
is that after does that include ones we
add or not
well we add those in there right so wait
why isn't that number higher than right
cuz we add box storage here and like
what's going on something's weird here
so if we look at what the total box
count is it's not different really hmm
and you know what I might want to do too
is make these print deaths more
printouts more labeled so what I might
want to do is say like in here let me
label which one we're doing so before we
go anywhere further in here we'll just
do like
so here we'll just say look if we're
using the old KD we'll say old if we're
using the new KD we'll say new that way
we can see which one we are in really
easy in the printout right so here I can
say like okay that's the new one and
then I can go ahead and switch it to the
old one but something's not adding up
here we've got a pretty obvious bug
happening and we just got to go fix that
probably an index bug just like I said
at the beginning of the stream so if you
look at these two right here's the old
one and here's the new one so we didn't
add that many more leaves though is the
thing so if we didn't add that many more
leaves why are we testing so many more
leaves how is that possible like it
shouldn't be possible because the leaves
always have to be contiguous so it's not
like like any given node can only refer
to one set of leaves so we've got a
problem
something's busted in the way that we're
pulling out the leaf labels right
because it should not be possible to
test that many more leaves using only
one only a walk down one side of the
tree how is that possible
something's something's up
[Music]
yeah I'm not seeing it I'm not seeing it
I mean here's another example right so
let's just see if we just nerf this
entirely so now we are literally only
doing the first run down the tree how
many leaves are we testing
so that's the old one let's switch to
the new one
I mean isn't that just so broken like
something is so I'm totally at a loss to
explain what's going on here how on
earth could you possibly test five
million leaf nodes so which is ten times
more than the old algorithm without ever
doing a tree walk you're only testing
one node at that point right because the
very first time you ever test any Leafs
at all you exit the loop what's going on
this is like impossible like this should
not even be remotely possible to do what
we're seeing it should be should be an
actually impossible right so let's watch
what happens because I'm totally at a
loss to explain that let's look at the
first time through here's us walking
down right and we walk down to a depth
of whatever we're going to test some
leaves I guess to be fair there's a lot
of them way too many so I think our
splitter is still totally busted
right
so I I mean one answer is like somehow
we really just have that many leaves in
this tree in the in that many leaves in
the one node yeah and then we exit so
the answer is there's really just that
many so 43 testing 43 leaves it's kind
of nuts the testing only 43 leaves per
raycast is still so slow right but it is
so how did we end up in a situation
where there were 43 leaves we couldn't
split I mean how is that possible it
doesn't seem likely you know right it
seems like our split katie is just
really bad or something so we come
through here we say look we're gonna
pick a splitter and it's gonna be the
centroid of you know the the boxes we
all add it up and then we're gonna go
through and if that's the wrong one
yeah so we're gonna move through here
we're gonna say alright if the box max
is greater than the class distance then
the count for a goes up if the box min
is less than the class distance then
count B goes up and whichever the larger
the two is if that is less than the best
we have we record it right so then we go
in through here and maybe this code is
busted and just isn't ever working so
then we come through and we say alright
let's add these we say okay let's build
erect min max for the Box we're looking
at let's see if the maximum is on the
other side of the flame D or if the
minimum is on the other side sort him
and record the bounds which seems like
what you would want if we were able to
split at all so if anybody went on one
side of the other then we record the
split
otherwise we don't I mean is that really
failing that often like how is that
possible just seems so not possible I
feel like we must be working with these
boxes in an incorrect way
because since we have like mostly boxes
that are just like grids of boxes how
the heck could you not split them
they're not overlapping most of the time
right even if we have some places where
there's two boxes on top of each that's
like that's two total boxes everything
else should still be able to be
separated that way I guess since we
probably want this to be like a equal to
in this case though here's one thing I
would say so like
like we don't actually need this to be a
less than right we'll consider that to
be not necessary to test I would think
right I mean it's possible that would
lead to cracks in the lighting so it's a
little bit hard to say like maybe that's
not what we want maybe we want like one
side the min side or something to be a
less than and the box
max side to be less than or equal to I
don't really know so I guess what I want
to do now is look at that routine and
just see what the heck it's doing not
that
so what do we normally see like when we
go through here the first time like what
sir what's our min count like what's our
count eh what's our can't be and what's
the source
so that just looks this looks totally
fictitious I mean I guess this is
actually Jim index which is zero how is
it possible that you're telling me that
the maximum for the x value of these
boxes is greater than or equal to a
value and the minimum is also less than
that value for basically every box in
the system like what
how are you arriving at that answer that
seems totally nuts I mean that's that's
not possible what am I missing here so
we're like totally off in la-la land are
these box refs wrong like are the box
wrecks refs at this point garbage don't
I mean they look like they should be
correct because here they are so
something is like really broken badly
and it's frustrating me that I can't
tell what it is
[Music]
so I'm just gonna actually step through
those comparisons I'm like it should be
that I would immediately see that error
but I am like obviously so out to lunch
today it's a bad programming day
apparently we've learned you know Anna
sometimes says she has a bad drawing day
and like nothing looks right well it's a
bad programming day because I don't see
like this is obviously just totally
wrong and I'd not actually sure I know
why so here's the the actual
discriminator that we're looking at for
these so let's just put them up here so
here's our values here's our KD index
and here's our total ban center so we're
discriminate this thing for negative
like all right so even even just that is
ridiculous like what the heck box is 35
units long in our system what box is
that is this because we change the
storage format and totally screwed it up
somehow like what are you talking about
and if so why didn't the other one fail
so this is the place where we actually
do this work right we loop through the
boxes and we update the way that they're
actually being recorded so
[Music]
oops right now that's okay that's that
sowhat's yeah I don't know that just
doesn't seem right I'm gonna keep
running and just see how is that how big
most of these things are what the heck
how are the max values of all these
boxes the same what is going on so that
that's like it didn't do this transform
right like this transform is supposed to
be the thing that changes it from the
old position to the radius value why
isn't that looks like it's not doing
that here's what that looks like is the
box count not set yet no it is
I'm gonna step through this part I guess
you see why I'm freaking out here right
yeah I mean we were getting those those
old values is what we were getting right
that's what we want to see so why aren't
we seeing that because we do this update
right
so that's going to run over all 14 48
boxes so how are we getting those values
how come they're wrong
oops so I'm gonna take a look here and
see what these now are set to yeah so
these are all set correctly well I
shouldn't say all because I didn't
actually get chance to step through them
I tried to but hit the wrong button
so these are all set correctly so what
the heck like what am I seeing in there
why was I seeing such weird values and
what is this so what what the heck like
what's box wrap box riff is zero I
didn't think we were supposed to have a
box zero but I guess we do all right so
if it is box zero then what does that
box look like
all right so why were we seeing that
weird Cady index value because it's not
it's not what it said
you
hmm so is this maybe this is just a
remedy bug is that possible yes maybe
let's see yes okay okay cool all right
so it's just a remedy bug actually
there's a bug in remedy with how to
access off of the e-value there because
if you actually put something in here
that's oh no it's not already bug it's
my bug yay so remedy help me find my bug
because that's a three that should not
be a three Thank You remedy remedy
basically had the same bug or I put code
into a asked remedy to evaluate the
thing that I did wrong and it was like
hey I also did it wrong and I'm like yes
awesome
so remedy was a debugger in a different
way just then it it evaluated my bogus
expression to the wrong thing which is
what you would get and off we go
so that's good all I needed to do was
say this is dim index not KD index here
and and off we go
that was a cut-and-paste bug I don't
know if this will help us here hopefully
it will to a certain extent because now
we've got rid of that obvious bug let's
take a look at what it says yeah so
[Music]
I don't think this is probably gonna get
us out of the woods because that was
just one of probably many bugs that we
have here um so a couple things like I
assume we're running in the nerfed mode
now and that's why this is so fast but
at least it is fast now which is what it
should have been and the leaf count is
like now down in a more reasonable range
and so on all right so we're getting
there I'm gonna stop debugging for today
and we'll start debugging later tomorrow
so if I just put this back in I'll leave
it this way and then we can start
debugging it next weekend so here's what
it would actually cost which is
expensive so it's it still sucks but at
least now it sucks in a slightly
different way so at least now we can
[Music]
start to look at like the building of
the tree and whether it makes sense and
then look at our actual runtime code and
see if it's doing what we expect to do
and then next weekend we can hopefully
get through all that and make a judgment
call on whether this is an improvement
or not right because we don't really
know but you can see how much worse it
is here so it's it's still running very
poorly it's just not as bad as it was
previously and I'm gonna let this go so
I could see what the TPL values are
[Music]
right so we can kind of see what that
break