hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream this is our first time
back actually programming on handmade
hero we did some test streams this is
our first time back program at handmade
hero since we fixed the streaming
machine and the whole reason we fix the
streaming machine was because we were
trying to program a shader and our AMD
card was like card crashing the driver I
I don't even really know if we had a bug
in the shader I mean we certainly hadn't
even gotten close to finishing the
shader because we were just in the
middle of working on it so it's not like
it's done or anything so it certainly
has bugs in the sense that there are
whole parts of it they're not even
implemented but I don't know if there's
actually anything in it that was crashy
but we certainly had something in that
that was crashy for the old AMD card so
we decided it was time to finally take
take the step of upgrading to a two
machine setup which we did it took a lot
longer than I was expecting to build
because we had a bad CPU in the mix
turns out the streaming setup is too
core i7s one in each machine and one of
them was bad which took forever to try
and debug so that wasn't great but that
you know finally got resolved and now
we've done some test streams and it
seems like everything is recording and
streaming properly aid we haven't had
anything weird happen like a machine
crash in the middle of the stream or
anything so hopefully we can now do some
programming on GPU stuff and if we do
crash it's okay right it should not
cause any kind of problems also we got
some fringe benefits the fact that now
we're streaming using an HDMI capture on
a secondary machine also means that we
no longer have to worry about weird
stuff like when we're trying to profile
our game or get the streaming of the
game working we no longer have to do
special things to try and work around
the fact that like OBS is running in the
background or that the whole window
capture is running in an interrupted
compositor and all sorts of other things
like this so it does give us a much more
true setup to
it would be like if you were game
developing on you know just a machine
your own machine because normally when
you're developing you don't have these
constraints like you're not trying to
stream the running of the game and
you're not trying to do any sort of
weird like you know coding in with OBS
running the background and all those
sorts of stuff so this is more like what
a typical dev machine would be if you
were using it so that's also kind of a
nice fringe benefit and obviously we can
also if we do crash the driver it's no
big deal we can just reboot the Machine
and the stream and the recording don't
stop so again just it just it's a nice
way to bring us closer to how it will
actually feel if you're doing this on
your machine is you know at home or
working at a company on developing stuff
you don't normally have to worry about
those things you know and now we don't
have to worry about them either so
that's pretty nice ok so I will go ahead
and sort of open up the code base here
now it's been a long time so I fully
expect everyone to have forgotten what
we're doing so we'll take it pretty slow
today don't ask me why I remember what
we're doing I probably should have
forgotten as well but I didn't so I
guess that's good but I'm gonna go ahead
and open up for coder here and just get
the game running and do the various sort
of basic startup stuff so here's our
handmade project I'm gonna go ahead and
build it and make sure we're still
building and running that again we kind
of did test this on the test stream we
didn't do any code changes though but
we've got the kind of weird visual
studio you know when I reinstalled video
studio it's it's visual studio whatever
the latest one is i20 visual studio 20
49 starring Harrison Ford and Ryan
Gosling so anyway if we if we load up
the project I don't know what all this
garbage is I could probably figure out a
way to stop but if we look in the
settings but if we load up the game it's
still running correctly and I believe
this is actually also correct because we
left off when we're doing lighting
and we hadn't optimized the lighting at
all so if I remember correctly what we
had done is we put the lighting on a
switch and so we would it won't actually
do any calculations till we like hit
whatever the hotkey is and then it would
sort of try to run the shader to show it
as well and so that is where we're at
and that's where we're going to go back
to here now also note that we have like
kind of we haven't really done any of
the work in the renderer to really fully
support what we were trying to do so
there's also some weird artifacts here
like for example this since this text
actually goes through the same shader we
didn't like have anything in the render
that switches the text to a separate
shader all of the lighting code is
actually running on the text as well so
the text is like when all of the world
is black because there are no lights
then you also will get the text
appearing black as well so that's where
we're at now if you bring up the code
here if you take a look at the rendering
code that we have so you can see here at
the bottom we've got sort of how the
where where we left off in terms of how
we were doing the debugging here you can
actually see what we were sort of trying
to do so the way this was working just
to refresh everyone's memory is we put
in a little I don't know like a shunt
here basically that instead of trying to
do lighting on the GPU at first we were
actually just computing lighting on the
CPU so we had this little piece of code
here that would take all of the
quadrilaterals that we'd sent down right
so normally when the game's rendering
all of the sprites and all of the cubes
that make up the sort of floating
landmass all of those are going down as
a set of quadrilaterals that can
optionally have textures on them but
they can also if you want them to be as
they like
landmasses are at the moment just be
solid color and the way solid color is
implemented is with just it's you always
do select a texture on every quad but
you can select just a pure white texture
so instead of it being something like
grassy or whatever that it would
normally be it can also just be you know
whatever the color of the quad is and
not have any actual texture on it so
that's the way we were implementing that
and you can see here in the extract
reflectors from quads function
essentially what we were doing is going
through all of those and making little
dummy reflector objects which are sort
of these things that we compute the
lighting on and they're just sort of
like we haven't really decided how
exactly that's going to work so we were
just playing around with it and
basically what does it just puts a bunch
of like little elements in the scene
that we're gonna transfer the light
around on right it's just a very
approximate thing yep
I think we're using the verts one now
but I'm not sure I'll go check
extract reflectors from virtues the same
thing but instead of using this like the
quadrilaterals themselves is where to
put it this one put it at the vertices
right or near the vertices so I think
what it does didn't like that in the
corner or something like that right we
then have the lighting test function
which would essentially do sort of you
know a crappy lighting simulation and
the way that this worked was it would go
over all of the reflectors and it would
do a lighting computation on them now we
had two things we were doing one of them
there was this approximation of how much
each of these reflectors was occluding
sorted like sort of an ambient occlusion
thing and I don't really think we're
using that anymore
could be wrong about that but I'm not
yeah I think we sort of decided that was
maybe not the most interesting thing to
do and so what I did instead was I ended
up putting in shadow casting in here so
effectively what happens is in the
compute lighting when we would actually
look at the transfer of light between
each of the elements we actually do hit
testing on the lighting elements as well
so that's how that was working and what
that would do is for every one of these
lighting elements that we generated it
would sort of store what it thought the
end lighting was and we hadn't done
anything fancy here
it was really basic but it was sort of
working right it could sort of it sort
of had shadows and it sort of had
lighting transfer that made some sense
so it's not completely out to lunch but
it's also not like good or anything yet
we then had output lighting quads and
what output lighting quads does is well
there's sort of two verse of what we do
when we out because we I need to get me
compute this lighting on these like
intermediate elements we then need some
way of having that actually you know go
feedback in to the rendering so you can
actually see it and you can kind of see
here that we have a number of different
ways that that happens right so output
letting quads is one that just instead
of rendering the scene it actually just
hijacks the scene essentially and over
writes the scene with the just like a
basically a debug view by taking each of
the lighting elements and replacing the
quad that it came from with itself you
know with with the the lighting element
so that you get to see what we computed
for lighting elements we then add an
output lighting verts one and this was
kind of shame because this actually was
kind of cool-looking right it started to
look reasonable if not particularly good
and what that did was it went through
and it took the lighting elements and it
put the lighting element information
back into each quadrilateral but each of
the vertices of the quadrilateral have
the lighting information separate so
that you could get a color wash across
things because because you know it was
for when we did extract lighting for
vertex lighting elements we would be
computing the lighting lighting near
each of the vertices and so we ended up
having sort of a better you know a
pretty nice letting thing there but
still not nearly good enough to use it
was just like okay that's much better
it was rain all right so now we get down
to some of the other stuff here it's
what we were trying to work on when we
ended up crashing the AMD card so output
texture debug what this does is this is
something that takes sort of a more
voxel approach we were starting to work
on and what this was was a way of saying
okay what we want to be able to do is
maybe do per-pixel lighting on the GPU
where every time we're filling any pixel
at all we want to be able to look up
into a lighting table that tells us what
the lighting should be around this area
right so what this does right here
output texture debug is this is
something that just puts that
information into the into the renderer
in a way we can see so it just goes
through each of the you know in we
haven't gone over like what we're
actually talking about here in terms of
what's in the voxel grid but assuming
that you have a voxel grid of these
dimensions it goes through each cell in
the voxel grid takes whatever the like
lighting value was there and creates a
cube in that in that grid of the vaak
like in the render stream it creates an
actual cube that will be drawn and puts
it there with the lighting color that it
should have and that was basically just
so we could see that there was a grid
and that values were getting filled in
in the grid right but that doesn't have
anything to do with actually using that
lighting for per pixel computations it's
just there to create a render stream
that we can view if we want to see
whether the voxel has valid data in it
that's all it is
all right so then we've got output
loading textures output lighting
textures is the actual code that's
closer to what we would be doing if we
were doing this for real and again we
probably I don't know that we will do
this on the CPU either way
we may do all of the lighting on the GPU
it's hard to say so doing it for real
just means doing the correct set of
steps I don't necessarily mean the way
we would necessarily ship it but point
being what we do for output loading
textures here is we go through and we
see for all of our lighting elements
that we've got we go through all of
those lighting elements and we figure
out what the bounding area is of those
lighting elements because that is the
total amount of space that we will have
to have covered by our voxel right we
then go through and figure out how big
the voxel has to be right so how big
each voxel cell has to be to cover that
area because we don't ever change the
dimensions the cell counts right there's
always the same number of cells in the
voxel along X or Y and on Z all we do is
stretch how big those cells are so that
they properly fit into the so that it
properly covers the entirety of the
lighting elements that are involved we
then go through each of the elements
themselves we look to see where we would
have to place those elements in the
voxel and we place them into the voxel
you can see here we sort of grabbed out
whatever the the emission value was of
that lighting element and we looks like
what we're doing curious saying I'm not
not really sure what this is meant to be
doing here but it looks like we're
looking for a bright emitter just to
find one bright emitter right like debug
X debug why here so I'm not sure what I
don't quite remember what we were doing
with our debug X debug wide debug Z and
we were just wanted to see some emitter
that had a is not really brightness it's
it's the radius so it's we were looking
for a large emitter I'm not sure why we
were bothering with this but that's one
of those things we can look back at the
Mt
Gide if we need to know I suppose but
anyway as we go through these what we
were doing is we're saying for each of
the elements we daisy-chained them
effectively into their location in the
grid right so we take a look at each
element in series and we put them into
the lighting at their correct voxel grid
by creating a linked list at each voxel
location right and that was
substantively what we were doing now I
don't know where our actual hmm the only
thing that's a little bit weird there is
I'm not sure okay so we were so in line
I was like I'm not sure where we're
doing the thing that actually packs it
into a texture but I do now no it was
just it's just right done right there so
in addition to that we also sort of had
a format for this texture right and you
can see that happening here sort of
we're actually packing these down to
16-bit values here so if we take a look
I assume that is in our render structure
here let's go ahead and take a look
respect out somewhere I feel like we
should this part I don't remember yeah I
don't see where we actually if if yes I
should say we actually defined it
anywhere what we were doing with that
but so you can kind of see how we were
doing this right well there it is so
let's see it's we know that that's a
desk
we know that the desk texture is it's
lighting textures right dest and you can
see it looking at the P next texture so
that should be in here right
planning textures so it is here it's in
handmade platform though right because
it has to be accessed by the OpenGL code
so yeah that makes sense
all right so anyway this was the actual
thing we were building right and this is
you know in a kind of a wonky format
because it's designed to be read by the
card and so the idea here is that here
is the voxel and here is a index right
like so this is basically a texture a
three-dimensional texture of 16-bit
values each 16-bit value is just a look
up into this other you know sort of a.m.
it's it's sort of a voxel look up into
just a big linear list of of information
right so if we go to this this lighting
Texel here called p next what that is is
it's a thing that says what the position
is and what the next value was right and
similarly I believe that this is a
parallel texture here right so we
basically have two textures two 32-bit
textures one that I'm not 32-bit search
for sorry we have one
texture that is for 32-bit values right
XY and Z of the position of the light
letting element and a next value which
is just an actual index into the P next
array right this could actually be you
16 but we don't have any reason for it
to be at the moment because we can't use
the 16 for anything else and then we've
got another parallel array here that is
a color for each of these right so by
looking up into P next and see you can
find out both what the position of the
light is the color of the light is and
whatever the next light element would be
in this voxel right so the idea here is
that anybody who's trying to render a
pixel can do a lookup value the lookup
value is going to tell them what the
color is of the light they're what the
position of the light is and then where
to look for the next light like and they
could just keep going until that value
is zero and know that they've processed
all of the lights in that voxel cell so
in theory what we should be able to do
at that point is make it so that when we
move a point around in space it can look
up in its location it can look up the
eight voxels that are around where it is
as a sort of bilinear blend and take all
into account all of the the lighting
elements that are in that area and that
can be the lighting value for the pixel
right that's the entirety of the scheme
it's not particularly exciting so you
know that's and we've got a hard bound
here on 4096 elements because that's how
big the texture is that's gonna store
them all so if you wanted to you have to
you would have to go in there and be a
little bit more specific about how many
they're gonna be like maybe that needs
to be a larger array like maybe that
means to be 8192 maybe you could you
know maybe these to be six five five
three six I don't know how big it needs
to actually be because right now so
we're doing the lighting on the CPU and
we don't use any sort of LOD for
lighting we're just computing it like
completely N squared
you just can't push the number very high
but when we fix those things we may want
to push the number quite a bit higher
than this and at that point we would
need to expand that texture because
it'll we would run out of room and the
texture to some sorta lighting so that's
about it
that's where we're at and like I said I
don't have anything in particular I
wanna do today we're just sort of
getting back into it so let's just go
ahead and relook up if I remember
correctly like I said the way this
worked is we had sort of a lighting
operation that we would do here and I
thought that would happen there was that
yeah you can see we have our F key input
thing here so I believe what happens is
when you push the F key we'll compute
the lighting and we'll send it down let
me just verify that that's true and then
we can go ahead and try to start start
to try and get that working again so you
can see here that we just recheck all
the F keys so f1 is the first F key and
it looks like we've got yeah two places
where that happens you can see that
letting test getting called here so in
theory if we just press f1 it will do
the lighting this is what crashed the
computer
well didn't really crash for your
Creston graphics driver I guess last
time which was enough to take down the
stream so if I push it you know we pause
and here I've done letting computation
you can see all of the voxel cubes here
that I I guess we're from when we before
the stream got crashed out I don't know
if we had like reverted it from that or
what had happened because I'm not sure
this is actually running the exact code
path that crashed the stream last time
but yeah you get the idea so we've this
is the one that
puts all the cubes and I believe all
these cubes are currently using the
shader that if they're all black like
I'm they're not showing any color
because I think all these should have
their lighting color associated with
them now I think that means that the
video card just doesn't crash on the
shader because I think it means the
shader is actually running right I think
that means that now I'll go verify that
fact but I think that means we you know
we left the code as is basically I'm not
positive about that so that may not be
true all right so let's go over to
OpenGL and see what's up with that
and we can also I think we installed
render doc on this machine and it will
work unlike before when we didn't have
any way to do graphs debugging so we'll
also be able to use a debugger around
the graphics now which is really nice
actually
so anyway so let's take a look at what's
going on here
so this I believe is yeah so this is the
main shader right this is the Z bias
program and what you can see here is it
does have the while loop for lighting
right in it right so we are actually
running this we are doing these textile
fetches we are yeah we're doing
everything exactly like what we plan to
do and what had crashed the scream I
think but don't quote me on that it may
be that this is not actually doing it
maybe that we like commented something
out that was crashing it I don't quite
exactly remember that right so it looks
like what we were doing at the end of
this is just seeing whether this loop
worked at all what's odd about this is
it looks like we're stuffing the green
value right you can see this here and so
what's odd about this loop is what it
looks likes going on here is it looks
like this lighting index is just coming
back zero right away right in other
words I'm assuming that if I went ahead
and did this okay we can see I've got a
light color here
that's being stuffed to read if I was to
get into inside this loop I would stuff
green and I'm assuming that what I do
here is always just see red right so
here's before we've computed any
lighting now I press the F key I've
computed lighting but there are no green
elements right so there's never a pixel
that thinks it ever got a lighting value
no matter what happens so yet obviously
not great we need to figure out why our
texels texture situation is not doing
anything right like why are we not
getting anything I before I dive too far
into that what I would like to do is and
I can set this back to black now that we
know that's the case what I'd like to do
is see what we have in terms of
debugging capabilities now since we have
the ability to use a graph to bugger I
think now would be a good time to show
how to use one because like I've said
many times a stream before if you do
have one you want to use it if you don't
have one you don't have one so that's
not an issue but we do have one in this
case we've got render dock and what we
can do with a tool like this again since
we did not we tried to use one on the
stream before so you remember us trying
to but we couldn't what we can do with
the cool tool like this is run it and
what these tools effectively do is they
will patch calls to the driver to
capture the state of the graphics
library and it as it runs so effectively
like you know if you think about OpenGL
right when the OpenGL driver is running
you know there's a bunch of calls to
OpenGL that would allow us to say read
back what the texture is at a particular
texture location or read back the state
of a vertex buffer call or read back
this read back that right so there's a
lot of ways we can go get information
from the graphics card also
[Music]
from external point of view if you
imagine what happens in the in the
executable in our executable we asked
the driver for all of those calls to
OpenGL right and we're calling in to the
driver with OpenGL calls asking it to do
stuff what tools like this do is they
can insert themselves in between the
driver and those calls so that they also
know they can record every call we made
and capture the information we were
pointing to from that call right so
basically what happens is these tools
are sort of recorders that just sit in
between your executable and the graphics
driver record everything you ask the
graphics driver to do and by looking at
all of those things that you ask the
driver to do it can also know what calls
to make to the driver to gab to grab out
various textures and other things that
it can then store to show you the state
of the program as it goes right more
sophisticated ones can also do stuff
like replaying the graphic stream up to
a particular point so that you can see
the state of like a specific buffer or
something at that point and all sorts of
other things like that so it's you know
like if you just understand that basic
work down then you can kind of imagine
all the things that they can do so it's
kind of nice to have something like that
around yeah and it just it just helps a
lot with crash debugging as you'll see
so I we made a profile here when we sort
of tested this out on the test stream
and basically all you have to do to run
one of these programs on your executable
is you just have to fill out some
information here just like you would in
the debug settings of like visual studio
that we did for debugging it right it
needs to know where the executable is it
needs to know what directory the
executable should start up in and it
needs to know any other information that
you would normally pass now we don't
have any command line arguments or
environment variables that are relevant
to the program so we don't have to worry
about those but if you did you know you
would put them in here so that's all we
really need to do
and then once we have that going what
these tools generally do and again if
you know there's there's more than one
of them u n site is another one that I
have used a bunch for that's for NVIDIA
cards typically we're using this one
because it's a little more like sort of
cross vendor right so if you have an AMD
card out there you should be able to use
this as well you don't have to have an
nvidia card for specifically so once you
have one of these all set up
I can't tell right now yeah as I say
that my head is hiding so I gonna have
to do this the launch and close buttons
so once we have it all set up we need to
get this launch button and what that
should do is it should run our program
right now thankfully render dock has
built into it the concept that it's not
really recording everything all the time
all it's doing is just watching right
and you can see that it's added an
overlay here and this overlay like I
said since it's hooked into our
application and intercepting our calls
to the driver what it can also do is
insert its own rendering into our
rendering right it can insert some calls
that render this overlay and so that's
exactly what it has done here right so
once we are getting a state where we
actually want to capture you can see it
says what the instructions are right
here you just print F - what'd you hit
f12 or print screen to start the capture
right and that will capture whatever
frame we were on that time who charged a
now we don't want to capture a frame yet
because we haven't sent the lighting
textures down to the card at all so we
wouldn't really do us any good to look
now because we expect those textures to
be zeroed so first what I need to do is
hit f1 so that we know that we've
actually run the lighting in theory at
least sent it down you can see that this
got a lot slower here but I think that's
probably just because we have a lot more
cues I'm not really sure why it's slower
we haven't done any work to see why it
is but you can kind of see that it's
like it's it's pretty pokey
I'm not sure why that is that might be
something to do with render doc itself
I'm not sure but anyway then I'm gonna
go ahead and hit f12 to get a capture on
that and you can see it kind of pauses
for a second capturing a frame takes a
lot more time right and the reason for
that is because again it's got to
intercept all those calls and record
data but we've done that now and so we
should be able to close the application
and you can see here it loading up what
it captured and processing it so we got
to give that a second hopefully it works
but now once you do that you can see get
a lot of really great information this
is why I say these tools are really nice
if you have one you should use it if you
know if one works on your card or your
console or whatever you're programming
on because you can kind of see that
we've got like a lot of information
already about just what's going on like
even just this is sort of a nice thing
to see because it's kind of just it's
just like stepping through your own
program in the debugger you get to see
like exactly what it does unambiguously
right you know you you always think you
know what your program does because you
wrote it but you don't always know
whether you've you're thinking about it
correctly
now unfortunately render doc seems to be
a little janky here like I can barely
even use it I think probably because
it's trying to do too much background
processing to update something I'm not
sure but it's well yeah so I don't know
maybe we will have to use insight
because this is pretty bad right like
this is not really useable here for
whatever reason like I can't really
click on anything you know I'm saying
and like I said I I think I said this on
the test stream I've never used render
doc so I'm the wrong one to say what
should happen in in in a circumstance
like this where it's not acting
particularly nicely you can see that
it's sort of just freaking out all the
time like I can't even really interact
with it hardly at all
so yeah I don't know why that is but I
guess that's a non-starter
yeah so anyway if you can get render dr.
work go for it that was that is about
the experience I normally have with
render doc which is why I tend to use
insight because insight doesn't seem to
have quite so much that kind of a
problem so that's why I've never really
gotten into render doc is because I've
I've just never really gotten it to work
so I'm gonna go ahead and put insight on
here instead that is not okay I'm gonna
click on this anyway this is not the
insight you want we do not need life in
digital brought to you by insight that
is not actually what we want we want
this one so what this does is if you
download this one here insight visual
studio edition unfortunately they don't
have a version that runs outside vigil
studio so you kind of have to use Visual
Studio with it this is really
unfortunate because you know I would
rather it just kind of be a standalone
thing but unfortunately it's not so I'm
gonna go ahead and download it here I
think that actually downloaded anything
I think all you need is this cuz I think
we already have a driver I don't know if
we do or not while this is downloading
ah all right so I guess I need to login
as a member so as far as I know this is
not hard to do I assume that this is
pretty straightforward like I did not
have to do anything special that but it
looks like I will have to actually
download it this way if you hold on one
second though I can do that pretty
easily
helpfully I already have exactly such a
developer camp now why you need to
developer account in order to download
this tool I have no idea
that's a good question if anyone from
Nvidia happens to be watching the show
and wanted to tell me what the point is
that would be great because it just
seems superfluous but if I look up my
log in here I know I've got it somewhere
there we go
so if I go ahead here
let's try to log in let's go ahead and
login as me
and unfortunately I do use gigantic
impossible passwords even for things
like this where it doesn't matter if
anyone steals your password because it's
literally a junk account that is used
only for downloading insight but oh well
hopefully I type that correctly and off
we go alright so we need to download
this here but I don't know how to do
that still because where did the
download go here we go downloads
download download there we go so now
we've got it downloaded and the only
thing that we have to verify is that we
have a driver that's late enough because
it does it did say that that was
important I'm gonna this way that was
only necessary for a loop for looking
that up there we go back there ok
so in theory now we've got insight and
we can try that one instead because like
I said I would like to have a debugger
and since render doc doesn't work I
think we might as well switch to insight
like I said even though I had like that
was not some kind of thing that NVIDIA
gave me special
that's just like anyone who goes to
their little join now thing can create
one of these accounts and use insight as
far as I know there's no like special
you don't have to be some kind of a like
provable game developer to do it as far
as I know so the only thing that I
wanted to check here was was the
requirements there they said like
something about having to have the right
version you know quite remember where we
saw that was it the page before here
let's see cuz I check the version of our
graphics driver so down here here we go
and video display driver three eight
four nine four or newer so let's just
verify that that's what we've got
so this is 380 205 which is I guess
pretty old then I mean well not that for
old I guess but definitely not the one
they recommended so let's go ahead and
update that because again this is one of
the nice benefits of having a stream
that that doesn't go down if we want to
reboot the machine so let's go ahead and
do that this is a GeForce 1080 card
there we go we don't actually need to do
this because it's all one integrated
driver but I think they just want to
collect product information I guess
alright so 388 0 is quite a bit later
than what we have
and definitely later than the one they
recommended right because they said 384
if I remember correctly these are hard
to keep straight
they said 384 9 for newer this would be
388 so off we go we will agree in
download and now in theory we should be
able to update the graphics driver
sure
waiting
well this is exciting
how big is this graphics driver four
hundred forty megabytes compressed the
graphics driver
I suppose that's probably because
there's lots of like patch stuff in
there and like here's like eight hundred
thousand games we've hand optimized in
all of the shaders that weari patch and
all that stuff so it's probably not the
graphics driver that's that sighs it's
probably like a ton of like data for
every application checking system
compatibility okay we do want a graphs
driver I don't know what that is or that
I definitely don't want a GeForce
experience or physics
that's interesting so there's a GT X
1080 Terry 1070 TI I'm not sure what
that means I don't know what the TI
means I just thought it was some like
branding thing right that's like oh it's
you know the 1080 is good but like the
1080i is like really good but I guess
now we've got a 1070 TI so then the
question is is a 1070 TI better than a
1080 I assume it's not better than a
1080 TI but I don't know if it's better
than a 1080 regular what is the T I mean
it's anyone's guess really now we're
getting some nice ads here for some
random games which is always good does
this let me pick between them so I can
be like destiny shadow war destiny
shadow of war
titanium 1070 what if I want to learn
more about this what if this what if
behind this learn more button look
there we go we got a speed boost there
that was like in Mario Kart where you
hit the little thing that like boosts
you forward okay there we go so now we
should be good to go hopefully if
Windows doesn't like
you
so that's interesting I guess we'll have
to remember that updating the graphics
driver it it will reinstall effectively
the HDMI sound output right and that's
actually a problem because what Windows
does in that situation is it will then
revert this setting which is the way
we're getting output so I always got to
make sure I check to see if I'm getting
output but luckily I did there so it
looks like it's back and hopefully it
should be fine that's fine right yeah
alright so I think we are now ok I'm
gonna go ahead and ask it to install in
site and here is a giant License
Agreement that no one could possibly
understand and I don't even know if this
is enforceable in court because how any
normal person who isn't a lawyer would
have any idea what they're agreeing to I
don't know I would really like someone
to test that in court someday but I'm
gonna go in here to customize it just
make sure that everything makes sense I
don't know what these things are we
probably don't really need this but we
might as well put it on there who knows
maybe someday we will need it
that's a friendly-looking name
so now if we're not completely wrong
about this we should be able to use the
insight utility anytime we want to to
profile stuff now we again don't really
know whether that's true or not because
we haven't tried it yet on this machine
because we were gonna try and use render
dock well fortunately no dock didn't
really work looks like I said it's kind
of par for the course render dock
unfortunately that's it's just the
experience I've always had with it and
so if I now go to visual studio and we
go to our project we should now have
additional options now that insight is
installed so you can see here insight is
got its own drop-down that's put in here
and one of the options that we have is
start graphics debugging so like
normally when we hit debug and we do
start debugging with f5 that would run
just regular but now if we want to we
can say start gravis debugging and if we
do start graphics debugging yeah you can
we don't care if it's secure if you do
start gravis debugging then in theory
what should happen is it should launch
our application with the insight HUD
enabled right and you can see that
that's actually exactly what's going on
here so you know now the application is
running it's showing us some performance
information which is nice if we're
trying to optimize the game right this
can tell us information about that and
if I run the lighting thing you can see
that we've we've go ahead and run that
now you'll notice render dock slowed to
a crawl when we were in this mode but
insights just humming along which is
kind of nice right so now if I go over
here into the if I you know alt tab back
to the real studio while the game is
still running what you'll notice is
there is a thing that says pause and
capture frame and so if I want to I can
just now do the same thing we're trying
to thread or dock get a frame of data
and take a look at it
so if I hit that it's gonna take a
little bit because it's got to actually
figure out you know like I said the same
things a render doc had to wear it's got
to go through each sort of step of the
program and grab all the information
that it needs who knows how long that
will take but hopefully it'll finish at
some point all right there we go it's
got this weird HUD thing here but I
never use this because it doesn't work
on my other actual death machine
I've never gotten it to work I think cuz
I use a multi-monitor setup and maybe it
doesn't handle a multi-monitor setup or
something but it literally doesn't work
at all so I never use that I always use
the other part of it which I don't know
how to get back to here of course on
multi Mun usually don't have to care a
little computer so I'm not sure exactly
what's going on here the HUD on this
machine works you can see here I'm
running through all of the events like
every quad that gets drawn we can look
at separately right which is pretty it's
pretty great
except I mean for the fact that you know
their only reason that's the case is
because we never did a texture atlas to
pack our textures but that's a separate
issue so the hot eyes actually working
here but unfortunately I don't actually
know how to get back to visual studio
like if I alt-tab the visual studio it
does not bring it up
is there some way I can force it to
minimize again like I said on my main
dev machine I don't have this this
problem because I have the debugger pops
up in the other monitor so I've never
tried to figure out why it wouldn't let
me view it so we kind of have opposite
problems on this machine the HUD works
but I can't get back to visual studio
which is not great there must be some
way so I guess one thing I could do
so by killing the application I am I was
that was actually able to get back here
except I didn't kill the application I
hit alt f4 the applications still here
so I guess that just killed the hood I
don't know that is very peculiar and not
at all how it works on my dev machine
but okay
I guess that's all right I'm not too
worried about it as long as we get
something working that's fine point
being when you actually can back get
back to visual studio which I guess we
can so that's good
what you can see here is it adds a bunch
more windows to your to your IDE right
and these things are basically the same
sorts of things that we had and render
doc only like unlike render doc we can
actually interact with them and so we
can actually get some information out of
them and what you can see is you get a
lot of pretty good information if you
take a look up here this thing called
the scrubber that's sort of the
equivalent of the event list thing it's
like saying here's all the things that
happened and you can kind of go between
them I don't think they update over here
maybe they do if you if you don't have
to do the Alta for to kill the app thing
but the point is you can scrub through
these things and what you can do is you
can look and see what all the
information is at the time of any
particular dispatch so for example for
this particular set of this particular
quad you can take a look at what the
vertex specifications were so you've got
all the sorts of stuff in here that we
were setting up right like here's the
vertex format here's like GL float for
elements of GL float that was for the
position X Y Z W we've got two elements
of GL float for like the textures right
we've got four elements of unsigned byte
for the color and that's recep these are
just the vertex stuff that we set up
right
and you could also see like some of the
settings we have here whether you know
array buffers are enabled or indirect
drawing primitive restart you know we're
not using these things so they're off
but it would tell you if they were on we
also have like the generic attributes
you can set with like immediate mode or
you know those sorts of things you know
everything everything you want to know
about versification will show up in this
window right the transform view if you
click on that instead this is basically
showing you all the things you can find
out about this this like dispatch right
so it's whatever it's selected here
these are the the parts of it you can
see so if you look at the transform you
can see like it says you know was death
clamping on you know what what's the
depth mode is it negative 1 to 1 or 1 0
to 1 whatever here's what the viewport
was set to right like 1920 by 1080 and 0
to 1 for the near for clip planes blah
blah blah right so again just a lot of
good information it's it's basically
really helps with debugging
when you just want to know like what's
up right here's the vertex shader so
inside the vertex shader you can see
that basically there's no captured
information that we've got here I don't
know if that's because we accidentally
stopped the running oops I didn't mean
to undock that scrubber so what I can do
is see whether if I continue running
here I get it back or if there's some
way to get it back so it looks like I
can't really get it back
we'd like to be able to get that to work
let me see again I'm gonna just try some
other things here so if I go ahead and
do insight start graphics debugging
again so now I'm gonna window this just
to see if that helps so now that this is
in a window I'm gonna go over to that
pause and capture frame option and I'm
gonna do it so now okay so basically it
looks like it was just the fact that was
fullscreen couldn't handle so this is
much better now because you can see to
here if I leave this the game if I don't
have to alt f4 the HUD version of the
game replay thing then the other nice
thing is when you scrub through you get
to see everything that's being drawn at
the time right and and I can even do
that like I can make this smaller right
and I can scrub through these and I can
write I can see actually how far I've
gone through the drawing process which
is awesome right and I guess now that
this works on the HUD to which I said my
dead machine that's not true but now
that the this works on the HUD as well
it means that you can actually scrub it
on the hood and I don't know if it's
smart enough to keep them synched it
might be I don't think it is so if I set
this one it does set this one if I set
this one no it does all right so I just
wanted to keep them synced as well so if
I come out to here right I I'm on three
eight seven seven it'll set it to three
at 7-7 here so for our purposes that
doesn't really super matter at the
moment right because we're not trying to
bug a specific part of the drawing but
you can imagine why that would be nice
if you had a specific thing that was
messed up you can imagine why
- like dial-in - just where that was so
that you know you you're not just
hunting through a giant thing of garbage
now there's other ways you can do that
you could there's things called debug
markers you can output in the OpenGL
stream specifically for purposes like
this where you have an integrated
debugger and so if we were trying to
nail something specific that was not
visual like this is good for finding
visual errors if there's a particular
draw call we want to debug or something
there's also ways you can do that we can
go in and insert a debug marker into the
debug stream and it would show up as
something we could we could jump to here
right so this right here allows us to
show some various things about what gets
set and what gets changed right but we
don't really care about that at the
moment so anyway let's take a look at
here if I can now look at the vertex
shader yeah so I can so since I didn't
have to alt f4
out of the window this is what I was
expecting to see here so you can see
that if we step to the if we messed up
if we select vertex shader we can
actually open out the source code for
the vertex shader as well and this is
just what we fed you know what we fed to
the graphics card when we sent down the
shader right and yeah we can look at
basically anything we want there these
here which are kind of the more
important part usually because we kind
of know what text we sent down these
here are the uniform values at the time
and this is really great Ruby - because
it lets me see right
what like the transform matrix was so I
can verify that we sent that down right
at a particular draw call it lets me see
like what we set for other fog values
like our you know our special values
that we set are all here and that's
really great
right it's so much more visible than we
had before for the raster ops this is
just a thing that says okay how are
things how is our triangles gonna get
filled right so you know what's the
calling state what's the line state
point state is rasterizer discard
enabled is smoothing enabled is multi
sampling on right it is in our case
everything you want to know here we've
got the fragment shader which is the
same
as we had been you know expecting it to
be right this is this is the fragment
shader we're expecting and this is the
fragment shader that has our while loop
in it right and so now the interesting
part and the thing that I actually
wanted to get to is that these pieces of
information here this is exactly what I
wanted to bugger for like first of all
we can actually see all of the
information that we set in our in our
shader like what the voxel dimensions
are and those sorts of things and it
looks like those aren't set properly
either so that that's probably a big
problem we've got to make sure those are
set but the other thing is the thing
that I really wanted to see that's you
know the kind of hard to debug normally
is I'd like to know what is contained in
our samplers right so what textures are
actually loaded and what do those
textures look like right so what we can
see here just right off the bat one of
the nice things about it is we can see
for example our depth map right or other
things like that we can look at the
various things that we've rendered which
are kind of interesting in our def peels
right and stuff like that so we can see
all of that sort of stuff in here and
that's just really informational when
we're debugging you know it really helps
figure out what's going on when we have
bugs so I really like that part of it
right so let's go ahead and actually try
a debugging step here first of all I
think I want to fix this box in seldom
box mink or anything while I'm looking
at it because that should have been set
and isn't set so you can see here this
is the attempt to set it Foxman corner
and Vox in seldom are being set to these
open gel constant values here I don't
know maybe those never got set or
something we'll have to see what what
the deal is
here's where they should have been
getting set it looks like
[Music]
when we get the lighting entry transfer
we're pulling it out there and so in
theory right when we call this push
lighting that information should have
been set right here now why it wasn't
set I'm not sure but that's what we're
gonna have to find out now what may have
happened there and let's just verify it
is I may not have run the lighting
because this was just my test to see if
I could get it working in windowed mode
there so let's go to windowed mode again
let's run the lighting and maybe now
when I pause and capture frame we may
find that those are set properly because
it maybe I just I don't think I did ooh
what happened here
it looks like it can't write to the end
of the peak message block why would that
be the case
okay what is going on here how come I
can't view the disassembly of our code
is this some kind of Visual Studio 2017
nonsense or is that just because I can't
debug something that has insight running
in it maybe let's hope that's the case
because if I lost the ability to view
debug mode I don't even know what to say
about that this is looking sketchy this
is looking sketchy
let me reboot this one thing I will say
it's insight does crash on me fairly
frequently on my dead machine so that's
not surprising that's just something I
live with I'm not sure why it crashes so
frequently or like what you know what is
the cause of those crashes but it
definitely crashes so you will have to
sort of expect that it was not as bad as
render doc in terms of like like the
whole like not being able to use it
thing but definitely had issues alright
so it looks like I can't alt tab between
it for some reason one thing I do wonder
- I'm interested to know so in and build
up at we've got this handmade streaming
thing and if I remember correctly that
was like a workaround for the fact that
we had like we had to sort of change the
double buffering modes and stuff like
this so I'm wondering if maybe also if
we got rid of that it might help because
the normal way to run it is not with
double buffering off so we can get rid
of that now because we don't have to
worry about that workaround for
streaming so we can basically get rid of
references to handmade streaming in the
codebase entirely we can always use
double buffer in our pixel format
and we can get rid of the sort of go to
no streaming second power Flags nonsense
so this stuff can get get out of there
right however I don't know that we ever
actually set handmade streaming to one
because we never would have set that
well actually maybe we did in the show
let's find out
so we never set that in the show anyway
so double buffering would have been
running already I guess uh and I don't
know about this to do here can we just
build both with one eggsy I'm not sure
what that was referring to anyway so I'm
gonna get rid of that as well yes so so
yeah I don't know it just looks like we
can't alt tab between them but I'm not
sure why it looks like n site brick
breaks that
so I guess I just won't do that just
have to remember not to
I sent a report all right so let's see
here if if I only alt-tab a once though
it seemed like it worked I don't know
maybe that's wishful thinking but so if
I run the lighting and then I go here
and hit pause and capture frame oops
that's wrong first I got a start
graphics debugging so if I go ahead and
do a pause and capture frame without alt
tabbing back it does not crash and once
I've done that it looks like I'm fine so
it's just don't do it before you hit
pause to capture frame I guess so yeah I
don't know hopefully that's reliable I
don't know if it will be but let's just
hope that it is and go from there so
there's the lighting and I'll tap back
pause and capture frame so it looks like
maybe I can't do it
if I have run the lighting capture why
would it need to launch this what is it
doing I feel like it's launching a
second copy of the executable or
something would everyone agree with that
it looks like it's launching a second
copy of the executable I'm going to take
a look on here and see what's up
so here's the section that we would pop
up in so let me go ahead and pin this so
if I go ahead and run here we go so
there's our win32 your handmade right
there
I run the lighting alt-tab I hit pause
and capture frame so it looks like I
didn't I did not even actually have to
to look I don't think I ever actually
clicked pause and capture frame so maybe
it didn't I don't know that's pretty
bizarre so I'm gonna hit debug sure
launch another copy if you want to where
we crash it
I don't even want to know
so here's the Nvidia graphics stack
where are the threads this is what
crashed this is the only thread we get
yeah well this does create a bit of a
problem if we can't ever actually get it
to stable II be able to not crash I mean
hopefully this is just whatever we're
specifying erroneously that is the
reason why we crashed the AMD driver
maybe this is also what crashes this
driver look maybe when we're specifying
those textures we're specifying them
incorrectly or something like this I
don't know but I'm not sure how we can
debug this much further
so the first thing I'm going to do here
because I don't have any other ideas is
I'm going to take a look to see if
there's something I can do to maybe make
things more stable so when we send down
the lighting
whoa very tired let me sit down the
lighting it's right here
and what you can see is we you know
specify these textures here I'm trying
to figure out is there something that
we're doing in here that's causing the
problem so for example let's suppose we
just didn't send those down I'm just
trying to guess what we might be doing
that could cause the the faulting right
so let's suppose I did that so I've
rebuilt now where I've got a version
that doesn't that doesn't even send down
any textures at all I and now I'm gonna
start debugging again run the lighting
everything appears temporarily normal
come back here
it's see what's really about that is I
don't even ever have to click on that it
looks like right
it looks like it's before I even click
on it all I have to do is just go to the
menus I know that sounds weird but it
really felt like that so like if I come
back here for example see that all I had
to do is click on the insight menu and
it crashed like all I had to do was that
why that is I have no idea I wonder if
there's anything on here that I can do
that would cause it to not do that
so I don't see anything particularly
useful in here
hmm
so I guess this has been a complete bust
we could not really get rendered luck to
work we cannot really get insight to
work and that's unfortunate because you
know that sort of means that in order to
in order to use the graphics debugger
you have to already have debug your
graphics assuming that it's something
that we're doing I don't actually know
that it could be that it's not it could
be this has nothing to do with us and
these would just crash anyway but
assuming that there's something we're
doing buggy and that is the reason why
we are crashing then it's like a
catch-22 it's like hey I'd like to use a
grafter burger to help debug my program
I was like oh sorry you have to already
have debugged your graphics in order to
use the graphs to work very well that's
so I'm just gonna poke at this a little
bit longer just to see what we can learn
about it if I go ahead and run my
program I'm assuming that that doesn't
happen normally no it does so basically
something about the instrumentation and
we're getting it we're getting it really
weird we're getting a really weird crash
in there that I don't super understand
and the fact that I can't ever get any
disassembly on my application is
freaking me out too like you know I
should be able to go to a disassembly of
this and okay so okay so in the I am
able to get the disassembly I am able to
get the disassembly
if I just don't have insight running
that's less less of a problem so let's
let's figure out what's going on here
I'm trying to I'm trying to get a handle
on what what's happening here so if we
take a look at this code here at this
time to block peek message bit what I'm
assuming is I'm assuming that this bit
here is you know is the part that has to
do with with finishing this time block
the reason that I think that just for
folks who aren't assembly language
reading sorts of people because I'm
taking a look here and you see this
locked ad right
the lock prefix instruction is the thing
that lets us know that we're doing a
multi-threaded operation here which you
know the call to peek message occurring
right here we know that that has none no
such things right that's going to call
into Windows if they had any
synchronization to be behind that call
and then we're picking up the value from
it but then we go right into this lock
tab and so if we take a look at what
happens in the debug code the timed
block function it creates one of these
little automatic things that like
creates and destroys itself you can see
it does a begin block and then an end
block right and so we don't want to do
is look at the end block call for
wherever that is right here and that
records a debug event and record debug
event is this code right here so this
our DTSC that you see there that reads
the clock value that's right here and no
one else is going to be doing an RDP SC
right so this is the reading of the
clock value right here
you can see there's an I'm all that I'm
all is gonna be probably for this
referencing off the array here right and
you can see the locked add the locked
add is
atomic add you 64 right so this all fits
the profile exactly of what I would have
expected the ending of time block to be
and so that's what I think I'm looking
at even though the source code Visual
Studio did a very poor job of telling me
that this was the destructor it should
have said right this time to block part
should have been like right there
because that's what this code came from
but it you know it's too dumb to do that
so anyway what I'm seeing here is that
you know after this after this compare
and jump here it's this assertion is
what's happening so essentially what's
crashing the application isn't that
really a crash it's an assertion that we
don't run out of space for our debug
event table like that's what actually
happened so I guess what's happening is
something about the way we're running it
right now is causing our debug events to
pile up and overflow I so they're just
we are adding debug events adding debug
events and we're never like clearing out
the debug events that's that's what's
basically happening why that's happening
we don't know but it is happening so we
got two options the first thing we can
do is probably the easiest just to fix
things now but then we're gonna have to
fix figure out what to do about it later
so what we want to do here just say oh
okay well you know let's just just turn
off hamate eternal right at that point
we won't have any debug events in the
first place so then we shouldn't have
any problem so here's the graphs
debugging running I launch the lighting
done and then I click back here
and it's all good so it looks like if we
all tab away we stop getting those debug
events cleared I don't know exactly why
that would be but it must have something
to do with the fact that we're no longer
getting a swap message but we are on
some other threads or something doing
work that creates debug messages I
really don't know but point being at
least we did figure out how to get it to
work right so that means we can it pause
and capture frame now and in theory that
should allow us to inspect the lighting
information maybe after all that work
there we go yeah maybe
there we go so at that point we are
functional right and we can look at me
can see the textures are so in theory
that would allow us to do the debug
stuff I wanted to do but man that was a
lot of work so at that point however it
I'm not sure what I want to do now I'm
not sure if I want to actually do the
the debug if I want to actually look and
see what the debug looks like on the
lighting or if I'd rather go and fix the
whatever the overflow path is on the
debug events I suppose the more sensible
thing is to fix the overflow path than
the debug events because presumably if
we took a look at the lighting we
wouldn't have time to fix it to anyway
does that depend so let's let's just see
what's going on here so we know that the
way that these things are cleared right
is at the end of our win32 loop we every
time you know we come through the win32
loop we do a sort of a mutex thing here
where we swap the debug arrays where is
that this is for textures
[Music]
so it's right here that's that's debug
frame end so debug frame end is you know
called you know substantively every time
through the loop and I don't really know
any way that it can avoid being called I
mean as far as I know it's gonna be
called every time unless well is it
inside global pause no
so basically there's really no way
around it so how we are still producing
debug events without calling through
this I'm not sure I guess what maybe
could happen is if our windows let's say
windows is sending us a bunch of
messages that we would generate debug
information for somehow like in here I
don't know that there's any look I don't
know that there's any way in here that
that would happen
so what we do know is this is the place
where it's happening right so one thing
might be if we ended up in here right
let's let's do this so just so we can
debug it maybe a little bit better if we
were to go ahead and make a counter here
that we check so that we could just see
how many times through we've gone so
let's say we set like a global here and
we just made a global variable called
you know I guess I don't want to set
that there so if I just counted how many
times I've gone through this loop then I
wonder if I can just see really easily
how many times you know when we get that
fault did we get like caught up in this
loop somehow where we're peak our peak
message is getting like somehow like an
infinitely long thing I'm not sure but
let's just find out if that's the case
all right so we're launching into the
debugger for no apparent reason you know
I don't care about your browse info just
do whatever you want
so actually that's not where I wanted to
break I don't actually want to open up
that debugger like so what I want to do
actually here is slightly different what
I want to do is I want to do the version
that actually broke inside here
sorry Nvidia for all of these does this
one work there it goes
so I don't actually need insight to be
running it looks like and that's great
because that way we can take that out of
the equation so let's take a look at
what for counter looks like so that's
massive so somehow we're getting stuck
in this for loop where we you know we
come through here we get an actual
message we process the message whatever
it is right and then we are kind of just
infinitely we're just going forever and
so we're generating a debug message
every time and somehow we got five
hundred twenty four thousand Windows
messages right what I would like to know
is what are these messages like what can
I inspect what messages we're getting
that's causing this kind of absurd
overflow so message 18:48
let's take a look at that in hex so o X
738 so what message is that exactly
would be my first question and in order
to answer that question what I'm gonna
do here is say let's copy that in
like why are we getting that message
just spammed at us and maybe it's not
always that message I mean we don't know
it could be that every time through
we're getting a different message to
what I really probably want to do is log
these messages and and you know what
let's just do that because it won't take
very long
so what I'm going to do here is I'm just
creating a global variable again just
for debug purposes we'll delete these in
a moment called message buff and what
I'm going to do is I'm going to take the
four counter so every time through this
four loop right right after we get the
message I'm gonna stuff the message into
this message buffer so whatever the
message is that we got I'm gonna stuff
it into this buffer and I'm gonna use it
like it just a rolling like a ring
buffer I'm gonna write all the way
through it and when I get to the end I'm
just gonna loop right back to beginning
so that's what this mod does here right
I'm gonna take however many there are
and it's gonna mod by that so I'm just
kind of rolling in a ring around it
right so this way I can see you know are
we just getting spammed with this
message ad infinitum or is something
else going on I don't know but I do know
that when I come in here right yeah we
get your throw that exception and so now
if I pop back out I can see you know
what message buff looks like and it
seems pretty clear I mean that pretty
much says it all right we're just
getting spammed with that message
whatever that message is so the next
step is to find out what that message is
right and I don't know if there's a
window message look up there's an error
look up
right that's kind of handy so if you
have a Windows error you can go in here
and you can look it up but knowing what
that message is that's a little bit
harder however what we should be able to
do I think is we should be able to go in
and let's take a look here here we go we
should be able to use our search project
like we do oftentimes a hand-made hero
we should be able to say like okay well
let's just look up where WM mousemove is
right so here's like you know the wind
user H which has just like all these
messages in it right so maybe if we're
lucky we can just sort of blindly find
that Windows message you can see they're
listed in hex here so we know the one
that we're looking for in hacks is hex
seven three eight oops
and so the first thing you can do is
just see whether I find it in wind user
but sadly I didn't right so the next
question is well okay whatever seven
three eight is you know I know where the
windows directory is it's wherever I am
right now right Here I am it's this
absolutely freaking absurd nonsense that
like Windows does now when they install
things right a completely ridiculous
title but here's like where all the
stuff is I guess there's like when may
just make sure I can find wind user in
here so I'm not crazy there's one user
so if I take this directory and then I
go to find in files wherever that ended
up there it is
oh boy I can't even paste can i you've
got alright I guess I get to find that
entire name
so it's Program Files x86 Windows kits
10 include um
so what I'm going to do here is search
to see if I can find that Windows
message anywhere just by chance right
this is not a scientific process I wish
it was but I'm just gonna see if I can
find it so here's our find results and
you can see there's a ton of like grids
and crap and stuff like this what I'm
gonna do is search in here to see if I
can find any WMS can't so it's not
looking good for us right my next
thought is what's WM user set to these
days
so actually oh okay Wow
so WM user set to hex Oh 400 so actually
that that that I don't know if we've
gone over this on handmade here before
us let us mention him so one of the
things they did when they originally
designed Windows was they have these
windows messages that get passed around
right like we get some like WM
underscore this time you know screw into
that and they're just a ways of the
operating systems calling your you know
one callback function and giving it lots
of different things that happened like
event types right but one things they
did is they said well you know what
we're only gonna use a certain segment
of those and we're gonna define WM user
to be a certain number that above that
number you can make your own messages
right so WM user I thought different
user was a lot higher than that but it's
not so what that means is WM user that
738 is actually something getting sent
by some other app in the system right
that's not a Windows message it's some
kind of special message registered by
somebody sent to us I guess I don't know
how to back figure out who sent a
message I don't know that spy can give
us that information but I'm gonna try so
I'm gonna fire up spy plus plus here
which we've used before in Hana me here
it's just a way of watching the Windows
messages come in so what I'm going to do
is I'm gonna switch back to handmade
hero and I'm going to go ahead and run
the application here so I'm running
and I'm gonna go through here and say
alright where if I can even get it to go
that long
so it looks like we also it looks like
we have some kind of a weird lock up
when we alt-tab away we stopped running
for some reason but why
like like why would did you see that why
is that happening
so something's wrong but I just don't
know what and so we have to figure out a
way to track this down cuz yeah this is
this is weird right
not sure why we don't get a sizing bar
on this thing
anyway so now in spy plus plus though we
you know here's the app running we
should be able to go ahead and just grab
the handmade hero window in fact I could
probably even do it this way and I'm
just going to look at the messages
well I thought I was going to but I
guess I'm not
so why are we not seeing any messages if
I picked a different one would I see
messages is this not spy 64 oh well
there you go
for some reason even though I guess
maybe it thought I don't know why it
thought we would want to launch the
32-bit version assuming that x86 like I
want spy 64 people
I feel like we went through this already
on the old machine but I guess we
unfortunately we unfortunately will have
to do this work again to figure out how
to get Spy 64 the 64-bit version of spy
because the 32-bit version of spy can't
look at the messages of a 64-bit
application so it's not gonna do us any
good so we need the 64-bit edition of
spy which I thought visual studio would
have launched but the fact that says x86
on it suggests to me that it isn't
launching it and that it's actually
launching the 32-bit version because I
think it would say x64 version if it was
I don't know that that's necessarily
true
but here's the one I actually wanted and
I'm gonna try to pin that out as well
ya see x64 edition so that's the one we
actually wanted I'm gonna see if I can
pin this so that we can run in any time
we want so we don't to go through that
again
alright so now assuming that that was
the problem I should be able to get the
messages for this window which is what I
wanted to see in the first place and
yeah there we go so there's all our
messages everything seems to be
operating fine right now so let's take a
look at what happens when I go over here
and do whatever the bad thing is that
didn't like doesn't look like I'm
crashing now
of course I could also be the case that
just the fact that wind spy is looking
at it you know means it's fine because
it's doing something that you know makes
that not happen but you can see that
we're mostly getting eighty fours these
are all eighty four is definitely not
seven three eighths or whatever so
that's not really helping all right so
here if we run this let's launch the
lighting
see if I get scratch again
oh you know what I also forgot our
cietrade ID that doesn't restore it on
startup does it so we have come to the
end poor see Trey
see Trey doesn't last three reboots I
should probably do something about that
huh haha sorry see Trey we have come to
the end but let me just finish what I
was doing here because I'm interested to
know so I don't actually want a message
search I would actually want is Windows
and I want to look at this window can I
do that
probably not
anyway I just want this to be able to
crash on us but I can't seem to do it
while spy is watching right
unfortunately so yeah if I run light
switch and it does not seem to crash now
either right let me see what happens if
I close by run
I don't know what happened here so I run
light switch yeah we magically like
fixed the problem somewhere like
whatever the application was that was
sending those seven to eight has stopped
sending them which is bad because now we
can't figure out who it was curiouser
and curiouser so let's try running the
full graphics debug one like so
so that still crashes it so well you
know as long as I've got a way to crash
it I think we're good right as long as
I've got a way to force that situation I
can hopefully find the answer right so
let me go ahead and run spy again maybe
if I'm lucky if I set up spy right now
like so
can it okay cannot fine really
Oh probably cos got to refresh it go
ahead and hit messages getting all the
messages here right oh wait I forgot to
run it under the thing that more time
insight start graphics debugging all
right so now we're under the graphics
debugger refresh the windows
now we're watching the messages in here
I'm gonna switch back to insight can't
click provoke it
alright lighting
No
the screen
well so what we know is that we're
getting that crazy message and we're
getting flooded we can prevent that
pretty easily so I can fix this
particular bug but I would like to know
who is sending it and why I am
interested to know if maybe there's
something I could just track myself that
would find out what that is
so what I'm going to do here is I'm just
gonna take a second and I'm gonna look
and see in the windows project that
where I can search things I'm gonna see
about that message structure what's all
the stuff I could get and then I'll have
to also see I suppose if there's any
queries I can use to get additional
information on the message right so you
know this is not going to give me very
much
unfortunately let me see if there's any
information on that
oh boy stackoverflow says there isn't
any way to do it which often means that
there actually is a way to do it there's
been multiple times that I've found
someone sections are like there is no
way and then I find the way so I'm not
sure that's necessarily true but it
usually doesn't mean there's no
straightforward way
yeah
hmm I can't really think of anything
offhand want to see if anyone had
actually
I mean the things I'm thinking ever not
particularly attractive right like it
seems like okay so one way to do it
would be to try to make something that
cooked to everything to find out who
when whenever someone calls send message
we get the actual call we like hook all
calls to send message and then full can
see like yeah we look and see anyone
who's gonna send an IX seven to eight
message
yeah I don't know I don't know about
that so I guess I mean I guess at the
moment we just fix it because I'm not
sure what else we can actually do we
know that the problem is that we're
getting spammed with a particular
message that we can't seem to avoid
right I suppose it could be our message
like do we ever send that message
anywhere I'm not sure I don't think we
defined any custom windows messages did
we because we don't have any of that so
it can't be ours I don't think we're
never we're never using a custom message
so we're not sending it someone else
would have to be sending it to our
window maybe we can look at regice move
you look at registration for them so I
don't know if you can iterate over who
has registered stuff I don't think you
can but this is a function called
register window message where you give
it a string and it gives you back a
message well but it's not one of those
it says it's between oxc thousand and
oxf all the way and so that it could not
have been registered through register
window message so if you haven't called
register window message you're not
supposed to be sending the message in
the first place because it could
conflict' with some other
you're not supposed to be sending
outside your application that's seven
two seven three eight message so this is
a real puzzler I don't know where this
message is coming from I'm not sure I
would really like to know
but either way we've got different ways
we can deal with it one way we can deal
with it is by discarding that particular
message right another way we could deal
with it is trying to make this thing so
that just never like you know we could
do this so we don't ever time our called
a peak message and so we're not
generating debug events so we won't
crash but we'd still like have to sit
here processing them all which isn't
great but you know it would in theory
fix the problem so let's see what
happens if we do that so if I start
graphics debugging now on the
application run the lighting alt-tab
back go to insight now we've avoided the
crash right so that's good I you know
I'm happy about that but you know we we
figured out what the problem was but
it's like well I would really like to
know who is spamming us with a WM user
message outside of the legal range that
you're never supposed to cross app spam
it seems like there's a bug in some
other program
[Music]
and I don't know is there a reason our
cietrade icon isn't here by the way
sure does take a long time
well I'll go ahead and start with
questions anyway while we're dealing
with this
best alloys said regarding message o X
seven three eight and then posted a link
let's take a look at that link okay
copy link address and I spent her a lot
of time last week debugging a third
prayer application that froze up in some
places on Windows 10 1703 but work
perfectly on previous versions long
story short this application calls peak
message many times on every trip around
smashes loop as a verse in 1703 it
appears to the widow message o x7 3:8 is
occasionally sent in the internals of
peak message that message goes into the
queue so get message returns immediately
and the loop goes around again that pegs
the CPU at what this is exactly what we
just saw the solution was the pass I can
put to check whether the message ID is
those hex 738 and if it is ignore the
message by jumping back to right before
the get message indication invocation
okay so is Windows itself actually
sending something in the WM user range
have they lost their minds I mean I
already know they lost their minds
Windows 10 is you know is you know an
operating system written by children so
I don't know why I'm surprised if that's
really the case that's nuts
windows itself should never be sending a
WM user range message that's crazy
because other applications may have
already used that message right that
could break all sorts of stuff so I
let's hope that's not really the case
all right let's let's kill this go go
away yes stop debugging so if that's
really the case then I might actually
say let's filter out message if other
people are seeing this happen then 738
should should definitely get filtered
but the problem is
that I mean how do we filter it
effectively right like I mean we can't
just ignore it forever can we I mean we
have to remove it from the queue or do
we just let it pile up
because we can skip polling it entirely
right but like WM paint and W mousemove
we can skip entirely but if this message
I don't know whether this message is a
generated message or not if it's a
generated message then we could skip it
entirely if it's not a generated message
I don't know that we can skip entirely
because I don't know if it would just
fill up on our thread the whole time
right so that's kind of right it's kind
of a little bit tricky so you know if
you imagine extending this routine out a
little bit to something that was like
d-word skipped messages right
if you imagine a sink here we'll all
right we want to skip WM paint we want
to skip WM mass move everyone want to
skip whatever the heck elect 7 3 8 is
that's not even a message that's
supposed to exist then we could do a
thing here where we do a fryer loop over
like skip index equals zero you know
skip the next yields rate count skip
messages plus plus skip index like so
and then we would just do this right
we're each time through we would say all
right
like we we're gonna start the messages
at like last message equals zero or
something we're gonna start the messages
I at last message we're gonna go to you
know skip minus one and then we're gonna
skip stack that set last message equal
to skip plus 1 so it will hop over every
time whatever that thing was right seems
reasonable enough and you know we I
guess we end on that it'll kind of it'll
end at FF FF FF FF D but I'm ok with
that
if that makes sense so yeah I think that
would be fine the other way we could do
it is via ranges which maybe is better I
don't know but whatever so anyway in
here when we're doing this yeah we could
just get rid of all of this code now and
it would just look like this so we would
go through and try each of the ranges as
we go and that skip message is obviously
just like skip messages skip index like
so right
so that would skip message 738 entirely
so it just doesn't ever get there and
yeah I think that's fine
this is complaining that we might not
initialize this but we will I mean and I
actually I'm not sure why static
analysis can't figure that out because
it should be able to see that you always
get in here this is a constant value
certain the static analysis and the
compiler must not be able to poke
through that for loop which is fine on
I'll clear it so now in theory anyway
in the vaguest of theories if I run this
I should be able to put this back in
actually so now if I run
[Music]
and here we are running I if I do
lighting and then switch back and do
this stuff I don't crash anymore right
so there I've run the lighting I can
come back here I can say hey possum
capture frame and all that works so it
looks like yeah we can just skip that
message probably and then and we don't
have to care if windows start spamming
us with it for some reason maybe it's a
generative message maybe it isn't I
don't know I mean that's just like yeah
I don't want to say about that
I guess there's one other thing we could
do
yeah I'm not gonna do it though all
right so let's go back to let me let me
see about questions
and there's another someone else posted
an additional looks like the same info
though alright so that was a kind of
frustrating thing to have to do but at
least it actually worked so you know at
the end of the day I guess that is a
good thing I'm not gonna complain we
were able to figure out what was going
on it was pretty bizarre but you know
there there you are of it so if you take
a look here at at our rendering
information we can now start to ask the
questions that I actually wanted to like
here's the fragment shader for example
and we can look up stuff like you know
the look up sampler or whatever we can
kind of go in here and see what the
value actually is what the values are
for these things
right now we have them commented out
because I had tested that to see if that
would help which it you know turned out
tonight everything do oh no buddy don't
turkey time today so at least in theory
now that we kind of got all that craft
out of the way and figured out what
Windows 10 was doing to destroy our
application
what just happened there why did that
here we go
paste please thank you it would be nice
to know why Windows has started sending
a 738 and X 738 message I mean that's
just totally effed up but at least we
fix it so I guess tomorrow will be
cleared to actually debug our lighting
like we wanted to and we got rid of the
thing that was standing in our way we
got rid of render dock unfortunately
that didn't work insight does appear to
be working so we can that and we got rid
of the Windows 10 thing that was
preventing it from working so we should
be good to go so I guess I'll end the
stream there other issue what do you
mean by generated message so this is
kind of a confusing aspect of Windows
but what happens is when you call peak
message and get message right the
intended behavior of those functions is
that there's a message queue for your
application in Windows and it's per
thread usually so whenever you're
whatever thread you're on when you call
the functions to check messages it looks
at the message queue the for that thread
and if there is a message waiting in the
queue you get the message back right and
that's that's exactly right that's what
you would expect nothing weird about
that but that is only for certain kinds
of window messages the majority of
window messages first other special
kinds of window messages such as paint
and mouse move instead of that what it
does is if you ever ask for one meaning
if when you call peek message and you
pass the range and the range includes
paint or mouse move if there are no
messages in your queue to give you so if
there's enough
is nothing actually in the queue that
someone has posted like a WM size
message or something then it will
generate a paint and a mouse move
message for you right so it will
basically create them to tell you you
need them if the mouse has moved or your
your window has been obscured and needs
to be repainted it will generate them on
the fly now we don't use WM paint or WM
Mouse move so we don't actually want it
to generate them so we just say don't
bother right because it's just wasting
work and causing this loop to have to go
around a bunch more times potentially
when we really don't want to uplink
coder says this seems to be a known bug
since Windows 10 build 1703 how is that
possible
what were they doing posting a Windows
message that's in the WM user range
that's nuts
that's nuts Raymond where is Raymond
Chen Raymond Chen what is Oh X 738 tell
me why is Windows posting Oh X 7 3 8
messages to applications that's in the
WM user range Raymond what is going on
how is the performance of the from
scratch written render compared to
OpenGL we haven't updated the from
scratch renderer yet to do 3d so it
still runs the old 2d path so we don't
have a way to compare the performance
yet how in for coder you make possible
to have type def highlight irie compiled
it from source I actually we licensed
the source code to for for code or from
alan since it's the editor we use it
Molly for everything so we can just
rebuild it if we need to
I don't know if there's a way to do it
other than that there might be there's
there might be keyword highlighting but
at the time there wasn't programmable
keyword highlighting
let's see if got any more questions
about what we're doing today crab this
has been answered many times I'll dig
back through YouTube but when why did
HMH move from being fully software in a
product using graphs api's so i don't
remember why but i think it was just
because we wanted to be able to do more
like high res rendering and and be able
to use them any sprites as we want and
not have to care and stuff like that so
we at some point we just did both so you
could switch between them we've added
some 3d stuff now which our 2d path
doesn't know about
so we'll ping-pong back there at some
point and update it so that the software
render version will match the 3d the
harbor under version as well so in the
end we will run on both as equivalently
the only difference will be that the you
know software renderer is always gonna
be much slower I in compared to the
hardware render peak you know that's
obvious right cuz it's not able to use
the most of the power on the machine and
she has to run the game with the letting
actually on just roll time sake no not
till we've fixed the new one
how would you cast a pointer and call it
directly with that an extra type - how
would you cast a pointer and call it
directly without an extra type death are
you talking we talk about like a
function pointer so I'm not sure I'm not
sure that what you're asking but I'll
try to answer it
so here it I'll just make one right here
right
so I think what you're saying is let's
suppose that I had a function correct me
if I'm wrong let's suppose that I had a
function like this is this what we're
talking about and you want to call this
function
I so is this what we're talking about
and then you have a thing that's like oh
okay I've got a void star let's say
that's a pointer to that function is
that is that roughly what we're talking
about so you've got this situation and
you want to know how you call it
without making any kind of type def so
you want to do something where you're
gonna call like food pointer five is
this is this what you're trying to do
and then it'll you know it says though I
can't I don't know how to do that is
that what we're talking about or santak
how about 2d house prints they're just
go back and look we there's a whole
bunch of streams where we were doing
that we we didn't do like a fully
optimized one but it you know it ran
reasonably
okay yeah so so this is what he wants to
know about all right so if you want to
do this it's really kind of difficult to
do because the the this is where the C
the C way that they use declarations is
just very counterintuitive and difficult
but the basic idea right the way you
would do it like start this way so
suppose you did have the type def the
thing that you don't want right the
thing that you don't want looks like
that
correct so if I wanted to be able to
call this without having to worry about
like without your constraint then what I
need to do here is I need to cast it
inside the parentheses here right so
before it tries to use it as a function
I need to cast it in here right
but that will work right and we can
verify that that will work because I can
actually make it happen here right so
we're definitely calling it so now the
question is well what if I want to get
rid of this type def well what I would
need to do here is I need to figure out
a way to put the information from the
type def which is effectively this right
in here so what I'd like to be able to
do is that right but it's not quite
right because if you look at what
happens here it's like all right the the
the way this is gonna get read is gonna
get read in the wrong order
right foo pointer is Right a pointer to
function taking an integer returning a
void or sort of like well not really
because it's gonna read it in the
opposite direction so like you know
doing it exactly that way is doesn't
actually work right because of the low
of the of the see order where the
parenthetical for the argument list not
try to say this it goes in the other
place from where the type from where the
type name is I'm not saying that very
well but like right I mean it goes it
goes after the the type name instead of
before so the pointer part you know
would have to go would have to have like
the the argument part has to go after it
right how you actually make it
understand the how you actually make it
do the cast I'm not sure because as you
can see like I believe this is the
correct form right but it doesn't
actually allow you to do it so yeah so
basically this is this is the form for a
function type right and we need a
pointer to a function type so what it
read here was like void star returning a
void star an integer by parenthetical
izing that I forced it to read the star
first so it goes like pointer to a
function taking an integer returning a
void because it's inside another set of
parentheses I know this is really weird
but you can kind of imagine that it's
reading an invisible identifier name
inside the inner most set of parentheses
I guess is the best way to say it so
sorry I'm doing such a bad job
explaining this let me do it from the
let me do it two ways and see if that
helps make it clear maybe that was
already clear but I doubt it was just
because it was really confusing so
what's going to happen inside the C
compiler is it's going to make an
abstract syntax tree that describes what
the heck is going on here right so so
inside the compiler somewhere here's my
Milton Ness what day are we on for a six
so inside the compiler it's gonna have
to make an address in Czech Street and
so you know objects abstract syntax
trees have a binary descending notion to
them that makes them different from a
left-to-right reading order right and so
it's worth thinking about this just for
a second because this is why these sorts
of things come up
the reason these sorts of things come up
and see in other languages as well
is because there's a fundamental
difference between a linear line of text
and how a compiler ends up interpreting
that linear line of text when it
actually goes to process it semantically
okay
and so you can think about operator
precedence as a very common way in which
this happens so for example you may see
a linear line of text that is a plus B
times C plus D right and if you were to
look at this as a line of text then the
order of operations that you would
perform is very clear it would be to
take a right and add B to it right I
would then take the sum of this which is
like a plus B right I produce the result
then I would multiply by C right so now
I've got C times a plus B and then I
would add D to it right so that's what I
would actually end up with if I was
interpreting this as just a stream of
things going from left to right I would
do a plus B that's a value times C just
like I was hitting them on calculator
buttons so it does the a plus B first
then it does the time C then it does the
plus D right but that's not how the
compiler wants to do it because it's
trying to imitate how math is notated so
we all know that there's like an
implicit idea that multiplication will
happen first and then plus will happen
because that's the math way right so
instead what happens is when the
compiler parses this it uses the what
it's called operator precedence which is
which operators bind together first to
create a different look for this
expression
and there's two ways that a compiler
could do this it doesn't have to do with
an abstract syntax tree which I'll talk
about a second you can actually do this
with just straight up stack parsing
right it can do something by saying well
I've got an A and I've got a plus right
I know that a plus can might be a high
precedence a plus might be an operator
that happens after certain other tighter
binding operators like times so what I'm
gonna do is I'm just gonna push like a +
+ on a stack and then I'm gonna see what
comes next and I got a B and then I get
a times and a C and on the stack I then
say oh okay
C times B is like a totally fine
operation for me to perform because
there's nothing that can happen that's
tighter binding them at let's say so
then I just compute that and then leave
the new result of that like B times C on
the stack right then I see the plus
which I push again and I'm like oh this
plus in fact you know you could even
think of this as the more general case
where you don't have to make it about
anything I just push be x + C on the
stack
I see the plus I know this plus is a
higher precedence than this x or I
should say lower precedence and the
times it depends on how you want to
define your precedents there it's looser
binding so then I can go back and say
anything that was previously you know
less you know a tighter binding me can
now get collapsed right so we can do
things like that
you know it can it can have sort of a
stack logic to it like that's where like
and if you ever heard of shunting yard
came up on the stream one time I'd
actually never use this algorithm but
it's kind of neat it's a Dijkstra
algorithm that actually just like
processes in order you don't have to
build a tree you can build a tree if you
wanted to but it can just process it
expressions in order and it knows when
to collapse each precedence based on
what it sees right but anyway the point
is at some point usually compilers that
do more comp separations they don't try
to execute everything in line like that
what they what they do is they try to
build a tree that says what's going on
and what that tree looks like is it
looks like an order of operations style
sorting of the information so the most
high level constructs we have here are
the pluses so the first plus would be
here and it would have an a on its left
and it would have everything else on
this side on its right right now again
the most important thing on this side is
a plus it's the most like coarse-grained
operator so that will have the B times C
on this side and the D on this side and
on this side then we would have the
times operator and we'd have the B and
the C right so this expression when a
compiler looks at it the compiler
actually looks at it in a very different
way it's gonna turn it into using this
operator precedence rules a tree that
looks like this and then when it's
thinking about the tree it's actually
thinking about it like this so when it
goes to generate code it's gonna say oh
I've gotta add two things and it's gonna
look down the two branches to say
alright I need to prepare what's going
on the left side and prepare what's
going on on the right side so that I can
do my ad right and then it will you know
progressively go down the tree and wind
back up so then you end up getting all
the way down to the times a plus B it
will create like the mul a B right and
it's gonna put that into a location that
the plus can then do right so then it'll
do an ad whatever this is whatever the
result was here right it's gonna add
that the R and the D I'm gonna put that
in another result right result two or
whatever and then it's gonna do the add
of the result two and the a and put that
in the final result of this tree right
so it kind of goes down the tree and
then resolves the tree on the way up
outputting each of this sort of like
assembly instructions it will need this
is not real assembly language obviously
but you get the idea right
so the same exact process that happens
there that hopefully is fairly intuitive
with the equation how that happens right
because I have to turn this into a
linear series of operations on the
CPU and I need them to go in the order
the programmer expects if B is time C
you supposed to happen first I'd better
not add a and B first I'm gonna get the
wrong result so it needs to build a tree
that reflects the correct order of
operations that same process is
happening everywhere in the compiler for
all things not just operator precedence
so when you see something in the
compiler like a cast so let's say I see
something like this I will get something
that's like okay there's an equals
operator which is this right here the
hot them the most granular thing right
I've got a target of the equals here
which is a and then I've got a cast
expression here right cast expression
the left side of the cast expression is
the keyword int on the inside of here
and the right side of the cast
expression is six point 2f a constant
right this is a key word this is a
variable this is a constant right so
then when it goes to execute this it's
like okay and actually strong word
generate code for it it goes okay I know
you know I've got some information about
a from up above in the code I know where
I'm gonna put this okay I've got to do a
cast it's a constant cast so I can cast
this maybe just right now inside the
compiler I don't have to actually
generate information to cast it right
and I know I need to cast it to an
integer I know what an integer is
because I have a type table tells
managers a 32-bit value that's signed in
blah blah blah right so that's what's
happening okay
so now we finally get to what we're
trying to write here and we'll take what
I wrote the first time and we'll take a
look at it a little more carefully and
then we'll look at how I fixed it by
putting the parentheses in there all
right so the first thing that I wrote
was all right I want a void star
inte all right like that food pointer
right and this whole thing was inside a
set of parentheses but we don't really
care about that because that was just so
we could call it as a function we really
care is getting the cat getting it to
cast to the type of a pointer to a
function so I wrote that one first and
this one casts it to an actual function
which you can't do
you can only cast a pointers to
functions you can't cast to a function
because that would be like this whole
block of data and write code all right
so what we know here is because these of
these parentheses this informs the
compiler that it has a cast expression
so these two things become the cast
expression right so then it needs to
make sense of both sides of the cast
expression it's sort of like if I had an
operator here right a magical operator
that meant cast I would write it like
this right and this operator is the cast
expression but we don't write it that
way and see because if there isn't an
operator for cast so instead it's if you
parenthesize a type name it is a cast
right so that's what happened this casts
right so those go away and we just have
this on the left side and this on the
right well okay so this is just a
variable so there's nothing interesting
here so now the question is what happens
over here it's got a parse this
definition somehow right and it has to
figure out what that means but all it
sees is a type on one side void star and
a function parameter list on the other
side int right so what it thinks is
going on here is oh okay I'm defining a
function prototype right and I'm
defining the parameter list on this side
right so this is the Paramus which just
has int in it and no more parameters
like I would the parameters would chain
up here if there was comma
CAIR star or whatever and then it's got
a return type over on this side right
and that is a pointer that is a pointer
to there's only one print for a pointer
to avoid right so it's function pointer
here to avoid so what it sees would we
go to cast this is it sees that this
left side is completely you know it's
just a line of type information so it's
just gonna take it in order right from
its gonna read it basically this way and
it's gonna say you know pointer to avoid
and that's so it's like okay that's the
return value and when it sees this
integer here it's gonna say oh okay
that's the paramus cuz it's what it sees
the parentheses I should say it's gonna
be that's the pram list it's gonna read
it out right so that's what its gonna
think however if you introduce a
parenthetical there right so how I fixed
that function right was I said oh okay
void star int right then what's gonna
happen is because it builds these from
the innermost part out right from the
innermost part out and I really left one
part out here that again it's hard
because C++ and C and C++ just use this
syntax very difficult to grok there's
remember how I said oh you know permit
this parenthetical is an implicit lis
like I wrote a cast operator well
imagine there was another operator
that's like a function operator right
well what would it look like then
instead of void star parentheses int and
right in here there's a magical function
operator that's the part that's so
confusing there's like funk is right
here so it's really void star keyword
func
like this is a keyword it says make a
function right and
the parameters come after it or
something right so if we have this
magical funk operator it'd be a lot
easier to see what was going on because
there it is right and the things that go
on this side of it are the parameters
and the things that come on this side of
it is the return value right that makes
sense so what we're doing effectively
when we add this parenthesis is that
magical funk the operators now on the
outside right so it's gonna start with
the pointer because it's the most
parenthetical thing and it's gonna flip
the order of these two things it's gonna
say pointer no right and funk goes here
does that make sense but it's really
hard to see that because it's this
parenthesis that is the de-facto funk
operator it's the fact that we have a
parenthetical paramus that makes the
function but what that does see the
parser works from that the way that c
type parsing is designed right is it
works from the innermost thing out and
that's exactly like what happens again
with that operator precedence the
innermost parentheses
you know pluses should happen after
stars right so normally this plus would
have happened first if it was a plus I'm
sorry normally is plus would have
happened second if it was a plus B times
C but because we parenthetical eyes it
the parser starts on the inside right
and it will do that first when it
constructing the tree and that's the
exact same thing that happens here the
most parenthetical thing is the thing
that starts the type declaration so it
reads star first before ever getting to
the parenthetical list that says create
a function so when you read one of these
if you see void star int like so think
this is a function taking an integer
right I should point to this this is a
function
taking an integer returning a void star
why because function has the most like
powerful granularity there right it's
the thing that will appear at the top of
that tree so you start with it just like
you would start with plus at the top of
the tree because it's the most you know
I I'm using the wrong I don't know how
to say it right I'm you it's the
coarsest grain operation func is the
coarse grain operation in the type
definition right so we start by saying
func then we say okay what's on either
side of the func what's the rent value
it's this what's the parameters it's
this right but if we were to insert a
parenthesis then what we're really
saying there is oh just like we
parenthesize plus expressions to make
them happen first when normally they
would be the coarsest thing this
parenthetical makes the pointer the most
important first thing and it happens
first then we read the next thing
outside the parentheses which is the
func right which is this because it now
has the highest of course look the you
know most powerful coarseness does that
help clarify that at all I know this is
really weird and complicated and it's
one of the most hard things to
understand in C it's also one of the
most hard things when you're writing a C
compiler to get right is going wait a
minute it's not actually the most hard
thing is probably the preprocessor cuz
the pound defined macro syntax is so
messed up but it's one of the hardest
things to grap your head around cuz you
know we all kind of Intuit when there's
actual operators we can actually see
it's a lot easier to understand how this
gets broken up cuz you're like oh right
plus this happened after time so they
come up higher in the tree in whatever
but this stuff is really hard because
there's no operators they're all
implicit in the like the parentheses
tutor I was doing some compiler things
she wants to go could a parser
programming maybe operate a pressing
only stream I'm not really the one to do
that that would really be a John thing
he's more the compiler guy he said he
would do one one time but he's just you
know I think he's got enough stuff he's
interested in doing right now that just
hasn't bubbled up but you know go bug
Mesa ready can you explain how you would
fix some stuff such as the fog in pub G
is the fog broken what do you want to
fix about the fog do you want to look
more realistic fog or something
what blackboard program are you using
there's a program that was written
specifically for this stream by Sergio
art that's sorry sir Serge it's
Serg e underscore RGB he doesn't use
Sergio as the chat so on the chat it's
Serge RGB I don't know if he's probably
not on today but he wrote this program
called Milton and it's pretty cool it's
a great black boarding program how they
recommend using it if you're streaming
and you can get it for free and it comes
with source code so it's it's pretty
awesome actually all right I think
that's it so I'm going and wrap it up
oops yeah this the I try to avoid that
stuff you know we've never covered this
on handmade here uh simply because it's
just ridiculous like I don't even think
people should bother learning it unless
you just you know unless you're doing C
compiler stuff because just make the
time test you know make the type def
it's easier to read everyone understands
that whereas if you try to put a
function pointer in a cast expression
it's just nuts I mean you can imagine
how nuts this stuff gets and it's just
and nobody knows why like most people
don't understand what's going on here
and why would you it's a it's like a
compiler
artifact almost if that's how that works
like who I mean I don't know the
function precedent like that's
remembering what precedents function
versus pointer is in the type
declaration syntax of C is just not it's
not the thing that a programmer should
really have to spend their time like
dealing with you know because operator
precedence in the in the mass sense it's
logical for that to be something that
programmer has to know because they have
to know how to do math anyway so the
fact that you need to know that multiply
happens before plus for addition you
know that's just obvious that's you're
not burdening the programmer with that
because if they didn't know that then
they don't even know how to do the kind
of math basic math they need to know how
to do to be effective at programming
anyway but in the case where you've got
like something like these weird type
definitions they're just they're just
dumb like type definitions don't branch
like they really just don't for the most
part and so it's dumb that they aren't
just a line of things like it'd be way
more saying if C looked like that right
or better yet like that where it's like
five integers is foo or something like
that you know what I mean like it would
be better if you just could read the
thing in order and it was what it said
right and you know it's like pointer to
five integers is a lot more legible than
what we ended up with in my opinion but
it's like at this point you know it's
the horse is out of the barn so it's
like you can't really change that knocks
we're also used to you know typing this
that I can understand why you got to
keep it but it's not good I don't think
all right I'm gonna wrap it up thank you
everyone for joining me for the lip soda
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along with the series at
home you can always pre-order the game
on hand made here at org and it comes
with a source code now why we just
crashed Windows 10 apparently by closing
some applications I don't know but
that's kind of par for the course today
it's been a real unreliable programming
day but not because of anything we wrote
largely due to Microsoft and graphics
card stuff but oh well
anyway you can always go to hammer here
org and pre-order the game comes with
source code if you want to play around
with it as of tonight when I update our
code the source code for handmade ray
should also be in there so if you wanted
to take a look at the ray tracer we did
as a test dream while we're working on
getting a streaming setup working
that'll also be in the source tree now
both in the github and in the
downloadable zip files so that should be
it
yeah until next time don't forget we
have a schedule bot that tells you when
the streams gonna be live and we have an
episode guide if you want to catch up on
old episodes I referenced that in the
stream today actually I think at the pre
stream might I point to someone to it so
don't forget to check that out as well
that's it for today thanks for joining
me everyone and until I I guess until
tomorrow we'll be back here at what time
I think it's 10 o'clock tomorrow Pacific
Daylight Time its Pacific a lifetime
right yeah I think it's yeah 10 o'clock
Pacific Daylight Time tomorrow until
then have fun programming and I'll see
everyone on the Internet take it easy
everybody