hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show where we could a complete
game live on Twitch you know today I'm
hoping that we can do something kind of
fun with our with our debug system
because we had to do a bunch of work we
were making something to analyze the
running of our program and you know we
kind of did something that I think is
pretty cool we're actually now tracking
a heck of a lot of information about the
running of the program and we sort of on
Friday just did the work to kind of
start collating it but we haven't had a
chance to really see what that data
actually says because we only just got
the basics of collation in and we
essentially collect a ton of information
but don't have much in the way of any
kind of visualization to see what it all
means and so I'm kind of looking forward
to this week because I think this you
know we kind of had to do a bunch of
work to under the hood to make it all of
the actual data get collected properly
and so now I think this will be kind of
a more fun part where we get to start
seeing a little bit more about how our
program is working and kind of get the
payoffs of having done that work if you
will I'm gonna go ahead and get started
if you want to follow along today is day
185 and so if you want to follow along
day 184 a source code is the source code
that you want to unpack if you're
someone who has spirit of the game on
handmade here at work so taking a look
at where we left off we had just sort of
we typed in some collation code but I
don't think we'd ever actually run it or
check to see if it was at all valid I
don't actually remember to be honest
with you I do not remember what we did
on Friday I don't even know if we ran it
maybe we ran it yeah so it looks like we
have not actually ran it yet we would
have assuredly saw that it looks like
our current frame is zero-- here and so
yeah obviously this this bit where we
actually get a new frame for collation
we have not actually we have not
actually done the work to actually have
any anything in that frame so frames is
0 so whenever we get a new frame from
there it's it's going to be garbage and
then we're going to write to it which is
going to crash so a
this point we just want to kind of again
no mystery here we just want to go in
and just finish the code we you know
like I said we had started it it's not
done yet
and so we kind of want to finish up the
code which is easier said than done
because of course I don't remember what
we were doing it's been a while yeah had
a lot of work to do over the weekend and
so and then work to do today and so it's
been you know it's been paged out but
here is our debug frame frames and if
you remember what we decided to do is we
have essentially a debug scratchpad a
bunch of memory we can just use to do
whatever we want in and it just gets
thrown away every frame so we can just
we just do it everyone at party on it
and then it just gets reset basically so
when we're in there when we initialize
everything right at the beginning right
here we begin the temporary memory and
then we call collate debug records
collate debug records has the ability to
basically use that memory however it
wants and you can see it sets frame
count to zero but what it doesn't do is
actually initially initialize frames in
any actual way and so what we want to do
there is we can just go ahead and say
let's get some frames
oops or fangs as the case may be those
are always good those are of course a
very close relative of the frame a Fang
so what we can do here is just do a push
array since we have that that collation
arena we can do whatever we want with it
so if I want to push an array on here I
can say that however many frames we are
going to have and of course we know how
many we're going to have right because
we have a certain a bit of storage for
that of course so for some reason I
don't actually see it being used here at
all which is a bit odd so that's that's
a bit weird but I guess do we ever even
define it I guess we wouldn't have to
have but let's take a look so we do have
max debug frame count here so we can go
ahead and use that as well like so
although the other thing that we could
do is since we're using a scratch pad we
could do something like daisy chained
the frames together and if we do change
the frames together then we actually
wouldn't have to do anything like that
we wouldn't have to we wouldn't have to
do anything where we yeah we wouldn't
have to do anything where we guess that
my knee would just be how much memory we
have now it occurs to me though that
because max debug frame count is being
used here in the event count the
interesting thing about it is that
assumes that we only issue one frame end
event every time because otherwise
yeah the event counts we wouldn't be
able to hold enough event arrays to
actually count any more frames than that
but technically inside the frames we
could actually have tons of those frame
end events if you wanted to so it's kind
of weird like max debug frame count is
not really probably the best word for
that it's really event array counts and
technically those things are not really
coupled like you don't have to have
those two things be related it's a
little bit weird right it's hard to say
but you know it's just it's just a
little odd so technically you know we
could say well you know it's technically
let's say that it's something like we
can't have any more than two or four of
those four frame or who knows what and
technically we should only have the same
number as those but there isn't anything
preventing the code from outputting
multiple frame and events inside a
single event array which would lead to
more frames than event arrays if that
makes sense hopefully it makes some
sense so anyway what we want to do is
again just allocate some debug frames
here so let me go ahead and do that that
allocates just an array for storing
those guys again max debug frame count
here not what we want that we want event
array count like so and as we kind of go
through like I said current frame is
getting used every time we every time we
see one of those frame markers we
advance it to a new pointer and when we
do that now we're gonna actually have
valid memory for it but when we have
that valid memory again if you look here
we've got these debug frame regions
which is something that we're going to
want to start writing into and so we
need some way of actually allocating
enough
those regions we want to allocate a set
of those regions so we can kind of show
where they are right and so we got to
start thinking about how we're going to
do that and in order to have some memory
for that we're also going to probably
want right to to allocate space in that
current frame for the region
so we'd have current frame regions and
in there we would say something like
push array we could also actually again
do it where we didn't do push array like
that but we could for now I'm gonna go
ahead and just do it that way where we
then say I don't know how much we
allocated into a frame let's see here
probably something like I don't know if
max debug event count is probably a
little too large so I'll do it on the
order of this for now but again these
are kind of just arbitrary and we may
want to switch to a thing where we just
use the memory that we need as we go
rather than kind of doing these array
based ones because I don't know that we
actually need a raise for any particular
reason so I'm gonna do it like this for
now but I think we may want to do it a
little bit more conservatively just cuz
we don't really know much about what's
going on here and so maybe just daisy
chaining together would be the smarter
way to go so yeah if we go ahead and and
put these recent since sure now we have
place to store the regions and I can
compile this and that's probably fine
and I could probably run it okay so we
do like I said we do run out of space
they're part of that I don't know how
much memory we actually reserved for
debugging probably not as much as we
might want let me take a look here yeah
so debug storage size is actually quite
small as the case may be so in terms of
just storing these massive numbers of
events or something like that it's not
going to be able to do it so I don't
know exactly again what we want to do
there but probably something hmm for now
I might actually say that let's just do
something kind of tiny just for just for
a temporary thing I'm gonna see how much
we can do so we can't really do very
much at all with that size of arena I'm
gonna go ahead and do that
what is it complaining about their
current frame region cat looks like I
did not allocate this properly is that
correct we've got our debug frames how
many frames do we have let's see here
frame count oh my so we're doing
something a little bit odd here it looks
like we've got some kind of a bug
because there should not nearly be that
many frames right so it looks like it
looks like we've done something bad
let's see what's our event rate index is
3 I rent a valid event it's 1 so it
doesn't feel like we should have gotten
up that high it's a bit odd I'm gonna
I'm gonna take out just a quick gander
here what's going on I don't like the
looks of that at all
so as we roll through these events here
here we are adding one in how are there
that many of these this is bizarre ah
that's the problem this is totally bogus
we need to actually only loop through
the event indices that are actually
there so that's that's just wrong right
we actually need to do this so that we
can loop over the amount of events that
are actually present so that that's just
a bug and so now we should be in a much
better position to see about the memory
usage all right ok so now we're at least
in in reasonable running shape so let's
continue on with with doing some of this
collation because I want to work out how
we actually have to collate this stuff
since it's a little bit tricky I think
so let's take a look so what's gonna
happen here is we've got these debug
events and the debug events themselves
they we don't even really know how much
time a particular debugger event takes
right because we don't have any
when it actually ends so when we see a
debug event we see like it's begin block
we don't know when we're going to see
the end block right so we have kind of a
nasty problem where we have to start
pairing these things up together and we
do have the debug record index which is
something that allows us to figure that
out but we need some way of actually
creating a like a collation space where
this can happen so we know that any
given debug record index you know we can
we can have I'm gonna go ahead and draw
this out here for any given debug record
index looks like we zoomed out see
that's more what it typically looks like
now all right so this is fairly
complicated right J 185 so the way that
this would work is we've got a set of
functions we've got a set set of blocks
in the code and each block you know I
don't know we've got some code in here
right and each block is gonna have that
begin in that endpoint but we don't know
very much about the circumstances under
which one of these could be called so
for example if this isn't some kind of a
function right so this is in some
function called foo in fact let me just
go ahead and say write it here so let's
suppose we have a function called foo
and in that function it calls itself
recursively so even just in this simple
scenario we know that in a single
invocation of foo we may end up re
invoking foo itself and thereby opening
one of these begin blocks multiple times
before we ever see an end block and so
what that's going to write out in the
log is it's gonna write out something
like you know begin foo begin foo and
let's say just goes too deep so then it
goes n foo and foo
you know so that is how this would look
and these are paired thusly
you know we would see begin foo and then
we would see begin foo again we would
know that we can't begin foo a second
time if we've already begun at once
without seeing an end unless it's a sub
invocation so we would know that
somewhere down the line foo called
itself either directly or indirectly
right now this is true only insofar as
the thread index is the same because at
the same time on a separate thread
somebody might have called begin foo
here like might have called through and
maybe how to begin in an end pair and so
what we could see is something like this
I'm gonna put thread numbers here so the
thread the thread ID is here and this is
the event so the thread ID on thread 0
might do begin foo the thread ID on
thread 1 might then do a begin foo then
the thread ID 0 might do an end foo then
thread ID 1 might do another begin foo
and then thread ID 1 might do an end foo
and then throw out a 1 dozen other hand
foo now the naive parse of this right is
that it would look like this
begin and this begin look like this this
one part pairs to that and this one
pairs to that right that's what it would
look like but it's not true because
there's two different threads in play so
they can only pair if they're on the
same thread because obviously throw in
two different threads than the beginning
the end o match so we only look at 0
right and we say oh ok there's a pairing
there then we only look at one and we
say oh ok there's the pairing there and
there is the pairing there that's the
actual operations that we need to do and
that would tell us how these things are
grouped up so in order to do that as
we're reading through these things
right as we kind of read through them
for every one that we get of these guys
we need to tennis a alright so we have
the location right because that that is
the counter index we know the counter
index we have a way to index it off of
its got a unique ID right so we have a
unique ID and that plus the thread ID
gives us essentially a completely unique
ID and then the same is true for the end
so we're really looking for the thread
ID plus the counter ID right and I
shouldn't say plus it's more like
appended to right it's it's almost like
the thread ID dot the counter ID you
know it's like a grouped number what
we're doing is we're looking for paired
versions of that and so I don't know the
best way to do this I'm going to do it
as a simple stack for now because I feel
like the number of these that can be
open at a time it's not that high and so
I feel like doing a giant opening open
like a dressing kind of a scheme where I
have like some giant thing which is like
thread IDs this way see IDs this way and
each one of these guys is some linked
list of open things that get closed off
or something I think I'd rather avoid
doing that entirely I don't think that's
a good use of anyone's time because in
general any time you see an end it's
going to match the most recent begin on
that particular channel right and
furthermore beginning ends kind of end
up being paired most of the time so you
shouldn't have to look back very far
most of the time and end block pairs
with the thing that was the most
recently opened you know and so I think
what I'd like to do is just per thread
so per thread ID I will keep a linked
list of what blocks are open and I'll
just search that linked list from the
end back towards the beginning if that
makes sense to see what closed and if
something closes out you know I'll
remove it if we wanted a special case it
and say that we don't allow anything to
be overlapped on the same thread meaning
we don't
someone to go begin foo on thread zero
begin bar also on thread zero then end
foo on thread zero and bar on thread
zero you see how that does like this hop
it does like an inter leave its like it
begins one thing begins another then
ends not the one that's most interior
but the exterior like that if we didn't
allow that then you would always match
the last one right you never have a
circumstance where the thing that gets
matched isn't the very last one so we
could also make that restriction without
really much of a loss of generality but
because it's not too hard probably to
search through the linked list in the
rare case where that's not true we might
as well just support it because I'm not
sure there's that much a reason not to
it may ruin some kind of like stacking
notion that we have it makes it kind of
hard to draw bars because the bars can
overlap even on the same thread you know
like if you're looking at a thread and
and we wanted to draw like bars like we
were saying where we have thread 0 and
thread 1 if we want to draw these kind
of bars in there
it's kind of weird because now you might
get a bar where this is the time for a
foo and this is the time for bar here
but actually it kind of penetrates a bit
into there so it's kind of hard to draw
that too right because they overlap and
so it's almost like you need as many
lanes as you have open things and that's
again it makes it difficult
visualization wise so it may be that
there's just a good reason to say we
just don't allow that and we consider
that an error and then when you're doing
your block timing you always you should
never always use like a time block that
you know closes in order because I don't
know that we'd give up anything for that
and it does ensure that our
visualization will be easier and it's
easier for us to see what's going on
rather than having to try and invent
some visualization that's not that that
doesn't obey the standard scoping rules
of like see where you know things get
closed out in the order that they get
opened and stuff like
okay
so let's see so I need some storage for
I just need like you know open like an
open block an open debug block and the
open debug block would have some kind of
like a pointer to its the previous
blocker or the parent I suppose right
like whoever was above me and the
information in here I think would be the
same information roughly as would be in
the debug event structure so I would say
that what we'll do is we just say let's
point to the debug event structure
itself so this is the opening event and
that that is presumably all we need and
we get to the end event we then would
have the beginning and the end events
and we can then collapse them and do
whatever it is that we want to do with
that information because we would have
all the information that we actually
need right hmm she's me I think that
would be fine yeah so then we would just
have to have one of these for every
thread so we have like open block for
thread and you know again I don't mind
having a lot of max values in here
because again I don't we can it's just
for our own purposes it's not something
that ever runs on the end-users machine
or anything like that
and plus I guess we could say some
ridiculous number that we will never
have the luxury of having because I
don't know that handmade hero could
really make use of 256 threads but in
the future there will certainly be
computers that can do 206 threads I mean
you know Xeon Phi someday probably will
do 60 will do 206 threads in a couple
years
I would think potentially seems
reasonable anyway I mean obviously you
could make turn of reducers threads on
anything
I mean Tori's threads that actually are
all doing work at the same time so if I
have that open block for thread then
what I should be able to do is put in
and I could probably use this for the
thread ID stuff as well
so what I could probably do is say all
right for the thread IDs I'll also go in
here to where we keep the talk of that
junior this is technically not a thread
index is the thread ID we should
probably note it as such and then I'll
come in here to the debug open block and
I'll do something like say that we've
got a thread ID on there and then when
we initialize these at the start of the
debugging process as they might say in
Canada I will do a open block for thread
in fact I suppose I can actually just do
it this way
you know what I might even do it
slightly differently I might say like
debug thread or something like that and
I might actually put the thread ID in
here and the first open debug block in
here like so and then I will just say
that we've got an array of debug threads
and that way I can sort of add more
information in there for the collation
walk as we go I also don't know that we
need this in the actual debug state
itself so what I might do too is I might
say that at least for now until I have
like a real reason not to I might put it
up here as well so I do something like
we've got our debug threads here and our
debug threads is just going to do a push
array and that's gonna do the thing to
get us some storage for the number that
there are mass debug Redcat so if i push
those on there i can then run through
them and initialize them to whatever i
would like them to be
u3 - mm-hmm and i guess the other thing
to think about is when we do get lane
from thread i can kind of collapse these
down so get lane from thread since like
entering them in order I guess we don't
even need max debug thread now I think
about it we could just change these if
we wanted to it's kind of a little bit
janky err but they're all going to be
relatively close to each other
potentially I'll know that Matt I'm torn
I'm touring a little bit I'll leave it
this way for now but we don't really
even need to do that first to some
degree we could we could actually avoid
having there be any fixed number so
maybe I'll just do it that way and we'll
see if there's any real penalty for
doing it that way but if I have a debug
thread like so and then I just do like a
next on there I can do something much
more simple which is I can just say
debug thread first thread
right and I guess that goes here
so if I did that then we don't clear or
do anything at all at the outset and the
same would have been true for frames
that's why I saying maybe I should have
just been doing that kind of policy and
so when that happens in here what we
would do is when we say when we call it
to this function that's like get lane
from thread index instead of doing it
that way what I'd rather do is something
more like debug thread get thread or get
debug thread something like that so that
we can get it back this we'd pass in
instead of the debug state which is not
what we want we would just pass in that
first thread pointer you know that's
that's all we would need there so if I
pass in the first thread pointer I
assume the debug code we'll get that
back for me now when I have that thread
as a thing the lane index presumably can
just be retrieved directly from there
you know what I'm saying
so on here on the debug thread it would
just have a lane index on it now I
there's gonna be a couple of different
things that kind of need to be there
which is one reason why maybe on debug
state we might want to put it there but
frame bar lane count actually I guess is
the thing so if we pass if I pass debug
state into this I suppose I can just use
that and still keep it this way I'm just
trying to figure out whether I want the
threads I probably do so I'll just go
ahead and stick it here there we go
so that does the collation it'll do like
first thread equals zero and just clear
it out and then from then on out it'll
it'll use it there I'll just leave it
that way okay so when I grab that thread
out I then have the ability to search to
see what's going on with this guy
and so inside here when we do our begin
block and unblock pairs what I should be
able to do is say well for the begin
block we know we're always going to
create a new open block every time we
see
begin block you know so we're always
gonna have like for every for every one
of these when I come through here I've
got a debug block I'm going to do a push
struct onto the debug arena and I'm just
going to push on a new one of these open
guys although I probably will want to
recycle those since we pop these guys
off but we can do that in a second
in fact I guess I could well I guess I
could do it now again pretty
straightforward open debug block first
free block so what I would do there
again is when I initially do these guys
here when we sort of initialize
everything at the beginning we just set
those both to zero and that's all fine
so in here when I do my push block
instead what I can do is just say
alright let's set it equal to the first
free block first so we'll just set it to
the debug state first free block and
then assuming that we got one we would
set the bug block first free block to be
our next right which I suppose we would
just do something like this we don't
really care right seems simple enough
and then we've got our debug block but
if we don't have one of those then we
need to make a new one so if we don't
have one of those we just go okay the
debug block equals the push struct and
we grab one once we have a debug block
we need to set the values to whatever it
is that we're actually trying to record
and so if we take a look at where that
is we have the opening event we know
what that that is the event that we're
on right now so that's just the event
pointer that we're processing we know
or that open diva buck what its parent
was and the parent was whatever was
previously on this stack like whatever
the open blocks were whatever is on this
thread stack so since we have the thread
we would just say whatever the first
open block is that's the person who must
have called us because that's the last
thing that was opened before we got
before we got hit and then finally we
know that now we are that new block so
we're kind of just jay-z training these
guys together right and that's that's
all there is on there we can also set
the next three equal to zero though that
doesn't really matter because no one's
gonna be looking at that pointer but we
can set it that way just for fun so
that's all that would happen there when
we end a block we're going to do the
opposite set of events so what we want
to do here is we want to go ahead and
pull off the matching block for this
block now in order to do that we have to
figure out what block actually is
matching ours which should be the last
one on our thread and so what we could
do again is we could assert that they
match and not actually ever do any other
processing but we could also write
something that searches for them and so
I'm gonna write the thing that asserts
for now so you can see if we have any of
those but it would be fairly easy to
search through the list and find the one
that matches either way but so we hit
the end block we come through here and I
suppose you know the other thing too is
there might not be an end block it might
just be an open block now that I think
about it because it may be that the open
block happened many frames ago and those
frames have fallen out of the event or
array you know so it's possible that we
just don't have one and so the other
thing we could do is we could just say
that like at that point it's just an
indeterminate lo pin' block so maybe
I'll do that
we'll just see so first of all I'll say
you know assuming that the thread has an
open block then we'll say all right if
the threads first open block
opening events if that matches and in
order to match it needs to have a couple
things be true first of all it would
need the thread ID to match our thread
editing oops
then it would need and you know what I'm
gonna I'm gonna pull this out into a
closing event just so I don't have to
keep I'm sorry into opening event so I
don't have to keep doing that giant
dereference it's just a lot of typing
like so so we have the thread ID we have
the debug record index and then finally
we have the translation unit if all of
those things are the same then we know
that these two events match if they
don't we know that this event ended but
there was no beginning to it and how we
choose to record that is going to be up
to us probably what we'd wanna do is put
in a bar that kind of stretches back to
the beginning of time you know at the
beginning of the chart but we're not
really quite up to that point yet in
terms of even having a handle on the
visualization but so assuming that we
get a match we now know that these two
events close right these two events line
up with each other and so what I'd like
to know I suppose is what event I'm
sorry what frame we were actually on
when we did our begin because if the
frame that we're beginning on was not
the frame that we were ending on then we
kind of have some work to do in terms of
recording how this actually went down
and so I feel like in here we probably
want some way of saying not there in
here we want some way of saying for the
open event what was the frame index
you know so that in here when we're
looking through in fact I'll go ahead
and say we have a frame index like so
and looking through we've got you know
the frame count stuff and all of that so
as that happens I guess we don't really
need frame index because it's actually
specified right here to some degree
whatever that frame count is that's the
thing so we could just do it could just
do it like this and record that frame
count it's really the frame count minus
one is the only thing but you know
that's certainly something we could do
if we wanted to so if that's the frame
index then while we're in here we can
just say whatever the opening event is
when we do this this open debug block we
can say that we know that the frame
index or this you know starting frame
index is equal to whatever the frame
index was at that time and so here we
could do a test to see so we could say
if the debug block starting frame index
equals whatever frame digs X we're on
then we would you know do sort of the
standard span otherwise we would have to
do something where we like do two halves
of a span on the starting and ending
frames and full spans all the way in
between so again that's going to require
a little bit more work on our part in
terms of recording in fact I'll just say
record span that goes to the beginning
of the frame series this is record all
frames in between and begin and spans
and then this is the standard case this
is the case for most of our stuff where
we're just inside one frame we're
putting in one of those bars and so here
what we can do is we can actually add a
debug region which is what we're
actually drawing and so if we wanted to
draw this debug region we would say you
know add region I don't actually know
how we do that exactly but you know
debug state and current frame it's where
we're trying to add it so when we add
one of these in we can then specify this
stuff so the lane index we know is
whatever the the lane index of the
thread that we're on because all of the
things in this thread go into that Lane
we know in addition to the lane index
the min and Max T are just us sort of
mapping the beginning end clocks which
we now know mapping those into the total
time region for this particular frame
and how we map those in I don't remember
if this is 0 to 1 I don't remember how
we did the drawing I suppose we could
take a look at how that was done
perhaps separately Oh tired Katie hmm I
don't have a lot of energy it's true
that's because i overate i overate
yesterday there was a lot of food
consumed just not really the right
amount of food for for a single kc to be
eating so we inside the debug code where
we draw this how did we choose to do it
we do scale and scale is whatever the
frame bar scale actually is so I guess
we don't know it's it's entirely up to
us what we wish to do so I suppose the
way that to do that is just allow our T
values to kind of be crazy our DTSC
based stuff that seems like probably
what we would want to do I don't know if
we want to store our 64's as a result
but
we can think about that a little bit
separately but in terms of these here
then for min T max teeth and so on what
I can do there is say all right the
opening event and then the closing event
which is us we know where those are in
time because we have the clock value can
you see 2 4 o'clock value and so if I
cast that to an R 64 so I can do some
operations on it right I could then
choose to sort of regularize that a
little bit like for example you know
what I could do I could use a floating
point value to store it and this is kind
of inaccurate again I don't know if I
love this but we have that relative
clock concept which is just whatever the
start of the frame was so we know that
we could take that out and now we have
like a much smaller number to deal with
we know that it would this this number
would only be you know roughly on the
order of a couple hundred thousand I'm
sorry a couple hundred million right and
so that's not too bad to represent
potentially in an r32 yeah but again we
might want it we might want to do a
little bit more something a little bit
nicer there I'm not sure okay so if we
do that we now have the ability to sort
of categorize things in the lanes
properly and now we know like roughly
where they are as well we could also do
something where we don't if if the total
size of something is not large enough we
wouldn't maybe consider it so directly
and furthermore we kind of have a
situation where we may want to do
fancier things where we're talking about
a time range a specific time range where
like the current frame is not really
what our time basis wants to be talking
about if that makes sense
so we have some more things to do I'm
gonna leave it like this just
temporarily but yeah but afterwards
we'll kind of we'll kind of look at that
a little bit more in a little bit more
detail in fact now that I think about it
we probably want to address this a
little bit a little bit more
correctly even at the start because like
I said what I kind of want to do
originally was make it so it drills down
kind of gradually and so in order to
make it so it drills down what I would
want to do is I would want to have the
notion that I'm only looking at say
things that are one level deep in the
stack or that are there one level deep
in the stack under something in
particular and that's actually not that
hard to do actually with the way that
we're doing things here so it's actually
pretty straightforward to to make
something like that and I guess I like I
said I don't have to do it just yet but
that is kind of what I would rather aim
for now let's do it let's just do that
so in order to do that what we'd want to
do is see okay for this particular thing
I only want things that are going to be
at the like quote unquote top level but
top level might be differently defined
and so I'll start by doing the simplest
form on top level which is actual top
level which is to say that I'm only
going to record a debug block as taking
up space on our chart meaning as an
actual face in the region if the opening
event right on the on the first open
block right so this this thing here if
that first open block doesn't have any
one above it yeah so if we take a look
at what that means here so remember
we're keeping a list of these and they
have parents so if the parent of the
open block equals zero then I know it's
a top level function that's being called
right if it's parent was something but
that something didn't have a parent I
would know it was two functions deep and
so I'm gonna do some things where we
kind of like get a little progressively
fancier there on how we do this but for
now that would that would do it right so
I think if you excuse me for a second I
just have to quickly I changed that to
being called thread ID so I need to
change
here to be that so we need to implement
get debug thread first free block should
be off of debug state it's just a typo
yeah okay
so that's all good if Tebow block
starting frame and x equals frame index
that would be red so what I actually
need here is our matching block I guess
I want to call it debug open block so
this is our matching block so so what I
want to say here is matching look so I
need to blur those two functions the
thing I need to do is once we actually
find an ending for something so we're
here and we now know that we actually
matched this thing you know what I mean
we need to remove it that that block
this matching block structure is like
sitting there you know and it needs to
be yanked off of the sack so that we
don't keep growing the stack at
infinitum so we want to have the thread
first open block equal matching block
next right or parent I should say so
that it pulls off and thread first open
block itself we would want to put that
on to the free stack like so so yeah so
that's basically what we're talking
about thread first open block the next
free it's gonna be equal to whatever was
there before and then we just we've
popped it off right so we need to
implement these guys because they're not
going to implement themselves and I'm
not sure what we want to do about add
region
how we want that to work exactly but get
debug thread is pretty straightforward
so that's going to take a thread ID and
it's gonna look to see if it could find
it so remember we've got this concept of
the debug thread and we know that our
debug state has you know a list of those
so we can just loop over them really
trivially and say that you know starting
from that starting from that thread and
while it's still equal to something if
we find a thread with this thread ID
then we know that was the thread we
wanted
if we don't so if we get down here and
result has never been set to anything
then we know we need to make another one
of these guys and so in order to do that
again we can just we can just go ahead
and grab that push array and we can
change it to a fish truck so now we've
got a new one and when we get the new
one again we want to add it to that list
so it'll be there so we've got our first
thread oops our debug state our first
thread just needs to get single chains
on there so now we're tracking that
properly and that's good but we need to
figure out some way to add region and we
still have not done that and yeah in
order to do that we would need to figure
out where we're gonna put it so here's
debug frame region result Tran results
and for now we can just do like the
cheesy way I'm thought about really how
we want these to be going hmm but for
now since we kind of are saying that
they're all stored in something that
looks like this really all we would
doing is saying you know assert that the
current frame region count is less than
however many of these regions we
typically have right so if we do this
you know max regions per frame and
that's I said they're just a lot of max
ish things in here which seems a little
unnecessary and so that's why I saying
it might want to just kind of daisy
chain these things so that we don't have
to care about that it's just a thought
it doesn't really matter which way we do
it it's debug code so as long as it runs
okay for us we don't have to care we
never have to battle proof it for an act
and users machines so at some level you
can just do whatever is expedient and it
won't really matter but we do want to
make sure that it doesn't end up slowing
our frame time down too much because
then we won't use it as much and that's
always bad so we do want to make sure
we're at least you know somewhat
conscientious of how this is going to
work at some level but anyway so if we
go ahead and just do the standard thing
here when we get back one of these
regions all of this stuff is going to
get initialized sighs I assume but so
we'll just leave it as it is and let's
go ahead and compile that so now we have
everything implemented the only thing
that we don't do at the moment is our
frame bar scale is still not such
anything in particular in order to set
that I'm not sure what the smartest
thing to do there would be for the
moment I'm going to do something that's
not terribly good for our visualization
but there will at least let us see what
we want to see and that is every time we
see a frame marker I'm going to look to
see if there was a current frame you can
see how we do it here and we get the end
clock so that every frame has the
beginning an end clock what I'd like to
do is say all right if I take the begin
clock and the end clock then I kind of
have a clock range
that makes sense so this is like the the
the total amount of time that's taking
up and so the frame bar scale if I
wanted to map that into a range from
zero to one
I would just do 1.0 over the clock range
so I'll just say assuming that the clock
range is greater than zero so that there
was some time taken by the frame we'll
set it up like that okay so I've got
about ten minutes left on the clock
because we started a little late today
so I would like to go ahead and see if I
get this working that's something which
I did not do off the bat looks like I
did it kind of a dumb thing here with
the with the debug thread affiliation
which is fine it's fine
don't worry about it so let's see what
did I do
I accidently Boop a thread back on
itself I did well
ah so that's not what happened
I just never initialized the thread ID
so yeah that's a bit of mistake
admit that okay it's true obviously if
you're going to try to look these things
up you kind of gotta actually set the
values to something you can't just let
them be their default values or zero
because they actually need to match now
so yeah we need to set that ID properly
we want to probably set the first open
block to zero which we didn't do so we
just kind of received the switcher we
didn't do any of the stuff that we
actually need to do on startup the lane
index is just I think gonna probably be
frame bar lane count so debug state
frame bar lane cat will just increment
that so that each thread gets the
successive lane index and that's fine so
let's see here
how many regions there were I want
how many regions were there sixty-four
regions that seems so I think we've got
another bug here I guess it's been a
sleepy day so I wouldn't be surprised
you have a bunch of bugs seems pretty
fair but I feel like there shouldn't be
that many regions at the top level of
any given frame and the reason for that
is because we're only yeah we're only
looking at just the top level so how
many of things can open and close just
just at the top level I don't know if
it's gonna be that many now I could be
wrong about that because I guess that
could include sort of the other threads
which are not really inside anything
else
so maybe ones that that do like open and
close more often may be good I don't
know it seems unlikely I'm a little bit
a little bit weary of this but I'm gonna
let it ride just for a second just so we
can get a little bit more reconnaissance
on where we are at but it doesn't feel
me
with a with a warm sort of fuzzy glowy
happy bouncy feeling if that makes sense
so let's take a look
max regions per frame if I was to set
that up to something high what would
happen so it actually does work
incredibly incredibly slowly I would
point out so we're taking a time time in
the debug because this if you turn the
debug off runs in real time you can see
how kind of how slow it is already but
we are actually running so that's
interesting to some degree so what we
want to do now is we want to see if we
can get these things working properly in
order to do that I'm gonna have to step
in and see where we're at
for how the collation goes so I'm going
to try stepping in here and seeing what
happens so when we actually start up
frame things I want to see let's start
by just seeing what the frame bar scale
is because that'll give us a little bit
oh well you know what that was kind of a
dumb thing that I did now that I think
about it too so one of the stupid things
I just one of the things I was thinking
is I was meant to keep whatever the
largest one of this was whatever the
largest clock range was and I did not do
that
that was kind of dumb and so I'm gonna
go ahead and assume something more like
this here where we just go okay this
will be the frame bar scale and I'm only
gonna keep it I'm going to say if the
frame bar scale right if this guy here
is greater than this then I'll keep it
so I'll allow it to get kind of you know
progressively wider who wants to that's
what I meant to do otherwise what it's
going to do is just take the last frames
time and make it do that and so just
wanted to fix that while we're still in
there again not really probably what we
want to do at the end of things but
we'll do it
wait for now okay so I'm just want to
see what our frame bar scale ends up
being at the end of all of this so I'm
gonna go ahead and set it to here I'll
just step out and then I'm going to take
a look at like what I'm just gonna
inspect some of these values so I can
get a little bit of a feel for what's
going on so the frame bar scale I'm
gonna look at what one over the frame
bar scale is which will give me some
notion of what its size is so that's
about 47 million that's the totally
reasonable value because remember these
are TTS CSR in clocks so I that seems
okay I'm like okay with that value and
so if we take a look at the frames
themselves if I see I'm like okay so
there's 62 regions there's two what
looked like fairly reasonable begin and
end clock times here are the regions
themselves there's 62 of them here's
laying index 0 it goes from here to here
again that seems like okay like that
doesn't seem that doesn't seem
ridiculous so it doesn't look like we're
computing anything ridiculous right now
so let's go ahead and take a look at the
drawing of this when we actually go to
draw it so I can see because we're not
seeing anything right now so you know we
never we don't have any tested drawing
code for it either so it could just be
that I did something stupid here or
wasn't really thinking through how it
goes or how it should go
so let's take a look here we are at our
first region that we're going to draw so
I'm gonna go ahead and look at what it
includes here's the min T here is the
max T again our frame bar scale oops
debug state oh well I already pulled it
out into scale so there we go so let's
take a look at one point no F over scale
that seems wrong that doesn't seem like
what I what I saw before right it was a
much more reasonable value when I looked
at it just moments ago
so where is that coming from I would
like to know hmm I say so it must have
just only been the first frame that it
was sensible I suppose it's also
possible that since we were in the debug
timing code it would be different
ah you know what else is true we don't
well no that's not true either
hmm so I want to take a closer look at
that but in the interest of focusing on
other things first I'm gonna set this to
a hard-coded value so that I know that
it will not be part of the issue if you
will so I'm just going to assume
something like 50 million right
I'm gonna sue Mike 50 million per frame
jimena cycles because if you think about
like how many cycles there might be if
you're doing say 30 frames a second and
you're on a 2 gigahertz machine or
something like that that's gonna be that
right which is you know 60 million or
something like this so that seems
totally fine as a value so I'm gonna set
it to that so that we just have some
known base and we could take it out and
then we can worry about calculating our
scale a little bit later yeah so let's
break that all right so the question is
why aren't we getting some more
reasonable values you can actually see
that there were some values there but
there just be with little blips so let's
go ahead and and take a look again let's
sort of step into that got a well we're
just about out of time so I'm just going
to step through this one time with the
drawing so I can take a look at what
it's actually doing and then we'll pick
this up tomorrow
okay so here we are with our first
region we have a region index which is
just which number it is we grab out
whatever color is happening there should
probably get the colors in a better way
too but and so that's fine we take a
look at what the this min Y and this max
Y are and they're relatively same value
same problem is the clock values are
small enough that they don't span any
actual space right and then we draw them
so the question is are all of our values
coming out that way so let's take a look
as we come through the next time yeah so
these just don't take up very much time
at all right
so I don't know if that just means I'm
being overzealous with the amount of
cycles but it should be counting the
entire outside cycles which means it
should have been somewhat close to that
value that I was suggesting there but it
clearly isn't so I'm not sure why we'll
have to take a look and find out which
indeed yeah so we're almost at the end
of the regions so yeah I don't know why
we are so far off there that doesn't
really make a whole lot of sense to me
because I feel like this scale should be
roughly correct if that makes sense I
also don't know why there's so many of
those so that also suggests that we
probably have a different we probably
have a bug in there as well because
there shouldn't probably be 64 different
things open and closing that doesn't
really you know honest on a single on a
single frame I don't know doesn't seem
that likely
I guess across all the threads maybe
that's maybe that's possible across all
the threads maybe but I doesn't sound
right so if we take a look here opening
clock - begin clock event clock - we can
clock that looks like the right values
to me still and so the only thing that I
don't know about is is is this is the
frame bar scale incorrect and I don't
know oh well it occurs to me though that
we don't ever multiply by the height
here so our scale factor is actually
missing this value so maybe it's
actually fine right because it needs to
divide by the the bar scale and then
multiply out to the chart height so
actually that could have just been
largely chalked up to that bug which
which does seem like like an oversight
however let's let's go ahead and we go
through here
yeah um so yeah looking at this we still
are getting fairly nonsensical results
out of this though because we should be
seeing a bar for every frame and we're
totally not seeing that right like this
is this is clearly not making any sense
in terms of of the individual frames
themselves yeah so I'm gonna leave that
because like I said we're out of time
I'm gonna go to the QA and I believe I
believe tomorrow we should it should be
relatively trivial for us to just debug
that part and get it up into a good
shape which would be nice because I
think that's mostly it for getting
something good on the screen and then we
can just start focusing on how we want
to like you know be able to pick from
the data and like switch between a
couple of different ways of viewing it
so that we can see what's going on and
that's where stuff which I think will be
nice all right so that's pretty good
assuming we can do it tomorrow I'm gonna
go ahead and go to the QA and see if
people have questions if you have a
question about what we are doing please
put Q : the front of it so that I can
see it
insofar as is there going to be debug
visualization of the asset memory chunks
yeah I would like to do the same thing
for memory as we're doing for time so
that we can see not not necessarily just
the memory asset memory chunks but also
the other memory chunks as well said -
can you make a mini episode about
project management outsourcing freelance
hiring programming is great but making
game takes more if not can you point to
good resource on the topic that's not my
expertise that you'd have to ask someone
who does that sort of thing for a living
do use the same memory model as in
hammer here when writing utilities or
meta programs or do you just malloc and
it wouldn't matter because the thing
runs once does its thing and closes so
when you're metaprogramming you
basically so the point of meta
programming is to get all the benefits
that you normally get from going to sort
of like uploaded crappy thing like
templates or something without the
bloated crappiness so actually what you
do in meta programming is you just have
all of the stuff that you want for a
memory allocation and data structures so
like you know do you want bite you know
AVL tree do you want hash table do you
want a Reena allocator do you want
reference County allocator I mean heck
if you even you want garbage collection
whatever you want you can implement
those systems and then since your meta
programming it's free for you to just
basically wave a magic wand and say bonk
this section works like this and the
Medeco just generates that thing for you
because I I daddy is the right way to
program in my opinion I you know my my
objection to C++ programming with
templates like that is that templates
are fundamentally a bad meta programming
system it's not that you don't want to
be able to just write a linked list once
and then use it that's exactly what you
want to do in programming the problem is
see much less doesn't give you any way
because it's so lousy as a language
right so when you say like what kind of
every man should use when you remember
metaprogramming well you just you pick
whatever is appropriate for the job and
it's a lot easier than what I'm doing
here where I have to hand code things
because I don't once you do it on a meta
scale you don't have to worry about how
expensive it is to implement you only
have to worry about how expensive it is
to run and you can pick the thing that
is the least expensive to run in that
case that does the thing that you want
and that's fundamentally how programming
should but does not work because we
don't have good languages clover fly
what are the pros and cons of viewing
debug information real time versus
logging them and viewing them after the
fact speed is number one as we've
already seen you know it takes up a
significant amount of the frame time
potentially to run through all this
debug information because we're dumping
lots and lots of debug events at the
moment and you want to be able to dump a
lot of them so speed is one for lack of
a better term accessibility on the on
the developers workstation not sure how
else to put it but a typical situation
in professional game development is that
I may not be running the game on the
same machine that I'm that is that I'm
working that the game that I'm like
actively developing on so the example
would be like if I'm going to develop
this game for PlayStation 4 so your
drilling campaign here hero PlayStation
4 well the PlayStation 4 dev kit thing
may not have like a mouse and keyboard
hooked up to it or any way of
interacting with it in a good way right
and so if you have a way of just sending
all of those debug events over the
network so that they can come off of the
target platform and onto your dev
machine where you can then view them in
a nice little application that isn't you
know some kind of janky thing you have
to use a gamepad to view right that's
really
and so we don't have that situation hey
I mean hero but you could understand how
in a professional game development
setting you may be in a situation where
that was true so that's that's the
second thing
the third thing is historical analysis
so if we're just keeping the things in
memory and we're not dumping them out to
disk this isn't so much a benefit or a
drawback to doing it real time it's more
like why might you want to dump them to
disk even if you did like even if you
still are viewing them real time you
might want to dump into this because
then you can look if you have a
particular run of the program that you
think is weird come you know but you're
not sure you could maybe look and
compare it to another run and go you
know was this thing that I that I'm
seeing is it really that unusual or it
maybe was in previous runs like how long
has it's been happening how long do
these things typically take you know
that sort of stuff so historical
analysis either across a long run of the
same across a long timeline for the same
run or across multiple timelines for
multiple revisions of the program are
both reasons you may want that
historical data those are probably not
none of those are probably super
compelling reasons for us to do it on
him a hero because we probably won't
need that much of that but you could see
again in a professional game development
setting sometimes you have circumstances
that are going to be different that can
warrant wanting these things like
developing it for a console like having
play test data that's happening remotely
right things that we're probably not
going to encounter I am a hero which
mean that it we won't get we would not
get married very much value potentially
out of it money something like that
versus the time it would take a simple
minute so on handmade hero might be a
bad decision to go make that or if you
know if you're making an indie game it
might be a bad decision for you to do
that if you're talking about a game
development scenario where you're on a
team of 50 people and there's a QA
department and god knows what else is
going on you know sometimes these these
things then become valuable to do
because of these like other
circumstances that aren't similar
hmm Abner Cumbre people want you to
actually drink chocolate wine sometime
are you up for it yeah I mean I'm going
to drink chocolate wine at some time but
I can't promise that I'm going to
actually even drink a glass of it I mean
I may drink like a smallest tiny sip and
go that was absolutely disgusting
because remember I think wine is awful
so it's possible that I'll drink
chocolate wine and decide that chocolate
wine is actually good but it's also
possible that I'll think chocolate wine
tastes too much like regular wine which
I don't like are you going to indicate
in clever city no would you recommend it
I don't know I've never been Elvan
thanks for mentioning see mere addresses
a lot of my issues directly and as much
more human readable what was the get
token written for for config files
doesn't seem like 4c code yeah it's for
config files so it's for stuff that's
like through equals you know number
semicolon foo equals string comma
another string comma number semicolon
right so like little like expressions
but no like functions or things like
that
how will you do bug the OpenGL direct3d
stuff when you will ship so are you
talking about so we don't use any OpenGL
directory at the moment are you talking
about once we do once we write OpenGL
directory stuff
the answer to how we debug it is you
know the same way you debug anything on
a GPU is like ad hoc man debugging on
GPUs is awful it's it's one of the
reasons I really don't like GPUs I wish
we didn't have them it's just the case
that that you have to do a lot of
malarkey sometimes you can use some
tools that sometimes work there's you
know there's there was pics there's you
know insight debugger and there was you
know Grem ADIZ thing and there's the GL
trace that valve made for linux there's
there's tools you can use that may help
you but a lot of times the way I do it
is just old-fashioned like test you know
set some things test to see I know that
I should see this if this happens I
don't see that okay so I know that this
isn't working it's just you know a lot
of times debugging GPU code is it's
really annoying because you can't step
into it and and I don't like that i
think it's lousy I complain about GPUs
all the time and I mean it I think
they're a bad thing for programming
they're sloppy they don't have and I
said they don't have real debugging
they're just a bad thing for programming
they're not CPUs are good and GPUs are
bad generally and so you know I hope
that maybe someday that gets rectified
and and things are more like a CPU that
have proper debugging support and you
know like I said sometimes you can get a
tool depending on your platform
depending on what card you add depending
on this depending on depending on
depending on depending on depending on
you may be able to get some tools that
you can use that are shipped by either
the vendor or some third party which
will allow you to get some semblance of
debugging maybe not like actually
stepping through things but some summits
of debugging for your GPU
and sometimes sometimes you won't have
that and you just have to roll up your
sleeves into it the old-fashioned way
TV with Thomas 426 did I misunderstand
Molly record of character or should
there be a comic today having something
to do with your project oh man so you
actually I didn't know anyone was
actually going to Molly rocket there's
no there is a test thing up there I
didn't know anyone went to it yet there
is a test page up there but actually
it'll probably be this coming Monday
that the that the updates will start
this was homie for testing I didn't know
anyone went to my rocket oh sorry but
yes you interpreted it roughly correctly
actually the first announcements will
actually be about handmade hero but then
there will be information about our
project so yes starting this coming
Monday I'm still ironing out CSS issues
this this is also not actually quite
what the site looks like yet like I said
it's a test page the site is a little
more designed now and has some
navigation and stuff in it so I was kind
of working that stuff out so this coming
Monday will be the first post and then
every Monday thereafter there'll be a
new post with information on stuff that
we're doing
let me see if there any mark topics
about what we were looking on
okay so I don't see any other questions
that are specifically about what we were
doing so since we're roughly out of time
I'm going to go ahead and wrap up here
it looks like anything else just yeah
okay so yeah anyway if you if you do
want sorry I again like I said I didn't
realize that anyone looks at this page
yet I was going to announce it as soon
as we had the the website design done we
have the content ready for it so we
could have actually posted the thing
today and started our updates today but
web development being what it is I'm
still not really done with all of this
stuff that's necessary for like you know
the CSS awesomeness and all that stuff
but yeah it will start the updates and
like I said the first one will actually
the first one possibly two will actually
be about handmade hero because there's
some announcements I have to make about
that that have kind of been backed up
because we did we didn't have a website
and then we'll start a little article
series about the game we're doing at my
rocket that'll kind of like lead up to
an announcement of that as well so yeah
alright but that said we go ahead and
wind down the stream here save this guy
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for another episode of hand made here
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to follow along at
home with the source code you always can
pre-order the actual game and it comes
to the source code if so if you want to
kind of like do your own experiments
where they'd learn from it and stuff
like that you could do that and I update
source code every night so you can
always stay up to date with whatever I'm
doing we also have a patreon page if you
just want to support the video series
you can subscribe to that we have a
forum site you can go to if you want to
ask questions or like look at an
annotated episode guide that people have
put together that's pretty cool that
kind of stuff it's all up there I highly
recommend checking it out we also have a
tweet bot that tweets the schedule at
you so if you want to know when the
streams gonna be live you want to catch
it live that's the place to go for that
I will be back here tomorrow 5:00 p.m.
Pacific Daylight Time where we will play
around with our charts and kind of get
the charts working I think we pretty
much did all the work that needs to
happen today so I think we're just
basically out of debugging and then from
there we can sort of start to build a
little bit of a UI on there so we can
kind of like have a way to you know
click through things and inspect things
hover over something and see what
function it is that's taking the time
that sort of stuff so we'll give that a
shot and play around the business a
little bit that's about it so until then
I hope that everyone has oops that was
supposed to be closed until then I hope
everyone has fun programming and I'll
see you guys on the Internet take it
easy everyone