start hello everyone welcome to hand
made here on the show Rico to complete
games live on twitch from scratch no
libraries no engines so that we know
everything that goes on nothing hides
from us we are in there with the with
the flashlight looking under the bed
scaring the monsters away even if
they're particularly scary monsters we
just generally are completely
unpersuaded by that because we're kind
of big and gnarly and have hairy fangs
ourselves anyway if you would like to
follow along with today's episode and
you have pre-ordered the game on
handmade hero org please don't forget to
download the source code from the link
in your email and you will want to
unpack de 94 is source code I believe
that's correct date IV I'm sorry day 93
source code so that you can do de 94
which is what rond today that is all you
should need to do and then you will be
exactly where I am so assuming that that
is all good with you I would like to say
a few words about where we left off just
so everyone it's on the same page so
what we did last week is we basically
started our renderer and we did a bunch
of stuff on it as you can see in the
middle of the screen now kind of
ridiculous we don't really have an
excuse for why a tree would be rotating
in place other than it was our test fit
map and you can kind of see right now
that we've actually implemented texture
mapping so that we can freely rotate and
scale things and we did it with the
bilinear filtering so you actually get
kind of a nice smooth version there as
well now we're gonna talk about
something today that normally I don't
think I would really talk about two
completely honest with you but we're
talking about it have to be test of Wan
Chun who made me promise that I would
talk about it on the stream so here we
go it's it's gamma correction and
somebody actually asked about it in one
of the Q&amp;A s they didn't ask for it by
name but I believe they were asking
about it sort of indirectly and so at
least we know there's one person out
there who wanted to know about it and so
it won't be completely useless let's put
it that way
and it's very near and dear to one's
heart apparently so he really wanted
everyone to know so we're gonna do it
and what the person who asked in the Q&amp;A
they were saying they had seen some
video about how color blending is done
incorrectly on computers and he said
like since you're doing this all from
scratch you have the opportunity to do
it correctly so one thing that I should
point out is when they say that blending
on computers is done incorrectly they're
actually just talking about paint
programs games actually do do blending
correctly games we have been doing
blending correctly for a long time
actually for probably about four years
gamma corrected pipelines have been in
the works you know I probably since
half-life 2 certainly in the last of us
and and what was it called uncharted 2
those were all using gamma corrected
pipelines so that they could
specifically do color blending correctly
always right and so games have actually
been way out ahead on this and yes it's
true that people like Adobe and stuff
may not be doing any of this stuff
correctly and that's I think what the
video that you were referring to is
talking about because they don't do
stuff gamma corrected in a lot of places
and there's plenty of art packages that
don't do gamma correction properly but
games are not really one of them
you know maybe 2d games don't do it as
much because it doesn't really matter
but but certainly 3d games where it's
very important for lighting and for HDR
high dynamic range imaging which games
use nowadays that that stuff is really
where you got to get your dammit correct
so so games actually have been doing
gamma correctly and you know you know
I'm not certainly not a gamma expert but
I'll try to give you what the idea is so
that you know you can be aware of it
maybe do some reading on your own and
then I'll show you how we can sort of
implement it a little bit in our
software rasterizer in our hardware
version will do it 100% correctly it's
actually really easy to do correctly in
there a hundred percents probably a
little wrong term but very close to
hundred-percent so basically here is a
chart I don't know if you guys can see
this in fact maybe I'll I'll go ahead
and just play with this this camera
setting here for a second let's see if I
can do this here so if I if I pick
webcam
right can you guys see this chart you
see that you see what it says there so
at the bottom right on the x-axis
it says gray level right and that is
like the pixel value okay that's like
what we're sending like 0 to 255 okay
and then on the on the y-axis there and
see if I can get a little closer on the
y-axis
it says brightness in candelas per meter
squared right
so that is actually gosh darn it we need
to turn off of our sources hold on
second I need to turn off these
assertions I left them in there so we
would know but okay so candelas per
meter squared is the brightness that the
monitor is actually putting out there
okay and what you can see is this does
not form a line right it forms a curve
it forms a curve not a straight line
which means that as you change the
values that you're sending to the
monitor the pixel values they actually
get a lot less bright for every
increment that you use when you're down
at the low end right so down in here if
you add one you know one or two to your
pixel value it actually doesn't get much
brighter right whereas on the other side
like up here when you add one or two to
the value it actually gets significantly
brighter by comparison right does that
make some sense that's what monitors do
and so basically a oh dear the focus is
all gone crazy
hello focus focus on me there we go
mm-hmm let's go back to the programming
stream there okay so that curve is how
monitors operate we could go into the
history of why they operate that way but
you know honestly I'm probably the wrong
person tell that see here I got to start
a new day so we can do some drawing on
the blackboard so here we are day 94
oops
day 94
gamma and as you can see you know the
curve on that thing
Kuras candelas per meter squared which
is basically like a measure of
brightness just like it's you know
candelas are a measure of brightness per
meter squared means you know normalized
to an area how big of an area that's
coming out of the screen right and here
is the actual pixel value it was down at
the bottom right and you notice that
that that thing went like that right it
kind of like had a lot of resolution
down here so you could change a little
bit and have it not changed very much
we'd have a lot of control down here and
then you had very little control up here
so you have like you know high control
down here and low control down here
right and the reason that they did this
as far as I know is well actually to the
truth I don't really know the reason why
I did it I'm not gonna pretend I know
you should go read about it I believe
that the the reason it stays this way is
because your eye is more sensitive to
contrast in darker areas than it is in
brighter areas I believe this is just an
aspect of the human visual system that
basically says that if you have two
bright colors too bright you know color
we can take out a too bright gray values
next to each other and to dark gray
values next to each other a small
difference in the dark gray values will
be much more evident to your eye than a
small difference in the light values
right so basically you can see
differences here
less then you can see them here right so
they put more control in there so that
you'd have more ability to specify finer
shades of those dark Gray's instead of
putting it linear where you'd have the
same control up here which just wasn't
that useful right so why do we care
about this at all why are we even
bringing this up why does one care about
this right so why does one care and why
does the person who asked the quest
what was the video they're referring to
why did the video care so the answer is
because maths is the answer right if
this is the question mass is the answer
the problem with this curve is that a
lot of the things that we want to
compute are in brightness terms right so
if I for example want to do any
operation that I might want to do in
color space right including all of the
ones that we've currently done for
example just yesterday we did the
bilinear blend right we took four pixel
values right a b c and d and we said
let's make a little imaginary rectangle
well square in this case of out of these
we will blend between a and b linearly
we will blend between C and D linearly
and then we will blend between the
result linearly in order to get what the
color should be here now implicit in all
of this was us saying this word right
here linear we were expecting that as we
blended between a and B that if we were
to for example go halfway in between
them we would have a result that looked
let's say half of a plus half of B
that's what we wanted to look like so if
this was say 25% the brightness that the
monitor could output and this was 75% we
wanted this to be 50% right does that
make some sense another way to say that
might be if this was 0% and this was a
hundred percent we want this to be 50%
as well right any balanced range on
either side we want it to come out in
the middle of those two right but what's
actually going to happen when we do that
blend well here is where we're doing the
blend we're doing the blend in pixel
value space right and so let's take a
look at what happens here and
unfortunately I you know it may not come
out that great because you know I didn't
draw the world's most perfect diagram
right but here are the two endpoints of
the pixel value curve right so if I were
to
do that bilinear blend again in the
space are just a linear blend in the
space we just talked about in pixel
space in the color space I would get
here as my 50% value right this is 0
this is 255 I'm gonna get 128 it's gonna
be right there right in the middle
well what brightness that I did I
blended black with white essentially
right as white as the monitor can do and
as black as the matter could do that's
what I blended and I ended up with that
that is like dark gray right it's
nowhere near half the brightness half
the brightness would be up here right so
the result of not taking gamma into
account is that all of this maths
break they all break because we were
doing them in a space and the math is
certainly correct for that space but our
understanding of what that space meant
is wrong we thought we were getting a
brightness blend we're getting a blend
in some space that has nothing to do
with the brightness right it's a totally
different space and when we map it to
the brightness we get a completely wrong
value does that make sense hopefully
that makes some sense so if we actually
want our math to properly be able to
blend things together what we need to do
is undo the effects of this curve right
and unfortunately when you think about
it you're like well there's no way to
really undo the effects of this curve at
some kind of fundamental level because
the monitor outputs this curve and there
ain't no way you're gonna change the
monitor the user already bought the
monitor and you can't really do anything
about that right so what we need to do
is essentially account for the fact that
the user bought this monitor and take
into account all of the ramifications
that go with it now when I say user
unfortunately I don't just mean the
player okay that is one person but
there's another person that matters here
and that is the artist so both your
artist and your player have monitors and
those monitors
look like this so when the artist makes
an image they are actually making the
image in that gamete space right
assuming they're using Photoshop on this
default settings I believe it is called
srgb is the Adobe standard which is sort
of a modified it's it's basically that
gamma curve it's a little tweaked but
that's basically what it is right and so
the artist actually made an image that
was in that space okay they painted it
looking at the monitor so they've tuned
it to be in this space already
and so when we've lit it to the screen
if we didn't do any math on it it would
be correct right so we sort of had a
case where our input right is in this
space this isn't this is an sRGB space
right and our output also needs to be in
srgb space because the monitor is going
to do it right the monitor needs to see
srgb the artist makes srgb so if there's
nothing in between we don't have to
worry but the instant that we do
anything to color values and expect them
to be linear such as a bilinear blend
which you've already seen we need to do
for texture mapping in here where we are
doing them where the maths happen we
have a problem so what we need to do if
we want to correct this problem is we
must do the maths in a linear space we
want to take them out of srg space
that's RGB space actually should have
drawn that a little bit differently
maths linear we want to take them out of
srgb and put them into a linear space
then we want to take them for the linear
space and put them into the srgb space
again when we are finished right so that
is actually the gamma correct pipeline
and it is what Triple A games do is what
a competent engine does if you went and
use the Unreal 4 engine I'm sure it does
it that way I assume unity does now I
don't think they did originally but I
with their photo realistic shader
updates they did I they would have had
to have done this so I'm assuming they
do it now and really anyone who knows
what they're doing does this it's very
easy to do graphics hardware actually
built-in now you just have to turn it
all right but since we're in a software
rasterizer we have to do it so how do we
do it right what exactly are we going to
do right and so what we have to do is we
have to figure out a way to basically
straighten out this curve on when we are
about to operate on things so we have to
be able to straighten it out and then we
have to flatten it again right so we
have to be able to kind of like do this
curve you know in and out right and so
what we thankfully this srgb right
has an actual definition and you can
look it up right sRGB where they've
actually sort of defined what the curve
is and we're probably not going to be
able to use the curve exactly unless we
choose to use a lookup table it'll
depend but we can certainly look at what
the curve is defined to be and then try
to come up with some approximation
thereof now this is a lot more
information than probably I would have
hoped for yeah yeah so this has got all
of the transforms for how they're
computing it yeah so this is a little
bit so basically if we wanted to do
exactly srgb which you know there's the
it's basically a fairly complicated
color space transform here right they're
transforming the colors slightly into
different space and then they're doing
the the gamma-d code here they've got
the exponents listed blah blah blah like
all this stuff if we actually wanted to
do all of this in a software rasterizer
we'd have to do it with the table right
we'd have to have a lookup table that
translates gamma values and I don't know
whether we want to do a lookup table or
not yeah I don't actually know if we
want to do that or not so let me let me
see if I can find just a standard
monitor gamma thing because you're
usually what you do is you assume that
the gamma is about 2.2 and that's an
easier thing that I could sort of show
you how we could do in software right so
in fact you can see it right here
right
the equation that typically ends up
happening where is it
well they kind of wrote it in a way that
I don't love I'm just gonna write it
myself I kind of wanted Wikipedia I
always go to Wikipedia because I want to
show some math and I feel like it always
lets me down a little bit right like you
know what I can do
here's one thing I could do here's what
I'll point you to so that you can read
about this on your own
that's what I'll do I'll point you to
something that's that's better than this
because I do know a place so let me see
gamma correct rendering naughty naughty
dog 2010 here we go so I believe here
you go so these are the slides from the
Uncharted presentation I think they gave
it GDC at one point where they were
explaining how they were doing
gamma correct rendering right and you
can see they drew in that that gamma
there and all the sorts of stuff and
they kind of show kind of nicely what
the math is here relatively well I think
oh well maybe maybe I'm wrong about that
yeah not going my way today I mean here
is basically the equation which is
saying you know that it's it's whatever
the color value is raised to the 2.2
power but I was kind of hoping they
would just have written it out and they
didn't write out the reverse one you can
see they have it here where where
they've got the translation right so two
point two and point four or five which
are the powers that you would go back
and forth right point four five is one
over two point two all right so I don't
know I'll still leave you with this
recommendation because I think it's
probably a good thing to read I remember
it being a pretty good sort of way of
learning about it a little bit right and
you know hopefully you can snap this if
you can pause the video or something on
the YouTube you can snap this guy and
and take a look at here it's John hables
the guy's name and and really like I
said this is kind of the slide that's
that's pretty good here right which is
kind of saying like okay you know if
you're if you've got trying to think if
I see if they've got a
yeah they still down I feel like the
actual presentation had better slides
than this so maybe actually go try to
download the actual talk which I don't
know it should also also be up here oh
well well anyway I did the best I could
I apologize so we'll just leave it at
that and I'll move on here so basically
what ends up happening is instead of
trying to mimic srgb exactly which would
require a table lookup what we can sort
of do is say well this monitor curve is
generally expected to be an output of
the form pow right and I can don't even
have to I guess right pal but I can just
say it is the color value right whatever
it is like the are the G or the B so you
know like R or whatever to the 2.2 power
right so the thing that you actually
this is actually what's going on when
the monitor is going to to display
things right
you've actually got it raising it to the
2.2 power now the 2.2 power is a little
bit problematic obviously because it's a
pal function it's actually you know
raising raising a color value to an
explicit power is a little bit daunting
but potentially in a software rasterizer
again that would be something we'd kind
of think about table driving but what
the compromise that I reached with wom
when he was demanding that I cover this
on the stream was 2.2 is pretty close to
2 right so a curve in fact we could
probably I don't know if Wolfram Alpha
or I think Google made actually do graph
X to the 2 and X to the 2.2 can it do
that so if you look at these curves you
know they're not bad especially in the
range of 1 to 1 I don't know if they
have a way of me sort of explicitly
saying I want to see just that area but
like let's zoom in here right like so
and you can kind of see like from the
area of that we care about from 0 to 1
which is really the color area there to
care about they're really pretty darn
close in there right you can see there
they're not bad right and so it's
certainly a you know one I was basically
saying well you know I don't know that
I'm going to do POW - - you know maybe
we
table drive it I'd really like to keep
tables out of the software rasterizer is
possible so we're not constantly doing
fetches into them etc etc and so to
point to was kind of settled on as not
being possible or something I didn't
really want to do but but two would be
doable and the reason that two is doable
is because squaring something is easy
right that's just R times R and that's
an easy computation for us to do and the
inverse right because we need both of
these right we need to be able to put it
into the space and out of the space so
we would need to be able to do R times R
which is easy and then we do be able to
do square root of R which used to be
actually pretty tough
but nowadays is a lot easier because
processors actually have accelerated
square root of our pretty well now like
Intel processors actually don't have
that hard of a time computing square
root of R because it gets used a lot in
like normalization right like you've
seen us do it on the stream where we had
to do like ok we have a vector and we
want to know how long it is right it's x
squared plus y squared Square rooted
right so you need that quantity a lot
for normalization or to tell how long
things are and stuff like that so this
ended up getting accelerated quite a bit
so R times R and square root of R things
that we could do pretty quickly and you
know maybe if we're feeling super
motivated to try and get closer to 2.2
we could do some fancy numerical stuff
there and try to do that but at the very
least I said well ok that's not that big
of a deal like we can definitely handle
that
so really all this boils down to is when
the artist has the colors right when
they when they put these colors in there
we need to take them out of this space
by doing the forward operation to put
them into linear space so we need to
basically have right here right
we need srgb to linear right and then
right here after we're done doing all of
our operations we need another thing
which is linear - srgb
right and there's two ways that you
could envision this pipeline and they
make sense in different scenarios right
one way is that the frame buffer itself
is linear okay so meaning remember
what we're doing here is we start with
uh with like a canvas right a blank
screen and we start bleeding stuff on to
it right we've got whatever we got trees
and ground and hero's and whatever we
start bleeding stuff onto it right and
all of these things are in srgb sources
but the question is what is this what is
the frame buffer right because we have
two choices when we pull things from
sRGB to linear we can write that linear
into the frame buffer directly or we can
do the blend on it and then convert it
back to srgb and write the srgb into the
frame buffer so the frame buffer can
either be a linear frame buffer or it
can be an sRGB frame buffer and we have
to decide which we want to use right in
our case because we're a software
renderer and because we're not doing a
lot of 3d constructive stuff we're
taking bitmaps that are mostly finished
art maybe doing a little relighting on
them and then you know bleeding them on
top of each other basically we probably
wouldn't get that much use out of a
linear frame buffer right so we'd only
be talking about the need to sort of if
we were trying to save that conversion
to srgb
right which is to say if we're trying to
save these in and outs so that we only
do the in we only do the srgb to linear
and then we only you know we do all our
blitz on top of each other and then we
only once at the very end take the frame
buffer and when we put it out to the
screen right at the very end we'll
translate it back to srgb right and so
that would save repeated transforms when
things you know overlap each other when
we're drawing on top of each other that
would save a bunch of out transforms
right that would save a bunch of linear
to srgb transfer owns but my assumption
and I could be wrong about this my
assumption is that mostly we're going to
care about bandwidth and in order to
store a linear frame buffer we would
need at least 16 bits per pixel per
channel sorry instead of the 8 bits per
channel that we're using now because 8
bits per channel simply isn't enough to
store linear color without banding and
the reason for that is exactly this up
here right 8 bits are sort of enough to
avoid banding
you are in this curve because it puts
the resolution where the resolution
belongs which is at the bottom end right
but if you were to straighten this out
you would not have enough resolution
down here to prevent banding so you need
to set store more bits of precision in
order to actually prevent the banding
you have to go up to 16 right so I don't
want to do that because that would
double the bandwidth requirements for
our reads and writes to the frame buffer
which I don't want to do right now there
are ways we can get around that there
are lots of other things you could
consider there so if we really thought
for some reason we really needed a
linear frame buffer it's entirely
possible that we could structure our
rasterizer around that but I don't
really think that we need it for
anything so I suspect that what we will
want to do is do the in and out on the
blit because we'll already because we're
soft reservoir try to minimize our
overdraw by doing some intelligent
things probably and so I think that
that's probably just the right way to go
because that'll save on the bandwidth
for us save on the cache solution
there's just less in the mix there and
this should be hopefully relatively
cheap to do that extra half of the in
and out that's the hope anyway right so
yeah so that's basically what we're all
we really have to do you know and like I
said try and maybe if you can take a
look at this this is this is really not
unfortunately this is not kind of what I
had hoped for III I guess I should try
and look for the slides because I don't
know I want to point the slides had more
stuff on them and I was kind of hoping
to point you to that as an extra
resource that I know people usually ask
afterwards if there's a thing they can
read about and there is it's a pretty
good presentation I just don't know
where the actual slides are and I was
kind of hoping that maybe someone would
find them
yeah I don't know so I'll look one more
time is there is there a slides here
they are here here we go let's see here
we go so this is another one maybe snap
this address if you can to take a look
at because yeah see there's a lot more
slides in here - he just had like the
highlights in the other one and he shows
like more examples of things right and
that sort of stuff so I don't know I
just I feel like it's a pretty good way
to kind of get more comfortable with it
to look through this whole thing and he
shows kind of like okay you know how
it's stored and how its output and and
that sort of stuff right so yeah alright
so what we want to do here right is we
essentially want to to mimic and of
course again like I said I'm not a gamma
expert so you always have to take these
with a grain of salt and if I make a
mistake somewhere hopefully someone will
catch me because I I'm not you know the
kind of guy who does a lot of this kind
of graphics programming but what we want
to do is we want to first mimic what the
monitor is doing to make uniform
brightness out of these values right so
if the monitor is doing red to the 2.2
right and we're saying we're gonna do a
simpler version which is red to the -
we're going to pretend that's what it's
doing we want to do red to the 2.2 to
get us out of srgb and put us into
linear space we then do all of our
operations that we need to do with math
there then we do the square root of that
right to get us back to srgb space and
we write that down
okay so it's really really simple for us
to implement this you know sort of not
full srgb but very close kind of
approximation because if we go take our
render group and we look at what we were
already doing with draw rectangles
slowly if we want to come in here and do
that really all we have to do is take
these color values that we were
extracting right ABCD right like that
all we have to do is make a function
that's basically like you know Texel a
equals srgb to linear Texel a right this
is all we really need to do
something that takes them out of here
right kcd so that will turn them into
values that are light linear right so
this is you know go from s srgb to light
linear space or we could call it
brightness linear linear brightness
space I don't know what you want to call
it maybe we should just yeah it's there
are some other little tweaky bits which
is like brightness is kind of a
measurement that combines RG and B and
maybe you could argue this isn't quite
linear brightness but it's at least
gamma corrected right it's so we're not
you know we're not having that gamma
curve in there anymore
so let's call it let's call it linear
brighten his space just to sort of put
some scare quotes around it then we do
all of our math which is assuming that
it's in linear right and then when we
are done with that and we want to write
it out we need to convert them back
right now one thing that's kind of
annoying here is these are not
normalized values these are still 255
you know these are still 255 0 to 255
and presumably if we want to do the
squaring here we would really prefer
them to be in zero to one space so we
probably also want to do the inversion
here so maybe like we want to call this
srgb 255 to linear one right because
we're going from 0 55 to that one right
so we'll do that then what we do is
we'll do our operations in that space
and I believe that if we do it in that
space we can now get rid of some of this
this additional the 255 miss that we
were doing so for example si is actually
just correct now it doesn't need to be
divided by 255 because we're now
actually correcting that our source
pixel when we read that in write R I'm
sorry our desk pixel when we read that
in also has to be corrected if our frame
buffer is in srgb space we need to do
the exact same thing there so if we go
ahead here and do
a desk you know to read that in when we
create that and let's see here that
needs to be rgba see here so we have our
we have G oops G B and a there we go
correct our is 16 so now we need our G B
a there we go sorry got to keep that
correct
RGBA yeah there we go got a Gutterman
love that Intel that sorry not Intel
that window is ordering there all right
so we get that desk fix it pixel in and
now we need to be able to do that as
well so that we put that into linear
space so and then what we want to do is
we want to do all of our other
operations on that now I'm going to go
ahead and actually I'm gonna I'm gonna
actually go ahead and change the SAS RS
GSD stuff here to just be like Texel our
Texel g Texel be and similarly like the
desk here we'll do desk are dest g test
be and so that looks about right now we
actually have to before we write them
out we have to convert them back right
so we have to you know convert this
vector we're going to have to do
something here where we say the the this
like desk 255 or something is linear one
- srgb
255 right and we're gonna have to have
this in some actual space that we can do
here like you know this will actually be
I guess blended maybe this will be
blended 255 these are better names for
these things blended
there we go and so if I go ahead and
make this one now into an aggregate
there's the a so that goes at the end
here's the our G and the B and so that
would give me a more correct pipeline so
this is yeah this is go from s 1 to B 2
linear space this is OK and that is as
well and this is to go from that linear
space back to the srgb space right so
now we actually have to implement those
functions obviously since we don't have
them yet so we got srgb to linear and
oops got a couple bugs here that's an A
and then these guys have to be blended
to 55 a or and B all right so let's go
ahead and actually put these in here so
we've got you know a function that we
want that will turn our our color values
from srgb to d5 to linear and then from
linear to srgb to 55 so in this case
like I said what we want to do is create
a result here that's going to be squared
right just like the monitor would do and
we don't touch the Alpha because the
Alpha is not a brightness value the
Alpha is just you know a very the Alpha
is strictly a value which tells us how
much we want to blend as a percentage
and so we only ever operates in that
linear space anyway so we're just going
to assume at least for the time being
that our inputs are in linearly encoded
alpha although you know who knows really
it's hard to say what alpha is encoded
in depending on what the program it came
out of
you know but it should generally be
considered a linear value like if it's
coverage it would be linear and stuff
like that so our G and D values are
going to be you know just whatever the
input was squared there so trying to
mimic what the monitor is doing with
that curve where it's squaring the curve
right and then when we want to take it
out of that we have to do the inverse of
that right so we have our result our
result R is going to be equal to see
that R Square rooted
all right like so and the a is going to
be a pass through just like it was
before okay and then we return the
result now in this process I said we've
got that 255 in there as well right and
so one thing that we want to do before
we do this and in fact do I have a
squaring function I usually write one I
suspect I did yes we actually should
just write it like this there we go okay
so what we want to do here is we want to
convert this first right to that that
that inverse 255 value right we want to
be able to turn this into a value that's
from zero to one before we square it
right I said that that was going to be
baked into this routine that's why it's
s RGB 255 to linear one right so it does
that and the same is going to be true
here where we want to blow it back out
to that because you know we said that
that was how this is going to work right
and we'll go ahead and do that here
so that way we've got that sort of pre
baked in now I believe
everything should be kosher now but I
kind of made a lot of modifications
there so we may end up with a totally
messed up tree yeah as as as one might
have guessed so let's go ahead and go
through that a little more with a little
bit more of a fine-tooth comb and try to
make sure that everything is kosher and
maybe step through it as well just the
bug all of that so let's make sure that
we've got this stuff working properly so
we want to be able to square our values
that come in our our G's and B's they go
through and we're going to we I said I
wasn't going to spray the Alpha and yet
I did square the Alpha make sure that
doesn't happen okay there we go
so that's fixed so right we don't want
to square the alpha we just want to
square the color values and we want to
square them after they converted didn't
converted to the range 0 to 1 right so
we can do that now we don't necessarily
have that what we could do instead we
could still do everything in two to five
space I suppose it's just I'm guessing
that we since we're gonna have to do
that multiply either way we might as
well do it first what we could do is
square them and then multiply by a by
the inverse of 25 to scale them back
down to 0 to 35 but just seems like you
might as well put them to 255 first that
you can do all your operations in the 0
to 1 range which usually makes it a lot
easier so anyway I also think I can't
remember if there's well no I guess
there might not be any accelerated way
it's a necessity to do that you may just
have to do the same your multiply anyway
so you know off we go that looks okay to
me the result here is doing that sort of
- putting that 255 back in there which
is what we want and it's passing the
Alpha through which is also what we want
because we don't actually want the alpha
to be touched in any way in terms of
modifying there oh that's that's not
right though I still want that in there
oops ok yeah and so let's take a look at
the rest of it here you are rectangles
slowly and we'll go to about 6:15 today
since we started pretty late
where are we alright so we grab our
texels out there is our Texel pointers a
b c and d man we've got to stop I've
gotta stop those assertions they're
killing me so I'm gonna go ahead and
just say that we're not gonna start on
those anymore we proved we didn't fetch
outside the texture so we'll just take
those guys off for now we'll leave on
the asserts for the other stuff all
right there we go
so we read out our Texas textures here
we get our Texel a B C and D exactly we
do before we touch any of that we map if
each of those from the 255 space to the
linear space because they are in the 255
0 to 255 space which which is yes which
needs mapping so we mapped them out we
then do the bilinear blend right between
the texels by by doing just a straight
linear blend we didn't touch any of that
we grabbed the textile ABC out there
although I guess we were saying that
sort of I don't know why we we actually
were doing that let's let's just do plug
this right back in there there we go so
let's see here we grab the texels a
times that color a which is the the
which is that value that we were getting
passed in in case you modulate which
should just be 1.0 at this point
although I guess we don't know what that
color value actually is presumably it's
in its in that space there right color
yeah so those color vials are coming in
in in the 0 to 1 space as well so those
are all fine we grab the desktop by
reading from the pixel into let's see
RGB and a which looks right and then we
need to convert that from srgb to linear
so we do that we then take our
destination alpha which is here and we
compute the inverse of the source alpha
we multiply the inverse source alpha
times the dest red we add the Texel red
that we had sampled same thing with the
ji
the B so that's a one that's a inverse
source alpha one blending mode we then
compute using RSA and RDA the final
values so this this is not good though
this 255 should not be in here right
that should not be there that was a bad
that was old get rid of that we then
convert back to srgb space by taking our
blended 255 there which should multiply
by 255 and get our colorist back for us
and then we go ahead and pack in our a
and ar-ar-ar-ar-ar G and RB into pixel
so that seems like it should be
relatively straightforward I'm assuming
that we must have some kind of typo
there so I'm gonna go ahead and just set
a breakpoint so I can watch and see what
happens in there and see if I can't spot
what goes wrong so here we go in the
routine here and it should be hopefully
pretty easy to spot what goes wrong
because I mean it's all black so any
pixel that's getting computed is
basically wrong right so let's take a
look at what our Texel values end up
actually being right so if we take a
look at our Texel values they are
correctly in the range of 0 to 1 so
that's good and hopefully all of them
are right that one is as well Texel see
Texel d right so all of those guys are
in the range 0 to 1 you can see there so
so at least we know we're loading them
in operating on them in in sort of a
reasonable way for the srgb there is our
blend our bilinear blend let's take a
look at what our RSA value is which is
going to be our our source blend which
is one so our source is I guess that's
kind of odd don't you think what why why
how is that the case hold on a second
here what is our Texel dot a and our
Clara dot a
wait a minute why would our color did we
really stop on a pixel that has a color
value of one an alpha value of one
that's kind of weird don't you think I
feel like the first pixel that we
encounter should have an alpha value is
zero because it's gonna be on an edge
maybe this isn't the first one let's
find out why min - Oh 380 oh so this
isn't let's do let's do it this way I
want to I want to see somebody who's
that I want to prove to myself that
we've got an alpha value of zero at at
that first pixel that we hit so let's
take a look here so just to make sure
although that could have been it just
the first one that was included I
suppose all right hey there there we go
okay so we're all zeros here which is
good so this should leave the
destination intact which we know it
isn't so again we should be able to see
why it isn't hopefully relatively easily
our RSA value is zero what is our desk
look like this is reading out of the
frame buffer it's that lovely purple
color I'm not sure why it's how it's at
that lovely purple color that's a bit
odd to say the least because it
shouldn't be that purple color right the
only time this should be drawing it
should be drawing on top of valid stuff
so I guess it's cuz oh the first very
first frame I guess it wouldn't be
because we haven't filled our ground
patches yet so okay I can I can believe
that for now all right so we do our s
RGB - linear which again converts those
to what they should be which is one we
compute our inverse RSA which is one and
so that should leave us with basically
just the dest and nothing getting added
in right so our blended should basically
be equal to the destination there so
there's the desk
there's the blended and that is exactly
what they should be looks like and then
we're going to do our linear
RGB conversion and so that should give
us values in the range of 0 to 55 and it
totally did not so what got messed up
there what is the problem
ah well that serves me right for being
hasty you can see what the problem is
here
I wanted to square root them before I
multiply them by 255 but I actually was
multiplying by 25 first because I just
kind of like mindlessly typing that in
so that's no good definitely not good
that may be our only book let's find out
we don't really know they'll find out so
there is our tree you can now see in all
its gamma collect corrected glory our
tree sort of rotating around there of
course we don't really have any good
tests at the moment to test whether
we're gamma correcting properly so I
guess I don't know for sure that we
actually are but we are at least going
through the correct pipeline now we're
actually doing sort of the math into the
space and the map out of the space so
you know at the very least Juan will not
have to lose any sleep over it but again
like I said it's not the kind of thing
that I've ever really seen a difference
for in 2d sprite composition I've even
seen demos where people say that it
makes a difference and I didn't see the
difference so I'm not anticipating this
really doing anything for us you know I
I'm sorry I apologize to people like I
totally for HDR and 3d rendering stuff
I'm totally on board with the gamma it
definitely works and it's definitely
important but it's for 2d compositing
stuff I've just never seen the effect
and so you know I mean the only place
you're gonna see it is where we're
actually doing blends between relatively
disparate colors and you know I don't
know so again we may not have done it
quite correctly maybe we've got a bug in
there but even so it's just like you
know I don't know that there is that
much wrong
the original way to begin with anyway so
I'm not sure you know but there's really
all that much to get excited about what
we could do is we could have a little
toggle that allows us to switch it on
and off potentially and maybe see if it
makes a difference I don't know but
again not really expecting much out of
it but anyway that is the Gama and you
do want to know this it is good I mean
one is correct I should show it because
it's something you do need to know when
you start to do some more fancier
effects that you know maybe you don't do
as much in 2d stuff but that you would
do in 3d it's important and so now we've
got it out of the way at least we know
it's in there we can make sure our you
know our pipeline handles it well enough
and so so there you go we'll have to
talk about how we're gonna optimize that
when we get to the optimization stuff
because now we've got to deal with a
square root in there but it's like I
said it's not that big of a deal to
handle a square root nowadays it used to
be a big deal but it's not so much
anymore so that's really it I guess we
won't even need the extra time that I
said that I would take but that's really
all there is to it that's that's that's
the majority of it so we pretty much
just have have to do that slight bit of
work and then we're good now I wasn't
what maybe what I'll throw in at the end
here since we do have about 10 minutes
before before our hour is up what I
might do is let's go ahead and take that
color value that's getting passed in
here and actually use it so draw would
call it draw a rectangle slowly what I'd
like to do is say okay when we pass this
color value here that's not the color
value sorry when we passed this color
value here let's actually start using
that right so what we can do is we can
do sort of a modulation of the color
right we can multiply the color values
that come in with the color values that
we're reading to tint whatever it is
that we want so for example right you
know if I have something this is pretty
straightforward right but if I have a
certain amount you know if I have the r
g and b of the Texel right that's coming
in if i want to tint this I can
introduce coefficients like CR C G and C
be right that multiply
these values and if those coefficients
are 0 to 1 I can control how much blue
how much green and how much red I read
out of the texture map right so it's
pretty free for us to add a thing that
allows us into our texture maps by just
allowing this color that we were passing
in to draw the rectangle with as a solid
color before we can just use that to
actually just multiply the colors that
they come in right it's really really
straightforward for us to to be able to
implement something like that all we
would have to do is introduce here a
place where we multiply you know the
color values together right like so
because we're already multiplying in our
RSA we are already multiplying oops
that's the desk sorry we're already
multiplying by that color alpha value so
we're already doing something where
we're taking into account the pre
multiplication of it so all we really
have to do here is just multiply the
color values that we read out of the
Texel by those colors that are input and
then we content right or at least we
should be able to send tint so if you
take a look at what happens there right
where we've got our tree get our tree up
there and then I'm gonna go ahead and
and allow ourselves to sort of do it the
live code editing that we that we so
love here on the show so if I do that
coordinate system thing here where we're
passing that color I'm gonna go ahead
and pull that color out into something
that we can see a little bit more
directly so here it is alright there's
the color there it is so you can see
we've got some kind of crazy stuff in
here with still an alpha of one point
now so if I go ahead and compile that we
can now play around with this pretty
easily we could call this color angle
and we could make sure that it oscillate
s' a lot more frequently like maybe that
is you know 5.0 times the angle instead
of so just you know it cycles much more
frequently and there you can kind of see
right a much sort of clearer
demonstration
of tinting those textures right like so
we can just put a modulation in there
it's pretty much free it allows us to
kind of play with the RG and B values
after the fact which will probably be
something that we'll want to use if not
for normal stuff although you know a lot
of times you do use tinting like that
for normal stuff if not for normal
circumstances that their very least for
like special effects that kind of things
maybe where we have sort of like sprites
that want to be like you know bullets or
special effects that want to get tinted
certain colors to depend on what the
effect is you know that's a pretty cheap
way again to get more out of your art
thereby allowing them to be kind of
freely tempted and again that's an easy
thing to do the hardware does that as
well so you know it would translate
directly over to OpenGL and all that
sort of stuff so again that's pretty
easy thing we can throw in there and
then wow we've still got five minutes
left so I don't really know I guess
we'll just go to the QA because I don't
have really anything else short that I
want to start talking about at the
moment but that's pretty much that's
pretty much it for the gamma and the
color stuff I could also I guess very if
I if I throw in here the Alpha value I
could I could sort of vary the
transparency of it and we could see if
that works at all that that seems to be
working yeah looks like it now of course
one thing that I guess we didn't do is
we're not pre multiplying that alpha
properly so if we change here's the
thing I was thinking right we're
handling the preap we're handling the
Alpha by multiplying the Alpha by the
Texel egg so our destination we will use
less of the destination as this goes to
zero right so it can it can fade out our
sprite but really these values don't go
to zero I'm sorry it uses less of the
value because it's inverted uses less of
the value as this goes to 1.0 if the
Texel was one point out right but these
colors here are supposed to be pre
multiplied by alpha because we just add
them straight in right if you remember
when we talked about premultiplied alpha
and maybe I can maybe I'll use the ring
for a minutes to talk a little more
about that these really want to be
multiplied by that color a as
well right because they have not been
yet so really this should in fact be in
here like so in order to get the correct
equation for the blending so now we're
good now we're now we're blending
correctly all right at least I believe
we are that is a weird that is a really
weird tree let me go ahead and make that
oscillate a little bit more quickly
there we go
so anyway let me briefly mention what I
did there just so that people understand
it so what we were doing is we were
doing premultiplied alpha and I talked
about the importance of that which is
basically because much like the gamma
premultiplied alpha is the only kind of
alpha that properly works through linear
blends right so when you're doing linear
blends and stuff you need to be
premultiplied alpha because post
multiplied alpha or non P multiplied
alpha it's not pre multiplied I'm not
post multiply but non people applied
alpha does not actually work as we
talked about before so what was
happening there is we have an equation
right for like each of our channels
which was you know one minus the alpha
times the dest right plus the source
because we're assuming that the source
is already multiplied by the Alpha this
is this equation 1 minus a D plus a s
right assuming that the a s was already
collapsed into the S right now so it's
really s prime right it's like s prime
equals a s and so when we added another
color in there if I was to take that
other color we had we had modulated in
there
well we essentially didn't take into
account the alpha of that color that
second color that we were doing so we
had what I had written inadvertently was
one - a d you know plus si s prime B
where the the color that came out of the
texture right this is the Texel that was
pre multiplied but the color that came
from the function was not and so when
you multiply something that's non pre
multiplied by something that is P
multiplied you get like a half-and-half
result right so what I actually wanted
to do was make this S prime a right I
wanted to multiply the source color by
its own alpha first right and so that's
all I did to make sure that all of the
alphas were pre multiplied in the
pipeline alright with that
I think we can go ahead and go to the QA
there we go
what would be the visual artifact of
using two instead of 2.2 for the gamma
so the answer is nothing for what we're
doing because there isn't even a visual
artifact
for not doing the game as all at all as
you saw
so really the reason it's it's basically
hmm if you look at this curve right so
you know here's the actual curve right
this is the 2.2 curve right and here's
the 2.0 curve right those are the two
curves let's say here's one and here's
zero right and here's you know max
brightness or something and I guess that
they both cross at one because of the
properties of raising things to powers
so that's not quite accurate there so
let me go ahead and kind of fix that a
little bit right so basically the only
visual artifact is things are a little
bit darker than they should be if you're
using the 2.0 instead of the 2.2 right
because when you bringing those things
up to linear you're you're not quite
getting them you're not quite pulling
them back to exactly linear you're
pulling them back to almost linear so
you know I don't even know if you
could perceive that difference to be
honest with you I don't know but I I
would suspect that it would be a very
small difference in most circumstances
if there was one so it's not a huge deal
garlanded loom says also need to do
additive color tinting for full
expressiveness
well garland Oh bloom that is is one of
well I guess if you want additive like
so you want to be able to add in red
where there wasn't red before basically
so there's a plus there's a there's an
addition in that I don't know how I feel
about that I mean how would you well
alright I mean maybe well think about it
we'll think about it
I have a CS background but I'm two
months behind on coding this it is much
easier to follow when I'm not trying to
type myself how detrimental would it be
to my understanding to watch and just
stop coding if I get too far behind
sometimes when you're moving things
around I have to watch that bit two to
three times I don't know it's a good
question
but I don't know the answer to that
question I mean one of the problems is
that if you don't do things you tend to
not really learn them so I would say
it's probably not a great idea to not
try to actually do the code because
remember there's no such thing as
keeping up with handmade hero it's a
video series it's gonna last a fixed
number of hours I don't know how many
that's gonna be five six hundred
something like that and that's gonna be
over and so you will have your entire
life to catch up with it if you want to
you don't have to stay up to date in any
kind of you know real sense so I would
say just take it at your own pace and
don't worry too much about being up to
date you can always ask questions on the
forums you don't have to ask questions
live would it be worth only using gamma
correction on texels that have an alpha
not equal to zero or one so technically
no because we're doing a bilinear blend
between texels so technically those
texels want to all be gamma corrected as
well so that bilinear blend will work so
you know we're doing this for one and so
you know maybe we'll just have it so you
can compile out the gamma correction if
this if it actually makes a different
speed wise when we actually profile it
but you know we put it in there for now
okay robot chocolate Dino says could we
do our maths in sRGB space so you you
the answer is you could but if you were
going to do the minister jaysis they'd
look like a bunch of power functions
right because your linear blend is now
like the definition of your linear blend
is actually right because okay so here's
our current lerp our current lerp for a
tea B right is 1 minus T a plus T B
right that's what we're currently doing
if you wanted to make a linear
interpolant in srgb space well we know
what it actually is
it is this function it is the with our
approximation it is the square root of 1
minus T a squared plus M plus T B
squared right so you know I I mean you
could write your lips that way always
where you square a and you square B you
do the blender than a square root them
but it just would be way less efficient
to always do the math this way instead
of doing it just once at the top to get
that squaring and then once at the end
to do the square root you know what I
mean so it just doesn't seem like you'd
ever want to do the math and s reduces
but you could you just have to do that
translation every time if that makes
sense what's kind of interesting about
this is this kind of is like a I've
never really thought about this before
because I never really looked at what
happens if you simplify gamma down to
square and square root which is what
we're doing here but this is kind of
interesting right because it looks like
a triangle right it looks like this
where lurk is here and you know this is
one minus T Square rooted a and this is
square root of T B which is just kind of
interesting I don't really know I don't
really know if that has any
ramifications but it kind of looks like
that right I mean so let's say that I
had this triangle right and I wanted to
solve for lerp and I know I have a side
that's this and I have a side of that
right well I know that I would take you
know a squared plus B squared square
root it is the formula right so plugging
those in I would get you know 1 minus T
a squared which is just 1 minus T a
squared and I would have you know root T
B squared which is just T B squared and
I would add those together square root
them that Gurian theorem to get miler
it's kind of interesting that it looks
that way not sure that there's really
anything special about that but it's
kind of interesting right it's just one
of those things that catches your eye
when you see it I wonder I wonder if you
could translate the lerp so that you
just did the operation on the T value if
that makes sense
and didn't actually have to square the a
or the B I don't know if that if what
I'm saying makes any sense but basically
like I'd be interested to know if you
could turn this into something where you
could get the equivalent of this out by
just manipulating the TV
I use I don't know if you can or not
let's let's let's just you know what
sorry I think maybe this QA just turned
into an exploration so let's say we've
got this here so this is our F of T I'm
just going to shorten it so I can write
it easier but it's really F of a TB
equals that
so let's square both sides we'd get f
squared T right equals one minus T a
squared plus T B squared right and I
feel like the problem is you're gonna
get this cross term in here but there's
nothing you can really do with you know
yeah well let's keep going f of T equals
a squared minus T a squared plus T B
squared which is of course the familiar
hmm excuse me which is the familiar a
squared minus T or sorry plus T B
squared minus a squared right so yeah I
don't think there's much you're really
going to do with that unfortunately yeah
and I don't see that
if you could get it so that the tea
would move outside but I just don't see
how that's gonna happen I mean then Yuri
square root it right I mean I guess I'd
really didn't need the square root in
the first I mean the really need to
square it in the first place because
it's all under the radical anyway but
you've got a squared right plus T B
squared minus a squared and you still
can't pull that that T out in any useful
way like you want to move this out here
if you could yeah I don't know it's kind
of interesting anyway I'll go back to QA
mmm-hmm what are you going to start
implementing OpenGL for the rendering
well probably not till we're done with a
software like well we'll do the
optimized software renderer but OpenGL
is just kind of there for performance
but you know we won't learn a whole lot
by implementing OpenGL so we're not
really focused on that wouldn't the
10-10-10 2 format which is available in
hardware be sufficient to avoid banding
well yeah so the 10-10-10 2 format
I mean really it depends on how what we
end up doing with our frame buffer so if
we end up using destination in the frame
but destination alpha in the frame
buffer for translucency 2 bits for alpha
I'm gonna cut it so you know we could
use something like 10 10 10 2 or 11 11
11 10 for example with no alpha in the
frame buffer we could decide to try and
do something like that and that might be
enough to avoid the banding but we would
be sort of boxing ourselves in because
then we wouldn't have any way to do
destination alpha right and so that's a
little dicey I don't know that I would
want to go down that route if we'd have
to
what is the point of using 2.2 at all
why not just use two for gamma because
it's less accurate I mean the answer is
you can just use two for gamma if you're
in a pinch but if you want it to be 100%
accurate everywhere you want to point to
and so when you're in a situation where
like hardware for example uses klutz
oftentimes they use color look-up tables
for this I believe they can just do
exactly the srgb profile so they don't
have any of that wiggle room but yeah
the answer is I think two is probably
okay for a lot of uses and I believe a
lot of people have used two as an
optimization before so we're not like
doing that that's not like some new
thing we're doing that's like I believe
that's an accepted optimization of like
yeah it's close enough right by
repeatedly converting between linear and
our approximated gamma space when doing
each blend are we compounding our errors
so you know yes and no if we thought
that if we were accumulating so you have
to understand what do you mean by errors
right so if you take a look at what's
happening on the screen a lot of stuff
is just the result of the final pixel
that gets written there and there isn't
a lot of translucency that's happening
so the only time that you really end up
with what's you know seeing the result
of repetitive blending is that the edges
of things or when there's a thing that's
like translucent like a transfer
semi-transparent I should say not
translucent translucency is a different
thing translucency is like a superset of
transparency so forget I said that
something that's like semi-transparent
so you know we really won't have that
much error to compound but you're right
for for things where a lot of edges were
overlapping we would be potentially
compounding our errors there we'd have
like one bit of rounding error that
would happen each time potentially for
example right
but at the end of the day I don't know
that that really is gonna add up to all
that much but that is one motivation for
why when you're start to doing thing
when you're starting to do things like
trying to do photorealistic rendering
and stuff like that you will keep all
your stuff in flow
point so that you have a lot more bits
of precision so that you don't fall into
you know traps like that where you might
end up with something that looks a
little wrong gets a little bandit or
something because of it we just don't
have that kind of scenario happening so
we really don't have a situation where
we're going to need to worry about every
little last bit of precision because
we're just not doing stuff of that
nature at the moment do all monitors use
the same 2.2 curve no actually they
don't and in fact that is why you get
these things which are like color
calibration curves for your monitor the
the fact is and and I guess this might
be another argument for why 2.0 might be
good enough to point to is not exact to
point to is an approximation of what
most monitors are trying to do not all
monitors are doing that not everyone has
their monitors set up the same way you
know the contrast on the monitor may be
set differently there's all these other
things and you will often see stuff
where people will actually try to figure
out what the gamma curve is for a game
if you've ever seen something where a
game comes up and says adjust this knob
which is like a little thing on the
screen until these gray colors look the
same
if you ever seen that that was them
trying to figure out what your monitor
dama was right so yeah there it's
there's no perfect solution for it it's
one of those sad facts of life where you
just don't get the information that you
need to do the perfect solution so you
know again that's why using 2.2 is
probably not that bad of a compromise
because it's much better than not doing
gamma at all but it's probably not that
much more incorrect than doing 2.2 for
most circumstances I would suspect not a
game expert I'm not the guy to ask so
that's just my supposition you would
have to ask somebody who was a little
more hardcore about it
is raising the color value to two
instead of two point two really going to
save that much processing power yeah
actually probably a ton because the
difference between squaring something
and raising it to the two point two
power like squaring something is like
one extra instruction it's one
multiplication but getting it to the two
point two it involves a ton of extra
like many more instructions right I
don't know exactly how many we'd have to
actually go work it out but when you're
talking about the differing one
instruction and many instructions like
even let's say it was only five
instructions when we're talking about
something we do for every pixel on the
screen you cannot afford six times more
expensive right like that's what that
would be right
so six times as expensive I should say
so yeah two point two is a lot more
expensive than two as it happens but
that said that's me saying it as if you
were going to implement it like pow
so it may be the case that if you worked
out a good approximation specifically
for two point two that you could get it
down to not very many instructions but I
doubt it would be as fast as one
instruction which is probably all I'm
willing to spare for gamma probably I
would guess but you know who knows and
again it's not just that raised to the
two point two you have to do you have to
do the two point two route right the the
raised to the 1 over two point two power
to map it back so you're paying it on
both sides and you need a good
approximation on both sides
I got stuck implementing a bit shift+
PRNG
in our engine thanks for showing a code
comment about weighing hashing earlier
which was just what I needed
well very glad that Wang hashing helped
you have
let's see here all right so I think
we're all good looks like the end of the
questions so I will wrap it up for today
right on time in fact I guess we're a
little bit over but that's that's no
problem no biggie
so all right it's closed down let's
close down that tree is getting
increasingly trippy it's a very very
bizarre tree all of a sudden so yeah I
would recommend doing some are reading
on gamma because again handmade hero
won't be the place to really see gamma
in action because we're just not doing
anything where gamma is gonna matter I
don't think but now you know about what
it is I would definitely say go do some
light reading on it just so you kind of
get a feel for it because it's something
that you want to know for when you're
working on 3d stuff or when you're
looking at some things that maybe where
it's important it's good to know so it's
in the back of your head you can go oh
wait what I'm doing right now might be
affected by gamma let me make sure that
I'm doing it right that's just a good
thing to know and every graphics printer
should know it so thank you everyone for
joining me for another episode of
handmade hereit's what a pleasure coding
with us always we did gamma today thank
you to Wan Chun for forcing the issue
because it does need to be talked about
and people should know what it is and
honestly I was gonna skip it because it
just wasn't the sort of thing that's
gonna make much of an impact on our game
but you know it's not always about just
doing what makes impact on the game it's
about trying to teach people what they
need to know to make their own games and
maybe your game isn't exactly like
handmade hero so at that point it is
good for you to know these sorts of
things that they're out there and you
can go take a closer look at them if you
need to so if you would like to oh my
goodness I'm having that's the first
time I think my phone has ever rang on
the screen on the stream I forget that
my phone can be rung on the laptop which
is very kind of disquieting alright
sorry if you would like to follow along
at home you can always pre-order the
game at handmade hero org and you can
see there you can get a link in your
email which will allow you download the
source code and you can play around with
and do whatever you want to do while you
try to learn sort of you know from the
stuff that we do on the stream sometimes
it helps to be able to play around the
code because that's just a good way to
learn and a good way to sort of practice
for when you need to write your own
stuff so you can do that on here made
here or we also have the patriotic last
part the video series you can subscribe
there it's always very appreciated
there's forums so you can ask questions
and it also has ports to Mac and Linux
stuff like that it's a good place to go
if you're trying to learn from the
series we have a tweet bot that tweets
the schedule so if you want to catch
this series live it's great place to go
and yeah we will be here at 5 p.m. every
day this week
so if you want to come back and see us
again we'll be here 5 p.m. tomorrow on
Twitch love to see here when we will
maybe start talking about how to
structure this rasterizer for actually
getting some performance out of it and
that will probably open up a whole bunch
of cans of worms including sort of some
performance analysis stuff that we sort
of have been talked about for a while so
I highly recommend checking it out I
think it's gonna be a fun week and and
we'll be do some interesting stuff hope
see you there and have a good Tuesday
either way thanks for tuning everyone