hello everyone thank you for joining us
for handmade here oh sure we quote a
complete-game live on stream and we are
kind of in some interesting territory
now probably going to be kind of fun
depending on how much GPU nonsense we
hit but we implement lingual cups
yesterday and we kind of get start
playing with those today a little bit
which should be kind of fun and
interesting I think let me kind of show
you where we're at just you have some
sense of it I will run the game here and
what you can see is we've striped our
voxel light look up with red green and
blue colors so you can kind of see
inside the letting volume those stripes
which are just kind of a debug view for
us that let us know that the locks will
look up on one of our voxels it's
working properly that's great because
that means from here on out we can play
with this a little bit and sort of start
to see a we can get some some sort of
ballpark opinion of how slow it will be
if we actually do six full voxel lookups
for a complete lighting right now we're
only doing that one I mean technically
we've got the six calls in there but I'm
assuming that the shader compiler
eliminated five of them because they
weren't used for anything
normally the shader compiler is pretty
aggressive right it's not gonna leave
dead code in there for obvious reasons
they're trying to be as hype before it's
as possible so you're not gonna sit
around sampling textures that nobody
then uses so we can start to get some
performance profile rich today we also
probably want to figure out how much
time we are taking and figure out how
we're gonna get these voxels down
quickly bunch of stuff like that so we
had a lot of interesting work to do but
hopefully we won't hit too many more GPU
snags or anything like that so we can
mostly have fun with the lighting and
try to get into position where it's it's
working
like I said the main thing we need to do
now is try to figure out to what extent
all of these voxels can be sampled
together that's obviously something that
we can kind of start to layer in a
little bit so since I'm pretty sure that
these voxels will get sampled the same
way we probably don't need to worry too
much about that part but what I do not
know is to what
and the voxels are getting Sam sent down
properly as separate voxels so what I'd
like to start by doing just really
quickly to get us back into the swing of
things today is I'd like to go ahead you
can see if we go to the Z bias program
here so let me just jump to that you can
see where we're doing our sampling here
is the sum total of the lighting
sampling that we're actually doing this
is the part we're worried about we don't
know how long this will take
it's it's a requirement to sample six
voxels now what we can do in the future
is we can probably keep this to three
voxels total maybe by being a little bit
creative I'm not sure how hard that will
actually be but it might be kind of
difficult we'll see
because I don't know to what extent we
can use index lookups into samplers it
may be that we can it may be that we
can't and again that's really about how
the shading language allows you to
reference things so worst case scenario
we have to sample six and in the case
where we have to sample six that would
be our least performant case and I like
I said just don't know how bad that's
going to be and so one of the things
that we can start to do again to look at
the the frame rate cost one thing I did
is I opened up insight I asked them to
take some frame profile for us a couple
of things I don't know I don't know how
much time of that is spent in some of
our lighting stuff that we haven't
really worked on yet one thing I can do
there is if we go look at when we're
calling compute light propagation that
sort of stuff
are we doing anything in end lighting
computation that's actually expensive
you know or that we can get rid of so
for example we're calling compute light
propagation let's say I got rid of that
let's say maybe I got rid of all this
stuff right so we're not really doing
any work in the in the lighting
computation again I'm just trying to
keep it to just the voxel work so that I
could get up just a basic idea how fast
that is and so here is that same code
running with that stuff commented out
again don't know how fast this is so
what I'd like to do is again run it
under insight just get some ideas of how
is that working right
so let's go ahead and do that I'm gonna
load up insight here and then I'm gonna
launch the frame profiler and that
should just give me an idea of how slow
things are right now what you can see on
here is it's it's saying that there's a
22 milliseconds per frame hit right and
of course the problem is I really just
don't know where that 25 milliseconds
that's getting spent I I don't know yeah
I don't know if I capture for live
analysis if I we don't know how accurate
this is actually is but what you can see
here if you believe this diagram which I
don't know if we do right but let's
suppose we did you can see here that it
claims we're only spending four point
six six milliseconds on the graphics and
if you look at what is detailed here in
the texture calls you can see where the
various calls are happening buying
texture calls the vertex array calls
these sorts of things use program bind
buffer right here's the texture
submission you can see that we're
spending two point five two milliseconds
and 15 point 13 milliseconds in fact and
you know what that right there looks
like the time right so if we look here
you can see we've got this this sort of
four point six six milliseconds it looks
like that is talking about the GPU time
if we believe this performance analysis
that right there is is our problem so
this this submission of the 3d voxel
down to the card really really bad
that's a huge problem and if we just
look at our frame time that's pretty
much where the problem lies that's
actually surprisingly good news it's
good news for two reasons one is we can
reduce the size of the voxel which will
dramatically reduce the cost of
submitting it we can probably cut that
number in a quarter
by just changing to a 64 cubed voxel
instead of 128 cube box'll so that's
really good news right there the other
good news is we have done literally
nothing right now to make sure that the
graphics card is getting that voxel in
the most expedient way and what I mean
by that is we our leader literally just
taking a user space pointer and we are
saying to the graphics card hey grab
this card why don't you take this user
space pointer and do something with it
right so that's the least efficient way
for the CPU to do anything it can't be
multi-threaded because it doesn't know
when we will touch that memory again so
it has to do everything behind the
geotextile image call right away has to
do a full copy into its own space to
make sure that it preserves the memory
that's there at the time of the call and
furthermore it has to do at least that
one copy because even if it didn't have
to do it right away it can't and it
could overlap it it's not to do it and
the reason is because we didn't allocate
the memory for that transfer buffer from
the graphics card so it can't put it in
a space where the graphics card itself
could gather it and deuce whistling on
its own or whatever it's going to do so
we're feeding it in the worst possible
way
is probably the best way to think about
that so the first question would be well
you know can we can we just like can we
optimize this out somehow that geo text
some image let's just verify to
ourselves because I don't know if we
terminate the running program here and
we go back to our code if we inside the
OpenGL renderer itself
yes so if we go to the renderer itself
and we just go down and look at how
we're doing things every frame we send
down this and that's what we're going to
need to do because we need when we send
it down when we send down the letting
information every time we need to make
sure we wait what the hey why are we
doing this every frame I don't know why
we're calling Geo text promoter eyes so
many times here that's not what I
intended so that's a little weird
hold on a sec I'm sorry this is not what
I wanted to talk about right now but
open Jill in it when we create these
textures should be the only time that we
actually needed to do that so that was a
mistake
those should have been here right so
sorry let me just make sure that that's
fixed that but we don't need to be I
don't think that would have done
anything because the OpenGL layer does a
lot of different or those anyway but I
just want to make sure that we moved
those to the right place yeah because
those those did not need to be called
there and that's just getting cruft in
the way and no point in that all right
so this is the call that we're talking
about here that takes a while if I just
actually throw in a local persist here
that's just like only twice or something
I don't know and we just send this down
or for the first 10 frames or something
something like that just to make sure
that the game has actually sent some
information down to it at some point
what I can do is just say like if only
twice and of course now it's 10 times
that's really making any sense
what I can do here is just say like oh
all right let's do like only twice this
is probably fine leave that there let's
only do this a few times
send it down only a few times right and
this way we can get a feel for the speed
if we're not doing that texture transfer
right so just keeping that texture
transfer out of the loop so here's that
and we're running now off we go if we
double check the speed now so I'm gonna
launch it from here and we look at what
the profile is my assumption is the
profile will jump up dramatically and
you can see it here now we're at a very
reasonable frame rate right that's
actually hitting 120 which is pretty
good and as we get out to a harder sort
of view we're still way above 60 right
and so if our goal dish is to shift this
game on a modern graphics card it should
run at 60 frames a second we're well
within tolerance here and we haven't
really done much type of facial work so
that's good right that's a good thing
now let's continue down this path a
little bit just as we go here let's try
and I'm gonna go ahead and hit terminate
there or try to incite isn't great about
closing apps in case you're wondering
like it's like you know could you
terminate my application please yeah I
don't know who knows anyway point being
if we push on this a little bit more
what I'd like to do is when we go and
submit our voxels
let's put different things in different
voxels so for example if I go into the
handmade lighting code and you can see
us stuffing our voxels with our
structured art here again structured our
a very important way to debug things and
test things because if we just put real
artwork or real lighting in here it's
very hard to tell if it's wrong subtly
if subtle runs obvious like serious bugs
show up clearly subtle bugs don't so
structured arts a really good way to do
that plus when things are in serious
bugs even though the real artwork you
can still tell you're a serious bug you
can't necessarily see what this serious
bug is but structured art makes it much
easier to see if you only see the red
Channel for example you know that it's
this particular voxel is being
over-represented than the other
aren't or something right you can see
through the structured art clues that
you wouldn't see to the bug even if the
bug would have been clear in normal
circumstance so structured aren't very
important putting debug values into
precise locations in your artwork is
very important you see me do it many
many many times it's one of the most
important tips I credit Mike Biddle comb
for that he's the one who even coined
that term for me he probably didn't
coined the term in toto but he was going
to introduce me of that term and it's
like structured art yes very smart and
so what we want to do here is start to
take a look at we've got these box
indexes here what if I start stuffing
the other box indexes with something
else so here I'm going to say all right
let's do all of our box surfaces here so
when we talk about our boxes here in the
order we normally put them south north
down up and my goal here is just going
to be let's fill these voxels with
something that lets us know they're
actually working and at the same time
that will force us to know that they're
all getting sampled so we can get a
realistic profile estimate of how much
that fragment shader is gonna cost us in
the worst possible case on optimize just
running itself into the ground what's
that going to look like right so what I
want to do here is I want to create sort
of a set of Lighting's here that are
gonna be structured arts that's
structured in such a way is to put
different things into the colors of each
voxel and so what I'm going to do is
duplicate the code I had up here but
change the striping patterns right so
basically like I'm gonna compute
different patterns for west east south
north down and up
so what I want to do will start out
pretty simply what I'll do here is say
let's go ahead and strike further apart
so I can get kind of two different
stripe patterns going
and so maybe what we do here is we say
like okay let's suppose that we do like
a X divided two kind of thing so now
what we're going to do is reduce that
period down right and so like if I do
something like this right and then I'm
gonna do something like put them in two
different ones so we'll do west and east
stripes like that fact maybe we'll just
do those two for right now and so now if
I run what I should see is I'll only see
red striping because we're only drawing
the westward voxel and so I'll only see
the red striping and again it's twice as
banded as before before the bands were
more frequent now they're less frequent
right and the other thing you can you
know you can kinda see here too is I
think our voxels just over it's too
dense right you're just even looking at
it it's just it's just too dense when
you look at how it lies on to these
things I think we probably have just way
too more more density than we need to
capture the kinds of letting details
that we're trying to capture with the
voxel so in my opinion this is also
probably too big and the so we can
reduce that size now but I don't want to
do that yet you know like one thing that
time so now let's go into the fragment
shader and let's try to pull in some of
those other channels then we know we're
already asking for them but like I said
they're getting optimized out so if we
look at where this light sampler East
and West they are getting pulled in
right but you can see here we just take
the light West RGB and that's not gonna
cut it because that means that it can
just optimize out the likes to eat light
East entirely so if we were to do
something where we some of these in fact
you know what I should probably do this
a different way let's do it like this
let's take the light data and let's just
set that equal to zero and then let's
just sum these in a way that's just
convenient for us for debugging purposes
right so we'll start summing in the
light unpacks for each of these
serious like so and so I'm gonna go
ahead and compile that and now I would
expect to see two different sets of
bands one set coming from the West word
facing voxel one from the eastward
facing voxel that's the hope it looks
like I screwed something up what did I
screw up
that is when I screwed up probably
should have showed you a new feature
actually if we if we have an error in
our shader compiler again I'll do it
in fact let me just do it for you
suppose I didn't know that right so one
of the things George expert team picks
on the chat recently updated our
debugger remedy debugger of champions
and if you look here Nick like before
oops if I spell it right wait I did that
compile that supposed to crash
well not crash it was supposed to assert
on the shader compiler compiler right
did I miss it yeah there it goes um so
if you look at something like this right
in the past you know when you were
trying to view string as it was hard in
here because it had you know some
different displays for them or whatever
in theory now supposedly we can just do
this and if you do calm a stir on
something then you get like a little
effectively text editor view in here so
you can see really cleanly like what the
actual con is the string is it's really
nice it's much nicer than the MS vc-1
which pops up like a modal window you
can't get rid of so this is kind of nice
you can just kind of look at this in
here and you even have a scroll bar so
if this happens to be tiny and you don't
want to expand it you can still see the
entire string conveniently in there
formatted properly which is really
baller and just want to thank George for
doing that for us again like just it's
so nice to have somebody who knows what
they're doing working on the de bugger
instead of the visual studio debugger
which you know no one no one who knows
what they're doing ever works on as far
as I can tell so it just keeps getting
worse
whereas this one keeps getting better
and and so thanks for that that's really
good and it will help us out a lot so
that's pretty awesome anyway just wanted
to mention that was there we didn't need
it this time but we're definitely gonna
need it sometimes because you know as
you know we you know often times will
put mistakes into our shaders so anyway
going back to
the correct version of the shader in
theory if we take a look here at what
we've got you can see now we're pulling
from both voxels right because one of
them is the green stripes one of them is
the red stripes so what I can do now is
start to layer some lights on top of
this and that's what I'm gonna try and
do so the south and north voxels what
I'm gonna do is actually go ahead and
make those be a higher frequency stripe
on top so I'm gonna go down to just the
again looking at the the frequency here
instead of it being half the frequency
I'm going to use the full frequency and
the South and North voxels oops
source south and north voxels they will
just be effectively the same striping
but on top at a higher frequency right
and so if we go ahead and do that and
you know what maybe maybe not
let me do let me do that instead so
every 4th one they will kick in that
might be easier to verify right so every
4th we should see a red and a green
highlight on that let's go ahead and
kick those in here now
and for good measure let's go ahead and
kick these in here because we never
gonna need them so now we're sampling
from all the voxels and you know maybe
we can just go in here and do something
like this so now we've got everybody and
we can just stuff the down and up so now
we've got a Z stripe in there too and so
now we should be able to do some kind of
light verification hopefully we'll find
out whether or not we can actually pull
from all these voxels successfully
without maybe there if there's any kind
of bugs in how we were sending them down
or anything but you know this is in
theory sampling all the voxels and just
trying to verify which ones are in there
at this point so looking at it yeah so
the green striping I don't think that's
doing exactly what I had hoped hold on
second let's do let's do it slightly
let's do it this way I think this will
be easier so this will basically say
look we should see two four two four
look on the on the on the stripes we
should just see like regular patterns
now and looking at it that looks a
little still more frequent than I would
have expected X mod four equals 0x month
four equals two am I just doing
something stupid here
I might be if I said X mod eight I might
be doing something stupid here but
basically all I was trying to do is just
say look let's space out these things
fairly far but I guess I didn't there we
go that's a little easier to see right
so our voxels just way too dense it
seems like but anyway now you can see
we're we're getting a certain space in
there if I turn off the mod for people
so let's let's go ahead and move the mod
for people down here like so right so if
I go ahead and turn off the mod for
people like this then what we should see
and in fact I can toggle this at runtime
actually if we just run it so we could
see it change if we run it we should see
fairly far spacing for our different
ones and you do right so there's our you
know fairly distantly spaced now I turn
on the second set of lines we can see
all of them become more frequent right
hopefully oh but we won't because we're
not sending it down every frame so let
me run it again because remember we
stopped and now we should see more
frequent on each and we do so I think
we're pulling from all of the voxels now
and since we're pulling from all of the
voxels now I think now I can go in and
actually run the frame profiler and see
what's up right so here's our frame
profile here's us pulling from every
from every voxel right and we're a
little high on there let's go ahead and
do a capture for live analysis and see
who's taking the time we'll just see
what's up at that and looking here
honestly it looks like it's just chewing
through this like you know it was steak
tartare or something it seems like
really the GPU just eats it for
breakfast
so it's just us it's just our CPU side
stuff so in theory if I if if I nerf
this our frame rate would presumably go
up
so let's actually try that see I don't
know if M site can actually do the
reload properly so I don't know if you
can hot code reload inside n site that
may be asking a little bit too much but
I'll try it
so here's its frame rate estimation
right and I'm gonna go over to the code
I'm going to take out the part where we
actually fill the lighting buffers
because they've already been sent down
so it doesn't matter and we're gonna see
on the on the reload what happens yeah
there it is so what you can see is
actually the GPU just crushes this so it
you know cuz it said this is a 1080 I
think in this machine or a nine eighty
ten eighty nine eighty eight to nine
eighty you know I don't know what's in
this machine
[Laughter]
I don't remember what's in this machine
that's that's how bad it is my work
machine has a 1080 in it but this
machine is older so me you know this
might not have a kind of unit anyway the
GPU eats it for breakfast if I actually
go if I actually go take a look at
what's in this machine here
well ii can you terminate disconnect
there we go close do something for the
love of God here in sight thank you so
yeah if we actually go look at what
we're running here I don't actually
remember does this actually tell us it
doesn't tell us
thanks.thanks windows take a look at
that video control panel if we go look
in here at the system information that
should tell us which graphics card were
actually running and it is a 1080 yeah
there we go I'm like I thought it was
something good
uh so anyway this is a 1080 it's
obviously not the latest and greatest
the latest greatest is like one of those
artsy X cards 220 heck they're called
the numbering schemes are complete
marketing food and make no sense but
point being it's still a very fast
graphics card very capable and so I
suppose it's not surprising to see that
nowadays these things are so powerful
that pulling from six voxels at a time
is like not even really interesting to
them they're just like yes or whatever
man here you go I don't care um so it
looks like this is totally fine and not
only does it look totally fine but it
looks like if we wanted to we could
increase the number of voxel samples
we're taking so we could probably even
go more nuts with it if we wanted to so
what it looks like to me is our biggest
problem is how the heck do we fill these
voxels with something right that looks
like it's going to be our biggest
challenge and the reason that I think
that's you know that it's a big
challenge is because again I I really
don't know that we want to put voxel
ization on the GPU side because that
would require us to use unorder to
access views and that's just getting
into the territory of like only really
good graphics drivers probably work at
all for this good graphics cards because
unordered access views are a whole
nother ballgame we've never really
covered them on handmade Hira but
basically what you have to remember is
the graphics pipeline is set up so that
fragment shaders get invoked on blocks
of pixels probably like 4 by 4 8 by 8 or
8 by 4 you know blocks of pixels at
least 16 pixels at a time could be as
much as 32 64 who knows right but
they're getting it invoked on blocks of
pixels that are based on the width of
the ALU units in the graphics card so if
they've got ill units that do 16
multiplies at a time then you're gonna
be a 4 by 4 block of pixels or something
right because you're gonna do them all
together
and when you do those blocks those
blocks are effectively like you have to
think of those blocks as being almost
like bins that are getting fed into a
back-end that has to serialize the work
to combine them and the reason for that
is because graphics has a draw order
which is kind of annoying but that's
just how graphics works if I draw a one
triangle and they draw another triangle
and the second triangle overlaps the
first triangle the second triangle is
the one you're going to see not the
first right and so if there's a z-buffer
in there the z-buffer will do testing or
whatever but if you just have zebras who
turned off the second triangle is the
one that drops period right so that
whatever draws last it draws and the
graphics card is not allowed to pick an
arbitrary order it has to be the same
order every time so even if it decided
that instead you know some other
triangle should draw whatever it has to
be the same every time whether you get
flickering right and so what happens is
there's a there's a part of the graphics
pipeline that takes all of the filled
pixel chunks and combines them together
to produce the final output chunk for
that region of the screen if lots of
triangles overlap it they have to get
reconciled by a blend unit and if you're
wondering why that's why like blending
is really weak why you have to specify
like a fixed equation with some fixed
coefficients and that's how blending
works rather than be able to write your
own blending shader that's why it's
specifically because that part of the
back end has to be super fast and has to
it can't really be wide because it have
its serial right it has to go in order
and so that's why you don't see
programmable blending very often on very
many cards is because really high
throughput cards can't afford it right
so all that said so unordered access
views are saying forget that we just
want to write wherever the heck we want
to write we want to do whatever we want
to do right and summit so an unordered
access view is basically saying I'm not
going to tell you what block of pixels
I'm even going to touch could be any set
of pixels anywhere in and in texture I
don't care and you're gonna have to deal
with it so it's basically like saying I
get to write anywhere in the frame
buffer I want to write and so an
unordered access view is just really bad
in that sense it creates on the graphics
card side a need to basically treat the
blending output unit as almost like a
cache rather than an actual guaranteed
part of the pipeline because now you
have no idea which set of blocks I'm
even talking about until after you run
the shader right
and so obviously graphics card companies
are smart they know what they're doing
they've probably on the high end like
I'm sure on this on this graph on this
GPU right here I'm sure they're
unordered access views probably run
almost as fast is not right I'm sure
they probably got the chip organized so
that it caches it properly and just
pulls in to the right blocks and
whichever ones you touch gets
synchronized through a back-end thing
I'm sure they've got it dialed right
fire up into integrated graphics someday
and I'm not sure that's gonna be the
case folks right and so I'm nervous
about using an order to access views
because I don't know I'd have to ask a
person who does more GPU compat work I
don't really know how likely unordered
access views are to work in a lot of
places and work fast
you know so I'm really nervous about
voxel izing voxel izing things on the
GPU side is scary to me
and so that's a problem for us because
it means that if we were to voxel eyes
on the CPU side it kind of makes it
tough CPU side Vox Latian maybe kind of
rough but you know we can use six threat
we can well probably count at least four
threads and we can do it wide so we can
do four threads and four wide which
might get us a you know ballpark a 16x
boost so you know it's possible that it
could work we could in theory do a good
job block slicing on the CPU side so for
now I'm gonna hope that we can and then
we'll deal with the can't part of the
maybe not maybe we can't part when it
turns out that we can because hey we
would want a reference implementation
running on the CPU side anyway so we can
get it all working there first that's
where we're at
alright so let's start by actually
looking at how big this voxel needs to
be so here is the size of a voxel stripe
I'm gonna go into the OpenGL renderer
temporarily I've already turned off
mipmapping I'm gonna turn off linear
blending as well the B's going to turn
off the linear blending is because I
don't want it to blur the boundaries I
want to see exactly where these voxels
actually are and so when we create in
OpenGL in it when we create these I'm
gonna turn off this filtering right here
so we can see where the voxel boundaries
themselves actually are right and so if
I run it now in theory what I should see
maybe if I did it right is the width of
an actual voxel right so if you take a
look at how detailed this is
let's move out to an area where we're
fairly zoomed out so I think like the
most zoom that we ever get and maybe be
too much zoom I don't know but it's
something like this if you look at that
amount of lighting you know I think
that's probably fine we need it to be a
little bit bigger than that so the light
bounds need to be spread out a little
bit more than that I'm not sure what's
going on there let me take a look at
that so in here we're looking at this
world camera rekt I'm guessing that's
just wrong or something
I absolutely don't that that number is
actually what's wrong what why did we do
that
don't we know the don't we know that
number like what the heck I guess we
must just not be saving that number you
know I'm saying if you come in here you
can see us doing this rotation and we do
like Delta stuff here and blah blah blah
right I'm gonna go ahead and just guess
that the simulation center versus the
like it should probably be a delta from
the simulation center I'm guessing don't
really know but I think that's probably
the case so in here if I like took a
look at this if I took the camera z-axis
and did an inner product on that you
know what I'm saying if I did something
like the simulation center so the the
the location of the camera right like
where the camera actually is versus the
simulation center let me take a look
here
so we've got in in this we've got the
game camera and you can see here we've
got sort of the stuff going on here you
can see right here the focus
Minzy and Maxie I think that's what we
want right so I don't even have to do
this computation I was about to
contemplate because this is the value we
actually need so I think the expected
focus Minzy and if it's already Maxie is
like the region in which we're supposed
to be looking so I think if we just said
like the bounds between those I don't
know
exactly how far through those we want to
go but let's go ahead and say yeah I'm
gonna I'm gonna sort of ballpark it here
let's go ahead and say that if we took a
look at the worlds mode camera expected
focus Minzy and we want to sort of bound
that region maybe we do a sort of a a
split I don't know
so something like this maybe what we
really should be doing is taking both
and then sort of building a pound or
something but I'm so I'm not sure but
let's say we do something like this I'm
just gonna play with this a little bit
and see if we can get those bounds a
little bit better cuz the bounds are
kind of crappy at the moment and I'm
just I'm not sure why there might be
some bugs in it as well
so now one of the nice things is you can
kind of see we don't really have that
lighting problem anymore we're actually
act actively lighting sort of the
correct region more more so than we were
before right
we may be lighting a little larger than
we should so we might want to we might
not want it quite that big it's hard to
say but if you take a look at the sort
of difference between these two yeah
hard to say but anyway I think that's
fine for the most part with where the
light is I think that's all good so
let's let's leave it like that
temporarily and so if we take a look at
how sparse that voxel it I mean how
detailed that voxel is even in this case
it's just way more voxel information
than we need it's it's almost four per
grid sweatt's grid cell only nearly need
one per grid cell right for a Nyquist we
could go to two per grid cell but I mean
it's just not I know I don't really
think it's necessary so if you look at
even if for a pulled out version it's
just it's just way more detail than we
need so I must say we can definitely
drop down to 64 at the very least we
might even be able to go lower than that
but you know I'm gonna say that at a
minimum we go to 64 oops
because one twenty eighths way too
detailed and we're just going to be
blowing a ton of time voxel izing stuff
because it's way more detail than we
need and I just don't think it's worth
it right
so there's a much more reasonable
science for the learning but again it
seems like it's probably I wonder if
three two by 32 would actually be better
it's still just a little too detailed I
think right so I kind of feel like maybe
what we want is more like 32 by 32 and
let's and we could try to get the
lighting bands a little tighter in
general
and so now you can see it's a little I
think it's a little nicer right now you
can kind of see that it's roughly yeah
it seems like roughly the right size I
do think this this band the band in Y is
is too it's too thick and I'm not really
sure why that would be the case because
the band in that direction should
actually been smaller so I that doesn't
quite add up to me I think there's some
kind of bug in our algorithm or
something
cuz riddle me this if the bounds are
shorter in Y than an X which they
obviously are you can see that they are
right I mean it would help if I could
move it back a little bit so we could
see the top bound as well I guess it's
kind of hard to see the top out but I
mean I only see one stripe on there
right that doesn't really make any sense
so something's wrong with our sampling
or our for our fill but I don't or our
our constant that we sent down so
something weird is going on and we need
to fix that so let's figure out what's
up with that so in set light bounds like
if we have in light dim here and and we
do this to map into the voxel space I'm
wondering is that computation like bogus
or something or did something weird
happen so I kind of want to know what
what that like what is this process
doing it's something untoward happening
there I'm gonna go ahead and see if I
can look at operator divide on the
vector I just want to see like what that
will do so here's that that code it
looks like it should do one over each of
the dimensions which is what I wanted
so I'm not sure what's wrong there let
me look at the shader as well and then
we'll just step through it and try to
bug what's going on because something
weird is happening and I'm not sure what
so if we look at the Z bias program
which is right here here's how we're
producing this we first subtract the
voxel mid-corner away that should put it
relative to the min corner then we
multiplied by what was effectively
divided by the total length of the voxel
that should be giving us a 0 to 1 on
each of our dimensions so again not
really sure I see why we're getting a
problem there if I pop back to lighting
really quick just to see if there's
anything weird happening here I don't
see anything strange there but you know
did I mess up the indexing so this is
our x coordinate right for every Y we
need to move the full voxel dimension
right which is this forward we could go
double-check that that's correct as well
I suppose
and then for Z we need to move that
squared right because it's an entire y
sheet of the voxel at that point XY
sheet so I don't know like but
something's up so we need to debug that
first and make sure that because we
should see each of the the voxels the
same in every direction it's 32 by 32 by
32 now so we should see exactly four
stripes in the lighting and in each one
that's what we needed to see right but
you can see when I open it up here
that's totally not what I get and
interestingly enough you can see like
like just to underscore just how wrong
this is
what you can see happening is
if I go back here and you say if I
wanted to know how many times you can go
from zero to eight inside 32 right I
would expect the answer to be four right
so X mod 8 at 0 will be 0 I then go have
to go all the way up to 8 before it's
again so it happens at 0 times at 8
it'll happen again at 16 and at 24 and
then there is no 32 because that's when
this loop would stop so that's 4 stripes
of red right oh but this is if 0 ok
never mind that that works
so now do I see four stripes of red
let's find out so I expect to see four
stripes of red in along X it looks like
maybe I would write one two three four
yeah so that's good right that's exactly
what I want to see so now the question
is why don't I see any any of the green
right where's the green and you know I I
don't know if I was to to look at this
the light east value right it should be
coming in here it looks like that's
getting set if I go to the shader here
is the sampling it's being sampled by
the same exact parameter right so I
don't know let's do some testing let's
suppose that I look at the lady Estelle
you here and I say what if I change it
to like West so now it's in the same
voxel right so those stripes are not on
two different voxels oops they're now on
the same voxel so it's not the sampling
of the voxel right in terms of which one
were sampling it's either the sampling
of all the voxels period or it's the
filling out of all the voxels but it's
it's you know it has nothing to do with
whether it's in the west or the east
facing voxel right so let's think about
that for a second
we know that that we get this problem in
either case that means that I guess
maybe the way we're sending down the the
total dam is wrong
because the min corner looks like it's
in the right place but the the total dim
the y total dim mutt must be wrong
I mean just looking at this equation
right first of all this is busted that
was supposed to be an axe so that's
great I don't think that's enough to
mess with it much I also don't
understand why oh wait no that's not
what that supposed to be that's shifting
the Y by two never mind
that's what that's fine but again we
probably want to fix it you shouldn't
have to do that because that should have
been counted for in the in the camera
rectangle stuff you can see it's adding
to it here but we're adding to it on
both counts let's get rid of this for a
second see what we've got
so I think we probably want to work on
our query anyway so I think we're gonna
maybe leave it like this and then just
fix the query rather than having those
weird like you know adjustments in here
so I'm gonna leave this out for now and
we will take a look at that in a little
bit the ad radius two part may need to
stay but we'll see so anyway uh inter
cuz we do kind of probably want an apron
because we need to get light that comes
from the outside so I guess we'll see
but anyway when we've got our set light
bounds here I want to know what's going
on why we don't see those stripes so I
want to know what's going on with this
inflight dim here so I want to kind of
look and see what this value is and just
why we're getting such a strange
disparity between the two and maybe
there's something else going on there as
well so I should check here as well we
look in you can see just to make sure
that this is you know getting sent down
right it looks like it is when we do the
push setup here and I could also look to
see where we actually get those out so
where we actually send them down to the
graphs card that's going to be in the
use program call for Z bias program so
in here where we have this used for
gonna begin we're sending down the min
corner in the in filled in like this it
looks like it's right I mean for the
most part I don't see anything
particularly odd happening there so it
feels like it's probably okay and let me
go ahead and switch our build mode now
to not be optimized so this'll be a a -
ot and I'm gonna go any and inspect
those variables cuz I don't really know
what's going on I'm not sure why I'm
getting that kind of fun expected
pattern there so looking at the game and
debug mode here again so just to recap
I'm seeing the the red stripes I expect
I'm not seeing the green stripes that I
expect to see and for all I know it's
because the Y dimension is like really
large or something like just totally
wrong I don't know and so what I need to
do is just figure out what's going on
there so I'm gonna look into the
world mode here and I just want to try
and figure out like alright if I look at
the world mode where it's actually
getting that in-flight dem they're like
I want to break right here and I just
want to see what we're actually sending
down so if we look at in-flight dim you
know you could kind of see here that
it's the Y is twice what the X and z are
you know what I mean so you know that
does imply we would expect to see half
that I mean like the distance between
the stripes would be 2x off right but
I'm not sure that's enough to account
for it because
[Music]
if we look in here and we say well
alright if it's 2x off that means that
let's let's say it's even off 2 X in the
wrong direction right then what we would
expect to see is well it would mean the
first green stripe would be about there
right it'd be that far because it'd be
the second one so be like there right
and ain't no green stripe my friend
ain't no green stripe you know I'm
saying uh so something weird is going on
there and I don't know what I really
couldn't tell you and so I'm gonna look
at a couple different things first I'm
gonna go validate the I'm gonna try and
validate the actual voxel because I
don't know if that's right so if I am in
the OpenGL code right let's go down to
where we submit it like here and let's
just set a breakpoint on the submission
line and look at what we're actually
sending it cuz you know maybe that's
totally wrong who knows so if we go here
and we take a look at the light data
and we're trying to send down you know a
32 by 32 by 32 so you know I mean maybe
I maybe there's an unpack weirdness
going on here or something but let me
let me also change this to hexadecimal I
think you do kind of X for that yeah so
what you can see here is there's their
red stripes every eight which is exactly
what we would expect right and if we
keep going what we should see eventually
is we should see some green in here
right but but we don't I don't know what
that means sure what TBI means there but
we don't so what I'm curious about is
well okay so honestly there's you know
something that's kind of confusing here
oh oh you know what no the stripes are
in here am I talking about I'm like the
first one should have had it these are
strips so if there's our first green
stripe which we saw right so that's good
and what we should see is then at after
we go eight more counts of 32 we should
see another band right which we may run
out of space here for I'm not sure if
there's a way in remedy to tell it to do
more probably like you put it after this
or something but I don't know that I
really want that anyway because what I
would rather do I think in this case is
I'd probably rather use an offset so I
know where I'm at without scrolling down
so if we were to look at where we expect
the offset to be right mm-hmm
we would expect remember each row each
stripe is 32 long so we would expect the
next one to occur around 26 which we can
jump directly to right so let's just
start at I don't know if I can do this
yeah um so we'd expect the next one to
be here it's not here which isn't great
right so I'm not sure what to make of
that
exactly if I was to ask remedy to
display more of these let's say 512 of
them then what I should see is you know
the 507 is the marked one the 4 3 5 4
isn't so when I get up to 256 yeah it's
just not there um so maybe I just don't
know what I'm doing and and should
retire from programming that seems like
a likely thing to expect this code is
obviously incorrect and I just did it
wrong right so if we take a look at what
we would expect to have happen here
right so let's suppose we take just the
first Z layer where Z equals zero then I
expect this to just be 0 and then I
would expect the X to be an offset and
the Y to be strided by 32 because Vox
dim is supposed to be 32 right that's
what I'm expecting because that's the
way I expect it now we should maybe
check that it is but I mean we know that
the X is striping by 32 correctly at
least it seems like it is you know and
I'm saying to you so I'm not sure what's
up with that
so anyway what I would expect here is
that at y equals 0 I should hit this
case which is y ma T equals 0 and then I
would expect once I and that would set
light East right and then the light East
code would just go in here pretty
straightforward right
and then I would expect furthermore to
see like the yeah
I would expect to see it happen every
every eight times 32 now I'm gonna
hazard a guess and say maybe what
happened is I've got the pointers messed
up so maybe what happens is this light
index voxel bracket stuff is not working
properly June I'm saying so for example
if I go to commands I let me take a look
here how is it set and so if I look here
I've got pointers to six different banks
of you thirty twos right so the question
is how do I initialize this maybe I
initialize them wrong there's a pretty
easy way to test I can just set these at
different values but I also just want to
look first and see if I set them wrong
because I may well have right so
actually if I just go to open jilanne it
here and I go through and try to find
out what's going on with the
initialization of those parameters oh
you know what it's begin frame actually
isn't it yeah so here is the place where
we set these up and we set the you know
five pointers up here to be open GL
light data so if I look at what the
actual Open GL struct has in it for the
storage here just trying to make sure it
has oh great so that's totally wrong I
don't know what open geo light index
voxel dim is but it's some thing that
has nothing to do with what we defined
so that was good fantastic what is that
doing there
I don't know what any of this stuff is
that's old stuff great we just had a
typo fantastic where else is that being
used yeah none of this stuff is good
that's all bad that should be in here
right so we actually want to use this
stuff but that was our problem so I kind
of knew that right away once I inspected
the voxel so that was pretty easy to
figure out that's good but like yeah
them I don't know why any of this stuff
was being set there it should be in here
like we obviously just got confused
probably because I only program this
once a week but anyway so you can tell
that that was just just being stupid so
we want these in the renderer and we
want them to be specified here max light
probe count right should just be
something that we define and we don't
really know exactly what that is but I
you know it's probably just something
like that sir and then for light
occluders same thing and it's especially
stupid that those were open jail because
we don't actually use them on the
graphics card but what do you do
open up max occluder count this
all right try again
so now let's see what our stripes look
like so we know what we're begging here
that is much closer to what I would have
expected to see and I want to do
something now because we have clamped to
edge set I want to go ahead and do when
we fill out our voxel here just so I can
see where the edges are what I'd like to
do is set the edges as well so what I
would like to do is like if we're on an
edge set that like very clearly so for
example I'll do like if Z equals vox
10-1
you know like west or equals fat or
something and we can just set these up
so we can see where the end is and
that'll just give us some ability to see
what the actual bounds of the lighting
is on the screen which we kind of want
to be able to do right so if we look now
where the actual light bound is you can
see like very clearly that there's four
stripes across and four stripes that way
we don't really have the ability to
verify the depth of this voxel very well
because we don't really have any good
places to look at striping vertically we
need some kind of like a tall polygon or
something right to get some information
about that but we can sort of go here
and hop onto an area that least has some
stuff stacked on top of each other
move the lighting so it's kind of over
it and then we can probably see
something about that maybe I may I don't
really know but here if we look you can
see the the blue stripe right and so
that would be a size of a voxel in Z
which is totally fine and so yeah like
looking at how big these voxels are that
just seems probably fine and the only
question I have is if we expand the
light bounds out to actually fit the
area properly
um what does it look like right so yeah
you know maybe 32 is a little bit too
much I guess what I would say is depth
wise it's definitely not too much so we
may want to use irregular bounds like
non-uniform bounce we may want to do
like 64 by 64 by 32 or maybe even 64 by
64 at 16
I don't know depending on how deep we
want to go but just the stacking is
probably not so hard that we would have
to actually have the same resolution
like a 64 by 6 432 would probably be
fine you wouldn't need a 64 by 6 for us
64 probably right um and so what I would
like to do is maybe go a little bit
further with this and try to make it now
so that these are like that we have a
stable voxel grid and and get that
working kind of on top of what we've
already got or something like that not
sure yet it's a little bit hard to say
maybe let's just do the lighting first
and maybe let's just get that working
first and then we'll worry about fitting
this thing on there nicely that's
probably fine too so if we run now
Jimmie if we run the game and we just
look at what comes up that's like
totally fine it's pretty clear that the
resolution is like way better than we
even would need it to be that's
especially true and why because but I
think that's partially because it's kind
of sized a little inappropriate at this
point so assuming we want those to be
kind of regular what I might suggest is
saying look when we do the light
bounding maybe we make sure that the Y
is actually the same as the X and so you
know in here we would say something like
for the light bounce let's take the min
Y and subtract like an adjustment and in
both and just say look we want the
adjustment to be applied to Y such that
the
mention of Y is going to be the same as
the dimension in X so it's an actual
it's a proper cube right so if we did
that we would say something along the
lines of adjustment y equals get dim
light bounds X minus get dim light
bounds Y and that just lets us you know
compare those two and make sure that the
Y is the same so this would keep our
stripes the same size which I think we
kind of want because we really don't
want the lighting to be
anisotropic in terms of how its sampled
we would like it to be nice squares and
so here you can see what happens when we
make it into a square and yeah that
doesn't fit the screen region maybe as
well but I'm like not that worried about
that right okay
so if we start doing lighting on this
grid and then we worry about locking it
to the world as a separate pass we'll
worry about later this is clearly high
resolution enough it's arguably too high
resolution so we may actually size this
up a bit
from where it is probably but we can get
started now right so let's go ahead and
start flooding these voxels also if I
look here I would be interested to know
if I actually turn on a grid now so
let's say I did something more like this
so I can really see the voxel very
clearly this is every other stripe it
will be will be a band so this this
shows you the literal voxel now there it
is and what you can see is like inside a
single cube we have tons of resolution
on that box so like I said arguably too
much resolution on the voxel we probably
wanted even smaller than that but it
will get smaller than that like once we
get out to a large room so if I come out
here to a room that's very large right
like so now in this room which is kind
of the most zoomed out the
hammer is you can now see that like if I
go in and take a look at one of these
squares it's actually just that Nyquist
right so it's it's two samples per
square which is probably fine now maybe
that's still too small too fine I should
say so I don't know maybe we need to
even go up a little bit more so maybe we
will maybe we should should Jack it up a
little bit more if I look at how we're
running band wise in Z it's three as
well so maybe this needs to be a little
bit smaller even still I don't know that
would be great news because it's it's
just less work we have to do but if I
was to drop it down to sixteen I don't
know that seems way too low so and I
don't know that we can do anything else
I think it has to be a power too so what
we could do is use the 32 by 32 but not
fill it at all
but here's what that looks like right
and that's like way more like the
resolution I actually want when we hop
out here though I'm assuming that'll
just be too big and so now if we look at
like how this lines up you can see that
it's roughly one voxel per light probe
which seems good right and yeah I don't
know like maybe that's right
maybe that's the size of the voxel we
actually want so I'm not sure but that
could be basically all we really need
for the lighting resolution I'm not sure
but that that that may be all we really
need in terms of covering relatively
good coverage for the kinds of scenes
that we're looking for that may be you
know
so we'll start playing with it at that
level and we'll see but I just don't
know I I do think we may need 32 and the
reason I say that is because I'll give
you a look at what happens kind of the
outskirts of that area what you see in
in sort of the the out the the outlying
areas out here is if we were to actually
scale this to fit the whole scene it
would have to be a little bit larger and
then yours
starting to get down to two it might
it'll actually encompass two so it's
just really hard to say but I do think
like 32 by 32 by 16 we're probably just
fine and we could just not use all the
voxels
we could just only fill the center of it
up and skip some of the outside ones
would be fine that it's two resolute
right but I'm gonna start with that for
now and we'll go from there
all right so let's suppose we wanted to
actually light with this thing and start
playing around with with that what does
that look like well if I was to flood my
vox with something that would allow me
to to see that right let's suppose that
I sort of nuke some of this stuff for
now and what I'm going to do is I'm just
gonna take one of my voxels so let's say
the voxel for West were facing light and
I'm gonna say that that just gets some
light and nobody else does so what I'm
going to do is I'm gonna send down some
light light down that channel and I'm
gonna see what happens if we lay in a
lighting equation that's actually
somewhat correct with westward facing
lighting so this is as if there's just a
strong white light everywhere coming
from the west side right and so if we
have you know if we imagine what this is
supposed to say we have a strong light
coming from this side
bright white now obviously right now all
we just get is a uniform light on the
scene because we're not computing a
lighting equation so what we want to do
now is go add a lighting equation and
see what happens right so let's go to
the Z bias program and let's try to do
an actual full on lighting equation
right that we can drop in here and have
some understanding of you know what it's
actually doing so here's where we get
our light data from you know
and what we want to do is we probably
want I mean there's a couple different
ways we could look at doing this right
and I don't know which one is the
smarter way to do it but what I assume
II more or less want to do is produce a
composite light vector that's just the
result of blending in the various
lighting directions that we have right
and so we kind of want something that's
gonna well I mean again I really just
don't know me there's a there's
different ways you design I don't know
which way is the smartest way we could
do a separate lighting equation for each
light and maybe that's the smartest
thing to do at first the problem is the
directionality of the light at that
point is not very well represented so I
kind of think we don't want that so I
think what we probably want to do is
treat it as a single incoming light
source that is blended right and we want
to do that in a sensitive way so that we
don't end up neutralizing the direction
of the light too much
so I think what I might say is if we
were to consider the various light
contributions here right each one of
them has sort of a dot product with our
surface normal right
and so if we were to look and say
alright let's only collect the light
values that actually have to do with the
surface facing direction that we have
you know I'm saying and start with that
and that I assume would give us the
information that we need to produce a
reasonable blended lighting based on the
information that we're getting from our
cubed right I'm not really sure that's
right because the other way to do it is
to light as if each face of the cube was
an incoming light source that was
separate the reason I don't want to do
that on that I think that's a probably
bad idea is because if you think about
what that will create is it creates
fundamentally biased lighting sample
lighting directions and I think we would
see that in the lighting we would see
the fact that as lights move as things
move it probably fine as lights move you
would see them sort of have this banding
effect as they moved around I I don't I
think that would create artifacts that
would be objectionable as my gut feeling
I'm not sure
whereas if instead we take the lighting
directions to say how much lights coming
from this face cube how much light is
coming from that face book cube combine
those together to produce a average
light direction and an average amount of
light Jun and I mean that seems to me to
be maybe a better idea
III really don't have any more
intelligent thing to say than that I'm
afraid
yeah so I don't know that's just what
I'm gonna go with I don't know the view
direction here which I kind of need to
know so oh I do fantastic so I have the
camera P and I have the world P and
that's fantastic because that basically
lets me do everything that I want to do
in terms of a full lighting equation so
what I'm going to do is construct a
fairly basic light equation first we can
make it a little bit more complicated as
we go but basically let me just draw out
the the basic we've covered the sort of
thing before but just that the basic
version that I'll do now
whereas Milton
again I'll ask I asked every time but no
one seems to know is there any way to
get at Milton that has that it's fixed
sampling the sampling got busted and now
it's hard to draw with it and I don't
know if anyone ever fixed it but anyway
so what I want to do is I just want to
say look I've got a surface and I've got
a surface normal right
I know the world position I know this P
and I also know the camera position is
out here somewhere
so it's pretty easy for me to find a
vector that is which is how like how am
I looking at this thing and so what I
want to know is when I bounce that you
know when I look at this surface I want
to be able to look up at the light
source that are in this direction right
and so if I reflect this vector off of
this surface I get a direction that is
the direction I want to sample the
inbound light right now
if we're actually going to compute some
more advanced lighting right so trying
to set this up to do better lighting the
first thing we can do is really really
simple and do a crappy version which is
just take the direction of the light and
try to figure out from our lighting
probe which is a cube right try to
figure out like okay if I'm looking in
this direction and the cube says that
I've got these three directions that are
like similar to it right blend those
together based on how close they are to
this and I'll get some lighting that's
like what should be off in that
direction right but um that's 100
percent specular right because that's
just looking at what exactly is right in
the direction I'm looking so that would
be like a mirror right now we will we
won't see any mirrored graphics when if
we when we type the same but when we
type in I'm going to type it in first we
won't see a mirror but the only reason
we're not seeing a mirror is because our
light probes aren't detailed enough
right if we had a really detailed
lighting probe that we were sending down
like really really really really
detailed right so this was actually a
cube map that was like 256 by 26 on a
side and we did the sampling we'd get a
mirror that's what we get because we're
gonna look and see what's exactly in
that direction right so
again like it's worth noting that
equation will seem like it's not really
mirrored but it is 100% specular right
so in order to get a more fair lighting
equation that we would want is we can do
this calculation and produce what we
would see for the specular we can blend
those things together and say well we
want a specular contribution in a
diffuse contribution the diffuse
contribution should be more taking into
account the full range of things right
and so what that should be doing is that
should be taking a look at the normal
and saying what are all the faces that
the normal can see so all three faces
are we can see average those together
and that would be our diffuse light
because we know that diffuse light is
subject subject to the cosine rule
however meaning that inbound diffuse
light you know as you know right
remember the cosine rule this bit here I
do that poorly but right so what we know
is the the the surface of the light as
it reflects up the amount the size of a
shaft of light that can come in and hit
that surface is proportional to the
cosine and so we actually want to use
the cosine rule during that average to
say the inbound light coming from that
direction can only provide this much
light based on the cosine rule but we
would sum it up based on the normal not
on the camera direction because the
direction that the camera is looking
would not actually be effect would not
actually be affecting that inbound light
because we're assuming for a diffuse
surface it radiates light out in all
directions uniformly in that case right
so it wouldn't matter it only matters
how the light is falling on the surface
how much the it can send back out now
this is the kind of thing that I never
freaking know because I just don't spend
enough time doing line equations it may
be double cosine rule there meaning we
also have to count the sending out but I
don't know and that's I'm gonna have to
go work out the math exactly but at
least as one cosine rule which is the
surface following rule
okay so first things first produced that
reflection vector what's the reflection
vector you all should know this by now I
don't want to hear anyone out there
who's been watching handmade here Oh
tell me they don't know how to compute
this because they do so you better know
how to compute this right what we're
what we want is we want that vector
right here's what we have is we have the
camera position and the world position
right of the two points we know we can
produce this right we know we can
produce that inbound vector what's that
inbound vector it's W minus C right
that's the inbound vector so we'll call
that like I don't know
I'll call that the incident direction or
something right so we have this inbound
vector we know we can produce it it's
just W minus C very very straightforward
okay we know we have the normal it's
this so how do we produce this outbound
vector look how do we get that again
recenter this thing that produces this
right if we just assume that this vector
here is starting from the origin of our
coordinate system which is just going to
be the world position for this point
right so that's our vector we want that
same vector just coming out of the
surface rather than going into it what
what is the part of it that's going into
the surface right what is it you have a
unit length vector here right you have a
unit length vector so if I take the
cross I've said that's good the cross
product the dot product of that vector
with the surface normal
I get specifically this length right
because it's unit unit normal so when I
take that top rack I'm getting this
length here that means if I want to flip
this around right if I wanted to bring
it to here I would subtract away this
much if I want to reflect it I would
subtract twice that much right so I know
I want to subtract twice this dot
product right to flip it around so if I
subtract twice the stop product from the
original vector so you know if I take I
minus two I transpose and
I need a direction to do that along we
know the direction it's n so there's the
complete construction it's I minus 2 I
transpose n times n that gives me this
reflection vector I probably want to
normalize that so I'm probably going to
want to divide by the length of I to
produce a normalized version of this
equation but you know that depends on
what we're gonna do next
maybe we normalize it maybe we don't
maybe we normalize it later I don't know
but that's that's what we're talking
about here right so everyone should have
known how to do that no one should have
needed me to explain that if you did me
need to explain that you haven't been
watching a series enough so you need to
go back and watch it watch those
episodes use the episode guide to find
the part where we talk about reflection
vectors here let me help you click on
watch click on reflection right do it
watch it tons of stuff in here right
find it I know you can do it all right
so here's our basic way we're going to
produce that reflection so I want to do
exactly what I just said
and I want to produce that here in the
lighting system so that when we're per
fragment lighting we're gonna use this
information so first we're gonna take
that camera position right and like I
said we want to take the world position
minus the camera position so we we do
that and this is our inbound vector so
this is just going to be our antibellum
vector here right so that's the world -
the camera P what we then want to do is
we want to produce this equation out of
it so we're gonna want to do that I
minus 2 I transpose N and so what we
want to do there is say let's produce a
new one which is our reflection vector
our reflection vector is going to be
literally the eye minus 2 times this I
transpose and so that's gonna be like an
inner product right of I and N the N
again is the world normal so that's the
normal of the surface that we're
reflecting off of
we're then gonna have to multiply that
by some vector so we know which
direction to move along again that's the
world normal that's that entire top of
the equation there so this here is our
reflection vector do we want to
normalize it yes we probably do I don't
actually know which stuff we put in here
for our shaders I've forgotten by now so
if you look at compiled Z bias program I
think we have sort of like a boilerplate
kind of set of stuff we use for
compilation I don't actually know that I
just think that's true let's find out
yeah here it is
seriously global shader code you can see
we can do an inner product here but you
can do we do lengths here and so on
lerp clamp right so in this case what I
would like to do it looks like we didn't
define an inverse square roots
unfortunately and that's kind of a
problem because see we've got some other
stuff to find here but none of it is
really particularly helpful so what I'd
like to do is see to what extent we want
to just take advantage of GLSL there
exactly so in this case when I up so I'm
in the wrong place I wanted the web
browser or there we go I want to see
what they've got for primitives here we
should use this is a common operation
and grabs we should use there's if it's
there it is normalized is right there so
we're going to call that and so if I
want to do that I just want to put a
define in here that nas a is normalized
a like that and I think that's really
all there is to it so we here we want to
do a normalize of this that gives us our
normalized reflection vector for now
that's what we'll work with I'm gonna go
ahead and compile in theory they should
do absolutely nothing I just want to see
if we got any errors there make sure
that that is doing that that is a loud
math that I that I think it is right and
I don't know so let's just check to take
a look we've got an air Q but see
undefined variable world's it looks like
I typed something in weird
yes I did I was looking at the
reflection vector I'm like where did I
take that it's like well actually send
the line above it okay so now that we
have this reflection vector we need to
do something with it and like I said the
very first thing we could do is just
sample the light in that direction and
all that's gonna do is tell us like okay
how much light in general would we
expect to see if we looked off towards
this you know in this way so the way I
can do that right is I can think of each
of these as being a particular direction
and in fact I can just define these this
way for now and we can optimize this
quite a bit in the future but for now
I'm going to write it out longhand the
lighting west direction like we know
which direction that's coming from right
it's it's just that direction right
that's the the sort of the light normal
that the direction that the light is
coming from if we looked off in that
direction it's that right and the same
is true for any of these I can write all
of these as a specific value right so in
each case I'm going to go ahead and do
that and you can just kind of see me
doing that here
and finally up and down and so once I
have normals in each of those directions
you know I can do some pretty simple
blending if I want to I can do just some
kind of like a radial blend on these for
example or whatever I really want to so
we can think about how we want to blend
those leader but for the moment I'm just
gonna do a really really simple blend I
want to basically say it's like the dot
product fall off or something will be
how I'll blend them together and that
will just be how the lighting
contribution works or something right
and we'll we'll worry about that as we
sort of get further along with our
lighting okay um so for each of these
what I want to do is basically have a
mini utility function here right that I
can use that gives me back the the light
contribution so this here would
basically be something where I would you
know get your radiance or something like
and that what we'll do is when we sample
these textures right in fact maybe I'll
just do a pound of fine so it can
actually just be inlined in here what I
want to say is like alright so for a
light you know whatever it is and like
normal right so like a or a light value
and a light normal or something like
that if I want a sample the some
direction so like the sample normal
compute what that should be and I guess
if I do it this way actually I can just
make it a function there's no real
reason not to so I'm able do that um so
in this case I'll just say alright you
got a light value you got a light normal
you've got a sample normal and I want
this thing to return the light value
right so in this case the the result I
guess is something and I return it and
that something is going to be this
equation right
so it's basically like whatever the
light value is expanded out to be a real
light value so that's an actual
intensity like in floating point and
then I just want the inner products of
the light and sample end that tells me
the fall-off right and furthermore I
need to clamp that between zero and one
because I don't want it to ever be
negative so I just take the cosine
fall-off I use that to apply how much
light is supposed to bounce off this
thing and then then that's it right
that's it that's the light happy
birthday and that's the end of it all
right so if I was to then sample the
irradiance here and instead replace
right all of my light data summations
when actual you know their radiance
calculations here so I say all right
there's like less light West N and then
my are my sample direction right and
just nuke all of this but now what I
should be able to do is sum all my
lighting up by just you know doing east
south north down right and as long as I
use the the correct direction paired
with the value in question now I am
actually computing a really crappy but
still not completely ridiculous lighting
equation off of the light probes that
are in this you know nominal voxel or
whatever the heck is going on so now
when we look at the voxel we should see
some degree of lighting occur that has
to do with you know the direction that
you're facing looking at it here it
looks more like it's positional so we've
got some bugs but that's where we're all
right so now let's see yeah what did I
screw up let's let's fix everything
right so I again world peak camera P
that is what we want that's the inbound
vector the reflection vector is
just that that vector itself right minus
two times the inner product with the
normal times normal so that should bring
it up and we normalize that that seems
good here's all of our light normals I
think they're correct here's our summing
if irradiance is probably the wrong term
here but well so let's see how bad this
this is let's like it did we do
something wrong here I'm not sure anyway
so we're taking the dot product between
the light and the normal and we're
clamping that between zero and one which
I think should give us the correct
blending factor there right and so I'm
just trying to figure out what I really
want for now is just like why is
position involved at all right because
we're stuffing the box Allah every point
so why would the world P why would that
matter at all
oh you know what no actually that does
make sense because as we get to the
middle of the screen we're looking the
other direction so you know what that
actually makes for sense
you know that's exactly right so no I
totally take it back because remember
remember what I said originally this is
a mirror now it is literally all of our
surfaces are mirroring the incoming
light now they have a texture applied as
well so it's a mirror that is actually
colored with a pattern but it's a mirror
still and so it's going to look at the
light that's in coming from a direction
and repeat it exactly it's not gonna sum
it at all right and so as we look across
the stream eventually we're looking in
the other direction this was all looking
west right and then now we're looking
east and as we stop and start looking
east yeah we do expect that fall-off to
occur now what I don't think is correct
is the fall-off I feel like should have
been gradual so it should be getting
gradually dimmer and it should it should
have like it is tapered a little bit but
not that much like so that fall-off rate
seems like it might be wrong but it's
hard to really say because cosine
fall-off is a sine curve or cosine curve
you know so you know you do have to
wonder a little bit about that and I
guess that part I'm not really sure so
kind of a little bit tough to say I'm
not super prepared to say that it's
actually wrong so hard to say right but
for example now if we were to create
sort of a more complicated Eleni
equation we could blend those together
let's go ahead and try lighting from
different directions and make sure that
that actually creates what we expected
to create so if I go to the lighting
code and in here now I just start to
fill in different things so let's say I
feel in East now and now we should see
the opposite occur to the east situs of
the reflections that we see and just
make sure that's right again just trying
to check that lighting equation and see
if it actually works so that looks good
there right that's that's what we would
expect to see I guess
so there is one thing also I think is
wrong which is that is that I feel like
that world P is sent down from the wrong
place though so you can see this is a
slight bug we should probably fix at
some point when we're competing our
lighting we're computing it with the
debug camera when the debug can't remove
so you could see that happening here
right and that's really not what should
be happening we should be computing it
just with if the game camera so this
world P is being sent down wrong I think
so that's kind of an issue as well but
we can alright so let's try some other
ones let's try a North look North would
light and then at South red light oops
South would like first sorry
so now what were expecting to see here
so a southward light is going to be
coming from negative Y so it's coming
from this direction so what we expect to
see now is anything facing that
direction like these should just get it
totally right well I mean we're kind of
pointing downwards I guess but let's see
here and then yeah as I tilt the camera
so that seems sort of wrong to me
actually look as I'm looking I feel like
I feel like what I'm seeing is that it's
actually coming from the wrong direction
so South should be behind us looks like
that reflection is sort of wrong that
doesn't feel right to me the southward
one is so it's because it's coming from
right negative one and so as I got down
there that reflection should have been
looking out so I do think we've got a
bug here I'm not sure what it is but I
do think we've got one that doesn't look
right to me and again that could be
because the debug camera part of things
is wrong I'm not sure what's being sent
down there for that value so maybe I'm
overreacting here but I do think
something's a little fishy with that
doesn't seem correct to me if you assume
that that lighting
what would that be from and of course I
can't step into it because it's on the
GPU so you always give that nice aspect
of it so if you take a look at the light
normal and the sample normal there the
sample normal still us I don't wonder
I'm passing all these quickly as well
you can see that it's fine right so just
should be corrupt the south normal looks
fine
yeah so I don't see I don't see exactly
what's wrong with that
so I guess I can't come up with a
hypothesis for why that would be doing
that and so we may have to save that for
next weekend because I don't I can't
think of anything quickly offhand why
that doesn't appear to be lit correctly
in my opinion though just looking at
what's happening there doesn't make a
lot of sense Oh
or does it though I don't know if the
normals are correct for our sprites you
know what our normals are probably wrong
for us right that's probably all it is
so looking at it here cuz I'm looking at
the cubes and the cubes are exactly
right so I think our normals are just
wrong on our sprites right now that's
that's almost certainly what the problem
is all right so so forget the sprites
the sprites are wrong let's just not
look at those and we'll go fix the
normals our sprites some other time so
now I think that's right that actually
does look right now so that's fine I was
gonna say like I can't go everything and
the answer is because yeah we're not
looking the wrong thing all right so
let's try the northward light and I'll
just verify the rest and then we'll end
for the day so I think we're all good
here and we can then go forward with the
lighting as weak as we would have
normally and I'm sure fixing the normals
on the sprites won't be a huge deal
because we probably never set them up
right the first place all right so that
looks about right
until we find their and now let's just
try the up-and-down there's the down
again looks looks great exactly what I
want so I think I think we're good thank
you good shouldn't bother restarting the
game I don't know why I don't just go in
and make it so it downloads the thing
every time again because it won't be
that slow looks good all right I think
we're good
I'm happy with that so I think like
mostly what we need to do now is just
yeah like I mean and you know what we
could even do one last thing before we
finish so let's suppose we just do like
you know something where we do like some
some different colored lights that come
in from different areas so there's a
purple and a yellow light for up and
down right so now you've got like a
purple light coming from above a yellow
light coming from below and so we should
be able to see some kind of like vague
application on the cubes of just a
uniform blanket light in there right and
again it's a mirror right so we're
looking at these things as we tilt
around so as we come head on right you
can't really see any of it because it's
it's there's literally no light coming
from the azimuth so you can actually see
that black band in there and so as you
look straight ahead this is like a
mirror I'm looking straight down it's
nothing right back up and looking at the
purple sky right and then I come back
down here and the same would be true of
course we don't have any bright services
for the yellow ground but like for
example on a glancing angle you can see
I imagine this is a mirror right and you
look down and like the yellow sky so I
think we're exactly right I think that's
that's working working well and and I'm
happy with that
so yeah for now I'm not gonna do
anything else with it we're gonna leave
it like that and then next weekend we
can start to work on our lighting for
you know in earnest ray but I think
we're good that I'm pretty I'm pretty
happy with where we're at now that's
looking pretty good
let's go Zen site there and yeah all
right let's go to a QA and remember you
can use the disk word there's a pound
live channel on the discord if you'd
like to go over there you can actually
you can actually just go ahead and type
questions in there and I take them from
from disk or as well I think there's
also a link in the bottom of the twitch
page if you're on twitch
shouldn't it be I plus as opposed to I -
yeah I think you might be right because
the normal is pointing the other
direction already so it would be a
negative value I think you're right
not close I did close my editor don't
know why I closed my editor
um you know what else is kind of dumb
about this now that you mention it I
probably could have just used there's a
reflect function which I think I could
have used but yeah I do think you're
right because I did it in Bound I think
I did it specifically so that you could
just do a plus and then I didn't do the
plus so I'm not sure why but yeah
because the world normals pointing up
away from the inbound vector
unfortunately I'm not sure why we were
getting correct results though that
might just be bad testing but I wonder
if we have something else wrong because
it seems like it was reflecting in the
correct direction and that's confusing
which one is stuffed with so the
upward-facing light should be oh so you
know we should have known that I had
that backwards in fact that was dumb
because it was a yellow that was coming
from the top not purple so yeah we did
have that backwards good catch somebody
took my name
not sure why I glossed over that because
I just was about to do that test and I
did and then didn't notice so no that's
all yeah that's correct now so we had
the reflection going the opposite
direction I think that also probably
keeps all of the rep yes it was just it
was just flipped but otherwise it's good
you can see it still has the azimuth
that black which it should and we can't
see the purple but that's just because
there's nothing just really no way to
see the purple maybe if I did this right
there you go so there's reflecting the
purple off of the thing right we just
don't have a way to look upward
unfortunately so so yeah I can't
actually verify the purpose guy very
well but
XX to the big foxes I think subtraction
is right actually isn't it um so the the
thing you have to remember is it depends
what you're doing so if to go back to
the diagram because either one could be
correct it depends on what you're doing
if I drew that so the way I drew the
diagram it's plus oops and again you
should be able to do this at home like I
said we've done this a billion times so
you should be able to do this at home
work it out yourself and convince
yourself that you've got it but if this
is the camera position and this is the
world position here's the normal right
then there's two ways I can draw this
diagram one is I can do C minus W right
and the other is I can do W minus C so
if I do C minus W what I get is a vector
going out to the camera right so this is
going out towards the thing that's like
the I direction if I do W minus C then I
get a vector going this direction the
same vector but they're pointing in
opposite directions right so this is the
one I was talking about the eye as
opposed to it that's probably bad
incident as opposed to I right either
way so let's suppose I do it with this
one well when I take the normal right
the dot product onto the normal is
already going to be negative jaren I'm
saying so if I want to remove that
amount so I died out of the normal it's
going to be negative I want to remove
that much from the vector oh you know
what you know what maybe I talked myself
out of it
now you guys have me confused because
when I drew it the first time a cab did
sound right to me and I'm what kinda
game so but as I'm driving right now
it's I gotta say this number is negative
and you want to add the normal you want
to go in this direction so actually I
think I was right the first time and how
did i NNN I read this wrong up is purple
so no sorry okay ignoring this entire
Q&amp;A I thought yeah no it was right sorry
sorry the big Fox but anyway what I was
trying to say is if you let me go
through the rest of this though because
obviously it's confusing because you
managed to convince me I was wrong when
I didn't look at it very carefully right
but no the upward light is purple so
it's correct I don't know and then I
thought I saw that yeah I don't know
just just totally bonkers I guess this
is what happens when you program on
stream I need more coffee um so if you
take a look here at the e right let's
suppose I did it with that vector now
when I take the dot product the dot
product is positive
right and so if I want to flip this
vector around
it's a weirder kind of behavior because
what I want to do is start with the
opposite of it because I want to flip it
down here right and then if I had done
the dot product with the positive
version now I would be adding that in so
you would take negative E Plus 2 you
know blah blah blah right so either you
do I minus 2 times the thing or negative
e plus 2 times you know e transpose does
that make sense so at least I get my
full self full credit I did it correctly
I just should have said that instead of
assuming this person who wrote in caught
an actual bug it's right the way it was
and we should see purple sky so I don't
know why yeah I guess that's just
I usually assume I make a mistake but
someone catches it rather than assuming
I didn't and maybe that's the bad habit
to get into that's what it should look
like
pretty sure anyway
where would you put material information
for the lighting in the ray-tracing part
of the algorithm that we still have not
plugged in or in the shader so my
assumption and I could be very wrong
about this but my assumption is that we
will not be able to we will not have the
computational resources necessary to use
that information meaning we cannot
actually sample any real material
information so I'm assuming that what we
will actually do is we will just use a
color value at best a color value per
face but possibly just a single color
value for the entire occluder and that's
just purely for computational efficiency
obviously if if we didn't have to worry
about computational efficiency we would
actually just look up the texture index
of the occluder and see what the actual
value was at the point we hit right but
I'm pretty sure there's just no way we
could ever afford that a GPU could GPU
ray-tracing could totally this is an
Archie X card we just go ahead and do
that right by the CPU CPU sucks at
texture sampling one of the big reasons
GPUs are faster are faster than CPUs at
rendering one of the big reasons is
texture sampling CPUs actually have
pretty good math throughput it's not
horrible
right but their ability to sample
texture is frickin terrible especially X
64 X Z 4 is absolute garbage sampling
textures if avx-512 ever becomes the
thing then if that has gathered in it
and then you could start to actually
sample textures in a way that might not
be extremely slow but it would still be
horrible compared to a GPU because GPU
has special-purpose texture sampling
units built in I mean I don't even know
I am trying to get a image here where
that might show it
so I can't really get a good image I
want a die shot I don't really want that
anyway what I want is a die shot
so what I would like is a picture of
this with the texture units outlined can
I get that
sadly it doesn't look like I can
actually
she's trying to find something that
would be relatively
so I don't know I can't even actually
load this out here so I'm not sure
anyway doesn't matter point being
texture units are a big deal and CPUs
don't have that's pretty much the end of
story
AVX 512 at least has instructions so
that you don't have to downshift and
pull everything out to the scalar part
of the chip to just go fetch the memory
you need for your textures so it helps a
lot but it's not the same as having
texture units texture units are way
frickin faster than that's going to be
especially when you have so many of them
in the on a GPU so it's just it's not
it's just not gonna happen
the big fox s are the AV x load
instructions actually fast have you
tested them no I don't I guess I do have
one chip now I think I have a core i9 in
my dead machine that does have an
avx-512 instruction set but my
assumption is that well I don't know I
don't want to make assumptions my
assumption is that there really isn't
any point in profiling avx-512
instructions yet because not only are
these chips probably not particularly
good at avx-512 yet but nobody has them
anyway so even if the avx-512 load
instruction actually was fast
you couldn't ship a game youth that
relied on it right so I think avx-512
well it does have instructions that
actually make some sense is not really
interesting yet it will be maybe someday
maybe depending on how market
penetration goes but you know I I'm just
considering it a not particularly
interesting thing at the moment the big
I was gonna type in the big fox for some
reason which is one of the people who
was commenting on the street that's now
I wanted real Road tech comm gt1 200
someone posted this there it is great
thank you very much here is a diagram
unfortunately it is not necessarily a
modern chip but it is at least a chip do
you see where the texture units are on
there right so you see the memory
controllers and the texture units and
just look at how much space they take up
right I mean these are the shading units
here they're not even like half the dye
right so the texture unit itself is
really really substantial footprint
compared to the ALU Sieben right and so
you just get the CPU just done this box
isn't there on a CPU you just don't have
it right all you've got is this this
part and so those texture units you know
they don't put them on GPUs because they
think it's fun they put it on GPUs
because the only way to get the kind of
performance that you get out of modern
GPUs is to have special purpose hardware
that does nothing other than take
bilinear and trilinear samples out of
textures right because knowing that that
is what you do and welding that right up
to the memory controller so that you in
like as fast as possible get things in
cache them blend them and output them in
the color format right do the up convert
from from 8-bit to float having all that
like welded right in there is pretty
important Elvis ass was the piece ps3's
SPU's good at texture sampling no idea
never program an s2 you actually
whoo my assumption is that an SP you
would be absolutely horrible at texture
sampling in the real world and the
reason for that is how do you get a
sample a texture the ps3s SPU's relies
on scheduled DMA to fill its local
buffer it can't do anything from main
memory so you would have to have a
really deep texture querying pipeline
that has scheduled DMA is quite far in
advance and pull them in and there's not
that much space it's 20 56k of local
space I mean you can do it but it's not
the architecture you want definitely not
right
because basically I mean another way to
say it would be the way that these
things work on the GPU is they have very
deep pipelines a shader processor is
like processing tons and tons of crap
and it thinks 'yes it needs 30 different
texture fetches it issues them all those
processes and more stuff issues more and
it probably has like a gigantic stack of
texture fetches all outstanding to a ton
of texture units and all of those
textures then come back and then the
shader processor then pulls them back in
and starts working on the dependent
instructions for them right and so an SP
you just whip with 20 faces que where's
that depth coming from like it is
freaking nowhere to be found my friend
right so I really don't I mean maybe in
the ps3 days because resolutions were so
much smaller like 1080p was like pushing
it right so maybe in those days because
textures are so much smaller and vertex
buffers are so much smaller maybe you
can do something with that but like
nowadays frickin forget it right and SPU
is just it does not have the memory
throughput I'm sorry the memory
footprint I don't think to do anything
useful there and it's not really set up
the way you would want probably that's
just my guess right SPU's are much
better at localized memory operations so
for example vertex transforms right very
good I can take a in batch and an out
batch just concentrate on it chew
through little chunks at a time that's
what it's optimized for think when you
think it's when you think digital signal
processor that's what it is right and
that's what it was best at scatter
gather not its thing right
alright let's go ahead and wrap it up
Thank You Ana for joining me for another
episode of hand made here it's my
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow the series at
home you can always peer to the game on
handmade hero or comes the source code
so you can play around with it we've got
the lighting stuff mostly set up now and
so we're gonna start playing with that a
little bit more aggressively next week
OOP see you back here for that but
before I get to it maybe now would be a
good time for you folks out there to
play around with it and see what you can
do right
maybe maybe start putting some little
local area lights in there and see if
you can sample them properly who knows
right you can play around with it it's
in a good place to play around with
right now so if you're someone who
follows along with the source code at
home I would recommend it see what you
can do in advance of next week's
episodes that's about it for today I'll
be back here next week until then have
fun programming I'll see everyone on the
Internet
Diggy's everybody