alright hello everyone and welcome to
handmade hero this is the show where we
could a complete-game live on stream
although lately we have mostly been
trying to work around the graphics
driver which we have to do today we are
trying to pass integers down to our
shader and we are not getting them which
means that we are making some kind of an
incorrect call somewhere and we have the
distinct pleasure of trying to guess
where that might be now fortunately one
of the folks on the chat spotted
something that thought might be the
problem and it did sound like a pretty
good guess so that might be something we
could start looking at today we don't
really know though that might not be it
we'll find out in a second so let's go
ahead and and load up our code here and
see where we're at okay and Visual
Studio blazing speed as always there we
go
so if I go ahead and run it what you
could see here is we've colored the
surfaces in the world by what integers
it appears to be getting from the buffer
they should have been a nice gradient
wash basically we should have seen
increasingly brighter colors going from
dark to light but as you can see we're
just seeing kind of arbitrary garbage
here this is probably channels that are
all slammed to FF or something like that
or I don't know I guess they're you in
sixteen so you know more like FFF or
fffe or something like this we're seeing
lots of very bright stuff so we're
pretty sure that the first problem with
our system right now because this is in
this debug visualization tells us that
we're really just not getting the values
we actually submitted now the suggestion
from the stream which i think is a good
one was that we forgot to put an eye the
letter i' in our call i and i'll i'll
show you what i mean by that so here are
these vertex a trip pointer things here
these vertex of trip pointers are ways
of us
fine to OpenGL where we expect to get
our vertex data from and unfortunately
for us we're in this situation where we
have to make different calls depending
on the circumstance so we want this
vertex at trim point or sorry vertex at
crib pointer and you can see right here
we've got this GL vertex a trim pointer
call this is the one we're calling and
so if we take a look at the the
definition for it you can see even
though it's only listed once in the
outside there's the secret i version
underneath here right and the deal is I
guess you just have to be able to call
the right one whether you want floats or
intz because when you pass this enum
type right even though you're gonna
specify that they're unsigned shorts
instead of looking at what the shader
has defined and what you have defined
and matching them up I think it just
goes and says I'm going to convert it to
insert floats one of the other you tell
me which here and even if the other side
ends up asking for intz but you told me
to convert it to floats I'm gonna send
them as floats
sorry my friend so it's like all right
there you go so if that's the case what
that means is that these have to have an
i included like so because they have to
be vertex at rib eye pointer in order to
send down indices now everything else is
the same except for normalized because
you can't normalize something out if
it's going to be an integer obviously
it's just gonna get converted directly
so this false can go away now we don't
actually have we never grabbed a pointer
to that function in OpenGL because we've
never used it before so we also have to
go ahead and put that into our win32
platform layer so that we actually have
the ability to call it right so we need
to grab that ARB GL core GH or whatever
it's called no not drugs for chronic
heart failure that would be interesting
all right what can you say to that
so at rib eye pointers specification is
right here this is what we need to call
and so I'm gonna go ahead and grab it
ctrl C and we obviously had a trim
pointer as well the GL vertex a trim
pointer is right here so I'll just put
this right under it I will go ahead and
make that definition there and this is
all we really needed so then I'm just
going to go through and see where we did
GL vertex at rib pointer for everything
else and just make the eye version so
now in theory we should have a handle to
that function that we can call and so
now when I make the call in theory we'll
be sending them down and it looks like
that was the problem thank you very much
I forget who suggested that on the
stream let's see who we thank for that
cuz that probably saved us a lot of time
where is it supposed to be back a bit
I somehow can't find this but I don't
know why was it not a question
did it not have a cute colon in front of
it or something because I'm looking here
on the chat log but I don't see it
it was seventh chord Thank You us off
all right so thank you seventh chord for
that one because that probably saved us
a heck of a lot of time so now what you
can see here is this is more what I was
expecting
right I was expecting to see actual
values in here that sort of went
linearly upwards and you can see that
they're sort of doing that now so that
means now we could start to actually
engage with the other parts of the
problem now that we know that those
values are coming through more correctly
I'm going to go ahead and try before we
do anything else I'm gonna go ahead and
try getting rid of the unsigned value
here as well because if these are coming
through as integers then we should be
able to just get rid of the word
unsigned because the only reason we're
using a scientist because they were
shorts before and we wanted a little
more range with integers there's no way
we're ever gonna have computations for
four billion light sources two billion
will be just fine so we can definitely
set those to just regular intz and not
have a problem that also means we
wouldn't have to do any sort of casting
here like so and then we would end up
pretty much in the same situation all
right
so in theory now we should have okay
in theory now we should have the same
exact results and we do so that's good
so and hopefully that will fix anything
that Kim was saying before that he was
having problems with the
compiling unsigned into the shaders that
it was the Connecticut Potter was
complaining about it okay so what we
need to do here is now start moving back
to actually testing the lighting
information so hopefully our light count
is now a reasonable value instead of
before so we can actually do the loop
over it and we can also come in here and
try to actually call our sunlight
function and see what actually happens
so that should be good as well so we can
get rid of this branch here and here
we're just not actually ever get we're
never using the actual light of the
actual reflectance of the surface at all
at the moment we're just using the pure
light color so we're just drawing the
lights directly and seeing what we get
there right okay
so already right off the bat at least
now we're in sort of for lack of a
better term striking distance like now
it's actually sort of doing something
that resembles a real result whereas
before we had those integers were not
being sent down properly we were
obviously getting completely bogus
information now at the moment we this
like looks like our debug view is kind
of off as well and that makes sense
because our debug view is showing it
probably doesn't line up the the the
light counts and light values correctly
but the good news is that it looks like
now we're in San in we're insane land
we're insane territory right so
hopefully we can sort of push on from
here and start to get things working
properly
oops I forgot that we have a camera
thing in there that makes the the hero
look downstairs when he stops next to
the stairs
I remember that anyway so yeah so this
is what we want to focus on now and
let's let's try to do a couple different
things we've got a lot of work we can do
here I think the first thing I probably
want to address as the thing we work on
today is at this point we're sort of
verging on how we're gonna be doing this
lighting stuff and in fact it's rather
rapid as well with so many fewer
surfaces like even on the CPU side it's
very quick so I think we're definitely
getting to a place where this actually
could be something workable I'm pretty
happy with that with how fast that's
going as well so we've got a couple of
things we need to do and you can see
that like alright like for some reason
the light sources are very blown out I'm
not sure why that is happening I'll have
to look I don't know are we not
normalizing anymore or something in our
lights um or something like this I think
we are though yeah so not I'm not really
sure why we're we may have nursed
something along the way but yeah I'm not
really sure why we're not getting
similarly softer lighting results than
we were before I'm not quite sure about
that because this should still be this
is still summing the result a the
contribution values here and then it
should be it should be averaging it out
here sort of normalizing the result to a
total contribution of one so that should
still be doing roughly the same
computation as doing four so I'd have to
look to see what's actually happening
there that makes it kind of different I
also am a little bit curious what are we
sending down in our world's mode push
light call in terms of the emission
value I don't really remember yes so
we're only sending down in a mission
value of one so some things a little
book there shouldn't really be having
such a weirdly bright scenario so we've
still got to go fix that stuff up but at
least now we're in a good place so
here's the stuff that we need to do
before we start tackling the actual like
alright now let's optimize our lighting
solution also you'll note that already
we're sort of seeing what I wanted to
see which is that the surfaces are lit
but smooth right and we're not getting
those blobby sort of results in there
right and that's exactly what I wanted
to have happen so when we when we sort
of get this stuff a little bit more
straightened out I think this is gonna
solve exactly the problem that I wanted
solved so I'm pretty pleased with that
and I think we'll be able to do a
reasonable job with it
we'll see you certainly so yeah what we
need to do now though is I want to
figure out a couple different things
that we need to do and they're not
really hard they're just sort of
organizational problems so the first
thing we need to do is I think we need a
way now because we've got real lighting
that's going to be going into the
pipeline now for real we need a way of
specifying that things aren't going
through the lighting pipeline right so
right now we have the Z bias program and
even our text goes through the Z bias
program right that's a problem because
it means that our text is getting lit
right and I don't mean lit in the like
Microsoft recruiter email like hell like
getting lit on a Friday night or
whatever Monday night I'm not talking
about that I'm talking about like lit as
in actual having lighting simulation on
it and we don't want stuff like that
right furthermore when I draw the Steve
bug stuff here like I want to be able to
draw this debug stuff in a way that says
don't put lighting on it I'm just trying
to draw some values here that I'm using
as a debug display if you light it then
it's gonna perhaps get wrong values or
who knows what right so we need a way of
specifying that there's a light that
that there's a way to not light things
now one of the interesting things about
what we did is that it may be possible
to do this without actually having any
switches that we pull because since
we're sending down primitives with an
information about how many lights to use
what we could do is just have one light
at the beginning of the array or even
just a special case in the shader that
says if the light count is zero then
don't light the surface or something
right we could or if it's you
if it's you know some really high value
right we could have a special code that
says don't light it and that way we can
always send down primitives that don't
get lit just by setting something
special with those surfaces right
and so that's kind of a compelling
option one that I think I might use so
we want to do that the second thing we
want to do is we'd also like to be able
to send down occluders separately from
lighting samples right so this is
something that's kind of gonna be a
little bit tricky but what I'd like to
do is figure out a way to make it so
that we specify the same geometry and
that's what gets rendered we specify
occluder geometry and that is what
bounces the light around and then we
specify sampling geometry right and
sampling geometry is where we take those
lights or samples we kind of want
control over all of this now why do we
want control over all of this well let's
draw this out so it's clear what I'm
talking about
before we try to start typing I should
also just kill the app we don't really
need that anymore okay I just need
Milton okay all right so here we are on
day four one six and we are talking
about light and geometry
specification so what we want to do here
is we want to be able to control a
couple of different things first of all
we may want to draw something that is
not the same as the thing that's
collecting the light for example let's
suppose we are drawing one of those
trees right and so here is my tree and
this space here is all empty right we
don't necessarily want to go all the way
and start actually doing like bitmap
lookups in our ray tracing code because
the ray tracing code is supposed to be
very fast we may not want to do
something like that right maybe we do we
don't know like maybe we just maybe we
will sample textures in the ray tracing
code and allow the rays to pass through
if it's alpha zero or not if it's not
but maybe we don't right furthermore
those cards maybe in a really weird way
like this maybe the geometry of the
scene and this might be where the light
where the sprite card is being drawn but
really conceptually the thing the tree
is taking up this space right so we want
this to be the occluder not this right
this is just a fictitious drawing
element meant to occupy the space of
this thing here to the viewer right but
it's not meant to actually be the thing
that's collecting light because it's a
nonsense geometry right and we need the
freedom to be able to adjust this
geometry however we want to get the
scene to look correct with sprites so
we're going to keep playing with that
probably when we go to kind of finalize
the graphics and we really just don't
want that to affect the light we want to
be able to do anything we want with
geometry there right so we need to be
able to send down occluders separate
from sprites
so that's the first thing we want to do
and that's pretty easy because that's
just basically making a separate buffer
of occluders right so when we're doing
pushes into things we've got a blush
buffer that we push our sprites into and
our cubes into and stuff that gets drawn
on the screen and then we just have
another buffer that we push occluders
into and that's just for occlusion
purposes right that's that's what
happens so that's not difficult again
it's just bookkeeping right this is all
just bookkeeping I don't know if there's
two K's in bookkeeping or one so let's
say there's an optional Kay here this is
optional so this is all just bookkeeping
but we have to do it right so we want to
we want a thing that allows us to do
this bookkeeping where we push occluders
and we note we can have any given thing
can have an occluder or a light source
that's part of it and that is it part of
the rendered geometry it's just
something separate and they all kind of
go into sordid situations that allow us
to have and sorting I mean we're like
the Harry Potter sorting cap not sorting
as in Z order or anything so we kind of
want that stuff to be accurate right
like we want that stuff to be able to be
specified directly one or the other so
that's one thing I do the other thing we
got to do is like sampling control and
that's gonna be kind of tricky as well
so the issue that we face here is that
we need information about the lighting
environment and we may want that to be
separate from occluders and it's kind of
hard to understand exactly what we mean
by this
but yeah it's I'm not sure exactly how
possible it is to have us have for us to
have complete freedom because of the way
that the lighting solution is going to
work but let me just tell you what we
would want ideally and then we can talk
about what the chances are that we can
actually make it happen right but I
think we probably could so what we want
to do here is say okay let's
suppose that we send down an occluder
alright and furthermore let's suppose
this occluder is on something that is
actually 3d geometry like one of our
cubes that we have that's you know
creating some kind of a geometrical
feature in the game like so and so one
of the things we might want to do is try
to capture the light at a couple
different places like at the corners of
these things and maybe in the middle or
something like that so that we have some
various places that the light can be
blending too and obviously like if this
thing is here we may want to set these
points so that they're at where it joins
the next one right we don't necessarily
want those points to be at specific
locations all the time
we may often want them to be at at
things that aren't the vertex corners
right there are different locations and
so what we want to do is send down an
occluder that's just this thing and not
have to care about that and then be able
to specify whatever lighting sample
points we think are most logical right
and we don't really want to have to
break the occluder up into a grid or
anything because when it's actually
doing intersection testing we don't
actually care at first whether it hits a
particular point here we just care to
know if it hit at all right and so we
might want the occluders to be specified
as one thing and the points that are
sampled on the include err to be
specified as another and then what we
have to do though is we have to figure
out a way of these lighting samples
gaining information right based on what
ends up happening with this occluder in
the light computation
so there's a couple of different ways we
can do this one is that when light hits
the surface here after we realize that
it hit this surface we look for the
closest sample point and we assign that
hit to that sample point right so
effectively we have as many sample
points total as we specified are the
other lighting elements but each element
is assigned to an occluder that is the
occluder that will activate that light
element when hit right and it only
activates one of the lighting elements
or maybe it spreads it out to some
within a radius so maybe like when we
hit it'll add energy to all the lights
in a radius of that hit or something
right
proportional to how far away it was who
knows so we do kind of have to figure
out some sort of a way of making this
make sense but there you go so that's
what I'm more or less talking about
right so we want to be able to specify
samples and we want to be able to
specify occluders and we don't
necessarily want those two things to be
coupled by a rule a generation rule we
may want those things to be hand I mean
mmm they're got hand placed in the sense
that you know we're not editing the
level design putting them in but they're
hand placed from the perspective of the
the world generation where when things
are created next to each other or
anything else like this we want them to
be able to set their sample points in a
logical fashion right so that's
basically what I'm talking about here
and this is all just bookkeeping which
we kind of need to do so I think that's
what we want to do today and and again
just to relist it here let's actually
this the three things we want to do so
we want an occluder buffer we want
samples
/ occluder and we want no lighting
lighting right which is to say some way
of specifying that a thing doesn't isn't
supposed to get any light at all it's
just supposed to be drawn normally all
right so let's start on these three
things and see how much of them we can
get done today
that is our goal so the first thing the
no light lighting at the moment we don't
really have to worry about optimization
too much because we're still kind of in
the experimental phase of everything so
really let's just go ahead and for the
moment do the simplest possible thing
and that is that instead of calling
sunlight on something what we can do is
say if the light index or the light
count or something is a special number
then we will do no lighting so for
example let's just say that light index
one so you know if the frag light index
equals zero then we will say that any
anything that has a frag light index of
zero does not get lit right and Pat's
the better way to say this would be well
since the surface reflect color coming
through here is normally unadulterated
what we could actually do is just put
all of this stuff entirely within this
here right so then we could say oh all
right if you want to send that something
that doesn't have any lighting then if
the frag light index it's not equal to
zero will do the sunlight call and we'll
modify the surface reflectance
in fact we could now actually put that
in there like so right and then what
we'll do is if you want to keep
something unlit you just set the frag
light index equal to zero and off you go
right so I think that's really all there
is to it
I don't think there's much else so now
when I run this of course that will mean
that pretty much everything should say
as normal except for one thing the very
first thing that gets drawn will be
unlit and you can see it right there
right then everything else will be lit
so then all we have to do is make sure
that now when we actually send things
down we correlate them properly in that
way so when we have a render group here
and we're sending these things down what
we could do is now just say okay
in the render group not sure exactly how
we want to do this but in the render
group we can say that we you know have a
boolean or something that turns on
lighting so we can have like lighting
enabled is some you know some kind of a
boolean that we specify here right and
we actually we also have a render
transform thing and maybe we can put it
we can put it in there too if we want to
like we do the default upright transform
or the default flat transform those
things those transforms had stuff in
them that we were using before as well
we could potentially use that I'm not
sure which one makes more sense for now
I think I'll use the render group and
that will have light enabled and it'll
also have light index in there probably
and what we'll do is we'll just say you
can turn the lighting on and off via
this via the render group right all
right so when we go in to push quad what
we can see is that push quad had
hard-coded a light count and a light
index in here right and so what we want
to do here is we want to say all right
the light count and the light index we
only want to set them to something
if lighting is enabled so normally you
know in this case we could take a look
at the render group here somewhere right
there it is
so basically say if the group lighting
enabled then we do some lighting
otherwise we just leave these at zero
values right
so here we'll say okay maybe the light
count equals four if lighting is enabled
right and then we'll set the light index
whatever is getting sent down that will
be the light index for the group and
then we'll say lighten the group light
index gets incremented by four so that's
just doing four lights per and what we
want to extend this to in the future
obviously is we want to be able to
change this to have it so that when
people are pushing quads down they can
choose how many letting samples they're
sending right but at the moment now
we'll just have a thing that allows us
to not do lighting if we don't want to
do lighting right okay so now since that
should be initialized to zero by default
nothing should be lit right so
everything is now not going through the
lighting pipeline and this is nice too
because here you know you can see when
we are doing our debug display we can
actually see the results that do display
not going through lighting our debug
stuff actually works now as well so
that's all nice as well and everything
is kind of happy and pleasant at that
point so that's all good but now we want
to kind of let me see here I have a
question
can we run it full res now
yeah I was wondering why we were so
blurry and I was like oh I forgot we
dropped the res way down when we were
fussing with some of the other lighting
stuff yeah looks so much nicer at 1920
by 1080 um maybe doesn't on the stream
because you know compression is on
anyway so now if we want to turn on
lighting there's a couple of things you
want to do so what we want to do here is
in the render group that light index we
kinda have a problem with we don't want
it to be set to zero right because zero
means we're not going to do any lighting
so we want to make sure that the first
thing we send down in a render group is
gonna be a 1 or something right so when
we initialize the render group right
here what we want to do is make sure our
initial set up there has the light index
of 1 that way we always start at
something that we'll get with and again
it's this render setup thing here this
is where I don't know like because this
candles like clip recs and stuff I don't
know if that might be a better place for
the lighting to live I'm really not sure
it depends on whether you tend to
alternate lit versus unlit things and I
really don't know so we're gonna find
out so then what I'm going to do is I'm
just gonna have an inline void here
called a naval lighting and inside here
I'm just gonna say alright like enabled
was true
sorry lighting enabled all right so now
my hope is that here in the worlds mode
when we do the begin render group for
update and render worlds we can just
enable the lighting here and be off with
it now I don't actually know who should
do it because I don't know if anyone
wants to be able to do unlit stuff in
there as well
I'm not really sure but you can kind of
see in here right we get a render group
and we call some stuff and it looks like
to me like it really just wants to get
enabled in there probably I'm not
totally sure exactly where I want that
to be eventually but probably here is
where we want that to happen I'm
guessing right and then hopefully you
know from there now you can see we've
already kind of got one positive aspect
of it is now our our debug stuff can
actually be visible because we kind of
didn't have that working before the way
we would have hoped right and now if I
run the lighting we get the lighting
solution as we should and what I should
be able to do now is in this when we're
drawing the debug lighting I should be
able to intentionally make debug
lighting output like if we're in world
mode show lighting I can just say like
if we're not showing up lighting right
because I don't want to enable lighting
unless we're trying to actually let's
show the world so now in our debug
display lighting is turned off so we can
actually see the real values as they
appear which is what I wanted and then
when we do the actual scene render we
can see it lit by the values in question
which again is is the goal right
I'm gonna get that little drinky-poo
all right um so I think that's really it
for that part of the problem like I
think that's all we needed
basically that's just you know that's
just it lighting lighting over letting
done and so I think yeah like it sure
seems to work okay everything that
should be lit is lit everything that
shouldn't be lit isn't lit so it's all
good so I think then that would be ready
to then start working on the lighting
quality which again we're not going to
do quite yet because we got to do the
other two things we said we're going to
do which is and I can even we have to do
the occluder buffer and the samples for
occlusion stuff so what we want to do
here again is like this this seem sort
of shows you everything you need to know
about exactly what we need to do here so
if I go over here and and look at what's
happening so these trees are actually
those like cards that are kind of
sticking out there and that's not really
very helpful in terms of doing lighting
solutions it basically means that for
example like if you look at the way in
which these trees will block light it
appears when you're looking at these
trees that they're tall trees right
they're like you know that's a tree that
you are looking at and it should be
fairly high I don't know if it should be
as high as maybe one of these but it
should be pretty high so you would
expect it to be blocking like one tiles
worth of light or so over here you would
expect this tile to be shadowed and have
a lot less light falling on it if the
light was coming from over here
however that is not what will actually
happen and the reason for that is
because the light is actually almost not
blocked at all there's just this really
laying down flat thin kind of thing
right
and so it's the opposite of what you
would want for shadowing things on the
other side there so that's the problem
as it stands at the moment and what we
want to do is we want to go ahead and be
able to like replace stuff like that
with little stand up you know
rectangular prisms or something that
will block the light as if they were
straight up and down for the purposes of
a lighting solution right and what we
actually replace them with I don't know
but we just need some way of specifying
quads right an alternate you know we're
drawing this one quad we want to specify
an alternate maybe like two quads maybe
in an X shape or something like that
that would cut just to cut light out
here right and furthermore we also
probably want the ability to light this
tree the same would be true right we
need a surface that will collect the
light and map that on to the tree if
that makes sense and so we kind of need
a way to collect those lighting samples
which we also don't have right so I
think that's pretty much everything we
said I can think of yeah
it's gonna be fun to have this working
in real time it already sort of is
pretty quick I'm not sure will
I guess just because we cut down the
number of occluders I'm curious how slow
we run if we run it real time I don't
actually know sorry to get distracted
here but I kind of just want to see what
happens if we just run it every time I'm
gonna get rid of this so now you know
when I run this around right I can I'm
sure it won't run fast enough to do real
time but I'm just curious so it's it's
surprisingly fast compared to what I was
expecting right and you can kind of see
that like hey that's actually gonna be
kind of cool as we get that smoothed out
uh-huh and and improve the quality of
those and that's plenty fast to run on
the GPU as well I think but you know we
don't we're gonna have to do work to
smooth out the values we don't want them
to flicker obviously it's stuff like
that but we haven't even gotten this
down to a real lighting solution anyway
yet so there's that as well but that's
gonna be kind of nice once we have that
working because it'll really allow us to
sort of have some cool lighting effects
in the game that we definitely would not
have been able to have any other way
right
yeah so we're definitely getting there I
think it's been worth the trouble to try
and figure out a good way to have our
scene be lit in a quasi accurate way
just so we can start to have some of
those kind of nice interesting effects
and yeah it just looks like most of our
problem is gonna probably be as we
improve the letting quality solution
which I think we'll be able to do pretty
easily it looks like most of our
problems just gonna be making sure that
our values don't flicker over time
that's part of the part of having a
stochastic process is that if you get
under sampled regions they're highly
likely to flicker because the random
value sometimes get things in that area
and sometimes don't right and so you
know one way to work around that is
fiction right you can make all of your
lights be torches and then all of a
sudden nobody complains right because
it's they think it's just part of the
effect but yeah assuming that we want
sort of stationary lit environments that
don't have flickering light sources but
you know honestly I don't know that we
have any of those I think everything we
have is supposed to be kind of lit
flickery so for all I know we won't
really have to do that much work but
yeah we will make these more stable over
time either way just because I think
there's a lot of stuff we can do to
improve the sampling quality but it's
just kind of cool that this is already
running on the CPU in real time without
us having optimized it at all that's
kind of reassuring and nice because it
means that we probably won't have a huge
uphill battle to to make some scenes
right now there'll be more lights in a
scene than this but again we will be
attacking that with some
multi-resolution stuff because we're
only really going to be doing bounces on
on full geometry in areas like right
where we are right we're not going to do
it for everything but that's pretty cool
actually
so yeah so not not 60 frames a second
but also not optimized and running on
the CPU so that bodes well I think right
that bodes well for when we need it to
be 60 years
you know if it was running it you know
one one frame every five seconds or
something that would that's a lot
scarier cuz the gap that you have to
bridge to get it to perform it is just
so huge right okay so and that's
probably just because we're compiling an
optimized mode right so we're getting
probably the compiler is doing an okay
job of like maybe making some some good
decisions there I don't know all right
so what we want to do now is we want to
go ahead and move to the sort of
separate occluders and world geometry
kind of mode of thinking and this is
gonna be useful not only because not a
not only because we don't really want to
have too many occluders in the scene but
the other reason we don't really want to
lock those two together is because
certain things you might want to draw
there might be a lot of them and we
don't want them to bog down the letting
solution so for example let's say we've
got something that that's like spewing
out like thousands of particles right
well thousands of particles would
immediately tank our lighting solution
we can't afford to light each individual
particle as if it's it's own reflector
or distributor kind of a thing right
maybe in ten years we'll have that kind
of technology our horsepower at our
disposal but not today so we're gonna
want to be able to put in sort of meta
information like meta occluders for
things like that so that particle
systems are just broken up into regions
and lit you know with with sort of
approximate geometry and that sort of
thing so because we need to do stuff
like that we it's not just for accuracy
purposes that we need to do this right
it's not just so we can avoid the like
weird slanted tree is not you know
collecting the right light scenario it's
all
because even if some some things that we
draw even if they would work correctly
if we push them all through the lighting
system we can't afford the the time
budget the processing budget to actually
compute all that lighting and so that's
why this changes is important for those
reasons as well so if we go in here and
take a look at what we're gonna have to
do to have these two things kept
separate what we know right now is we
sort of have a platform vertex structure
what does it called textured vertex that
gets communicated to the graphics
subsystem and what you can see here is
this thing has the light index and the
light count value attached to it and
then it's using the lighting textures to
gather that information fundamentally
this doesn't have to change at all
what does have to change is instead of
pulling the occluders out of this we now
just need some other thing here which is
a light occluder or something or maybe
we'll just call it a lighting surface we
were calling them lighting elements I
don't think we actually want let's take
a look at this so here's the lighting
elements and what you can see from this
is that most of the stuff that's getting
sent down
so it does kind of look like we could it
does kind of look like we could just
start talking about these lighting
elements directly perhaps so just to
sort of sketch out what we need to do
here right so we kind of have surfaces
and points right and the points if we
were to distribute these things that if
we were to take the things that were
previously composed together to form a
single lighting element and slip them up
into the things that occur at sample
points versus the things that are
surface based right then what we pretty
much see is we've got this stuff here in
the lighting surface we have where it is
what its normal is right whether it's
transparent width and height it's x-axis
and I don't really know whether the
color should be prayer lighting point or
not so let's just say for now that
that's that it's this way so you've kind
of got a lighting point which is a point
on one of these surfaces it's got a
reflector in an emitter right so this is
how it reflects light this is how much
it's emitting at the moment and then we
would have these would be break it
broken up into sort of lighting
immediate s--
intermediates rather so you know you
would specify the lighting services and
the loading points and then you would
specify and then it would generate
lighting intermediates for those which
are done in sort of passes right where
there's sort of an accumulated emission
and there's a direction to the light
source right and those things are
normalized later so I think that's
mostly what we're talking about here I
don't really know but that seems like it
may be sort of a little bit kind of
possibly and the only other thing we
need is to understand how lighting
points are distributed on lighting
services and really those are just going
to be this stuff right so every lighting
surface is going to have information
about how many points in the point array
go with it and those are going to
directly correspond to people who want
to use those here right so we would have
the exact same thing up here so this
would be our lighting surfaces and these
would be our lighting points these would
be our intermediate values that got get
computed by the lighting system they
don't necessarily need to be defined
here and I think that's basically it we
would no longer have lighting textures
as a thing that's not really something
we would need anymore because the only
stuff that gets put in there is the next
emmitt C and the average direction of
light so all of this stuff would kind of
go away and the voxel stuff would go
away right all of that stuff so the C
and the D values
the C value is the next omit C the D
value is the average direction to light
right so that lighting intermediate is
really the thing that we're computing
and you know we could just send it down
directly it depends on how feisty we're
feeling but obviously we could just have
it so that those two textures you just
have two floating-point textures you can
send them down right
so anyway that seems like the sameness
way to break those apart so let's just
go ahead and suggest that we're going to
go ahead and do that and you know maybe
I will send down those lighting
intermediates directly I'm not sure all
right so I think first things first
let's take this slowly because again
this is GPU code on the back end and it
is hard to debug GPU code right GPU code
you don't have a lot of visibility in it
so what we want to do is we want to take
it in in slow managed steps so that we
can see if we break anything you know
right away and and we eliminate the
number of things that could break in any
given change so that it's easier for us
to debug right so all I want to do here
is just get that compiling here and then
in here where we have our lighting
solution what I'm gonna do with that is
I'm gonna pretend so so before we're
doing is we're taking all these vertices
down we're extracting them out into a
lighting solution and then wrangling
solution in fact what we're doing now is
free when we're pushing we're gonna pre
make the things that we're using what I
want to do first is actually still run
the extraction pass so instead what I'm
gonna do here is I'm going to say oK
we've got these lighting surfaces that
we're gonna pull out we've got those
letting points that we're gonna put out
and then we've got our lighting
intermediates okay and then what I want
to do is I want to go ahead and make
these buffers be extracted and run the
letting station that we already have on
them okay so when we do extractor from
extract reflectors from quads what I'm
going to do is I'm just going to have
three things here I'm going to have
surface point and intermediate yeah like
so and then everywhere that this thing
all right so everywhere that this thing
actually was accessing a specific one of
these we're gonna access like we're
gonna access all three so in here we're
looping through let's just use the
single index for this so you know we've
got let's say we've got an element index
you know what now I think about it we're
these are going at different rates so I
guess we don't really want to even do
that so I guess we really do want to do
something like this where we just say
okay the surface point an intermediate
like so and as we come down through here
what we want to say is all right we're
going to extract a a surface and this
surface is going to be the whole width
and height right so for example here
we've just got that this is the P
equation here is actually fine but we
need to do the middle P equation so
we're gonna need something like this so
here's like the location of our occluder
or our surface rather than the X sub
thing here we really just want to do 0.5
times width and 0.5 times height right I
think that's right
let me go ahead and look at all the
things we need to fill out here so we
have to fill out P and and now I think
about it do we really need to fill out n
here or should mb per point I don't
really know
it depends on whether we want to model
different facing directions I don't
think we do so I think they all want to
have the same facing direction probably
because we need that for coming so I'm
gonna leave it there
transparency width and height x axis Y
axis and these two okay
so here we are recording the surface
that we actually wanted and what we need
to do now is we need to have for that
surface we need to produce a bunch of
points right so you can see we've got
this point here also we might as well
say at the end of this right we're doing
plus plus surface I don't know what bit
maps is doing here probably it was from
the old days when we were still
recording that we're not recording it
anymore so we can just get rid of that
that's a dead variable it's not doing
anything
so plus plus surface will advance that
surface for us and then we've got this
subdivision count and so the subdivision
count is going to give us our points so
we're basically to modify a bunch of
points and then do a point plus plus
right and on the point we also have the
inter meet two intermediate values like
so right okay although well you know
what honestly because we know the offset
of these we probably should just use it
so that whatever the light index is set
to we can actually use right we also
don't want to light anything that is set
to zero so the other thing we can do
here is say if vert zero light index
equals zero we don't do it
right
so I think that's mostly what we want
here seems saying so if the latex is my
equal to zero we pull out all the
information and we create the surface
from it and now we just need to create
the points from it and the point is
gonna be points plus surface light index
or I should say just maybe just light
index right intermediate plus light
index and here we're gonna do a plus
plus light index and that light index is
just going to start off late index zero
and then here we're going to just do an
assertion that light index equals the
light count and in in the future what
we're gonna do is use this light count
to tell how to strip how to distribute
points probably will say however many it
asks for will distribute them although
in the future we're probably going to
want them to be distributed more
manually or more specifically like so
they'll probably be the person who
pushes the quad will say how they're
distributed so this probably won't
distribute them in this way right this
routine would be hoisted up to a more
knowledgeable place so anyway we're
gonna go ahead and and write these out
here so we've got the point P we know we
want the this stuff is not relevant
anymore we know we want the ref color in
here right we don't need the
transparency because that can't vary so
it's gonna stay the same as above we've
got the emission amounts as well and
then we've got the intermediate values
which just need to be cleared right and
we could have just cleared the whole
buffer and maybe that's what we should
do in the future but that's the GP
you'll be doing that
and I think that's it right so that I
think should initialize the surfaces and
the points and everything else there
right
we need this color value to be unpacked
here
and let's see then we're yeah then we're
sort of good to go so now when we do ray
casting if the Ray casting really just
needs to figure out when it's doing its
testing it it really doesn't have to
test against as many services as it used
to right before we were forcing it to do
a ray cast against four times as many
services as we will now and that's a big
reason for bundling those occluders
together right if you have a big old
plane you can test against to see if you
hit it even if you're taking samples all
over that plane you'd rather just test
the hit on that one surface then figure
out where you were closest to right so
what we want to do here is say all right
go through the sources these sources are
specifically going to be lighting
services for each one of the elements
that we go through we really want the
surface count here so we're going to
need to record that right in the
lighting solution so in the lighting
solution we need two separate things
here
we need a surface counts that's how many
surfaces to test and we need a light
count or a point count that's how many
sample points there are now we don't
really need to know what the point count
is because the point count is just kind
of always known from the other
information you have but we probably
want to store that because eventually we
have to send down the point information
as a sub texture maybe we want to know
how many there were I don't know so
we'll keep that value for now but it's
not really that important right so here
we have solution we know what these are
just by default we know the surface
count is going to be although we don't
actually now I think about it no we
don't know that because since things can
be taken out of the lighting solution we
don't know that ahead of time so yeah so
we really actually do need to track
these now that I think about it so let's
go ahead and do that so here is our
surface count
here is our point count and I'm gonna
put these at the end
oops and we will go ahead and do this
the other way round
so again just because we're still using
so couple fixed arrays for this just
let's just make sure we're not out of
bounds for now because hey we might miss
something and that would be stupid
right so I can go ahead and and inline
that plus there and we could so point
count is harder because point count
could be anywhere really in the array so
we really just need to do a max on that
that value we really need to my max on
that every time we use the light index
we basically have to see okay is the
light index greater than the solutions
point count if so and maybe the right
way to write this actually is is it less
than and if it is it should become equal
to right so every time we use the light
index we check and we have to bump those
bounds up and we can also assert when we
do that that the solution point count is
less than the light data with
so that just makes sure like if there's
some funny business going on we were
overwriting that buffer during testing
we would see and know that we were like
oh yeah right you got to fix that okay
so let's see in here this will just be a
surface count well I guess it needs to
be point count because we're gonna tell
you which point you hit probably
probably since we don't do final gather
anymore
so I'm not sure exactly how we want to
do this this we don't do final gather
staff stuff anymore we only do forward
push and we might not do final gather I
might slightly change the way this goes
so maybe we only really need to return
the I value here and we don't need to
return the color value right because
it's not really getting used anymore
and if we take a look at gather final
lighting right all it's doing is
normalizing the direction so this is not
you know the hemisphere sampling
nonsense it's not really doing anything
for us we if spirited out so the problem
is yeah we still wanted a way to do the
skylight stuff and maybe we want to do
some samples take some samples for the
skylight stuff that's a hard I'm not
sure but either way I don't think we
want to return the color in there
because yeah that just doesn't make
sense so I think we're gonna go ahead
and change this slightly all right this
is gonna just return the u-32 so we'll
just say that the u32 results
is going to be the element counts the
service count rather and when we go
through here we'll do everything else
that we want to do here I guess you can
just kind of do write it all just works
and then the results will just be equal
to the source index in the case where we
we hit properly right and I think that
just works so now if we want to do a
sample accumulation here like we were
doing before what we need to do is we
need to have a way of getting like the
normal and also the intermediate so it
needs two things it needs the surface
[Music]
and it needs the intermediate so it
needs the surface there
and the intermediates they're in there
right
so in compute light propagation what
we're doing here again is saying like
alright we got a loop through all of our
surfaces and figure out which ones are
shining light out anything so for this
what we want to do is we want to take a
look
per surface at the lights involved now
this is a little bit tricky because we
don't have a way of going back to the
the surface from which we're emanating
the light but maybe we don't care like
so we've got two choices here right and
I'm not sure which one makes more sense
one is that we say that each lighting
point also stores its normal right eye
and if each lighting points toward its
normal we would know what the hemisphere
was that we were trying to sample from
that point and we wouldn't have to look
backwards at the lighting like back ref
to the lighting surface to figure out
what the normal was right
so that's would make it so we could just
do a loop directly over the points but
we also wouldn't know how to take each
lighting service out we wouldn't know
how to do the suppression right because
we wouldn't know what the index was so
it seems kind of tricky and it suggests
that we kind of need to have the sub
loop I'm just worried that that sub loop
is gonna cause problems so I wonder if
you just want the data duplicated in
there you know I'm saying
rather than compressing it away like I'm
wondering if basically it shouldn't just
be this because you just want to loop
over all of your lighting points and do
the lighting directly on those points
you don't really want to be looking back
at the lighting services for any
particular reason pulling them into the
cache for no reason at all right
although everything may be fitting in
the cache I don't really know so that
may be a poor consideration but point
being you still have to do that extra
indirection for no reason and have an
extra loop and all that stuff so it
seems like you may want those things
duplicated so I'm gonna duplicate them
for the time being and then I guess
we'll just have to figure out I'm gonna
have to figure that out later because we
don't really have enough information to
know I really don't know but obviously
they're pretty easy right to do it you
just have
the surface index and the normal are
just inherited and that's it so what
happens at that point is we're doing
compute light propagation we would just
be the only thing we would be iterating
over right is the are the points
themselves right so I guess we can call
that at the emit index and that's going
to loop over the point count and we're
just going to loop over any points in
theory all the points should be used
besides point zero right we know point
zero was never used but every other
point should be because we decided that
the light offset zero was was the key
that you weren't doing any lighting
right you did not want to do any
lighting
[Music]
all right so anyway if we go over each
of these lighting points like so then
for each one of them we can take a look
to see whether or not it can it has any
emission to spray out into the world and
if it does then we can do our ray cast
and we'll get back a hit index if the
hit index suggests that we've hit a
surface then what we need to do is
figure out what the lighting point is
that we actually hit right now this is
not immediate we have to then take a
look to see for each of the lights in
that surface how far they are from the
hit point and wait are lighting
contribution accordingly or we can just
use the closest one like I don't know
which of those would be better again
this is very approximating what we're
effectively saying is if I have some
points on the surface and I hit
somewhere where do I record the light
right which of these gets the light that
was hit and one thing to do would be
like to spread it out among couple of
them another thing might be just give it
to the closest one another one would be
to give it to all of them and it just
gets weighted as it goes that's
something we're just gonna have to tune
because again it's like well we're
trying to do something that we would
like to do at every point on the surface
and we're approximated by doing it a few
points is thereit's which approximation
gives the more pleasing results for the
types of lights that we're using in the
types of services you're using I don't
know so we are gonna have to do a little
bit of a loop-de-loop ear where we go
through each of the so we have like a
surface you know point index equals zero
surface point index is less than I guess
what i want to do here is say that we
have a hit surface and that's going to
be the solution surfaces plus the hit
index so for each surface point index up
to what we called this no there we go
it's just light count so each of these
surface point index each of these two
different nations refers to a sub point
on the surface so we've got sorry so
we've got each individual point being
referenced off of sort of the sub region
that this surface corresponds to so we
take its first light index we add the
one that we're on relative to the
surface point and that gives us back one
of the points and then we can accumulate
our hit sample there right now what we
don't know is we don't actually know
what the amount of I guess the light
power if you will that we're getting
here we can modify that power by the
distance for example to the point if we
wanted to so for for example what we
could say is that the higher that
distance the less it should be or
something else like that so we could say
like you know you know this power equals
whatever the light power should have
been you know divided by like 1.0 F plus
the distance or something like that
right so we could do like distance
squared to the point and have like a
fall-off so that the amount that gets
added is you know is it's different sort
of that I'm not gonna try
to do that yet
because that's a little bit too much for
this pass through the code alright so
let's take a look here so we have oops
that's supposed to be in it yeah
and that needs to take the intermediate
as well I guess so this is the point
index so now we have both of those like
point to letting surface oh so we don't
actually need the hit point at all we
actually just need to surf the surface
that got hit which we know and the
intermediate we don't need the point I
guess all right it's so for a final
portion through here we can see we're
doing here is this is actually sort of
collapsing the intermediates and the
points together so that's gonna be
another one of these loops that goes
over the emitters like so like this and
so this is going to be
between points and intermediates and as
we go through those rename that
two-point index a little clearer as we
go through those
we just need to say that whatever the
point is versus the intermediate in
which you know reference the correct one
of those as we pull out the values but
that's really it so I think
average direction to light is kind of a
little wonky and that's probably
something we want to look at in a little
more detail later but one of the things
that we probably should do here I think
is just put this at the end of this and
then just get rid of this scatter final
lighting nonsense because we're not
doing that anymore
so we should just normalize at the end
to be done with it all right so that's
pretty much all of the modifications to
this routine that needs to happen so now
we just have to deal with the stuff that
actually outputs any of this stuff and
we need to come up with ways that we can
visualize what we're looking at here
right so this is a little tricky because
now we sort of have two pieces of
information we have points and we have
reflectors and we probably want a way to
visualize either of those two things and
so I think what we're gonna want to do
here is have two two different routines
one that's like output the sample points
and one as little tiny rectangles and
one that's like output the surfaces as
what they actually are and maybe just
draws them with their average amount of
light that they have so average the
points together something like this
I'm not going to quite write those yet
so instead we're just gonna take a look
at this and see if we can have put this
stuff correctly I'm tempted to start
deleting the voxel code just so it's not
in the way because I'm pretty sure we're
just never gonna use it again I think
this is the better way to go but you
never know it's hard it's tempting but
you never know okay so when we come
through here what we need to do we don't
need those surfaces any more of those
are not relevant right so all we need to
do is just go through our points and
copy our points over so we should just
be able to say that the points as they
come over I think it's just the
intermediate values that we need right
it's just the oh no but we copy the
emits the in
so I think we just go through all of
these and we copy them all over right we
can even copy zero over even though it
doesn't really ever get used it doesn't
really matter so we go through here and
take all of the same measurements we're
taking before we don't really have to
look at the desk D packed stuff for the
P next stuff that stuff's not getting
used anymore right
so all we really have to do is just pack
to the point index
so all we should really have to do here
is take the intermediates and the point
values copy them down to the textures as
before can off we go all right so now we
got to take a look at what
oh wait that's not that's not gonna do
anything this actually needs to be
probably more like this go just verify
that we're gonna add as many as we're
supposed to let's try again all right
well not particularly good results here
since I'm not getting any actual
lighting um so let's step through and
see where we're at all so I'm gonna go
ahead and turn off the optimizer so that
I can step through this more easily
all right sir first index equals zero
which is what we'd expect here's our
first surface and looks reasonable
nothing particularly weird there let's
take a look at our lights
again seems pretty reasonable
so that all seems pretty good we got 468
surfaces and zero points so cap yeah
forgot that we were putting that in a
temporary variable let's try that again
so that looks again relatively okay so
that may have been our only significant
problem there let's go ahead and change
that back to Oh two
so there we go
now again this is going to be
drastically worse because right now
we're not actually correctly handling
the fact that we've got multiple points
we're not like adding that light in any
sane way right we're we're we're taking
every hit to a surface and adding it to
all the points on that surface which is
kind of busted right so anyway but what
you can actually see here in an amusing
way is that even just that change of of
reducing the count by four because ray
tracing is entirely determined the speed
of a ray tracer is pretty much dominated
by that ray cast reducing the number of
things I had to Ray cast against by four
sped up our frame rate to the point
where we're almost running at thirty now
we're not quite we're more like running
at fifteen right but it's pretty
hilarious just how much that one change
helps right but that's why I wanted
again those occluders to be things that
can be specified in a different way from
the actual geometry and the actual
lighting sampling because we may want to
sample the lighting more densely than we
actually do occlusions on now remember
we did not actually decrease the number
of points we were sampling we we still
did t-this the samples as separate
points we emit from points so we're
still looping over the same number of
those we just reduced the number of
things we can hit when we do our test
because we you know don't need to trip
to test against as many so that's kind
of nice and again continues to bode well
for the future work that we might want
to do here right okay so that's all good
and I think that lets us keep these
things separated now the thing that I
don't like about the way we had to write
that was I don't like the way I the
point of having a lighting intermediate
here is that you want to have something
that you write to all the time so I
think that it may be the case that the
lighting point information and the
lighting intermediate information I
think that maybe this needs to get
merged into here or something I need to
think about how that's working because I
think there needs to be like two of
those buffers or something like this but
you don't want to have to read from the
lighting point the solution should be
encapsulated in the lighting
intermediate I guess is the thing so
so it's kind of hard to say how we want
to do that but I think really it's
actually probably the case that we want
completely separate buffers for it I'm
just thinking about how this has to
eventually be moved down to hardware
right
nothing's not running and hardware
already but you know what I mean
and it feels like the average direction
to light is just an accumulation buffer
that constantly gets accumulated over
and over and over again and it never has
anything done to it except at the very
end when it gets normalized right so
that's pretty straightforward that that
would just be its own thing that doesn't
really have anything else to do with
anybody the omission on the other hand
ping pongs back and forth you start with
1 emission buffer that's the input
emission you write to a new emission
buffer as you go right and then you swap
them so I feel like the lighting
intermediate actually kind of wants to
be something more like this
that sort of thing and you would just
ping-pong the these two back and forth
right so what I want to do is I want to
say all right I I take average direction
to light that's always getting
accumulated until the very end gets
normalized I take admit see in next to
Mitzi and every pass through the light
propagation I swap which buffer I'm
pointing to as my source emits seed
right so it's kind of like source emit
seed estimate see and they swap I don't
know if she'll let me swap these two
pointers let me I always forget what it
has a problem with them what it doesn't
in the actual memory would work but I
don't remember always which of those two
will happen but what I do want to do
here is just say like okay so we need
the we need the clearing here to
basically say that
solution destined at sea of whatever our
light index is solution average light
direction those are both going to get
cleared and then this is gonna be a
solution sourcing it see light index
like that okay I guess that to do can
stand it's still relevant and so then in
here when we do these sample
accumulations really all we need is we
need the index here and then we can just
do
that
okay so these have to be point index
indexed and these intermediates here
[Music]
yeah now that I think about it I don't
really know I that was just kind of a
brain fart C's not going to do that
because it's gonna actually just put
this mini vector threes in there right
so these have to be pointers this one
can cannot be but these have to be
because otherwise it'll just put all the
vector threes in there and I just
actually want just a pointer right that
I'm referencing off of so I can flip
them
although
that's not entirely true I could choose
to still do it like this and do it
slightly differently what I could do is
say instead that and then what I could
do is say alright emit c0 is going to
get initialized to the thing emits c1 is
going to be the cleared one then the
decimate see here is actually that has
to get passed in right so what we would
do is we'd say no you don't get to do
that you have to actually pass me at the
destined at C and the average light
direction sorry that's just something
you're going to have to do
okay then in here instead of the
intermediate stuff what we do is we're
gonna have to pass it those two things
so what we want to do is we want to say
okay the solution average direction to
light that vector we know is pretty easy
to get always the other one is harder to
get because that hit intermediate there
that actually is going to have to be
whatever the desk emits E is and that
will be a pointer that changes each pass
through right so it's gonna look like
that instead okay so then what we do up
here is we have our destined at C and
our source in it C like so and those two
pointers will start out pointing to the
emit C 0 and the emit C 1 right so we've
got both of those two pointers are set
to the correct values and then when we
actually go to use them we're using one
of the two buffers but we can always
switch with which one we're using at any
time right what is the complaint here
argument oh yeah so these are pluses not
brackets right so anyway in here for the
intermediates now we have eliminated
those entirely so anything that was
doing intermediate needs to actually
talk about the thing it was talking
about directly so here where we talk
about the point amid C or any of this
stuff we don't have to do this
accumulation step anymore exactly on to
the points themselves those are between
the destined source emissions so instead
what we do is we just say okay let's get
rid of all this we just say that
whatever the whatever the source emits E
was and I guess we don't have to swap
them if we're going to do it this way
maybe
if we're actually doing a sum here which
is kind of odd if we actually keep doing
a sum here then we don't have to swap
them if we stop doing the sum which I
think we probably will then we would
just swap them but if we keep doing the
sum then we don't have to actually do
that right if we keep doing a sum here
then we're gonna have to go over them
every time anyway so we can't just swap
them and clear one of them so I guess
we'll have to see I guess we'll have to
see how that shakes out and I'm not sure
how it will or not right
but either way either we someone buffer
into the other or we swap them and clear
one of them either way it's the same
basic idea right except and that should
really be it right I don't think there's
much else to it than that let's take a
look here intermediates this is just the
average direction to light so that's
literally just going to be solution
equals normalize and that's it
and then these ones here they would
never read out of the point anymore so
there's just going to be an omit C which
is the solution source emit see point
index
and the average direction to the lights
it's pulled out there as well I and so I
think that should do roughly the same
thing that it is doing or not it's like
I've got some problem there so I think
that's roughly it I'm still not crazy
about how that's going it's better right
setup this way that is the way that it
was set up because at least now these
are more like what you would imagine
happening on the GPU there right which
is what I want but yeah it's just it's
still a little bit wonky I feel like
those want to be ping pong buffers
because as you're going through them
you're basically computing a new one
from the old one so it feels a little
weird that we don't actually use in that
way we never actually ping pong we're
always going back to the source we never
swapped the two of those but that's okay
I see what our bug is though it's that
typo right there so I think that's at
least in a better general sort of well
maybe not that's in a better like
general structure than we had before so
I think that's probably about right
okay so I'll save whether or not we want
a ping pong those for when we actually
get to like sort of figuring out exactly
whether the light transport always adds
light or whether it doesn't and then
maybe we don't have to ping pong them at
all we'll find out and then in this case
this was not so important but I do think
those still want to be separate buffers
so I think that was the correct thing to
do as far as those were concerned either
way all right so let's just make sure
this is going properly here Arum it's
easy Rose gets an initialize to the
emission hour emit c1 gets initialized
to zero and our average
direction is cleared right so all those
things seem correct to me and then when
we do our accumulation we're
accumulating into whatever the
destination one is right and that's
exactly right that's this is what we
want to do here same with the average
direction to light there so that all
seems fine then in here we're doing our
summation on the source and we're
clearing the desk that also seems fine
and then we're normalizing that average
direction to light which also seems good
so that seems fairly sane so I'm not
sure where we ran afoul there so let's
go ahead and step in and see what it is
that we're doing that that it doesn't
like so I'm gonna go ahead and turn off
optimizations for a second so it'll be
easier to inspect the values in the
debugger and then I'm just going to go
ahead and step through to make sure that
we're setting the stuff up properly all
right so here we are in our extraction
code now we didn't change the surface
stuff so that stuff should be the same
but we did change the this other
solution stuff here so we've got the the
emit c0 right and the emit c1 those are
both 0 for this because this is does not
have an emission value an average
direction to the light is getting clear
these are all on the light index which
all seems good so that looks like I mean
that looks like the right thing to me
let's jump down here to our light
propagation
there's our source there's our desk
let's take a quick look at those let's
just scan through them there should be
some meters somewhere how many point
counts how many points do we actually
have 1873 so we know there should be not
very many emitters at the outset there's
very few but we know we should be able
to find some so there they are they're
the very last lights we pushed on but
that's ok and there you can see them
they're getting pushed on with a power
of 10 which oh right 1.0 is the maximum
light emission value so it's actually a
power 10 light that's why it's so bright
okay that makes sense I looked before I
fooled myself and so now we're going to
go through here the testament see this
should be all zeros we're gonna go
through these submitters here I oh wait
we're still using oh we forgot to delete
that value there's our problem
we forgot to admit the emit C value from
from that lighting element that's that's
that's what we've done so the lighting
element here in platform dot H that emit
C should not have been still on there
right this value should not have
probably been on there
so let's take a look here we've got that
Hadamard product here of these two this
should actually be the sourcing at sea
like so so I think that's it
that was probably the the main problem
because we weren't getting any light
input so when the bounces the bounces
never happened right
alright so that's back to what we had
before so that's good and let's go ahead
and turn on the optimizer okay so now
we're back to sanity here and I will say
that a power 10 light is a bit
aggressive in this case but you know
what you're gonna do
we could probably try turning that down
flip it but this is basically what we
wanted and so let's just go ahead and
see about making those points take a
distribution of the light a little bit
more sanely so for example when we apply
this light if we were going to
accumulate the sample we could at least
divide by the light count and distribute
it fairly across her eyes that's
probably where the extra power is coming
from is that we're adding to we're sadly
4 times the light because we're adding
it to each of the parts so let's suppose
we have the light power here oops
so we're going to call this sample power
and I'm just gonna say that the sample
power is the light power divided by the
light count
like so and that way oops there we go
and so that way we'll we'll have sort of
a fairer light distribution than we had
before I think not entirely certain but
I think that should have helped although
I can't say that it really looks like it
did because that should well look it
lets me just test something here
so the light power by default let's just
take it and drop it down quite a bit I
want to see if that correctly produces
less light bouncing around I'm just
gonna jump in here and reduce it further
so it does
interesting alright so that didn't
really help us very much so I'm gonna
actually try doing a thing here where I
looked and see and I'm gonna just add it
to whatever the closest point that got
hit was right just for fun so what I
want to do here is I'm looping over the
surface points and instead of calling
accumulate sample I'm only going to call
queue mate sample once and I'm gonna
call it out here right and say alright
I'm gonna accumulate the power to
whichever point index I found that was
closest okay
so this point index like will be a
closest point index and that's the one
that will give the light to so in here
we'll just do we know that the point
where we hit because the raycast itself
would have been able to tell that which
I guess gets me back to the point where
we've got to return this rapey so I
tried rate cast results to not have this
returned that but it's going to have to
uh so yeah the index gonna be the
solution surface count then what we'll
do here is just say okay result that
index result dot P all right so then
when we do raycast result here we'll do
that we'll just say all right we get the
rate cast hit index back we do exactly
what we're doing before now we can do is
we can take the closest distance squared
to the point that was hit by the right
right so we can do here is say closest
distance squared and closest point index
and then we do is as we loop through
here I I guess we can say that if there
is no surface count if there is no light
count we just won't do this right that
seems reasonable so we can say if
closest point index do it otherwise
don't so in here what we'll say is all
right here's where we this is the point
in expert testing we don't need this
sample power or this hit point oh I
guess we do any of the hit point now
we're actually going to use it we're
gonna take a look at that letting point
for this point index if that log and
then we'll do the distance squared here
we'll do a length squared function on
the Ray point where we hit so this is
where we hit on the surface versus the
point that we're testing
and wherever that point is so it's gonna
be scattered somewhere on the surface
right we're gonna take the length
squared there and see and once we have
that we'll compare them and take
whichever one is best so if the closest
point that we've seen so far is actually
further away okay then we will go ahead
and record that as the new closest point
and that'll be the only one that gets
added to the only sample point that will
actually add to and I think that's it so
this will actually distribute the light
on the surface too depending on where it
hit to a more or less appropriate sample
in theory now and I'm looking at that
looking at the results here it doesn't
look like it doing I'm not getting any
gradient wash really there which is odd
so I feel like we're still doing
something a little wonky here like we're
not it still feels like we're adding
them all uniformly you know what I mean
or that maybe our sampler is not
actually using the samplers not using
all the samples I'm not sure let me take
a look and see where we're at with our
sunlight function it looks like we're
still doing our loop over the light
right here's that call here
for some of the lights together and
multiplying by the bad service
reflectance of that surface I'm gonna
here where we do the summation we are
grabbing the light count out so that all
looks relatively sane and let's make
sure when we're packing them or packing
them properly so here's all our points
and those seem to be packing down so I'm
not 100% certain why we're not getting
gradations there right we should be
seeing gradations there but instead we
really seem to be getting more of a like
uniform color per block and that doesn't
really make sense as to why since each
of these should have four and they
should be distributed separately
something's a little wonky there
let's take a quick look we can save this
for next weekend's debugging Alice Lee
that so we've got our light zero our
light index here in both cases we're
setting the emitters and these
separately the points should be set yeah
we are setting multiple points to
different positions so this all looks
reasonable right what we need to do is
is actually do the debug display now so
we can see it right let's see what's
going on there
because that all looks fairly saying to
me but there should be no way for us to
be having the same color across the
surface when there's four separate
interpolation regions right that just
doesn't make any sense so something is
busted about the way we're doing it but
I'm not sure what and we're only doing
one accumulate sample here when we get a
hit on a surface so that seems a bit
weird right doesn't make a lot of sense
doesn't make a lot of sense
well I'm gonna go ahead and go to the
Q&amp;A either way cuz this me what I want
to do I think in what is probably the
right thing to do is to go draw make the
thing that draws the sample points so we
can see exactly what they're showing and
we will go ahead and do that next time
for now we're at least getting closer to
where we wanted to be in terms of
separating those things out but
something is up with the way we're
sending these down or in the way that
we're producing because wait we almost
never get any gradients now occasionally
we get some once in a while we get a
little bit of a gradient but it's pretty
rare so I think something is up with
that and we will have to debug that
further so I'm gonna say that till next
time we'll do brief Q&amp;A
chemicals asked short of a manual
comparison how do you obtain an enum
fields name by supplying a corresponding
numeric value eg 1 is Sunday yeah I mean
metaprogramming is the only answer for
that because c plus plus has been so
derelict in supporting obvious
introspection abilities and reflection
abilities in the language I mean that
should be something that the compiler
just generates for you you should be
able to say generate a table that tells
me the names of these enums so that I
can look it up but it can't the other
gigantic struct printf of which one
automate in the way of not having to
manually missed all its fields
medipartner is the way to go here right
probably take the difference yeah I mean
I showed how to do that on the stream
right in the meta programming stream I
did I showed how to parse C and output
the struct definitions right so that's
gets your only choice and again it's
just because C++ is it absolutely
pathetic language
we're doing the ray-tracing on the GPU
with open sealer ku to be viable yeah
but I don't think we're gonna need those
we can do them probably just in a
regular shader actually do you have any
issues with the Microsoft C runtime
labor and Windows do you think memory
management could be improved so the
Microsoft C runtime library on Windows
is I you don't even get to memory
management before it's a hard no for me
they still have not figured out a way to
let you ship with the CRT reliably it's
a disaster I mean I can't tell you how
many programs have to run an installer
to like first install the right dll's to
use the CRT on windows statically
linking with it mitigates some of these
problems but not all so I just don't
ship things with the CRT I just don't
there's no point to it doesn't give you
anything once you replace a few
functions there's there's no point to
it's just a giant liability right so the
Microsoft CRT is like a hard no I don't
ship things with it and I don't like it
long boolean concerning the flickering
when does mixing between frames give
appropriate results and when not so the
answer is when things move mixing
between frames gives you incorrect
results right but that doesn't mean we
won't use it because we don't need our
lighting to be super accurate we're not
trying to capture a hard shadows with
this or anything this is just trying to
give us a general feel so that things
get brighter as light sources move
around and it properly sort of
illuminates the space in a pleasing way
so we may use frame to frame blending to
ill to reduce the noise
carried your Hansen cementery this is
probably a bit premature because I have
looked into her throw but there's the
CPM station of jail and directx called
swift shader could be useful for
debugging purposes yeah sometimes it can
be but it's hard to say right
sometimes it's asbestos if ik aspect of
the card or driver that you're working
with that is causing the bug and so
sometimes it's hard to utilize the
software path for debugging those things
and also you have to make sure the
software path actually supports
everything you're doing which it often
doesn't but yes if you can find a
complete software stack with source code
that you can step into sometimes that
can help you validate what you're doing
right
alright looks like we are free of
questions so I'm gonna go ahead and
close things down I made a change to the
alright I didn't think I did ok thank
you everyone for joining me for the
episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you want to follow along with the
episodes at home you can always peer to
the game that comes with a source code
so you can follow along we have a forum
site and go to ask questions we have a
contribution page which does not use
patreon anymore if you'd like to
contribute to some of the products that
support the video series like the
episode guide and hand made network
where the forums are hosted we have a
schedule but you can use that tells you
we're gonna be live and of course we
have that aforementioned episode guide
which is a really great resource which
allows you to search through stuff for
terms that you might care about and it
tells you all of the places where those
are used that's about it for this
weekend next weekend we're heading into
the holiday so the holiday scheduled for
handmade hero
it's obviously Christmas time around
here in Washington the schedule may
fluctuate I'm not sure when we'll be
streaming or if we'll be streaming so
there might be some days off I'm not
sure so definitely check the schedule
bot for the schedule now if you're
interested in catching live streams over
Christmas break because they may move
around or who knows what will happen
with them that's about it until next
time a hero have fun program everyone
and I'll see you all on the Internet
take it easy everybody