hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show where we code a complete
game live on stream we are in the middle
of doing some gameplay coding here we're
basically trying to set up our entities
and get our sort of understanding of how
creatures move through the world working
in preparation for writing what we want
the gameplay to feel like and be like so
in order to do that I sort of we didn't
really get the chance to do what I
wanted to do on the previous stream
because I had a stupid bug that was one
of those bugs where it's it's not it's
not a bug something's actually doing
what it was supposed to do but you
forget that you put something in another
place and so you you think something you
wrote is behaving incorrectly and you go
search a new search and can't find the
bug and of course it's because there is
no bug it's actually you were using
something completely wrong and the bug
is actually back in completely unrelated
code that has nothing to do with it so
we we spent a bunch of time chasing our
tails on that for no apparent reason but
what are you gonna do I mean that's the
nature of bugs right if if they always
happen in the places you have that you
thought they would then debugging
wouldn't be hard right there'd be never
be any skill to that I suppose but
anyway that's settled now but we still
got to do the stuff that is what I
actually wanted to do which is push a
little harder into exactly how we're
moving the people around so that we can
make some certain guarantees about what
happens when they move so today is day
285 so if you want to go ahead and
follow along with today's episode day
284 is the is the source code to start
with we're also using a new version of
for coder today which I don't have very
much experience with basically the main
difference with it is there's a new
indentation pass in there so now like
hopefully this will fix on the
indentation problems we were having
because it's it's sort of new and
improved indentation over what we were
using there's also some things that I
don't haven't really looked into
like for example I don't usually use
scroll bars it has scroll bars now I
don't know if you can turn them off so
at some point we'll have to do a stream
where we actually go through and because
it's like new UI basically that you can
access in for coder some of which is on
by default and I don't necessarily know
how to turn it off so there's a couple
things in there that are that might be a
little unusual but we'll we'll deal with
them as they come so anyway yeah I'm
gonna go ahead and open up oh and
another thing that's kind of cool is now
you can interact with these things and
kind of a nice way to but that's beside
the point
so anyway I'm gonna go ahead and open
things up here and get us going and over
the course the stream we'll take a look
at how the indentation stuff is going
and hopefully we can find if there's any
problems with the new indentation we can
sort of isolate what is the reason like
like we're in the Hamby tiro code was
the indentation wrong and that way Allen
will actually have some kind of a solid
case that he can use to debug it right
because the thing with indentation is
this very context-specific so it's like
you're just like it's not indenting
braces right sometimes well that's not
very helpful for a programmer because
there's like okay like what times so if
we can sort of I'm hoping that we can
use the stream as sort of a thing that's
like when we see an indentation happen
we'll be like okay there's an
indentation problem so and you can use
exactly that code to see what what was
occurring right alright so where we left
things off was we've got this this sort
of notion of the player moving around
right and the player is moving and they
can move on to points and they will move
with the points when those points move
and in general the part that I didn't
get to do because you know that's sort
of working now obviously the part that I
didn't get to do that I wanted to do was
I would like it so that when I move on
to points those points understand that I
am the person who is on the point and
then if somebody else wanted to move on
to that point I would not be able to do
so right I'm sorry they would not be
able to do so and so we we just want to
get a little simple transactional system
going on there that would be you know
what we that will allow us to do that
testing and also I can sort of stop with
the angled things for the moment in the
rooms because I don't really want
in there we're not really working on
that part right now so I'm gonna go
ahead and turn off that sort of angled
fact that the room is on a sort of a
slant a gradual slope so if we just take
out this line then the offset Z for
things that we build will will just be
zero which is what we want and then
we've got kind of a flat room we could
hop around on normally right and we've
still got our little dude here so in
case you want to try hopping onto the
moving guy if I time it so that it's
there when I hop over then I can kind of
get on it and so we'll leave that in
there because there's no reason not to
have that for anything that we might
want to test so off we go all right so
what I want to do now is I want to start
again making this sort of concept of
standing on be a little bit more sort of
specific and in order to do that I'm
gonna need some sort of a registry
basically I'm gonna need some sort of a
conceptualization of who is standing on
what so that when you are standing on
something the sim region understands
that and the sim region will not allow
anyone else to go there or if you do
want to go there it can tell you oh that
that's empty you can go whatever so we
basically need some code that's gonna
start tracking this and so that's
something that we have to write now
there's a couple of different ways that
we could do this obviously we could do
this in the unpacked entity itself and
that might be the best place to do it
because since you have to know what
traversable you had to have found a
traversable in the first place
it probably makes sense to just store
who is standing on it right there and
during the unpack process is a pretty
easy place for us to do that so it seems
like something pretty straightforward I
think that's probably the easiest way to
go so let's take a look at how that
would how that would work
so all right in let's uh let's see here
well
looks like we have a for coder issue of
some kind on switching windows I don't
really know I'm able to edit in here but
I'm not able to edit in here hmm it's a
little odd yeah it looks like I'm not
able to edit in the second window which
is weird not sure what that would what
would be the cause of that I guess I
thought it's okay I don't really need to
edit in the second window but I'll
definitely at the track down what that
is
it might be a problem with my config
file too I mean I do the weird modal
stuff implemented entirely in my config
file and I don't really know to what
extent that may have sort of deleterious
effects so let me just see can i edit in
the yeah so I in this pane everything
seems to be fine and there doesn't seem
to be any weirdness so we'll just keep
going all right so if I go to the sim
region stuff oh wait I guess we we
actually have it in entity now I switch
I go to the entity stuff we have the
concept of the traversable point inside
the collision volume and what I can do
here is if I want to I could say this is
a particular entity that lives on this
traversable point right so I could say
that there's an entity reference for
example and the entity reference stands
on here now I don't really need to pack
this information because the enemy of
themselves know who they're standing on
right so really all I need to do is just
store the entity pointer and when this
gets packed out eventually that pointer
could just be thrown away because it
only has to be like it only has to be
valid during the sim region and nobody
else has to ever look at it and then
during pack unpack we can just write
that pointer I guess during pack we
don't do anything we just omit it when
we're saving it streaming out the data
and on unpack we update it right so
basically
during the during the world pack
operation when we do pack entity into
chunk when we do pack traversal
reference pack entity reference that
stuff we don't need to do any particular
operations here because that pointer
eventually will just get thrown away but
inside sim region when we do the unpack
which probably to be symmetric we should
move into the world
I'm guessing either that or move
everything out here well we need during
creation time to pack so I guess we'll
see what happens there but during the
unpack which is right here when we call
that entity and we want to do the the
unpacks for it right which I guess is
this here I'm sorry that's wrong it's in
the second pass it's in connect entity
pointers when we load the traversable z'
what we would want to do is during that
load we want to instead of just loading
the entity reference after we load the
entity reference that's what we're
standing on we would want to look and
see if the entity that we ended up
loading is valid then we want to
actually write to that entities
collision volume and we want to say
whatever your traversable was that we're
talking about here we want to update it
so that it knows that whatever it knows
who's standing on it right the person
who's standing on it at that point is us
so we need to know when we do this load
to rustle reference we need to node like
the source entity that where it came
from and we need to put that in here
during the unpack right so let's go
ahead and and fix the I guess it's the
pointer version here
is that a no that's an era traversals is
not a member that's because I spelled it
wrong
and so in cure when we're loading this
out we know what entity it is because
that's how we're getting the deed in the
first place
and so yeah so now when we load we
should be updating those pointers
correctly right and so what we could do
now to see what happens when we hop
around is I'm going to color those
points based on whether they have a
pointer set so that we can see what's
happening right and it'll be wrong at
first because we never clear them but
you know at least this way we'll be able
to see that happening as we work on the
code so I'm going to do that before I
write anything else so let's see here is
the code for drawing the traversable
index why when we do a push rect outline
Oh cuz they don't have any colliders on
them that's why so when I do a push rect
here and draw this traversable what I
want to do is say well here's what the
color was of this traversable oh dude
that is nice right there that's a
actually doing much better in that it
used to indent just back to the thing
that's awesome
that's real cool roll I'm a fan all
right anyway so what I want to do here
is say okay if the traversable point if
it had a standing on or you know and
let's see maybe we'll call that occupier
let's say if there's an occupier for
this for this traversal point I'll just
draw it in a different color so instead
of being in sort of that that I don't
know inoffensive beige orange thing I'll
just go ahead and draw it in a blue
color so that we can see it and then I'm
gonna change the traversable point
definition to just be occupier here and
fix that in the places where that was
being used before
all right okay so I guess I would be a
liar if I said I expected those all to
change immediately because I would think
that those would be set to nothing
initially but I guess we don't clear
them at first I'm not real sure what's
going on there oh you know what that's
because they're shared these are
actually these these collision points
are actually shared so I suppose this is
not really a safe way to do that right
it real actually needs to be it would
need to actually be on the entity itself
right the entity has to have knowledge
of who would be in there so that kind of
raises an interesting question for us
right we have kind of a an open question
here which is do we want to continue
sharing these things or do we want to
stream them out right meaning do we want
that data to be included and it's it's
kind of a difficult question
the reason it's a difficult question is
because the data is not that big right
you know if it were 64 K of collision
data then you'd probably want to share
it but since we don't really have that
kind of situation it's kind of a
question as to whether I want to
multiply it out so you can see what what
the problem is right the problem is that
this is actually a shared structure
everyone shares but like it's what kind
of closing group of your oh I'm this
kind of collision group right and so the
question is do we want that to be
written out as part of the entity so
that the entity itself has you know a
particular can have an arbitrary
collision group as it goes and and so
that's like kind of a tricky question
and my gut instinct says that since the
idea behind this is that things can be
very sort of permute
and configurable and weird in this game
and I'm trying to go for very very
expressive organic entity system that
probably what you would want to do is
rather than solving this problem by
storing the occupiers as a separate
thing I think maybe the better thing to
do would be to actually have the
traversable points be new things in
every entity and that they're not shared
so that they can be moved around and
changed per entity in various ways I
don't know that's just my gut feeling
normally I wouldn't make that call and
the reason is because I feel like a lot
of the traversable ZAR going to be the
same right like most ground tiles are
gonna have it just at zero zero zero so
you know it's it's shared on the other
hand hey you got a store eight bytes
potentially well I guess we could
compress that down to an index into a
table so I guess it wouldn't have to be
you know we could store a byte I suppose
for it
versus having to store you know 16 bytes
or something like this or twelve bytes
to store the location otherwise that's a
tough call it's a tough call
I think what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
make this be a property of the entity
and I guess what I could do is say let's
not make it a property of the collision
group yet so we can still share
collision groups for now and we can
think about that a little bit more but
let's make the traversable x' be a
property of the entity and go from there
okay so traversable points is not gonna
be inside a collision group it's just
gonna be stored off the entity and that
way things like the occupiers can be on
it directly now this is kind of
interesting and probably I would like to
handle this actually directly right now
if possible rather than doing anything
else with it
because one thing we could do is say oh
there's a hard-coded number of these
right and then everything that we have
right now would just work and I guess
you know I'll do that first just to get
it working as those but then I think
maybe this is a good time since the
point of what we're doing right now is
to work on the entity system I think
maybe now's a good time to make that a
flexible array right so it can change
how big it is and if we need to write
every entity can have a different number
of these so let's go ahead and make that
happen and get some space with
traversable now instead of going through
the collision we'll just it'll just rock
right off of the the traversals here and
this you know so all of these just get a
little simpler they're acting directly
off of the enemy and they don't have to
look at the volume group anymore so
let's take a look at this code doesn't
really need to access that anymore the
volume group is not relevant at all
entity is undeclared that's true it's
test entity my bad a traversable count
so in here where we do make simple fork
collision we're gonna still want this
code so I'm gonna have to go ahead and
grab that out but it's not gonna be on
simple floor collision anymore it's
gonna be like where we actually add the
simple room or what does it make simple
room
remember what that function is called
standard room so it's going to be in
cure where we create one of these floor
collision grounded entities when we
create that entity we're gonna have to
give it the traversable that it needs
right so in here we're gonna have to say
that the entity traversable zero is
gonna be you know what it is and the
entity Oh symbols zero occupier is also
nothing right but that's about it and so
after we do that I think we would be in
a situation where now we're all good to
go
and if we run we should I think be
exactly the same as we were before and
oh or not that was unexpected oh I only
added it to one case oh that was that's
kind of magical I mean you can see what
happened there right i I didn't add one
to the other one so I only added it to
the magic one that moves up and down so
it immediately had to hop the guy over
cuz that was the closest Collider that
was the closest place he could stand
that's funny all right
but yeah point being we want to add this
in either case certainly and then we
should be back to normal so now as we go
you can kind of see as I'm moving around
I'm sort of packed Manning these up in a
sense as I hop on them you can see
they're changing to have their occupier
pointer set now like I said the problem
here of course is that it's having the
occupier set it will never get cleared
because right now all we're doing is
doing it on the path where when we
actually move the guy we're not actually
dealing with updating that information
instead all we're doing is setting it on
unpacked so the person moved if they
moved on the previous frame during
unpack of this frame it gets set that's
not gonna cut it and it also doesn't
help us with the thing we're actually
trying to do yet which is prevent two
people from occupying the same square so
what we need to do
now is we need to start introducing the
notion of checking to see when you would
have occupied a new square you're going
to have to check to see whether it's
allowed or not so let's go ahead and
look at that code by the way how am I
now suddenly editing in this window
again so what happened there must have
been some kind of weird bug that froze
up the editing or something or maybe
maybe I got into some kind of mode but
it's weird because I'm this was the this
window was not working before but it's
working now right didn't notice when
that happened but it did so anyway in in
this codebase right right now we don't
have a very good notion oops
hero head we don't have a very good
notion of like asking that permission
all we're doing is just straight up
setting it right so if we look at what
happens in here you can see us setting
it this moving to this traversable this
is essentially the problem right this is
not what we want to do so when we're
about to set this we want to do some
kind of a transaction here where we say
we would like to move here
can we move here and so the way that I'm
going to do that is I'm gonna do some
kind of thing like transactional occupy
or something like this and I'm just
gonna say this is what I would like to
do right I would like to take this
moving - you know I'm I'm this entity I
would like this slot in me to
transactionally occupy this this
traversable please and so I'll have that
piece of code returned to me whether or
not it's okay for me to do that and if
it is then we'll initiate the hop if
it's not then we won't and honestly I
probably
- ifs for this because eventually the
controller is going to have to take
different action possibly depending on
whether which you know this because one
of them in this situation we're not
trying to go anywhere if this turns out
to be a failure if this turns out to be
a field we were trying to go somewhere
we just couldn't right and so we're
probably gonna need to know the
difference those case so I'm going to
leave them as separate yester now so I
want to compile that will it'll tell us
that a transactional occupy is not gonna
happen and then in here what I'll do is
I'll say okay inside the sim region
where we've got like move entity we've
got sort of another operation here which
is transactional occupy which is
something that is just going to allow
you know an entity to or not to I guess
that's a pool to or not to switch up but
reversible so this is it's the thing
that's actually getting modified here is
going to be ended traversable sorry a
traversable reference and that's what's
going to get updated and this is a this
traversable here is a separate reference
oops
which is the like desired right that's
the thing we want to occupy so the first
thing is first we need to check whether
the desired position and I believe so
when we have one of these traversal
references let me take a look at entity
when we have one of these traversable
references it tells us what the entity
is and it tells us what the index is so
we need to then go figure out whether
that traversable is occupiable or not
and I guess inside the sim region we've
got the get we've got to get sims face
traversable but we don't actually have a
way to just get a traversable and so I
think and I think we probably want to
I think we probably want to move these
out well all right I'm just gonna do it
one step at a time it's not sure first
I'm going to do is say well I want to be
able to get traversable points back
easily so I want to do get traversable
and in here be able to pass one of those
references sort of cleanly so in here
where we where we say get traversable
with one of these entity references I'm
just going to go ahead and do this right
so this is going to be a pointer and I'm
gonna grab it like that
and this way there's an assertion there
too to kind of guard that array access
if it's you know if somebody is doing
something stupid will catch him and I'm
gonna also allow you to call it exactly
as the other one you know manual
currying welcome to it so in here we're
just gonna say traversable reference and
that's just going to call get
traversable with the reference entity
pointer and the reference index
okay so in this case now what we need to
do is we need to actually get this so we
need to get the entity traversable point
and when we get that traversable I guess
I'll call this desired and desired ref
so I'll take that desired point and I'll
get the reference from it all right
rather I'll get the point from the
reference and then I want to see if it's
occupied right the result of this
function will assume that I cannot
occupy the square in the case where it
is not occupied now I can occupy the
square and I'll say okay the occupier is
now whatever the entity is that was
trying to occupy the square and
similarly similarly wherever we were
occupying previously we we want to
relinquish right so the traversable
reference that's the destination here is
now going to not have an occupier on
whoever it was so we've got another
entity traversal point in the mix the
Angelo traversal point is the DES point
alcohol get reversible on that and I
guess I'll just call this best and best
ref to be sort of the same with it there
so the deaths occupier now becomes
nothing nobody's occupying that point
anymore
and in addition I need to set the the
desk reference I need to set it to be
equal to the desired reference
I think that's mostly everything that
needs to happen right now it's possible
that the destination is uninitialized
and if the destination is uninitialized
then I we would assume that guests would
return zero and I probably want that in
to be a legal case right
so inside handmade sim region I probably
want to do a check here where we say
like okay when you do get traversable
then we maybe we assume here that the
result is 0 and then we only if there's
a valid entity pointer actually retrieve
the value if that makes sense
similarly now this guy can totally
piggyback off the case of get reversible
I guess so maybe I'll make this guy safe
as well oops I'm not sure to what extent
I actually want to do that
so I think here's what I'll do I'll say
that we've got an idiot reversal point
result and we'll assume to begin with
that the result P is going to be equal
to the enemy P so in the case where
things fall apart we'll still be okay
we'll get the traversable point by
calling get traversable on this entity
in this index and if the result that we
get back on I guess I should say point
when we get the result back I will check
to see if it was valid if it is then
I'll add the that points displacement in
and leave it at that right we'll see how
that goes
all right so coops so that's all good
there's one sort of touchy aspect of
this that I'll talk about in a second
but and you know to the degree to which
we care about it might be different so
it looks like I'm not actually why am I
not moving the body am i returning foe
because I didn't set it to true ever so
when we actually do the transaction it
goes without saying that if I never
return true we'd be in bad shape so in
the case where it's not about I need to
actually return true so that someone
will actually move off of it right okay
so
now I have a couple problems
I think I'm not actually sure if I do if
I don't but I believe I have a couple
problems that I have to address so the
first problem is I think both of these
like I don't really know to what extent
the head occupy is a point versus the
body occupying a point because before it
looked like they were both occupying
points so I'm wondering does the head
keep a stand on because I think it does
there we go so I'm wondering what the
hero head if the hair had ever sets any
of these it doesn't all right so all
right so there's one problem I have is
like I said the one problem I have is
that when I if I just ransom so right
now we don't distinguish between things
like moving to which is not actually
occupying a thing necessarily and
standing on right so I'm not sure look
we're gonna have to do a little bit more
work to make transact transactional
occupy do what we needed to do when the
head goes over to to the side and you're
about to hop into it right
we only once we start taking the square
we're sort of in between two squares and
I don't know to what degree we
relinquishing quit right away out
there's stuff it's a little complicated
I guess is what I would say it's it's a
bit tricky and the degree to which I
have moving to and standing on I've got
to think that through it'll the more
immediate problem is when we do our
unpacks in here where we do load entity
reference and low traversable reference
so part of the problem is I really don't
want to do this probably this occupier
thing for anything other than like
standing on like what the thing is that
you're on right
it's like which one you're occupying is
kind of I'm gonna have to draw this out
so here's essentially the problem how
much time we got left we got about 20
minutes all right so here is the hero
and for the hop we had two things one we
had standing on and the other we had was
moving to now the problem that we have
here is we probably only want to occupy
one squared time or maybe we don't
maybe we occupy both I don't know but at
some point we have to relinquish this
square and at some point we have to take
this square and what we do know that
this is a and this is B what we do know
that in time if I was to look at two
channels essentially in time and be like
this is showing the occupation I'm
starting out occupying a and then at
some point I have to release a right and
then I have B and I know that I end
occupying B all I really know is that
this point here has to either be right
on when I release a or some time before
it right there can't be a gap between
here and here right there could be an
overlap so I could do it like this or
they can be right on but I couldn't have
empty space right I couldn't do this
because if I did this then in here
someone could occupy the squares and
then I would have nowhere to land right
there'd be nowhere to go
if someone was allowed to like come in
and take the old square but then the new
square became occupied I would you know
it that's an unacceptable scenario
basically so the question is just what's
the actual procedure for that right and
right now I'm taking both squares and
that's not good because I'm not
releasing the moving to whenever so the
question is just what should I do here
should I always occupy one I'll move it
to here and then the thing that I do the
jump just remembers an old position but
it doesn't actually use it doesn't
actually occupy that position if that
makes sense I don't know I'm not sure so
let's let's play with it because when I
don't know I play around and I see what
makes the most sense in the code right
so let's switch over to entity and I
guess what I'm going to do with entity
is say well alright let's suppose that I
only keep one square ever so I never
take more than one square and or if I do
take more than one squares and I'm an
entity who always takes more into one
square all the time look I just have a
footprint that's larger right and that's
just how I work or something although I
don't know to what degree I really want
that to happen in this game but whatever
maybe certain boss monsters right so
I've got these traversable references
and I'm saying that I'm going to occupy
particular squares and hmm what I want
to do is say well okay I've got this
notion that I'm occupying one of them
and I'm just going to call that
occupying and then I'm gonna assume that
I just have a thing that was like came
from okay and then what I'm gonna say is
only occupying actually occupies the
other one doesn't right
and so if I come through here and say
well okay we've got packed reversible
reference standing on and moving to when
we pack these these can be these are not
oops wait what does I call it came from
all right
that's hot that error condition seems to
hop oh I'm not oh that's weird
I think I may have a bug I think I may
have to update my eye for code or custom
for the new UI stuff because I noticed
my my jump to script doesn't always
actually seem to go in the get into the
buffer where the error is I think I may
have to do something
see that it didn't actually it didn't
actually hold the : so I have to look at
how that works I'm not sure what's going
on there
yeah well anyway something look out
later solo traversable reference is
gonna be the same but basically what I
want to do here is say well when we
connect these up I'm gonna say that load
traversable reference doesn't do this
automatically right so maybe this is
actually it only happens down here right
so low traversal reference doesn't need
the source entity that's not actually
required and so when this happens after
it loads occupying it will it will
update in here so it'll say like okay I
loaded occupying assuming that entity
occupying has an actual pointer
associated with it then it'll do the
entity occupying
and these don't these anymore and source
gonna be is now entity standing on is
occupying so we're probably going to
need a creation time system for
guaranteeing no overlapping occupation
right here we go so now let's take a
look here so this is assuming that
occupying is not the same then we're
going to want to do a transition a
transactional thing for occupying with
the traversable but we're gonna need to
save that one that we're you know are
sort of our came from if you will so
before we do that we're going to want
came from to equal our old occupy pretty
much regardless because it should have
been equal anyway so that in here when
we're going to be adjusting the location
of the entity during standing that'll
just be this and movement to and
movement from is going to be basically
the same but now it's a little bit
reversed so we're always the occupying
value is always where we're going to and
what we're moving from is is the came
from value
then when we finally land then we want
to set came from equal to occupy like so
so really this line may be redundant you
know that that may not ever really need
to happen but you know it certainly
can't hurt famous last words
so now you can see that the blue is
working the way that I wanted it to
right I'm as I come sort of through
there I'm you know I'm getting I'm a
well yeah I'm basically moving to that
point as soon as my head crosses into it
and then the hop happens what I'm
interested to know is let's say what if
we dropped another hero in here I'm
gonna introduce a key so I can drop new
heroes in because I think that might
just be helpful for us but for when were
you know sort of working on stuff so
what I'd like to be able to do is
basically like redo the ad player so you
can see in here where we do this like
was class controller start ad player
situation I'm gonna go ahead and just
put that in in in sort of the game you I
normally so when you have any of the
index already I'll drop and I'll make it
so that you can drop another one in
there using some kind of something maybe
that is I don't know what that would be
I don't know which keys we really have
either but well for now let's just say
maybe we'll we'll take one of the debug
keys and and use that I don't know well
yeah I just don't know
so in here where we do indie index ad
player I don't want to double ad the
player in this case and so maybe you
know I don't know if the else button
would be a problem here let's let's take
a look
oh we're gonna have to zero out that
velocity
amusingly I can hit him and he bounces I
guess we put our physics in there for
that that's kind of weird
all right so essentially we got what we
wanted and we have to work on our
controllers a little bit but this
actually works exactly right so I have
to skip that point if it's occupied and
right now since the head is allowed to
move as far from the body as it wants it
can always go find another point right
that's so grotesque
but otherwise yeah it's all good so
that's exactly what I wanted and I think
I'm trying to think about I guess let's
double check that I didn't break start
up with that change in the way that that
these guys work yeah I did because we
simulate the start button press there
and it won't think any heroes exist when
we do this let's take a look at at the
code a little further down and look at
the heroes exist situation so you know
we could do that in here and and maybe
that would be a smarter thing that code
is still it's kind of a little janky we
probably want to make it more explicit
anyway I feel like that should have
worked
I'm not really sure why that didn't so
heroes exist assumed to be false we come
through here we take a look
hero gets created by doing an ad player
and it saves the entity index in here
right it doesn't do this code but that
should be okay right because you
shouldn't have to wait what oh right so
it should be fine you would think and
then when you come through here you say
all right let's go through all the
entities and you know we update the
entities and when we go through and we
see the hero ahead we should I mean I
guess I could do it up here even but
either way it should just work right
there shouldn't be it should not have
thought that there were none so I'm kind
of interested to know what's happening
there I feel like something's not quite
the what I way I expected and again this
is sort of a little bit janky the way
that we had this coded we probably want
something a little bit nicer but I just
want to understand why it doesn't work
so let's just step in I guess oh because
the simulation has started already yeah
that's that's why so that entity is not
actually added into the world during
this ad player it's added into the
storage for the world and that's just
basically a bug like we don't really
want to do that so ad player needs to
add to the sim dissimulation
right so that's that's just bad and I
probably should fix that right now
before it ever before it gets any more
out of hand so AB player should not
should not be doing any of this stuff
really it should not be doing and entity
or any of that stuff what it should be
doing is it should do it like in an
immediate unpack into the sim region so
the sim region do you mean the way that
the sim region works when it unpacked
stuff we should what we what we
basically want to be able to do is have
there be an ad entity operation which
effectively mirrors what happens when
you begin sim and then when you call an
entity in here right we could just say
well are we in a simmer aren't we and if
we're in a sim so we can use the same
code in both cases if we're in a sim we
unpack into the sim if we're in a and if
in if we're not we don't
I think that's what we actually want to
do here so what we could do is say well
okay there's world mode if world mode
you know active sim or something like
this then we do one path else we do the
other path something like that
and so in here I guess I would say well
let me think about this a little bit
longer probably should wrap up very soon
here but I'm just not sure exactly how I
want that to go so inside the sim region
we just need this one piece of code
right this atom be here and when we add
identity and we're passing it sort of
that packed data there's two things we
could do one is we can still pack and
then ask it to unpack into a temp buffer
right and that would follow the same
path with the same unpacking and that's
kind of nice because then we know there
are no surprises
yeah on the other hand it's definitely
less efficient than if we just wrote
directly into one of the new SIM slots
right because instead we could just do
an ad and B and say here's where we're
gonna add the entity and let's go ahead
and write directly to it I'm not sure I
mean the other thing we could say is
that things always get added at the end
of the frame anyway so effectively they
get packed into chunks and an unpacked
maybe that's not really a problem maybe
that's fine yeah I don't know I really
don't I'm not sure what to make of that
I guess here's what I'll say for now the
fix is pretty easy
it's obviously hero's exist whether if
we've created one if there's not I guess
that I think about it the way that we're
doing it where we pack them and then
unpack them is actually possibly correct
like I mean that's actually kind of nice
so I don't know maybe maybe I just want
to keep it that way
it's very symmetric doesn't require any
changes to the code and you know Euro is
going through the same path and no one
can be created inside a frame they'll
always be created on the start of the
next frame which also has a certain
purity to it that feels like it might
pay big dividends like so we don't have
to worry about something getting created
in the middle of a frame where half the
people are updated I don't know it could
be good alright so I guess I'm gonna
call that done for now
so I'll go ahead and hit the QA
yeah I do kind of agree that the
debugging worlds is gets kind of weird
and you know that's that's actually kind
of the way debug code goes you know
there are some pretty gruesome things
created during debugging you know some
some some parade of Horrible's that
there's definitely a fair bit of that
and I don't really know I don't know
what to say
a lot of times 3d when you're
programming in 3d it could it could be
even worse because you mess up a little
thing in a transform somewhere in how
that's supposed to be you know you got a
bug somewhere like that and suddenly
people are getting all smushed around
and extort distorted like really
gruesomely
and so in 2d it's a little better
because you're only typically stretching
like we were it doesn't it maybe doesn't
not so likely to get awful but yeah
remilia why don't the cloned players
jump to points when their heads move
over them uh so it's a it's a good
question and the reason is because if
you look at where that we just chose to
do the code for that we're doing it
inside the controller binding for a hero
head right now we don't have to do that
we could choose to do it outside the
controller binding for the hero head if
that's what we wanted and so you know
you can see and hear there's a certain
degree of where con hero was actually
getting used and you can see it right
through here but it stops at some point
right so we could for example take this
piece of code I don't know why timer
recenter I guess cuz this code needs to
know what it what that is but we could
make it so that the hopping
didn't require connected here oh right
it didn't require knowledge of like the
pushing around and in order to do that
it's it's actually pretty trivial so I
don't know do we write to con her here
ever well you know I'll just I'll show
you so what we could do if we wanted to
have that happen is we can make it so
that our our controlled hero has sort of
like a dummy thing like let's say con
hero underscore that's just nothing and
then in here we could say like okay we
got
let me let me back that up a second more
like this so we'd sort of say this sort
of thing we want to know who's connected
to this guy and maybe nobody is right
look maybe no one's connected to him and
we don't really have a way to look it up
so we're just searching to see if we
could find it right so in here what
we're doing is saying like okay let's
initialize the connected hero to be just
nothing it's just a garbage here you
know like an on a non-active hero
controller and then in here we'll say
like alright let's check take the test
hero and see whether the test hero does
this we're looking at the four
controllers is any orb well however mate
those are are we're looking to see if
any one of those controllers is attached
to this hero if it is we're gonna use
that as the controller for this hero
right then we can just come out here and
say all right everything else just
assumes that we've got a valid one of
those and operates so now you don't have
to have a connected hero to do the rest
of the things that you were going to do
and off you go right so if we did that
then I think you know now the controller
code runs whether you have someone that
I shouldn't control code the logic for
the hero head will now run whether or
not anyone's plugged into it right
so normally like I'm hopping around it's
fine but if I was to you know do sort of
the thing where I I switch heroes now
the controller code will run now what
you'll notice is this means the hero
will always stop and that's because
there's that spring on the hero head
that keeps it close to the body so if we
wanted to we could we would also have to
do something if we wanted the heroes to
sort of go in a direction so you could
see them hopping what we would need to
do is make it so that well when a hero
doesn't have a connected entity
we're gonna have to push we're gonna
have to have some push in that direction
right so we're gonna have to have the
Heroes DDP X let's say equal to
something like in this case oops
what's going on okay so if we initialize
that you know they'll all they'll all go
that direction right so if I put one
here it's just gonna act like there's a
controller that it's pushing him towards
you know wherever he's going right which
is pretty funny as you can see so
there's that and I feel like at that
point if you know if that's the sort of
thing that we're doing you probably want
to make the add player code right when
when we do the get closest traversable
z' code for that and we place them down
we're probably going to want to do here
is say well let's add an unoccupied flag
for get closest closest reversible so in
the sim region when we call get closest
traversable we're gonna want something
here that's like you know a traversable
flag or a traversable search flag and
we're gonna want something like that's
reversible search unoccupied equals you
know x1 or something and so then in here
we'd have a thing where we're like okay
Oh Alan loving that alignment dude so
good I was really missing that from
emacs
and now I don't have to miss that at all
that's so nice
alright so you know we got the flags in
here we could say well just search for
an unoccupied traversable
and in here we'll just say get closest
reversible blah blah blah and so what I
was saying here was well okay in inside
inside here when we're checking these in
addition to checking the other stuff we
could just say well alright if the P
that you were doing oh well the the Lord
giveth and Lord taketh away so this is a
bogus indentation right because that if
should be over here I believe I'm not
mistaken but it seems to want to push it
in all right anyway so we've got this
point and we're gonna say if flags and
traversable search unoccupied if it has
to if that's not set then it's fine
but if that is set then the P - occupier
has to be nothing there can't be anyone
on it and so that's just something that
we want to do with this traversable
search so now we'll find the closest
point that isn't occupied and that's
where we'll actually put the player now
if we do that now we can stop adding the
player at camera P well first of all I
should test that code so now what I
should be able to do is drop people down
on top of me in theory right oh my god
oh my god that's so creepy
that is doing what I wanted it to do but
it's not I it's finding the point but
it's not putting them on it that I can't
say I know why what does add player do
for placement oh my god that was creepy
ah so add player is kind of busted here
right we need to know where that actual
it's it's got a it's got to add it to it
at an actual place in the world and
we're not doing that at the moment so
yeah we're gonna need to do something
like if that's the traversable reference
we would want to do you know this is
game world mode
we're probably gonna want to do like you
know sim region I may have bitten off a
little bit more than I can chew in 15
minutes unfortunately I just want to be
able to place people around me right and
I'm not sure so the problem is when I
call ad player I need to be able to get
the position as a world position I guess
that's not that tough I guess I could
say map into chunks base region let me
see here
so the sim region origin right we've got
this sort of concept of the sim region
origin so I could say region you know
worlds sim region origin and then I just
want to map into chunks space whatever
the traversable get traversable I just
want that point get sim spaced
reversible standing on and I suppose
that is an OK way to do it the only
difference is this I've got it past the
sim region but that's ok because
whenever we add a player we have one of
those because they come inactive at the
moment so yeah so I think that would
work
I don't know yeah I did it rather
quickly
now still not right
because that's still adding the player
at that location
oh because we're calling it at camera P
all right so I've got a little bit more
work to do here when we call it at
camera P I actually want to call it at
the entity location so what I actually
wanted here is for this to come down I
don't know why star con hero equals that
at the point we don't really need that
so I guess I can maybe make a flying
leap at this so what I want to do is I
want to say well I'll just store whether
I wanted to make one of these like I do
everything else so the con hero oops
and maybe I wear is con hero there it is
we'll do like debug spawn or something
like this and I'll just say like debug
spawn equals true and then I'll just
grab this out and I'll do it down what
we actually we're sort of doing the
controlled hero stuff so cure I'll say
like oh hey if the test hero
debug spawn
we'll then we'll do this sort of weird
this sort of weird crazy thing that we
do and in here when I pass camera P
instead now I'll pass into VP Oh
oh my the other thing we got to do clear
that variable otherwise we would just
spawn all day all right
so almost there might as well just
finish it up so when I spawn here I'm
still it's still not picking the right
location so something about traversable
search unoccupied I up that code in my
haste so let's take a look at get
closest reversible
so if the flags is not if we don't have
an unoccupied set then obviously we can
check this flag or if the occupier of
the point I'm testing is zero then I can
check it that seems correct so what did
I what did I do wrong there
because if the P occupier equals zero it
will always work which is what I want I
guess I could take the flag out of it
for a second of course that'll create
other problems so it's not even the flag
it just that just doesn't seem to work
hmmmm I say
I mean that passes back a copy of the
yeah so I wonder if we just don't want
to actually ever pass back by value
there I guess we have to if we're saying
it space because you couldn't write to
it but I guess that's okay I'll allow it
basically we need to copy in the
occupier right because what we weren't
ever copying that in
all right uh so let's see here so that's
all good and now occupying me let me get
closest reversible so that's all correct
now and so let's just finish this off
and say all right in handmade world mode
when we do debug spawn you know what I
might say is let's actually make it so
that we don't override the one that we
are so now we're basically just spawn
people from our location rather than
actually have them take over right so
now we can kind of just go along and
just add new people right seems like a
good thing to do
this is kind of ridiculous
and I admit that but what can you do
I'm also sort of interested to know
profile lies where what happens here so
yeah you know you can see our crappy
physics stuff is definitely not up to
this task either right which is fine
right we know we have to it's it's not a
that's routine is complete garbage but
it's just kind of interesting to know
when you start putting some actual
entities in here who gets upset and you
know a lot of it's there because there's
a lot of calls to it it looks like how
do you pause that there we go it looks
like also we've got just the unpack and
so on now this is not a debug time this
is a debug build so everything takes a
lot longer so that's not really that
foot anyway all right now I think we're
good we've we've settled that issue of
having lots of creepy dudes which is
important
alright I'm gonna wind up let's take a
look so I think we only had one 4 code
or weirdness today which is that the if
aligned itself with a with a drop indent
of a line so it was like let's see if
that's reproducible not not so much so
it looks like it may be specific to that
or some of the surrounding things were
important there so hopefully we caught
that on the stream anyway otherwise we
didn't have any other indentation
problems thank you everyone for joining
me for another episode of hand made here
oh it's been a pleasure coding with you
as always if you would like to follow
along with the series at home you can
always pre-order the game on hand made
here at org and it comes with a source
code so you can follow along with the
development we also have a forum site
you can go to if you wanna ask questions
a patreon page you wanna support the
video series it's a schedule bot where
you can follow the book well you can see
what the schedule for the week is and an
episode guide you can use to catch up on
past episodes as always the editor we
used on the stream is for coder which
just shipped a new version recently and
it's getting pretty formidable you can
support that project on patreon I don't
know how to get there there it is
you can support that project on patreon
by pledging on here and you can get a
copy of the editor early and also our
episode guide of course is is done by
our very own mid blow from the chat and
you can actually support him well you
know what the easiest way to do it is
actually is if you go to the episode
guide itself you can see his patreon
link right here tell them you got to
make it bigger but no one's made it
bigger yet so those are some people you
get support as well if you like the
series and are looking for ways for
people who I guess make it possible now
we also have yeah really have to kind of
put a little thing in here that lists
who the other people are our editor for
we actually also recently switched to a
new graphic editor also
being done by someone on the stream so
we got a lot of them now and that one I
don't have a convenient link to yet it's
called Milton and so you can go and find
it on here but I need to get a better
link to it because it's hard to find but
yeah slowly but surely and through a lot
of generous support from people we're
slowly getting to the point where we
have like really good workable
replacements for all the stuff we were
using which is kind of cool anyway
that's it for today I will catch you
guys I'm tomorrow's day off I will catch
you guys Wednesday until then have fun
programming and I will see you guys on
the Internet take it easy everyone