hello welcome to handmade here I'll show
the codes it can play well the show that
codes a complete PNG reader live on
stream because we wanted add a PNG
reader to our game for a live art asset
updating and we've written all most of
the code we have not written the fixed
Huffman table version we didn't actually
have any files at the moment that use
the fixed Huffman table version so we
don't actually know maybe we'll never
actually do that I don't know it could
turn out to be that we don't ever
actually get any files that have that
and this is only for our files so we
don't really need to but so we've
written all of the code for a PNG
decompressor including the transforms
which we wrote yesterday but we are not
quite correct yet we have a bug or
multiple bugs in the code that we now
have to debug in order to get proper PNG
images out the other end that is all
we're doing today so we're just going to
look at that code and figure out what's
wrong with it now if you remember
correctly we are going in phases right
now we have not really looked very
carefully at trying to make sure that
our output is correct we sort of
cursorily inspected it but we haven't
really taken the time to test to make
sure it's exactly right and so that's
something we might do a little later on
right now what we're doing is trying to
figure out how to make sure our
decompressor produces consistent output
what I mean by that is that it should
always produce an image of the size that
we were told that we had and the reason
that this is a difficult problem is
because if you think about what happens
with a Huffman encoder or other kinds of
things like that like are in play with
PNG compressed file formats and like any
little bug that you have in interpreting
how many times to replicate a symbol or
what the particular symbol code should
be or any of those sorts of things they
will lead to you misinterpreting the
data stream which will lead to producing
too much or too little
data and so what we will find when we
debug this situation for example is that
something we have done incorrectly in
how we are handling the data stream is
causing us to produce say too much
information or it's causing us to try to
because remember this is a dictionary
compressor so we read from our output to
produce new output so we read from both
the input and the output when we have
look backs we may if we misinterpret the
look backs we will jump too far
backwards all of those sorts of things
they're very twiki and very finicky you
can get just one little bit wrong and
you can still decode several images
perhaps but when you get a particular
image that has some aspect to it that
that hits upon the thing that you've
done incorrectly that case will lead you
to produce too much too little data read
outside the image whatever so what we're
trying to do right now is get our system
to the point where we don't do that
anymore that doesn't mean we're
producing the right images we can still
have bugs that are unrelated to properly
decompressing the literal bit stream but
right now we're trying to do is get to
that point so we want our Huffman
decoder to always produce the right
number of bytes when we get an input
stream from a PNG so what we want to do
today is to start working towards that
and we're not that far but even though I
think we're not very far from a working
PNG compressor this is hard debugging
this is the kind of onion that's
difficult because we didn't write the
file format we're just going based off
what we think we understand from the
spec which we don't actually know that
we do right and so we're constantly not
sure exactly what we should or shouldn't
see in any particular place that makes
debugging difficult
now I will also point out the fact that
if you had to write your own PNG reader
at home for some reason and you it was
not about a programming exercise a
perfectly reasonable thing to do is to
look at someone else's PNG reader run
that PNG reader to the same point in the
output as yours see if your output
matches this can help you figure out
where you've gone wrong so having a
working version can be a very valuable
way to debug something I don't want to
do that because I want to show you the
process and this is why I've done it
this way so far the process of going
from just a speck because if you are
someone who programs new stuff does
engine programming that starts before
living you will often come into
circumstances where you do not have
working versions of something that you
need to load so I don't mean to imply
that you shouldn't do that
you should it's a useful technique it's
just I won't trying to show at this
point
how did debug or what the process looks
like when you're trying to bug something
where you don't have the luxury of just
being able to go and look response code
same without hand mate how in hammer
here we will often rewrite something
maybe we could have gone and gotten code
to do for example something that was in
an STB library again the reason for that
is because this is educational we're
supposed to be showing how to do these
things because you don't always have one
available if you are a programmer who's
you know pushing the boundary is working
on a new engine working on things that
people haven't done before you don't
have the luxury of going Stack Exchange
and posting a stupid question so let's
go ahead and finish with that this is
the broken file and just to refresh your
memory when we run it what we see when
we get to this point you can see that we
have two our two pointers here right
we've got the source that we're supposed
to be reppin from we have the desk that
we are writing to and when we look at
these two what we see here actually is
that the source is not actually off the
end
so you can kind of see here I don't know
if this will let me do this huh that's
what I wanted what you can see here is
that the source technically this line
will not crash the source the source
technically is still readable it looks
like here right because the the the very
specific one it is reading is actually
still valid now it would have crashed
right
it still has 46 ago it would have
crashed the source but it's actually the
dest that crashed first so you can see
here that it wrote the 243 out let me
just take a look here let's let's take a
look at what was was in the previous
wrap of both of these guys just so we
can get an idea what that was
yeah so it copied this 243 to this 243
it did that copy right but then when it
went to advance the source it was like
oh I could read you know another 243
that would be just fine
and then the desk was like I can't read
the memory now what I want you to build
in your mind here because again we're
trying to debug a fairly complex
circumstance so I would encourage you to
really try to visualize in your head as
you're going through this what is
actually literally happening here right
well what you can see is res an LZ
compressor right it's an LZ style
compressor what that means is when I'm
reading source and destination in like
this case here right what I'm doing is
I'm reading from the destination and
copying it into the destination right I
know it seems weird because normally we
think of copying from one place to
another and they're different in this
case they're the same now I'm copying
slightly offset right so that's why it
works I'm not copying from literally the
same place to the same place otherwise
we'd do nothing right I'm copying from a
little bit offset so I'm just a little
bit back I'm reading a little bit
backwards and writing a little bit
forwards right
or maybe a lot depending on the jump but
what I want you understand is so the
source and destination are the same
block of memory and if we look at what
their actual values are do you see this
they're very close right what's the
source plus one it's the destination
right so even just from this one stop
here I can see the thing that we that we
sort of went out on now we don't know
this was the cause of the error because
it could have been multiple compounding
errors going forward we have no idea
where the actual bug is but the actual
cause of the stoppage was a rep
instruction where we were told to
basically copy a byte many many many
times now what do I mean by that well in
an LZ compressor and I covered this
before so hopefully those of you who
have your thinking caps on will remember
what I'm talking about in an LZ
compressor it can go ahead and encode
effectively a run length encoding LZ
compressor is normally made to take
chunks of data and move them forward
right oh I see this thing and I want to
copy it here because I'm repeating
myself right but it is not limited to
that it can also repeat the most recent
chunk of data however long you want the
most recent thing that thing can be
repeated at infinity of times well not
infinity whatever the maximum repeat
count is right how do I do that well
let's say that I copied ABCD efg right
and that's what's sitting in the
destination and now I'm going to write
after it right well if I just tell you
to go back to the a and copy 20,000
characters what will you do well you'll
write ABCD efg into the output then
you'll start reading from the place that
you just wrote ABCD efg which will cause
you to write another ABCD efg and you'll
just keep rewriting the thing you just
wrote over and over and over again so in
LG Chem
sir has a way of encoding effectively a
block that just repeats many many times
all it has to do is first do one copy
from somewhere way back into the stream
to find the block it needs copy it once
now it just says go back however many
long that block was and then just
however many copies it wants it can just
kind of copy it ad infinitum bla bla bla
bla baby my baby my plan right so just
keep taking the block writing it into
the destination now it'll start reading
from that place right into the
destination reads in that plate right
it's always one block behind itself
reading and one block behind itself
writing that's exactly what we went out
on
so we faulted on a place where we had
some kind of a length where we were told
you need to repeat the value 243 for a
long long long long long long long long
time right so we need at least 46 of
these right who knows how many it
actually was we don't have an original
length here the Len tab symbol was 258
so I think that means we were it was at
least yeah it's at least 258 long and
the distance here was what we know what
this is was it was one backward right so
we don't know what the actual length is
because we don't know what the extra
bits are because obviously you know how
good visual studio ever show us the
value of extra bits because it was in
this other block I mean it's impossible
right I mean how could you ever do it
let's not ask for miracles inspecting a
variable that was used just a few lines
before is probably completely out of the
question I don't know if even in debug
mode don't ask me it used to work I
don't know if the compiler now over
writes those values even in debug mode
or something I'm not sure but anyway
neither here nor there Visual Studio as
always happy did not help you but point
being
length was not 46 it was 258 or more
originally and then we started copying
that 243 and we just kept on copying so
instead of stopping at the end of the
buffer where we should have stopped
we just didn't write so what I want to
do very quickly is I want to go ahead
and see what happens next
so I'm going to go ahead and set length
equal to zero all right guess I'll do
now I'll do zero and then I'm going to
go ahead and let this thing bottom out
so now we're outside of this function I
want to see what comes next
right so it's another 258 oso cubed e
bits used as 0 so I guess there would be
no extra bits anyway so visual studio
doesn't really didn't really screw us
too hard there because it turns out that
extra bits would have wouldn't have been
necessary so the fact that it never lets
us inspect any of these variables
doesn't matter because they weren't
actually used in that case so we know it
actually was 258 was the Rob right the
distance is 1 again and off we go
ok so what we're looking at here is a
bunch of Rob's that seem to be going too
far I'm gonna start I'm gonna just start
by looking at this routine a little bit
more closely this is not because I
suspect if the bug is here I just we
haven't really spent much time looking
at it
I just want to quickly before I start
digging deeper and making some test
cases in here and stuff like that I just
want to quickly verify to myself because
I don't really know that I didn't do
anything obviously stupid with like
those tables or
the way that we're decoding these things
so I want to kind of I want to just look
at this and get a sense for whether or
not I've you know I've whether or not
I've decoded this properly right so
we're doing a lip a literal or length
Huffman de code here and that you know
one thing we could have screwed up is
these Huffman tables so we're doing that
that decode here and then we're going to
output literals in the case where we
ended up with binary codes less than two
to five right we're gonna write those
out so that seems pretty straightforward
that case doesn't seem like it's
probably all that unlikely 256 is
actually our stoppage case so you'll
notice too many six just falls out to
nothing in the case that we're over 256
we then have this sort of lend tabindex
thing I don't do we use little n
anywhere else we don't so basically we
immediately take that and turn it into
something we can look up into the table
you can see us looking it up here and
basically what we want is our length to
be read out of there now I want to go
back and look at that table calculation
I want to look at all of this stuff I
want to make sure that this makes sense
because I don't know that it does right
so I want to kind of get a sense of
whether this is working properly or not
so here's the length extra lookup table
that we've got here here's the PNG dis
extra these are the two things that
we're looking up into so if I look into
this table looking up the bits here so
that means we jumped all the way to like
this one right if it was 258 with zero
extra bits that means that we were
encoding value 285 into the table all
the time which was this one right here
right and that again doesn't consume any
extra bits it just uses the straight 258
length value so I'm gonna go again I
want to like just validate this table
and I also want to look to make sure
that
I'm interpreting that case correctly and
and not doing anything stupid in this
case right alright so here's that
deflate algorithm here and here's that
table that we looked at before so if we
got value 257 we expect extra bits of
zero and a length of three right so
here's three zero right it's like three
four five six seven eight nine ten to go
to leave to 64 so three four five six
seven eight nine ten goes to 264 and
that's good right
then we have 265 it starts at one and
sorry it starts at eleven yeah starts at
eleven and reads one bit 13 15 17 19 15
17 19 23 27 31 and those were four twos
right - two - two
then we go to the threes thirty-five and
forty three thirty five forty three
fifty one fifty nine yeah 67 83 99 115
those are our forests 131 163 195 227
258 okay so I just want to spot check
that table you know we hadn't really
looked at it much looks reasonable let
me just take a look at this one as well
again make sure we've got our extra bits
here there's four zeros and the distance
is one two three four
just before then we've got let's see
what we got here five seven nine I'm
sorry five and seven yep 9 13
[Music]
yeah 17:25 let's see we got 33 4965 97
129 and 193 57 385 yeah 513 769 let's
see 1025 1537 240 not 2049 3073 both
tens 4097 6145 those are both 1180 193
is a 12 1 2 2 8 9 12 16 385 13 and 24
577 so 13 okay so I think those are
right
[Music]
Cephas was drafted because secretary
cigarettes either literal bytes from the
alphabet of byte valiance lengths
backward distance pairs where the length
is drawn from 358 and the distance is
drawn from 1 to 32 blah
in fact the literal in length outfits
are merged into a single alphabet we're
evaluating the value to said block 27 to
delink codes extra bits follows blah
blah blah okay
the co-surgeon extra code straight above
we show the code feel for added clarity
literal length values 286 &amp; 287 will
never actually occur in the compressed
data but participate in the code
construction okay
what is meant by that
our distance code 0 through 31 are
represented by fixed length 5 bit codes
with possible additional bits as shown
in the table and 30 and 31 will never
occur alright so I just want to make
sure I understand that last part there
so when we're creating these tables for
the literal length Huffman's here so
when we create these Huffman tables
we're gonna read in how long the table
was so
so basically I don't know that we care
about that part because it seems like
they would have told us whether or not
those things like when we actually read
the H lit value in the H lit value will
tell us how many things participate in
the table construction so don't quite
get that part of it not feeling great
about that not feeling great about that
yeah I might want to look at that anyway
we have the little end this table the
little end disable let's see so it's 32
64 plus 2 57 yeah that's gonna fit in
there just fine I
I should probably assert here what did I
just do so I'm gonna go ahead and just
assert in here that the length count is
less than or equal to the array account
of the whittlin disc table just because
I didn't don't know why I didn't put my
name before but that's like a hard bound
on that obviously so yeah so coming
through here where I do the compute huff
man we should look at those Huffman
codes so the Huffman decode then when we
grab out these this part here we look up
the Hoffman decode so we subtract 257
from it because that's the base value
that seems correct when we look up into
our length table we start with whatever
the base value has to be we then look at
how many bits we consume extra from the
input data we grab those bits and we
just add that in as the additional
length value we then go into the dist
tab index that Huffman 2 code is using
the other Huffman table this one so I
feel like and maybe I'm being premature
but I feel like this part is not
relevant well that's not true so this
part cannot cause us to be
wrong in the way that we were wrong
meaning we weren't fetching off the
beginning of the buffer so our distance
value even if it was wrong isn't causing
the problem but I shouldn't say that it
can't still be the cause of the problem
and the reason for that is because if
you look at this extra bit situation
because reading the Huffman out of here
then tells us how many extra bits we
should read if this is done incorrectly
it's the like the Huffman table was
built incorrectly we will get the wrong
symbol value out and that will then
cause us to read the wrong number of
bits when we read the wrong number of
bits we put our stream off by some
number of bits and then everything
subsequent will be wrong
you know I'm saying so even though this
itself getting the distance wrong is not
relevant getting this this number wrong
is not relevant to the - getting the
wrong number of bytes in the output but
it still can be the cause of that
problem because of the stream offset
right uh so yeah so what I could do here
- we can stop a little earlier
we can basically say like we want to
make sure that the decompressed pixel
ending is not going to be something that
gets exceeded so as I can do this right
and so that should I think if I wrote
that correctly that should assert prior
to us writing off the buffer so here we
can look at what the values were gonna
be right like we surmised it was 258 it
is this allows us to see who is about to
produce the problem and so in this case
actually everyone will like the desk and
the source will both exceed the deaths
will exceed at first but the source will
exceed it as well right so they both
would have written would have gone off
the end in either case right so the
other thing we can look at here is I'm
interested to know as well the
decompressed pixels end now I guess I
guess that's all I really know all right
so I would say that we kind of have two
avenues to go down now to try and figure
out what is causing the problem
one thing route is to go down looking at
the Huffman table calculation and see if
we have problems with it seems plausible
that there'd be a bug in there it's a
little bit of a weird routine however I
don't have anything to compare it
against right so my main problem was
starting with the Huffman table is I
don't have
a way to take some known good data for
what the Huffman table should be and
actually look at what mine is and go oh
there's the problem right so that seems
implausible as an Avenue so the first
thing I might do instead is actually
just look at the little end part of
things and see if I can't get that to
give me a clue right so the first thing
that I wanted you here is I want to take
the images that we have and I well I've
got myself into a situation right that
that's a little bit unwieldy all of
these nice tiny easy to inspect images
they don't have any bugs right or well I
shouldn't say that they don't have any
of this bug the kind that we're looking
for maybe they don't produce the right
image we haven't tested yet but they
don't have any obvious bugs this one
does but it's huge right I mean we look
at the properties of this thing it's a
monster it's 1024 I'm not gonna inspect
all that so my first question is can I
make this error occur without needing
the full image in question and so I want
to basically try just dicing this image
up and seeing whether a smaller version
of the image will cause the problem so
what I'm going to do is I'm just gonna
take the crop tool and I'm gonna split
the image in half and see if it's still
I'm basically going to do a manual
binary search to see whether I can
produce a smaller image that still
reproduces the problem but that I can
visually inspect so I know sort of
what's going on now they changed all the
icons and so honestly I don't know
where the crop is anymore
probably that that's not at all what it
used to look like
all right so what I'm gonna do is I'm
going to take a 512 by 512 sub piece you
can see down here there's a pixel
counter so I'm going to look for 512 on
both axes and I'm taking the top corner
and I probably could have done this just
with the in fact you know what here's an
easier way to do it if we just did
canvassize I can do 512 by 512 and we'll
just take that upper that upper corner
right so now I'm gonna say like okay
resize it we've just got this so now I'm
going to save this as just a generic
name test to write or maybe test small
and I'm going to export that so now what
I'm going to do is I'm going to keep
loading this in until I can get it to
I'm gonna keep making it smaller until
it doesn't crash and it would take the
one that's just a little bigger than
that right
oops that's not what's called all right
so let's see it go through here so now I
don't crash so even just that split even
that just that split by itself causes us
not to crash that again pretty rough on
us it basically means that we're in a
situation where this is a little this
must be a fairly subtle problem we have
but hey we've got a few we've gotta fix
subtle problems we can't only fix
clearing problems so let's go for it so
I'm gonna try a different thing now I'm
going to try having the image only this
way so that we still have runs that are
large in that direction on see if that
helps right
are we still are we actually parsing
this thing yep we are all right so it
doesn't crash in that case either okay
not a good start for us here folks try
one more thing let's look at the bottom
of the image okay so this is good we've
produced a potentially different error
it's not necessarily the same but it is
still an error that's good because they
probably both come from the same place
which is probably a corrupted read like
a read that reads too many or too few
bits and gets the whole stream out of
whack right so what I do know is that I
can use this smaller image so let's keep
trying again to get it smaller and
smaller so I'm gonna go ahead and try to
I'm gonna go ahead and try to make it
even smaller than this and so the first
thing I'm going to do is I'm going to
try just the white part here so get rid
of that the actual data I'm assuming
that the problem is in the actual data
part not in this but we don't know maybe
it's a problem with our large runs you
know and in which case it could be that
this part is the important part
so that part read through just fine
that also collapses down to a single
it--at chunk I don't know if that's
relevant at all it's worth noting all
right so now I'm gonna do the same thing
again but I'm gonna try just with the
upper chunk right so now I'm going to
try just this top chunk here so there's
my resize again now I'm gonna go ahead
and do an export to small again and
run okay same problem this is good again
we're narrowing down the size of this
thing
I'm gonna get it even smaller now let's
get it down to 128 again bisecting
keep the top part still has the bug I'm
now going to split because I've gotten
it well you know what let's just see how
small we can make it this way why not go
down to 64 okay so I can peat the top or
the bottom
gonna keep the top okay so the top
didn't work let's keep the bottom
awesome still buggy so we've got a bug
case here that's that's getting quite
small let me keep going down to 32 right
pretty tiny keeping the top not buggy
keeping the bottom
okay so we've gotten to a place where it
looks like we sort of have to have both
of these or at least something else I
don't know I mean I could just for sake
of argument try keeping the middle part
of it like so this so that's just the
middle you know who knows maybe but it
looks like we needed at least that big
in order to get repro yeah so it looks
like this is our test case here and that
gives us an error right so now we've got
something at least much smaller we can
look at I will now try to bisect it the
other direction this probably won't work
to to reproduce the problem but I'm
gonna try it anyway so we're gonna try
just the left side and now just the
right side
yeah all right so this is what I've got
it's not that small but it's at least
you know let me see what happens here
too with this so I will note that again
that the multiple i dapped chunk thing
is interesting like I I just want to
know I'm so interested to know if that's
related so if I take it down to the 512
like I was doing before and I export it
is it still to I that chunks it's not
that's so suspicious all right so let me
go ahead and cuz like I'm just wondering
if that's all it is
is it just that we have a multi I that
chunk bug i I can't imagine it is but
I'm just I'm really curious now so I'm
gonna take this down a little bit more
see if I can generate one that still has
two I'd out chunks in it and does that
reproduce the problem trying to find one
that still has two I that chunks I mean
don't you think that's really suspicious
I mean it just seems really suspicious
to me
I mean that is just so suspicious like I
just don't know what to make of that
but it sure looks like something that's
wrong with the AI datte chunks I feel
like we need to look at those Ida chunks
in the spec so you know good news is
we've got this down to a much simpler
test case right I mean that's way more
straightforward than it was before I'm
gonna now try one more thing before I go
look at anything else so I'm gonna
assume let's suppose that we had highly
uncompressible data data that doesn't
compress particularly well it looks like
rates into either chunks of 8192
right so 81 92 divided by 4 is 2048
right and this is this the square root
button it's like 45 so a 64 by 64 should
be big enough that I break into multiple
adept chunks right if the data is not
compressible so here's a 64 by 64 I'm
gonna create something here and I'm just
gonna paint a bunch of nonsense in here
oops not with that
I want this to have an alpha Channel
I'm gonna erase some stuff too
so I'm just going for something just
hard to compress that not hard to
compress for you know any compressor but
specifically hard to compress for ping
all right I'm gonna blur this
so all the values are kind of wonky
all right and now I'm going to try to
see if I if I have made one okay I want
to try and see if I can make one here
that is still - itit jumps right a
totally different file but that has two
IDOT chunks so this is Gibbs 64 by 64
and it helps if I don't type the name
okay so did I make - I that chunks yes I
did and doobie crash yes we do totally
different file right and the only thing
is it has two different Ayodhya chunks
in it so I'm gonna go ahead and say that
I am now fairly certain we have at least
one I that chunk related bug in here I
don't know what it is yet but I think we
probably have one so the first thing I'm
gonna look at is how I'm handling those
IDOT chunks and am i potentially
misinterpreting the length so for
example in here when we get this content
size for the Ida chunk right is it
possible that that length gets rounded
and I need to unrounded or something
like that to a certain bit length or
things like this so I wanna to basically
read the Ida
chunk part of the ping spec and see if
there was something we forgot because
there it's been a while since we read
that part and there may have been
something in there that was like and we
round up to blah or whatever right so
anyway a for beta so given number of
bytes that chunks data field the length
counts only the data field not itself
the chunk type or the CRT zero is a
valid length it kotas guys should treat
the link that's unsigned and it
shouldn't exceed two to the 31st - one
bit okay so we prop
we use the chunk header length which has
been swapped as the size of the data and
we use the chunk data as the data that's
what we'd expect so that's good let's
look at the Ida chunk information and
see what it says about how they work so
the four bytes shunk type field contains
decimal values 73 68 65 84
I assume that's just I'd at write that a
chunk contains the actual image data
which the output stream of the
compression I go to see Clause 9 and
compressor details to me about I checked
if so they should be consecutive with no
other debris chunks the compressed data
stream is then the concatenation of the
contents of the data fields of all the i
dot chunks which is what I think we were
trying to do here right so we put
together chunks of that size right we
say here's the length
here's the data and we put it in there
right and you know it can only be the
length it's it's not bit length it's a
byte length so that's how many there are
when we look at the last pointer we
string them together so are we correctly
appending these we say the last pointer
is going to be equal to the chunk that's
what we want we set the next pointer on
the last one to this one or the first
depending on whether there is one or not
that seems right as well so that should
produce a singly linked list of all them
I so that seems good okay so in here
where we do I'd app headers here's the
I'd app header that comes in I thought
and maybe I'm wrong about this but my
recollection was that when you move to
another I don't head err they did not
have any more header information I'm
almost positive that that was true so
I'm pretty sure that that that's correct
all right
it is important to emphasize that the
boundaries between Ida chunks are
arbitrary and can fall anywhere in the Z
live data stream there is not
necessarily any correlation between Ida
chunk boundaries and deflate block
boundaries or any other feature of the
zeal of data for example isn't entirely
possible the terminating Z lib check
value to be split across
IDOT chunks similarly there is no
required Crowley should be the structure
of the image data and deflate block
boundaries or as Yuma is a complete
filtered PNG which is represented by a
single zeal of data stream that's stored
in a number of I dot chunks
well
I guess the first thing I should do is
just look at how these are constructed
and when they're read from so
so when we're reading these it's pretty
straightforward right we consume bits
looking for the B final
so it looks like here we've got a
Huffman decode within the first block
and we read an invalid symbol
yeah hmm hmm so
at the point where we read the invalid
symbol which buffer are we on
oh my
so yeah that I mean in case I was
wondering that's not good
so yeah it under flowed
so this is just busted
kind of says you're on the Anfal first
this equals file first content size
let's step through that so did this hit
it did well but that's the first one so
that never got hit even though we under
set the underflow flag so so what we
really want here is to look at this
under flip flag yep yep yep yep yep yep
that's a bug folks you saw it too I'm
sure
well MTS MOC saw it because he said he'd
to bug this earlier so this is wrong so
basically what's happening the problem
here is consumed is the thing that can
advance we wrote this before we
supported multiple eyelet chunks Whedon
failed to actually write it correctly so
what we're trying to do here is we're
trying to loop until we don't have as
many bits as we think that we need you
know also I'm gonna put an assert in
there it would have caught this bug
earlier so if you look at this bit count
less and pick this part here it needs to
at least try to call consume or it won't
refill the buffer right so once we try
it here
we could say like oh okay you know if we
succeeded in getting a bite then that's
fine if we didn't get succeed in getting
a bite then then we break right
um so that's it really is looking like
that this isn't right because if the
buffer was only one big we don't want to
break out so it's like we need some way
of consume actually telling us whether
or not there's anything that we got and
so right we need some information from
consume about what it actually what it
actually returned right so you know
I'm gonna go like this and say that this
flag is now like a thing that we have
that's part of the consumed call so like
something like that so basically now the
underflow flag gets set outside and
consumed sighs this thing will keep
going trying to get more bits until the
underflow flag gets set at which point
you will bail and off we go so now let's
see if we get any more love here
hopefully we can start to figure out
what's going on um I love better all
right so I maybe I don't know if I still
screwed it up there let me make sure we
recompiled this here but let me see if I
can get it now to the point we're
actually reading that because that was
definitely a bug all right so now we're
at least actually reading the real bits
in we did actually advance what I don't
know is did we advance correctly so
we're still it's a little bit odd here I
still think we might have a little bit
bucks we did advance this doesn't really
matter we did advance and we read all
the way till 13 bytes from the end and
then we got in
a bogus symbol I think right that looks
like what happened here to master why I
had that in their choice so that got us
significantly further right so that was
at least that was a pretty major bug I'm
also assuming that that was not the bug
from this one but I don't know it was
okay so that was actually the bug we
were having on the test case what the
heck what is scripted sandbox 64
just what is it
oh boy anyway so I guess that was the
bug that was causing stuff with the
wrong number symbols in there so I guess
now we actually have to focus on this
other case because now that case is
actually not buggy anymore which is
great so never mind but I do want to
find out why our 64 by 64 is wrong so
let's go ahead and get that one going
now - all right so this one is reading
an incorrect symbol at the end where you
know it's it's we're getting some symbol
that we don't think we should be getting
one that wasn't supposed to actually
occur in the input stream so the I don't
know what the bytes we actually got here
okay so we got one one two seven six as
the bits that we got 15 bit
we got one one two seven six as the bits
that we got those bits are not don't map
to anything that's like they were not
bits we actually expected to see so
we're like what happened right okay
now I still don't really know that we
fixed the bug that we had I tried to fix
the bug that we had but I don't know
that we did so what I would like to do
is just verify that I think that that
loop still works
so while the bit count is insufficient
and we have not yet under flowed the
buffer it will try to consume new bytes
and shift them in right and that seems
relatively straightforward it will then
take the bit buffer and yeah the peak
bits it just uses those bits and that's
it right and then you can discard the
number of bits that you actually used
you know however many that was
and that seems reasonable I guess
all right so now I'm gonna have to
progress through this one as if it's a
totally new test case though because
although I fixed one underflow problem
with the idea let me just meet I also
want to make sure I did that test right
we had two of these right we had
test small
yeah
so and you know what else I wanna do too
while we're at it just to see if these
test cases are really freezing they're
out of my data
I wanna assert that the destination
equals the end so when we get here I
want to assert that the last thing we
wrote is where the end of the buffer
should have been right because maybe
it's not actually producing it okay so
now we actually we've made quite a bit
of progress I'm pretty happy about that
that was a pretty stupid bug to have but
it's just because we wrote that we
updated that thing right and didn't
update the part of the code that
actually needed to care about it so now
it looks like we've pretty much got
everybody producing the right amount of
data except for our 64 by 64 friend here
right and our 64 by 64 a friend here is
actually really close to the end I think
let me see I don't know how close to the
end of the output it actually is so it's
only 9 bytes away from the end when it
encounters the bad symbol of course it
may be totally wrong data so that may
not mean a thing but it's just worth
noting and also as we know the input
that's actually reading from the comp
data the comp date has actually been
processed almost entirely it's got 13
left 4 9 9 actual bytes all right so
this one's gonna be rough because this
so I guess there's still two things that
could be wrong here
so one could be that the huffman table
was built incorrectly and this symbol
that we actually got is a symbol that
could be encoded so you know it's
possible that the data stream is now
functioning correctly but the Huffman
table is functioning wrong however it is
also the case that that's not true and
that what actually happened is we still
have a bug in the bit stream reading
across either chunks that only happens
at certain times so I'm a check for that
first and here's I'm in do and it's
gonna look a little weird but what I
want to do is I want look at the peek
bits call and you can see where we're
doing this consume here I want to know
when we do
so if buff content size is less than
eight so if we're going to advance
forward I just want to know how many
bits were in the bit buffer that's it
so I just want to say look here's how
many bits I had when I went to rap I
just I'm just curious
don't ask me why I just want to know if
there's a difference between the cases
that do work in that dough so so that
tells me something right there that oh
sorry I mentioned one so I guess it's
just zero if I was about to advance the
buffer
so there were 12 bits in the bit buffer
before I went to advance
fixed huffman not yet oh yeah
so that's actually just one that we
don't handle no problem it's fine
well I'm glad I looked at the output
good that gives us an excuse to go do
that now so maybe we don't have a bug
we don't know maybe we don't have a bug
at all what we do know is that we need
to put the fixed huffin tables in now so
let's put them in seems like as good a
time as any
looking back at our specification we
have to find sir okay here we go the
Huffman codes for the two alphabets are
fixed and are not represented in the
data the Huffman code lengths for the
literal length alphabet are 0 through
143 get 8 bits
144 through 25 get 9 to be 6 through 279
gets 7 and 280 through 287 get 8 I mean
is that as simple as it sounds is that
all I have to do I mean I'll just try it
I guess can't hurt to try it so
basically what I'm trying to do here is
just seed this Huffman table so you know
the this nonsense here I still want to
do this you know this bit right bit
right here so I still want to produce
these too but I don't really need to
he says I don't really need to look at
the hold on
so where is where does the distance
huffman oh here it is love of ice okay
so that's when I read this before and
didn't it was talking about it's talking
about this only this only the fixed
codes this is not a new header that's
just the page break threw me off
please go 303 one over fix like five bit
codes distance Co straighter it never
occurred in the compressed data okay so
let's start so 287 okay okay okay so
what I want to do here is just see these
in so let's go ahead and actually do
this here's the little end disk table in
fact I can just you know we can just
make this thing happen out here so
here's a little in dis table I can go
ahead and just fill that thing out we
now know that H lit will basically be
fixed so the number of each lip codes
there R is now non-variable right
because it's a fixed up in code to don't
read it from anywhere and so we know
that the H lit value actually goes up to
280 what 288 right is the first one
because 27 is the last code that
actually participates yeah 387 so tweety
eight is the first distance code if I'm
understanding that correctly
so I'm gonna go like this
and I'm just going to write stuff into
that little end table and so I'm going
to do here is just say well the bit
count I don't remember what we actually
made these things you three twos so the
bit count here is gonna just be based on
where we are in the actual stream in
there in the thing right and you could
make these into multiple ones if you
wanted to multiple 4i loops but I'm not
even gonna well yeah I mean I guess I
could do that I mean let's just do this
right
so what I'm going to do here is I'm just
gonna do like this stopping point and
the bit count right so I'm just gonna
say what this thing says
so it's like okay we've got zero to one
forty three are gonna be eight bits
right so I'll just do like zero to one
forty three or eight bits 144 to 255 is
nine bits 256 to 279 so that's just to
79 is seven bits to 82 to 87 is eight
bits right and then the length values
which go on which going after that are
32 is that correct so it'd just be like
319 so I think that's what we're talking
about here don't quote me on that
so if I want to set the bit count index
maybe we'll do it like this oops uh so
here's what I'll say
I guess we'll call these range in the
C's so yeah how's this how's this boy
think of this it's not fabulous but I
think I get the job done so basically
what we do is we start at bit County
index zero we need to fill out the ho
table we have a little cheat sheet here
that tells us like we're to what to go
up through right and so wait a minute so
288 + 32 320 yep so we're good so you
know we just read out okay what's the
stopping value for this range of bits
and we just rub that value in there then
we do the Huffman table based on that
the exact same way we would have done
the Huffman table which is good because
I think that means we can just do this
and get rid of this part here and that
way we can just have H lit and H dist B
variables that actually get set
separately
and off we go okay so wait what index
undeclared it what where is that where
are you seeing index from that line so
confused right now
did I do something really strange here
whoa whoa how did that get over there my
bad
all right so now that we got a fixed
huffin case here let me just step into
this one time and see what we get out of
it so I'm gonna look at this little n
just table nonsense and just see if if
it set up what the spec says or at least
is what I configure so we expect to see
8 going from 0 to 143 so here is a bunch
of 8 and there's 143 right now we've got
1 44 55 should be nines okay now we've
got 256 to 279 should be 7s and now I
got to 82 to 87 should be 8 and then
everything after that should be fives I
just don't know how far up the 5 should
go I think my like my feeling on that is
that it should go up to 3 19 by oh no we
exited properly so you know maybe we're
good I don't know so at this point we're
kind of now at a place where we need to
start figuring out okay we we're not
like obviously erroring out in the
middle of stuff but we don't actually
know
look we don't actually know if we are
producing reasonable images at all right
we did some little hand inspection but
it would be nice now if we could like
diff the image or something to determine
whether or not we actually have an exact
replica or if we've got pixel errors so
I don't know where we are on time I
think we're almost out of time actually
I think we're only ten minutes to go so
what I think I'll probably do is just
run a few more tests images through it
first what we'll do next weekend is
we'll actually just put in start putting
in real images to it and test them
versus like a bitmap version of them
that we can load exactly and diff them
so that we can then just verify that we
actually have what we think we have if I
remember correctly we've got a case that
still asserted out and we've never
called it so this guy the averaging guy
never gets got used so I don't know what
to make of that like we still haven't
asserted in there I'll go ahead and
remove that assertion temporarily but
like I'm gonna leave it to do in there
because at some point would really nice
to figure out whether that works right
so let's go ahead and take I don't know
the best way to do this here but let's
suppose that we went to twitch.tv slash
handmade hero and just took a look at
this nonsense that's going on here
surely we want the 1080p version right
and then what I could do is just capture
this and try to save it right so what
I'm gonna do is screenshot snipping
tool' let's go ahead and let that play
well
to a new here we'll grab it there we go
let's go ahead and now we'll save that
out as an image and we'll save it from a
you know as a PNG from a different
program this is from the snipping tool
just to get something like totally
different in the mix that I can test
against - all right um so let's see what
happens when we throw that at it maybe
that'll expose some more bugs in our
stream handling that we haven't thought
about yet sorry as I forget literally
the file name I just typed in a chat
underscore capture so that's good it
looks like we ran okay so I think we're
at the point now where our stream
handling isn't too bad a lot of I dot
chunks in there we decompressed we
didn't exceed our boundaries we produced
the exact right amount of data so that
to me suggests that we are in reasonable
shape right okay so let me go ahead and
put a key way up on there let me also
ask so MTS mocks you said in the in the
pre stream that you had worked to find
the bug so did you find it was that the
one that you found I'm curious to know
awesome okay so Dee do you think that
took me a reasonable amount of time to
find too long or not I don't know you
said you thought it took a long time to
find for you I don't know you could use
the Ray casting code for save image
files so we can see what happens it
should be a quick thing to do that's a
good point
handmade ray which we did when we were
starting to test this new streaming
machine does have images that we can use
so here's an example of a bitmap version
of the image and oops know what I just
did there oh it's just this I just want
you to use this Microsoft
where's why isn't on there
alright so here's like a thing that was
produced by the raytracer and here I'll
export that to the test directory as a
PNG yes I don't really know what stuff
to put in here but sure see how that
does
so great I'm really happy about that
that seems pretty robust now in terms of
handling the stream I mean that was a
lot of stuff to get right and we got
right we only had one real nasty bit
there we do have to give credit where
credit is due to somebody who probably
saved us some debugging work coming up
because remember our filters could all
be totally busted right now we have no
idea we haven't really checked but I
guess what I would say is we somebody
mentioned the fact that I had read the
spec wrong about the B value being too
high up being up one above not two
behind so for the C value rather so that
one was somebody somebody treated me on
that one
do you purposely screenshot my message
saying you are handsome no I didn't I
didn't even notice that
frosty ninja I think he meant save out
the decoded p.m. geez as a rub bitmap so
we can see the result oh I see what
you're saying you're saying use the
bitmap saving code you know what that's
also a good idea that both the ideas
that you that I interpreted you as
saying and the idea you actually had
which not the same are both good ideas
yes we could we did write on handmade
ray a bitmap thing here somewhere
I don't remember where but we do have
one in there that saves a bitmap anyone
remember where that is here it is
so yeah we couldn't we could totally do
that that's pretty trivial to do so if
we want to dump that in here we would
just need the bitmap header struct that
bitmap header struct I don't know if
it's already in here it might be yeah it
is so all we would really need to do is
like put the width and the height in
here and then put that in here we don't
have the bitmap header but we do now
there we go
and then this image pixels bit here is
just gonna have to be something that we
pass in yeah so that seems good maybe I
don't know but yeah so after PNG filter
reconstruct here where we are what
what's going on here so we can do W do
we have a tempter we do although it's
filled with other stuff in it though
maybe it's time to clean that out move
rename
temp to old temp make your temp so you
know something like this ish so that'd
be pretty easy for us to implement right
we can just say like if argh count is
greater than equal to 2 or equals 3
right then we say like okay the you know
in file name and the out file name so
then we do like that
uh and just you know pass this thing in
here so honestly I think actually the
waitest thing had it before though with
having a package that you return is
probably a good idea right so we
probably actually want to keep that
thing that had before to a certain
extent because this read this thing here
this parse P&amp;G is gonna have to return
something and you know it would be nice
if you could return the metrics of the
file as well so you know this image u-32
nonsense that we introduced in here
somewhere is actually probably the right
thing or not necessarily the right thing
but like it's useful so we know we can
just dump that in here and say like okay
yeah you know this thing returns one of
this these and then you can just do this
and you know it's good to still have
this take the broken out pieces I kind
of feel like because there's no sense
and not how do you do that but it's good
to have this for the return value so
that seemed useful to me so I'm going to
keep that as it is so if this returns an
image u-32 I'm just gonna say that
there's a result one here when we come
through here we've got the final pixels
the width and the height are things that
need to be out here but at this point
now when we come down here I can just
basically romp those in and
I don't know why define it at the top
yeah that was not necessary so this this
could actually just happen down here
it's just like a way to bundle up the
information that comes back like so and
so now at that point that should be fine
and maybe that'll work I don't know
let's see so there's our temp file whoa
okay so it looks like we have a couple
problems so all of these I think are not
problems with our reader though so first
of all the PNG comes in RGBA the bitmap
goes out the other bitmaps have the
white reversed version so there's that
bitmaps also flip upside down so those
two things we would have to handle but
otherwise I think we're good
like I think that's just correct so
that's yeah so when we let's call this
right image top-down rgba what this
would have to do here I think you can do
that I think we can do that if we want
to but since we have to reverse the
channels anyway what I could do here is
just do the row swap at the same time I
do the bit swap so what I could do is
say all right you know row equals zero
or I should people should do this y
equals 0 less than header height
/ - I want to round that up I'll do
midpoint sue based I'm gonna do is say
like look let's go to the halfway point
here and what I could do is take two
rows swap the two rows and swap the Arn
and swap the R and B channels which
should give me a valid bit map out in
theory right so basically I can say is
like you know row 0 equals well I can do
it like this actually
so row 0 equals pixels row you know 1
equals pixels plus the height times the
width like that so just get me to the
last row so now I've got pointed it to
either right either one and then each
time through I can just do like in fact
it you know
yeah well row so step one you know from
the top down dealer from the bottom up
right and then we can just go through
and and do the pixels right pick 0
equals row zero picks one row one for
you 32 X equals zero X is less than with
plus plus X and here I just need to swap
the two right so C 0 equals pics 0 C 1
equals
six-one I've read out both the colors
then I will just write them back
together here although actually I guess
we'll just swap them right and so now
what I need to do is swap the R and the
B of each of them maybe I'd do it like
this no I do it like this
so I'll swap the R &amp; B of this I'll swap
the R &amp; B of that and then I'll just
write them out in the opposite order
right so that flips the image I believe
and flips that are in B channels which I
need it to do so then all I need here is
a thing that will do that swap so when I
say swap R&amp;B like there's the color for
the input and so if you think about
what's gonna happen to to these top tip
the values right the Alpha and the green
stay in the same place and only the R
and the B swap right so to produce the
result value if I just start writing
this out longhand I know that I can
knock out the values in question like
that so this will leave me with just the
Alpha and green channels intact
oops sorry little fat finger today so
then the question is just what else do I
have to put in here well I need the red
channel to swell depends how you wanna
look at it
I need the input that went here to slide
down I need the input the weight here to
slide up right so I need to slide down
16 bits and or in what would it be in
the low at that point right so just slot
in whatever
that's taking what was here and sliding
it there right so that's one part of it
then I need to take the bottom part and
slide it up right and what I can do
there is just end it with oxf FF first
then slide it up so that I still use the
same mask both times right it's pretty
simple I think that swaps them we'll
have to double check I meant to type
that and so now that was pretty quick
and dirty I admit that but I think that
might be what we wanted let's take a
look okay there's no way that produced
exactly the same image oh I forgot to
advance those pointers it didn't produce
exactly the same age it produced almost
exactly the same image it only did the
first column um so yeah right there
sorry about that
one more time so there's the you know
there's there's the image that we
produced from the ping and if I go look
at the test data that we got here's the
input ping now I'm not really sure how
to diff these two exactly if we had like
beyond compare or like one of those
utilities we could just ask it to diff I
don't know if Kemp can diff it's sort of
good right like what I could do is this
open hand made ray open
you know temp oops I meant open as
layers temp and then set this layer to
subtract and see what we get so that's
what the difference says I don't know if
that means we've got some bugs on the
outline here if I don't set it to
difference can we see those bugs oh it
looks like we shifted the image I wonder
if that's because my swap
like we shifted the image did you notice
that is that true
let's take a look I'm look at the top
yeah so the image is shifted up by one
what happened at the bottom oh there's
no way to tell is there because there's
nothing on the bottom there it's blank
so uh so that's I think we're good it's
just we this right bitmap is off by one
here so let's see
so
I can't I'm sure that I should be able
to immediately see what the problem is
up there just straight-up typos don't
ask me why that was doing that all right
so if I now run this we should now have
an exact version hopefully hopefully so
that's the one in the actual temp
directory so that's the one we produced
let me open as layers the original one
that's an handmade test handmade ray and
so let me set that to difference now
this is not really correct because it
won't handle overflow and underflow but
at least now we can see that there's no
obvious glaring errors so we're doing
pretty good not bad for a Sunday let me
take some questions
isn't it true the compiler optimizations
of your code and the way the CPU works
the sometimes cause instructions to
happen in a different order than you
wrote them if so won't that screw up
profiling measurements I yes and yes I
guess is what I'd say this is off topic
right because we're not doing profiling
measurements today I mean I you're not
you're not asking question about what
we're doing here right that's just a
general question the answer is yes it
can and yes it can
those are those things are true can you
quantify how fast you type not
particularly easily because most typing
thing measurements just give you words
to type which are different than typing
code so it's a little hard to say it's
like what do you mean by how fast can
you type you know would you say that for
coder is the ideal text editor well
probably not the ideal text editor but
it's like the one that I prefer I mean
the ideal text editor would have all
sorts of crazy stuff in it
I mean Alan's only been
working on for coder for not that many
hours right so I feel like I don't think
he thinks it's the ideal text editor
either he's got tons of things planned
for it that you know will make it better
how often do I work out I do not really
work out per se I go rock climbing which
kind of just ends up being your work out
in the bitmap write routine I think you
have a bug you advanced rozier too soon
yes you are correct we just found that
one double check the shifting it's not a
git pastry error it's not it was just us
it's just us it's just us just trying a
week ago and having that time to go fill
a serious can you say in overall what
have you done on the product and what is
left to do so at this point we're
basically putting art in after we're
done putting art in we're gonna base
we're going to mostly be doing gameplay
programming which is like programming
like you know NPCs hopping around and
you interacting with the world in ways
to stuff like that that's that's what we
have to do now and along with that
there'll be world generation code stuff
because we don't have we just have a
very simple world generation in there
right now we will do some passes on the
graphics later to add more stuff like
more like good particles and stuff we we
have like some sort of placeholder stuff
in there for some things and those
things will have to improve
do you have any project recommendations
for beginner intermediate C programmers
which kind so the one I usually say for
game programming is asteroids it's like
the easiest game to write so it's a good
one to start with if you're not talking
about real time and you and/or you want
something that's not has no platform
dependent parts raytracer is good seems
a bit casual today what's your favorite
album Oh
what's my favorite album you know that's
real tough
I don't think I can pick a favorite
album I really just don't think I don't
think it could pick one I'm sorry what
is the craziest file format to parse
[Music]
well I guess I don't know what you mean
so the craziest file format you might
try to parse in practice would probably
be 3d studio max because there is no
text version it is binary it is
undocumented and it depends entirely on
which plugins are active and it changes
with every revision so probably like
reading max files directly would be like
one of the most nuts of things you could
do
I'm sure there's harder but that's just
the one that comes to mind what is the
most difficult file format to read have
you ever tried to read PDF files and try
doing a vector renderer for those no
Brasil TDF files aren't bad no there's
there's way worse stuff out there than
that what's my favorite pasta dish so I
think I would say that a straightforward
sausage rigatoni would probably it like
a red sauce sausage in rigatoni like
it's a pretty standard Italian dish I
like that a lot
how come no one is me I saw a debugger
is it difficult no it's not particularly
difficult I think the problem is it's
not particularly profitable
I think one of the main issues that we
face these days I guess I would say
developers don't pay for software much
they expect everything to be open source
and free now to a large extent and the
problem ends up being that there's no
money in it to make these tools so as a
result no one does and you just end up
with like crappy free stuff that isn't
very good or like the one remaining tool
from Microsoft or something well the
game the only room based I don't know
we have scrolling in there so I don't
really we I don't know
am i musician not really I can play the
piano though did you write music for
handmade here oh no I'm not writing
music for handmade hero how can I send
data over the internet for a game that
can be picked up in a code that I write
well usually you use sockets for that so
usually you use like rect V or send to
send packets I mean I'm not sure what
you're asking but that's how that's done
usually we'll be parsing compiler debug
output for cool game game devices no
we're not get a parse dwarf dwarf
speaking of disasters file formats 3ds
is worse than PCSO three not 3ds max 3ds
files aren't aren't awful 3d spells
aren't great but they're not awful max
files are awful dot ma x way worse than
PSD way worse we've had a handmaid ray
bonus series what about having asteroids
maybe someday I don't know no promises
all right I'm calling it a day
hey we made a PNG reader that was cool
first time I ever parsed PNG never had
to write it before I will probably go
move that into my codebase - because why
not now I don't have to use other
people's code to read a PNG if I want to
I could also make something that writes
of PNG now that I think about it because
it wouldn't be very hard to reverse and
to go the other direction anyway alright
so I want to close this down because we
don't need all these specs anymore but
if we encounter bugs in the future in
our PNG reader it'd be nice to have them
so what I might do is just say like
let's make a little PNG Doc's thing here
so we don't have to go dig these up
again and let's just drop these in there
the links oh you know what be even
better let's just save the documents
because these are text files aren't they
so can I just save this thing of course
this wouldn't have the diagrams would it
like what's this thing okay well I mean
it could still load the pings I guess I
don't know so all of these are just
would just save right we wouldn't have
to save the links we could just save the
file
so anyway now we've got those in there
at least these two we can open up as
text which is nice these two not so much
looks like that worked okay yeah so I'll
just leave those there because you know
we only know that a small smattering of
tests seem to work properly we have not
done any robust validation of this PNG
reader so we don't really know that
we've handled all the cases correctly
and we could in practice as we start
using this in the game find that we've
got some art assets that don't load
properly because maybe Photoshop does
some slightly different things then
does and it does compression it so etc
so we want those documents handy because
we're gonna have to refer to them again
when we hit a bug right so we'll leave
those there for now but that way I don't
have to keep them up here all the time
all right thank you for one for joining
me for the handmade hero so in pleasure
code with you as always I'm glad that
that PNG reader went pretty smoothly I
don't know we only spent what eight
hours on it twelve hours on it from
start to finish
PNG reader that's pretty cool and now we
can load p.m. cheese immediately so
that'll allow us to have a nice
Photoshop turnaround time so we can go
ahead and started playing that next
weekend just roll that into the asset
system so we can just import assets on
the fly alright that's it if you want to
follow along at home obviously as I say
all the time you go here to the game on
handmade hero org it comes with source
code so you can play around it yourself
so yeah if you want to take a shot at
adding hot loading of PNG s before I do
next weekend you could dig out the asset
system and give it a give it a shot
alright until then have fun program
everyone I'll see you on the Internet
I'll be back here next week to start
rolling that that PNG reader into our
mainline code we'll try to do that in a
way that allows us to still keep the
test cases running again specifically
because I don't want to run this
situation where we hit some new bug and
we don't have an easy way to bug it so
we'll do that sorry next weekend hope
see you back
that till then take these everybody I'll
see you any minute