hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete game live on
stream I coming back after the holiday
break we did not have episodes last
weekend but have them this weekend we
are kind of getting close to lighting
I'm happy with actually we've done a
pretty good job of sort of navigating
through the rather difficult waters of
real-time lighting and I think that
we've kind of gotten to a point where I
can see this being the thing that we
would ship right so the key components
of it are smoothing over time and
specifying what light gathers go with
which rendered objects seems to be the
crucial aspects of the lighting model
that make it work for us and so what
we're really trying to do now is now
start to solidify things down into a
shippable system that's like reliable
and not too slow and so on right and so
we only just hit upon all of these
things kind of coming together last time
we program so two weeks ago and so we've
got some bugs in there that already we
just have to fix the assignment we had
just added the ability to assign
specific lighting samples to elements in
the in the world and I believe that
stable assignment is broken at the
moment so we gotta actually solve that
problem it's you know it's just gonna be
some bugs in there that we've got to fix
and then we have to start moving our
like locking down how that stuff gets
transmitted to the renderer and actually
put in the ability to do sort of a multi
resolution approach and on the GPU as
well so we basically just have like a
bunch of finishing work to do now but
I'm pretty happy with sort of what we
have discovered in terms of a reasonable
way to do some lighting in real time
that gets the sort of flow of lighting
out into the world that I wanted for the
game I think it'll be sufficient and you
know I'm I'm happy enough with it so far
that I think it could be what we go with
the game does not require super advanced
lighting for any particular gameplay
things it just wants to be able to have
an
nice coherent lighting environment and
so I think that this will accomplish
that certainly if the game was really
about specific reflections or seeing
people and mirrors and things like this
you know we haven't taken it to those
kinds of extremes at all
so if you were trying to do a game that
had really specific lighting concerns
you know this is maybe not the lighting
solution that goes as far as you would
want but again this is not what we
needed for this game but we needed for
us atmospherics sort of effects that are
going to make you feel like you're
really in the world things that sort of
give you information about where things
are like you know fires that are lit and
kind of glowing and things like this
maybe things like carrying a lantern
around might be nice etcetera and that's
the thing sort of thing that we can do
with the system that we have now so I'm
gonna say that that's what what what I'm
happy sort of turning the crank on and
shipping so let's just revisit where we
were because I just said we had some
bugs but for those of you who type the
wrong thing there for those of you who
may have been you know working on other
stuff for the past few weeks and don't
remember where we were in handmade hero
which for some reason doesn't include me
even though I was working I happen to
remember
I guess because hey I'm the one who has
to program it it's my responsibility to
remember I will refresh your memory as
to what I mean by there were some bugs
and the thing that we added that we
needed to fix at the end of the last
episode specifically what we were doing
is we were adding some smoothing and in
order to smooth the light samples over
time there were two ways that we could
have approached this and each of the two
ways of approaching this were well you
know what that's interesting because I
thought we had did we just turn us so I
guess I need to refresh my memory too
because I actually don't remember us
having a black screen here I remember us
having a smoother like I remember us
having some lighting running here and
the lighting was only working on half
the grid so I don't actually remember
this being a problem so maybe I am not
remembering either but point being
whether I'm remembering
that part correctly or not it was
already buggy and we needed to sort of
fix it so the first thing that we need
to do today is get those lighting
assignment points working correctly and
I believe we left a big to-do as well in
the render group stuff that sort of
talked about the problem where was that
guy was here so you'll see very
important finish in planning and
debugging lighting index assignment in
the render group before doing anything
else with lighting and you can see this
is the thing that I left at the end
which we definitely need to do right so
anyway I'm gonna go ahead and proceed
under the assumption that the bugs that
we had in this system that we're causing
it to only partially work are probably
the same things that are causing us on
fresh reboot to not work because we're
probably just not initializing things
properly or not sending down the right
stuff and so we're probably it was just
accidental that we it was half working
before and we really have to go ahead
and make it work properly right so let
me just go over what we were doing we
have these things called entity pieces
that's just the way of allowing a
particular entity in the game to have a
couple different like sprite components
for example with it and what you can see
about these entity pieces is that they
have a way of assigning lights now to
themselves and lights is the wrong way
sorry a lighting like sample point to
themselves so the way that it works is
inside the lighting system we have
things that emit light and then we also
have things that occlude light and
things that pick up light as sort of
sensors in the world and so occluders
are things that can block light from
being transmitted around so those are
things like our cubes or whatever that
are going to create obstacles that the
light cannot flow through and then we've
got emitters that are sort of the same
thing as obstacles only instead of
preventing light from going through them
they're sending light out and then
finally we've got light actual lighting
points and these are points that are
trying to collect what light they will
see from where they are right and so
what happens is for each entity visible
piece we have a lighting index and that
lighting index tells us the
first light in a range of lights that
will sorry the first lighting sample in
a range of letting samples that will be
used to light this piece and the reason
that that's stored in the entity
structure is that's because it has to be
coherent from frame to frame meaning
that on frame zero if we say that this
particular piece identity is getting lit
by these and samples then on frame one
we have to say the same and samples now
the reason for that is because we don't
want to deal with trying to interpolate
the lighting based on the location of
things because in order to interpolate
things we would run into a situation
where things have to do spatial lookups
and one of the things that I'm trying to
avoid is though spatial lookups because
having to deal with the voxel was kind
of annoying it just added a lot of
complexity and we had problems about the
fact that you know voxel cells we'd have
to make sure that they were always
filled and if there wasn't any
particular thing in that voxel cell then
what would we fill it with and how do we
interpolate between them it kind of
starts to exponentially grow you know a
cubed number of samples that we have to
take and blah blah blah so I really just
thought it was a better way to actually
do frame to frame direct assignment
rather than some things being based on
spatial map matching and so that's kind
of the way that we were going with it
now when this actually happens this
light index here that the entity visible
piece is responsible for sending down
what you can kind of see is that that
light index when you do a push light or
a push cube which are the two things
that are currently getting sent down to
the lighting system
I don't think push bitmap does it yeah
it doesn't those are basically
specifying these lighting indexes which
are saying where these these things
should go right we're into the lighting
array these things should go that
actually reminds me what happens in push
bitmap that presumably sends down a lady
next to 0 which means that bitmaps
aren't lit which I think is the correct
thing that we're observing here what you
can see that bitmaps are
lit right now and that's by design at
the moment they will be lit later will
actually scatter points on them or
something similar to that but so you can
see that only lights and cubes are sus
to be participating in it so what we
expect to see right is we expect to see
our light here that's floating right
here we want that to be scattering light
out to our cubes and we're not seeing
that right now so that's the immediate
bug that we are seeing the bug that we
saw before that when we were working on
this last week was that we were only
getting like half of our world was
getting lit and the other half wasn't
properly and so on so our goal is to
debug this thing right here and if we
look inside the render group to see
where that was actually taking effect
what you can see is that uh they go
ahead and search for that first cube
there it is we've got sort of this
lighting index store thing that's what
was getting passed here what happens is
when we come down through here at the
light index store if it is valid meaning
we actually got a pointer which again we
wouldn't understand we when we're doing
things like push fit that we don't get
any but when we do something like a push
cube and if we see a light index store
what we do is we say how many lights
were going to be putting on this
particular thing then we in the in this
case light count is per face of the cube
we then say okay if the thing that's
already there in the address that we're
going to be storing the light
information the storing the light index
back to if there's something that's
already in there I mean if it was non
zero then we're gonna assume that it's
this it's one that got assigned in a
previous frame and we're gonna use it
otherwise what we're gonna do is just a
sign it one and again you can see here
that this is already a to do this won't
work when things are moving in and out
of the active set so what we actually
need is some kind of a thing that that
that takes chunks and reassigns them
it's just got to be like a free list
sort of a thing that's not gonna be hard
to implement but I don't think that's
our bug right now because right now
we're just looking at something that's
not really getting reassigned I don't
think now maybe it is and maybe that's
why this is happening so it could be
that I'm actually pretty stupid for
saying that so maybe we should go ahead
and fix that first
I don't know but point being I want to
investigate the bug first before jumping
to any conclusions about what is
and isn't the problem but point thing
that has to get fixed eventually as well
so then what we see is that hey whenever
this happens we also sort of advanced
the light index by the light count times
six which is six face to the cube that's
just so that when we go through we're
putting things in places that are
ostensibly named when we go ahead and do
our our push quad you can see that we
send down the light index so whatever
the lighting index was we send it down
here and we we increment it as we go now
one of the things that's a little bit
busted about that is that means that
anything that was not getting lit it's
gonna be kind of wrong because it will
actually still assign lights to it it
should assign zero this whole time but
it wouldn't oh no that's not true
light count would be still set to zero
so that's fine so it would pass a zero
in all these so that's fine I take it
back there's not a bug there so anyway
when we go up to push quad what you can
see here it's the light index just flows
through to the actual push quad which
you can see here has like the emission
value the light count the light index
let me just make sure those getting
passed in the correct order down here
let count let me ask yep so when we go
through impact go to push quad we can
see is that the light a sunlight count
are stored in each vertex again that's
wasteful it's in it's a to do inside our
vertex structure we we just did that
because in getting it working I didn't
want to bother adding a new vertex
stream to pass down that information but
we can actually optimize that out and
pass just one light index and count for
each primitive so this can be simplified
but at the moment we're just passing
every vertex so it will always be there
no matter which vertex are looking at so
that's probably fine so that's how this
works
and that information just goes into the
stream to be used later on now that gets
picked up eventually by the lighting
code so if we take a look inside where
the light actually happens you can see
that in extract reflectors from quads we
kind of come through here and we build
you know this this code will go away
eventually this will just be welded into
the thing that's actually outputting
manatees in the first place but what
we're doing is we're going through and
we're putting points on the surf
of these quads proportional to the
number that we were asked to do now we
didn't actually write this code because
like I said it's not real it's just here
for its placeholder so it's actually
just locked to them always use the same
pattern because we know where are we
sending down for but in the future will
be scatting you know scattering these
lights more intelligently Scott
scattering sent sample points more
intelligently presumably anyway so what
we then do is we come through here we
output all of our lighting information
into these little solution elements we
then run our compute light propagation
function and it goes through and it
propagates the lights all around to
these light samples and when it's done
with that it goes ahead and says all
right I I'm gonna go through and I'm
gonna normalize all of my results right
and I'm going to linearly interpolate my
results that I got meaning the results I
got this time I'm gonna linearly
linearly interpolate
from what I started with which is the
last emission here right I'm gonna
interpolate from what I started with
toward my solution every time so that
it's slowly it will slowly sort of
interpolate there now what we do to
avoid startup problems is if we have
never gotten a valid lighting solution
so meaning on frame zero where there
wasn't anything beforehand we don't want
to lurk because we're looping from bogus
values so you want to just set the value
equal to whatever it would be on this
frame and the way that we do that is we
just look to see whether this solution
was ever marked as valid if it's never
been marked as valid then we just assume
that we can linearly interpolate between
the value in itself and so it will
always get itself no matter what the
value of T is right so that's how we're
working at the moment
now what we have to do is investigate
this and find out where we're going
wrong and why everything is coming out
black so the first thing we can do here
is let's go ahead and switch back to a
debug build let me go ahead and
switch to the OD here and if I go ahead
and run the program now it should still
be yet does seem it does seem like maybe
we're just not getting any emission
honestly because you can notice how fast
it's running - that's how fast I think
it would be running if you just weren't
emitting anything right which is kind of
bizarre
yeah it's kind of weird and lighting
disabled should always be false anyway
anyway sorry I lost my train of thought
there as I was looking at her a little
menu thing here um so anyway point being
since all these things are coming up
black what we need to do is kind of go
up the chain and just take a look at
where we you know what sorts of things
we're seeing in terms of stepping into
the debug code why we're never getting
any emitters in meeting anything here
because it looks to me like we're never
getting any emission at all the reason
that I say that is because currently our
algorithm will slow down proportional to
how much emission there is and the fact
that this is running in debug mode right
now meaning the code is not even running
through the optimizer and it's running
it at close to 60 frames a second that
just suggests to me that we're not
really getting any lighting happening at
all like nothing is actually starting
the emission process so one of the
things that I can do here is maybe I
kind of come through here and I first of
all just make sure we're actually
pushing a light on to the stack at all
but you know here it looks like we are
see what the emission value is so there
is here's the light that has an emission
value on it and let's make sure that
that gets assigned some proper light
indexes here you know what I should just
do step into o or I won't so here in the
push tube function just looking through
it does correctly assign a light index
here yep so it's doing what I think it
should be doing right there's no there's
nothing weird going on here that I can
see so far and what I can do is I can
take a look now in the lighting code
just to see whether or not I don't know
why I just typed render group that's
good
I wanted to switch to render group and I
forgot that the the command that what I
mean in visual studio is not that where
is the render group can I grab it here
there we go so what I want to do here is
I just want to set a breakpoint in the
lighting so I can actually see what's
going on in terms of whether we get any
emitters and why they're not getting
pushed out into the world at all because
it looks like the lighting isn't even
running on them that's what it looks
like because we're not getting a
framerate hit from it so here it looks
like we're not running extract
reflectors from quads right so we must
have the lighting turned off in some way
maybe I just forgot how we were running
the lighting or something like this at
the end of last episode maybe I just
turned it off really quickly you can see
we're not even calling lighting tests so
if I jump back to handmade worlds that
would probably answer the question as to
what it is I forgot so recompute
lighting is false if the F key is
pressed five six one four
update lighting is serum
so it looks like if I just press f4
okay so there we go I was not on crack
I just forgot that we had bound it to a
key so that's good this is the problem
with binding things two keys sometimes
you forget what those keys actually are
so instead of f 1 we had bound that to F
4 maybe I should go ahead and take that
out and put that on the default so
there's us sort of running the thing
that I was saying before but that still
has bugs you can see that the leg
interpolation is actually working quite
nicely down on the bottom there it's
kind of flicker free and tracks me
relatively well it's still it's not
great right but remember this is running
on software sauron if we ran it in GPU
we'd get even better results and it
could update much more quickly so you
know I think this is totally plausible
totally plausible and and I'm not too
worried about it right I'm not too
worried about where that's going what I
am worried about is the thing that I was
saying before which is that you'll
notice that for whatever reason you know
when I'm moving the main light around
you can kind of see that everything sort
of seems like it's working properly like
you know it's like yeah this seems like
pretty sane lighting if we assume that
these guys are lighting that up or
whatever right but you know before our
snake got stuck in the corner backed
himself into the corner what hopefully
you can see here is that you know with
the faster-moving guy yeah the trails
behind looks much but look at what
happens right here when the snake moves
into the upper corner it stops it's
light stops working it just stopped
right and we have no explanation for
that so I'm assuming that the problem
that we're seeing there has to do with
how we are assigning
these light outputs like something to do
with what happens when the the draw
order changes for those lights you get
some kind of really erroneous results
again we haven't implemented the whole
lighting assignment scheme so it could
even just be the thing I was talking
about before where we you know that
thing doesn't have a proper alligator in
there I'm not 100% certain
so the important thing to remember there
is just that yeah that that could easily
be that or could be something else but
that was the bug that we wanted to track
down
now since the updating lighting stuff
already bit me once they're not turning
on I'm gonna just turn it on at startup
by default because it already runs fast
enough even without being optimized on
the GPU at the moment for us to go ahead
and and keep it running all the time so
we don't really have to worry about
turning that off at the moment so what
I'm going to do there is take this
updating lighting boolean here and when
we create the the game world for the
first time I'm just gonna set that equal
to true for now so that way we will have
a yeah one of these that's on by default
so you can see here where we do our set
game mode and we push the struck for
world mode on here I'm just gonna go
ahead and say that updating lighting is
equal to true here and then we can
always delete that line if we go back to
doing something slow with the lighting
that we're worried about running right
but now when we boot up we've at least
got the lighting running and so now we
just have to figure out why when our
when our little saucy snake gentleman
here hops up onto this you know whatever
you want to call this the top half of
the arena why the lights no longer take
effect the way that they are when it's
on the lower part and again the fact
that it's leaving a long trail is not
concerning that's just the slow blend
over a hundred frames we can trivially
make that not happen by switching the
blend coefficient here to something
higher so if we if we only blend it over
ten frames for example we would get much
more flickering lighting you can kind of
see that the lighting is sort of a
little flickering now but now you can
see that the light cleans up much more
quickly as the snake moves along so
that's like you know quite a bit more
reasonable right and it has much more
quick response to you know as I'm moving
this light around as well so the
seems pretty good and I'm you know again
relatively happy with that but again the
problem here is just that we don't know
why when it comes up on here it's not
working properly so there's two things
that could be happening there
one is that something's happening with
the assignment of the receivers in the
top half and the other is that
something's happening with assignments
of the transmitters in the upper half
and we don't actually know which one of
those is happening so what I'd like to
do is try to figure out which one is
happening I'm gonna start by assuming
that it's assignment of the emitter
right that it's these that are getting
assigned erroneously and the reason that
I want to start with that assumption is
because it seems like my my main cube
light here that I move around is not
having the problem so if it was a
circumstance where it was the receivers
that were getting assigned improperly
then I would have expected it to be the
case that the lighting would not work in
the upper half for my cube light either
however since I'm seeing it work for my
cube light I'm assuming that that's got
to be something specific to these
emitters that's causing the problem
ergo my assumption is that when this
remember these when we simulate the
world we simulate a subset of the world
that's the world we can see at the
current time and the way that that works
is we take entities that are packed into
world storage we unpack them into a
simulation region do our simulation and
then pack them back what that means is
that the order in which they were are
rendered is based on where they are
spatially in the world because we pull
out all of the world storage chunks that
we can see in a in a region do our
computations and then put them back so
it's entirely plausible that for this
person to hop up into this region of the
screen I should say this region of the
world that would change their assignment
in such a way that they got different
draw order and hence some kind of
for an thing happening with their
lighting indices and not sure what
now since lighting indices are stored
with the entity I'm not 100% sure why we
would ever see this bud because in
theory all of the entities have been
seen at this point they should all have
light indices assigned to them and so
they should be always outputting the
same light indices no matter where they
hop in the world however again we're
dealing with something that's buggy so
obviously my assumptions about what's
happening there's something wrong
somewhere so I'm choosing to assume that
that something wrong happens to be in
there somewhere in that set of
assumptions it might be somewhere else
let's find out so the first thing I'm
going to do is I want to go ahead and
take the the lighting index of that
piece there I want to see what those
learning indices are and I think the
easiest way to do that is just to take a
look at that push light call again
because the only entities that are
actually having their lights pushed on
there is one of these are these people
right here now why that did not stop by
DOE because we're not in debug mode
sorry that function probably got
optimized out because it's just a little
tiny so here's that push light call and
what you can see from the push light
call is that if we go up the stack the
place where that's getting called is
specifically when there's one of those
lights that's happening here and you
know what I can do - let's actually take
one more step before we do byte just to
make things a little bit easier on
ourselves let's go ahead and take out as
many parts of the equation as we can so
that we're going to be able to most
easily zero in on the particular cause
of the problem so what I'm going to do
is I'm going to comment out this push
light call so that I no longer control
light right so for starters I got rid of
that we now only have the little snake
gentleman hopping around as you can see
and the other thing that I'm going to do
is I'm going to go
take out the push light calls that are
happening on behalf of the other parts
of snake so actually when you add the
snake in instead of it always getting an
ad piece light like it does here what
I'm gonna do is say if the segment index
is zero then sure otherwise no and I
don't know if I have to make that one or
not I'm not sure if the snake segment
happens if it's if it's a snake segment
zero or not let's let's find out so
there we go
now you can kind of see that the segment
index it's only the head that is
currently a light source now and you can
see that the bug persists so we have
only one light now and that should give
me what I need to make this work so if
we go into the running code here and now
I that push light breakpoint right we
can see that we're in a state where we
do have the light working properly so I
can come in here and I can look and see
oops let me use this step into I try
this before it's gonna work this time
right right there it is oh it's just
show ah that's interesting instead of
showing up over here it's showing up
over here don't know why because there's
the arrow so it should show up over here
but you know visual studio has its own
special way of enriching our lives every
day and that's just one of them so let's
go into the push cube call and let's
take a look at what we're actually
storing in terms of the volume indices
here we go you can see that we do have
one here we should have one in here
already we do we pull it out and so
we're storing two light index 1033 a
fantastic number if ever there was one
there it is right there in fact so we're
storing two 1033 and then that means
we're gonna start a 1033 1037 1041 1045
1049 right 1053 so those are now all
stored in there that's all great and so
what I want to do now is verify that we
keep using that same light index every
time we come through here that's what I
would like to do so there's that 1033
I can set the breakpoint out here and
inspect that value totally easily right
1033 1033 1033 1033 right always good so
let's go ahead and disable this
breakpoint and let's go ahead and wait
till the the dude is up in a place where
he's not lighting anything right which
is right now so now I've set it and you
can see he's hopped up in here where
he's not he's not actually emitting
light to these surfaces so what I want
to see now is is anything weird
happening so you could see 1033 that's
still the same light that's been
assigned here right and when I come
through yeah
presumably all of this stuff is
functioning as normal I assume white
count is four let me say 33 and we're
assigning these to the exact same lights
1037 1041 1045 1049 1053 so I'm not
really sure why we're not lighting those
but let's let's just push through and
see what the lighting code actually does
I mean another possibility somehow the
light propagation is not propagating two
lights that are far away and integers I
don't know I uh no idea why that's
happening so this ought to be
entertaining so if we come down here do
it extract reflectors from quads if I
and you know what the other interesting
thing is too you can kind of see here it
looks like this could just be the blend
happening but what you can kind of see
there too is I think the light is still
able to light this stuff so this light
is emitting light into the world it's
just not emitting light into the upper
half of the world so it must have
something to do with why an emitter at
10:33 cannot spread light two emitters
in certain
index ranges or something but I'm not
sure I know how that's really possible
so we're gonna have to dig a little
deeper to really even get a clue as to
what this bug is I honestly can't think
of what it could be I'm a bit stumpy
I'm stumpy right now so taking a look at
what we're extracting here so the stuff
for extracting is exactly what we would
think for you know light we have a light
index in and I count to four right and
we're putting these guys out in there
we're filling in the emit and direction
information here I'm assuming we've got
a lighting solution right so it should
be the solution again visual studio
enriching our lives
should have lasted adds up to one does
again the point count is 177 so 1033 is
kind of Falls sort of in the middle
there we don't have a lot of ideas about
what precisely well you know what now
that I think about it another thing we
probably should do soon is color the
world based on light index because we
did do something like that before we
know there's a hundred and seventeen
hundred and seventy seven different
lighting points in the world and so one
thing that we should do is go ahead and
see if we can't color the world from
from one to one 777 in terms of shades
and that way we can kind of see where
the indices are assigned and see if
there is some coherent thing that's
getting that's happening to the light
indices in that top area because that
might give us again a clue as to why
they're having a problem so in here we
sort of look through and we we try to
figure out what our point count is going
to be presumably as we come through
these light indices here
we will have some idea of what the
maximum value is once we're done running
it we find we have 444 services I don't
know
how many vertices we have processed
because I can't verify that number here
but what I could do is say here is the
base pointer here's the current pointer
so if we've retired nineteen hundred and
sixty-four vertices right so the quad
count should be roughly a quarter of
that
so 1964 divided by four is exactly what
you would expect so if each quad had
four light samples
I'm sorry sixteen light light samples
mmm if each quad had four light samples
on it we would have expected 1964 points
but we're not seeing that now that's
possibly okay because again a bunch of
in fact it's definitely okay because a
bunch of our quads are sprites and those
sprites don't have lighting so that's
totally okay that those would be skipped
there I'm just trying to think if
somehow those getting skipped might
somehow miss a sign
you know I'm just trying to figure out
if somehow those getting skipped can
miss assign the indices so that maybe
they're looking at parts of the lighting
array that are not getting filled and I
don't really know how exactly that would
happen because you can see here we grab
our lighting index off of zero slight
index that's the same thing
that the code in the shader should be
grabbing from and so I'm not sure why we
would be getting something weird
happening there now I gotta go look to
make sure that's true maybe the vertex
shader is actually assigning things
incorrectly there in which case that
would be you know fairly important part
of why things were working wrong but I'm
assuming that that's working correctly
so when we come through here we're
looking at solution points that are
based off that light index that lighting
X is pulled directly out of the vertex
record and the surface light index
itself is also driven off of that so
that again should correctly say that
this particular surface corresponds with
this particular range of light indices
which are you know matched to the vertex
so it's it's what that quad will pull
from when it is done now after we do
compute light propagation which I'll
check later when we do that compute
light propagation and we output the
points you can see that we go through
the points here and we pull out these
values oh wait this is our debug output
letting points know we want to link
textures so outputting textures we go
through here and we use the point
indices and we put back the the arrays
that we're sending down based on just
the point indices so what that means is
the point indices have to line up with
the light indices so let's see if that's
true right so is solution points point
index is that going to line up properly
right with the light indices what that
means is that the light index as we come
through this loop up here should be used
to access the pointer
and what you can see here is it does
appear to be the case so there's
lighting point right you can see it
doing its thing here and similarly emit
0 and average direction of light also
driven off the light index so it does
look like everything is driven off the
light index there properly as it should
be so the other question is well you
know when we're outputting them are we
actually correctly outputting all of
them so what you can see here is when we
do point index loops we're going to
solution point count which again is 1777
which is I think probably the correct
number to be doing here since again
we're skipping sprites which have
bitmaps on them at the moment
just the bitmap sprites we're only doing
the cubes so yeah
[Music]
again not not having the stroke of
inspiration here in terms of telling me
maybe some to Jionni I'm too tired
so I'm gonna go ahead and say that I
think my next step is just to gain some
insight into how those lighting indices
are assigned so I can see if something
weird is going on so let's just take a
brief moment because I do want to keep
pushing the debugging more but I feel
like I'm a little bit too aimless in my
debugging right now I don't know where
to focus my efforts and so what I'm
gonna try and do is find a clue to how
to focus those efforts by changing the
way the OpenGL shader is shading so that
it shows me what the light indices
actually are that's what I would like to
do so here's the Z bias program you can
see in here the way that we're doing the
lighting we grab the light index out
here and we loop through the light count
like this fetching the light values and
doing the ops on those light values
right here right so if I wanted to do
things differently than this what I
could do instead is rather than textile
fetching this information off of light I
the way that we're doing it here I can
come down here and say well instead of
that value let's instead make lb equal
to something based off of the fried
light index and the way that we would do
that is say okay let's perhaps say that
the red value is going to be maybe the
the low part of the frag well you know I
could start by just doing grayscale
since I know that this is how many I've
got what I could do is say maybe maybe
something like this
so I know that now my grayscale value
that I get here will actually just tell
me what it is that I want to know and
similarly I can do something more like
this in fact I can leave these even on
right and what I do is I just I just
clobber the value that I was gonna use
before with an actual direct lighting
value that just tells me exactly what
the lighting index is assigned right so
what you can see out of this is you know
lo and behold my suspicion is at least
somewhat correct the the values of the
lights that are being assigned here are
definitely coherent with this spatial
location in the world right so low
lighting indices are down on the bottom
highlighting high light indices are up
at the top and so what we're basically
seeing is that the higher the light
index gets the the closer we get to
failing to compute the light correctly
so it looks like about the halfway point
you know give or take somewhere around
there we stopped producing lighting for
the snake now remember we still produce
lighting for the moving Cube and that's
the really weird part about it right
it's not like the lighting doesn't work
at all yeah it's just that the moving
cube light doesn't work in this
particular case there so that's
particularly strange I'm gonna watch one
other thing here so what you can see is
there's the light index of this guy and
it never changes that's just I'm just
trying to verify there that it's always
the same and it is or at least it
appears to be that was what I was trying
to verify before numerically we always
saw it being 1033 so that's good like we
kind of get the idea there so I'm gonna
do one other check here what I'm gonna
do is it want to see a breaking point so
I can get a little bit of a better idea
of what's going on there rather than
assigning it based on grace fate scale
I'm going
say okay services liked RGB is going to
equal something like green unless of
course the frag light like index is
greater than 1033 which is our lights
value and then I'm going to change it to
red so red values will be ones that are
above 1033 green values are ones that
are below 1033 so the reason I did this
and you'll see a very suspicious pattern
emerging here all of the places where we
are not getting light contribution from
our 1033 light source happen to all be
above 1033 now why did I think to do
this well a because it's just a
convenient number that is sort of in the
middle ish of the range so I kind of got
a little bit of sinking suspicion about
that and the second reason I did it was
because the difference in my mind that I
was when I was thinking about what the
difference is between the light that
worked and the light that doesn't work
is the light that doesn't work happen to
got pushed on last remember it's a push
like that deed that cube that that I was
moving around is a light is a as a light
cube that gets pushed on by the world
code at the end of the render which
means it would have had a very high if
not the highest light index value and
that one was working so in my mind I'm
thinking maybe I have a bug where light
only gets distributed to things that are
lower than the value of the light source
and not higher than it low and behold
that looks like exactly what's happening
so that tells me that my light
propagation loop probably has a bug in
it somewhere
where I'm not looping over lights I'm
not able to transmit two lights that are
say higher than the emitter index so you
can see right here the way this loop
works for example let's just start with
this one and see I'm not sure it's in
this loop I'm just starting here
randomly but you can see here I've got
my emitter index and I'm looping between
the from from one to the point count and
then I'm going through here and I'm
doing my emission
from these points right as we go so when
I'm going through here at the emitter
index to start with would have been 1033
that's what we're looking at in terms of
where we're starting and presumably we
come down to this code and presumably
this this actually does execute why do I
think it executes well I think it
executes because this light is
propagating to other surfaces just not
ones that are higher than 1033 so when I
look down in here I see okay then I'm
gonna start doing ray casting I'm gonna
sample the hemisphere here I'm gonna do
my ray casts and then I'm gonna look to
see whether the hit index that comes
back is less than the surface count that
I've got for the solution now the
surface count let's make sure that ray
cast actually returns surfaces and not
points but it must because again it's
only looping over surfaces so that is
what it what it sends back here that's
what we would expect so result in X
equal source index that source index is
gonna be within the surfaces so if it
hits something that's what it's going to
get that seems fine when I come through
here I then say all right let's pull out
that hit surface using the hit index
here it is then we'll say okay let's go
from zero to however many the hit
surface had and we'll go say the point
index we're gonna distribute to is going
to be equal to the hit surface like this
plus the service point index right
that's what we would expect cuz in here
we're storing an index and array where
this guy starts we're coming through the
hit points on this guy by saying okay
for each of those point indexes let's
loop over them right and look at the
distance between them so the distance
between where we hit and where the point
on the surface that we're looking at and
where we hit we're gonna find whichever
the closest one was so if the closest
distance squared here it's greater than
distance car we're gonna use it right
and then what we're gonna do is we're
going to accumulate the sample if we
found one of these closest point indices
right I don't see anything immediately
in there that is biasing us towards not
counting stuff higher than our emitter
so I don't immediately see what's going
on but what I can do is I can step into
this code and watch what it does on
number 1033 and then I guess I will see
why we are not distributing to any
surfaces above there and one of the
things that you know I would mention
sort of in passing is when one of the
biggest source of problems in graphics
programming programming and general
McGrath specifically is that you tend to
have a lot of these sort of disparate
arrays that all pull together to create
some solution to something right whether
it's vertices on a mesh or lighting
sample points or anything else you tend
to have a lot of indices and they all
have to line up at the end and it's
really easy to get into a situation
where something isn't lining up right or
something's doing something wrong with
these indices and so we're probably
looking at a situation like that and
they do take a while to debug the reason
they take a while to the bug is because
debuggers are garbage so they don't
allow you to do things like trace back
points easily through all the things
that affected them and go oh okay I see
how this data flowed through here and
why we got the wrong result here so you
end up having to do a lot of staged
debugging like I'm doing now in the
future in fact I made a tool for
debugging this stuff at rad one time
called mustache that used to make
debugging problems like this basically
like shooting fish in a barrel
unfortunately and it was for doing video
debugging unfortunately we don't have
those tools in the general case yet
because people don't innovate on
debugging anymore but someday when they
start to again trust me these tools are
not hard to build people just don't
build them anyway moving on so in here
we've got this that situation occurring
something's wrong with our with our
indices there so let's go ahead and step
into it now it's gonna be hard to step
into this at the right time so rather
than try to do that what I'm gonna do
instead is add some code that will allow
me to trigger specifically when I think
the bug is happening starting from most
specific case and working our way
backwards for more general cases as I
see them so the most specific case would
be if at some point we actually were
about to do the operation I'm saying I
don't think happens so if the emission
index is equal to 1033 right so I'm in
meeting from 1033 that emitter and what
I can really do is say well if it's
greater than 1033 or or start and it's
less than or equal to you know what are
we saying that there's basically on that
you know on that cube of emission if
it's 1033 then we've got six sides of
the cube each which have force there's
24 on there so we're actually gonna go
up to ten fifty-seven which I think we
inspected before as well so let's say
we're looking at the emission being in
that range right so if the emission is
in that range then we know we are trying
to transmit from the thing that we're
saying isn't transmitting properly then
let's see if the point index that we're
testing at this point happens to pun
intended happens to be above the 10:57
range right so if it's a point if it's a
point that we think we shouldn't be
seeing any transmission from because we
know there's a bug there that's not
getting transferred if it's a point that
we think is buggy and we are trying to
emit from this the emitter which really
probably yeah it doesn't matter let's go
find out why this is this isn't
triggering so either we hit here and we
trace out to see what's going on or we
don't even hit here which means
move this up one stage of the loop right
all right so let me go ahead and set
this to OD here and let me come through
and run it and so as this is is running
along I'm gonna go switch to find that
location and just go ahead and take a
break point there so what we can see
here is unless I've really mistaken the
situation I did have now correctly
captured apart point where we're trying
to do an emission from one of the points
on the snake emitter right and we're
trying to emit to something that is not
get gathering any emission from that
from the snake right so we've hit a
point where we would say that that's
what we wanted to do right closest point
index is above 1033 closest distance
squared is just 1.05 right so off we go
looking at this here finding that
closest point it looks like we found a
new closest point again still above
range but that one was closer so that's
probably the hit and now we have
finished right so we found a point we
want to distribute some emission to we
go through the closest point index we're
gonna call in to accumulate sample with
this closest point index so we go in
there let me do that step into again I'm
you stop coming out the back now I know
to look right so accumulate sample comes
in we compute the angular fall-off which
is not going to nullify it we compute
the power again not going to nullify it
the weight not going to nullify it we
generate our result which is a regional
value we have our destiny at C value
here which we can sort of check to see
what's going on in terms of where that
is in our loop it's a little bit hard to
do at the moment but we can
just snap this pointer value here there
we go just we can remember which one it
is and we can even go through here and
this is a v3 pointer array so we can
take a look at what it's actually set to
so what we can do is watch that
accumulation happen so there we've
accumulated some lighting in there and
we've returned our result out that's
going to subtract away the lighting
right there Maria's gonna keep doing it
so what we should see there is yeah
every all of that light just gets it is
getting distributed in there properly
let's see what happens at the end of the
loop so if I jump out to the end of the
loop so what you can see here is by the
time we get to the end of the loop all
of its light has been dissipated so
something is happening where all of the
light that should have was a and we saw
getting accumulated right is getting
wiped out and the only real way it can
get wiped out there is in this line here
where the retained light where where it
essentially gets okay so there's our
answer that's just dumb
so what you can see here is us being
fairly stupid this needs to be a plus
equals not in equals we're taking an
amount of source light and we're saying
any amount of source light that did not
get transmitted needs to get added back
in however instead of adding it back
into the light that's already been
accumulated for this point we're just
coal dropping it right over the top
right that is almost certainly the
entirety of the bug so it wasn't really
even indexed I mean it happens to be
indexed base because of the that meant
that you could only transmit light sort
of earlier to people who were earlier
than you who hadn't wrapped already
pretty simple fix as it turns out so
let's take a look at how that goes now I
guess I'm also gonna have to change the
shader in here to no longer be
outputting in debug mode so let's go
ahead and do this stuff here yeah okay
so now our lighting transmission should
should work when it gets up there and lo
and behold it does alright so now I can
go in here and in theory return things
to semi normal and we should see
everything kind of playing nicely
together I can go back into the world
mode and add another at our lights back
in I can go into the debug light and
turn that back on and now in theory all
of these should be working correctly
right
so that looks pretty clean and now I'm
not seeing anymore of those artifacts
our light transmission should also be
better and more stable now because now
we're not having this forward only
transmission so each iteration of our
lighting is doing better work now than
it was before and so we're also probably
getting a better light solution even for
the things that we're already working
because that was just reducing the
effectiveness of our light propagation
so that's looking pretty nice I'm pretty
happy with that
I will say there's still a little
weirdness I think maybe I'm not 100%
sure it's a little hard to say but I'm
not 100% positive oh no I think that's
right never mind I was gonna say I'm not
positive these should be lit but they
they definitely are in fact it's it's
doing the leg just right it can't light
that surface but it can light this one
and it is
so that seems pretty good I'm relatively
happy with that and the other thing that
I would point out here that at least
that I'm hoping will happen and I don't
really know if it will or not but it's
the way that I'm sort of approaching
this is for example you know the
difference in lighting on these on these
squares is desirable because one of the
things that I wanted to have happen in
the game is you know I want to have it
emphasized the fact that the game is
square based because you hop from square
to square but other times we may not
want to emphasize that so for example
when you have two surfaces that are
right up next to each other in a flat
wall like this here we may not want to
have that lighting discontinuity now in
order to sample the light enough times
to make sure there's no discontinuity
there we'd have to do way too much work
and that's just not going to happen
so what we can do though is the reason
that I architected the system the way
that I did now when I sort of said oh
let's make it so we passed down those
lighting indices is when we do our world
Jen it would be free for us as long as
we put the logic in that generator
properly to say that when we have a
situation like this share the lighting
samples across the seam right because
what we can do is place lighting samples
across the surface and the lighting
samples can be placed right on the seam
and both of these two faces can share
them that way when we interpolate the
lighting across the seam should
relatively disappear right now we may
have to do some special work with our
interpreters to make that really be
seamless because interpolating scattered
point sources is kind of difficult so
you know it's easier said than done but
in terms of computing the information we
need I think we can't do it and that'll
give us smoother washes there right so
we have some work to do with the
interpolation and we definitely will
have some work to do at World Gym time
but now I think we're in pretty good
shape
as far as as that's concerned because
I'm getting the kind of results that I
want from the lighting system and
everything is fine right now it's worth
noting that we still have a lot of
problems to deal with if I was to make
the world slightly bigger it's going to
get too slow so like I said we kind of
need to start taking more steps now to
sort of make this into a solution
that's scalable to to things that are as
large as we might be using so if I kind
of go into world mode now what I'd like
to do is take a look at what happens
when we start to build out things to as
big as we're going to kind of let them
fail and be too slow and then we'll sort
of try to start to push forwards from
there okay
so let's take a look at what's gonna
happen there when I do add standard room
what we can see here is we're only
adding like one of them let's say we
added two of them you can see how much
more our solution slows down right
because it doesn't have any scalability
built into it now I'm pretty sure that
it's not the the actual rendering that's
taking the time
however we probably want to verify that
that's the case so what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna go well actually I don't even
have to do that let me just go ahead and
turn it off temporarily so here I have
turned off updating of the lighting
solution and what you can see from the
results is that it's really just that
lighting update which is what we would
expect but we want to make sure that's
true
and so what you can see is it's just the
lighting update that takes the time so
once you have the lighting solution
submitted the per pixel interpolators
are not causing a problem right I'm I'm
spinning this around here just fine
and you know the framerate is is not a
problem at the moment but once I tell it
to start recalculating the lighting
solution you can see we go up to a
really expensive amount of time and then
when I turn it back off we're right back
down to a reasonable frame rate now we
we're not complete great because we
still have the weird like too many we do
too much work still in our renderer
because we do the multi pass nonsense
and and stuff like that so you know
there's stuff that we still want to do
to optimize a renderer probably quite a
bit of stuff we want to do but you
no this is still totally usable at this
stage of development no question right
um and so what we see here is just that
it's that lighting update that's taking
the time so what we're gonna have to do
in order to start scaling out some more
rooms because obviously like you know we
get up to two something like four it
will be completely unusable in terms of
real time wedding right so you can kind
of see here here is a thing that's got
rooms stacked on top of each other I
thought I said four oh right we only can
see three of them we fade out when we
get to the bottom is that correct
am I right about that we need to add a
weighted to debug move down you know
currently have a way to do that and why
is the world small let's fix that
all right so now I should also be able
to kind of go down the stairs I think
although did we make the rooms I think
we made the rooms too high as well so
you can't actually get down them anymore
because you the the steps were like too
far apart or something of this nature
right but here we can see the lighting
operating on sort of a more
three-dimensional level and you again
can see that it really is starting to
work the way that I wanted it to work
where you know if we do do an update on
it it does produce pretty much exactly
what I would have wanted now of course
the problem is the update only kind of
blends in over time so you have to do
several updates to get a real solution
you can kind of see how slow it is
updating the lighting right but if we
were to speed that up which I think we
can really easily do well easily
I think there's direct ways of us
getting to that point I think we'll be
in good shape and so you know again
looking at this I think we're I think
we're almost there this is again sort of
more representative of what you'll be
looking at on the screen when you'd
actually be playing modular the fact
that the you know the artwork is not
really what we would be normally doing
but if you take a look at with what
you're seeing on the screen right now
that's sort of more representative to
the level of complexity on the screen
that you would be looking at and what
you can see here again is that you know
we're still at 30 frames a second even
without the optimized without any
optimizations really in the renderer so
we're pretty good like I really just
don't think we have too much to worry
about so this scheme I think will be
fine
and it again captures a lot of the stuff
that I wanted to capture you know you
can get lighting that kind of plays off
various places here and you get you know
all sorts of nice sort of effects
happening there if I go ahead and sort
of stop it at the beginning where you
can kind of see that people are in this
you know the places where they're light
sources actually are let me go ahead and
turn the lighting off or try to
why am I not able to turn the lighting
up there we go well that was really
weird what's going on I got some weird
hotkeys stuff set up here
oh I'm pushing f5 instead of f4 so all I
was doing was reducing the number of
bounces ah that's awesome alright so
anyway back to what I was saying so you
can kind of see that if you know if you
just take a look at the initial solution
it's doing roughly what I want you're
getting bounce light off of this from
here and you're doing all this stuff
that you know exactly what I want to
have happen you look down here you can
kind of see illumination happening in
kind of a cave-like environment where
there's no you know up here we've got
the the main light debug like going
there down here you can see we've got
kind of the sort of this sort of
localized effect happening here so I
think that that is is all good like I
think we're in good shape here
yeah and off we go if I was to generate
a lot more of these and allowed them to
generate any way they wanted to so you
know in here where we do our random
choice stuff maybe re-enable the thing
that lets us go any way that we want not
sure we haven't worked on that generator
code in a while but here's a lighting
solution for example that is operating
well
doesn't seem like it actually picked any
we gotta move on to world generations
sometime soon just so we have this this
routine so so broken
okay so here's this this guy right here
is the problem yes you can see here what
I kind of expected to happen before but
that didn't actually happen you can see
that we've got too many points like too
many lighting points so what I'm gonna
do is I'm just gonna up you know that
lighting count and again my goal here is
just to stress out the system so that we
have a good example of you know what
it's gonna look like so I'll just go
ahead and and 2x how much we've got here
again these are 1d textures so it's
really just not a problem in terms of
the storage or transmission of these per
frame the problem is just in the
lighting computation right so if we take
a look at what the lighting computed
here again it does pretty much exactly
what we want like all the lighting is
localized to where those lights were
actually yeah and you know this game
takes place at night and so I think this
is kind of right roughly what we want so
yeah let me see how much time we have
here so we've got about a half hour left
I think if I'm not mistaken so looking
at this we've got we can now sort of
build a list of the things that we're
gonna have to do to make make the final
lighting stuff and again like I said I'm
really pleased with the speed of
everything here it's just this is
running on a really good graphics card
so that fact that as you get in here you
I guess a couple things that aren't
obvious potentially that I'm just
knowing in my head that that we I'm not
singing loud
so I want you to take a look at the
frame rate up here and what you can see
is we're actually getting 60 frames a
second right now but if i zoom in we are
not getting 60 frames a second right and
so you may wonder what is going on there
right because nothing has changed about
the world when i zoom that like
nothing's changing the camera does not
do anything to the world when it's in
debug mode right when the camera moves
in in this mode things can come in and
out of the active simulation said and
all sorts of things could happen so
obviously moving the camera in this mode
we would expect to see frame rate
fluctuations potentially if we've got
something that's not working
particularly well or that's unoptimized
or whatever but looking at the game here
this camera is not affecting anything
the game is running exactly the same way
so why is it slowing down when i zoom in
and the answer is although I guess I
can't prove this immediately because we
didn't look into it but I'm assuming the
answer is this happens when the fill
rate right the the per pixel cost of the
GPU is something that is slowing down
the frame rate as i zoom in more pixels
on the screen are filled right when I'm
out here the whole world occupies very
few pixels right and the smaller the
less number of pixels it fills right
the less I am seeing the framerate hit
right if that makes sense
as i zoom in I get slower and slower
that's what I was seeing for
although I'll be honest that's not
happening now I'm not entirely sure why
it was happening for
let's take a look here maybe I'm wrong
so I'm assuming that peak message being
the thing that is taking all the time
would have to be because that's where
we're actually getting the OpenGL render
time where we're actually seeing that I
could be wrong about that let me run
this again and see so here we are
muster to debug camera can see we're
running at 20 frames a second here 16
frames a second here so that's
interesting peak message actually starts
taking more time later we must have a
bug in our windows message loop
I mean look at it eating up this time
and look at where it is now
hmm okay really really don't want to
know when I'm gonna find when I dig in
here I'm hoping that it's just hey
that's where the times getting
attributed to wall stuff is happening on
the other threads because of rendering
or something if this turns out to be
another one of those windows 10 Dinges
maneuvers I am just gonna be a sad sad
panda so if you remember we had this
problem where we were getting Windows 10
sending us a bunch of junk messages
right and we were doing stuff where we
would say okay if the thing we needed to
do was if we needed to skip a message
right then we would so I would like to
know which messages were getting here
where cuz you can see this is the block
the peek message block here this is
where we're hanging up behind sucking
down all this extra time and I have no
idea why now let me just double check
something real quick
as you can see we're holding pretty
stable in terms of memory usage let's
just double check that assumption
we're still
where's the resource monitor thinking me
here it is they always move these things
around I never know where everything
goes
so you can see here that we're pretty
stable we're not doing anything weird
right we're hardly taking any memory
really in terms of what we're touching
we do still do that weird thing where we
reserved a bunch of memory we don't use
which we should probably stop doing
because we don't really need to do it
anymore but you can see the stuff that's
in the working set is mostly not
changing
so yeah
[Music]
you know it could just be me but it sort
of seems like the more I do stuff in the
window the more peak message starts to
show up I'm not sure I managed to get it
all the way to the top before
but I would really like to know what was
going on there
see how it's crawling up again
see that
you see in this so with it up at the top
there I'm gonna go ahead and just set a
breakpoint in there and see if I can
figure out what is happening now
unfortunately we're not in debug mode so
I may need to change back to debug mode
at some point and disable the lighting
just so I can be able to like inspect
more stuff in the in the loop here but
we can see
I mean that doesn't really look like
it's hitting very often and you'll
notice now it got sent back down to the
bottom I wonder if there's some thing
getting done with our cue
so there we go I've gotten it back to
the top right holdin steady right there
at 25 percent of the time in the peek
message loop let's just alt tab alt tab
and it's gone
so all tabbing away must make windows
stop doing whatever spam it was spamming
us with right and then it wasn't as I
spamming us it could just be that it was
well in fact we know it's not spamming
us cuz they can look at what this must
mean so let's just go ahead and and look
at what we're talking about here so
here's where I entered the time block I
go through this loop skip index only
this many times right paint mouse move o
X 7 3 8 and ffffff right now we then
exit the timed block right so it's only
timing this thing in here not the outer
code like we're not counting any of this
operations at all and it's gonna tell us
the count so if we look in here right
if we look in here
when peak message shows up on here which
it doesn't at the moment but we can make
it show up I suppose or try to make it
show up there it is it has a 1 next to
it right so it means it only went
through that loop one time you know I'm
saying so it just went through here once
got the message and left which means it
didn't get a message at all right
yeah I mean it just didn't process any
messages so then if I come through here
on these frames that should be getting a
mouse message right so if I was to do
let's say right when it hits about here
I'll do a mouse message right and then I
pause I should be able to go back here
and see peek message being done with a -
and there you can so that's me clicking
the mouse right I got the message right
this is so cool
so we know that we're not even getting
any messages when this says one that's
just the exit condition so that's just
how long it took witness to tell us that
we don't have any messages the four
times or whatever we call peek message
right so let's go ahead and and just
spam this thing with tons and tons of
mouse movement like we were doing before
and now what we see is that peak message
is taking 30 some-odd percent of the
time right to do nothing so it's not
returning us a message it's saying we
didn't get one
and yet it's taking 34% 36% whatever at
the time to not do something so it must
be doing something during those calls
that you know we that we can't see right
now one thing we could do here is be
more specific about the profiling right
so what we could do here is say all
right let's put the time block in in the
actual loop so we should see it be
called you know four times or whatever
to do the four ranges so zero dope
they're gonna paint having picked a
mouse move Mouse from seven three eight
seven three eight dev ffs right so now
our default value of peek message while
we're running should be for all the time
right and hey it is that's what we would
expect so then I come in here and I and
I you know wangle around a bunch right
wranglin wranglin wang lin
like so and now we can see is yeah we've
we've worked peak message all the way to
four right and it's taking 26% of the
time so we've definitely verified that
we're just calling it four times for
each one of those ranges and calling it
those four times has caused us to have a
20 to 30% ding on our frame rate which
is huge right absolutely huge it's nuts
it's taking as much time as the graphics
is taking right like do all this GP
unoptimized GPU work we're doing it's
all taking the same amount of time is
the peak message basically if we just
wiggle the mouse enough look at that so
something is seriously messed up here
and I don't know what only this sort of
you know rocket science came over at
Microsoft that can't figure out how to
deliver a message and less than what was
that it's multiple milliseconds know
what's going on with that special sauce
I'm imagining that part of the problem
might be because we are trying to avoid
this bad situation from happening where
we're getting spammed with these
messages
maybe that is causing some kind of an
odd problem to occur I'm not sure what
we can do is we can test some theories
here right so if we put the time block
back where we had it before right so
we're timing the peek message on the
interior what I can do is say well
alright if I go ahead and do a
bracket around this and then just you
know say give me all the messages that
that you know you you might be inclined
to give me and maybe call this in in a
way that's more more consistent with
what it normally would do right so I
believe it's just yeah it's just zero
and zero here we'll we'll just do that
and this will allow me to test the sort
of more straightforward path see if
anything weird is happening about the
call pattern that we were using to try
and avoid spurious messages which we
were getting so here's the profile
there's peak message and what you can
see now is just moving the mouse will
cause a to the reason for that is we're
now getting mousemove messages so
mousemove messages we are not skipping
the mousemove message which we didn't
want and so let's see if the same thing
happens again
so it looks to me like you can't skip
those mousemove messages right it looks
to me like you something about calling
it that way is making Windows get very
confused about what it should do we had
changed it to this way based on a
suggestion from a viewer who was saying
maybe we could avoid getting a spurious
masters messages however I'm gonna go
ahead and say that that's maybe not such
a good idea after all based on what I
just saw now let's take a look and see
how accurate that actually is I'm gonna
go ahead in here and say well alright
let's rename all this path maybe let's
take out the WM mouse move or the WM
paint and see if it's one specific one
of these that is causing the problem
right so I've put us back to doing the
range based query and I'm gonna take a
look now to see if I come in here and
take a look at the profile I'm gonna
make sure that I can generate the same
bad case just by rapid mouse movements
and already it's you know doing sort of
worse than it was before with peak
message moving up to 25 percent of the
time we zoom out and get it to take up
even more percent of the time right a
ridiculous number of cycles here being
taken by peak message so let's go ahead
I mean you're gonna get that it's
that's a another swear yeah all
right one more episode of swears in it
got it like bleep you need to let me a
little sensor somebody's just feel to
push to the like of that little button
that's like um I grew up to like six now
or something like that six episodes that
have curses in it something like that
it's not great I mean compared to the
amount that I swear normally it's
fantastic but you know what do you do
anyway so look at that it's it's
ridiculous right it's it's I mean I
don't know how that's even remotely
justifiable amount of time to be spend d
queueing a message and more specifically
not D queueing a message that's how long
it's taking to tell us it doesn't have
anything right
Microsoft window is the only thing that
can take you know 19 million cycles to
say I don't have anything for you so we
need to address that again now that I
know that I can produce that again with
reliably let's comment out the paint
looks like peak message is slowly moving
up exactly as you would expect and the
fact that it seems to be triggered by
moving the mouse does suggest that you
know Mouse move is an obvious sort of
potential culprit let's go ahead and
take it out the mouse move so now we
will be sampling mouse move messages
oops in the actual loop here
and looks to me like that is indeed the
culprit so as I kind of yeah as I kind
of suspected you can't leave those WMS
moves in the queue so paint can be
skipped
Oh x7 3:8 can be skipped
but mousemove can't miss get
so that you know not exactly what I
wanted to do at the end of today's
episode but definitely good that we
found that and I guess what I would say
just to reinforce something that I said
originally back when we built the
profiler what I originally built the
profiler I was actually asked the
question specifically why was building
the profiler and the debug system when I
didn't really have a need from the time
and the answer is you know specifically
this that is an example of a really
really problematic scenario if we had
started to do some profiling on
particular pieces of code or just looked
at a framerate counter and saw that we
were getting these slow frame rates
there we would have jumped to the
conclusion that it was us and we would
have been weirded out by this or maybe
never even known it at all but because I
happen to have that profiler running all
the time it makes it easy for me to see
that it's not our code that's causing
the problem it's we knows that's causing
the problem and we could quickly
identify the fact that that where that
problem was and how to mitigate it so
now our frame rate is not affected by us
we can go back to using those frame rate
measurements more reliably now why this
is happening I have no idea maybe
someone who works for Microsoft can go
heaven help you go into the code for
peak message and find out what kind of
special let's let's just say what what
kind of remarkable procedures are
occurring in there that are causing it
to take five million cycles per call
to tell us that nothing happened and if
we ask for our mouths move messages all
of a sudden that's fine I'm guessing
that something happens like there's a
mouse move q and if you don't drain the
mouse move Q it fills up to a point
where it causes a spillover scenario
that's somehow slow I don't really know
I'm really making stuff up at this point
but it kind of looks like something like
that is happening now I'm concerned I'm
worried about what might be happening
here and so what I would also like to do
is I'd like to try and check to see
whether a similar scenario can happen
with paint so I'm gonna go ahead and try
to trigger lots and lots of paint
messages and see if the same thing
happens
so it doesn't look to me like paint has
the same kind of drawback there
I may just not be able to generate
enough paint messages I'm not sure it's
hard to know how many paint messages are
actually being generated by various
mouse movements you can see that paint
messages are sort of would be generated
here I'm pretty sure and I think they're
generated all through this whole
procedure
I believe anyway but I I mean I couldn't
tell you for sure the other thing is
paint messages may be getting dispatched
directly to the window on drag so it may
be that they are getting handled anyway
I'm not sure let me let me go ahead and
see to what extent that's true yeah so
you can see that those are getting
dispatched directly in this case so if I
go ahead and move up here like this
yeah you can see they get dispatched
directly so the fact that we're not
asking for them is not really changing
the situation pretty much at all and in
fact I'm not sure why yeah again I think
this may have just been a bad suggestion
from the person who suggested that this
was the case because I think they were
just wrong about what happens with like
the paint generation because as you saw
they get dispatch directly to the window
anyway and I'm pretty sure that that
they don't actually get generated in any
other circumstance right so if you look
at what's happening here you know we're
not getting we're not getting any
messages till the circumstances where we
were where we were getting the messages
so I think that might just be bad right
that might have just been not not the
right thing to do so I I guess what I
would say is I still don't know about
this though this 7:38 does seem like a
bad situation
so we may keep skipping that one I'm
going to go ahead and see what happens
if I turn that off
and I don't remember the exact
circumstances under which we were
getting lots of these messages
maybe they fixed that so it's hard to
say
I really can't test that one
all right
let's go ahead to the Q&amp;A says did you
notice that the annotation search
doesn't seem to be working anymore no I
did not know that I generally don't test
it or anything because I don't maintain
it but I agree with you that does not
see any working at all if someone could
remind me well you know what no you
don't have to because I can just do it
right here
I will send a mail
all right
I send me about that yeah I don't know
anything about this system obviously
this is just the hard work of both mid
blow and the folks at handmade Network
in terms of the hosting of it I would
suspect I know that the way that this
works is mid blow wrote a system for
doing annotations and it gets like
munched into the handmade Network
something and probably in that munging
something has gotten lost in translation
it would would be my guess so
such that the search stops working I
don't really know but that'd be my guess
so hopefully it's something simple that
wouldn't that that's not going to cause
them a huge headache I don't know
Khaos come why do you call peak message
once for each element the skip list
instead of retrieving the message once
if any and comparing it against the
message you want skip the reason for
that is because what we were trying to
avoid was Windows generating messages on
demand so the way that Windows works is
that some messages get generated
apparently when you ask for them and if
you don't ask for them they don't get
generated right and so we were trying to
avoid ever asking for the things in the
Skip list we weren't trying to skip them
because we don't actually need to skip
them we're okay if we get it mouths me
message back it's fine we'll just ignore
it
so that was what we're trying to do
there but I think that may have just
been incorrect advice on the part of the
people who suggested it
possibly so you've got that messages
while debugging with the NVIDIA GPU dev
thinking correct
thank you for refreshing my memory yes
that is exactly what was happening I'm
gonna add that in here
so let's see if that is actually what's
going on here
where's my where's my my hood for some
reason my fonts are not here
that's weird I would say that makes a
little harder to test but I guess it's
not impossible still I'll just do so
I'll just go ahead and break on the
situation where
wait a minute
sir no way to actually oh right
mmm it's not gonna like that
so okay what I could do is say I know a
cheap maneuver but the optimizer won't
see it coming maybe maybe it will try
one more time I'm not having any luck
all right fine
so I am getting that message even
without n site running which is kind of
interesting
I wish we knew who sent it to us yes so
this is correctly preventing that from
occurring right so this is not really
true but it does look like it's not
creating enough of a problem I guess
oh I heard you've talked about already
but do you have any comments you would
like to make about melt inspector on the
record I missed the pre stream yeah I
could summarize so I send the pre stream
really easily
basically my pain is that currently if a
machine is running an executable of any
kind really JavaScript x64 native
whatever it's an insecure machine the
only way you can have security is to
actually know that all of those things
were written by you or people you trust
and that they don't that they weren't
trying to compromise your machine so the
current state of affairs is that I don't
know that meltdown or Spectre really
change that at all because they're just
yet another way to do some slight you
know compromising of something but you
already could have done that
compromising you know thousands of other
ways if you are running any kind of code
on a machine so I just see them as as
bugs that need to get fixed in the
hardware because we do want the hardware
to eventually be stable and secure I
don't see them as changing the software
landscape at all because the software is
currently insecure and simply remain so
after meltdown inspector if I thought
there was any way to secure a machine
that was running foreign executables on
it then these would be concerning
because they would be the first ways
that people could have done something to
that machine but that is just simply so
far from the case that I think it's kind
of laughable to think that they change
the landscape at all I mean I just
assumed that like I assume the handmade
hero machine is easily compromisable
because you know it's got steam
installed on it and people can pay
hundred dollars in post next
on Steam and I download it and I run it
and it's my machine right I'm just
assuming that can easily happen right I
assume that if I run a web browser on a
machine it can easily be compromised
right I just assume that
so those assumptions don't change in the
face of meltdown inspector so I don't
that's why I'm not particularly
concerned about them if we got to a
world where that wasn't true then I
think they would be more concerning
Dragoon x6 what is your opinion what in
your opinion is the biggest lie myth
most programmers follow or believe in I
think I would say that generally it's
just that there's such a thing as like
clean or elegant code that isn't about
measuring something in the code right so
that seems to be kind of the root of
most bad things in programming it's it's
people who think there is something
about code that makes it good that is
not something they have measured or
tried to measure and that drives a lot
of the stupidity around programming
practices that are counterproductive
what makes code good is the total time
of maintenance on that code from
creation to shipment to updating right
and if you're not measuring that and
tracking it back to actual persons then
you're just kind of making stuff up
right to make yourself feel good and so
a lot of what I see that's talked about
in terms of when people say things like
best practices or what they look for in
code reviews are things that they
actually have never really done any due
diligence to determine are actually
effective and also furthermore what is
or is not an effective programming
practice is not universal it depends on
the programmers who are deploying it
programmers make different kinds of
mistakes I will make different mistakes
than you will some programmers make more
mistakes than others some teams make
more mistakes than others things that
you're doing encode to help prevent make
mistakes had better be targeted at the
people who are actually maintaining that
code otherwise they are a waste of time
guarding against mistakes your team
won't make is a waste of time right and
so talking about a programming practice
as if it is universally good is often
also misguided because usually things
are only locally good there are probably
some program practice that extend to all
programmers however a lot of programming
practices are only extend to some
programmers a subset of programmers and
not knowing which programmer you are or
your team is is also going to mean you
can't really make any kinds of
statements about what you should or
should not be looking for hey Casey June
about SF ml if so what is your opinion
about it no I do not
nice field Oh what do you mean mean you
mentioned browser security is a concern
these days should the OS be secure
instead of the browser or something like
that so in my opinion I don't think
security would be particularly difficult
to achieve actually in practice or
rather I don't think a fairly high level
of security that's much higher than what
we currently can achieve would be
difficult in practice if you took all of
what we're doing right now and
completely threw it out and just said
this is all wrong and went back to the
drawing board and said the goal of us
creating a computer is to have it run
one thing at a time and that thing can
only you know communicate effectively by
like packets sent back and forth then I
think we could achieve a much more same
level of security right the concept that
when I run a game on my machine then it
can even see or think about the other
things on the machine at all is nuts and
yet that's just the standard behavior
right there isn't a single operating
system that I know of right now that
even considers it the important to make
those kinds of hard deletions right but
they do so yeah of course like the
concept that I have a web browser and
the web browser opens multiple tabs and
those tabs are all running in the same
you know conceptual space to a large
extent is nuts
and yeah browser manufacturers are doing
a better job now if at least spinning
them to separate processes but the point
is why are those things even considered
in the same space why do they even have
access to the same things why are they
even seeing the same hard drive right it
doesn't make sense to me so I think the
way you would achieve real security is
the same way I achieve it some
Magisterium practice I have a machine
for development and a machine for
browsing the web and never the two shall
meet I transfer data between them in the
most secure ways I can possibly think of
but that's just how machines should have
been architected right like they're you
should be able to run a machine such
that it's essentially running only
thing and you know let's say I put two
hard drives in my machine one is for
development I boot on that hard drive I
should be able to switch that machine
over to then running a separate hard
drive for when I'm doing my web browsing
and that should be fairly instantaneous
right like that's how things should be
design physical actual separate security
and that way the only thing you're
trying to secure is just the very small
transfer part between those gaskets
whereas right now it's everything whoo
the same kernels mapped into the address
space of all the processes it's running
them all at the same time I don't even
know what's running on this machine what
is all this crap
none of this should be happening right
this the fact that like wit that
Microsoft even says the word security
when this is what a tab of currently
active things looks like on their
operating system is ludicrous there this
is not secure at all there are so many
backdoors
I don't even need to know anything about
the code in here I guarantee you that
just the fact that the number of things
on this list this is a default install
of Windows 10 that's have almost nothing
installed it's like Visual Studio right
that the list is this long alone tells
me that there are backdoors upon
backdoors upon backdoors in this
operating system just waiting to be
found
and they will never find them all forget
it right so all we're doing right now is
having a big old fun rat race to see
whether the people at windows and other
security research firms who are white
hat can find all the hundreds of
thousands of bugs that are in this list
alone right let alone all the other
stuff that's running when I cope this is
just the services panel right how about
the process panel what's all this stuff
right it's nuts
so just this that the size of this list
should be one thing right and you know
maybe in this case two or three because
I'm running three things that are
actually talking to each other so this
list should have three things on it
right and that's it
and until then talking about security is
a joke and thinking that cash timing
attacks are your primary problem and
that oh my god like we've got these cash
of it come on man like yeah cash timing
attacks are a problem do I want Intel
the to start designing hardware that
doesn't have them yes obviously are they
relevant to how many billions of ways
Microsoft has already dropped in here
for us for our people just slide right
in and compromise your machine no
absolutely not
they're gonna fix these cash timing
attacks and then there's still gonna be
eight hundred thousand different ways to
pone your machine by sending the right
gift to some stupid thing in here that's
in the photo viewing service or
something
right so it's pointless
jageun do you think code reviews and our
writing tests helps with that and that
meaning be the Lima that most
programmers are forced to or aren't
thinking about what's actually effective
um I guess I would say is it's just a
meta statement right
I don't think code reviews or writing
tests help or don't help in an absolute
sense almost everything you might do in
code that is not directly producing code
you use so I'm literally writing a
routine here and optimizing this routine
or something
everything you do putting in Const
putting code reviews in place writing
test code stepping through things in the
debugger that aren't for finding bugs
just to watch them right talking with
people on a whiteboard bla bla bla bla
bla bla bla right all of those things
are not good or bad in the absolute
sense they have effects on your
productivity sometimes positive
sometimes negative and whether or not
they're generally good practices can
depends on the circumstance and the team
some teams would be better off never
doing a single code review other teams
might be better off doing code reviews
fairly frequently
other times I suspect this is often the
case code reviews might be a good idea
when you're bringing new people on but
become not such a good idea later when
everyone kind of knows what's going on
right and again that all depends on it's
a it's a time for a trade-off that
you're making if you spend a thousand
hours doing code reviews to save a
hundred hours of debugging you're making
a huge mistake if you spend a hundred
dollars of code reviews to spend a
thousand hours hours of debugging you're
not right and so you have to tailor
things to what your gains are right
similarly there's risk forward trade-off
some software goes out the door if
there's a bug in it it doesn't matter
it's not that big a deal that bug is
relatively harmless it can be patched
it's just not that critical other
software goes out the doors is a bug in
it it could cause a catastrophic failure
but the classic example
launching a rocket into space if there's
a bug in some piece of software there
could mean the entire you know 100
million dollar rocket gets lost well you
know do I want to spend a lot more time
reviewing the code and testing it in
that scenario absolutely and so again
you always have to go back to think
about what I am trying to do we are
trying to be more productive we're
trying to produce the same quality
software with the same number of
features in the least amount of time are
these things that I'm doing making that
happen are they really making that
happen or am I just doing them because I
watched some stupid video on YouTube
where some engineer didn't know what
they were talking about told me it was a
good idea right or to be slightly more
generous some Engineer who did know what
they were talking about talked about
something that they did on their team
but that just just doesn't apply to your
team or you right and so that's really
the thing that's really crucial to get
into your head is like it is all
relative there is no such thing as a
universally good programming practice
except possibly in the very smallest
cases right
it's like talking about you know all of
you know all of the things that you
might do in a day like which ones of
those are good habits and bad habits
right well who are you you know which
which person are you what's your goals
in life what you know all of these are
how old are you like all of these things
change what is the right advice to give
someone right and the same is true from
programming you just can't boil it down
to this is what everyone should do and
so you have to be willing to be flexible
and you have to be willing to go how do
I analyze my choices all the time to see
whether what we're doing really makes
sense for us or whether we're just
wasting our time right and it's the same
answer for everything when people ask me
about test-driven development or all
their other buzzwords right agile
programming Bob about whatever it is the
answer is always the same
some of
practices are good some of the time
right and and you have to develop the
skills to critically assess whether you
are wasting your time or not and it
usually is pretty obvious if you
actually take a bird's-eye view of it
you know what you're spending your time
doing and you know whether that's it's
finding bugs or producing better code if
you actually measure something you care
about right how long it took you to
write the code how many bugs got found
in that code how easy it was for someone
else to maintain the code all of those
things are actually things you can sort
of get a handle on not that hard if you
look but if what you always assume is
someone told me X or clean code means X
or whatever and so I think that this was
better because we ended up with this
thing that's an abstract concept the
answer is no that's wrong right that did
not tell you anything because you didn't
actually measure or observe anything
that actually matters to the code that
you're shipping right and that's the
crucial part that you have to make sure
you develop all the time right you have
to always be thinking about this am i
doing stuff right now that it's just
wasting my time and the converse is if
I'm identifying things that are taking
too much time or other programming
practice out there that can catch that
can fix that waste of time right and
that's a good example right the simplest
possible thing is with Const right
there's two examples so let's say you
find yourself having a lot of bugs in
your code where you're modifying things
that we're not supposed to be modified
add more Const
that's what cost is for add more Const
right on the other hand if you find that
you're never having Const errors right
in the compiler but you've been adding
cost all the time that's a good thing to
say hey maybe I shouldn't be using
constants so much because it's obviously
not catching any bugs for me right so
you can always figure out ways to look
for are these things that I've been told
are good or that I think might be good
or are they actually saving me anything
and by the converse you can usually say
am i finding myself having problems
that there is a coding practice out
there or something that's been advocated
that might address in that case let me
experiment with it and see if it does
address it right and so you can usually
figure out a way to check both sides of
something right in and you should
whichever one you're doing if you are
doing it practice there usually is a way
to start checking is this practice
actually doing something for me and if
you're not doing it practice there
usually is also a thing to say is there
some canary in the mine shaft that is
telling me hey I'm having this problem
maybe I should start doing this code
practice to help fix it in these
circumstances right
only just clicked you anymore I watched
the first 50 episodes of Hamid here a
quick question about the cursor things
GP OpenGL shader is part of the product
now yes there is a GPU accelerated
renderer the practice that's what we've
been playing with recently when do you
plan on showing adding in the new art
just as soon as I'm comfortable with
where everything is in terms of
rendering a opinion of the dotnet
framework platform it's garbage
one argument I get from people that use
advanced with less features is that the
resulting code is more secure and robust
do you agree with that nope and the
reason is because the advanced C++
features as far as I can tell are rarely
about doing any of such thing right C++
is not a language that's designed for
robustness and I've never seen them at a
high level construct that was effective
at achieving it so I mean I could talk
about a specific advanced feature but
you know I mean the obvious things that
improve code robustness are things like
meta programming and they don't really
support them I mean they don't even this
for an introspection yet right that was
like a brand new thing they're adding
and the in the latest stuff and you know
simple things that create secure and
robust code are things that allow wide
application of solid principles and the
modification of those principles and C++
is doesn't have it oh it really does
have any features for that to be honest
it's it's almost feature void in terms
of that so
all right I'm gonna go ahead and close
this down all right thank you everyone
for joining me for the left side
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you want to
follow along the series at home you can
always peer to the game on handmade hero
org we also have replaced the patreon
page with a contribution page where you
can contribute to things like the
episode guide which funds development on
things like that so if you're interested
in contributing series that's the place
to go for that and of course the episode
guide is is always there we also have a
schedule bot if you would like to go and
find out when the series going to be
live but I tell you right now it's gonna
be live again tomorrow in 21 hours 29
seconds and I'm sorry 21 hours 29
minutes and 5 4 3 2 1 0 seconds so hope
see you back here for that we are going
to take some next steps in our lighting
to try and get us to a place where we're
sort of happy with how that's going
again the goal there now is to just sort
of scale out this solution clean
everything up and wrap it up in a nice
bow so that we can have lighting
wherever we want it in the game and not
worry about it slowing down our
performance so we have some work to do
there but thankfully we've kind of
cracked I think the lighting problem in
terms of what's appropriate for our game
in terms of the architecture so I'm
pretty happy with that and I think we'll
have some success there as we move
forwards that's about it for today hope
to see Becker tomorrow till then have
fun programming everyone and I'll see
you on the Internet take it easy
everybody