hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show where we code a complete
game live on stream we are on Friday we
actually did some stuff to the enemy
system that we didn't really get a
chance to finish we implemented this new
system that I wanted to use or wanted to
try out as far as how we would create
control code for entities that were more
complicated than just a simple single
unit that moves around and so what I
wanted to do was finish that up today or
I shouldn't say finish it up but at
least get it to the point where I could
actually test the thing I wanted to test
because we implemented the basics but we
didn't actually go and finish the actual
system so let's take a look at that
today as I just flashed as de 288 Sol de
287 source code is a source code that
you're going to want to start with if
you're trying to follow along with the
series at home all right so let's load
up
handmade hero here and if I remember
correctly we left it compiling but we
hadn't yet actually ported over the full
feature set
so it's compiling but only nom it's like
just nominally like compiling it's not
actually doing anything so for example I
am unable to control the hero right so
we're still booting and all the entities
show up where they should show up and
that's all fine but the controllers
aren't actually executing yet and if you
remember why that is it's because we
haven't actually gone excuse me let me
load this up here we haven't actually
gone and implemented any of that brain
code we just sort of put it in place and
created the entities with stuff in their
brain type slot and ID but we didn't
actually implement the hash table that
loads them in we just kind of left it
there so right now there's never going
to be an actual brain triggering when it
goes to loop through the array of brains
sounds like something a zombie wrote to
say the least so anyway if I come in
here and look you can see that we
created the notion of a brain hash right
there's a brain hash right here
and we also have this concept of max
brain count and brain there right and so
we have the the trappings of a thing
that stores and executes these brains we
just never actually made any of the
actual brains and so that's what I'm
gonna go ahead and do and sort of make
that start to happen so let's take a
look here in let me see let me take a
look at stem region sorry I just want to
adjust my chair there we go so if I take
a look in tsim region there's the part
where we sort of push on to the entities
and that's here an identity right you
can see that we're gonna need
essentially the same thing for ADD brain
right and what we want to do here is we
want to I guess so I'm curious here it
looks like our rule when we did identity
when we get this entry is we assume that
if someone's calling a brain that that
means they've already tested the hash
table and they didn't find anything in
it now that's a little bit odd to me to
be completely honest I'm not sure
because we're already doing this hash
look up here it seems to me that we
would want to check to make sure we
hadn't already added it or a rather that
we would have done a lookup already but
I guess the nature of it is I guess the
nature is that we don't because we know
that we're loading them so I feel like a
brain is gonna be a little bit different
I feel like a brain might be like yet or
a brain in the sense that I feel like
this is one where you're going to
constantly try to add the brain multiple
times the reason I say that is because
unlike the entities which are packed
uniquely into some place in the world
brains are created spontaneously when
patterns of entities are seen in the
world and that means that when we see an
entity with a particular brain type in
an ID we're gonna be trying to create
that but there may already be that brain
in our simulation and we're just trying
to attach an entity to it right and so
that's the thing that I think
differentiates these two and it's what I
think means that we will want to make it
so that this is a single function that
either creates or returns the same brain
and we don't really need it to even do
the return probably we'll probably won't
use it
I'll do it any
way here but really what we're saying is
just hey we might not always add one we
may just take one that we already had in
return it now I don't actually know much
about the world mode situation here like
for example I don't know why this is
taking a world mode it's really only a
sim region that it needs
maybe there's something specific going
on there but I'm gonna remove that from
here for now because I don't actually
know what it's doing there and I don't
like having parameters lying around but
I don't know if they're actually being
used so I'm gonna keep it out of there
for now we can always add it back in if
we need it so that's fine so what I want
to do here is say okay there's a sim
region and what I want to do is I want
to be able to create a brain and you
know what we are gonna need this because
we're gonna have to insert entities into
it so we are gonna need to return it I
take it back we actually will use that
return I think almost right away now I
just wasn't thinking it through quite
all the way I think that'll actually
happen so if we want to create a brain
really all a brain is is an ID and a
type and then a bunch of slots right and
we haven't quite gotten to the slot part
of things yet but we know that we're
gonna need a brain ID and a brain type
so at a minimum you're gonna have to
pass those two things as you want to
create a brain and then what we're gonna
do here is we're gonna say alright we've
got a result brain and we're going to
return that result brain and assuming
that we can't find that result brain
then what we're gonna have to do is
we're going to have to create a new one
and we're gonna initialize its settings
to the settings that we are given here
like so so the first question is where
is that brain coming from well the way
that we're doing it here is we just push
them onto this sort of stack right and
we're gonna keep that for now that may
change in the future if we want to make
sure that we can go to as many as we
want and grow dynamically we may change
that for right now we certainly don't
need to because we're treating entities
this way we can treat brains this way as
well and so we're just gonna leave it
like that for now so here we'll just
allocate a new brain off the stack and
just so we know later on in the in the
as we're sort of moving through this we
want to make sure that we don't have
oops sorry it's a max brain count there
we want to make sure that we never
overflow that because we want to know
that again we may change it later so
that it can't overflow it'll just grab
more memory or something like this but
for the moment we just want to make sure
we don't hit that case and wonder why
we're having a bug so that assertion is
there to protect us from that during
development so here we are getting a
our brain and setting it and then
returning it so the only thing we need
to do now is use that hash table so we
want to have a brain hash here and we
want to sort of do that same get hashed
by ID where we're gonna ask for a hash
this is asking from a different hash
table certainly than the other one
but I guess in this case yeah we don't
assert I suppose we just say that result
equals whatever the hash pointer was and
so in this case if we find that the
result wasn't equal to anything then at
the end we also want to make sure we set
the hash pointer so the next person
through will find it properly okay
that's pretty much all we need the only
problem now is we don't have a hash
table for these particular guys that's
no real big ID we saw a big idea Wow
talking big problem really all we need
here is another one of these and this
one presumably will work roughly the
same way we could almost use the same
hash table for these things but or a
same hash table code I don't know that
it's worth trying to like make sort of a
template eyes version of this or
anything like that I tend not to super
like things like that especially when
the code is so straightforward and there
isn't very much of it there because you
never know when we're gonna want to
specialize these things or do other
things in that in that case so I feel
like yeah brain hash pretty much the
exact same code here really nothing
particularly unusual I think we really
much do exactly what we're doing and so
I think it's pretty much just that I
don't think there's really much else to
it now
let's see brain hash I think we've made
the name of this thing be ID and we
probably should make the name of the
other one ID as well but we can always
do that a little bit later when we're
cleaning things up so let's see in this
case we got a return a brain hash
obviously not vanity hash that's fine
and yeah we also have to change this to
a brain - go when we do add entity we
remove the world mood parameter for it
just well as some cleanup well of us
moving through there so there we go
we're good to go
what I want to do now is I want to say
all right when we do add entity here
what we want to do is every time we add
an entity we're going to and this is the
only place we do that at the moment
right so this that add enemy call could
actually be sort of streamlined in here
if we want to I don't know what add
entity raw is you know what I have no
idea what that does I don't think it
does anything so that should probably go
away identity is actually code that that
you never call unless you're doing an
unpack and so actually really this could
just be included directly in that unpack
which might be actually a little bit
better
now that I think about it so you know it
might be that this is really the the
right way to do it is to have this all
in line because I feel like this is just
a giant the giant unpack function
probably is gonna want to be something a
little bit more direct like this right
and so I think what I might do is say
okay let's say that this is just dest
right here and then we sort of do a
thing where we check for the overlap and
then when we come in here we do that oh
wait no sorry that's that's not true its
source okay we check that and then when
we when we're done with that we can kind
of come in and say oh okay we've got the
the rest of stuff here we just do our
addition right in line and that that
seems like like a fairly fairly good
idea to me so it's all you know we get
rid of that stuff and make it a little
bit more straightforward there okay let
me just double check that that's all
fine yeah all right so anyway here we
are inside the unpack function which
does all the sort of unpacking of the
world into a simulated state and what I
want to do in here is I want to whenever
whenever we've added an entity right
which is this sort of thing here
whenever we've added an entity and we've
we finished doing that assuming that the
entity is updatable I think we would
want it to have a brain controller now I
guess even if it's not updatable we
might want it so that the brain knows
it's there and just not simulated well
we haven't really done much with the
updatable stuff that's gonna probably
stuff it's got to change a little bit in
the future to be a little different than
it is right now but we'll sort of ignore
that for now anyway point being in here
what I want to do is say well if this
destination
you know we've got the certain notion of
the brain type on the enemy and what I
want to do is say if the entity's brain
type is you know is something that is
nonzero and I don't know I guess it's
nap type I guess it was ID that we said
if the brain ID is nonzero then I want
to create a brain for it so I'm gonna do
an ADD brain here and I guess what we
call what did we call it get our add
brain yeah so I'm gonna pass the sim
region here and then I'm gonna pass my
brain ID and my brain type and I don't
remember which order we passed them in
but I'm sure the compiler will tell me
in a second so that was the order we
passed them in so once I have a brain
and I've got my brain idea in my brain
type now the only thing I really need to
do is I need to figure out how we
actually store these things right now
this is something that I said if you
remember I alluded to I said we're gonna
do some stuff here that's gonna be a
little more complicated than what I do
up front what I'm gonna do first just to
get it working is I'm going to say that
there is sort of just this collection of
brain slots where is the same region
here it is these are these are probably
gonna move out into a different location
in the future as well so I'm not but I'm
at apply be a file looks like brain dot
H or something right but for now I'm
gonna put them in here so we basically
have you know we have the entity and
then we've got the brain as well so
there's the brain and what's gonna
happen here is inside the brain there's
gonna be something that looks like this
which is like you know members or
something or parts to be honest I really
don't know what this is gonna be called
but then there's gonna be some number in
here right that's like the maximum brain
parts and I don't know how many there's
gonna be this is probably not exactly
how it's going to go right it's not
gonna look exactly like that but it's
gonna look something like that
and probably honestly what we'll end up
doing is something like this where we
sort of have like okay there's a union
that's all these entity pointers if you
just want to know what the random
pointer is inside it but then there's
also you know something like this where
you know we have if it's a hero brain
then it's got you know
any star ahead and any star body or
something like this right so you know
that's the sort of thing that will
probably end up seeing I don't know
exactly how we're gonna do it but it'll
be something that looks a little bit
like that and so yeah that will happen
we probably and to be completely honest
we might even do something like this you
know Kuro or bring your parts or
something like that where we do entity
head and entity body we might even do
something like that where we just say
like okay you know if you're a hero we
just do something like this so now we
can ask them in either as named things
if we're doing a particular brain or is
just a generic list of things if we're
not right
and so it'll be something like this that
I don't know exactly what one we're
going to do right so I you know that'll
that'll sort of shake itself out a
little bit further on but anyway point
being here what would do inside the
inside this situation and these are
going to get more complicated later if
you can have more of these right
but what we're gonna do here is say
alright the brain
everybody has their sort of slot you can
remember we said in here we've got the
brain type and we've got the brain slot
right so the brain slot has a value and
that tells us where we go in here now I
can assert that it fits so that we don't
have any kind of weirdness going on so I
figure like okay yeah make sure that
that it fits but assuming it fits the
destination entity goes into that right
so now we actually are building for
realz these controllers and yeah and
that's that's just how that goes Am I is
it index is it actually I think it might
be index see yeah so now we should
actually be building brains but we're
not actually oh well you know what else
we got to do we have to actually
allocate some so the other thing we need
to do is when we create a sim region at
the moment I think we don't have a max
brain count happening here so and
actually you know what what's
interesting is yeah okay so so yeah we
would just want to in cure say how many
brains can you have and I don't know how
many brains you can have right I have no
idea what that number is but and I'm
just making it up
certainly we would want to we want to
actually do some work here to figure
that out in the future once we actually
have like the whole game you know sort
of running will we'd come back and
figure this sort of thing out but for
now we just need some for testing
purposes oops and so now we've got them
now we haven't actually done anything
with these brains yet so in theory
nothing should happen and as you can see
nothing does happen but we are now at
least creating them in theory so for
example the hero should have a brain
created what that means is that if we
pop back to world mode and take a look
at where that sort of brain situation
happened here in brain hero you can see
that we never actually fill these in
right and so what we'd want to do is is
put these grab them out of the the hero
right we want to say okay I be sorry
grab them out of the brain so you'd want
to say the brain Kiro dot head is is
what we're looking for there and here
dot body is what we're looking for for
the body exactly what you would expect
and then when I go ahead and run that
now in theory we should actually have
and you can see we're starting to get
that information right you can see that
we're actually standing on this guy now
so that code is actually running because
I don't think that runs elsewhere could
be right about that though all right so
now we have to actually figure out I
don't know
in fact let me see are we actually
running this code we might actually be
running to it we got to verify that yeah
so we are actually running this code and
you can kind of see that because I can
span the world with these guys right and
then I remember that code that just
looks for the closest unoccupied point
to us and sticks people on it we all
right don't ask me why I did that don't
know also you know he was noticing that
we never deleted identity so I'm gonna
go ahead and delete that goodbye all
right so we've got the brains working
now but we've got to actually make sure
they really actually do what they need
to do and if I remember correctly part
of the problem there was we sort of had
this old janky way from way back when
that we were using to move people which
is instead of actually calling or
putting in a move request into the
entity itself we actually had that move
request sort of cascade through I don't
know if you remember this but basically
what was happening there is inside you
know down at the end can't remember
where we actually were doing this it's
like yeah down at the end you know we'd
have this thing you know if this thing
is movable then we would call move
entity on it with you know with the with
its acceleration value or whatever and
so what I'd rather do here is I'd rather
make it so that that's actually because
now we're gonna be doing packing and
stuff what we want to do is be able to
sort of put accelerations into objects
and have them just do those
accelerations later right so brains can
assign a bunch of accelerations that
it's trying to do to whatever parts it
has and then later when the physics
kicks in which is going to be sort of
this separate wave which it already kind
of is now that'll just happen right and
that's how we want that to work ideally
for a number of reasons anyway not the
least of which being if we don't know
the accelerations of objects when we go
to do collision detection we have a
problem I'll give you a real simple
example right of this is
and I know that I don't know if Sergio
was watching I apologize I'm not updated
Milton yet I know he's freaking out
because he had a bug in the latest
Milton and he doesn't want the
blackboard for him made here to get lost
I appreciate that but I'll be honest no
one's ever gonna use these blackboard
files anyway so after I'm off the stream
I will try to remember to update Milton
but either or not really a big deal
anyway
so what I wanted to say was so DDP right
so what happens in our system right
because we did a little basic physics
thing back in the getting when we're
sort of getting things sort of started
but we never really did our final pass
on it and that's okay because this is
the whole point is we wanted to get to
the point where we have things like
brains doing stuff we wanted we want to
keep incrementally building building the
engine which is exactly what we did and
so then you always are implementing the
thing at the time when you actually have
information so a lot of times that's not
really a good idea to do a really full
version of something until you know
what's actually going on and so the case
that I want to talk about here is you
know if I was to move each entity in
turn like we were doing before then we
have this problem of let's suppose that
both of these entities are moving in
this direction or want to move in this
direction right well because they're
right next to each other if I happen to
try and move this one first right it's
gonna hit this entity and it can't go
the full amount that was gonna go even
though if we just looked and waited and
saw that this entity was going to move
as well if he was the second one to move
we would then know that this guy could
have moved to where who's gonna be right
so you end up with all these fractious
micro bumping things happening if you
don't first assign all of your
accelerations and then simulate the
people together right because I would
know where this guy was in this at this
point in time if I knew what his
acceleration was right so you want to
try and do as much simultaneous movement
as you can so you want your brains to go
and assign all of their accelerations so
that you know how everything's supposed
to move so that you don't end up hitting
each other in times when you shouldn't
actually ever hit each other right so
yeah so we come in here and we get
something like the let's see where is it
the hero controller
here's brain here oh right and what I
want to do here is I want to actually
assign DDP to write to the actual hero
you can see we've got some weird stuff
happening we've got these like brains
getting iterated and then we also have
like the controller stuff here happening
so the controller stuff happens down
here we kind of want to integrate this
stuff in I think right we want this
controller index this controller stuff
to be a little bit more sensible than it
is right now right now it's kind of
janky and so we're gonna try and
probably fix that at the same time
hopefully so let's start out by doing
something a little bit more
straightforward let's start by just
drawing whatever that DDP actually is so
I'm gonna say that from now on we're
storing in the entity we're gonna store
the DDP now note that that's not
something that actually s get packed
because acceleration doesn't persist
from frame to frame only velocity and
position do and so the DDP is strictly
an accumulator so it's that we know
who's actually trying to apply forces to
these objects right that's all we're
trying to figure out here so we never
actually need the DDP to be stored in
the permanent record it's just a
temporary accumulator so that everyone
who's trying to push on this thing can
push on it right and then later we can
figure out what that actually means now
to be honest I guess I don't know that
we really need to do that because
there's a number of reasons why maybe we
don't but I'm just gonna do it that way
for now we could we could do it directly
into the velocity but I'm just gonna do
it this way for now because I feel like
it's a little more straightforward so
what I want to do is I want to sort of
change this controller code around a
little bit you can see here that we've
got controller code that's good writing
over these things and in this case it's
taking a look to see if a controller
doesn't have a player assigned if it
does have a player assign it's gonna if
it doesn't have player a sign and they
push the start button it's going to
create a new player all right we want to
keep that code that code makes a lot of
sense we do want that to happen right so
we're gonna make this piece of code
here no Casey this is like look to see
if any players are trying to join
because that's what this code does it
just looks for any controllers that are
trying to hit start right so that's all
fine then the next thing I want to do is
like you know run all brains and so when
we're running the brains what I want to
do is figure out a way and I don't think
this is going to be particularly hard
what I want to do here is figure out a
way to make it so that instead of having
to do this weird like looping over the
controller nonsense you remember we had
this nonsense in here right where we
loop over the controller is to see if
any of the controllers pertain to our
hero that's just dumb because we should
be able to now that we have this solid
concept of the brain which is
controlling the entity it seems like we
should be able to do something much more
solid which is just go get whichever
controller is the one that corresponds
to this particular hero right doesn't
seem particularly hard so I want to take
that code out and I want to put that
code in and I want to put it over here
right so right where we're about to do
that work like this
we know we're always gonna have a
controller if it's a hero because if it
wasn't it probably wouldn't be I mean we
could still double check to make sure
that's true but if it wasn't that it
wouldn't really be a hero what makes a
hero a hero is the fact that it's got a
connection to controller right and if we
were going to have another brain that
was similar to a hero but used its own
control logic well we would make another
brain type for that probably and then
they'd share perhaps a bunch of code but
that would be the primary difference
between the two controller types one is
from a controller and one is from on
artificial intelligence of some kind
okay so yeah if I go in here and now do
a thing that that sort of gets that
controllers could controller stuff
happening then you can see what I want
to do is if I'm caught if I'm calling
this code where I get the the gaming
controller from the controller index
right
all I need to get started is I just need
some notion of what that controller
index is right so I just need a way of
having the controller index properly
correspond in some way that's all I'm
looking for here and once I have some
way to get that controller then the rest
of the stuff that I do can can all just
work and similarly in this case I don't
really have any circumstances right
where I I don't really have any
circumstances where I wouldn't have a
con here anymore and like I said we can
make like if we want to make the little
hoppin zombie guy we can now make that
guy by sharing code perhaps we'll share
a bunch of this code but we wouldn't
want to make it be the same brain type
because I think we want this brain type
to mean i get my control from a
controller and then we want other brain
types for things like zombie or whatever
right and there's a bunch of more stuff
we can do to that regard but you get the
idea so that's how the controller stuff
works and then this stuff doesn't really
have to happen in this say that the test
hero stuff doesn't have to happen
instead what we can do is just directly
use this code and because we don't have
a real way to add one of those zombies
anymore I'm gonna if throw this out for
the moment right and maybe we'll go
ahead and re-enable that and actually
make a zombie brain that works the same
as the hero brain as a test case which
actually sounds like a great idea to me
so all the rest of this stuff just works
and there's really no modification that
has to happen to it so presumably all
that should happen now is we just don't
know the controller index so the
question is where do we get the
controller index well I'm gonna be mr.
sly pants sly pants II man and just say
that well where we get the controller
index should probably just be based off
of the brain ID because we can just
reserve a slot of brain IDs for all the
controllers that we might have and then
we know that the actual brain ID itself
maps directly to which controller we're
looking at right and we can sort of
assert here I don't know what get
controller actually does I'll be
completely honest with you I don't
remember if it checks so it just doesn't
assertion yeah so alright so I don't
have to reassert there it's gonna assert
for me but the controller index can just
be whatever the brain IDs value is and
if zero is not a valid brain ID which
I'm pretty sure it's not then they would
just start 1 2 3 4 right so what that
means is that our controllers are
numbered from 0 I believe and so what we
probably want to do is just subtract 1
there to make right but to make that a
little bit more festive and creative
let's say that we actually have a
numerator for it and we'll call it like
brain reserved or reserved brain ID
underscore first hero or something like
this and then what I can do is say ok
with those brain IDs we just know right
off the bat right that we're going to
require those slots for brains to be
reserved so you know in here it will
actually no I could do it for it in the
entity as well where we're talking about
brains
so in here I could do something like
enum
reserved brain ID kind of a thing and in
here there's like the first hero is
reserved one and then you know there's
reserved brain count or or something
like that or I should say first fun
first free ID or something like that
right
yeah something like that and so then in
here I do reserved brain ID last hero
and the last hero would just be you know
the first here of plus however many
controllers there are so in the platform
code you can see that you know we want
one per controller so it's gonna be the
array count of however many of these are
I'll make a pound to find for it cuz why
not max controller account and that way
it's a little clearer what's going on
there but that way we can just say well
we'll just reserve however many there
are and then however many
are we now know that that's the last one
right now since we don't really have to
reserve the very last that all of those
because you know we've got first here oh
it's zero based right so we don't need
you know it would be the value of first
free wants to be the one after the last
one you'd use so I'm going to take back
one there to make sure that we only
reserve the ones we actually use now
that there's any penalty for not doing
it we've got certainly got plenty but
you get the idea so that's what's going
on there right and what I'm gonna do up
here is the the reverse so when we add a
player instead of it returning me the
brain ID I actually want that brain ID
to be something that I pass in so I'm
gonna say here okay I've got brain ID
for this guy and it's gonna be whatever
the controller index was plus whatever
that first hero is right so I now know
that that's what my brain ID actually is
and I'm gonna pass that in right so now
in that add player code instead of that
returning the brain ID it's not going to
do that it's gonna take the brain ID in
and it's not gonna be this add brain
thing is never gonna happen in here
because it's been you know it's sort of
something that's only for when you're
adding to the end of that free list so
then what we need to do is when we
initially create the brains themselves
we need to make sure that we start out
with the first free brain and we don't
ever like actually use any that we
haven't any that are reserved right so
what we're gonna do there is say well
okay we're we're getting the brains from
it's kind of some weird things that end
up being said when we're talking about
this where we're getting the brains from
inside our storage indexes here right is
I guess this last use entity storage and
I guess they're using the same ones for
that so what I want to do is I guess I
could just still even do it make sure
that that starts after the first because
reserved brain ID now we can split these
into two arrays but at the moment we
don't really care too much about that so
I'm just going to make sure that no
entities are in that range either we
just have a range we start after right
so now that should be fine and I think
that's basically it
right so now we should be actually
creating one that goes with a particular
controller in theory anyway
now that doesn't help us that's just
what we needed to do to make things
cleaner in general but that doesn't help
us as you can see oh well I guess it
does I was gonna say doesn't help us
with the DDP thing but it does help us
see that we're actually now corrected to
the connected to the correct hero right
because I can change his facing
direction since that's not something
that relies on the acceleration but we
still haven't put the acceleration back
in and like I said in order to put the
acceleration back in we just need to
start treating that as sort of an
accumulation right and so now when we
have some of the things that were in
that Kankuro we don't actually need to
be in the conure so the DDP can is
actually in the entity now does not need
to be in the connected hero so now some
of the things can come out of there
which we're not really ever you know
shouldn't actually be in there in the
first place handmade H so let's see
where that is controlled hero first of
all we don't need the brain ideas
because they're mapped implicitly we
don't need DDP and the sword or DZ we
really just need I don't even know if we
need exited we might need exited and
debug spawn I'm not totally sure we do
you know what I don't think we need
really anything but the recenter timer
I'm pretty sure that we don't need
anything but let the recenter timer but
we'll find out in a second and we'll go
from there so I'm pretty sure now you
can see that this just cleaned up things
a lot right because now everything's in
the correct place we don't have this
weird like storage thing going on that
we don't really need to have that we
didn't really want want to or need to
have happen in the first place so we'll
keep the sword in there
we need to rename it cuz that's not what
it means anymore but you know for now
we're just as we're doing the code
transformation that's fine you can see
us initializing these things here these
were getting initialized already so we
can just make those to happen I don't
know what exited and debug spawn really
need to be but
at this point we'll just clear them to
zero when we come through here then all
of the things where we had
Kankuro DDP before we just want to have
entity DDP and said right we're just
gonna go ahead and and set those
although you know to be honest I guess
it might be more fun to just have DDP be
something that we can create directly
and then we'll set it later
oops what do I want to do oh no this one
I wanted to conjure up VDP with just DDP
so I'm just gonna go ahead and what did
I do
I need to remember to make automatically
repeat last replace I haven't done that
in my I custom file yet I should all
right so we're coming down here doing
some stuff so yeah when we create these
DDPs then what I want to do is finally
set my entity DDP equal to whatever the
one is that I got there right for the
most part I think I don't really
remember what the things are that we
wanted to do I think that's true I think
that's true do we do anything with that
so I guess that's not even true it looks
like it looks like we don't even want to
assign that because it looks like we're
manhandling it here to a large extent
right it looks like we're just straight
up
we're just straight-up set in the
velocity am i right huh I'm sort of
confused right now be completely honest
because I didn't I didn't realize that
we just straight up set the velocity is
that gosh huh
but I mean seems relatively
incontrovertible since like that's what
we were doing all right well you know if
that's the case then we just do that and
off we go
but that's not probably what we should
be doing I mean probably what we should
be doing is setting this in here so we
got a bunch of clean up to do here
because that's not what I even thought
we were doing but I guess we just never
really wrote that code for real which is
fine Oh
looks like I spoke too soon I guess we
do need to sort we don't really actually
need to store the brain idea but looks
like we want to store something there so
we know that it's assigned right so
that's yeah I guess that's that does
make some sense so yeah yeah let's take
a look here so if I set that in handmade
aged
then when I do my ad player it just
looks like this alright so this was some
holdover stuff that we don't really want
anymore I'm gonna get rid of it let's
see our debug spawn is set to true there
that's something that bull I guess deal
with a little bit later let's see we've
got our d sword con hero D sword is just
gonna be D sword I know that was behind
my head couldn't see what I did okay
yeah that seems reasonable
we need to process that exited code are
we processing that down here when do we
actually process yeah we do
so if we exited we set that to false but
we don't really do that we delete the
entity and set the brain ID so that's
what we would want to do anyway that's
all good
alright so our D Z Kanye rode easy I
don't think we want jumping in there
anymore so that's gone so I think now
we're back to everything trimmed out and
going through the brain so now we just
have to actually get this guide back in
motion and so setting the DP directly
means all we have to do is call move
entity on the hero but I'm not sure yeah
I said that was I was kind of surprised
at how that was was going anyway it
doesn't matter but we're gonna have to
to make the rest of this stuff go
alright so let's see what we've got here
there's the switch for entity type
most of the code happens in the hero
struck now so it looks like what's
happening here in the movement mode code
I think this stuff I mean just looking
at it this stuff really wants to be
probably more so this looks like this is
gonna have to be a slightly separate
stage of things right so the idea here
is we want to be able to share methods
of movement so we kind of have the like
concept that something's planted versus
the concept that something is hopping
around right and so what we'd like to do
here is we'd like to make this be a
little bit more a little bit more
separated from from the notion like this
bit doesn't really make sense in terms
of planted because this part right here
assumes that you've got a notion of
someone you're leaning towards which is
not true for general planted people
right so it feels like we want a little
more granularity here hopping looks
about correct right
because hopping you just says hey look
if I'm trying to hop from one place to
the other here you go right and it
doesn't really require any sort of you
know that doesn't really require any
sort of knowledge of other people or
what's going on so if entities in is a
hopping mode you can see that it just
sort of works and so it's really just
the the sort of the part inside planted
that's that's not okay and we can get
rid of that temporarily because planted
is not a particularly interests Tay
where you are right so that's really not
so bad but we're gonna have to sort of
take these one by one because there's
just a lot of code here and we're trying
to sort of sort these out a little more
cleanly what is the complaint here
there is a null entity ah I see
you see occupying an entity came from
inside get some space reversible I am
Not sure I'm not sure what's going on
here which entity are we updating right
now we're updating brain type brain Hiro
so we're updating a hero we're updating
the body of a hero right and it is in
the hopping mode it's trying to update
its came from but there is no came from
which I guess is the problem so how did
we get into hopping mode without it came
from it's a reasonable question let's
take a look so in order to get into
hopping mode we would need where is that
code here we go in order to getting the
hopping mode we need to get here right
and when we do that we have to set came
from and so you can see I guess when we
first start up I guess we're not
occupying anything yeah index 0
but we did set the pointer so at this
point both came from Oh No okay but we
set it in transactional occupy so okay
so came from in this case is you know
occupying I guess was originally set to
nothing which doesn't really make sense
it should have been sent to something
right because occupying is supposed to
be initialized at least I believe that
should be true so when we were on ad
player right we should have set
occupying equal of something and maybe
we never did but it seems like it should
be so I wanted to see what happened
there it could be that our packing code
is not right yet which because we didn't
quite do as much of that as we should so
you can see we set that there and then
when we call end entity it should be
packing the body in you know it should
be packing that properly so here we are
in the Packer and we're gonna pack
occupying and came from both of which
are set to something although I'll be
honest with you oh sorry no it came from
is not it's just occupying so when we go
to pack occupying let's see what happens
there so the ref pointer is gonna be
something right it's not deleted so we
set the ref index to something let's see
what our reference of being so it looks
like that packs properly to me right
that all looks good so I'm not sure what
the problem is there but I'm gonna go
ahead and and check I guess when we do
the unpack to see what happens
maybe there's something weird happening
I don't know why something weird would
happen there that's the hero of body and
it's the only hero body so I'm not quite
sure why we would end up in a situation
where that wouldn't be correct
well okay so I guess if we add it it
won't get unpacked but that's okay we'll
skip it this time through right it won't
have been added yet I mean technically
that should probably at the end because
we really don't want any in there that
never got used but I guess that's a
separate issue but yeah we come through
here we shouldn't have any heroes there
should be no heroes at all right and so
you know yeah we're just we're never
gonna actually have a hero in there and
then the next time through you would
think anyway that our hero should have
had that set properly I would think but
I guess he doesn't let's see why not
alright so we're gonna grab the head and
the body here look at the body and I
want to look at those pieces of
information occupying came from so yeah
it totally lost its occupying
information like that's just set to
nothing so I guess like my unpack code
is broken or something like this and I
want to find out why because obviously
we're not gonna get very far if we can't
pack our stuff properly and this code is
kind of a unnecessarily obtuse right
because this stuff will get a little bit
more Systema is when we actually start
doing packing and unpacking but for
right now it's sort of in an interim
state which does make it a little bit
more difficult to use certainly but
let's take a look so this is gonna be in
connect entity pointers it's when this
will happen and hope well you know to do
reenable this would probably be why
that's not getting unpacked shockingly
all right that's great so yeah in this
case we don't need head we just need
occupying and came from I don't know
looks like we're just unpacking and
marking that as used which is fine so
that that should hopefully solve that
problem of why those aren't getting
impact all right so let's see well no I
guess it didn't but that is definitely a
problem you have to admit it's not
particularly it's not particularly
friendly if you if you're trying to get
a location when you're supposed to be
occupying something and you never unpack
it alright so who is this exactly we're
looking at a body here and somehow it's
occupying again got set to zero though
right but I don't understand why that
would be because the occupying should
never really get set to zero let me
double check that I didn't mess
something up here we do low traversal
reference on the occupying we
double-check and set the entity to make
it occupy but I don't know where where
it's load so when we load it we just see
whether or not there's an index there
and if there is we go ahead and and and
get the entity out which seems fine so
I'm gonna go ahead and set a breakpoint
there I want to see what happens when
that when that unpacks and you know
what's weird about that too is I saw the
the fact that it was being occupied
because it turned blue before and so I
feel like yeah I feel like that was a
little bit odd but it's ok now I still
got about 10 minutes left so I'm gonna
go ahead and hunt this guy down before
stopping
excuse me all right so somewhere
somebody is setting this to zero which
is not what I would have preferred they
do and what I'd like to do is is take a
look at which actual value ID this guy
is right so every time we run its Guide
to 19 right you can see here it back up
a bit here so right ID value to 19
that's what I want to do is just insert
a little bit of code to help me out and
say that when we're actually doing this
unpacking when we do connect entity
pointers I'm just going to make it so
that you know if the entity ID value
equals to 19 you know I want you to just
stop right probably more interesting
would just be to give me a line to stop
on and then I can just set it and unset
it as as I wish so now if I look at some
region here when we actually do the the
connect up I can just set a breakpoint
and run and now I can see what happens
when we're about to unpack the entity
that I know is the problem and this is
just a common thing that I do you've
seen me do it before where I'm like oh
it's it would be kind of finicky to try
to step to that code all the time
because it's a school it's this code
gets run a bunch of times every frame
and and I don't want to spend a lot of
time getting to it so instead I just put
some code in that I know will only
trigger when on the thing that I want to
see and so then we can see what happens
so let's at least see now what happens
with occupying so it looks like we're
actually coming in wrong so our the
point where we actually saved it out
must also be erroneous or something
because by the time we get to the unpack
it's not correct right so let's try and
figure out why that's happening I can
sort of keep this exact same concept
going by going into
so weird for the world the world code
and when we do the pack
I can stop on the pack as well and see
if there's anything weird happening
there so for example on this guy I could
say like oh yeah tell me when this
entity gets packed and I guess sorry
21 the source I need to get packed and
then we'll go from there alright so
let's see both sides of the equation now
here we are packing the source and we
can see that occupying is already set to
no so now I just have to kind of ask the
question all right if this is entity 219
and it's already set to no why was it
set to no when we're adding this player
why are we not adding the player
correctly
oh well that's why because the head is
not the thing that the head is not the
thing which gets an occupying heads
don't occupy only the body occupies so
that's a little weird right hmm well
that kind of answers our question right
yeah that kind of answers our question
you know what I might do
I might do something like this where we
can just set this value madam I'll just
do it it doesn't matter like how long
did that take to add table you know two
seconds 12 seconds 15 seconds 30 seconds
75 seconds not very many seconds is the
point all right so all I want to do now
is go take a look at that code and see
why we're ever looking at the occupying
value for the head cuz that just looks
like I must have made a typo there so
let's go ahead and run and let it crash
at the place it was crashing because
that doesn't that should not actually be
happening yes so why is the body what's
going on with the with that did I I may
have mixed up I may have mixed up
which word switch and so another thing
too is we could take this opportunity to
especially if that is the bug take this
opportunity to fix that so let's see
here so the head is in slot one of the
bodies in slot zero so I was wrong
already right so what I'd like to do is
I'd like to have a way of making this
more robust right and it's a little
tricky to do that because C C++ don't
really let you do this very well but you
see what the bug is right it's actually
this goes into this slot and this goes
into that slot that was what was
supposed to happen so you know finish
running this here so that's the actual
problem with with why we were crashing
and so now we're back to normal
but you can see what we want to do is we
want to make it so that it's much easier
to put them in the right slot so we want
to make a way that we can take one of
these entity brains that we have and if
we define a nice template here not a
people s template out so you but you
know
I mean the actual textbook definition of
template if we have one of these we want
to be able to get the index by just
figuring out what it would have been
right so I'm gonna make a macro for that
because like I said there really isn't a
lot of there really isn't a good way to
do it and so you know I want to make
something just like look brain slot for
and you basically say oh you know what
was the brain slot type you were looking
for and what was the member I should do
it this way right type and member so
that I can say like oh okay the brain
slot in this case is the brain slot for
a brain here of parts you know which one
is this your body and this one is the
brain slot for the brain hero parts head
so at least I know that they'll come
back reliably and so how do I do that
well this is an overlay on top of this
array so I know that if I take the
offset from the base of that then I
could figure out where it was right so
in other words this structure has a set
of entity pointers in it and I know if I
just look at how many bytes in a
particular one of those is and I divide
by the size of one of these entity
pointers right then I would know that's
how far I go in right divided by eight
bytes right the size of a pointer so I
can make a little macro that basically
does that that thing what I could do is
I could say like okay let me cast you
know like some something like zero to
whatever the type is that I'm trying to
talk about which is the brain here of
parts in this case right so I've got a
brain here of parts here and I know that
if I had a pointer to brain here of
parts right I could get out of that
whatever the member was that that I was
referring to right so there's my member
and this is essentially like this
pointer right would be how far in
I would be from from the start of the
structure right if the structure was at
zero then you know if I if I took like
the address let's say of this member
then that's how many bytes in I am from
the start of the structure make sense
and so from there I can figure out how
many entity pointers in that is by just
dividing by the size of one of those
entity pointers right so I could say
well alright however many in that is I
could divide that value you know well
you know I wouldn't even have to do that
I could just use pointer arithmetic for
it if that's a pointer I could just say
pretend that pointer to that member is a
pointer to an entity star star which
actually I definitely under pretend it
is that right so I could just say take
that do I have enough parentheses here
okay take that and subtract it from if
you believed that that zero itself was a
pointer to an entity star right and that
would get me back in index that says
what the brain slot actually was so hold
on one second and I'll walk that a bit
no pretty fan which takes right in of in
1664 oh right sorry I forgot to actually
wrap that up in well you know I could
just do this for now
okay so I think that should work but
we'll double-check it yeah it does okay
so let me just explain that one more
time for people who think that's kind of
crazy and weird just what's going on
there so you know that this is just an
overlay on this right because they're a
union so if I want to know which slot
one of these would have lined up in all
I'm doing is saying hey take the address
of it if you assumed that you were
starting at zero how far in what I have
to go to get to that member right and
then I'm just telling them Pilar hey by
the way how many entities stars is it
from zero to their right so that
automatically tells us how's the
compiler do that divided for me right
and yeah it's not pretty but that's
there you go now this is exactly the
kind of thing to that compiler vendors
who basically are like trying to make
programmer slaves more difficult will
get and optimize in weird ways that
because they're like well we don't come
from the same memory pool because
technically you never allocated and blah
blah blah blah blah that kind of stuff
is the most annoying stuff ever and I
hate it this particular one I don't
believe they optimized for it because
there's really nothing you can do about
it because they could have come from the
same memory pool in this case so I'm
pretty sure this one's safe but yeah a
lot of times you find yourself having to
do operations like this because the
language I mean it's pretty obvious the
language should support this exact
operation which is to say I want to name
slots in an array it's kind of obvious
but of course it doesn't and so you know
a lot of times you have to compensate
for it and then it's super annoying when
compiler vendors come in and make it
hard for you to compensate for the
problems in the language by making it
impossible for you to use the things
that compensate for the fit problems in
the language but you know there you are
so anyway this is definitely that kind
of a thing but sometimes you need to do
that I would like this to return an
actual brain slot value so what I might
do as well is I might sort of take this
to be a little bit more of an official
thing and say ok there's actually an
inline function called brain slot 4 and
that just needs to take whatever
that pointer offset is like whatever the
the actual distance is there or whatever
so we'll just say like or you know this
is just the pack value or something
right so this way we can put it into the
right type of a structure and I'm really
doing this because we're not using the
most the most modern dialect of C where
I could have just done the bracket
initializer for it there so anyway I
could do brain slot results equals pack
value and then just return it so that
way we don't have to do this indexed
nonsense anymore either which is makes
that also a little bit nicer
alright so that's about it we'll go
ahead and go to the Q&amp;A and so we still
have tomorrow we got to finish up our
acceleration stuff but that's no big
deal
we've gotten the brain stuff working
which is nice can we have a look at the
C time stats so far yes I believe that
should be easy enough to do right C time
is in yes it is
oops so if we take a look at actually
where we storing it in build know where
we're actually storing it sorry I just
don't remember where we decided to put
this maybe it's just in code
yeah so you're just looking at stats you
just want to know this oops
remember what the command is Oh - stats
sorry so so far we've spent a total of 7
minutes and 29 seconds building
apparently yeah so that's in in 400
we've built 417 times that's a
tremendous number of times
uh-huh in in 10 days so we build an
average of 40 times an episode can you
imagine what it would be like like can
you imagine what it would be like in if
that was like uh you know took took a
minute to compile or something that
would be brutal dude in basement what
would we do for the production assert
well in in release mode that they're
they don't compile in so there won't be
any there is no production of sorry may
this brain system allow for things like
two characters carrying a felled tree
between them with both of their brains
controlling the movement of the tree
well I guess what I would say is I don't
know that I would have chosen to use the
brain system for that because it doesn't
necessarily I don't know that that would
be the best way to use the brain system
but you certainly could the reason that
I don't think I would use the brain
system for that is because if you wanted
to have to like let's say you then
wanted to have other types of people who
are carrying the tree well if the brain
system is what determines is carrying
the tree then you you could you know
it's easy enough to write a hero hero
tree carrier but now I got a right oh
what if one of the people was a monster
and I have to have a tree monster
carrying thing and blah blah blah right
so I feel like maybe what you would do
there is you would have probably and and
this will probably happen right our
brains will probably have behaviors and
stuff in them they're probably just be
like a thing that's like am i carrying a
tree if so then I have special stuff
that I might do on one side of the tree
or something I don't know but I'm not
sure that that would be the best way to
implement it I have to see that's not
really something on handmade hero that
since hammer here is a sinker player
game I haven't really thought too hard
about how you would need to do stuff
like that and whether there's something
intelligent you would want to do there
all right no more questions we can end I
don't see any I'm waiting I don't see no
questions I don't see no questions I
don't see no questions no questions no
questions no questions
frosty ninja try not to make the brain
self-aware we can't have stumpy over
there taking over the world
well I think the person you should be
more concerned about is in sohbat right
because in sohbat is definitely way more
advanced than any of the brains we're
making on handmade hero and so if
something's gonna take over the world
it's going to be in sohbat the Cizek
four brain types why not an enum for the
array indices well the problem with
array indices in this case is that's
just more typing that I don't really
want to have to do but because then you
have to constantly be like the thing in
the brackets we could do it you know and
the other reason is you can mix and
match them accidentally right I mean you
know since since nobody's asking any
other questions let me just go ahead and
actually be 100% explicit on why I don't
want to do that because it's worth
elaborating so here's what we've got
currently right and you've got brain
here a parts head and body and so what
happens there is when I'm actually doing
that the construction code would not be
any different really or any more
error-prone if you used enums so in that
case I think you could use either fairly
interchangeably because there's no
really clean way to make this work I
don't I don't think
I mean we could maybe do some I don't
know the the point being no I don't
think there's much we could do here to
make this less error-prone but the only
reason that I wanted to maybe do it
without the enums was because in the
case where you're actually getting the
code out right in here this is a little
easier to not screw up in my opinion
because you can do stuff like that
in the case where I've got a lot of
these and I can just and I can write and
I can make sure that everything comes
from the same understanding right now if
instead I was to do it this way
right well probably I'd have to always
do this and I'd have to always make sure
these were correct and the reason is
because it'd be real easy to
accidentally use the enum from some
other brain type in this entity right so
you'd always have to I'd have to at
least always make sure I was very
consistent with these prefixes because
if I did this you know maybe that's the
wrong that's not the hero body that's
some other body which is in a different
slot right because you're gonna have a
bunch of different types of brains so
this one kind of makes it so that it's
scoped a little more properly in my mind
and that's the reason I didn't go with
enums now maybe I should have gone with
enums because maybe that's really not a
realistic error to be worried about but
that's what I was thinking
Josiah Mariette how would you go about
making game entities moddable well it
depends what you're trying to mod about
them I mean like that's kind of I feel
like that's really not a question you
can answer because the moddable is not
really moddable is not really a
definition like moddable doesn't mean
anything right I mean for handmade hero
the trivial answer is like oh well all
the source codes available so if anyone
wants to make a different stuff they can
just make it right so the question is
like what do you actually want to get
out of the modding do they just want to
be able to swap in bitmaps do they want
to be able to define new behaviors that
are existing combinations of existing
behaviors or do they need to be able to
write completely new behaviors that are
like coded totally differently from
other behaviors right and so if you're
trying to okay so it says I was thinking
of trying to find whole types of holder
types entities so if you're trying to
find whole new types of entities then
you would probably have to do something
where you where you load a dll right if
you wanted them to be able to to be able
to find entirely new entity you have to
be able to load a dll right
yeah because the only alternative that
really is is a scripting language right
if you if you want to be able to load
actual code in you'd have to either load
a scripting language or load a DLL with
that has you know code in it and you
know for handmade hero we definitely
wouldn't ever do a scripting language so
that's kind of like a whole another
project right to implement one of those
but you know you could see loading a DLL
or something and and then you would just
have to do some kind of understanding of
how you would marshal those behaviors
right like how you would assign them to
different things and obviously because
you run into the problem of defining a
new type of entity you would have to
figure out how you're picking entities
to begin with right
and so we would probably do is take
those brain types and the brain types
would now be picked very much similar to
where the asset system picks things so
instead of specifically creating a brain
type and said you would have some
parameters and it would you know do
whatever just I and marry it I guess
there's no way to mitigate DLL security
concerns well you can if you want to
right that's like for example what
chrome does is you could sandbox the DLL
and you can force it not to load any be
able to load from anything but certainly
that's not something I would care about
at all because you know security
concerns of that form in my mind that
was Microsoft's job and they abdicated
their responsibility there and so I'm
certainly not gonna step in and do
Microsoft's job for them you know it's
ridiculous that you could ever possibly
have a security concern with a video
game right that the even the mere fact
that that's even a concept is just kind
of like a testament to how bad Microsoft
is at their job because it's ridicu it
it doesn't even make sense the point of
an operating system just in general was
that there was no way for a game to be
able to do anything on your machine
right that was like the whole point of
time sharing
operating systems in the first place
well I shouldn't say time sorry
operating systems but of having
protection in the first place it was
that
so users couldn't do that and so it's
it's kind of silly that that's even the
concept that you would even ever think
of having to do security as a game
developer is ludicrous right
the only kind of security a game
developer should be thinking about is if
they're talking to like a server or
something because obviously that's
something that you know that that could
be hacked in a separate way but so yeah
that's just that's that's just
Microsoft's problem as far as I'm
concerned static motion all the brain
code is now in the switch brain type how
many brains do you expect to have what
if we have a hundred brains where you
keep all the code in there well I don't
know that we would necessarily get rid
of the switch statement but we probably
wouldn't keep the switch statement in
line in this file so there probably be a
plan made brain dot cpp and then we'd
have the switch statement there now
we're keep in mind that these brains
will start sharing a lot of code so the
brain code will not be probably so huge
it'll probably be calling functions to
do things that are common among brains
so that'll change a little bit all right
we're out of time so
okay thank you everyone for joining me
for another episode of hand made here
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to follow along
series at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade hero argh and it
comes with a source code so you can play
around with it on your own we also have
a forum site you can go to if you would
like to some sort of ask questions and
or if you find bugs or anything like
that that you want to report there's
there's forums on there you can use we
have a patreon page you can use you want
support the video series we have a
schedule bot which when I remember it up
below the schedule tells you what the
schedule is going to be I forgot to do
that this weekend I'll do that tonight
we also have a past episodes guide that
you can use to catch up with parts three
series it's really cool it has time
coded links and everything I brought to
you by our very own Niblo and that's
about it I will see you guys back here I
believe tomorrow will be another stream
day but double check the three pot which
I'll update tonight but I believe we'll
be back here again at 5 p.m. Pacific
Daylight Time tomorrow just as we
normally are that's about all there is
to say about that thanks for joining me
I will see you guys tomorrow until then
have fun programming and I'll see you on
the Internet