hello everyone and welcome to handmade
heroes show recode a complete game live
on stream we did what we needed to do
yesterday to put multiple render layer
compositing into the software renderer
but we didn't have a chance to optimize
it so when you run it right now it's
kind of unbearably slow for example if I
load it up here due to to do and run it
this is the the speed we're looking at
normally which is around 30 frames
second here on the software renderer and
then when I hop on the stairs and try to
go upwards you can see it chug down to
like almost you know I don't know what
that is it's a hundred milliseconds of
frame so you know something ridiculous
like six frames a second or something
like that I don't know really our ten
frame segments rather not great not
great and we know why that is it's
pretty straightforward actually because
we didn't do an optimized version of the
blip we just did a reference one to make
sure that everything was working
properly and that's great but we need to
replace it now with one that actually
does a more optimized version so when I
look at blend render target here you can
see here is the super slow version right
and that is because it's you know it's
not at all using any SSE or anything
like that it's just doing the standard
slow way so what we need to do here is
take effectively this code that we were
using for filling rectangles and convert
it to do blending of these two
rectangles right so that's what we're
trying to do here so I'm going to go
ahead and see how hard it is to make
that happen you can see here most of the
stuff starting and clip masks and all
that stuff is going to be basically the
same right there's really not a whole
lot to it I don't think as come
like as far as this is concerned I think
this is all going to be pretty basic and
yeah nothing in here really needs to
change this is just sort of prepping
this in fact I wonder if we could some
point make this some shared code I feel
like we could have shared some of this
but anyway so let's see so in here where
we're actually taking a look at the row
pointers this should be essentially the
same as it was before and so when we've
got sort of the row and row advanced
here really all we need to do is take
the same queue you know it's going to be
exactly this the same stuff that we've
got here so there really isn't anything
special about it right you can see it's
the exact same code that was getting
operated they're the only difference is
now we need two of them and so we've got
a destro advance and a source row
advance as well one for each but other
than that we're good to go so then we
come into this code and you know you can
see that we're just going to do it
pretty much exactly the same kind of a
loop the only difference is here instead
of just one pixel now we've got a death
pixel and a source pixel again this is
exactly analogous to what we were doing
before and then we're going to go
through and we got to port all this code
where we're going through and doing the
operation but then at the end really all
we need to do is just make sure that we
update everywhere we were updating only
one thing before we have to update both
things but that's it oops
so once we've got that there really
isn't a lot more to it other than going
through and changing it so we're
actually going to do the right pixel ops
now so we don't have this concept of a
color that's being modulated anymore we
just have an alpha so we've got
basically an alpha for X we don't have
you know any of the other stuff there
that we have to deal with so really what
we need to do here is sort of do when
we're doing our load destination and you
can kind of see how we were doing that
here we just need to now load both the
destination and the source right so
instead of having a constant color that
we're using we need to have both so we
sort of got an original death and an
original source and those are just you
know getting the desk fiction sorsrex
allowed when we load the destination and
are going to operate in that we want to
be able to do a load destination and a
load source so we want to do both of
these now right and so if you take a
look at what happens here all of this
stuff can stay exactly the same and so
this just needs to be modified so that
instead of a test its source everywhere
so basically just produces a source
version doing the exact same load up
that we were doing before and that's it
right now when we do our modulate by
incoming color here we're not actually
going to be I think this was a bogus
comment this is just a sign well I guess
it's not we were just using the texel as
a way of storing that because texel kind
of got you know was all in there so this
right here where we're sort of doing the
well actually
no I don't I don't really I guess to be
honest I don't really know we're
clamping this but we shouldn't actually
have to clamp I mean I guess we could
clamp if we wanted to clamp but we had
since it's constant I don't even know
this this code is super crappy we should
probably just cut that out of our other
code because doing a min min max PS on a
constant value makes no sense at all so
so I don't even know why we're doing
this this is just dumb so I'm going to
go ahead and get rid of all of that we
don't need any of that alright so in
this case we need to be able to square
our color values again we have to do
that for both of them here so I'm just
going to go ahead and change it so that
we do both the source scan the desk so
that we go you know in we basically do
the gamma step undo the gamma correct
then we got to do our blend and in this
case our in textile a is actually a
constant here right so if we want to we
could actually pull this out so that we
kind of have the info texel a and the
texel a we can do that that operation in
a much more efficient way so I'm going
to go ahead and pull that out here
because we don't need to compute that
every time so we've got a in Val 4 for X
and that's just going to be whatever
alpha 4 X was in this case right and the
same thing is true here I guess I should
look to see where we load up up the the
where we do the alpha blending I'm
interested to see here I when we do when
we actually do the blend so we do the
mall and then we go we do the the
reverse reciprocal square root
to get back into brightness space but
I'm concerned because I'm just not sure
what whether the alpha values are what
space we were expecting them in because
if we look at this code here right I
feel like this code is all assuming yeah
and that that looks very clearly the
case to me this is all going to be in
bases 02 65536 space right sir 535 suite
225 squared right and so when we do our
destination blending here and we're
going to do our ad with our mole moles
and all that our texel stuff should not
be in 255 space right should be inverse
space so I feel like this doesn't need
to happen now because that was if we had
loaded it and it wasn't 255 space it's
not so we should be able to just do our
sub PS where we just subtract 1 minus
alpha we could even do this more
directly and just say you know it's that
so it's clearer so we have alpha inverse
alpha and I think those want to be 0 to
1 because we're using them as a
straight-up blend so then when we do our
destination planned we would now since
we're doing up a real blend not a pre
multiply blend we're doing a full blend
we have to expand our mole out to
basically account for that you know I'm
saying uh so there we go so we have to
do a mole on both sides and in the case
of the second side that we're just doing
our alpha 4 X oops and then here we just
have our in alpha 4 X
and we're blending the desk and we're
going to blend the source so I don't
need this texel nonsense anymore okay so
now we have our blended values those in
theory should flow through the pipeline
correctly so I don't think we'll have to
do anything really I don't think there's
anything comp more complicated that we
need to do there I'll go ahead and I
don't know why we've still got these
blocks in here maybe we were testing the
map I'm not entirely certain but anyway
so if we take a look at what's going on
here I think that's roughly all I just
want to make sure i have the Destin
source in the right order there with how
we defined the Alpha yeah it's 1 minus
alpha x desc so I think that's basically
the routine we're looking at it's not
super complicated and like most of the
work is just shared and it's done the
same way in both things right so now we
can sort of see what happens if we
actually run it you know maybe all hell
breaks loose or maybe it's fine okay so
it looks like that's just fine actually
so it looks like that's actually
actually great and we don't take too
much of a hit there i mean it is
definitely slower but it's not that much
lower it's still you know roughly about
the same frame rate so that's all good
so yay all right we've got our you know
I'm not not going to say particularly
well optimized but you know optimized
enough so optimized enough to not be a
problem so now what we have to do is is
this to do right here right
and the problem with this guy is that it
sets the Alpha value to 1 and we don't
want the Alpha value to be set to 1 and
furthermore I think we you know for
clears I think we want to be a little
bit more explicit about how we're
clearing these buffers I think we can
write a much faster routine right
because for these clears in particular
we're not using like we know we're not
doing any operations we're just romping
a value in there right so in theory you
know we should be able to take something
like this blood render target routine
and make a clear routine that's much
better right that doesn't take as much
time to do the actual clear and it
doesn't have to have the Alpha weirdness
to it right so we should be able to do
something more you know like this where
we just say well okay we know we've just
got a desk in this case you know no
source and you know we we know we don't
have to load anything we know we don't
have to do any of this stuff right so
all we really need to do in this case is
set these values so really we're just
talking about you know up here we would
just say you know color our color g
color be
and since those are all going to be
constant we could do that to be get like
we could do that initially right so this
really really all of this stuff falls
away and we can just pre make
essentially this thing right up here and
once we do that then all we really have
to do is say well we don't need to load
the original desk we don't need to load
really anything so all we have to do in
this case is just write out the death
pixel I guess well if we want to support
fractional clears I guess we do have to
load the desk right because if we were
trying to if we had a clip wrecked that
was down the middle of one of our of our
four wide pixel things you that could be
a problem right so i suppose in that
sense we do want to leave original desk
as being loaded so we basically have you
know the original desk pixel and then we
want to do our mast out where we've got
our out value that gets combined with
the right mask to get the original test
in there and then it writes it out but
really that's the entirety of the loop
you know this is this is what we're
talking about here and so you can kind
of see in this case it's much nicer
right it's a much nicer thing and I'm
going to get rid of our ayaka there
because we don't really care about that
uh so yeah that's you know that's what
I'm talking about for a clear it seems
you know plenty saying to do that and
you can see how simple the code will be
if we do it that way so coming back up
here I don't really know that we need
any of this stuff probably will see
which of it we actually need in fact
I'll just go ahead and undo this for now
now to see what's ones we need but in
terms of preparing the buffer all we
really need to do to prepare the buffer
is a you know exactly the things we were
previously doing here we can now do its
just instead of loading these colors up
here instead we can just choose name
instead we can just make these guys come
from our color values well actually I
guess all right so yes so if i do a
color r equals mm set 1 p.s and i use
whatever the color r is and i just get
these loaded up in here basically all
I'm doing is I'm just making a baked
value that I can use to romp values in
let's take a look at clear wrecked and
we don't need this and we need that okay
that's federal way all right and so now
in theory we could instead of doing this
we could say
instead of draw a rectangle we will do
clear what did I call it clear rectangle
let's call it clear rectangle and it
just takes a wrecked a desk tarro we
don't even need the way we do we need
the desk target so it just needs a
wrecked a desk target and that's it so
yeah if we're going to do that the
rectangle in this case is is like this
right here and the color we can now use
directly so I think it's roughly that I
don't think there's a lot more to it so
let's see how that does now and so
that's clearing to black which I'll be
honest I'm not sure that doesn't seem
right so we must have a bug in our code
there but at least now you can see we're
clearing the Alpha value well I guess
now we weren't so why I don't know why
that's clearing to black we'll have to
take a look at what's actually going on
with with the colors here so this
actually gets assembled we don't really
need to assemble this in SSC for any
particular reason either so that's kind
of a little bit weird i suppose but you
know in fact yeah i have no idea why we
would do that that's a little bit odd
because really all we need is one of
these guys you know we could just take
the pack you know do a standard pack
color operation on it and then put it in
there yeah well anyway so I'm going to
step in in here just so I can take a
look at what's actually going on there
and see
what I think in terms of debugging it
and then we'll go from there so let's
see we want handmade render and we want
in here somewhere too there's clear
rectangle alright so what's the color
value oh I also want to turn off
optimizations because I want to actually
be able to look at my code novel concept
I know so we come in here to my little
lovely routine and oh god okay great one
more thing we need to do is turn off
threads because of course visual studio
doesn't make it easy to just step
through the individual thread so let's
see where we actually take our make
queues for the high priority queues I
think let's see here high priority queue
so can I just say zero here we should
have a an easy way to turn off threading
and the renderer so all right here's our
settings nonsense let's take a look at
what we're actually asked to do so
here's the clear call the clear call is
actually setting the Alpha value to 1
and so that's actually not we would have
wanted and 15 15 15 is the actual or is
the actual color values that we're
working with their point point 15 and so
let's take a look at what we actually
created here
as what we wanted to make so yeah that
looks unconvincing to say the least
right because let's see how how we went
wrong there because you know we get
color are that's point one five point
one five point one five and so on we
then do a mall ah yeah so we so we saw
the like spaces that you're in when you
forget so these are not x 2 55 so
basically you know this this guy needs
to still be here and you need to do a
mole to get it up to the right range
right of course I could also just do
this I suppose there we go and I think
that's about it let me look at how alpha
so alpha gets packed in directly as well
so I think that is more correct however
we still and man this is so slow running
in debug mode with no threads so that's
that's always fine but that still looks
like it's not clearing to the correct
color right it's not clearing to gray
which is what it should have been
clearing to so we do our set 1 p.s from
the 255 elevated colors we then do the
the mole
let's take a look
so r SG so these are those look like
more correct values though so that seems
fine although they are very dark so I do
wonder linear 021 Brighton space to sRGB
0225 of course those comments are wrong
because they're not actually in 021
brightness space to probably eliminate
those because those exist down below and
our incorrect so reciprocal square root
this is going to be provide one over the
square root of of the value right so you
know where see here I don't really know
I wish I could remember when we had done
this originally I don't really remember
why we phrase it that way
there we go
j 318 so you know we have a value X and
we want to produce right square root of
x but we only have reciprocal square
root of x so we can produce 1 over root
X right and we want to do an operation
to this that will you know eventually
produce just rude x right if that makes
sense so it would seem that you would
want to do an inversion there so I'm not
sure we are currently multiplying by the
original X ok so that's actually neat
trick so I guess what we did and I guess
maybe we outsmarted or I outsmarted
myself here we basically said like can
we multiply this by something that will
give us this right so we said you know
what times 1 over root x equals root X
and it's like well okay you know if I
have a over root x equals root X then I
multiply both of these together right to
cancel i multiply both sides by root x 2
to solve for a and I just get X right so
it turns out if i multiply by the
reciprocal square root I get the right
term so that actually looks correct to
me and then when we do our conversions
off we go right so it feels like that
color value is being interpreted
correctly now yet at the same time it
just it seems like it's awfully dark
compared to what's happening in the
other pass so i guess and i don't know
but when we do a GL clear see here there
it is so when we do a GL clear color
here uh I don't actually know if GL
clear will obey the
srgb factors or not that's kind of the
unfortunate the unfortunate part of it
so you know I don't know which is the
correct way to too I don't know what
open gel is actually going to do with an
srgb frame buffer when we ask it to
clear is it going to clear to those
values natively or is it going to clear
to those values srgb adjusted and of
course it's probably pretty hard to tell
but let's find out so let's see clear
color uh Taylor some friends let's see
when GL framebuffer a cervix isn't able
to cook okay so basically if we want to
be if we want to be compliant we would
have to with how the clear is working in
the other case we actually can't we
don't want to do any of this correction
actually so we just want to treat the
values directly
alright so we're a little better now but
that's still not that doesn't look this
like the same color to me oh I'm going
to be it if they are in linear space
then when they get packed into the
buffer this that is what should be
happening because if they're in linear
space coming in they then have to be
adjusted to pack into the srgb frame
buffer which will get loaded out later
so the comment still stands but this
operation is correct I believe
so I still don't quite know why we're
getting that effect I do also want to
before we go any further want to see why
when we do the clear when we set the
clear color see here render group clear
I would like to know why the clear color
when we set it and I'm assuming that's
getting set in here i miss i don't know
why the background color was getting set
with an alpha value of one that doesn't
make a whole lot of sense to me um but
you know i guess it was so yeah in
theory we now have everything correct
except for why that color value isn't
matching the opengl side of things and
so we'll have to take a look at why
that's going on but first let me go back
to here and oops we enable our threading
go
so let's go up here so that's still
those I don't know why those alpha
values there are
actually I do I take it back so we do
have one more bug we've got the color
bug which is that we got to go find out
why our color doesn't line up but we
have one more bug as well which is that
in our our blend render target routine
now that we know that the clear or at
least now that we're trying to make sure
the clear uprights properly it occurs to
me that this actually does not use the
source alpha at all in the blend and it
needs to otherwise you will never get
any of the matte effect right we need to
look to see if there's anything in the
source first so it actually is going to
multiply the Alpha value here in other
words this source color a you know this
is this is sort of the the global alpha
right but the pixel alpha is the alpha
value times whatever the whatever the
source colors alpha value was so we
actually do need to do that and that's
actually the correct thing because
otherwise we're not going to get the
transparency the correct transparency
from our source not sure why i spaced on
that but I did so here where we can see
doing the alpha inverse alpha that means
the inverse alpha and alpha actually
can't be stored if that makes sense we
do actually have to do the multiply
right so let me go ahead and grab those
in here so right before we do our alpha
blend in this case we've got our alpha 4
X it's just going to be a mul and i'll
call this pixel alpha
and we'll just use that pixel oops so
that pixel alpha that we load is going
to have to be the multiplication of our
original alpha for X and whatever we
loaded as our source alpha right and the
source alpha when we load it is going to
be in 0 to 255 space so we also have to
make sure that we get that subtraction
happening right so when we load it here
we have to do at MMO PS of give'em 255
to make sure that the Alpha value is on
the range of 0 to 1 once it is then
we're we're fine right
because we can do our 1 minus although I
guess I can't wait it's just called one
of course i didn't had a Forks into that
no one knows why I just didn't so that's
actually the correct thing to do there
and so now if i did that properly when
we actually do the composite step on top
we should get it showing through in the
places where it's supposed to show
through right at least that's the hope
yeah so now that's actually working the
way it's supposed to work and not having
those weird solids there so now I think
we actually are down to just the bug of
of having the incorrect value on vm on
the color so let's take a look briefly
back at the place where in World mode
where we were actually specifying not
the color but those those blocks there
where we're rendering the traversable I
guess that's an entity here we go so I
basically changed the size of those so
that it was like they were those weird
little slats so if I put that back to
the previous size of course we do have
the problem of not we don't edge them
with anything at the moment which makes
it really hard for them to see also have
you noticed when we're in this render
mode by the way we don't get the the we
don't get the bending I wondering did we
not do the correct sorry the to jump
around here but did we not do the
correct bending for a render entry
bitmap I'm wondering about that
so here it is right and it's like
entropy and it's got the x-axis and the
y-axis but it doesn't seem to actually
bend the way that you would expect it to
you know what I mean was there something
else that was being done here that would
have made that happen female color like
is our draw rectangle quickly doing
something that it shouldn't be doing as
far as the x-axis and y-axis are
concerned I'm not sure
because like just I mean just take a
look at the difference you see the
bending that's happening there right and
now if I switch to the software renderer
it doesn't Bend so like that that
equation is wrong so something about how
we're positioning it it might be just
the minimum p positioning that's wrong
I'm not one hundred percent certain but
we do also have a bug in there that's
not a bug that we introduced with what
we're doing here or anything like that
but that does seem to be a problem and
so I'm not sure what this stuff is doing
here I also don't know why we have a
value called NZ scale that nobody uses
like literally nobody touches that value
let's trim some of this out here goodbye
and what's n x axis injuries x length
squared
so we've got some and we got some other
things here but I don't know that they
actually do anything either do they
so it looks like we've got some errors
and how the texel lookup works when we
do bending here I'm not sure when we
want to go fix that but I'm going to put
a note in here but it's sure it sure
seems like there's a bug in there yeah I
mean you can see what that's doing right
it's it's not it's not actually
producing the correct lateral movement
even though the vertical movement
actually looks amantha vertical movement
but the vertical shear actually looks
somewhat okay but but the other part
doesn't right yeah so that's interesting
to see why that's happening
there's also some really weird stuff
with our sort groups at the moment why
are we getting all of those sort groups
that's very strange oops I guess that
could be because it doesn't know what
yeah I'm not sure basically I think
we've got a lot of debugging to do if
that makes sense it's never really all
that fun to have two different renderers
I suppose but that's just the way it
goes I wish we could only have the soft
for a renderer but you know times being
what they are you can't yes I know you
don't recognize that because the open
Joe render doesn't have support for for
the compositor but anyway all right
let's take these in order though since
we have too many bugs we got to look at
them one at a time so if I take a look
at what's happening here with the color
I feel like you know most of our other
color stuff seems to be happening
properly we don't seem to have a lot of
other color problems if I switch between
these two the colors look pretty much
correct for the most part right um
although why is that pink
that is purely bizarre
hmm so I think I'm just going to start
with that one and then we'll look at
some of the other bugs tomorrow because
we've had about budgam now uh so in push
let's see they're not push in render
handmade render in clear rectangle it
does look like we're doing the
operations that I would expect to be
correct if that makes sense but I'm not
getting the results that I would expect
to get and so I'm not sure exactly
what's going on there I I think so so
when we do our convert PS epi 32 right
we're expecting the values to be in the
range of 0 to 255 right obviously uh so
I'm not one hundred percent sure though
uh when we do our shipping left so ah so
I think the problem here is just again
the cleverness the problem is these
values actually need to be in the 255
squared range right so although we're
not we don't want to actually square the
values because they're a linear space
they do need to be in the correct actual
range and so what we were doing in our
previous routine and I think this is the
only probably the only bug now I think
about it what we were doing in our
routine before is you know we have to
square the values and the values were to
25 on the value 0 to 25 when we square
those we get 6 5 5 34 or whatever as the
maximum value so given that fact we had
baked in a reduction by 2 15
five into the shift right you can see it
here the way that we were sort of doing
our shift left we're shifting the values
down to put them into the right place
that makes sense
now why why we would do it this way
exactly i'm not sure and it kind of
looks a little bit janky so when we do
this convert EP i'm going to look at the
other i'm going to look at the other
render code as well just look at what
we're doing here so yeah so there's the
squaring right so now it's 65536 and
then we do the square root and and i
think this should be that right so that
goes down to the srgb and then when
we're done and we do the conversion I
would have thought I don't understand
why these ores don't require a mask so
it's basically saying well blue is in
the right position because it's centered
right r has to go up 16 so it's like it
thinks these are 0 to 255 but and I
guess the RS squirt does that ok so I'm
relatively happy with this now I think
that's all correct so I think all we
really had to do was put them in the 65
534 space to begin with then everything
else works properly that makes sense so
I think that's correct let's take a look
at how close we are at the moment will
be a little bit off because we're
squaring not doing actual srgb so we're
pretty good there although why I'd also
like to know why we get we suddenly get
pink when i switch back to this one I
suppose
yeah because that doesn't really make a
whole lot of sense why we would get pink
when we switch back it could actually be
because when we do our render copy there
the texture has a hole in it basically
so I yeah so I guess you know
technically our original clear wants an
alpha of one and our subsequent clear
wants an alpha of not one so really
let's take a look here inside rendered
CPP where we call clear rectangle you
know technically I guess what we do want
to do is something like this actually I
got a better idea I think what we
actually want to do is say hey when we
display a bitmap via OpenGL we just want
to make sure that blending is not on
right so like we want GL disabled GL
blend so and then we can re-enable it
after I think that's actually the more
correct thing because we shouldn't be
blending that bitmap anyway and that's
what was actually happening I believe
there yeah so now we're good to go
alright so let's see what happens is we
hop up ye olde stairs nicely blended so
that's all good and so I think
everything is fine now with a with our
clearing and all that stuff so I think
now our primary thing that we have to to
fix is that we clearly have a bug in the
actual texture fill 4shared for things
that are sheared right so that's got to
get fixed and the other thing that
looked like a problem was the sorting
groups we're looking odd looks like
they're okay here so I guess it's just
when we went up the stairs and of course
we don't have there we haven't finished
this renderer yet we haven't added the
render targets to it so I suppose we
have to go do that at some point before
we can start debugging this by you know
going up the stairs and seeing if that's
where we were having trouble with it but
I just wanted to double check what was
going on there alright so we'll tackle
that bug first which is inside our draw
rectangle quickly
let's see what we've got besides being
out of stuff to drink let's see we have
a bug in our text to look up where we're
not properly to the texel or Phil values
this does seem true we're taking a look
at unnormalized so this these are just
normalized versions of our axes so
they're their versions that point in the
same direction as the axes point but
with without without having the length
right and so that's this is just that's
a seems totally reasonable not not
really a problem and the fill region is
computed from the original axes and that
looks like what exactly what I would
have expected so let's take a look in
here and see where we're actually using
these so when we do our U and V lookups
what we're doing there is we're
multiplying the axis normal x by
whatever the i assume that's where the
pixel yeah wherever we are on Y so we're
basically producing measurements along
the normalized axes now why we're
producing measurements along the
normalized axes I'm not one hundred
percent sure
because it seems like what you would
want to be doing is producing them
instead along the universe scaled so
those actually aren't normalized per se
that's the y-axis length over the x-axis
length so it's actually like a very
strange that's a very strange thing to
be computing right we're baking in we're
baking in a normalization of the X but
then a scale by the Y by however long
the Y is and then similarly the other
way around we're doing a like a scale in
the opposite direction so we're
basically exchanging the lengths of our
axes we're making the x-axis be as long
as the y axis and the y axis as long as
the x axis is what we're actually
accomplishing here why we wanted to do
that I don't know this is we're going
back and watching the video would
probably help so be like oh that's why I
wanted to do that and so in here where
I'm saying how I'm computing the values
it looks like i'm taking where the pixel
is in y relative to the origin and then
I'm sort of finding out where it is on
those two sort of weird axes I assume
those were directly the axes yet they
are so I'm measuring it along those and
I'm saying that the U and V values are
you know our mappings into those sort of
odds faces
that just doesn't seem I don't like that
seems wrong to me and we know that it is
wrong I guess because we're looking at
it being wrong but I'm also not sure why
we like what were we trying to do with
that do we remember like that doesn't
really make a whole lot of sense that
doesn't really make a whole lot of sense
to me at all so what I would have
expected to see right is I would have
expected to see something where I was
mapping into the you space by
multiplying by dot product with with a
you know dot product thing with an axis
that was designed to give me back a
number from 0 to 1 along my myself which
would have been yeah I don't I don't get
it so what I would have expected this to
be here is like instead of the x axis
being like y axis length over x axis
length I would have expected it to be
like you know that being unnormalized x
axis and then because i have a
normalized x axis but i know that the
thing is going to run further than that
what I actually want to do is divide by
it again right so that is I think what I
would have expected to see and and I
wish I knew why I didn't see that right
I would expect you to see something like
that and you can see right here I did
index axis legs for it that's that's
this this right here is exactly what I
was expecting Oh
whoa that's freaky ha okay all right I'm
going to get rid of this stuff I'm just
I'm just going to delete this okay thank
God that makes a lot more sense so in
faxes length squared is there we go so
so that it looks like I just kind of
psyched myself out there by having some
weird old vestigial code that that is
not what I wanted at all so yeah in vex
axis length squared times x axis for
this guy that actually makes a lot more
sense to me so that's all good there we
go all right so at least now I'm not
looking at something that looked like it
was it was kind of out in left field so
now let's try to look at like obviously
that was not correct so let's try to
figure out what went wrong here in our
reasoning because it looks pretty
straight forward like
you know it it looks like computing that
dot product is pretty alright what I
suspect is that I must have a I haven't
thought through whether I could take the
dot product when the two things get skew
like that it may be that I can't and and
I have to be a little bit more I have to
take some extra terms into account it
looks like we're almost out of time so i
won't work that out on the whiteboard
today but that's what we'll do tomorrow
and basically just to point out what I'm
talking about so when you have two
orthogonal basis right and I'm talking
about a point in here I can measure it
here and I can measure it here and
that's how I was getting basically the U
and V coordinates I was saying here's a
point inside you know this box and I
want to measure these two now if these
are both unit vectors then it's just the
dot product right of the point and it's
fine but we know that they're not right
they actually have some length so
they're actually some however long they
are right this is the length of the
y-axis that we pass in this is the
length of the x axis that we pass in and
so when we dot product on them we're
going to get you know if this is my PX
here we're going to get the dot product
of these two things if I didn't modify
the access right we know it's equal to
sort of the the length of each of these
vectors like the PX x length of X right
times cosine of the angle between them
these two values in here I like this one
right I want to know how far along I am
on this on this thing for sure but I
don't like this one and the reason for
that is because now however long this is
I want my you value my U and V values to
be in the range of 0 to 1 right but now
I'm getting this this thing in here
that's actually going to multiply as you
go further out it's going to make it
worse and worse right so that's why I
was doing the one over the length of x
squared is because i was using the
this dot product to bake in the
normalization from zero to one right to
counteract this and then also divided by
X so I would end up with this which is
what I actually wanted right I was
trying to end up with that now that
works just fine when things are
orthogonal but the question is when I
start passing in things that aren't so
suppose I've got something that looks
like this right well now any motion in X
or Y is actually going to affect my
location potentially on both of these
axes right because this is my projection
oops because this is my projection here
and this is my projection here and so
when I move in why I'm actually moving
in both U and V space and when I move
here I'm moving in both you the few NV
space and that's correct meaning that is
what should be happening but we don't
know if we did the math correctly to
actually get the correct thing to happen
right we may have to create different
basis vectors or a different math
operation to actually do that mapping so
that's what we'll have to do tomorrow
let's go ahead and go with Q&amp;A
crystal him a year earlier when the pink
color showed up that was the color you
use long ago when you were setting up to
the open jilla render yeah but I was
confused as to why we were getting it
right I know that's you know that's the
pink that's like hey there's a problem I
didn't know why so let me just briefly
explain why it was happening so the
reason it was happening is we have a
OpenGL like back buffer right and when
we do the software renderer we were
previously making a completely solid
bitmap because our clear set the Alpha
21 right so everywhere in here the Alpha
value was one there were no holes in it
so when we then drew it using OpenGL to
the OpenGL back buffer it didn't leave
any space but now what we're doing is
when we clear that where we were
clearing that back buffer I was clearing
the Alpha 20 which meant that if this is
what you actually filled in when you
drew the back buffer this was actually a
now an alpha hole where alpha was 0 so
when it then went to draw to the screen
whatever was in the back buffer to begin
with whatever was there a hole would be
left when this got blended onto it right
allowing stuff to show through that was
not the clear color so that was just
that was just because when we did that
but that's happening now there the
solution to that was I was like well I
don't want the blip to actually take
that into account so what does i did is
i turned off blending so now there's no
more blending on the blit which means
that alpha holes don't show through
right it's not using the Alpha to do
anything and that's you know sort of a
better situation I suppose
thus Isaac are the py n X and V
calculations correct I don't know we're
going to have to look at them tomorrow
and see they might be wrong well we know
they're wrong we just don't know how
they're wrong I mean they're obviously
wrong because they're picking their own
texture coordinates
as far as the vectors go for movement
can you just add U and V to get the new
movement no we have to have u and V
calculated separately because they look
up into a texture map Brian me wag could
normal maps be render targets here with
appropriate enums branching to blend and
light or do they still belong outside
the current render targets array well
normal maps would be part of the sprite
they wouldn't really be render targets
they would just be like an art asset
right that gets loaded in along with the
sprite like whatever its normal map is
so I don't think it would really
implicate render targets unless you're
talking about something else relisted
one do you think you could transform
this game into a network game that
multiple players can have different
kinds of character assets yes obviously
we can I mean you can transform any game
into that and if yes what you consider
doing it no networking is not going to
be covered on handmade hero i kind of
said that at the outset and that's just
something i'm not going to be doing this
isaac as saying it looks like there
might be an XY swap in those two
variables uh you think I feel like an XY
swap a straight-up XY swap is unlikely
because if there was our characters
would be coming out rotated 90 degree
well you know flipped like that so it
can't be a straight up it has to be a
little bit more complicated than that
right
Brian wag I'm comparing it to deferred
rendering which I'm excellent uh so in
yeah we are not a deferred render path
so if you're doing deferred rendering
then you every you have to have a render
target for basically every possible
property that you need to have for your
final lighting equation so you might
need a specular power place in the
render target a normal map you know you
might have to have text material index
all these sorts of things right so so
yeah deferred rendering path is very
different and you have a lot more render
target space depending on how much you
can afford right and you tend to pack a
bunch of stuff into those render targets
and then you do a final pass on the
screen where you look up and diretta
tart to get all that stuff just a one
you should be you should do networking
you could charge for extra items or
levels thus making a reliable stream of
money no I don't think so thus Isaac I
mean you you use an X variable where you
meant to Y verbal yeah I mean we'll find
out tomorrow obviously you know that
would be nice if it's that simple but I
suspect it's more about the the
underlying concept of doing the dot
products that way is probably not right
once you start to once you start to skew
that would be my assumption but
I'm you can see here it's pretty basic
right you've got the pixel p y value and
you compute the dot product of basically
that the component of the dot product of
the x and the y with the py right and
then in the next phase you compute the
component of the dot product that's the
X you know I mean and you add it to the
one that you had before to get a
complete dot product so I don't think
there's a lot of room for error in that
I mean that looks like it's doing the
math up correctly so I will find out but
I feel like it's it's the it's the math
is conceptually wrong therefore sku if
that makes sense i think that so so all
right let me I guess I'll just give a
brief explanation of why my intuition
says that that's the case so if I have
essentially what we're talking about
here is we're talking about when you
have two basis vectors like this right
and here is my Y basis vector here's my
ex basis vector right and I want to know
what the UV coordinates for this thing
are something that expresses that in as
if this were a texture you know that was
warped kind of on here then essentially
what i'm trying to do is I'm trying to
invert this matrix problem in some sense
right what I'm trying to do is I'm
saying well I had you know something
like this
let's say that and now I have this right
and what I want to know is I want to
know where this thing was in the
original space right and so these two
vectors here they form my a matrix
essentially right that's that's what
they're effectively doing and I
basically have this problem right and so
what I need to do is I need to do that
to solve for the original point and
we're not actually doing that inversion
we're just we're just transposing
basically right and so I think the
problem is there's we actually need to
invert that matrix for real the matrix
that is you know the x-axis and the
y-axis sort of a thing I guess I should
say that right and I think basically
what we're doing now is is this which is
wrong but again only when you're skew
right it's wrong only a few skew because
otherwise the matrix is orthogonal in
which and therefore you can do this
because for an orthogonal matrix the and
i don't mean orthonormal matrix I mean
orthogonal 1 over the length of the
vectors like if the we normalize those
vectors 1 over the square of the of the
vector length when we produce the
transpose matrix then we'll do the right
thing as long as all you're doing is
scaling and I know this is confusing
because we haven't covered matrix math
but I'll go over it tomorrow when we
actually to solve this bug because i'm
pretty sure that this is the problem so
i think i need to go do a better math
for that what is the blackboard software
using it's called milton looks like
someone gave you the
that link already so on nub three sock
asked if you would consider local
multiplayer we already support local
multiplayer I guess maybe you haven't
weren't here since the earlier days of
the stream but you can join as many
people as you want on the same machine
right now right now like if you just
plug in an Xbox controller and push the
start button a second hero will appear I
don't think the game the eventual game
will not support local multiplayer
because the game design doesn't support
local multiplayer it's not a multiplayer
game but the engine handles it just fine
may blow ass speaking of normal maps
could we have used those to help sort
the sprites I know they don't give you
3d data but is there anything in there
that we could leverage I mean yeah maybe
I mean a normal map does sort of have
some correlation to depth it's not uh
it's not exactly right but you know it's
it's not nothing so i guess i'm not sure
how to answer that exactly i would
suspect that it's probably not worth
trying to do it at least not for this
game maybe for other games but even in
other games i suspect that it's still
just not really the information you need
you know you really more need a depth
map and you also need a scale value to
let you know how that depth map
corresponds to the actual world but yeah
it's interesting idea I just don't know
that it's can really be put into
practice that much because basically a
normal map is that is it you know you
could think of it almost as like a
derivative the derivative of a depth map
but what you actually use the debt map
and you don't have a way to integrate
the normal map back up to a depth map
because you don't know how much I you
know you don't really know anything
about where the surface started or
anything like that but you could try you
know you could integrate a normal map up
and see it I don't know it sounds like
it would be a lot of work for not a lot
of payoff but that doesn't mean it
wouldn't work you know you just have to
right thing the base who does an
integration integrates the normal map
and goes from there so
alright
I'm going to wrap it up thank you
everyone for joining me for the episode
of handmade hero it's and a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home you can
know we use peer to the game on handmade
here org and it comes with the source
code yeah so you can play around and
experiment with it we also have a forum
site we can go to ask questions a
patreon page you can go to if you want
to support our video series a schedule
bot that tells you when the series is
going to be live in case you want to
catch it when it's on and we also have a
episode guide that you can go to to
catch up on old episodes that's about it
for today I'll be back to last few more
the week tomorrow at eight p.m. pacific
daylight time i believe until then
everyone have fun programming and i'll
see you on internet take it easy
everyone