hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Shira the show where we code a complete
game live on Twitch we are coding some
interface code right now we're coding
some UI some user interface only this is
actually not user interface for the game
it's user interface for the developer we
are trying to make a few little UI
elements that we can use when we are
running the game in sort of our
development mode so that we can do
things like you know if we want to edit
values or we want to toggle things on
and off work be able to select what we
are trying to view in our profiler was
kind of one of the things that you know
motivated us to do this particular thing
that we're doing with the UI elements
and so we implemented a simple radial
control yesterday and got most of the
way through actually doing it I mean
it's it's it's functional it's just not
particularly pretty and so today what
I'd like to do is kind of build out that
build that out a little bit more kind of
like look at maybe doing in addition to
a radial sort of pick style thing also
maybe some listing and those sorts of
things so again I'm kind of just gonna
go for a little bit I'm just gonna like
make some more UI stuff as we go and
then you know at some point and I may do
some of it today I mean not again this
is it's entirely flexible it's just
based on taste sort of as I come through
different parts of the program what I
feel like should be the next logical
step based on what I'm looking at we may
start to sort of pull out the radial
control stuff into something that's
that's a little cleaner and more useable
because right now it's just kind of a
hard-coded thing that we did to just see
how to code it in general I may start
pulling that out or I may leave that for
a little bit later I may hard-code a
bunch of different UI element things and
then see them kind of operating together
and then start to pull them out into a
more reasonably architected thing so I
don't know we'll see when I feel when I
am feeling comfortable as I look at it
when when I'm feeling comfortable that
enough is there to start doing that kind
of piecing
out that is when I'll start so we're
here on day one 92 if you want to follow
along at home and you have pre-ordered
the game on Hamid org
you can unpack day 191 a source code
that's what I'm starting with
that is what I am starting with so
here's where we were at when we stopped
yesterday you can see that there's
actually sort of this radio-control
thing here and it's it's like I said we
did all the basic work teams a minute
but it's still kind of ugly like that
you know the things can can kind of
overlap each other and there's no way to
not pick something right now right so we
just whichever one the cursor is closest
to that's the one I picked so this would
not be like a particularly great control
we also haven't lined these things up in
any way that's particularly intelligent
so you know like I said there's plenty
of stuff that we would want to do here
but it's already working so if I want to
I could just do kind of a nice right
swipe there does the toggle profile
graph write a diagonal up swipe right
and you can see I don't even have to
think about it to pick it's just a nice
muscle memory thing so that's kind of
just like it's nice to have radial menus
for that very reason because they're
very fast to use and it's kind of just a
nice little user interface element to
have again real simple I mean you saw me
implement it and I don't know maybe 40
minutes I'm not sure what total extreme
time we spent out of yesterday's stream
doing it but again 40 minutes to
implement a basic thing and we could
clean this up a little bit more in
another 20-30 minutes to make it look a
little nicer and behave a little nicer
so you know you're talking about an hour
and a half of total dev time or
something like that even if you're
starting from almost nothing as long as
you have a way to just output some text
you can make one of these and again
they're pretty handy so I'm gonna go
ahead and start thinking about this up
through a little bit more just trying to
think about what we're kind of going to
need here in terms of other UI things
just so I can kind of put some of that
out there and like I said before I don't
really like to try and anticipate what
I'm gonna need for stuff so what I might
do what I think might be kind of a smart
way to approach this problem
is to kind of go back in look at the
debug code we've already done because
we've already had a plenty of times
where we if zero things out and we add
little debug overlays and stuff on to
things that we just kind of did in the
code in fact if you look we've got a
we've got this yellow border right
there's a yellow border running around
the screen and that yellow border all
that is is a thing to let us know that
we've lined everything up exactly it's a
thing that says where this where the the
screen should be and we also had a thing
that let us like zoom the camera out so
we've had like tons of debug things that
we've written as part of getting all of
the engine stuff done to the point where
we wanted it to be right we've done all
that stuff and so the question is how
can we go ahead and make that be a more
sort of fundamental fundamentally
accessible kind of a thing where all of
those options are going to be kind of
easy to for us to get to what I you know
my my kind of dream scenario it's like
you just click the right mouse button or
something right and you get access to
all that debugging but there's gonna be
way more there than could possibly just
be listed flat on the screen certainly
more that can be in a radial menu but
even if we had you know sort of stuff
all over the screen it's probably gonna
take a little bit of thought so what I
think I might do in fact now that I'm
even talking it through I think that
kind of sets the stage even maybe even
before I implement any more of the
actual UI stuff maybe I'm gonna go
through and figure out what is a good
way to make those things turn on and off
and let me pull that out because I was
thinking about that the other day I was
kind of thinking on how me here I was
like we should tie into the debug system
a way to kind of turn off and on these
sort of debug system so you know maybe
I've changed my mind maybe I want to do
that first
and start to pull those things out into
the debug system proper so that we can
kind of see how that that's gonna work
right I think that's that that would be
my preference okay
so let's take the most simple example
that I can think of so far which is that
in handmade render group right we had
this concept that the camera could be
pulled back in sort of a debug way if I
remember correctly there was sort of
this this concept of a debug camera and
so the way that this worked is
everything still used the camera
entirely consistently right so it was
exactly the same as it used to be there
was nothing there's nothing that changed
the only difference was that if I if I
let came in here you know and I changed
this guy to an if one it would like
bring everything out oops that's no good
translation unit ah so this is kind of a
little annoying I wonder how much this
will affect our loop live code editing
if we have stuff that changes when we
when we do the reload I wonder if we're
going to get problems here where it
can't use the I wonder I guess I'm
saying is I wonder if when we do the the
reload we're going to have to do
something where we flush because I am
assuming that what happens here is that
if we look at what actually is going on
so we've got opening event opening event
is garbage there well you know what that
does seem this just looks like maybe
regular a straight-up bug just a regular
old bug does it not
how would that why would that have
caused a problem
that's a little tricky because I want to
say like oh well yeah we probably should
whenever we reset the debug system
whenever we do a reload of the code
since all of our marker points all of
our counter places might change
we should flush all of the debug events
right that should be a reset that seems
pretty logical to me however the one
thing I don't want to do is do that and
have that mask a sort of different bug
that we might actually have in here so
it kind of feels like we have some kind
of a different problem so I just want to
take a second to investigate that a
little bit just so I can see and make
sure that there isn't something kind of
more wrong there so you can see like
this first open block is just nonsense
right it's just total totally garbage
from the reload and I guess you know if
you think about to how that's gonna go
since we have incremental frame
processing it does mean that when we do
a code reload it means that the like
these pointers to that that debug memory
are going to kind of get vacated right
because that is a static variable that
lives in there it's also you know again
that's another reason why the counters
are less good because the counters need
to look up into that static variable in
this kind of annoying way so I feel like
it's probably safe at least for the time
being to go ahead and flush that buffer
I feel like that's probably okay and
that's really easy for us to do because
we know when the executable is reloaded
right so when we come in and we've kind
of have our debug frame end happening
here we can if we want to go ahead and
just sort of reset all of the variable
that's really easy to do all we would
really have to do there is is vaporize
the array invent it like our whole array
event index structure like all of those
cat all of the all of accounts right so
if we if we were to look at the handmade
platform dot H where we have the event
array so the event count if all of those
just got vaporized right that would be
sufficient to do the reset I would
assume so if we want to we can just go
ahead and say all right everything if we
need to do a deep you know we'll just do
one here something like this debug reset
or debug event reset set so what we need
to do here is say all of the event
counts in the entire system however many
there are in the global debug table
however many of those there are they all
need to get reset to zero right however
well you know what now I'm thinking
about two though wouldn't why wouldn't
they automatically get set to zero
because since they're in the DLL I feel
like they should already get set to zero
so now that I think about it probably
really we only have to reset we only
have to reset the the incremental frame
processing that's it because yeah so I
think really actually the only thing we
need to do is reset this stuff right we
just need to do restart collation
on that yeah that's all we need to do so
I suppose all we really need to do is
say okay you know in the event after
after we kind of set this stuff up we
can just go ahead and restart the
collation oops just our collation debug
state it's like so so we must do if
we're in the situation where we have
have done a debug reset which I'm
assuming I guess we probably want to put
it in there I am assuming that that's
something that we should just get past
in here right so if we take a look at
platform when we get to game frame end
oops all we're getting right now is the
game memory and I don't know if that
passes it doesn't right so the game
memory doesn't pass whether the
executable was reset whether the
executable was reset is actually passed
in the input right now so I'm gonna go
ahead and move that I think because I
feel like that's something that I
probably want in the memory because
that's the people who would normally
deal with it are probably gonna deal
with it there a little bit more so I'm
just gonna do it here and say okay if
the memory executable reloaded is true
then I restart the coalition so then all
I have to do is I have to go in through
here and make sure that this is going to
be the game memory that gets this set
and I assume game memory yeah okay it's
game memory
and that should do it see how that goes
okay
look at our little handmade hero there
it's awfully cute alright so I'm going
to test this out again and see let's go
ahead Dan happen there's our little
handmade hero kind of running around in
there he's super happy and everything's
fine if I come in here to our render
let's see also about this guy here there
we go consume him in see if we can zoom
back out okay so now we clear that
collation so hopefully and that may be a
bug that you kind of have to catch at
just the right time but hopefully you
can kind of see that we can you know
kind of make that happen
relatively reliably now so what I want
to do is say okay I like the way that's
working right I like more or less how
that's happening and I don't necessarily
know that I want a super change the way
that code works but but one problem I
have is I just don't like having to go
find it right so what I want to be able
to do here is say something you know
like you know if debug UI and then in
here
I put some name so I don't know what the
name exactly would be but you know if
debug you I use debug camera or
something like this so let's say I did
something like that what I'd really like
to do is make it so that actually you
know what happens is when I access the
UI it actually just compiles that code
in or out right so it actually it like
changes the vow that whatever that value
is and then like recompile the code or
something so that it actually so I can
do stuff that actually might be really
expensive and it will just actually
recompile the code did you know what I
mean it won't like leave it in there
necessarily that's kind of what I
actually want to have happen I mean do
you think that's ridiculous do you think
that's too much to ask cuz you have to
admit it's a little tricky it would be a
little tricky to make that work right
but let's see
let's start right let's just start by
making things relatively simple for
ourselves let's say so suppose I have
handmade debug switches or something
like this right or handmade config dot H
maybe right just totally making this up
I've never done this before
I'm just full-on playing around so let's
suppose I were to do that and in this
file I am going to make that equals zero
so now if I were to compile this file
yeah it's going to know that this is is
not going to be used of course it's
knowing that because it hasn't actually
ever seen the config so I need to put
the config probably I probably even want
the config at the top in fact I probably
want it in have a platform so that
everyone sees it right it probably wants
to be the very most like like like the
primal the most primal thing that anyone
actually gets right so handmade config
is like everyone sees it always platform
layer everywhere right
so in handmade config you know it's got
these variables and that's the one for
using the debug camera so now right like
I can go to the handmade config file if
I want to right
and inside here I can make it so that I
just switch you know that on and off and
that works fine right so no problems
there it's all good but the question is
how would I get that out into a UI
element so for example if I wanted to
attach that to the radial menu right how
would I do it
right it's a tough question and and I
guess I would say you know it probably
requires a little bit of finesse I'm
trying to decide whether I should do
this because I think I know the answer
and it's kind of a little banana cakes
but sometimes you got to be banana cakes
on handmade hero I would say so let's
just go ahead and do it let's just go
ahead and say we wanted that to be part
of the UI
well the UI is gonna need to know one
other thing I think probably right just
if we're being realistic the UI is gonna
need to know one other thing and that's
the fact that this was a boolean right
so that's like a b32 you know what I
mean
so it's probably gonna need to know that
this is you know either a 0 or a 1 right
something like this as opposed to some
other defined value which could be
something else entirely if that makes
sense so I feel like I feel like that's
a fairly reasonable thing to do so now
if I wanted to present a UI that had the
thing you know things in it like use
debug camera the only way I could do
that automatically is I would have to
make some way for our game to edit this
file right the game if the UI wanted to
actually do the whole process to produce
they actually change the code at runtime
it would have to edit this file and then
it would have to recompile right that's
just what it would have to do and so in
order to do that I'm pretty sure yeah it
has to kind of rewrite the file now
that's not that big a deal probably if
it would just look like this because
rewriting this file is pretty
straightforward right there's nothing
all that weird
happening there I would think so let's
see if we can just get our our debug
code as it stands right now two
hard-coded rewrite that file for us
right just rewrite that file in its
entirety okay
so if I wanted to do that what I would
do is I would say okay maybe there is a
function here called right hand made
config yeah something like this and it
takes the debug state I don't know
again just guessing and then it's going
to go ahead and use the platform layer
to write the entire file so if I go into
a hand-made platform and I come down
here we have debug right entire file
debug right entire file
where is oops debug write debug platform
write entire file is going to take this
stuff so it's going to take a filename
which we don't really know what that is
yet and then it's going to take the
total size of whatever it is that we're
trying to write yeah
well that shouldn't be too difficult I
suppose at the end of the day let's just
do the most straightforward thing and
you know what this actually dovetails
nicely because we're gonna have to
replace the stuff that does print effing
in standard i/o because we still are
using that so this will be another
reason for that because we would need to
use it here as well so again if we can
just tie everything to just one thing
where we're like we need to replace a
little printf thing then that's kind of
a good impetus to do it so we're not
replacing something just for the one
debug output it actually feels like
maybe there's a little bit more that
we're using there right so what I'm
going to do is I'm going to take the
debug state debug arena
and I'm gonna say that we just have some
room there for writing this file I guess
I don't actually know maybe I'll even do
it a little bit simpler so maybe I'll
just do something like you know temp
here I'm just gonna do the most basic
thing for the moment so if I have
something like that literally if I just
called what we have in this in the what
we were already calling in here right
where is that guy right we've got this
guy here so if I'm already calling that
then I know that as long as I play stat
function then both of these guys will
work so I won't have to worry about
doing extra stuff when I go to replace
that stare and IO dot H include so if I
go ahead and print out to this guy I
know what I would need to print for
replacing this config file I would just
need to print debug you I use camera
like so right and then I would need to
print whatever that value of it was and
I would need to print this be 32
whatever that is and I need to print the
pound to find in front of it
but that would right that would reprint
out what's in that file you know and it
would print it out to this buffer and
then this would tell me how big it was
so this is how this is how much because
this function returns how many things
that output so I could just say write
that whatever you stuck in the temp
write it out to whatever the config file
is and so can made config file name or
something I don't know who knows right
whatever the config file name actually
is so if that's what we're gonna do go
ahead
take a drink there so that what we're
gonna do all we need to do know then is
what the actual state of this thing's
gonna pay for just for the moment I'll
go ahead and take in something that's
like you know use debug camera like so
and now this will print you know either
0 1 depending on what that was set to
and so that will change that
automatically and then we'll write that
and for the moment I'll just our code
this string so that we don't have to
deal with that at the moment but we'll
have to change this just to make sure
that it works on everyone else's machine
although I guess if our bill directory
is relative right if builds if we're
running in handmade data then all we
need to do is go back 1 for code so I
guess all we really have to do is say we
go back 1 go in the code directory and
we rewrite handmade config dot H right
so if I was to do that I guess that
would probably just always work would it
not so we just need our platform here
and I don't remember what the name of
that actually was it so it's just
platform so if I do that that rewrites
the config file right it rewrites the C
file for us so in here if I was to go
through and every time we were to
execute one of these guys right where we
do this sort of nonsense if I were to go
ahead and actually rewrite the config
file here like so for now I'll just
hard-coded to setting it to true that
means every time we do a gesture it'll
rewrite the config file does that make
sense so we can see this in action
presumably already there's handmade duct
config and here I go running I'm gonna
go in here I'm just gonna execute
anything and then I'm gonna close and in
theory now when I reload this you can
see it changed the config file from a 0
to a 1 right so now we've got our
receipt program is writing out its own
self so that it can modify itself
without us having to do anything
complicated like write our own compiler
right so now the only question is how
would we get ourselves to recompile
right because we want to be able to
recompile so let me go ahead and set
that back to zero so we're not using the
debug camera and so what I want to do is
be able to make it so that I execute
that and then it just recompiles itself
right so if I was going to do that how
would I do that
well if I want to do that really what I
need is I need the platform layer to do
something here which I assume is
something like you know execute debug
execute system command right something
like that and presumably what I want to
say is well where is the build normally
run from well all we normally do is in
handmade code we run the build dot bat
right we just run that thing so in that
same way I could say go to this
directory run build duck bat except it's
a little bit trickier than that because
technically it's not build not bat that
we're running because build up at is a
batch file right technically what we're
doing is we're running CMD write CMD is
the command-line interpreter I did see
windows write system 32 probably right
that's what we're actually running and
so if I wanted to run that I could tell
that hey I need you to execute that
build dot bat and presumably it would oh
I think you need a command-line switch
there right like minus K something like
that I don't remember
is there a switch let's see curiously
the commands for the string and then
terminates so /c is what it is looks
like let's try that so if I did /c build
bat so there it is right that built and
then if we were to execute oh and it
sorry it auto execute so I didn't need
to exit right so just /c build that bat
is really the only thing that we need to
do right we can just run command deck
dot exe and tell it hey I need you to
run build that bat so if we had a way of
saying
I need you to execute this system
command in this directory please that
would make our stuff work and so the
question is can we do that and of course
obviously if things can execute system
commands there must be a way to do it
and of course in win32 there actually is
I mean you know right so if I wanted to
go ahead and expand our platform layer
slightly here to say that there's going
to be some kind of a debug think you're
we're in addition to all these other
things we have debug platform you know
execute system command something like
that debug platform execute system
command and again that's going to take
sort of the the path the command and the
command line right and presumably I
guess if we return to bool through -
that's like whether well you know what
it could I think most system commands
typically return like like an S 32 like
an int error code so maybe maybe we'll
get that back I don't really know but so
we'll try that and then what I'll do is
I'll say okay that debug platform
execute system command thing I'm just
gonna go ahead and and inside like one
of these guys here so I don't know like
a platform API where we have all the
rest of stuff and it's gonna say debug
execute system command is gonna be in
there so at that point everything would
work if we had this magical thing that
actually would do debug execute system
command so we just have to figure out
some way to do that yeah in win32 right
so there's our texture system and
platform right entire file like that
so debug execute system command here we
are and I don't even remember how to do
this in Windows win32 execute system
command let's see how we do that system
function shell execute is not really
what we want see if they got this here
create process is probably what we want
actually I know that I think about it
yeah I think create process is probably
what we want I don't think she'll
execute is what we want because she'll
execute goes to the shell and that's
more for like I want to open a file you
know the way Explorer would open a file
which doesn't seem particularly useful
to me so I think we probably just want
to do create process that seems like the
better thing to do mmm that's what I
would say so if we're gonna do create
process that's gonna return us the
success or the failure there so here we
go we've got application name we've got
all this stuff here so the application
name we know what that is right that's
gonna be one of the things that we got
passed in here right so let's take a
look that's gonna be command of the
command line we have it's this process
attributes I have no idea what that even
means those are security attributes so
let's just say that that's null for now
cuz I don't really know what it should
be
thread attributes again these are just
security attributes we don't probably
care about those inherit handles is
whether it will inherit are like
printing and that's rest up I don't
think I want to do that yet if we do it
at all right
we have DW creation flags what are the
creation flags this friend let's see
creation flags screen also controls the
new processes priority class for a list
of values if another protocol says the
process normal that's what we want I
don't think we need anything besides
normal so let's see here do we care
about any of these separating suspended
debug process I don't think we need any
of these so I think that's probably just
a zero
I don't think we have any flags that
could be wrong I don't think so we don't
need to change the environment it can
just use the calling processes
environment yes I would think I guess
I'd have to yeah I think that's fine
yeah
current directory we know what that is
that's this path here the startup info
let's see can this be no important just
startup info or a startup info e^x is
there anything in so we do need one of
these guys it looks like and then
process information receives a handle
about the new process so we need a
startup info let's see what's in there
and a process information ok it seems to
be off by one here that's a bit of a
mistake
so startup info do I really can't I just
get this from somewhere do I really need
to fill all that out that seems like a
lot
response we're ensuring the standard
handle feels these fields yeah I don't
know create process they're a good
example creating processes I want to see
what they say if I actually have to do
all that startup info oh it looks like
it's going to take care of it for me if
I just pass all zeros it looks like it's
fine that's what they're doing here so
that should be pretty easy looks like if
I just initialize those two to nothing
and then I need to make sure I set the
startup info I think it had a size one
of those things we have to set the size
as Windows loves to do one of the
dumbest API decisions so stupid but yeah
so the Seabee structure has to be set to
the size of
info and I don't know if process info
also has that but I suspect that it does
not but let's take a look yes oh that's
fine
so there we go we're just going to call
create process there and for now I'm
just going to return the result of zero
because we're not even going to wait for
the process to finish but we'll probably
add that so we'll just do something here
where we have liked it if so we know
that we will do something to do wait for
completion and get return code probably
but let's take a look I think we had 15
minutes left on the clock so we probably
have about 20 minutes left right now
so d-box might actually commands too few
arguments for call is that really true
really I think there are three there so
I must have typed made a typo down here
and let's take a look d boobs go away
you next thing I can't see I'm not you
next thing handmaid hear a thing I can't
see my mini buffer fade away fade away
five-minute warning needs to fade away
alright it's not fading away execute
system command debug askew system
command debug platform boots platform
execute system
oh I was just missing a comma that's all
alright um so this needs to be that was
a typo that needs to be executed system
command okay so I don't know what this
is gonna do they're probably not quite
ready yet but I'll go ahead and test it
so here we are and we go ahead and
toggle something and it does not appear
to have actually we compiled anything
right at least I don't I don't see
anything so we probably did rewrite the
file because that was working just fine
that's in config so I'm guessing that
got changed right but we didn't
recompile and so what I want to do is
see why we didn't compile right so debug
execute system command I want to go
ahead and see what happens if I step in
there here we go right and I've got the
command as command eggsy I've got the
command line C build up bat I've got all
this stuff set to nothing start up in
fair process info I'm gonna go ahead and
run I want to see if anything happened
so we got back false so that didn't work
and so basically we just have a bug in
the way we're calling this we're
probably not specifying something
correctly so what I'm gonna do is see if
I can get a little bit more error
information from Windows in the case
where it goes wrong right and so get
last error is the way Windows does their
reporting it's super janky and not
particularly fantastic but you go in
here and you say get last error and it
returns you a D word that tells you what
the error was so if we do this we can
then you know look at what the error
actually is just I yeah you know I'm
gonna have to put so it doesn't go out
of scope because the visual studio
debugger is so awful I gotta just kind
of do something with it there so that we
can actually see it but if I set this
breakpoint and we run the game I should
be able to step in there and and see
what happens so there we go
here is the error code the error code is
two and there's a little convenient
tool I think usually here error lookup
you can put in the two and hit lookup
cannot find the file specified so I'm
guessing that it's just not in the path
for some reason I'm not sure but if
that's the case that's pretty easy to
solve right if that's the case we can
just do something like this right and
say could you go run that please right
now the other thing too that I don't
actually know is I don't know whether
this needs to be back slashed as well so
maybe I'll just try that for us just to
make sure yeah all right so let's see
what happens if I give it a more
explicit path to the file the
interpreter and we'll see if that works
so it actually does appear to work right
that seems like it is running our build
just fine
would you agree so given the fats the
case now that we have that compiling
what I'll probably do is just say okay
let's go ahead and actually make that
feature work because why not
so if I come in here and I do something
like again I'm just sort of showing give
getting the sort of basic stuff out
there so if I have something in here
that's going to track what this variable
actually should be I guess now I think
about it all I really have to do I don't
even really need a variable all I really
need to do is just say hey whenever you
go to write this thing out right and
hand-made debug that cpp just write out
whatever you had in your config file
right just write out the opposite of
that
so that'll do a toggle right so now
every time that I want to switch I
should be able to switch and it will
compile right like this and you can see
now we can actually switch between them
so now we basically have sort of like
uber uber debug UI in the sense that now
we actually don't even have to have any
runtime cost for our debug stuff at all
they can literally be compiled out
completely and we can still toggle them
at runtime while the game is running and
not have to actually do anything at all
right it's the it's the perfect it's
like you get the perfect everything
right now one thing that's a little
annoying there that's you know that's
not probably not the best thing in the
world is that annoying kind of pop-up
that sort of happens there so what I
would like to do instead I think is
maybe manage that process a little bit
more what I'd like to know is can I just
go ahead and make it so that that thing
doesn't actually pop up an actual window
so I'm gonna I don't know very much
about calling CMD like this like I said
I've never done this before what I'm
doing I'm totally making this up as I go
so if I go in here and I say for CMD
what do you do
let's see so it looks like a hyper file
to be antsy causes the output of
internal transfer of high profile to be
unicode blah blah blah blah blah
none of this stuff looks interesting at
all yeah so what I want to do is I want
to have a little bit more control over
that window so I'm just wondering I
wondering if the startup info stuff
would allow me to do that so if I went
did the startup info thing I wonder if I
can pass something in the startup info
right that would make that not happen so
say for example wmw show window which is
the show window code in Windows I wonder
if I just straight up set that to say
like hi you know like don't show right
don't show the window if it would
prevent the window from pop you would
just leave it minimized which I'd be
fine with right so if we if we did show
window let's see here
right it can be whatever we want this
member can be any of the values that can
be specified in show window so SW hide
should be one of them right so I feel
like that might be a good way just to
start cleaning that up a little bit so
let's go ahead and and look it winds
pretty - handmade let's go in here and
say all right
we we've got the got the startup info so
I'm gonna go ahead and set that value
doo doo doo where'd you go W show window
and I'm just gonna see if that helps us
at all avoid that kind of annoying
window nonsense so it's still showing it
right that is not hiding a window I
don't see that as being a hide at all so
that's kind of annoying why is that the
case why did you not hide the window why
why I asked you oh it's if DW flags so I
have to all sorry I have to also set you
show window okay so I have to also set
you show window in DW flags that seems
easy enough to do let's go ahead and do
that
startup info W flags equals start a few
show window so now will you hide the
window please nice
it's lovely right good how nice that is
okay so what I'd like to do now is since
we're not showing the window we don't
really know if it compiles in progress
or exactly what's happening and we don't
know if there were errors in the compile
or any of that stuff so it might be nice
to kind of make that a little bit just a
little bit better when we actually do
this create process right we're gonna
get back this process info that process
info thing is going to come back to us
so if I look here at process information
we're actually going to get back this
this sort of handle information here
right a handle to the newly created
process this handle is yousef s4 the
process in all functions that perform
operations on the process object right
and IDs and stuff like this so what I
could do after that process information
thing happens is I could look and see if
there's some way to just say hey is this
process still active right like what's
the state of this process because there
should be something on here which allows
me to do that right I don't know what it
is get process maybe there's an is is
process
and maybe query process query I don't
really know I could wait on the process
but I don't really want to do that I
just want something that tells me what
the state of the process is and I'm not
really sure what that would be now maybe
I could do a wait for single object on
the process like we saw before we have
the ability to wait on things so it's
possible that I could do a wait for
single object on a process and then just
give it a timeout of zero seconds right
Oh or is signaled whatever it was there
is one for is signaled right Bank
because again I have a handle of the
process which is itself a windows handle
that I can do checking on just like we
saw when we were working on this before
where it's got this concept of being in
a single state much like the seven-four
isn't that sort of thing so I should be
able to do something like wait on it or
check to see what its state actually is
so is there an azure also is there any
way to just query that guy this is
something I probably should know but
have forgotten actually sorry to say so
if I do
blah-blah-blah-blah-blah reset events at
events bum
unregister wait wait for multiple
objects so wait for single object is
probably all I would really need so if I
did wait for single object it would
return to me whether that object was
signal signaled right so what I could do
is just pass the handle and and then see
so I'm gonna I'm just gonna see what
happens here
if I do wait for single object so I'm
gonna do wait for single object I'm
gonna pass the object that I got so that
is gonna be in my process info and I
think it just called H process for
americlean and I'm safe for the
millisecond i'ma say infinite so I'm
just gonna have the game lock up until
the compile is done that's what I'm
hoping will happen here I don't really
know right so here we go that's a good
sign perfect okay so if that's the case
that means I should be able to check to
see if it's actually true let's see what
the what does the D word supposed to
return to me let's see here remarks
where's return value if it succeeds I'm
going to the event that caused the
function return it can be one of the
following values weight object zero okay
so what we want to do is we want to say
if weight person's about object equals
weight object zero then and we can also
pass zero here then we know that this
thing finished right so what I'm gonna
do is I'm gonna give the debug system a
way of actually managing that process
sort of saying is the compiled like
what's the status of the compile right
like what's happening what's happening
down there in that compile in that
compiled so what I want to do is I want
to say that there's some other thing
happening here which is like a debug you
know process something like that a debug
executing process something like that
and it's gonna have a return code and
it's you know it's gonna have like a
bool like is it running you know I'm
saying
and so what that'll do and and and I
guess what we'll say is and did it did
it
started successfully you know like was
it able to actually start the process is
is it running now and then when it's not
running anymore you could check the
return code something like that and so
when you actually do this execute system
command it will return you one of these
and so what I can do is I can say here
is that process to me and we can also
stick in here something like an OS
handle thing because everyone's going to
be either in a 64-bit integer and ensure
of something like that so we should be
able to also just make sure that we can
always just stuff it in there so we
don't have to do anything fancier like a
pointer where we'd have to allocate
memory for no real good reason right
okay so if I have one of these now I've
got a different kind of result it's
coming back so in here what we do is
we'd say if we got in here then we
started it successfully so that's true
and then we have the result is running
it's also going to be equal to true you
know now that I think about it if this
is gonna be a query sort of a situation
that's not actually what I would do I
guess it's really more like this type
def struct debug executing process
actually is just a handle probably and
this is a debug process State and it
returns these sorts of things I would
assume is more the situation right and
so this OS handle will just be set to
like an invalid handle value if things
don't work that be my Debbie my guess
right and so what we do is say debug
platform get system command state or
something or get process state
and you just pass this executing process
handle back that's what I think so yeah
in here you would get a debug process
state back and you'd pass debug
executing process in like so and then
when you do get the process state form
process state you can find out you know
if it's still running or what's going on
right that seems reasonable for now
that's the basic the basic okay so debug
executing process pure if you get in
cure to the starting successfully bit
and all that kind of stuff I'm gonna go
ahead and actually just make this stuff
happen as well because we kind of know
exactly what this is gonna do now I
already just said exactly what's gonna
do so we've got debug get process state
so so what I want to do is that's going
to go in here like this
and what's going to happen is right here
when we call create process that's when
we would know that we can set the OS
handle equal to whatever the process
info each process is so we can store it
for later right something like that so I
guess we actually so I don't really know
how to maybe convert I guess what we
would probably want to do is do this the
other direction so we probably want to
just assert that whatever size our OS
handle is it's greater than or equal to
whatever the size of this thing is so we
know we can store it properly and then
we probably want to do it actually like
this right we're just gonna say like
romp into that memory whatever the H
process is we don't care how big it is
as long as it fits just fit it in
and that'll be fine if that doesn't
happen then what we'll do is set result
OS handle equal to invalid handle value
and so then I think we're all good
at least I think okay say the reason why
we wouldn't be so then when we come in
here we would know that this thing that
we need to do do by process State result
all we would need to do there is say
okay first of all if if the OS handle
that we'd get so if the process OS
handle if that equals invalid handle
value then we know that the result
started successfully is false
in fact old we know all that stuff is
zero so we just leave it as it is so
basically it's only if it's not people
to enhance invalid handle value that we
would go through with it and assuming
that it's not we can then look and say
okay if we if we go ahead and say the
process to me OS handle pass that back
to Windows say is this still running
if Windows says it's not running then we
can close the handle here because we
don't need to deal with the handle
anymore right we could just get rid of
it and and waste I think that seems
reasonable
I don't know if we want to do that we
may want to release the handle in sort
of a different way that's that's a tough
call it's a tough call I'm gonna do it
this way for now but to do do we want a
formal release mechanism here probably
debug code doesn't really matter but so
anyway we'll go ahead and close this up
effect I'll I'll go ahead and and do get
the H process back bear more explicitly
there it is so assuming that we get back
with the fact that it's been signaled
then we kind of know what happened here
we know that it well we know in either
case it started successfully and we also
know that it's running now or I should
say it's running if we don't lock on it
in this case we know that it has stopped
running it's completed so we want the
return code I don't know if we can do I
think there's something like get exit
code or something like that that we can
do like get process exit code there
should be some way we can get the exit
code so get-get-get where is it
hello no rush there okay so if we pass
the process it'll give us back the exit
code so that's cool
I think that's what we want so basically
we say is here's the exit code actually
I guess we just do this
code zero turn code and then we'll just
assume that that goes okay what it's
it's fine don't worry about it
all right so if that's where we're at I
think that's mostly implemented for the
most part for the most part oops we need
a debug executing process and debug
process State and so I'm almost that
time I am out of time I got a stop codon
it's too bad this kind of fun thing to
do and wanted to kind of finish but you
know what are you gonna do all right so
let's go ahead here and make that work
that way as well so that it doesn't
complain about my little shuffle
typecasting doing my little thing and
dancing around and so on and here we can
do the same thing so we just go each
process and that is that so now what we
can do is we can do something like in
the debug system we can have we can keep
one of these so we hand may platform we
have the debug process state we can have
the compiler you know or something is
there
oops I didn't mean that I mean give a
executing process like so and what I can
do is I can say initialize this maybe
we'll just say compiling as a thing and
there's the handle of the compiler so
then what I'll do is when we launch one
of those we know the compiling is
normally set to false when we go ahead
and set that up
when we do a right hand made config and
we do our execute debug command what
we'll do is we'll say debug state
compiling equals true I'm also gonna do
it here where I say if debug state
compiling it's not equal to true
or I should say if not compiling I don't
want to launch two compilers then we set
it equal to true we step set the
compiler we put a platform debug system
okay
and so in theory now what should happen
is when I do this it will only let us
compile once right because we set it and
we never clear it so now it did one
compile and now if I do another compile
it should not do anything and that's
what it does right so what I want to do
now is I just want to take one more step
like I said coming into this so I sorry
I went if I'm going like three or four
minutes over here but now when I've got
that and I know it's compiling what I
can do is when I when I'm printing out
debug text here write this this sort of
thing debug text align what I can do is
at the top of this right I can do
something where I sort of say like oh
hey you know if a debug state compiling
then I want to in here get the status of
that I want to do I want to find out the
process state so I want to I want to
figure out what that state is so I want
to do a platform debug process state and
I want to pass it the compiler and if
the state is running
then I'm just gonna print out a debug
text sign this just says compiling you
know me if it's not then that's done so
we're done with the process and I can I
can set compiling to false
you know I mean seems pretty reasonable
to me nothing too bizarre going down
there a platform API doesn't have that
oh man it doesn't totes
right man you are totes right about that
let's fix that
where am i platform API OTT where it at
sorry used slang there that's not good
kids you should talk in regular English
okay so debug get processed state groups
so debug get process states happening
and I'm gonna go ahead and where is that
stuff API it is
get process state so now I should be
able to actually compile and in theory
now the compiler runs as a subset of our
game and there it is compiling and now
it's done compiling done beautiful
beautiful so that's pretty awesome I
would say because the stuff that we are
about to be able to do with that is
gonna be kind of off the chain if I
don't mind saying I have never done that
before I don't know why but this is
about to get pretty real here
tomorrow's gonna be a pretty crazy day I
have a feeling but I'm gonna stop there
so we can take a few minutes of
questions
all right folks let's do this
send me your questions Q : please
powers c9k why be able to compile from
the game if we can do it from the editor
is it just to be cool well being cool is
definitely a good idea I I wouldn't
necessarily knock that as a reason but
it's so that we can just not have to tab
back and forth right it's like if I'm
running the game and I'm trying to work
on something here right and I want to do
some UI thing it's cut you know and I
want to turn something on and off I'd
rather not have to then tab you know go
like this recompile tab back and then
finish what I was doing right I want to
be able to just do stuff and have an
update now like I said I've never really
done it before so maybe it turns out to
not be that useful or something but I
just feel like that's kind of a cool way
to do a debug switch instead of actually
having the debug switches always be
actually all compiled in and actually
doing branches all over the place to
decide whether or not they're going to
execute CRO hell dragon compile and mr.
fourths editor and do all the game
development work from in-game yeah I
would love it if if mr. forest editor
was a thing that you could just kind of
compile in to your stuffer or there's
like a deal all you just call that would
be pretty awesome
and I see I like how it started info and
process underscore information
inconsistency even in a single small
part of the one API do such things
annoying you in a professional API you
know those things might annoy me if it
weren't for the fact that there's so
much other busted stuff you know that is
a pretty small thing if that was the
worst thing I would actually be really
happy so so that sort of stuff you know
it would it would only annoy me if we
got rid of all the things that are
absolutely horrifically bad that are
separate from that it's a pretty
low-hanging thing
mr. fourth-dimension why are we writing
to a code file instead of just passing -
D - the build line seems like it would
be a little easier although I have to
admit you made that look pretty easy the
reason is because it's about to get a
lot more complicated than that and
they'll probably be like 200 of those
and they probably will have all things
like strings in them or expressions and
stuff that might be annoying to try to
quote properly for passing to the shell
and might overflow size buffers or who
knows what right so a code file I know I
can do anything with and also it means
that I they get remembered for like the
next build that happens outside you know
what I mean because like those settings
I want to potentially persist if that
makes sense
zebra Caleb why not use system instead
of create process so system if I'm not
mistaken is in the C runtime library
probably I don't actually know
yeah systems in the C runtime library
and so like I said I don't really want
to use any libraries on handmade here
like the final game I'd like to ship no
libraries at all and right now the only
thing that prevents us from saying we're
already there is the C runtime library
so I feel like I want to remove it and
so if I want to minimize the number of
things that we call in there so that
it's as easy as possible to remove it
and so it was since it was free for me
to use create process I didn't use
system because it wouldn't take me any
it didn't really take me any longer I
mean it maybe it would have saved five
or ten minutes but it makes it so I
don't have to use the C runtime library
because like I said the end goal frame
made here we already really only don't
use any libraries that are external but
we do still linked with the compilers
library and I'd like to not even link
with that when we get to the end
gleamin 16:05 do you plan on reading the
original config file and then rewriting
with modified values yes
thus Isaac why not just set a boolean
variable instead of recompiling a pound
to fine because now we have no
performance overhead so for example we
can put tons of debug code everywhere in
our game including and here's the
spoiler alert including our profiling
blocks so we can now turn on and off our
profiling blocks dynamically in the
game's UI so that if we have things that
we don't want to profile a lot of the
times because they generate too many
debug events it's okay we can actually
turn them on in certain circumstances to
turn them off and that can all be
completely flexible and handled within
the game's UI which is gonna be pretty
awesome
will there be a dev console probably not
cuz I don't I can't think of any reason
why I would need that student I'm 73
also system runs a program through
command dot exe which is yet another
dependency uh like it is but but not
really because we need that for our
build anyway so it's not really an
additional dependency right
I would everything I mean we need CMD so
that's not really an additional one I
don't think but I don't know so it's at
the end of the questions
that's pretty great I wish Microsoft's
compiler wasn't so slow because that
would the turnaround time there would be
much faster if it wasn't I guess we
don't need the asset builder to be built
anymore really because we did what we
wanted to do with it so there's that but
the chat recommended create new window
as a process creation flag you could
probably use that instead of the
minimized window I don't think it's
minimized though is it so if it's
compiling it's not it's not there so
it's it's SW hide is not SW minimize SW
hide means don't ever show the window to
the user at all so I don't think we need
to make it not create a window I think
it's okay that it creates its window we
just don't ever display that window and
I think that might be better cuz I don't
really know what happens if you tell it
not to create a window at all I'm afraid
that that maybe you know who knows if
that breaks something sometimes I don't
even know what is in the batch file
that's run it's just our batch it's our
standard build bat file that this is the
build that we use so it's just running
our normal build power c 9k why does it
zoom out because that's what it's
modifying the debug camera that's what
it's actually setting every time we do
that it sets the debug camera at acos it
are using sublime no I'm using Emacs
quantum placeand can you add a radial
menu for debug camera instead of
piggybacking off topography it's bugging
me no because that's what we will be
doing tomorrow no jumping ahead all
right I'm gonna go ahead and shut down
here that was pretty exciting I'm pretty
psyched about what that will let me do
never actually done that before I don't
know why it took 60 minutes probably
should've
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for another episode of hand made here
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with this series at home you can always
pre-order the game handmade hero on
handmade hero org and it comes with a
source code so you can play around that
at home experiment with it do whatever
sorts of explorations you are trying to
do and learn from it which is a great
way to go if you if you wanna learn from
the series we also a patreon page you
just want to support our video series
you can always subscribe to that it's
very much appreciated we also have a
forum site you can go to ask questions
and look at the annotated episode guide
to catch up on past episodes and a tweet
bot you can go to look at what the
schedule is for the upcoming week and
also if you want us to follow that tweet
bot it'll tweet reminders at you when
the stream goes live so if you're trying
to catch it live and just want to know
that's a pretty handy little tool as
well so that's it I will be back
tomorrow when I will be playing with
this compiled feature because I'm pretty
psyched about it and there's all sorts
of things I can think of that we could
do so I'm pretty pretty psyched about
that so that's about it for now I'll be
back tomorrow for that hope see you here
again 5 p.m. Pacific Daylight Time until
then please have fun programming I'll
see you guys on the Internet take me as
everyone