all right hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hiro sure we could a complete
game live on stream I will be trying to
put into practice and things we read
yesterday I was pretty interested one of
the things I try to do on handmade Hiro
is we obviously always try things
ourselves but a lot of times what I'm
actually programming I'll read a lot of
papers and it's kind of hard on handmade
Hiro because reading papers isn't really
something you can do on stream very well
I mean I guess we could all sit here in
silence while we all read the paper so
it's a little bit tough but what it does
mean is that it kind of robs us a little
bit of one of the main tools that I
would normally have when we're actually
working which is the ability to go
gather information from lots of people
who have worked on stuff now we happen
to luck out on the stream yesterday in
that we tended to HAP we ended up
stumbling upon a few things that we kind
of wanted to know in a way that was
quick and easy for us to actually read
on stream we could go through it they
happen to be written in a very
convenient form like you know wasn't a
huge pile of math equations that I then
had to kind of like work out it was
actually a very well-written paper on
the subject we cared about and it was
really easy for us to to digest and
process but anyway point being I was
really into the octahedral encoding idea
that and it was very easy to sort of
quickly see what they were doing and
presented on stream as well and so today
I want to go ahead and try putting that
in so we can kind of move a little bit
closer to finishing up this lighting
because lighting is the really the
biggest stumbling point we have right
now we really just haven't been able to
quite make it click and I feel like the
octahedral encoding part of things would
really help us out because the biggest
problem we have right now is we don't
really know how to store these things
and update them and it seems pretty easy
to use this as a way of doing that now I
do still think it's a little bit of an
open question as to whether or not where
you want to use a texture array or a
texture Atlas one of the things we
figured out on yesterday stream was that
there's actually inversion that happens
such that you cannot
actually use a rapt sampling mode when
you are interpolating your vectors for
these you know for the octahedral
encoding and that's just because you
know there's no way to actually wrap the
coordinates correctly but what I don't
know is I still don't know why you
wouldn't use a texture array because
even though it means you can't do proper
rap sampling it still seems like you
would want to clamp to edge right and
for some reason they didn't do that and
I don't know why and again one of the
big problems with this is I respect the
authors of this paper and I think
they're very good so if they didn't do
it it probably means you don't do it
meaning like they wouldn't have chosen
an inferior scheme and so that part's
still a little bit iffy to me and just
to give you some which paper would it be
is it this one hmm yeah I don't think
they would have chosen an inferior
scheme now maybe they would have for
some other reason like it could be that
there is some reason they chose this
scheme that has nothing to do with its
efficacy maybe they wanted to be able to
display the maps in a certain way or
something like this but if we look at
how they supposedly actually shipped
this thing they pack all of their stuff
and you can see it here they pack all of
their stuff into little squares in a
texture Atlas and what that means is
when they're sampling them they will at
the very least have to have a little
border edge that they would use in order
to make that sampling work now here's
what I'm thinking and I don't actually
know if it's true
but my assumption is the reason that
they would have done that if we assume
that they chose it on purpose and not
arbitrarily which I think is the safer
assumption here based on who the authors
are I'm wondering if maybe part of their
scheme actually goes back through after
they so if they're using like an 8 by 8
here like they said they do say they
leave a gutter region and what I'm
wondering is
maybe they have a pass that goes back
through once they've computed all their
eight by eights and actually fills in a
gutter with fetches from the other side
of the texture so that they actually get
proper interpretive sampling I'm gonna
go ahead and say that I think that's
probably why I don't know if they say
that outright they didn't seem to
immediately in the paper but I'm
thinking that the reason you might need
to do that is when you're computing the
lighting on something if you didn't have
that as you went around the seam you
would presumably see a lighting pop
right so I'm kind of thinking that if
they're using bilinear filtering when
they look up in here I'm kind of
thinking that that is what they've done
so I'm thinking they may have wanted to
use an atlas because at that point
there's no reason to use a texture array
I mean it doesn't do anything for you
so you're just wasting extra coordinates
there's nothing you know it can't it
can't help you at that point so my
assumption and I don't know if it's true
but my assumption is that's what's going
on here that primarily what they're
doing is they're going to take an 8 by 8
or whatever the resolution they chose
because I think they said it was 8 by 8
for the lighting but you know you could
put whatever you want for my for 8 by 8
whatever you I'm suspecting they took
the 8 by 8 they added a 1 pixel border
around the whole thing which they kind
of said they did and then before they go
to actually use it
they probably replicate the correct part
of that the that the octahedron where
its neighbor would have actually been
the correct neighbor they'd probably
move those pixels over so that you get a
seamless sampling I would assume that's
probably what they do but I guess I
don't know
yeah I mean I guess I don't know so you
can see right now they say like one
pixel texture gutter border insurers
correct bilinear interpolation and
additional padding aligns probes on four
by four right boundaries so we know that
they do sort of some of the stuff that
I'm talking about we just don't know
what they put in the padding right so
let's take a quick look just to see
what's up you can see here that they say
like okay we're gonna trace a bunch of
probes here which is fine we don't
really care about that part because
we're doing that a little bit
differently anyway but you know we're
gonna do something like that here's
where they actually figure out what the
illumination is going to be doesn't
really matter again for us and they say
then they go through and the texels in
the octahedron unwrapped octahedron they
do the blending and they figure out what
the result should be and that's fine and
then what I want to know is is there a
set after this right that kind of like
fixes things at all and trying to look
here and see again it's hard to read
papers on stream but just to see if
there's anything like I'm not seeing
anything yet
like I don't see any where were they
really saying specifically but so here
they're talking about how they're
storing it in terms of individual light
like the in terms of the actual value
format but I don't actually see I don't
actually see them really talking about
this one way or the other so I don't
know that part I think is just a little
bit of a question mark and I guess what
I would say is you know what we do have
to go on here where we look at the
actual lighting data that we see which
would be like here right
looking at this lighting data more
closely is really all we've got to go on
and if we look you can kind of see that
at the very least what I'm saying I
guess I would say doesn't seem to quite
hold water with what I what you see here
and the reason I say that is because if
you look at these two pieces they don't
match so if you actually work copying
the border in some way that that
replicated one side over to the other
side you would expect to see this line
and this line roughly match up and they
don't look like they do in any real
sense right like it doesn't look like
unless yeah I mean I'm assuming that's
the scene between two of them because it
should be smooth everywhere to a certain
extent
and I just yeah I don't see that as
being the same as that flipped around at
all I could be wrong but it just it
really doesn't look convincing and so I
really don't know what to make of that
but you see where my dilemma is right so
again really don't know what the goal
was there or what they were doing and so
I think we're gonna have to kind of play
that part by ear
and we do know that they've they've
given us some source code to work with
we've got the supplement here and you
know so we have a little bit of data and
if we open back up again what we're
looking at here we can look at like
there see file but again I don't really
know that we're gonna be able to
determine exactly what they're doing
here because this is not complete source
code I don't think it's it's just a you
know sort of a vague sketch it's like
part of the source code or whatever and
you know looking at the actual process I
don't know who's gonna tell us that
unless there's an obvious smoking gun
like fill gutters with the thing or
something like that and you know I don't
doubt that that's you know living in
here so you know looking through it
update irradiance probes you know here's
that code happening so here is a blend
pass on these it looks like it's
probably doing some of the final stuff
I'm not sure what shader this is using
irradiance field copy probe edges haha
they did not include that one
unfortunately so I guess what I would
say is that is maybe the smoking gun I
was looking for so if you call something
copy probe Edge's you are at least doing
something as far as you know trying to
do that pad so I guess that tells me
most of what I need to know well I don't
know exactly how they're copying the
probe edges because that particular
pixel shader does not appear to have
been included so I guess I don't know
what I will say is that I do then kind
of know that they're doing a copy of the
probe edges so I will also probably want
to do a copy of the probe edges and it's
just a question of how to copy and since
I know they're doing a copy I guess I
don't need to clone their copy I kind of
know what I probably want to put in
there so that's really all I needed to
know that takes at least the mystery out
of it they are doing roughly what I was
guessing I would want to do and that
gives me some confidence that I
understand what they were doing and I'm
not missing a crucial part of the
process so that satisfies me I'm I'm
pretty happy now I think I know all the
steps I would want in this process and
I've got at least rudimentary
confirmation from the code they
published with the paper that they're
doing something that would at least be
in line with what I'm thinking and again
we don't know for sure exactly what it
is but we don't really need to know
exactly what it is because we can figure
it out ourselves what we want to put
there and it might be different from
what they did anyway it might be that
our usage is different okay so let's go
ahead and start figuring out how we
would actually make this work and I
think what I want to do first is I'm
going to want to have some method that I
can use to just compute these things and
display them without using them for
lighting because it's gonna take us a
little while to get this working and I
don't want to try to infer
from the lighting in the game whether
it's working I want to be able to
directly see it and I don't want to have
to run my thing under like you know
render dock or something and like grab a
periodic thing I want to be able to like
see it in real time
as we're walking around the game and so
what I would like to do is make
something that will render like let's
say we just add a pass at the end of the
rendering where every voxel grid square
in our cube in our world will show it's
floating in that space what it thinks
the octahedral unwrapping for the space
was right so that I can get some idea of
what's going on in each individual space
in the game so it's a little bit hard to
do it'll take a little bit of work to
like write a thing that's gonna actually
do that manually but it's not really a
huge deal right it's just a bunch of
little like quads that would be camera
facing that pick out the exact region of
the thing and so I'll tackle that in two
steps the first one is getting that
texture atlas set up and the second one
actually will do three steps get the
texture atlas set up and and outputting
some data into it too we'll be drawing
the texture atlas itself down like in
the corner or something so we can just
see it and then third we'll be placing
those individual octahedral unwrapped
quads into the world where they actually
occur so that we can try to correlate
them and see that they're actually
producing something that makes sense
at the points where they are nominally
existing right alright so if we go ahead
and build oops
and we go here and we get the game
running
just make sure everything's kosher here
yeah everything seems good there so if
we go ahead and make sure that we have
somewhere that this is going to actually
be stored what I want to do is start
probably in the OpenGL layer not that
that and in here we look at what we're
currently sending down right and these
are the buffers that we actually store
so you can see we've got light data N
and light data see we've got these
handles and stuff for the textures and
whatnot and the thing that we're gonna
have to reckon with here is that at this
point now we're really not going to be
sending down the data in this format
probably any more is my guess we could
but we would just need a tremendous
number of these because we want to use
octave we want to lose a little texture
so we're going to have something
slightly different happening here we're
going to have a light Atlas handle and
this is going to be a texture that just
has all of those little 2d unwrapped
octahedral unwrapping x' just strewn
throughout it right and in our case
since we know that we're always going to
be doing light probes on a grid right
we're always going to be doing a voxel
of them we really don't need any more
information than that if we look at
something like this what we're gonna see
here is is essentially useless data we
don't need to know any information about
our voxels anymore because just the
voxel information itself like what what
the index would be so the three
coordinates that tell you which voxel
cube you were in just that information
will itself be in
- unwrap into the light Atlas to look up
your lighting so I don't think we're
actually going to need that information
right now it's worth noting that at
least in this paper they did something a
little bit fancier then what we have
done so far and you can see we didn't
talk about this but you can see you
might wonder what's this stuff down here
like why are there why is there extra
information and the answer is because
we've been talking entirely about what
you know in here we've been talking
entirely about what the color of the
light what the irradiance was for a
given probe so you know we're talking
about what's the light value we're gonna
need coming in here and what you have to
remember is when we construct the
lighting from these light probes we're
going to be asking from a particular
location in the world we're gonna be
asking hey what light would be
contributed from this light probe or
something right but we're asking for a
location that is not where the light
probe actually exists and so what
happens there is if we actually have
some features in between the light
probes so basically like we have a light
probe into like you know this light
probe in this light probe so to
neighboring light probes and we're
asking right like what's the lighting
here well the answer is going to be a
combination of these two light probes
only if there isn't like a wall in the
way right so one of the questions we
might want to ask ourselves is from this
light probe to the point we're actually
looking at could we have actually seen
that light probe and that seems like
it's gonna require another raycast right
but it turns out that when we've done
all this work beforehand if we just
store the depth that we tend to see in
that direction like how far the light
probe goes before it hits something in
that direction that would tell us
whether in general
we tend to be able to get far enough out
to encompass the point we're actually
sampling right and so all they do is
just like look let's just store an
additional sample here that's the depth
that we went so that we have that
information in addition right and that
seems like really good idea because if
we do that then we don't really have to
worry anymore right like we can just say
all right we're all ready we already
know that information because we had to
do the rate cast and the rate cast
output how far we went to get the color
value so at that point it just seems
like pretty easy for us to keep that
information and we can improve our
sampling of the light probes with it
so I'm gonna go ahead and say while
we're doing this path let's just do that
and we don't have to use that so maybe
we'll call this like light color Atlas
handle and light depth Atlas handle so
that we can we can have both of those
and in the future we will start to make
use of this whereas at first we can
probably just ignore it because it's yet
another thing that could go wrong but we
might as well just remember okay we're
gonna be outputting that so let's do it
while we do all the rest of this stuff
and we don't have to debug at the same
time but we can at least make sure that
the whole data flow is working and we
don't have to come back and do it so if
we want to do that then we're basically
saying look we're just gonna submit two
things here right and rather than like
did it in light day to see we just have
to have these things in captured for us
and the main thing that we're gonna have
to know here is what the size of our
voxel is because for each voxel we're
gonna have one of those so if we take a
look at this light lookup voxel
dimension we know we're gonna have that
cubed right and I might just go ahead
and say that since we know that these
will be roughly similar I guess we don't
actually know that yeah so
in order to provide the data for these
for the light color data and the light
depth data we know that each of these
are going to store precisely as many
entries effectively as there are voxel
cells which is going to be the cube of
whatever our dimension is but then we
also know that we need some size for
each of them so we need a secondary
parameter here that's going to be like
similar to light
lookup Fox of them right so in addition
to this we're also going to need one
more thing which is the light look up
you know square dim or something and
we're going to have two of these
probably because we don't know that
we're gonna store the depth and the
color at the same resolution and there's
really no reason to unifying that
resolution we could but it doesn't
really save us anything like it may save
us yeah you know I can't think of
anything that saves us so we it's free
for us to find two different constants
that's whatever that square dim is so
the light lookup squared dim is going to
be something else and maybe that's like
eight or whatever right and we probably
again need the padding so it'd be
something like this like it'd be an
eight by eight but with plus two padding
or something like that and we might want
to define the padding or I don't know
how I don't know how we're gonna want to
specify this but it'd be something like
that right and we can break this up into
multiple Defiance later what that means
is we're gonna have something like this
and if we want two different ones one
for the color one for the depth it would
be like this
and this now it's kind of hard to read
that and you know we might want to do
this right where you can pass something
in and it just says that so we just say
alright if I want to cube something I
can just use a macro for that and if I
want to square something I can use a
macro for that because then it's like
well it's the square of this times the
cube of that and that's just easier for
someone to come along and read right so
I feel like that's probably useful I
mean it just it just makes it easier to
read and edit these things and without
that it's kind of a little bit
ridiculous how long it gets there so
then you can say alright it's the square
of this times the cube of that and then
we know what we're actually dealing with
here I'll leave these the same at the
moment and we'll just kind of put light
color and light depth in here but we'll
split those out and play around with
those a little bit more later I might
move this into the math side of things
oh all right
we already had that so I guess we just
weren't using it because we forgot we
had it typical of what we do here but
you know what are the downsides have
only programs something once a week all
right so if we look at what we're doing
here we now have the ability to send
these down we don't need this we don't
need this and so now we've just got one
texture atlas it'll still store all the
color data for our lighting and one that
will store all the depth data for our
lighting I think that's all we actually
will need these again are not submitted
to the shaders these are just submitted
to the
system so they need to stay here but
they don't actually have anything to do
with the texture submission so we're
gonna need to fill these out once a
frame and we're gonna need to submit
them using the using these handles but
once we do that we've pretty much got
the pipeline ready for us and we just
have to go start working on actually
getting the values out right furthermore
I think trying to think here but I
believe if you set these both to white
like we probably could make something
that allows us to turn off the lighting
without actually turning it off meaning
that just subbed in things here that
just say you're getting uniform lighting
from everywhere right so we'll see about
that as well at some point anyway okay
so let's go ahead and start making that
work we're gonna have to start by
changing when we actually create these
things so if you look here when we
actually Gen these textures we're
actually just generating one texture now
instead of a bunch of them
we're just generating one texture for
each of these so we've got the light
color atlas handle and then we've got
the light depth atlas handle that's what
we need there we don't actually need to
do a four eye loop here anymore this is
just going to be sort of your basic it
doesn't need to do any loops it's just
your basic assignment and so if we just
take these the first thing we want to do
is create a light color atlas handle it
is not a 2d texture our 3d texture
anymore anyway it's a 2d one and what
I'm gonna do is at first you know I
guess I don't really know if we can
afford it I on this suit because there's
a high end card I assume we could afford
it what I would like to do is have
everything be float first
I like as much as possible to be able to
get quantization crap out of the process
so that I can eliminate those kinds of
bugs by knowing they don't exist until
I'm done with the other parts younger
them and then I can turn to a quantize
format and deal with bugs that show up
because it it segregates the bugs into
two different kinds of bug so that you
don't have to tackle them both at the
same time now the problem is this is
gonna be pretty big so if it's a 32
[Music]
oops I promised I would never use that
again
where's my speed calc where's most weeks
where's must recalc crap didn't we have
this all set up there that took way too
long all right so if we assume that this
thing is going to be like 32 at least 30
2 cubed times what were we saying 10 so
it was 10 squared so that's not huge you
know each one of those is going to be at
that point 16 wide though so it's a 52
megabyte texture so but that's fine like
for testing purposes right how bad does
it get if we get one more down ouch
so yeah like if we were to go to 64 by
64 by 64 which we may well want to for
resolution quality at that point like
it's pretty dicey and you would
definitely want it to be that so but
even so it would probably just run
slowly like making a half gigabyte
texture on this card will still work
it's just not something we want to do
much right so it's fine so so I'm gonna
say sure like this will work hopefully
it just might be slow and crappy but it
will work right although now that I
think about it how the heck are we gonna
submit this thing
yeah that that is scarier isn't it
because one of the things that I guess
we didn't count on when we thought about
this was most of this would probably
have to now be done on the graphics card
like if we just think about what we're
doing here
it doesn't seem particularly possible
that we would be able to we wouldn't be
able to prepare these textures and send
them down you're not gonna be submitting
that much data per frame and ever it's
never gonna happen so I guess what I
would say is we can start off with this
but we're pretty much gonna have to
we're gonna have to use a 32 by 32 by 32
pretty much we can't try a more resolute
version unless we move it to the card I
mean that's what this tells us right so
we can proceed currently doing it on the
CPU side this way but if we wanted to
move to a higher resolution we'd have to
throw it onto the graphics card there's
no other way to do it right and that has
nothing to do with the computation time
it's literally just the amount of data
traffic that would be involved is
prohibitive week
we could investigate ways of sending
down other stuff but yeah so so I think
basically we have to do here is we'll
get it working this way and then if we
want to do a more resolute version we're
gonna have to run the graphs part which
we may not need to do I don't know the
this resolution may be fine
and if it is then we can stick with our
current method because 32 cubed times 10
squared times 4 is only 13 megabytes and
that is not a troubling number for
sending down to the card every frames so
that would be our target for release
shipping if we can do that we're
probably good we could also change the
resolution in Z because that's probably
less important since we we don't need to
see as many levels of the game
necessarily although I kind of like the
fact that we can see down deeper so but
anyway let's let's just go ahead and
save this what we're gonna do for now
and we'll cross that bridge when company
if we wanna kick it up to 64 by 6 first
before we'd have to go to the graph scar
at that point but either way so at that
point we know that look we've got light
lookup voxel dim times light color
lookup square dim that's our dimension
so it's just that and this can all stay
the same we're only going to need to
send down an RGB float at the moment we
don't need to send down anything else
so that'll just be fine in the future
we'll have to think about how we're
actually gonna store them and that'll
kind of be a issue for another day now
the depth will be easier we don't have
to care about the depth nearly as much
and the reason for that is just because
the depth is just one value so it
doesn't multiply up by 4 like it was
before Oh actually did I forget to do
that no I didn't I remember them so
actually this version is the largest it
could possibly be rather than the
smallest it could possibly be and it
could get as low as x 1 at which point
even the resolute version is probably
not too bad right yeah so even the
really high-res version would still be
untroubled n't have to get x 4
so it's really not that bad by
comparison to the other version which is
quite bad because it's a hundred
megabytes of traffic instead of 26
megabytes and those are pretty different
so anyway all seems fine I don't really
want this as a format in fact I really
just want one color for the depth handle
and when I bind this out I'm gonna want
a 2d texture again I'm gonna want it to
be a are 32f so just one I'm gonna want
it to be the same dimensions as before
but the only difference is we're gonna
use a slightly different constant so
that we can control the size of these
two things separately even though we
don't actually know that we ever
actually want that there's really no
reason not to do it because they're
always gonna be separate code paths I
think for the most part that can just
use a different constant in that place
so it shouldn't be a huge deal for us to
fix that part so off we go
that just looks fine I guess I don't
remember exactly what happens in GL
texture 2d though in terms of parameters
I should look because I don't know if
this extra parameter is there so you
know I'm just gonna real quick pop over
to Doc's top GL and take a look at what
GL texture to text image 2d actually
takes because it's always just this big
string of parameter so I want to make
sure we've got it right
so target check level check internal
format check width and height check
border check format type data so I think
we've got that correct like that looks
that looks fine so this is all we really
needed to do I think that pretty much
gets us what we want and the only
difference here is since we're storing
floats at the moment I'm just gonna say
all right at the moment instead of you
32s these are gonna be like v3 s and F
32 s because again I just want to start
out in float so that we don't have to
worry about quantization until we get
everything else working it just keeps
it's something complicated like lighting
I'm just trying to manage the complexity
a little bit because it's always bad and
you don't want to give yourself even
more to worry about that's probably not
actually a a dynamic call there that's
probably just built in yeah alright so
what is the problem here
term does not have vowed to oh yeah
forgot the comma all right so now all we
need to do is in the light Direction
count here a loop that we were doing
before this is not going to happen so
when we fill out these commands the game
render commands we just need to pass
only these two things that we actually
needed so here we have lightbox we'll
see
in late voxel n that's actually going to
be changed and it's going to be light
voxel C and light voxel D oops and these
two here I guess we don't really need to
do that we can just have this be a
pointer in each case and this is a v3
and that's an f32 so these are you know
not gonna be labeled anymore done with
that so these are gonna gather the
information we actually need here and I
think we're good to go from there
what I would like to do is get rid of
the for loop because we don't need that
anymore and then these should be C and D
and they should point to light color
data light depth dates depth data and
they no longer have multiple indices
it's just one of each alright so now
that we've got that out of the way
the binding textures here again no
longer necessary to actually have a for
loop because we're only gonna bind one
of them we don't need to do text sub
image because it's actually just sorry
we don't need to do text sub to D
because it's 3d it's actually 2d and
similarly all of those can go by the
wayside so we have a light color Atlas
handle and a light depth Atlas handle
and in here where we actually specify
like the offset we're only going to need
two offsets not three so we've got the
level and the X&amp;Y
we then have the size of the thing that
we're going to be doing here and again
that's going to be the voxel dim times
the light color lookup Square and then
we're gonna need to do the same thing
for these
so again just sending down those two
however wait you know what this is not
quite right I just realized something
these still need to be unpacked so
actually we do need a place to store the
cube version so one of our dimensions
and I guess I don't know which one
actually needs to be bigger than that
right so hmm I guess I don't know did we
that we need this thing to be square for
any particular reason because we're not
mipmapping it or anything yes oh I guess
I don't know that this needs to be
square for any particular reason
although it may be better to do so I
mean it may still be nice to have powers
of two for it but I guess that's a
separate thing but point being one of
these dimensions has to be larger right
and I don't know which one we want to do
because if you imagine right we've got
sheets that are light lookup voxel dim
by light looks like lookup voxel dim
number of octahedral unwrapping but then
we have another voxel dims worth of each
of those because it's three-dimensional
right so one of our dimensions has to
have that in there right like we have to
have like the X be longer or the Y be
longer I don't know which one we
probably want I'll say let's double the
X for now right so basically our X has
the equivalent of the whole thing in it
and you know the Y like the Y is
actually gonna be the Z at this point
right so I didn't really think that
through that that was not what we wanted
to do there sorry about that
let me think about that for a second
yeah I think that would be fine
I think that'll just work so we need to
when we actually create them we need to
fix that then and so where we actually
do the text the original text image duty
we need to make sure that we actually do
it that way the problem with that there
is I'm not really sure again like I'm
not sure how to really encode that it
seems like it's fine the way it is let
me just go back here and change that so
if we double this voxel dim here on the
X I guess for now we'll just remember
that's the case but we nice to make that
a little bit more systemic it's just
it's a little wonky right but all right
so suppose we do that I'm gonna go ahead
and make this be C and this be D and
then we can run all right so that's what
we're looking at or trying to look at
here oops I don't know why that's a 3d
that's what we're looking at and now we
just need to actually get rid of our
compilers obviously that's a built-in
again just like it was before I don't
remember what this is called light color
data yeah and like depth data at that
point I think we have created the
textures and we've bound the textures
but we don't ever accept the textures
okay here we go with that right so oh
wait no nevermind
so here we submit the textures we just
haven't ever used the textures so now we
need to actually use the textures which
happens in here so we're gonna have the
light data C or light color data and the
light depth data
we don't need this index anymore and
we've only got it just the one time
and so in here we don't really need this
anymore it's just three two and three
right there's nothing particularly fancy
happening there and I think that's it so
now in the actual shader we will have to
pull from these a little bit differently
right in this particular case these are
texture two DS now this also is a handle
and I think we just want to go to the
shader now right so this is us actually
filling this stuff out in the actual
lighting code which we do want to go
address but that's sort of step two so
before we do that we should go to the
compile Z bias program which is the
thing that actually needs to take this
information and when it actually does
you can see here it got all this stuff
none of that is actually what we want
anymore
so now we want a light color sampler and
a light depth sampler and there's only
going to be just those two so we're not
gonna do any more of those right so
that's the entirety of it and I don't
think anyone else cared about this right
it's just this shader is the only one
that actually samples the lighting I
think and so now these are going to be
uniform samplers that look like this and
we've got color sampler and a depth
sampler when we actually go to sample
them like in you know this stuff here is
now kind of all wrong
we're gonna have to rewrite all of this
stuff because this is all doing totally
different stuff than we were doing
before and so we're gonna have to do a
completely different way of sampling
because now we're gonna actually be
using octahedral samples and we're going
to be getting eight of them and actually
like you know pulling from those eight
and blending together all right so I
want to say that all like literally all
of this unfortunately is now kind of
just not right
and so I kind of think we can just maybe
not use we can just delete it really we
know that this is roughly correct but
everything past there is like we're not
going to be using any voxel lookups
anymore and so I think we can just say
all right look that is gonna happen and
this stuff is gonna happen totally
differently so we can probably just not
do this I mean it's not really gonna
help I'll leave it in for now but I'm
mostly just gonna not use it so let's go
ahead and say all right there's just an
f0 here that's gonna be taken out of the
equation it's literally inside the
sunlight call what we'll do is we'll
just return a white light for now and
we'll just leave it at that
so it doesn't matter what you send down
it's never gonna get looked at it's just
going to be no lighting
all right and oops here where we
actually send down lighting from the
voxel cells again this is going to
totally change so we should probably
just not bother doing much with this
stuff anyway in fact I think I'm just
gonna delete this cuz it's completely
useless so off that goes as well all
right so now let's just get things
working at all so let's take a look at
our OpenGL errors you can see here we're
getting an error message from up in jail
let's see what it says of course we
can't because the debug info won't tell
us I feel like we should be able to see
that at least cuz it's a parameter yeah
GL invalid enum so I don't know where
this is happening but presumably yeah I
was gonna say presumably just missed a
texture 3d so the I hate absolutely hate
the way OpenGL does that they fixed it
all but of course trying to be in OpenGL
3 means you can't really use it instead
of just saying what the handle is you
always say what the target is which
means every time you change what kind of
texture you got to change all the enums
related to that texture which it doesn't
make any sense it's it's a nonsense way
to do things I don't know why they did
it that way but point being we need to
make sure that we in fact really
shouldn't have a texture 3d anywhere
anymore I don't think so like all of
these should all be text 2d I think
and this doesn't need to be here anymore
for obvious reasons because it's not
actually 3d so there's no wrapping that
can happen in our right so let's take a
look and see if there's any other
texture 3ds anywhere because we know
they're probably wrong yeah so I think
we can just for now get rid of those we
don't have any Vox lookups we need to do
so let's just get rid of those all right
oops let's rerun that and see if we can
get to some other error and texture type
and format combinations about all right
so let's take a look who is asking for
this so this it did not like oh I think
because that's not the I think it's GL
I'm just going to read and I think those
are actually different I guess I'm not
sure I guess I'm not really sure but
let's try and find out
I think that's right
exception thrown but it doesn't say who
has thrown the exception who has thrown
this exception somebody has thrown an
exception but we cannot see a call stack
I don't know why oh because we threw an
exception on the red really that seems
bad how can we not get what would
involve a jump of that nature that seems
a little bit weird I wonder where that
is let's see if we can step through and
just so we can find out roughly where
we're crashing
so we initialize okay so we must be
getting a problem when we actually go to
render something let's see if we make it
to end frame let's put it that way so we
do make it to the end of the frame let's
see what happens if we step into the
frame submission we should be here it
could be that we screwed up
like this for example right Oh
in fact that is screwed up yeah and
that's what it is not sure why it
couldn't tell us that I guess because
since we were giving it memory that we
had known it must have just overwritten
some things somehow I guess I'm not
really sure why it would have because
we're not writing to memory here that we
don't own we're asking it to fetch
memory doesn't own which should have
just faulted on the read but that
doesn't look like what actually happened
so I guess I don't know why that
occurred exactly but apparently it did
so off we go so that should be right
here
and that's the problems that we told it
three components which is not what we're
actually submitting right we're actually
submitting one component so it was
reading three times as much data because
we said here's the dimensions and then
we said well there's three per element
but there isn't and obviously that's not
in the mix so here's the renderer
running songs lighting so there's no
lighting being used but in theory the
lighting textures exist and are being
submitted now and so the first thing I
would say is let's do exactly what we
did last time let's try to output
standard spherical lighting into the
octahedrons that will take at least the
rest of the day today if not into next
weekend and that will be our goal so
then we can output spherical lighting
from one light source into the
octahedrons
unencoded them in light with that
results in the actual renderer and we
can display those textures so that's a
ton of work to do and if we actually get
that done we've put ourselves once
that's done we've put ourselves in very
good position for finishing up right all
right so let's go ahead and do that
the first thing we would need to do is
implement the octahedral wrap and unwrap
so I'm going to go ahead into math land
here and I'm just gonna have an
octahedral wrap and unwrap so I'm gonna
have a v2 that comes out of this and I'm
going to have like unit vector or
octahedral from unit vector something
like that and then I'm gonna have a v3
which is like unit vector from
octahedral and these will just be my
functions that transform in and out
right and I guess we'll call this V and
this o or something right and so we know
we're gonna compute something like this
and let's go through the steps so we
know that if we want to compute an
octahedral mapping from a direction
vector we know that we need to start by
taking the absolute value so we're going
to need the fact absolute value of the
three components of this thing
in order to cause remember we start by
taking the one norm right so we need to
take the one norm of this thing that
goes down here so now we know its
magnitude and again this is so we can
transform it from a sphere which is
obviously gonna it's going to have that
that signature bowing out that a sphere
has right it's it's got the sine cosine
curve baked in there we're taking that
out right so we start with the one norm
we've computed the one norm now we need
to figure out what the xy-plane ER
projection would be so getting rid of
the Z so if we take the V XY here and we
take the reciprocal of the one norm so
this right so if we invert the one norm
and then we use that as a coefficient to
multiply the XY the actual planar
version of this octahedron that's gonna
get us back the actual result right
that's our actual octahedral mapping
right there but we now need to take care
of the bottom half of the sphere so this
would take a the hemispherical map and
we just be done but in the case where
the Z is less than zero now we have to
compute a version of this thing that
blows out those under the underside of
the sphere out into the unfolded part of
the octahedral map so to do that we need
to start by saying well okay if V is
less than zero then we're in that case
if we're not then just don't do it right
so this is complete if we were on the
top half of the sphere the Z positive
half the sphere
oh that's tart as a lemon juice anyway
so we get that and we want to say all
right let's take the let's take the
unfolding that we already have which is
this and let's push it out into the
corners now if you remember the way that
we did this what we effectively said is
look let's take the absolute value of
these and I don't know I don't think we
have an absolute value for a vector do
we because we don't really have that and
maybe we should so I don't know like
let's say maybe we do want this because
hey it's probably a thing right so what
we want to do here is say let's take the
absolute value of this thing and that
just allows us to do this a little bit
more flexibly I suppose right and yeah
that looks right all right just take the
absolute value two components and pop
back the result so we know we've got the
absolute value here and we want to take
the absolute value of whatever the
result was the problem that we're gonna
have is we need to swap these right
because remember in addition to taking
the absolute value you know we want to
do this and maybe you know what maybe
this is premature maybe we don't
actually need this because I think we're
gonna have to swap these I'm gonna write
this in scalar because we need to swap
them and we need to subtract them from
one and this isn't two shader so we
don't have all of the conveniences of a
shader at the moment like we don't have
the Swizzle ability and so on
so in here we've got result X what we're
actually gonna want to do is subtract
the absolute value of result Y and again
that's because we're going the opposite
direction we're coming back from the
edge now but also we're rotating 90
degrees because of the way this thing
folded out and for those of you who were
here yesterday already know exactly I'm
talking about but this is the diagram
that we're doing here so that first step
I should should have said this the
beginning I just assumed everyone's here
yesterday but not everyone would have
been this first step here right
computing the one norm and take the
result that's just taking this top half
of the sphere and mapping it into a
diamond right because we get rid of the
Z so this flattens down right and then
we take the one norm which turns these
Boeing bowed arcs here right obviously
Boeing is different a bowed arc is an
arc that has a curve on it a Boeing arc
is one that goes straight into the
ground because they are literally so
Calais with human life that they didn't
even bother to employ any real software
engineering practices in their planes so
that's always good
moving on from that particular horrific
reality of modern programming and coming
back to this we actually have the other
part of the sphere which is the bottom
part here and that part needs to be
unfolded out and so when we are figuring
out how to take this mapping because
remember after we've done this the top
and the bottom half of the sphere have
mapped on to each other they're both in
this diamond so we need to take each of
these quadrants of the diamond and fold
it out into the other part so that it
won't do that this part here would be
the end of it right this this right here
will take any part like so no matter
where we were any one of these we will
now turn ourselves into this top part
here right but because we've taken the
absolute value of each of these so it
doesn't matter where you were in here
we're up here now and we've subtracted
them from one right so we've taken this
one and turned it into this one right we
flipped the two coordinates I'm
subtracting
one which mirrors it and puts it up in
the corner but now we need to put it
back where it was
right now we've got a sign of here right
and you can see our sign of function
doesn't return zero so it's what we want
so what we need to do is put this thing
back in the quadrant where it actually
belongs so we need to take our sign of
whatever the result X was and multiply
that by whatever the flipped version
actually is which sends the thing back
down to whatever quadrant it should have
actually been in and I believe that now
gives us the complete octahedral mapping
that we were looking for in the first
place now doing a unit vector from
octahedral mapping is the other way
round
right and so what we're gonna need to do
here is reverse this process so you can
see that we're gonna have two branches
because we had two branches to begin
with but we don't actually know what
those branches should be yet because we
haven't looked at what these will
actually come out to now I would assume
that if we were to take these two
together so if I took oxo Y right and I
took the absolute value of these two
things I'm just gonna try and write this
myself I haven't looked at what the
actual code is for it so let's try to
write it ourselves first and then we'll
go look at what the actual code is that
they gave and just to see if we're right
or if we you know we probably will we
might be right but we might be probably
would be less efficient because they've
probably thought about this for longer
than we have and worked out the most
optimal way of doing it right but anyway
if I take my X in my Y so what can you
tell like what does this triangle have
to say about itself or any of these
trials the interior well what they have
to say about themselves is the X plus
the Y is less than one right or equal to
one right it can't be more than one
because if it was it would be in one of
the outer triangles so I posit that our
two branches should look like this
okay so we've got two branches one is
where the 1-norm is great and zero what
sorry where's greater than one and one
where it is less than one so in the case
where it's less than one we're inside
the diamond which these are on the top
half of the sphere so if we're on the
top half of the sphere then I think
actually all we need to do is
reconstruct what we would have done so
in the top half of the sphere that's
this half here what we're gonna want to
do is say well here's what we did before
right here was what our XY was
previously in the top half of the sphere
I'm gonna call this yet but if we had
our one norm we know that this is what
we were going to do so the thing we
actually want is this right this is well
you know what this is this is OH dot XY
is what this is here's the thing we
actually want which is result XY right
and we need to solve these well hey
guess what algebra can do that for us
right the problem is we don't know this
actual thing because this includes
adding Z so we'll call this one norm
plus Z right this is the one norm
without Z so if we wanted to we could do
this right move this over to this side
by inverting it oops
right so instead of dividing by the one
norm now we're just multiplying by the
one norm so if we were to multiply by
the warrant one norm plus whatever the Z
value was then we would get back what we
actually wanted for XY here the problem
is we don't know what the Z value was
right like I have no idea what the Z
value was because they didn't send it to
me right but if we actually look at what
this was this was V X V Y V Z we added
these together and I'm probably have to
do this out on the blackboard but and
then we divided by them so actually we
know that we were only missing one value
here from the original one norm if we
wanted to reconstitute it right and now
I think about it I suppose so I don't
actually know that I really have to do
this to be completely honest with you
because if we know where this was we
should actually be able to just blow it
out to a circle okay doesn't matter
point being I'm gonna actually do this
out on the blackboard because it's
usually better to do the math than not
but you see where I'm going with this
right I need to reconstruct these values
and it turns out that the only value I
don't know is Z I know what the other
two values were after the fact so I'm
just trying to reconstitute what they
would have been so let me just write
these out explicitly and we'll go from
there
here is my Milton
and if we look at what's actually gonna
happen here I guess we'll do unit oops
octahedral - unit alright so looking at
what we've got here we know that we have
a vector here which is like V X V Y V Z
and then we know we have an oxn an O Y
which we can map between these two we
know the mapping going forwards we're
trying to figure out the mapping going
backwards we know that the relationship
between these two things is always that
Oh X equals because we know this right
this equation here the V X times this 1
over the 1 norm right so it's going to
be 1 over V X V Y VZ cubes
right so we know that this is the
equation for x given these and we know
that this is the equation for a y also
given the same thing right so we know
we've got these two equations and we can
run them forwards but the problem is now
we want to be able to run them backwards
and so if we actually try to solve this
what we would get is we multiply through
both sides and again we're trying to
solve for the VX in the view Y we will
divide through both sides and we get
something for like this equation we'd
have like Oh X times VX plus Oh x times
V y plus
Oh x times V Z equals and you can see
that that was me just from multiplying
back through equals like VX right and
similarly you'd get the other one too
they dupes they'd be exactly the same
right so we know we have two equations
here but the problem is of the things
that we actually need to know we we
don't have this value right so we don't
know what the input V Z actually was so
although we've got two equations in two
unknowns otherwise this part we don't
actually know right and looking through
it the only information that we will get
is whether or not Z was positive or
negative right so we hope we know like
positive or negative Z but how are we
going to solve two equations in three
unknowns right what can we do well I
assume the answer here is that we did
have one more piece of information
although it is not written down here we
know right in the statement that when we
produce an answer
we are not going
to consider any actual answers that
don't involve a unit vector so we
expected a unit vector in and we're
going to produce a unit vector out which
means that I can write the additional
equation of one equals the square root
of VX squared plus V y squared plus VZ
squared right I know this is the answer
I'm sorry I know this is a constraint
because I said so we're never going to
translate anything else into this into
the octahedral map and by definition we
couldn't because we're trying to unwrap
the surface of a sphere never the inside
or outside of that sphere so we know
that no matter what we do it's always
gonna look like this right and we picked
a unit sphere so it's 1 but if we want
we could do it in it with any radius
sphere just by changing this number
right so what that means is that if we
did want to solve these three equations
we now have an additional weapon in our
arsenal which is one because I can
square both sides equals vs square V y
squared plus V Z squared and the only
thing that we wouldn't necessarily know
here again is the signs because as you
can see all the signs in this will be
destroyed right thankfully we will end
up knowing all of the signs why because
we know what quadrant we put the thing
in and we know whether the Z was
positive or negative based on which
branch were in so even though we destroy
all our signs with our third equation it
doesn't matter because we actually can
reconstruct those signs separately right
so we should be able to just solve this
thing thinking everything is positive
right just assuming everybody's positive
and then we just place it into the
quadrant that we need it to be Earth's
octant I should say because we know all
the signs from other external
information that doesn't really relate
to actually figure out the values are
okay
so if this is the case how can we
actually go about solving this equation
like what can we actually do here to try
and and and put this together well I
guess when I would first start out doing
is I would try to solve this equation
probably this is going to be pretty ugly
but we'll see what happens so if I
wanted to solve for
for example VZ squared then I would end
up with oops not squared then I would
end up with 1 minus the x squared plus V
y squared right I'm just swapping these
out here so these two moved to their
side and I'm positive on this side so
off we go right so then I would have VZ
equals positive or negative square root
of 1 minus VX squared plus well actually
that's not right
Yeah right and so if I wanted to plug VZ
into these equations up here I could
just do it it would provide me with
these other two right and it's a little
nasty because that's not really what you
want to see as far as plugging something
in to both sides if I'm completely
honest about it it's it's not great
right
not sure if there's a way to simplify
that down it doesn't really look like
there is to me there III don't really
see any any real clever way to do that
yeah so I don't know so anyway if we
assumed if that was what we had to plug
in so 1 minus u x squared minus V Y
squared then if you looked at one of
these equations you would be able to sub
in this term right so you would be able
to basically say like alright you know
we've got VX plus v y plus this heinous
thing here and that's gonna equal the x
on the other side or you could subtract
it over as well well they couldn't pull
it out I'm not sure that really helps us
much
it's got to be an easier way to do this
that I'm just not thinking of
I mean here's one thing I'll just
mention so let's suppose that we took
the diamond because I don't really want
to chug through that math to be
completely honest with you because it
seems like maybe there should be a
simpler way to conceive of it right like
I feel like I'm over complicating it so
if we were to assume that we took the
diamond here right if we were lying flat
in the diamond plane meaning we were on
one of these lines right so we knew that
if we knew that Z was zero right then we
know that what we would actually be
doing is just to normalizing this thing
you know I'm saying so we know that all
we would have to actually do is say x
squared like you know our Oh X squared
plus our Oh Y squared is going to equal
the sorry Square rooted right this is
going to equal the length of of our
vector and we know that it has to end up
equaling one right so we know that in
order to produce the final values our
result X or our V X is going to be our
Oh X over this term and our V Y oops
it's bad V our V Y is going to be Oh Y
over this term right so for just that
slice we would know what to do and the
reason that we know that is because we
know that like the Oh Y value here is
zero right
so the real question would be well what
would we do once we start to move up
from there right so if we needed to be
like up further how would we actually
determine that well we know that you
know obviously if the oxo Y is zero then
we would know that the I'm sorry the Oh
Z we would know that the Oh Z value
would
actually be one in that case and so we
know the other ones would be zero but
what do we do as we kind of smoothly go
up and down in there well I mean one way
to think about it would be when we did
this mapping we could imagine doing the
whole mapping right so if we said V X V
Y V Z goes to oxo Y and we said this
right if we then had an AZ value which
was V Z times 1 over the X plus V y plus
VZ right that would be the complete
mapping and then we would know exactly
what to do so if we had o X o Y and O's
e then all we would have to do is
reverse the process right so we would
just say like oh ok if this was the
normalization before we just multiply
each one by whatever this is and and
we're done right so you know we
previously did this so we just need to
multiply each value by this to get the
to get the thing back right
and furthermore I guess you would never
actually need that because if you know
you're always producing a unit vector
then you know that these things have the
right length and so actually if you had
oszi right you would just be doing this
you would just say oh x squared plus y
squared plus Z squared right Square
rooted equals your length value and then
your V X equals the Oh X over the length
your V y equals the Y over the length
and your V Z equals the Oh Z over the
length right so if you look at how this
would have to work you'd go like okay
well if I think about this process here
and look at the computation of the
length again this is the part that I
don't actually know and the Oh x squared
plus the Oh Y squared I know they
originally summed to one right so before
I did the divided by the value that I
don't actually know I know they
originally sum to one
oh but wait but I specified that they
sum to one okay I'm an idiot I don't
even know why I had to think about that
so after all that yeah so I basically
specify that these had to sum to 1
because I divided by then by the norm
but I'm an idiot
so oszi is always equal to 1 minus o X
plus or Y I mean that's the definition
of the 1 norm right that's Wow all right
talk about spending a lot of time to
figure out something you should have
known immediately can you tell I haven't
done 3d programming in a while yeah
kind of obvious at this point so that's
actually trivial so oszi we know right
and basically like oszi is just 1 minus
the sum of these two right because we
know that they had to sum up to whatever
the part we know that the x and the y
summed up to 1 when you included oszi
whatever the heck Ozzie was right so you
know that they would have summed up to 1
after the divide because this divide
ensured that they did not-- I'm saying
so once we know what Ozzie is then we
know what all three values were which
means we can produce the unit vector
trivially right so the only thing I'm
not sure about is how to do the
unquantified at so yeah
so we sum the X Y we know if the X Y is
greater than one then we know that Z is
actually negative right so we know that
Z equals negative Oh Z otherwise it's
positive and then that's it right I mean
I think we're done we just say the
results is Oh X Y Z and we normalize it
right I don't know why that took me so
long I forgot about the constraint they
were gonna have to add to one after the
one norm but I think that's correct so
we take the X to the Y we add them
together at that point we know that
since the first thing we did before we
did anything else back here is we know
the result is always gonna have to sum
to one because we won normalized it
first so we know to construct Z to
reconstruct Z after the fact we know
that the magnitude of ossie is always
just whatever would have made these two
sum to one because that's exactly what
we did before right so then we just
check all right is it greater than one
if it the sum of the two if it was were
in one of the unfolding quadrants so
that means Z was negative if it wasn't
it means he was positive so we leave it
exactly as it was right at the end of
the day we then have a vector we know
that that vector has all of the correct
components in it we just don't know
whether or not it means like what
direction sorry we know that it has the
right sign and the right magnitude so
then we just have to normalize it out to
the unit sphere right now the only thing
I'm not sure about is because of the
unfolding there's that one minus so this
part here I'm not sure how to
reconstruct that but I guess we know
which one it is so and I guess I'll you
know what I should do here I should do
this
let's do that so now I think about it no
we actually know that as well because
when were in the some XY phase here we
know now where we were so if we did
unfold we unfolded in this branch so we
can actually just undo this right so we
know that what we would have done inside
this branch is Oh X and oh I would have
gone through this process we can just
reverse the solve and do the opposite
operation so previously what we had done
is we've said let's take the absolute
value instructor from one so now what we
can do is just do the opposite of that
so take and flip it right we can we can
do exactly the same like this this is
literally the same thing
right because we just literally want to
do the flip again we just want we just
want to undo this 1.0 flip here that's
that's all we're really trying to do and
so we can literally be exact same thing
again to flip to do to undo the flip
that we did and then we the exact same
thing now we have the swizzle again
so we want to unseal which is that right
sign of the results one - the results
and in this case we've got the absolute
value of the thing that we stored and we
want to multiply it by the sign of that
thing because it comes back in as that
sign right so I think it looks like that
so I think that's where we're at all
right let's see how close we got do they
have an implementation here I don't know
if they do so here is something that
goes to the octahedral mapping and if we
look at at that you can see that it does
exactly what we do on the first step so
that's here it's doing these two
together which is fine you don't need it
again so you could tell you do that and
then it just does yeah it does it does
exactly the same thing we do so I think
that's all correct and then for the
octave float version which is going the
other way around the first thing it does
is it says let's create a vector that's
what's the X Y and the one minus the two
abs is and that's exactly what we do
yep so that that's exactly what we just
did here and then it says if it's less
than zero it does this otherwise it
returns the normalized or well it always
returns from its version so that's
exactly what we do
and so the only question is does this do
the same thing let's see if it does so
in their branch which is here they do
this that's the X y equals 1 minus the
abs of the Y X that's exactly what we're
doing here times the sign of the X Y so
no they don't flip the mmm so they've
got that right and that was what I was
agonizing about the end there and so why
is that the case though because the flip
oh ok ok ok no ice I see what that's
case that's the case because we're
trying to leave the thing in the same
quadrant as it was and so we don't
actually want when we do that flip
that's just a 90 degree rotation but it
we don't want to change the quadrant so
ok I do I believe that so we almost got
it but no we were slightly wrong there
with the flip and I should have known
that cuz hey you have to invert the
function it's gonna have to flip and
maintain the sine the same way that did
in the input so I suppose that makes
sense but alright that seems fair
I'm totally fine with that I don't know
if that compiles - forgot errors in
there let's take a look looks like looks
like we're good so now we have a way of
doing our octahedral mapping for any
particular direction and we can also
unmapped it if we need to I don't know
that we actually need this without for
completeness sake I wanted to put in the
full mapping in and out because I don't
know maybe we want that I'm not sure at
the very least we'll have to use this in
the shader so you know there's that so
let's go ahead and take a look at how
we're actually encoding these things and
sending them down so if we take a look
at the lining code here let's go ahead
and switch to one of our test functions
because we have a lot of different stuff
here let me got test cast from probes
right and then we got the voxel output
nonsense here and all that right
and so we're gonna have to do now is to
start to think about these in a way that
actually allows us to output them a
little more sanely
and I guess what we could do here is
just keep the way that we're storing
them at the moment and you know again I
don't really know that we want these to
be stored the winter store but I'm gonna
sort of ignore that part of things for a
little while
so what I'm gonna do instead is say all
right we are storing light voxel cells
here which I have to have a bunch of
information in them I'm gonna say that
we're just gonna store this stuff as
actual little kernels of information
here so in our light color where we're
storing that I'm gonna actually say look
let's put that in the light color lookup
square dim let's just do that right so
here's the little square and the same
will be true of the D so the depth value
right
so for each voxel cell I'm just gonna
store this explicitly in the cell for
now I don't think this is gonna be
probably the way we want to do in the
end but I want this most straightforward
thing so that we don't really have any
ambiguity here right like I don't want
there to be any nonsense so yeah so
we'll start with that and we'll deal
with later what this is actually gonna
do now when we're accumulating into
these things I feel like the
accumulation can happen at the end using
the data that's in the transfer buffer
so I'm gonna go ahead and say that these
can just be probably
well time stretch hmm I guess for the
interest of simplicity for now that's
not what I'm going to say so let's do it
this way right so we can do our
accumulation separately I I just don't
know if that makes much sense in the
long run I think that's just dumb so you
know we'll we'll we'll smarten that up
later but for now we can just you know
we'll we'll do the fully expanded thing
just so we can isolate errors a little
bit better so that's gonna be our voxel
cells and when we put stuff in there
we'll put them in based on the
octahedral mapping all right let's see
here so we've got some trilinear
interpolation stuff happening you can
see the trailer pier is grabbing out of
whichever field we're looking for and
all that garbage so we could still do
that the only difference now is that the
field parameter has to actually have a
more interesting piece of information
with it and so when we're doing compute
radians here we're going to have to
actually do a smarter sum right so this
is not what we actually want we're gonna
have to yeah I mean I'm gonna if this
out for now right because we're gonna
want to do something different there but
for now we'll just say we get back
nothing and what we actually want to do
here is we're gonna actually we're going
to want to sample the particular
direction that we're looking in so this
is really just going to be a sample by
when we actually need to do this compute
voxel irradiance
we're just going to need to actually
produce a sample there right like so
take the direction figure out you know
do octahedral from unit vector and then
get
the actual particular X&amp;Y out that we
want to index and that's what we would
do in the end so it's actually not gonna
be very hard well and and there will
only be right it'll look like this right
well we'll take an octahedral we'll
convert it to like a Texel or a table
and like that by just multiplying it by
the total number of pixels that there
are right so it'll be really simple for
us to do actually at the end of the day
we will know exactly what we're looking
at there and and it'll be fine but when
we actually do our get irradiance value
we're not gonna we're probably going to
need to have this be a little smoother
so what we might have to do here is
actually take a tri linear filter of
bilinear filters right because we wanna
when we actually do that sample we want
to actually get this so this part will
actually maybe turn into a bilinear
sample but we won't have to call this
four times right it'll just be once with
one value and that's all we would
actually need so anyway anyway alright
so in here where we're doing our
accumulation again not a thing so we
kind of need this too you know this
stuff will have to be sort of written in
a little bit more a little bit later on
and yeah so all of this stuff yes still
not not really gonna work yet
so these all have to be kind of stub to
do yep
all right so I think we're now at the
actual place we care about so we don't
want to do these tests what we want to
do is just test a light sphere first and
so let's go ahead and do that or maybe
we want to take a test of checker board
first we probably want to do both
honestly but we'll take a look so when
we look at how these are going to be
written to this is not probably what we
want anymore
would be my guess probably what we want
to do is just write directly to the
voxel in question because now we need to
kind of think about which one we're
actually writing to right so and you
know I guess the other way to look at it
would be if this is if this is actually
the test version of it then maybe what
we would want to do is where are these
getting copied out though okay so this
is writing directly into the bitmap as
well so that's fine all right so if
we're going to go through all of these I
think what the or them want to do is
actually have where we write out we're
gonna want to write the individual
values that we have like so we're gonna
want to loop through the the
two-dimensional octahedral unwrapped
block right so what we're gonna want to
do here is have a thing where we write
out for each direction like we're going
to want to do sort of our r-tx
in rty and these are going to be
wrapping the whole thing right as ugly
as that as that is right yeah so for
each of these we're going to need to
output a light color and a light depth
and if I start them off like so then we
just need to actually have like our test
light sphere do something right and so
the first thing presumably we would do
is say all right we needed to get a unit
vector from whatever the octahedral
sample actually is in this case and
we're not gonna worry about the gutter
right now so we'll sort of start by
doing this without the gutter and then
we'll work out the gutter part
separately so the actual vector here so
like the Oh X Y vector we know that it's
the T X and the T Y but they actually
have to be normalized out right so we
have to take T X and divide it by light
color lookup squared M minus 1 and we
need our t y to be link color lookup
squared M minus 1 oops
and then we've got our sort of in that's
our input so it's normalized zero to one
inside the octahedron and we now need to
convert that out to a direction right so
this is the light der like this is or
this is the sample der so this is which
direction we're looking so the o XY goes
in the sample direction comes out and
then we need to like figure out what the
heck we're doing with the sphere here so
you can see we're trying to compute some
other stuff about where we are in voxel
space that's all fine so then we have to
look and say alright what is all this
about
like what's the intensity of light in
this direction
you know what would we see from the
light source if we were pointing in this
direction and so on and I guess what we
would say is if we know this stuff like
we've got how far away it is and all
that I don't know this is multiple
lights and I guess I don't really want
that at the moment so let's let's delete
some of this stuff here all right so we
just want to say what the color of the
light would be at this point I don't
know why we've got an extra I don't know
why there's an extra one of these it
shouldn't be I think that's right right
yeah so for each of these directions we
need to put something in here for the
light and I guess this is a little bit
tough for us to know what this should be
because we don't really know like what
we don't really know what we're talking
about here because it's it's light
that's coming from all directions and
we're you know it's hard to translate a
point light into that environment
because it's not really what that means
so I guess what we could do is let's
pretend that we just have a directional
light because that would actually work
okay so if we wanted a directional light
or
or I guess we go gonna do is a point
light with a with a size right we could
sort of say look what how close are you
to pointing to this thing and we'll just
fall off from there
so if we said all right the direction to
the light from where we are is like the
light UVW - the vox uvw right and the
light uvw is up here right so wherever
the light is we know this points towards
the light we know this is how far we are
from the light we can do the fall-off
exactly as we would have done before and
then we can kind of just stuff this
thing in there for the light color that
all would work but now we need to also
take into account the clamped zero to
one inner product between the direction
we're pointing and the direction we're
sampling right so we just need to say
look whatever the light normal was we
want to dot that with whatever our
sample direction was and fall off from
there so the actual light a right in
this case is going to multiply by this
clamped version here so that we can get
you know what we would have expected
once we get the light color I don't
really want it ranging from negative one
to one per se anymore it should just be
zero to one so this part is kind of
wrong and this is yeah just not what we
actually want so what we probably should
say is like clamp zero one here of the
light see so something like that is more
or less what we want and so the light
color would just be you know whatever
the actual light color would be so maybe
that for now but times this information
right
all right our light depth we don't fill
in here so we'll just leave that as you
know some other large value I don't know
what it should be something like this I
guess and we'll kind of cross that
bridge when we come to it because we
will need this somewhere so I don't know
how many units the maximum travel should
be but you know I don't know let's say
it's 128 for no real reason and then
we'll just say max light death so
that'll fill out our table and what is
the complaint I hads a previous
definition what is the previous
definition oh it's this definition all
right so we're gonna make that light
seen like D then because oh well and
this is light color so what we probably
wanted to look at here is now okay are
those things actually getting output
anywhere because they don't think they
are right so at some point we then have
to actually write this data out and and
we're not doing that right like I don't
I don't see that happening anywhere
yeah so you know you look at what's
happening here these need to actually be
written somewhere if they need to be
written into the voxel somewhere and I
guess I'm not I'm not sure when we would
have wanted to do that it seems like you
would have wanted to do it right here
but for some reason we're not where is
this where is this at
hmm so I guess I don't understand what's
going on here because looking at
producing these values I don't really
ending if we're doing this in the hot
dimension here right then what we should
be able to do is each time we come
through here we should then be able to
write this thing back but no one is
actually writing it back you can see
that here it would have been running it
back but like what were so what was
going on here or did these just directly
write before because they don't now so
I'm not sure I really understand why
what's going on with that I guess we
just accidentally deleted the code that
would have done that here but again this
is the code that would have done that
you can see it writing it out here right
like this is the part that would have
actually done that piece of work so I'm
super confused it looks like this is old
news or maybe accidentally deleted
something important there but point
being like this is what we would
actually want right so in here we would
actually want to put you know we'd want
to put this this here so we would want
like our light data see in our light
data D you know we would we would be
doing this right and so we would need to
be able to to index out into those in a
way that made sense here and so I don't
really know exactly what's going on
there
that's pretty confusing but anyway you
know it would look something like this
so that would write it into the texture
now the problem is we don't know what
this value actually is like yes this is
using the dimensions of the hot corner
part properly in theory to locate us in
the actual texture but the problem is
this doesn't take into account the
actual size of the actual image of each
like footprint right
so what we actually need to do here is
say alright we are indexing into this
thing by every time we take a step in X
it's actually x times the x the like
ktem right whatever the octahedral
dimension is so we every time we take a
7 X we're going one octave over right
every time we take a step in Y it's
actually hot dim you know times acht dim
right because we have to go that many
X's and every time we take a step in Z
we need to take a step x times the ktem
squared because we're actually taking
you know a step in both of those the two
that both things right it's it's taking
a step in this total bit here I believe
is that correct yeah yep I think that's
right
so I think that's what we would actually
do and the oxygen of course in this case
is not actually pulled out from so if
you look at the hot damn it comes out of
here but it we actually know this and
it actually looks like this right and in
theory that's how we would actually
write out the pixels right that's where
they go and we don't really want to do
that long term because it's pretty bad
the way we're doing that but you know
this is just getting things working so
this is the we have two of these right
one is the one for the color and ones
for the depth and the only difference
between them is who's you know ktem you
used and I think that's it and then we
just need to you know at this point we
probably want to clean this code up a
little bit I'm not really sure what the
game render commands actually called
this thing so light voxels see and light
voxel D so I think that's all we need
this is just I don't know what we want
to actually compute here I guess this is
just a so so this is the a the a and the
again and I think that's all
all right so that doesn't really help us
because you know we don't really have
time to do anything with it so you know
we're writing out those values but you
know we don't know they're not actually
doing anything anyways and we don't have
an idea of what that even looks like at
the moment now I could actually try to
throw the lighting in there real quick
but I don't really want to because we
need to actually sit down and do the
rest of it now so we'll just probably
leave it at that for today what I would
say is let's take a just as a final
thing at the end of the of the process
here let's just go ahead and try to open
our handmade render launch so let's just
see if we can't take a quick capture of
a frame and validate that we actually
even are sending anything and that they
are actually at least somewhat the right
dimensions or something right so if we
take a look at one of these color passes
here you can see some draw elements
calls building these things up in theory
there should be an actual texture that
goes along with that and if we looked at
the texture viewer I guess I'm not sure
I'm not really we've mostly been using
insight so I'm not super facile with
render doc but we should be able to go
look and see what textures were actually
being sampled here or could have been
sampled
I don't know where to get that
information unfortunately um hmm so
where's the bound textures does that do
we know where that would be maybe I'll
save this for next time because like I
said I never use render dock we used
insight most of the time so I don't even
know how we're picking a texture here
like is there a texture list somewhere
there we go ah ha ha there it is
I found it so there should be a
dimension listed here so here's some
dimensions listed here right and looking
at this that I don't know well that's a
checkerboard though I guess because it's
this thing here so looking at looking at
these you can see like the various ones
we have here and it looks like those are
probably the ones where's our texture
atlas oh man our texture array I don't
know where our texture array is it
should be your summer so there's a one
by one by one that's not that's like our
null texture or whatever there it is so
here's all our sprites right and I don't
I don't know how you flip through those
[Music]
here we go so here's our like there's
our texture atlas right so that's our
dual texture here's our texture atlas
this presumably is our lighting data and
I'll be honest that's not very good like
there's nothing in there which seems bad
because we should have written something
right and there's our depth somehow our
depth actually has information in it
which makes no sense because it
shouldn't but it apparently does so
there's that right how did that happen
oh because we are writing maxilla max
light depth but we should have written
it everywhere and we very clearly don't
oh I know why that is as well so in
addition here where we do our slices we
also have to do our are offset by our X
Y so our TX has to be in here obviously
and our T Y has to be in here as well
and the T Y has to move down by you know
the x ox dim oops let me put that on the
next line to unpack into the texture
Atlas properly we need to do a I split
this poorly
right I need to actually develop some
addressing for this so the why here in
this case the TX will just step one at a
time but the T Y is going to have to
step down a row at a time right and in
this particular case I guess I don't
know how we were planning to store these
because we never really talked about it
but I'm assuming that we would want to
store them in actual rows in actual 2d
rows what that means is that instead of
a separate T Y there we kind of just
want we want to multiply that by the hot
dim times the oxy dim itself right
because we need to move down an entire
row at a time right so this Y here is
actually this because for each Y we need
to move down an entire see dims worth of
rows so it would actually look like this
we're gonna have to systematize this
because that's pretty ugly right but
that's that's what we actually have to
do and
so there we go
but right so that would actually be the
summation there I don't know why our
Lightsey values are coming out as zero
all the time whereas our light D values
are actually writing in properly so I
guess like this is not working right
apparently so we'll have to take a look
at what's happening there because we
should at least get something sometimes
right for this stuff so we'll have to
look at what's actually going in there a
little bit later but let me just double
check that this in fact writes we want
to be able to write - wait a minute how
do I stop the capture did I already stop
the capture um close capture I guess
again my non familiarity with render
dock is a little bit rough here so
anyway yeah if we wanted to just just
verify for our own purposes that we were
getting anything out there
it looks like the read values we're
getting written for us but I don't know
about anybody else so if I actually come
through here oops that's not what I
wanted if I actually launched this this
fellow into a print screen and then
closed now what I should be able to do
is take a look at that texture that was
read before which is this and there's
some stuff in there which is read before
it should be all read which it is now it
doesn't really mean it's right it just
means we are at least writing to the
whole thing which is what we wanted and
looking at this one we actually get some
stuff in here but it looks wrong so it's
probably not quite right it's probably
almost right but our indexing might be
slightly off just looking at what's
going on here or our octahedral stuff
could
also be buggy right um yeah so I don't
know what to make of that exactly but
it's not the worst thing that we've ever
made so I think it puts us in position
to get going next weekend
all right I'm happy to go to a brief Q&amp;A
now
ah okay yeah you're right I did do that
where's the let me switch back here
you're right so this one we can't quite
do because we need it so I guess in this
case I can just do that right because we
don't actually change these values so I
can just do them this way I suppose
right
I think the Uzi doesn't need to be
negated in the unit vector from
octahedral function um I think you're
wrong I think it does need to be negated
right you know what i'm santi so if if
you look at what's happening and enya in
here we probably wanna do the same thing
right
so I'm not sure how we write that
cleanly so if I hmm so I'm not really
sure what we would do there so I guess
what we would do is say all right yeah
because this one's nice because we
already sort of made it out into more
variable so it's easy for us to make
this work without worrying about the
overwrite right
someone took my name does it always know
so we're trying to produce a unit vector
right so Z has to be pointing in the
correct direction so I'm pretty sure we
always have to check were we on the
bottom of the sphere if we are we have
to negate Z because Z this is always
going to be Plus this is always going to
give us a positive Z but Z points down
sometimes right so yeah
so I'm pretty sure we need this line as
to how to rewrite this one so what's the
cleanest way to do this but that makes
that vector notation so much nicer when
you think about it because you don't
have this problem in there it'd be nice
if we could do that but we can't really
but anyway so yeah I guess we just have
to compute them as temps whoa just
happened that was weird
all right you know we we could do this
you know I guess if one minus sum X Y is
less than zero no but but it's not it's
it's whether it's less than 1 not 0
right
oh I see you just uh hmm yeah all right
now that's a good point it would already
turn negative all right no all right I
believe you I believe you yeah because
if if these were greater than one then
this will be negative anyway so we don't
have to negate it because it will negate
it itself yeah I buy that yeah so the
reference code does use sign of not zero
but that's actually the same for us so
if you look at sign of for us we
actually do ours is a sign of not zero
that's how we defined our sign of I
guess in their land sign of would return
zero if it was equal to zero ours
already returns positive so we kind of
already did that which makes us not
quite be Nam and clay chore compatible
but that's okay I mean you're never
going to be exactly but let me let me
double check this area I think I have a
typo in the trial Earp code
so what trailer code though we don't
have any of that at the moment right
it's returning positive for zero yeah we
that's what we do but it wouldn't really
matter you could you could return either
when you want it but we return positive
for zero as well why would we need it to
I don't think that's true why would we
need to return zero for zero actually
you know I disagree I think it I think
it actually can't return zero for zero
if it returns zero for zero I think it
would be a bug actually are you sure
their code returns zero for zero because
that actually doesn't seem necessary in
this case at all right yeah no their
code does not do that their code very
specifically does not return zero ever
right it isn't it does not do that and
neither does ours right so it can only
return positive one or negative one
right just like ours and like I said I
think that's crucial I don't think this
routine where if this returns zero I
think this routine would stop working
because if you you want to retain the
value even in the case where it's zero
because you're actually Swizzle your you
know what I'm saying like you're
actually so like in this case you you
are using the sine of X but the
magnitude of Y and so if X happens to be
zero you don't want to ruin your y
computation because you don't know that
Y is one because remember Z is in the
mix so if X is zero Y might not be one
like it doesn't have to be because Z
could have been it could have been on
the Y Z slice so X can be 0 and
I can still be any value between zero
and one pretty negative one in one so I
think this actually very specifically
there's a reason they called this sine
not zero is because they can't actually
return it's not the regular sine
function the regular sine function I
think returns zero for zero I think
maybe not but they at least know that's
not okay like they need to know what the
actual sine would have been quadrant
wise and you can pick plus or minus
depending on 0 like this could go the
opposite way this could be a greater
than instead of greater than equal to
and I think the routine would just would
still just work fine but what you can't
do is ever actually return 0 there
because that knocks out the equation and
you would you would miss the ring so so
let me let me take a look at the that
the you were talk about the txt y thing
though as a separate issue so let me
just take a look at that oh yeah this
one yeah I mean we're not actually gonna
use this though so they can ignore that
that that's you know we're gonna have to
rewrite that little part but it's gonna
look something like that right all right
folks wanted a recap on render doc just
to see if this Rizal changed things much
we can totally do that but we probably
VAT other problems right we just kind of
hacked that in there really quickly
haven't tested anything yet so you know
I think we got a ways to go because
there's a lot of moving parts in here
so here it is um I don't know that that
looks like it might still have some
errors in it it's better than it was
though but I'm not sure right we'll see
we're not far I mean we just got a
streamline this right so you'll be fine
he's oxly I'm supposed to be mapped
between 0 and negative 0 and 1 or
negative 1 1 in the light setup code oh
yeah you know what so actually that's a
good point
so I believe this hmm
I believe this generally wants to map
between negative 1 and 1
so this maps between negative 1 and 1
and so I assume what we actually want to
do here when we're doing the actual fill
we probably want to actually make that
before we forget map this between 0 &amp; 1
first because when we actually do the TX
dy this code here this right here
probably need is going to need to map
this to negative 1 to 1 so once we
actually do the mapping from 0 to 1 we
need to do this
right good catch there cuz we it's not
it's not mapped the right way round
right because it the txt why is talking
about pixels in a grid and it starts at
zero and so we want to actually change
that into the unit square which we need
to do differently right so again that
that'll affect the unwrapping
all right so there's our where we're
gonna leave it right and you know it
kind of looks like some lighting sort of
I mean I could believe that that was
storing some lighting couldn't you I
wouldn't want to bet on it but it looks
okay like I said I think it's a
reasonable starting point we got a lot
of debugging to do and we're gonna want
to clean that stuff up and and all that
so it's it's you know we've got a we got
some work to do but I don't think we're
in bad shape right we've got the basics
started so I think we're okay if it's
okay to ask something off topic why
aren't more engines using dynamic DLL
deso for hot deployment of game code I
think they are I mean isn't that what
unreal does I don't think that's unusual
I think lots of engines do it do you
find it annoying to keep hopping between
editor and debugger when you're
programming in your ideal environment
with these two tools be unified in the
same window I guess I don't really know
they probably wouldn't be in the same
window because I want my debugger on my
second monitor normally and I want my
editor on my main monitor so like the
main monitor runs my editor in the game
and like a secondary monitor runs the
debugger so probably all I really want
is the ability to synchronize the view
between the two and we've kind of talked
about this before I talked with George
about this and I think it's not that
hard to do that right but what I really
just want is my editor and my debugger
to stay in sync I don't really want them
to necessarily be the same application
for any particular reason
and I definitely don't want them to be
the same display it's a special case of
handmade hero that it looks like this
normally I would not have my debugger on
the same monitor
could be a good idea to add to the debug
system a way to look at the OpenGL
texture we could switch lists from the
game well no I I don't know if you
remember but I specifically said that's
exactly what we're going to do so we
haven't gotten there yet but we're
definitely doing that don't you think
using a CPP file instead of a batch file
for build setup and configuration would
be better since patch files are so bad
who builds the C file right at the
minimum you need a batch file to build
the C file that then does the build so
sure you could go that route but you
still need build up at you can never get
rid of build that bad unreal only does
it fairly recently using an external
tool which cost the most zero
implementation effort yeah like I I
don't know I mean I don't know why
anyone does what they do I have no idea
it's easy to reload code but I mean one
thing you have to remember is when you
go into giant C++ nonsense land
reloading code becomes very difficult
because you've got all these function
pointers strewn throughout all your code
sitting in dynamic tables all over the
place and you've done fifty million
calls to new and you have no idea what
they allocated so like the fact that we
program sensibly on handmade hero is one
of the things that made it so easy to do
and so I guess what I would say is
sometimes the reason people can't do
this is cuz they make a lot of really
bad decisions and use a lot of stupid
modern C++ features that suck so you can
make it a lot harder on yourself by
using virtual functions for example
all right
thank you everyone for joining me flips
on a handmade hero sort of pleasure
coating with you as always if you would
like to follow series at home you can
always peer to the game on handmade here
org and it comes with a source code I
will be back here next week when we will
do some work streamlining that process
and trying to getting our lighting up
and running using just a simple sphere
light like we were doing before just so
we can test that Atlas packing scheme
and see if we can you know kind of iron
out all the rough edges and and get
everything debugged that's it for this
week until next week have fun
programming and I will see everyone on
the Internet
take it easy everybody