hello everybody and welcome to handmade
heroes show Rico to complete game live
on stream we need to test our font
importing today and fix anything that's
broken with it if I remember correctly
there's one thing we didn't quite get to
finish last weekend when we did all this
stuff it was that when you encounter in
the font in sort of the manifest if you
will that says what kinds of information
go with this font we have a routine
that's like stubbed-out currently which
needs to do the import of the PNG for
the font glyph and this is just a rehash
of code we already have to import the
PNG and pack it into the art pack file
but we didn't do the work of actually
like calling out to the correct things
to do that so we need to do a little bit
of like of a code reorganization just
some a little bit to make sure that we
can reuse that same path for both cases
the case where we import a sprite and
the case where we import a font glyph so
we need to do that today and then get
everything debugged which would probably
I'm sure we'll take today and tomorrow
to do because there was a lot of
subtlety in it if I remember correctly
so what we want to do now is just jump
into that particular implementation
detail get that working and then we can
move on to testing everything and
debugging it so I'm gonna load up and
made hero here gonna go ahead and do the
builds and I don't know if this probably
builds okay yeah cuz we had a not
implemented there and so actually we
haven't searched for not implement in a
while how much we got let's take a look
so it looks like we've got a 1 hanging
around here in the in the room generator
stuff which is fine that looks like
that's not even in there anymore there's
the one we're talking about
and then right we have to do the base
name so we've got 2
we want to do today this one's trivial
it's just changing get a create asset
source file to be able to use a non null
terminated string because we just kind
of moved away from those and there's
still a couple old parts of the codebase
that still use them I don't really want
them hanging around and then we have to
do this import glyph so those are the
two things we want to do today let's
start with this one because it's
probably a little bit more
straightforward in the getter create
asset source file the original call was
taking this care start base name here
what I'd like to do is change it to take
the base name as actual string which is
you know a length string as opposed to a
null terminated string and so what I
really want to do here is just to pull
this part out and actually you know
implement the one implement it off of
this kind of a call and then the one
that has the null terminated if we want
to we don't really have to go patch the
rest of the people who were doing this
what we can do instead here is just wrap
it and then pass it along that's not as
efficient but it's totally fine for our
purposes at the moment because again
this is not really a hot code path that
we care about so we don't really care
about the fact that maybe some people
out there who are currently doing worked
and they'll terminate something that
they didn't need to know terminate now
don't have to do that I don't really
care so what I'm going to do instead is
just you know have this thunk through to
the call that uses the string itself
like so and since we really don't use
the string for anything other than
matching and hashing both of which
already work off of strings I think
literally just moving the code into
something where base name is Mark this
type string as opposed to marked as type
care star is probably sufficient but let
me double check there may be one or two
small things we have to do there I just
type oh but yes so that that's it right
so again not really a big deal because
op function overloading took care of
that port for us right we have a strings
are equal in a string hash of for
regular strings so we didn't really even
need to change the code it just kind of
works right so that's it for that
what we need to do now is go back and
deal with the glyphs part of things and
that's a little bit more Squinkie
because we've got we've got more work to
do there right what's happening here is
when we asked to import a glyph with a
particular base name we need to do all
of the things we were doing before for
importing pngs
and so we want to try and figure out how
to share those two code paths so that we
don't have to do them twice and what you
can see here is you know the in the
normal code path it's kind of welded
together so if we take a look in here
and you know this is the branch that
we're talking about when we get to the
end where everything's been parsed for
like our sprites or something what you
can see is that when we get into the
needs will rebuild part of the code
this where we open the file that
contains the PNG builds the checksum
right it goes ahead and makes a stream
for reading the PNG asks it to be parsed
doesn't import types which and then
picks one of the import kinds right and
then comes out here to do the asset
metadata updating that whole series of
things wants to happen here as well and
in addition to that there was already
something up here that it happened that
we also care about which as you can see
we build a location that we want this
thing to come from right so it's got a
art directory associated with it that's
off of the sources path and what we want
to be able to do there is we want to go
off of the sources path find the PNG
file look to see whether or not that PNG
file is newer than the last time we read
it you know and that's what's happening
here and or report if we didn't find it
and then move on from there
right so that's what we're trying to do
here and so I kind of want something
that's going to allow me to reuse some
of this code so that I'm not duplicating
anything that I want to make sure
happens the same way in both cases
um again like I don't really care too
much one eye I'm not a fetishist when it
comes to you know as you know I always
try to emphasize practical programming
so I don't care about abstracting things
for abstraction steak or object-oriented
programming or any of that garbage I
think it's all a waste of time but what
I do care about is not creating extra
work for myself because that's the most
important thing in programming is to not
create extra work and if we just cut and
paste these things together what's gonna
happen is if I need to maintain
something so if I need to change part of
it right I'm gonna have to change it in
multiple places and that becomes a
maintenance headache for me when things
are complicated like they are inside the
asset import system so again the
complexity of the system versus how much
maintenance might be required all these
sorts of things they combine in this
case to make me nervous in a way that I
don't want this code getting spread out
to lots of places where each one is
doing it and then perhaps the way
they're doing it ends up diverging I
don't like that idea so what I want here
is a way of making sure that the parts
that are sensitive are shared so that I
only have to change those parts once if
I need to like update the way that it's
done so again what I'm going to do is
standard compression or in a program
approach here I'm going to do the cut
and paste temporarily I'm going to see
what I write an import glyph and then
I'm going to try and pull out the common
sections to have both code paths call
those common sections and in doing it
that way I'm hoping that I will avoid
abstracting things in a way that
actually makes them cumbersome and
instead focus on only abstracting those
things that can be cleanly done
parametrically all right so here we go
I'm gonna go ahead and copy this part
because I know it will have to happen
right I'm going to need to do a file
name I don't need to parse it because
I'm getting it passed in here so the
part that would normally come from file
name is actually already done the format
string however would be the same and it
would need to use the HHA stem the
subtor in this case is known to always
be font
so we can pretty much hard-code that one
actually you know to this because
they're not allowed to come from
anywhere else at least at the moment and
then we have the bitmap base name coming
in here which is like that and this is
how we produced that source so again you
know looking at that that that looks
like something we'll be able to compress
into a common call because it's very
very structured right very much what we
would expect when we go through here and
do the get file path this stuff all
would be exactly the same way and the
match would would be the same as well
all of these things would be exactly the
same and the needs full rebuild would be
the same as well so you can you can see
why I think that this wants to be shared
because just looking at it a lot of the
things are exactly the same now when we
actually issue the error here we do have
a problem we don't really know where we
would be issuing that error to hopefully
and here the context has that it does so
that makes it easier on us so we should
be able to do something like okay let's
output to this error stream like so and
we can say file not found with this path
that we looked for that should be
sufficient right because we don't really
need to attach a token name to it since
the path should be fairly obvious now if
we did want to attach a token to it we
could do it that way by having import
cliff take an actual token here because
we do have one that comes with and it
could take the tokenizer and the token I
don't know how you guys feel about that
it's it would be Barrett slightly better
err reporting so maybe it is worth it in
other words maybe it's a better idea to
just do something like this and then
what I can do is say alright it's fine
here's the tokenizer and here's the
source token in question it seems okay
and then when we call import glyph when
we're doing this it's pretty easy
because we we would be calling it
directly off of a glyph parse right so
in here where we do glyph
are we even calling you forklift yet
gonna be honest I'm not sure if he ever
did that dude oh yeah we I'm like where
is it I just couldn't see it comes off
the side so in here right we know
exactly where we would call this because
we have the glyph token so yeah I'm just
gonna go ahead and say let's pass that
through because it just would lead to
better error reporting so that when you
get an error the person will get a file
on line number then they can go look at
to know what's wrong in their tags file
that seems like a worthwhile case so
just go ahead and pass it along right
all right um so that's the start that
opens up the source PNG as necessary so
when we get this file we would say all
right you know check to see whether we
already know about this file let's see
whether or not we need to do a full
rebuild so etc and so then the next
thing that we want to do is we want to
copy the part that actually parses the
PNG so let's go through here and do that
here's that full rebuild this is this
desk file index part is also the same
right like all of this stuff is pretty
much the same so all through here what
we would do is copy this entire block
right there it is
and you can see through here we would
just say alright assuming that we were
able to find a file this thing goes with
because you know we if we can't then we
we assume that we air it out in here and
we we don't want to proceed assuming
that it worked out what we're gonna do
is check to make sure that we've labeled
this and if it turns out that it moved
eight days we need to mark a full
rebuild
and many come through here actually just
looking at it I'm wondering if we can
just pull out this entire thing and I
don't really need to cut and paste it if
you look at what happens here it looks
like it's almost entirely reusable just
directly as it is and if we pass the
import grid in here which we could do I
think we would just be done so I'm
actually gonna go ahead and say I'm not
even gonna bother with this one here I'm
just gonna say like this is the update
you know imported asset file or
something like this so there's going to
be a call here called like update
imported asset data from file or
something right and what I'm going to do
is extract this code out as that call
because it's just so obviously clear
that I can there's not a lot of point in
me actually going through and changing
anything because I don't think I would
change anything so in here we're gonna
have update asset data from file that's
gonna take whatever we determine it
actually needs to take in order for us
to get in order in order for us to get
out of it what we want and so when I
call import glyph I'm going to call it
and similarly when you know when were in
here we're gonna call it like so now
there's a little bit of a rub the import
glyph needs to be able to know what the
bitmap was that it imported and so
that's gonna kind of be a separate part
that we need to weld into that update
acid data from file that's the one thing
that's going to require a little bit of
modification in order for it to be used
with import glyph but other than that
everything probably is going to be okay
if we take a look at update acid data
from file now I want to work backwards
from the place where it was originally
done to figure out what it actually
needs to be passed for file information
looking at it it's pretty obvious that
we're gonna need the context so you know
cuz that goes through anything that's
doing
or it means that the information in that
context so it's gonna need that it's
also going to need the assuming the
needs full rebuild flag because maybe
someone wants to force the full rebuild
to happen and so again that needs to
occur there it needs to have that match
file so the this thing here that we were
actually pulling out is what is the the
information about the source file that
we've stored that has to be there as
well because that's been found by the
outer code so we need those and then
when we come through here we can start
to see this temporary nakir actually
comes out of the context I will go ahead
and pull that out just to make it a
little easier you can see that's a thing
we've got here that just makes it so I'd
have to go through and change this this
typing everything else in here looks
okay the file info needs to be passed so
meaning this platform file basically the
things that we're at the top of this you
know those need to be passed in so this
is where the file is coming from uh
maybe that would go here and what else
so all of this stuff is is
self-contained so then when we come
through here we've got stuff like is art
is audio and then we have like the
import type and you know honestly just
looking at that it seems kind of stupid
for it to be done that way we don't so
we don't really need that is audio we
don't we don't really need that stuff
anymore so I think I'm going to go ahead
and simplify that case and then we'll
look at the the next part so for example
in here right we've just got this parse
PNG with the image here I feel like that
is just it's not that much code so I
feel like this is just fine right and in
fact we could just pull these out right
so we've got you know these two here and
then the sound goes in here and these
or like that right and that way you were
only really passing one thing down there
oops I mean do that I meant to do that
so that would be only need to pass one
thing to this this function and that is
which type of content import you were
intending to do and that's the only
thing that you'll have to tell me right
that's the only thing that you have to
tell that code so if I go ahead and grab
import type and put that up here that
should take care of that part looking in
here as at the like is audio is art
stuff III should also look to see
whether anyone actually cares about that
so no one does it looks like the only
thing that actually people care about
here is the is art flag is used to do a
couple things so I think that is all you
can just go away we we just don't need
that and really all we need is the one
thing that says is art is true because
there's some errors and some things we
do that we wouldn't do if it wasn't art
right so that seems pretty easy and so
then in here for something like the is
art side of things and seeing whether or
not we need to make this stuff get
mapped I feel like that's something we
could still do outside I don't know
exactly how I want that to happen
so this might want to not occur here as
I guess what I'm saying
I may want this to be only in the other
code path
I'm let's put it there temporarily and
see what we want to do with the line
points separately so what I'm going to
do is I'm not going to I'm not going to
unify that code path just yet about let
that happen here right and that way it
should be such that this kind of returns
some sort of a result here and assuming
that this thing matches I guess we'll do
something like this so meaning if there
were if it if it thinks it's okay right
then off we would go so then I think
that leaves us mostly just looking at
what's happening here
with just these extra things that need
to get sort of sorted out which is the
fields the template tags and the append
tag so those are the things that need to
happen to make sure that the metadata
for the asset gets updated with the
information that we have and looking at
that I do think this becomes the right
decision and the reason for that is that
fonts don't have updating we get our
kerning information out of the file so
we don't we we can't really edit that in
the game because if we did it wouldn't
it would get overwritten by the HH font
utility if you ever tried to modify the
font anyway so it seems to me like
that's not really something we would
need to have happen so that does suggest
to me that maybe this is what it should
look like now if I go grab how the rest
of this stuff is supposed to work so we
look in here we've got append tags and
template tags and that stuff if we want
to
make that stuff work as something that's
passed in I'm going to have to have a
place where it does get passed in so
we're gonna have to have the append tags
here we're gonna need the template as
well which is here and the fields so I
think that's pretty much it and then in
here we would pass that directly so it
would look something like this and I
think then that pretty much just creates
the the same code path we were doing
before but it has now the ability to be
called from elsewhere now if we actually
want to call this properly and didn't
look like we get in the errors there so
it looks like we're pretty much good to
go if we go ahead and just make sure we
pass all these well they all should
basically just be stuff that we already
hopes that's the wrong thing let's try
that one more time so if we just take
the context the match the file info
passed those down we know the import
type we know the needs full rebuild
we've got the fields and the template
tags and the append tags we've got
everything it needs to do its job so I
think that should create a correct call
and so then we're just down to the fact
that when we want to do an import glyph
scuse me when we want to do an import
glyph we need to be able to call it here
now what I'm sort of seeing as I look at
this is it looks like import clip import
glyph probably won't actually have to be
its own function assuming that we make a
utility that does this because like I
said it's happening in two places that I
want to make sure it happens the same
the
it's really gonna end up being like two
or three calls total inside this import
cliff thing and there's really not it's
just gonna create more work for me to
call it as something separate so I'm not
gonna do that what I'm gonna do instead
is weld it directly into the code that
does the font processing so right here
where we do this import glyph call I'm
actually just gonna say let's knife that
temporarily and let's jam this whole
piece of block of code right in here and
and simplify it down in place and I
think that's gonna be a more effective
way to finish this off all right so we
know that here we're gonna want to do
you know we're gonna want to do this
exact stuff that we were doing so we're
will tackle that in a second and then
finally we want to call update acid data
assets data from file and in order to
call that we need to make sure that we
actually can pass it all of the because
it needs quite a few things to be able
to do that processing right if you just
look at what goes on here so if we need
to pass all of these things the question
is do we actually have them and let's
see so we know we've got the context we
know we're gonna determine the match we
know we can determine the file info for
import type there is only one import
type that we're allowing for a font and
that's gonna be probably import type
single tile meaning it has to be you
know just just one bitmap there right we
could call it a plate I don't really
know hmm okay so if I go to process
plate import versus process single tile
what am I gonna see what's the
difference between those two you know
here they are so in one case so the
really the only difference is that
plates have a higher maximum dimension
that's it
there's no otherwise these are exactly
the same really we should just have one
call and all it does is passed it right
I mean there's nothing else the only
difference between these two is the
right I mean unless I'm missing
something there there is no they are
exact copies I mean check me on this I
don't want to be wrong so I think what
we could say here is that process plate
import if you if all you did was take a
maximum dim value then effectively these
just collapse down to one call so if I
go to the update asset data from file
call here and say well when these are
actually going through their motions if
we want to do a multi tile well then it
does need to do its little like search
function but if we're going to do a
single tile or a plate then really those
can just call process single tile and
then take either the max plate dim or
the max bright dim right so it would
just be this exact same path no
difference and really it's just that
parameter that creates the difference so
that would allow us to get rid of
process plate import and replace it with
something that just takes a maximum
dimension that maximum dimension gets
passed here and here and we're done so
that's kind of a nice collapse as well
anyway point being it for that purpose
now we know if we just pass single tile
that's fine for what we were trying to
do there where's our font wow there's a
lot of things called font that's the one
we're actually looking for so in here
where we do our import when we're
talking about the import type if my head
moves out of the way
we've got single time port the needs
full rebuild we don't really know what
that's gonna be oh wait what we actually
are did to find I was gonna say we need
you know it's gonna be something that
gets set up here but we did do that
array so we've got that we know we've
got the
yields and then so what we're really
talking about is the template tags in
the appendix now I think and maybe I'm
wrong about this but I think that our
template tags are just irrelevant
because there's nothing really we need
to set there let's find out I don't
actually know if that's true so that's
an import grid tags so the asset basic
category is probably something we would
want to set which is to say that the
basic categories we don't really need to
set it but it seems like we might as
well hmm I mean I guess technically it
just doesn't need a basic category
because fog lifts are looked up directly
so I don't know it doesn't so I think we
literally just don't care and I don't
know if that if if the basic category
when you do
I don't know if it correctly checks to
see so when it does asset type equals
zero and then sets it you know it looks
yeah
it looks like it's always gonna chain
these together I kind of want it to just
ignore anything that's type zero though
you know what I'm saying to you so I
kind of feel like I want it to say like
only do this if it's actually valid like
I don't really want to keep chains Eero
stuff because you should never be
looking up on a tag for a chains ero so
I'm kind of gonna say let's just leave
that out for now and maybe that's a bad
idea but I think that's the way I want
it so we'll make that work eventually in
import grid tags here that means that
this is just gonna be nothing and so I
can just sort of have that be you know
something that nobody cares about I
don't actually know if we do that
anywhere else here I don't think we do
so when we do the import I think that
pretty much takes care of it so the
template tags are just garbage and then
that leaves us just with append tags and
append tags again I think can just be
nothing the reason I think that it can
just be nothing is because again these
all of these bitmaps Parden are not they
have no information on them they they
aren't ever looked up outside of the
font itself so I think when we append it
we can just say like no don't stick any
tags on these things they're completely
blank all we need to know is what the
bitmap ID is and that's the end of it
right
okay so the only problem that I think
we're left with here I is that this
piece of code needs still needs to work
so after we do the import we need some
way of saying if we were able to like
actually import this piece this glyph
this piece of the fonts we need some way
of getting back what the bitmap ID
actually was and the problem is we're
not gonna have any way to do that
because update asset data from file may
actually produce lots of bitmaps right
in the case where you've got multi tile
it's gonna just do a whole whole host of
things right so there is a bit of an
issue there but I believe we are saved
by the fact that since we're already
doing backing storage where we say what
came out of what file if we look inside
the asset system itself for those
matches that we're tracking like you
know we're tracking these source files
if you go look at the asset source file
information it just so happens to keep
all of those asset indices already so
what we should be able to do is say look
you don't need to return me that
information I can just say hey after
you're done if it worked then the asset
index you actually used is going to be
sitting in 0 0 of this source file
anyway because that's the only thing
that you're actually allowed to update
in a single tile export so it kind of
does work to return the stuff that we
wanted it to returned so that's pretty
great and I think that just kind of
works moving forward I don't know if I
don't know if there's really anything
else we need to do I think that might
just work so I think we're basically
left with just wanting this
piece of code to not have sort of the
duplication in its yeah like I think we
just don't want that to be duplicated
I'm not do you have I think all of those
things get handled when you close out so
those just get allocated and then closed
out yeah so I think this is all just
fine so really all I want to do is I
just want this piece of code probably to
to be a little bit cleaner I think we
can wrap it all up into just one
function that returns three things these
three things and then that's it and we
can also then probably simplify this to
just take that bundle directly so I
think that's it so what I propose here
is that in here we just have something
along the lines of import file match and
that's just going to take this I mean
that's just gonna bundle this so it will
record whether or not there was a full
rebuild it will have the matching file
and it will have the file info by the
way you know maybe we have a valid flag
on there I don't know just to say
whether everything went okay I don't
know if I really want that or not but
maybe I do
and so in here you know after you do it
we would could just then in here say
look if this import file match that we
do so that the match now is more like
this right
if the file match is valid then I can do
this stuff and by the way maybe I passed
that directly so we don't need to send
this and we don't need to send that
because they're already bundled up in
this thing which just makes it cleaner
so that you're not letting all have all
these things spread around anyway this
whole thing can happen inside
there which means that this all now
becomes import file match match it
equals some call that we do like you
know finds find file for import or
something or match find matching file
for and so in here you know look at this
stuff that path can just be something
that it uses in temporary storage you
know this thing needs the context file
group and that's stuff and it looks like
it could pretty much just operate
entirely if we just give it that context
and so I think all we really need is
sorry is to pass the context the subtor
right so where you wanted to look for it
and then the base name that may be all
you really need and so if we extract
this piece of code out now you can kind
of see how that's getting nice and clean
right
and so we here if I just say look here's
the internal code for that it's gonna
return you an import file match right
this is the entirety it's really really
straightforward right and you can see
again I say this all the time by just it
always bears repeating because it's one
of the most common mistakes that even
like experience burgers make just you
don't need to pre factor or think about
or design your stuff that's wasteful the
the right way to do it is just write it
out messy first and then collapse it up
right because then you get exactly the
routines you need instead of having to
guess which routines you need and then
find out later that you forgot something
right so that just you know I didn't
have to think ahead of time like what
are the pieces of this code that would
assemble to create an asset system it
just like oh I can see now which pieces
are shared by what to the code so just
those and it's like shooting fish in a
barrel as opposed to shooting fish in an
ocean which is very difficult so fine
matching file for it just needs to take
the exact stuff that we already know
that it takes I don't have to guess
about what the parameters are right
because we know exactly what it takes it
takes these three things and then I can
verify that it doesn't need anything
else letting the compiler do that work
for me
right there's that sub dirt the bitmap
base name so now we can just say alright
import file match starts out it's
nothing the subduer is passed and for me
I do one of these format string
nonsenses to get you know out exactly
you know what I expect here this this is
not a bitmap based name anymore because
it could be anything so I'm next called
base name and then you know we're gonna
call the get file by path to load out
something that matches that path if it's
got it we're gonna then look for the
match that's going to go in here
the assert match call is fine still
right because it has to work go ahead
and set that up too and I think we're
okay so as far as the error part is
concerned that part I think I want to
leave to the external code because I
don't know exactly who is calling this
or why so I would like to let them
determine the error especially if in the
future I want it to potentially not
error because maybe it wants to look in
like more than one place so instead
that's where that valid thing comes in
so I'm gonna do this where I set valid
here so that way we know that look I'm
telling you whether it's valid you issue
the error if you want an error and that
also gets me out of the business of
having to pass all of the information
into the function that's necessary for
correctly reporting the error because
maybe some people have some information
and some people have other information I
don't want to have to worry too much
about that right so in this case the
only issue that I get is not knowing
what the
actually is there which is a little bit
less good but I don't know how much I
care about that because you should know
like where what that actually is the
path part here so that part it's kind of
making me change my mind right because
if I have the path here
I want to potentially be able to print
that out I could store the path but I
don't really know why I would want to
because it's really only necessary if
I'm going to print out the error right
so that does now kind of make me go well
alright I take it back it's easier for
me to pass the the the token information
in so maybe I just do that right yeah
and just because I don't really want to
have to store that or keep that around
it's just wasteful it's alright I'm okay
with that I changed my mind very quickly
off we go where did I went past that oh
there's the final two things there right
after the context all right so moving
along if we just need to finish up the
import call there so let's take a look
at that final matching for there it is I
want to go over here to my head stops me
in the way it was it's good it's getting
in the way too often uh so I need to
pass the tokenizer and the glyph token
here not a big deal I wanted to avoid
that but you know didn't work out
that's fine so here's the code that we
need for that and if I then want to
again collapse it down so I'm only using
this in one place again not particularly
difficult all I have to do is say all
right let's change the way we were doing
this so instead of asset source file and
file info being here and the path and
this kind of stuff I don't want any of
that instead I'm just going to do it
like this where we say okay
let's let this call into the other piece
of code and produce that match for us
here and then when we were going to use
the match before we don't actually need
to do an F match valid we can actually
do that somewhere else so everywhere
that we were looking at match valid but
we can do it like this right so here
where we've got match this is actually
going to be source right match dot
source and I want to keep going here
ya can just kind of get rid of code here
so that seems fine
and then I just need to rename this one
so its result that source there and I
think we're good
alright let's clean up any compilers
doesn't know that it doesn't know that
oops
just fix that keep going
there we go uh sooo this file info is
just inside the results and that's also
inside the results so in here we have
what's our air sub der undeclared ah yes
so it's not really sub during this case
its fonts right that's where we're
always looking bitmap base name I
thought we did have that maybe we don't
it's actually file name it looks like
right
yeah and then what
looks like a pen tags already it looks
like template tags and a pen tag so we
already kind of had those nerfed out are
they always ignored yeah so I guess we
don't really need that either
cannot convert argument 5 from token
well that's true function does not take
six parameters is that so
well how many does it take ah yes so I
forgot to update this with the fact that
we now have that import file match so
what I'd like to do there is just say
okay let's pass that file match in and
then we don't have to pass these around
like I said so I think that's better and
then you hear where we're actually using
those we have to do something more like
this it's see where else we've got usage
of that file info so that's
seems reasonable this should tell us
where all the errors are so rather than
me hunt for them so I guess we I guess
maybe we want to do it like this so if
we modify something I don't know if we
want the modify to propagate out we
might so I don't know whether we want to
like you know we could do it more like
this where we pass this in and then when
we change this it doesn't get changed in
the outer code I'm gonna say let's do it
that way for now and the reason I want
to do it that way is because better to
not touch other people's data and then
later change it so that we do as opposed
to touching it when we don't really need
to because then we're creating more
opportunities for like surprise you know
so I would rather be in a situation
where like let's assume we don't touch
the external data you know closer to a
functional program right so there's less
surprise and then if later we determine
that we actually need to do that we can
do it then and that way we don't
introduce like extraneous chances for
failure there that you know we would
just have been better to avoid okay so I
think that's about it
it's like those are all just matched
source calls and then that's it
so that should allow us to import those
bitmaps as glyphs and that's you know
they're probably asset indexes or
something like this let's take a look
actually should just jump right to that
asset indices don't ask me why I called
it that but you know I did there we go
import file match does not have an
overloaded operator that is correct
so okay is that it that's it
so I think we're now we've got the
entire codes sort of like all sketched
out if that makes sense I really want to
take it slow here to try and because you
know we've done just a tremendous amount
of work here on making the asset system
sort of have all of this flexibility to
it you know you can now define tag files
that allow you to import whatever you
want and mark them up with the data that
you want and it's lives you can change
them on the fly and it'll Rhian
edit it in the game and it'll save it
out and there's just a lot of moving
parts there right it's way more
complicated than I would have liked to
support but you know what can you do
sometimes you just got a games just got
to have some stuff so I feel like that
there's probably a lot of bugs lurking
around in there there'll be some obvious
ones that we can find right away but I
want to also kind of maybe take it slow
as we try to now do some font importing
and I would like to try and make it so
that we can step through it carefully
make sure yeah just make sure we know
what we're doing this by the way didn't
end up being a problem so let's do that
let's just sort of start gently first
thought things first we can test is to
just make sure that we didn't break
anything in the import process I'm a
load up remedy and I'm gonna go ahead
and grab win through two handmade here
I'm gonna run it and you know obviously
we're in debug mode so this is gonna be
kind of slower here you know slow
framerate and skip you sound which is
totally fine for now
but I just want to make sure that we
didn't break anything obvious like you
know I want
make sure that if we reinforced ill
works properly and so I want to test
that out right so what if I go in now
and just delete like all the stuff that
we've got can it rebuild it properly
right I and so inside the handmade data
directory we've got these hhas here and
I want to go ahead and you know kind of
move those out to a temporary sort of
holding tank or maybe just delete them
entirely but you know it's an attempt
directory yeah so let's suppose I go
here and I move based game dot HHA or
dot star to temp and I move into a
cutscene
HHA or dot start temp so we've got
nothing now if I go ahead and rerun and
this will be very slow because it's in
it's in debug right it's not in release
but I want to be able to catch any
errors so so I'm going to go ahead and
just run it and we'll go ahead and see
if it can actually replace everything
properly
not counting the fonts so this is just a
test to see did I break anything right
and so what we should be able to see
here is the intro cutscene right this
should kind of grow as it imports all
this stuff I wish there's a way to see
this update in real time doesn't right
but
we need some like periodic size checking
program that you know can let us know
anyway so I just want it to run do all
of the intro cutscene import that it's
going to do and I I think although I
can't remember but I think we don't
include the font file in here yet anyway
so it shouldn't do any font work yet so
this is will literally unless I'm you
know mistaken this should all this
should do is Tessa see if we broke
anything right
how's it going over there chat land well
we've got some time
almost there
[Music]
are you having any issues with the
debugger or is it okay even if it's an
early version um yeah I mean it it he's
definitely been rough around the edges
because it's brand new and you know it's
not even a official version it's like
beta so there's plenty of stuff like
when I'm working with it I'm constantly
like making sure I take notes if
anything doesn't work or something and
so you know started off a little rough
there some things didn't work whatever
but but George has been very responsive
to bug reports like anything serious
gets fixed very quickly and so at this
point you know there's there's features
I would like that aren't necessarily
there at the moment but the actual
stability of the debugger and the
ability to view information has sort of
studied out to the point where I don't
find myself encountering problems with
it in everyday use much at all I think
he's probably only a few solid weeks
which I know it's hard for him because
he it's a spare time project but you
know if he spent a few if he spent a
month or two working on it full-time
I don't I think it would probably just
be better than Visual Studio in all ways
and that would just be it it's not far
it just needs a few things like you know
it can't save many dumps I don't think
it doesn't have data breakpoints or
conditional breakpoints it doesn't have
a way to select what you want to step
into you know there's a handful of
features that take some work to
implement so it's not like they're just
like oh 10 seconds but there's just not
that many and everything else is like
light years ahead of Visual Studio like
it steps instantly in the watch window
updates instantly Visual Studio takes
seconds
to update that watch window sometime
right it's just it's a disaster and so
like everything else about it is just
way better and so I think I would say
probably by next year of this time I
think we'll probably be in a state where
you'd be crazy to ever bother installing
visual studios at the plugger like that
that'll probably just be a stupid idea
right so it's going very well and
hopefully it will continue um so it
looks like everything imported properly
all the alignments look correct and I
yeah like all the stuff is stacked
properly so the points look proper all
that stuff looks good the environment
looks proper the sound is playing so I
think we're good let me let me run in
release mode really quickly just to make
sure that the sound doesn't have any
issues with it
since we we don't really do much to make
sure that works in low framerate yet so
it's hard to tell right
[Music]
so I think we didn't break anything
right and the fact that that loaded
instantaneously also means that it
correctly knows that there wasn't a
change right so I think that's good and
I think what we want to do now is just
move into the phase of trying to get the
fonts in there because that's really the
only thing now that isn't completely
done through through a dynamically
updating dynamic packing in game system
so we'll just finish that up and then I
think we're we're in pretty good shape
it probably stand to spend a weekend or
two screwing with the asset system and
cleaning it up which we may do because
it's so there's so much capability in
there now it's a little bit we put a lot
of stuff in there and you know sometimes
you want to kind of go through and do
some polishing when you've got that much
stuff going um so okay the first thing
we need to do here is we changed how we
wanted to write these things out we
decided not to do what we were doing
here so if you look at the code if you
go look at how we decided we wanted
these things written out what you can
see is that there's some information
missing that needs to get put in the
font file and then there's some
information formatted in ways that were
not the way we actually wanted them
formatted going forward so I need to go
now to you know process font block
basically or what's it called parse font
block and first this stuff so the glyph
count the ascender height the descender
height and the external letting those
all need to actually get written into
the file because at the moment they're
not there okay
so when we look at this right here we're
gonna have to put before glyph count
equals and present you right so that
needs to be in here
we need to go find out what the glyph
county is and then in here we've got
these other guys they don't have to go
in a particular order but we might as
well just put them in the order like it
you know might as well just do this so
now we do have some floating-point stuff
in there we've got the ascender height
that's a floating-point we've got the
descender height
that's a floating-point and then we've
got the external wedding and other than
that there aren't any other properties
of the font that we're storing at the
moment but if we had other ones that's
where they would go so it looks like
these are in here but they're gonna be
wrong if you look at what's happening so
if you look at me like a sender height
and the D Center height external ending
in stuff like that if you look at how
that's working like when we get down to
stuff like the horizontal advance when
we print that out we've got to scale it
you know what I mean
so that scale ratio has to has to come
into play here and I think probably that
code was just garbage if you look at it
the phrase scale yeah I mean when it
divides this thing by four it's not
going to be an even number so I feel
like those horizontally floats
[Music]
I don't know if you want to keep
rounding fine
I don't really care so anyway if we then
go to the you know the other stuff here
you know maybe we want those to be I
don't know III really I'm sorry I just
have no idea what we want to do here it
looks like it we store floats for these
do we store floats for the horizontally
store floats for everything here it just
feels like why why not just put it in by
not put a percent F I I mean I'm gonna
do it it may be dumb so I apologize for
that but I'm just gonna I'm just gonna
say let's do it no one needs to human
edit these font files so it's just I
don't I don't care that it's like you
know gonna be like spammy and difficult
to read yeah that's totally fine with me
uhm so let's clean this stuff up we've
got the horizontal vans got the glyph
they're all this stuff looks fine I
don't know why there's a slash oh
because that's the output file name not
stem
[Music]
you know looking at this PNG file name
only where is that coming from
that doesn't seem like what we would
want to write it's this is the PNG we're
trying to report right so did that
presumably that code is just busted
because like we never really worked with
it or something right if I go in here
and load one of the load up one of these
is it correct it's correct
how is it correct
how is that correct Oh because it just
sets it no no I'm pretty clever all
right
so it just sets it to point into the
same buffer so as you change the buffer
it just works that's kind of nuts but
okay I guess so moving on from that what
I was trying to say here is all of these
things have to be scaled so the scale
ratio needs to multiply like all of this
stuff when we export it because we're
exporting the far fought large and then
we're shrinking it down so when we say
the ascender high P Center right next
are in a letting we have to scale down
by however much that was right when we
go in here and look at this we want to
write short values out and in order to
write those short values we need to look
at the file formats and include that so
that we can call for example this stuff
right I want to be able to do a set a
line point here where I take a fake
alignment point that's you know some
fake thing like this I write in to the
alignment point with the information
like the type the parent all that stuff
so in here I want to say give me the
default I don't know what this is for
so I want to go in here and say look
let's do an alignment point for type
default right which is this one yes it
goes to the parent the size and the P
percent for size were always 1.0 and for
P percent it's this garbage right here
right because we've already computed it
we just need to actually pack it down
into two u16s so if we do that
now each of these percent use is
something that I actually know the first
one we just never did but we have it
it's just the code point so I can put
that in that's like the utf-32 version
like of what it what the code point
actually is right and then those two
percent use are just the P percent
values that come out of the align point
that we just packed so if I look at
these two here right
I can I can just print those out as
integers now and off we go
the only weird thing is like I'm not
storing any of the other broadline
points but we don't need them because
those things are are known like a font
only ever has these specific alignment
points so we don't really care and it
should be fine so I think that will
correctly give us what we want I need to
include these here what was that called
file formats the 3p
oh nice typo so I need those here and I
need to make sure just a 5 struct type
redefinition where was it defined before
oh we just like I'd copied that in here
but we don't need that right that can
just be yeah so now I think we'll be
writing out font files that match what
we expect what I don't really remember
in here so and we may need to fix this
when we're doing the parsing you can see
us reading all this information out
right and there's us reading the glyphs
and we're calling the stuff out I don't
think we're setting this a line point
anywhere like we've got it right and we
we modified it to be whatever we read
out of the file and that's great but
once we actually get this code point
here that bitmap ID never really gets
those alignment points attached to it
and it needs that to have happened right
so
so that part is a little bit trickier
because I don't actually know once we
update that particular piece of
information it's a little bit confusing
as to whether we want it to do a
reemployed or not I don't think I really
necessarily care so I don't think I'm
really gonna worry about that I think
what I would rather do is just get the
asset and slam the alignment point into
it just directly so in here you know if
we go ahead and get the actual asset I
mean I guess I could look if I let's see
asset data from file if I if I look at
how that's being done elsewhere I mean
here's where that's being done here
right we've got these loops that loop
over the asset grid and then they look
to see if they can get the asset then
they write the alignment point into that
asset and I guess to be honest looking
at that - you know that probably should
mark the file here if the thing doesn't
equal if they're not equal
so in a way it kind of feels like maybe
you just want this code to be shared and
you pass it an alignment point grid in
so I mean I don't know it seems to me
like maybe we just want that to happen
and then it will actually get processed
properly and I don't need that to do
because just if you take a look at what
happens here you know if I word it to go
full pull and say when you call update
acid data from file if we actually put
this in here where you know you have a
thing where you would pass in
information about what was going on what
we could do is say well you know there's
a parameter at the end of this thing
which is like if it's is art then we
pass in you know the what is what's
what's getting passed here it's like the
a line point yeah so it's this thing
right we can pass in in the line point
grid kind of a thing and if not then not
you know what I'm saying so we could do
something like that and if we did that
then both pieces of code could do the
same thing right
both would pass down their line points
and that would be fine I don't know how
I feel about it but then all this is is
something that says look if we got in a
line points pointer which would be this
nonsense here
so in here where we do update a sedated
from file we would have some that said
like look I want a pointer to this
ridiculous array of garbage and you know
by default maybe it can just be zero if
you don't care I guess I just force you
to pass through anyway but you know if
you pass in one of these then I'll read
the alignment points out of it how about
that right and I you know I should
probably mention here so it gets a
little C has some weird ways in which
because it basically relies on artifacts
of how parsers worked and how parse
trees are constructed some things about
it are a little bit weird you would
probably expect if you were not a C
programmer
or if you don't program C a lot or
haven't ever studied this even you would
probably expect this to be cleared like
this meaning if I want a array you okay
you can see what I want here I want an
array of alignment points right I want
to pass one of these in but I don't want
to pass like the entire array in I want
to pass like a player to the array right
and so you might think like oh I want to
do this but if you did that what it
would mean is actually that you have an
array of pointers to alignment points
and you're still passing the whole array
you're passing the whole array of
pointers now instead of a whole array of
points but that's the only difference
and so you saw me reflexively do this
and that was just because I in my head
was like oh I I need a pointer to this
big array of alignment points the way C
treats its parse tree is it works from
the identifier name outward so it starts
going outward to the right and then goes
outward to the left and so if you want
to make sure that it reads it as a
pointer to an array you need the
parentheses the reason is that since it
starts working outward to the right the
first thing it will see
when it goes to figure out what type
align points is is this array asset
import grid max then it will look at
asset report grid max second dimension
then it will see HH bitmap all point
count only when it hits the end will it
ever look to the left so it's reading
then becomes a line points is a array of
asset import grid max arrays of accent
import grid max of a raise of HH bitmap
a line point count of pointers to
alignment points right and what I needed
to do is I needed to see the star first
you know what I'm saying like I'm trying
to make sure that it looks at the star
as the first thing so by wrapping it in
parentheses all I was trying to do there
is say hey read what's in the
parentheses first then keep doing what
you're going to do so then it tries to
look to the right and goes well there's
nothing to the right because I hit a
parenthesis there so I have to do
everything the parentheses before I go
any further so then it looks to the left
and sees it's a pointer okay so a line
points is a pointer to what to an array
of this array of that array of this of
that right so that's a way of force you
get to go left one time first and then
it can go right you know that's all um
so if I want to point past something
like that in there then what would
happen is this whole thing occurs and so
then I need to dereference this just a
little bit like that to make sure I can
still use this rate otherwise it's
totally fine I don't I don't even really
know now I think about it whether I need
to actually do that star but I think I
do
because otherwise I would be accessing
an array of those things so I need to
like peel off one of those stars first
it's not super essential to get that
right because the compiler will generate
in there for you that lets you know that
you did that wrong but yeah it's just
worth noting so if I do that then I can
just pass this in I also don't need to
do this anymore
I think I will keep doing it and what
that means is that now I can create one
of those alignment point arrays like so
and just stuff the data that I need when
I parse the font block I can just have
it take care of that for me
so in here if we create an empty array
of these things then the align point
setup that we do here would not go into
a fake one but rather it would do set a
line point of the specific a line point
in question so zero zero zero which is
the only one we will ever write is the
one that we're going to set and then in
here we will pass the align points down
as something that gets used and apply it
to pass the address of that giant block
as well because we are using the address
of there
I think again that's one of those things
that's always hard it is implicitly an
address so it might be just fine passing
it but I don't will let the compiler
tell me the second eye that's all well
and good and I think then at that point
we are done right
big oops making that work okay that's an
S
and off we go
all good okay
um like I said when we're in this
particular routine here I don't think
this was correctly marking these files
as having been changed so when we come
through here and write back our
alignment points
I feel like this thing should be saying
if these two alignment points were not
the same then we need to mark the file
as needing to be rewritten the h of j
files like metadata needs to get
rewritten there I would think right so
it's a little bit weird that that's not
actually happening and I don't actually
know why it's not doing that but that's
the case so that's a little bit strange
and I I do wonder so I'm going to move
the to do down into here
that part I yeah I just it doesn't seem
logical to me so I think we wanted to do
there and we probably want to fix that
at some point because I'm I wouldn't
have to go make sure that it's actually
true but I think we want to always mark
the art assets as having changed if you
see a difference in the alignment points
that are getting passed in I could be
wrong about that but I think that's what
we want so yeah I think that's probably
good but maybe that's not yeah I don't
know maybe that's not how that should
happen but we'll see um so now that we
have this code working properly for
everything else I just need to make sure
I guess I should do the rebuild one more
time I'm gonna do it in O to this time
so it doesn't take as long I and because
I just want to double-check that moving
this in here didn't break anything
we know that the full rebuild worked
just before so if it doesn't work now
then we know that it has something to do
with that move I'm gonna delete the
intro cutscene and the base game H at J
and then I'm gonna run it since we're in
release mode I think it should work a
lot more quickly now in fact you can
actually able to see how much faster
this thing updates and then when we're
done I will try a loading fonts
all right so that seems good
I got everything seems fine so we'll
leave it at that
if I now want to go look at the font
stuff I think probably all hell's gonna
break loose so let's take it slow the
first thing we need to do is we need to
move our test font stuff out of here so
we're gonna move that into temp
and now we like don't have fonts so in
theory if I ran the game it would just
break immediately because there are no
fonts or remedy will crash I am Not sure
okay if I remember correctly visual
studio is currently installed as the
debugger and Visual Studio is broken
because it like its certificate expired
or whatever because you know
certificates are awesome and so I can't
hit debug and save a mini dump for
George which I need to do so I think
what we want to do here is setup windbg
as our just-in-time editor and although
it probably requires a reboot crap well
I'll try it anyway just in case it
doesn't
I that's what I wanted that is not what
I wanted this is what this is what we
want okay so what happens in Windows is
when it goes and like this when it
detects a fault it looks to see whether
in the registry anyone has registered a
debugger that's supposed to launch to
debug the program that keeled over right
and so you can see here where the
registry keys are if I go out so this is
what HQ local machine software
it looks like Microsoft Windows NT
currentversion a e debug alright so in
here this registry key shows you who is
currently registered as the debugger
that will handle you know any broken any
software that that breaks when it's not
already running under a debugger so if I
were to change this key to point to win
debug or something right then I should
be okay so in if I open up a windbag
here like window bug preview right let's
see I don't know how to actually get to
the place where this is where are you
win debug preview where do you exist
right now
so oh my okay
is that really is that really where you
are seriously
so in case anyone was wondering if you
baked the version name into the path of
the debugger when you install it exactly
what are you supposed to set the
registry key to for just-in-time
debugging because when it updates it's
going to break I don't know what goes on
at Microsoft anymore it's just what a
madhouse so here's the debugger this is
because it has to be installed via the
Windows Store which of course is a
gigantic pile of garbage that no one
should ever use so I'm gonna go ahead
and not do that I'm gonna cut and paste
all those files because I can it does
thank God that it happens to be one of
the thing only things Microsoft ships
that does not require you to basically
have an entire it doesn't require you to
have like an entire install process to
use so I think if we just go in here and
do windbg oh it looks like we already
have a windy B preview there okay so
I've already done this once so if I do
this I should be able to do a paste to
replace all these files and then in
theory now I could point it here instead
of to the store which is an absurd path
that won't work for more than like 15
minutes right so if we do this and then
where's the actual there it is this is
the program right there it is and cut
and paste this in there now the path is
correct but the problem is I don't
actually know if these parameters are
the parameters that Windy bug actually
needs so I want to go look at that real
quick and make sure
those are correct as well
so it looks like maybe it's that so
we're just gonna guess that it is and
cross our fingers it looks very similar
to what was there before so I'm just
gonna say okay alright so now it's it's
it's the yeah it's the debug shell there
I'm also gonna take some quality of life
take a minor quality of life step here
as well and say maybe while we're at it
let's not make f12 be the key to break
into the debugger because that f12
drives me nuts right sit debug
great
I don't really remember what the
register it's like user debug key or
something like that oh is it just
sitting there actually oh it's user
that's right there so this needs to be
of the K code in order for it to not be
set to f12 and so I in order to do that
what I would need to do is just look up
the VK table and see if I can't find
like let's say we use pause maybe
so that's oh x3 n-- so hopefully that's
fine
and we'll see what happens
wait what did you just do oh there we go
so hopefully that's fine and we'll leave
with that all right so that at least if
we save this out right our registry is
now saved in theory we have updated the
debugger I just think you may have to
reboot for take effect so when I click
debug here I'm not sure we'll actually
get windy bug but I'll reboot the
machine after the stream and then like
next time this happens we it should work
so we'll see
so that looks like I did set it but not
correctly is that true I may have just
made it a little bit wrong let's see
here oh I so close I'm trying not to
rage out Microsoft because I just it
drives me insane all the time you cannot
map drives you know in a way that works
across users the drive w is not mapped
for the administrator which is what will
probably run the debugger so I need to
use the unmapped version of the path in
order to tell it where to find this
program so it actually needs to be this
right that may be enough so I think
maybe it would have worked and I blew it
so sorry about that oh well so hopefully
we can get that crash to happen again
let's test it and see if we got this
working so so what did I do here I I ran
it through remedy right there we go so
running it through remedy is reliably
crashing which is good so now we can get
our JIT working so let me go ahead and
try to get it debugged perfect that's
what we wanted I think unfortunately
[Music]
windy bug is now deciding to download
the symbols for the entire operating
system because that's just what it wants
to do we don't really care about that
what we care about is capturing a mini
dump for George because he can't really
do bug this crash without more
information you know what I'm saying so
we need to be able to save the mini dump
now windbag for some reason never puts
anything in the actual
you I so as far as I know like there's
no I mean maybe there's a way to do it
up here but I've you know for whatever
weird reason they never like put
anything out in the actual there's never
any actual UI it's just it's like no I
don't I don't like to have you eyes for
some reason so you have to go to the
console which I don't actually know why
that's not here at the moment but if you
go to the View menu and get it which is
this oh no nevermind it is it's just
here for some reason
um you can actually do a dump so I
believe it's dot dump or what's the
what's the way to get the so I don't
know how to get help on this I'm sorry I
just don't use wind bug very often but
if we do a dot dump we should be able to
say we want a mini dump
I believe em - ma means everything
included and that's saying mini dump
with all options and then we can say all
right place that somewhere where we can
get it so you know see work temp remedy
crash on starting H H I don't remember
what it is but it's probably a dot BMP
file
dot dump oh that's the command um let's
see do they have an examples yeah dot
DMPs I thought so I thought it is let me
verify my command-line switches while
I'm at it because I guess I don't really
remember what they I don't use this that
often /ma that's what we want yeah
large and more complete file all
optional additions yeah okay so I'm
gonna try that here there we go and so
now what I'm done today I can send
George that mini dump file and he should
be able to figure out what went wrong
there again this is a really nice thing
to learn to do if you don't know how to
save him any dump like that
I think Visual Studio has a way to save
a mini dump in the file menu I hope I'm
saying that right
but those mini dumps are very valuable
because then you can go grab this dump
file here right upload it to like a
google drivers and they're huge they get
a lot tinier though if you sip them so
if you nope nope don't do that if you
first zip it into a zip file you get a
lot of compression because it's mostly
compressed highly compressible memory
there's some zeros and stuff like that
or runs of common numbers and stuff like
this so if you compress it you get a lot
of compression that probably goes down
to 30 40 megabytes
probably yeah so if I just send that now
to George he can load that on his
machine in his debugger and see where
the program crashed and also look at
some of the variables and the structures
which is really helpful because that way
he can maybe get some information about
like what happened so we're gonna let
him have a crack at that in the meantime
I want to take a look at debugging this
stuff so what I'm gonna do here is I
don't actually know is it just any
startup of remedy is dangerous right now
I'm not actually sure so I'm gonna take
a look if I open up
went through hand-made if i @ f 11 do i
crash I don't so it seems like it was
something that actually from just
running free caused it to crash I'm not
sure but either way I'm gonna see if I
can just debug the one part I want to
and we'll let George figure out what's
going on later and you know we can sort
of deal with that part separately so I'm
gonna look at this function cuz that's
really the only thing that I want to see
we'll see if I can run it it looks like
I can so we're fine I don't actually
know what the crash was um so looking
through here oh well actually nevermind
we don't really do this yet cuz well
this thing is this is not gonna do
anything right I don't know why those
files got marked as modified that's
probably a bad sign
because they don't need to be actually
oops uh so we should probably find out
why that's happening to let me put it to
do in there for that but was gonna say
is we need to actually put the font
information in there first
so we need to track that down at some
point all right so we run this thing we
get to here
what we need to do is add a new h HT for
the font so besides the two that it
parses normally we need like that one
more in there now for the font so what
I'm going to do for that is I'm gonna
actually run our font generator and see
if we can't get it to produce something
that looks useable to us so let's go to
here delete all this and I'm gonna run
HH font now so I don't actually remember
which font swing were you thinking um I
think it was just the console I think it
was probably just this I don't really
know so I'm gonna say this is what we
were using even though I don't know that
it was what we were using let's suppose
it was we're gonna use the test care set
we're gonna use the let's see liberation
mono hht and then we're gonna write to w
10 font right so that creates all of our
glyphs in theory you know here they all
are know if they're correct and so then
what we want to do is write this you
know move this over to our font
directory or our sources directory so
that there actually is some place where
these fonts can live I you know I guess
I would say
maybe do we just want like a separate
fonts HHA or did we want that to just be
included in bass game
I don't really know let's say it gets
included here there we go
so here's those fonts and then maybe in
here we say that the hht file because
we've got the hhe file in here somewhere
right although actually it doesn't
appear that we do where did the HSE file
go W template oh it's back in here so
that hht file for liberation mono that
wants to go somewhere and I assume that
it probably wants to go in the base game
directory as well or so if we go to
handmade tags and we've got liberation
monitor hht you know maybe I'll do this
this could be really stupid but it's
just what I'm gonna do for now so this
base game that hht could now include
that and if I go into the fonts
directory and take a look at this I
looks good right
I could print out these letters much
more concisely by looking at them and
seeing whether they're not they're whole
numbers like they are here and then not
including all of the zeros but you know
what are you doing so let's see I did
what I just did there and in you know in
bass game that face came open yet no in
W handmade tags bass game we have the
ability to do like a pound include right
so I'm assuming that here I could do
like pound include this file right so
liberation mano de hht in the fonts
directory because I thought we had
something like this support for this so
then it would do this right and you know
off would go it would be nice to be able
to place you know and I think I'll go
ahead and maybe do this when we extract
the font it would be nice to give it
like the author and description fields
as to just having come from h/h font or
something because otherwise it wouldn't
have any
I don't really know so anyway if we do
the pound include there I don't really
know where it looks for those files so
if we go to asset import I just want to
see when it doesn't include where does
it actually look and it looks like it
would work properly because it looks
always in the tags file directory so I
think that would just work I'm gonna go
ahead and compile oh wait I don't need
to compile I guess weird this we only
modify the tax file I'm gonna go ahead
and watch what happens now so when we
parse that that base game hht I want to
see what happens now if we get if we can
parse the font or not and and if so what
happens when we do so going into the
parse hht I'm pretty sure that in this
case the first one is actually the intro
cutscene which doesn't have an include
file in it anyway so I'm gonna skip this
one and we're gonna look at the next one
so here's this this is the actual hhd
that we want one of the first things we
see is after the hht should be that
include so when we hit this include
we're gonna say alright like what's the
file name that we're actually looking at
and there it is so the text there is
fonts liberation but that's exactly what
I expect so we're going to take a look
at whether or not we you know produce a
sensible path there just like we do when
we do included file info we're gonna see
whether or not we set this up properly
it looks like we sort of do maybe
all right so we're in harsh top little
block which is wrong so right off the
bat I think the problem here is we never
put in a font block detection so I think
here this needs to look for fonts right
yeah I'm saying so that needs to happen
and now that at least we know that it
gets there correctly I should be able to
go ahead and stop us right here instead
because hopefully that'll work there we
go
so here we are in parse font lock and we
first look to see whether we get the
glyph count and so let's find out if we
do oh sorry
and it looks like we do it says a
hundred there's that hundred value so
when we look okay that didn't work so
why didn't that work
glyph count tokens s3 two is definitely
greater than 100 so we must have missed
one of the parsing things must have
aired out so there wasn't error
we just don't know what that error
actually was so maybe it was that yeah
so this is the problem it's not actually
an identifier in this case it's a string
like if you look it's a quoted string
liberation mono that seems like probably
it should remain that way because if you
look at what happens everywhere else it
is you know it's probably should really
be the t TF so if we're gonna be more
estranged about this I would say we
probably want to take the TTF file name
which is this and actually make that TTF
file name be the thing that gets placed
after the font call
so right here so I don't really know if
name stem is the right thing that's a
really tough call
I'll leave it the way it is but either
way when this parsing happens for parts
Mart block that needs to be a string not
a identifier right so I think that's we
want to do there and in our tokenizer I
don't remember if we need to do an
uncoated string value call
just looking to see whether the quotes
are included they're not alright so this
should work just fine when we get that
because we're doing a require token on
that so that needs to be fixed there we
compile this here and so now when we
actually get to that block we should be
able to enter because there shouldn't be
any errors in it hopefully there we go
and so now when we look for the font
name text this should come back with a
new file right there shouldn't be
anything in it because we haven't
processed this before so if I look at
font source file it should have nothing
right these should all be you know
nothing and they are and it should just
have the base name liberation mono when
we start moving through here we should
get the hundred for the glyph count
right that was the thing that we have
there we allocate our storage here that
we're gonna be using for the font data
itself
we initialize all this stuff to be zero
because we're going to be pulling that
out as we go the first thing we see
should be the ascender height so we
should grab that and then the descender
height and then the external letting
whether those are all good or not I
don't know so let's take a look and see
if they make sense
the external letting is possibly just
the value of these two plus so that may
be correct I don't actually remember
what that values to be but I think it
might be the addition of those so
ignoring that looks fine and then we
should read a glyph so reading the
glyphs in here let's see what we get if
these all make sense which Cliffton
glyph index
well cliff index zero is not going to be
particularly interesting right
that doesn't make a whole lot of sense
does it
because that should be this what do I
miss a token filename oh what the wrong
thing it's this value that's correct
alright so set a line point blah blah
blah true 1.0 so that all looks like
it's gonna go well let's let's look at
what the values that that's that are
getting pass in hard to make sure
they're reasonable good point a line X
the line y 32 and 0 is that actually
what's in here no
so that parsing looks kind of broken oh
and you can see why so we weren't using
the brackets so this is actually an
error scenario here and we will end up
erroring out so let's fix that
so now we should be grabbing all of that
correctly we might also I suppose want
to double-check that by the time we get
down here the parsing like don't bother
doing any of this if the parser was not
working because we might just end up
loading some garbage file and you know
making a mess of things
or crashing unnecessarily so we'll just
do a check there to make sure that we
don't like go off on some wild tangent
all right so if we now jump down into
there we grab this stuff out I'm hoping
that I'll see some more sensible
information here but line-x still looks
wrong so right that that should not be 0
so I'm again curious as it should be
thirty to forty nine five nine forty
nine five nine right so again not sure
if that's a parsing bug or if that's the
tokenize are hitting an error it did so
we've still got something a little bit
weird wonky here we parse the glyph
index which comes in brackets
we're not parsing the brackets either
this little thing is kind of just busted
right
because these brackets should be around
the toque the glyph index right then
there should be in equals yeah I don't
know what were we doing here we were way
asleep at the switch then there should
be an equal sign right then there should
be the string then a comma then the code
point then another comma then the brace
then the numbers and then embrace right
that's that's what we should have seen
and somehow that's like not even close
to what I wrote there so I guess we were
just kind of not paying attention
because there's no way I thought that
other thing was actually rational or
good right so now we've got no errors
which is better so now this stuff and it
does look correct right the glyph index
of one that is what that is so that
looks good
so let's take a look at this we're gonna
have to look into the Fah structure to
see if we can find this let's see if
we're actually loading something that
makes sense here because I'm not
actually sure if we are so here's the
path that we're looking which is based
game fast liberation mono yeah I that
does exist and we should be able to load
it so hopefully this will work it looks
like it did when we come out here we
look if the matches valid it is so we
try to update it using this garbage here
I when we come through the code to see
if the age of shape matches it doesn't
so we need to do a floor evil but we
already would have done that anyway we
load the zero file and here we go ahead
and parse a PNG and looks like we got an
underflow on this witch so this PNG is
also invalid externally but I because
it's zero size it's zero by zero
however even though that's an illegal
PNG and we probably shouldn't write one
I I thought our reader would work and
the fact that I'm wrong about that makes
me concerned because that means I don't
really understand how this thing was
working
so maybe it's actually the case that we
have an incorrect it could be that we
don't right out be final correctly when
we do this export that's entirely
possible so maybe we should look at that
because I would like it to work even
though technically so technically there
is no way to produce a valid PNG with
zero by zero as the dimensions according
to the spec you can't you're not allowed
to do that
so you know maybe we shouldn't really do
this we should just not have a file
there if there's no like don't export
the code point if there's no information
but I just want to make sure this works
so I'm gonna try and make it work first
and then we can also go in and not
export it later as a separate pass so if
you look here you can sort of see what
would happen if the chunk count just
ends up zero which is what would happen
right because the total length is just 0
plus 1 now 0 times 4 plus 1 times 0
which is 0 then all the rest of this
stuff will just zero out right
so I guess what we have to do here is
say if chunk count equals zero chunk
count equals one when we come down
through this code and we do this loop
this should just not trigger these
should all be zero and so that should
maybe be fine right that's my story for
now let's go ahead and run the font
generator thingy and I guess I can just
make this generate the fonts directly
into their location so that would be
handmade sources based game fonts right
now I don't know like I said in theory I
think this will still be busted
meaning 32 also I guess these are by
code point not by glyph number which I
guess is the right thing to do anyway
let's take a look if the if that helps
at all so I think that works very place
where Tim W handmade sources based game
fonts so all I wanted to do was update
the PNG is there let me just make sure
that that that actually did do that so
it was modified one a minute ago that's
what I want and now let me let me step
through that code one more time
so let's try that so now that time we
can parse the PNG and it should come
back as a zero by zero and it does we'll
import it and we'll keep running let's
see what happens when we get one that
actually has data in it seems good so
that will keep on running for a while
pulling in bitmaps and then at the very
end we're hoping we get here
no parse errors that's great
so that means in theory we also read the
horizontal advance table properly in
theory so then we go ahead and say look
let's get the file that we want to store
this font itself in make that all look
reasonable needs full rebuild in this
case should obviously be true because
the first time we've ever seen this font
and it is we set the data for it which
leads to
everything looking right we update the
asset data and write it out for the font
and then I think we're done right so all
of that went well but then when we go to
actually get this font
it looks like the font isn't a font for
lack of a better statement um so we have
to fill out what's going on there
and that may be because the font
couldn't be found yeah so when it tried
to find the font it couldn't find it
what font is it trying to find start
with that it's trying to find a font
type debug we haven't created any
matches for this yet so that's probably
the problem um we need to specify a tags
array probably in there to make the font
actually get tagged but we also don't
know for setting everything else
properly so there's probably some more
work to do there as well like if you're
looking here I don't know that we're
actually over setting the font type to
font right in fact it doesn't look like
we do so when you know this stuff here
should get set and I don't know that we
ever are so like inside inside the HHA
itself this HH font exists inside an HHA
asset that a JK asset is having some of
its stuff get written like this but I
don't think we're ever setting the type
right we're setting the tags here and I
don't know if we're I'm saying the type
let me look inside update single asset
metadata to see if it ever sets the time
of the asset I mean so looking at
dot type you know I'll be honest when
does that ever get set for anybody
so what am I missing that has to get set
because if it doesn't get set
there should be assertions about what
the piece of data is and right so asset
the HHA asset information should be set
there I'm gonna look to see what's going
on not see anything actually no what I
could do
let's see where we use this stuff so if
I do where's my set types
so if I just did something like tell me
every place that I do type equals HHA
Asset fit map where is it all right so
here is where we're setting this
information this is in right image to
HHA so it's where this stuff gets
written out I'm assuming that process
audio import therefore also sets it that
way yeah there it is so we just needed
that to happen in the fonts and we never
did right so that seems pretty obvious
as a first step and then the other thing
is we need to actually tag it so I can
get found in the parse block code what I
was about to do is what exactly what I
do want to do right so this bit here
needs to be asset type so that will at
least mark the font as the correct type
which is something that we want
and that's all well and good but we also
need to be tagged presumably or it won't
match although it might just match by
default even though it's not tagged that
part I'm not sure about but at least now
it will get marked properly in theory
right and so then we need to actually
tag it with something I do want to look
and see I don't know well I guess yeah
that doesn't really matter when you're
looking for a font I don't know why we
don't restrict it only to things of the
font type but doesn't really matter
anyway so what we need here is we need
to be able to set the font type this way
and that should be pretty easy I guess
in handmade asset age I'm sorry in a
match of this in liberation mono dot H
we need this to be tagged with something
right so we need to say like you know
tags equals font type so we need
something like that it's not quite what
I would want to have happen
but we'll go with it for now that looks
like it worked where are we at here so
string-length who's who's doing this
it's like we've got an error problem
here it looks like we're parsing a
thought block again what is this magical
font block
where are we surfer parsing liberation
mono da HH key directly or when is this
happening
no it's part of the include so for some
reason ah
so the glyph count is not coming first
and it needs to it's required to come
first I forgot about that but why is
that an why did that create a bad error
message here what happened
we've done something bad when we went to
output like the rest of this information
well that looks like an issue right
there potentially oh no no it's not
there's 29 so that's fine
hmm all right well let's take a look so
what's this string string is just a
garbage pointer of course that may be
because it advance pass it what were we
looking for we were looking for this
temp here that's all just yeah we
couldn't get the argh out so it's this
call Oh No so I don't normally get a lot
of crashes in remedy I guess this latest
version must have had something weird
happening in it cuz like I used it all
week and never had any crashes so I
don't know I must be doing something
weird I'm sure George will know what it
is but let's see let me write this out
it's probably with something specific in
our PD B that's bad
okay so now we've got both dump files we
should be able to send it to him so I'm
not really sure what's going on with
that and I I'm gonna even though I know
what we want to do is move this I want
to run again and see if we can't figure
out what what went wrong there because
it shouldn't that's that error should be
allowed and it should print out properly
it shouldn't crash like that that's so
something's busted there so if I look at
what we're passing here
so will it crash again if I try to
inspect this format yeah so it's like
it's like you can't for some reason it
can't look at that it's super dangerous
for some reason
so expected percent s with match looks
ok right because that's you know it's
glyph count that's what you would expect
so that's getting passed down here and
then it's issuing the error and you know
presumably so ok so it's just the name
format doesn't matter with like I don't
know if it's because formats also a
function or something I'm not sure but
it just does not want to inspect that so
I don't know what would be wrong with
that because it looks looks right to me
and I'm not sure what it's having a
problem with there
calling a crowd filled with all right so
the format is like just a percent lower
case s is what's coming down is format
and the mashed strings so then when we
get to here we're getting them at that
percent s and the arglist for that which
is one argh list we're then going into
out FR glist
and so this format is just a percent s
for mastering and the arglist is one
care star right which is exactly I
didn't mean to do that I think I like
that better yeah okay so I think that's
like I don't know why that would be
weird
let me double check the format string
and make sure I'm not crazy I mean it's
just a percent s and I yeah so
although
I see the bug we have had this bug
before we're kind of fired for having
the same bug twice so the problem here
is that it's looking at var glist which
happens to it it's not actually matching
the type because it happens to be a
nonsense like pound defying thing the C
runtime library does so really we need
this to be error arglist
and we need to do this so that it
because it was picking the wrong
overloaded function so that's all that
was happening there right so that was
just a overloading nonsense we should be
fine now okay yeah I don't know why but
we just have to make sure those are
differentiated okay so this time it
should actually just run properly but
produce the errors and then get back to
our original like we can't find the font
and so I think I can now safely say that
since we fixed that thing if I go to
liberation mind if I add the tags below
the gift count now that should be
allowed and so now we should tag them
but it looks like we're still not
finding them I know there could be a lot
of reasons for that and so I probably
will save that debugging for tomorrow
but I think we're good to go now in
basically everything except maybe how
those tags are getting set up there I
want to look just real quick though when
we do do the initialization for the
fonts I want to look at this call just
real quick so when we do get best match
asset with a particular basic category
I'm guessing the problem is just yeah
the problem is that basic category never
got tagged so maybe I won't save all
that a bug from around me just fix that
one minor issue first which is that the
basic category for this thing never got
set so when we're doing those append
tags here there's the pen tags thing
that comes in here
this thing we actually do need to write
out the tags it does need to have its
basic typeset and it's not happening I
thought this would do it but it's not
doing it and I'm guessing that the
reason it's not doing it is because that
like doesn't this do that I guess it
doesn't do it it's this right that's not
happening and also it's not really
getting set properly so so we do need to
do that in here before we export this
thing we want to use one of these so I'm
gonna pull this down the append tags and
say that this because this thing where
we're we're we're importing the bitmap
we never want to have tags but this
asset we do actually want to have tags
so here we want to do like begin tag
builder nonsense this thing
so we want this thing to build the grid
tag in question for our append acts and
this tag array here with the first and
last thing I don't know what import grid
tag really has to do with it it's just
oh it's that right so we just want this
to happen and then we want our appendage
to be combined tags tags like that right
so this will give it the tag that says
what it's what's base type is then
what's just what it needs to be found we
know
oh and that also ok so that also needs
to be there hmm so I guess I really want
it both ways right I want this thing to
have null tags and I do want to track
the append tags because the parser wants
to add things to that right so I do want
this and then the template tags I guess
is the place that I want this to go
right
so I think I really want that as weird
as it sounds um import tag array fact
it's just that so I think that's what I
want because that weight properly gets
marked as a font which is what I
actually want I think but we'll find out
this code could stand for some nice
clean up
there's too many moving pieces that
don't really need to be there no it
still didn't quite work so I'm gonna
save that debugging for tomorrow because
this is the part now that needs to get
set up properly and when this update
single asset metadata call gets called
right that should call set data type
there so the import grid tags tags here
that get that are getting passed
it looks like extra tags for the import
grid tag is actually where I wanted that
even so too much tags I think part of
the problem is these tags just turn out
of control we need to like make a
cleaner way of handling tags and writing
them right which wouldn't be hard okay
so let's see if that got it mashed
properly no so now but something like
that should be that should be working
and and we should get it I'm sorry I'm
obsessing here I said I was going to
wait till tomorrow but I keep not doing
that if I do parse our font block here
yes so that's the problem is that's
actually not getting entered so why not
so there is an error
what's the air
so that file as we expect
unrecognized tagname unsurprising here
we go and so now we are creating that
font tag this should now actually add
that font type so hopefully yeah there
we go
hopefully we now have a font so whether
the font works or not it doesn't look
like it does because we should be seeing
some something up here right and so it
looks like we're not it looks like we're
not properly getting that font but at
least we're closer than we were before
right and it looks like here right
because the the font this is probably
the font code right and it's getting
like you know probably garbage IDs or
something yeah it's probably getting
like weird yeah it's getting like out of
range IDs so it's just it's just a
little bit forked looking at yeah we're
probably like putting the wrong data
into like the you know the the glyph map
or whatever so like for example inside
the parse font block if you look at
what's going on in here like this right
a set data is probably like writing
stuff out incorrectly you can give me
like and maybe we're setting this stuff
wrong who knows
it's code points Oh
is this okay so this is getting set here
so yeah the unicode code point gets set
and then the bitmap ID ostensively gets
set ah actually that though needs to
happen regardless so meaning this has to
happen always because even if you don't
import the thing you still need to set
the bitmap ID for the font in case it
gets written out right so that actually
does always need to be there and it
needs to be an error if for some reason
you can't find a font with and hopefully
that already would have been an error so
you know we it's really a duplicate
error but just in case you know we
double market that seems better possibly
maybe and I don't know like that's a
change to the code which we don't really
support right now in terms of diffing so
we are at a bit of a disadvantage
because I don't know if that will
actually ever I don't know if that will
actually update our font
it probably won't right so we're gonna
hit this either way so let me go ahead
and set a breakpoint in parse from block
because I don't think it will actually
properly come back down here we'll see
so
Oh interesting I wonder why that is
so that seems like a bug - I really have
to stop debugging sorry you know how I
am when I start I just like want to fix
the problems so it's a little bit
difficult but so you know this right
here why are we not getting our font is
how what does this stuff look like look
valid looks pretty good
5:08 that seems like right where it
should be see what the last one says
5:02 looks really find me a chit shade
that data upset because we did a reserve
on it with the data size that seems
right does it not
I don't know it seems pretty good what's
the code point size 800
that's exactly what I would expect
well in for a penny in for a pound what
happens when we actually asked to load
this font right so here's the font asset
number 507 you know here we go trying to
figure out how big we're supposed to
loaded up it's 800 just like we thought
so off we go it read it okay so what's
the deal if we actually look at font
glyphs do we get the same stuff we were
just looking at sure it looks like it
so what's the problem
alright so I guess we fixed it now we
didn't so what's the problem how are we
getting this this weird garbage how are
we getting like six six to six back for
this thing but that doesn't really make
a lot of sense does it
we've got the font and we know what code
point we're looking for so if I open up
the font table and I look at the unicode
mapping right I should be able to do
like font Unicode map and then look at
code point 85 so it says to look at 54
so we'll look at 54 it says bitmap ID
for 57 so how did it return
there's something I don't understand I
probably forgot up that we did about the
fonts and now it came back to bite me so
let's find out what is happening get
glyph from code-point this is exactly
what I just did right I mean that that
is what I did for Coke by the way what
code point are we looking for 85 hey
great so looking at the Unicode map it
should return me the value 54 right yes
then when we do get bitmap for glyph I
should say okay
I see
I will now explain what's happening and
I guess it's actually quite easy for us
to fix and I guess it's all fine because
we use a side IDs at runtime that are
merged meaning there is only one index
that is used to access an asset and so
even if there were many HHA files that
were all loaded into the game at launch
you can still just use one integer to
refer to an asset there's only two ways
you can really make a system like that
work
one is to pre allocate all of your asset
ID is to make sure they don't conflict
such as what we did on the witness for
example but another way which the way we
use here is that at runtime when you
load you have a rebasing value that
anyone who needs to refer to something
by an ID offset actually knows to use
the part in the when you loaded this HHA
how far did it have to get moved up to
sure that didn't conflic with any other
hhas then you use that offset since we
don't really ever do that other than
with fonts because of the only things
that are actual assets that refer to
other assets we forgot to actually apply
that difference so in here where we set
this bitmap ID the actual source index
in question here that says which asset
we used when we imported this thing that
needs to be slid back by whatever this
asset source file actually had its base
value be because that value is going to
get added back to it when we go to
expand the font right because the font
when it looks the bibbity it's gonna
rebase that value by however much get
thought the file was slid up so in that
in that asset here this asset based
value needs to be subtracted away right
so we need to use this asset file the
actual destination asset file which we
know but we need to actually know use
that to subtract off the value here
right and so what I'd like to do is say
okay wherever we were going to write
this thing and you know what I might do
to I might say we could do this as a
separate pass because I think that might
be a little bit safer so once we get
down in here and we say look what are we
writing to you we've got this desk file
index right so now I should be able to
go and say get or asset file no it's not
that it is there it is so what I need to
be able to do here is say look give me
the asset file back oh and it looks like
I'm already doing that right so here we
have the asset file and then I need to
run over my array here and rebase these
things so the asset base needs to get
subtracted from that glyph that code
point bitmap in index right
so when we actually do when we actually
do this right I need to make that value
get get subtracted away so for each code
point right before I save it out I need
to to go through and rebase it so that
they're all in the right position what
is this code points I think so let's
just double check that right so you can
see this happening here where this asset
base needs to be adjusted
perfect Hey look our fox importing works
now or sort of works at least who knows
um it looks like the spacing is a little
tight or something I don't know that
could be correct I'm not entirely sure
but it looks a little off so I think
maybe there's a there's still some bugs
in there I wouldn't call that done yet
but it's pretty close right
all right let's double check that
everything in there is working and then
we'll call it a day so tomorrow we'll
just at the debug why some of those
don't look quite right to me
or at least I don't know they don't seem
to so if I change - OH - here
[Music]
so this all seems to be working properly
I'm just not sure about the font
alignment necessarily I'm not sure if
it's quite right but I'll see any
thought like obvious font bugs so I
think we're pretty close
you
[Music]
alright okay we'll go to a brief Q&amp;A but
I think we're done so let's go ahead and
if you had to support ligatures for
instance FFI cannot request a lift when
using some fonts how would you store
that information in an asset file
I think Arabic works in a similar way
what about substitutions like in some
fonts uppercase Q can have a longer tail
went in front of a you at like inquest
um
so typically speaking that is not stored
in the asset file because you don't need
to write a ligature is its own code
point just to give you some perspective
on that right
so languages that have ligatures
typically get their own code points so
all you would do is say that you wanted
the FFI code point in your actual well
you know what if you want we could just
do it
basically but all you would do is say
include this in the font set so remember
how I said we want to be able to have
lots of different types of character
Maps this is why so in here we included
the kanji owl right and the reason we
included the kanji owl is because we
wanted to be able to put these like text
characters in there if you remember our
text up it has some kind of nonsense for
code points I think yeah so if you do a
backslash and then for hex digits it'll
just put in that thing
so I mean we can just do it if we want
to I might as well demo this right so
for example if we wanted the kanji owl
in there if I went to the editor and for
no good reason
you know in the camera section or
something let me let me go write like we
could just do that and once we run that
when we output our strings when it looks
at a string if it sees a code point
specified directly it will look up that
in the font as a code point number right
or maybe not did I know did I read that
wrong it was a back slash wasn't it
right this is the its backslash X are we
not calling text up we must be calling
text up right what is what is button and
stuff call yeah it's calling text up so
I'm not sure why that isn't because like
this is the code that gets that I should
guess I should look at is hex oh okay
so for whatever reason we decided it had
to be our format was it had to be
uppercase why I'm gonna say no to that
I I don't know why we wouldn't want our
is hex to allow lower case so I'm just
gonna change that
alright let's try that again alright so
when we do this it should parse that
code point and we should we'll see it
I'm not sure it looks like it couldn't
find that particular code point but I
thought I used one that we would have
although this may be broken as well yep
[Music]
there it is
so although we weren't certain lowercase
characters from reason so that was a
longer excursion than I'd hoped but you
can see that it just inserts whatever
the code point is there so if we wanted
to do the ligature thing that you were
talking about what we would want to do
there is and you'll have to forgive me I
don't remember what is okay fc5 COF so
let's see for some reason we wanted to
say like that there was a ligature in
here right like that and so you know we
run it and we get
this and you know you want it to have
the actual look real ligature across to
the eye let's just say right then what
you would do is inside HH font you would
say hey let's get the ligatures and in
here we would you know put those in here
while we're at it we should just look up
all the ones that you know you might
want here you go
so in English which is the only thing
we're currently doing and when you
expand to other languages we would want
to go X you know expand this out I think
these are the only ones that I normally
see right FFT and these so what we'd
want to do is support all that right so
we'd say like okay basically FB 0
through F beef 5
so we'd include all of those ligatures
in our actual font export and again
that's just a test set so you know
eventually we'd make one of these for
English and one for you know French or
whatever you know the languages that you
wanted to support as you like build out
your localization plan or whatever you
wanted to do there right and then when
we run HH fonts and have it dump the
thing out now there's going to be some
more glyphs than there were originally
so if we go to liberation mono to hht i
this is the only part that we're adding
in so everything else should be fine so
all I would say is like let's just copy
that okay
and now when we loaded it should have
more stuff and you can see that it does
right let me put that tags in there I
want a way to inject these tags I don't
really want to edit this file so that's
something that it would be nice to be
able to do so now if we saved it in
theory we should be able to use that
actual ligature instead of the other
thigh so in here we've got that FFI I
want to typeset with ligatures so what I
actually do here instead is I specified
the actual ligature for FFI which I
don't remember which one that is FB 0 3
so if this font had that ligature which
I don't think it does we would see an
actual thing there instead we just see
that little missing symbol which I
assume is what that is although maybe we
picked we got the I don't know maybe I
got the glyph point wrong but who knows
right but that's all you would do I
don't really know how to determine
whether we got that right or wrong I
guess we would have to look so I don't
really know how to do this in a test so
if I select liberation mono and I do an
insert special character you can
that did not work at all
so a reason it doesn't know
so
is it because this is clipping me out
I just I want to know I I don't really
know how I can go about testing the font
to see if it has this ligature they
don't have like a font editor installed
in this machine
so I'm assuming that likes ago would
have liked all of them because it's like
a Microsoft standard UI font
so let me see if this lets me insert
that special character so there it is
right and so I suspect the problem we
are having is that that like liberation
mono just doesn't have it so that's why
we couldn't extract it so if I go here
and do liberation mono it's looks like
it's still ariel right like it can't
change it
I'm sorry yeah it can't oh well no wait
but well but that's not liberation mono
is it cuz it's not mono space so I don't
know it must be doing a font
substitution there it's probably doing a
font substitution so yeah cuz that's not
VF you know so don't know I don't know
how to determine what just happened
there I I wish I knew how to look at a
font more specifically
so what we could do is change which font
we're loading just real quick so like
for example I couldn't here say I don't
actually know where that font file is
but we can find out
so like Segoe UI regular and I'll just
do like
and so in theory that will have those
ligatures included with it and if I move
Segoe UI or copy I should say Segoe UI
to here then theory I can include that
instead and see if that allows us to
pull the ligature or not if I went into
the Segoe UI file and throw the same tag
in there oops so that it can be picked
as a debug font then if I went to base
game DHT in here I could do like pound
include fonts Segoe UI to hht and that
would pull that in as another font I
don't think we support like deleting the
font from the hht really at the moment
so I'm not sure this is actually going
to work but we can try it
at the very least I can probably just
delete everything and restart the
packing yes so that's still the old one
so let me do we don't really have a way
of saying I didn't see this thing so
delete the asset right I think the only
thing we have for that is just like you
got a repack which isn't great but it's
not the end of the world
I don't do we have anything tips up that
remedies remedies really acting up today
it looks like anytime handmade hero was
going to crash
it looks like remedy couldn't handle it
for some reason like it got into like
some kind of a bad state you know what I
mean
yeah did I spell that wrong or something
it's it's just having the problem of not
finding a font which we probably should
make not crash like we should probably
just have that work okay because it's
not it wouldn't normally crash it's an
assertion so you know if we just
compiled in release mode it wouldn't
crash it would just run so it seems bad
to like box ourselves that way but it's
oh is that actually the correct name for
that s e-g Oh II you i dot h HT that
seems right it's got the tags in there
what was the problem
files look good I think
yeah I don't know
hmm well I'm just gonna see what happens
here if we can step in oops
so Wow no I guess it just can't do it
all right well we'll do what we'll deal
with this tomorrow I guess and maybe we
can see if there's a patch for for
remedy because I'm not sure I have not
had that problem it seems like something
in the latest build maybe but I'm not
sure the problem is but anyway if we use
a font where the ligature actually
exists presumably we can get it if I
look in here too and just look at this
ago we should be able to see if the
ligature actually got exported it looks
like it did right so so that was the
reason we weren't getting it before I
assumed that for the other one
liberation mono there was no yeah
there's no ligature so it looks like F I
and F L got exported sort of right I
mean they don't they're not actual
ligatures but they did get exported but
for some reason some of these other ones
just didn't and I don't know what
Windows fought why windows fought mapper
in particular has an issue with that but
that's all you would do for ligatures is
that and I wouldn't recommend doing it
really any other way you want to be able
to mint like it might be tempting to say
well let me just every time i output
strings look for FF I and replace it
with the ligature that's not a great
idea typically because you usually want
control over whether the ligature is
used or not used in any given context
and so it's usually better even if you
do do an automated system like that do
it at creation time so you can hand tune
it as necessary don't do it like on the
fly because then sometimes the rule may
be wrong and you don't and it's bad
right
so you know that's something to keep in
mind
it it's not there's not one kanji for
owl right it was a string it was a bunch
of them I thought we did we did four of
them so I'm not sure which it was it was
these four or maybe they were just other
test ones but it was
because I remember we looked it up and
it was like a specific kind of owl to or
something I don't remember exactly what
we did we have to go back to the video
but it was specifically all of these put
together that we used and I don't
remember why why we didn't just use this
I don't know but there was some kind of
nonsense like that
[Music]
it does anyone remember why it was it
was a it was a big block of text we use
and I don't remember why
maybe we did this
well we didn't use that so yeah I don't
know why we I don't know you got me man
we should go back and look because we
went yes I I know that that means small
but I don't remember what the other
characters mean at all although one of
them was like day or something wasn't it
or moon or since I can't I don't
remember where they what they were it
was it was like the three
that one's would write the one the tree
one so anyway I don't know where we got
the kanji for owl it would have been
nice if you just use this that but I
don't think for some reason we didn't
find that
I noticed you to clear the platform
struct with all the function pointers as
externa and handmade platform that age
how does the linker resolve that isn't
the platform a different excute Abul
well the reason that that's declared is
X turn in platform that age I think
though is has nothing to do with what
executables in I think that was done
because we wanted to be able to build
two-part executables there was there was
a reason why we did that it was like oh
we want the ping loader to be able to
create a platform context and stuff like
that so I don't think it had anything to
do with it wasn't because we were
separating them across the DLL
boundaries or anything like that because
we pass it into the game how did we
render text and you have any thoughts of
dealing with large number of glyphs such
as in Chinese we already deal with that
just fine we allow you to use any
Unicode code points you want and we just
fill up the glyphs tables as necessary
if you want to pile 3,000 characters in
there go right ahead since all of our
art is paged on demand it will just load
the symbols that are necessary right one
thing I would like to do is have a
smaller bitmaps table like right now we
use 512 512 for everything which is way
too big for glyphs we probably want a 64
64 like glyph table as well to small
store small things like small font info
but that's sort of a that's an
optimization for saving memory sort of a
another thing
do you think most the optimizations use
are domain-specific I game development
related and if so do you think it's
possibly a couple optimizations and
algorithms in the context of games I'm
not sure I understand the question I
don't really think of optimizations as
being domain-specific typically
optimizations are about like how you map
an algorithm to the CPU which doesn't
tend to depend on whether you're using
it in a game or elsewhere it is true
that sometimes you optimize things in
games that don't ever occur elsewhere so
like I mean you you know oh I'm doing
something with inner products that can
be pretty approximated here whereas it
couldn't be approximated elsewhere so
I'm I don't know I'm trying to make
something up I'm not sure I'm really
coming up with much to be honest
what was your experience with Cygnus ed
on the Amiga how do you compare it to
Emacs I would say that Cygnus ed doesn't
really have very many text editing
features as compared to Emacs so it's
pretty underpowered because it's
obviously hasn't had the billions of
hours of time making weird extensions
and stuff that Emacs has had but man the
speed like Cygnus ed is so much faster
than Emacs so Cygnus said on the Amiga
has a like much much higher frame rate
than Emacs on today's machine like no
joke Cigna said with 60 frames a second
always Emacs has never heard of 60
frames a second that they don't like 60
frames a second is like some mythical
thing that Richard Stallman doesn't
believe exists or something right
it looks like midlow has located where
we found the owl thing so did anyone
manage to figure out what the heck where
we found those characters or why
I mean it's weird because like here's a
ton of different types of owls none of
which are the symbols we ended up with
so I don't know where we got that from
we should probably fix it this seems
like a pretty definitive page I mean if
you're telling how to translate a Shrike
and agreed you probably know what you're
doing because those are some pretty
arbitrarily weird bird names right that
this is starting to look because that
that looks like what we got so maybe it
was like a small eared owl
yeah I'm saying
so that you know I that sounds vaguely
plausible would you agree with that that
maybe we were trying to say like small
ear owl small eared owl
because I think this is what we had and
then we just had small we had this we
had we also had small I don't see small
eared owl here but yeah but it seems
seems
okay short-eared owls okay yeah all
right so we we didn't write it totally
wrong but we did pick at various was
their kind of owl it seems which is fine
with me all right I'm gonna wrap it up
thank you for for joining me for another
episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you want to follow along series at home
you can always pre-order the game at
hand made here org and it comes to the
source code so that you can play around
with it
I'll be back tomorrow I'd like to see
why we're not loading segoe properly and
then like I said I think we probably
want to just like turn a little bit on
this system maybe just do some
refinement now that everything works
some of its looking at janky and we
don't really want to fight it like we
want it to kind of be nice and smooth so
it now might be a good time to just kind
of like clean this stuff up and make
sure that everything works okay so hope
to see you back here for that until then
have fun programming and I'll see
everyone on the Internet take it easy
everybody