hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here on the show where we code complete
game live on Twitch when my microphone
does not get in the way I really need a
longer cord for this thing it actually
caused us to lose a whole episodes
recording although we got it back from
Twitter just because I can't even when I
go down to like adjust it I'm in danger
of bumping the power cord but anyway we
will not last stop that us we will not
let that stop us we are in the middle of
doing some rendering code here on
handmade hero and we found out on Friday
much to our surprise that the
optimization work that we did over the
past two weeks to our renderer has left
us with a renderer now that is actually
running at 60 frames a second 1920 by
1080 which we were not expecting I guess
machines are just extremely fast these
days and when you have a 2-d game you
don't even need a GPU in the system
anymore even if you're doing full sub
pixel accurate rotation and all these
are the sorts of things I guess we'll
see if that holds up once we start
throwing more sprites and stuff at it
we'll see it's hard to say but we were
all pretty shocked anyway at least I was
to to find out kind of at the end of the
day exactly how fast this thing was
running so a little bit crazy a little
bit crazy it's true but that's where
we're at so we have some more work we
need to do what we're gonna do this week
is we're gonna clean up all of the
render code now that we kind of have
things roughly working we're gonna take
a snapshot kind of and look at what we
have at the end of that and then we're
gonna make some estimates as to allude
to these way back at the beginning of
the optimization pass we're gonna try
and make some estimates as to what we
actually think our throughput should be
and how much you know basically what do
we think the renderer could run at
capacity on this particular machine so
that we have some idea of like where
we're at in terms of that it may be that
we're already pretty close to the metal
it may be that we're actually far away
we really don't know and so the goal is
is going to be to try and like
sort of catch that up try to try to make
make some determination about that and
it turns out that just by doing the
straight porting work we needed to do to
get things into optimizable state before
we did that estimate happen to make our
code extremely fast which i guess is
just how it goes sometimes so hey we'll
take it anyway we are going to be doing
programming today we may do a little bit
on the blackboard but we're gonna be
doing programming today so if you want
to follow along at home today is a day
127 so unpack day 126 is source code
from the source archive if you have
pre-ordered the game and wanted to
follow along at home alright so the
first order of business that we have to
do here is we have to deal with
something that we have not really been
dealing with and it's a it's something
that we kind of have to tidy up and we
left it till now because it wasn't
really super relevant to any stuff for
doing but in order to kind of finish
things up we've got to address it at
this point so if you remember where we
left things we were running quite fast
actually but we did not quite have a
complete multi-threaded tiled renderer
working because if you remember there
are all of these black lines everywhere
and so everything is running quite
nicely actually but we shrunk our tiles
by a little bit which is kind of nice
because it allows us to see them but
that's certainly not what we would ever
ship in the game we don't want our game
to look like it's running at a bunch of
tiles not to mention the fact that it
messes up all of our background tiles as
well because they now have the lines in
them too so there's all kinds of reasons
why this is not a particularly good
thing to have happening so what we would
like to do is we would like to go ahead
and and look at why we had to do that
and sort of get into a position where we
no longer have to worry about that
mm-hmm
also I have a few sort of tidbits I
double checked these I looked them up
and I also double check them with the
rad folks who as you know are usually
the authority I would go to when I want
actually to actually know something
about how the processor works in
practice because they confront these
sorts of things head-on all the time
they confirmed for me I remember I kind
of went back and forth on this a couple
times but they confirmed for me that s
fences are not necessary now you
remember I said at the beginning when we
started talking about multi-threaded
code I said that the x64 processor had
very strong memory ordering so rights
were gonna be ordered in general but
then I kind of backtracked that a little
bit I was like well there's this s fence
instruction now I don't know maybe my
knowledge is out-of-date and so and I
and I kind of said we kind of got a we
kind of have to go do a little bit of
reading or figure out what the what the
truth is so we know whether we have to
insert these or not and the answer is
that it has not changed s fences are not
necessary
and so the reason that s fences are in
there and do not necessary is because of
a thing and this this actually was true
all the way back it wasn't even a change
from from my sort of knowledge of how
things worked so that was pretty nice
for me because a lot of times on
handmade here when I go to teach
something I have to kind of couch it and
say well this is how it used to work and
then I got to go check and oftentimes
it's like it's been evolved somewhat
since then so I got to be like alright
remember I said this well that's not
exactly true anymore stuff like this but
this is still the same since when I
first learned it so that's kind of nice
but anyway what I want to talk about
here is a thing called right combining
memory really quickly so essentially the
way things work in the processor
hopefully it's it's all sort of sunk in
by now since we've talked about this
many many many many times is that we
have a CPU and it's got registers right
and the registers are where things
actually happen so we kind of have these
registers and maybe it's a sim D
register or something like this so it's
wide it's got a bunch of values who
knows but point being these registers
then get written or they get read from
the cache right and the cache is the
thing that basically stores the contents
of memory locations that are being
frequently used by this processor well
anything that gets used by the processor
goes into the cache first before it is
used at least most of the time and then
you know it gets operated on in the
cache then later it will get put back
out to memory so memory is out here
somewhere and
much slower so we're working in the cash
and then things kind of come back and
forth in and out and so on and this cash
also happens to be a thing we talked
about cash snooping where there's other
processors and their caches and they
talk to each other to figure out who
owns what memory at what times and all
this other sorts of good stuff so the
answer in terms of fencing we talked
about this you should all know what
fencing is on the CPU side CPU fencing
the answer is on the x64 right there is
no need to worry about right ordering
because rights are always ordered and so
the order in which you see the rights
occur in the code meaning whatever the
compiler outputs in the order those
rights will be retired in that order ok
so we still need that right barrier
there because the right barrier remember
is not an instruction it's just a thing
that tells the compiler not to move
stores around but the question was do we
need to also tell the CPU not to move
them around ok and so the answer as to
why that offense is even there if the
CPU is always ordering instructions is
because sometimes there's actually a
concept of special memory right in some
sense and and I guess specials probably
the wrong word from it let's just say
that there are things that are memory
types ok so not all memory is treated
the same by the processors basically
what this means normally when we have
memory that we allocated and we know
what's going on with it
it's something we got from the operating
system is just plain old vanilla memory
for our use those rights will be ordered
so in this case like for example this
stuff right here it's all just vanilla
stuff it was declared on the stack or in
the heap or something like this
happening there is no need to worry
about it those rights are strongly
ordered but there is another thing well
I already wrote it I'll just point it up
here called right combining memory and
there's also other types of memory the
processor has different ways you can
think about memory so when you have a
special circumstance sometimes you get a
different type of memory and right
combining memory for example is one of
those types of memory and what that
usually is is if the hardware like like
say a GPU or something like this right
in fact I'll just write GPU here so if a
GPU where something has some memory out
on it out on the card itself and the CPU
on the the sort of the the
bored side of things has mapped that
memory right so basically the GPU this
these two memory regions are basically
like coinciding right so we have some
GPU memory and it's backed by some
memory on the on the mainboard and like
the CPU is gonna write into this memory
somewhere right and then the GPU like
the PCI bus is gonna you know sort of
sync these across to the GPU or stuff
like this right so if we have some weird
stuff going on here what can happen
sometimes is the memory in the machine
if it has special constraints like this
all sorts of weird things happen once
the PCI bus once the GPU is like looking
at memory you're also you know who knows
what's happening right when the CPU is
writing to memory like this memory that
has special Hardware consequences beyond
the normal just storage of bits then
what happens is it has to write out
cache lines in a carefully considered
way okay because whenever it decides to
actually flush a cache line out to
memory and make that considered a write
the G it will actually have consequences
in terms of the speed at which things
can be done because it has to make sure
that the GPU can see it and then it's
visible in the right way and that the
GPU wasn't looking at it so maybe that's
the lock with system bus who knows what
happens I don't have any idea I don't
study these kinds of things at all but
the point is complex stuff starts to be
afoot here and what that means is the
CPU actually is much slower at dealing
with writes that go out to this memory
so what it will often do is try to
combine right this is where the right
combining comes to it will try to
combine writes to this memory so that it
does not actually have to flush them out
serially right so the example here would
be let's say we have two cache lines
right here's cache line a and here's
cache line B okay the CPU writes to this
part of this cache line and then it
writes to this part of this cache line
right then it writes to this part of
this cache line and then it writes to
this part of this cache line right well
with right combining memory it might be
smarter for the
you two wait and see what's going on
here wait for these to kind of get
filled up with all those rights and then
flush them out right but the problem is
here if you know let's say we just had
the rights in order we wrote you know
this was a bad idea for me to label them
that way let me write them in the order
they're written so we have this thing
gets written one this thing gets written
two then this thing gets written three
right well it may end up in a situation
where this thing wants to get flushed
but this thing wants to be held because
it knows that the three is going in
there and it doesn't want to write it
out to memory until the three is in
there so only has to do one right of
this cash line out to that memory right
then what would happen is the two may
end up happening before the one so what
the s fence is is the S fence is
actually in there only for putting in
memory fences when you are writing to
things like right combining memory which
may reorder rights for you if you are
not writing to that kind of memory then
you do not ever have to worry about s
fence because normal memory never needs
an s fence the rights are ordered
automatically and the cache works
properly no matter what you do right so
I just thought I'd point that out okay
so that's that that's right combining if
that's what the S fences are for so we
don't need that s fence and I've double
triple verified that so we're all good
we only need the right barrier that's
the only part that we have to ensure is
working properly and remember our
interlock compare exchanges would be
increased inserting memory fences anyway
so those are also sensing us but we
don't even really need to care about
that too much because the the right
barrier is already happening for us up
here okay so let's talk about our other
problem that we have here which is the
the whole problem with us shrinking
everything so if we went down here to
our tiles you can see where we do our
tile cueing here's our tiled render
group to output thing which goes through
each of the tiles that we want to render
and it renders them but of course it
shrinks them first and you can kind of
see here that that it's doing this
shrinking right and so we have to ask
ourselves
what is going on here and why did we
have to do this and there's two reasons
that we had to do it and both of them we
can fix by being a little bit smarter if
there's one sort of nasty element to it
and you'll kind of see what we have to
do to work around that but but most of
its actually just sort of a head end
problem that we can solve so let's talk
about why we were doing this shrinking
okay so let's talk about our tiles and
our alignment here okay so the first
problem that we have right and you can
kind of see that this is this is going
to be the case is we are always
processing for pixels at a time right so
at a bare minimum when we are doing this
rendering we kind of have to know that
we can always process for pixels at a
time right so if for example our bitmap
that we had allocated was not going to
be a multiple of four so let's say that
we look at how you know why this thing
is and in fact I believe we actually had
this this circumstance already if we
take a look here
I think 950 because we had nineteen
twenty divided by two
right Coop's nineteen twenty eight
divided - oh it was 960 never mind all
right never mind I was gonna say we
might even had that with our original
thing but never mind so point being we
need to make sure first of all that if
we always that if we break things up
into sort of four pixel buckets that
they're actually always will be four
pixel buckets to do and that we don't
end up with like a three pixel bucket at
the end and then some like either
invalid or like the first pixel of the
next line shows up over here right so
the first thing we have to do is make
sure we have to set up the memory so
that we know we always have a even
multiple of four pixels on every for
every row right that just has that we
just flat out I have to do that that's a
requirement so there's that but beyond
that we also have to look at the fact
that we are actually currently writing
our stuff unaligned
right we do a load on the lines and we
do a store on a line for the desk and we
actually start right on or end right on
the complete pixel remember we had our
choice of doing that and since start up
with easier
right masking what we chose to do was
end on the correct pixel but what that
means is that if we always end on the
correct pixel that means if we were
actually doing something that was like
this sort of trying to think of what the
right look read if we're always ending
on a for right and we were bleeding
something in here then that means we're
always gonna kind of have a thing where
the the blit is actually sort of
operating on sort of this with this
wider region and I have to think about
thinking about this I don't know that
that ever actually matters for what
we're doing though now that I think
about it I was gonna say something here
about that alignment but I don't know
that we actually really care that much
about that alignment that alignment may
always be fine because either it got
clipped to the boundary or it didn't so
yeah so we're okay there never mind so
we don't have to worry too much about
that actually I think that actually
could stay what we do have to worry
about is again our tiles right our tiles
have to be multiples of four always
because if our tiles aren't multiples of
four then if our even though our bitmap
was multiple of four we would again
create this situation where we have
tiles that don't quite align to this
four pixel boundary now you may wonder
why that's actually relevant because who
cares that the tiles are or aren't the
reason for that is because we want to
avoid a situation I'm going to go ahead
and mark off some some things here so
here's four pixels four pixels four
pixels four pixels right suppose that
our tile boundary happened right here so
there's two pixels on in this tile and
two pixels on this tile right so here
are the pixels so this is tile a over
here in these two pixels belong to tile
a and here's the tile B and these pixels
the belong to tile B right
so squares we have a situation like that
the problem that we will end up in if we
allow this to happen is that our tiles
are now being rendered by two separate
threads potentially right because the
work queue could decide well you know
we're not doing anything special there
the work you could easily hand this over
to korzy
right and this over to core one and they
could be happily going along processing
these at the exact same time now what
that means is remember interlocked
increments and those sorts of things
always work synchronous with the CP with
the cores and won't have a problem but
these here are not anything like that we
load in an unaligned thing here right so
we would potentially be loading in this
part here right that we're trying to get
at
we may be loading in some kind of a for
wide thing like let's say that this
happened to be you know if we if we back
if we were doing it so that we ended
right here maybe we load this part right
here in right we load this into core
zero so it's got the AABB there right
but then core one may come and load that
exact same thing in right it may also
load in AABB they both will process it
and now they'll both try to right back
to it right and the problem is if they
both are trying to right back to this
same piece of data one of the or the
other will overwrite the work that the
other person did right because this
person's going to replace the a a with
some new stuff right it's going to
replace that with something else right
like X X or something and it's gonna try
to write back x x.b be here but then
this guy is going to replace the BV with
something else right it's gonna replace
it with y Y or something so what's going
to try to write back YY but when it
tries to write back YY the a and the a
are still in that for wide block so the
a a will overwrite the X X and undo the
work that this core did if this core
retires the memory afterwards right so
again strong right ordering is all fine
but you have to remember that once
things get loaded into a processor
they're in the register of the processor
and that's what you're working on the
cache has no idea that that's supposed
to refer to it or until you go back and
do a store later so you're constantly
talking about like moving this memory
into the bus are working out and putting
it back out during that time when it is
inside the processors registers you have
no synchronization with the other cores
at all and so you'd better make sure
that no two people are going to write
over what each other we're trying
to store as data right so we need to
make sure that we align we absolutely
have to align I don't know what just
happened there okay we have to make sure
that we align our tiles to these four
wide boundaries and that nobody is ever
doing any kind of unaligned fetching
across those tile boundaries in any way
but I'm pretty sure there's no way they
can so even though we're doing unaligned
here I don't think that actually matters
at all we timed it we notice that the
lined or unlined this didn't seem to
matter so that was fine we can always
reject that again later but what we do
need to make sure so we can make that
online we just have to make sure that it
never crosses that boundary we know it
won't cross the boundary at the end but
in order to make sure that it also
doesn't cross the mouth beginning we
need to make sure that these tiles are
always exactly four wide so let's start
by doing that part and and we should be
able to make sure actually just by
assertion that the rest of its true
because it seems like it's already
actually is true and that'll be fine so
what we need to do here is say okay
we've got our tile with we've got our
tile height that we computed and we need
to make sure that those are rounded to
the nearest four because if we don't
then we won't be able to align this
right furthermore we need to make sure
that anywhere that we're ready to is
actually aligned to the actual four byte
boundary absolutely because that's what
we're actually looking at so we kind of
needed it to make those two things
happen exactly no you know what I missed
one thing we are doing our load
unaligned but all okay so we do have to
do the thing that I was thinking of
sorry haven't paged this entire routine
in it ends wherever the bitmap ends
right so it's gonna end wherever the
bitmap happened in which may be in the
middle but I guess that now that's still
okay too
it really just does not matter because
as long as the it's clipped to the tiles
I think we're fine all right never mind
I had a like a brains faster than a
reverse brain spasm okay so back to our
plan here
what we need to do is we need to make
sure that we're going to always get
aligned tiles and so what we want to do
first of all is say let's make sure that
the output target always actually allows
us to get that that sort of to get the
amount of the tiling that we actually
need so what we can do is we can just
count on if we want to we can count on
the upstream code to always allocate the
target to basically be correct if that
makes sense
so we have our output target and you
know what I realize this is probably
actually wrong here because the tile
width we need to think a little bit more
about what this this actually means but
we can we can sort of talk about that in
a second what we want to do here is we
want to say all right when we separate
this into a four by four array of tiles
we want to make sure that we actually
ended up with things that are going to
be on even multiples of four so when we
take the tile with here we want to take
a look now and see and make sure that
that's what we actually got so the tile
width right we need to go ahead and say
if you know assert essentially that the
tile with is well I should be a little
more specific here I'll tell you exactly
what we need to do so we're going to
compute some tile with right and we
could have any old resolution here let's
say we have you know the resolution that
the user wanted or something was nine
hundred and sixty seven pixels right
something like this well nine hundred
and sixty seven pixels right if I
actually go and divide that by four so I
go ahead and say you know I want to do a
quick calculi no 67 plus three divided
by four
I get two hundred and forty two point
five right and so obviously I'm not
going to fit the right number of those
you know that that width is not actually
going to be correct
like I guess I could just do it this way
as well nine hundred and sixty-seven I
divided by four so I know that I can fit
two hundred and forty forty-one of those
in there right I'm sorry
each one will
241 wide but I have to round it up in
order to cover the screen because 240
175 if I actually has tiled 241 I would
be missing some pixels at the end so 242
would have to be the width of the tiles
right if there's going to be 4 of them
right so there'd be 242 would be the
width right now 242 then we have to
press these in back to the 4 pixels that
is 60 60.5 4 pixel units right so again
that's not an even multiple either right
so really it would have to process 61 4
pixel units in order to actually work
out right so what we then need to go
back and do is say okay well if we're
gonna process 61 for a pixel units right
and we know that we're going to have
four of these
then how many does that actually give us
at the end of the day if we were going
to use 4 by 61 by 4 basically right or
16 times 61 right that's gonna give us
976 right so that means our effective
resolution what we're actually gonna be
filling here is 976 pixels okay and
hopefully I went through that a little
bit quickly but you see what I did there
basically I was just saying all right if
we were actually to do the divides and
then round up how many pixels would we
have to fill at a minimum if he wanted
to do always 4 pixel units and four
chunks across a row right and the answer
is we would have to do 976 pixels so
what we need to ensure is that the
destination buffer always would allow us
to overwrite the end of it by that much
does that make sense because since we're
going to be processing it in these
batches it just means that that's the
way things are going to line up right
and we have to be able to to overwrite
it by a certain amount now we only
really have to overwrite we can set the
clipping
we can set that clipping line to the
nearest for a pixel boundary so we said
we wanted 967 right and we can actually
hard clip to there so we don't need to
worry about the fact that we don't
really need the full 976 right because
we can just have that final tile be kind
of small right
but that 967 will not actually work
because we will actually right over that
slightly so we just have to make sure
that that is rounded to a 4 pixel
boundary if that makes sense because
what we'll do is that final tile like
each of these tiles right this will be
61 this will be 61 this will be 61 right
for a total of oops 61 times 4 times 3
for a total of 732 so you know this will
be 732 and then we will have nine
hundred and sixty seven minus that 732
right so nine hundred and sixty seven
minus seven hundred thirty-two and we
end up with 235 right
this is 235 pixels here right and these
guys right were 732 divide before these
guys were the way I did that what I do
wrong there what did I do wrong there
these guys are 61 times for their 244
that's does yeah so these guys are 244
each so these guys would be 244 each for
each tile but then the final tile would
be missing some right that's just how
that would that would work out and it
would be 235 pixels so that's fine we
can set the clipping region so that we
only process 235 pixels but we're going
to go over by however much this this is
off by rounding to 4 right
so whatever 235 divided by 4 is right 58
0.75 so we would need 59 times 4 or 236
right so it's off by 1 we just need to
make sure that that that buffer actually
supports us over writing a little bit we
have to be able to overwrite it just
that little bit right
and then we're good
so all the things we need to do we need
to make sure that each of the tile
boundaries happens on a four pixel
boundary we need to make sure that the
final tile actually has spaced out at
past the end of it so we can overwrite
that little region because we're doing
those rights you know that's just the
way that we're doing the rights wide
potentially and then once we have gotten
all of that worked out we should just be
good to go to leave our tiles exactly
you know for exactly fitfully filling
the screen without any sort of borders
so that's the stuff that we need to do
and we need to ensure the alignment of
the start of the row as well we need to
make sure we've talked about alignment
before we need to make sure that that
start of the row is also aligned because
if each of these is going to be aligned
we need to start it out aligned as well
right so let's go ahead and try to put
our buffer into this forum as much as we
can so the first thing I want to do is I
want to assert that whatever the output
targets actual destination is Right the
output target go ahead and look up what
these actually are see here wait so the
memory right for that I want to make
sure that that memory if I were to look
at what the memory actually is I want to
ensure that that memory is already
aligned to a four pixel boundary right
and now a four pixel boundary remember
pixels actually take up four bytes of
space so we're actually talking about 16
actual bytes for 4 pixels right so what
we want to do is make sure that if we
were to look at at this value ANDed with
15 so looking at those bottom bits there
we want to make sure that they are all
equal to 0 so that it is aligned at the
start right and we want to be able to
assert I'm going to turn off
our optimization here so we want to make
sure that it is not ever on a line right
and so right now I guess I don't
actually know if we're doing any work in
the platform layer to actually make sure
that it is aligned but you can see that
we are actually getting aligned so
that's a good thing so the next thing we
need to do is make sure that our tile
widths are tri lights don't matter
because our tile Heights remember we
never process four pixels vertically we
only process four pixels horizontally so
our tile widths they happen to actually
be totally fine as long as they're for
as long as there are four pixels wide
right so we can get rid of these hmm
guess we should leave that one so what
we want to do is go ahead and say tile
lip whatever the tile with is it needs
to get rounded up to the next to two to
the four byte boundary right and
actually we can bake that in here I
suppose if we want to we can just say
whatever the the tile width is we can
round it up by adding in first whatever
the the value is that we're dividing by
minus one right that's just a little
trick for getting the rounded value
because it's basically like since we're
going to truncate we just make sure that
we will put it up to just before
whatever the next round you would have
been and then divide that way it will
always give us that rounding if it
happened to be over whatever the
rounding point was so this will give us
the tile with rounded up to the nearest
four although I guess now that I think
about it that's that's actually dumb I
take that back
because we want to be able to change
tile count it just happens to be the
right thing but we want to be able to
change this to any number so let's not
do it that way instead let's go ahead
and say we just want to round this guy
so we want to take tile whip right and
we want to whatever the result value is
of tied with we want to round it to the
nearest four so what I'm gonna do there
is I'm gonna do tile with you know I
want it to add in three and divide by
four right so I want to do what I was
doing there but I want to do it after
the fact so that we actually ensure that
we we have we've done that that rounding
so that will give us the the actual
number if I then multiply it by four at
at the end that will give us the actual
number rounded up right so if we kind of
if we take a look in here I want to see
what what numbers we were actually good
and maybe that we're already getting
those numbers anyway like I said we we
kind of just put that in there because
we wanted to be safe about it but we may
have already actually been getting
numbers that didn't actually need to be
rounded so let's go ahead and here so if
we take a look at tile width right oops
I want to do that before so you take a
look at tile width it's already 64 which
is already plenty divisible so that's
that's not gonna be a problem let's
let's go ahead and let it run so that
those are probably ground chunks that
are coming in here so let's go ahead and
do this again 480 run it 480 so we're
actually already getting ones that are
that are nicely rounded we may have to
test them with some sizes that aren't
rounded just to make sure that our math
is working here properly but you know
what are you gonna do so this will do
the truncation and then it will it will
multiply back out so this will leave us
with a value that's that's properly
rounded so then what we need to do is we
make need to make sure that our last
that final tile with actually account to
the fact that it's going to be smaller
right so what we need to do is we need
to do a final tile whip and that final
tile whip needs to be whatever the total
was so whatever the full screen size is
minus the tiles that will actually be
this sort of potentially inflated size
right so we need to say whatever the
tiles that would have been done besides
the final tile that final tile only
accounts for however much is left right
then what we need to do in here when
we're doing this right well actually now
think about it we could actually do this
a little bit easier in fact you know
what we don't even need to do that all
we need to do is when we do our clip
Breck max our maximum there all we need
to do is say you know what if that
cliprect
maximum would actually be greater than
that the actual output target then just
go ahead and set it to the output target
right that'll automatically clip us when
we get to the end so that's that's as
easy as doing anything else would be
right so then if we go in here we no
longer need to do these sort of
adjustments because we're trying to sort
of take care of that
in a separate way so now we've got our
tile with adjusted and we can sort of
say let's go ahead and make sure that
you know that that'll works let's run
that here see how we're doing uh we are
loading from something that it's not
allowed hold on a second
the clip F max F is greater than the
upper target with this equals alpha
Tiger with that looks correct to me
alright so we'll have to go debug this
and see what's going on there of course
I don't actually know if we actually did
render enough oh you know what else I
can do I'll go ahead and make it so that
we're also running single threaded for
the moment so that we can not have to
worry about multiple threads while we're
debugging which is kind of nice by the
way in the thread view you I don't know
if you guys noticed you can see our
worker threads right and they're all
chillin in thread proc waiting for work
they won't do anything since now we're
not pushing the mam or single threaded
right now but just so you can see them
on thread window there there they are
we made those alright anyway so we're
loading off of nonsense here
unfortunately and I'm not sure where we
actually are so X I equals know what min
x equals negative 1 so this backed up
behind the pixel boundary
okay so right we're only clipping to the
end but we don't do it handle any
clipping at the beginning hmm all right
so this may actually be the thing that I
keep saying that we need to think about
and then when I go in and look at it we
don't need to think about it but let's
see if this is actually it I think that
would actually be it so here you go
so the way that things are working at
the moment yeah okay so this is what I
this is this is the problem I sort of
went in and said oh it won't happen on
this end but it will happen on the other
end so we will have to deal with it I I
knew we'd have to deal with it at some
point so the problem that we have right
now is when you blitt something in right
and I guess I'll do it over here first
so when you blitz something in here's a
screen and here's a this is the bitmap
we stop we align things to the end of
the blitz so this will get clipped right
the rectangle will get clipped and then
we'll start at this end in terms of
lining things up and we'll kind of go
like this right where each of these is
for pixels and you know this part
doesn't matter because it gets masked it
won't get written and we'll fill them in
here right but the problem is if we do
that over here on this side right yes we
will do the clipping but then when we
actually do the 4 pixel alignment bit
right we will end up being off sort of
on the on the end right and we'll be
writing into the beginning of the buffer
here which obviously is is not you know
is not particularly useful that's not
particularly that's not great right it's
not fabulous so I feel like the easiest
way to solve that problem and this is
what I was saying before but then I was
like man we don't need to do it at the
end it's true we don't need to at the
end we need to at the beginning because
the way we wrote the routine I feel like
the way to solve this problem properly
is we would need to make sure that we
that we always allocated some extra
space the beginning however which would
be trivial for us to go and do however
this presents a problem for us
it presents a problem that is the
problem that I kept alluding to and that
I you know was saying we maybe wouldn't
have to face because I was like looking
through and going no but we do it to
face it and that is what happens when
this occurs at a tile boundary right so
I was saying up here that you know this
would be a bad condition well guess what
that is exactly what will happen if we
have a bitmap that happens to end say
right here but that is six long right
because we'll align it so that we're
writing to these four pixels but then
when we go to write these will actually
be talking about this this set of four
even though there are only two we're
gonna write and we'll end up with that
with that problem with the writing right
so what that says to me is we do
actually have to do the thing that I
kept thinking we would have to do which
is that we will have to make sure that
we are essentially always writing
aligned and that we mask both our front
and our back right because remember the
reason that we were writing unaligned is
so that we could avoid having to do one
of the mask rights what can I say that's
just the way it is sometimes you try to
avoid it and it doesn't work so that's
what we're gonna have to do and the
reason that it's a little bit annoying
I'll show you why is because before you
know it there's no magic to it it's
exactly what we did here right what we
did is we said okay when we're starting
up we know how much we're going to fill
and if the fill width is is not you know
gonna is not actually going to be
aligned then we need to align the start
right and so that's all we really did
was just align that start right I'm
sorry we need to make a mask for the
start and then and then go ahead right
but what we actually want to do here is
we actually want to make sure that we
align the actual whole blip to whatever
the nearest boundary is right and if we
align the whole blit to the to a
boundary what that's unfortunately to do
is it's going to mean that there might
be a mask at the start and the end
because if we are always working on
aligned for 4-byte wide I'm sorry for
pixel wide options then that means that
the start up and the end might might
both be clipped right so if there's no
way getting around if there's nobody
getting around it that's fine let's go
ahead and and work it out so I'm going
to take a look here I'm
going to say alright we've got this fill
rect let's see here I got a page this
code into my own little memory cache so
what I want to look at here is I want to
say well if we've got it we don't really
care about the fill width so much what
we care about actually is the min X
right we need to get that min X aligned
and I guess we need to get the max X
aligned as well and so the first thing
that we probably want to check is is the
min X aligned right and so I'm going to
start with that so I'm going to say all
right if the fill rect min X is not
aligned we'll move it back okay so we'll
say if the fill rect min X is is not
aligned we got to move it back and I
guess we'll we'll sort of say we've got
our start up clip fast and our so to our
I guess our left to fats and our right
clip mask might be the right thing
because there's one at the end when one
at the beginning one at the end or I
could call them beginning start clip
mask and end clip mask and they're not
sure what's going there but anyway we'll
got these two clip mask will assume that
there's no clipping well then say all
right if the Phil rec min X is actually
something that's that's going to be
unaligned we'll go ahead and align it so
we'll say that the min X is gonna knock
out whatever those bits are right so the
the min X gets knocked down and I guess
we could say new min X maybe equals that
and then say full rectum in x equals and
x like so and we need to go ahead and
make our our masks here and I feel like
we might as well just do that actually
you know this is this is actually you
know what we don't even need to do that
this is gonna be a lot simpler than that
what we can really just do here is say
start up cliff mask equals you know clip
masks and we'll just go ahead and make a
little table of them since there's only
going to be a few right we'll just say
that whatever it is and three look that
up and that's the clip mask right and
then go ahead and make sure that it is
actually aligned okay so that's pretty
straightforward then what we have to do
is say all right if the max X is is also
not aligned then that one has to do it
has to be aligned as well and that's
gonna be the exact same thing only
unfortunately this time it's got a round
up not down right and so we need to let
the check out the clip mask thing there
it's actually just it's I think it's
just the we could actually just subtract
the value from it but we'll take a look
at that in a second anyway so the fill
Rack filler X Max X here is going to be
you know done the exact same way to
knock out those bits but then if we can
just add 4 to it to basically round it
up instead of down if that makes sense
so that seems pretty straightforward
there so once we have those aligned I
don't know if fill width is or either of
these things I'm used ever again no so
we should be able to actually kind of
blow these away I think I don't think
anything has to happen there so if we
change all the filler echt up there then
really all we need to do is is make our
clip Basques here so this will be the
the M 128 I clipped masks we need to set
those so we need to say we've got each
of these right something like this and
those will be correct for startup clip
masks right so this is essentially
taking what's set to all ones right oops
I got put in clip that's there this
one's set to all ones and let me go
ahead and we shift it so that we end up
with ones that are properly done for the
startup so this goes ahead and mash out
the first sorry this one goes out head
and mash up first pixel this one a
second pixel this mask masks out the
third pixel right now we want to do the
exact same thing for the I guess I
should do it this way
we want to do the exact same thing for
the startup in the shut down clip masks
there start clip mask
there's end clip masks and I said we
could Rob ibly do this a little bit
clever but I don't wanna get clever just
yet
so we'll do this the straightforward way
and all this is gonna be is the exact
opposite right this is just gonna be
shifts in the opposite direction so
instead of masking out the first pixels
this max out the end pixels so however
unaligned that max X is there we're
gonna do the opposite thing wait I got
to think about that it's not actually
correct so well let's just do it in
blackboard instead of thinking it's
always better to do the drawing so at
the end what's gonna happen here is that
they're right on the zero boundary then
we don't have a problem it's aligned
right but let's say that it was here so
they it actually has to write one of
these guys then what we want to do is we
want to have you know in in our
processor order right like so we want to
have FS down here and zeros up here
right so what we wanted to do is we want
to have sort of a shift we want to shift
this way we want to shift right right
and we want to shift right by three
right so I think it actually looks
something more like that right no three
two one like so so I think we want to do
something actually more like that right
and technically we could even if we want
to here just do these these don't
actually have to be predicated I don't
know if we want them predicated or not
but we don't actually have to have them
predicated right so anyway we've got
start clipping masks and in clipped mass
I think those are set right now so this
one would be you know shift out three of
the pixels this one would only shift out
the first two this one we shift out the
first one and I think that's what we
actually want right because as that gets
up higher in terms of where it is on the
line meant that's what we want to do and
so we have a start clipping mask on in
clipped mask the only problem is now we
don't actually know when to use the end
clip mask right because the routine
already handles that start up here where
it does the it resets the clip mask
to be negative one but what we have to
do now is when this is why it's a little
ugly as we unless I'm missing some
clever thing and this is why I didn't
really want to do in the first place we
actually have to put in some predication
here to actually set the clip mask right
we have to do something where we're
going to check to see what the what the
status is in terms of X I write because
you can kind of see it stepping up here
now I don't actually know x i's never
used anywhere so what I'd like to do
here is potentially make this a little
bit friendlier for the test right so we
can maybe loop over something other than
that so we'll do that in a second but
for right now what I'll do is just say
okay if whatever X I is gonna be next
right so I'm gonna you know if X I plus
4 that's the iteration we're about to do
right if whatever we do next
plus 4 would be outside the bounds then
that's going to be the the last one so I
want to actually go ahead and set the
clip mass to the end clip mask on that
final run right if that makes sense so
that's what I want to start out by doing
right
oops start clip mask and clip mask yeah
it's dark - clip mask
there we go so I want to fix that up a
little bit potentially but I just want
to see if we're getting a little closer
there ooh that's a little ugly a little
bit ugly that that is not quite correct
I think we all have to agree that that
is not that does not look fabulous I
think we're all like we're all on the
same page there uh-huh but you know it's
getting there
oh whoops I've got the sense of this
reversed if it's under max X it's not on
the last one so that's okay that's
problem number one sorry about that okay
so actually now we look a little more
correct right that looks like a more
correct lit and we are also not crashing
which is a nice
aspect of it so what I want to do now is
see if we're always aligned so I'm going
to take out these store these use the
store you and the load you I want to go
ahead and and make sure we're always
loading and storing actually aligned
right and so we shouldn't it those will
crash if we're they will like actually
fault if we're not aligned so I just
want to make sure that we're not getting
that crash and they're we're not getting
that crash okay so let's step it up
another notch
make sure everything's kosher here I'm
going to set us 202 and see how we're
doing you know to we're doing pretty
good here that's that's looking okay so
that's that's that's not too bad right
that's all good and I'll go ahead and
also see what happens if we if we turn
on threading child render group here we
go so there we go so it's looking pretty
good we don't have those those nasty
tiles anymore so that's all nice and so
I think that's pretty reasonable now the
platform code has to still be
guaranteeing us that it's doing that
it's allocating the memory aligned and I
want to go just double check to make
sure that it is in fact doing that and
that we're not getting that by accident
if that makes sense
because again this assertion here we
need to make sure that these are all
actually assumptions that are not going
to be totally invalid
right so let's take a look if I go in
here to where we allocate that right you
can see us virtual a locking this here
and so in here we do the win32 resize
dip section that's where we do the
virtual elect with our bitmap memory
size you can see the bitmap memory size
here is not actually doing anything in
particular to make sure that the size is
around a properly but virtual a lock
will always return us memory that starts
on a page boundary which by definition
will be aligned to actually I think fork
K not just 16 bytes so it'll be way over
a line for that
but the problem is the the pitch here we
don't actually have any guarantee that
we're actually going to be aligned to
four pixel boundaries so what I want to
do is make sure that we're aligned to
four pixel boundaries at least when we
do this so what I want to do is change
the way that we're making this happen a
little bit here I want to go ahead and
bring the pitch computation up above
here I want to say that the pitch
computation is going to be the width
times bytes per pixel and then I'm going
to allocate based on multiplying the
pitch times the height and what I want
to do there is I want to go ahead and
round this value so that this value will
be rounded to an even multiple of four
right so I want to say or to sixteen
bytes basically right so I want to do
something I'm just gonna call a line
sixteen right and I want a line sixteen
to align things properly now I don't
know if we've ever actually put in any
kind of alignment code into anything
here I don't think we have but I'd like
to kind of introduce that so what I want
to do is introduce a thing a line
sixteen which takes some kind of a value
doesn't matter what the value is and
then does exactly what's happening in
these things here right it's it's
something that's going to to produce the
desired rounding right so what I'm gonna
do there is gonna say I want to take the
value whatever that value is I want to
add 15 to it right and then I want to
masked out whatever the part of it is
that that would have been on aligned
right so this will round it up right
this will round it up to the nearest
value that it that is a multiple of 16
so that way we can guarantee that that
pitch is always going to actually be
it's actually always going to be valid
for the assumptions that we have in the
renderer which again it was already
happening because of the width that we
happen to choose but I just wanted to
make sure that that would always be the
case because now our renderer literally
cannot accept anything other than that
so we wanted to make sure that that's
fine and now that is fine so I think
we're good now on rendering
everything looks fine here we are at
1920 by 1080 and everything's fine
so that's all good we still haven't
actually done anything with our with our
sorting or any of that stuff yet but
we're we're in good shape here I think
that's all pretty reasonable how much
time we got left here we got 2 minutes
left so we did that that's all good
we'll come back here we can remove this
now we've got the assertion in there so
that'll fire in the case where we have a
problem I can also I suppose based on
looking at how this was with o2d weekend
where our game even at 1920 by 1080 is
totally fine to use right now even in
debug builds because if we turn
multi-threading on we just get a pretty
big boost from it so that's nice
obviously mm-hmm but at this point I
also want to go ahead and maybe just
play with it a little bit to make sure
nothing breaks oh I know what I can do
in the last two minutes actually this
will be better so Martin's pointed out
something that we forgot to do I don't
know if you guys noticed it I'll show
you what the problem is but for some
reason and I don't know why I just
wasn't thinking I put these global
pointer assignments inside memory is
initialized but the problem there is
that that doesn't actually help us
during reload right so if we're using
our hot reloading function you know
we're doing all this sort of stuff
and we go ahead and we do a hot reload
we'll crash and we'll crash because we
do not actually have the valid pointers
anymore because our global memory our
global variables our statics all get
wiped whenever our DLL gets reloaded so
the more proper thing to do and what I
should have been doing the entire time
is I should always be setting up those
pointers right at the beginning right
you should always copy them in because
in case we got reloaded we want to make
sure that that's the case right and so
now we can just verify that we don't
actually crash so that was something
that I should have done all right so now
we're actually rendering very nicely
everything is kosher everything looks
nice and smooth and pretty so that's all
good we should probably take care of our
debug rectangles at some point
because they're not sub-pixel correct
maybe we never really care about that
but so yes so that's good for today and
I think that now that we're doing
aligned with the and and we've got the
masking in there we're in good shape I
worry when we go back to return to the
to optimizing that function I'm a little
nervous about the having to have that
extra branch in there but I'm hoping
that maybe that doesn't work out to be
that big of a deal because hey the X 64
is actually really good at branching so
we may be fine so that should be good
all right so we'll leave that we'll go
to the Q&amp;A I don't know that there'll be
a whole lot of Q&amp;A because really all we
had to do was do that alignment stuff
but if you have questions about
alignment now would be the time to ask
them okay
the bitmap memory size tattoos and
squares bytes per pixel odd did I not
remove one of the bytes for pixels ah
thank you yeah so when I moved out the
pitch I forgot to delete this bytes per
pixel which doesn't need to be there
anymore so thanks for catching that
that's good yeah because you see we
pulled out the bytes per pixel into here
so we didn't actually need to keep it
inside wouldn't actually do anything but
it just it's just waste memory right
because we're not we know we're not
gonna use that memory so yeah can you
test if weird resolutions are actually
working yes and that was what I was kind
of saying before going to the QA I
wanted to kind of do I want to test two
things first thing I want to do is test
like weird stuff with this right because
I don't actually you know we probably
got we could have some bugs in the math
we're like it doesn't work properly
reset weird tile sizes right so I want
to just set like make sure that you know
we can pick whatever we want there and
it doesn't go down in giant flames so
there's like you can see a bug there
that we have which I'm not sure whose
fault it is but you can see that
actually in the in the renderer for the
tile chunks they appear to be off
slightly so that's something we should
probably track down so we're working
fine but we do have some kind of a
clipping bug right I don't know that may
not come out on stream but there's like
a very little there's like a hairline
part where it did not fill so it's like
it was over clipping or something to
that due to that effect oh well you know
what that's just because this is not
rounding though
that's all that's all that actually is
so what we have to do here is we have to
make sure that we essentially we need to
be able to round up the tile width I
guess like I was sort of saying if if
the tile count here doesn't divide
evenly into it we're rounding up the
tile width so that it fits in a you know
that it always is a power 4 but we need
to do something to make sure that we
always fill the correct number what we
probably should do is just adjust the
last one like maybe we should do
something more like this I don't know
what do you guys think of this if we
just say if this happens to be the last
one right if this is the last tile in
either direction we just make sure that
it actually you know that it actually
lines that it actually goes all the way
to the end right so that that may be the
better solution so there that's there
that's go in there okay
so that seems good so 9 is probably not
a good number I'll leave it at 4 here
for now though we may actually want to
be smaller than that we'll see I'm not
actually sure what the optimal number is
but we'll do some timings so let me also
check while we're at it the actual
overall resolution so if we want to run
in some totally weird you know thing
besides 1920 by 1080 right if we're
trying to run in some really weird mode
I will go ahead and just introduce some
graphics number like 1371 let's say by
913 or better yet well you know what
let's let's get some Prime's in here
that aren't divisible by anything Prime
list of prime numbers
let's take a look at the prime numbers
so let's do a prime number
how about you know I'm feeling good
about maybe something like 1277 or 1279
nice and prime nothing divides into it
evenly so that's good and you know maybe
we'll go out and grab how do you feel
about maybe 719 so it's pretty close to
720p mode there but it's totally prime
so nothing divides evenly into it and
let's make sure so there yeah awesome so
you can see we definitely have a bug
somewhere where we're not incrementing
one of the values properly so that's a
good thing to test we're running just
fine but our pitch is off so we need to
go figure out why our pitches off now
what's weird is this almost looks like
it's maybe just the blit in win32 that's
off so I want to go whoo double check
that blitz I don't actually know what
that does so stretch di bits buffer info
so the the pitch the pitch is not
actually being used here so I actually
suspect that it's actually just this
code that's wrong that's that's my Sigma
that's my suspicion so I'm gonna take a
look at stretch di bits and see if it
accepts the pitch okay in the pin like
the bitmap info I'm assuming it's where
that would go because you can see
there's no mention of pitch anywhere in
here so we gotta go we've got to go make
sure that's that's actually gonna be
right so in the bitmap info header this
may be a non-starter unfortunately right
there is no pitch it looks like so we
may not be allowed to use stretch so so
honestly I think that's probably all
that is is we the thing we're using to
copy it to the screen can't handle and
our trail solution so I think we
actually are handling it but they are
not handling it so yeah that's
unfortunate to say the least but that
just looks like how it goes so so yeah
we can't can't really do much with that
I'm afraid what we can do is we did
verify that it looks like it renders
properly in our code anyway but stretch
di bits is not going to accept that I
don't know we could probably try to
create something else here but yeah I
mean copying it to Windows we we just
have to do some kind of a copy ourselves
there anyway right so anyway I think
that's roughly correct the other thing
we could do is we could change the back
buffer inside the actual renderer to be
different so for example you know we
could do something where we set it to
1920 by 1080 so it's it's always running
properly through windows
and it doesn't need to know about our
pitch and what's happening there but
then what we could do is inside the the
render itself when we come in here we
could just fake the size right to be
different so for example in handmade CPP
where we do the output target stuff
let's go ahead and see where that
actually is when I do to render so we've
got raw buffer right so here withdraw
buffer we kind of go ahead and set up
this stuff for the buffer so what I'm
thinking is maybe maybe we can just here
do a little thing where we hard set it
so that even though Windows has the
backing store that it's okay with we
still run in a prime mode and see how
that goes
so that that looks sort of correct to me
yeah I think we're all good there looks
pretty reasonable all right okay uh so
yeah I think I'll leave that in here
just so we have a like note Casey enable
this to test weird buffer sizes in the
renderer and there we go
will you check for cash aliasing with
this much alignment hitting cache
aliasing is much easier
unfortunately I can't check for cache
aliasing very quickly right now because
we need some ability to go read
performance information which we don't
really have at the moment so eventually
we could get there but yeah at the
moment no I can't and I catch so yeah I
know what kind of aliasing you're
talking about well we'll try to get to
that later that's kind of a very
advanced topic but we can try to to get
to that later maybe we can run some
Intel performance gathering library that
will allow us to read like l2 cache
misses and stuff like that from the from
the chip and and that that has some
aliasing data in it if I remember
correctly so you can you can actually
look at those
what about the extra pixel around the
edges to deal with bilinear filtering
will you get rid of that I don't know if
we will ever get rid of that we will
take a look at that maybe I'm not sure
in a somewhere possibly this week when
we go through and just look at what
we're doing regarding pixel centers and
stuff but we may not ever fix that
depending on how we choose to do our
bitmap stuff we may end up making it so
that what we actually do there is we
always Pat our bitmaps so that we can
fetch a little extra
looks like that is the end of the
questions
did I not recompile with that zero it
out
there we go
yeah and so one of the things that that
I'll do and I was I guess maybe we
should do this sometime soon I'll have
to update the art pack with full res
assets because I actually I asked
yangshin to do all the assets for 4k
resolution and so I actually all these
are actually downsampled
I downsampled them because when we
started working we didn't have scaling
and so what I probably will do is we'll
go ahead and properly sized them now for
1920 by 1080 since obviously that's what
we're gonna want to run the game in and
so I'll only scale them down by 2x for
use so we'll have to do that eventually
I don't know when we'll do that maybe in
a couple weeks when we want to start
playing around with some of the some of
the other stuff maybe after we're done
with debug output so yeah when you keep
the rendering of the two lines on
separate hyper threads so we haven't
actually done that yet right and the
reason for that is because and it's
something that we have to get to or at
least I mean to be honest maybe what we
should do is just not bother any more
with it because I wasn't expecting the
renderer to be so fast as it is already
and so it might not be that useful for
us to belabor the point but as you can
see we're not actually using too hyper
threads yet we just have a single thread
do both and so the reason that we're
doing that currently is because with the
job queue it's actually somewhat
difficult for us to make sure that the
same like core will grab two of the same
tile and then use threads interleaved
it's it's kind of tricky to figure out
how to really make that work right and
so that's like sort of a separate thing
and so since it's so fast doing the
rendering the way that's doing it I am
wondering whether it's something we just
actually don't need to do
and I don't know I really don't so
yeah it's tough to say and it may be
something we should just bolt and get
rid of the every other line thing
entirely right that may just be be
better
and if the person who's asking whether
it's going to be a 4k Zelda one style
game it's actually not gonna be 4k like
I just had the art assets done in 4k
because I wasn't sure what how we needed
to scale them exactly so it'll be 1920
by 1080 is what it'll actually be and I
at some point maybe many you know
several years down the line when people
are actually have 4k displays and
actually are have graphics cards that
output to them reliably and stuff we
could ship the you know a very large
version of the game that had the 4k
assets in it potentially as well I don't
know what we'll do there but yeah I mean
the long and short of it is we do we
should have the capability to run at 4k
in terms of art assets at such time when
that actually makes some sense but at
the moment the vast majority of people
don't have a 4k display not to mention
whether they had necessarily have a
machine that would run it so it's not
really that's not part of the goal of
this game alright looks like we are
concluded all right so this is good
today we've got our render and a place
where now it we could actually use it
because doesn't have weird tile
boundaries on it anymore so that's a
good thing that's all very good and so
what we need to do tomorrow is we need
to start taking a look at some other
aspects of that that code I want to go
through and just tighten up some more
things maybe take a look at the sort of
the render queue the way things are
flowing through it and just the the way
that pixel centers and textile center is
working that code I just want to kind of
do a pass now that we've done a bunch of
work on it here I want to do a pass to
make sure everything is kind of kosher
there and and we don't have any weird
surprises going on but that does seem
like you know hopefully that wouldn't
take too long just wanna do some of that
stuff and maybe we'll try to I don't
know people always seem extremely upset
about sorting so maybe we could also
kind of roll that in there I don't know
but they hate it when like he comes here
and he's not behind the tree
everyone just can't deal with it I don't
really know why but they can't handle it
so we could do that potentially as well
so anyway just want to start doing some
render cleanup passes get us down to the
point where we're in a place where we're
comfortable we've got the threading
working we've got an optimized version
of one of the Blitz well it's actually a
texture mapper at this point we've got
an optimized texture mapper and then
we'll have sort of like cleanup the
render queue and we can actually take a
look at like okay here's the whole
renderer here's the performance looks
like right now
what's the memory throughput in total
that we actually are getting and how
close is that to the maximum so that we
have some idea of you know what our
performance is so we'll go ahead and do
that tomorrow and again same time same
place
5:00 5:00 p.m. Pacific Daylight Time
here on Twitch so hopefully that will be
something you will come and join us for
I'm gonna go ahead and shut things down
here info header alright thank you
everyone for joining me for another
episode of hand made he wrote some
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
you can always go to handmade hero org
and pre-order the game it comes with all
the source code so that you can play
around with it at home we also have a
forum site we can ask questions and view
the annotate episode guide get ports to
Mac and Linux all kinds of good stuff we
have a patreon page if you want to
support the video series you can
subscribe to that we also have a tweet
bot which tweets the schedule at you and
we have a little live button which gives
you a countdown until the next live
stream so check all that out it's all
pretty useful and in the meantime until
tomorrow at 5 p.m. when I hope to see
everyone back here have a good time
coding and I will see you all on the
Internet's
take it easy everyone