hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream before we get started
case you weren't with us yesterday just
want to point out we're doing a
Kickstarter right now for our comic moly
rocket so please do check it out
you can go directly to the Kickstarter
website with this address if you want to
but also we put a little banner on the
hand made here a page so you can just
click on that if you want to get there
and we're pretty excited about it it
looks like it will probably hit its goal
so if you're interested in a print copy
of our comic please check it out it's
the only way to actually get one so
let's get started today and I also at
the end of this I wanted to mention
we're going to be putting up some fun
stuff for in celebration the Kickstarter
so I'll point that out the end of the
stream but for now let's get started
so yeah yesterday we left on a fairly
unfortunate note I'm afraid we tried to
capture the lighting solution in to
basically test files that we could run
and for whatever reason we got
completely different results when we
tried to run it in the test app versus
when I run it in the game and we don't
actually know why and so one thing that
I would like to do here is I want to go
ahead and try capturing someone
mentioned at the end of the stream and I
think it's a good idea I wanted to try
capturing the lighting solution in a
single-threaded case to see whether we
have some multi thread bug we didn't
know about that's like not an actual
like race condition or something but
something where we're using something
unpredictably because we do use entropy
in the system and so for example if we
had two threads reading an entry value
that overrode it at different times or
something you'd never see that bug
because it's not even necessarily really
a bug it's just because you're trying to
get random numbers anyway so we'd never
know right so what I'd like to do is
maybe try to make it so that we're a
little bit more specific about how we're
doing it here so what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna make a change to the code
where we can capture a couple of
different ways of like sort of a couple
different packets of data and then I'm
gonna see if there's any difference
between them
and this is again all we're trying to do
here is we have kind of a weird
situation that we don't understand so as
we go or as we go through the debugging
process we're trying to do is build up
like an understanding of what the
problem might be so that we can find it
and so eliminating things like whether
there's threading involved or not in the
pathology of the bug is very helpful
because it lets us cut out a swath of
potential failures right away without us
having to really do any kind of advanced
debugging work to find them so that's
what we want to do we're trying to find
the cheapest possible ways like the
least amount of time that we can take to
find a bug that like narrow down that
where the bug could be right so if we go
ahead and do a compile here I want to
say we're gonna be using o2 because
that's the thing because we're doing
profiling work so we want to be doing oh
to in as much as we can and what I'd
like to do is just go ahead and we'll
run this under remedy and we'll do some
captures in two different directories
and I'll just save them off so if we go
ahead oh you know what one other thing I
wanted to do that I forgot to do so one
of the things that I would like to do is
when we set that capture variable it
captures continuously which is not
particularly useful because we just want
one capture we don't want to keep
overriding the capture so what I might
also do is say look when we do the the
dump so you can see here when we when we
do the final piece of dumping out the
data I would like to go to lightbox dump
trigger and turn that off right so after
we do a dump of all the lighting data
that we can use in the test app I wanted
them go ahead and say don't don't do
anymore so we set it at true it'll set
itself back to false after it finishes
one complete right of the data stream so
that's all we're doing not very
complicated so let me go ahead and load
up handmade hero here I'm gonna go ahead
and take what is this about work and oh
interesting so we made a change to this
and it looks like we broke something
when we actually did
the the arrangement of these work index
indexes in the lighting core system the
it looks like we're not getting an
aligned version of the work count what's
up with that so this is interesting and
good let me go ahead and go in debug
mode because anything that we can get to
provoke a actual assertion maybe will
help us mcmerkin in there so I don't
know it probably isn't I probably just
didn't do something when we pull this
out but you know I can be hopeful I can
be hopeful you know don't you know don't
put that on me so if we take a look here
what we're trying to do is we're trying
to check to make sure that this is
aligned to 64 and you can see that it's
not the bottom value should be 0 there
and you know it's not zero at all so
that doesn't really make much sense
but I so like let me go ahead and I
don't know what I can actually cast this
to here maybe that I don't know if
remedy can do this yeah it doesn't seem
to like this I'm not sure why George I
don't know how to do that I don't know
maybe you can do this or can I do this
no all right so I'm not sure how to do
this maybe X 13 can tell us how we may
have just generated about report for
George all right George you're on that
one anyway doesn't really matter I don't
need to see it I know the assertions
firing I believe it I I don't think
that's false I so what I oh you know
what I know why it's just because our
pad is wrong so this right here where we
added these two in that means our pad is
going to be off here because we want
these things aligned so they wouldn't be
over so remember we're using this for
summing data on multiple threads we
don't want the threads to be looking at
the same cache line so we need this
lighting work structure to be aligned
properly to those cache lines we should
probably put a CTO cert in here for that
right so if you look here we have a an
ability to do like a static assert I'm
gonna say like let's just assert that
the lighting work is always going to be
one cache line long and if it's one
cache line long then we know that the
rest of the code will work fine if it's
not one cache line long oh and I guess I
don't have to put in a name because we
actually already put a thing in there so
that should give us our assertion right
so now what we should see is that should
fire and it does so that's good so this
is an error now right and then we would
know we just have to change this so we
know that we were supposed to have this
exact thing minus eight because we we
change this to having one pointer to
having two pointers so we added eight to
it so that just means we would subtract
eight here and then we should be fine
right
so that's good unfortunately that's not
our book that was just a thing when we
changed it for the lighting system we
forgot we wanted to keep that padded
properly so we got an assertion in there
now that'll fire that's all fine all
right so we're good let's go back to
capturing the lighting data I wish that
had been something that we could have
counted on to cause our problem but it
you know it isn't so if I go ahead and
run here here's the game running right
and we want to capture the lighting we
don't really care where we're capturing
the lighting but we want to capture it
in two different ways
we want to capture it multi-threaded and
we want to capture it single threaded
into two different packages of data so
what I'm going to do here is I'm gonna
go to the debug directory so in
hand-made debug and I'm just gonna sort
by type so we have our dump files here
I'm gonna delete those files so we know
that we're not storing any of them I'm
then gonna just go ahead and say like
before we enter this part of the routine
I'm going to go ahead and set
this lightbox dump trigger to true in
fact I guess I can just do that how do
we we don't really have a way to do that
do we at the moment you know what I
maybe should do can we just make this be
like one of these things we just put
that in here I might do that actually I
think that's then we just push a button
and it does it right I figure I don't
know where that thing is waiting here so
this thing here
I just yeah I mean I feel like maybe we
just put this out here as an editable
value debug b32
lightbox dump trigger maybe so if I do
that I think I might just be able to
just have a one click thing so I just
click it and then you know that seems
fair right so if this thing if we just
said like dump in theory I want to say
that it dumps it for us so that means we
could just create a couple directories
here so we've got these set of dumps and
these set of dumps would be
multi-threaded right and then we can do
a similar dump that's just for single
threaded so if I come in here and just
recompile with the without the lighting
cue so if I take that and make stuff
that with a zero so now the lighting
will run single threaded if that makes
sense so like if we take a look back at
the game here it'll run much slower you
can see it's running much slower because
it's single threaded now so instead of
using 8 cores well I think it was only
using 6 for the lighting but instead of
using all those cores it's actually
using one so it should be about like 6
times slower
and now I should be able to dump it
again in single threaded mode and here's
a single threaded version so now I have
a capture of a single threaded version
and a capture of a multi threaded
version so we can look at those two and
see if there's any difference between
them I'm guessing there won't be but if
there is we're like one works and one
doesn't then that's a clue right it's
just a clue for us that we've got
something weird happening in terms of
sharing a value that we didn't think we
were sharing across the threads so
that's I think all we really need to do
there so I'll undo the part where we
where we did that
turning off the multi-threading so now
we're back to to doing it multi-threaded
and you know the game runs at the normal
speed so all that seems fine and now
with remedy BG I should be able to set
the directory here to like debug
multi-threaded oh well I guess you know
I don't even have to do it in remedy BG
because I'm not really debugging right
now so I guess I can just come in here
and do it right so inside handmade debug
if I go to single threaded I can go run
build HH light prof and see what happens
so that's what the single threaded one
reports if I go to multi-threaded and do
it it's like the same I mean these are
two different captures right so they're
gonna be a little bit different but you
can see it's not like one work than the
other one did in we get different we get
different results right
in either case so it's like okay so this
is not great right this is not a good
thing
it means we don't have any further
information it means we don't probably
have some strange multi-threading bug
where we're sharing values but it
doesn't tell us what we're actually
doing wrong in the light profiler
because it's you know it should be the
case that once we set this stuff up when
we go down into the guts of the
of the program this should run
fundamentally the same way that it runs
in the main app right they should run
the same way and they're obviously not
so the question is why now one of the
things that's true is when we set up the
light Atlas is here I don't know if
maybe there's something that we're not
doing that we should be doing when we're
setting up the light Atlas is that part
is not clear to me so we might want to
check that right we might want to see if
there's something weird going on there
I'm not actually sure but you know we
can look to see if there's if there's
some kind of weird like voxel difference
I don't actually know but the reason
that again why I say this is suspicious
or rather why I'm confused about what's
going on is that if we look at the
lighting core here and we see what we're
calling we're calling exactly the same
thing in both cases and yet when we do
our validation pass we see that their
results are completely different so we
don't even get remotely what we would
expect to get after calling exactly
functionally exactly the same thing and
the question is just why is it that we
have such a difference between these two
things is there something going on in
here that we don't understand or is my
validation routine busted
I don't really know right so in terms of
what's going on with the validation you
can see how this is is working here and
you know it seems like we're taking a
sane approach to it we make our light
atlases and we just seed them with the
data that was already in them
when we start so when we call internal
lighting core here which is what we're
about to call we dump out right you can
see here we dump out the texels right
and we load those texels in I mean
that's all that's happening here and so
we should be starting with exactly the
same data that we had
and I guess I don't have any way of
knowing that it really is exactly the
same data so I suppose that's a little
bit weird but yeah I don't know what's
going on there similarly like the
solutions should be the same here's it
writing out the boxes that it started
with and that seems right I guess I
should double-check that there's nothing
weird that happens with the boxes I mean
it looks fine right you can see it
taking the Box account here and the box
ref count will be 0 when we start so all
of that should be fine this building the
diffuse maps will get saved when we save
the solution itself so that will come in
with the correct Maps or should so again
I don't see where the difference is
coming in so I think I mean unless I can
think of something else to do I think
the only way we're really gonna be able
to debug this is by stepping through
carefully in both and seeing where they
diverge I don't know any other way to
really do it so what I could start with
is trying to validate more things so for
example in here where we've got this
debug light dump trigger we can go back
and we can put that at the very top so
now everyone can look at this we can go
to any particular step of the process
and make sure that when that step
happens we validate after it so for
example when we do the build light
partition part of things so after this
part here where we build the spatial
partition for lighting we can just make
that also get validated so for example
let's suppose in here we did a test here
and in addition to dumping the data we
have we call this results
spatial partition and then what we can
do is say whatever the spatial partition
that we produced was we dump that whole
thing out and I believe the spatial
partition itself because we haven't
gotten creative with it yet
there really isn't it's basically the
same as this call you know all we did
was increase the number of boxes because
we just built more boxes right that's
that's all there is so we can dump those
out here the spatial partition and the
you know box refs I guess because I
think there's also the Box refs you can
see here we've got the box ref count and
the box table here you know I'm saying
so I think we should be able to to put
those out I don't know whether like I
said I don't know whether the box ref
count and the Box table themselves are
getting reset properly but they should
be when we load in the lighting solution
it should be set to zero box refs I
believe or whatever the correct setting
was for the initial sweep so I wouldn't
imagine we would have a problem there
but again let's just check we don't know
where our bug is so we can't afford not
to be paranoid so what I would say here
is yeah we can read dump the boxes so
maybe I just won't even call it that
I'll just call it result light boxes and
then I'll call this result box wraps so
in here we can basically say all right
there's a box ref count and it can be a
dump of this thing right so in fact I'll
just do it this way box table so we'll
dump that whole thing and then we have a
I don't know we have that list right so
that would at least let us verify what
the set of things was that we produced
during the spatial partition build so
that we can eliminate that from the from
the problem like from the we're just
trying to bisect the program into pieces
so we know which part to focus our
attention on because otherwise it'll
take us forever right so here I'm going
to dump out these two in addition and
then so we'll just run our app like we
normally would and do exactly what we
were gonna do the last time to dump so
I'm just gonna come in here and say okay
dump out now we should have a dump that
has you know all of this same stuff in
it but with the two editions of the the
Box refs and the light boxes on the
output side rather than only on the
input side right so if I go into that
code now and if I go into the test code
I can now add those loaders in here so
in here we can say all right we owe and
by the way we can delete these now
because we don't actually care about
those there was no nothing was learned
unfortunately why can I not delete that
Thank You Windows so let's go ahead and
take a look at loading these in if I if
I do what did i call this result light
boxes oops so if I load the result light
boxes in and I load the result box refs
box laughs yeah
we can now validate those and validating
those is pretty easy because all we
really need to do is take this piece of
code here and after we build the spatial
partition which would be in this
internal lighting core bit here right we
just have to validate it
so so after this call we would just
validate and see if it's the same
because I don't think there's any
changes that happen in here there
shouldn't be because again it's
multi-threaded across so if people were
updating that letting hierarchy during
that it would be very bad so we should
be able to verify these at the end and
if they're wrong that's a bug anyway so
I'm fine with that so what we want to do
here is do our validation so we would
right here we would say okay compare
right and I thought we had a compare
memory or diff memory maybe we don't are
equal anyone anyone no I mean it's this
code right you can just call this code
it's exactly the same right you can see
here it's it's the same this it's this
routine so sure
so all we need to do here is is do like
a compare I don't I thought we had a mem
compare but I guess we'd never called it
that so yeah maybe we should I don't
know we'll talk about that in a second
but anyway so when we load this in
here's our result light boxes and we
want to take the count of that and
here's the light result light boxes of
data so that's one of the inputs and
then we have in addition to the count
and data for the light boxes we also
want to be able to oh and you know what
do we have an R equal on buffers gosh we
don't this weird that's weird
anyway so we want to compare the result
light boxes to the light boxes that we
actually have so the light box we
actually have is however big a lighting
box is oops times the account so I think
that's that's all that is and then the
solution light boxes I'm pretty sure
right box hand boxes so that's all we're
comparing there so if that fails then we
want to print an error for that right
so there's an error we can print for
that and these have to be you know care
star casts because we don't have the
right function so that's why I think I
want to make a function for that so
that's all we need there and if I now
run this here so that's messed up
those don't match I mean that's great
because it means that now we can
actually go see how the heck are dump is
failing so badly but you know it's weird
right
I must be missing something obvious
which is always the case because you
start thinking about complex reasons why
your code is failing but and sometimes
you find them immediately when you don't
find them really it usually means that
like something obvious is failing that
you didn't think about that shouldn't be
failing you're like Oh duh right so you
know let's just go ahead here and see
what's up solution box riffs so now
we'll check both of those uh box table
sorry
there we go so I think that's better
so basically none of this stuff is right
so that's good I guess I mean it means
that right off the bat we're wrong and
if we're wrong immediately that's better
than being wrong later I guess so I
guess that's good I just to be honest
don't really understand how that's
possible it's a bit strange right so I
don't know if that means like we're
reading the data in wrong or were
writing the data out wrong could also be
the case I don't know but it seems weird
and why we would get different results
and build spatial partition I have no
idea because you can see how simple this
routine is it's not multi-threaded right
so this we don't we don't attempt to do
this across multiple threads so it's not
even really doing anything interesting
so okay I'm gonna go ahead and try to do
this in a structured way here where we
can actually do a test of what happens
in the debug dump and then the debug
reload which is going to be kind of a
pain in the butt like it's not it's not
gonna be fun but we're gonna try so
here's how we're gonna do it and you
know for better for worse I'm gonna set
the debug trigger right so in here I'm
gonna set this debug trigger to true
okay so that means on the first time
through we're gonna start dumping the
data okay so if I now and I've set it to
debug build right so when we come to
internal lighting core we should the
very first time we should come through
here and we should hit this breakpoint
before we've even seen a frame of our
game right so then what I'm going to do
is I'm going to say let's take a look at
what the status of thing is is here so
here's our solution right
and here's the number of boxes that have
been entered the box ref count is zero
which it should be because we don't have
anything we haven't built the spatial
partition right so I'm going to go ahead
and let this dump all of the things that
we just talked about so you know oh so
that's a bug right there as I just step
through it that was supposed to be a
star right you saw that right those miss
me what's up at that mistakes you can't
make when you have metaprogramming
so anyway when we come through here now
we're gonna dump that again and I guess
now let's let's actually test to make
sure that wasn't our only problem
because that's a complete disaster right
so now we should have our dumps here's
the game running incredibly slowly
because it's in debug mode we should
have our dumps let's just see what
happens now
if we actually try to run the light Prof
of course again this is in Seoul says
they don't match so you know maybe we're
still maybe that wasn't the only problem
it's not so bad although I would say
this error dropped dramatically just
from that however we're still getting
these two complaints so I'm not sure why
that's a little bit messed up let me
just see what's going on there
so yeah I'm not sure why that is wrong
because I don't feel like those should
have been wrong so I think we still have
some issues here now it could be that
the only that there only it could be
that the only reason that they don't
match is because of again some like
minor floating-point differences so I
guess it's hard to say because when I
look at this I'm like man that is well
within floating-point tolerance now this
was not really this is so if the total
error across the entire sixty one six
hundred and fourteen thousand four
hundred texels was point for that error
protects all is so low that's definitely
down in we're floating point error could
have done something so I don't really
know now so let's actually make
something that validates our light boxes
to see what the floating point error is
of them which will take a little bit
more time although if the box refs are
different so the box refs though
shouldn't be different right because the
box refs are just numbers and unless the
floating point error was so large that
it actually caused us to make different
decisions when we were splitting the
lighting we shouldn't have had that
happen so I'm gonna go ahead and say
yeah I'm not not comfortable yet I'm
still a little worried so let's do what
I was going to do we found one problem
so good on us but I'm I'm not convinced
yet so we'll we'll leave it at that for
now
oh so there right yeah okay so we just
we had a cop we had a cut-and-paste
there there though right I'm glad to
know it was our dump that was wrong and
not our code cuz the debug dump being
wrong is is much easier to fix uh where
was that
so there you go all right okay so let me
try that one more time here's the run of
the game again in debug mode okay
so super slow debug mode run like prof.
run so it looks like our box refs are a
little bork there but the light boxes
were correct so I'm not sure why that
would be the case but let's go ahead and
take a look did I mess up this as well
so box ref count times the box table
pointed to the table I think that should
be right shouldn't it box with Count
time session Punk's table time support
of the box table hmm so yeah I don't
know about that let's go ahead and take
a look at those values cuz we should be
able to validate that those are right or
wrong pretty easily with the setup we've
got so let's just see so let's go ahead
to the debug dump of the box table the
reference table so in here we would
expect to see this box table come out
right so this is what we would expect to
see coming out when we dump and the size
that we would expect if we look at the
Box ref count here so the Box ref count
is 25
25 24 25 24 times 2 which is the total
size of the of each reference because
each reference is au 16 should be 5048
so when we step in here and we asked
dump what we would like to see is that
number and we do so that's fine right
and if I copy this value in here so we
remember what it is
although I guess I don't even have to do
that really what I can do is just put
this on the side so I'm going to go
ahead and run another copy of remedy and
I'm just gonna put it like over here
right I'm gonna go in to the recent menu
and load up the profile program now and
I'm gonna step in to that so we're gonna
launch it in D hand-made debug I'm gonna
step through here and I just want to see
what happens when we like go to do this
comparison like what's actually happens
wrong so here's where we're gonna get
that printf so here's where we're saying
that it's busted so if we look at result
box refs so that size is wrong 53 72 is
not correct so when we did our F tell
for that file we didn't get 50 48 right
I mean that's just a truncation problem
yeah so so that's just plain busted and
I'm not sure what is exactly busted
about it but like this process didn't
work properly or something and so we
would need to figure out like what
what's happening there
right
and that seems odd it's almost like it's
ignoring this or something I don't know
but anyway so if you look at that size
we expect that dump to be oh no no no no
okay sorry I I went too fast this has to
actually do the dump first so now it has
dumped that file and hopefully now this
would be correct my bat got a little bit
too aggressive there now I'm still not
optimistic about that because it should
be the same either case right like it's
a it's on startup that that happened so
I'm not sure why we would ever get
different results but you know just
trying to be fair here right all right
so yeah it's still wrong so that's what
I would have expected so somehow the
5048 dump we're getting the wrong value
there and I'm not sure exactly what the
reason is possibly because the FTL mode
isn't stable way to do that I don't know
if we look at result box reps dump
though 53 72 is the actual size of it so
why this is not working is a little bit
confusing right because we tried to
write it out at that size but didn't and
it's not clear why so that's our first
problem right because there's result box
refs boxes that dump that's what we
tried to write out expect it to be that
big and it wasn't so let's go ahead and
see if we can figure out why that's the
case
look why we didn't get the size we
expected I'm gonna go in here and turn
this off the I'm gonna stop the debug of
the light prof program so I'm gonna take
a jump back into this debug dump output
and see what is going on there so if I
come in here and I say I want to write
data to file I'm expecting 50 48 I come
in here and we go alright
you know what's going on
it looks like this so I can tell already
what the problem is so it looks like the
problem here is that we don't have a way
of saying that it should set the file
size I guess right like it's just going
to replace that files first part and I
don't know that we ever put in a way to
change that so this right here um we can
fix the comparison but we might want to
actually add a way to set the file size
because currently we don't have that so
the dumps aren't the right size
necessarily right so when we do platform
right data to file it doesn't look like
we have a way to set what we expect the
file size to be right and that would be
a platform function that we would
actually need unless we have a way to
say just replace the file when you
actually open it but I don't think we do
right so we have like open file like
read and open file right we don't have
an open file replace so I don't know I
don't know that I actually want to do
that now but I might just say
so the way we can fix this though is
pretty simple we would just say look we
don't really care about what the size
was we're gonna use this size in both
cases right so regardless of what you
load we we just use this so something
like this so this validates that all of
them are the same but it doesn't
actually check the size of the data
which I don't love so I feel like we
probably don't really yeah I feel like
we probably don't really want that we
want the dump to be what it is you know
what I mean
so I guess what I would say is let's
let's just do it let's just bite the
bullet man you know I'm saying to you
let's just bite the bullet so let's go
in here and say all right there's gonna
be a way that we can change this so in
here we can say like open file close
file and they'll also be like set file
size right so in here we can do a thing
where we're actually gonna have you know
much like we had all the rest of these
platform things we're gonna have exactly
the same thing and so when we have you
know one of these open file things then
we can have a set file size so in
addition to so in addition to like write
data to file we would have one here
that's like platform set file size and
it's really just that that's it
and if I go into the win32 code here and
look for the open file part of things so
platform open files here we should be
able to just do you know a set file size
call right so in here we do like win32
set file size and here's the handle ie
don't actually remember offhand what the
prototype is for that set into file
that's what's called so I'm pretty sure
the only way to do it well that's not
true there is a different way to do it
if you want to set the end of a file
with the old-school win32 API switch is
mostly what we've been using so I think
we should you first have to move the
file cursor to the end of the file and
then set the end of the file if you want
to use a a single call to do it I think
there is a way to do it it's called like
set file info or some px or something
like this you actually can do it it's
just it's only in like Windows 8 and up
or one of those it's one of those things
I'm sorry I can't remember which one it
is at the moment I'm I'm 99.9% sure I
just can't remember what it's called so
you'll just have to take my word for it
you can do that what's this guy I don't
think that's what that's not what I was
thinking of so I apologize there's no
real way to there's no real way for me
to tell you how to do it cuz I don't
remember what the call is and it's hard
to find in here but you'll just have to
trust me there is a way you can do that
I'm pretty sure with one call but we're
gonna do it in two to use the old-school
ones that work back in on XP and
everything right so if we call set file
pointer X here oops
like so and then we do set file end or
set end of file it was called
set end-of-file that will do it
and there is a little bit of an issue
here with race conditions if you use set
file pointer anywhere else thankfully as
you can see we always just use the
directed read so do you see how we use
the overlapped read here so we never set
the file pointer so the fact that we
only set it here means that there won't
be any race conditions because even if
two people call set file size at the
same time well one of them was going to
win anyway if they were both calling it
unlocked so it doesn't matter whose set
file pointer ends up working right so if
you do it this way and I'll put this in
here you know I'm Sam so there's a
subtlety there that's worth
understanding if you're going to be
doing this in your own code base you
can't be using the file pointer for your
reads and writes if you're using it for
this because or you could but you'd have
to introduce locking right because
otherwise what could happen is you'd set
the file pointer e.x your thread gets
suspended right here before set into
file somebody else issues a write sets
the file pointer somewhere else then you
end up doing
set end of file CNM saying and you you
end up setting them to the file there
which is not what anyone ever asked for
so it's a completely nonsensical result
does that make sense so that's just it's
got to understand it that's all so we
don't really have to do much it's it's
literally just this
and we can put an error here as well but
that's the entirety of the code so set
file pointer reacts takes the handle a
large integer the move method is just
set so file begin and then the new file
pointer so we don't care about that we
need to put this in a large integer just
because that's what it's used to taking
so let's go ahead and do that we can set
quad part
so maybe this let's say oops so we fill
out a large integer we'll pass that down
and we'll call it a day what did I do
wrong there win32 file error Oh oops
all right so I think that's it
we obviously have to fill this out so
in-game memory platform API set file
size we have to do you know
remember that set file size there and I
think now if we just call that in our
lighting code our dump should be correct
so in debug dump data not that one in
debug dump data in here before we close
the file we would just say platform set
file size and we'd tell it that the dump
size was the entire size right so I just
feel more comfortable with that that's
how it should work in the first place so
let's just see if that fixes our
situation
all right so we should have a data dump
now from the first run and I should be
able to validate that hmm perfect so I
guess what I would say is I'm fairly
confident that that's a reasonable
result if the total error in your entire
thing is that you know what I might want
to do though let's also take the max
error because if all of that error came
from one pixel that would be bad so we
don't really care I guess what the total
error is so much as we care what the
maximum error is so let's make sure we
track that so this will tell us for the
part of the image for the Texel that's
the absolute worst at replicating the
original results what was it
right um and so if we take a look at
that value you know like it's below the
visible range but does it mean you know
0.01 would I have liked it to be lower
probably is it possibly with still
within range maybe is it possibly a bug
I don't know right
so I'm not sure how to validate this
further again the problem with compiling
two different pieces of code or I should
say two versions of the same piece of
code is if they're floating point they
could come out completely different so
it's a little bit hard to know what to
validate in that case I'm gonna go ahead
and see if I run the game in retail mode
I want to see what it what the
validation error looks like there and
maybe I also want to see what the error
looks like in another scenario so let's
suppose that I also go somewhere else
you know what I'll also turn off the the
auto dump since we don't really need
that to be happening every time we start
the game what's at that false so I'm
gonna go ahead and run to a different
location and see if the error stays
roughly the same everywhere which would
be better at least a slightly better
indication I mean it's not risked a
little not really good but so if I dump
there oops if I dump there what do we
get similar level of error
hire error there I mean I guess not
super much higher but like still
so I don't know I'm nervous about it
like the total error per Texel is still
low but the max error is kind of high
you know what I'm saying to you and like
what's this about right again that could
just be because of floating-point
differences between the two compilations
but it's very hard to know so I'm just
not sure how to proceed I guess what I
would say is I suppose I'm comfortable
with proceeding from here without
further validation for one reason and
that is because the end result of this
is just to produce the lighting result
anyway so when we put if we change the
code around and put it back into our
game we will see the error when we run
if it's wrong like meaning if it
produces an unusable result we'd know so
I suppose I'm okay with that
I suppose so maybe I'm okay going
forward with that I don't know how much
time I have here does anyone know how
much time I have left
just one o'clock twelve I have at least
a half an hour right
alright let me just try some stuff here
so let me see and what we want to do I'm
gonna go - oops not Visual Studio they
should be to an amplifier that's what it
we want so I'm gonna go ahead and
running an analysis here I'm gonna go to
our oops
our instructions per clock let me take a
look at those I just want to see what's
going on oops
how do I get back - I'm so bad it be -
so bad it be tuned how do I get back to
the way you've launched an application
there we go so this is no longer gonna
be a thing and now we go so run says
light boxes don't magic and oh right
because it because they don't so now we
have a problem that our thing runs too
quickly right because we we have this
situation where we're only running one
frame in one frame hmm through the
system so I'm not sure how we want to
get around that normally what we'd like
to do is run the thing many times but
I'm not sure how feasible that actually
is I suppose we could just set the box
rest in the box back the boxes back
every time and just rerun it but really
we only care about just that one piece
of the lighting core anyway so I suppose
what we could do is maybe something like
inside internal lighting core if we want
to just run the work distribution many
times we just do so maybe this thing we
just do like
something like this so we can pass a
repeat index in here and actually you
know what let me do it this way so we'll
just say the debug repeat count is
something that you can pass in normally
it only runs one time but if you want to
you can tell it to run like lots of
times so we can tell this to do you know
200 frames or you know let's say we want
to run for 5 seconds or something
and now we won't validate if that's set
so we can't do a validation on here but
you know we can just say if repeat count
was one then we can validate otherwise
we can't write so yeah we can do
something like that and it's a little
bit annoying we probably want to do run
where we do the repeat count at the end
just for validation purposes so we
probably want to do something more like
this where we say internal you know
debug run or profile run and what we
would do is this entire nonsense right
we would do the whole thing twice right
so what we would do is probably
something like this where the repeat
count is isn't here so we passed their
repeat count in or something right and
when we do the profile run we just do
two of them so we do one and then we do
you know a bunch right and that way we
would do them both ways we would do them
one way for you know for validation and
then another way for just trying to time
the thing you know I'm saying so we do
something like that
and it would print out that thing then
it you don't print out the error and all
that so we could see if it went rogue
and then we also have one where you know
we would then stall out like we're doing
here to take a long time I don't know
how
we actually needed to take probably that
was a little too long so because
probably we're only running at 30 frames
a second now oh and we're threat we're
not threaded so that was a much too high
of an estimate so you know maybe
something like this
this may be too short but we'll see
maybe too short so I don't know
well let's maybe say that we're gonna do
something along those lines and then
we'll see if if if vtune can can handle
that
all right so that looks like it works
okay and you can kind of see what we're
getting here in terms of cycle issues I
and you know I think we're in an okay
place now for trying to start
optimization work it looks like we're
validating you on that data again the
problem
here is just that like I'm not sure
floating point wise how to make this be
more validated than that I really
couldn't tell you because it's tough to
know I'm a little suspicious but we'll
see so if we want to start with the
optimization process here there's a
couple things that I want to look at and
you can see that we sort of have to I
guess you might say we have actually
three places to look at so one place to
look at is just when we're actually in
here doing our updates of like how we're
doing our our texture fills and stuff
like that so there's stuff in here that
we can potentially try to optimize that
is just how we post process the textures
we can also turn that off if we don't
care about looking at that particular
piece of code yet but the other thing we
can do here is we can say oh well you
know the raycast thing here's how that's
working and it's not particularly good
right now so if you take a look at
what's happening with the leaf container
stuff you can see that here is the
actual piece of code that loops over
that loops over a bounding boxes to
check this piece of code which loops
over sort of sides of this part like
spatial partitions to see which parts of
the partition we need to talk to look at
that part is actually kind of totally
messed up we know that these come out in
exactly the right order so we don't need
to be calling this routine it
just an indirect load for no reason so
we can pretty trivially get rid of that
if we want to and similarly like a lot
of this data isn't actually loaded in
the most efficient if this efficient way
it could be already like we're doing
operations on stuff we don't actually
care about so if you look here the box
radius for example just flat-out isn't
used anywhere in the partition testing
code right so if we were to sketch out
what this code would look like in terms
of what we actually care about you can
see that our should push is basically
you know a little binary composite here
of these pieces of information so we
know we need close enough masks and
actually T valid even used here yeah
it's here so so we need to compute these
particular values which means we need
the min and the max right max Pass is
yes still use 40 inside so T min and T
max are what we compute which means we
need box Minh and box max right which
means we need these two Hadamard
products which means we just need we
just need the Box Minh in the box max to
have been here so we don't actually care
about the box P at all right we don't
need that value we don't care about the
box radius at all all we really wanted
to know was the Box min in the Box max
so those are the two values that we like
should have been storing right because
although we care about those potentially
here maybe it's unclear that we actually
do but maybe we do right mostly we just
want to know like hey we just need to
know the box in box max for the testing
so we would want to just store those two
things and furthermore when we look at
what we actually are pushing on here
when we read this out you can see what
we actually get out of the box itself
what we need to know is is it a leaf
right what's its first child index and
what's the child count right that's what
we actually wanted to know out of that
because we never look at this box again
so if you imagined packing that
information into something more concise
we could make this routine be a lot less
stupid you know I'm saying to you so
let's start with some simple things we
can use to improve what we're doing dumb
at the moment so let's start by saying
what if we create a custom structure
here that's like our raycast stack right
and the raycast stack is just gonna
store the stuff we actually care about
right so the only thing we really need
to know here is oh and you know what
before I do any of this let's actually
also get a metric in place because we
should just be able to grab that right
so when we go here and run our light
prof code here so this this piece of
code right so that let's take a let's
take a wall clock time right let's just
take a wall clock time so if I come down
to this code here in
[Music]
everyone fine with windows H yeah so if
we want to then inside the profile run a
set of of fun missus here what I want to
do is when we go into the internal
lighting core I want to snap a timing so
I just want to do a like query
performance counter at the beginning in
the end right like that but query for
performance
counter is kind of a pain in the butt I
don't love the way it works so we may
make a separate one for it but yeah
let's see so if we just use query
performance counter which you know query
performance counter which apparently
meant like there'd be some glasses I
wished I could get got that back there
was like some sunglasses for some reason
so if I do large integers start and end
here there's the start or start time and
time then we just have a wall clock time
it's like how long did this thing take
right and then if I asked what the
performance frequency okay I swear to
god man they just Microsoft is such a
disaster query performance frequency I
get the frequency back
and then I just want to print out the
timely results so basically what I want
to do what I want to know here is like
how long did this thing take like how
long do you take to run so in order to
do that we know we just want to subtract
the two so assuming that we got a run
that wasn't one of these types of runs
I'm just gonna say look let's just take
the difference here right so the diff is
going to be start time quad part end
time quad part we're just gonna subtract
these two right actually let's just do
it that way annoyed by the fact that my
head is in the way there we go so let's
take a diff and then we'll divide by the
frequency right so we'll just say like
total seconds equals the diff divided by
the frequency like so and we'll print
that out to standard out
and this is just there to see if we can
see any particularly large improvements
in this in the speed while we're at it
was total seconds and we may want to do
that a little bit differently
we'll see so if we go ahead now and we
just take a here if we run this I should
be able to see how long it took to do
all of these and you know we'll see it
we should see an improvement in the
speed if we make any major changes but
really we're just doing that just to
make sure like we have some kind of
ballpark number to go by and it's
surprisingly stable as you can see even
with all the variance just because we're
running so many of those right now if we
want to start actually putting real
timing into this we have to do more work
we'd have to figure out how we want to
actually time it and we'd want to like
maybe check for like if the total time
went down run it again and keep going
there's a lot of ways you can do this
but for the interest of just like
programming on stream we'll leave it
that way for now so let's just go ahead
and take a look at what happens if I
change that stack out so that's all I'm
gonna do here
okay so rake has stack entry in here I'm
just gonna say what are the things
actually needed to know right so here's
root box what is it used for that's it
right that's it
so we only care about like the only
things we care about at all in the
raycast
is was it a leaf right so we just want
to know like what's the first child
index oops
what's the child count I guess what's
the you know what's the child count I
mean we could store that add I don't
know maybe what's the last or one past
last child index and I know so we store
like the range that we're going to go
over
yeah I'm gonna leave it like that for
now so we'll store the range this is the
range we're going to go over and then
we'll pad this out to a 64-bit value by
just saying then there's the like is
leaf right so then what we would do
instead of the way that we were pulling
these things off before is we would say
like oh okay so actually what's gonna
happen here is we're gonna say like
there's a starting box okay and that's
going to be the box that we get out of
the root box the box stack original
depth here so box tack goes something
like this we need to do like is leaf and
that's gonna be you know this this
nonsense here and really we know it's
always true so I mean I mean always
false for the first one so we could just
initialize that to false I guess I don't
know how we want to treat that depends
what you're going for here but so the
first index is just this thing the last
index is this nonsense here and then
we've pushed the thing right so that's
how you would push something on and then
the Box stack is going to be rake a
stock entry now like so so once we do
that our are pulling off this thing oops
looks like that and now what we do is
just like okay entry is leaf it's gonna
be this right entry first index is that
entry one past last index is that so now
we're just pulling off just this little
token that says hey this is the
information you actually needed to
remember right and this doesn't really
get us very far but it's at least
something right so you know it's a start
towards what we actually want so we'll
just keep you know we'll keep whittling
away at it right so then all we need to
do is when we actually do a push on here
again like the the should push thing we
want to just get this piece of data up
here so here's the like push entry right
the push entry is leaf equals a thing
the push entry first index equals a
thing to push entry one passed last
index equals the thing right then we
just say if we should push then it's the
push entry otherwise it's not so we just
do the conditional assignment there like
we would have any other way right all
right so in the push entry we just need
this code and now instead of root box
which doesn't exist it's just box right
so these are all the same but it's just
box
we won't have root box anymore oops
so starting box starting box starting
box and we're done okay so let me just
take a look at what that does because it
should run and produce the same error
which it does and I don't know that
they'll actually improve things for our
run time at all but hopefully doesn't
make them slower wow it does make them
slower alright so we've learned
something so for whatever reason it
likes better or the thing we were doing
before
doesn't make a whole lot of sense to me
I wonder why
is it because it doesn't actually know
is it because that's a struct it is
doing something dumb let's take a look
so I'm interested to know what the
difference is here so let me just take a
look at the assembly because I want to
see why it changed
so here you can see it's actually doing
the test I believe here so because I
don't see a seam ah've what the heck oh
I mean I'm in the wrong application I'm
like how is this looking multi-threaded
come back to me where is my lighting
code so I want to see right here and I
want to see what the assembly looks like
so yeah it's not good so there is a seam
off there's a seam off here so that
correctly see mobbed this but it did not
correctly see mob this so I'm just
curious hold on a second
if I don't do this and instead make a
thing that's like
so you just pass like the box pointer
and then we do something like this so
you know the is leaf container boolean
flag gets put I don't know
what's that actual value it's one so
maybe it's just like yeah is leaf
container actually we'll just store that
for now so we'll do is leaf container or
first child index shifted up by 16 and
then this nonsense here also shifted up
by 16 right so we just or all this
nonsense together and that's our art
pack right and then we just have to have
a nun tack
I can probably actually just do that at
the top so never mind all right so we
get rid of this we say podcast entry
this is what the past don't ask me why
that's a 16 so we can pack cast entry
this way let's do it here so we just say
all right box tack depth by the way this
is now just a you 64 we just say box
tack depth plus plus equals pack cast
entry and we say that we want that to be
our starting box like that we come down
here and we say this is going to be a
you 64 push entry equals packed box pack
cast entry for some other box right and
then we try to make this part work by
just saying entry equals whatever the
latest entry was we take a look at this
value and say if the entry and light box
leaf container if if that's true then do
your nonsense the first index and the
one pass last index we unpack this way
by saying whatever the entry is shifted
down by 16 ANDed out and the entry
shifted down by 32 and it out right
what is this complaining about this
needs to be up casted to you 32 and
fortune I mean you 64 because see is
stupid
and this is not a thing okay so let me
just see if it get any effect the
compiler got any smarter by doing that I
mean maybe who knows
also let me actually see if this works
because I kind of jammed that together
seems fine produce the same results
right so and now we're back to the same
time again so again zero cost
abstraction putting those in a structure
totally didn't work this is why I try to
tell people that's not a thing
no one ever believes me but if you
actually ever spend time looking at what
the compiler does it anything you try to
do is very likely to not be one right
all right so we're still doing no so you
see how we don't have any jumps anymore
right so we do our loads and the only
jump is to jump back to the only jump is
to jump back to the top of the loop
right so I think it might not be true
let's take a look
so what's all this nonsense
what are all these jumps for
compiler
why are you jumpy alright
what's wrong with the compiler here why
does it not want to do what I want it to
do so here's an idea
what if I actually were to store this
piece of information so the compiler
can't mess with me and it's just part of
the data that we push right that would
fix the problem unfortunately it
requires me to edit the lighting box
structure a little bit but that's ok so
if you looked in here and you were like
oh alright
like what's all this about if we
actually just made this oh and you know
what this could all fits into you 32
doesn't it right so if we just made this
B what we actually grabbed if we
Lemongrab that out then it really can't
hurt us can it so what if I told it this
right what if I said like all right
there's a-you 32 that I need you to grab
in fact in fact in fact
so we want a lightning box pack in here
right like so and the data would still
be the same but now like places like
this you just you use you know dot pack
right all of these need a pack and no no
no yes yes yes yes yes all right so here
we could just say all right the Box
stack is a lighting box pack which is
just 32 the power can't figure this out
I do not know what to tell it all right
so there's all you got to do is put 32
bits on a stack like can you manage it
right so put 3-2 bits on the stack
please that's all you have to do all you
have to do is copy that 32 bits onto a
stack that's all I'm asking right
there you go right super super simple
nothing no ands no nothing just real
basic not remember what this is that
right alright um first index is its
first child index there is everyone
happy now there's everyone smiling and
delighted in the revelry of it all I
certainly hope so so now this is nothing
we're not even to do anything right all
we're gonna do is push pack on there
that's it
and hopefully the compiler can figure
that out I don't know if I can though
did that work yes
okay and by the way we actually did get
faster now which is what I would have
expected I wouldn't really have expected
to get much faster but it got a little
bit faster which is what I would have
expected right we were seven point one
seven point two before we dropped down
to seven point oh now right all right
thank you mister compiler now let's take
a look at the code here and see if it
actually got rid of the stupid jumps
like why is that jump still there it
looks like we still have jumps here
you
like there's less but why are we still
jumping who is jumping in why do you
know what I'm saying like what what is
with the jump
what's with the jump festival here's our
computations chef and sub in right
that's all the stuff I would expect
here's us doing the compares and the min
it's all good so I'll fine we move masks
and we do a test and then we J and Z so
the compiler thought it was better to do
a jump than to just do the mauve mask
instructions
what the heck man
what is the compiler doing why is it
doing that
I I don't I'm kind of at a loss here for
what's the deal with that it's probably
because it's looking at this and
expanding this out to like the if
version of it because it's like well I
don't have to evaluate this if this is
already true and I think I'm saving time
but I'm not so let's look at these
so what's any true do so any true does a
mauve mask PS of comparison P into the
boolean result right so mob mask mauve
mass PS those two any closer and any
inside so this is getting masked on any
close enough so so what is okay so what
are these close enough we don't even use
anymore do we
I mean I thought we were kind of saying
that we were done with that
hmm so we are still stopping our
traversal when we get too far away
apparently 15 meters from the
origination point hmm
so I don't know about that like what
happens if we just take that out dude do
we get really slow
I just I'm curious
like how much are we relying on that
because I don't know I'm not sure to
what extent that is you know something
we rely on so to a certain extent it's
it's quite a bit it looks like I mean
unless that changed something else we
are actually taking advantage of that
early out case
so I guess what I would say is is this
really the right way to do this masking
look could we mask these in the
registers first and then move them out
do these actually have to be done
separate so like any inside means if
we're inside this box we would want to
traverse down right if any are of or the
Rays were so that makes sense if any of
the hits in this box it's our closer
potentially than the ones we already
have in that Lane then we do want to go
down right but any close enough is just
saying could we have hid is it too far
away we don't want we're trying to knock
out so I feel like those should be able
to go on the same line right so I mean
couldn't we do like this
I mean is this really that bad if we
just said
whoops what did i do that's supposed to
just be box pack
so I don't know like is that totally bad
to do it that way so it produces
basically the same result and you can
see it got faster to do it that way
right the total error is still the same
and that improved the speed so does that
now successfully convince the compiler
to stop monkeying around no it doesn't
there's the mob masks there's the end
jump not equal what are you doing
I don't know man
I don't know how to convince this thing
to get all these jumps out of here they
don't you don't need to do any of these
jumps and it really wants to do them so
I'll try one more thing you know we've
got the Deaf plus one should push here
right maybe the other thing is like if
it does it think just because this is a
struct if I change this to just be a you
thirty-two would that help it know what
was going on like I don't know so if I
just said hey look this is literally
just a blind value okay so like trust me
just write a you thirty-two to the stack
for the love of God right oops
is that is that in the tape and the
cards or not
nope I don't know man
it seems pretty intent on Jan seeing
this thing and I have no idea why just
just change these two things to see
moths like why why are you doing that is
there a way to force this stupid
compiler to like do a seamoth can you
why am I in DuckDuckGo
so here's the Intel C compiler that's
not what we're talking about
anyone stackoverflow that's talking
about the
so conditional st. killing only one
comparison this is somebody who is
trying to do the same thing I'm trying
to I don't know
so like this this help please just just
generate a conditional move for me I
just want to see what the code runs like
with with a conditional move
I hate compiler I hate the entire idea
like it should be a given that a modern
compiler and a modern language would
just let you say that you wanted to see
move somewhere
I'm the programmer listen to me but of
course they've added I can make lambdas
that I pass the things I can have Auto
declared variables I can be added
everything under the moon
I can't just frigging see move something
it's like they don't understand that
like programming computer means I'm
trying to actually tell the computer
what to do not often language flower
land with mr. Rogers alright anyway um
so I don't know if we can try to finesse
this I'm just trying to see if I can get
this thing to output a stupid C move
that's that's all I was trying to do and
it's it's not looking likely right it
doesn't seem to want to do that
I mean that's as as concise as I think
it can be I don't even know if it can be
oh no no no no it could well let me try
that first though I mean we try them
both I guess there is one other thing I
could try see if it helps
nope it's got one so it it so it
correctly knows that that's a si move
but I guess that's not so what could we
do is this possible like what if we did
this what if we did like that so I just
use a reference instead of a pointer
same exact thing like doesn't mean
anything means exactly the same thing
does compiler know that No
we still got a J&amp;Z up here even if I'm
not mistaken like where's that coming
from
what's going on
we load in we do our math ups we subdue
we do whatever it's fine
testy ax e ax for Jan Z so this should
push is what's getting test there and we
do the Jan Z so just then we have it's
trying to avoid doing this comparison in
the move so that that's unfortunate I'm
not sure if there's any way to crossbar
this it could be that what we should do
is do the broadcast up here so one thing
we could do is like is do the or up here
somehow we can't do a straight line orcs
need to or all of them together
I'm not sure what the way to do that
would be to move the mask internally so
let me just see what we've got here
and let's let's also see if we just
yeah nothing nothing no luck
so without adding extra instructions
here I'm not sure how we would do that I
mean we could go ahead and futz around
more like we could do a thing that
looked like this where we basically said
all right so the push call is going to
take the closer close enough right and
we're gonna do like a chuffing and to it
right so we do like a shuffle so we just
say all right I I don't know we would
just say take closer close enough get
the first and second thing from that and
we and I guess then you would take the
other part of this one so you'd say you
want the first and second part of close
are close enough and the first and
second part of any inside right I think
that's what we're talking about here and
then you would do another one of those
where you said and then take and stack
the second and third parts of both of
those right so you do like stacks zero
stacked one so we're just shuffling to
get things into the right lanes so now
we've got one that's got 0 1 0 1 and 2 3
2 3 we would order those together
right so now we know if 0 and 2 match 1
in 3 match right and so then we just
have to do that one more time and we
would be good right because now we just
have 0 we just need to do and I'll just
call it this I don't know what to call
them so we just need to do it another
shuffle for X of that result right cuz
in the wait that's not quite right
so in 0 1 we got 0 1 0 1 2 3 2 3 we do
those now we have to do that one more
time so we have to do this exact thing
one more time right although that's
possibly not true because we could pack
these I'm just sorry I'm just trying to
see what's going on here so I could do
like stack o 1 and then this is like Y Z
here this is XY or whatever right so
then we just say like okay take a 1 and
produce you know the the 0 1 2 3 here
right
so this is just the slow oaring together
you have to like or or or it's like a
horizontal or right and then at the end
now you just do the one chef so you just
do what's the word we're looking for
should push equals any true stack equai
I guess
this is actually called tea inside there
we go so that's a little hacky I
probably shouldn't leave that in there I
was just curious I could get this thing
to do something resembling anything that
I wanted it to do which you know didn't
look likely but let's go ahead and take
a look let's jump here
so that's one seam of for the stack but
not for this one here right let's take a
look at it one more time so here we are
loading up shuffling we do our nonsense
dance here we do our subs our mobs we
compare and move I don't know oops I
accidentally hit step in that ruined
window I guess we do our auras together
we do our mouth masks and so we're
almost down to it if we could just why
is this moving so many things in there -
what's I don't know why it's doing that
but let's try one more time to get this
to work so here we're almost like what
if we just change the way we're doing
this so we're just like look stack at is
this thing and we just say the thing
we're gonna push in there right is it's
one of these two we then say box back
depth equals stack at and we have to do
that before we update the depth do you
understand that
probably not
Hey look at that folks
it only took like 30 minutes but I think
I was able to teach the compiler how to
do a conditional move there it is
alright but I probably screwed up there
because any time you write simony code
because SSC is a disaster of instruction
set
you usually get something wrong so I'm
guessing that the error is high here Oh
No all right it was the same so I didn't
screw it up I guess maybe I'm not sure
all right so we can see move those now
the problem is yeah it's slower because
I had to do all this extra crap like we
don't want that in there so I don't know
let's see if I rien a ballista it it did
that that little squiggle I did there
does that help maybe that's all we
needed and if that's the case we can go
back to doing it the not slow way and to
see no it did not so the problem is as
far as I can tell as soon as you start
to do this it thinks it needs to do it
thinks it needs to do a test on this but
I don't actually want it to do that so
maybe I can phrase this in a different
way so for example if I was to write
that would it work now that's not the
same expression so I don't actually know
that we want to do that but let's just
see what it does
I'm just curious yes so if I was to do
that with an or
how would I make this happen so if we do
any true on closer close enough and then
we do any inside we've got those two and
I want to or those two together we know
we've got a mask now that's like you
know 16 bits of mask we only actually
care about four bits out of the 16 any
four will do as long as they're spread
out by four bits each and the question
is is there some way we can quickly
produce that result
but wait that's an or suey that should
just work shouldn't it what am i what am
I talking about
we just care if anything set so that's
fine what I don't know why I'm freaking
out so wait does that work just doing
what I did there
so it does work okay so we can get the
conditional move to happen we can get
this to happen but we don't necessarily
produce faster code here do we because
that didn't look faster to me let me
take a look at what we've got yeah
although those things yes so I guess I'm
not sure why that wouldn't always be
faster but also so this doesn't actually
have to be this way too it could be it
could just use the mask and close enough
as a mob it doesn't have to do an and in
this space here but I'm not sure why
that would itself be slower it might be
because this is clogging up the pipe a
little so can we just do
can we just do this should push equals
any true tea inside or any true
[Music]
can we do this does this does this help
us so we just mouth mask those guys and
then do it in scaler you know I'm saying
to you does anyone like that yes it's
fine with that all right so does that
help us at all
don't know if it does so I don't know
why we're slower that way but it looks
like I mean from testing those two paths
that we'd have to investigate them a
little bit further but it looks like
that it looks like that doing the jump
is cheaper than doing the to see moves
like it would rather do it so skipping a
few of these opps with a potentially
mispredicted branch maybe the branch is
very predictable it could be the answer
there because if you if you don't
usually miss predict the branch then
saving the work might actually help us
but I don't know so I think this is the
first thing I would like to look at love
to look at it with V tune in mind there
but it looks like it actually would just
prefer to do the the test right so if we
if we let it do what it wanted to do
which is this
okay
should really like check both of these
so that's what it wanted to do before so
here's with the the branchy like you
know doing lots of jumps around
and that's like way faster right it just
it prefers that right so if I cut and
paste this and I just say alright like
here's that part of the routine let's
put both of those in so we can check
them then next weekend what we can do is
take a look and see what exactly is
going on there just so we understand why
it's faster to do it that way because
I'm not sure I understand why because it
seems like that branch shouldn't be very
predictable right and so I just would
like to know like what the heck
right like what's happening there and it
could be that there's a bunch of things
that I'm not like thinking of right so
here's the if one here's the else Clause
oops so there we go
and it looks like that was still in
there even in the fast case right so
this just looks like that
right so in here we would then say like
okay we got to do this check this is
like the current fast path right and
then we want to know like we want to
know what's going on here
and so let me just recreate this so it
is correct it's like any true T inside
double or and then the and well I guess
we're saying she close enough was the
fast one so basically like this
this is the should push written the same
way as the outer should push right oops
so in theory now if I actually run this
like so
that's the fast lane if I go like this
it's slower way now it's not like much
slower but it is slower and so it'd be
nice to know like why wouldn't having
that be branchless be better and we'd
like to just go look at it because it
does seem like that's a bit weird to me
and I'd like to just grab the to
assembly languages outputs and compare
them let's go ahead and go to the the
Q&amp;A well hmm you know what I just
realized though so there is something a
little bit bad about this loop why the C
mobs might not actually be an
improvement and that I think about it
it's because we only do a fan-out of two
on each of these partitions so our
partition stuff is pretty crappy that's
why we were like going to like be
replacing this with with a more
streamlined thing so it could be that
that's what's happening is that it does
the C mobs but then it immediately has
to load the C mobs here in order to
start doing this branch so that's just
the mispredicted branch again probably
right so I could see that it'll be nice
that we could figure out a way to not
have this branch here but I'm not sure
there's any way to do that
I mean there is one way to do it I guess
and that's if you actually streamed out
the boxes and then streamed them back in
thank you that would not work I don't
think
anyway QA hmm I think the MSDN you were
looking for is potentially set file
information by Handel yes that sounds
right like I said like I said I think I
think there's an API for it and that
sounds like the right one I knew there
was one but it's just a later API it was
one they they added
so
so logical or and are only
short-circuited if the compiler has to
short-circuit them since there's no side
effects here there's no it the compiler
I mean unless the compiler is really
weird isn't going to think that it can't
do an and for some registers right the
only time it has to care about the
short-circuiting property is if there's
a side-effect and there isn't one here
can't you just use clothes enough
instead of clothes are close enough in
the should push assignment close enough
is already ANDed with masks this is 0-1
a set of Oh
you are correct let me leave this one in
the branchless case this is the
branchless version not the branch
eversion
so one thing that's interesting is so if
we had a bug but still produce the same
result that also kind of means that one
of the problems is these branches aren't
particularly well exercised so it that
could also be like another reason right
so you notice that one's pretty close to
fast enough when we did them all in when
we just use one any true and then went
with the the branchless version so I do
wonder if maybe that means we should be
we should be looking at this a little
bit more carefully and doing a faster
version of this you know I'm saying oh
this is and this is an annoying way to
test code yeah because this one was much
slower right this was like 7.3 yes and
point five so this way is I guess the
current fastest branchless version that
we had
and anyway so some of the chat was
pointing out to this so why do we need
to do an or here because clothes are
close enough was ANDed with this and the
reason is because well I guess now that
we took that out though yeah that's a
good question well no because you I
think because in this particular case no
yeah no you're right we don't really
need this do we
that's just superfluous I don't know why
I did that so I guess it's just close
enough so this is just this I don't know
why that extra hand was in there doesn't
need to be
right
all right so if we do Prof on this path
this is the branchless path although I
have to go verify that it's still
branchless since we don't really know
what the compiler decided to do and then
if I do this path this is the branchy
path oops
close enough so this is the branchy path
yeah
so it's a little bit weird but because
those see moves are used like
potentially immediately after I can see
why that's not such a good idea so if we
were streaming this out more maybe they
would be better but were not so for
example if it were a circularbuffer you
know what I'm saying it would be
interesting to test this with a
circularbuffer
so that instead of popping the last
thing you wrote you pop the leak like
the thing you wrote as far back as you
can then you would not be having those
questions I don't know I'm gonna put a
note in just to try that because that
might be interesting
somebody in chat had the idea of loading
the raycast through the DLL for testing
could this remove the floating point
errors in the test code that that is a
pretty good idea I like that idea a lot
[Music]
yeah we could do that so the only thing
we would have to do there is we'd have
to make an entry point for it
I'm sorry there's so many questions I
can't really handle them all
is it possible to structure the game
code so that it would run recently fast
in debug mode would that be worth the
hassle sure you can just don't run the
lighting right
will you come to the dark side and track
us the optimizer doesn't use Const so
there's there's very one there's one
specific case where the compiler can
optimize with constant we don't even
have that case so it causes useless for
optimization if you don't believe me go
watch Chandler Harris talk about it the
guy oversees the optimizer for LLVM so
if he says they don't use it I believe
him let's see what am i dropping a
little of course as soon as it's done
well I have you up the last Hameed here
episode on my rocky to account um so
there is only one account now it's just
since we post everything on that one
account I just call it Molly rocket now
it's the only account we have we don't
have another account I just changed the
name from handmade hero to molly rocket
because like I'm not
we had other videos we wanted to post
and we posted like the Anna draws it
there as well like back when I posted
that so it's just called Molly rocket
now and so stuff gets posted there
that's Molly Rock related it's handmade
hero we're not
mm-hmm MSP C is very often not
optimizing away obvious things basically
you cannot do so-called zero cast
abstractions with it for example it
always does short-circuiting or from
experience I also remember it sometimes
calls empty constructors why don't use
reads with violet clang gcci CC so clang
also has a bunch of problems generate
like clang generates slower code for
meow hash than MSB C so it's never clear
win to switch compilers I don't use G
clang on windows because like it still
has a little ways to go before it's
battle proofed in my opinion like it's
only just been recently that you could
use clang on Windows and get like usable
debug info so I do think eventually like
I will probably switch to clang
permanently on Windows but maybe like in
a year or two hmm like when I'm really
really sure that that I'm not gonna be
having weird stuff like I'm trying to
bug my app and like it it output like a
crappy PDB that doesn't quite show the
right info or whatever right which it
was doing for awhile and one of the very
first episode and here you mentioned it
would be good idea to recreate the
window if WM destroy was caught in the
window procedure and what's our snare
does this happen I'm not sure what
you're referring to recreate the window
if WM destroy was caught in the window
procedure I'm not sure what I would have
meant by recreate the window I guess if
I just meant look if someone tried to
destroy our window we could just make a
new one
maybe I don't I don't know sorry it's
been a long time I don't remember
exactly what kind of said that in
and just to be clear about the comms
thing it's not like it's MSV see that
doesn't use cost like clang doesn't use
cost either because you can't the C++
spec pretty much prevents the optimizer
from using Const because Const Cass is
legal these optimized need to be
low-level how do you know when it's
worth going to this level versus zooming
out to examine the overall algorithm
remember they are data volume so
actually we're sort of at the beginning
of things here which is just
investigation so more specifically what
I was doing there was not so much trying
to optimize this routine per se as I was
trying to look at what effect branches
were having in that routine right so I
wouldn't actually we're not optimizing
yet we're just looking at what's
happening in these routines to get a
feel for what's going on
as far as when to look at the overall
algorithm we're going to do that very
shortly because we need our spatial
partition to be better but before to
unwind the entire thing before I replace
how we're storing the spatial partition
I wanted to verify that nothing stupid
was happening in the current one so I
wanted to make sure that the Brandt
extra branches in there weren't a
problem it looks like they aren't so I
do think at least at this point we could
consider this traversal to be
representative of this spatial hierarchy
right that's important because I don't
want to go replacing the spatial
hierarchy and claiming that it got
faster when really the reason that it
got faster but because there something
stupid happening in the previous one
right so it's important to kind of look
at what's going on now and make sure
there's nothing dumb billing on before
we start to claim that we changed
something and made an improvement so the
answer is no we're not really looking at
low level optimizations right now all we
were doing today and the reason we were
looking at a finicky thing today was
just trying to vary I just wanted to see
is it fair to say that this loop is
operating as expected or was there
something weird going on
I wanted to make sure that using C mobs
wouldn't be like a huge win or something
in there before I claimed that it was
running at roughly the speed I could
expect right hopefully that helps
if John's talking I restarted yeah we
could raid it after this I guess what
I'm curious about is why you shouldn't
just terminate the application if you
get that mean destroy procedure cuz who
knows where it came from I mean we
should have been the ones to quit our
application right how many hours of week
do I work normally a total including
being on stream for hand-made here oh
you mean I don't know a lot
a lot of hours
many many hours I don't know 60 of
actual work like I don't count it as
work if I'm like not actually
programming or something
yeah my RSI problem is like totally gone
so switching away from Emacs so not
using ctrl + alt keys when I program and
rock climbing pretty much fixed it I
don't have any wrist pain anymore is it
possible to not call virtual Alec at all
so create a global array of bytes and
then point to that um you could but it's
pointless because the place that those
bytes came from was virtual Alec anyway
so all you're doing there is having the
OS call virtual Alec for you instead of
you calling it so you could try but it
doesn't really do anything
we'll be releasing peace Lakota
me yeah after handmade hero is done I
think I said two years after ships will
release it in the public domain would
you use a set of control keys yeah
they're not I don't use them commands
cuz I never was a VI user I was an Emacs
user so I didn't have any like pre
biased towards VI ik controls but I did
create my own modal binding that's you
know a a modal binding like vim so
escape and tilde switch between command
and edit mode and I just made my own key
bindings so they're not really very much
like vim but they are modal in the way
that vim is modal and has different
modes of editing so I don't know if that
answers the question but they're not vim
controls but they're in a similar spirit
could you stream your daily working
process of activity 5 sometime no that's
all private code we don't talk about any
of that and yeah you can it su adding
cost with clang does induce an
optimization if the front-end can see
that the Const is being used in a
particular way right so the front-end
can see a Const that it knows can't be
cast that's where you get an
optimization well you might get an
optimization if the cop if the compiler
happens to see it right everywhere else
it doesn't help you so and it especially
doesn't help you and what we're doing
now where the compiler can see all the
values so when the compiler can see all
of the values you don't need Const
because it's not telling the compiler or
anything it doesn't already know that
makes sense it's important nowadays you
so support x86 probably not there could
be certain specific markets where you
care
it kind of depends if that makes sense
but it's it's pretty specialized if
you're just like someone shipping a game
on Steam like no right
and no we're never gonna use Vulcan on
handmade hero I can't stand Vulcan hmm I
mean we do a d3 212 port before we did a
Vulcan port if we were gonna do a port
something all righty let's go ahead and
wrap it up too many things too many
windows are open right now all right
thank you everyone join me for those
sort of handmade here oh it's a pleasure
coating with you as always if you want
to following stories at home you can
always pre-order the game on handmade
hero org and it comes with source code
so you can play around with it at home
if you would like to we also have a
kickstart going right now for our comic
if you're interested in in a print
edition of it that's the place to go
there's a banner on the page you'd have
to remember the URL you can just click
on the banner on handmade hero we also
have some fun stuff coming up shortly
after this I will be posting the first
video on the Molly Rocket youtube
channel that is a a little series and I
made called plots Illustrated and it's
it's just a little thing where Anna and
I like basically talk to each other
about like trying to reconstruct the
plot of a movie our first one we do is
rise of the skywalker and that'll be
posted to the handmade hero channel
immediately after this and then anna
tries to like draw out the plots and we
have several of these as anna finishes
drawing them we'll be posting them
different like going through the plot in
like little two minute chunks basically
that she kind of does like little pseudo
animation for so those will be coming up
as well so please stay tuned to the hint
to the same place to get the handmade
hero stuff just in my rocket youtube
channel if just go there it'll be on
there i'll post it on twitter as well
that's it for today I'll be back here
next week to take a little bit closer
look at how we can get those loops
a little bit better and we'll have to
start to think about what the right way
is to do that obviously fixing our
spatial partition to be better is going
to be a big part of that too so we'll
sort of start that optimization path see
if we can't get those numbers down I'm
gonna go ahead and see if I can get
twitch to raid John's channel now maybe
I can maybe I can't but if I can't
please go to twitch.tv slash naysayer 88
because he's doing his talk now so he
and Shawn are to be chatting for a while
and that'd be a place to go if you like
handmade here are you're probably like
that so we're gonna try and get over to
that and I'll see you folks next week
tegus everybody