all right hello everyone and welcome to
handmade hero we are
really just in a debugging situation
here because i think we
got everything we really wanted to get
uh out of the um
out of the lighting code surprisingly
just the fact that we no longer have
large z stacks
uh in the world we basically said we
didn't really need them so we removed
them and just that
was enough to make our lighting run 60
frames a second just fine
and so really now we just have to tune
in a little bit to
uh make sure that we're casting the
right number of rays now because we can
cast a lot more rays per frame
um than we were before like a lot more
like eight times more
uh
just just a very very large uh
difference so we'll be able to get much
faster much more accurate lighting
uh to start with but then we also have
to fix a bunch of bugs because we are
sort of as we're clipping as we're
taking out some of that stuff that was
in there originally
we have the issue of
you know
we we aren't quite right like we
as we pull stuff out we have some
certain things that are not exactly
uh lined up the way they used to and and
the old code was very highly optimized
so it's it's fairly brittle in that
sense right um
when we do code that's
kind of not that optimized right where
we haven't like done a bunch of cindy
work and threading work and all this
stuff to kind of like see when we have
to do like lighting we kind of to see
how performant it was we didn't have the
luxury of just leaving it
sort of unoptimized
in that case you end up restricting how
flexible the code is or how easy it is
to change right
it's the actual premature optimization
thing kind of that uh
that knuth was probably referring to to
the extent that he was
um
in the sense that you know
i don't think in this case it was
premature to optimize i think we
optimized it at the correct time because
we needed to see what the performance
was but the point is if we had done that
just willy-nilly
you can see where you end up in a bad
situation because like it takes more
work than to shift what it does because
it's so tightly optimized to this one
the case
so we do have a little bit more work to
do here but that's okay uh that's the
nature of performance optimization it's
harder than normal code when you
actually go down this route um but again
this is more what people are talking
about not the kind like people use the
phrase premature optimization to refer
to things that are in no way premature
optimization
um and in this case it wasn't premature
it was at the right time but it has
those same drawbacks like this is you
can see
literally what is being talked about
there is that it will be harder for us
to modify this code because we're trying
to modify code that is optimized
and that's always more difficult
in this case we really just didn't have
a choice because part of the reason we
had to do this was to see how fast
lighting was because we just don't know
right and until you when you have
something that's this heavy weight uh
you really don't have the luxury of
using a unoptimized version so
uh so looking at the actual code here
if we
you know let me just show you where
we're at uh we're actually running just
fine but we have a number of things that
we need to look at uh in terms of
there's obviously it's it's a little bit
buggy so the lighting is not
running properly like it was before
and we need to fix the like problems
with like the grid alignment and how
it's stepping and stuff um and that's
just going to take a little while but if
there's not a lot like it's not
completely broken or anything it still
actually kind of looks sort of right
like it's it's not that bad so we're not
far from a correct situation but we're
not like you can see there's kind of
weird like you know
uh
there's just a lot of like like what was
happening there right it doesn't make
much sense so we definitely have things
that need to get fixed there's some
weirdness going on here
uh and we need to sort of uh go through
all that and and clean it up we also
probably have to change a little bit
about how the lighting is working um
in addition to that uh piece of the sort
of the accuracy part of the puzzle
uh because one of the things that you
will see in here is that the the actual
lighting
we want to now drive it at a much higher
rate than we were driving it before and
what you can see if you look in here is
that we have we sort of optimized this
code for a very modest kind of light
transport where in each pass we were
only expecting to cast
eight total rays
and those correspond
essentially to the eight
uh faces of the octahedral map so we
have an octahedral map that we record
the lighting into that's eight sample
directions
for the lighting meaning that in each
one of those uh
sample directions out of an octahedron
we have some resolution like you know we
can set the resolution of this
octahedral map to take you know
more samples in the octahedron or
whatever it's just a way of representing
the lighting
uh around a sphere like we need to for
light probes you can argue whether it's
good or bad or not i'm not really a
rendering guy so i'm not going to defend
it as good or bad it's just something
that works
and that's what we need is something
that works so that's what we're using
you know maybe it would be smarter to
switch to something
uh
like spherical harmonics or you know
whatever else there's there's plenty of
ways you could imagine storing light
probe information
this one uh
is kind of nice because it's direct and
easy to understand and easy to visualize
the bad part about it is converting from
specular to diffuse is expensive and we
do pay a high cost for that
so you know there's trade-offs in it
whatever we're not really going to
revisit that probably because it seems
good enough as it is
uh but the point is we kind of optimized
this originally for just sending out
eight rays those eight rays are one out
of each of the octahedral faces and then
every frame we would pick sort of a new
direction
out of each octahedral face to trace so
that over some number of frames we would
kind of like reasonably sample
the sphere right
as represented by the octahedral map you
know what i'm saying
so
um
if you imagine that
that now we're going to be sending out a
lot of a lot more rays potentially then
what you can see here is this is no
longer probably the optimal way to do it
because you know what we tried to do to
see what would happen if we sent
out additional numbers of rays is i
added this for loop here for a sample
batch and what this does is it calls the
grid raycast that routine we're just
looking at
it calls that routine
as many times as we want like we can
change this right and so we can slow it
down to a level that's too slow right if
i set this up to 64
so that's 64 times 8 raise
per map per frame right
you can see that i've slowed down now to
a fairly slow frame rate right it's it's
quite slow right
whereas if i drop this down to a very
small number which again is still eight
times what we were doing originally um
so it's it's way more than the previous
version but still uh you can see that we
run uh pretty much at an i-60 in fact i
think we can actually take a look at the
the specific time there um and you know
this number here without the debug
system it's already basically at uh 60
frames a second but with the debug
system running it will sometimes miss so
you know in general we could we could
easily hit 60 frames a second with this
amount of raycasting and it's quite
stable and quite responsive as you can
see right
um but
even this
which is fine
we still wouldn't really want to do it
this way and the reason is because we're
still duplicating a ton of work for no
reason if instead we pushed this eight
down into the grid raycast right
so if we instead pushed it down to here
so that this simply loops over 64 things
that would be way better because this
raycast which is this piece of code here
right
um this raycast does the same amount of
work in any case no matter how many rays
we send
but this which is the thing which then
computes like okay
what are we going to do in terms of like
how these would get written back to
the octahedral map or whatever right
that code there
doesn't really need to have its right
back occur until after we've blended all
the ones we're going to do for this
frame this code right here that loads
the old specular map texel values
um
loads the new values in that we just
computed
blends them together to basically do a
little bit of temporal anti-aliasing
right
and then writes them back out
right now when we increase the sample
batch size from one to two to three to
four to five to eight to six four to
whatever
whatever this value is it's doing these
this load blend right
each time
but there's no reason for it to do that
right it doesn't have to do that for any
particular reason
instead we could just run this code this
this transfer pps code right this
transfer pps code we should put the loop
there and then only do this load modify
right after we've done all of the sample
batches
that we plan to do
and so that part is kind of the more
uh important way of structuring the loop
and i do think we probably want to do
that
because there's no reason not to do it
and yeah i mean we really want to go fix
that
okay
um so i would say let's fix that first
actually because it's kind of an
additional like weirdness in the process
and the reason that we didn't do that is
the originally is because the sample
directions that get passed down here
this light sample direction sample
directions this part here
um that part was getting prepped by this
particular piece of code here that's
stepping over these octahedral indices
and there's there's other stuff that's
kind of confusing about this which is
that
we don't really know what our entropy
story is here like you know we we have
this thing where we pre-compute stepping
tables that allow us to do fast
recasting
and we're basically just picking which
of those tables we're going to use and
the table determines like how the ray
actually gets cast and blah blah blah
blah right
there's not a lot to it but you know
that is how it's currently uh working
and
so we want to make sure that we're
actually utilizing the correct set of
sample directions so that as we sort of
step through
um
you know we we always get kind of like
a reasonable distribution of rays coming
from whatever sample source we're
actually looking for we want to make
sure that we're actually stepping
through those fairly like we don't want
to have some weird thing where because
we haven't really analyzed the code
properly and we just kind of like you
know smushed it together that it turns
out we're only sampling like four of the
directions at like our step just always
like mods them poorly or something and
you know those are the kind of things
you can have happen when you're trying
to optimize code like this and you're
using table driven stuff and you're not
able to use a real random number or
whatever right there's a lot of issues
you can run into so we probably want to
make sure that we're doing that sort of
thing correctly
and so we're going to have to analyze
that as well
but
looking through this what you can see is
when we call full cast
typically there's like this entropy
index value that gets passed in uh and
if you look at where that actually gets
uh worked out it's right in here and
what i'm wondering is you know can we
just say that maybe this entropy index
just gets passed down directly like
maybe our grid raycast this goes away um
this outer loop here goes away and we
just literally drop it down into the
other uh piece of code so
you know we we get rid of this right
and we go into
um this this uh ray index code here like
this code right
and we do something where this is going
to get accumulated so you know maybe
it's like that uh and we we wrap this
code up
in us in the second for loop directly
right so now we kind of have these two
for loops nested the way that they
should be
and so we do our raycasts eight wide
like we were doing it before
but we
in when i say eight wide we're not it's
not like eight wide sim d uh we're just
doing them eight at a time so eight wide
is probably the wrong term uh the th we
do use simdi but it's wide in the
collision side so we cast a single ray
replicated across four lanes in simdi
we cast that against
four
boxes at a time right we don't do the
opposite which is another way you can
write these kinds of casters where you
cast four rays at a time it's called a
ray bundle uh you can cast four rays at
a time against one box right
um so that there's a lot of different
ways you can imagine doing this um
one side or the other has to be wide
otherwise you won't speed up right
so you're just trying to leverage
the floating point alu here
so if we did it this way and we have
this entropy index that comes down right
so that uh you know that entropy index
here
uh
i'm just going to try and follow this
value through to see if i can back out a
reasonable way to track this entropy
index across
the system you can see here it gets a
sample point entropy and it calls full
cast with that entropy index the
point of this is to make sure that each
one of these like voxels uh cells that
we're producing lighting for is going to
use a different uh arrangement of casts
out of its um faces because the goal is
to make sure that you don't see aliasing
in the lighting based on the fact that
like every grid cell casts the same
direction or something right so it's
trying to make sure that that's
each different light probe uses a
different set of directions
so pretty straightforward um so what
we're going to do there it when we pass
down that entropy index it's just an
index that we can use as like a random
number generation kind of thing so into
full cast we go and you can see that the
entropy index uh is is passed in here i
don't think that this makes a whole lot
of sense i think we can probably say
look we're gonna
not do it that way with the address
we shouldn't actually need that i think
i was just hacking that in before
but that shouldn't actually be necessary
so if we look at how the entropy index
gets updated this shouldn't probably be
an address there if we send down this
entropy index we should be able to
do as we were doing before where each
one of these kind of gets expanded the
interview index gets incremented in some
really weird way or whatever right i'm
not sure exactly what we would do but
you know you can imagine something where
we just add some really weird value to
it here where we're going to step
through these fairly randomly
we even could at this point here
probably actually do a random series off
of the entropy index um presumably
really wouldn't be that big of a deal
right
now i don't know what the best way to
seed that would be but like you know um
you can see us doing here where we we
have a random series in each frame
uh we we're probably picking right like
you can see here where we pick a u32
value that goes into each one of these
work units so each one of these has a
different random value and then what we
really want here is to also have these
to be seated to a random value as well
now i don't know what we did here for
doing this random seed that's a 4x
random seed which we
don't really need but um
let me see
[Music]
yeah
so
here's our random series pcg which i
don't know if this is what we're
currently using
looks like we have a couple different
ones
pcgs aren't actually that good um
i think i was kind of more into them
when we first did handmade hero because
they were supposed to be pretty good but
they're really not because they don't
semdy very well so you know it's
probably not something you would
actually use today but you know whatever
times change
um
so when we call this i think this random
next u32 is presumably calling this part
of it i don't actually know but because
we could take a look in fact i guess i
can just jump over the lighting and see
which one we were using
um
lighting solution
random series is
which one oops
what is
yeah
uh
so it looks like there's only the h file
so there's only this one random series
and it's always an f32 4x i guess
so that's a little weird
um but i guess we always do it four wide
i guess i mean that's i guess how we do
it we just do it wide
so when we do random next 32 it looks
like we just extract one value from it
which is fine i mean that doesn't really
you know
no real issue there
um but if you look at the way this works
you can see where we do a random seed
here
and
i guess you might say that it's a little
bit squinky because
i guess if we did a random seed offset
we could take a number that came from
the random number generator
and this would probably be fine so you
know we we could imagine doing
sort of a sequential update to this
thing
uh that would be okay or you know we
could imagine rolling something like
this in there
right where we
are
you know doing this each update
and and going from there i don't know
it seems like you'd probably want to
keep this in scalar because we don't
actually need four of these random
values or maybe we do i mean i guess the
other question is if we kept two of
these around could we just use those in
each and each step through the random
series
we would actually just
update all four random numbers
and that
might actually be good so
hmm
so you know that gives us an option
i guess maybe we should think about that
so if we look at what's happening inside
full cast right um it's just the entropy
does not factor into full cast at all
it's a completely
100 non-entropic thing that's happening
here it's only grid raycast right where
this actually happens so if you take a
look at grid raycast this is what
actually now needs the entropy and it
just needs the entropy for the thing
we're talking about which is to figure
out which of the sample table there's
like this sample table
and we just want to figure out which one
of
the
indexes
indices we're going to use right
so we would pull out the sample
direction by grabbing the table
uh and
just we pick one of the octahedrons and
then we do all eight samples out of the
octahedron right at that point
so really this part is the only part we
really need if we know that we're going
to do batches we could just use the
random numbers
out of the batches so actually
it may mean that the best thing to do is
to just actually use a random series and
allow the random series to update each
time um
that's probably actually fine
i mean maybe that's dumb i don't know
but it kind of seems reasonable so it
could be that the right thing to do here
is say look we're going to have a random
series uh that's the entropy for this
and
we've got a random seed offset function
right like this thing
and we can just go like okay there's a
sample point entropy
and that gets placed in here um and then
we do pass down an address like we were
doing before but rather than passing an
address
of a simple like you
know uh
rather than passing an address of like a
simple
index that just gets updated we're
actually going to pass a random series
and we're going to grab those values out
uh that actu the indices we're going to
actually grab out um
right
so if we wanted to do that
and also you can see how this here
you know
[Music]
if you look at how this function is
working
um
i also don't know like
where this
supposedly
was going to convert itself to anything
in particular like you can see we've got
these f324x states here
and these aren't really f32 values right
they're actually just u32 values
um
and so i'm not actually sure like
i'm not actually sure how we were
previously planning to use these it
looks like we mostly convert them
you can kind of see here
like how that was happening right
um like effectively you convert you do a
u32 to f32 right
um so in this case we would want to just
literally get out the values and if you
think about what's happening here i
would assume that we don't have a large
enough table set so if you
actually look at like the lighting
include there's like an inl for this uh
sampling spheres
if you actually look at this you can see
like how many octahedrons there are like
that's not very many
um
i don't know why it's so low right
we probably want to increase that number
in the future to something higher i
would think
uh but either way if it's only gonna be
16 different octahedrons
um
i mean at that point
i guess my other question is if there's
only going to be 16 octahedrons maybe we
just
say forget the en entropy altogether if
that
turns out to be sufficient let's just do
all 16.
you know that like elon musk
face
where he like just smoked pot on the joe
rogan show
you know what i'm talking about it's
like
it's like where he's got the
the joint or whatever i don't actually
know what he was handed i don't remember
i think it's a joint
and he's like got like a a face that's
like
that face
do you know what i'm talking about
anybody
well anyway i'm making that face right
now and thinking
maybe
maybe uh we don't care
and i would say great
at that point if we're always just gonna
say there's only 16
octahedron i mean
then let's just cast all 16 octahedrons
so i'm just making that judgment call
because it's the easiest thing to do and
let's just find out if maybe that's fine
because at that point it even removes
one more step to this process which is
to say
that now we just don't need entropy at
all so the entropy is just gone from the
system and the sampling is just
just literally over the octahedron so we
basically have this u32 octahedron index
it's just going to be zero
and then it's going to go to whatever
the octahedron count is and that's like
it
right
so then we don't use the mask or any of
those things we just say like okay the
sample direction is going to be whatever
the
you know whatever the
uh computed offset is into the table
uh and and that's it
right uh
that would be it
so
i have to think about if i'm missing
something here there's also this other
thing a light sampling sphere mask
which again don't really remember much
about that i think that's probably going
to be below these here
right yeah
so there's a sphere count
of sample directions
and it's using the same offset
i i really couldn't say i know why we
have both of these
sample direction table
like what is the point
of that hold on a second
so the sample sphere doesn't get used
so those must have just been old things
i guess
um so that just goes away right so in
here we're just grabbing the octahedron
that we're going to use and that sample
dir we just pull out of here
like it's this right
um and this function doesn't get past
sample directions
uh
nor does it get past i mean we could
pass it the base pointer if we wanted to
but nor does it get past the
uh what and what the heck is quadrant
index
so oh quadrant index is just which of
the four yet okay that's fine we don't
care about that either
um so that's that can still stay in
there so if i get rid of sample
directions i just want to see where
we're at here
um so this does this guy not have the
solution pointer no he does so he has
that
um
we have the octahedron index
sample
directions
ray index walk table offset so this is
just it's just these
i mean that's all it is
right
uh and so the only thing is what is it
complaining about sample batch is not
did not get replaced so
this would do
all of them right
this would do the entire set every frame
uh and
the only problem is this code right here
um
where transfer pps gets written to the
rgb
uh
for this particular array you know what
i'm saying
um
you can see here that i'm grumpy about
this apparently like this part didn't
really get optimized that's okay because
we're now sort of changing a little bit
how it works so maybe we want that
anyway
uh so we'll find out uh yeah we can we
can probably update this to be better
than it is right uh because we can fix
the you know we can fix the way that it
actually gets sort of handled through
this loop when we're doing kind of final
options we don't have to do that now
but we can make this better for sure
so when we look at this uh
really what we're what we're talking
about now is if we just clear this
instead
um so here where we start at transfer vs
this used to not bother clearing it
because it was just gonna wasn't
actually gonna
ever get used it was always gonna get
overwritten
if we now clear it first
and then we go ahead and do a
like a basically a sum
where we average all of the things
together that we put in here
you can then imagine this to just being
a plus equals
right
this sort of a thing
um
and
we should
be able to multiply this by the weight
like um you know like rayweight or
something
and you can see that this is just stupid
code like this should be done wide and
isn't you can see why we put this
comment in here so that comment
remains true this should all be done
wide and then we just convert it down at
the end but at the moment we don't care
too much about that
but if we just do an accumulator there
right so that we accumulate those values
together just average the samples that
are sent out we know what the ray weight
is it's just going to be how many
octahedrons we're going to do so it's
this value here
um so if we just
take the total number of octahedrons
and we say
we're going to do all the octahedrons
that we have that we generate
we are going to divide
that you know one over that number we're
going to divide to find out how much
each individual octahedron should
compute to the whole so we have 16 so
each one contributes 1 16 of the
lighting answer right
and we do that each time we now get rid
of any sort of external understanding of
like what the sample directions are or
what the entropy index is or any of that
stuff
and now we're literally just stepping
through the rows of the atlas table
um
as we go
right
uh now
i guess i to be honest i'm not sure i
understand how we know which one so like
i think about this but s y here
uh
like the lighting atlas texas like which
one that we're
using
um
that
i don't understand how we know
so so this is a little confusing so
let's let's try to work this out because
this i don't remember how this works
and there's a little bit of an issue
here that i'm not sure i follow
so when we
like call into grid raycast right we've
got the spec texel here and the spec
texel is what
what the first texel is in the row you
can see that we're going to step by wise
and write all the x's
when we pick out a sample direction
i don't think i understand
how does this know which row
we're on
so this seems like
either there was a bug
in it already
there's three possibilities there's a
bug in it already a
seems probably unlikely b i don't really
understand what this code is doing and i
missed something
or c i i accidentally deleted something
very important
so um
here's what i'm trying to say
we go over these ray indices here and
there's eight of them that's not an
accident the reason there are eight is
because each row of an octahedral map
because we said that they were eight by
eight each row of our octahedral map
there's eight rows represented
here
by the sy loop
this is the eight rows of the octahedral
map right
and these eight rows of the i think by
the way we did this already
um the eight rows of the octahedral map
here
are then
this eight is the eight columns of that
row of the octahedral map
now each one of those
has to go out a particular direction
right so the sample direction ray index
this part here is what makes sure that
you're grabbing the correct one
but what i don't understand is how
did this
this this walking of the indices
has to be correct for the direction
which at this point i don't know that it
is it's probably not that might have
been the bug
so we look at the sampling spheres part
i don't understand how this got packed
in here exactly right
you can see there's a total light sample
direction count for these sampling
directions these are the directions that
come out the sphere right
and you can see here that we've got
this which is light light sample
directions per octahedron this is what
i'm talking about there's it's it's a
square right it's a it's the map dim
which is eight times the map dim which
is eight right it's eight times eight
so the total number is the octahedral
count times the light sample directions
per octahedron
you know what i'm saying
i think you know what i'm saying
so i think the part that i'm missing
is these are packed these are obviously
packed so that we have them in the
correct order right we've got them
in the order where it is
by
row then by column or whatever right
and so this
has to actually respect that and right
now it would not be
you know what i'm saying
so light sample directions per
octahedron this is actually
not
correct
yeah so this needs an sy
value
so i guess
what i would say
is
we really just need the base pointer
in here
[Music]
to
to be something along the following
lines
right
if you imagine the sample direction
is just unpacked
here
right
then we actually would know what the
sample direction offset is so the sample
the light sample direction here for
sample dir we can actually compute that
index directly it's going to be the ray
index is the small is the minor index so
it just goes each time right
it's the octahedron index times
the light samples
uh directions per octahedron right
then it's going to be plus
the rho index so right and and this is
this ray index is really column index
right
so the row index times the uh
light octahedral map dim
plus the ray index that's the actual
like
that's the actual way that this is being
stepped
you know what i'm saying
and since this piece of code doesn't
actually know the
the actual s y
it can't compute the correct value here
and that was the one missing piece that
was confusing me but it's not convincing
me now because i worked through it right
so what we actually want to do here is
you know honestly
we we really would rather rebuild the
lighting table to
go in the correct order
meaning what you'd rather do
is just make it so that the
[Music]
right
take a look at how this is stepped
this
is the thing that's actually in the
outside loop
so what we would rather do is move this
as the prime index
and the octahedron as the interior index
so that we inside here just slight step
it one one at a time
we don't have to do that right now
but that's just smarter at that point
right it's a much easier to
for the code to be understood
so i want to do that eventually
okay
so let's assume that we go with that
um
either way
we do need the sy
value here and maybe that gets rolled in
here too i don't know that's a good
question
but if we take a look at how the sy
value works out so in full cast
um all it's doing is stepping through
those texels and calling grid raycast
right that's like the only thing
that it actually does so it may make
sense to now actually finally collapse
these routines so that
grid raycast gets welded in here right
as this gets simplified we may find that
that's possible i don't know uh it may
or may not be we're gonna you know we'll
have to see
for the time being though in order to
keep things relatively straightforward
what i'm going to do is slightly simpler
than that i'm just going to pass
um the sy value
down the line so in here there's just
going to be like a sy value that gets
passed in and i'll just put so after the
the work value that sy value will will
get passed down
and so if we have the sy value then we
can
back out the sample direction
value directly here
and we can just say like okay
here's the sample direction table here's
the octahedral index that we're talking
about and we just need an additional
value in here um
for
i don't remember what the value was
where's that i know
it is this
so we take the base pointer that's the
entire table
we offset it by which row we're on
right
as well as which octahedron we're on and
right now it looks kind of like that
you know what i'm saying
so as you step through the sys this is
what you get right
and i don't actually remember i want to
check to make sure the sy value isn't
offset there i don't know it might be no
it's not right so it's stepping from
zero to eight
uh so that's fine total casts initiated
is now totally false so now this is
going to actually include this number
um so that's fine
but doesn't really matter at the moment
okay
so
when we call full cast
we
have the tile the center and the entropy
index so the entropy now goes away
and you know we can leave the sample
point entropy in the work order
just in case we decide to add it back in
there's no real cost to having it there
but if it turns out that all this stuff
works to our satisfaction later we can
just pull the entry index out entirely
because now there's no actual entropy in
the lighting system anymore which you
know maybe is good maybe is bad i'm not
actually sure
um which one it is okay so now we're
actually
also totally stable like the lighting
has none of the artifacts anymore
which suggests that that was a bug it is
however set at too low of a blend rate
right now
because the blending is now happening
automatically so what we should be able
to find uh somewhere in here
uh is like an over 60 the the you know
the actual value here this should be
able to um crank this up to something
much more aggressive so let's say
it only takes maybe four frames for the
lighting to be completely
uh up to date so very little a low
amount of lag right
which would look like this
and you know it looks okay but you can
see we get there there is a little bit
of
shifting that's happening oddly enough
it seems to happen mostly when the
lighting
slides
um so i assume that has to do with the
fact that we've and we have some weird
artifacts there like like i don't know
that that this is probably because these
are no longer centered as you know we
kind of
have them now at the corners of these
things which is not what we intended
originally so there's a little bit of
that going on as well
so we're getting closer now but we still
have this every time the lighting shifts
it looks like there's like kind of weird
artifacts based on your alignment
um
where you know where you are because
when you're actually when you're
stationary even if the light moves it's
kind of okay but you can see you know it
doesn't look quite right so i think we
probably still have some bugs in how
we're indexing these things at the very
least right and and we can sort of
go from there
um that said again pretty stable i don't
know what this value should actually be
um
i think let's hold off on tuning
anything like this until we actually do
a debugging pass which i think is what
we want to do now
um looking at the performance of this
now
we're not even in the fullest
performance build and i think we're
pretty much okay
um you know like it's not quite as good
as i would like it to be at the moment
but it's not it's not bad
and
now we're like in a we're in a very
stable zone i would say
right um we're in a very stable zone for
performance so i think we just
concentrate on getting this now to be
less buggy but i think it will be pretty
stable
uh
going forward
also we can
if we want to
um we can add some more
uh
we can figure out some ways to to maybe
add the entropy back in
by generating more light spheres and
every frame we use a different light
sphere set uh we didn't do that
originally because we already were
thinking that we wouldn't do all 16 like
you know 16 was the number that we
thought was the total amount we'd cycle
through and we did one every frame so it
took 16 frames to sample all the
octahedrons now we're like okay that was
fine like we easily can do all of those
so maybe we want to up that number right
to 256 spheres or something
and then that way you know we can still
introduce some entropy to the system
that's why i said i didn't want to pull
that out later because we may we may
find that we actually still need that
okay but at the moment we're fine for
performance and stability i think and
now i think we're just in bug land and
we want to go figure out how to
reduce the sort of bugginess of the
actual light computation which i think
is probably wrong you know what i mean i
i think it's you know since we made the
simplifications i think it's probably
incorrect at the moment and what we're
going to want to do is you know
sort of reduce the the sort of wonkiness
there by
actually going through and looking at
where arrays are being cast from make
sure they're being cast from the correct
place and that they're stepping properly
all that stuff because we kind of
shifted that stuff a little bit and we
do have a bunch of like debug
code in here right so that we can look
at individual light casts and things
like this
um and do various stepping so we when we
debug the lighting the first time around
we left in the code that we would need
to be able to fix some of that stuff and
so you know i think that is
we we shouldn't be starting completely
from scratch like we've got
uh
we've got stuff here that we can use you
know what i mean
all right so let's first just
make sure we're all on the same page
here because like i said it's been a
while so we looked at this code
so we now step over all 16 octahedrons
that we have we grab out the sample
direction batch by saying it's the table
times which octahedron where you think
we're on times whichever row we want
that gives us our initial sample
direction and then we're going to go
over all eight of those sample
directions one at a time we're gonna
produce after the raycast and uh
doing like sort of the computation of
the reflectance and all that stuff
sampling this this is basically where we
sample the uh the old octahedral map
right when we do the sampling we figure
out how much we're going to transfer and
then we sum that into our transfer value
we're going to do that for every
octahedron so we're going to do that 16
times
and then we're going to write it out
once to the final map right so
that's what this is doing and that app
this right here applies that blend rate
so that t update blend rate that's what
this is right
so we're going to do that and we do that
for anybody who is not inside
um who doesn't start off inside a
one of our grid leaves
and we sort of determined that's
actually kind of buggy though
because if a light
if you're enclosed by a light
you are not supposed to be completely
dim like you should probably have at
least whatever the value of that light
is should be what you write in as your
uh
as your light value like you should be
radiating that in all directions right
because you're you know you're basically
like enclosed by the light
so i don't know how we want to handle
that maybe we i don't know what we want
to do it could be that the correct thing
to do there is something else but you
know we we probably need to do something
about that
so that's going to have to change and we
know that's going to have to change
um
that said
everything else i think is fairly
straightforward
i don't know um
there are a few things that might
not be true anymore as well
so one of the things that we did here
is we computed the walk table and we
verified that it's faster to compute the
walk table
and just look up
the walk table
than it is to
uh produce the walk table dynamically on
the fly
however
right
um
we don't actually know
that that's true anymore
now that we've moved to 2d because this
was for 3d which is a lot more
complicated because you have three
possible step directions you can take
x y and z
and three when you're talking about a
really tight loop
uh where everything counts three is a
lot more expensive than two two is
literally just one
branch right either you're going to go
a step in y or you're going to go step
in x when you have to do like x or y or
z
you can see how maybe that would have
tipped the balance in favor of a table
whereas if you just have x and y and
it's just a straight bresenham walk
along there not only
you know not only might it change but we
could probably do at a literal like
integer bresenham walk or something like
this
where where
we don't even use the float
where we don't even use the um
sse registers right so it could be that
we could actually hide the cost of doing
the walk
which would get us out of the business
of building these tables at all right we
could literally do
the comparison just the one comparison
each time
uh and go
now it may be that that is still just
too expensive because it's mispredicted
and having a table that just you always
grab whatever it is each time
uh is just too compelling right uh
you know i just don't know um
i just don't know
so we probably will have to run that
test again at some point i don't think
we should do it now but you know at some
point that is something we would
probably have to figure out because we
definitely have
you know uh
we definitely have some some
flexibility there that we didn't have
before
so
all right um if we take a look at how we
do the get quadrant 4 stuff let's just
go over this one more time because again
this is subtle as well
so the way this works
is we're going to loop over all of the
sample directions
you can
you can see how this works here we're
going to loop over all the sample
directions and the sample directions
are for whichever uh you know whatever
particular node you are we have this
idea that
we
the actual places you're casting from
are
they're finer grained like there are
more
light nodes in fact i think we can just
put that back in here i don't i don't
um
i'm gonna turn on draw octahedral values
so you can see what i'm talking about
so
these are the locations
if you can see there uh these are the
locations where we are actually taking
light probes
so each one of these
places
stores
a
a light probe
value and on each frame we cast
uh out from from these
so on each frame we cast
uh however many rays it was now so it's
16 times eight so right uh
i think
no it's 16 times 8 times 8. so it's 16
times 20 16 times 64.
right
so we cast 16 times 64 raised out of
each one of these every frame just to
let you know how powerful computers are
right i mean yes we completely
multi-threaded this and yes it is simdee
so it's going it's it's utilizing the
performance of the cpu well but i mean
come on man computers are fast
so we're doing those casts out of each
one of these right
um but the but the thing is if you look
and i don't know if we have enough debug
space for these i should probably switch
to using the other debug diagram stuff
but
um
yeah we don't
uh so
[Music]
where is our debug lines
debug line
count let's just give ourselves a little
more debug space here
all right how what oh
is this just
because we have a um
we only have 16 bit for
line indices
so the problem here
is actually just that like we can't
actually fit
um
this many
lines
yeah we should we should just fix that
we should just have multiple line
batches because this is the that's the
problem that we're getting here right is
that
we end up with too many of these
uh
when we push them on
so you know we could fix that right um
in fact
it should be pretty easy to fix it right
um let's just see what happens if we try
to fix that here
so if we go to when we do the draw debug
lines um
the lighting values when they actually
push out the
the
the debug lines there right
this
um
i feel like this is actually a lot we i
don't know why we didn't do this before
but i feel like we could just solve this
by breaking this up into chunks
right so if we did something like this
which is like debug lines left and we
just said all right this is how many
debug lines there are
if we want to keep the indices always
below 16 bits because that's what we
have for dispatching to the graphics
card
and we don't want to bump that to 32.
it seems pretty easy at this point to
just say well whatever debug lines are
left we'll just say as long as there are
debug lines left to draw
we will
[Music]
compute a batch value
which is just whatever the minimum value
is between how many lines are left
and what fits in 16 bits
right
that kind of thing
um we'll then just like go through those
uh and maybe we can you know we can do
this with an offset so it'll be a little
easier for us we could do something like
this so we say like
debug line index we'll start at zero
um and we'll just say look while the
debug line index is less than however
many debug lines there are
we will compute the value of the lines
left by subtracting where we're at from
the total number like so uh and then
we'll just say look we're gonna do as
many as we can which sometimes is all of
them and sometimes is only 16 bits worth
uh we'll then ask that for that value
we'll loop through that value
um
and we will
have a sub index here where we push you
know we push the line segments one at a
time
like so
uh when we're done we just advance debug
line index
uh
you know
by the batch count and that should allow
us to just batch these up into 16-bit
capable chunks which in theory should
mean that we don't have
a limitation right
or at least i think it should
we should probably switch this into
one second
yeah so
we should probably search this in debug
mode to make sure this is actually going
to do it because it looks like it still
doesn't like that but i'm not sure why
it wouldn't do we have a total frame
limit on 16 bits do we never reduce
those do we never rebase those values
um that would be kind of weird
if that's true
but it might be
here's where we like update batches
it sure looks like this would be fine
right
so if we take a look at
what this says here
there's a max quads per batch that
already has this baked in right
so it looks like this should work
meaning it looks like as long as we
you know don't try to call this value
with something that's too large there
it sure seems like that would work
i mean it could be the pr the fact that
this is slightly off
i guess the problem is the max quads per
batch value we probably need this to
respect i mean you just like here
let's suppose we just said the max batch
value is 4 000 of these right
um
yeah
so we just need that batch value to be
you know maybe we need to export that
from the renderer so the we know like
look you have to
[Music]
provide a number that's that's you know
sufficient but anyway now we're out of
the we don't have the issue anymore of
having too many
debug lines we can have as many as we
want um so we can draw everything now of
course there is the issue of we can't
figure out what the heck anything is so
there's that um but
uh if we turn off like
like maybe rendering the occluders we
can look at the sort of thing that i was
talking about before so if we go um and
in fact you can also kind of see
here in this area
where
uh
you've got the occluders drawn right or
i should say where you've got
arbitrary stuff drawn so just things are
being drawn that are lights or occluders
you can see that for example we have
trees in this area right those are
that's what these all are
but then you've also got like this stuff
which i don't have any idea what that is
i assume those are the lights right
there wherever the lights are
um and you can also see kind of the
problem that i was saying before is that
like plenty of sample points are inside
where the lights are and right now we're
treating that as if they're inside
occluders but they're not they're inside
lights right
so
that's an issue
to be sure
so um
so i'm not sure what we want to do with
that we're going to have to think about
that a little bit more
right um
inside here you can see there's a lot
more
occluders that's because there are
ceiling tiles so those are the ceiling
tiles there um and those are there just
because interior spaces need to have
bounce from the ceiling exterior spaces
obviously wouldn't
have bounced from anything but interior
spaces even though we're not drawing a
ceiling want to have lighting bounce
from the ceiling so that's why those are
there
uh similarly you can see the thing that
i was talking about before where you
know you can see how these are
these
bits are kind of off so the first thing
i think i might want to do is let's try
to restore the alignment of these
to actually be aligned more on the
actual like i feel like these want to be
aligned so that their centers are at the
we want the centers of the sampling to
be at the centers of our actual grid
because that's where people are going to
be most of the time so we'd like to have
the lighting computed properly around
like where the things are we're actually
lighting um and furthermore it avoids
problems of like having stuff that's
right on the boundary of being inside or
outside something which again is just
creating a lot of problems for us that
we wouldn't ordinarily have to deal with
if we're not putting our probes right on
the boundary of where something goes
from being inside being outside although
we probably do need to deal with that in
in separate ways
in other ways anyway but
so why did we get that alignment change
um
last weekend we we basically had that
happen
and
i'm assuming that it has to do with the
fact that we
i'm assuming that when we went to change
the alignment of things in the world to
not use z
we used the plus five offset
like we used that
that uh
offset by a percentage of a tile right
and so if we want the lighting to be
centered around it the lighting center
would also have to be offset by
that
right
so when we do our alignment in the
lighting code
um we need the lighting itself to align
to a tile boundary that's off by
that same percent that same
fifth of a tile
like so in here right where we do all
this stuff like voxel dim is one
fundamental unit and blah blah blah
right
and
we
we do all this stuff to determine like
where the thing is going to be which is
right down here
and we say all right it's going to be at
this particular offset
um
right you can see here where we where
we're saying like we set the offset to
this particular value and all that stuff
so
this part needs to be offset by that 0.5
of a cell dim
right
so
i mean really i think i i don't know to
what extent this is
going to be exactly correct but i think
we're really just talking about
like atlas min corner the x value would
be offset by
whatever the voxel size is
right so half of one of these voxels
so
the like when we pass in here
we've got the vox cell dim right
i think we just want this offset by half
because that's how things are aligned in
the world currently
something like this
right
um
and we should be able to do i don't know
if we've got x y but
maybe we do
yeah
so if we just offset the x y
by that much leave the z where it is
because that's this kind of absolute
thing and it's off differently then in
theory the location where we take these
samples would now be centered whoa
that's some interesting light poisoning
presumably because now it's sampling off
the edge
that's pretty cool though
you have to admit
that's some interesting light poisoning
uh but anyway
light poisoning aside
um
i assume we effectively want to do that
right like i assume we effectively want
to sample
lighting add an offset of the boundary
like that now why that would actually
produce
the light poisoning that we just saw
though i'm not sure why so you know we
know we've got some bugs in here so it
could just be related to other problems
that we're having it might not really
have anything to do with that and this
just exposed it but the fact that that
occurred was not what i was expecting
um so that's a little disconcerting
right um i don't understand exactly why
that would have provoked it because in
theory this should just be
in theory that sampling shouldn't really
have
much to do with anything and the
alignment relative you know the
alignment of
the cells of the
spatial partition
should be the same either way because
the whole thing got shifted
in that direction
you know what i mean so you can see that
like the cells of the spatial prediction
also got shifted 0.5 so there really
shouldn't have been a behavioral
difference i don't know why this in
particular like leaving this out
i don't know why
small changes in that
alignment
should produce light poisoning like that
or not i
i can't intuit that
um
offhand so that's really confusing
and a bit troubling i mean it may just
be that you know when we go fix whatever
other bugs we have that just goes away
because it's actually just a product of
uh one of the other things that we
haven't
sort of debugged yet
but if it does actually have to do with
how they're aligned
i don't quite understand why that would
be
um
so that's a bit weird right i i don't
understand why that would be because the
spatial grid is derived from the atlas
grid so they're always these two are
always going to be aligned so the
lighting system in theory
the part that i'm not intuiting as to
why this would make a difference is it
shouldn't really matter like where i
slide the lighting
alignment if i move it just a little bit
in one direction why would that change
the like
feedback
uh
properties of it right
it doesn't really make good sense to me
um it's possible that it's totally fine
and it's just related to something else
like we know the light the lighting is
busted
um and we have to debug it so it could
be that that's just
that's just an artifact of
the bustedness
but i don't know it's a bit confusing to
say the least
um
so anyway i'm gonna leave that in there
for now because i think the more bugs we
have the better in this case because
uh the sort of more obvious the failure
of the lighting the hopefully easier it
will be to find those bugs
um i love that light leaking over time
it looks super cool um
unfortunately we would rather have that
happen when we want it to happen and not
when we don't uh but you know what are
you gonna do
anyway uh so let's
let's uh
nerf that out now
uh and let's start talking about uh how
we want to look at these values
uh a little bit more closely
so
you know
um
so i guess i would start
with the observation
that there is very clearly
that's just really strange
so i think we're just sampling
directions wrong i mean honestly i think
that's mostly what's happening you can
see that here it's like oh you know
everybody seems to suddenly be able to
see the light source
um
in one case and nobody can see it in the
other and that strikes me as just a
sampling issue
uh
so i feel like we probably just have a
sample direction issue here where we're
not really sampling the sample
directions the way that we think we are
um
and so i think what i'll start with is
now that we can like i'm gonna go back
to debug draw
um octahedral values and i'm gonna put
back in the
thing that draws like the actual
octahedral map
uh so that we can see those and now that
i know that i can crank my debug line
count up a bunch um i should be fine to
see them all right
so what i'd like to do now is just these
are these are our little kind of like i
don't know if those of you remember like
those little koosh balls
right like they were they were like um
you remember these things
they were like
all the rage for a little while
uh in like the 19 early 90s maybe
um
i want to say
maybe
uh
so
like the koosh ball
is is effectively what we're drawing
here right we're drawing a little koosh
ball
um and the koosh ball shows us what the
lighting is in any particular direction
from one of these light probes so it
gives us a way of sort of trying to
figure out what the heck is going on
because it's hard with lighting
um it's easy to debug an individual
raycast or something which is the you
know something we're going to want to do
for sure because we may find that our
raycast is just busted or something like
that right so when you start small it's
easy to debug an individual raycast but
then it starts to get kind of harder
when you talk about just like okay is
the light transport sensible right now
or not or you know various things like
this
so if we take a look at the little koosh
ball it kind of helps us a little to
figure out what's going on um and we can
sort of see in certain cases i think i
would like to turn on the voxel cells
um so draw spatial grid
um i'm gonna say like let's let's draw
part of the spatial grid and not the
other part so this is just like me going
you know what don't draw the actual like
occluders and stuff i don't want to see
those
um let's just draw the cell boundaries
just so i can see where they are
so here are like the cells they're drawn
inset slightly only slightly
um so they you know there's not actually
a gap between them but they're just
drawn that way so you can see them a
little more clearly
uh and if you look you can kind of see
like some nonsensical stuff here right
you can see that these particular koosh
balls got basically no lighting
even though these got tons of lighting
so some fairly nonsensical things
going on
and what we determined for
these sort of blatant ones here
um and in fact i guess i can turn this
on temporarily so you can see it
although it just becomes too much
unfortunately to really parse hopefully
you can see it if i narrate it
um
what you can see here is that actually
these
are inside lights so there's a you see
how there's a light that moves with the
hero's head here
right
um
and and you know what you can see a
pretty obvious bug there too
like
why does that
not update now
like what's going on
so there's some pretty weird stuff
happening right you can see how strange
this is so i mean it's kind of good news
right i mean it's never good news that
you have a bug but it's always good news
if the bug is blatant because it gives
us a better chance of finding it right
lighting can be real like you see what
happened there
those were black as i hopped through
them which is what you would expect to
have happen with that if it's enclosed
right like you can see it's entirely
enclosed there
um
but that one that's now entirely
enclosed
because we available it right in order
to go down to this new 2d uh sort of
flat plain version that we're doing
and so
i think we just want to start there and
work our way up from the raycast because
i think the raycast might just plain be
broken
that's my guess because it does make
sense that these things inside the light
are registering as black because we do
have code that does that it does not
make sense why they're not registering
as black
consistently so that is
wrong you know what i mean
ah um
so the heroes lightbox sometimes red and
sometimes green
uh the reason for that is just to make
it easier to see which node it's in i
mean easier to see and this is kind of a
laughable thing to say because there's
too many boxes but what what's happening
there is just that
if you look at the spatial partition i
colored it so that there's cyan and
magenta
alternating
right
um and so when you turn off
like let's turn off the
the non-occluders so the the actual
spatial grid will now go away
and this is just the occluders what i
did is i colored the occluders based on
which cells they were in just so you can
see alternating cell boundaries so as
the hero's light source moves between
cell boundaries it will be cyan when
it's inside a cyan boundary
like in that case or it will be magenta
when it's inside a magenta boundary and
when it moves between the two you can
actually see
that the it will be clipped so half will
be magenta and half will be cyan because
it's in two different nodes
at once and in fact if we do i think we
have a thing here i don't even remember
where it is
uh in like a time there's like a way to
slow the time step down
so if i if i really slow the time step
down um so that i can hop the hero like
really slowly
you can actually see what i'm talking
about here so like
you see how there's like two boxes
you know what i'm saying
so basically the the coloration here
doesn't show any state information
it's purely just telling you
what node things got sorted into
and currently like to the best of my
visual ability given that this isn't the
world's best visualization but
to the extent that i can parse it um
it sure looks
fine like the spatial partition looks
correct i don't see any obvious
indication that the spatial partition is
wrong
maybe i'll slow this down a little bit
here
so as you move things such as the hero's
light source around the spatial
partition um even when the spatial
partition is sliding like it is now or
doing things it looks pretty much right
like like i don't see any evidence that
things are getting sorted wrong um or
that boxes aren't clipping properly into
the spatial partition or any of that
stuff it all actually looks like
a-okay
right
so it looks to me like the place to
start is the raycaster the raycaster
looks like we probably broke it um and
that makes perfect sense because it was
pretty crazily optimized like because
because that was the part we were just
trying to figure out how fast we could
make it
run uh it makes sense right uh oh heroin
wants to
suggest something in line 152
line 152.
the first factor be s y times 16 times
eight
do you mean this one right here
by the way
um
this one
okay
um
i don't believe so
but again we haven't looked at this
closely so just to explain where that
number comes from
so when we compute the lighting table
we have this thing called light sample
directions per octahedron which is 64.
right
um
so i don't think so
because this is already
this is already the number it should be
right like it's 64.
you know what i'm saying
i don't know where you got 16 times 8
from
so if you really think it should be 16
times 8
then then that's not what it is it's
actually 8 times 8 at the moment right
but assuming that you meant eight times
eight
it does
that is what that factor is it's baked
into here
um
i don't know if that answers the
question
but like i said this stuff we need to go
look at so
this may be wrong i don't think what
you're talking about is wrong
but then again
like i said this kind of needs to now be
updated because we really kind of
changed dramatically what it was doing
and so this was highly optimized for the
case that we had because we needed to to
take some performance analysis of it so
we didn't really have a choice
and now we're kind of changing some of
those assumptions so some of something
it could very well be wrong i i'm not
i'm just saying why i don't think what
you were saying
is wrong
based on my current
analysis of how this is working but that
is far from final right um does that
make sense
yeah it's a it's a bit weird because the
outside there's a loop outside here over
eight things and a loop inside here over
eight things and what's actually
happening is the stride here
is
is getting picked up by
this um
and this might this part might be wrong
um
right here
let me think about that
no i think that's right so so basically
what you're doing right is you're saying
here's the sample direction table it was
built basically wrong because it was
built for the old way we were looping
over these but we don't really want to
go change that right now i mean we could
but you know we didn't so we're still
using the same lookup and the old lookup
used to be
you would loop over all the sys and all
the sx's so it was an sy sx loop
for one octahedron which is 64 things
what we're doing now is taking one sl
one octahedron which is 64 things going
into a random row of it based on what
the outside loop tells us to do and then
going over eight of those so we're
effectively like doing eight and then
skipping
64 minus eight like we're going 64
forward after having done eight in that
location going so far forward and doing
eight there does that make sense and the
reason we're doing that is because the
table was made for the other the table
was made for octahedral index being the
outer index
sy being the middle index and sx being
the interior index and we flipped
sy and octahedron now we're doing all
the octahedrons for one sy
right
so if we built the table now and like i
said when i when we went over this code
actually said this and i mean it we
should rebuild the table to actually be
in the other order where
s y and uh sx
octahedralines are sorted so that we go
s y
first
then
octahedron then
sx that's the actual order we want right
um because we update rows of the map at
a time
and then inside the rows of the map we
want to cast lots of rays for each
column
and we weren't set up to do that before
hopefully that explains a little bit
does it um
about how this is working
yeah it's it's non-intuitive
specifically because the table was built
for the old way of doing it and we are
trying to not update the table right now
but
this is not how you want it to look you
want it to look the way you were just
saying so the reason that they don't
match up is very specifically because
of that weirdness right
so
so anyway
uh
unfortunately i mean unfortunately i
think this is probably still correct
though right um i would like it to be
wrong because then it would just be like
something that maybe would cause the
problem but i don't actually think it's
wrong right now but but hold that
thought because again
we have not really done a good pass over
this to make sure that that's true so it
still could just be wrong i just gave
you the explanation of why i think it's
right at the moment but that could just
be complete bs and when we actually look
a little bit closer we'll find that in
fact actually no right
all right
so uh getting back to the raycast itself
i think what we want to do now is try to
actually get some kind of verification
that the raycast is working at all
because it's entirely possible that when
we
change the computation of the walk table
let's say then we just completely broke
it like it could be that the raycasting
is just not working anymore one of the
problems with some of the lighting
is it's really hard to see errors like
when we're looking at it
we can see that
that it's probably not right but it's
just such a subtle like lighting is such
a subtle thing
that although we can tell it's probably
not perfect
we can't tell how it's broken we just
kind of
see that it doesn't quite look right but
it's like
your brain doesn't have a lot of
intuition when it looks at something
like lighting unless it's just
completely bonkers where you just get
complete nonsense
and your brain's like oh like there's
nands in there or something right you
know what i mean
um
when you get to this point where you're
like well it's probably not working but
it kind of still does look like lighting
the problem we have is
you you're just nothing's going to jump
out at you right like you're not going
to look at something you're like oh it's
probably x right
so we need to do now is kind of go into
a more detailed analysis of like maybe
some test cases like pick some isolated
particular places to cast rays from and
see what the raycast result does
because we probably just have some
fundamental bug in like the raycast
right where we're we're actually just
you know stepping through the grid wrong
so that rays are fairly arbitrary and
incoherent or something like this we
probably have something going on like
that and so if we have something going
on like that that helps us understand
what the heck um
it will help us understand what the heck
is going on by isolating some cases what
i would like to do um at the moment is
ask the question
what the heck is going on in here right
uh so
so this part
i mean you can see some some oddity
you can see some oddity here
this code when we do full cast
is
basically saying
all right
find out if you are inside if one of
these
lighting nodes
is inside
a
leaf of the spatial partition
and it looks like what we do in that
case is actually not to write black into
it but to actually write nothing into it
and so that means that the thing that i
saw when i was like hopping along and i
was like oh that seems wrong
actually the thing that was wrong is the
thing i thought was right meaning when
we hopped over something and it did
change to black that actually is the
thing that doesn't make sense because
according to this we don't update those
values they just stay the same
so i think the first thing i might
suggest
is if we look at how this code works uh
in the sy iterator for uh
writing these textuals
i might add something here that the
moment will just be for debug but
eventually we'll want to actually do
something here
where we loop over these spec texels and
you can see here us like doing a write a
read modify write on the spec texels
what i want to do here is to just say
maybe we
are going to just write
like black
so here you know eventually
we will uh or you know what we could
even do something fancier than that we
could write
magenta right um
let me take a look at our
uh
on our sim decode here
i assume we have something for loads yet
so let's let's do a magenta thing
right
if we wanted to write out magenta to
each of these slots it's a little bit
squeaky uh the way that that works
because they're they're
we're writing out
times 6 24
right
we're writing out 24 but it's actually
three times eight
so it's
first color goes here second color spans
these two
right
makes sense then we're uh
back
here
uh and that's one pack
right
so it's
color a you know color zero
color
one
color two
color three for a pack of four
um
and then it just repeats again so i can
actually just use the same pattern
uh but this will just cold right magenta
to directly into these slots
for the spec texel
and
that will let us see what we actually
think is interior and what we don't so
when we run this
right
here is our purple
magic purple set
um and what you can see here is actually
that's just totally correct so that
piece of code is is
is definitely working right
right
so that thing we saw where it was going
to black before was like another bug
right that's like another buggy thing
um that's happening there i also
this weird like strobing effect that you
see there that should really not be
occurring so that
that also feels like our copy is busted
like we've got a lot of broken stuff
right so i think it's
this is actually not that bad it just
means that when we did this sort of like
adjustment we definitely broke stuff
just like we thought we would
and hopefully as we work through it and
remove those bugs that that'll be the
end of it right it'll just be
it'll be correct so you can kind of see
the what's happening um
here
this looks like we kind of had a bug in
general that we didn't know about
originally in our lighting code though
we never really thought about the fact
that lights would fall into that uh
region and so we you know you can see
here those are the sources of light they
were actually getting set to black which
is totally wrong
um before i mean they wouldn't be set to
black but they would not be picking up
light from their actual local light
source like they should have been
so we we actually kind of found a bug
there that we never really addressed in
the original version as well so we'll
this will actually be better in that way
too because we'll come up with a
solution for that like allowing casting
uh allowing it to do a gather
um when it's inside
uh in some way you know or another right
uh on clan sweeney i totally agree with
that comment
all right uh so this is good and i think
i might leave this in here for now uh we
can turn it on and off at will so you
know maybe
while we're debugging some of the other
things in the lighting uh we can set
this uh to off if we want to
we can also sort of have it set to on
but have a choice of what happens here
so we can do
like a
[Music]
something more like this
where we just clear everything so
everything is going to go to black now
um which will probably be more useful
for debugging the lighting so it's not
leading to magenta bleed into everything
um so if we clamp the black values to
black now
and we can probably turn off the spatial
partition because you know maybe we'll
turn it on again from time to time
but we can more or less turn off that uh
rendering because at the moment
it looks totally that looks totally
right it just it appears to be
um
where's our octahedral value oh i'm in
the wrong piece of code there we go
uh
it looks like the spatial partition is
always creating the correct actual
partition
we are just looking up into it
incorrectly or something like that right
so i don't think we need to draw that at
the moment
um as far as i can tell either
so looking now at this
we should be able to now start focusing
on
yeah like exactly what you expect and
you can see like just looking at the
koosh ball display
you can see like
some pretty obvious indications that
things are wrong here
like it doesn't really make a lot of
sense what we're seeing in in these
uh
in these koosh balls anyway i mean
you wouldn't like why is there an
equivalent amount of light coming from
the left of this
um
and the right of this
when pretty clearly more light sources
are over here on this side right that
doesn't really make a lot of sense
there's no light coming from over here
um
that we know of and we similarly like we
have no idea what's producing this weird
green light out here right
probably something to do with
out of bounds fetching incorrectly or
something so you know we've we've got
issues right
uh and like i said that's not really a
bad thing
uh because the more pronounced they are
the easier they're gonna be for us to
know if we found them
you know
uh so all right
so moving on um
the looking at the koosh
uh i want to take a look at this uh at
the quadrant
stuff
and i want to think about
what we're actually seeing
um
quadrant rise so we've got this thing
that does a quadrant index
right uh
we look up into the lighting walk table
and i don't actually know
uh where we where we actually compute
that or i should say allocate that
in here we
we grab you know the sample direction
table
we
we have the sample direction table
from
the uh from the inl file
it's this thing
uh and it's gonna be that
the the light sample directions for
octahedron right this this whole thing
you know what i mean
so we have the sample direction table
and we index into that based on
where we are
uh
which direction we're heading out of the
cell
and then interior to that
we have the quadrants
right so when we do compute walk table
we
pick these xy quadrants they used to be
octans now they're quadrants
uh because the resolution of the spatial
grid is half that of the actual sampling
of lighting because we just found that
we weren't having enough
occluders in there
right
um
uh
yes greg
greg inc that's exactly right um
another way to say it would be
the more blatant an error is the easier
it is to find
and so the worst thing is if you have
like a really subtle error one that you
that is causing perception like it like
you can see that the lighting is not
quite
as good as you think it should be but
but it's like you really can't find any
obvious reasons why like it's not like
oh there's blatant you know here's this
obviously grotesque error right
because it really doesn't give you any
idea where to look you know what i mean
um
you
the the more like pronounced an error is
the happier you usually are
and the more subtle or
rare an error is
the scarier it is because you're like
the harder it is to see this thing occur
the less likely i am going to be able to
find it right you know like it just
keeps getting harder and harder to track
the less of a trail it leaves right
now the bad news is
we probably also have subtle errors in
the lighting because you almost always
do
so
these ones that we're looking at now are
going to be easy ones to find and then
after they're gone
the bad news is there's probably also
subtle ones so
it's not quite the same as saying yay we
only have
you know blatant errors it's more like
i'm happy to be working on the blatant
errors now because i more or less know
we're going to have not so blatant ones
later and those are going to be bad
right that makes some sense
hopefully that like uh you know
clarifies that a little bit right
um subtle errors are the worst by far
by far i mean they're so bad that
sometimes you don't even know you have
them right that's the that's the real
thing
um if an error doesn't appear
to you like you you don't think you
don't even know it's there that's the
worst kind because then you know it
crops up later
uh on like a end user's machine or
something right um so it's like ah right
so so usually you really really hope
that your bugs are bad like they have
bad obvious effects that occur on your
machine
and in a reliable way because you have a
really good chance of finding those in a
reasonable amount of time
and the opposite is not true like the
subtle bugs
i
you know
where you can't really tell is the
lighting yeah it kind of feels like it's
a little wrong you know that kind of
stuff that's just the worst because you
know then you're really talking about
having to be extraordinarily meticulous
and you have to add all of this
infrastructure to try and like
okay can we you know corroborate these
values with some other system and you
know it just it becomes really difficult
so so you usually are very happy in
something like lighting anyway usually
very happy if something's obviously
wrong that's that's like a way better
situation than when just got that
sinking feeling it's like it doesn't
feel like it's quite right
a lot harder
anyway uh so when we do our walk table
computations here uh with the remainder
stuff i want to see if those are getting
computed properly
in the grid raycast or if i at least
think they are right i i want to just do
a quick check to see how those are
actually getting computed
so like
the remainder
is getting pushed down
by full cast i think
so basically what happens is the outer
code uh that calls
full cast
um
that code is stepping through the voxel
for sampling
and at each point in the voxel for
sampling
we know that we're in whatever quadrant
is like
the
you know the the truncation
of atlas index the the like ending of
the bottom bit if you will so like x is
like
uh zero quadrant one quadrant zero quad
one quadrant of x and y is like zero
quadrant one quadrant zerocoin as we
step through
so when we do
this
atlas index
when we pass the atlas index in here uh
we divide it by two to know
where we would be in the spatial
partition
and we are basically using the remainder
to know what the
quadrant is that we're in
now
the problem
with that
uh is that
we should verify
that it still works out to be the
correct partition
this atlas to spatial grid index offset
that presumably is like one one zero or
whatever right
um
let's find out if that's actually true
yeah
um
so it skips one spatial grid because in
you know there's an apron
uh in the spatial partition that
basically says like if you're inside
this apron you're
you're outside of where we're sampling
lighting so just stop your you know stop
your search right
um
so that offset prevents you from being
in the apron and the other part here
this half atlas index
uh is the part that says where you
actually are inside it
uh
drawing this seems good like if we
should probably draw the raycast to make
sure that it's picking the correct
spatial index
um so we'll have to test that out in a
second
uh but anyway so
then when we loop through here and we
look to see whether we're in things i
feel like the initial
like the initial grid index computation
so this computation
kind of has to be correct because if it
wasn't correct
this code wouldn't work and we kind of
verified that it did like if you look
at where
um
the
blacked out koosh balls are
they're exactly correct like i don't see
any error there at all period right
um
i do see errors in shifting so like this
that when we slide that just looks
totally wrong
those that should not be happening
right so our copy like when we
uh
when the lighting so this
that slide
does not work properly
um
so we definitely have to debug this
slide and that's fine that's just the
block copy operation
um
but
the actual spacer facial partition
lookup appears completely correct
like i don't see any indication of it
being wrong
so i think we can safely eliminate this
particular part where we compute the
initial grid index
that seems to be correct now is the
quadrant index computed correctly i
suppose it could be wrong
but we at least know that the initial
index isn't wrong so maybe the quadrant
in this could be wrong
i don't know um we'll have to see
but this part seems correct
all right
so looking into grid raycast and compute
walk table these have to agree because
basically compute walktable is just
precomputing what gridcast would have
done
had we figured out which steps to take
directly rather than building a table
for them
so when we
look uh
at how the table is laid out
hmm
um
i'll be completely honest i'm not really
sure exactly how this is working so i
may want to go look
at walk table entry here i guess well
okay so i guess i see what's happening
but i um
yeah so
this is a little bit squirrely
so you can kind of see how this is
packed in here we've got the lighting
table and for each of the entries into
the lighting table we are storing four
different tables one for each quadrant
which makes perfect sense right that's
fine
um
but
uh
and and you can see too here like you
can see why
it would make sense for us to compute to
be able to compute this on the fly which
we might now be able to do
i'm not sure how much it would cost
to you know we did the analysis before
when it was octants and in 3d but it
might be different now there's quadrants
in 2d
you can see why this is annoying because
when we actually look at what the
quadrants are
um it it limits our ability to change
the spatial
partition's relative size
to the uh
to the um
to the sampling
if it's computed on the fly
we don't have that problem
if it's pre-computed
if it's pre-computed we do have that
problem because pre-computation involves
storing a table the more
uh offsets you can be at inside the
spatial audition the more tables we have
to store you know what i'm saying
so i do think computing this on the fly
would be better
if we can now get away with it which
it's possible that we would be able to
because it would just be a very simple
we could do a very simple breslin ham
uh that just does xy right uh so it only
has to do like
it would be it would be branchless
um
and it's fairly simple
maybe the skylake can figure it out okay
you know we don't really don't know
so anyway uh i feel like we should
probably try that i just don't want to
do that yet because uh with so many bugs
in play we don't want to be changing yet
another thing so i want to first get
that working with the table and then
swap it to dynamic uh also that way we
can see if we take a bad speed hit for
switching it to dynamic
um
or maybe we could even get a speed
improvement now you know who knows how
that uh cost has has switched
so in here what we're effectively doing
is saying well there's going to be a
quadrant offset which we compute by just
looping over the four quadrants that
there would be
uh and the starting location uh puts
sort of a cell dimension
you know it puts us a quarter of a cell
dimension in
um
to start with and then it goes a half
cell dimension
from there
uh
i mean i that seems like that would
always be correct
and again we don't care about z anymore
so we're just only talking about x and y
um
so it seems like that would always be
proper
i mean that seems correct to me
i don't know maybe it's not
but anyway we go through the sample
directions here we pull them out and we
do the
walk um
we do an over complicated thing here
because it used to do all three
dimensions so you can see it kind of
doing more probably than it needs to
um
really in this case
and then uh yeah we just you can see us
had so we had some debug cases in here
we were doing before they're still here
um
we
pretty much just do what you would
expect and we choose
which uh
you know which
one of these we want based on whichever
the best dimension was you know at the
time this is the delta this is like
where how you'd step through it right
um
and i don't really see
i don't see anything particularly
suspicious
in here
yeah i can't see anything suspicious
like that just all looks pretty
reasonable right um
there's nothing there's nothing
particularly
so one thing that's a little odd is so
the way that t terminate works here
um
[Music]
not actually sure i understand
uh
i guess that just prevents us from
casting rays particularly far
right
um
i i don't
actually know
in grid raycast i assume we just
don't go further than that
you can see here like whenever we end
we just do
and you know this is interesting so when
we get to a terminator like if we cast
outside
um
you can see here
us doing the like sample out of there uh
that may also be part of the reason we
get that light leaking you'll have to
think about that whether this is
actually
what you want or not but
um either way so that t terminates just
there so that we do gathers if you know
things that are far away we don't just
keep casting for other forever
uh we do gathers on those
uh
so i guess i would say like i just don't
see
i don't see any obvious uh places in the
code where it's wrong so i think the the
thing we want to do now
is go in there and
try to draw
one particular raycast i don't know
uh
what the best way to pick
a raycast direction would be
but
you know
at startup
at startup i would say
you know
this seems kind of implausible anyway
probably
um
you know i think we could probably just
do at startup we could do a cast
and we'll pick one that happens to be
close to the hero or something and just
look at what it looks like because
most of the area seems wrong like most
of the lighting seems sort of subtly
wrong at least
so probably we can go from there let's
make sure before i start this that the
walk table stuff actually does make
sense
when you look at the light sampling walk
table
and you look up the quadrant index there
i wanted to see like in the lighting
solution itself how exactly
was this yeah so so this here
um
the light sampling walk table here
has an index value of eight it doesn't
need to do that anymore right it's only
four now
um
but other than that i mean that was just
extra space that's not being used other
than that it's fine
um it's exactly
you know it's used exact same way just
the the top four entries aren't used so
you know it doesn't actually need to be
there
um
and the way this is getting indexed is
exactly how we would expect it looks up
the quadrant index
it offsets it by whatever the walk table
offset thinks it should be
um at that point to produce the you know
for for this particular array direction
and then it just uses that walk table
entry
uh from then on
and that seems correct
so it's like we left in some of this
test code here as well too for like
things like checking boundaries so
that's kind of good it's not turned on
right now
but
that doesn't let us do some
some further testing so you can see here
like the very simple update that we're
doing as well
all seems normal
um
i guess i don't quite see how
t-terminate is working here
why is t-terminate written differently
per step
does that make any sense
i that that seems a little
weird like why do we need to update to
terminate per step
like wouldn't you just
i guess we're just doing that as a
convenience feature so that you just
look that up in the table so you don't
have to pull it yourself so when you get
to a terminate
um
like when cost metric drops below zero
you just use whatever that termination
position was and off you go i guess
how does cost metric get updated
interesting
so we actually had our cost metric
our cost metric is just
weighted by how many
leaves you tested
what an interesting dynamic condition
i don't know if that was really smart or
really weird but
i like it
so
that value might be
a bit low
as well
right
like
that's a really
kind of conservative value like only
eight squares of testing
um and i can see why we may have done
that before because we were trying to
optimize things but that that may also
just be kind of
not necessary right
um
so i don't know what we want to do about
that
uh i don't know how flexible we are here
like like if we wanted to do more than
that number
how would we feel about it
like it still seems pretty stable in
terms of frame rate so i don't think
that cost was too particularly bad right
um
like like it's worse right you can see
it's definitely worse it's more like a
30 frames per second but it's also
drawing a bunch of debug stuff
you know what i mean
um
we need a way of ha we probably should
have a thing where we we do an actual
test that doesn't have to do you know
that doesn't need debug stuff in it
right but
yeah so
you know that that value could stand to
be a lot higher and i suspect we
probably want it to be a lot more like
16 now that the lighting is pretty fast
because i feel like it wasn't much light
transport before if it's if it's only
doing eight i don't know it's hard to
say though um
it's good to know like i'm glad we know
that number is there and that we can
change it to something else because
you know we'll see but at the moment i
guess i would say
you know who knows so
i'm gonna put a to do in there because
you know
let's tune this value in the future
maybe it should be more than eight
um because that's pretty conservative
that's basically saying you're only
going to search through eight cells
and if any of those eight cells were
like complicated and had like two or
three leaves then it's even less like
maybe it's more like five cells that
you're going to search through
and since the gather is kind of bucket
brigade like it's still going to sample
from where the for where the ray ends
um
[Music]
it's not like the lighting doesn't still
transport over distances but it
transports more slowly right
at the on the other hand it does reduce
the error that's introduced in casting
rays particularly far because they start
being fairly they're not very dense in
terms of how they're sampled
so it is
hard to say what this correct value
should be maybe having it low is
actually good
it could also be that we want to stop
doing a cost analysis and just do a
distance
you know there's a lot of ways we want
to think about this so i would say we'll
you know want to talk about that a
little bit more um
so that's gonna need a little more work
for sure
okay
so
let's
try
to
[Music]
get more
sane here let's try to to to get a
little bit more in the weeds
so
when we actually do our raycast we have
a bunch of things that help us draw what
actually happens during the raycast
so i think what we need to do is kind of
re-enable those right
when we pass down the debugging thing
here
uh
we you can see us kind of doing some
debug
drawing right
um
here's us showing like
what we were looking at and what we were
con testing against
right
so
uh
yeah
i i guess
i guess we just probably want that to be
turned back on and i would say we
probably want this to be like a pound to
find
um so they don't have to like
go through all of these
conditions manually and turn them on and
off
so we probably just want to say like
look if we're debugging
um oh i forgot about this age comp
we yeah we do someday need to figure out
whether that h-comp is a good idea
at the moment nobody knows
right
got a lot of little like
notes about probable bugs in here maybe
our bugs are in some of those routines
all right
um now we don't really know uh which one
of these we want to debug but it
shouldn't be that hard for us to figure
out you know what i mean
um
we have some kind of a
complaint here with wrecked center damn
looks like there's
is rect center dim
it's two v threes
is probe sample piece single maybe not
the right kind of value
yeah so the problem is probe samples we
we updated this code now pro sample
piece single is is really ray origin
packed
comes in directly it looks like
um
that that puts ray origin single in
there so i wonder if maybe that
value needs to be
replaced with with rare origin single
i'm not sure
what it actually wants to do so
it's taking probe sample piece single
ray origin single
it's really just that probe sample piece
single so the probe sample piece single
looks like it it's never really single
anymore like we probably just didn't
update the name
right
but it's always computed packed
now
and you can kind of see like
this does the entire sample
you know we we compute the the
coordinates off of this thing
although to be honest i don't totally
understand what this is trying to do
like this is
this is wide but it's always still just
a scalar value like you could extract
any given one of these and it would work
right
so i don't know my assumption here is
that we can just extract this like
we can just do like
any component of probe p single
is what we want to draw here
i think
uh we'll find out
right
um
although i guess we can't
it's not a get component because they're
packed in like xyz
so
now
um
i guess we need to do
this makes sense
so we just need to turn them into sort
of the scalar version for use with the
debug routines and i think that's mostly
what we're talking about here
um
and this is like you know
actually e
zero one two
well they might be i don't really
remember what we how these worked out
yeah no it's e
so that's kind of a pain but you know
whatever it's just a piece of debug code
so we don't really care
so with debugging turned on
we should now be able to
send down
a request to
debug
something
in the grid raycast here
it's a little
difficult to
figure out how we're going to handle
this because we're doing eight rays at a
time
so which one of these is going to be the
one that you debug is a little bit
confusing
but presumably it just does the first
ray in the set
i guess we could try to make something
that allows you to select a sub ray out
of that
but
at the moment we'll just do the first
one
problem is it could be that the first
one is correct and other ones are wrong
because we're stepping through this
table incorrectly so we probably will
need to do something where we pick a
particular one right so like in here we
turn on debugging based on which one of
this like what the actual octahedral
sample versus you know
and ray sample we do one particular one
of those to pluck out a particular value
so uh you know like that might be a
little bit
uh of an issue for sure
[Music]
um but we'll see so inside full cast
here what we want to be able to do
is send down a debug value here like
debug true
at some point
um and
i guess because we know what the atlas
index is
like
i think this code is probably what we
want more or less
it's just
kind of old right so
if we put this
uh in here
it's really atlas index
x
atlas index y
and atlas index z and they want to all
equal something like whichever the debug
value is that we're looking for right so
it's like oh it's you know
it's some particular one of these
who knows what
uh and then debug this
gets
sent down
as
you know in this grid
raycast here or whatever
um
it looks like this one
you know i'm not sure why these two are
separate
maybe this was not one we actually care
about at the moment it's really this one
um that we care about right so
like that
uh
then when this gets called here we just
need to update the sy here will just be
let's say zero because that's the debug
that's the sy we're gonna debug
the
rest of this looks a little off so the
initial grid index
and then the quadrant index so basically
like this
because we changed this around
um
looks like that
and
this will allow us to do a debug pass on
whatever we set solution debug grid
index to be right
so in here debug grid index
is
currently set to some random thing
right
um
and debug ray index i don't know where
that
gets used by anybody
that's
i guess that's what tries to determine
which one of these we're going to do
yeah so these are done internal
right now so
that's kind of a problem because
so although this value we can pull out
the correct thing
um
for ty
tx is handled internal now so that's not
gonna cut it right
now we could pass these values down
which maybe is what we want to do like
instead of debug there's like an actual
debug like packet that you pass down
that has this information in it i don't
know
um
so yeah i think we may have to kind of
like update the way we do this a little
maybe we make a little debug bundle that
has like exactly what you're trying to
debug you pass that down and you go from
there
um okay
so so i think this maybe is not so
useful
um
[Music]
i'm gonna get rid of this because i
don't think we care about that anymore
uh yeah
um so this should draw a raycast i
believe uh and we'll see but i believe
it will draw one raycast
but we have to actually pick which one
we want it to be because we have no idea
which of these raycasts it's actually
going to draw
and maybe i will like turn off some of
this other debugging now just so i can
see it a little bit better
because we actually also don't know like
where it is at the moment so maybe i'll
turn off the octahedral values
and
we'll see if we can find out where
that's going to be also we probably
should try to set it maybe that there
aren't that many of those
in the world that we may have it set to
a value that we never actually get to
because we reduced the number
dramatically
when we got rid of the z slices
so probably the
the actual
debug
this is probably too high
in fact
yeah it's 24 by 16 by two
so like
um
if we look at how many of these there
actually are
let me
just launch speed crunch there
24 by 16 by two
is 768 and this is set to 717 right um
so it's like
gonna be
like one of the last things off in the
corner like up here or something like
that
um
so
you know we
it may even be like in an apron or
something so
let's try setting this down a little bit
and then let's try like you know i don't
know whatever this is going to be
um
and we'll set debug ray index to zero or
something
and we'll kind of go from there
all right
um
so i don't see it though so let's step
through the code and see we may just
never we we may have a bug where we're
not actually triggering that code path
right
so let's go ahead and take a look at
that actually also
the other thing i would say is
we probably want that grid debug
grid lighting thing
to control the
the outer code as well so we you know
in the code where we did
if grid raycast debugging that probably
wants to be like a pound defined that's
up at the top of the code or maybe like
in here
or something to control
this
because
we want that grid raycast debugging
control to also happen to happen
uniformly so that the calling code
enables right like this code here wants
to enable at the same time
um
that's my story and i'm sticking to it
so then uh when this code sort of does
its thing we should at least see this
stuff running so it's a bit weird that
we don't and i don't really know why
that would be so let's go ahead and set
it to debug mode and find out like why
we don't ever seem to actually get
uh any stepping
like like why are we not seeing those
little steps in there and i don't know
so in the lighting code here
let's make sure this is running
correctly
so here's the debug build doing whatever
the debug build is doing
and then if i go down to that code
inside full cast
which is right here
you know
does this ever run
so
solution
[Music]
debug grid index is 200
initial grid index here
like
just is never 200
is that what we're learning
that sure seems to be the case
so am i
when we did the light look up voxel dim
am i misunderstanding what the actual
dimensions are that we step over
and if so that's a pretty bad mistake on
my part because that means i don't
understand how the actual light
propagation code like it should be
stepping over those total values right
[Music]
like
what's the deal so let's take a look at
atlas index
so these numbers we would expect to
range however voxel dim has ranged which
is exactly what i looked up right i mean
the number that i did was 24 times 16
times two
right
um oh
nope i'm wrong
so
actually
grid index is the spatial partition and
the spatial partition is only half that
so the spatial partition is actually 12
times 8 times 1.
so there's hardly anything in the
spatial partition there's hardly
much of a spatial partition at all right
which is weird
again sort of suggests that as we've
collapsed this down to 2d i mean there
could be situations where there's lots
of things involved but it's starting to
feel like maybe
for this ray casting you want
much coarser
than we're using because now we're not
using z and blah blah so you know
we'll cross that bridge when we come to
it but
so all right that's fine
um
[Music]
oops uh
debug grid index
let's try something much more
conservative like 30.
um
and now we are finally in the debug code
thankfully so that's good news
and
yeah
that's just good news
um so now we should be able to see it uh
i mean hopefully i don't know if that's
actually true
but we also might want to run it in
in o2
because debug
builds are not fast enough for lighting
at the moment everything else is fast
enough but not
that uh so now we just want to figure
out if we can see it it looks like it's
now like like hey there's
there's the uh the debug right um where
it's where it's doing some casting
and
uh
you know
if i had to say
i would say that's pretty wrong like
exactly what i think is happening seems
to be happening which is that this code
is kind of busted so
[Music]
uh let's try to move this into position
i don't we
i think we actually have a weird way of
doing that um that we put in here that's
kind of ridiculous
um like
right there was like a
this thing
so
we can actually move it to like
something that's inbounds like that
and we can see
where the actual hit location is
i will say that
hit location is correct right like it
actually did the raycast downward and it
properly picked the floor right
so hey the good news is our debug
visualization is quite good actually so
we're still in a good position there um
i i'll be honest i don't actually
remember what the purple line is we have
to go look at like what that's supposed
to be i have no idea
um but let's go ahead and re-enable this
because this is not really going to work
properly now this purple line
um because it's it's like we don't
we're not properly tracking like which
ray we're trying to cast
so we should probably try to make this
be an actual
you know thing we passed down for
debugging
um
and to do
that i'm going to need
like
debug
ray pick something like that
and in debug ray pic i am going to have
to pass down
like
the
particular index i guess of which ray
you want
um although
yeah i don't know
um
we'll say that there's an enabled and
then in here there's going to be
something like a pic value and i'm not
sure
maybe
um
we do it like this
like
i don't know
um
where you can basically say
which ray out of the eight ray pack and
which octahedron out of the 16
octahedrons that could cast like which
one are you talking about
it's something
i don't know
so if we imagined doing something like
that
then um
[Music]
when we go to do grid raycast then
actually the debug value here is like
like this
um
something like that
uh debugging in this case equals uh
debug pick enabled
right uh something like this
although
um also i don't really know why
these are separate
that doesn't really make a lot of sense
they probably should be together
uh this probably wants to be done
slightly differently it probably wants
to be done like that and then debugging
is actually
deferred to here
where we actually compute this
value
as
something based off of the debug pick
per ray
so in here we would say it's if it's
enabled
and the octahedron index is correct
and the ray index is correct well then
you can have your debugging and in any
other case
you can't
so debug pick octahedron index
you can see i'm just peeling these off
one at a time
debug pick
ray index
um and that way now you can sort of
slice that off and just you know you can
see exactly what you wanted to have
happen
on each individual raycast
um
in the case of here we don't want any
debugging so we can just pass
the the garbage value i i think i might
keep it as a default parameter here
though because
we probably want it to only happen when
grid raycast
is happening in the first place so we
may want to do something like this
um
[Music]
because we don't actually want to pass a
value here at all
um if we're not you know that doesn't
actually need to be there right
so then we have this debug repeat bundle
and we'll pass that along and in here
we're just going to say you know enabled
is obviously true
um octahedral index
equals something
and ray index equals
something right
uh so
we can now pick out which which specific
one we want
but we have sort of this this whole
situation is is probably less than ideal
i'm assuming we would actually want here
is just to have the solution actually
pick out each of these things
and
uh
you know maybe we can clamp each one of
these right um in it in a way as well
i'm gonna need i'm gonna get i'm out of
water here uh which is not great so we
may wanna take a quick break and get
some water
that probably should happen
but whatevs
uh so i pretty much just need to
make this so that we can pick these
more easily and if we
do so so we could probably
just change
the debug pick to maybe just be a pass
through
so like maybe
the grid index
is in here as well it just gets ignored
inside the raycast team but otherwise
it's fine
uh and all of these are like
debug pic dot you know so that's like
debug pic
dot grid index right debug this this
that the other thing
um
that seems like it makes some sense to
me maybe
um
and then the t y value
would be one more thing on here right so
there's like the grid index the s y the
octahedron and the ray and you know each
one of those you could sort of
uh
adjust separately to like pick out each
individual piece of the problem that you
have right
so let's go ahead and implement that but
i would say let's take a quick break
and get some water maybe even a snack is
everyone oh cool with that
maybe
anyone
bueller
you know snack time
yes
everyone says
what in sobot oh my god no in sobot
no
wrong
all right so snack time
uh
take five everybody
take five and do a snack time and we'll
be right back
no i'm not providing the snacks what do
you think this is google we don't have
12 billion dollars of snacks
for all of our
like no you got to provide your own
snacks
[Music]
foreign
bye
[Music]
[Applause]
oh
uh
[Music]
[Applause]
me
foreign
[Music]
be
[Applause]
[Music]
oh
bye
[Music]
[Applause]
um
oh
[Music]
[Applause]
all right hopefully everyone has snacked
up
everyone have their snacks
breakfast of champions
honeycomb cereal
i think we can all agree
they tried to change the formula for
honeycomb cereal and it was awful
and everyone complained so much they
changed it back and i was like thank god
because honeycomb cereal is great but
the new one they tried to change it to
is terrible
absolutely terrible
all right
let's do this so
yes choose the force
i still inhale it as an adult
that's what i'm saying
alright
so we want to be able to set these up
here
uh and now we kind of don't really need
to have this be
constructed here we can probably just
pass this down
uh directly so we can sort of do
something where we we check the grid
index here
and
then we
you know assuming the grid index passes
we just pass the the solution
uh debug pick down directly like so
and uh this
quadrant index value though
um
that's a little harder
because we need to be able to compute
that
right so
we probably want to make sure
that it's the same
like it should be the same quadrant
index that
whatever we computed because we're
checking to see we're on a particular
one we should use the same quadrant
index right
so i think that's okay
um a lot of these values we don't care
about right these are not relevant
anymore
so
like none of this stuff
matters at all
like at all at all
expected direction is kind of nice
we probably want to keep that
um and we still can
because we will know the tx and ty
um
it's basically this and maybe we want to
call it that so we have tx
nty here
like so
maybe that's just a better idea
um
and that way we can pull those values
out as necessary so i don't think we
need like any of this
that's just gone
uh but this we do want so we want to
do our debug pick
tx and rd bug pick ty
um
that seems that seems good and similarly
like that would get you know be that
we would pull it out of out of that
and off we go
so i think that's all good
um
we just have to make sure that
we now actually track those values so
instead of this stuff
like
these two things
we now have a debug ray pic
like this
and then in the places where we were uh
allowing you to edit those before we
need like actual thing to allow you to
pick them differently right
so
um i don't know what this is complaining
about initial greatness uh was there is
there no grid index in that i thought we
put a grid inside in there right yeah we
did
what's the problem
oh it's not a real 3-2 okay well that's
fine
we can fix that a second
that's going to be tx now
okay so i think we're all good
now we just need to make sure that all
this stuff
is reasonable
so we don't really know what we want all
this stuff to be
um
because we don't know what
ones we want to actually debug
but
that's
a question for the next thing we're
going to do
um so we should here be able to do like
okay solution debug pick enabled equals
true
um or maybe it's it's
this raycast debugging like it's enabled
if if we set that to one
i don't know what to do about this part
here
i guess we just say
hey we want to be able to do
each of these values separately so
there's the grid index and the
octahedron index the tx and the ty
and we want them to we want to do each
of them
so have fun
right
all right
so
i guess the first thing we can say is we
already know that like something's wrong
about this uh like like i screwed
something up right and it could just be
the debug stuff because we put it in
there but we noticed this right off the
bat when we first did it
so my understanding is that the ray
direction
which is that yellow line there
um it does seem like the ray direction
is sort of working in some sense meaning
it's going you know and it's doing some
kind of uh an actual ray cast there and
if we go
uh into the lighting control panel here
and we move the grid index around right
um which i guess we don't have for we
should probably that's why i said our
debug system sucks so one of the first
things i said was like we have to
improve the debug system someday
if we change this value to something
over here which i don't remember
what it roughly was
we'll have to have something that allows
you to
pick u32s easier but
um
if we make it something further over
there i mean it doesn't even matter you
can even see the error here
you can see that it's
the expected direction which i believe
is this um
that
line that's that's magenta
it's not going in the direction that we
actually raycast right so that may just
be because we tweak the debug code but
it could also be like hey that's problem
number one like we're casting
we're casting in a different direction
than we think we should be casting
based on the octahedral map's output
direction
right
so first things first
those two things have to line up and
they ain't
if we go
to full cast
you can see where those are getting
drawn
so this
right here
this is saying
for the specular atlas
we have a debug pic tx and a debug pic
ty right
we have to check to make sure that those
don't include the apron
they might
let's double check
it looks like those kind of include the
apron
sort of
like there's a minus one in there
right
so that seems maybe like
this
is actually this like we actually want
to add one
uh because this includes the apron
that's my story and i'm sticking to it
however
uh
doesn't really help because they're
still wrong
you know what i'm saying
uh so
the
the direction we expect
for the xy that we're writing to
is not the direction that is actually
getting cast
and so that's like
i mean problem number one
and you can see us drawing the expected
direction here from the location that we
start we're drawing out the expected
direction
that's the purple line
and then when we do our grid raycast
here
which presumably is slightly wrong
uh when we are drawing this stuff
where we you know do these debug boxes
and
push like sort of the the direct the ray
as it goes uh you can see probably at
the bottom here
we uh we
do like a long ray uh
that's how far we go right
um
this whole thing
is just wrong apparently apparently
right
this
value where we pick a
something out of the sample
table
and we
you know get the direction of it
that direction does not
necessarily match this
now i guess when i think about it that's
okay because this is a direction
straight out of so it doesn't have to be
exactly right i guess so so um
false alarm as long as it appears to
come out the same face of the octahedron
it's fine
right uh i guess is how we would put
that
so that's actually okay i guess now that
i think about it that's that's all right
all right so the next thing we need to
do is make it so that we can
edit those u32 values right in some way
um
and i think our trick for that before
was to say
um
we just make them real 32s because those
were editable
um
i'm not sure how i feel about that but
you know it's probably the wrong time to
go monkeying around in here
uh although we really would like to
improve this debug stuff because it's
terrible right
um
it was high on the list of things to
rip up entirely
but
so where we have
uh editable f32s
um we at the moment
don't have any way to
actually edit those
that is an interesting debug ui i don't
know what that's supposed to be there's
like literally nothing in it
okay
i guess we
don't put anything in that file anymore
um so where we actually edit these in
the debug system here which is like i
said way too complicated for what it
does so simplifying this is is high on
the list of things to do
um but when we actually draw these out
we've got sort of a thing for editing
these
where if it happens to be an f32
we have a way to
edit that but if it's not
we don't right
and
so
you know
when we draw these we track whether you
can hit them and when we do that you
know there's so there's the interact
code here
which i forget exactly where it is but
it's here it is
um you can see like booleans can toggle
r32s can drag
but you know u32s can't do anything at
the moment
so
you can see here if we wanted to we
could have a pretty
difficult to edit because it's not very
good but
you could see having a u32 one and
excuse me
it would just be that
so maybe we allow that to occur
i don't know
um
and or maybe it's just terrible
uh i guess we'll find out
so
not sure why i can't there we go um
so i don't actually know
how we want to deal with d mouse p here
because i'm not sure if that's like
normalized i'm not sure what we keep
those coordinates in
but
mostly we probably just want
this
we probably just want like a sine or
zero
which i guess we don't have
we only have sine of
which is a little unfortunate
right
so i don't know about that but
presumably we just want something more
like this
if it's less than zero
we would ink
if it's greater than zero
sorry
i mean deck
and if it's equal to zero we just don't
do anything
you know what i mean
um and that'll give us crappy editing of
those values
uh right so
you know it's not good
but
it's
it's workable for the immediate moment
um so then if we kind of look at what's
happening here with these casts uh i
guess i can't quite say what i'm looking
at there you can see there's kind of
some weirdness here where
you see like multiple cast values i
don't really know why
right
um and you know we're gonna have to
clamp these values because at the moment
if you go outside of the 16 you would
get a kind of meaningless value but
what's interesting is it it seems like
it's doing kind of weird things where
it's like casting straight down
for some like large number of these um
so i don't know like
i do want to go like get this working
because it looks like there is some
badness going on here
so let me just add a clamp for these and
then we'll kind of walk through them and
see like why is it doing what it's doing
because i don't really know
so inside the lining code
where we put those debug values in
when i go through the grid index thing i
guess when we do equals
grid index or whatever it is
um
oops
what just happened
debug pick dot grid there we go
search woes
uh when we actually get this we we want
to clamp these values i think i don't
think we have any real way to clamp
stuff that's you know i think these are
all just for floating point most times i
don't know it looks like we do have some
s32 stuff in here
um so we should probably be able to do
some clamping here
and what we would want to do
is make sure that like all of the values
that
have fixed lower upper and lower bounds
are within those upper and lower bounds
right
so
we know
that like the debug pick
tx value
can only be
between zero and seven
and the same with the t y value
so those have to be clamped we also know
that the octahedral index
is only allowed to go up to whatever
that
predefined constant is in the generation
table so like you're not allowed to
go over whatever the light sampling
octahedron count is
so that
is the maximum value it can take
and so we'll just make sure that those
values are clamped so that if you try to
do something higher than those
it just gets thrown out
because otherwise we could crash like
because
the debug
although this part wouldn't matter it
just wouldn't pick anything because
you'd be out of range of any value that
it actually tries same with the grid
index right
um that's not true for t y because t y
is actually going to say where in the
table you're going to look up you know
what i mean um so
you know
it does matter
all right
so
if
we've have it all if we look at like
some of these things maybe we put them
right in the middle there
right
um the first thing i would say is i
don't totally understand what i'm seeing
like i don't really quite get
why i'm seeing multiples i think what
i'm seeing here
is that it
is that it casts two z-layers
because which i guess makes sense so
we're seeing two different z-layers
because the grid index in the spatial
partition will be the same no matter
which one you are
and so it may make sense for us to
change that to an atlas index and maybe
i'll do that right now so that we're
only picking one
and not many
that to me
seems saner so
while we're at it
let's make sure we can pick
explicitly one of these so we have a
atlas index here
not a grid index
so when we're
looking through this
we have an atlas index i don't know if
we have an our equals comparator for
those if
we do
it would just be this
code
and we do
so when we're setting this up
we would you know actually set it to
something i don't know what um
you know
eight
four
zero or one i don't know
doesn't matter
uh and so that way we can actually see
these values i don't know if this is
possible to edit i don't think it is so
i don't think we want to pass it down as
a single debug value right
because we don't have an edit for that
so what we really want is just the x y
and z separate
um and we can clamp those as well
because we do know the dimensions of
this uh the
the sampling grid right
so when we are going through those
uh we should be able to clamp those as
well so where we do our clamp
of each of these we can also do
our clamp of atlas index
so
[Music]
we need the voxel dimension for the
actual uh we need the voxel dimension
for the atlas grid
right
and so the voxel grid
here
uh we want the cell count
out of that voxel grid so we would want
like atlas grids cell count x
we want to clamp it now i don't know if
we have a clamp that works with v3s
one of the bummers about this jump
stuff that's in
uh fork coder flurry
is it doesn't show you any of the types
so when you look at clamp you have no
idea like which clamp is which right it
doesn't really have overloading where it
just tells you the
the name of the thing so i don't
actually know if we have one because
like i said on handmade hero you know i
program on it so infrequently that i
don't remember like which stuff we've
written and which stuff we haven't
so i have no idea uh but presumably we
cannot do this like i assume
we don't have the ability to do
that
where it would just do the whole clamp
for us
um i'm not sure but let's find out
uh yeah it looks like we don't have one
but we could just add one uh you know it
seems like the kind of thing we might
want
so if we just had a clamp function in
here
that we
appended right so in math
maybe
um if we just had a clamp where we clamp
each individual member that seems like
something we would use
maybe it's not i don't know um but it
seems like something we would use
so let's suppose we just add that um to
this set of things we've got here
because you can see we have quite a few
things that operate on these like
integer
three wide integer vectors right
so maybe we just add a clamp the clamp
would
be uh
something like this
and i don't know if we have minimums or
maximums for vectors uh and i guess i
don't care i probably will just do it
like this where we say clamp
min x
vx max x
and
we just do
exactly what you would expect
oops
so now we should be able to uh do this
the only problem is this is an actual
maximum value not a dim so this also
needs to have one subtracted from it
uh in order to be proper other than that
i think it's fine
and
then we should be able to like actually
pick exactly who we're looking at
so
i don't remember oops that's debug break
which is not what i meant to do
i don't remember i had to learn which
commands it's okay so it looks like f7
is our friend
for lighting and so
in theory
i don't actually know if this is true
but in theory
um
we should be able to edit these although
i can't
i'm not sure why
o is because it's an s32
that's uh that's an interesting one
so i guess technically
um you would just do that
and you would allow
drag value to happen
on both
so i think that's fine
i don't actually know i think it's fine
so now we can like more precisely
sort of drag this along um with the
super crappy debug system but you know
it's there
um it would be nice to have like yeah it
would have nice to have just like you
click maybe you click the left button
that goes up and you click the right
button it goes down would be like a
nicer way to do it right
um because like how is that not clamping
the value also right like didn't we
select clamping for the value why does
it not clamp
i guess because this overwrites it
such a crappy debug system it's so
terrible
like i don't know why the clamping is
not reflected back in here like
like
it's it's weird like see that one does
right
but this one doesn't
why
i mean
no idea did i mess up the code that does
that
i mean sure looks like i'm writing back
to it right so you know why does that
not clamp i have no idea
um
i do think in this case maybe i i
because it's so
bad
maybe for now i actually do have a thing
here that's like you know um
instead of drag value there's like some
kind of thing like
uh
tick value
so
maybe in this case
um there's like a tick value
and
then when
we do that
in here i would just have one
for uh
this that lets you
click up or down by one or something
crappy like that um
you know uh
i'm not sure exactly what this
input state
really is so it's probably easy enough
to just say
all right uh we've got
this exact case here
and
it's
tick value
and
if you see it
you
actually just use like
if the input
um
[Music]
has like you know
the shift key down or something right
like something's extremely bad i don't
know why game input cannot be
found uh
it's like right there
um but anyway so
if we look here you've got like shift
down or something so maybe like just
shift if you're pressing shift it goes
upwards if you're not you're not or
something right so you just say like
shift down
[Music]
you subtract
not down you increment
and
and that's it
although oops that's in the wrong one
this
doesn't
doesn't exist
this does
yeah so not great again just because the
debug system is super crappy but i just
don't want to deal with it for right now
so we're just going to leave it crappy
uh and then maybe we can sort of figure
out a way to make this
do something
somehow that
doesn't seem to actually increment it
will decrement but it won't increment
which is a little bit weird
oh because
there's still an f in there
uh and then that's it
that'll just be what we use and it's
really bad but oh well
we should have written a better one if
we wanted a better one
so
there's us sort of
going through those particular values
right i don't know why sometimes it goes
too many i guess if you if you hold it
down it goes up yeah
i kind of only wanted to do on the end
of an interaction so i guess maybe
that's this
right
um
so on end interact that
might be the more
like sane place to put it so it could be
that like this
should actually be
where that happens
like right here
so when we do these interactions and
like there's the toggle value like the
tick value actually goes in there
um
and
so that you only do it once when you
click it doesn't like keep going while
you hold it down
uh
so
yeah
that's a lot more sane now um
although it looks like the uh
it still looks kind of like that was a
little bit weird like
why did it stop when we came out let's
look at this a little closely
so why is nine
why does only every other one show up
because i see because it's inside the
wall area so it never gets to that point
we should probably include drawing for
that shouldn't we
yeah
all right well anyway
fair enough
all right so let's try to set this to
something that we actually want to look
at and it's a little bit annoying
because we do have sort of light bleed
here
i don't know why that doesn't clamp like
we said before that's very weird and i
don't understand it
but
the debug system is its own pain painful
reality
that we will address in good time
so if we look here at the different ways
we can cast we can now kind of step
through them
so
if we
like here's one thing if we step through
all the octahedrons they should each be
like out a different face um
sorry
if we step through the tx and ty they
should all be out of different face but
the octahedron index should all be out
the same face so basically like all of
these should be out a downward face of
the octahedron
now one thing that doesn't make good
sense to me is the octahedron isn't
aligned this way
so actually i don't understand why we're
getting a straight down arrow for the
expected direction because that's not
actually a legal direction for the
octahedral map is it
like that doesn't make any sense
how is that a thing
like if we look at
um expected direction
this
how is expected direction for this
octahedral map
um
how is it pointing downward it should
never be able to point downward should
it
i mean that really just seems wrong
i mean that's that's that's just gotta
be wrong
so like i feel like this routine is
busted because there shouldn't yeah i
mean you can look at you can just look
at how it works right
when you call direction from txty you're
gonna step in here and you're gonna
compute the you're gonna remove the
apron part of this right
um and you're just gonna step through
the oxy coefficient.x is just telling
you
uh for each step
where are you in the octahedral map
right
um
so the direction vector heading out of
the octahedral map
is just going to be based on
i mean
i suppose if you're close to the bottom
of the thing uh okay i suppose that's
okay it's not really because it's not
really technically the face of the
octahedron that we're looking at here
it's which it's this particular pixel
right which could be close to down sure
i mean
uh greg inc by the way no they're not uh
light bleed is kind of a natural thing
that happens if you just don't have a
watertight ray tracing so you know
light bleed can mean like well i've got
a wall
and there's a light on the other side of
the wall
and it comes in
right
and you know that's not that big of a
problem you can choose to leave that in
if you want depends how bad it is or if
it affects your gameplay significantly
and so on you know so that's like
light bleed is is not that bad light
poisoning is like when you have some
critical error like we have at least one
of at the moment
where some values that are like out of
bounds or something cause the entire
system to create like basically a
feedback loop it's it's very much
the exact same thing as feedback and
audio so like a microphone and a
transmitter are like close to each other
and the and they just go like
you know what i mean um that's happening
in the light
and it the reason i call it poisoning is
because because you when you have like a
radiosity kind of effect
right
if there's any
one if there's any
critical bug like that
in just one part of your light solution
it will quickly spread to the whole
thing because they're all you're
bouncing the light around in real global
illumination if you don't do global
illumination you can't really have that
kind of light poisoning because your
lighting is all local so it won't spread
but when you have global illumination
your bug will spread
and so that's what i'm talking about i
call light poisoning it's not the same
as light bleed light bleed is something
that you might
be okay with like it's not necessarily a
bug it it is a bug in the grand scheme
of things meaning in terms of the
product but it may not actually be a bug
in the lighting system meaning your
lighting system may just not be designed
to handle that so you wouldn't
necessarily think of light bleed as like
a critical failure
light poisoning is always a bug like
like it's no matter what you did
you screwed up if you have light
poisoning whereas light bleed might be
something you just accept because your
lighting algorithm is always approximate
and like you just don't have the you
know
you you haven't dedicated the resources
to it or it's too cumbersome or whatever
so you you know light bleed you're just
gonna have it in the game and it ships
it's okay right so i would like to draw
distinction there because light bleed is
significantly less bad than light
poisoning and what i'm talking about
here is actually like poisoning like the
bad it's the worst case light bleed is
is not nearly as bad of a case
you might still want to get rid of it
but
it's not as bad as this it's not as bad
as this situation
okay so um
moving
forward
uh
we're doing the grid raycast and that
seems a little bit more sane um i'm okay
with that at the moment
um yeah to a certain extent right i
don't want to overstate it
um so let's suppose we go one
forward in x to something i can see so
like right here
so that's 10 4 1
i'm going to set that to be like what it
initializes to at the outset so that we
can on startup we're always going to be
there
um and then i'm just gonna like look at
some of these casts from here to see uh
what we end up doing um for some of the
octahedron right
so there's
um another cast
these are all should be facing pretty
much down okay so there's some really
critical failure
that's happening
um when the octahedron index so
you know supposedly
supposedly
when we look at the sampling tables that
we built we're supposed to get 16
different octahedron
but from looking at that
we don't
when we get up above a certain number of
octahedron they just look like they're
just repeating themselves
and so i don't actually know if that's a
problem with the table or a problem that
we're looking up into the table
but it's definitely not
correct
you know what i'm saying
so that's the first problem is we should
be able to drive that number all the way
to 15 and we shouldn't see it bottom out
like that
now looking at the table i would also
say that the table itself doesn't look
like it has that error because that
error would look like a bunch of things
that just have zero zero negative one in
them or something right and that doesn't
really seem to be the case so
yeah
um
and the total number of these that
should be in here is 16 times 64.
right because total light sample
direction count
is the octahedrons times the per
octahedron
that's 16 times 64.
so
16 times 64 is 1024
and i guess i don't know
uh exactly where line 1024 is but it
should still be yeah so so
there's definitely the correct number of
vectors in here
so it's not like we're reading off the
end of the table or something
by asking for those values so let's take
a look and see what's going on here
because something's
funny is going on
and i'm not really sure
what it is
so in grid raycast where we're picking
out this sample direction we're starting
out the sample table
um we're stepping through the
octahedrons here
and then through the sy values the
octahedrons
we should be going from zero to you know
16 or whatever right
and did i mess up like this thing
um
hmm
i mean it still looks correct
um
so
[Music]
so why is that happening let me just
recompile this real quick so that it has
the oops
what did i do
accidentally inserted a z
that's uh that's not gonna fly
um
so that's perplexing and maybe we just
step in in debug mode and see what's
going on there but that's pretty wild
and i don't understand it so the
octahedral index right we get 0 is right
1 is right 2 is right 3 is right 4
4 through 15 are just all wrong
so
how is that possible like like why are
all those values
apparently just pointing straight down
instead of actual correct values it
seemed it sure seems like we're stepping
too far or
or maybe we built the
table incorrectly
um
that's just really really confusing and
the more i stare at that thing though i
can't really figure out exactly why
um maybe we're looking up in that table
slightly wrong let's let's take a quick
look uh at maybe we're misunderstanding
how that table is packed
because it is kind of janky and we
should probably go back and and repack
it to the way we want it to be packed
now instead of trying to pull stuff out
of it but you never know
let's take a look at that sample
direction table stuff
right
um
so
the sample direction table
is is this thing i believe
um
and the walk table offset
aha
right
so i
kind of see what the problem is here
yep
so
much like a lot of things here it's just
the fact that we don't work on this code
very often so it falls out of our head
the walk table offset
again because this is highly optimized
code we don't have the luxury
well it's not highly optimized it is
optimized code
we don't have the luxury of having
everything
be kind of like sparse and easy to
modify
the walk table offset is accessed
directly from the sample direction table
it probably doesn't line up anymore
because previously
the walk table offset was generated
assuming there were octants
and other weird things like that
and none of that may be correct anymore
so we probably need to go make sure that
this actually lines up at all because it
might actually just not right now
um and we probably have to take this a
little more seriously
right
i mean that said this part
wouldn't be though
so maybe that's not really true
um because the array direction like like
ignore walk table temporarily the ray
direction here
that actually should be fine
so now i take it back
um
because we would still see it the
direction of the ray should still be
correct so still not quite
yeah still not quite making sense
so let's try to actually figure out what
these values are i mean maybe the best
thing to do here
would be to actually show what this
value is
so this
we will actually compute
as its own value we can inspect
and we'll put the directional asset
you know in there
um
we will also make it easier on ourselves
by doing this
if
set debug true kind of a thing that way
i can set a breakpoint
on that line which just speeds things up
a little bit
instead of having to look at an actual
value
so
if we go
in there
um
and we look at what sort of
numbers we're plucking out of this table
we could also add an assertion that just
says look let's make sure we're not
outside the table
um when we get here let's just look like
so what are all these values so what's
dur offset for example
right
okay
um and so now if i change like solution
so so let's go change the debug pick
octahedron i don't know if i can edit
these maybe i can let's change this to
something that was previously bad so 10
right
so now let's see what the directional
offset is now that it's 10.
so uh
that seems fine
right i mean that doesn't seem weird and
what's ray d single at this point
i mean how is it getting that value
so sample dir plus dir offset is is the
sample direction table so it's a
solution
sample
direction table
right
here's the table
um
we are looking at this 640th one
of those
and you're telling me that that's this
year then that appears
nowhere in that table
like those values are not in the table
so this lookup is broken we were correct
before
when we were like this looks suspicious
but somehow
our suspicions failed to actually find
the problem because there is a problem
but i don't know
what it actually is
one question would be do we copy this
table
and if the answer is that we copy the
are we copying it wrong
i don't know
um
so maybe let's take a little bit closer
look at that but in general
so sampleder now
is actually indexing into what we think
would be a correct uh correct placement
of the table
there's 1024 entries in it and we're
only on entry 640 we should be pulling
off
an actual valid
entry of the table
if we look uh at light sample direction
here right like
we should have
this should have been in in the right
place so
so i don't know i'm to try one other
thing
i'm going to look at sample direction
table directly so the global variable
sample direction table
right
this is the actual table
that's the hard-coded table before it
gets copied into the lighting system if
that's what actually happens
if i go to number 640 am i going to see
straight downward pointing vectors there
i don't know there's only 512 of them
and what is this about
are those actually there
i don't remember seeing that
if i go to 512 which would just be
slightly down from here
i don't see those values
maybe i do oh well no i do that's one
how many of those are there
so here's the scary part
looking more closely at the table
they're in there
so it looks like the um
culprit actually here
is our
table build
like our table is actually
busted
for reals though
for reals
um
so that's uh oh oh no sunday it's
three-dimensional global illumination
um at the moment
uh although we
we could simplify it down to being more
2d
um
at that at the moment it's like
completely 3d
but we may not really need it to be that
um although it seems fast enough
so
you know we'll probably just leave it as
3d
um
but you know we could simplify it
further and make it like really just 2d
um because the world is pretty 2d so you
could do
[Music]
you could take more advantage of that uh
at the moment it's
the only thing that we really did there
is we just squished it down so we're
only computing a very small number of
light probes because since the world is
2d we don't need a lot of probes in z
right
um so we get a speed boost from the fact
that the world is not uh very large in z
but at the moment we really don't take
advantage of it any other way so we
could
eventually move to something that takes
more advantage of the 2d nature of
things but at the moment we don't really
you know what i mean
anyway
uh so
well that's
good to know
um so i guess the answer is the table
generator is now needs to get fixed
before we do anything else because we
can't really count on what we're looking
at
um
with the table so
so that kind of has to get
uh fixed i don't actually even remember
where we had that um it's not in the
light profiler
um
it's
h8 sphere right
so
um in hh sphere we go through and we
generate these distributions and the
place where those kind of null like
those
those bs distributions um i believe are
probably coming from like this
so um if we don't find uh something on
the sphere that can go out the
that can go in the direction we're
trying to go
for this particular one i think that's
probably what's happening there
uh
so yeah like hard to say
probably what we want to do here is just
switch to stratified sampling we can
probably fix this to be a little bit
better than it is
anyway um
but i think that's what we actually need
to do here so
this code probably needs to be cleaned
up
uh pretty much as the next thing to do
and then we can finish debugging the
raycasting which now i'm wondering you
know
how much
this has been contributing to our
lighting woes right
so fixing this table
uh maybe we should say that until next
weekend because we know exac that's
starting in you know fresh
so i think we kind of know what we have
to do
uh so maybe we save that until the next
time we
fix the table and we can while we're
doing that we reorganize the table so
that it it just samples in the correct
order so that this garbage goes away
right because now we don't have to use a
table that was built for the old system
we just build the table in the correct
order
when we build the table in the correct
order we will solve uh you know and
we'll fix what was happening here where
we weren't uh we're we're obviously
generating uh totally bogus
uh samples
so we'll you know we'll generate the
table that way
and uh
we can
then i think just
you know
at that point i think we just go
ahead with debugging the raycasting then
because
that should eliminate the problem we're
seeing currently and i don't know how
much of our problems that we're seeing
have to do with that the table being bad
because that may have caused other
problems as well you don't know how much
bad stuff there is in this table
um
it's also possible that the sample
directions now could just be randomized
samples that are
stratified inside
each of the different
octahedral regions
and that may actually be preferable now
so instead of doing poisson sampling
which is what we're doing before
it may make more sense now to switch to
basically stratified sampling where we
just say let's pick white noise inside
the
you know the xy
the the txty locations
um
it's probably still better to do poisson
distributions
i mean
you know it's probably still better
uh
because okay you're not allowed to
comment on that if your lame is
literally poisson process on twitch
poisson distributions are still going to
be better
so we probably just want to fix the
sphere distribution there's it's a
little bit hard because when you produce
a poisson distribution over the sphere
you
then have this problem of you're going
to have to be at least slightly over
sampling because otherwise you won't get
enough samples
falling within each one of your
grid locations each one of your
octahedral quadrants right
so you kind of have this problem
where you have to sort of set your
coefficients
conservatively so that you
you know you have a poisson distribution
but the poisson distribution is slightly
more dense than what you're actually
going to use so that when you go to pick
elements out of it you always know that
you'll have enough in each one of your
regions
right
um
and we could make the generator sort of
aware of that so one thing the generator
could do is it could sort of say well
look
we're going to keep increasing the
density
of the poisson distribution until we get
one
where there's the right number
um
you know
that seems plausible
uh
so yeah
sorry what's the question there
will it still be mapped to the
octahedral map because if so couldn't we
just generate the noise on there that
has a square surface right
um
so the problem with that is that we want
to sample the sphere evenly
you know what i'm saying
we don't care about sampling the
octahedral map evenly because the noise
in our lighting is going to come from
sampling the sphere evenly or unevenly
the fact that they have to then get
bucketed into
texels on the octahedral map
is kind of incidental right
so we just want to make sure that we
have
in each one
but we want them to be evenly
distributed on the sphere not on the
octahedron we don't care how they're
distributed on the octahedron at all
except that there needs to be 16 of them
per tile right
so i don't know that we really want to
generate them on the octahedron i mean
you could generate the energy but you
still want to measure
as far as the poisson nature of the
distribution you want to measure it on
the sphere not on the octahedron unless
i'm missing something there if that
makes sense
so
so i'm gonna say uh i think we're in
good shape here we
this is looking pretty good
i think we just need to then say all
right we're gonna do another the next
stream we start off the first thing we
do is rebuild the tables and we make
sure the tables are really good right so
that's our next goal and while we're
doing that we can nicely rearrange them
so that we step through the table
linearly here
right
and
i think
you could also so
the other nice thing about this is we
can change this to a single loop
so what we can do next time right
is you can replace this
loop
um with something that looks like this
or like
uh
so
imagine it looks something more like
this
you know
so now what because the only reason we
needed this internal loop in the first
place is because we need transfer pps to
write out correctly as a row
but we don't actually need to
do two loops we just need to make sure
that we're writing into the right slot
of this so we can just then change it to
us just streaming through all of these
values
and picking out the correct ray
you know what i'm saying
so the other thing we can do now is
change the table to just be like we
literally just walk through this entire
table doing this each time and in fact
we can't even do something we can't even
we can even do better than that we can
have it so that we don't pass sy anymore
what we can do instead is just have it
so that this
function
[Music]
here
um we can just have it so that this
actually executes
on
the
uh
on the outside of the syllabus we just
change this so that instead of the
octahedron being here the s
the sy loop is actually here and then we
change this because we don't really need
it so we can weld all of this together
now right
i don't think there's any way to really
do
anything
fancier than that but
yeah
um
but i think that's everything right
um so i do think next time we've got a
pretty clear set of things we know
exactly what we want to do so i think
that's fine
and so i think we'll call it here
and then we'll go
uh next time and just look at building
the table correctly so it's just one
stream you do it you do the stream
straight through
and
uh yeah and then and off you go
in fact
in fact you could just do
this
and only advanced transfer pps each time
i'm not sure so one thing that that is
just sort of a a bigger question here is
now that we know we're going to do this
entire like raycast
convolution thing here uh where we do
the entire set of rays all at once
it may also be the case that there's
just a smarter way to
batch them
than this
and that i don't know
so
so we'll have to think about that as
well
but for now i'm going to leave it there
and we will come back to this
next time all right
thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero
i will be back here next time to
regenerate that table
uh and then i think we will be in better
shape alright
take it easy everybody
i'll see you next time