okay hello everyone and welcome to
handmade hero the show recode a complete
game live on stream and occasionally so
very occasionally mention actual
computer science topics like order
notation which we talked about for the
past two days and the reason that we
don't talk about that much is because I
don't study them so I really don't have
very much to say about them but
hopefully if in the past few days
everyone got like sort of the idea of
what goes on out there in CS land so if
they are urgent about it they can go
check it out and equally importantly I
hope they kind of got what the practical
part of order notation is so they can
understand when I say something like
that would be N squared or that would be
n log n I hope they just have an idea of
what that actually means for code and
why we might care about that aspect but
that's about the end of the CES I am a
very practical programmer not a lot of
computer science in my brain so that's
probably the last you'll hear of it that
said we still have some actual practical
programming to do based on some of that
CS which is to say that this is an o n
squared sort you know this is laughs
we'll just split it Casey this is the 0
N squared bubble sort right and we had
just a to do in here already which was
saying we could early out now we discuss
that when we're talking about sorts
which is that we don't actually have to
bubble sort forever and keep actually
doing the N squared the N passes over n
items if we can see that the list has
already sorted itself earlier we can
just stop and so what we could do here
is just introduce something which is
like list is is sorted we could just say
that that was true and then as we go
through here if we ever had to swap an
item we'll just say that the list is
sorted equals false so that we know that
we made a
swap which means the list may not be
sorted we found something that was out
of order and then at the end we could
just say okay well you know that if the
list is sorted in fact I could make this
even a loop condition here but why
bother I'll just say if the list is
sorted right we can get out early so we
don't have to do the entire account and
so this is a more traditional bubble
sort most people will include that
because it's relatively cheap obviously
to do we could do something even
slightly more ridiculous which is we
could instead of setting list is sorted
equal to false we could set out or equal
to the count value or some eat I mean
there's weird things that we could do
that like yeah but point being that is
the more traditional way that someone
might write a bubble sort which is to
say that once you can see that the list
is clearly sorted you don't keep going
that now if you remember order notation
wise what does that do does that change
it from 0 n squared no it does not it is
still worst case 0 N squared what does
that do it changes the expected running
time from 0 N squared to something less
right and we don't know how much less
because it would depend entirely on how
sorted the items are at the beginning if
we're handed lists that are already
sorted most of the time it would change
our running time 20 n if we typically
are handed things which happen to be out
of order to the extent where items that
should appear at the top are appearing
near the bottom we will remain N squared
and so we don't know in the general case
but that is what that does right okay so
now let's talk about some other sort
let's do for example we talked about
merge sort right and I explained how a
merge sort would work I basically said
okay you just break this thing up into
pieces and each individual piece gets
sorted and then merged with another
piece so it's like you break it in half
and half and half and half until you're
down to only things that have one or two
items in them
and then each one of those kind of gets
merged as you go so again let's go ahead
and see what we need to do here so we
start out and we have this array we've
got you know a certain what's the right
looking for we basically have a count
sized array and so what we want to do is
we're going to want to make this so we
can split it in half so what I'm going
to do there is I'm going to start by
saying let's implement this recursively
because it's probably the easiest way to
implement it so we don't write our own
stack we're just going to use the
program stack and we'll go ahead and do
that here but later we may want to
change that depending on which sort we
end up to trying to use it sounded like
people were most excited about radix
sort so we probably won't actually use
this merge sort but just so we can see
how it works so here on the merge sort
what we need to do is we need to say
okay there's a starting point so here's
like the first entry and then we've got
a count and so the first thing we'd do
is we'd call merge sort and just say
please merge sort like my entire list
right maybe I'll put the count first
because I tend to like having counts
come first so I'm going to do that okay
so we're going to say hey you gotta do
this and I'll maybe make an if 0 here
because otherwise the list will already
be sorted so here's our merge sort so we
do our merge sort and say okay here is
the count here are the entries and in
the merge sort we need to go alright if
the count is 1 then we are obviously
already sorted right so if the count is
1 we don't need to do any work right
right because what would be the point if
the count is 2 then we just have to look
at the two items and can swap them right
so we really just have to do exactly
this thing that we had here right
because if we're looking at two two
entries and we know that that's all we
had to sort well then if the sort keys
happen and in fact I can just I can
actually construct this to look exactly
like the other one we basically have
whatever the first one is and whatever
the second one is right if they are in
the wrong order
it then we swap them all right that's it
and so that gives us both of our sort of
termination cases like our stub cases
where we know what to do in any other
case then the way our merge sort has to
work is it has to split it into two
smaller problems right so what we then
need to do is figure out what the half
count is so what's our half count right
because we need to partition this into
two pieces that we're going to sort
separately so we've got our half count
and we'll call that may be the first
half like the the half that were the you
know half one maybe well you know it was
called half 0 and then to produce half
the other half we would just say well
whatever the other count was whatever
the count originally was however many
were in the first half well we know that
this is going to be the remainder will
be in the second half okay and we know
that this is not always the same number
because we might have had an odd number
of items so we can't split it into two
even has one house going to have more
than the other potentially right and
that's totally fine we sought to handle
that so there we go we got half 0 and
half 1 and then what we have to do is
sort what we've got left right so we
have to say all right we need to sort
both of those pieces so we need to merge
sort the first part right which we know
has this many in it and we know that
that's still at the same location as
ours the first empty was the same and
then we've got another half that's like
the part that comes after that that hath
we merge sort it as well right so that
would merge sort our items for us but
now we have to put those in order right
because we've we've we've sorted the two
halves but the halves themselves are not
together sorted right they have to be
interleaved you remember how I said
after we have two sorted things we then
have to go through step through each one
and interleave them properly right so
that's what we have to do right here and
so in order to do that I have to sweep
through both halves effectively until I
get to the end of each 10
so uh I don't actually know I feel like
we should be able to if we were clever
right it seems like there might be some
way let's let's think about this for a
second this is one of those things where
we could cheat and Gus go read about
whether or not you could do a merge sort
in place but again for the sake of
Education I feel like we should
challenge ourselves and try to figure
out can we do this in place or do we you
know should we have extra storage
chances are we should have extra storage
either way it's probably going to be
much faster if we do have extra storage
because we or always know exactly how
much extra storage we would need and we
could just pass that as a side band
because we never would need more extra
storage than the size of the original
list right but I just kind of want to
see if we could do it right just see if
it's possible because we should be able
to determine that and so what we have
here we've got two halves right here's
half 0 and here is half one right if we
had more halves we could even have half
three and half three would be confirmed
right half three confirmed anyway so if
we have two halves and we've got the
entries in them all i need to do is just
produce the composite buffer by starting
here remember how this works i'm
starting here I know these are sorted so
I know these go in order and I know
these go in order and I just need to
pick at each moment from like to you
know read locations right one here one
here I usually to go which one of these
should come first and when I know which
one of these should come first I put
that into the entry okay and then I
advance it to the next one and that's
all I need to do the problem is right
what would happen if I wanted to do this
in place well if I wanted to do this in
place I've effectively got a pointer to
this guy here this is where I would want
to store the original guy so if half 0
contains
the correct the person who should go
first then we got in a problem if this
contains the person who should go first
right then I would need to swap these
two elements the problem is if I swap
these two elements how would I remember
that this guy is actually from this list
right it's a little tricky but I think
we can do it all we would need is the
knowledge that we had swapped so that
when we actually take from this guy
again instead of advancing his pointer
this way we restore his pointer to what
it should have been before right I mean
it seems like that should be pretty
straightforward correct me if I'm wrong
I'm on this guy I have to pick an entry
I look and see that the entry that's in
the slot where I would actually put it
is not the one that goes there
unfortunately if it was I just advance
its pointer and I don't need to move
anything so I'm trying to take from half
one so what do I do well when I take
from half one I put that into here I
swap this guy out to here I change the
read pointer for the this half to here
and set a flag that says the next time
you take from half 0 it's actually out
in the swap place right so when you do
that restore the pointer to point to
where it should have pointed as if we
had advanced it right and since we can
only at most be holding one element
right or no we'd have to be we'd keep
adding elements so we just increment
that whatever that counter was that said
how many we could advance before
ping-ponging back we just increment that
for every swap we did
does that work it's rather complicated
which is why i say i don't know that
you'd want to do this because it seems
like you may just want to use extra
space but it feels like it should work
because i can't think of any particular
reason why it wouldn't work right i mean
it seems pretty pretty reasonable I
don't know so there we go we got these
two to have sir let's do it here is our
interleave so we're going to go through
here and we effectively have you know a
right pointer right so we've got our
tile sort entry you know this is our
this is our out pointer and our out
pointer obviously starts at first and
when we get to the end we should
probably assert that our out pointer
equals first plus count because you know
we've got to write all the entries in
this thing you know what I'm saying so
that's good furthermore i suppose what
we should also do here you know what we
should do before we do anything else
actually let's let's go ahead and
comment this out we should just put in a
test because we're writing a relatively
complicated sort the chances that we
messed up the bubble sort fairly low
chances that we messed up the MER sort
could be relatively high let's go ahead
and put in a validator right here right
let's just say you know if we're in
validation mode let's just go through
here and actually make sure that all of
the items are actually in order instead
of just assuming that they are let's
actually just test it right because that
way when we run this thing will know
whether we messed it up so here's our
index like so here is our test and so
we'll just say okay for each pair of
items as we move through this list we
want to ensure that the first one is
always less than or equal to the second
one so that's just our assertion and
that would validate right so now if we
and this we should be able to validate
this this code and see if it's actually
correct and we're already wrong what's
the deal with that oh whoops sorry count
minus one we can't very well read off
the end of our array so there we go and
at least now we can sort of verify that
we're not getting any bugs in there and
let's just make to make sure let's go
ahead and turn off the sort entirely so
that we can verify that it actually does
catch unsorted if we were to pass it's
something unsorted that we would would
effectively trigger the assert we do so
that's good and now we know we've got a
little safety net in there that could
tell us when we messed up okay so let's
switch to merge sort now we'll turn the
merge sort back on and for example if I
didn't do this interleave right if I
didn't do the interleave then we should
get an immediate firing of that
assertion because it won't sort the
array right and there we go and that's
it so now what we're trying to do is
basically get ourselves out of this
morass where we've accidentally made our
sort break because we switch to a new
algorithm that's not done yet so here we
go we've got to actually interleave this
guy okay so we do our merge sort here we
know that these two halves are in order
for each one of these we would say okay
I guess we could just go through counts
so here's our index here or out index
that's going to go through the count
we're going to do it so at each point I
just need to know what I should do to
that out pointer yeah so I need to say
and in fact you could imagine let's just
write this just for a in half 0 just for
so we can kind of see let's write it as
if we have the temporary memory first
right so we've got this in fact i can
write it like this
so we can see the pointers to the two
halves so there's the pointers to the
two halves right so as we go through
each out index here what we want to do
is say okay let's go ahead and read in
the two you know compare the two entries
like so and we want to select whichever
one we should be reading from so in if
in half 0 if it's sort key is less than
in half one sort key then I want to pick
in half in half 0 right so I'd want to
write in half 0 if on the other hand in
half one should come first then I want
to write in half one and in either case
i want to advance the pointers now
obviously we do have a problem here
which is that we might consume all of in
half 0 before we're finished in which
case we would start reading into items
that were actually in in half one or
something or worse yet if we consumed
all of in half one we'd start reading
into items that were just passed the end
of the array so neither of those two
situations is good so we need to have
some way of knowing that we've gotten to
the end of one of these and no longer
consider those for retirement right so
what we could do here there's a number
of ways we could do that we could say
for example and you know I don't know if
I actually want to do it this way I
might want to do this just for fun just
to make it a little more explicit and so
we can debug it easier we could call
these read half like this
right and if we did that then we could
also do something like you know just
write out the cases explicitly if in
half 0 or sorry if read half 0 equals in
half one then we know we've gotten to
the end right and so basically if we've
gotten to the end of read half 0 we know
we would always take this this one we
always take from in half one right and
furthermore we'd want to assert that
read half one was not equal to end right
and the end would just be read half 1
plus half one that's like the end of the
of the things we're reading from right
okay and in fact I guess that's just we
could even say first plus count here and
then I could say assert that out equals
and there we go so similarly if read
half 1 equal in half right end then we
would know well we don't know sir that
cuz we rechecked it so then we would
know that we have to take from read half
0 right and then otherwise we could do
this
okay right now we can simplify this a
little bit already if we want to but I'm
not really going to because like I said
we want to try to make this in place and
this is not in place at the moment mmm
or i could just spill water all over
myself that's also great that's a good
thing to do basically that's a really
great way if you're doing if you're
implementing sort if you're trying to
sort things that's a really great ways
to just spill water all over yourself
first because if you spill water all
over yourself then the sort it basically
like makes the it makes it much more
easy for the sorting to happen because
you've got that like extra water to
lubricate all right so here we go this
is what we would do presumably if we
wanted to to make it sort into a
separate buffer this would presumably
work again we'll just maybe run through
it we're trying to make sure that the
logic is proper but that's all we would
really need to do right and we could
simplify this down more than we have you
know obviously we could make these ifs
be a little bit more intelligent but you
get the idea so given that we want to do
it in place we now have this problem
where if we were going to do anything
where we read off of half 0 we wouldn't
have to change anything that would work
right in fact all that would happen here
is we wouldn't actually do anything at
all like we wouldn't actually have to
have to do anything but the problem is
when we read half one we're going to
overwrite whatever was in there for read
half 0 so I think what we would have to
do is first insert some sort of an
additional thing here which is like uh
you know it's it's gonna be something
like read half stack end or something
like that right in read a stack and
would have to tell us whether or not we
had gotten to the end of the in-place
version that we were doing
right I'm just trying to think through
what we would do in this case when when
half three is confirmed basically you
know imagine we just take the very
simple scenario where I've got my two
pieces imagine I've got this scenario
and I keep pulling from this this guy so
I gotta write this guy to hear I got to
write this guy to hear I got to write
this guy to hear that means that these
guys all get swapped down into this
these locations right so each one of
those is sort of getting pushed on there
there's King swap swap swap and so when
I go to read I need to know that I'm
actually reading from here not from here
so let's do the simplest version of this
first which is like you know half 0
stack count equals 0 and half 0 stack
well I guess the appt 0 stacks always in
the same place right it's always here
it's always at in half one so we really
only need to know how many things we
pushed on right okay so the first thing
I guess we would do is say you know if
you get this guy first I'm going to do
all these cases and then we'll probably
be able I think to simplify it down but
i'm going to write all the cases
explicitly first before we try to get
clever so if the read half one is at its
end meaning read app one cannot go any
further then we would know that if the
half 0 stack count right if that equals
0 then we would just read out of where
we actually are in read half does that
make sense
because that's like that means there's
there's nothing left in half one so we
just have to see if there's nothing in
the stack we would read normally if
there is something in the stack we would
decrement the stack right and oh wait
but we wouldn't have to do anything at
that point right because if that was the
case that means that the entire rest of
the buffer just contains the items that
we swapped into it which means they're
all correct they're all the right ones
in order right because as we swapped
them out they were still in sorted order
so if we fill this whole thing up and
got to the end then all of these must be
correct so actually we wouldn't have to
do anything so if the half stack count
is 0 then we do need to do something
otherwise we can just end everything is
in order and we're done right because
the number of swaps can only be as many
as there were in that buffer I think
no I take it back so we have two things
to worry about here we go this is going
to be tricky I like this this is good
for friday because I feel like I'm
Friday's people tend to get get it lazy
but we've got 30 minutes left we can do
this so the problem is if i come here
and here as I swap these things out
let's say that this buffer was much
shorter so there's just like two things
in here there's a and B in here or
whatever right hey this is what was here
and here is like one two three four I'll
number of these and letter these you can
see so let's say a and B have to come
first so the first things we do is one
comes into here right and a goes here
too comes into here and B goes here
right now we're at the case I was
talking about and the problem is this
right is now supposed to come after like
this is supposed to come down here and
this is supposed to come up in there so
it's as if we now have another version
of this of this interleave which almost
kind of makes me wonder if you could
sort of phrase this as just as always
being between two buffers and we just
changed which two buffers we were
talking about
I almost feel like we can I almost feel
like we can let's let's do this I'm
gonna I'm gonna I'm gonna go I'm gonna
go crazy here I'm just going to go nuts
here so yeah imagine imagine if you will
but what do we have so we've got this
guy originally so when we start out
right we would say here's the to sort
keys we're going to read from one of
these but what we basically said is this
guy this is now a swap right this is now
a swap so instead a read half 0 you'd
have 0 oops you know what I'm going to
make this a little easier on myself feel
like I just want to be able to swap
seems like a good thing I want to do
right so let's do this here's my be be a
a there we go
alright so now we can just do swap entry
a entry be makes it easier to read and
makes it less error-prone and here i
would say swap read half 0 read half one
and i could also put that in here okay
so what I was about to say was here we
go I got this DS to store keys if I
going to retire the one that's in the
thing that I want it's already in the
correct place then I don't need to do
anything right all I would do is skip
over the location that I'm actually
trying to write to right and and in that
case i'm also going to update read half
0 so in some sense read half 0 just is
the out pointer i don't really need to
do anything while I'm advancing right so
that just like gets me pass any of the
entries that don't that that I'm just
getting past any entries that are
already in the right position that's all
I'm doing so as I do that I advance
forward in fact I don't really need that
right I just kind of advanced this guy
forwards till he gets to the right
position otherwise I gotta swap right so
if I have to swap then I'm going to swap
read half 0 and read half 1 and what I
want to do here is I want to actually
just keep going with as for as many
swaps as I might need right so i swapped
the two that are there
and I just want to do as many swaps as I
might need so basically this algorithm
has you know two phases so far right I I
basically say I find the place first
that's the like actual start of where we
need to sort because as long as these
are before this guy I don't have to do
anything right and in fact maybe I'll
just label these steps you know so here
we go get rid of this here's step one
step one find the first out of order
pair right and so all we do there is we
just read through a read half 0 so I
basically say you know while read half 0
is not equal to read half one right well
it's well there and they're sort keys
the sort key is less than the sort key
there I can advance so that's just a
simple while loop that goes find which
one is out of order right because you
know at the front of the array there
might just be a bunch that are just in
order we skip those okay so after we've
skipped all those we know we've come
either to the end so at this point if
read have 0 equals read half 1 we're
done because it means that the two abs
were completely in order right already
but if they're not equal to each other
then we know we would have to do some
number of swaps right to put them into
the correct positions i get rid of all
this nonsense goodbye thank you okay
right so that's that's a pretty basic
right and we could we know as well that
half one I believe we could say right
that since we know that the count was at
least three we know that each of these
is greater than one so there's no
condition we need to handle there where
there isn't a read half one read half 10
always exists right so we just kind of
read move retasked 0 till it gets to the
end and then if it's not right so then
we say step to swap as many half ones as
occur at the beginning although I
shouldn't actually say that let's not
say that yet because I gotta go works
out in the whiteboard alright so now
what we know is we're at a position
we've we've taken care of anything that
was at the beginning so now we're at a
position where the item that's here has
to move here and they're going to swap
out right and some number of these will
do that so some number will move in here
and and now we will be left with right
all of this is correct so we know that
all of the swapped values are correct we
have some number that might remain right
we don't know how many but we have some
number that might remain and we have
excuse me we now have a part of the
buffer here that's actually that that we
have basically two buffers we have this
buffer and this buffer that now i should
say three buffers we've got this buffer
this buffer and this buffer and we do
know right how these things relate to
each other right this buffer comes
before this one and this buffer is is
just the remainder of half one so my
feeling is we maybe we need we might
need a stack we'll have to see in a
second here but my feeling is once we're
at that point we should be able to then
just adjust which buffers we're pulling
from and repeat the same process right
we should just be able I mean seems like
that would make perfect sense because at
this point when we get to step two we
have three potential buffers we have
well I guess sorry it's tough to swap as
many items as necessary so here we just
go okay while read half 1 is not equal
to end and read half 0 tubing read half
0 is still a valid entry write and read
half one is actually the guy who should
be in this position so i want to say the
guy who moves right should we swap in
like so so if i want to do that sort if
i want to do this this thing I've got to
swap now read half 0 and read half one
right so that puts them in into the
correct position and both of these
pointers advance right is that actually
true no that's not true when I do the
swap I as I'm doing those swaps I need
to now make read half 0 I need to make
read half 0 be what read half one
previously was right so read half 0 is I
need like a second pointer for writing
so that I can keep a you know track of
who i am who i am comparing against
right so i basically say like here's my
comparator or whatever compared with say
i'm comparing with this guy so here's my
compared with as i move read half one up
if i need to do that swap the compared
with needs to move right trying to think
if this actually needs to happen I guess
the first one we actually know
automatically happens so actually this
happens immediately now I think about it
right we know that this would have kept
going if necessary right so we would
swap these two guys although i should
say
what about equals do we care about being
stable I don't think we do but we'll
just say all right so we swap these two
guys so they're now in separate
positions and I now need to say like the
person that we're actually comparing
with is in is actually in the read half
one slot right that's where that guy
actually exists at the moment so we're
going to keep comparing with that guy
while we read out what's there right so
then we advance both pointers read have
zero and read half one they're both past
where they were and while we can still
do that right well read half one is is
not equal to the end we should be able
to
you know kind of think of why I just did
that I can just do this right this is
this is going to be strictly better I
think than what is about to say so
instead I guess what I would say is just
store the person we're comparing with
and now we don't even have to swap right
we've got the person we're comparing
with and so we just keep going so we
just say like all right while read half
is not equal to the end then we would
come in here and say we have zero plus
plus equals read half 1 plus plus
right
so that I think does the thing that I
was trying to do before this is kind of
fun I have never written numbered sort
in place before in case you're wondering
so I have absolutely no idea how to do
it I'm just figuring it out as I go and
that sort of thing is quite fun all
right so here's what we know we've
gotten to this point where we anything
that was in order we finished right we
then say well now we know that we've got
an element that's out of order and these
guys have to come into place so what we
then do is we say okay we store the sky
out to a temporary location and then we
start swapping people right so we we
swap these two right so we put this guy
here and that guy there we swap these
two so we put this guy and put this guy
there and then at some point we get to
either the end meaning we have no more
of these guys to do or we get to a point
where they compared unfavorably so we'd
have to stop let's say there was a guy
here who would cause us to stop right so
we know these two are in order but we
know we hit a guy who actually I'm sorry
we know we hit like say this guy who is
actually not less than the first item
right so we know that this guy it needs
we need to wait and we need to put these
guys in first right so now what we would
need to do is we would need to look at
this as having a certain number of extra
buffers here right we have
some number of remainder on half 0 right
so this is like the half 0 bit we have
some number of swapped so here's the
like we've got the first part right this
is like the second part of half 0 we've
got the first part of half 0 right and
then we also have the remainder the
second part of half 1 all of these are
in order right so I believe now we just
have to figure out a way to take the
second half 0 part and we have to like
overwrite these values we have to
overwrite these values with this and
this right we have to put them in here
and pushing out the remainder again
right sounds a little mind bendy right
again mind you we don't actually know
that merge sort in place is possible so
there's also the possibility that we
simply can't do it but rather I said
then looking it up I feel like we should
at least give it a shot first so I'm
still going to spend probably another 15
minutes looking at this before we cheat
and see whether you can do it or maybe I
won't even do that maybe I'll wait and
see do the whole time and then we'll see
on monday who knows so we can get rid of
that part we can swap as many as
necessary and then we're and we end up
with essentially three buffers as I
guess what I'm saying right we've got a
weave why's that what's what's going on
there we go kind of in dead wrong
so here we've got step 3 3 buffers so
this is the tricky part so we now it's
essentially at this point after this
first step we now know that we have
essentially just a sorted piece that we
don't even care about anymore right it's
the first part of it so really now at
this point we're just sorting read half
0 read half one we're sorting we're
sorting kind of the remaining part so
this just skips the part we don't need
to care about then we do as many swaps
as we can and so now we've got a fully
and order part that that comes up to
where we'd have 0 actually is at this
point and so at that at that point we
would also know that the original read
half pointer so this part right here so
in half one we essentially have in half
one is the swapped part of half 0 right
we have lead have 0 the unswept part of
half 0 and destination for next item
right and then we have read half 1 which
is the remainder or I should say I'm
swap part of half 1 right
and we know that this part and this part
have to be you know processed and it has
to swap into here which is that's the
tricky part which is the part that makes
me worried that maybe we can't do this
but I'm not sure so we'll find out so
how would we do that so if we were to do
that right I mean one way to do it is
you can look at it just directly where
we would say okay um in half one in half
one I if it's going to have to swap
basically with with its self right it's
going to have to if it's not the correct
thing it's going to have to be swapped
in with itself yeah I'm in the other
part of half 0 because if in half one
was coming next it would have to go
there right and actually I guess we know
we know that it will write because we
got to the part what we know is we would
have kept going here this would have
kept going if it wasn't the case that we
now needed to swap in that part right so
we now know that actually what we need
to do is we need to put back in this
part right this part has to come back in
so this would be going as far as we
would have to go swapping half 0 in for
where read half 0 actually was so that
basically pushes that back out again
right um yeah I mean I think that just
works so let's see so let's just say
this is swap as many half 0 half 1 items
in as necessary and you know what else I
might want to do I feel like it would be
kind of good to hear
we can construct a false case like we
can construct a test case here so
instead of using the actual push buffer
things we can call this with a thing
where we've set it up so we can see them
they're just like 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 right
so we can when we can watch it in the
debugger and see really clearly how our
sort is behaving or you know we can step
through it all right so swabs me half
items is necessary step 3 now what we
want to do is a swap in as many swapped
half 04 swap back as many swapped have 0
items as necessary right so we're going
to push those guys on there and it feels
like that's going to be recursive
because then we're going to happy aware
I think we're going to have to move this
into a function because then we're going
to have to go like as soon as we stop
that you know we're gonna have to
remember how far down we went but let's
just keep writing it and see so okay so
assuming this actually goes here
otherwise we were done there we go so we
go all right while read half or I guess
we can even say if read half
this is in half saree okay so it's
actually if in half one that's where are
things are so now we want to say okay if
in half one or rather a while in half 1
is not equal to read half 1 so that's
that's the that's the bounds right of
the problem we're going between those
two and in fact maybe we want to say
what that was so we'll say tell sword
entry and a swap and this is the part
that we ended at is right there so we
came through and we have read half one
that marks the end of the parts that we
swapped out from read half 0 right and
so what we want to do is say okay let's
go ahead and read from there I guess so
let's do this swap read equals in half
one that's where that was so while the
swap read is not equal to the swap and
we need to basically swap these guys
back in right so as long as these that
are compared with guy is now going to be
read half one and again we only need to
do this I assume we only need to do that
compass this particular step if read
half one this this part probably remains
if read half 1 is not equal to the end
right because the free half 1 equals the
end then the only thing that we would
need to do is is is reverse our swaps so
like if there's no more of that guy
right so we've got this and I got this
we basically went through here and we
took this whole thing right and we stuck
it somewhere in here
so this doesn't exist anymore right but
in its place in this whole thing's place
is whatever was up here right so now
what we need to do is we need to put
right that back here and this needs to
go down here right so you know it's
essentially like a nasty move operation
where I've got to take this piece and
I've got to put it here while putting
this piece there and it's got a bubble
down to the bottom this is going to be
awful man yeah in play smart but you
never know like some usually or
sometimes occasionally maybe not
assuming that it is again possible to do
it starts out really nasty and Harry but
as you actually see what it ends up
being oftentimes you can like make it
simply simpler so you know we're we're
at the worst stage of it when we're
working through and figuring out how to
go once you actually have the whole
thing working you can usually go oh like
these cases kind of collapse here and
you know it can get simpler as you can
analyze it so I wouldn't despair I I
don't want to the reason I'm not just
like oh let's give up now is because you
never know you want to kind of look you
want to get a little bit past that
breaking point to just make sure there
isn't like a maybe it would be clean you
know or just over the horizon right so
anyway okay so if we assume that read
half n read half 1 was equal to end the
note this is just reassembly of half 0
here right but otherwise if we weren't
going to do if that wasn't going to be
the case so there is still a read half
one left then we would need to swap as
many as the v's right in there
and i guess i would say at this point
that's what these are right so yeah
pretty tricky definitely pretty tricky
but this is this is the reassembly of
half 0 the original half 0 it does make
me wonder too uh I wonder if we swapped
our items smarter if there's something
we could do with that right I don't
think of anything but so we'll just
leave that for now all right so we got
those two pieces we we've swapped some
number and then we just have to figure
out like okay we've got these three
buffers how do we actually merge them
right how do we merge these three
buffers so we've got the swore off the
swapped part of half 0 the unlocked part
of half 0 and the you know but I guess
this is just the remainder we don't have
to think of that as being swapped or not
swap okay so let's take the case where
we know that we're just reassembling
half 0 so like I said that looks like
this if we were to take our buffer here
is the half marker now what we've
effectively got is we know that we
swapped out like basically everything
there was right so we know that the
entirety this was completely consumed we
know that all of this is all the first
part of half 0 right so this is the
first part and we know that you know
we're at some place here that there's
some other part and so what we need to
do is reverse the order of these two
things we need this chunk to come before
this chunk right and so
uh I sis I don't know that may is that
even is there any way to do that I mean
without doing it really without ending
up this costing a huge number of extra
things right because in order to do that
right I need this element to end up here
right then that would you know so that
would put it in its correct place but
then this thing would be in the wrong
place right and then like you're
constantly going to have these things
being being in their wrong places yeah
that's looking ugly I mean because I
think basically what this would end up
doing is this will end up making it so
that there's no way for us to ever do
this efficiently because if we have to
swap the order of two blocks of
different sizes right whatever those two
sizes are here's all ras here's all our
bees then in order to do that right I
could I mean I could just swap a into
the correct place right so there's
there's my a is now in the correct place
and now i have b but then i'm right back
to the exact same problem i had before
so now you know that be has to be at the
end so now i have to swap that part out
right I end up doing Oh n swaps on this
thing to put it in that order I don't
think there's anything else I could do
other than doing Oh n swaps and if I had
to do if I have to do those oh n swaps
and a little worried well yeah well
let's just do it what the hey uh so yeah
so if I need to rearrange the two halves
of this thing right so I guess what I
would do their say like okay as long as
I still have some left I've got to keep
swapping this thing in so what are my
two halves I've got in f1 that's the
swapped part I've got read half one
that's the unswept part and I need to
move in half one up to where read half
one actually is right so if I were to do
that that would just be like okay
however much in half one it's right here
while swap read not equal to swap end
star slop slop read trying to think if
I'm swapping it in what happens when I
get to the end of it yeah this is super
nasty this is super nasty because
there's two cases here to write if it
looks like this right then the thing
that I'm swapping will because I'm
putting this into this location one of
these is bigger than the other right so
you'd presumably want to do it so that
you did the bigger one first so if I
want to put this one you know if the
goal is to swap the order these two if I
want to put this one this one has to
come first then after I swap this many
right then I'm at a position where I'm
ending up with three buffers again
because now I have the right stuff comes
at the head end and so then I've got to
go these two buffers now need to be
swapped so it's kind of like a recursive
swapping thing right it's like okay swap
as much as you could and then you got to
recursively swap these two guys it just
doesn't seem worth it does it we're just
going to spend all our time swap like we
just spent all our time swapping well
I'm just I should probably go to the QA
the problem is if somebody cheated and
looked it up because i'm going to say do
you guys have any ideas but if somebody
would probably already went and looked
it up then they're going to cheat and
cheating is not fair because the
question is is there some crucial thing
that I'm missing that it's like if we
just were smarter about where we swapped
could we have done it without having to
do so many right is there a way we could
eliminate like like is there some way I
could have
not put myself into this position when
we got down here so I wouldn't have to
worry about having to do so many of
those hmmm
well let me think this through one more
time maybe i am missing something let's
see what actually just happens so here
are my two halves right and here are my
entries alright so i start off and i
skip some number of entries so let's say
I get to hear because the first one
already contains the letter A so it's
correct but the next one has lexi or
maybe d and b and c are here so we need
d and maybe d e f come next so those are
in order so then what happens right i'm
at a i swap these guys out so i get b
and I get see in here and D and E come
in here right but then I get to F G is
here then I get to F and G and I'm like
f is actually the thing that comes first
right so what I should really be doing
is saying oh why don't you just compare
a why don't you just compare F with this
guy
that's what should be happening right
yeah because we got to hear we said all
right we've got d we've got see right we
swapped in the scene because that was
still ahead of the of the of the person
we were spinning on which was the D
right that was the guy we were checking
on we got to the point where it was no
longer the case right so the guy who was
here is not less than D so at that point
is it sufficient to simply say oh then
the person you should be comparing with
just resets to hear can't we just back
up to here so then we compare F&amp;D we
find the DEA's first we swap the f in
their right and move it forwards and the
d comes out then we come down to the e
right we compared against whatever was
was in there as well which would be what
at this point I don't know like I J or
something like that we compare the I
against the e because we know ah that's
the key we know all the things that were
in here right we know that these things
came before the thing that we stopped on
so does that just work does it just work
to just reset the pointer you see what
I'm saying meaning if we do this where
we say this obviously is fine right we
just skip just skip things as far as we
want to skip we swap things as far as we
need to swap at that point can we just
say like as as long as we still have
stuff to go can we just run this thing
and at the end after we do all of our
swaps just reset the pointer to where we
had swapped from
I feel like that could work let's let's
let's see let's just let's just see what
happens so if we just said here okay
read half the pointer that we're reading
from from read half one is just going to
equal in half one again that's it right
I see here 795 what is the problem
syntax error what is the syntax error
syntax error oh I wrote that correctly
and emacs got confused didn't it think
it did let's see ya alright so let's see
here could this putt can this possibly
be correct let's find out I want to look
at this one more time that's so cool if
this works this is going to be so crazy
or something very close to it works
alright I'm going to construct a case
here just to see what happens ok so
we've got a and then we got bc then we
got like d e f g h i j k l all right
let's do this so we skip a we're
comparing a and B we take we keep a
right so we just advance the pointer
comes down one right so now we're
looking at d we compare D&amp;B and we find
that b is actually the things that
should be in this place so we get rid of
that and we do this swap right we keep
going so we say like okay what about
we're still comparing against d so what
about D and C well c is still better so
we get rid of this we put this here and
we put the sea there right then we're
still comparing against d source a D&amp;G
which one's better well clearly d is
better so now we halt and we set the
pointer back
up to here right and so we're still
looking we're still our right position
is still here right it's at F and so now
we're back to looking at F and D now
since we know that all of these must
have come before this one here right is
that correct no that is that's not true
we don't actually know that do we we got
to G we said that G was we know that
this guy came before him but we don't
know anything about these I guess that's
the actual problem right so this guy
will work properly but we don't actually
know if the next guy could have could
have been worse right the next guy could
have been worse than somebody here so i
think that that is why that doesn't
quite work yeah because we don't really
know we know that all of these guys will
be below this dude so we definitely know
that that swapping back guy back in now
is the correct operation but we don't
really know anything about any of these
so yeah so I don't know that there's
anything else we could do so in so when
we look at this position we need to look
we need to look at at this guy and that
this guy
you
now you gotta I feel like you gotta be
able to do this because we just need to
know which one to swap in and then we
can proceed right because let's say
whoever we end up swapping in here right
they go into whichever location they go
into their pulling out so if I swap in
this this D right and the F comes here
and then I move down here I'm still in a
position to know that I wouldn't revisit
these guys until I revisited every until
I visited everyone down here so it feels
like all I should need is just a stack
of these swap pointers a stack of the
swap base pointer I feel like that's it
all right i think what i'm going to do i
think what i'm going to do is I'm going
to say I'm not going to look at the chat
I'm not going to look at it because I
want to actually try this on monday i
want to see if we can do this because i
think that's all I really need I think
all i need to do is remember this this
stack pointer here right and I just need
I so i would need some space but i only
need space to store that that that
recurs of course you know what I I
suppose you could argue well that space
to store that back pointer though that's
that's cheating right I mean that is the
storage so at that point so it's only if
I could figure out something clever that
allows me to not ever store it
explicitly and I'm not seeing how to do
that because you don't know how many you
put in there
so I think that that may be enough to
convince me that you can't do it in
place because it seems like no matter
what you do I will have to solve I would
have to store that back pointer and
every time I switch between the two I
would need to remember where that was
which means that if you constructed
exactly the right ping pong I I can't I
can't do it right
that's a bummer so that means I would
predict based on having a sword that I
would predict that somebody has shown
that bird short can't be done in place
but it's a pretty weak prediction right
we didn't try that hard we didn't really
look at it that that closely we
certainly didn't prove anything so it's
possible that we're just missing one
clever insight that would allow us to do
something more clever yeah but I can't
think of what it would be so yeah so if
that was the case right we would need
some storage so when we do this merge
sort we would need some temporary
storage now in order to do that right we
can we can do kind of the the crappy way
I suppose which is to say that the first
you know just just for the sake of
finishing it up we can just do like a
temp pointer here that we always keep
and we'll do like the worst possible
version of this because we're basically
out of time the worst possible version
of this is we literally just do what I
wrote before where we say okay Kyle
sword entry out equals temp zero index
less than count + + index and then here
we just do exactly this thing so we have
our two loops we have our two entries
which is
and a half 10 we have our two reads we
say if we have 0 is less than three half
one then we just say the out location
equals read half 0 plus plus otherwise
we say at the location equals read half
one like so and then of course we have
to do the thing here to where if we have
1 or 0 equals in half one we always read
for the other one because that means
we're out of data on that one and same
thing here
so that actually just flat-out does what
we wanted to do that puts them all into
the temp thing and then we could
literally just copy it back now if we
are smarter about the way we ping pong
or buffers we wouldn't need to do the
copy back so to do not really necessary
if we think pong but again we'll just do
the easiest version first so here all we
need to do is say okay we have our our
first there we just do first index
equals temp index that's just the copy
back and that's really it so in here we
now need again we need that we need
space for the sorting and I believe we
actually have space for the sorting I
don't know if we actually do or not so
when we call merge sort we need like
temp space and I don't really remember
whether we had temp space or not so when
we do sword entries oops when we call
sword entries I don't quite remember
push before element count push before
base sort entry yet I don't remember if
we ever yeah so when we do sword entries
we did this sort space thing here where
we had the temporary nuh we don't need
that anymore right sort space is not a
thing anymore for these guys and we're
still doing that everywhere aren't we so
we don't really need that all we really
need to do is do it here right 41 41
just just before we do anything we do
that that sort entries that makes sense
so that would just take the temporary
nuh here let me call sword entries there
we go and
now we can get any memory that we want
and yeah begin temporary the temper Rena
we don't actually need to do that
anymore here right that stuff is just
not necessary okay and I want that to go
away entirely because we don't need to
do it anymore because it just happens in
here I'm pretty sure that's all fine
right is that not true because sword
entries doesn't happen for thread
anymore that's or never really did so
that's it and so all I need to do is
actually get that that temp space so
yeah when we call sort entries the temp
space is just tile sword entry temp
space I'm just going to grab however
many the count is and that should do it
right so yeah got to put some stars in
there and the assertion where'd my
assertion go I want to put my assertion
back in as well I want to do an assert
that out epolls temp plus well I guess I
know that that's definitely true but we
might as well do it anyway and then I'll
cert that read have 0 equals skin half 1
and read half 1 equals end let's just
make that happen there and then think
we're good
don't know why that guy's confused
they're probably because emacs gets
confused sometimes it thinks something's
a template that it's not there yeah yeah
all right so let's see what that does
again we should have an assertion if we
don't sort properly why am I getting oh
that's great yeah obviously it doesn't
have to be greater than 1 it just has to
be greater than or equal to 1 there we
go so we should get some assertions here
if we do something wrong looks like we
didn't do anything wrong I guess yeah so
yeah I disappointed that we couldn't
figure out how to do that in place but I
guess what we'll do now since since it
seems like i don't know i don't i feel
like i don't have any great ideas for
that i don't know if i want spoilers
wording or not I don't know if I want to
look and find out if it is or if if we
want to try to think about it over the
weekend I'm afraid to look at the chat
because I know someone has almost
certainly already looked it up
yeah i'm going to guess that you can't
do it in place i'm just going to guess
and then i'm going to feel bad if it
turns out you can and we just should
have thought about it longer we could
have figured it out let's see ya so it
looks like I'm roughly correct it looks
like you would need a lot more work if
you didn't at least they seem to say on
wikipedia that you need a lot more work
if you wanted to actually do it in place
let's see is there any
let's see
well this oh no there it is yeah yep
that's it right there so I don't know I
mean who's to say that penguin ed EWU
edu has the most clever in place merge
sort but you can see they do a whole
block copy to move everything up by one
which is not you know that's exactly the
kind of thing that I was saying I don't
think you can do it without so all right
well I don't feel bad about the fact
that we couldn't figure out a clever i
do it because it doesn't look like there
is one but it is a bummer because it
would be cool if there was a way to do
it in place I guess I can go I guess I
can go check the chat now
so yeah and given that it means that
almost certainly you want the 10th
memory the 10th memory is always going
to be faster if you can't do it more
clearly than that because basically all
we have to do is just actually swap use
like a basically ping-pong to to do it
and we will be able to eliminate this
entirely so this is going to be way
better than doing it in place so sad but
that's just how it is I'm not actually
going to do a Q&amp;A because that took you
long and hopefully there's not much to
QA about I mean you saw what I was doing
I just tried to figure it out but
ince of iris I didn't look this up so it
might not work but came up with whenever
an element from the upper half has
chosen put it in place in the lower half
shift the upper half down to fill the
space that the chosen element from the
upper from the lower half news face at
the end of the upper half Taylor are you
pointed that n bit thoughts yeah my
feeling on that is just that's that's
too much work right that that block
copies as soon as you have to do a block
copy you might as well just two views
the temp space right because at that
point I know I'm doing so much more
extra work that I just I can't see I
can't see doing it that makes sense
elephant off topic but I made a post
about the 2 to the 2 to the N arguments
for the TSP on the forums if you're
interested I am insured i'll probably
take a look at that this weekend then
Roberto crush Gracia could you post the
bit of rotation math in the pre stream
in the YouTube channel I generally don't
post the pre streams but you are welcome
to watch it on on twitch it'll be
archived on Twitch for two weeks one of
the variance in the wikipedia article
claimed only one slot Plus Row one extra
pointers well if you use the block copy
like I said if you block copy everything
down you could just do it if you didn't
care how many more comparisons if you
were willing to do Oh n more comparisons
and 0 n more move operations it seems
like you could do it in the fairly naive
way like you just go okay I find you
know I moved down I do this part I do
this this part and instead of swapping I
just find where this thing actually goes
and push everything down to put it in
place right so it's an insertion sort at
that point right
that makes sense like you insertion sort
this into half one if that makes sense
which is just really bad like that's
just super duplicant I I mean we can
certainly do it in place but it would be
so expensive that it you wouldn't want
to write I was hoping we would find some
way of just cleverly doing it so you
didn't ever move more than the number of
items you know just going through but I
don't know
but yeah who knows maybe there's still
something clever out there I don't know
it depends if anyone's proved anything
about it it could be that maybe we could
come up with something very clever that
people haven't thought of yet and it
would just work I don't know
but yeah I mean if I ever think of
something and I'm like oh here's a way
we could cleverly do that then I'll you
know we'll do it on a future strain all
right I'm going to wrap it up here as
you can see very very easy to write it
as I sort of show to the very beginning
very very easy to write it if you have
if you don't care about temp memory very
very hard to write it if you do want to
be efficient I couldn't figure out an
efficient way to write it without with
that temp so but then we haven't spent
that much time so I don't know all right
let's wind down thank you everyone for
joining me for an episode of handmade
here so I'm pleasure coding with URL you
as always unfortunately we couldn't
figure out any efficient in place merge
sort maybe one doesn't exist but maybe
one does and we just didn't think of the
right way to do it so you know we've got
the weekend to think about it if anyone
comes up with a particularly clever way
of doing it but does not involve a block
move every time we get to an item that's
out of place uh maybe posts on the
forums and maybe we'll figure out
something interesting or maybe we just
need to search the web a little bit and
it turns out that you know it's just not
a top hit but someone has to get out a
really clever merge sort who knows
anyway that's it for today and that's it
for this week we'll be back next week
with with more handmade here obviously
if you want to follow along at home you
can always pre-order the game comes with
a source code so you can follow along at
home and you can do that on handmade
hero or you can also find links to our
forums we can ask questions or discuss
the series for example if you think you
figure it out a particularly clever way
to do merge sort that doesn't involve a
bunch of la copies that'd be the place
to do it and let us all know also a
patreon page you can a sports video
series if you like supporting the video
series soy is very much appreciated we
have a tweet papa tweet the schedule so
if you want to catch us live you know
in and we'll be back next week so check
the tweet but over the weekend for a
schedule probably will be 5 p.m. pacific
standard time again on monday until then
have a great weekend coding and i will
see you guys on the internet don't
forget to think about merge sort and and
we'll see you next week take it easy
everyone