hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream we have to do some
lighting today we sort of put things
into actually I would say a pretty nice
place at the end of last stream where we
had a decent or at least decent enough
representation of the world and we did
some bounce lighting on it and the
problem that I think we had at the end
of the last dream was just that we don't
really know at the moment whether or not
it's it's actually lighting correctly we
sort of you know did we did the basic so
we got the basic stuff implemented with
our new scheme but you know we don't
have any sort of real like
well-constructed tests in there to
really determine whether or not we're
actually performing computations
correctly you know we put in a thing
that does ray casting against
essentially like quadrilaterals and we
didn't really do any sort of
verification that that ray test actually
works and so I think when we looked at
the results it looked like maybe the
that wasn't really working correctly or
at least you know maybe something else
was wrong so it kind of we kind of are
getting close to having something we can
sort of iterate on and then we're flying
down to something that we want but word
I think we're still at the point where
we need to do a little bit more sort of
testing and checking on it maybe
construct some structured tests where we
can verify that it's working or at least
draw some things that would let us know
I'm Oh Hannah made ray is still up that
just loaded handmade ray where's here we
go we need him here oh okay so if we
take a look at what happens here in the
world if I run the lighting you can
actually see what we've got here here is
like a subdivided version we
one of the things that we added was the
ability to subdivide services down to
get sort of a higher resolution result
right and we can sort of see that the
things are sort of making sense I mean
it there's some things that indicate you
know correct behavior but there's
definitely other things that you know
maybe don't if you look at like what's
going on here I'm not 100% clear on why
this would hello nobody's running
can we stop kami um yeah could we just
[Music]
I'm sorry I don't know why the
diagnostic tools were like tracking that
there I was not trying to run a
performance profile um so anyway so if
we take a look at what's going on here
we can sort of see that some of it looks
reasonable but some of it maybe doesn't
and I think you know like I said it's
it's gonna be hard for us to converge on
a good lighting solution unless week
maybe get a little bit more information
about whether things are working the way
that we think they should work and so on
we also have some other things that I
think are pretty indicative of stuff
that should be modified if you look at
like what this giant plate is here
that's actually the hero right eye and
one of the things that's interesting
about that is that it should really be
pulling its lighting from something
that's more representative of what it
represents in the world and not
necessarily it's sprite plate right
because it's sprite plate is not
necessarily where we want to light the
hero right
the here I may want to be lit as if it's
straight up and down
so it may want to be pulling its
lighting from an interpolator
that's different from where it's drawing
its lighting because of that fo 2 D
aspect of it right so that's also
something that we were gonna want to
take a look at but as you can kind of
see we're getting closer to something
that's sort of useable as the hero moves
around in here we do have you know sort
of light playing across it and it does
interpolate smoothly like we're not
getting a lot of artifacts and stuff we
do have a little bit of sort of a
directional banding aspect to it so
we're probably going to want to do
something to address that that will
probably be as simple as making sure
that our sampling is a little more
jittered and it's kind of subtle you
can't really see it that obvious in most
places but you can sort of see it that
sort of bias that occurs because of the
fact that our lighting is done on voxels
alright so if we switch back here and
take a look at this man I'm struggling
today get some water here
what I would like to do again is just
maybe sort of start to figure out
whether you know we've got reasonable
equations in there for example for the
raycasting and also for the way in which
the light is getting transferred and
there are definitely some things in
there that kind of feel like maybe we're
not getting very reasonable results from
them I don't actually know like you know
if I if I look at some of these things
it does seem a little odd I don't know
how many rays per element we were
casting but in this case here for
example you know we're getting
situations where certain lighting
elements have like overwhelmingly blue
or overwhelmingly red right next to each
other and in order for those sorts of
things to be true for example you know
we would have to have like only one hit
me the direction that's not entirely out
of the question obviously because we
sort of have light only coming from
those two places and directly above is
not actually producing any light so I
could sort of see that happening one of
the things that we probably do want to
do as well here is put in some kind of
ambient lighting that gives it just
something besides that the basic light
that's coming in so that we don't have
such strong directionality you know in
this case we've got just one light
that's right here it's the only light in
the entire world so everything has to be
bounce light that kind of comes from
this light eventually and again so if I
look at how this is working some things
that make me a little uncomfortable you
can kind of see that that in here we've
got like sort of some of these things
can't see the light at all others of
these things can like for example trying
to see if I can zoom in here there we go
I would expect in a lot of cases like
for the light which is this thing right
here I would expect it to not be able to
see for example this
right here but that element is lit that
seems very peculiar to me I also don't
understand why these can't see the light
source maybe they randomly picked wrong
but again it just seems kind of like
maybe we're getting some pho results
here that I don't necessarily trust so
I'm gonna try and figure out a strategy
today I think the job for the day is
gonna be a metaphor a strategy today
where I can try to validate some things
about our raycasting and some things
about our light transfer to just try to
debug it under the assumption that there
are bugs in it and while I don't
necessarily know that there are just
think we have some strong indications
that there are again another example
would be like right here you can see
that there's no light on these even
though the light is right next to it and
it would seem like almost anywhere you
could have picked on here would have hit
this light and I don't know why right so
just a lot of stuff like that is just
making me nervous so although this looks
like it's doing something that sort of
resembles the lighting solution I
suspect we've got some serious bugs in
there they may be subtle math mistakes
or something like that but they create
the serious problems I think and so I
want to go ahead and take a look at
those just sort of methodically today as
much as I can so if I bring up the if I
bring up the render group here and we
take a look at the lighting equations we
got them right here so here is our our
ray cast so what we'd like to do is
validate this ray cast validate that
it's actually working and that it does
what we think it's supposed to do and
then the other thing that we want to do
is this compute light propagation here
compute light propagation is the thing
that actually spreads the light around
and uses the ray casts and we we want to
try and figure out whether this is you
know sort of correctly setting there's
light values on each iteration I don't
know how many iterations we're doing
right now
so we do four and then the final gather
that is just the thing that looks from a
particular surface and tries to see what
kind of light it's getting obviously
that can also have a mistake in it and
and we'll have to see I guess one thing
that's interesting about the final
gather is that it kind of throws away
the information that we've already used
when we spread the light around kind of
right which is kind of odd because each
of these surface elements it already had
in here emission information stored so I
suppose we probably should be using that
emission information as a guide in some
way probably or at least find ways of
tracking that emission information maybe
while we're doing this compute light
propagation it would seem right like as
we go through the admit errs and we push
things on it would seem like you would
want to build this up yeah hard to say
but anyway so these this again even if
the raycast was working properly
there might be something we're doing in
here that's dumb and if we went ahead
and looked at at what's going on there
we could maybe figure out some some sort
of maybe accumulation bug or there's
also of course the just how we're
sampling that might be dumb so there's a
lot of things that we can do in here
that you know may might be important
even just this way of sampling the
hemisphere is probably not great so even
that can be improved I don't know that
it's necessarily buggy but that's a you
know that's definitely something we
could fix all right so let's first start
with an inspection of this code and make
sure that it makes reasonable sense to
us and then maybe let's try to construct
some test cases that lets us know
whether or not we're actually doing this
rate cast properly and one of the things
too is when we're calling this rate cast
right we should verify that we're
actually calling it with the right
things that we think we should be
calling it with all right so a couple
things here that also I would point out
so when we're running through here right
we're looking for a closest hit as well
so we're sort of when we don't get a hit
this is where we would put in the
ambient lighting if there was going to
be like a skybox or something like that
that would be what would be in here so
if somebody like shoots array and never
hits anything this is where we would put
that and just as an example like you
know if we said for example this value
right here which is the result color I
think
well I guess not I was gonna say I think
this would be okay but it doesn't
actually look like for the light
spreading anyway so it would have to be
in here where we get this incident color
on the raycast yeah so during the final
gather where we do the raycast we
retrieve an incident color and what we
could do there is say alright so it's
free for us to just return an ambient
color here so if we wanted say like a
grey sky box that was going to come in
we could do so pretty trivially right
and then when we ran the lighting we
would have ambient light so for example
if I were to run it here I should get
some and you can so you know looking at
that the difference that that that
created Alone's is pretty like that's
not what that should have done it looks
like we've got some overflow problems
like adding light should never have made
the scene darker it looks like we've got
some problems where we're passing
something over bright like we're not
clamping the light amount or something
I'm not sure how that's possible like we
do definitely clamp but we must be doing
something weird there yeah I mean I I
think we've already sort of hit upon a
bug because adding more light to the
scene should never should never be able
to do that so we're doing something real
dumb here I guess one thing is this the
the normals are typically bent in the
direction of the strongest incident
light and I suppose that could be you
know that could be something so let me
just take that out of the I don't know
if you guys remember this but one of the
things we were doing is saying well
let's go ahead and produce normals that
are weighted by the direction that the
light the strongest incoming light let
me just see what happens if I get rid of
that yeah so that doesn't really affect
it too appreciably it looks like so yeah
I guess all I could say is we definitely
got some bad bugs in here so now it's a
question of finding out what they are
looking at this I mean it's pretty
straightforward we start with a zero
accumulator we accumulate colors we
write those colors back that's really it
so I'm not sure how that could really be
all that weird you know
we'll start with obvious stuff if the
incident light was always just pure red
just a pure red light what do we see
right and so that's
kind of strange so if I was to leave the
average if I was to set the average
direction to the light to be just the
surface normal and then I was to set the
incident light to always just be red
I should just see a red scene right I
mean that's what I should see you know
but that is not what I'm seeing like
that's just kind of somewhat nonsensical
so yeah we got to figure out what's
going on here I don't really know what's
going on um so when we output our
lighting quads
I guess the lighting quads we're we're
outputting just the emitters though so I
guess that that actually makes some
sense right so these are just the
emitters if I switch off from just the
admit errs this is a more of a
representation of that final gather
right but looking at that here I mean
it's still wrong you know I'm saying it
still looks roughly to be that same
problematic look
so what's going on I have no idea I
guess I'm just gonna step through this
and see because if we are cold setting
the incident light in the average
directional light those are the only
things we actually use right
of course we did make it greater than
4000 I'm sitting taking a look at
lighting textures here I would say that
[Music]
well there are a couple things that we
should probably probably try to do here
the first is that if I look at what's
going on in the OpenGL code so here's
the program that actually does the
lighting so if I take a look at the the
lighting code that's right here
and you can see that it's doing I mean
exactly what you expect it's taking the
light and it's doing a it's doing a
distance fall-off and it's doing a
cosine fall-off on wherever that
incoming light is
[Music]
yeah there's just so many things going
on here sort of need to be separate at
the same time because for starters since
we've got this voxel lighting going on I
I don't actually know why we would be
having light positions involved here at
all because the light positions we don't
even know I mean I guess I guess this is
just because we're trying to do a blend
here of multiple sample points and we're
trying to get those sample points to you
know interpolate so I don't actually
know I don't actually know that there's
really distance fall-off here per se
this is really just a case of taking a
couple scattered sample points and
combining them together so this is
really the only fall off but what I
would say is this probably shouldn't be
part of the contribution equation
because the contribution should be
entirely like the contribution of this
thing should be based on the
interpolation between the samples but
but that contribution should not be
modified by the direction of fall-off
the directional Falls should just affect
the light right so it should look more
like that or perhaps more to the point
so something like this where we're
saying like alright we've got the
contribution amount that gets multiplied
in but we've also got the directional
fault that gets multiplied in the
direction of false doesn't count for
renormalization right because we don't
want the light to get brighter the
fall-off will create the light dimming
effect as the angle gets steeper but if
we were to track that in the contribs
well then when we renormalize we will of
course renormalize it away which we
don't want to do so I think that's what
I think that was just kind of a mistake
there right so when we're doing this
this RGB here and we do the one over
result a this maybe also needs to get
clamped it's hard to say
I mean I guess if we look at how this is
working here the contribution of these
samples as we go through them
I mean I don't really even know to be
honest whether this should be doing like
just do we really want this at all like
so this represents the location of the
light in the world
of the it's and it's not really a light
right what it does is it represents a
location of a lighting sample that we
took and so we've got two levels of
London going on here right we have a
voxel blending that's going on and then
we're looping between those but it's
unclear to me that we even want to take
this light position into account like if
we actually want the voxel lighting to
be just a straight box of light we
wouldn't do that so whether this makes
any sense or not I'm not sure what this
is basically doing is saying as I get
closer or further from a particular
light sample I want to diminish its
contribution right and when we
renormalize this we're basically saying
we want that to to be brought back up to
1.0 so no matter how much we added here
we just want to eventually make sure
that that it's that it's even what you
can see here is although this gets
clamped from 0 to 1 we're summing a
bunch of them so it could be very well
higher than 1 but in theory this should
should knock it back
so I don't see any real way that that
could overflow
but it's hard to say what I do think is
clear is that the directional fall-off
there should not have been involved in
the contribution that's just a straight
up oops
expected x equals comma unexpected x
equals boobs I agree
x equals doesn't make a lot of sense
there all right so let's keep moving on
so that you know was not a particularly
relevant part of the lighting solution
at this point either although you cans
can see it made some difference it
doesn't seem to super make a lot like we
still get all kinds of weird stuff
happening and we're still not getting
that ambient light that I thought we
should get so we've still got lots of
problems here there's actually good news
the more problems we have the more
likely our lighting will get better as
we fix them up which is good
all right so but I don't see any ways
that this can overflow really so I think
that that wasn't the problem I think
something else is the problem I'm just
not sure exactly what
so let's ping-pong back over here so we
got the incident light in the average
direction to light their hard set so
right now things retain their surface
normal instead of bending it towards the
light sources and we have the incident
light which is just supposed to be set
to read what we would expect about that
after doing gather final lighting would
we would expect that if we drew the
incident light in the average direction
to light we would just get pure red
right that's what we would expect
everywhere because when we come through
here and we do the output lighting
texture is call when we come through
here and we output our link list of
light samples per voxel then what we
would see here is we we should see this
incident light getting 1 0-0 which
should end up giving us a to 5500 value
that we pack in there right so I guess
what the first thing I could do is just
verify that that's actually what's
happening but that's what we would
expect to be happening and that's what
we would expect to be sending down to
the voxel layer right
so I should see here's where we run the
output I should be able to see in the
incident light oh sorry we're still
running a debug big build here which
doesn't really let us inspect the values
the difference of speed between debug
and release is rather pronounced so
here's the incident light values they
are what we expect them to be so that's
good
and if we look at the packing version
that's exactly what I would expect it to
be as well and so when we actually go to
send this down yeah I mean that looks
fully correct that's exactly at what I
would expect let's take a look at the
average directional light as well
in this case we're looking at negative Z
negative Y so these these look like
surface normals to me so that all looks
fine like we got you know most of our
things or cubes in the world these that
makes perfect sense so that all seems
pretty good so yeah if all of those
things are getting sent down exactly
that way I mean one problem that we do
have right is we don't have a way of
directly visit visualizing the lighting
clouds here because when we do an output
lighting quads those lighting quads are
going to get lit by the the voxel itself
which messes up our debug view right so
like for example you know when I run
this back to release mode there turn
around
so if we take a look at what happens
here right
all of these emitters that we're viewing
right now are also being lit you know by
the Z bias program which we don't
actually want if we just wanted to see
what their pure emission values are
right and that's why if you take a look
at what you're seeing here it's when we
switch back to doing actual rendering
there's a lot more light that's because
the emitter quads version is showing the
results of just the emission bounces
whereas this is showing the results of
the actual gather right so yeah that's
all but again so if you take a look at
what we're seeing here the result of the
action will gather again doesn't make a
lot of sense because I'm I'm throwing
away that information I'm I'm not
actually recording the actual gather
information I'm just setting the
incident light color to red and the
direction to be whatever the surface
normal was but you can see what I'm
seeing here is actually a very distinct
set of patterns that are not constant in
any way like they're very variable they
you know they have way too much
information in there for something that
was supposed to be hard set so we
definitely have some problems here and
again I'm just kind of slowly moved
towards what they might be so
what the book got changed here so again
going back to the shader code I'm kind
of wondering here what I am doing that's
making such a weird thing happen now if
there were no lighting samples in a
voxel then this wouldn't produce any
light
and now that I think about it I'm not
sure why this is result dot a greater
than one because it should renormalize
regardless right it should be if it's
greater than zero I don't know where
that came from
because it always should renormalize the
contribution so that's just weird as
well right so after you like add all the
contributions in you should get
something that renormalize is back to
one so that was also a mistake probably
because we've made so many modifications
to this code you know stuff kind of gets
Squinkie in there but again you know
just absolutely nonsensical results here
right like this should be like how is it
black it should be pure red and I have
no idea why so again let's start with
some sort of obvious stuff here I'm
gonna stuff the color value here I'm
just gonna tell it that the color is
green always so no matter what voxel it
happens to be picking for lighting it
will always think that that voxel is
green and we should get just pure green
right and it looks like we do so this is
just green times the value ah okay well
I should have guessed that I guess haha
so that's why under a pure red light I
guess it does make sense that the blue
surface which cannot reflect any red
light that that makes sense okay I'll
give that one to you
fair enough okay so we're gonna just
return to your green light here and
verify that that's okay
and these are both black because red and
the red and green surfaces don't reflect
in a green light so when they multiply
they won't get any any results that's
totally fine looks like I'm going to go
ahead and set it to pure blue light
again that looks okay and pure red light
and then I'll seems pretty reasonable
I'm not sure why these steps are darker
I don't know if those steps are supposed
to have a darker color to them so I'm a
little unsure about that but all right
so that'll looks fine so if we were to
stuff the voxel with ones we should just
get a pure yeah and we do and okay so
these should be darker they were green
whereas the ground is white at the
moment so that's fine
so the voxel interpolation is it like
totally busted or anything right
it's producing sane results in the case
where we just stuff a white light in
there you know everything's fine so if I
was to then go and say well okay let's
pretend that every light that we loop
through has a known set of values so the
light color let's say was white so every
light sample here is going to be white I
would expect to get and and that the
direct the direction fall-off is going
to be 1.0 so there's no directional
fall-off and the light color is white
I should see just pure white now it
didn't like that try to redefine the
variable
assignment of incompatible types like
color is not everybody used anymore so
that's okay so we'll do that all right
too much yeah I agree with that too
sorry too many typos all right so now
I'm assuming that the light color is
white and I'm summing it together so
here is one where we basically have you
know white light samples everywhere and
you could kind of see that this is bad
because here we just have nothing but
white light samples and yet we still get
places where things are wrong and I
don't know I'm just assuming that the
reason for that is because the voxels in
that area didn't get any sample values
in them like this happens to be a voxel
it just doesn't have any data and so
when it goes there it can't figure out
what the color must be right and there's
a couple of different ways that we could
you know try to fix that we could try to
add to a given voxel we could try to
like add you know duplicate light
sources that are near the boundaries of
voxels or things like this but this is
kind of a problem with this lighting
scheme that the voxel lookup doesn't
super handle very well which is just
that fact that it can't really it
doesn't grab the light from the plate
everywhere that it would necessarily
need to grab the light right
and this is one of those things where
like you know we can imagine running
something on our Vauxhall that would
sort of spread the light out especially
if we go to some scheme where we
actually just have the voxel itself has
a bit of like what's the light going
through it which is kind of what we've
been moving towards but we haven't quite
gotten there yet but again you can kind
of see some weirdness here right like
why are we getting these sort of darker
patterns here you know what's going on
so looking at this there's a couple
different reasons for this like one
could be because the contributes were
bad or wrong because we know the
direction will fall off is not that any
more but you know we're summing up these
contributes and then we're normalizing
by them after the fact I so it should
that should just be taken out of the
equation so the only really thing that
should be possible there is if there are
no light indices at all so you know what
would how could we test for that right
so let's go ahead and say if there was
no light index so there's no lights in
this box at all then what I'm going to
do is I'm going to set light or just the
result I'm gonna set the result to pure
yellow anywhere that there's no light
sample so I can verify to myself that
that's actually what's going on right
so here is that and what you can kind of
see here is that suggest sit no that's
that's not what's going on here right
something that we got a different bug
because you can see it blurring towards
yellow on the outside of the voxel where
there might not be anything I guess you
know maybe I'd say that oh but you know
what that's a blue light so so how would
I go about that
because the problem is this gets
multiplied after I guess what I could do
is temporarily so here's one thing I
could do let's get rid of that for one
second and I'll go in here and say okay
during this service select RGB times L
bit I'm gonna just actually set it to
the light color so now whatever the
light color is is what we will see this
is whatever comes back from the light
color and you can see that you know it's
sort of darker in here right so those
are the light colors that are incoming
so if I come back here now and say all
right why is that happening
now if I wanted to I could say if light
I equals zero well okay in that case the
result is going to be equal to that
bright yellow so now we should be able
to see that bright yellow anywhere that
you know we're getting in correct
lighting results or can't compute
letting results correctly everything is
yell at the start because the voxel is
completely empty which means it's not
finding any lighting samples then when I
go ahead and move on here what you can
see is like yeah we're getting exactly
the problem I was talking about you can
see that as we look through here there's
just a ton of places where there's just
no lighting samples to pull from so the
next question I guess is why are there
no lighting samples to pull from and a
closely related question would be can we
do something about that how that is it
right so let's take a look at what
happens if I set this to red instead of
yet yellow so it's a little easier to
see like I put the pure red
and what you can see is that there's
some places like right in here that seem
pretty bad but honestly a lot of the
places are only trending towards a
location in the voxel that doesn't have
samples but they're still inside a
region that does right
so one thing we probably want to do is
let the contribute I think would be my
suggestion so instead of renormalizing
the voxel sample here I think what we
want to do is actually have some voxel
light return the full v4 that way the
contribution value is tracked and then
when we come through and do our our
voxel summation here what we could do is
try to make the looping respect that
right
so if we grab each of these we now would
have if we restore the actual v4 we
would now know what the voxel lighting
was in that area and whether or not we
got any samples right then when we lurk
we could try to take this into account
right we could try to take into account
that lack of lighting as necessary right
and so yeah like imagine doing something
here called Vox slurp
and again a lot of the stuff we're gonna
have to think hard about because you
know you can't be doing as I'm really
like just playing with the lighting here
and trying to figure out stuff that we
think can work but this is like pretty
expensive stuff that's going on here so
it's not necessarily a given that we
would be able to do any of this stuff
actually in the shipping version but
we're just trying to find something that
can work and then you know we'll
optimize it from the working version as
much as we can but with lighting again
we just the fine thing that works first
and then once we have found it then we
have to try and figure how to get it to
run reasonably right so here is a box
lerp that's just gonna do the straight
lip exactly as it was doing it ooh but
somehow that changed the result what
happened there oh right I this has to
renormalize at the end
so there's oddly enough that already
looks better which doesn't make really
much sense to me although I guess the
fact that it's doing the voxel
interpolation using the contribution
values is itself enough yeah that's
pretty interesting that that alone
helped but then when I was going to say
is when we're actually doing this this
looping value what I wanted to then do
was say alright let's just assume that
the result is l0 right so I'll just
start with that and what we'll do is say
if L 1 dot a is 0 or I should say if
trying to think of how to write this
exactly
maybe something like this so I guess a
if L zeros alpha value is zero so
there's no samples there then we just
want to use L 1 right we're not going to
blend between them because we can't
there's no light there similarly if L
zeros is all right actually now I think
about this we could I'm gonna I'll keep
doing this just for fun but we could
actually do this in an easier way to
what we could do is just for every voxel
when we set that voxel value we could
look to see if its neighbors or rather
for every voxel in the grid after we're
done computing it for any voxel that
doesn't have any lights in it just set
its light pointer to point to the light
of some voxel in its vicinity that does
have one right because then we wouldn't
need to do any of the special casing in
fact I think that's just better because
that incurs no speed penalty like this
does in just a regular case so I think
that's actually better than what I was
doing
all right
all right so I think what I'll do is
I'll do that yeah I'll come do that I'm
gonna I think I might take a quick break
from streaming I but let's do that when
I come back let's loop through all the
voxels and and what we'll do is we'll
set a neighbor as equal to two ones that
any empty neighbor will get set to a
full neighbor neighbor in the way I'm
going to take a quick break from stream
and then I will be back in just a few
moments okay back to it so yeah the I
think the first thing that I do want to
do then is just try to get it so that
we're not sampling from places don't
have samples in them and I think the
only way to do that is just to make sure
that we get that we always that we
always flood fill our voxel essentially
and make sure that things that don't
have anything in them take something
from their neighbor where possible right
so here in output lighting textures
right what I could do is say you know
much like we were doing in this loop
here what I could do is do a simple sort
of directional fill after the fact here
so this is our lighting textures output
lighting textures function
so right here where we go through each
of the values what I can do is just look
for any given one of these look at its
neighbors if it's zero so we could say
it's like alright if we take a look at
the thing that we were packing here
which is look at that this value right
here voxels ZYX if I was to go ahead and
look at that and see that it was not
filled then what I could do is is set it
to like a neighbor value and all I would
do here is look to see where I could
find a neighbor value right now for
simplicity I think what I'll do at the
moment is I'll just go ahead and only
search just the you know reduced set by
one so I know anytime I find one I can
just look at each of the direct
neighbors to see what's in there
right so I could say all right neighbor
equals deaths look up you know Z minus 1
Y X like so and then I can do like
neighbor equals neighbor and neighbor
and just look through each of these in
turn and again this is only when we
initially create the voxel that we're
doing this we're not doing it on every
lookup right so we'll look at Z plus 1
and Z minus 1
and I don't know how many of these we
actually want to do but you know I guess
in this case we probably wanted do it
this way we go
so here I'll do like all the Z minus
ones so we'll do Cu minus one
I guess we could we could just do all of
them here so we'll do all the Z minus
ones will do I almost want to do this in
a for loop there's so many of them but
I'll do the Z minus ones here and we'll
do y -1 to y plus one like so and in
each of these cases we would do X minus
1/2 X plus 1 right
so here we have all the combinations for
the Z minus 1 layer we've got y -1 X
minus 1
you know minus 1 plus 0 or whatever we
would do this for each of them like so
kind of an unholy terror and all we be
changing it was the Z layer part of it
and that's it so this should propagate
it'll just search the neighborhood of
the voxel and if it finds anything that
it can use is the pointer to the light
samples it will use it right what's it
saying you 16 and that's it so I don't
know hopefully that would give us
something where we propagate those light
values out to neighbors who don't have
any light values and we'll see what
happens so I don't see any difference
there at all that looks exactly same to
me which is weird right because that
should have allowed to grab some
neighbor light values there which it
doesn't look like it did and I don't
know why right
anymore
ah that's a little peculiar
so I guess well you know what they know
and maybe isn't so because the voxel
that could just be on the edge of the
voxel as well in fact I think it is
yeah but even so so looking at that
again since the voxel boundaries are
presumably relatively tight fit to the
scene what we should probably do is also
expand those but again since this is
only this isn't actually doing that
search it doesn't have an apron there
right so you know if we really want this
to go all the way to the edge it has to
actually not have these one and minus
ones in there but even that so let's
take a look at some we know aren't on
the edge right we know all of these are
not on the edge right none of those are
on the edge so again it's kind of kind
of busted like there's just a lot of
bugs in here I have to figure out a good
way to sort of pare this down because
there's just a lot of stuff that isn't
making sense so we have a lot of
problems but it's hard with something
like lighting to figure out exactly how
to go about track of them sort of using
the structured art procedure here to do
it where I'm like putting in known
values to see what happens on the way
out but it's not really sufficient and
it feels like we're gonna have to
construct a more rigorous test case if
we want to get anywhere on it so if I if
I step back for a second and just say
what
you know let's let's verify that that's
working at all just first because that
should have filled interior nodes it
doesn't even look like it was doing that
so I'm kind of not sure what's happening
there you'll see is so bad at telling
you anything about what your code did in
release mode I guess what I can do is
set something so in this case what I'll
do is I'll just stop assuming that it
filled something in I'll stop the
program there so it should crash there I
mean well the cert there right if I ever
fill in a value so yes you can see that
I am filling in a value in theory right
and hey it looks like it wasn't
optimized away this time so you know it
is finding a value there and it is
actually doing a you know replacement of
whatever this previous value was which
was zero is now getting replaced with of
course it's now getting replaced with an
actual value so it does seem to be doing
some fill right it does seem to be
putting some values in to places where
they weren't previously put so that's
good
but it doesn't solve our problem right
like we are still seeing exactly what we
were seeing before to a first
approximation
so the question is what to do next I'm
gonna get rid of this for now leave it
in there in case you want to play with
something like that later
so again focusing on this just for a
second these locations are places that
just don't have voxel lighting samples
right and some of the patterns that I'm
seeing you're just really strange too
right
like I don't really understand this
pattern here because it should be a
fairly straightforward voxel pattern
like it shouldn't be something that's
got like a circular feel to it like that
I know it's just it's very strange I
don't understand the results at all like
I'm completely at a loss to what's
actually going on there and again I
think part of that is just this sort of
issue with too many things going on not
well enough tested if I go through and
set here if I take a stick back from
here and just say you know
if I just took the voxel values
themselves and I draw them so this
should give us like kind of a rainbow
sort of a look right based on where in
the voxel you actually are and you can
see it sort of does right now I don't
remember and I have to look what the
voxel so our voxel is only eight by
eight by eight somehow so actually
that's a more reasonable normalization
factor there so this is just an attempt
to verify that the voxel interpolation
itself didn't become broken and that
looks reasonable right that's a nice
color wash you know I don't see a lot of
artifacting on that so it seems anyway
at least a first approximation that the
voxel interpolation is fine
so that's fine so it's just what we're
returning from the voxel that's somehow
producing that patterns so this must be
pretty busted in here right like where
we end up having contributions and don't
or something
must be pretty bizarre so let's start
again by doing some things that are
relatively simple let's just ignore all
of this stuff entirely and let's just
set the results to be green or red based
on whether or not there was a sample and
so this should give us something
obviously starts out all red because
there are no box of samples and now it's
green and there's only red where there
aren't samples right now again I really
don't quite know how it's possible that
there's no samples and wherever we're
interpolating to but I guess that's
because you know like if I had to let's
say I had to assume that there wasn't a
bug then the reason that we're getting
say red in this area would be because
there's a voxel cell right here where
there is no there are no samples it
would be nice to be able to see the
voxels easily so I wonder if maybe I
should do that real quick we already had
a way to draw that right
it's
this one right here yeah
I think it's actually this
so here you can sort of see the lighting
solution visualized in voxel form and
anywhere where there is a sample there
will be a green cube and so you know
here's the here's a hole right here and
you can see that that that is probably
what's happening right there so let's
turn on the filling oh you know what I'm
an idiot this the filling we were doing
before the packing so that well no
that's fine because we're updating that
texture directly though so I'm not I
mean well I am an idiot but I'm not any
because of that I think it's important
to remember so if we go ahead here and
and take a look at what we end up with
now there isn't I don't think any hole
there right
yeah
so that did work that whole feeling so
let me go ahead and try to do something
a little more sane here so what I'm
going to do is I'm going to turn this
into four I loop like I saying I wanted
to
and what I'm gonna look at this value
I'm just gonna do like plus DZ plus plus
DX plus dy so I'm gonna say turn that
into a four I loop like I wanted to do
which again is doesn't really help us
yet but because I want to do a slight
change to it so it can fill everything
so what I didn't want to do is I want to
be able to take this these downs here
and widen this up to look at the entire
voxel and so here I just want to say
like okay you know if Z equals zero then
I don't want to look behind I just want
to start at the current Z level and if Z
equals like look up Z minus one then I
don't want to go ahead so this is right
the new way that's actually clamped
so this way we can do this on the lookup
oops
missing a parenthesis there there we go
not sure why didn't get that there we go
it's been a bad day alright so anyway we
can look at the X Y Z's there and clamp
them so that now we're only going to run
within the legal offset from wherever we
are if we get to the edge of the voxel
we won't look beyond into the void right
into a legal place or at least well
that's what I tried to do but I
obviously didn't quite do it right I
missed one there
and so now we should be filling
basically everything or anything that
had a neighbor even close to it and it
looks like now we're pretty close to
good and so I think all we would
probably have to do is clamp our voxel
lookups to not interpolate outside so if
we take a look what's happening here
where we do this textile fetch here that
that voxel at you can see it's it's not
like clamped at all right so if it was
gonna look outside of where the voxel
was it just would and we don't really
want that to happen so when we go to
actually some of this what we want to do
is clamp these app values we know we
shouldn't ever not really sure we don't
really pass down the the voxel here so
you know I'm trying to get our best way
to clamp the voxel um so you can see
here we do our inverse seldom times the
min corner right and we we're sort of
making sure that that we get the you
know the the eight voxels that surround
this this point but some of those voxels
might not actually be in right we might
be looking at a negative or negative one
or or an 8 which would be outside so we
want to be able to do here is say when
we go to look this up you know we want
to be able to do like a
we want to do something like this and
this is is really just right and we want
to know what the voxel dimension is here
so we're going to want that to be an
actual like included value sorry about
that
and ideally now you know it wouldn't be
if I did that correctly it wouldn't ever
look outside the voxel so now we've
filled all the holes in the voxel grid
and we have that we might look in right
and we have made it so that it never
like looks outside of the voxel grid it
just resamples the same voxel it's in if
it would have tried to look outside
because we know there's nothing there to
look for and so now we've we've
eliminated those red patches which is
like important and what we'd like to do
here is like like get a Vox dimension
and so let's take a look let me see
about putting this in here so right here
this is where we would want to do that
so we know we've got this like these
constants here and we would like them to
come through in the shader so what I'm
going to do is actually have them
literally just come through in the
shader as confines right so we got the X
Y and the Z here there's the x y&amp;z there
and now that way those will be available
in the shader and if we change them they
are properly changed all right so what
we would do here is say like that
something like that
and that way we can do in here we just
do clamp box and now we should have a
way to clamp our voxel - if we decide to
make it bigger or smaller or you know
whatever else whoa
or not what did i do there
sorry I meant to pass minus one there I
am not sure where that's coming from
so yeah that's where that's going from
it's an ugly
typo'd all right um so I think we're
pretty good now on that part of things
that all made sense as we went through
it but that's just the first step right
so now we have to start saying well okay
so we figured out how to keep ourselves
from sampling voxel values that weren't
there but now we have to make it so that
when we sample values that are there
they make sense okay so here's taking
the directional fall-off out of the
equation and setting the light value is
always equal to one but having the
contribution value be whatever the
contribution value was for the samples
so this is basically now we're trying to
get our sample interpolation to be
something sane right and so that's gonna
take a bit of work as well so what we
can see here is that once we turn on
that part of things we get a lot of
weird like scalloping like sort of
spherical weirdness happening right and
so now let's try to like hone in on that
and figure out like what what we're
getting here so fundamentally speaking
inside one of these voxels what we're
doing is we're throwing down a bunch of
light samples and there could be like a
dozen of these right there could be a
bunch of them which are basically points
in space which say we computed lighting
at this place so what we want to do is
we want to try and figure out what that
implies for the actual pixel that we're
trying to light right now right so it
seems like we would want the fall-off
and that sort of stuff to make sense
right what we want to do
is we want to have it so that as you go
towards any one of these points since we
know we computed the lighting at that
point when you get to that point the
light should be very strongly correlated
hmm with what we computed at that
location right because we don't really
have to do much reconstruction in that
in that case because what the incident
light is at that point we is known it's
not like in between sample points where
we're trying to reconstruct it so that
contribution value right is supposed to
be 1.0 when you're right on it which it
should be because the length of of these
the sample point in world space right
that length should be 0 at that location
and you know we want to sort of make it
so that that value ramps up quickly
potentially so it's pretty tight
fall-off so what we're doing here is
we're saying r8 would take that length
we want that length off to potentially
be very fast but we don't necessarily
ever want it what we'd like to do is
we'd like to make it so that it never
quite goes to 0 potentially because we
don't want to lose the sample ever
probably I would say uh so I'd say the
way that we're doing it right now is
maybe not the smartest thing in the
world I would say that the way that
we're doing it right now what we
probably want to do is
[Music]
we want it to sort of asymptotically
approach one right
so I'm not sure exactly what that should
be here but basically what I'm saying is
we want a value here right where this
will go rapidly towards one as it goes
away from the point but never quite get
there so that we always keep at least a
little bit of contribution from this
thing but as you get further away from
it you get much less contribution and
I'm trying to think of how I would do
that but I'm not quite sure this value
is sort of unbounded right because we
don't really know what its maximum could
be I suppose it can't be bigger than the
voxel but that's really all we know
about it and if we were to divide it
directly by that value you know yeah I'm
not really sure what we want to do here
this is a bit tricky but whatever the
inverse voxel dimension is right we know
what that is because we've got it
right we've got that box in cell dim so
if we wanted to we could use the box and
seldom here as a multiplier because
since it's already won over this the
dimension of the cell that would give us
something that we knew it couldn't
exceed one
it just doesn't necessarily ask him talk
to me I approach it quickly like I
wanted it to I think there's probably
smarter math we could do here but if I
went ahead and said okay let's take the
end
the Vox them sell dim so if I take this
distance and I multiply that it should
now normalize it so that the maximum
distance would be like 1 1 1 right so it
would be like a square root of 3 right
where is how do I do square root on this
crazy calculator is is that supposed to
be square root it looks more like a
checkmark apparently so
all right so I'm thinking maybe just
like you know I I want to multiply by
the inverse of that to keep you know to
keep the value same so I want something
like how do I invert this value this
calculator is is nuts
where's the IMP button
I don't even know what to say is there
no inverse button wait of course yeah
there must not be an inverse button
because here are the two these are the
inverse of each other and they're both
on here god anyway I don't even know how
to copy a value here because there's no
menu on this thing this is such a piece
of look at me right-clicking on this
it's not doing anything weird oh man how
do you mess up a calculator answer you
ask Microsoft to write it alright so
here's the here's the value I actually
wanted maybe a little bit too precise so
I'm basically just looking at something
that would would try to keep things
bounded to the length of a voxel in
terms of interpolation values I don't
know whether that's really sufficient
though and so you know yeah if you look
at what's going on here from what we're
getting we get these weird like radial
fall-off patterns and again I don't
really understand those so I'm I want to
investigate further because I there
remember we're not actually blending
different samples we're blending the
same sample because I'm overwriting the
values here the direction will fall off
in the light color which are the things
that we actually were computing I'm
throwing out right so the only thing
we're looking at here is the result of
the renormalization by the contribute
that's all now we know we always enter
this loop right because if we didn't
enter this loop we
would have seen it before right so if I
if I look remember we did this this is
what we were doing for if I note that we
never enter the loop I can stuff that
read value and the work we did before I
seem to be ensuring that that was never
happening right so that means we always
enter the loop right you can see no red
so given that we always enter the loop
what that means is we must be getting
contribute of zero right because of this
or something so I'm going to start by
seeing if that's true so does the
scalloped pattern come solely from this
equation I my guess is it must but let's
first validate that that's true maybe
we've got a different bug and we just
don't understand it okay so that looks
right everything is just the white color
which is what we would expect so it's
just this equation that's causing our
country values our alpha value to go to
zero occasionally and the question is
how is that happening if we're taking
the length of something that's supposed
to be renormalized we know that both ah
well okay I think I see what we're doing
here potentially since we are computing
the value outside we're competing these
values in neighboring voxels as well
that does mean that we could be more
than one voxel unit away from the thing
that we're using we could actually be
two voxel units away right so rather
than being one one one it would actually
be two to two right
so we'd actually be talking about this
value to eight eight six seven right
that would be the actual value that
would be required to ensure that we
never go to zero on the contribution so
it's better but we still have that
problem so we're just not computing this
quite right the other thing that I would
point out about this is like I said I
would rather have a better math
operation to be using here right I would
rather have something you know and maybe
I should just do like so you know right
so you know I'd rather have something
like this fundamentally speaking where
like you know the thing just goes up
forever and you know trends towards zero
but never actually hits it because I
don't I just want to make sure that
samples that are closer to you are more
reasonable and and you know so maybe we
just use a fall from that and not try to
get that that way we always are waiting
everything but we just wait things lower
as we go and maybe we need to tune that
fall function but that way we don't have
to try and like get that correct or
whatever all right so now if we assume
that the light color is is always
going to come from the right place now
we go back to like executing the
lighting equation now we're actually
blending samples together correctly
well correctly is a strong term in this
case we're actually blending colors
together in a way that doesn't produce
its own set of artifacts right and
already things are definitely looking
better I just think maybe we've still
got some weird issues here potentially
but you can sort of see that it's
starting to get rid of some of the
artifacts we were seeing even though we
still have quite a few to deal with
right all right so let's take a look at
what we let's see what we can see here
from the render group itself we do know
that we're stuffing a an incident light
value of one I read rightful red Channel
and we're stuffing that value directly
so if I go in here and look at what I
would expect to see if I was to take the
fall-off out of it so we'll leave the
fall-off part in here then what I would
expect to see is always blending red
light with red light right and that
should give me pure red everywhere so
once we take a look at the fall-off
aspect of it then what we're doing is
we're saying alright we want to take the
light direction whatever the light
direction is and we want that light
direction to now do a fall-off on versus
what our normal is and if I put that in
we get a bunch of things that look wrong
I think what we may be doing here is we
may be encoding our normals wrong or
or something but I don't like the look
of that at all so instead of using this
fall-off instead of doing this which I
don't think is particularly instructive
and it's not gonna really help us do a
great job you're freaking out it's going
on I'm gonna get rid of the fall-off and
so do I'm gonna do is I'm gonna stuff
the light color that we're gonna use in
this equation I'm going to stuff that
color with the light direction so I can
just render what it thinks the light
direction is at any given point directly
or not what do you do what's it
complaining about there
oh that's what it's complaining about
can't set a v4 from a v3 everyone knows
that I so now if we take a look at at
what we're getting here I I would say
that that's pretty like doesn't make a
whole lot of sense to me
now the problem is we're averaging these
things together there's multiple normals
in the voxels so actually I guess the
one problem we've got here is that we're
we have no real way of visualizing what
all the normals are in there so we don't
really know if that's at all wrong
because you know you have to remember
this is a voxel and so for example the
you know right in here there's this
plate for the hero and all of those
normals are gonna add it in like so like
they will affect the normals here and so
on right but each of those samples is
stored separately
so I don't really know what I want to do
is see whether these normals are
reasonable but I don't really have a
good way of drawing that since I have to
just draw in this the way we're sampling
the shader I have to just draw one value
and so I don't really have
hmm I don't really have much I can do to
debug that value directly in the shader
right because what I would expect to see
but which I can't necessarily figure out
a way to directly visualize is like all
the normals should be the same across
all these phases right so what that
means is that if I were to pick the part
of the normal in that voxel the lighting
samples that were coming from these
phases should all have the same normal
but I don't know which one of those I'm
looking at when I look at the various
links in the voxel list right so that
part's a little bit nuts and there's I'm
not sure what I can really do to
mitigate that like what I want to do is
basically draw a bunch of little arrows
in here that show me where all the we're
all the point samples sorry the problem
is if even though I can go ahead and do
that and that is more or less what we do
when we are doing those lighting
elements what I don't have is a way to
do that from what the shader thinks they
are right because you know I can go to
bug this from the other side and add
some drawing in there that would allow
me to see where those light samples are
and what their normals are unfortunately
that doesn't help me with the other part
of the other side of it which is are
they getting read correctly in the
shader right so one of them is easier to
debug one of them is harder I suppose we
could start by just doing the easier one
to debug because if we find bugs there
then hey that was free right that was
let me not free but it was a lot cheaper
than what we'd have to chart figuring
out in order to debug it on the other
side so I guess that's probably the way
we should do it's there I can't think of
a like great way to do it either way but
you know what are you gonna do so I
let's take a look at what's going on
here so when we do extract reflectors
from quads and we are gonna record these
thermals we're recording the normal from
one vertex in that you know whatever
that thing was right and I guess I mean
I don't know for sure but I guess we've
never really verified that those are
100% correct values so even our input is
potentially suspect however when we were
just doing basic lighting you know it
looked like our normals were pretty good
so I'm not super suspect of this value
here but honestly if we're gonna go the
the whole way and debug it entirely we
don't really even know that our element
normals are correct right so we might
want to we might want to verify even
that but if we then go and look at where
this the average light directions stuff
is coming from which is what this
directional fall-off light D RGB thing
is is coming from if we look at where
that's coming from right now we're just
passing through those element normals
and so we should never like those never
get modified like anywhere else right
they get set here and there's never a
place where they get changed right so
we're literally taking just those
normals which we assumed to be correct
but again we don't necessarily now and
then what we're doing is we're just
stuffing that directly into the average
direction to light when we go to encode
the average directional light which is
not there yeah
mmm-hmm we're gonna include that value
we're just encoding it directly we Pat
it with a zero because it's getting
stuffed in a color bitmap and we pack it
in here we're literally just taking
whatever is the packing index and we're
sticking in that D value right look
that's it so yeah I mean at least in
theory I don't see a lot of ways that
that could really be going wrong it's
hard to say
it just looks really straightforward and
when we were looking at this incident
like Direction values you know I stepped
through here and I did take a look at
what we were packing him sending out
there and it did seem like the average
Direction delight was generally sane so
yeah I don't know what's going on there
so I guess one thing we could do is say
well alright I you know I guess we also
don't know let's draw the world normal
as well that should be 100% consistent
just as a start
so that looks very good to me right that
that looks like quite good I am very
very okay with that so yeah it seems
like this world numbers are reasonable
it seemed like the light directions are
reasonable as well so I'm just not sure
I understand why something would be
going wrong in there but it kind of
looks like something is
but I get even even that I mean I guess
I don't really know that that's true if
we go back and look at what we're seeing
here we know that we're stuffing pure
red into the light source when we are
looking at things with unambiguous
normals like you're in here it actually
looks like it's giving pretty reasonable
results right to a certain extent anyway
I would say so you know it's mostly
things kind of like up in here that are
not making a lot of sense to me like
here and here and I you know I guess I
could convince myself that that was sort
of being done correctly in that these
were places where the fact that there is
you know additional light normals is
getting weighted in more heavily at
[Music]
hey I'm just not sure I mean effectively
the problem that I'm having with it
right is I just don't really know when
we're sort of getting that fall-off
value in there I just don't really know
what to expect from it on the one hand
you know where we've got sort of the
world normals which I think we know are
correct and then we've got the incoming
light direction dotting those two
together should be pretty
straightforward and give us the fault
that we want on the other hand you have
to recall that we're summing up a bunch
of samples here and in the case right
now where we're stuffing the light
direction to be coming from a very from
directly away from whatever the surface
is right because we're stuffing in a
false value there right I just don't
know what to expect from it I don't feel
like I have a good wave because we're
summing a bunch of them together I don't
feel like I have a good way to really
like push structure to are through there
and get something that I expect out
um yeah I'm just not sure I'm interested
to see what we look like currently if we
do our standard lighting path
so this includes our ambient light at
the moment right I'm gonna go ahead and
take off that ambient light because now
it seems to actually be working so now
we'll just have that one this light
source right here and I'm just
interested to see what we end up with so
you
I guess I would say you know it's
getting closer to same but I still think
we've got some bugs separate from the
lighting transport which we haven't
started debugging it I still think we've
got some nastiness going on in there let
me see what happens here if we add back
in the surface reflectance as well so
you know it's getting a lot better right
fixing the voxel interpolation bugs
definitely made a big improvement to the
quality right and so I think we're kind
of we're still behind the eight ball a
little bit here but we're getting a lot
better I mean that's starting to look
pretty good and we've just got some like
you know why are we getting no light in
these sort of under clipped areas
probably because those reflectors never
got any contribution there because like
their their distribution point was like
underground or most of the distribution
or underground or something like this I
don't know exactly but but you know like
that's that's starting to be lighting
that you could actually imagine using
right it's not there yet but like you
can see as I move around I'm getting
some pretty good like I'm getting some
pretty good results from that right and
this is something I think we could run
on the GPU pretty easily and that's just
pretty cool right I'm getting a little
excited about that like this might
actually turn out pretty pretty neat you
know I know when I started it whether we
would get somewhere usable or not but
that seems like you know if I come back
here and I look at what we're looking at
right and I just like try some lighting
mean that's that's great that's really
usable in terms of you know light and
that's not special case to one light so
this is something that could have as
many lights in it as we want it doesn't
cost more to have more lights really
so I think that's pretty good and you
can see that we've still definitely got
some bugs like that shouldn't have been
able to see the light source so I think
if we go and just just push a little bit
harder on the debugging eye and get a
few more steps down I think we might
actually have a nice real time letting
solution here right that we can have so
we can have kind of nice lights in
handmade Hiro which I want cuz they're
nice and they help the mood a lot right
like having just a big ol flat game with
without anything in the game really
responding to the lighting at all I
definitely makes it harder to establish
that kind of nice mood and sense so I
like I like where this is going right
that's starting to look pretty cool to
me that's a good thing so yeah I think
the next thing we got to do is is take a
look at why we're getting like no
samples or weird sample stuff in some of
these areas right where it doesn't
really make a whole lot of sense as to
why they would be so under sampled and I
and I don't know if that's because like
all the samples are underground or what
exactly it's happening like I said
before I'm not not sure what's going on
there uh but we got to fix that and then
the other thing I think we lot of fixes
I think are light transport is still
kind of busted I think our ray caster
might be slightly busted or maybe we're
like just allowing things that shouldn't
be allowed somewhere in there and then I
think we could be at a point where we'll
transfer it over the GPU side of things
and try to figure out a way to run it on
the GPU for a few iterations so that
it'll be reasonably quick
yeah
so if we assumed that let's go back to
our sort of ambient light here
so if we assume like an incoming ambient
light there you can see that really
brightens up the scene quite a bit but
we lose a lot of that sort of
directional niceness for this light so
it seems like that's almost a little bit
too that's it's like weird that that's
producing that much ambient light for
the final gather
well I guess what's interesting about
that is we aren't using a divisor here
though
which explains it because yeah I mean
this should be this should be able to be
set to something like this so really
this should have a divisor there the
number of raised we sample when we do
our final lighting should divide the
accumulator right right so for every Ray
we sample we should be multiplying
whatever the the incident accumulator is
that that's I don't know why we weren't
doing that must have had a reason I'm
just not sure what that reason was so
that's more like it right now we can see
that there is an ambient gray light like
a skylight coming in that's the sort of
omnidirectional and then we've also got
our sort of point light here that we're
moving around so you know you get more
light in this area and less light sort
of in the other areas I don't really
remember where we set the strength of
that light source but again right you
can just see how this is really starting
to come together right I mean that's
that's looking much nicer now and I
think we've still got some nasty bugs in
there I think it'll get a lot better
once we get those out of there but just
looking at this I think if even if we
move just this to the GPU it would look
pretty cool
you just have some nasty artifacts right
like this kind of crap is no good so
we're getting there I think we're
getting there
yeah let's go ahead and do some Q&amp;A here
I can't seem to use the mouse for some
reason
recruiting win cat the size the window
determines how many buttons are shown
you can either stretch the window
vertically or you can press the up arrow
button to make this shown buttons shift
into the other set seriously why doesn't
it set the size by default to how big it
should be
oh my god
[Music]
all right
the car - said I think the error and the
colors are this in the same positions
where the normal calculations look funny
yeah I agree I mean like I said I'm
really just not quite sure what's
happening there but I think we've got
some I think we've got some like little
insidious bugs in in some you know much
like the voxel interpolation stuff you
kinda just have to go in in like
validate each individual section because
I think we've got some obvious bugs in I
think the Ray caster probably also has
some bugs in there so yeah
right it said not sure if you heard but
someone rewrote depends that exe for
Windows 10 no I did not know that but
that's pretty great let me see what's
going on with that that's pretty cool
well I'm a fan of that we don't really
use that much on handmade hero right now
but that's very good to know
do they have an easy download here
yeah that's that's pretty cool we might
have to take a look at that at some
point if we ever have a reason to do so
that's cool because yeah the I like the
old dependency Walker program it's cool
but it definitely it was definitely like
not maintained really you know so it's
cool that someone is taking that on
alright looks like new cues so I will go
ahead and shut things down
to green x6 so you used Emacs without
code completion F for critter how do you
work without code completion code
completion so I assume you mean like
like structure members or whatever
because I do use word completion right
so I often do like you know that sort of
thing
I don't so code completion is a tough
one for me because I don't really want
code completion most of the time when
I've you had to use like Visual Studio
and stuff when it had it on it drives me
nuts but I think mostly that's because
of the way it was implemented so I think
code completion would be useful if it
was done probably differently like like
I probably never really want code
completion I probably just want a
heads-up display that shows me the
structs and the functions that I happen
to be around at that time because what I
usually do right is I do that manually
by going like you know finding the thing
that I'm looking for here and then
typing in here or whatever so I have it
up and I'm looking at it that's really
what I want the completion I don't
really care that much about other than
obviously when I hit tab it could use
that information to only offer
completions that made sense
so that's you know a plus but I don't
find that to be a huge for activity
problem the thing that I would probably
get us at least a slight win from is if
it just automatically brought up the
things that I was that were involved in
the current function automatically line
them up on the left that's what I would
really want right
long billion when the lighting is in
real time will that tend to hide some of
them are minor artifacts I don't think
so if anything the opposite will
probably be true like for all we know we
will have some artifacts that only
really are evident when we are moving
the light around continuously or lights
are moving around continuously so I
would say that we we certainly shouldn't
count on having any you know gifts if
you will in terms of covering up our
mistakes from the real-time lighting if
anything I think we'll probably end up
with the opposite where you know we
might end up with a artifact or two that
we have to address that is only actually
noticeable when you move around
all right
dragoon six was sending a gift
I can't seem to open it on my machine
for some reason like it's hard to copy
things like links to in the terminal
they underlined but then they don't open
era know why Linux is doing that but so
I'm not really sure what this gif is
showing during the typing it just looks
like yeah I don't really know what
that's gif is showing
sorry I can't quite tell I mean I
watched it but it doesn't really it just
kind of showed the it just kind of
showed like a copy of the identifiers
below where it was being typed which I'm
not sure what that how that relates to
the previous discussion
shooing a heads-up display of the
possible I have that didn't that was not
in the gift the gift didn't show that
you serve that gift shows that at least
on mine someone it just types sad and
then it shows sad bar underneath it and
then it just becomes a blank screen
there's no arguments shown there am I
wrong about that
maybe the gift is busted
saiyr twink she says I know finding a
bad API is not hard but if you're a
steed you ever run into an API that was
great to work with one that you seem to
magically just click with
I mean I guess it depends on I mean it
depends on what you consider part of in
the API and and how much I I mean I
think the short answer is probably no
you know I don't really think I have
there's certainly certain api's that I
feel like have good parts of them are
parts of api's that seem to be
particularly good
but I don't know yeah I'm having trouble
thinking of something that I thought was
like a really great API I mean the sad
fact of the matter is it seems to me
like most people don't spend any time
designing api's and they don't spend any
time practicing or getting better at it
either
so most api's are just shipped by people
who have no API design experience and
they don't spend any time making their
api's actually work
I will say that doesn't appear to work
very well does it
is this supposed to be showing me some
dependencies it doesn't seem too
try to read this gif again yeah it
doesn't work on this either I'm using
chromium but it just goes blank after
that part
uh all right I'm gonna wind it down soon
Oh another another attempt at that get
the guess I could try it in Firefox
going okay yeah this one's working
better um so yeah like what what I'm
seeing in this this gif is is works for
me and know that that what's shown in
that gif is the kind of stuff that I
don't want look I definitely don't want
that I find that to be counterproductive
and I'm slower with that than I am
without it the reason is because I I
don't want it to be transient it needs
to be permanent so when I am editing a
piece of code it has to show me the
related stuff permanently on the side it
can't be flickering in and out that is
not useful to me it needs to be
permanently there so if you know the
function that I'm in or the 10 line
window that I'm editing right now or
whatever involves these three structures
and these five functions those the
prototypes and structs that have to be
on the right side in full permanently
and until I move somewhere else and
start editing something else they can't
flicker in and out right it's just not
useful I don't need you to show me
something so restricted right because I
know my code pretty well what I need you
to do is give me a heads up display that
shows the parts of my code that are
related to this part of the code so that
I can look at them and glance and make
sure that there wasn't something
forgotten in those or see if there was
comments in there that I needed to be
reading while I'm doing this you know
and these types of code completion
things they don't really solve that
problem which is the problem that I
actually
have just like telling me which member
functions around this thing is just not
a problem I tend to have that much right
like and it's not a problem that's like
gonna make a huge difference if it
solves it for me what I want is
situational awareness and that requires
actual permanent clear display of the
related parts of the code hopefully that
makes some sense all right why this
depends program doesn't work I don't
know but I guess that's the end of that
all right um I'm gonna go ahead and
close everything down thank you for one
for joining me for an episode of hand
made here at certified recording with
you as always if you would like to
follow along with series at home you can
always pre-order the game on hand Mahiro
org it comes with a source code so you
can play around with it we also have a
forum site you can go to if you want to
ask questions we have a patreon page you
go to from us fourth video series we
have a schedule bot that tells you when
we're gonna be live and an episode guide
which we will try to figure out how to
get updated I guess it wasn't updating
because of a server problem
I don't do the episode guy that's other
folks so yeah but I will be talking to
me below ever to see if I can figure out
fix the thing that is stopping him from
being able to update it and then that
should be back as well alright that's it
for today I will not be here tomorrow
because I have prior record engagements
I have to do so I will be back probably
the weekend after until then take it
easy everyone have fun programming and
I'll see everyone on the Internet thank
you is everybody