hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show we could a complete game
live on stream we yesterday did
something that I think was pretty
important to do and I probably should
have done it a little sooner but I'm
glad we finally did it which was just
moving lighting code over to the CPU
side for development purposes just so we
can see everything more clearly and
actually develop the algorithm in a more
flexible environment before trying to
run it on the GPU which I really should
have done initially I just didn't think
of it for some reason thankfully we
didn't spend that much time doing
anything with GPU lighting that we
didn't probably already need to do in
terms of like just making the rendering
pipeline more flexible but definitely a
good idea so I'm glad we did that so
today what we want to do now that we
we've gotten that working is to go in
and actually start to try to get the
lighting equations and some method of
executing them that's not too slow into
a place where we're happy with it and
comfortable with what's going on and so
that's what I'd like to do today there's
a couple things that we need to do with
respect to that and we'll sort of take
them one by one
today is day 400 so you want to start
with day 399 source code if you're
following along at home I will go ahead
and load up the build here just so you
can see what I'm talking about if you
didn't catch yesterday stream so I'm
going to go ahead and build we are
building in release mode at the moment
because we happen to be doing some
n-squared
stuff for testing how we're doing the
lighting obvi we won't be doing in
squared stuff eventually but in order to
make it run fast enough well we're sort
of randomly testing stuff we need to
have the optimizer optimize our code for
us so what you can see right here is
instead of rendering the game right now
we're just rendering a series of little
reflector discs we don't bother
rendering them as actual bits we just
you could imagine these being circular
but they're they're diamond subscribed
to the disk that we actually
representing and these are just little
lighting pieces of lighting information
that we are going to stimulate on now we
haven't decided officially anything
about the letting algorithm this is just
our start and you can see right now that
we've just got a simple lighting
equation happening here that's not
particularly useful but you can kind of
see that it has a facing Direction
concept built in so for example all of
these things which are facing the light
source here are white right now all of
these things that are facing away from
the light sorts are black that is
actually correct per the current
lighting equation that's in there we
have some decisions to make in some work
to do regarding double-sided miss and
how we want that to work but we'll see
as we kind of go forwards how that's
going to play out so anyway you can you
can see roughly what we're trying to
simulate here and what we want to do
today is to start getting a little bit
really two things we want to start
getting a little bit more specific about
how we're doing the lighting in terms of
the test case so for example right now
you can see what happens is as I move
around the lighting is varying quite a
bit by the hero illumination itself and
that's just because rather than move the
light around we just did a kind of
cheesy little thing that lights up one
of the things on the hero and if it's in
a radius right it's kind of dumb so what
we should probably do today is get it so
that we are actually specifying lighting
information to the renderer so we can
just specify that there's a light
somewhere that moves around and know
that it's moving around smoothly and
consistently and isn't a part of the
weird like hero situation right so we
want to do something like that
and the other thing that we want to do
is actually start thinking about how
we're going to be computing these
lighting equations for real you can see
how we've got these these light sources
here moving around and it's sort of
computing some lighting but it has a
number of things that aren't right it
looks a little flicker II I think that
may have to do with how we're specifying
the light sources to begin with not the
wedding equation but there is that
anyway we have to deal with a bunch of
things we have to go in and do some
reasonable fall-off we have to do how
we're going to do reflection and then we
also have to figure out how we're going
to start propagating the stuff around in
a better way and that will probably
involve the other thing that we might
want to do today if we have time which
is to create a scene that's a little
more useful so for example right now we
pretty much don't even really have any
tall walls in the scene you know it's
just a couple little trees around the
outside and the ground for lighting we
would like to have some walls just so we
can see that we're properly like
reducing the amount of light that
happens like behind the wall or other
things like this so we got some things
we want to do there and that's really
just you know a vague idea of the sorts
of stuff we're going to poke into
nothing too specific it's just the
general sorts of things that we want to
start playing with so if I open up that
lighting code you can see the way it's
working here we currently have let me
see here we do have a type of valve us
talked about this typo we do X have a
typo here the front emit see this should
be a summation was not a summation that
was a mistake obviously every lighting
past we were supposed to sum up what was
going on when we didn't so that's what
that's what this is here this is this
now the one that's properly some ated
which is good and similarly we had taken
off the distance fall-off so this was
actually how that should have been
running here is distance fall-off with
summation and you can see that actually
this is not so bad it's really just a
flicker eNOS that we want to look at and
I'm like I said I'm not sure about a lot
of things here in terms of what we have
working properly and what we don't so I
want to go through now because we only
just did this yesterday I'd like
go through now and be able to kind of
play around with this a little bit more
so one of the things about this I think
so this bill huh we're still computing
the GPU lighting stuff which is kind of
fine we're computing the lighting on the
lighting which is kind of funny anyway
we have the we have our normals view
here which I guess is still kind of
potentially useful one thing that is a
little bit odd is those normals don't
look quite right for for the hero that's
moving around there so anyway it'll be
interesting to see what as we sort of
step through this a little bit more and
gain a better understanding of what's
going on if we can figure out some ways
to get some more you know some improved
lighting here and and and figure out if
we can do something reasonable with this
approach and again like we've kind of
got some weird stuff in terms of how
we're structuring it so we don't even
really know if this is the way we want
to do reflectors in terms of how they're
placed right now we're just doing one
reflector per card but if you think
about how we might want to in the future
we may want to do more than one
reflector per card we also don't know if
a disc is the right way to represent it
we may want to try to represent them in
different ways and bla bla bla bla so we
have a lot to to think about now that we
actually have a reasonable place we can
experiment and figure out what's going
on so let's start by just I want to
verify that the the diffused inner
product here is the thing that's causing
the flickering because I assume that it
is and so I'm just going to comment that
out for a moment
and verify that everything is smooth and
so okay so it's not so that's really
good actually because that does suggest
that we've got some other sort of thing
going on here that doesn't have to do
with the lighting angle so that's
actually pretty nice and and that
suggests to me that that it's just
bug that or you know potentially with
again with the lighting specification I
don't know exactly how would how it's
being affected there but that's really
good so let's start by taking the step
of getting a very specific light source
in place so we don't have this weird way
that the light source is currently being
specified that's not you know not good
at all and so what we've got here you
can see this is the way that we're doing
the lighting right now it's basically
testing to see whether or not an element
is far enough away from the sort of the
debug light source that's been specified
and if it's too far away it's not a life
it's close enough it is a light so
basically we're just creating a sphere
that makes things light sources into the
side of fear what I'd rather have
obviously is I'd rather just have some
light sources so some things that are
specifically light sources and that's
all but unfortunately we don't really
have a way to do that at the moment and
so the question is how can we do that
right we would like some way ideally of
being able to specify that there's some
lighting in here that is the places
where lights are actually emitted you
know where they're actually emitting
light directly and so in order to do
that we need some emissions data now
that emissions data again it's a little
bit difficult to think about how this
should be specified because there's a
number of different ways that we might
want to do it and they all have kind of
interesting implications right so one
way we can do it is just to augment our
notion of color with something that says
whether there's some immittance or not
right so the most straightforward way to
do it would just be to say like okay
when we look at one of those platform
vertices this thing here that we're
actually using for all the rendering
what we would say is well all right you
know we've got a v4 that's the position
of VP that's the normal v2 this UV and
then a color and that's reflected color
if we just had a value here that's
emission that ranged from zero to one
like you know this sort of thing then
you could imagine that being used to
determine whether a particular sprite
card was emissive or not and the problem
with that of course is that it's
massively over specified for our
purposes we don't have very many things
that will be emitting probably you know
in in a typical game a lot more things
or non emitters than our emitters you
know unless your geometry wars or
something like this where everything is
bright and glowy and lit up so you know
at least theoretically the the textured
vertex in this case would be a massively
over specified weighted to it now I
don't actually know if there's anything
wrong with that so it may be that it's
not really too much extra bandwidth and
hey it's just convenient to be able to
light anything up that we want to but
there you go the other way we could be
doing this is we could be specifying a
separate set of data where in addition
to specifying all the textured vertices
in one array we actually have a
secondary array that's just for the lit
ones and then you know if they were
something that happened in a separate
pass that would occur I'm gonna start as
we typically do with the simplest
possible thing and say that let's just
tack an emission value onto the end of
the textured vertex structure so after
the color value will have an emission
value and it does make this structure a
little bit bigger which is not great but
oh well and we can also if we wanted to
imagine trying to smush this down into
something that's more precise or I
should say smaller and not floating
point we could say that the v2 UV that
we have that's two floating point values
for the UV coordinate but we don't
really need that the reason we don't
need that is because if you think about
our textures
we don't have any textures that actually
aren't just zero to one for the most
part for the UVs so probably for most
purposes we could get away with
something much less than a
floating-point value for our UV
coordinates and it wouldn't cause a
problem so if we wanted to start
smashing this down we definitely could
similarly the normal does not have to be
sort in that format so I'm going to go
ahead and say that it's probably okay to
put the emission in here because we have
a lot of fat in here already if it
became time to really get aggressive
with how this stuff was packed down we
could easily make this thing probably
half the size that it is and not suffer
much so I'm not going to worry about
that too much because again I think we
have a lot of headroom there we're not
pushing up against anything in
particular so I'm not going to consider
that a critical part at least not at
this point so if we added an emission
value there
in theory I think everything is
currently based off the size of that so
nothing happens right everything
currently correctly looks at the size of
that textured vertex including the GPU
code so adding the emission there
doesn't really affect anybody now what
we need to be able to do though is when
we do a push quad inside the render
group so if you take a look at at the
push quad call here which is the thing
that puts all of the actual rendering
data into the render buffers at the GPU
see you can see that it never sets that
information so what we really need here
is emission to be specified in some way
and so so if we have something here like
your mission that's going to specify
what's getting emitted out of this this
particular sprite or cubeface either one
if we have an emission value there we
just need some way for the push quad to
actually set that value right and if you
take a look at where push quad of being
used typically what happens is you know
we call it from something that's trying
to generate you know here's a push
bitmap call the generate said here's a
push to you call
and so if we assume that like maybe the
push cube call is the thing that will
make you are lighting at the moment just
because why not what we can do there is
say well okay maybe the push Claud just
has a default value that's like the
emission and it by default is set to
zero right and then we can make other
things set it to something that's not
zero if I go into the lighting code
right now and now correct for the fact
that we were setting this emission in
sort of a more ad hoc way what I can do
is say element here front emit C equals
the emission of vertex say zero to vert
cero
emission can become the front you may
see right or more specifically I suppose
since we need a color value here we'll
just take whatever the reflection color
is of this thing and multiply it by the
emission value right so that's a good
way to be able to set the emission in
there and we'll leave it at that
so right now in theory everything should
should be unlit because there's now no
light source right and so what we want
to do is actually add a light source in
here and so inside the render group
where I do push cube let's take a look
at that ago yeah you can see here so if
I was going to do a push cube like this
one here and I wanted to have it do
emission again I can just make an
emission value here and that emission
value can be zero and then later I can I
can make one of these that pushes a
light source on for example in this case
what I can do is say maybe I'll make a
thing that's just like a push light
thing something like this and there's an
emission value here and a color value
right we're going to get rid of the
height value so
they'll just be a little like see earth
effect effectively it won't really be
quite treated as a sphere at that time
and so what I'll do here is just say
that there's that white bitmap right
that we use when we don't want a bitmap
to be involved I don't think we can
specify zero here but we can specify a
white bitmap and so the white bitmap is
just a thing in the render commands
right so if I go ahead and save the
render command swipe it path is what the
bitmap is going to be used every time we
do a push cube we passed past the P the
radius and then we say that the height
is also has the radius and off we go
then we have the color and the emission
now the problem here is that I believe
the p-value is like the floor point so
we would also want to basically do
something where we take and we offset
this by half the radius I think don't
quote me on that but I believe that if
we wanted to Center the light about the
P point I believe that's how it's
currently working I could be wrong yeah
okay
don't ask me why we did that probably
because we were thinking if it was
mostly floor values I don't know maybe
it's a good idea maybe it stupid hard
site anyway so if we take a look at the
push light call now and compile it
should be fine I'm going to go ahead and
add one in now and then we can also pull
out that concept of debug light
completely so inside world mode where
we're setting the debug light P like
this what I can do is say all right
after you know we're going to go do this
stuff and we're going to push our
entities on so we're in here right and
we do you know whatever we're going to
do I could say all right after we figure
out our debug light stuff then I'm going
to go ahead and push that light onto the
on the stack here under the rendering
stack the emission values can be 1.0 the
color value at the moment will be white
although we probably want to start
playing around that a little
the radius probably shouldn't be too big
let's just say it's like tenth of a
meter let's go ahead and make the
location of it be this debug light
position that we bothered to do there
and then of course yeah that bitmap ID
we don't need anymore so we can just
delete that entirely so that's something
that will add a light on oops I gotta
grab the render grip here so that will
add a light at the default light
position lights can't really be
translucent in this case so I think I
should probably change that value now
that I think about it
instead it should be a v3 color and when
you push the cube on it should probably
be done in that fashion right so in
theory now we should be pushing on a
little cube light but you know I'll be
honest I don't see a lot of Cube lights
there to you well it's right there
actually so now I take it back I do see
it it's just not lit up so that's an
issue so the question is why are we not
getting any emission there so let's take
a look at how that flows through the
pipe ah it's because we're not passing
it here we go oh wait but that's the
wrong one sorry this was the one I
wanted there we go
so now we'll get those push quads in
there there we go
then the two over those convert all the
argument types is there some other push
Claude and we have multiple squads here
that took different parameters note
there's only one oh no there is there
there's one so let's get that mission in
there and this is just the thing that
does the packing their submission all
right so now in theory we should have
there we go so now we know that this
light is moving along smoothly and it
does have considerably less of that
flickering occurring so that's actually
quite nice so that's a good start anyway
let's take a look and see if we can't
see that little one right there so
that's where the lights coming from now
why that isn't lit I'm not sure why it's
not lit itself right because that's the
that's the light right there that we're
looking at right so that's a little bit
odd I don't pretend to know why that's
happening let's take a look at what's
going on there so if I now if I hop down
here to the lighting routine so
obviously the light distance is not
going to transfer I guess the problem is
just a qmc is not going to have that
front in it in it anywhere
but it should start out with that value
right it should have the front emit from
here where it gets its initial emission
set and so in theory when we do the copy
light out we should be getting I would
think we should be getting that color
value to be lit up for all of those
light vertices right so that's
definitely a little bit strange and I
don't know why we're not getting I
definitely don't know why we're not
getting anything there
hmm hmm I say well I guess one thing is
we should be able to isolate it pretty
easily and see what's going on we could
do something like this I guess I don't
really want to stop here all right so
let me go ahead and grab oh well this is
in not in debug mode you know what but
I'll switch to debug mode real quick so
that we can see what's going on there we
go it's crazy how much slower this is in
debug mode it'd be fun to look at the
assembly for that loop and see what is
so slow about debug mode right it's
pretty amazing
anyway so if we go ahead and switch over
to the render group here it looks like
we don't have that let me go ahead and
do floating test so if I go ahead and
set the breakpoint here then we know
which one we're on at this point
is one of the lit ones so it's quad
indexed for 53 out of 483 so quad for 53
is the or at least one of the lighting
quads if the mission is one its RGB is
one so it should be white right so now
let's take a look so for 453 in theory
like you know that it should not really
get modified at all because if anything
it should only increase the lighting
value that's there so it starts out with
a front emission of one one one which is
you know full light so
question is what happens to it right so
let's take a look here at the end let's
take a look at 4:53 and see what we end
up with so if I come through here and we
look at the we've got quad index I'm
going to set a break point condition
quad index equals 4 53 and I'm going to
run it so here we are we should be on
quad index for 53 now which we know is
our lit quad and it is so we take a look
at the front of it color and it is
exactly what I expect it to be which is
1 1 1 so looking here at what we
generate for the color let's take a look
oh we did it again I have another typo
it's not supposed to be using the
accusing that we had two typos that's
okay we only working on the code for a
day all right what you get when you
don't drink coffee in the morning
I enjoy coffee yesterday I am the coffee
today so I don't even know how I'm even
having any idea what the code is so that
means we were not we were still not
correctly looking at a multipath
lighting solution there all right we can
switch back at it debug modal I would
like to see why do you but my so slow
that would be nice because I think maybe
there's probably there's some things in
there that shouldn't be as slow as they
are or something going on will be
interesting
all right
so now we're correctly viewing those
front admits values which is nice and
you can see here that we've got our
little cube is now properly having some
little light sources there right yeah so
now we're in good shape let's go ahead
and increase the iteration count now
that we should actually be able to see
it so here's a three iteration lighting
and of course things are much brighter
now which is exactly what you'd expect
however you get a lot of that that
flutter it's pretty interesting and
again I assume that comes from the fact
that the hero is a light source that
propagates light at words from the main
light or something like this so we'll
have to let's play around with this a
little bit see I'm not sure why you get
so violent though but anyway let's leave
it at one iteration for now all right so
now that we basically have what we need
let's do one more thing before we start
trying to actually get to working
lighting in here
let's try at least making a wall of some
kind so we can have some sort of testing
regarding that so for example like you
know if we just raised up maybe some of
these these things here just made them
higher so there were some blockers there
so all I'm going to do there is in world
mode where we do ad standard room I'm
just going to do something where we say
like you know here where we're doing our
P offset stuff and we have our sort of
you know
adding adding of information for
creating a grass piece I want to
basically create a I want to create a
thing that looks to see kind of a wall
height sort of thing
I assume let me check this first I don't
really remember how add piece is working
this code is is just all the placeholder
world stuff which is just kind of random
so add piece takes a height or a
dimension I guess in this case and the
dimension gets set here so the dimension
is presumably the radius and the height
so I'm going to go ahead and do that I'm
going to say wall height right now so
point five and put that in here and then
what I'll do is I'll say this 0.5 plus
0.5 when we're in random unilateral I'm
also going to add in the wall height
here right so I'm going to say let's add
the wall height so it'll get moved
upward if it gets higher and then what I
want to do is do all right if offset you
know X is greater than or equal to I
don't know
negative two and offset X is less than
or equal to one let's say and then we'll
do offset y equals negative 2i
then we'll do wall hype equals you know
three
so there's a wall you can kind of see
now I've got a wall in there I think I
actually want to be on the other side so
let's actually have it be in front of me
in the standard view so there's that
wall right
so that's pretty reasonable
so I think that's all we should really
need right because now we have a wall
value we have like a thing that's sort
of standing up right there so I can move
behind that right like so and I can move
in front of that and we should be able
to do something to see whether we're
getting a lighting solution that
properly sort of prevents light from
getting too far that from propagating
too much in areas behind occluders which
is really all we want from the lighting
is some way of like you know because we
already have obviously ways of getting
it to sort of be brighter around the
light source so kind of what we want is
something that propagates the light
around obstacles poorly right it should
not show much light behind obstacles and
you know that will give it sort of the
more of a sense of space more of a sense
that the lighting it's actually light
and that it can is stopped by walls
right so you can kind of already see
some problems that I anticipate with
that which is why I think we may need a
better element representation just not
sure what it would be which is that like
these things probably aren't fit very
well for the stop I mean it might still
work okay again we're just looking for a
rough solution here but you can see that
like you know they they take the
shortest diameter they can find which
means that they are they don't get tall
here which means they wouldn't shadow as
much as they should and other things
like that so anyway all right so we now
have a little thing we can play around
with it's a reasonable approximation for
what the lighting you know for a place
that the lighting should light I guess
the other thing we're not quite doing at
the moment is we don't have a way of
showing the actual world again and so
maybe let's get that in there too before
we get much further so basically like
this thing that we were doing before
where we can show a couple different
passes here let's let's actually make
that'd be a little bit more coherent so
what I'd like to do is I'd like to turn
on and off the copy out lighting so for
example one thing I could do when we're
doing the lightening computation here
when we do the copy of the lighting out
what I'd like to do is say well okay so
when we copy the lighting out let's
actually just not modify the vertices in
the case where you know we'll just
modify the color let's say by the front
emission so you know something that's
sort of like this will come through here
and say all right we grab we grab out
the lighting data and we overwrite it in
the case where we're trying to show the
debug view if we're not trying to show
the debug view out from behind my head
there if we're not trying to show the
debug view then let's use this emission
value more intelligently so for example
let's say in both cases we're going to
grab out what that front emit color was
there but then when we come through here
we're going to set the colors in some
more sane fashion so maybe something
like this I think I want to do this
so maybe something like this you take
the color value that you already have
right you do an RGB unpack that unpacks
the color you multiply it by the front
emit which we know now is like a zero to
one value and we reset it back in
something like that
[Applause]
and then we just need if here this like
whether or not we're doing the debug
view or not and that of course is a
having Mart product which is say each
element of each vector is multiplied
independently so it's our front emit not
a v4 I guess yeah so we should probably
do it as a v4 and then down here
I'll do it like that
all right so in theory this should give
us a way of viewing the world again and
like you can see here it actually does
exactly what we want as well which is it
transfers the lighting on to the thing
that the lighting should have been
transferred onto right and so in theory
anyway as we improve the quality of this
we should be able to we should be able
to get better and better lighting into
the game right so yeah I mean I think
this will work just fine so anyway one
of the things that we've got a problem
with at the moment too though is you can
kind of see this and this is sort of
something that I feel like was part of
the original original algorithm we
should probably put back in which is
that if you look at what's happening
right now
you can kind of see that the we wouldn't
be getting lighting values at the
various vertices right we'd only be
getting lighting values for the entire
sprites which is not going to be very
good so I think what we might want to do
is light at the corners of the
reflectors if this makes any sense in
some way so that we basically put you
know per face we put for lighting
calx sort of on there and and solve them
that way which is how the original
algorithm worked as well it was based on
vertices like oh I can't sit down there
cuz the tree line was preventing me from
getting down there anyway so what I'd
like to do again is just sort of start
to work with this lighting a little bit
better get to a place where it's it's
more what I want right so let's think
about this for a second so if we were to
do exact like what I just suggested we
could for example instead of doing quads
we could do like I said we could do
vertices
excuse me so if I wanted to make the
lighting elements line up with vertices
I would just instead of looping over the
quads
I just loop over the vertices right and
so the way we would do that and I think
that's probably the more interesting way
to go here because for all intents and
purposes I feel like that makes this a
little bit yeah it just makes this a
little bit more clean because then we
get color values at each vertex which
gives us a smoother kind of lighting
interpolation unfortunately I guess I
don't know if that's going to be good
enough in the long run like maybe we
actually want to be able to do per-pixel
lighting and do gathers from this on a
per pixel basis that might be something
we would like to do and so I guess you
know what I'm not going to switch to
that just yet because we can see whether
or not the lighting is working right
from just doing it per face and so we'll
worry about how we do our discretization
and gather let's worry about that
another time right let's worry about
that later all right so what I'd like to
do now is I'd like to make it so that we
have a way of accessing this information
in a little bit more of a toggleable
programmatic fashion so what I want to
do here is I'd like to get it so that we
can quickly toggle with some some keys
between the various views here
so I'd like to be able to have like yeah
you know here in another couple other
places I'd like to be able to have some
some values that we can toggle so we
here if we have this config which is at
this point very dated I don't think we
use much of this but anyway I'm going to
go ahead and add a couple variables here
that we can toggle on and off so one of
them would be like the renderer would be
something like
[Music]
nearly lighting show reflectors like
that and so if I you know put that in
there I should be able to now toggle
that back and back and forth with a key
or something like that I can put that in
there I'd also like to make the the
iteration count here so I'd like to make
that be something we can control as well
so in here it'd be like you know
something like this and and then I would
just need some way of actually modifying
these so I'm going to go into the limb
fairy two codes here and I'm just going
to take a look at the
we have take a look at how this stuff is
working here so what I really want is I
just want one of these incrementer sort
of things for the the reflectors and
that sort of stuff
so I'm just going to go ahead and add
one of those here like let's say we take
BK like f1 or something like so and I'll
just have like show reflectors equals
not show reflectors right and in theory
does this not know about the Global's so
now how does this not know about the
Global's are these statics hmm
hmm well that's unfortunate
if the Global's are not exposed to the
win32 layer I can't hack in keyboard
commands for them I I don't know if I
want to do that or not the problem here
is since we're rendering it low-res at
the moment which I guess we don't
necessarily have to do anymore because I
could turn off all of the lighting stuff
that was happening on the GPU side so
let me actually do that and then we
could just use the regular interface for
it you can see what I mean like right
now using the this thing is a nightmare
because it's too big but I guess the
reason that we were you know in the
OpenGL world we were doing a bunch of
stuff that we didn't really need to be
doing at that we don't really need to be
doing at the moment because of the
OpenGL lighting we don't need to do
compute lighting transport for example
right it's completely irrelevant I guess
I'll just not call it
so since we're not doing any of that
code anymore we can probably go ahead
and increase the resolution back up now
[Applause]
and that's fine you know it's still a
little slow but it's not not a huge deal
right it's totally usable for lighting
so yeah so now if I look in here I could
add these to the renderer I would like
it to be faster than that
so I don't love this as a solution but
yeah yeah not not my favorite thing but
what are you going to do so the the
lighting stuff here we can edit now and
fear anyway so yeah if I go into
renderer lighting show reflectors I can
toggle that on and off now and switch
between the two of them we don't have a
way of editing integers at the moment so
I would have to add one of those for the
iteration count though
all right so that's all well and good
but I think so at this point yeah at
this point we would just need some way
of editing the iteration count and
that's about all we would have to do but
now it's pretty easy to switch between
them
I would like key for it but oh well so
in this situation now what I have to do
is start start looking at how we're
actually computing the lighting as it
propagates around to these various
reflectors so let's take a look at
basically the you know just lets the
think the whole lighting pipe in terms
of the equations there and see what we
want to do with it right so there's two
aspects that we want to start working on
and one of them is the one that I guess
I'll put tilt to last because we want to
make sure we have our lighting equations
working well before I move to that and
that is that right now we're doing N
squared so we're checking every
reflector against every other reflector
obviously that will scale but
unfortunately lighting is N squared so
there's no way we're ever going to make
lighting not be fundamentally N squared
if we want to do a reasonable
approximation of it however what we can
do to make it not actually run M squared
is just do it hierarchically right and
again this is from the original
algorithms if we just go ahead and say
when we compute lighting transfer will
use the reflectors right around us to
compute actual reflector to reflector
ones we'll do that for you know five or
six of them but then as we get further
away
we'll use sort of aggregated reflectors
that are bigger averages of the other
reflectors in that area that's what
we'll use to determine the lighting
right so that way even though
technically the lighting will always be
N squared
and the N might be you know three
thousand five thousand something like
that and we could never do n times n
we're really going to change it to doing
n times M where you know yes five
thousand is the end but we have a
hierarchical versions of it so that
every time we loop through each one of
those five thousand we're actually not
going to loop through the five thousand
other ones to compare it against we're
going to loop through like twelve or
twenty right or a thirty right so we're
going to try to keep that number scaled
down the second number in that group
right so that's the you know the vague
plan anyway alright so here's how we
want to you know do this this
computation right so we're going to go
ahead and compute the lighting and when
we live through and we say you know how
do we you know can we see this other
light or whatever else we're going to
have to start using some some shadowing
and again this is going to continue to
make the algorithm slower and and
trickier but that's okay right so if we
go ahead and take a look at how the
shadowing is working here from the
original algorithm that we were sort of
vaguely starting with you know which is
not quite yeah I mean you get the idea
but basically what we do here is I the
way that shadows work in this algorithm
is kind of a little bit bogus it's
actually not a little bit bogus it's
kind of a lot bogus right so the way
that it works is it says we want to be
able to calculate how much can be seen
from each individual one of these
reflectors and the way that it chooses
to do that is by sort of computing a
general visibility for that occluder
before that reflector so what it says
it's like alright I need to be able to
see how many other reflectors might be
cutting off my view of the general area
around me so it's kind of just it's just
an ambient occlusion pass
right as far as I know for shadows in
the first instance right so that's
that's like all this thing will compute
is the ambient occlusion then when it
actually does the the lighting right so
all that the only kind of shadowing it
has is that kind of shadowing right and
then when they want to do the indirect
lighting for it here it just goes ahead
and does the same sort of transference
of the of the lighting values it does
the same sort of transference for the
lighting values that it was doing sort
of for the shadowing and it just assumes
that there's no more shadowing other
than that right and this is not
particularly good right so the reason
this is not particularly good is this
doesn't really give much this doesn't
really give much benefit to sort of the
shadowing of the kind that I was talking
about right like if I want to if I want
to sort of come in here and have this
this is that's a bit of an issue
it looks like the Z bias there is not
sufficient to I guess because this wall
is so high yeah that wall is extremely
high actually sorry where's oh yeah so
if we want to you know deal with this
particular part of the problem where
we're basically saying like okay we want
sort of the area back here to not show
very much light and there's something on
the other side of it that is that is
lighting it right then we definitely
have a problem where you know if there
is a wall on the other side here like
this tree for example whatever the the
let's actually turn on the
selectors there so like for example this
tree on the other side here what you can
kind of see is that well you know this
when we compute the ambient occlusion of
it yet it will have some less you know
ambient light because of this wall but
it's not going to have like a hundred
percent occlusion but that's roughly
what it should have if this was the only
light in the scene right like there's no
way for this wall to see this light
pretty much at all it's just going to be
dark back here this is the only light
even after you take into account
multiple bounces it's going to be very
dark because a little light will get in
by like bouncing it through here you
know best-case scenario but it'll be
still these very dark back there right
but that's not what we would compute
using this scheme because this scheme
doesn't really take into account
shadowing in that way and the reason
that it doesn't take into account having
that way is because it would be really
hard to do so I would think right
because if you if you consider how this
works it becomes almost an N cubed
problem it's like in fact it is
literally an N cube problem I think so
for every light
hmm for every light that we have that's
projecting out into the world and every
reflector you know that's receiving that
light every other reflector has to be
considered to see if it cuts down the
amount of light that's coming that's
going to hit it right and so that's just
not a very tenable solution right
there's not a lot of ways to do anything
to get around that fact and so as far as
I know like they don't even try to
address that in this in the original
sort of source material they just say
like well we compute a general shadow a
map so serious occlusion unless it right
so we doesn't have any way of really
computing the fact that lights can't
reach up can't reach some area in fact
you could construct pathological cases
right where you said something like okay
you know we've got a tall wall here that
completely cuts a room in half except
for like a little thing in the top of
the ceiling right and then there's like
this light here and we're talking about
this wall here and or even if it went
all the way up I suspect trying to
compute whether this thing saw this
light source is not that much different
if the thing is on this side of the wall
and this side of the wall like if the
light sphere or the lights here it
doesn't seem like you would really even
get that much of a difference in
solution right because it's not checking
to see whether the wall is in between it
or not it never has that calculation
really I don't think so let me
double-check again just to make sure
that I'm not stating that incorrectly
but let's see
bah-bah-bah
so it looks like the way they do it is
for actual specific lights themselves
they compute shadow maps to try and get
like that's how you're getting this
shadowing in here they just compute
shadow maps to try and make that direct
lighting work but that means that
effectively your bounce lighting doesn't
have any shadows it's only your direct
light and it only has a hard shadow it
only has like the shadow map shadow
right so yeah again you know not great
but that's just you know that's just the
way it is so I don't know I'm not
against old I'm using this is
particularly the way that we should do
it but you know let's go a little bit
further down here anyway because like I
said I don't know that we'll ever really
get anything good with the shadows
anyway in terms I mean without
pre-computation of how the light bounces
around the scene I'm not sure how much
of that we could really do now there is
to be honest there is something we could
look into this goes a little bit past
this which is to say that we could do
something that's an iterative solution
where basically like if you imagine
these these reflectors right so if I was
to say take a look at these we could do
something where every frame we do some
kind of an operation that retains
information about the lighting so that
as we like progressively determines how
much shadowing there is everywhere so
you know you could go down a route more
like that where there's like an interest
solution so it does try to do more in
terms of figuring out how the light
bouncing works and it just gets better
over over subsequent frames because it
would be too slow to do on one frame
from whole cloth but you could try to
store for every for every frame like
what you determined and use that on the
next frame to you know continue
determining it further so there is a
little bit of that right that we can do
but I don't know that I want to get into
that necessarily in the long run all
right so again let's let's try to let's
play with it a little bit more here
let's try to improve how we're doing our
Lighting's in general so for the
lighting computation if we wanted to
start doing the the thing that they were
talking about before in the paper about
computing a general idea of how much
shadowing there is on any particular
thing we could try that so let's just do
that part of it just to see what that
gives us in terms of anything that we
actually care about you know two terms
for anything that's actually useful
there right so what I'm going to do is
I'm going to create a thing in the
lighting element that's called like you
know visibility or something right and
what I'm going to do is in the initial
copy app path I'm going to set the
visibility equal to one so we're just
going to assume that every reflector can
see the entire hemisphere that's in
front of it that's the initial
assumption right don't need the same
work so when I run will have that then
what I'm going to do is yeah we've got
this lighting computation I'm not even
going to care about it though what I'm
going to do instead is am in a set front
emit just going to cold set it here and
in fact I can even do it this way
[Applause]
what I'm going to do is I'm going to set
front emit equal to just straight up the
visibility of the element and I'll go
into the config and make that a
configuration parameter as well and I'll
make them both happening at the moment
[Applause]
and so now what will happen is every one
should start out with that visibility
value as 1 so this everything should be
perfectly white right and so then what I
can do is I can say all right now let's
actually try doing that path where we do
the disk to disk sort of occlusion right
so here's the way that the ambient
occlusion is calculated that's the code
for it just clip that right now and just
go to the equation so you can see how
they do their approximation of the
shadow right and we talked about this
equation before so the way they do it is
they do 1 minus the R is the radius of
the sorry R is the distance between the
two right yeah it's this line our
distance between the two so how far away
they are we've got the cosine of the
angle to that line of the emitter we've
got the angle of the reflector right so
those are just two dot products there
and then we've got the area of the I
assume the the emitter right as well
let's see here
yeah
yep so we should be able to do a direct
implementation of this because we have
all the information that we actually
need so if we want to we can do that
again that's going to be one of these
loops here so this is just looping over
everything it's just a standard source
test loop that looks like this right so
we don't want to shadow ourselves so
when we do this this test we want to
sort of do like source and X naught
equal to destined next here because we
don't want to compute like our own
shadow on ourselves that doesn't really
make any sense right so it's a couple
ways you can test it but that's
definitely probably the easiest way and
so what we want to do here is you want
to compute that equation so we want to
do like this shadow here 1 minus sort of
that length so that's the R term there
this is the the cosine emitter
we've got maximum here of one and four
times the cosine of the reflector and
then that whole thing is over the square
root of the area over PI plus R squared
all right so this is the amid area times
one over PI and that's plus the distance
squared so that's what that equation
looks like there and you can see the way
that they implemented it here you can
see that they actually pre they pre
divided by PI for the emitter area I
don't know that we care about that doing
anything those are like just
optimizations of the equation for faster
computation we do want to do that
eventually I don't think we want to do
that quite yet right and the other thing
that looks like they did here is they
optimized out
the are so in this case here you can see
there's an R in the term and it looks
like they got rid of that right so you
can see probably what they decided to do
here not sure how they actually got rid
of that let's see what they decided to
do there pop in here
so here's the shadow approximation
equation they've got one minus R cosine
theta max 1/4 times cosine Phi and then
we've got all over root K over pi plus R
squared oops
here's what they're doing oops and
that's actually a 1 minus out there so
how they actually got rid of the are on
top is not immediately clear to me so
they did say that they're going to
assume that the area is pre divided by
PI right so they're assuming that this
is just going to be a if that makes
sense or some special value right that
that is the case but that's not really
the interesting part right the
interesting part is is the rest of it so
what I'm suing is the way they probably
got rid of this if this is R cosine
theta then what they probably do is just
say well okay we're going to take this
vector and this is pretty nice I like
this we're going to take this vector
between the two and I know that I need
to compute these cosine terms right so
you can see that I've got a in fact
period here it is
[Applause]
you can see that I got the cosine terms
here this cosine term and this cosine
term if I were to do these directly
without normalizing our first meaning
without turning into a unit vector then
by default I'm going to get our cosine e
anyway right that's what's going to
happen if I just do this with regular R
and I do the cosine with this vector if
I do the dot product of this vector I'm
going to get R cosine this angle anyway
so that term is free to - it's free to
get the R in there which makes sense of
why it doesn't show up this one on the
other hand where it's for cosine theta R
that one I'm not so sure about
because let's see what they're actually
computing in here right we've got one -
rescript reciprocal square root is what
R squared stands for so it's basically 1
over the square root if that makes sense
so they did 1 minus the reciprocal
square root of the emitter area which we
know is actually this because they're
actually pre dividing it they said over
R squared plus 1 right so it's the
square root of that over R squared plus
so they actually it's actually inverted
it right I'm assuming that that's
actually because reciprocal square root
was available in square root wasn't
because the otherwise I'm not sure why
you would do that do it that way that
does seem a little bit odd to me it does
seem a little bit odd to me but anyway
that's what they're computing there and
then their computing times the saturate
is just a maximum of 1 in the thing so
that is just that's that's just this the
M the emitter normal V so the emitter
normally is this def this cosine term
here so I called that one Phi I believe
right no I'm sorry
I called that one regular theta so they
do emitter normal V so that's regular
theta that's cosine theta times R
because you can see they didn't
normalize it here presumably at least
they didn't suggest they did maybe they
did
they didn't really say so not sure
anyway then they do a saturation of four
times the dot product so they do they do
this term as well and again that's
receiver normal B so that in theory
produces another R right so it looks
more to me like they're actually
computing this right
they're computing R cosine theta R
coasts for R cosine Phi and multiplying
those two together right it looks like
there's an R in there to me so the
question is did they get rid of that are
in some other way
and I don't know right so if they did
get rid of that are in some other way it
would be down in here and so what we
know we have insight here is that that
root term right we know is that root a
over PI over R squared plus one so I
believe what they've got here right
although actually I guess this divide
the wit now that's not true the plus one
this isn't math so the plus one is
actually be on the outside so it's
actually that right like so so that
actually makes some sense because if the
term that you were computing was this
right and you only had reciprocal square
root then probably they had to what they
had to do here was kind of fuss with
that equation to make it come out
properly but let's take a look so if
that's one over the square root of that
like so it's hard to really figure out
just by looking at it how that would
translate into a regular square root
term
but actually since this is on the
underside to begin with I guess that
makes so nevermind the reason they're
doing reciprocal square is probably cuz
they actually want the reciprocal square
root yeah because it actually is on the
other side so never mind so really it
actually is exactly equivalent just with
a weird weird lead to Vaught they are
weirdly dividing by r-squared there
which is not what they suggest that they
were doing before right so they had
previously on the bottom root a over pi
plus r squared and they change that into
a over r squared or a over pi over r
squared plus one so what does that
actually come out to equal
I guess it's a so so you know if I was
to start fussing with this you would
imagine combining these two terms right
so if I made this one into an R squared
over R squared which is free to do
because that equals one right if I made
that term into an R squared over R
squared you would end up with this which
allows me to add them together so it
would end up being a over PI plus R
squared over R squared the reason I did
that is because once I add them together
I can pull out the R squared right
because this equation can be written
again as a product of two terms it could
be written as the product of 1 over R
squared right times a PI plus R squared
over 1 right that that can be pulled out
and if we were going to do that the R
could the the 1 over R squared could
come out of the square root right
at least I believe that's true however I
like I said they put that in there for a
reason I'm not sure what the reason is
but if we were to move that out there I
believe we would end up with this which
is one over our a over pi plus r squared
so which is the original thing we we had
right it's this so I think that gets me
to where I wanted to be which is if you
look at that one over R that comes out
of this term it looks like what they did
is they shoved it down in there because
that's exactly the r I was missing
remember I was like where did the are go
that's this R because this R would come
out and it would make an R squared here
which you could push to the bottom by
adding an R here right I guess only
problem is that's a 1 over R squared
I'm sorry to 1 over R when it actually
should just be a regular R and it's not
that so I'm still a little bit off I
don't know
yeah because if I wanted to get rid of
the are here I would have to introduce
an R on the underside to cancel it right
am I wrong about that no I I am wrong
about that my master rusty so let's say
we actually did that through I think it
actually does come out the way I said so
let's say we have an extra R on the top
right and we want to move that R to the
bottom because we know that we're going
to be computing this thing an extra R is
going to pop out here that we don't want
in the equation well if I multiply both
sides by 1 over I mean if I multiply
both top and the bottom by 1 over R that
is what happens I get a 1 over R in here
and this one over R cancels that 1 over
R right so I guess that's correct
I could vaguely convince that myself
that's correct I don't love it
this is one of the things that's kind of
annoying like I don't love it when a
when a paper that's you know ostensibly
telling you how to do something will be
like so we're going to use this equation
for shadow approximation and we're not
really going to explain it much so you
got to work that out and then we're also
going to give you the source code to it
that actually bears no resemblance to
this equation and we're going to force
you to actually have to figure out how
to get get to that answer right it's fun
as an exercise for the reader in some
sense but it's also like well I don't
know how you did it and I can sit here
and guess but what if I can't quite make
it work out I'd like to be able to know
well what actually you know how actually
did you do it like what was the actual
process there or even if I can't figure
out why it would be nice to know what
your thought process was behind it right
so some explanation as to how you did it
would be good you know so anyway I
that's that's a little wonky to me I'm
not sure exactly that that's correct
but it's close to anyway
and I suspect again like I said what's
happening is that gut I assume that got
changed because of the extra are because
if it wasn't that then I'm not sure
where the extra are term went it looks
like they just magically said we don't
care but that's not good right so they
must that must have been their goal is
they were just like well we'll push that
into the R square term because it you
know it just so happens that it
simplifies out that way and that makes
it so that we don't have to ever
normalize V which you know we definitely
don't want to have to do for no reason
right if it turns out that we always
want our terms in there then off we go
so yeah so there we go that's you know
that's something but anyway yeah it
again if we look down at what they're
actually doing there so let's let's
compute because we've got sort of two
terms here right we've got the the two
the dot normal terms and then we have
the reciprocal square root term so if we
take a look at the dot normal terms
these two ones here I also would note
that they're doing the saturate on
they're doing a saturate on these but
I'm not sure I assume that's just a
clamp it down below zero
look I can't say I know exactly what
that saturation term is meant to be
doing there I assume that that
saturation term is just there to prevent
two things from shadowing each other if
they're facing opposite directions but
in our case I don't know that we
actually don't want that right because
we may want well oh yeah I don't know
maybe we do want to consider the
backside because we do have cubes in
there so I'm assuming that the only
point of this saturate right is to
prevent the thing this one here from
going down below zero this saturate is
because I believe the definition of
saturate indirect Xcode right
I believe the saturate function just
clamps to zero and one
yeah and so I believe that the this
initial saturate here for the emitter
normal and V right is it's never going
to be above one like there's no way that
this times this is going to be above one
if this were normalized whew that's even
weirder so if that's saturating from
zero to one that suggests that V already
is normalized because if it wasn't this
would saturate to one all the time
that's even weirder so I guess this is
normalized
they know they know where define Z that
I can see unless you guys see where
they're defining V
sets vector firm receiver to emitter
so here we go we take the vector to
emitter we dot V and V to find the
length of it they're adding an epsilon
here to avoid it being exactly zero
they're going to do you know going down
the Harkey here and they have not yes so
they normalize this V so that just seems
kind of strange because I feel like
that's not necessary
I have questions about the math in this
paper that doesn't seem necessary does
it I mean
I mean if this is really what you wanted
to compute let's just do it ignoring
their math and assume that that is
actually the equation you wanted to
compute which now that I'm questioning
the math in this paper I feel like I
want to derive the salad solid angle
shadowing myself but if I write this
literally just exactly the way they did
it
so let's see what happens here I guess
the problem so this one is obviously a
no break like that's just a no-brainer
that just works right because you would
get R cosine theta e if you didn't
normalize the V that's what you would
get so there's no reason not to do that
right on the other hand this term right
here the problem is this maximum value
right because the maximum value implies
that this first needs to have been
stripped of its length component so you
know if this were computing R for R
cosine theta are the max oh but no it
wouldn't because then all you'd have to
do is do max
R I guess you don't know R is the
problem it's like you could just do max
R and then you're good to go but know
you can't actually do that I take it
back
so if you want to clamp this thing to
one I guess there's your problem right
like the problem here is just we can't
there's no way to get the R to stop
being a problem inside here if we didn't
have to do this max we would I think in
pretty great shape because we could move
it out we could probably use this term
to cancel the our out for us but I guess
just looking at that it does look like
it makes some sense why they have to do
that because yeah I don't see yeah I
don't see any way I don't see nearly get
around that so it does look like all
they all they literally did is they
actually normalized V first and that 1
over R if this R right here coming down
to the bottom right it's what it
actually looks like happened and then
they shove it in here so that looks like
what they actually did so they just
compute this part on the top and they
move the are down to the bottom and
compute it as part of this equation
so all right I can I can live with that
it's fine so let's go ahead and compute
that what that means is that we have to
first actually normalize that sort of
lighting Delta value that we have there
so we want to do is take the despi and
the source B to get that vector and we
want to make sure that we're doing it
the same direction that they are if we
want to be consistent with the paper now
they didn't draw this in either
direction here and but but it is
directional right in a sense that when
you actually go to compute it this V
value is a directional value at that
point because the dot product will come
out differently either way so they have
the emitter and the reflector in this
direction so they're taking the
direction to the emitter so it's really
this right and that's the value that
they're calling V so they're producing
the value that goes from the from the
destination out to the source they're
taking the length of map so we're going
to take the length here Alvie and then
from there they're going to do the
reciprocal square root now I guess since
these will become equivalent like so
what I could do is do like if VLAN
greater than zero here right or some
it's got to be a certain distance away
or I don't know what right it's
something like that so if we first check
that then what we get in here we can we
can then take V and normalize it and now
we have the normal version of V and so
now we can we can actually compute the
solid angle function directly right
which is if this guy here so what we
want to do is say whoever is receiving
this light the amount of the hemisphere
that's blocked
of approximate Weig is going to be this
equation rank so again we've got the s
here ticket all this alright and so what
we want to compute here is 1 minus again
that's a reciprocal square root which I
don't think we actually created an
intrinsic for we probably should because
it is an actual thing but here's there's
some downsides to having reciprocal
square root it's less accurate if you
actually use the x64 our typical square
root so you know I'll put one in here
[Applause]
but what I'm actually going to do is I'm
just going to divide by the square root
and like I said you can call the actual
reciprocal square root here but the
reciprocal square root is less accurate
than the square root in my recollection
in x6 before so you don't really want to
do it until you know you don't care so
typically speaking I'm not going to make
that one do that operation at the outset
so anyways we got the reciprocal square
root we've got the emitter area emitter
area over R squared so we need a mid
area R squared is just the veal N
squared right that's that R vector so we
can just store that as it as an in
between if we want to like we can have
just we just we have a macro for that
essentially
[Applause]
so this computes all the values now we
have the vector between them we've got
the square of the length we've got the
length itself so if we take V squared
that's actually our squared right and do
that divided now the interesting thing
about that is well nevermind what nor
that so we have the reciprocal square
root and that's although I'm good from
there we want to also do our multiplies
now make this a little C caramelize the
saturate is really just our clamp zero
to one so these two terms are clamped
zero to one that's what saturate means
in the direct 3d parlance and here we're
just taking the the inner products again
with our two normals in like I said
these are actually now we've already
normalized these so there's no artisans
just the cosine if that makes sense so
the emitter normal times V and the
destination normal are our two cosine
terms there and we want four times this
one here because we're trying to see how
big it is as it as it tilts right now
the issue with these that I see here
though is this should this should
actually be a negative so I'm assuming
that they pulled the negative out
already because remember these two dot
products they are going in opposite
directions so I'm assuming that that's
that negative that you would get because
you want the if they were perfectly
facing each other it would be a 1 and a
right sorry it be a 1 in the negative 1
and you want to be a 1 and a 1 so I'm
assuming that they already pulled out
that negative but again I'm a little
suspicious of the math in the paper thus
far so I don't know I'll stick to what
it says that I would like to
independently verify that a little bit
better going forwards so this is the
shadowing amount and that shadowing
amount is just what we're going to write
into the element visibility right but
now we need some way of accumulating
this and because again that shadowing
amount is something that's going to
progressively like every person shadows
a little bit more right so in this case
when we look and say all right we've got
to compute this visibility we can't just
define it directly we have to sort of
sum them up right we have to sum up how
much visibility there actually is so
let's take a look at what we're actually
computing here so as these values get
higher so as we as the SI the distance
between them went up for example write
the reciprocal square root term which
divides by the V squared so we want that
reciprocal square root as it gets
further away to get the denominator gets
higher right so that the term in here
should get higher as it gets further
away and it looks like it would because
the emitter area the emitter area if you
get divided by a greater and a greater
and a greater value so that means that
the this term gets smaller and smaller
and smaller which means that the amount
that you add
one well no that's going to the app
straight so they so I take it back
so as this gets higher write as V
squared desire which is a distance
stream them this their this gets closer
to one right
this gets closer and closer to one so if
V squared was infinity so it's
infinitely far away this would just be
one so basically what this is computing
them is this is is computing the it is
it's not computing a shadow amount it's
computing the visibility amount right so
it is computing this thing that we
actually want and as these dot products
again this this seems a little strange
so if I look at that and I say okay I
clamp zero to one the inner product of
the source normal times the V so as i
elta way from it it's going to be less
effectual to me right so that makes
sense this this this is exactly what I
would expect I'm sorry this one is
exactly what I select the inner product
of the destination normal and the Z
because it goes to light source this one
on the other hand doesn't make any sense
I feel like this should be this right it
should be the negatives of the source
normal
although I think about that so scripture
companions of visibility I want this to
be higher if I pointed more towards me
yeah and so it seems like that should be
negative but it's not take a look down
here
so interestingly enough they don't ever
call that in here so this is like
this solid angle function they never
actually defined there either right
so I don't see why that wouldn't be a
negative the normals are not pointing
like V is pointing in only one direction
and the normals here have to be pointing
in the correct direction in order to see
how much visibility there is with that
particular occluder right
so either the diagram we drew was bogus
and they're actually looking at the
front faces or they have a bug in the
code or I'm missing something
now it's worth noting if the GI was I
going to code they wouldn't know because
since there's front and back faces this
would be the code for doing the front
faces right so if you wanted to know how
much this shadows you then the code
looks like this if you want to know how
much this shadows you then you want the
code to look like this I would argue
they should both be shadowing you in our
system so honestly I think this
shouldn't be a clamp 0 1 in ER it should
be an absolute value right I think what
that wants to do is take the value so
that it's 0 to 1 in either case
so let's break these out a little bit
more so we can understand them better so
this is the I guess the like a parent I
should I say it this is the like
apparent source angle or something like
that
we'll call it our apparent source amount
so that's the value that as the you know
if the if the source is sort of at a
steep angle to us it gets very low
let's do a parent death amount so those
two terms are fairly reasonable right
the the destination amount again it will
attenuate as the angle gets steeper to
the source it will consider it doing
less and less subtraction and the same a
source amount so then then we have the
like a parent source area which is this
and so since that's in a reciprocal
square-root like I was saying as the
apparent source area goes down it gets
closer to one but as it goes up it gets
further from one right and that does
seem correct so that all seems
reasonable
so now computing the emitter area is
pretty easy right because we have a
radius and so we know that if we want to
compute the area of a disk that's just
going to be PI R squared so pretty
straightforward and let's see the star
[Applause]
all right so now what we need to do is
have some way of combining these terms
together so this S term here is going to
keep like attenuating the thing and the
tough part here and this is why we have
to do two passes on it according to the
paper and I understand why so the
problem here is that if we have well in
fact they drew the diagram I won't have
to draw it myself I suppose so you can
see what happens here right what we're
computing is how much of the angle that
we're trying to view is sort of shadowed
by some occluder right and if you have
two occluders that are placed next to
each other then adding the amounts they
clued together make sense but if one of
them is in the shadow of the other one
already then technically it should not
really be darkening up at all because no
light really that comes from anywhere in
the general outer vicinity is going to
ever hit B but not a for the most part
so we wanted darken by quite a bit less
so what they decide to do to approximate
that as if the hack is to use a to pass
thing where they first compute the
visibility of everything as if there was
no self shadowing in that way forces
they occluded to occluder shadowing and
then in the next pass use the shadowing
value that you computed for each a
clearer to change how much of its
shadowing you apply right so basically
what would happen here is we'd say all
right inside the desk when we start we
would assume that the the destination
visibility is one right and we'd say
that there is an iteration here
[Applause]
where we iterate over at me say okay go
through each element we assume that it
is completely visible at the start we go
through the source all the sources and
every time that we get some amount of
occlusion we like subtract it away or
something right now of course in this
case this s is phrased the wrong way I
guess or is it's a one minus so yeah if
all of these were zero it would be one
so really what we want to do is not
phrase it as a one - I think we want to
do is phrase it as as just an actual as
just an actual shadow I think it could
be wrong up there why am i doing that
right
ah that's the okay that's a part I was
reading that wrong that's the part that
I was messing up there it's a one minus
square root there that makes a lot more
sense right so that way it's just the
square root term that has the one minus
associated with it so as the reciprocal
square root yeah okay that makes more
sense I don't know why I was so dense it
really yes like I said didn't have any
copy this morning so the brain is not
really taking in information so anyway I
so we've got the reciprocal square root
here of the apparent source area plus
one as the apparent source area goes
down the reciprocal square root gets
closer and closer to one which subtracts
away and produces a zero here for the
amount of shadowing that's occurring
which is what we want same with these
guys as they get closer to zero right so
now this is a shadowing amount so what
we could say is this visibility just
gets subtracted away from each time at
the end we can just say the element
visibility equals clamps or one element
visibility right so we're just like
reducing reducing reducing it to
something but then the next pass through
we can use that visibility as a
modulator on the occlusion so we can say
like okay we won't subtract out
something that's already sort of
occluded so a source value the
visibility here can modify if this
should be and alike you and I guess we
could also just make this a local so
this is just a visibility like so and
then we would just assign at the end
right so there's that visibility
calculation it's not pretty and there's
still some stuff in there that I would
like to kind of rego over but at least
we've got that part of the lighting in
there now and hopefully we can see it
there you go
and so what you can see out of that is
that like yet you know honestly even
just just before having gone through it
too much there it's not awful there's a
little bit broken about it but it does
look kind of reasonable in some case
right now you can see that it gets
darker around where more stuff is it's
darker underneath the hero for example
which is good
so getting a little bit of that
ambulation there's good the thing that
doesn't look right to me is I don't know
why these walls are black so definitely
something bugging in there that we need
to take a look at that just doesn't make
any sense because there's no way that
that's a hundred percent occluded
visibility wise right that's that's just
that doesn't make any sense at all right
so our terms are a little bit busted
there and we got to fix up something you
can see that it also works nicely as the
hero moves around we get some darkening
in there as well let me check
I'm curious if I just switch it to only
a single iteration so here's a single
iteration where we just do
and here's now with two iterations so
it's really weird that with two
iterations there's become black so that
just seems like I'm not to have a stupid
bug here because that shouldn't be
possible the second iteration should
never produce worse visibility values
than the first one
right because source visibility
shouldn't be able to be anything other
than higher than one so subtracting it
away on the second pass through it that
just doesn't make sense
ah there we go
I was in the wrong place so there that's
the problem it's just a that was inside
the loop improperly all right so here's
the actual version in theory see if this
is any better that's still the same
though that's weird
[Applause]
how could that be the same taking only
the last one is the same as as right I
mean that was that was a really bad bug
to have that in there but it produced
the same result that seems nonsensical
to me what am I missing
like I don't see any way those two
things could have been the same
and yet they are
or at least let's do it and they're not
maybe the same the same
so we start with a visibility of one we
lift through the shadowing approximation
and we compute it again source amount
source amount should be zero in the case
where they're oblique right and V has
been normalized at this point so that's
all fine we have our destination amount
which is again also going to be zero
when they're oblique to each other we
have a parent source area which is PI R
squared over the squared distance which
also seems right we compute the
shadowing amount from that which should
be a number between 0 and 1 and then we
subtract away
that amount that just looks fine to me
so I don't know why I'm really confused
as to why we get a situation where
somehow on the second pass you can have
something get darker than it gets on the
first pass because the computations
should be exactly the same right meaning
this is even you know it's redundant we
could even just store the result of this
calculation and then use it on the
second pass if you want to use N squared
storage right it's like we're not even
we're not even computing a new thing the
exactly the same thing the only
difference is that instead of
subtracting away the full value of s
whatever that is we are we are
subtracting away a lesser version of
that let's go ahead and put some
assertions in here let's just see if
there is any kind of funny business
going on here with values that exceed
the range that I expect them to be so I
can find out what the deal is with that
and also let's switch debug
all right so no assertions so gosh
that's just I don't even know Saul right
so looking at the desk visibility then
that is what we're using we run the
global lighting but we don't use it
right that's not being used what we're
using here is just taking we're just
taking the element visibility directly
and using that as our front emission
value right so when we create these here
we're just doing it straight that way
using a front of it no monkey business
so yeah I'm not sure I should probably
go to the Q&amp;A and we'll debug this next
weekend
but I'm not sure why I just don't
understand how that's possible didn't
so the second time through the iteration
right I would expect to see the
visibility to strictly increase there
should be no way for the visit for the
visibility to get less than it was
we should also be able to verify that we
never get in here for the same element
yeah so I guess the only thing I would
like to see is I would like to know that
if the iteration so if it equals one
assert guests or visibility is greater
than best visibility or greater than or
equal to right so that's the problem
we're seeing okay so it's Clint but the
clamped visibilities all right so let's
do this visibility equals plant through
one disability
so interesting so basically my
assumption is totally not true but I
have absolutely no idea why so how can
that be possible we have the same loop
running twice back to back
we are not modifying anything other than
the visibility value that's the only
thing we're setting we are subtracting
from one right a modulation of whatever
the source visibility is times the value
we compute the first time through all of
these will be equal to one ah but it
does feed back into itself right because
that visibility value is going to be
used in the other case so I guess
technically what I would have to do here
is I would have to say this right and
the problem with that is even in that
case I'm not quite doing it correctly so
you kind of need to you need almost two
visibility values in a sense right so
let's try that so we need to be careful
not to write back here so we have like
we have effectively two values right
we've got the visibility value that
we're writing this time and the
visibility value we're using for
modulation excuse me so maybe I'll have
visibility and shadow in this case and
so what we could do there is say like
okay so the visibility and the shadow
start out like so we can loop through
and we'll just do another one of these
like double loops just the same way we
were doing the letting computation from
before where we have the accumulation in
fact I suppose I could just use the
accumulator itself that we already have
but I'm going to ignore that for now so
we can look at the values all right so
we compute the visibility here like so
and then what I'm going to do is I'm
going to stay instead of computing
visibility I'm going to say something
like I'm going to call this shadow I'm
going to accumulate the shadow like so
and then I'm going to do something like
this
and then what we'll do is we'll come in
here and say all right
death visibility equals what - Jess
shadow right something like this
and now I decide to make sure that works
properly but the idea here is that
before I guess our problem was I forgot
the fact that we were using those terms
inside the loop and writing to them so
there would be a feedback that would
happen differently for different
elements based on where they happened in
the loop so I want to write to something
that I'm not reading from right so in
this case I've got my shadow value that
I compute i sum up my shadow values and
then I write them to the shadow output I
then at the end do a pass over all the
destinations to turn the shadow values
into visibility values and then we we
start the process over again right and
that way we can just use the visibility
value and know that it's not going to be
doing anything particularly strange
right now I'm still getting a problem
euro right
the shadow value should always be
strictly less than or equal to the
previous shadow value right and good now
we're actually able to get that okay so
now we took that that nasty feedback out
of there and now we can maybe I'll turn
on optimizations here and then we can
take a look at that ambulance solution
all right so here's the ambient
occlusion it's still a little wonky like
I feel like there's too much weight
being given to for example this like
look at these three things here they
they change quite a bit and it doesn't
feel like they should right so I think
we still got some bugs in there we want
to work out but it's not bad like it's
starting to get reasonable right so I'll
go ahead and go to the QA
um so yeah
Vica r2 says square root a over pi plus
R squared equals square root of R
squared times a over pi times R squared
plus 1 equals R times square root I
assume that just are you just doing the
are you just showing the derivation that
I was asking about in the original paper
like actually I should probably stop
here for more you're talking about the
simplification for this term from this
term
I can't highlight it but that term there
for those of you who can't see the chat
maybe on the like on the video on
YouTube or whatever watching an
after-the-fact
limit write down what V car to was
talking about so we've said square root
of area over pi plus R squared equals
square root of R squared times
area over PI R squared plus one equals R
times square root of area over PI R
squared plus one okay I totally agree
with that because here I guess if I was
going to do it out the long way if I was
going to pull an R squared out of here
then basically like pulling the R
squared out to here means that you know
this term just becomes a 1 and this term
needs a 1 over R squared in it which it
now does have even you can pull it out
and leave that so that our that's just
sitting out there though
ah I see thank you for that yes once
that R is sitting out there then that
that R cancels this R yes yes yes so
that's where the R goes once you want to
use just a normalized vector so that's
why there is no R in this equation here
where it used to be because there used
to be an arc here right and there isn't
one anymore so yeah that seems that
seems good
Alex killed though thank you very much
for 400 days of programming my pleasure
thanks for tuning in
MTS mocks what do extra iterations do
for ambient occlusion I understand it
for bouncing light but shadows so the
reason is sorry I get maybe that wasn't
clear as I pointed to their diagram but
maybe I should just draw our own diagram
here so basically here's what's going on
if you wanted to compute the actual
ambient occlusion for a surface so say
here's the surface that we're looking at
and I wanted to know what the ambient
occlusion was for a particular surface
here given these occluders so even if
I'm not talking about from a specific
light source even if I'm just talking
about the whole sky right like basically
like am a whole hemisphere then what I
need to do there is I need to compute
how much of the hemisphere is subtended
by by occluders right
and so in this 2d approximation to it
you know we say how much of the sky is
occluded well this is occluded right and
this is occluded and that is occluded
right so there's our occlusion
calculation and so if we were doing this
precisely mathematically speaking right
we would say oh there's like a hundred
and eighty degrees of visibility here
and we sum up how many degrees these are
let's say it sums to something looks
like roughly maybe ninety years eighty
or something so we'd say okay 180
degrees of visibility - 80 degrees
occluded equals the total visibility is
100 degrees of visibility right so
that's just like a vague idea of the
ambient occlusion right so that is the
calculation we actually want for an
abelian this algorithm is not producing
that right what this algorithm is
producing is the sum of all of these
angles right now the problem with that
is as you can see they overlap so for
example in here we are double counting
the occlusion of this occluder and this
ik loser where this area is being double
counted so we would come up with an
answer that was more like 180 minus 100
equals 80 right because we had an extra
10 degrees that got doubled in here or
an extra 20 degrees it got doubled right
so the reason we do two iterations of
the ambient occlusion in this algorithm
is because once we do one set of ambient
occlusion which is over counted we then
for each one of these occluders have a
percentage occlusion for it so if we
then modulate the occlusion that it does
by that percentage we are in effect
taking into account that overlap a
little bit and reducing the amount that
it contributes through shadow
so it's sort of like saying compute the
first pass ambient occlusion for
everything which we know is more ambient
occlusion than should be happening then
use the ambient occlusion we computed on
that pass to reduce the amount of
ambient occlusion that every occluder
contributes and hopefully get closer to
the right answer it's still not correct
right it's still not correct because you
don't know whether it was or not
contributing right so for example if I
have a situation like this it's probably
very good because once it sees that this
occluder has shaded this occluder and
this occluder right on the next pass
this occluder has you know some
percentage occlusion from this guy so
when it shadows this person it doesn't
use it gets its contribution to the
shadow is greatly reduced because it's
shadowed quite a bit by this occluder so
that works really well potentially on
the other hand in this case this
occluder is including a totally
different set of angles as this occluder
is so in this case there's no shared
occlusion and it's just wrong
right so it's really just a case of
tweaking it to see which is better how
many iterations make sense like which
you could do an iteration to just see
which one produces a more pleasing
result because it's definitely wrong
like it's not going to be right
just actually the accumulator for the
light passes beer set to zero the start
of the next pass which well we haven't
really are you talking about this one we
haven't really done anything with this
one yet
but yeah it should be you're totally
right even in what we have currently and
also it should really really be done
this way what we probably should be
doing is this right so we just start out
with zero we accumulate all the inbound
light and we put it away for a future
reference basically and yeah
what's the problem
oh that's that's a toll in nautical ah
there we go so yet no but that that is
totally true that's probably was why we
were getting that weird flickering but
like I said we haven't actually done
that part yet
do we have ability to switch it to that
here lighting show reflectors show
visibility false so there's the current
lighting we can also add that ambient
occlusion in there now as well so like
if we wanted to we could we could say
okay when we take the total light
transfer here that we computed between
these two we can also say well the the
total amount of light that can be
received from this occluder is going to
get bought it's going to get modulated
by that so you know the best visibility
in fact we don't do it every time we can
just say the desk visibility knocks out
a certain amount of the accumulation
right and so here's the the result of
here's a result of both of those things
combined
right
so we still have a ways to go here but
that's you know that's
and you can kind of feel like we're not
we're not getting we're not like we
would want that to be much darker over
here right and we're not really getting
that
but you know I mean like I said we're
not trying to produce a hundred percent
like amazing lighting or anything here
and you know eventually I could see us
getting this working relatively well I
mean it's already sort of usable like if
we smooth this out and use more
reflectors we could probably be
reasonably happy with it right you know
we're not trying to make the world's
most amazing lighting system or anything
we just want something that gives us a
little bit of you know a light feel
right like something that sort of has
some big lighting this to it
so how many Lenny passes are we doing at
the moment I don't actually know the
global rating iteration count let's see
config let's do a few light passes why
not and let's look at this
[Applause]
still still got weird stuff happening
right like it like we got to go fix that
lighting transfer equation and we got we
got a lot of stuff we got to do right
[Applause]
sighs like it seems like the ground
colors are off it looks like it goes
light green gray dark green yeah I agree
with that and I that may just be because
of the way that the sRGB is working like
we may have to when we do our unpack of
the color values because they're srgb
encoded we probably should srgb like
pink code we encode them
ah let's see
looks like that's about it for on topic
question I do not have time to take any
off-topic questions today so sorry about
that we could do those next weekend yeah
so it's interesting here
it what - look at this code more
carefully tomorrow
I mean next weekend
let me see what that disability code is
doing when we set visibility as a
viewable element ah so this actually is
not quite ripe this should also be this
[Applause]
hmm
although that should not have had it any
ill effects
really
[Music]
it's a little confusing I'm not sure why
that actually was was making things
appear transparent
there we go
all right
and yet there is a bunch of stuff we
have to do in terms of lighting values
because we're going to have to compute
these light linear and probably with
values that are going to be greater than
one as well and then we're going to have
to like tone map them down you can see
that's just really strange what happens
there that just seems very buggy so I'm
pretty sure we've got some bugs that we
got to go hunt down but that's fine
we've got plenty of time next weekend to
play with it
all right thank you for joining me for
an episode of handmade heroes and a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along stories
at home you can always peer to the game
on handmade hero org it comes to the
source code so you can follow along
yourself we also have a forum site you
can go to if you want to ask questions
we have a patreon page transport the
video series a schedule bot that tweets
the schedule at you if you want to know
when we're going to be live and an
episode guide you can use to catch up on
old episodes that's about it for this
week I'll be back next week with more
handmade hero until then have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the
Internet take it easy everybody