and start okay hello everyone and
welcome to handmade hero the show where
we code a complete game live on twitch
from scratch no libraries no engine
because basically our goal is to figure
out everything that happens sort of
examine everything that happens in the
entire pipeline on a game from how you
draw the pixels all the way up to how
the game code operates and decides
what's going to happen at a logistical
level so right now we're kind of in the
middle of our week of sort of starting
to use vector math in the code and
vector math is very important because
it's in sort of the same way that you
could think of C and C++ as getting you
a level above assembly language so that
you can start to think about things at a
slightly higher level while still
retaining most of the performance
benefits and the sort of direct access
that you're used to vector math is kind
of like that for the scalar math that
we've been doing it basically allows us
to do the same sort of operations we
were doing when we were manhandling the
x and y-coordinates of things and this
sort of stuff but it gives us the
opportunity to start thinking about
those as a pair and start defining
operations that work on them as a pair
which we can still use to get very
efficient code but it allows us to sort
of beat up at a slightly more a higher
semantic level and sometimes you still
have to go down there and muck with the
individual values in these in these
vectors but most of the time you can
start thinking of them conceptually and
it allows you to do a lot more powerful
stuff now we already did some of that we
already did some of that yesterday in
fact but before I dive into that let me
quickly go over as I always do how you
can be coding along at home if you are
someone who has period of the game at
hand made hero org you should have
gotten a link in your email in that
download page that you would get a link
to you can download both the test assets
that we use for development here on the
stream and you should have had the
ability download a zip file in which are
a bunch of other zip files you want to
grab the zip file for day 43 because
that is what I am starting with here on
day 44 so you always start with the
previous day zip if you unzip that into
a directory and start coding with it you
will be exactly where I am right now
okay so let's talk a little bit about
what we had just done in the
and then let's talk a little bit about
what we are going to do today to kind of
continue along in our and our vector
sorts of sorts of experiments here okay
so we had just finished implementing
simple equations of motion for our
little guy here and basically what we've
done so far is we had made a little tile
map right that the guy could walk around
on we had this we don't really have
there's just sort of a static background
sitting in here now so we haven't gotten
to how we're gonna render our tile map
yet but we do have the ability to kind
of draw these you know the sort of white
walls and the the doors and stuff so he
can go up a virtual staircase he can go
out the side of the screen and so on and
we just implemented the equations of
motion for him so basically he has you
know sort of more of what you would
expect a objects movement to be when you
are moving him around right and so as
I'm moving him around I can kind of feel
that momentum that we added and he stops
he has it he has a little bit of a sort
of a glide to a stop and he has a little
bit of acceleration when he picks up and
that just makes all the difference in
terms of feeling good about the
character motion when you're moving
around he's already much more engaging
to move around than he was even with
just that simple change and so that's
more that's sort of what we need to be
focusing on what we need to be doing for
our player movement code certainly but
we're also trying to learn about vectors
here so what I want to do is is perhaps
talk a little bit more about some stuff
that we can do with the vector code to
sort of see how it works a little bit
starting to think about it in terms of
slightly higher level stuff okay so one
of the things that we we did in terms of
using the vector math may actually have
not been all that obvious and I sort of
mentioned at the end of last stream but
I want to mention it again because it's
very important is you'll notice that
when I did all that talking about the
equations of motion yesterday and I sort
of was talking about how a little bit of
a fat finger type is there when I was
talking about how we were gonna do the
equations of motion and then we typed
them in and we did the equations of
motion just like I derived them and they
work the first time we just typed them
in and they worked perfectly it was
great and then we tuned the constants to
make the motion be what we wanted it to
be in terms of how fast accelerates and
how much drag he has that sort of stuff
well what turns out to be the case is
all of that derivation that I actually
did I just kind of did it as if it was
scalar right when we did
integrals and stuff and we did the work
on the equations of motion never did I
actually ever say that we were working
in vectors at all we were basically just
working with scalars and so when we
typed in this equation we essentially
just typed in a scalar equation right
all we did was just solve you know we
basically worked out some scalar
equations in Crete there right when we
were when we were drawing them out and
then we typed them into something that
is essentially a 2d process right this
guy can go in you know in any direction
he wants in this 2d plane here right
he's totally smoothly moving in 2d and
we didn't have to really account for
that at all right we we totally just
were able to work with those equations
just like they were scheduled at scalar
equations and then we plugged them into
something that was using vectors and
they just worked and that's kind of
again just a little bit of a slight hint
about why you should always care about
things like you know sort of these more
powerful math objects it's just because
they allow us to do things like that
where we can simplify thinking about
stuff instead of having to think about
the X's and the Y's and the Z's and
whatever we can just think about sort of
abstract quantities and know that they
will apply now there's some times that
we have to think about things and know
that they're actually vectors and so
there's things we have to learn in the
math that actually depend on the fact
that things are vectors but for a lot of
the time you can actually think about
scalar and vector interchangeably and
that's very powerful so yeah so there
you go so what I thought we might do
today and someone actually mentioned
this on the stream so that was kind of
fun is I was thinking that it might be
useful to a good a good thing to learn
about vectors would be to sort of see
how we would do a bounce how we would do
a like a bounce off the wall for example
so when this guy comes down here if you
were to bounce and his velocity would be
reflected you know in the other
direction right
and so what I was thinking about is
maybe we'll just construct I mean
there's a couple things we could do but
I think maybe we'll just construct that
case we'll just say when our hero here
hits the wall we want him to bounce off
of it as if he were you know sort of a
bouncing ball that was one thing I was
thinking we could do and another thing
that I would like to do maybe is make an
actual jump for him where even though I
don't anticipate this character jumping
on command he is going to have to hop
and so coding in a jump
it's gonna be interesting as well
because that kind of involves this
concept of height off of the ground
which is something I also want to get
into so you have a couple of things we
can do and I think maybe the bouncing
would be an interesting one of those
because it allows us to talk about some
of the vector math now we probably won't
actually want the character to bounce
off the walls in the future because that
doesn't make a whole lot of sense for
him to do but we will want things to
bounce off walls almost certainly and so
we need to learn how to do this code one
way or the other
all right so if I go over here and start
to construct the case so we can start
talking about that let's think about
what we have right so let's say I've got
a wall here right there's my wall and I
want to start to think about what's
gonna happen when this fellow bounces
off of it right and so I'm gonna imagine
just for sake of simplicity here I'm
gonna say that the bounce point is that
the origin of the world right this is at
zero zero right it doesn't really matter
because that's a free translation I
could move everything in the world such
that that were true for the purposes of
doing this computation right and then
move it back afterwards so translation I
can always translate things to a
convenient location if I want to so I'm
just gonna simplify things by saying
that that's what's going to happen and
so what I want to do is I want to say
that there's going to be some kind of
inbound vector here right there's going
to be an inbound vector and what we want
to do is we want to take this inbound
vector and we want to reflect it well
it's hard to draw today for some reason
I can't seem to draw good lines today we
want to reflect it out the other way
right the the sort of the notion of
what's gonna happen when you do a bounce
is something coming in is going to get
reflected at almost as if this thing was
a mirror right and so we want to think
about the incoming vector as somehow
giving us the information that we would
need to compute whatever the outbound
vector is right and so what exactly is
happening here in in terms of this
impact in response right well there's
some things that we probably aren't
going to think about really like I said
we're not doing deformable dynamics so
like the fact that some when something
hits something else that makes a dent or
things like that we're not really gonna
think about at this point but we are
gonna think about is the fact that
whatever is sort of the the velocity
that comes in here in some sense that
velocity has to be conserved right
there's there's a certain amount of
physics involved
we've got a certain amount of velocity
coming in we do expect that amount of
velocity to be the same leaving right
because of conservation momentum and so
on all of your your nice physics laws -
however much energy goes into this
impact right so there is probably going
to be some amount of energy lost in the
fact that you do make a dent and so on
and so we may want to simulate that as
well that loss of energy that that comes
in here in addition to what's going to
happen otherwise even if we don't
simulate modifying the wall we may want
to make the bounce more realistic by
saying that it doesn't bounce off at
full speed it loses some of its energy
in that impact right now what's
happening when this thing hits this wall
right well one of the interesting things
about this is this case starts to talk
about vectors in terms of their
components and it's kind of interesting
to sort of see what's going on there
well what's going to happen is if I look
at I know that this vector is composed
of two pieces right because we've talked
about this quite a bit it's composed of
its Y portion and it's composed of its
exporter right and if I think about what
happens to this vector
well the wall is only stopping one of
those portions right it's only stopping
the Y portion right so if I wanted to
reflect this guy I really don't want to
stop his X motion at all his X motion
could continue just as it was because
there is no wall horizontally here to
prevent him from going somewhere it's
only this this wall here that's
preventing him from moving vertically
right and so I could think about taking
this vector this velocity vector this is
the speed at which he's coming in right
and I could take that velocity vector
and just think about flipping it right
because this is the vector you know I'm
if it was based up here that's that's
that's not really the vector right the
vectors actual value is whatever these
two components are so if I think of the
vectors being really at the origin it
actually looks like this right and so
what I want to do is preserve this
amount right so this outgoing vector
here is going to have this amount right
here this X amount it's going to have
the same as the incoming the outgoing
velocity is going to have the same as
the incoming right but it's it's Y
component is gonna actually just be the
negative right you can kind of see that
whatever we thought however
faster moving in that direction we're
gonna flip it up to here right and again
we could after we compute this vector we
could do various things to to talk about
like treating it as if some energy was
absorbed in the impact we could lessen
the amount that it that it bounces this
way we could just lessen that speed and
in general if we want to go in the same
direction but lessen it so we could
think about various things to do here
and that is how we would do that bounce
right but there's something interesting
that I've baked in here and this is the
part where it starts to get because I
mean if you were to look at this you'd
say oh well based on that description KC
it's pretty easy to understand what's
going on if this is the incoming
velocity so this is the old velocity and
I want to complete compute that new
velocity right what would I do
well I just told you what to do right if
V right is equal to V X V Y right it's
got two components got the X component
the last seen the Y component I just
said well the new ones gonna have the
same X and it's just gonna have a
negative Y I I mean I just I pointed
that out in the diagram it's kind of
obvious right that's not what you do so
why are we talking about this and in
fact it doesn't even look like a vector
operation it just looks like we're
operating on the scalars again you know
and at this point you're just like I'm
gonna go watch John play nuclear thrown
on the other channel because frankly
you're not teaching about vectors at all
you're teaching about scalars and I
already know about scalars fair enough
but there is a rub here what I drew was
the convenient diagram where the axis
along which we were doing this
reflection was aligned with one of the
primary axes right X happens to be the
wall and that is why it is why that can
simply be negated what were to happen if
we had the same situation right even
still at the origin let's say but now I
have a slightly inclined wall right and
so I'm actually talking about a wall
with this normal to it right this is the
sort of it'd be the the surface pointing
out of the surface of the wall right
whereas here the Y axis was supporting
out of the surface of the wall and now
I've got this incoming thing right well
now if I were to take that incoming
thing and put it put it here right and
look at what I want to have
in terms of that reflection about the
wall because this is the wall right this
is no longer the wall this is the wall
well what am I going to do
that's not the y-component anymore right
these things have drastically different
like components there's the y component
of that one there's the Y component this
one ain't no negative gonna fix that
problem right you are not the man now
dog if you think that you're going to do
this right to solve this problem and so
this presents us with our first sort of
point where we have to start thinking
about vectors in terms of actual in
terms of the actual structure of them in
terms of the actual fact that they are
vectors and not just scalars because now
we have to start thinking about how do
we work with vectors in ways that do not
involve falling back to the scalars when
we need to do something on just one part
of them in just one piece of them right
and so the answer is simply that we need
to get familiar with remember I don't
know if you guys if you guys were with
me the whole time then you remember me
talking about something called the
Hadamard product right and I don't
remember if I is it two DS I don't even
remember is it that way
or is it that way I don't actually know
but I talked about the head of my
product and I said well that's what
happens you know if I have two vectors
and I want to multiply them together I
don't really want to right cross them to
write that if I have two vectors and I
want to do some kind of operation
between them that's multiplication well
one way to do it right is to multiply
the components together like so write a
times C and that goes in the X component
right and B times D goes in the Y
component that's called the Hadamard
product and that results in another
vector well that's really like I said
not that useful for a lot of the stuff
that we want to do so now it's time to
get acquainted with something that is
very useful for the things we want to do
and that is the inner product or better
known often times in game development
circles as the dot product okay that is
what is going to allow us to solve these
kinds of problems with relative ease
you'll notice I don't have almond milk
today I've got tea I'm doing some some
Bengals price
is that spacing what's happening right
now all right so excuse me let's take a
look at the dot product try to remember
these diagrams I don't have room for
everything so let's take a look at the
dot product what I wanted to do right is
I already showed you how to solve the
problem if everything were access
aligned and so what I really want to do
is I want to kind of have the ability to
make my own axis systems right like if I
could have just created a new axis
system that happened to be aligned with
the wall then I could have used the same
solution that I used before right
but I don't know how to do that and so
what we're gonna look at now is we're
gonna look at how to use the inner
product to do those sorts of things so
what is the inner product okay so if I
have two vectors right here's one vector
and then I'm gonna do this magical thing
the dot product I'm going to you the dot
product here if I have a B and I'm going
to do the dot product of a B with some
other vector CD right then what this
actually does is instead of producing
another vector meaning instead of
producing something like the Hadamard
product where it had two elements and it
was another vector just like the two
that came in this is actually going to
produce a single value as a result it's
going to contract these two vectors down
into a scalar and the way that it is
defined right is it is defined to be the
members multiplied by each other and
added right so it's a times C plus B
times D right it is a times C B times D
now this jumps ahead a little bit for me
to explain really how this is working
exactly because we haven't quite gotten
into matrix math yet but one thing that
is interesting to note and I'll kind of
show you how this this works is the way
matrices are multiplied it's actually
very easy and I alluded to it on an
earlier stream in fact but if we were to
think about these as matrices and we
were to think about this first the first
part of the dot product here this this
this fellow right here as being turned
from a column into a row so if we were
to think about it being aligned this way
right and then we take this guy
and we leave him as his columnar form
and we construct the multiplication of
these two in vector in matrix notation
while matrix multiplication is actually
very simple for each element that you
want to compute in the result you simply
it's basically just as easy as drawing a
line to find out where in each vector
you hit for the element now of course
there's only one element in this result
here if there was two matrices here we'd
have more of them but then you just work
your way down starting from the outside
first right a and C you multiply them
together and then you add you go to the
next one down D and B right there we go
and that is the dot product right now
this works for vectors of any size it
doesn't matter how long they are right
it doesn't matter at all you still would
know exactly how to produce them because
as many as I have here de F right G H I
J okay well I just take the first ones I
multiply those together G a I take the
second ones right B H and I just
multiply an ad multiply an ad all the
way till I get to the end fnl right and
that is how you can produce the product
right very easy and so often times
there's the the operation of changing
something from a row oriented
orientation to a column orientation like
that it's called a transpose and so
oftentimes you will actually see the dot
product and it's called the inner
product as well like I said because of
this exact look how it looks like that
you're getting the sort of the the inner
portion here right it's I mean it's hard
to say without the mixture because
there's a thing called an outer product
as well if I were to flip these the
other way it would produce more values
in fact let me just show you cuz it's
kind of interesting if I were to flip
these the other way c/d a/b right I can
produce the outer product and again I
follow the same rules do that
intersection right C times a and that's
it there's nothing more to do in either
that row or the column right so that's
one entry in my resulting 2x2 matrix do
it again here D times a right there's
another one C times B D times B
right you can learn matrix math in no
time because basically just learning
that is all you really need to know and
you can compute any matrix product that
you want but again until we actually
learn what any of these things do not
particular useful I just want to show
you that this is an outer product that's
an eery product you can kind of see why
it's called that because these two
things like kind of form the the smaller
space there and the larger space here
but anyway that's neither here nor there
all right so the inner product dot
product are oftentimes called the scalar
product as well because it produces a
single value no matter how big the
vectors are is something that is of
great utility and it may not seem like a
very useful thing right now because
you're looking at that going why would I
ever care about that at all
but the truth is it's actually quite
useful and the reason that's quite
useful is because this value despite its
innocuous look actually computes to
something very handy based on what these
vectors actually are so let's take a
look at what that actually is and I
won't probably go through the trouble of
proving it on because math proofs are
only interesting to some people
sometimes but point being I'll show you
the sort of the intuitive stuff and how
to think about it and if you want to
know the proofs I can actually maybe we
can talk about the on forums or
something like that anyway so the dot
product if I have two vectors so I'm
going to go ahead and say that my
vectors are now a equals ax okay Y right
and B equals BX and B Y right these are
my two vectors and somewhere in space
right I'm gonna think about these guys
here's my coordinate system and I've got
two vectors okay like so now when you
compute the dot product again often
written as as this because of that
transpose the T means the transpose
remember I'm turning one on its side and
then multiplying to get that thing
oftentimes written like this can also be
written just as a dot and so on there's
there's lots of different ways to notate
it I tend to use that one a transpose
because that's just the same in matrix
notation so that's the dot product there
right so that which again is just going
to be ax BX + a YB Y that's the entirety
of it right that's all it is that
quantity
actually equals something rather useful
it turns out that it's equal to however
long and this is one way that length is
often written so I'm just gonna write it
that way for now however long a is right
and so I'm gonna call this a and this B
over here however long a is scaler wise
right times however long B is scaler
wise right so that length here so this
this guy is that length and this guy is
that like there right times the cosine
of the angle between them so these two
guys here they've got this angle here
you're right let's call that theta the
angle between the two vectors whatever
its cosine is times the length of B
times the length of a that equals this
quantity because remember this is a
scalar because this is a scalar like
that's how long a is this is how long P
is and this is how long and this is the
cosine of the angle between them right
well again if you want to prove this you
use the law of cosines if you know
geometry I'm not going to do it right
now but basically you can prove this
using the law of cosines if you're
interesting that you can go check it out
but anyway that this quantity constructs
that actual identity right it actually
this scalar value equals this scalar
value and with just that just that one
relation we can do some incredibly
powerful stuff actually
so what stuff can we do well for
starters what if we wanted to know the
length of a vector like I want to know
how long a is right well there's two
ways we could think about doing that
right one is that I told you about the
Pythagorean theorem the other day right
so we could take here's a X here's a Y
we want to know this length here we
could do ax squared plus ay Y squared
equals whatever the length of a is
squared right and so that is how we
would compute that length we would route
this so we would go okay route ax
squared plus ay Y squared equals length
of a right that's what we would do and
that is one way to compute the length of
a in terms of thinking about how it's
done
right another way we could think about
it's done is just by using this equation
we have something in it with the length
of a right so what if we were just a
take instead of doing a transpose a and
take I'm saying instead of taking a
transpose B and taking the dot product
with B what if we just take the dot
product of a with itself right well if I
take a transpose a just following this
equation I would get the length of a
time's the length of a again times the
cosine of the angle between it and
itself now we know that the angle
between itself is 0 right so what's the
cosine of 0 well for those of you who
don't remember your sines and cosines
all right you know who you are out there
I'm gonna draw the circle you could
always draw the circle if you get scared
right you could always draw the circle
this is the starting point on the circle
right we wind up to here right that's 90
degrees we wind to here that's 180 we
wind to here right that's 270 line to
here and that's 360 again right this is
0 similarly if you're doing this with
radians if you guys remember your
radians it's 2pi out here right so this
is gonna be PI over here and this is PI
over 2 right and this is 3 PI over 2
remember the circle as we work around
the circle right the cosine is the
x-coordinate of the point of the circle
and the sine is the y-coordinate of the
circle so if I was at 0 which is right
here right well there ain't no
y-coordinate there's just the
x-coordinate and the x-coordinate is all
the way out right so the cosine of 0
equals 1 right cosine of 90 equals 0
cosine of 180 negative 1 right comes
back around and so on hopefully your
guys are all familiar with that if
you're not get used to your unit circle
unit circle is the man now dog is is
good ok unit circle good all right
so if I do this and I know that this is
one because there's no angle between a
and a is always 0 right it sits right on
top of itself I know that falls out and
I just get length of a times like today
which means a ta equals a squared right
so the square root of the dot product of
a with itself is the length of a not
surprising because guess what
this is the equation for the dot product
right what would happen if these were
AIDS it'd be a x squared plus ay Y
squared exactly what was on inside my
Pythagorean theorem the Pythagorean
theorem the dot product are very
intimately related right and you can see
that okay so what else can I do with
this surely I did not spend all that
time teaching you how to do something
that you already knew how to do and that
we already did yesterday and that's
correct
I didn't there's a lot more stuff in
here that we can use all right what is
it
ooh whoops didn't mean to quite get that
over zealous all right there we go all
right so what is it that we can do with
that right what is it that we can do
with a transpose a equals length of a
length of B cosine theta well the cosine
theta is the part that really comes in
particularly handy right the reason that
that comes in particularly handy is
because when we start to think about the
cosine of the angle between those two
vectors right if we start to think about
what that actually means well what if we
could take one of these guys out of the
equation essentially what if we could
just say a priori let's take B and let's
say B is a unit vector right a unit
vector is a vector with length 1 right
so if I said the length of B was 1 it's
one unit long then it would drop out of
here right and if B is length 1 then we
get a transpose B equals a cosine theta
right that's what we're actually going
to get so what does that actually do for
us why would I care about that well the
reason I would care about that is
because imagine that now we have our
wall again right that well we were
talking about
suppose we had write a unit vector that
was pointing the direction away from the
wall right just suppose that's something
we had well now if I have some other
vector right I've got this vector here
that's you know this guy's doing his his
incoming bounce right and so this is the
vector that
that incoming velocity this is that
incoming velocity so here's my vector B
right in this case and I guess in this
case I want to say that this is a for
our equation right so I didn't come lots
of these a well if you take a look at
what actually happens to these two
vectors I know that the length of B is
out of it so the result is going to be
however long a is which is this with it
which is this length right here right
but multiplied by the cosine of the
angle between the two vectors right and
that cosine again is going to be this
this right here right and to see this a
little bit better maybe it's kind of
hard on the diagram let me do it with a
more you know perhaps a slightly more
acute way let me put it up bring it out
here right so that we don't have to have
it sort of be bent back let's suppose
that they were more like this so they're
a little easier to see right so I know
my result my result is gonna have the
length of a in it but I also now the
cosine of these these that's between
these is now gonna multiply it out and
what does the cosine of M of a triangle
do for us right what does the cosine of
a right triangle do for us now you
should remember this again from your
from your grade school trig right what
does the cosine of a right triangle give
us right well it gives us this it gives
us this edge right here
if this is the hypotenuse right then
this is cosine theta H and this is sine
theta H right that's that's exactly what
that gives us it gives us the length of
that side and the sine gives us the
length of the other side right times the
hypotenuse however long it was again
this is stuff you should hopefully all
remember from your grade school trig
well what did that construct up here if
I was to build that right triangle right
that's built off of this angle I'm
getting this I'm getting this amount
right here right that's what I'd be
getting because I know that I've taken
the length of a into account it's right
here and I know I've taken that cosine
ratio into account right here so this is
just like here just like H cosine theta
gives me the length of this side in that
standard right triangles are used to
length of a cosine theta gives me
however long this guy is projected
effectively on to this vector so a
transfer
B is actually extraordinary powerful
because what it lets me do is it lets me
take any unit vector that I want anyone
and then for any other vector no matter
how long it is or what its shape is or
what its direction is and project it
down to see where it would land on that
vector right now you can imagine this
getting even more powerful what if I had
another orthogonal vector right that was
perpendicular to B also unit length
let's say this was C so C is also unit
length if I took the dot product with
that I would now know both coordinates
of this a in a new fictional space that
I've constructed right instead of the x
and y axis being how things are measured
by taking both dot products I would
essentially create new coordinates for a
new coordinates in a in a coordinate
system that I set up so essentially this
a transpose B allows me to measure any
vector that I want on any axis system
that I want just by setting up two unit
vectors that are orthogonal to each
other that are you know that are
perpendicular right so imagine I want to
do this what are the coordinates of a in
this new magical reference frame this BC
radical reference frame the knife that
I've constructed right well I just said
what they were they're a transpose B for
the x coordinate if this is my new x
axis I don't know maybe it's not maybe
that's this should be the x axis because
it's right hand rule right going that
way so this is actually not quite right
let's say that that's a transpose C
right is my x coordinate and a transpose
B is my y coordinate that's the new
vector and that tells me the coordinates
of a in this space makes sense right
okay so hopefully you're clear on that
and again you know I work through all of
it to show you how that actually happens
giving you the right triangle and so on
but what you really again you want to
internalize that and you want to spend
as much time as necessary to get
familiar with these guys but the
important takeaway conceptually right is
that measuring process okay it's that
measuring process it's saying that a
vector right dot a unit axis equals the
coordinate of that vector along that
axis
makes sense now this works even for the
axes we already have so if we were to
actually take the x-axis and the y-axis
and do this we'd get the right answers
why because what is the x-axis right
what is the y-axis well if we
represented them as vectors we'd get 0 1
for the y-axis right there's no X
component and it's going 1 and Y and for
the X we'd get 1 0 well what happens if
I dot product those with some vector in
the space right if I have a X here and a
Y what happens if I dot that with one of
these well you should be able to do that
right away you know it's ax times 1 so
that's ax and a watt plus ay Y times 0
which is 0 so it's just ax which is the
x coordinate of the vector in that space
same is true if you did it for Y right
so this is like the universal measuring
operator it has a lot of other uses
besides that and we'll see them later on
but that's the one that we're going to
talk about right now because with that
in mind with that power the old thing
that looks so complicated where how are
we going to deal with this arbitrary
wall becomes trivial right totally
trivial now so let's go back to our
diagram that we had before and see if
with the dot product we can now solve
the problem that was so sort of weird
before and difficult hit that in there
right so what I'm going to say is for
any wall in order to do a reflection off
of it all I need to know is I need to
know a unit vector that points out of
the wall right also called the normal of
the surface oftentimes right so there's
my there's my reflection and I'm just
gonna call that I'll just call that W
for now right we'll call that our wall
vector maybe I'll call it a reflection
vector trying to call it R I don't know
it's kind of cells like rotation we'll
call it our and what we have to say is
are the length of R is going to be 1 R
is a unit vector ok so now I take
anything that comes in that I want to
reflect any vector right so this is my V
this is my velocity right and again I'm
drawing it coming in here because that's
the physical version of the diagram but
really any vector is you know if we
think about it it's at the origin right
so this is actually my V and now what I
want to do is I want to reflect that
around here I want to reflect that
around here so what do I need to do to
reflect it well I said before that what
I need to do reflected isn't a gate its
y-component
was lined up with the y-axis right so
all we need to do now is figure out what
part of it we actually would need to
negate in this new axis system right if
this were the y-coordinate so how do we
do that
well I just said I can measure any
vector along along a you know another
unit vector which is what I have so if I
take the transpose R right if I take
that that will project me onto that
vector right so V transpose R gives me
this vector
well actually it gives me a scalar right
it gives me a scalar which is how long
this actually is along that along that
vector right so now the question is
that's the quantity I need to negate
right I need to make sure my feet my new
V my V prime right my new velocity
basically is the negative of that it's
going upwards but this is a scalar
quantity it's just a number it's the
measure along here how do I actually I
need a whole vector for reflection I
need to construct this whole vector so
what do I do
well it's pretty easy right if I were to
start
mm-hmm if I were to start by saying well
alright I have my V right I now need to
change it so that I'm going to get it so
that it reflects through here I just
need to add something to it right that's
going to move it up so that it will have
that reflection and I know exactly what
that quantity is my V transpose R is the
length along R that this was right and
that's going to be negative obviously
because we know it's going into the wall
so that's going to be negative so if I
multiply that scalar times R times the
actual did the the actual wall
reflection direction right that gives me
a vector that gives me essentially this
vector right here right that's that's
actually the vector now not just the
length so all I have to do to reflect
this across it is just subtract two of
those right just to move it up to here
first and then up to here a second if I
just subtract two of those I will flip
the vector around and have it go out in
the other direction right so again just
constructing it very much like it just
what I want to do with it so I take the
old V and I subtract two times this
quantity over here right where I've got
my V transpose R times R right that will
start at my V that will figure out how
long it is along the reflection vector
it'll move me back to the even line this
will move me back to the wall this first
one right and then by doing two I then
move myself basically to the mirror
position and this was a bad drawing of
where that would be it would actually be
like over here or something right
so my new V prime is just that that's
the entirety that's all I have to do I
have to take my incoming velocity I just
have to subtract twice
whatever that measure was along along
the reflection vector and then move it
in that direction along the reflection
vector right makes sense that is of
course if I've done the math right like
I said I'm horrible at math so anytime
we compute something like that we need
to then go test to see if I'm right
because a lot of times I'll just make a
straight-up mistake okay you know I just
realized I just realized my my Linux has
hung completely which is unfortunate to
say the very least
all right well that's all right we'll go
ahead and get that rebooting and has not
been a good week for a Linux ladies and
gentlemen it has not been a good week
for Linux my Linux crashes all the time
now it's very unfortunate anyway so this
is what we need to implement and all we
really need to do is anytime we want to
bounce something we can just go ahead
and say let's go ahead and define some
unit vector in the direction we want to
bounce and we can bounce and now we are
not restricted to just bouncing off of
things that are going to be you know
aligned with an axis system which would
have gotten this a certain you know a
certain degree of the way certainly
right we totally could have bounced off
just just you know the tile map edges
using that but as soon as we want to do
something fancier it would not have
worked right because if we want to have
a slant if some kind of a slanted wall
in there or anything like that you know
we'd be out of luck all right I'm gonna
go ahead and take one second here to go
ahead and start the hex chat back
up so I will actually be able to see
questions at the end so sorry about that
again not not the best situation for
Linux let's see is it so hard people is
it so hard it is apparently so hard okay
hopefully that'll stay up long enough
for me to answer the questions okay so
let's go ahead and do that let's go
ahead and just implement this so I now
want to do a thing where I compute that
bounce and in order to do that I know
that I need a dot product so we'll open
up our math routines and add one so in
line again it returns a scalar value
inner product it takes two things and I
might just call this inner because if
you use it so often it's pretty obvious
what it actually is and so the result
here again very straightforward
it's just ax times BX mmm
plus a Y times dy okay there we go
I'm out there and so that's our that's
our dot product inner products together
product whatever you want to call it and
that is what we're going to be computing
to do our reflection code and so if we
want to reflect here basically this is
in the case of the tile point not being
empty I guess what we could do is say
alright then if the tile point is not
going to be empty then we basically have
to figure out what direction the wall
was actually in which we haven't
actually done yet but let's pretend that
we do have that so we basically have our
our again this is going to be some some
value here which again is that our from
this equation and what we need to do is
take our velocity which again we have is
the game say D player P and what we need
to do is reflect it about there so we
need to do is say okay we've got the
deep layer P and the new deep layer P
for this frame or I guess have we
actually retired the point yet for this
frame we did the test so I guess it'll
just be for next frame this is count so
we take that deep layer P we're gonna
have to work on this player motion code
a bunch to say the least but anyway
we're gonna take that old deep layer P
we're going to subtract two times the
inner product of whatever it actually is
and our wall vector right and then we're
going
to multiply that by the wall vector
itself right so there we go that's the
actual equation that we need to use and
oops those were lowercase they should
not have been I wonder if I should make
those lowercase that's a good question
it lines up better with the shader code
if you make them lower case because
shaders have dot X dot Y of that sort of
thing if that makes sense all right so
what we need to now know is what
actually is that
so let's hard code it first to make sure
that we actually have our stuff working
at all
so if we actually want it to bounce off
that bottom wall that bottom wall is
going to be obviously just the just the
y-axis so this should do this should do
the initial thing that we just sort of
said was what we would do if we didn't
actually have the dot product or any of
that stuff
so let's see there we go of course
that's pretty funny yeah so there we go
no problems there seems to work pretty
good
of course I'm accelerating against it so
I kind of do there we go
yeah so that's pretty straightforward
nothing much to see there now of course
the problem would be if we actually do
that we we would have the wrong we would
have the entirely wrong behavior because
we're not actually computing the wall
correctly so we do need to do is figure
out some way to actually figure out what
the direction of the wall is that we ran
into and I don't think we really know
very much about how to do that at the
moment I guess we would have to sort of
say well when we check these points
right the new player P the player left
and the player right we need to figure
out which ones of them are are not
actually allowed because we don't really
have much in the way of collision code
at the moment we'd have to figure out
which ones of those were
interpenetrating and for whichever ones
were interpenetrating we would then have
to figure out which direction the step
was between the current position and the
new position like which which which
direction we stepped in the tile map
would tell us where the wall is and this
is one reason why you know like I said
later on I don't think we're gonna be
doing any collision protection on tile
maps because it's just kind of annoying
and
I don't think there we probably want to
have like a more interesting boundary
around things so yeah so I wouldn't I
wouldn't yeah I wouldn't basically I
wouldn't basically put much much much
weight into this this particular stuff
but the bounce code is correct and so
let's keep going with that anyway so
let's say that what we do here is we
take a look at these guys I guess we
could just say whichever one of these
yeah this is kind of ugly but let's just
do it because we might as well we're
here so we've got a bull 32 that's going
to say you know I guess well you know
what I don't even need one of those well
I do yeah I do okay
so we'll just say collided again this is
really bad this is not at all what I
would advise doing but I just want to
we're working on the wall code right now
so I don't really want to spend any time
thinking about it I just want do
something where we can get our wall out
and go and since we know we're not going
to be doing closed objective this way
eventually it's not particularly
interesting to me to think about it much
more so basically if the tile map is not
into their I'm gonna say collided equals
true right like this and then I'm just
essentially going to do that same thing
here so player right right and player
left so I'm just gonna take a look at
those collided and if I did collide then
what I'm gonna do here is see if there's
a tile map position call P or whatever
and that's gonna equal that's gonna
equal in the case of collision whatever
we actually found was the collision and
trigger right whoever actually collided
and this will let me know what actually
caused us to not move right and so this
now becomes collided if we did not
collide right then we can we can go
ahead and do yeah we can go ahead and do
our stuff and so that shouldn't change
anything as it is right we should still
be able to do whatever we were doing
before but now we can compare and figure
out what our where our wall actually is
right so if we want to see where the
wall is now we can essentially say well
we know we collided right and so in some
sense we could reverse the
the sense of these so that we can get
rid of that not there so you can
actually see more cleanly if we collided
with something we just need to figure
out what our wall is to figure out what
our wall is we then go all right
we know coal P is the thing that
collided so what we need to do is take
whatever the player P is right whatever
that whatever the player P currently is
which is this guy and we just need to
see what direction he was trying to go
in the tile map right so if you remember
here we have the tile map position we
have ABS tau XY and Z so we just need to
look and go alright if the ABS tile X is
less than the abs tight X here then we
know that this wall was a wall going in
in sort of in descending the player was
moving from a look to the left right the
play the player hit hit a wall to the
left and we could do the same stuff in
all the directions if it's if it's
greater than and if it's fat so on
and since we can't really make anything
collide diagonally at the moment we
don't guess we don't really need to
worry about that case but anyway here we
go we can basically do I think people
were saying we can do this right yes so
given that we've got what was it oh yeah
sobayed given that we've got that we
basically need to find the wall for each
of these motions so in this case I'm
moving to the left so that means the
wall is like it's normal pointing out to
the right in this case I is moving to
the right so I have the wall pointing to
the left in this case I am moving up and
so the wall is pointing down right is
that correct yes
wait no it's less than so it's moving
down so it would be up right right and
then and then that I believe that is all
of them potentially I'm just like all P
is used well if it collided we know that
well all right fine we'll just do this
yeah and we know that this we know that
these cases can't actually happen but
the compiler isn't being a bit
persnickety there so in theory that
should give us bouncing off of all the
walls yeah there we go right and so now
we're just a bouncy little fellow who's
pretty happy about his lot in life very
determined to go around bouncing along
things and the faster we go the harder
we bounce which is exactly what we
wanted in terms of our behavior now like
I said if we wanted to we could make him
bounce a little softer off things by
basically adding a coefficient in there
it's called a coefficient of restitution
the coefficient of restitution would
would basically be some number less than
one that we would multiply our vector by
to reduce how far out it went and so
that's that's really all that is yay
bouncy fellow okay all right sorry I'll
stop bouncing around a second puts kind
of fun yeah now in theory we don't
really handle the diagonal very well and
you can kind of see that so you can see
what kind of happens up in there and
that's because we only really handle
bouncing off of one or the other at the
time and that's because again like I
said I don't think the towel maps are
really that interesting way to do stuff
so I don't think we'll handle that
eventually that way anyway but what we
could do if we really wanted to start
doing if we really wanted the tile map
collision to be the way we did collision
what we could do is round those off a
little bit pretend they were rounded in
there a little bit and have a nicer
collision there but but it's still it's
fine I mean it works it's just it's not
pretty right yeah all right so now I got
another question for you because I've
given you I've given you everything I
give and I give stream I've given you
everything now it's time for you to give
back all right you're the man now dog
what I want to know is basically I told
you all this stuff
told you about the dot product right
instead of keeping it a secret it could
have been only me that knew the dot
product this whole time and only I can
do all these awesome things and now you
know it too
so tell me with that power how would you
now do something else with the collision
response let's say what I want to do is
have him have the standard the more
familiar kind of quake style movement
where if my guy runs into a wall then
basically he just runs along the wall
like that so instead of him bouncing out
like this he just kind of goes like that
right smoothly along it right how would
I do that now there's a trick to this
one part of it I expect you to get and
the other part II don't expect you to
get because one does a programming thing
and we haven't talked about that yet but
you should be able to do the math part
of this does anyone know anyone well
you're behind on the stream anyway I
know that so I can't really expect you
to answer right away but the reason that
I think this should be easy and if you
want to pause the screen try to figure
out yourself
I saw highly suggest it because it
should be is that I already told you
essentially exactly what you need to do
to do this instead of - in - you could
just subtract one version of this and
that would bring you right up to the
wall right that would bring your
velocity so that was just along the wall
so what we could do is instead just
instead of it being - - right I could
just make it be minus one now like I
said there's another trick to this
though
so if I do that there's another problem
that we have to solve that it will
expose that we've really should have
solved before but you know we don't
really we didn't really have to in that
case right now you'll notice when I come
on here right you can kind of see well
you know it's not as pronounced as I
thought it would be it sort of happened
a little bit there but it's not as bad
as I thought it would be yeah all right
I take it back maybe we don't have to
fix it I felt like we would have to fix
it but I guess we didn't but you can
kind of see now what happens is exactly
what I expect to happen which is that if
I'm going diagonally down you get that
grindy wall thing that you're supposed
to get in video games where you're going
little slower against the wall when
you're pushing into it and you go faster
if you let up
right which is exactly what we want to
feel that that's like a good game feel
thing and so that's right like totally
trivial but what I thought should have
had to happen
and there you can see him kind of
sticking a little there we go I was I
was gonna say should happen I hopefully
you could sort of see how he was
sticking there a little bit occasionally
there we go
right there see how he's stuck so that's
that's the problem that I was alluding
to that we had to fix so I was kind of
glad that that happened how that's like
well I told you there there it is they
read it again right you see that
sticking why is he sticking what's going
on right what's going on with the
sticking I can hear you saying it what's
going to sticking so the problem that we
have and this is a gets sort of to the
heart of collision detection at some
level and and we'll never totally escape
this I will show you the ways in which
we solve these problems in practice but
we will always have to keep thinking
about it there's no magic bullet is that
in the real world collisions aren't some
instantaneous thing everything is
happening kind of continuously and again
it's all atoms and they're all working
together and this sort of stuff and
collisions are this elastic thing where
something deforms a little and dents a
little and moves that whatever right
we're simulating collision like it's
this fixed step thing right and so what
we wrote our code to do way back when
this is not something we wrote today but
what we wrote our code to do way back
when was go okay I'm I'm here you know
here's my dude right so here's the hero
and he wants to go to here right but
this is inside a wall and so what we did
is we disallowed the move that's what we
did but what that means is now oops
when we have our code that's trying to
do this stuff when we skate along the
wall we get into a problem where if the
user is pushing down into the wall like
that right we can correct that velocity
but we've already denied the move so the
hero essentially doesn't move on that
frame even though we've corrected his
velocity right so what we really want to
do is we want to see if you would have
collided and if you would have collided
we want to correct this velocity and
then try to move them again and you can
see why this is a bit of a nasty cycle
because then your very next question
should be and legitimately should be
mind you what happens if he collides
then so you're kind of in
this nasty situation where you have to
deal very specifically with the
discreteness of everything and go oh
I've kind of got this nasty problem
where I've got a lot of different sort
of concerns there right and so what we
could do is very simply like you know we
could try twice and then give up or
whatever like there's different things
we can do we'll be looking for there's a
very there's a really interesting way I
solve this on the witness that I haven't
actually seen anyone talk about before
that I I've sort of considered doing in
handmade hero but I don't know if it's
the most appropriate thing for it so I
don't know if that's a good solution not
but we will look at various solutions
later when we do our full collision
detection but for so for now we'll have
to do something you know that somewhat
somewhat not does somewhat janky right
that's not that's not the nicest thing
in the world and so basically what we
would do there is say okay if we correct
our velocity let's try using that
velocity on this frame right and again
that's not exactly correct either okay
so I'm gonna go ahead and wrap this in a
four I loop we are going to do the new
player P right we've got the player P
offset that comes in here which we try
adding and then we go ahead and say once
we've actually computed that D player PE
we're going to write okay and so what we
need to do now is say alright now that
we've actually compute a new D player P
we need to be able to try again this
basic process right so I'm trying to
think this is a reflected vector that's
happened after the acceleration was
tried and do we really want do we want
to do how do we want to do that exactly
after we've clipped that velocity I
guess we just want to move him by that
velocity that we actually have left so I
guess I don't want to solve this in this
stream because here's what I actually
want to do and so maybe we should save
this for tomorrow because we just don't
have enough time left what I actually
want to do is I want to actually sort of
show a slightly more correct collision
response here which is when we have this
motion and we find that we intersect I
want to back up to the point where we
hit and put the guy there and then
correct his velocity and then step it
forward right I want to do something
like that
and so I would rather do
that potentially such a it's such a
tough choice here guys
or maybe I'll do the thing I didn't is
alright so you know what let's table
this till tomorrow because we don't have
any time left let's get ready for the QA
and let's just say this is a to be to
continued that we will talk about
tomorrow and I'm gonna think about which
way I want to solve it right now because
I think I might want to actually try the
witness way because it's actually kind
of cool and I think we can just do it
here and then whether or not we can
actually do it a little later on I'm not
sure because there's more to the witness
way than the way that I would be able to
do here so well it's this table this for
now it's a 59 and we will pick it up
again tomorrow so we can start the Q &amp; A
and basically what I would like you to
do is if you could write in and put your
questions with a Q : in front of them so
I can see them and also please keep your
questions to stuff we did on today's
stream or on a previous stream if you
want to ask off-topic questions we can
handle those during pre stream which is
basically come 15 minutes before the
scheduled start time and I answer
whatever questions come up on the stream
at that time but not at this time you
will note that if you ask questions that
are not related to the programming that
we've been doing I will just skip over
them it's like they didn't even exist
okay uh let's see here obviously was
bouncing now you need to add those
annoying bouncy enemies and deadly
spiked walls pits later you know I don't
really know what we're gonna do with
bouncing I haven't thought too much
about that but we should have something
bounce off at the very least at some
point you should be able to get some
kind of projectile bit bounces because I
like bouncy projectiles those are always
fun so we're gonna have salton that
bounces we just don't know what it will
be I mean we coded it we've got to use
it right
can you explain again why the hero will
stick against the wall I didn't get it
the first time okay yes I can so the
reason is this piece of code right here
so what happens is the code says did we
collide right
remember we compute the new location for
where the hero is right when we compute
that new location we then test to see
whether he could stand in that new
location that's all we were testing
remember because this is really old this
is this is just simple code that we've
been playing with so we didn't try to do
anything fancy we just said can he stand
in the new location that's all we're
going to test if he cannot stand in the
new location right he can't then what we
did is we said all right he won't we
won't take a step remember this right
here is the thing that actually puts the
player in the new location so if we
enter the collided branch we will update
his velocity properly but we will never
update his position at all so that means
as long as the game great that's good
thank you for that I needed that as long
as the game is in a situation where he's
trying to move and stand in a position
on the other side of the wall it won't
move him at all even though it corrects
his velocity on the next frame it may be
such that that velocity is is put right
like you could almost let me let me
actually show you exactly what's
happening if you could if you could
think about it he's got a velocity these
built up using the acceleration that has
been generated from the user input right
so he's moving along moving along that
acceleration has built him up to have a
velocity he slams into the wall okay
with this velocity he should step across
the wall he doesn't because we test and
see that he can't move there we correct
his velocity to be the bounce right so
I'm sorry not the bounce we correct the
velocity to be along the wall directly
now he still got a little distance to
the wall cuz remember we haven't done
anything to move him right up to the
wall so he might be a little bit away
from the wall and now his velocities
this so on the next frame we have his
acceleration his acceleration is still
into the wall but it's only an
acceleration so it only moves this
vector down a little bit so now he can
actually move here so he won't stick on
the next frame but on the frame after
that he
right right because he's now
accelerating more and more into the wall
and so he's constantly in this situation
of kind of trying to drive back into the
wall and if he drives directly back into
the wall he will stick so what ends up
happening is as he moves along the wall
he's actually constantly getting to
these stick scenarios where it's like up
he was into the wall overcorrect the
velocity up he was into the wall correct
the velocity so what we want to do to
prevent that is say okay if the player
accelerates into the wall right we don't
want to just deny the motion entirely we
want to just correct the motion so that
he moves to like here and correct the
velocity he should always still be
moving as far as he would have moved in
this direction right so he should move
there basically right he should so he so
that's what we need to do to correct
that hopefully that makes some sense
when we scale down the hero um possibly
for next week we don't really have to
care at the moment because we're not
really doing anything particularly
touchy about that but when we start to
do the like hopping code we'll probably
want to have him scaled properly so
probably for next week I'll maybe update
the art assets file with with stuff
that's scaled properly have I considered
using sine zero to sine 90 as a
nonlinear inertia curve no we haven't
really talked about any sorts of curve
interpolation yet so save that for
thinking down the road that's I don't
know that that's the one I would use
because sine is more expensive to
compute usually than other things that
would be essentially the same so I if I
was trying to do an inertia curve I
would probably just use a Bezier but you
know that's just off the top of my head
will you eventually handle both the
player and monsters uniformly with some
kind of physics engine so I don't really
want to use the term physics engine but
we will obviously have movement code
that is designed to handle what the
player and the monsters do together but
the word physics engine suggests that
it's actually trying to simulate physics
which is not really the goal here we
basically have a bunch of rules that we
want to do and some of them are based on
the underlying equations of motion which
are physical and so some of it is
physics II but physics engine usually
denotes a sort of different objective do
you need to code in different collision
detection for the enemies no our
collision detection will probably just
be one set of routines that works
relatively uniformly but we may have
special casing because we may want to
fine-tune how collision detection works
differently for enemies than the player
and depending on how we want to do it I
mean so there may be there may be some
things that are specific to the player
versus the enemies but in general
they'll go through the same path
this code is largely commented by video
will you be commenting it in the source
later for those who pre-ordered we only
will really do comments in the source
code once we've finished a section of
code and are kind of baking it away
because otherwise the comments just get
out of date even the to dues are already
out of date a lot of times so adding a
bunch of comments is usually a bad idea
you really only want to comment code
when you are actually ready to kind of
bake it because otherwise the comments
usually end up being worse than not
having comments because they actually
say the wrong thing and they'll confuse
people who are trying to understand
what's going on do you plan on having
non axes lined walls in the maps well I
don't actually plan on having non axis
aligned walls in the maps but I do plan
on having like what I want to do is
essentially say we're a tile map game in
terms of how the like generation goes
but like once the generator says you
know oh this is the structure of
something right like here's you know
here's here's how the you know this is
walkable in here and this is not then I
actually want to do like the way I want
it was hoping to do it is to sort of say
well then what's gonna happen is we're
gonna start placing things like if this
was a forest you know we'll start
placing trees and the trees make up the
wall right but then instead of collision
detecting with the wall will actually
collision detect with the trees so that
when the hero walks along them they
actually feel like the trees instead of
feeling like a tile map jus know what I
mean so I don't know that we're gonna
have we're not gonna have like walls
that are like diagonal or something but
we will have tons of like crenelated
surfaces potentially or other things
like that and we may also have entities
in the game that behave like walls that
could be angled depending on how they go
so we will have stuff where we will need
to be able to compute stuff that bounces
off of arbitrary surfaces it will not be
as straightforward as just doing the
four cardinal directions
what do you think about position based
dynamics leaving out velocity and
forests in doing physics directly using
the current and previous positions I
think it's good I mean we are sort of
already doing that in some sense because
really you're not really leaving out
force and velocity in those systems a
lot of times what you're actually doing
is you're just not trying to how should
I say that you still have to have a
notion of how fast something is going so
position based physics still does have
to take into account velocity right but
what you are doing typically in those
sessions that makes them position based
instead of velocity based or set of
acceleration based is where you choose
to resolve basically the the actual
stepping of the time step instead of
actually doing it as an integration
taking many samples of velocity and so
on as opposed to doing it directly on
the physics on the positions so you
still have to know all the equations of
motion it's just about where you resolve
that stuff and so at this point we
almost are really doing that because we
don't ever do anything we don't really
do any ever any numerical integration at
the velocity level or anything
let's see will the stream tomorrow
morning be coding or QA it's both we
always do coding and QA are we going to
make continuous collision detection well
there's no real such thing as continuous
collision detection I mean obviously
we're all discrete in computers but if
you're just talking about whether we
will check to see whether or not the guy
along a vector has intersected things
yes we will is the computational cost of
different functions something you only
learn through experience or are there
good references for C++ well the
computational cost of things doesn't
actually have anything to do a C++ it
has to do with the the CPU instructions
that get generated by the C++ and so
typically what you want to do is yeah
you have to learn by experience what
those are and how they tend to affect
performance but really what you want to
do is spend time profiling you want to
spend time timing different things in
your code and learning how they work
because that is really the only way so I
only have a rough idea in my head in a
given time of what the cost of a
function is but once I need to act start
optimizing you have to be very specific
in profile things which is not something
we've gotten to yet we will do that much
later yes I agree with the person who's
saying that the cursor in Krita is hard
to see and I'm not sure how to make it
do something more visible I know you can
do this thing I don't know if that if
that would help at all
I also don't know if krita's saves any
of my settings it didn't seem to I would
like it to but it didn't seem to want to
do that I don't know if I have to do
something else to make it do that but
basically yeah it doesn't ever seem to
say save the size of the brush but it
guess it will save the cursor so that's
fine so that's something anyway right
let's see are there any situations in
which other angles are more useful than
quaternions okay we're definitely that's
that's definitely a question for much
farther than the future and first of all
I don't know that we'll ever that will
ever be a question for the stream
because quaternions are only really
necessary for 3d rotations which we
won't really have to deal with will you
end up running into problems when
walking into a corner after the sticking
fix tomorrow it depends on how we fix it
possibly it depends will there be
minimum distance to the wall where any
input towards it is similarly replaced
with partial parallel correction vector
without looping over possibilities well
so it like I said it depends on how we
implement it I'm toying with may be
doing the witness thing but I just if we
were gonna stick with tile map collision
I would definitely do the witness thing
but I don't know based on where we're
gonna go with it I don't know if that's
a good idea or not
we're computing a vector that moves the
player just above the wall but still
along it solved the stopping problem in
collision well so the problem is not
computing the vector because we did
compute that vector right that's what
this does this computes exactly that
vector the problem is that we only
compute that vector after we know that
we collided and when we know that we
collided we don't accept the the new
position right does that make sense so
we have a bunch of work to do here to
figure out how we're going to make it so
that we can test the position and accept
the position while doing correction in
between was the problem right if that
makes sense
oh my god I'm am I reading this right I
feel like the moderators of the stream
are now arguing over you're the man now
dog
I get the projection of V onto our but
don't you end up just pointing back on
negative R by multiplying the projection
by negative 2r where is the other
component of the bounce handled I see I
see the question and that is a good
question so let's go ahead and answer
that question all right so I'm gonna
draw it orthogonal e4u all right I'm
gonna draw it without an axis system so
that we don't have the axis system in
there right here's our okay it extends
infinitely in all directions but it's
length is only one so you know it's it's
this direction but you know length of R
equals one right and so now we have
something that's coming in and it's
hitting here and so here is the vector
right that is hitting this is the
velocity vector so this is V we want to
compute a new V right we want to compute
V prime that is up here and so what we
are trying to do is perform this flip
now what you will notice is this
component right whatever this axis is we
don't even know what this axis is we
didn't even give it a name it's the wall
axis right but that portion of this
vector we don't want to touch right this
and this both map to the same location
on this other axis so we don't need to
modify that coordinate all we need to do
is flip this guy around you know all we
need to do is handle this coordinate
that Y we don't need to touch the other
one so that's why we did V plus our
bounce expression right and I mean
technically V - right we did B minus 2 V
T our R right it's because we start at
the existing velocity and all we're
doing is applying the correction that
does the flip that's why we don't have
to handle this specially now we could if
we wanted to handle it specially right
we could have another thing here which
would basically be W right and how would
we do that well then our V prime right
we would construct it
by saying what's our V prime well we
know that our V prime should have this
vector in it right it should have that
right so it's it's it's length along R
should be the negative of whatever it
was right and so we're like okay so we
know we want to subtract V transpose R R
to sort of start by getting us up to
here right because this is V transpose R
right this length so negative B
transpose R would get us up to here and
now we need to add this part back in
right we need to add we need to add this
W well what's that well that's just
going to be V transpose W right so it
would be V transpose W times W and
remember these are scalars and these are
vectors right hopefully that makes some
sense this would be our new this would
be our new vector and we could compute
it that way if we wanted to it just
means we have to have a second vector in
here which is this W vector now what do
we know about the W vector right well we
know that the W vector is perpendicular
to the R vector right so we know
basically that that that and this is
jumping ahead a little bit but we know
that this is true about their inner
product why do we know that's true
because what was that equation I showed
you before I showed you the equation
length of a length of B cosine angle
between them right well what's the
cosine of the angle between two
perpendicular vectors it's 90 degrees
right if it's 90 degrees the cosine of
90 is zero that means it doesn't matter
what anything else is this is zero
because these guys no matter what they
are can't multiply 0 to be anything
other than zero right so we know that W
transpose R is zero right so if we
looked at this extra expression that we
added here we've got a negative VTR and
then we've got a positive V T W right so
we've got V T W times W right and so
this we know you know if we're if we're
going to basically say well you know
we're gonna try and make we're going to
try and
sorry but I lost my trans off there for
a second oh we're gonna try and say well
well you know these two things should be
equal right well negative V to V T RR
you know V minus V this and this if they
should be equal I should be able to set
up that equality right if I'm if I'm
telling you this is true right and so
what I'm what I'm saying there is that V
this this oval squares of to VTR are
that should equal this equation negative
VTR r+ v tww right and you can kind of
start to see okay well if I transfer
this to the other side I would get V
minus VT R R that goes away right
because it adds one to that and V tww
right that's what that is so what that's
telling me is V transpose W times W must
be equal to V minus V transpose R R
right and we actually can see that
that's true right V which is this term
minus V transpose R R right which is
this distance times this vector which is
this right here right is equal to this
point V transpose W times W that is
exactly what we expected to see and it
is what we see right and so that's where
that comes from there yeah so there's
not a whole lot else I could really show
you about this without going into too
this and substituting in basically what
we have to do is say well let's break up
V into the sum of two vectors one of
which is going along R in one of those W
or whatever and then see how they died
out and blah blah blah but you get the
idea so hopefully that makes it a little
bit clearer is there a way to speed up
the drawbitmap code i'm trying it on my
laptop and it doesn't hit 33 FPS um
there are a lot of ways you could speed
up the draw a bit Mac code I don't
really know that I want to talk about
them right now though because one of our
very first tasks after we sort of
finished getting our basic movement
basic you know gameplay stuff in over
the next couple of weeks is to write the
renderer so I'd like to save it for then
because we're going to actually write a
whole renderer and
that'll be the time when we look at it
if you're looking at just the basic
thing that you might want to do if you
haven't already done it if you're just
trying to make it run faster what you
could do is is turn on optimization
right so if you go in here and you you
look at this it's the optimization
switches o2 if you put that o - if you
just if you just put an o2 in here that
would compile it to probably run quite a
bit faster so if you haven't already
done that you'd want to do that alright
it looks like we are done with questions
do I have any more questions if so we
yeah this is an early Q&amp;A I don't know
if that means nobody knows what I'm
talking about when I talk about the math
fact that that might be the case that
might be the case that would be too bad
I hope that's not true but it might be
we had some good math questions so some
people obviously know totally get what
the math is doing but I hope it's not
too much math sometimes people just
their eyes glaze over when we go to the
math but it's really easy to understand
if you always just think back to what
the actual stuff is doing and and you
can get it trust me I am really bad at
math so if I can do it you can do it you
just got to be willing to kind of dig in
a little bit and actually start
practicing with those things oh yes
whoever just suggested removing the
background yes that's a good point so if
you are having trouble we're basically
bleeding a giant background here for no
reason so if you wanted to you could
totally you could totally do that just
just comment out this code right and and
that would be you know an easy way to
get it to run faster if you want to put
a clear in there as well you could but
you know sometimes it's fun
yeah
Oh No I drew the triangle wrong I'm
sorry let me draw the triangle again
it's bound to happen when I'm drawing
stuff quick math wise well actually it's
usually the case that I'll make an
actual math mistake it's a miracle that
I haven't made one yet okay when I drew
this someone was saying I put it on the
wrong side I was I was trying to write
this but I think I must have inverted
them right so just to be clear on the
right triangle this is how it should go
and we did everything else right like
the dot product when we drew it was you
know working correctly but yeah sorry I
don't I don't know why I did that
sometimes I get carried away so yeah so
it's it's it's this guy it's this side
and so that's why again dot product wise
when you've got the two guys in here
when you're doing that mapping dropping
it down
here's that that guy you don't get this
length right that would be sine theta
what you get is this length now there is
something that does give you sine theta
right that's called the cross product
but but we haven't gotten to that yet
and we probably won't do much of that
actually because you don't really need
it in 2d very much it's more of a 3d
maybe you can mention formal keywords
like projection transformation and
spaces so people can look things up if
they need to yeah so I don't know that
we've played gotten to some of those
things yet but yeah I mean if you think
that is I mean we haven't really gotten
to matrices or all those sorts of things
so I don't know if they'll be a little
too confusing for people to kind of jump
straight into that but in general
essentially matrix math when you
actually do transforms matrix transforms
they are actually a series of dot
products and so you can't actually go
look up like he was saying spaces and
transforms those are things that we'll
talk about this sort of behavior but a
lot of them it's really hard to I don't
even know what to point you to to look
up for more information I don't know who
explains these sorts of things in a good
way necessarily so maybe go to the
forums if you're having trouble with
stuff and ask and some people who are
more math inclined there might have some
good resources that explain these in
nice intuitive ways and so they're just
throwing tons of equations at you and
hoping that you know what they're
talking about
was the witness collision trick to try
and maintain the distance traveled no
the witness collision trick is to do
movement as a search problem instead of
as a as a physics problem
let's see here
why does wall bouncing not seem to cause
cause sticking but wall sliding does
well if you think through the way that
code works hopefully you can kind of see
what's actually going on there so let's
take the situation with bounce right so
I got this situation and I'm going to
deny this move but I set the velocity to
here so that means on this frame the guy
doesn't move at all which we just can't
see cuz the frame rate so high if the
frame rate was like you know ten frames
a second we'd see him stick just at
every bounce right so one frame he
doesn't move but on the next frame his
velocities pointing in this direction so
he's definitely gonna move now so he
could never stick on the wall for more
than one frame right but in the other
scenario where all we do is do that then
if he gets close enough to the wall in
floating point math for the amount of
acceleration that we add every frame to
make it so that every frame it's
constantly we correct it but then on the
next frame it moves the acceleration to
here and he tries to go into the wall
again he could just stay there
constantly trying to get into the wall
right and never move anywhere that's
never gonna happen with this because if
he's pointing into the wall on the next
frame he's pointing out of the wall but
this will never make him point out at
the wall right he'll only point even or
in in fact it's always slightly in
because if you're if I'm holding down
the keys trying to push him into the
wall he's always having acceleration
added to him that pushes his velocity
vector into the wall
abner yes we will have debug info
rendered on the game itself that is
something we will be doing once our
render is kind of up somebody says that
you can look up a lot of these things on
Khan Academy so I don't know if that's
good or not but that's maybe one place
to look for a more mass stuff well the
rendering code be able to squash the
bitmaps for example to signal the
collision yes
well I don't know that will necessarily
do squashing into a collision but we
will allow bitmaps to be squashed and
stretched yeah
in fact that's kind of interesting
problem actually that people don't talk
about very much there's an interesting
there's an interesting part about bitmap
squashing and stretching that that is I
guess I would say is I've never seen it
actually just put forth as bluntly as it
probably should be and so when we get
there I will be bluntly putting it forth
could you would you benefit from
unrolling the collision check loop using
a predefined number of segments along
the movement vector we don't actually
have a collision check loop at the
moment but unrolling loops nowadays is
usually not particularly useful
depending on the circumstance so it
depends what you're talking about since
we don't have a collision loop yet I
can't really say if there'd be any
benefit to unrolling it all right I
think that is the end of the questions
so that is the end of the stream event
there we go so thank you everyone for
joining me it was a pleasure coding with
you for a very mafia handmade hero
tonight if you would like to follow
along at home you can pre-order the game
on him hero org and it comes with all
the source code so you'll get a link in
your email that allows you to download
every night after I finished coding I
upload the source code you can go ahead
and and grab that and play around with
it which is a great way to learn because
you can try out different stuff and see
what
if you want support the video series we
do have a patreon as well and we've got
a news and forum site that's pretty cool
to go to it's got a lot of useful stuff
on it like the schedule for the week is
up there there's an episode guide if you
want to catch up with old episodes got
time coded videos up there for you if
the coding resources page with ports to
Mac and Linux and other stuff that's
pretty handy and the code discussion
forum you can ask questions on if you
would like to ask questions so if you
try to learn from the stream I highly
recommend going there it's great place
to check out and there's a lot of very
helpful people very nice people up there
who answer questions and stuff so thank
you very much for joining me we will be
back here again not too long from now at
9 a.m. tomorrow morning to do some more
work on the player movement code I'm not
sure what we'll do after that I think I
want us maybe start getting into jumping
and bouncing that sort of stuff and so
that's probably what we'll get into I
don't know if we'll get into tomorrow
but certainly starting next week we will
get into that because that's what I'd
like to do as our next step that we're
going to do with vectors so again thank
you very much for joining me and I hope
to see you all tomorrow and if not if
it's too early in the morning I
understand I will see you Monday so
thanks for tuning in everyone