start recording so hello everyone and
welcome to a limping edition of handmade
hero which I know it's a little bit odd
to say but of you know especially since
our hero has no legs it's hard to limp
but unfortunately I guess twitch
suffered some sort of a cyber attack and
I'm sure was a sophisticated cyberattack
because no one ever says just cyber
attack because that would make it sound
like they didn't have sophisticated
security so I'm sure with a
sophisticated cyber attack that
consisted of someone running some
scripts somewhere and so there had to be
a bunch of oo oo 3 set key reset stream
reset stuff happening and so we're we're
sort of up and running but we don't
really have the QA system back up and
running yet because I haven't gone
through and figured out all the tokens I
need to reset to get it to connect again
so hopefully we'll be able to do that by
tomorrow but today we may have to do
basically like limited QA or or you know
not not really the kind of QA that we're
used to doing but we can stream the show
and so that's something and so if we
can't stream the show we should stream
the show and so in order to do that I
guess what we should probably do is it's
get started take a look at where we are
at and and yeah today is day 84 so if
you're trying to follow along at home
unzip day 83 source code if you're one
of people who pre-ordered on handmade
hero org 83 is the day that you want to
start with so let's take a look let's
let's do a little bit of our own damage
assessment here now that we no twitches
in the middle of their damage assessment
and let's take a look so we are at the
point we took a little bit of a
diversion last week and we made a thing
that does little background bitmap
composites it was kind of cool like I
like that little ground composite back
there that we just kind of hacked
together it was a pretty neat thing and
you know kind of validated the idea of
how we were going to build our
backgrounds but it was kind of a
diversion and also don't ask me why we
have all these heads floating here you
know
sometimes you just have a lot of heads
floating around everywhere and you know
we probably should should maybe you know
let me let me just take a minute and
turn those off because that's just too
many heads that's way too many heads and
we're just getting confused if that many
heads are floating around so let's let's
turn that back down let's get back to a
single floating head which is which is
easier for us to deal with
alright so hmm where we are at at the
moment is we we are trying to figure out
how to finish off our world construction
so that basically ground and stuff is is
more of a known quantity so that we can
move on and and call a call our Z
handling finished and right now
everything works kind of well as long as
you're on one level and we sort of
started working on stuff where you can
go multiple levels like that allows me
to kind of walk up for our mythical
staircase which you don't have graphics
for yet but we kind of drew some
rectangles in there so we could see
where it was and kind of see it's like
sort of 3d aspect to there to it right
but we now need to kind of take it just
to the to the final step that we haven't
done yet which is actually putting some
ground in so that we can see sort of
like when we have two levels one that
eclipses the other that we can see where
that is and also so that we can we
haven't really gone through and and
modified our collision loop to really
handle the the necessary like we haven't
really done the work that we need to do
in order to ensure that our people
actually walk on the ground right so
right now all we actually do is we just
assume that the ground is at zero and we
did the work to put in actual markers to
say what you know where the ground was
but we didn't actually do the work to
use them yet so that's sort of something
that we need to do and so I don't know
which order will tackle this and maybe
we'll just kind of start trying to move
towards a place where we are both
drawing some ground and where we know
where that ground actually is that seems
like probably the best thing for us to
be doing alright so
let's think about this a little right
now we have a thing that composites
ground in the background so we did that
but we haven't actually done any work to
actually put that into the world
anywhere it's just something that guys
called in the main loop so you can see
it just stays there in the upper right
hand corner and so one thing we might
want to think about now and this is kind
of where I'm leaning it's just how do we
get that into the world so that we can
have those sort of textures as our
actual ground texture and it will move
around as we move around right in order
to do that it seems like we probably
want to put an entity in there that is
you know that has that ground texture
and then when that entity comes in it's
going to get drawn with that ground
texture right and I don't know exactly
how we want to do that that's kind of a
you know kind of been up in the air
thing but you know let's just take a
look at where we're at with how we were
specifying the ground things and see if
there's something we can figure out
that'll be a reasonable way to sort of
start getting that worked into the
system so that it's not this sort of
floating weird separate thing
so we currently know that we've got this
sort of space option here this is the
entity it's sort of this concept that we
can it can can talk about empty space in
the world and basically these empty
space entities we can put around the
world and they tell us where the person
can walk right anywhere there's empty
space that's somewhere you can walk in
anywhere where there's a bottom to the
empty space like so that where there's
no more empty space beneath it that was
going to be our definition for where the
ground is and that seems like a pretty
good idea now the question is what do we
actually want to do in terms of drawing
those ground areas do we want that to be
something that's defined with the space
do we want that to be something that
sort of splat it out separately and I'm
not really sure it's a little bit tricky
well you know maybe let me flip to the
blackboard for a second and I'll try to
kind of go over with you what I was
thinking
let's see funny that we say we flip over
to the whiteboard and it says nowadays
nothing works reliably anymore that's
kind of a moral story today right
alright alright so let's see here we are
on on day 84 so let me go ahead and make
a little space here for day 84 and then
we will go ahead and and and talk about
this a little so right now where we're
at is we've got a pretty flexible system
right for defining where the ground is
and and so what we did is we said all
right we're gonna have sort of these
these spatial entities that define sort
of rooms almost right and those rooms
don't actually have to be literal rooms
right they can be outdoors or whatever
but there's basically bounding volumes
that say this is a walkable area the
user can walk around on here and the
bottom of it is considered to be solid
for all intents and purposes you know
unless there was another bounding volume
that kind of overlapped it right that
you could good work with but assuming
that you just had one like this then
this was actually ground and so it might
make some sense to say all right
maybe the ground is just defined the the
image of the ground is defined as being
something that's drawn sort of on this
bottom plate right and so that's one
thing we could say I it's a little
problematic though right because it has
this this issue and that issue is that
if we wanted to start making more
complex shapes right if we wanted to
start like carving out like let's say we
also carved out a little pit here by
adding another one of these right then
we wouldn't want the ground to be drawn
in there we'd want the ground ground the
ground to be drawn over here right and
we sort of have this nasty problem at
that point where how are we defining
like how would we know how this would
work how would we know how it was
clipped and so on in sand and
furthermore like when and how is this
bitmap being produced like I don't if we
have a giant world I don't want to store
that bitmap I don't want to store that
huge bitmap for the whole thing right I
want to store something a lot more
minimal so that I don't have to worry
about storing some gigantic data set
just to pre-produce the ground
especially when the ground is made up of
like you know if you take a look at this
from the top for looking at this you
know I don't want to store this giant
bitmap for the ground when really it was
just a bunch of like overlapping splats
anyway at worst I would just want to
store those splats right like all I'd
really want to do is store the splats
that went in here and and that seems to
me like a much more sane way to store it
because I could regenerate it pretty
easily from those splats and that gets
me out of the business of storing these
giant bitmaps and so how would I do that
storage along with the thing I don't
know it would need like the list of
splats like guess I'm not sure but point
being it's a little bit wonky but you
know we could do it so the next question
is let's say there's an ax button one
like you know there's another one over
here so it's like there's two rooms next
to each other maybe there's a doorway in
between them and we would like or maybe
there's nothing in between them maybe
just completely open right and it goes
this direction now what I'd like to do
especially if this is like so there's a
pit here you know it's like that and so
if we were to look at how this thing was
set up right there's another it
continues over here right this piece is
this piece here and when I'm building
these things together I want especially
if we are in an region where we want to
support smooth scrolling or something
like that we don't want there to be a
hard seam going across that sort of that
edge there right
I want this splat to contribute to here
so that we have a seamless texture that
goes all across and then there's be more
splats up here right and that's fine but
we want the ones that that work across
the boundary to work properly
right so you know there's definitely a
lot of there's a lot of tweaking us here
there's a lot of things to think about
so what I really need to do is I need
some way I think what I'm gonna need to
do if I want to do this the splat stuff
and and I don't think the splats
probably want to be entities really I
mean there's no need for destroy them
all those entities we could do that
the simplest way to do this obviously
would be to store all the slots as
entities but I mean then we're really
starting to talk about really
multiplying that entity account for no
reason because these things are just
things that produce a ground texture and
I don't know that we ever really want to
start talking about them as entities
they can't really get modified much even
if they could get modified we probably
wouldn't necessarily modify them in the
way that they would be entities right we
just kind of like overlay bitmaps on top
of them to show like scorch marks or
something right but we probably wouldn't
actually be modifying these things like
we wouldn't slide around the splats or
anything like that that doesn't seem
like a very logical thing for us to want
to do and certainly not as a full entity
that's gonna have all these properties
and stuff it just doesn't seem like that
would be necessary now maybe I'll be
wrong about that and we'll see again all
of these things whenever you're going
through architecture stuff like this
you're just trying to do your best guess
first and you can never really be sure
when a game goes down you know through
the rest in production there's always
gonna be things where you find out you
were wrong and that's ok but you do want
at least try to make that initial guess
when you're doing your engine
architecture you want to have some
guiding principles there some reason to
suspect you might be right you don't
just want to do nothing or do the
easiest thing because then you're really
not doing your job setting the engine up
for success right so anyway
and that's just again part of the that's
sort of the same mentality with right
the usage case first right it's like you
want to try and do something that you
really think is what the game will
actually do when you're designing the
engine you want that to sort of drive
how the engine works you don't want to
just do whatever is easiest in the
engine or something like that or ignore
a problem till later on you want to try
and envision okay how do I actually make
this work let's try to make that work in
a first pass that we have a reasonable
set up there that we believe might
actually be effective okay so there's
some pretty easy ways I could store the
splat list right and so I'm thinking
that basically that one of the easiest
things to do would probably just store
the splat list as something that
actually you know exactly as we were to
to use it before
so if you look at this draw test ground
you can see the parameters coming in
here are essentially nothing right it's
basically just a width and height of a
buffer that needs to get composited and
then a random seed that just is like you
know some some value that we're saying
to seed the random number with and then
it's just picking random values now I
don't think that'll be the entirety of
it I think we're gonna add more
complicated stuff like when we want to
have like dirt roads going like paths
going through things or stuff like that
we're gonna have more information here
so it's gonna be a little more
complicated than that but on the whole
if we were to generate one of these
splat sets really all we would need is
some notion of how big we want to seem
to be like the radius how big we want
the splat region to be how many splats
we want it to do or some other metrics
like that right that's really all we
need to do in order to put this thing
together without actually having to
store where the things went so we don't
need to store all hundred grasses we
don't need to store all hundred stones
or whatever it's flats that we did we
can just store something that's net that
we use to generate those and that will
be sufficient so I'm thinking that you
know storing the splat list is going to
be something pretty simple it's gonna be
something like you know sort of some
definition of the region to splat some
definition of what - splat right but
that's really all we're gonna need to do
for that I think
and then we'll regenerate it so the more
complex thing I think in general is
going to be about figuring out the shape
of the ground right because where the
ground is really has to do with what
those spatial entities are that have
been set up those empty space entities
and that's a little bit more complicated
to do right we kind of have to have some
sort of an opinion about where that
ground is and it's it's a little bit
tricky now what I think I could do is
basically when I am pulling in when I'm
doing the rendering right I'm gonna know
for any given screen right I'm gonna
know all the spatial entities that over
that are
involved right and so I'm gonna have a
notion of like here's all the spatial
entities that have been defined you know
on the screen or something like that
that overlap the screen you know on
every in every at every Z level right so
there might be some down here as well
and so on and so forth right so what I
could do is imagine the essentially
taking slices through the world right
saying okay there's going to be some
fixed number of Z levels so there's some
going to be some fixed number of Z
levels in the game right that are
visible at any given time we have one z
level which is like whatever the players
standing on to some degree or whatever
is you know fairly close to that and
maybe you know that is is sort of this
region here right these are the empty
spaces that that are sort of all lined
up with where the player is standing and
then maybe there's some that are
actually like below where the players
standing as well so maybe this one is
like a lower Z level so maybe this is
you know a Z equals you know negative
one and this is Z equals zero or
whatever you know we're not really
assigning any values here but just
thinking how that goes and so what I
could do certainly is I could build up a
region and say okay this is you know
roughly what has to be regenerated right
for the ground I could sort of build up
that region and say let's go ahead and
build up the splats that are in these
regions we'll build them up and we'll
clip them to whatever this region looks
like right so as you move around
we'll just regenerate whatever we need
to you know what I'm saying because
really the each Z level could have its
own buffer that's as big as we want in
terms for caching so we could be working
on a buffer that's that's fairly large
right that we just used for caching and
then when it Scrolls if there's a region
of it that hasn't been filled yet we'll
fill it but it's not quite as simple as
that because that region has to have
holes in it right in other words like I
was saying if this is the edge let's say
this you know a better example maybe
would be to say let's say we're looking
at a place where the hero is standing on
some stuff here right and the hero is up
here
and they're stuffed down below so
there's a Ledge that they're kind of
looking over right and there's another
region here and so if this region here
is at a different Z level than this
region here then we need sort of two
right there's two buffers at play here
there's the one that's that's up higher
right that the player is standing on and
then there's that one that's lower
and we can't composite them both into
the same region in terms of if we're
doing some sort of lazy sort of building
of what the what these things look like
we can't do them both into the same
buffer and the reason for that is that
this layer will move at a different rate
than this layer you know potentially if
we want there to be that like parallax
happening then when the hero like moves
this way right this line is going to
move this way faster than this thing
moves this way right that's just how
that's going to work and so I I don't
really know exactly how we want to
handle this the easiest way is if we
could just know ahead of time that
there's a certain number of Z slices
right and and so you know what I would
like to be able to do is say all right
add a maximum we've got some depth some
number of Z slices right so there's like
our Z zero slice you know our our z1 our
z2 r z3 and these don't correspond to
actual Z's in some sense they're really
layers in fact I could say that this is
really more it's not Z it's just depth
right so this is like depth 0 this is
depth 1 depth 2 type 3 right and like
depth 0 might be above the player so
this is above the player this is like at
the player you know this is below the
player and this is like a second layer
of below right and so normally you don't
see this one unless you're transitioning
so if the player is kind of going up
into this layer then they will actually
experience it right they will see it
come in and it will kind of blend in but
then it will become the at layer again
right and similarly these below layers
will work the same way like if you were
walking down the stairs then this layer
comes up at you this one comes up at you
and then a new one comes in from the
bottom right and the
at layer becomes that above layer so if
you think about it we sort of you know
what I'd like to do is have this sort of
notion that the game has to work within
some constraints you can't have
arbitrary stuff going on here because
we're not a 3d renderer and that would
caused a bunch of problems right so
that's probably the way that I'd most
like to look at it because that would be
really kind of easy to conceptualize
again the problem with it is it wouldn't
let us do sort of arbitrary stuff it
wouldn't let us have arbitrary levels of
ground right so if we wanted another
piece of ground thing in here we you
know we couldn't have ground be doing
all these weird sorts of things right so
if we wanted to have like another ledge
in there and another legend here and so
on that becomes much more difficult if
we were to do it this way
and so there's kind of like a tension
there in terms of how we want to do that
compositing now we could also again say
that we're just gonna do it will allow
as many depth layers as as show up right
that's something that could totally be
plausible but I just don't know how
realistic that actually is so I don't
know I might sort of look at it this way
for now and then if when we get in there
if it turns out that there's an easy way
to make it more general maybe we will
but I'm thinking that just based on also
the way the game is sort of
conceptualized where there just isn't a
lot of complex Z level stuff happening
in in terms of like walking up little
mounds or little things and going down
I don't know this will be necessary
because remember this is only for the
ground so objects that are on here can
be all kinds of Heights in here so we
can certainly we can AB objects that
give us sort of more height interest in
here they just won't be part of like the
ground compositing stuff with the
seamless texturing and that sort of
thing right so yeah that is that is what
I'm thinking in terms of Ground
generation is we have some fixed number
of layers and then those layers called
upon now again what we need to do is we
need to figure out a good way of you
having the ground actually knowing where
where that ground actually is and isn't
right and so again what we're looking at
there is if we if we think about how
we've defined this if we have some kind
of definition for the space where the
space you know we sort of said there's
empty space here and there's empty space
here you know and there's empty space
here or even like this so it turns out
to be just like a hole right here that
you can see down into or something like
this if we have something like that or
or or even if we have something that's a
little bit different where we carved out
empty space for the whole thing and then
did a region you know in the middle that
was supposed to fill it back in right so
you know this was empty space all here
but then there was like a solid piece
here and or something like that I'm not
sure exactly what but a way of defining
it so that we used a large empty area
but then we sort of filled it in or who
knows what
I guess the trivial example here
actually I can draw it in 3d pretty
easily right is let's say we made the
empty space like we did here and we go
back to that pit oops that pit example
right so I I draw a pit entity I'm not
entity empty space it is still an entity
but you know what I'm saying so there's
a pit in here right and so that means
that if we wanted to generate the ground
for this region right that thing looks
like this right this is the actual
region that wants to get filled with
ground and we don't want this region to
be filled we want that to remain this
should be like alpha zero in here right
so that we don't have any you know so
that we can see into that pit which was
you know the intention of whatever the
level was at the time where generated
that kind of a setup and so when we
think about that it's relatively easy
for us to sort of flatten these
rectangles and say okay this rectangle
here but it's harder for us to think
about how we would do this part and I
guess what would what we would probably
do
he's just splat the actual you know
maybe we just splat the actual region in
its entirety meaning including this part
and then have these fill-in alpha0
regions where they occur right that you
know seems like perhaps the more logical
thing to do here not sure but that just
seems like what would what would make
the most sense you know so I don't know
that seems like that seems like possibly
the way we might want to do it and if we
were to do it that way it wouldn't be
too difficult really for us to figure
out what to do with the ground really
all we'd have to do to figure out what
to do with the ground is fill the whole
area with ground right and then look for
any empty space regions that are carving
out places so it really be mostly just
about carving out the ground and never
really about filling it in because we
could always just feel more of it in
that doesn't sound like a bad idea to me
that seems pretty reasonable yeah that
seems pretty reasonable so maybe that's
the way I'll look at it for now we'll
say that empty space things are gonna
carve out regions like that we'll start
with that and then the other thing that
we'll do is again we'll sort of try to
we'll try to work out how we're gonna do
this depth peeling thing so I guess the
way that will maybe do that is we'll
have this notion and we'll just sort
things into there by ground entities you
know empty space entities that happen to
have their min fall near one of these
wherever these depth layers happen to be
will get sorted into there as as being
ground or rather we'll just use I guess
the depth of needs to cut out based on
whether they overlap these depth layers
that were peeling out right does that
seem like a good idea I don't know I'm a
little bit nervous about the fact that
we're doing this a little bit ad hoc in
terms of knowing where the ground
to draw it like like that but I don't
know really how else we would do it in
this circumstance because again we we
really don't want to go full pull and
start to try and like have each of these
entities have its own sort of
constructive solid geometry happen the
FEM produces like a textured area that
we then like it seems like you'd be
spending a ton of work to not really do
much since you know that the action is
fundamentally taking place on a few
separate planes and so my question is
just like it you know is there any
reason not to just say that there's a
fixed plane like there's a fixed set of
those planes and we'll just kind of have
those we'll just acknowledge those and
build them that way does seem alright I
mean that seems pretty reasonable to me
I don't know that seems like something
that we could we could work with and so
really the only question we have then is
if we need to produce a region right if
we need to produce one of these regions
the question is what are the splats for
the region and what we could do for now
is say well we're just gonna produce
those splats purely based on some you
know we won't even store what the splats
are basically we'll produce those splats
entirely from some kind of a random
number
oops some kind of a random number that's
seated off where we are in the world
right so you know if you think about it
like let's say that we're going to
produce this region we've got like some
buffer and we're trying to fill this
area right if we imagine whatever
there's sort of like some underlying
resolution at which we want to consider
splatting right we could just say all
right for each of these areas you know
and this is maybe the five meter radius
like we were doing before for each of
these regions wherever may be wherever
the center point is we just use that as
the random seed we do the splats for
this region right and so for every
region that we want to composite we just
see all of the tiles that that would
overlap very much like our tile chunk
system works for example we just see all
of the overlaps in that area and we do
all the splats that we would need to do
that could touch that area right but we
don't actually store anything to the
splats they're just generated based on
the spatial
patient right that seems pretty safe to
me
can't think of any reason not to really
so let's let's see let's let's try it
that way and and we'll see what happens
so let's first modify let's first get it
working just with a single ground plane
so like the first step the step will try
to start today with a single ground
plane let's just try to make the ground
plane scroll infinitely in all
directions so when we walk around when
when our hero walks around there will
always be ground and it will generate
and it's always fresh ground it's new
right so and it's never you know it
doesn't repeat it's not repeating text
or it's being generated on the fly right
let's see if we can do that we've
already sort of got a little bit of bit
of that happening with a draw test
ground let's see if we can do it so that
that that will work right so the way
that I'm gonna do that is I'm gonna use
exactly all the same stuff we already
did so we've got this loaded pit map
ground buffer here right but I'm gonna
take that ground buffer and I'm gonna
make that ground buffer relatively large
right so what I want to do is I want to
say that the ground buffer is going to
be big enough so that if it were you
know if it had to scale up one right if
it had to I'm sorry I've said the scale
down one so for example if the ground
buffer if I started walking up a
stairwell and the ground had to recede
into the background there would still be
enough apron around it so that it would
it would be able to to cover that region
right and so I'm not sure exactly how we
want to we're still at unfortunate a
little bit of an unfortunate place in
terms of not having written the renderer
yet we don't know exactly all the ways
in which this should be driven but we do
have that input buffer and we know how
big that is right so we know that like
our you know our actual render buffer
there that got passed into us we know
how big that is
so we could start with that size right
so we could say you know the the screen
width or I should say the the display
width or something like that and I know
we thought we'll call it screamin so we
could say that the screen width right is
is known
because we got it from the platform
layer right when when the platform layer
passed the start game launched off
stream buffer it told us how big that
was in pixels right so we we actually do
know that right so we've got those two
things now we also know that we're gonna
have to have some amount of Z scaling
that will make these things appear
smaller as they recede into the distance
right so if we wanted to think about it
this way we could say all right let's
suppose this were a real the screen
width right so then we could say well
our lowest depth layer has to be big
enough so that the pixels right that are
in it still you know cover the screen
you know trying to just give you it give
you an idea here of what I'm talking
about
if this is the screen then if we wanted
to have ground that filled this region
all we would have to use right is we
just use a buffer that was the width of
the screen times the height of the
screen right it's like that's width by
height that would that would store all
the pixels that we're gonna display on
screen right but now if we imagine that
this screen actually recedes into the
into the distance of the book because
the hero walks up the stairs right so if
the hero walks up stairs now we have a
case where this is actually the screen
and what used to be the screen is
actually like a lower depth level right
that we're looking into and so now it
has to actually be wider and taller
right in order to actually fill the
whole screen and so what we need to know
there is what our Z scaling factor
actually is between the very top level
and the very bottom level right and we
don't actually know what that what that
actually is yet but we can at least set
ourselves up for success by saying that
we have some maximum Z scale that's
going to happen you know and maybe
that's half the size or something right
that would be all we would actually have
to do in order to that that would be the
minimum we'd actually have to do right
Birds I started the maximum size we have
to do
for one of these buffers now at first we
don't have to worry about that because
we're only allocating one of them but
we're gonna allocate more of them so so
the first one could actually be just
just that one size and so what I'm gonna
say here is just our overscan our ground
overscan I guess we'll say that that's
1.2 and all I'm doing there I'm pulling
that number totally randomly out of thin
air is we're gonna over scan a little
bit we're gonna compute a little bit
extra so that when we scroll we don't
have to update quite as often right it's
not it doesn't have to update every
frame necessarily so we might want to
just do some over-over scan to to make
it so that we we have more time there
and really where that comes in that'll
come into play later probably when we're
doing multi-threading when we have
threads in the background that are doing
stuff like ground compositing or
whatever else we don't want them to have
to hit every frame a complete update and
so like for example when the hero walks
sideways we want you know when this sort
of starts to scroll we want there to be
time where we know we have to fill in
something we want there to be some time
where we can do that right so I don't
know maybe it's maybe it's more than
that I'm not sure but let's go ahead and
say that we've got some ground over scan
of having an extra half there and so
what we end up with in terms of our base
ground level right so our ground buffer
width is going to be whatever the screen
is times that ground overscan right
that's going to be its width and we can
we can round that guy so round and same
with the height right the heights just
going to be that that same thing and so
now that we have those we could say all
right let's make an empty bitmap that's
the ground buffer width in the ground
buffer height like so and that'll just
give us that backing store that we
wanted that's sorry that's an indirect
reference there what's
not casting clear real are you happy
about that there we go so that that
gives me enough space now I don't know
we probably need to start using the
transient area but that's separator so
that gives us enough space now to
produce something that we could scroll
with and so now what we need to do is we
need to go in and actually partition
that into something that we can can use
in a more illogical way right we need to
be able to scroll that around now what
we can do first right is we can we can
introduce some notion of where the
ground is so that it moves with the
camera
that's like obviously something that we
would want to do as well so what we
could do first is let's get it moving
with the camera and we're going to want
to move the camera in such a way that
you know for those of you again who
aren't familiar with this when we move
with the camera when we move this with
the camera what's going to happen is
we've got the buffer here right and we
have the screen here that we're seeing
now as the hero moves in a particular
direction it will get to a part a point
where the buffer is is at like the end
of where it could logically be right
like we can't move any further over and
while the player is moving that way
they're going to keep moving that way
what we then need to do is recenter that
buffer so then what we do when we come
down here when we know when we've got
the situation here is we sort of
teleport back to - like here right so as
the as the player continues to move in
that direction we then teleport them
back into the space and the buffer by
basically taking all of the stuff that
was in the buffer here and copying it
backwards right so we just placed the
player's view into the buffer backwards
and we also move everything that was in
the buffer backwards right so that now
it's like that and now this region is
ready for filling and we can fill that
with new ground splats and the player
can keep walking that direction right so
we're just kind of like doing that kind
of standard sort of
allow them to scroll through it then
Phil then you know copy back Phil let's
go through a copy back Phil and like I
said this won't be multi-threaded at the
moment so we're gonna have a hiccup
every time that happens because we don't
we
composite very slowly right now so
that'll happen but that's fine that's
not a problem that's something that will
solve over time and so we'll just you
know we'll be okay with that but we got
to get the rest of the stuff working
before we can think about stuff like
hiding that computation time like or
speeding it up first of all and then
also hiding it by putting it on a
separate thread or doing something else
so what I want to do now is I want to
say all right let's let's actually move
that thing so what I need to do there is
I need to have some notion of where the
ground buffer is relative to the camera
right so I need to kind of know you know
where where is this and probably the
easiest thing to do I guess is to use
our sort of location stuff like our
camera P right it's probably easiest to
use the ground buffer as one of those so
we'll start it out coincident with the
camera then we'll let the camera move
away from it and then when it gets too
far we'll kind of snap it in right
that's what I'm thinking anyway so if I
wanted to do that the first thing that I
need to do is I need to say all right
we're drawing a bitmap that's the ground
buffer here we need to know where that
ground buffer is relative to the camera
we know that there's the screen Center X
screen Center Y right and so if I was to
draw it like this screen Center X screen
Center Y well it would also kind of have
to be offset by how large it was as well
so there is that I think we want to
basically draw off the center so that's
the competition I'm going to use so
we'll do ground X and ground Y like so
so if we put in the ground X ground Y
here then what we need to compute is
from the screen Center we need to move
back to the upper corner so that this
bitmap is still drawing out of the upper
corner so we need to subtract however
big that ground buffer actually is right
we need to subtract half of that to move
back to its appropriate location so I'm
just gonna do that here again pretty
straightforward nothing the same same
math you've seen me do on here a billion
times so that's gonna draw it at the
center I believe of the screen and
that's exactly what it did so that's
good and so now what I want to do is I
want to displace it by however much the
camera has moved right so I'm gonna make
this in I think I'm gonna make this into
a V - why not just so it could be a
little easier on me and there we go
and so if I go ahead and make this
ground now displaced by that difference
you'll remember that we have a very easy
way to find that out it's it's in here
somewhere
let's find it again
subtract that's it so if I want to take
two of these guys and subtract them I
want to see basically how far is the
ground buffer from the camera right so
I've got that game state that camera P
and I've got that ground buffer P I want
to see how far away those are and that
returns me back I believe a v3 right and
so that's that Delta like so now I'm
gonna ignore the the Z of it but later
on I think we'll probably want to use
that because we're gonna use that for
doing like the ground scaling and other
stuff like that so we'll probably
actually use that later on just just not
right now so I'm going to go ahead and
add that Delta in and oops I got
actually passed the game world there
probably huh world position and these
want to be addresses so I've got them so
now if I run it we should see it move
and it is moving and so oh well you know
it's moving but it's moving in pixels
not meters this is in meters and this is
in pixels this is actually a render
operation so we need to actually take
and and do our meters to pixels here so
that we can do our rendering properly
and I feel like that was already it
that's also going the wrong direction in
Y which is because again are we kind of
needs something that does our render
transform for us that's what the render
would normally be doing and we haven't
written it yet and it's kind of annoying
to constantly have to do this ourselves
right but you know it's one of those
things that do we take the time to go do
that or we just keep fussing with this
stuff and it feels to me like we want to
just keep fussing with this stuff for
the most part just because you know
you've got to kind of pick and choose
when you do each individual battles so
like you know that Delta there we want
it to be you know we want it to be in
our pixel coordinate system and it's
coming out in our world core system
where Y goes up which is always going to
be wrong so anyway yeah that's that's
what we would have expected so now it's
locked with the world correctly we
probably
want to start by saying that at the
outset it's where the camera is right
that seems like a pretty sane thing to
do so our game state ground buffer P you
know should start out being wherever the
games take camera P is like that and
then when we walk it should you know be
there right and so what we need to do
now is we need to say whenever our
ground buffer would be getting to the
point where it would run out of pixel
coverage right we want to snap it
towards the cameras direction right so
we need to do like that copy and we need
to yeah we basically need to do the copy
we need to change the location of it so
what I'd like to do for that first of
all what I'd really like to do is not be
constrained anymore
by these trees so I think what I might
do is temporarily turn off this
generation stuff entirely so so let's go
ahead and do that let's go ahead and get
rid of those those let's get rid of that
Chris do put the walls back in don't
forget yeah but while we're doing this
you know so there we have it right now I
can just walk around randomly and like I
said the problem is that when we get to
the end of the ground
we can't oh you know what we need more
empty space though too don't we because
we wouldn't have much empty space but
this might be enough for me to do my
testing on it anyway although I could
make that empty space just really large
as well let's take a look where is the
empty space adder let's see the empty
space adder add standard room is right
there uh well you know what else I could
do this is what I'll do I'll just say
that we'll go back to the old way of
fate you know forcing it not to create a
Z door right so when it does this random
choice thing
I'm gonna I'm gonna go ahead and say no
you know it's only allowed to generate
flat stuff and that'll let me do my
walking that I wanted to do so there we
go
now we're good everyone's happy
everyone's everyone's smiling good to go
and similarly I think we can turn off
the thing that like we had a thing that
only generates like one room or
something like that right we stopped
doing our actual room generation in some
way we can we can probably put that back
in now right so that we have more rooms
there's more stuff in them alright so
now we've got you know those rooms back
you can walk through them it's all good
and so now let's just try to make it
fill with ground you know what I'm
saying so when we walk up here right and
you know and we walk into this room we
want it there to be grounded here as
well we want that to just be constantly
generating itself right so how do we do
that well first thing we probably want
to do is when we actually generate stuff
here we want to generate we want to
generate the screen in some kind of an
intelligent way so let's think about how
we want to do this I guess it's kind of
a rote issue we don't really need to
tile it this is pretty straightforward I
think so I think if we do our draw test
ground thing here right really all we
need to do is say when you do draw test
ground make sure you fill the whole
buffer right so in draw test ground when
this is doing its thing what we want to
do is instead of doing this radius thing
here what we want to do is generate
randomness that goes out to the edges
you know of the actual buffer right we
want something that's going to be big
enough that way although again if we're
going to regenerate the seed properly we
need to do that on tile boundary so
here's I'll just draw that out will
actually say what I was what I was
thinking there so what I was trying to
say is this is gets back to thing I was
talking about before so what will happen
is we're gonna have a buffer and the
buffer is going to be filled with
round right we are going to move like I
showed before in here and when the
player moves off let's say they move off
this side of the screen we're going to
have a problem where now we copy this
part of the buffer we copy it into here
and now we need to fill in this part of
this buffer right now normally if we
just had a repeating tile texture that
repeated everywhere all we would have to
do is just call and say refill this
region and it would just do it it would
be easy right but that's not what we
have we're randomly generating what goes
in there and it may be fairly
complicated like there may be stuff like
like things that run through here and we
want to generate stuff on them and stuff
so really what we need to do is we need
to consider this in places where we can
guarantee that we generate the same
things every time for that region and in
order to do that like I said with the
splats if we wanted to make the splats
be procedural based on just where you
were in the world we need that to be
some fixed thing that doesn't that isn't
randomly getting moved around by how
this thing moves and so I think the only
way to do that really honestly is to
break it into chunks so we need to sort
of do chunks where we can say okay if
we're filling anything with this chunk
we kind of use you know we use some
known value to produce the splats in
that chunk right so I think draw test
ground is gonna be like draw ground
chunk or something like this right it's
gonna take a loaded bitmap buffer right
which is what it's going to draw into
but then it's got to take a little bit
more information so it knows what it's
supposed to actually do and I guess when
I say draw a ground chunk
so when I say draw a ground chunk
there's there's a little bit more to it
than that there's like we're drawing we
have to be yeah let's put it this way we
have to know what the the location is of
this chunk I guess so we'll actually use
whatever its world location actually is
let's say to do that there's a lot of
stuff that's complicated here I'm kind
of explain them in a good order if that
makes sense so this is the the chunk P
right so when we draw a ground chunk
we're gonna want to know whatever that
chunk P was and we're gonna use that for
something and that chunk P is arbitrary
it doesn't really matter that it's where
it is in the world it just matters that
for any given location that we're trying
to redraw we always use the same initial
position for it input position so that
the random stuff comes out the same
right so we need to know that we have
that that buffer that's what we're
actually drawing into and then we also
want to we want to be able to say okay
when we're drawing into this thing we
need some bounding region right because
we don't want to draw we don't want to
recompose it stuff that's in the bitmap
that we already had so we need to have
some kind of a like a clipping region as
well that we use now there's a trick we
can use for that so I'll guess I'll
ignore that temporarily for now and I'll
show you a trick we can use for that so
we don't have to do it but anyway when
we come in here our chunk P let's figure
out some way to do we'll use this chunk
P to generate our random seed and
that'll just be like you know like the
chunk X the chunk Y and the chunk Z
we'll just grab those out and just
full-on
do complete nonsense here I don't even
pretend this is reasonable when I'm
typing in but there you go yeah not so
let's do something even more ridiculous
so there you go I've typed in some
absolutely ludicrous things and really
I'm just trying to take these three
numbers and produce a random seed out of
them and now when we
get to random number generation you know
we might want to say look into Wang
hashing here or some other spatial seed
generation thing we might want to try
and do something better for generating
random numbers off of positions but for
right now that'll be fine so once we
have that what we want to do is we want
to generate chunks that we know will
sort of fill in this region for us and
we'll do a better job of that later when
we get to world generation for reals but
for right now what we want to do is put
those stamps down so that they kind of
nicely cover that space so what we want
to do is say instead of radius being
system fixed value here which isn't
particularly useful we probably want to
get rid of this notion of meters to
pixels here and say let's actually use
the size of the whole bitmap right let's
actually use that as our offset so what
we want to do for there is we'd want to
say half the height we could actually
use a random unilateral here and move it
that way so let's just use a random
unilateral right from a series in both
of these and we'll use whatever that
input width and height is right so in
fact I'll pull these out something like
that so that we can have them at the
ready maybe I'll even just call this
width and height okay so let's do this
this is the width times random
unilateral this is the height times the
random unilateral and that produces what
we wanted we can then actually we don't
need Center at all Center doesn't have
to happen radius doesn't have to happen
at all
offset none of this stuff has to happen
so really I think the only thing that's
really yeah really nothing has to happen
it's it's just it's just the offset
minus the bitmap Senate right yep we're
almost at the QA
we'll go ahead and wrap this up like I
said I don't know if we're gonna be able
do Q&amp;A today because we haven't
regenerated Oh off keys and Lord knows
what else alright so if I do that we
want to we're basically doing the same
thing here we didn't really compress
this code very much at all it's quite
sort of still all kind of kind of count
janky in here but that's okay again you
know everything in its time so if I go
ahead and get this going here
let's see v2i width and height that's
not necessary anymore so we can do that
draw a test ground okay that's draw a
ground chunk right there we go and we
can pass in for now we'll pass in the
ground buffer P but that's not actually
what we want to pass in that'll be
different later on but let's just see if
this properly fills things out as it
should yeah so there we go so now you
can see that that buffer is is is
getting you know the whole buffer is
getting filled in unfortunately we
haven't done enough slotting to actually
cover it at any reasonable amount of
detail though so we probably would want
to increase those hundreds to something
higher but you know that's that's a
separate issue so again how to do
coverage and stuff there is sort of a
separate thing and that will think about
later but so there's now we've at least
got some ground that spans the first
region and mostly all we'll have to do
is figure out how to do again that the
update as we move and then we'll sort of
have our progressive ground working all
right so let's go ahead and do a little
try to do a little Q&amp;A I think we might
as well try but unfortunately I don't
actually know yeah I don't actually know
how well this will work but let's go to
let's at least do a couple minutes Q&amp;A
and see how it works
please prefix your questions with Q :
although I don't know that'll actually
help but I can at least try to scan for
those manually even though the twitch
thing is broken in terms of showing us
what's actually there
let's see
when we fill the entire game window
instead of having all that black space
actually that's intentional so I guess
one thing that might be a problem is
people who are new to the stream might
not realize that we're in development
stuff like if you wanted to see it fill
the whole screen you know you could
already do that that's not really a big
deal but in development what you want to
do is you don't want to ever pretty much
look at your your actual game output as
a in full-screen the reason for that is
you may have drawing bugs that happen
off off the edges of things and stuff
like that and so usually what I do is I
always have stuff that looks essentially
like this when I'm working and will
probably go even further than what we
are doing right now and actually show
you know the way that our debug will
work in the future will be something
where this is actually centered but not
filling the whole screen so basically
this this thing here will be centered in
the thing in the middle and we'll draw a
little bit outside of it as well and
we'll verify that everything is drawing
properly and we'll have like a safe
region marker that shows us so we can
see what's happening outside the game
area because what you know showing just
the game area that's a view for players
that's not a view for developers
developers generally shouldn't be
looking at a view that just shows what
the player will see they should be
seeing more than that and they should be
looking for problems and so typically
what we'll end up with is more stuff out
here and maybe this will be centered but
what we won't do is draw fullscreen in
general that's only a thing that will
test periodically to make sure that it
works properly because that's what the
players will do and when we're in sort
of final testing we'll we'll maybe do a
lot more playing with it in that mode
but that's not the general mode we want
to be in for developing because it
doesn't show us it won't be showing us
as much as we need to see hopefully that
makes some sense
not seeing a lot of questions here are
some of these issues with dealing with
display on multiple levels stemming from
the lack of a Z coordinate for the
camera to just do a lerp on no not
really because we have a Z coordinate
for the camera we actually know what
that is most of the problem with the
thinking through Z issues is largely
just because we don't have actual 3d
geometry right so if we were to build
the whole game in 3d then this wouldn't
be an issue but as it needs to be kind
of there's some things a lot of things
get easier when you do a 2-d game mostly
the asset creation right like your
artists will have a much easier time in
2d and 3d you know a single artist can
do a whole 2-d game by themselves and it
can look great
3d not so much like you're not gonna
have one artist do call a duty right
that's not on the table
and so you get some benefits when you go
to 2d because your art quality for the
number of artists you have your art
quality goes up dramatically and that's
a good thing but some of your
programming complexity well a lot of
your current flexi also goes down
because you don't to deal with all the
asset pipeline stuff which is a huge
headache for 3d and pre-processing and
all your shader stuff all that stuff
that's a lot you know there's there's a
whole bunch of programs nothing it's
simpler but there are some probably
things get more complicated if you want
to do interesting things with it now we
could have cut out all this and just
said there's only one Z level right and
then you wouldn't have to do any of the
things that I've been talked about also
you could have said you don't move
smoothly up stairwells and that would be
fine as well so basically like I would
say that if you wanted to not try to
tackle hard programming problems we
could have done that too and that's not
a bad thing it's just that this is a
programming stream I try to do things
that are more complicated than than the
simplest right I try not to just do
whatever be easiest for us to do because
I'm not that really that interested in
teaching how to people how to do stuff
that's simple I feel like if you want to
do something that's simple you could
just go grab game maker or something
right and so I want to show you how to
do is push a lot of boundaries and do a
lot of interesting things with the code
and
so that's what we're doing like
procedurally-generated ground is a good
example of something that you may not be
able to do if you just grab an
off-the-shelf tool and so we want to do
stuff like that because if all I ever
show you how to do is just rebuild
exactly what's in some off-the-shelf
tools that's a good thing for some set
of programmers but also doesn't
encourage some of the things that I
would like to encourage which is pushing
beyond what you would just be able to do
with a simple basic tool that you could
just buy right if no one's asking
related questions could you ballpark a
time frame when adding a font and text
rendering system will become useful or
necessary I would say it's gonna be
right here it's actually already on the
schedule I think it's right there and
the answer is is not that long actually
right we've got some hard things to work
through here none of which I think will
really require font for display but then
we're gonna get into stuff like asset
streaming which you really want to have
some debug vis stuff for and you really
want fonts to be in there at the time
for debug if there's a debug flaw so you
don't have to do final fonts but just
debug files
and for folks that are asking stuff like
any advice I'm publishing my first game
and stuff like that that's really stuff
we talk about more in the pre stream so
this is more time for the programming
questions if you want to come back about
15 minutes before a scheduled start time
and ask those questions we could totally
cover them although to be honest with
you I don't know very much about game
publishing I'm not a publisher I'm a
programmer so you'd probably have to ask
a different person
all right it doesn't look like we really
have any questions look I don't see many
programming questions on here aster
what's the most some people are asking
this is a very standard question we get
a lot which is what's the most efficient
way to learn C++ or what's a good
tutorial for learning OpenGL with Super
Plus and so on with C and so on I don't
really know I mean one of the reasons
I'm doing this series is because I don't
know the best way to teach where people
should go to learn things there aren't a
lot of good learning materials out there
there's a lot of bad learning materials
but finding good ones is pretty tough
and so I don't really know what I would
recommend there are some reasonable like
the arc synthesis tutorials for the
OpenGL question
are bad I don't know where they are
though does anyone actually link to the
arc synthesis toriel's in here here we
go here we know oh no don't tell me
they're gone are they actually gone that
would be awful if they were gone the arc
synthesis tutorials if you can find them
would actually be a good place to go but
and I hope they're not gone
that would be real bad maybe I'm
spelling it wrong or something no I
don't know all right well if Yorkton
this tutorials are gone I don't even
know what to point you to for good
OpenGL tutorial we'll be doing some
graphics AP on the stream maybe if we're
lucky
Vulcan will be ready and we can do that
so we'll be doing one later on but right
now the arc synthesis tutorials were
pretty good if I remember correctly but
you know
they look like they're disappeared or
something
you mentioned offloading ground drawing
to a separate thread to prevent hitches
is it possible to offload the drawing
work over multiple frames and would
there be any benefits over either method
yeah my intention would be to offload it
to a separate fred's so that it would
happen over multiple frames and the
reason for that is because usually
there's just a lot of CPU power sitting
around that you know especially for a
2-d game where if once we start taking
advantage of the GPU for rendering we're
gonna have probably cores sitting around
not doing anything on the CPU and so
what I'd like to do is have those
running completely asynchronously from
the main thread generating stuff that we
might want it to generate and so I think
we'll probably have like a CPU that's
doing a lot of background loading and
decompression or who knows what and
we'll probably also have a CPU thread
that's doing a bunch of generation along
the same lines and I don't think those
will need to be coupled at all to the
main thread they'll they'll just you
know communicate by queues or something
and I think that's probably the way that
we'll want will end up doing it I can't
promise that that will be true but I
think so
how much of a memory footprint is your
game using already certainly it won't be
large but I'm more meaning how many
different containers are there how many
different containers can you be more
specific as to what you mean by
container I guess and then I can try to
answer that let's see procedural
generation of 2d graphics is there some
mainstream math for that well it's not
only math II per se something there are
some math that elements to it such as
good noise patterns and stuff like that
but it's sort of more of a black art
kind of thing like procedurally
generating 2d graphics is you know one
of those things that you just kind of
got to learn to work with and like I
said we'll be doing some of it on the
stream like will be doing ground
generation will be doing much better
ground generation than we're doing right
now for example and so that'll be one
place we'll be kind of exploring that a
little bit
what is my programming experience as
before handmade hero
oh it's well I'm a game tech guy I've
been doing game technology for I don't
know 20 years now or something like that
so I worked at rad game tools which is a
company that makes like game libraries
that are used in lots of thousands of
games really and I did a 3d animation
system and a video codec while I was
there and then I've done work on actual
games before like just this last this
most recent game I worked on was the
witness which isn't quite out yet it's a
game you should definitely check out if
you hadn't yet it's a it's John Blair's
new game and I I did a bunch of work on
the collision detection and the editor
for that so that's mostly what I what
I've worked on in the past I've worked
on other things too but you know those
are the notable things sorry for
confusing with terminology javis
distribution of classes how many
different classes are you having to use
already well I mean sort of I guess the
answer is we don't use any classes in
that sense we have some systems so for
example we have a sim region which is
sort of a collection of things that's
used to do simulation of the of a game
area we have a world rep representation
right which is sort of divides the world
into chunks and allows us to quickly
access those trunks but we don't we
don't use classes so classes are sort of
a mental thing right really they're a
way of breaking things down in an
object-oriented we don't really do that
we sort of work with things in in more
of a systemic sense where stuff is kind
of grouped together and so we have
structs that define data layouts but
really our systems are a little more
broader and they're not really thought
of in the same class way but you can
still think of them kind of
similarly like what you might think of
breaking down as a class you would think
of us breaking down as a system in our
in our approach
thank you is amaro 37 by the way for
posting the opengl tutorial there
hopefully that's that's a good one I
don't know if it is or not is that the
arc synthesis ones I'm not sure
is there a simple way to explain
pointers and references in C++ if so can
you briefly explain when you would use
either if that's to clump K just don't
worry about answering this that is is
not complicated in fact it's not there
is no difference there a syntactic thing
so try to think of the easiest way to
show this here but basically if I have
something like int X and then I have
something like int star X right or y
equals x I should say maybe I'll say
pointer X hmm
then what this is doing is it saying
alright I would like the compiler to
know that I am trying to refer to the
memory the first like I want a number
that's the first byte of memory occupied
by X right because X is a 32-bit integer
it occupies 4 bytes in memory
I want a pointer to it so I've taken the
address of it and I can store that here
now the compiler may never actually do
that operation because it only needs to
do that operation if it's going to do
something else with it later for example
if the only thing I ever did with this
right is dereference the pointer and set
it equal to 3 then the compiler probably
will never actually take the address of
X and never actually produce a register
with the address in it it'll probably
just know where X is on the stack and
directly write 3 into it right now on
the other hand if I actually go to do
something where that actually needs to
be done in terms of taking the address
it actually will for example if I was to
do something like have a mem copy
routine or something like some kind of
like copy memory routine that's going to
take that pointer to X now it will
actually do the work of to figuring out
where it is putting that in a register
and letting copy memory work on it or
something that that might happen right
now if I wanted to have a reference as
well
right where I do something like this all
that's doing is this a different
Cley cheer for pointer it's basically a
Naaman clay Chur for a pointer or what a
pointer was representing that does not
need to be dereferenced in order to use
it so it's just saying hey look I want
you to essentially treat this
essentially like a pointer right but now
I'm going to call it a reference and
what's gonna happen is everywhere I use
it pretend that I was just dereferencing
the pointer that you had so it's sort of
just another name for X right that's all
it is it's another name for X at that
point right
but implementation wise they're still
gonna have to do exactly the same things
that the pointer was doing if it needs
to figure out what the address is to
point it to send it to something like if
I'm gonna call something like let's say
let's say this was giant for some reason
I'm traveling but this is like struck
giant right okay
so there's no way that that's ever gonna
be passed in registers right but if I
wanted to do something where I was
actually gonna modify that thing so I
have a giant one right and now I've got
a pointer to it like so and I've got a
reference to it or whatever right and
now I want to call some function where
I'm actually gonna operate on on this
thing right well if I was gonna do it by
pointer so I have food giant star
whatever like this if I was gonna
operate on it by pointer then we all
know what would happen here when I call
foo with my giant whatever it is with my
pointer to giant it's just gonna pass
the address and then this function is
going to work off the address of that
object to actually modify it right so
you know if I wanted to hear do
something like this so as I shouldn't
call this the same thing
there we go if I wanted to operate off
it like that
basically what it'd be doing is it would
be taking that address it would be using
this layout to know where it should go
to operate on the 30th integer that's at
that address right and it would do
whatever the operation is I told it to
do now equivalently if I was to make
another one of these
that took a reference to that thing and
modified it right now this may look a
little different because I'm using the
dot operator and this is actually the
bar it's you know in some sense it's
actually a giant not a pointer giant
syntactically in terms of what the
compiler is gonna generate if the
compiler has any sense at all it will
generate exactly the same code for these
two foods right through one in foo two
will generate exactly the same code and
exactly the same way hopefully so really
will still end up just being a pointer
when the compiler actually uses it so
it's really just about how you
syntactically wanted to treat that thing
it doesn't do anything right it doesn't
actually have any different effect than
a pointer effectively would in most
cases in terms of the compilers going to
do right so hopefully that helps a
little bit I mean in fact really you
could think of it as unless you're
trying to use some c++ features that
need you to not use the dereference
thing like if you had some crazy c++
features you were caring about you might
need to use references but otherwise you
never need to use them references
pointers just do the same thing you
would never actually use reference it's
just a syntactic convenience for you if
you prefer it
all right
all right I think that's about it for
questions today because I can't actually
read the questions very well since the
twitch thing is down
I'll get that working tonight so that
tomorrow we'll be in good shape but I
think I'm going to call it for today
because it's really hard to read the
twitch dream without my little filter
that normally runs on it so yeah all
right so I think that's it for now
tomorrow I think
let's I'm liking where we're going with
the ground thing so tomorrow we'll do
some more work on that and we'll get it
to the point where we're actually
generating a continuous ground and then
we'll maybe the day after that we'll
start working on hole cutting in that
and then after that we can actually do
multiple layers so maybe you know by the
end of the week we'll actually have some
relatively solid ground stuff drawing in
there and that would be pretty fun cuz
that's another pretty major to do that
would be off our list so thank you
everyone for joining me for another
episode of handmade Hira it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
with a source code you can pre-order the
game at handmade hero org using the
little pre-order button and it comes
with a source code you'll get a link in
your email that you can use to download
the source code anytime you want and i
think if i refresh the page yes and i
added a thing down here to resend if
you've lost your order email you can use
this little habit we sent button to have
it resent to you so that's pretty handy
I found out that I could I could do that
with send owl so I did that so that's
good thing to know if you want support
the video series we also have a patreon
page you could subscribe to so he's very
much appreciated we also have a news and
forum site that has stuff on it like a
place to ask questions ports to Linux
and Mac if you're interested in
following along on another platform and
episode guide for catching up on old
episodes there's also a tweet bot I
highly recommend subscribing the tweet
bot if you would like to know the
schedule it will tell you what the
schedule is every day as well as
tweeting out on the weekends what the
schedule will be for the week so please
check those things out when you get a
chance and I hope see you back here
tomorrow it'll be 5 p.m. Pacific
Daylight Time again tomorrow hope to see
you here
have a fabulous Tuesday though either
way take it easy everyone