hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream we are I think pretty
much done with all of our memory stuff
that we were doing i was showing how to
change over from fixed memory
allocations to dynamic memory
allocations in case people wanted the
ability to use all the same sort of
style of memory use that we've been
doing on handmade hero but wanted to
allow their programs to grow to fill
arbitrary amounts of memory so something
that's like for example if you're using
if you're writing tools or something
like that where you don't want to say
ahead of time how much memory something
can take you just want to be able to use
all the memory of the machine or all the
virtual memory or anything else like
that how you write something in that
style without how you write some of that
capabilities while still writing exactly
the same style so I showed how to do
some of that stuff we do have one bug
left however which was that when I
merged the win32 and arena memory block
headers something I did caused a problem
with the loop live code editing save
restore feature and we need to kind of
go figure out what's going on there
because that is the only thing that I
know of that we are not currently doing
so I'm going to go ahead and and dive in
there because that is I think a good
to-do item for today is to kind of
finish that stuff off now if I take a
look at where we are here we're on day 2
47 so you want to be day 246 if you're
trying to follow along with the source
code and I will go ahead and let's load
it up here get us back to where we were
so I'm going to load in and build and
then I'm going to run so now if we take
a look at what's going on here this is
running through the arena system at the
moment and it's doing dynamic allocation
so the arenas grow as necessary
and everything seems to work fine and
our memory footprint stays pretty stable
so we're not like leaking anything or
anything like that it looks relatively
stable it doesn't you know grow without
bound or anything like that so that's a
nice thing but what ends up happening is
when we go to actually do stuff with the
loop live coding if I hit the L key you
can see that we end up our block chain
ends up being corrupted as far as I can
tell when we look at these source blocks
which are supposed to be strung together
what we see is that they're not there
they're not coherent right the next
pointers are not when we loop through
them it's not creating a nice list we
end up jumping kind of often to the
middle of nowhere and so what I wanted
to do is just take a quick look and make
sure that there wasn't anything stupid
going on and then we gotta gotta we
gotta sit down and do a little bit more
work there to make sure that
everything's fine now if we take a look
at what's actually happening with our
memory blocks here we can see that what
we've got is the platform memory block
is actually a thing which keeps the
information necessary for the arena
itself which includes a previous pointer
which has nothing to do with the win32 s
previous Jane all that is is just the
thing for doing temporary memory we
winding on the arenas so when we do like
our begin temporary memory n temporary
memory blocks arena previous is just
used to walk back through dynamically
grown blocks to free the ones that are
no longer in use and if we take a look
over here 132 memory block we have the
real pre even next pointers and those
should never be touched by the arena in
fact the only way that the arena can
really ever touch those is if it was
going to corrupt them in some way by
doing an accidental over right so for
example if we have the platform memory
block here and we accidentally wrote
past it well then it could write into
here but in general we only return this
platform memory block to the arena it
never sees the fact that that was inside
a win32 memory block so technically
speaking unless we've got an over
bug rather relatively severe override
bug there we're not in danger of having
the arena erroneously say set the
previous pointer instead of the arena
previous pointer or some other type 0
like that because it never gets access
to these so we know that it's code is
not accessing these by name it could
only be over writing them by accident or
something like that but what we do know
is somebody at some point is doing
something wrong with these creating a
erroneous leaving the the list in an
erroneous setup so what I want to do is
just take a look and see if I can find
it you know what else I want to do is I
want my water where is my water
I'm glad I got that that was not going
to go well if I had no water this entire
time that would just be bad so let's
take a look here so here is our
allocation call and when we do our
allocation right this is the thing that
it does the checking to see if anyone
has set something up to allow underflow
or overflow and those sorts of things
and if so it goes the head and you know
makes everything aligned to the memory
pages in win32 so that you get you know
instant crashes on under flows or
overflows and and that's all well and
good and we tested that out and that
seemed to work pretty well now one thing
that I am sort of interested in at this
point actually now that I think about it
is we don't really know maybe we got the
math wrong here maybe we did something
stupid when we're setting up these
memory blocks in the case where we don't
do any overflow checking because when we
do overflow checking or or underflow
checking basically bounds checking we
allocate a separate page for the memory
and when we don't when we are not doing
overflow checking then we don't do that
and so what happens when we do this is
if we're going to have the underflow an
overflow checking turned off we take the
total size as being however much memory
we're supposed to be allocating and then
we take one of these win32 memory block
structures which we know we're going to
need as sort of like an appendage to it
and we stick them together then we say
that the offset that you're going to put
the actual memory at is going to be
after the win32 memory block right
okay so if we're going to do that then
in theory that seems reasonable because
the you know that makes sense we just
have a memory block first and then after
the memory block we have whatever the
memories we actually need when we do an
allocation here here is the block we do
the Alec we Alice for the total size and
the total size all makes pretty good
sense right you can kind of see here
that we do do exactly what we said we
were going to do we we move up kind of
passed a Jimmy we move past that win32
memory block oh by the way since both
these things don't work together they
should probably be nails we take a look
and we move past that win32 memory block
so now we've got both the wintry to
memory block and the base pointer for it
and then we take a look and see if we
need to any protecting in this case we
wouldn't be doing any protecting so then
we're just taking a look at linking
things up we grab the sentinel here and
the sentinel again never changes which
one the sentinel is so we don't have to
do any kind of locking around the
sentinel so we know which one the
sentinel is we get that we say that the
blocks next point is going to the
sentinel we remember the size which is
not again the size of the whole thing
it's only the size of the actual usable
portion of the at the moment we might
want to name that something else but you
know that's that's what that is and then
we have the flags field which is just
remembering what the flags are that we
actually asked for when we allocated
this thing and those are just things
like that the app asks for like don't
save and restore this piece of memory or
something like that right the looping
flags again are just for doing things
like remembering whether things were
allocated during looping or not that
sort of thing and then we have to go
into our ticket lock and the reason we
have to go into the ticket lock is
because if we're not inside the ticket
lock then there's no way for us to
ensure that no one else is being added
at the same time we're trying to add so
in order to maintain integrity of the
linked list we have to go into the
ticket lock once we're in the ticket
lock inside that block we can go ahead
and set the previous pointer to whoever
the Sentinels previous was inserting us
in the proper place to make sure that
our next pointer should point to the
Sentinel and then link ourselves up then
we're outside again we could exit the
mutex it's all good and we can just
return the actual platform block part to
the game now when we go to deallocate
you can see we're just doing the exactly
the same thing here we're casting back
to a block and then we just decide
either we leave the thing unfree in the
case where it's supposed to be free
during looping and we don't want to
touch it or we go ahead and free the
memory block now we know that only this
case is really the one we care about as
far as I know we don't have to worry
about free during looping yet because
we're getting this corruption before we
ever act on this flag as far as I know
so if we go to win 32 free memory block
we can take a look at what's going on
with that guy let's see here where is
that with due to free memory block there
you are and you can see what that does
is it takes the memory block we're
trying to free it enters the mutex first
right because again it's going to have
to unlink itself as soon as it on links
itself then it considers itself done and
it goes ahead and releases the memory
back to the system including the the
block header itself but that should be
fine because again we've already made
sure that the person who was to the
behind us is now pointing over us to the
next person and a person who was in
front of us isn't who is that next
person is now pointing back over us to
the to the previous person nobody's
pointing at us anymore so in theory that
should maintain a linked list that does
not have errors in it but that's not
what we're seeing so the question is
just what's going on here like why are
we seeing this problem happen and I
don't know so what I'd like to do is is
step in a little bit and just see maybe
let's step into win32 free memory block
and see I just want to take a quick look
to see what's happening when we do one
of these uh you know is I'm basic trying
to get a sense here is this a problem
that happens all the time or a problem
that only happens once in a while on
certain memory block
like how you know rare of a bug am I
looking for so I just I'm just trying to
get a spot check on that so when I step
in here I can take a look at this block
this is the block I enter the mutex I'm
ready to unlink it you can see that I've
got a block here that's got you know I
don't know reasonable size it's a
megabyte large that seems reasonable of
course only 8 oq only eight bytes it was
used not very efficient there so i guess
it was just a little bit of extra
overwrite of something not sure what's
going on there but it's fine so that's
something we could take a look at later
so that's all well and good and if we
take a look at the previous pointer it
both the previous pointer and the next
pointer it i just want to see like what
looks reasonable here it would help me
if I knew who the Sentinel was so I'm
going to go ahead and take a look global
waived oops Louisville win through to
state so you can see the memory sensible
here I want to just get a little bit of
a feel for where that is so here's the
address of the memory Sentinel and you
can see that that that's the address
right there and so that is this guy and
we can kind of identify them because
since it's a static you can see that
it's got the location in the executable
so we kind of know that that's the right
guy so you can see that the next pointer
is pointing to the Sentinel so this is
the last memory block and I just want to
see what happens I should probably leave
this out now I think about it because I
want to see what happens when we free it
I want to make sure that the list
remains in reasonable state what I
should be able to do since this is a
circular list I should be able to walk
all the way down until I get back at
some point right to the there it is to
the Sentinel so I can verify that my
list is in fact in reasonable shape
alright so here we're going to unlink
right we have now unlinked
our memory block so now our blocks next
and previous pointers are the people
before and after them are no longer
pointing to this block and in theory
that it's okay we should still be able
to have it so that the memory Sentinel
the memory sentinels if we've traveled
from it we should now be able to do the
exact same circular list and just see
that it's got one less thing in it right
but we but we still get back there so we
know that left our list in a reasonable
state so all of that looks pretty good
right there isn't anything particularly
unusual going on there as far as I can
tell and so what I want to do is I want
to rather than sit here trying to go
through this and debug it all the time I
pretty much know what's going on right
when I hit this this loop live code
editing I know that I'm coming in here
and I know exactly what I'm doing I'm
starting at the memory Sentinel and I'm
going through looking at these source
blocks until I get back to the Sentinel
that same process that I did in the
debugger where I just kept picking on
the next thing that's all I'm doing here
and then I know that when I look at
these sizes eventually I get to some
complete garbage data here right I'm
getting to just just completely nuts
data so what I want to do is say well
maybe if I if I now know right that I
have something and like I verified that
I'm not just being completely stupid
like it wasn't like every time I
unlinked one of these things I messed it
up right so it's a little more subtle
than that what I want to do is say well
ok let's just make something that's
called like you know verify memory and
30 to verify memory integrity or
something like this every list integrity
something like that what I can do is
just say all right what if I just source
to copy this code exactly as it is and
retain the important part of it right so
as I come through here basically every
piece of information or rather every
block that I go through if I was to just
say hey it's it's this death block
sighs bit that I care about here so
let's just go ahead and take that death
what the desk block size was going to be
put in an assertion that is the exact
same assertion that we had before so
that the block size was okay and we'll
make that be the the list integrity
verification thing right so now what I
should be able to do is say hey right
before we call that I should be able to
call win32 verify memoryless integrity
and we should crash while we're not
crashing we should assert their rather
than in the main loop and now we know we
have a function we can call at any time
that will fail if the list is in this
state so now what I can do is I can go
ahead and make sure that that checking
will occur whenever I I can make that
check incur whenever I want now there's
one thing that I probably should do here
and I don't know why we weren't doing
this and that is that this list kind of
needs to be checked it kind of needs to
be blocked out so that while we are
operating on it it probably shouldn't
change right so we should probably leave
our memory mutex around here where we
you know make sure that we don't have
anyone mucking with the list while we're
trying to edit it because it's entirely
possible that that could happen even
though it's probably very unlikely so
let's make sure we still get the problem
even in that case which I assume we will
yeah because it was happening so we're
so routinely that I knew that was the
case but now we know we can call this
anywhere we want so what I'm going to do
is I'm just going to go ahead and and
try some random stuff to try and provoke
the error in a place that would be more
conducive to catching it so first let's
just make sure that this error happens
at some point without us having to push
the L key so for example every time
through our main loop that's just very
by that memory right so here we go and
we trigger like right away so now we
know like when we come into this list
we've got a problem with our memory
integrity right and you can see it
doesn't happen the first time through
but it happens the second time through
right so it happens pretty quickly there
doesn't have to be much happening before
we get a memory integrity violation so
now let's say alright now that we know
that this memory this list is having a
problem pretty early on let's try
putting something into the allocation
and de-allocation routines where every
time we do the verification we'll just
check it every will just check it
whenever we do in operation right so any
time we call win32 deallocate memory or
win through to allocate memory we'll
just call it as a matter of course and
see if we can catch the bug that way
right so now here we go as we run and
you can see oops it mean to do that
let's try that one more time there we go
there we go and you can see we are
getting it here and we're getting it on
and allocate so now that I know that
we're getting it on and allocate I'm
going to do one more thing and what I'm
going to do here because now and again
this is all very standard debugging
stuff but you know I like to kind of
explain it out loud as I'm doing it so
that people who don't know some of these
techniques can be familiar with them can
become familiar with them you can see
right here when we call win through to
allocate memory well I come into this
routine I know that something in here
when I get to the end I get win32 verify
memoryless integrity I get a problem the
thing is I don't know if it was actually
one of these things that caused it or
some other thing that caused it right
because maybe it was already corrupted
when I came into this function so what
I'm gonna do now that I have a sort of
point of failure more localized I'm
going to go and put one
so now I know if the top one doesn't
fail but the bottom one does it's
something inside here that's the problem
right so let's give that a go and we'll
see which one it is I come in here and
now I'm seeing it's the top one right so
I know that something outside of this
the system it's not a case of like there
was a bug in this code it's a case of
between the last time somebody allocated
memory and this time somebody borked our
list right so somebody's actually doing
something problematic there that we
don't know that that we aren't aware of
right so well you know the other thing I
can do is let's see where in the code we
were inside allocate memory we're in
push size load bitmap so this is in the
main line code we're doing a load bitmap
we're doing a push struct on on a task
arena so that's actually calling one of
the multi-thread arenas here and asking
it to do that and i guess i'm not sure
why that would really be anything
particularly odd but point being that's
where we're having it happen right and
when we do the verify you can see that
we've got the problem that we thought we
were going to get so at that very point
in time we have the error has occurred
and so it's somewhere in here now I'm
going to take a look at the threads as
well and you can see we've got thread
prox sitting here the thread prox are
not doing anything at the moment right
they're all just sitting there inside
thread frock they're just waiting and
they're not doing anything useful at all
so what that sort of suggests to me and
again not conclusively but what that
sort of suggested me is this isn't a
threading problem this isn't the sort of
situation where it's like some thread
was allocating memory and my thread did
something and those two things
conflicted and weren't locked properly
or something like this so they ended up
you know doing something bad it doesn't
look that way it looks like something
where
you know we got more of a
straightforward kind of an error right
all right so I'm going to also take a
little look look here and see which
entity are we actually processing how
far did we get through here we're at
entity number nine so we've done a
certain amount of processing before
we've actually had this memory sort of
situation manifest itself so yeah so I
don't know that is sounding a little
suspicious I don't really I'm not really
sure let me take a quick look here I
want to look at the arena code I want to
take a look at the arena code and I want
to see how it uses some of this stuff
let's see here so yeah
and temporary memory tippmann block blah
blah blah free last block where it calls
you like a memory past the pad by
remember block which is the current
block and that's all good arena prieve
should always be set and we allocate a
new one to the Block in question and it
is so that all looks you know that looks
fairly reasonable to me so yeah I don't
really know why we're getting that kind
of an error here but you know what we
can probably do is we can probably look
to see you know where that thing is
getting where that thing is getting
corrupted so what I want to do now is I
want to set a breakpoint that will occur
at the appropriate time for this so I
want to show like I want to just
basically have a way of saying well I
know at some point I'm going to have
this memory list integrity violation
occur but I also know that it doesn't
happen for a while right so what I can
do is say all right let's suppose that I
had some kind of a static here right
or maybe not
it was just global variable there we go
I always forget what I call that in this
code base alright so let's say I have a
global variable here and I'm just going
to use this as a memory counter oh this
will just be our fail counter right it
tells us when things are going to fail
and so what I can do here is I can do
you know an interlocked increment on
this basically and in fact you know what
I could put it inside the verify so what
I can do is say inside win through to
verify memory list integrity I can just
say okay every time we go in here we
increment the fail counter and so now we
know you know which one of these is the
actual failing case so let's go ahead
and run it here is our failure we look
at the fail counter and see that the
fail counter is at 35 right that means
it took 34 successful calls to the
verifier before we actually had one fail
right so what we can do then is we could
say well okay let's go ahead and take a
look at what happens right around that
time so for example when this fail
counter increments what i could do is
say if the failed counter equals the
failure case right so if the fail
counter equals 35 give me a place to
break right so now what I should be able
to do is say all right here's the
failure case we know that we just
validated this thing properly right it
actually worked okay and that we you
know are expecting to be able to come
through here and have this thing work
all right so this guy's succeeded we got
our memory back this stuff's getting
allocated you know we do some things
let's just take a look at what happens
here you know we're doing whatever we're
doing here with our chunks and
everyone's chunking around and doing
chunky things we probably finish this
routine we come through here we do all
this nonsense with players and all that
kind of stuff right here we go with our
brains getting their thing
and whatever is happening and then we
come through here and the first time we
try to do right our update and render
entities call here every when we try to
draw something on entity index nine for
whatever reason when we try to actually
draw entity next nine then we do that
push and then we fail so we know that
somewhere in between those two things
somewhere in between at the start of the
sim region and what actually and
rendering that entity that's where the
thing got corrupted right so now we sort
of marked our two areas we know where
we're okay and we know where we fail so
now we just need to figure out who is it
exactly who is getting corrupted right
and I don't know the answer to that
question so the next thing I want to do
is step into the the failing one of
these so now we're in the failing one of
these right I let it go till the 35 case
so we know this is the one that fails so
now what I want to do is say all right
now I know that that's the one that
fails what's the actual anatomy of the
failing block here is the Sentinel we're
going to its next pointer and the next
pointer okay so this is good the very
first thing off the next pointer is like
this next pointer is garbage right so
now what I can do is say all right let's
go through here come to the break point
the part that we know we're okay what is
my next pointer here is my next pointer
and my next pointer looks good right so
now I said to figure out who changes
this right and i know that this size
gets changed or this next pointer gets
changed which one I don't know so let's
find out here's the next pointer that
I'm expecting is this value let me run
to the assertion well run to the next
one let's say and let's take a look
there's the Sentinel it's pointing to
the same person so what this tells me is
that there's no problem with the linked
list itself somebody is actually
stepping on the size parameter for some
reason
now i have so i hope you saw that whole
process i've taken a very random weird
occurring bug that we had no idea where
it is and now I know exactly what I need
to do to find out who the culprit is I
know that that particular value is
getting overwritten and I know when it
is getting over written in a bracket
right so all I have to do is now set a
breakpoint that will tell me that and I
can do that like this I know that now
I'm going to set this this value is
correct right here right I know that
it's all right in my next point or block
right I know that that's correct what I
want to do is say okay where is this
value in memory here is the value right
so now what I'm going to do is say let's
get a break point on that value let's
let's tell me when that value changes
right and probably should try and cut
and paste that there we go so I'll say
new data breakpoint tell me this guy
right here is the thing I want a late
bite so it doesn't really matter because
it's all getting modified it looks like
but either way just tell me about all
eight bytes and see if you can tell me
when that thing gets changed right so
let's run here we are and so now we get
a break point that says somebody is
touching that memory and we know that
they should never be touching that
memory so what just happened right so
let's take a look here we're inside push
render element and what we're doing is
we're setting an entry up that that's
our sprite bound for one of our entries
and we're looking at push that sword
entry right so that's when we did one of
our push buffer operations and so
something is going wrong here where
we're maybe like not out we're maybe
like using too much memory or you know
we don't know what's happening but when
we're trying to access this entry struct
we're like overwriting the memory right
so we've caught we've caught this fellow
now so now let's take a look at how that
happened so when we go in here and we
said what did we say push buffer and the
push buffer is what gave us back that
sword entry pointer and let's see what
that actually is but what is entry right
here
so entry yeah entry is 7935 can we get a
look and we get a look at what wintery
to global state is here of course we
can't because visuals alright so one of
the nice things about visual studio is
it doesn't show you variables if you're
in the wrong module so hold on a second
let me see if I can what is its global
win through to state right so there it
is can you show it to me here no you
can't all right it doesn't matter I'll
just back up the stack to here and it
could show between a global so it's fine
so here's the global here's that
Sentinel here's the next pointer and you
can see the entry is literally pointing
right at our memory block right so
that's just not good right that is not
at all a good thing that is presumably
why we were getting that error and if we
look at the base pointer the base
pointer is clearly pointing 40 elements
past that so the question is how did
this thing ever end up thinking that it
was going to right there and I don't
know let's find out how did that happen
so when we call on this this push buffer
here and we do push over push buffer
we're going to call up in here this is
the data size that we were expecting we
say here's the commands level blah we
say the sprite pound
sora sora entries is somewhere and we'll
have to take a look at where that is
because that's the thing that's actually
failing we say like okay as long as this
as long as that is not in the wrong
place we'll keep going as long as that
hasn't overflowed its bounds so let's
see get sort entries
I want to take a look at this
it would be nice if we could figure out
a way to actually step through this code
explicitly but we can't we're going to
weed have to do a little bit more work
to get to that point so what I'd rather
do is just see if I can't spot the error
myself in this code so if we go to get
sort entries that's at the push buffer
base itself so the push buffer base in
this case is just wrong we know that
that is not what the push buffer base
should be assuming that this is the same
memory layout as last time which it
might not be address space for
randomization may not be turned off in
this machine and not sir if it is or it
isn't but if we if we assume that that's
still where the sentinel is which I can
quickly verify let's go ahead and jump
back there global win32 state memory
sentinel next yet 7a be four zeros and I
come back here and I c7a be with four
zeros how did the commands push buffer
base get sent get set to a memory block
header value that's just should never
have been possible because the push
buffer base should not be set to that
right that's a clearly erroneous place
to write no matter what and that's just
not good at all so where do we set the
push buffer base let's find out there's
not very many places where we even use
it let's see here there's a push buffer
base command switch buffer base render
group push buffer base push buffer base
push buffer base oh hi that is not oh
right I know why because we set it
inside this little thing up here all
right oh that answers that question man
that was a tricky one that's because we
did this stupid thing here which is
probably not the smartest idea you can
see what happened right when we do
render command struct and we pass a push
buffer here probably what happened is we
called the allocator and the allocator
returns the block to us which is
probably wrong
so I'm going to go ahead and guess that
probably what should have happened here
is we probably should have said
something like that at which point we
would get an error where is the push
buffer there is the push buffer and you
can see the error right we do will win
3-2 memory allocation call but a win32
memory allocation call technically
produces a platform memory block pointer
and really if we want the push buffer
itself we have to do get the base
pointer back right so that's that oops
okay oh and that's a you ate there we go
so I think that's it and now if I do a
build here I think we should be good to
go let's find out if we are and there's
our loop live coded it path and off we
go and that's it yay bug is dead uh so
yeah that's the bug the bug has been
eliminated and you know um that's AMISOM
stuff happened I probably don't need
this stuff anymore but you know it seems
like all the stuff with the fail counter
and that sort of thing is probably
useful do we have a local persist we do
what we could do is move that in here
just call this our own little thing our
own little you know situation
and then just get rid of the calls to it
everywhere but then if we find another
bug like that we can always just call
that function again and and use it to
track down another problem with that
sort of thing right
okay so I think that's just about it for
the memory stuff I don't know that there
was anything else in terms of
implementation what we could do now if
we wanted to was also we could add a
little bit of information to our debug
display to let us know who is using
memory and how much they are using which
is kind of a nice sort of just ballpark
estimate to get now that we know that we
have that information so what we could
do there is we could much time I got
left only have 13 minutes but you know I
think we left ourselves in a reasonable
state here with these things where I
probably could do something where where
those kind of get displayed let's let's
just take a quick look I'm going to open
up the do list we did that debugging
let's go ahead and see about this one
right here just so we can have some idea
of of what's going on there what the
problem that we're going to have is we
don't really have any way for a memory
arena to really have its state
initialized with debug information and
I mean I'm not really sure like i said
how how best to do this now one thing
that we can do pretty easily if we want
to write if i can do a thing that's just
like win32 you know get memory stats and
it's pretty easy for us to go through
all of the memory blocks and figure out
what our statistics actually are right
so I can do like memory stats something
like this and just say alright you know
there's a block count there's a total
allocate you know total allocated and
total used and all we would have to do
when we come through here say all right
let's make one of these stats structures
let's every time we loop you know over
one of these blocks will say ok there's
a block there is a total allocated and a
total used coming out of it where we
could say source block size and source
block used now technically size doesn't
actually include the header but that's
okay for now I think see here no Casey
does not technically include the header
so this function would allow us to get a
quick picture of our memory stats return
stats that could be used by anyone for
you know printing out memory information
let's go ahead and compile that we need
to grab that Sentinel put that in here
and technically since this list is
accessed in that way we would have to go
ahead and mute x it as well
alright uh and i think that's about it
sighs right because its platform so it's
actually that right yeah so that would
gather up the information that we want
and now the only question is how do we
pass it to the debug system here is a
one way we could do that when we do the
debug endframe stuff you know we could
provide a function for getting this back
I don't like to pollute you know to have
too much in the way of debug calls but
you know we could have one in here we
could say something like your debug
platform get memory stats or something
something like that debug platform oops
for memory stats and the name and this
wouldn't have to take any parameters at
all typedef and then debug platform get
memory stats something like this and
then we could if we're in the internal
thing have debug platform get memory
stats you go get memory stats and that
would allow us to figure out to call
this dynamically and then I would just
go ahead and put that guy up here right
see here there it is and me maybe that
should have a debug on it let's say
and there we go oops now we'll just have
to update the win32 one to actually use
that additional debug one and this would
be called debug platform get memory
stats and then process eight when we're
in internal we can go ahead and say game
memory platform api debug get memory
stats and there we go
I think I need an internal before that
don't I though maybe not
there we go uh let's see here typedef
define should not have that semicolon
there we go so inside our debug system
now if I wanted to I could just print
this out so you know along with our sort
of other heads up display stuff oops you
know here in this this little dude where
we do like whatever nonsense we've got
here I could now also get this
information so i could say like alright
debug platform memory stats mem stats
equals a you know flat dot oops dot
debug get memory stats in a theory that
would maybe work although it looks like
oops platform sorry in theory that would
maybe work and then what we could do
here is do like memory you know percent
what is it for Long's is it is it lu % l
I can't remember what the actual print
out is for long for 64-bit integers
interesting it doesn't look like we
actually ever set one so do we want ll
to be 64 or do we want just L to be 64
like which one do we want to print out
is there a definition somewhere for this
mmmm I melt melt melt melt now ma'am
ma'am ma'am ma'am ma'am ma'am LOL
now that's non-standard long unsigned
int L long long ll okay how many bits is
that does anyone know or care
well you know what I'm going to make
that be someone else's problem I'm just
going to say that minus L is fine with
me so let's just say that the integer
length becomes 8 when you put a nail in
front of it happy birthday everybody
that's just how that goes into jeru
length and then that should just work
right because we already supported that
up here where we did like the if length
equals 8 get a you 64 nonsense we did
that already we did that and so inside
the debug code at memory oops mm stats I
just want to print out some of these
values that I worked so hard to get so
let's see debug platform memory stats I
want to do something like L you don't
ask me why the block count is a um em
but yeah blocks Alec used out of your
allocated right uh let's see so if we
print that out I just need to put these
in here so that would be men stats loc
count mm stats total size m stats total
used let's backwards and off we go so
let's see if that works at all I don't
know if it does
seventy seven blocks three hundred forty
megabytes used out of Ford and 14
megabytes allocated and that's it most
of that's in the asset arena I believe
so you can kind of see that how these
arena alligators are kind of nice too
because you can see that like there's
only been 78 actual allocations there
but when that number was like ticking up
and down and stuff those were actually
all tiny little allocations happening
but we're just doing our push trucks on
and it's nice that those are so cheap
right that they don't cost us very much
all right
all right uh so there we go
let's go ahead and go to the QA shall we
I feel like we did some fairly efficient
debugging today I think you can all give
yourselves on a pet a pat on the back
for doing a nice efficient debugging run
we didn't waste a lot of time we zeroed
in directly on the problem and yeah and
eliminated it
thus Isaac long is greater than equal to
32 bits long long Israeli go to 64 bits
so does that mean that technically we
should we should use ll then maybe I
mean the problem is we don't want
greater than or equal to 64 bits we need
to be actually 64 bits we need to print
that specify that's like this value is
64 bits long please I guess is this our
printf we can do whatever we want is one
answer but still it would be nice if
that was more rigorously specified
somewhere
yeah yeah Matt Matt Matt Matt man
windows is LLP 64 everything else is LP
64 the only difference between the two
is the size of long everything else
short int long long is the same says
pseudonym 73 you know see sure managed
to make its types complicated
I don't see any Q Collins
no q Colin's I might be done early
is there any plan on organizing the
episodes in a manner such as worked on
Mandela on these episodes well it's kind
of hard but because that's I mean maybe
someone could write something that that
parse the episode guide to do that the
only thing that there is for that at the
moment is if you go on the YouTube so
well actually gets the easiest way to do
that would be actually to do that if you
go on the YouTube there are playlists so
you know you can get some semblance of
that sort of thing by you know looking
at the memory playlist and there's you
know stuff that's marked for a memory
specifically uh and you know it's better
than nothing but is there any plan for
anyone to like meticulously do it
probably not at some point when the
Sirius is over probably someone could
could write a thing that parsed the
episode guides markers that midlo puts
in there and turns those into an index
of some kind and that would probably be
better because those are a little more
detailed and like would catch things
like well we didn't really work on
memory allocation much on this episode
but during this one little time window I
did go in there and fix a bug that we
you know because we had a bug that was
in the memory system that just came up
and so we went and fixed it so like you
know maybe that could happen at some
point too and that would be a little
better at the moment though the only
thing you can really do is use the
playlist there the only thing that that
really has that
and that has that aspect i guess i would
say Shh
Niebla says that they're going to have
category tagging in the new annotation
system I don't know anything about this
new annotation system but may blow says
they will have tagging which sounds like
the kind of thing
would handmade hero get a version for
Linux or is it strictly a windows
project if it's true why not using Linux
in work is it personal choice or is it
harder to debug something on windows so
the answer to that question is I've
answered this many times before it's
because there's no the the current
market for games you can't really make a
go of it on linux linux is almost zero
sales for games so you have to be able
to ship on windows as your primary pc
platform it's ninety-five percent of the
market right now so that's the reason I
show development on Windows primarily
it's also true that debugging on Linux
is worse typically because the to the
debugging tools just aren't as good
unfortunately well that's that's a
little ambiguous the visual debuggers
are not as good some tools are better on
Linux like they have better do typically
have better like you know static
analysis or bounds checking tools and
stuff like that you could you can
actually get better ones sometimes on
Linux them and windows so that that's
actually the case but so yeah if you're
if you're programming games you kind of
need your primary platform to be windows
that's what almost everyone who runs
your game will run it on and so you have
to be on that platform a lot and make
sure that you know that platform well
and get that platform nailed so am I
happy about that no like I don't like
how Microsoft is always sort of acting
as a very sort of greedy actor in this
space and making life harder for
developers to suit their own business
interests I don't like it obviously so I
wish we could have had everyone moved to
Linux but I just you know don't know if
or when that's ever going to happen so
unfortunately we're stuck in that kind
of reality you know
so yeah the day we can get a viable game
market where you know you can sell over
fifty percent of your sales come from
Linux or something that's going to be a
great day but you know that day is not
only not here yet but doesn't even look
like it's ever going to be here at the
moment because there's been like no no
buns seems to be able to make making any
inroads into making that happen so you
know that's that's just the way it is
that said if you do want the version of
the game that runs on linux I believe
people maintain one there is a Linux
port that people maintain of handmade
heroes code base and I will port it to
links when it's done as well myself and
they'll be an official one too so
there'll be plenty of opportunities to
run the code base on Linux it's just not
ever going to be the primary platform
for it because of the realities of the
game industry which like it or not are
pretty much windows centric and I don't
know you know that we're going to see
that change unfortunately time soon it
would be nice if we did but
foreigners don't use drugs message needs
to be added in the game's loading screen
i 100% agree if you want to put a log a
bug in the github for that I would be
happy to make sure that we get that
happening eventually zilla risco seems
like the questions aren't pull polling
in do you usually put your render update
input processing in the same function
like you have been doing yeah I tend to
break things out only when I find them
to be important to break out so I don't
usually have hard fast rules for that
it's just whatever ends up being right
for that project and the goals for that
project as time goes on it usually
becomes clear whether you want to do
things in separate passes or whether you
want to do them all in one pass and so
usually you don't have to really think
very hard about that it should be
obvious edvin home is the bending of the
heroes about it going to be like it is
now looks weird I know this is this is
not the real artwork for the game at the
moment so nothing that you see on the
screen is how it will actually be
moving from Windows to Linux how much of
the onus of making this change lice on
the consumers versus linux OS designers
linux distros aren't normally ordinary
user friendly i guess i would say i
don't know uh i think that's too complex
a question I don't know the answer to
how you get people to move to linux I
don't even know if you want people to
move to linux I mean linux is kind of
its own mess for a number of reasons so
I really couldn't tell you i don't i
don't really have a strong opinion about
that or like i don't think i know the
like way forwards and i can just say it
what do you think about free software um
well uh I don't really like it very much
i guess i would say um i like the idea
that i like the I guess what I would say
is I don't necessarily disagree with
where they're coming from the sort of
core concepts of free software uh and I
don't think it's a bad idea gee I just
it doesn't happen to be my ideology I
think software should be commercial I
don't generally don't think code should
be given away I think it's hard to write
very few people are good at it and you
should be able to make a living off of
it so I don't like the idea that source
code is generally just available for
people to use Andrea propriate but on
the flip side I don't like the
commercial I don't like restriction
lists software so I don't like things to
be completely commercial either meaning
I essentially like I feel like well you
shouldn't have to provide source code
and allow people to use that source code
just because you ship a product I do
think there should be restrict
on how you ship products that that rain
in the kinds of abuse that you see in a
lot of in a lot of domains right so if
you look at some of the core tenants of
free software what they were trying to
guarantee was sort of our along the
lines of things I approve of or also
want to guarantee right so you know free
software is typically what what they'll
say as well as you know it's free speech
not free beer the problem is the free
beer typically comes with the free
speech like it's really hard to have the
free speech part without the free beer
part and so typically what you end up
seeing with free software is that it
pretty much does have to be distributed
in a free beer kind of a way as soon as
one person has paid for it once there's
not a lot of ways around that right but
a lot of things they were trying to
guarantee with the free speech side of a
free software which was their goal or
good things like the fact that if you
buy a piece of software you can continue
to run it without the permission of the
person you bought it from right that's a
really big deal the fact that you can
install it on whatever Hardware you're
trying to run on like that's a really
big deal and what we see nowadays is
definitely a lot of sort of a lot of
commercial software is getting very
onerous and very restrictive of what you
can do with it and it's encroaching on
basic usage that I would consider the
core ways in which software should be
provided you know by law required to
work I should not have to contact
microsoft in order to run microsoft
windows on my laptop if I bought a copy
of it right that's like policing has
been taken too far or whatever I should
not have to update my microsoft windows
if I want to run an old version of
Microsoft Windows I should be able to do
so I should not have to have my machine
connected to the internet in order to
run photoshop right as long as I
purchased a legal copy i should be able
to run my software that's just a core
tenet of software that i think should be
enforced
and so to the extent that I part ways
with the free software ideology it's
it's really just in that I don't think
they figured out a very good way to
enforce the ideals they were trying to
enforce without making it very likely
that programmers wouldn't really get
paid the fair value of their work that's
what I think but on the whole I do tend
to come from a similar place
ideologically speaking because a lot of
the things that I see commercial
software companies doing right now I
don't approve of and then definitely
don't fit with my ideology at all so I
guess what I would say is that's that's
a fairly complete answer to it you know
do I think so do I think like the new
public license is a good license not
really because I generally think you
know software source code should be you
know generally proprietary and you
should probably have to pay for it and
you shouldn't just be able to then use
it for whatever you want to as long as
you also give away the source I don't
think that's very good in terms of
getting programmers compensated for what
they've done and I also don't think it
it ends up achieving the ideology
logical goals in the first place either
because if you take a look at let's say
you take a look at something like a
facebook or something right closed flat
platform draconian about what you can do
on it tries to lock down things so that
it all goes through their stuff bought
oculus and now controls that segment the
VR industry locs games to that platform
blah blah blah right none of that stuff
would be considered in keeping with with
the ideological understanding of free
software right but Facebook was 100%
built on free software there would be no
facebook today if if it weren't for many
free software foundation products right
i should say projects and so if you look
at the efficacy of the GPL or something
like that also it seems to basically do
neither of the two things you might want
it to do one to make sure that
programmers are fairly compensated for
their work and two in making sure that
the ideology
a that it represents is forced upon
those who would take advantage of that
suffer it does neither of those two
things in my mind right so yeah it's a
complex issue there's a lot of subtlety
to it I think it's not being done very
well right now if one were to look at it
from my perspective but that doesn't
necessarily mean that it's bad from the
people's perspective who who you know
are doing those sorts of projects maybe
they are getting what they want out of
it i don't know but hopefully that's a
pretty complete answer all right i'm
going to go ahead and close it up save
everything there thank you everyone for
joining me for another episode of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you want to
follow along with the series you can do
so by pre-ordering the game on handmade
hero or get comes with a source code so
you can follow along as we do stuff you
can play around with it we also a forum
site if you want to ask questions that's
a good place to do it a patreon page you
want to support the video series a
schedule bot that will tell you when
we're going to be live if you want to
catch up such lies and an episode guide
you can go to if you want to catch up on
old episodes I was scheduled to be back
here tomorrow 8 p.m. pacific daylight
time I do not know if I will be able to
make it or not so there may be a
schedule update definitely check the
tweet bot for that when you get a chance
just to make sure you don't show up here
expecting one and not getting it that's
about it for today if I don't see you
tomorrow I will see you the day after
either or thanks very much for joining
me and until the next episode I'll yeah
have fun coding and i'll see you guys on
the internet take it easy everyone