hello everybody and welcome to handmade
hero the show where we formerly coded a
complete gave live on stream and
hopefully will continue to code a
complete game live on stream but I am on
our side break right now so well the
hands are healing we're just still
hanging out because well there wasn't
really a good reason not to still stream
just not to type and I don't have to
type to stream so there you go we've
been basically taking questions where I
can sort of see if there's people who
have stuff that they would like me to
cover while we're on break and I've got
a question from somebody in email that
actually sort of there was a number of
things in it that I thought were kind of
important to nail down and so I'd like
to go over that now I'd probably take a
good portion of the program here and
some of it is going to be review for
people who followed all of handmade hira
but it was it was something that was I
it's it's worth understanding enough
that I just feel like it's worth doing
another whiteboard on just so people are
really comfortable with it and there's
no question about this the circumstance
here so I want to talk about the
difference between a conceptual resource
versus a physical resource because what
was apparent to me when I read the email
question it was that the person who was
asking it didn't seem to really
understand the difference between a
conceptual resource and a physical
resource and I can understand why that's
true because in a lot of systems where
you aren't programming from scratch so
you know on him a hero obviously as
educational scream so we program
everything from scratch and so we wrote
the thing that actually loads everything
off of the disk and we you know we did
all of that ourselves and if that's your
first introduction as it was for me for
example because when I was growing up
and writing these things there were
nesting as a game engine that didn't
that I don't even know if that word
existed until I was
gosh probably 15 16 or something right
so there really was no such thing as a
off the shelf thing that you got and
built a game you know wasn't like you
went and grabbed unity or something like
this and started making a game without
any idea of like what it was doing that
wasn't a thing but if that was your
first introduction to something that's
like the first time that you sort of
started thinking about game development
was with unity or game maker when these
things it's kind of easy to understand
why people could get confused between
the difference but or be confused or
conflate conceptual and physical
resources because sometimes they are is
set essentially the same in these tools
right meaning the two the engine that
you use may not differentiate between
those two things in any way that you can
perceive as an end user now under the
hood they almost certainly are
differentiating between them in their
own code but in your world like what you
see in terms of what the the game engine
exposes to you as a user they may never
show that difference and so I wanted to
kind of underscore what it was and I'll
answer the specific question the person
had in the email as part of that but
this I thought was kind of a bigger
issue that I wanted to make sure we
touched on so first of all let me
explain what a conceptual resource is a
conceptual resource is something you
think of and talk about as a asset or
something you use as part of the game
right so a conceptual resource might be
something like a mesh let's say right
like a 3d mesh that you're going to use
that you made in Maya or something like
that right the conceptual resource
another one so for handmade hero one
example would be a bitmap right so some
like image that you you know that you
made right these are conceptual
resources and what I mean by that is
that there isn't anything specific about
them that makes them physical resources
there's nothing that makes them uh have
to exist in any particular way because
they're just bits and bytes at the end
of the day right but conceptually we are
thinking of
specific bundle of bits right as meaning
this thing so we're thinking of this 3d
mesh as being a conceptually unit like
unified whole right that we talked about
we even give it a name right like maybe
this thing has some fun even a file name
if it's in a file or maybe if it's just
a mesh that's in a Maya file it's got
just a name so you know it's like it's
like hero underscore mesh or something
or whatever so we even have a name for
it like humans like to name concepts we
might even have names for them right
that's a conceptual resource and the
reason that I think it's important to
understand what that means is because a
conceptual resource has literally no
relationship to a physical resource okay
so what's a physical resource a physical
resource is something that you actually
have to get store load something that's
actually binary data coming from
somewhere in some kind of a package okay
so a physical resource might be
literally a file on a drive let's say or
a file that's on a network somewhere
some some like a URL addressable thing
right but it's something that is only
considered a unit as far as the
underlying system is concerned so for
example we may have something like you
know handmade assets dot you know text
or something like this which is a text
file that has a bunch of stuff in it or
whatever and this is a physical asset in
the sense that it is like on the drive
as a file right it actually exists as a
literal resource right and the reason
that I want to draw this distinction
here is because this text file might
have lots of conceptual resources in it
for example the text file might have
different sections and each section
might be conceptually different okay
more to the point and the thing that I
wanted to address sort of as specific to
the question that the person was asking
is we may have something called handmade
you know dot art or something or better
yet let me just actually use I forget
what the file thing is that we actually
called our stuff but in our data
directory HHA right so there's a test
one HHA or whatever so we've got
handmade ehh ehh okay and what is handy
that you say well it's a physical
physical resource right it's a file on
the drive but it is not a conceptual
resource because what's in it is lots of
concept it's a bundle right of lots of
conceptual resources there's tons and
tons and tons of bitmaps in there tons
of sounds in there whatever right okay
so this is a very very important concept
to understand and like I said for some
people whose introduction to programming
was through a more from scratch route
this is a trivial distinction you never
you've always understood it and it's
just second nature right but for someone
who's coming out at the other direction
it'd be very easy to not understand the
distinction between these two things
right okay so with that in mind I want
to talk about the specific question that
the person asked and that question was
maybe i'll leave this kind of right
there that question was why would a game
ever need more than one file right why
would it ever need more than one file
and this was talking yesterday because
remember yesterday I talked about oh
I've got a game and it's got art files
but I could package those all up into
one file right and so that by itself is
interested why would a game ever need
more than one file so say like why more
oops by more than one file and then the
second question that's a person asked
and I'm saying question but really it
was part of the question number one they
asked there's sort of a separate thing
that led to a different question that I
wanted to address and that is why would
every more in file and
said the only thing I can think of
they're saying is that if you wanted to
sort of have sprite sheets right and
we've talked about sprite sheets before
that's basically like a single bit map
that has a bunch of different frames of
animation for a sprite packed into it if
you want to have different sprite sheets
that you swapped in and out right for a
character let's say then you might want
to do that by having the the sprite
sheet for one character in spray chief
or another character match up exactly so
you could just pick which one you were
using by changing which file you were
using right so that's that's the next
question which is like a sprite sheet
sprite sheets and swapping is a thing
right and then three he sort of said are
their API limits or like you know file
size limits right that affect this
decision so I'm going to try and take
all of these questions because they're
all kind of lumped into one right so the
first question why more than one file
right and so conceptually speaking even
if you had no limitations so assuming
two and three have nothing to do with
this and we're just talking about the
game could do it anyway it wanted is
there any reason just to have more than
one file right separate from everything
else is there any reason why the game
just wants to have more than one file
for its own sake separate from the
sprite sheet questions separate from the
APA sis file size limits is there any
reason right so is there a reason to
have more than one file and the answer
there is potentially yes and the reason
there is because of expansion patching
etc right conceptually speaking you may
want to write a game and I should you
know what I should put in here to
modding conceptually speaking you may
want your game to break things up into
more than one file because those files
are
actually things that a user may want to
address in some way right meaning a user
may want to do something like mod a
particular thing and distribute that mod
and that may be easiest to do by
allowing there to be multiple files in
the directory so I want this file from
this guy in this file from this guy and
I want to put them together and I don't
want to have to write an interface in
the game right for pulling those files
in and rewriting them out to like a
single file because the game only
supports one file or something that
right so iterating over a number of
files and then merging their results or
picking and choosing which ones you use
is a way of providing an interface to
the user for editing the game and
furthermore it provides a convenient
interface for something like expansion
where you could ship an installer where
the installer is just a thing that
copies a new HHA file let's say with the
expect with all the new data in it into
the directory if the game is smart
enough to read all the HHA files that
are in that directory then your
expansion pack shipment is literally
just just that one file it just drops in
and off you got right so there's a bunch
of stuff like that potentially with
patching as well like I said it might be
easier on certain architectures because
remember you don't always have complete
control about how patching works
depending on the platform older and how
they demand patching works you may find
that having more files makes it easier
for you to work around limitations in
there patching system right so there's
plenty of reasons why you might
conceptually want to do this for your
own games ease of maintenance that don't
really have that much to do with the
actual act of loading files or storing
them to the drive or any other concerns
like the spritesheet question so
hopefully that sort of answers that
question let's move on to number two so
the sprite sheet and swapping question
so this is why I wanted to sort of
underscore the difference from
conceptual and physical resources is I
don't really understand that question
because it's having sprite sheet that
you swap is no harder to do inside a
pack file than outside of it right so if
i have a bitmap and B dot bitmap right
and I want to pick which one of these I
use
game for the hero that's no different
than if i have my HH a file and I've got
to I've got a bitmap packed in there and
beat up bitmap packed in there I still
when the game is running it still
chooses which one of these it's going to
load out of the HHA file into memory
right so the HH a file or any packed
file it doesn't give you any less
versatility at runtime right then having
them as separate files because at the
end of the day a physical resource has
nothing to do with a conceptual resource
a single physical resource can still be
loaded at in parts right as separate
conceptual resources so a conceptual
resource does not have to map 12 12 your
physical resources they're completely
different and you don't really have to
worry about that at all so the only time
again where you care about your
conceptual resource to physical resource
mapping is when you have some sort of
expansion patching modding idea and you
feel like it might be easier for you if
they were separated in this way because
then users don't have to copy like say
extra data that they don't actually need
to copy around when distributing a mod
or something right because they're doing
that through their own back Channel that
doesn't involve your game and so your
game can't help them extract and
redistribute the conceptual resources
right now that said even that not that
big of a deal because for example like
if you look at the doom community that
used dot wad files back bill doom
Wolfenstein you know success or doom by
in software the original doom it used
the pack file format called W ad and in
that file it just had all the resources
for the game and basically like the
modding community just wrote tools to
like extract and re combine them anyway
so at the end of the day like even even
at some level you might not really care
because people can overcome those
limitations pretty easily as long as
your document your pack file format and
make it easy for people to work with
it's really not a big deal right so
anyway there's that so now let's
actually talk about number three which
is our their API and file size limits
and the answer actually is yes so
what happens unfortunately is that
certain file systems impose a maximum
file size limit on the any single
contiguous file in that in that file
system so for example if you have say a
fat32 i believe the fat32 file system
limits any particular file to like i
either 2 or 4 gigabytes I think it's too
I think it's basically a signed integers
worth of sign 32-bit integers worth of
space so I think fat 32 is 2 gigabytes
for example so you know if you were
going to distribute let's say the
witness right if you're distributing the
witness then you have a thing that's
bigger than 2 gigabytes and so it can't
fit in a single pack file if that pack
file has to go on a fat from you to
drive now maybe you don't care about
supporting a fat32 drive and that's fine
but the point is yes there are actual
file size limits depending on the file
system that's chosen for the storage
medium that the game is going to run off
of right so there's that another
limitation is download right if people
have to download these files or do other
things with them then you might want to
think about the fact that like well okay
you know if if i'm distributing these
maybe I want to try to distribute them
in ways where the files themselves could
be useful or could be complete or
checked in smaller increments so that
you know if you've got it all I don't
know I mean I don't think so because
typically network distrib you're kind of
not in the loop there so I feel like
that's probably not really that relevant
but I don't know there could be reasons
for transfer on where you would care
about making things not be so huge but I
feel like most people are going through
a service like steam or you know or
something what God with a downloader
these days so I don't know I mean it's
probably just not that big a deal but
anyway so yeah there are some
limitations are their API limitations
well yes and no so in general most
modern operating system
allow 64bit control over your files so
you know if there's a file that's bigger
than two gigabytes or four gigabytes
it's not a problem for the operating
system it's only the problem if the file
system underlying it is you know the
wrong size that said there is a
interesting caveat which is for example
there's a thing called a memory map file
and we play with these a little at hand
made here when we were playing around
with the recording stuff and a memory
map file is when you basically tell the
operating system look I've got a memory
range you know and I want to map that
memory range to something on the disk so
here's a file right so whenever I read
from or write to this address in memory
I want you to read or write that same
thing to tour from the file and this is
a kind of depending on the circumstance
it's I don't like this let's for this
way I don't think memory map files are a
good idea pretty much ever but they do
have some nice properties one of them is
they behave better with the virtual
memory system in an oversubscription
scenario and voila bye I don't like
memory mapped files I think they're bad
idea that's it memory mapped files are
are basically a way of assigning a range
of memory to a range of bytes on the
drive right and if you only have a
32-bit address space for your memory it
means you can only have a 32-bit sized
file right so for example if I was on
x86 remember because there's two types
of processors there's x64 and x86 two
types of processor architectures at play
on PC there's the old style which is x86
it can only address a memory in a 32-bit
fashion
barring some large extensions blah blah
blah blah but for the most part you're
practically talking about 30 outer space
x64 can access 64-bit address space all
right so what that means is that older
computers which are running x86 they
don't have 64 bits of addressable memory
space and again this has nothing to do
with how much memory is actually in the
system I'm just talking about the range
of addresses that they can talk about
right because you know remember there's
the concept of a pointer we use them all
the time on handmade hero they point to
a particular place in memory right if
that pointer is 32 bits which it is on
x86 then it can only look at 32 bits
worth of address space doesn't matter
there could be 16 gigabytes of memory in
the system it any given application only
has the ability in its virtual address
space to talk about 32 bits which is 4
gigabytes that's it right so what that
means is no matter how much member you
pile into the machine or how much
virtual at memory you've set up your
system to use on x86 you can only have
32 bits worth of address space which
means that any file larger than 4
gigabytes can't even be mapped into
memory if you used all the memory of the
machine sorry not all the members in all
the address space of the machine you
couldn't even map it into memory you
couldn't even do it right which puts a
hard limit of 4 gigabytes on any file
you might push through this API but the
actual practical situation is even worse
than that because obviously you can't
use one hundred percent of the memory
range of your application because if you
did there be no room for anything else
so mapping afford to go bite file would
literally take up the entire address
space that your memory could that your
application could talk about right every
every single pointer would now point
into the file you could not point into
any of your own memory at all you could
never even allocate a block of memory
because there'd be no way to tell you
where it was because every possible
pointer all possible pointers in 32 bits
are all pointing to somewhere in the
file so in reality obviously it's less
than 4 gigabytes it's for goodbyes minus
however much memory you need right so
it's it's
it's minus the memory you need that's
how big the file is but it's worse than
that because not only does all the
memory you need have to be accounted for
all the memory the operating system
might need to use on your behalf also
has to be taken out and that's not even
really all that negotiable because the
way that Windows works is at startup for
the most part it partitions the memory
space in half and says the top two
gigabytes will be used for the system
the bottom two gigabytes will be used
for the application of the four gigabyte
address space that's 32 that for 32-bit
x86 okay and so what that means is you
start off with only two gigabytes to
begin with because the other two
gigabytes are used for all sorts of
operating system mapping now again I
want to underscore that this is the
applications virtual memory space
remember you talked a lot about this in
the early days but in case you forgot
virtual memory is what your program
talks about the memory as being right
when you say I want a dress whatever
some random pointer when you hold up
that pointer and say I want this address
that's what you mean now remember it
goes through a remapping table that the
operating system sets up in the CPU it
goes to remapping people to get the
physical memory so we're not so my
physical memory and again you can have
more physical memory and x86 machine
could have more physical memory in it in
theory I don't know if if that sort of
thing ever actually got built I don't
think it does but you know in theory
there could be a lot more physical
memory in the machine and you could like
maybe map each Bank to a different
processor and use some kind of segments
so I mean I don't know if the x86
architecture even allowed that I don't
remember because it was never a
practical issue that I ever addressed so
I don't know but point being we're not
even talking about physical memory we're
just talking about the address space
right we're just talking about the
address space that your program uses to
articulate what it wants to do okay and
that address space is partitioned into
two gigs two gigs and so what happens in
that upper two gigs here well this is
where like hardware stuff gets mapped in
like for example there's range
this that are used for mapping like how
we talked to the GPU so it backs memory
that's like across the PCI bus sometimes
it has all the stuff like file handles
that you have open it has the code for
the kernel that you can call into like
all the api's you can call to all the
dll's that are mapped they all go in
there right so everything is is even
worse than this picture might might make
it out to be you actually have two good
bites now there was a way on on Windows
if the user wanted to the user could run
windows in what was called a 3gb mode I
think it was called 3gb mode so called
because if you started the kernel with
the kernel parameter / 3 GB which you
could do by by changing the way windows
boot loaded worked if it's a long story
doesn't even matter but point being a
user could boot their machine in a way
that actually had oh dear what did I do
what have I done I've zoomed this there
we go a user could boot their machine in
a way that did not look like this that
would actually make it look like this
where there'd be three gigabytes and one
gigabyte so the system took less space
and the users application each
application could talk about three
gigabytes instead of two gigabytes right
so that was pretty handy that's like a
real nice thing right and so you could
do that but the user ID yep so you can't
ship an application that relies on that
because most users wouldn't even know
how to add the 3 GB switch to the
colonel boot so forget about that so you
have to assume you can only run in that
two gigabytes so again that puts the
practical limitations on how big of a
file you could map very small think you
know significant less than 2 gigabytes
right now let's say one more thing about
that so in addition to all of these
other nasty nas's there's one more thing
that makes the two gig thing a problem
is that even if you somehow took almost
no memory so you could use the whole two
gigabytes of your memory for actually
doing that memory map file it still
might not work because if you don't take
absolute care not to like
accidentally allocate out of the middle
of this or something right then that
memory map that file memory map it has
to be contiguous so the actual amount of
file mapping you can do in a 2 gigabyte
aerospace depends on the largest
contiguous free section so for example
if this was right at the one gigabyte
mark then and where I like accidentally
allocated some memory there to run the
game or whatever then it actually only
be one gigabyte free here and one
gigabyte free here which would mean well
unless both will be less because there's
some memory take down the middle but
approximately 1 gigabyte right at that
point I've just cut the size that I can
map a file in half even if I've only
taken like 4k to run my game the size of
the file I could map is cut in half
right in practice is going to be way
worse than that so you know again that's
a very practical API limitation you
don't have to worry about it so much in
64 bit because again since we're not
actually talking about physical memory
here we're talking about virtual memory
you can map a file that's much larger in
64 bit windows because when the opportu
some memory maps of file it's strictly
reserving the address range and saying
anything in this address range if
someone tries to touch it I'm going to
go get the part of file I need at that
time right it doesn't go try to load the
whole file actually into memory and
actually use physical memory for it it
will actually just leave it as sort of
conceptually mapped right it'll put it
in the mapping tables that it uses to
keep track of everything is but it won't
actually start pulling things into
physical memory until it actually needs
to and it won't over subscribe so if you
start pulling in other stuff it'll page
out part of the file you'll just you
know ungettable memory for some other
part of the file so at the end of the
day you can map very large files in
64-bit windows because you only have to
make sure that you have enough
contiguous virtual memory you know space
to map it and with 64 bits of address
space that is huge swathes you know
available right so you could probably I
mean I've never tribe you could probably
map a one terabyte file and
did be fine because there's going to be
a giant space somewhere in the 64-bit
address space that can support one
terabyte remember one terabytes only you
know a few bits above 32 right so it's
really not that big a deal for 64-bit so
so hopefully that answers the question
and let me take a look and see if we've
gotten any other q's queued up here at
sea let's see um you know what I didn't
know if I set the scroll back did I set
the scroll back and how do you kind of
say I want to remember everything like
infinite scroll back here we go scroll
back lines can I set scroll back lines
to infinite can I set it to zero or
something and have it be infinite does
that work I don't even know if it does
man
I'm not sure oh sounds alerts general
colors color switcher I don't even know
what am I looking at I have no idea I
don't know so I don't know if this
thing's working or not I have no idea
let's see all right question is there
any way to reverse engineer a pack file
and figure out how its laid out like
resident evil md1 files in PSX sure yeah
there's lots of ways and I'm the wrong
one to ask about like the tick some
tricks for that because I don't really
do a lot of that but yeah if you want to
reverse-engineer a file then typically
what ends up happening is typically ones
up happening is the you start to try and
piece through the binary data to look
for things that you recognize like
things that might be the counts of
something or things that look like a
particular type of data like zipped data
like something's been zip compressed or
something that looks like a texture in
txt format or who knows what right so
you do stuff like that and you can try
to reverse-engineer it the harder core
reverse engineering I'm assuming and
don't really know but I'm assuming the
harder course engineering tends to be
more um that you that the the people
disassemble and step through the actual
code of the game and look at how it
loads it in because then you can see
what sort of stuff it does like how it
decompresses it and how it jumps around
so I suspect that there's a fair bit of
like looking at the game code as well in
two to do more advanced file formats but
yes people absolutely do this all the
time I don't but you know it's it's
certainly a straightforward process but
it's a bit tedious Cuba Caleb why do you
think that Mary map files are bad idea
because you have very little control of
how they are overlapped and when they're
issued in terms of
when they read from any Victor the file
and so I just don't feel like it's a
good performance oriented programming
practice to memory map of file the GL 0
to stream allows to patch files instead
of overwrite them Otis team so could one
patch the one data file having an update
that is not a practically full reinstall
yes as far as I know there are so I
believe steam just works there are other
sometimes people make mistakes platform
vendors make mistakes and they do
something stupid and at the risk of
being overly opaque here I'll simply say
that I know that people have made
mistakes of the form they encrypt the
data that apps install because the
platform has drm or whatever and they
forgot about the fact that once you
encrypt something it becomes unpatch
abell because an encrypted thing all the
bitstream depends on everything that
that's downstream from it right so if
you if you have a platform that encrypts
files opaquely to you then you can't
patch anymore and everything's to
reinstall so that has happened in the
past more than once I believe and so
some platforms really screw that up but
but I don't think steam is one of them I
don't know this the game at Molly rocket
will be the first steam release that
that I'll have been directly doing
myself and so at that point I'll have
maybe I haven't looked at it myself yet
but that'll be the first time I really
have to think about how steam what's
team does and whether there's anything
particularly important I need to know
Elvin any ideas or thoughts about those
anti piracy ideas I'll stop you right
there and I'll just say I don't like
anti piracy full stop I think they're
just plain bad i don't like game piracy
obviously i don't like the fact that
people you know
don't participate in the market properly
and they basically like get you know
it's basically like someone who it's the
people who go to the restaurant and
don't tip right it's like you you're
forcing everyone else to subsidize your
purchases right because you won't pay
for the game so now everyone else has to
pay more for the game right because if
everyone actually paid for the game who
played it then games could be a lot
cheaper and even more importantly than
that some games that didn't sell enough
copies right now to actually be viable
or you have the budgets that they had
wood and those are very important things
so I really hate game piracy or just
software piracy in general but at the
same time I don't think that the right
solution to that is anti-piracy drm and
the reason for that is because it
creates some very serious problems it
means that users have a hard time
maintaining their game collection right
you know you end up with a disk you
can't even you bought grand theft auto
on the Xbox and now you'll never be able
to play that again you have to go buy it
again right and now you're actually
you're being taken advantage of you were
trying to participate in a market fairly
and pay the developers for what they did
and now you're actually being penalized
because you know you've been given a
copy that you can't run anymore right
and furthermore the same is true for
like people who find if their game
doesn't run because the drm doesn't work
on their system or something like this
which happens all the time it also
creates a problem for preservation it
means that it's harder for a museum or
archive.org or someone like this to
maintain a running copy of this game for
posterity and all those things I think
are really bad so I have no nothing to
say about anti-piracy ideas that people
have other than their stupid and don't
do them
long billion I've been thinking about
how to implement water reflections in a
top-down 2-d game what do you think
about using render layers like bottom to
top water reflection land shadows object
things then combining the layers I mean
it seems fine but you know it's hard to
talk in abstractions about something as
specific as how to render water
reflections you know captain craft do
you have any idea what do you have any
idea for hardware architecture design
that could improve performance for games
not really because I am not really a
hardware guy so I mean I you know I like
i said i have api i I feel like there's
some things I can say about API design
that are like this is good for
performance this is good for longevity
in terms of the interface between the
software and the hardware but once you
get into the hardware that I think is
just I don't have enough experience with
hardware to have any opinions that are
worth anything you know I just don't
know the realities of when you implement
something on silicon I just don't know
everything that's involved arrived very
cursory knowledge of it and so I feel
like my opinions on how you would
improve performance for games and
hardware are I mean into some to some
extent they're almost non-existent I
don't know what the current performance
problems are you know like I mean I
don't know what actually is the biggest
bottleneck for example in a modern
hardware part I sometimes maybe know
that somebody at Intel or somebody in
the video or somebody might have told me
that they think something is this and
but that's just hearsay I mean I have no
opinion my own opinion about this was a
bad luck or whatever you know maybe that
person is wrong or maybe you know
they're misguided or maybe that's not
the whole story so so I I don't know so
I i pretty much only deal with software
and the software at a hardware interface
I have some I things on because I've
seen enough of that and I have a fairly
good idea of what that sort of ends up
looking like at the Harbor substrate
level but I below that it's I just have
to trust that when a hardware vendor
tells me something that there
just making it up because I I don't know
and can't verify snov in 92 under
development and before the release of
the pc game are there good practices for
making sure that a game will work on end
user's machine and not get bugs caused
by users hardware no not really so i can
say that at least one thing for us at
molly is since this is our first release
on our first game release that we're
doing and it's entirely custom the
engine is completely custom we will
almost certainly do early access not for
any other reason then we need the
hardware testing so you know our game
may be completely done but we will
almost certainly still release on early
access to get a certain amount of beta
testing before we officially call it a
release because we're going to need that
now maybe we'll figure out a different
way to do it maybe we'll figure out a
way to test without that but we'll need
something like that we'll need some way
to release something that's a hardware
test that people can run in report bugs
to because we don't want a really be in
a situation where our day one release
has tons of hardware bugs because you
know people's crazy hardware has weird
things we have to work around or
whatever right so yeah I don't have a
good solution that problem the only
thing I think that a indie developer can
really do is release something as a test
whether that's a full early access build
of your game or maybe that's like a
little executable you post for free on
your website that runs basically the
game without the actual game like the
assets aren't there or whatever but it
kind of runs the basic stuff and then
has users like test it and say yes this
work for me or no it didn't so that you
can start to build up that understanding
of where the bugs are so we're going to
try to do something like that and like I
said I don't feel like there's really
any substitute for it at the moment at
least not for any developer maybe if
you're a massive L poor you could just
buy every machine that comes out every
year and spend you know a hundred
thousand dollars a year just buying
computers and have a giant testing lab
and run them but even that I feel like
might not be enough
because it's not always the hardware
that's the buddies can also be the
software like Oh someone installed adobe
acrobat and it's taking twenty-five
percent of the sea for you all the time
and your gain runs really poorly you
need to find that out and you need to be
able to post a thing that's like hey
users if your game is running slowly see
if adobe acrobat is running and kill it
like that's something you couldn't have
known just by testing hardware because
the hardware may be fine but this but
you know the 20,000 Bing toolbars and
the whatever the user has installed a
machine might be the problem and you you
have to find that out to right and
that's not something that a hardware lab
could really tell you pragma script do
you have to go to the steam greenlight
process and steam for your game do you
think it's a good idea we do not have to
go through the street in my process for
our game we already got our game
approved but do I think it's a good idea
I don't know I don't spend a lot of time
on steam greenlight in fact I guess I
don't spend any time at some green light
so I don't know very much about it it
seems to me like valve is pretty
generous with approving games these days
so I feel like Steam greenlight they
accept larger swathes than they used to
so I feel like if you have to go the
green light route to get your game
approved I suspect it's probably a lot
easier now than it used to be just
because they approve a whole lot more
games that said I don't really know much
about it so I couldn't give you any
specific advice Gary Johansson if you
had an easy way to write whatever code
you wanted on the GPU would you write
your own renderer and never use open
jail again yes I would and that's what
Larabee was supposed to be and I wish
that project had succeeded but it didn't
because I would really love to never
have to use a graphics API again the
jello so all the huge updates i get to
see have on steam or dev faults like 35
gigabytes over 35 gigabytes of clean
install do you know what was the one
gigabyte update of TW for i was
wondering why it was so huge so early um
so first of all I'll say like I said I
don't know with all the huge update
second you could have on seem our
developers faults they might be but they
might not be like I said I I just I'll
have more to say about that once I
actually look at the actual steam
distribution stuff but I don't think
they made any bugs as bad as the one
that I described where the whole thing
always has to be updated I think you can
patch things a little bit more grandly
than that but I don't know so someday
I'll I'll have more to say about that
when I actually have to go through it as
for the witness the one gigabyte update
for the witness may actually have been
legitimate because I think they did a
ton of video stuff that was actually
like had to get added in so I think I
think that may have been love it I but I
don't know yes asked John I'm not
involved in that process at all so it
may it may have been sloppiness it may
have been legitimate I couldn't tell you
I don't know I I don't even know yeah I
have no idea keeper Caleb how do you
feel about drm schemes like de nouveaux
that take considera- cpu time during
gameplay and add two hardest rights
which is bad for ssds like i said i
don't have any particular opinions about
a given DRM scheme I think they are all
a bad idea it's just dear M is just a
bad idea I don't like it I don't think
we should use it elvin I was just
curious in my question how some games
know if the player is playing a
legitimate versus cracked version where
they cranked the difficulty level and
make it impossible for a cracked version
to beat they use some sort of DLL
versioning signature or dot dot so it
depends a lot on the particular scheme
right uh but there's there's tons and
they date back you know as far back as
as some of the earliest home computer
games right so usually what happens is
they do something which is very hard to
detect when you disassemble the game and
takes a long time to find but that what
is substantively something that you can
still reverse-engineer around
and patch because obviously anything
running on a machine someone can reverse
engineer and then patch to remove the
drm so all DRM is breakable in that
sense because if you don't have hardware
assistance then there's nothing you can
do right so usually a good example would
be lets say the game comes on a well
let's say the game uses the net for
example so you have to have internet
connection to play it and what it might
do is send out a request to a server and
those requests are something that you
know it like a 1k of what appears to be
random data and the server sends back 1k
of what appears to be random data and
the game checks that 1k of rana data to
see if it's correct right because it has
some idea of how those things should be
matched and then assuming that it is it
continues playing right now obviously
you can imagine doing this in such a way
that it would be impossible for any
attacker to actually know what the 1k
responses should be right because let's
say I took something like the 1k I send
it out like like a public private key
encryption scheme right so let's say I
take 1k of data on the client side I
encrypt it with the private SR with the
public key for a server I sent to the
server the server sends me back a
version right encrypted with a you know
a different private public key or
something that I can decrypt with the
private key or something like that right
so the client side has two keys in it
that it can use to encrypt and receive
things from the server but the two other
corresponding keys well I guess you
don't you know you really wouldn't need
two keys now I think about it you would
pretty much only need yeah you really to
be honest you only actually need the one
key you just need the one coming back
from the server so i send 1k of random
data the server encrypts it with its
private key and sends it back I take my
public key for the server and I decrypt
it and I see if it's what I expect if
it's not I know the user has a is
cheating or something right
doesn't have a legitimate account or
whatever it is right and so in those
cases right if you start to hack it out
then typically like if it's really
trivial and I just do this one check you
know what let me just throw this out
because it's really generic so the way
this generally works right is you have
something that's the check right you
have a thing that's the check and what
the check does is something that's hard
for the user to duplicate so that one
that I was talking about we're like i
sensing after server and it comes back
and it has to be the right answer or I
don't keep going right that's one
example but another one like in the old
times when there was physical media they
used to do stuff like you'd have you
know the the disk would have some region
on it and that region of the disk would
have an intentional defect that you
could not reproduce when you burned your
own disk so it's like something that
would not happen normally we'd have a
defect on it that when you read it it
would read into it could read in either
way so you know maybe it's a thing where
it's like if you read it one time you
get 1 1 0 1 1 0 1 1 or something like
this right but if you read it a second
time you get 1 0 1 1 0 1 1 0 right well
now you've created something where the
game can see if you're reading off a
legitimate DVD right by just reading
that part of the DVD many times and
making sure that it gets back more than
one answer for the same sector of the
DVD right you turn off OS caching read
the DVD multiple times and you should
get back different answers right so
there's some kind of a check that's hard
for the user to duplicate this would be
very hard for you to duplicate right
because they'd have to make a DVD with
an intentional defect that work this way
right so you have to do that and then
you better check now the check is
something that in the game code you do
you call the check right you say hey
check this thing it does whatever that
test is and it comes back with a
positive or negative answer right yes
it's a valid version no it's not okay so
then you can just say well if the check
comes back you know true do this thing
if the check comes back false do this
thing and there's your there's your drm
right here's the case for the the valve
and here's the case for the invalid you
can do whatever you want you can crash
the game you can make it harder you can
do whatever you want right now the
problem with this is that this is a
giant like bullseye for the hacks or who
comes around and wants to crack your
game right so the cracker comes in they
know what you're going to try so they
look for things that read the DVD
whatever they disassemble the code they
find it back they track it back to this
if statement and go oh alright they've
got this if on the check so I'll just go
ahead and do whatever men do right I'll
just patch over this to be an if one
instead and it just works right so now
you don't need it the game is cracked
we're done so really what happens now
this is the way dear I'm used to work
like in the old days like Connor 64 days
right this would have been a floppy disk
here but basically the same thing where
you do the check then you have your path
for valid your paths or invalid or
whatever right and in valve is usually
just don't load well this part here you
want to make it much harder for that
cracker to know where that is so now
what people do is the actual source code
for the game is like littered with
things that are interwoven with the
checking so instead of a giant bullseye
there's just like one if that's like is
it legal or not right it's all
throughout the code there's like
dependencies on that and checking in
multiple places and you know try to
delay and repeat the checks and weird
ways that it's very hard to disassemble
and find right so basically you're sort
of doing essentially a meta code process
over the game where you're distributing
the check and dependencies on the check
all interwoven throughout the code so
that's very very hard for the cracker to
know that they've got them all and
that's also why they do stuff like
instead of just failing to load the game
they make it so you have to play the
game and see if it's actually completa
below that makes it much harder for that
cracker to know whether they've
succeeded right so that's how that stuff
works now what they do the part that I
don't know is these days I don't know
what they use for the check obviously
they don't use a DVD check anymore
because oftentimes games don't come on
DVDs so that doesn't happen
but yeah
so I think we're basically out of time
so anyone who has questions you might
want to I you might want to wait or
remember them it's that make sense let's
see if there's any other quick ones
so some of these I think there are some
good questions in here so i would say
folks save these questions for tomorrow
and and we will take them there they're
pretty good question so I'll take them
on stream tomorrow and I'm gonna I'm
going to call it a day so if you didn't
get your question answered some of those
were good questions I have to come back
tomorrow we will we will take a look at
some of those because yeah there's some
good stuff in there alright thank you
everyone for joining me for another
episode of handmade hero and a pleasure
coding with you as always if you want to
hang out with us again we're on our SI
break right now so no typing but if you
would like to hang out with us for more
game dev chat you can just go ahead and
come back here tomorrow 530 same time
and we will be back here if you get
confused just go to handmade here org
and you can push this little tweets
button and also this little nothing
scheduled thing if you refresh the page
usually it'll say like right now it says
live now if i refresh it when if i
refresh it sometime when I'm not on
it'll usually have a little countdown
timer that'll say you know what it is
but there's also the tweet bot and if
you check out the tweet bot you can see
besides Twitter's lovely advertisements
you can see like there'll be a schedule
and then little reminders so you can
always subscribe to the handmade hero
tweetbot and that will keep you up to
date so but you never have to worry so
there's that hope to see you guys
tomorrow it's been good hanging out as
always if you are programming this
evening have a good programming have
some good programming tomorrow and i'll
see you on the stream tomorrow at five
thirty PSD take it easy everyone