hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show that we code a complete
game live on stream we took a week off
because I was fairly dejected after last
week's stream where not only did visual
studio break but n site also broke and
the installation of the drivers that
insight requested not only broke the
program we were trying to use but also
broke our old ability news insights so
everything was in complete shambles now
amusingly enough
not only have I had Microsoft contact me
back when I filled out that survey on
stream about what they could do to fix
Visual Studio I seriously doubt that
much will get fixed and Visual Studio
because it's not the first time
Microsoft has asked me and so I don't
think it'll be the first time that they
ignore me but this time around
Nvidia also contacted me about the
problems with insight they were very
nice about it and apologetic and they
asked me if I could try doing a couple
things because they weren't sure they
were understanding what was happening
they actually looked at the crash dumps
which is more than I can say for
Microsoft and they were saying that the
crash was occurring in a call to wiggle
get proc address and it was occurring
inside the old driver now this is very
unusual I don't really understand it
because it shouldn't be occurring inside
the old driver since we installed the
new one in the new one said it completed
but it raises the question about whether
their installer was messed up and maybe
something where it happened
so at the beginning of today's stream I
would like to do them the courtesy of
gathering some information for them
because in my opinion if someone is
willing to help get the development
environment working then I am more than
happy to help them and hope that they
can so I'm gonna go ahead and just take
a look at some of those things they
asked me to take a look at and see if we
can figure out any more information
about what actually happened they
downloaded the source to handmade hero
and we're only able to reproduce it so
again like I said the nvidia team
definitely taking an interest and really
trying to fix things which i feel like
they should be commended for I really do
appreciate
that someone took the time to try and
figure out what was going wrong so let's
see if we can give them some information
to help here I'm gonna click on system
information here so I'm able to verify
at least as far as the control panel is
concerned that the driver version is in
fact the one that we thought was
installed so I'm not sure what's
happening on their ends or why they're
seeing that crash report reporting as
being in the old driver because it does
seem like the new driver at least is the
one that's happening here now one thing
that could have happened is maybe the
machine has rebooted since then maybe it
didn't take the first time maybe it took
now so maybe let me try running our
program again let's verify that it still
crashes send them another crash dump
hopefully that is at least a second
benchmark point and then they also said
installing the driver clean might help
maybe there was something that got left
on there they couldn't tell because
again they said they weren't really sure
why it was getting a report from the old
driver version because of course they
could see on stream that we installed
the new one so again I have no idea what
was going on there right so let's go
ahead and try hand-made here again this
is the thing we made for it now
presumably
if unless it was the case that the old
you know that there was a reboot or
something that that helped fix it in
this case what we should see is the same
crash again if we don't then it fixed
itself but no it's definitely crashing
let me go ahead and tag this here this
is a crash report with the Nvidia
control panel affirmatively confirming
that we are on 1903 90 101 I think that
was what it was what it was and we just
double check that don't want to
accidentally send them the wrong number
3:9 101 so hopefully they can take a
look at that and tell us what's going on
there I don't really know I don't know
if save meanie dump is something that's
worth doing here so I'm just gonna do it
and initial or let's say this is mini
dump zero zero right that way if they
need these mini dumps I don't know if
the send report sends the mini dump I
assume it does so I don't think we need
to save that but I don't know how their
crash reporting tool works so figure
better safe than sorry
all right so now that we know that
that's what's happening again we can try
just a couple simple things I'm going to
go ahead and reboot the system with a
clean install of the driver and we'll
see if that helps again I'm assuming
that it won't but we don't really know
right so let's go ahead and try that I
did when we installed it the first time
I did save just perhaps prophetically
the driver installation that we used so
if I double click on this here and we go
ahead and let it run here is the the 391
oh one driver just getting installed
fresh this time I'll do the exact same
install that I did but I will go ahead
and click on the clean install button
hopefully that will wipe everything else
off of the machine that might have been
on here that could still be causing some
kind of a weird old driver compat load
thing I don't really know how they were
getting a crash jump from 388 it seems
kind of unlikely but you know I don't
know how their system works so maybe
there's some explanation for that that I
can't fathom right
Coffee time there are very few things in
the world better than coffee I just like
to point that out one of the things that
I figured out kind of later in life I'll
a second let me make sure we check that
perform clean installation we don't need
any of this stuff so I think just those
two and clean installation that should
wipe everything and we should be left
with only a 391 driver and the HD audio
driver which we need for the streaming
setup and I go hit next and office
should go one of the things I noticed is
like coffee for me is sort of like it's
definitely like a psychoactive drug in a
sense I mean obviously it is for
everybody but the same sort of effects
that like ADHD people or whatever say
they get from like rid winter adderall
or things like this I totally get from
drinking just a little bit of coffee as
far as I can tell
so like the difference between me
drinking coffee once a day just like one
or two shots of espresso so like like a
hundred milligrams a hundred ish
milligrams of coffee let's of caffeine
let's say per day the difference in my
level of product on a concentrated task
is nuts
like it's just massively different I
think I probably would have scored like
much higher on my SATs for example if I
had just drink and some drank some
coffee before taking them I it's kind of
funny like the difference is kind of
massive and it's generally because like
when I when I my brain kind of has two
modes and they're sort of controlled by
coffee like one is very whimsical and
imaginative and one is like can be more
concrete and focused on technical
details and coffee generally picks which
one of those I'm in or I should say
caffeine in this case I suppose
and so in a lot of cases wait did that
just kill me so this has killed my
monitor is off now my monitor it didn't
it only came back on the HDMI output
I suppose that's fine I will go ahead
and just use the other one but you're
gonna lose audio in a second so I'm
gonna stop talking because when this
closes the
you
hello can you hear me now
all right so um that was a clean install
in all possible ways like everything was
removed so it's about as clean as it
gets and so we now have an installation
it was running Microsoft basic display
driver before now it's running 3 9 101
right and I'm going to try to install
insight graphics which is this right
here
and this is the best we can do we can't
do anything better than this it's a
clean install we verify the driver
number and so if it crashes this time I
got nothing I don't know what's going on
because there's really nothing else we
can do beyond that I don't know what
this is right here
doesn't seem like I can get rid of it
Microsoft has decided that you cannot
unpin this from the taskbar
dear Microsoft maybe you're confused
about what unpin from tasks are means
Believe It or Not unpin from taskbar
doesn't mean leave it on the taskbar
just like it was before I love I love
this do you want to allow this app to
make changes to your device
9b 7 6 DMS I like of course the average
user is going to be well aware of the
security implications of Microsoft
asking them if 9 B 7 6 DMS I should be
given permission to make changes to the
device they just make me laugh so hard
with their ridiculous security security
stuff would you like to allow a program
you don't recognize to do something we
won't tell you what it is yes or no
Windows is such a pile all right so we
have now reinstalled insight graphics at
least in theory unfortunately the old
insight graphics thing is super confused
I don't know how we got I don't know
what's going on here I'm ok there we go
finally got it removed so hopefully now
we can use the existing insight graphics
thing I'm gonna go ahead and make our
drive as we normally do there's our
handmade hero directory so we're back in
business now I'm gonna go ahead and do
insight let's go ahead and launch the
insight graphics tool we'd probably have
to remake this oh no we don't so it
saved this in some place that the
uninstall didn't remove so I can load it
again let's launch it and see how we go
all right so we now have our insight
working which means that something did
in fact go wrong with their installer
they just don't know what I don't know
what to make of that necessarily since
obviously the it would be nice if it got
fixed but I suppose at this point they
don't necessarily have the information
they would need to fix it which I
suppose is a bit of an issue
but it does look like our insight is
working so that's good I'm not actually
100% sure what we will do with insight
here at the moment I don't think we have
an immediate use for it we just wanted
to install it and now it is installed so
that's good I assume that we can now do
all the things that we wanted to do with
I don't know what happened here we have
crashed or something
I'm not sure what's going on there so it
looks like maybe we can't exit properly
possibly that's not really a problem
like I don't really care if that's a bug
or whatever there may be something we're
doing on termination that's bad
or maybe something we're not doing we
were fussing with this a little bit
trying to working so it's entirely
possible that that we just need to fix
something that we're doing busted there
but it looks like we can run just fine
but yeah when I hit up Altaf or maybe
it's just breaking into this for some
reason like maybe it just stops on exit
by like maybe that's just what it does
you know I don't I don't really know cuz
we've never used this tool before maybe
that's expected right so if we take a
look in here it looks like it's pretty
good like it's got all our stuff so
that's nice right these are our shaders
that we define in code so it's it's gone
ahead and laid the map for us which is
kind of nice
that's pretty sweet we presumably can
analyze some part of the pipeline if we
stop and capture a frame so maybe let's
go ahead and do that I'm gonna go ahead
and run this again is there just a run
like a command to run I guess they call
it connect so if I go ahead and run it
here what is what is that
control shift see looks like what that
is
all right so if I hit ctrl shift C to
bring this up then I can hit launch
there should be like an automatic launch
I feel like but at least this is working
here in theory now if I just do capture
for live analysis presumably it will
capture a frame in the same way that it
used to with the plugin for visual
studio I don't actually know but we'll
see it's it seems like it's trying to
anyway it's working on it all right
and so it looks to me like this is
basically the same as the plug-in only
thankfully it's outside of Visual Studio
now which kind of makes it a lot easier
for us to use so I'm pretty happy about
that it also looks like maybe this is a
little bit better than the one we had
maybe because they've upgraded since
then or maybe we have using an old
version of plug-in I don't know but it
looks a little bit more full-featured
and having it full view is kind of nice
as well but this is kind of nice and you
can see here this is this is pretty
great actually you can see all of our
calls just in a big old stream which is
great and you can also see like I mean
you know we talked about this but you
can see remember I've said very many
times we kind of need to use a texture
we need to do some texture packing if
you want to be efficient you can see how
inefficient this is right you see all
these draw by and draw by and draw Brian
nonsense right like you don't want to do
that and you can see it happening right
here as a very simple example right so
it's kind of nice I mean let's say we
didn't know that you know like maybe we
just haven't thought it through or
whatever you know it's kind of again
it's just a nice thing to have utility
like this where you can just see it now
it's pretty obvious to you what you're
doing right you can just see this in be
like oh I didn't realize how many of
those you were issuing or something
right so again like you know we kind of
know some of the things that we're doing
wrong so maybe that's not as useful here
but you can imagine a lot of
circumstances where especially in more
complicated graphics pipelines you
wouldn't have known all the things that
you might have been doing wrong or weird
patterns that may have emerged so it's
kind of nice be able to look at them
that way as well so you can kind of see
here the frame we can scrub through it I
guess right and I don't know what it's
decided to color code these bars as it
looks like maybe when you stop
hitting 30 frames a second it gets read
uh but I'm not sure look I don't know
what green blue and red are does it say
not really so we've got some learning to
do here because we don't actually
necessarily know what these things are
again one nice thing about this too is
it looks like if we scroll through these
we can see what the frame would be so
that's pretty cool right like we can say
oh let's go you know back here or
something and it looks ups looks like we
can sort of pop through the draw calls
and see where we were drawing you know
which is pretty nice as well
blah blah blah and then this we're
pretty familiar with like we've seen
this before we kind of played with it
before but it looks like it's all there
from the previous one which is nice and
we can look at the different textures
and so on right
so here's a one of our buffers and so
this is probably one of our deaf people
buffers right and so again this I feel
like this is pretty cool this will let
us see a lot more about what we were
trying to do there this looks like so
this is our third game's window and it
looks like we've got a bunch of options
here as well so in the game's window
itself it looks like we're able to do a
little bit of inspection here like if we
want to keep running like we do it looks
like we can stop at any time I'm not
sure what this allows us to do here know
what zoom does so that zoom looks like
let's take a look at the frame maybe I
can't quite tell it's not very
responsive in here so I'm not sure like
the cursor doesn't really seem to work
americo's I think maybe it was just
capturing maybe I don't really know yeah
because the cursor seems to work now oh
I see software cursor hardware cursor
so yeah this is pretty great right like
here's the start of the frame you can
see us like building it up right and now
we're building up the death feel and now
we're building up to the last depth peel
right and then we do our composite of
the depth peels and then we're drawing
those guys in there I don't know if we
can manipulate this in three dimensions
probably not I know maybe we can change
wireframe mode if you rent arced up
stencil texture and normalization
options export capture so I mean yeah
like I don't know we are neophytes at
the tool at the moment so I can't really
say much more about it but it sure looks
nice right I mean there's a lot of stuff
here that we could use and that's just a
really great when we go to fine start
you know cleaning up our graphics
pipeline which after the lighting pretty
much there's nothing else going into it
we may want to play with the particle
systems a little bit I think is the only
other thing that we might want to kind
of go back and revisit quickly because
we never really quite put much in there
you know this you can see why this would
be really handy right because it allows
us to really take a good close look at
what we're actually doing and it makes
it just a lot easier to see bugs or a
room for improvement as we go right and
it also kind of lets you see what like
those def peels look like so we don't
have to like put in lots of Moe's to
view them and again that's exactly what
you really want a debugger to do the
whole point of a debugger because you
could always debug without a debugger
but the whole point of the debugger is
to save you time by quickly giving you
access to information that would
otherwise cost you development time to
get right and so this is kind of nice
it's just a really fluid it's pretty
responsive after it captures the frame
as well so I would say good on NVIDIA so
it looks like the primary problem was
their installer must have some issues we
don't know what those issues are
fortunately I guess they won't haunt us
again for the time being because we can
just stay with this but yeah something's
up
with the install and we don't really
know what it is but point being where
we're now good to go I hopefully won't
need my little message board any further
but this is good if I pin this guy to
the taskbar now we should be able to go
ahead and get graphics debugging going
when we need it which I'm sure we will
in the near future all right
I'll save this mini dump in case they
want it but than that I think we're good
here okay
so let's see Oh
internal static void is saying you have
to close it in insight so I guess that's
someone confirming the thing that I have
was hypothesizing about how you can't
close the program outside of insight
because when you close it it will hold
it open it looks like so that's probably
just so that you can close and inspect
sort of endgame stuff or something
similar to that all right
so someone was asking can you summarize
how the issue is fixed so basically
complete uninstall and reinstall of all
the Nvidia stuff is what fixed it but we
don't know exactly what it was that's
just what they were recommending so
there must have been some kind of a
cross crufty situation I don't know
exactly what it was so let's go ahead
and load up our handmade hero stuff now
that we've taken care of that
and I did that okay so back to our
regularly scheduled program non graphics
to plugging addition so where we were at
is pretty simple we had done a bunch of
optimization work on the lighting and
honestly I think the lighting was
getting to a pretty nice place and what
we were trying to figure out was if we
could get rid of cosine weighted
sampling in our system by just waiting
our samples proportional to the cosine
in the first place and this is just a
standard sampling technique that's used
pretty often and essentially what it
does is it prevents you from it prevents
you from using a lot of your sample
samples simply to get a known
distribution that you already are saying
are there one way to look at it would be
that we know that every term in our
summation of the inbound lighting for a
particular point e is multiplied by
cosine theta what that means is that if
we just blindly do random sampling of
say the Hemisphere and we look at that
Hemisphere and say okay
each one of the things that comes in is
getting multiplied by cosine theta
essentially what we're doing is we're
integrating two things we're integrating
cosine theta whose integral we just know
right we're treating cosine theta and
we're integrating the actual lighting
that's coming in right and so what we'd
rather do is take the cosine theta
integration out of the picture and just
say look we know that we're gonna
integrate cosine theta into this let's
just put the samples in a pattern that
already waits by cosine theta and that
way we don't have to take account of
that term and we should converge faster
on a good solution because we're
concentrating our samples in places that
will be highly weighted rather than
concentrating our samples in places
where they won't be highly weighted
which also just helps get a better
answer with less samples and so that's
what we're doing right now this what
we're actually seeing on the screen at
the moment in fact
if I go ahead and bring this up to full
screen what we're seeing on screen at
the moment is literally just the version
with no cosine waiting where we have
adjusted the samples to be sort of
cosine weighted but one of the things
that we noticed when we did this is we
got significantly more light than we
would have gotten when we were using the
system before we had had a sample that
was we had a version that was waiting by
cosign samples and was using a pure
random distribution and we didn't see
anything we didn't see equivalent
amounts of light and so I am a little
concerned about the accuracy of that and
whether or not we need to concentrate
our samples in the slightly different
ways or whether we've got some kind of a
problem in there where we're not quite
right unfortunately the number of
samples we're taking is so low that we
can't really count and converge in the
first place so it's not necessarily
clear to me that we're really doing
anything wrong so much as just being
inaccurate which we already knew was the
case because let's face it we're trying
to simulate lighting with not a whole
lot of samples and we know that that's
just not really strictly possible right
so what I'd like to do now is take a
look at how we can sort of wrap up the
lighting to be maybe to just finish up
with it and move on and the reason for
that is that it's starting to be pretty
good like I'm actually lighting the
liking the way the Lighting's working I
feel like a lot of what we have on the
screen right now just looks really cool
to me like I'm really liking the way
that it feels and it seems like you know
a system that's that's fairly reasonable
there's a couple of things we may want
to do to kind of get it maybe into a
more shippable state for example one of
the things that we're not doing right
now that we could do is we don't have a
light distribution prepass so for
example right now we only do gathering
right and the fact that we only do
gathering may cause certain
circumstances like in the case of these
tiny lights
that are on the little hoppers here may
cause those to get undersampled now it
doesn't really look like it's causing
much of a problem because it does look
like we're getting a lot of light coming
from those tiny lights so it might be
that we're just fine and we don't need
to worry about it but like for example
these walls I don't know how much light
they're really picking up from these
guys here
maybe compared to what they should be
picking up because again it's hard to
hit little lights with these rays and so
one thing that you could imagine is
putting a little bit of a bias into the
system where we do a pre pass on things
that we know are illumination sources
that we want to emphasize again it's
just straight-up cheating but it's
something that lets us ensure that
elements that we know are emitters get a
little more attention we can do that we
don't have to do that you know maybe we
want to just remain pure and just say
look that's not the goal of the system I
don't know so we can do stuff like that
another thing that we need to do is
think about the performance a little bit
we've gotten it to a pretty good place
but we can probably do a little bit more
there so cleaning that up and making
sure that's compact and then finally
they're really the biggest thing that I
think we really want to do is figure out
a way to make the interpolation of the
lighting be a little bit more coherent
and so what I'd like to do is when we do
our world-building for example we need
to be able to do something where we're
going to use intelligent neighborhoods
of samples to produce the final lighting
and so what I'd like to do there is we
want to start looking at how we're doing
our lighting interpolation and we want
to make our lighting interpolation be
more of a focus so you know previously
all the stuff we were working on for the
most part was entirely based on
computing the lighting at sample points
and that's what we've been working on
the whole time we haven't spent any time
working on how we interpolate the
lighting after we stopped trying the
voxel stuff we haven't really gone and
paid attention to that now that we have
a good way to sample the lighting so I
think that's what I want to move on to
now and so the the two main areas to
focus well first will do that so we'll
try to get a good and we'll get
final looking thing and then we'll just
move on to a few more performance
optimization work sorts of stuff to make
sure that we can run this in real time
reasonably and right now we don't really
do that I think we're a little
overweight because this is a fast system
and so if this system can't run it
handily then we're gonna have problems
because some people will want to run
handmade here on slower systems than
this one
even when handmade hero is finally out
you know this might be a example of a
system that's a medium specification but
it's still you know it's not fast enough
right it's got to be faster than this so
yeah that's what we've got to do but
other than that I'm really liking it I
mean I think the lighting I think we did
a good job we went into it not having
any idea how we would do lighting in
this world and I think we came a wave
with a pretty cool system that does
captures a lot of interesting effects I
mean I love what's going on here right
you get this kind of blue lighting from
from bouncing off the walls here and you
get some nice little red kick back there
which is a blue red kick back and like
as you move across you know if you watch
what happens here you can kind of see
the red kick back change it's just it's
really nice I mean it adds a lot of
character to the scene and health make
it feel more like a nighttime scene this
game is supposed to take place at night
and so a lot of kind of light and dark
kinds of contrasts I think it really
helps make you feel like you're part of
that situation so like I said I think I
think we've done a good job what I want
to focus on now I think is to ping pong
away from the actual letting computation
for a little bit we'll come back to it
to sort of finalize it but get back into
interpolation and you know another
reason we want to do that is because you
take a look here and you've got like say
these trees we have to light those as
well and again that doesn't change the
lighting equations at all it just means
we need some way of applying the
lighting like to our sprites and so on
and so there's a lot of stuff like that
we want to be able to do and and you
know we want to insert fake lighting
objects where the trees are for example
that will catch light they're all that
sort of stuff
we want to be able to do and we really
just haven't thought that part through
because for the most part we've just
been working on the light simulation
part which admittedly is the hardest
part of the problem but now we Kurt sort
of have just the finicky part which is
the bookkeeping how do we go from our
scene to an understanding of where the
light needs to be collected and what the
occluders are and then from that
solution back map it back to how does
everything want to be interpolated so
since it's our first day back after kind
of a big upset there let's just take it
easy let's take a quick gander at our
OpenGL code we've got our shader here
which is the shader for the Z bias
program which is the program that
basically does everything for our basic
rendering and what you can see this is
the vertex shader what you can see here
is in the pixel shader is we have this
sunlight function and what the Sun line
function does is it reads in a light
count loops over the count of the lights
that it needs to sample and it
integrates them right it basically says
like okay well integrates the wrong word
that's the mathematical term I shouldn't
use that it blends them together based
on their distance so if I've got a few
different light sample points that are
being considered for this particular
surface what I'm doing is I'm reading in
each light sample point and then I am
saying okay that light sample point is
getting used in this way right and so
you can see here it's taking the
distance to the light sample point it's
using that distance as a way of
determining how it wants the light
sample to be computed so you can see
here for example it says all right I'm
gonna take the light distance X the
light distance Y those are both encoded
in the FSR the light Direction X
electrician Y those are both encoded I'm
going to take the direction Z get that
once I have that I know which direction
coming from I already have the position
of the light it's in it's mentioned here
here I compute the distance from the
light to the place in the world that I
am rendering which allows me to know how
to wait those light fall offs and then
here I do the basically the fall off
with the normal so I can tell based on
the lighting direction that's being
specified here what my surface direction
is versus that gives me the other
fall-off term and then I combine those
together to get my final term right so
that's what we're doing here and there's
a lot of ways that we might want to
reconsider how this is working so what's
our main goal well our main goal is to
take a scattered set of lighting samples
that we are computing because we know we
can't compute the light at every pixel
because you saw how expensive it is to
complete the lighting in general so
we're trying to take a scattered set of
lighting samples and take those and
recombine them into something that
allows us to shade our scene now there
was a couple of ways that we could do
this but they all have their kind of
drawbacks
we started off trying a voxel based
scheme where everybody who wanted to do
lighting would look up into the voxel
and see what their lighting should have
been you know based on where they were
in the voxel grid I didn't love that
system because it really ended up making
the lighting be kind of to diffuse
almost and it creates problems where
you're trying to figure out kind of what
yeah it's just hard to figure out how to
make sense of such a sparse grid of
lighting data and by necessity a voxel
has to be pretty sparse three
dimensional data can't be very dense if
it is it rapidly overwhelms memory and
processing power because three
dimensions is a cubed problem right it
doesn't take a very high dimension
number for something cube to become
intractable quickly something squared is
pretty bad something cubed is even worse
and so that's why it seemed like that
would probably be a bad idea
so what we decided to go with instead
is a system whereby everybody in the
game kind of knows what lighting sample
points they're actually using and those
lighting sample points are kind of
inferred back so any given element knows
which lighting samples it should
consider when it's reconstructing its
lighting now this has positive and
negative aspects the positive aspects is
we can have complete control when we
create a scene to place lighting sample
points and then gather them for our
surfaces the problem that we'll have
there is that we can't handle dynamic
entities as well as we might like to and
we're gonna have to figure out how we
want to account for that problem so
let's go to the blackboard for a minute
and see I could use some could use some
liquid holo second I want to see if
there's any liquid available
it turns out there is mm-hmm
I do have some sufficiently watered down
lemonade which will be perfect for this
sorry my throat was getting real dry too
much talking
alright um bring up Milton here and this
is going to be oh you know what we lost
our little day number because we had to
reboot the system and it's not in the
startup sequence so let's try that again
mmm is it for 42 is it for free to me
blow bud no may blow what day is today
for Fright - for free - so essentially
what I'm talking about here is you know
we've got things like a wall and what I
would like to do is place sample points
on the wall in like this kind of a
fashion right so rather than placing
four sample points per plate
I would rather place to sample points
along the seam instead of two on either
side of the seam for each plate right
and then I would like these two sort of
interpolate together you know that
that'd be my my my preference now
there's a number of reasons why this
might be a problem but I think that
generally speaking if we create worlds
like and have the world's just kind of
work like this I think we'll get away
with it most of the time so I think what
we can do is when we're creating our
stuff you know we know the game will
know when it creates a continuous wall
and it'll just place lighting points
along the wall you know like this if
this is top down right if I'm creating a
dungeon area like this sort of thing
right and it'll just know to place the
lighting points like this and then it'll
just you know assign this face to these
four this face to those four and so on
so essentially what we want for all of
our scenery is the ability to share
these lighting points in that fashion
right I think that's what we basically
want to have happen and so what we want
to do is tune our ability to specify
levy points in that way now I think that
will work
it'll take a little bit of
finesse to make sure that we do it just
right so there it's you know there's a
little bit of finesse involved in making
that work efficiently I'm guessing what
we'll probably do because I don't think
we want to use a lot of indirection in
the pixel shaders is we'll probably do a
forward copy pass so it actually
probably you know probably be more like
having these points be in an array where
there are four unique points and then
four more unique points so this plate is
reading from those and this place
reading from those and probably what
will happen is I'll just be one forward
pass at the before we start running the
scene that copies the result from save
these two and the you know the lighting
system will only compute two points and
it'll broadcast those results out to the
more complete texture right so I think
something like that will probably happen
to avoid using lots of indirection in
our shader which wouldn't probably be be
great so I think that part is pretty
reasonable so for our flat walls I don't
think we're gonna have a huge problem I
think we can make that work fairly
cleanly and we'll see how it goes
what is more troubling to me is the
individual elements running around in
here so for example you know we've got a
couple different things we've got those
trees right that are in the game and
then we've got like the hero who's in
the game you know and so the question is
how do we light them appropriately you
know how do we how do we deal with that
and to my mind probably what we want to
do right we need to put an occluder in
so we need to put a synthetic one of our
light blockers in there and that's
probably gonna have one plate and one
sample point you know per direction so I
probably be like six sample points and
six phases for occlusion right and yeah
so that'll be six sample points and six
phases for occlusion and those faces for
occlusion will just be there to make it
so that things get dimmer where people
are standing right which is what we want
to have happened right there they're
taking light out of the system at that
location and the thing that I want to
focus on then is so once we figure out
what's going on with that once we figure
out what these lighting values are we
then need to write those lighting values
into something that can be used to light
one of our sprites and so at first I
think probably what we'd want to do is
just light the sprite by using these
lighting values to just like maybe just
pick this one and use it at first or you
know or average these together like this
one this one in this one or whatever and
then eventually if we ever have normal
maps for our sprites for example we
could use the normal map to figure out
which direction we're closest to and
blend between them that way sort of use
this almost like a cube map with one
pixel per face right so that's probably
what we'd want to do for those and the
only thing that worries me about that is
the number of them that we're gonna have
because it really increases our
occlusion level pretty dramatically and
you know yeah I mean I just I I don't
know how problematic that's gonna be in
terms of proliferating and number of
occluders that we actually have in the
system but the point I'm trying to get
to there is you as you can kind of see
there's two very different oops
as I drop that there's two very
different types of things going on there
and we have to kind of think about how
we want those to work now one of the
things that's particularly sort of one
of the things that's a little bit
questionable there is you know do we
actually want to do it that way or do we
want a sparser method or a different
method for lighting things because
for example one thing we could do is say
look we don't even consider movable
objects at all in the system so we're
shouldn't say movable objects we don't
consider sprites in the system at all
they just don't participate instead what
we do is we use like the lights and
letting points that are in the system at
wherever they're near and we map them to
those lighting points right so one
example would be let's suppose that we
took a rectangular area that represented
the world here and we just have you know
some trees around the outside like we do
right now or whatever's going on and
maybe there's a wall here in a wall here
like we have and we scatter some
lighting points around sort of the
general vicinity and those letting
points just go into a spatial hierarchy
that we pull from when we want to light
a particular person we know where they
are and we just grab the nearby lighting
points and assign those lighting points
to them right
so it's really just again another
another form of broadcast it's saying
look we're just gonna we're gonna
compute a standard distribution of
points for lighting throughout the scene
and that's all you know we're gonna do
and off we go so and that would work
fine with the system as we have it now
because right now our system has the
concept of a gather and that gather
doesn't have to be hemispherical we can
have spherical gather so we can have
points that are spherical gather points
that are just strewn throughout the
world that just gather what the lighting
is at that point and then you're done
right and maybe that's a smarter way to
do it because then we just have a fixed
number of points strewn throughout the
world and people hopping around in the
world just get lit by those points again
really don't know what the right way to
do it is I'm just hypothesizing here
some of the ways in which we could make
this work and I think that that the
justing thing the reason that that way
may be useful is because it doesn't
proliferate the number of things based
on how many entities are in the scene so
it's a fixed cost to do for any scene
whether you've got a hundred entities in
it or five entities in it and all your
paying different is just the space
you'll look up per entity to figure out
what points are nearby which isn't a
very hard thing to do by comparison to
throwing more and more points and
include errs into the system for every
entity so I you know that's that's about
all I can really say about that I don't
have super strong feelings about it one
way or the other it just sometimes it
behooves you to pick algorithms which
have a flat performance profile like
that because then you know once you get
them reasonable that's just the quality
level and performance of the algorithm
and you don't have to constantly be
worrying about it limiting your game
because the game now can't add a hundred
enemies to a scene because all of a
sudden you know the lighting will roll
over and die even if the rest of the
game systems would be just fine with a
hundred entities hopping around you've
introduced this really nasty dependency
on a really difficult problem that you
know you won't be able to improve so
that to me sort of argues in a gameplay
sense to avoid constricting what is
possible in the game and what we might
want to do there that does kind of
suggest for that sort of loose network
so I think you know putting all of that
out out there on the table I think
probably the way that I would look at it
is very specifically to say oh you know
what I just forgot to do by the way
I don't know how to start the session
again we're so far of our session
alright well we'll just leave it for now
I should have a thing that says like put
the little the little blocker up just
just do it so anyway you know I think
that just to me says okay
based on our experience of letting so
far we know it's hard we know that we
have to do a lot of approximations we
know that we can't throw in points ad
infinitum we can definitely speed it up
a lot more than it is now but but there
will be a limit to how much we can speed
it up and there also are quality
implications potentially involved in any
speed ups that we do so that to me says
maybe what I want to do is try to do
something where we just distribute out a
network of points hemispherical points
in spherical points potentially so we've
got two different kinds of points and
those points capture the lighting
information with the system that we have
currently and then we just do a
distribution broadcast out to the lookup
parts for every one of our elements in
the system and and off we go that's
that's all I got that's all I got for
you I don't know how you feel about it
but that's that's what I'm thinking and
so I'm gonna go ahead and try that I
think just let that be the first thing
that we kind of work with and I think to
a certain extent what that means is that
we can really simplify the way that
we're doing the lighting in the pixel
shader right now because if you think
about what that means we can probably
make it so that the lighting kind of
comes in in a much more coherent fashion
where it doesn't have to do scattered
interpolation which allow us to make our
pixel shader much faster and possibly
just path data at vertices and leave it
at that
right because as long as we interpolate
the lighting information rather than the
lighting solution across our triangles
we should be okay from there so I'm just
gonna hypothesize that all of the things
that I just said are true even though we
have no real
way of knowing whether they're true and
that's how we're going to proceed to try
and get down to a nice shippable
lighting solution that we can use for
our game and like I said I'm pretty
happy with where we ended up with that
it's kind of cool looking in my opinion
and I think it's gonna be pretty
interesting so what I'm talking about
here is basically inside this sunlight
function what I'm basically saying is
let's stop doing all of this nonsense
because it's just too complicated and
it's gonna cost us a lot of time in our
pixel shader and we really don't want to
spend a lot of time on our pixel shader
if at the end of the day we don't really
use that information as much right so
what I want to do instead is I want to
focus on a way to get this to be more
vertex based and so what I'm thinking
curious will basically take our vertices
and we'll pass in along with our
vertices will pass in the lighting
information at the vertices because
that's sort of how we're going to be
screwing them about and like I was
saying we just don't have the ability at
this point to really generate dense
enough lighting samples anyway to care
about getting letting samples in the
middle of triangles and stuff like that
so what I'd rather do is is figure out a
way to pass down something like that now
granted one thing that is true is saying
vertices is a little bit difficult
perhaps to process properly and the
reason that I say that is just because
well you know if you think about what's
happening in this environment you know
if I have two cubes next to each other
say like this when I'm drawing these
cubes the place where I want the
lighting samples is like here but the
vertices are actually here right
so it puts us in sort of a difficult
position because what it means is that
these are not really vertices so part of
the problem is we do sort of want to
pass additional information so that we
know how to do our interplant properly
right uh and what we will end up with
there I think is we just need to know
for this face we just need to have some
information about how we want to render
it we still need to know the locations
of these things that we're interpolating
between and so that's kind of a it's not
as simple as passing information at the
vertices that's literally interpolated
along the vertices so that may argue
that we still want to pass it as part of
a texture that we look up in the pixel
shader it's hard to say right we could
still pass it at the vertices but then
use the additional information that's
supplied as part of it to figure out how
we actually want to do the interpolation
or we can do an extrapolation where we
just figure out what the values would
have been at the vertices in order to
produce the interpolated point that we
have so for example if we know that we
actually want the point to be here but
we know we're going to be passing
something here we can just take whatever
value this was and take the inverse of
the linear blend that would happen
between these two to figure out what we
should pass this as if we assume that we
pass down full floating-point values
that's probably fine because we could
always pick values that would work
but it feels a little touchy to me the
real really the reason it feels a little
touching to me is because interpolations
always very well behaved an
extrapolation even when you're
extrapolating to know that you're just
producing an interpolated value can get
kind of numerically unstable in that way
depending on what the Delta is that
you're trying to reproduce between the
two points I feel like this is
especially dangerous when you consider
that we're trying to interpolate
something one of the components is a
direction so ideally I think what I'd
like to do is be able to pass downn for
lighting points in addition to the for
geometry points and I would like to
interpolate between them by linearly I
think that's what I would still like to
do now that's a little bit harder to do
than we would like because now what we
have to do is like sort of reverse
figure out where we are among those four
points
but I don't really know that that's all
that problematic right
it's really hard to say let's try
playing with a few things first so if
you recall one of our big problems is
that our pixel shader is too slow even
at the moment because it's doing a nasty
loop and all sorts of things there and
so one of the things that you can see in
sort of a at least that we were getting
before maybe this is not happening
anymore in fact it isn't with the new
driver it looks like it looks like we
maintain 30 frames a second now because
we didn't used to right did they fix
something because we I feel like we used
to have a problem where we wouldn't hit
30 frames a second if you zoom if you
were actually getting some pixel shading
I feel like they may have like fixed
something in the pixel shader compiler
or something because didn't we used to
shoot up to 40 milliseconds I really
thought we did
when we were doing big fills there so I
don't know maybe maybe this is a bad
extrapolation to make anyway I'm gonna
go ahead and start cleaning some of this
stuff up but I wanted to talk about that
lighting a little bit there if we just
assumed that we were only gonna do a
couple little things with the lighting I
wanted to see how that would affect the
performance but if the if the pixel
shader is no longer actually causing a
performance from then this is kind of a
little bit academic at that point
because it was before and you know maybe
it isn't now
but anyway so let's go ahead and take a
look here at what we're what we're sort
of looking through we kind of have a lot
of test code going on here and I want to
kind of get some of it out of here at
the moment so we've got this point
distributor drawing thing here I'm gonna
get rid of that now so we'll get rid of
that little yellow blossom that we sort
of created in the middle of things
okay and there you can kind of see so so
now you can see it happening right now
you can see that that time delay I was
talking about so maybe the blossom just
had enough added enough additional draw
calls to make it Oh II slow right but
now we're down you can see the effect of
the pixel shader there we're like we
zoom in and we're getting 30
milliseconds per frame ish we zoom out
and we're getting 20 milliseconds per
frame or pretty you know you don't even
need to measure it with a real with any
accuracy you can see what a difference
that's making and again the lighting is
not changing here that's just
reconstruction of the lighting in the
pixel shader that's causing that problem
right that's the that's what we're
seeing there so if we wanted to play
around with that a little look I was
saying I'm interested to know what
happens if this is no longer a loop so
if in here we just assume that the light
count is always four lights I'm
interested to know to what extent the
optimization would get better or what
things we could do if we just know that
we are always going to fetch four lights
right so yeah if we just said light
count where is frag light count right
count Franklin counties here you can see
frag light indexes there that's where
we're starting to fetch from so if I
just set that instead to frag light
count equaling four I don't suspect this
will be much of a difference I just
wanted to see if it changed at all
and oddly enough even just that change
does make a difference right I don't
know if you can see that but even just
that change knocked about two
milliseconds off the time right and so
again I think regularizing this code a
little bit more would be good so you can
see us doing our textile fetching here
where we do a textile fetch with the
light index and those light index going
order we fetch them the two different
light samplers and so one thing we could
do because we sort of know what those we
know that those four light values that
are coming in here are values that we
want to interpolate we could probably do
something a little bit clever more
clever where we just let the regular
textile fetch figure this out for us
right so you know just pretend pretend
this pretend to pretend we're doing this
right so what we're doing right now is
we're packing four of these in like this
right and so what we have to do is fetch
this one fetch this one fetch this one
fetch this one and then we blend them
together but what we could potentially
do right another option is pack those
like this have a U and V value that we
use that does this for us right so set
using V's on these vertices that say how
we want a sample so for example this UV
value or whatever this would be 2 and
this would be 0 so that it would run
from 0 to 1 right here and then just to
2 there that'd be very well behaved and
it would clamp right here which is what
we want it to do at the sample points
right and then we could just align these
points into that texture such that we
could just use the regular bilinear
sampling to blend these together for us
right
so we could potentially speed this up a
bunch because we know we're just trying
to interpolate a region well what if we
just made that region be more sensible
right seems like a pretty sane thing to
do and then we could interpolate the
things together now it's a little bit
harder than it sounds because again we
sort of have this nasty issue where
because we want to do the interpolation
ourselves because we are encoding the
values in a particular way interpolating
the values ourselves might be more
difficult but I don't necessarily know
that it would be because this light Z
reconstruction I think could happen
either way and so yeah
I guess what I'm saying is the problem
that we have here is just looking at
whether or not the light D value is
positive or negative that's the one
thing that stops us from using a
built-in interpolator there because
that's gonna oscillate it's just
encoding it's it's doing an encoding of
a negative value for the reconstructed
square root so yeah that is a little bit
nasty but actually it's not that nasty
because if you think about what's gonna
happen here if you pass those U and V
values you don't need the light position
anymore at that point the light position
color and direction actually we can just
encode this stuff directly at that point
I think right really wish I hadn't run
out of lemonade so if we take a look at
what we're passing down here to the
renderer in terms of those those
textures
we were encoding this as the position X
Y Z and then the direction X and
Direction Y and then the color was in
here but if we wanted to change the way
these were encoded we could do that
pretty easily right you could see us
doing a different encoding that looks
like this actually encode the full
direction which would allow us to do
spiracle samples as well as
hemispherical samples and interpolate
them properly using automated
interpolation right as if that was an
RGB texture and then in here we would
just have the color so that would be a
direction and color both encoded and
those could be encoded more concisely as
well that could be encoded instead of as
floats of 16-bit values for example and
that would give us probably print plenty
of of material there so you could
imagine using these two as just an
encoding of the lighting input at that
point and then each of our vertices
would just have its UV value into its
light region and that would be it and
that's pretty straightforward I think
for us to do it's something to think
about I think that would be a pretty
efficient way to to do it so I'm not
going to start with that
because I feel like that's maybe taking
too many steps at once and since this is
gpu-based where although we do have a
nice new debugger to play with which
maybe would make it a little bit easier
on us you typically don't want to take
too many big steps because it's very
hard to get into the data and really see
what's going wrong so what I'd like to
do first is maybe change the sunlight
into a thing that's doing UV based
interpolation for example I think that
would be a more useful thing to do and
we'll get that working first then we
will go and try to encode the data more
compactly later on right so we'll start
by removing px py and PZ from use so
we'll get them out of the equation
entirely and then we will go and
re-encode once we know that they're out
of there and yeah like I said we can
move to this sort of encoding and
whether or not you know we can also the
other thing we can do is we could
normalize this vector so what we could
do is to use the length of this vector
to tell us something so for example this
CRC this CR CGC B we could store this 8
bit and we could make this dxdydz
be like color intensity
so then we only need one non 8-bit
texture like this would be an 8-bit RGB
texture and this would be an actual
floating point or 16-bit
higher dynamic range texture and then
we're not wasting all of the information
in there right because you only really
need two values like I said but we
because we need to interpolate and may
want to use built-in interpolation I you
know it's hard to say how we want to do
that so we'll see at the very least this
texture would be pretty easy to do
automatic interpolation on because of
course it's just color and we definitely
could make it just just do 8-bit there
although well yeah mmmm you know now I
think about it even that doesn't really
thrill me because since the if you want
the interpolation to work right if these
are supposed to be values that get you
know arbitrarily high then when you
interpolate between them you need to
make sure that the interpolation takes
in that difference in size as well so
yeah I don't know we don't need to think
about too hard just yet let's just focus
on the basics all right
so in here we've got a smooth in Veck to
frag UV right and we're going to need
additional information beyond that UV
we're going to need like a lighting UV
if that makes sense
and so yeah when you take a look at what
one of the vertices is this right here
this is not going to require a light
count anymore we're just going to say
that the light count is out of the out
of the picture but in here where we're
passing the point the normal and the UV
for the texture we're also going to want
to point put a UV in there
so although we're removing one u16 we're
going to want to add back in a UV for
the lighting so there basically be like
a light UV so you know we're sort of
expanding a little bit from what we had
before and the emission value for this
vertex I don't know what that was for
and I feel like that isn't necessary
anymore is that even getting used
anywhere hold on one second before I do
this change so it's not so let's just go
ahead and remove that right off the bat
because we don't need our for our
emission values go into the lighting
system they don't go into the vertex
stream so let's just get rid of that
emission value altogether because it's
simply not relevant to the way we've
structured our system that was sort of
an old part of the process that no one
cares about anymore and so we might have
to get rid of it so now if we look at
how this is laid out we have our p value
which we really can't touch we have our
V our n value and our n value at least
at the moment really doesn't vary it's
actually constant per primitive but that
may change when we start doing more
stuff with our sprites so it's hard to
say I strongly suspect that this
probably for all intents and purposes
that probably can be moved down here so
I suspect that we could have a per
primitive buffer that that specifies
normals because really it's just the P
in the UV that we really vary and the in
the color but not not the normal the
normal just points in a direction and
then it doesn't really do anything else
so yeah if we look at how much is is
being spent up here you can kind of see
that if we were to do this what we end
up there is there's probably just way
too much accuracy being specified in
these two things floating point values
for these really just probably aren't
sorry so these can also probably be
compacted quite a bit too 8-bit values
for the light UV would probably be
plenty and probably for this UV as well
because we tend to only use like whole
sprites we don't really have much
packing or anything maybe in the future
we would but these actually could
probably be 16 bits each honestly so we
could get this down to quite small one
problem that we would have there is I
don't know how good OpenGL is it as
accepting normalized you v's I think
it's pretty straightforward out you used
to actually be kind of bad at it
but I think it's OK at it now so if we
wanted to you know this could easily be
something more like this if that was
something we want to do and maybe that
is something we want to do so maybe we
should try playing with that a little
bit hard to say now one problem that we
will have is the light UV the this UV
probably can work this way very easily
because it's just picking out sprites
the light UV is probably not that way
because it's got to do the sort of weird
interpolation stuff that I was talking
about before so it may be that this one
actually has to be you know a real value
to certain extent if we take a look at
what we've got here where we've got you
know this would actually line up pretty
great this would be for floats to floats
and then essentially two more floats so
basically be the size of eight floats
right and so you know if you think about
it a 32 byte vertex kind of fits really
nicely and it's nicely cash aligned and
everything's great so you know that
might be a nice way to encode things if
this turns out to be all we need to
specify per vertex and then this stuff
down here is still aligned reasonably
well and all that the problem is that I
we really just don't want to specify
this stuff at all
I think this stuff wants to be specified
per vertex
I'm sorry primitive and not per vertex
so I think this is kind of extraneous
and bad but we can
sort of cross that bridge when we come
to it all right so again if we take a
look at how this UV stuff is working yes
so there's a couple ways we can do this
the other thing we can look at here with
the UVs is say look the light index now
can be rolled into these UV is because
if we're going to pack these into a
texture then what what we can do is into
the light UV if that's a float we can
just pack that in there
so really these two can go away entirely
and this would just have to be specified
per vertex right yeah and that'd be that
so at that point again I'm not sure I'm
sorry per primitive and I don't really
know how whether that makes sense to do
or not it may be that that's just slower
and it's just better to blow it out the
vertex with it I don't know all right
anyway enough hemming and hawing about
that so that's basically what we'd be
doing here so if we take a look at this
what I'm interested in doing here is is
making the light UV maybe encode this
value so the first thing I do is I'm
going to get rid of light count because
we don't need it anymore
you can see here we're passing that as
an array and we just don't want that
anymore
so I'm going to take a look at all the
places we were doing that we don't need
this vert light count thing anymore
and in theory that should do like
absolutely nothing differently right
it's just the same stuff no no big E's
right and we shouldn't see any
deleterious performance implications
from that and we don't because we're
just removing things right okay so next
step what I'd like to do here is figure
out a better way again of accessing
these textures so what I'm thinking
about here is this light UV value can we
use that to just pick out the
information we need and so what I'm
going to do is I'm gonna say let's maybe
stop with the light index part of things
and instead use just use the light UV to
figure out that value right
so yeah this requires passing the light
UV down so we're gonna need a way of
passing that information to the shaders
and interpolating that along as well
right and
I guess one kind of nasty aspect of this
is that so so maybe we want to do this
in the opposite order maybe we want to
pack these into the texture in the order
that I was suggesting they should be
packed and then still use the index the
the FET shader to do what we want to do
so for example inside some light here
you can see doing light I
it starts at frag light index and it in
increments right and does this does this
whole thing here so probably what I
should do is convert this to something
that just does the fetches into a
texture that is laid out the way that
I've suggested so two rows instead of
one so basically it fetches things that
it knows are supposed to be bilinear
blended instead right so in order to do
that what I would have to do is sort of
convert this blend call into something
that does more of a parameterised
version so if I took this out and I made
this call right here be something more
like fetching some or something like
this so what it's going to do is this is
going to do it's going to update this
result value here I I'm not sure how you
pass something to be modified in a
shader like that now that I think about
it my shader coding skills are poor to
say the least I usually look up
everything as I go what I could do here
is just do
actually just like this so what I could
do here just say well you know the
they're running some value like we'll
we'll set to zero here and then we'll
just call this four times
so in here we want to fetch these four
light positions we don't need any of
this stuff really in fact I can probably
just get rid of light I all together and
just say look it's this do four of this
sums they'll sum into running sum and
then here we'll just say results goes
running sum so that is the yeah I'm sure
there's a good way to pass something in
to fetch and sum but I don't know what
it is anyway so then we'll do our two
textile fetches we'll do all of our
computations we don't need any of this
stuff and that will update running some
with the value that we actually wanted
and from there we can we should be able
to kind of go forwards with starting to
make it fetch in a different way so here
we are doing our loading again at this
time we're doing it with those calls
instead of the loop right and again no
real problems with the performance
compared to the old performance so we're
not changing anything drastic so now
when we do this textile fetch and we're
doing this sort of summation here now
what I want to do is sort of change this
over to something that's going to do
again like I said a sort of a bilinear
blend and so what I'd like to do is make
it so maybe so fetch and some isn't that
really fetching some it's just like
fetch sample or something
and we can fetch the four different
samples that we want separately and then
use them right now the problem that I'm
going to have here is that again I don't
really know if we want to do this way
because we probably want to let the
automated summation stuff in the
bilinear blend in the textile fetch
bilinear plan just do it
for us so so I mean it may be that we
really kind of have to make this jump
all at once no I mean I think we just
still make baby steps so let's suppose
we leave this as fetching some hoops if
we leave this as fetch as some suppose I
just update these two and we pass in the
right values here then we should be able
to update those textures to have the
things in the order that I suggested
before and then it should be fine so I
think we can make this work in smaller
steps right so let's just double check
him and I'll see if I that's true
because we're almost out of time anyway
you got like 15 minutes left I think
okay that all still looks pretty
accurate
it's kind of weird one thing that's not
doesn't make a lot of sense is why that
is getting wet I mean I suppose that
those points are getting light on them
but yeah I guess as we start to spread
these light points out one of the things
we can do is start to debug some of
those things a little bit better because
right now the way that we're doing light
placement on surfaces is also a little
wonky and so sometimes I can't quite
guess if something's a bug or not and we
need better ways of identifying where
the things are bugs for stuff like this
really liking this lighting though it's
so pleasant you know so yeah what I'm
interested in doing here is turning
these into two-dimensional samples that
we can use the UV for so what I want to
do right in this case is I want to kind
of take this and turn it as strange as
it seems turn it into that basically
where we are sort of you know putting
those there's for the primitives we're
having like two rows of light
information and we'll sort of distribute
the light information in there
proportional to how we want to
interpolate it now light data width is
still is kind of a stupid name now and
furthermore we really don't need these
to be shaped this way they could be
shaped in in any way really because if
we actually make a light UV then
basically we just have a light map and
we're putting things into the light map
and you know that's just yeah it's it's
not that complicated of a thing to do
and
we pretty much could use a you know a
square texture we don't need a
rectangular texture anymore for that
purpose so that part's a little bit
trickier but we'll do it one step at a
time again to avoid anything that's
going to be to dilla tereus so if we
take a look at this here if we expanded
these light datas to be stepped in this
fashion then what we need to do is we
need to pack those in there in a way
that will make sense for fetching them
out later and so what I want to do is
when we go in and in the lighting
routine place the actual data in there
as you can see here what we're doing is
replacing the data into this point index
system where as we run through we know
that every point index in the system
corresponds to one entry in the lighting
setup and what we'd like to do instead
is have a more coherent notion of where
these points actually get packed into
Malaysia get packed into texture now one
thing I could do again to make even more
baby steps it so I just leave it the way
it was and instead introduce some notion
that the packing has to get packed
prescriptively then when we're looking
at these lighting points here what I can
do is say that there has to actually be
some information for a given lighting
point that says where the lighting point
is supposed to actually be packed right
and so if you take a look at how these
lighting points get added in the first
place
what you can see is that when we run
through here we go through each of the
boxes that we have in each of those
boxes then gets a point added to the
system as such and so what we could do
here is say look since we know how we're
placing these points relative to the
boxes that we're creating we should then
also be able to say for each one of the
points where we want it to get packed
back to right so for example in here we
could just have an integer that's like
PAC index and when we specify in here
what we want to pack we just say that
like point pack index equals something
in here when we're doing the points we
know how many we have so the PAC indices
should always be valid and what we can
do is say well alright at the moment we
know that the PAC index is just going to
be the same as the point index right so
there really isn't any difference
between those two things and they can
just be packed directly and then when we
come down here and we're going to do the
packing normally we were saying point
index before but instead what we're
going to do here is have a PAC index
what we can do is take the actual point
piece of point information get that out
and then in here we can just say okay
point P point and and
we're still doing the stuffing here and
again that's going to be something we
want to sort of when we start looking at
the normal information we're gonna want
to start stop doing that I recall it
didn't change very much but it might
change more as we start to distribute
our points out in different ways so what
we want to do again is just say okay now
when we go and pack these back we want
to use the PAC index here and again
that's just going to be given off of the
point
[Music]
oops what am i doing there and so now
we're just packing back at a place that
we've specified and at the moment that
doesn't do us anything it's the same as
it was before but as we move forward
here with doing stuff where we've got a
more coherent notion of how these things
should get spammed back into the
textures we can get more aggressive with
that right so now if we take a look at
these pieces of light data let's go
ahead and do the thing that I was saying
before where we say all right let's pack
these into two rows now so there's like
they're kind of in in more of a UV
pattern and what I'll do there is just
say oK we've got two packed indices
let's say so maybe this is a pack row
value and that's a pack index value and
then what I can do is say all right if I
know the pack index in the pack row I
can put these into the textures properly
and then when I can also do is when I'm
submitting these textures I can then
start thinking of them as things that
could be interpolated between by using
it by linear sample as long as I pack
the pieces of information in in a known
orientation that makes sense for the
surface so now when I come back here
what I want to do is be a little bit
more prescriptive about or specific
about how these are getting packed in so
if I have a row index and a pack index
what I know is my row index is actually
given by one of these because I got an X
sub and a Y sub so what I could say is
well my row index maybe is my Y sub
value so I have two rows that I'm
packing into and then my pack index for
X is going to be whatever the light
index is times two since I'll stride and
I don't really want that actually I
guess we want an actual value here but
plus my Y sub so I know that like I pack
two values in for every square right
because this is a square of a square
sample pattern so I just want to do two
rows two columns right and then we just
say okay my pack index right
Oh so yeah this actually gives me
roughly what I want here you can see
that we get this box light index value
so I could just use this value and that
would actually be fine for the moment so
yeah hmm hard to say what I want to do
about that
[Music]
so the reason that that's a little bit
wonky is just because the line index
that's coming down here is kind of
separate from where we might want to
pack these into the texture this light
index goes up by four every time because
there are four lights well no sorry it's
more than that right there's four upper
surface so it actually goes up by 24
points per box at the moment and we
don't really need to obey that at all
when we're doing our packing because
we've got two rows to pack into and
we're gonna have a lot of other packing
concerns involved so there's kind of
yeah it kind of fights this a little bit
and the way that we're doing these
submissions again I think needs to
cleaned up I don't know if you remember
what we kind of were saying that I have
this stuff needs to move to the world
generation stuff anyway how these points
get distributed so it's kind of a little
bit of a mishmash yeah it's kind of a
little bit of a of an issue there
so I'm not sure exactly how I want to do
that just yet like I said this parts all
gonna be finicky bookkeeping that's
really all that's going on here is
figuring out the most efficient way for
us to do this sort of stuff I can just
use the light index here probably the
base light index yeah I mean like for
now I can do that
but admittedly it's not great we kind of
need to start locking this out to a
higher level right where because the
distribution of points is not going to
be one-to-one with the blocks that it
uses
although again we could kind of yeah
this requires some thought so I'm gonna
back this out for a second
leave this the way it was and I think
this is where we'll pick up tomorrow
because what I want to do is I want to
figure out the most efficacious set of
steps to make here and I think we might
want to do is go into the world gencode
and actually figure out how we want to
generate the information about how these
things go together because there's two
ways we could do it and one of which one
of them is to leave boxes and light
sample points sort of aligned with each
other and maybe we really want to do
that and then just apply a blur right
like so you know maybe a different way
of looking at this problem would be
maybe we want to sort of sample the
lighting of these faces just as faces
and then have a thing that operates
after the fact that tries to produce
what these two points should be based on
the lighting here and here right
so I kind of want to think that through
a little bit more I don't want to do
that at the end of the stream because we
only got like four minutes left so I
think what I'd like to do is that's what
I'll pick up on tomorrow let's go make
something that actually generates like
you know a wall and places the points
where it will and just tries to figure
out how that forward bookkeeping is
gonna work cuz I feel like we need to
kind of push forward from that so we'll
do that that way I think that's the
right call so let's go ahead and go to
muse make sure that we lift this in good
state let's go ahead and go to our brief
Q&amp;A
hi Casey can you please remind the good
people on the stream 1y templates are
bad to what use cases templates can be
considered for which they are good and
bad for and what they can be replaced
with even then I'm gonna take a gander
it's metaprogramming um yes so you don't
let's just see if we have any on topic
questions first because that was not
really a topic of today's stream if we
don't have any other questions I'm happy
to fill the 15 minutes with that but
it's not it's not really apropos if that
makes sense
frosty Ninja has getting insight working
boosted your morale back and recovered
some hope well yes and no I mean I would
I would say not really and the reason
for that is just because you know it was
very depressing to have the whole thing
the other week where it's like okay we
couldn't even get an invidious website
to work in whatever and that's true and
that sucked and all that but on the
whole most of my experiences in the past
with NVIDIA have been good when I try to
talk to programmers there or driver
writers there to have them do stuff or
help me with something or fix something
I have generally found them to be easy
to work with so I wasn't like super down
on NVIDIA or anything so in some sense
the fact that they you know specifically
took the time to come and ask me if I
needed help on getting this going while
I'm really happy they did that they tend
to be good like that I generally have
positive experiences working with NVIDIA
you know and so I wouldn't say it
boosted my morale all that much because
really it just reinforced what I already
thought which is that if I'm really in
dire straits with something Nvidia
related I'm not that despondent because
they seem to be pretty good right and
you know if they hadn't and if we still
couldn't use insight maybe I would be an
even worse
mood but generally speaking nvidia is
not the primary problem when i think of
people who don't care about developers
it's not nvidia right and vidya among
you know the folks who developers
typically have to deal with them day to
day basis they are probably the least
problematic in terms of actually getting
them to pay attention to problems and
help with them and they certainly tend
to ship some of the more stable drivers
and tools and stuff that I use so I
don't know how to put it any more
specific than that am I still doing to
Montana no Germany planting shadows in
the game no I don't really want any
shadows in the game not hard shadows
anyway the there obviously are shadows
in the game already in the sense that
when you move like behind things you do
get shadows right so that's the shadow
of this wall that's why it is not there
so we actually have pretty advanced
shadowing very advanced shadowing in
fact at the moment what we don't have is
hard shadows so and I don't really want
to do hard shadows I don't like hard
shadows one thing that's kind of weird
about the way people do shadows and
games is like if you look at games
generally once the game gets to a
certain level of graphical complexity
and quality oftentimes you can't see
shadows anymore as such so for example
if you look at a game that looks really
good it's a pick one from recent memory
that I thought looked quite good you
know if you start to look at these the
shadows sort of start to become fairly
irrelevant so you look at this scene and
you're like well there's a little bit of
a direct shadow right there
and everything else is indirect lighting
right like there's no you just don't see
a lot of contribution of the direct
shadowing to the overall quality of the
scenes right and so you look at this
stuff in you know you can see these
sorts of pieces here as what the this is
the direct illumination pass that's
doing that right there it's just not the
most important part right in terms of
the character again you kind of look at
something like this and it's just I
can't even really see the direct shadows
here I guess it's that part is that this
is Assassin's Creed all of a sudden I
don't know why we're also looking at
that and so I just tend to not think of
it as that important right typically
speaking if you just want to ground the
player just putting in a little bit of
fake shadowing there tends to be good
enough and in our cases if you think
about how these are generally created
this is actually not that hard to do
creating these shows because it's
typically a shadow passed with whatever
your strongest direction of light is we
don't really have much of an option of
doing that because we don't have real
geometry for our stuff we just have
sprites so our shadows would be pretty
inaccurate as it is
so again just putting in just a standard
little darkening beneath the characters
is all I really plan to do and again
when I just look at these direct
shadowing just doesn't contribute that
much right typically what you see more
is just the fact that back the backs of
things aren't lit brightly and the
Front's are and the direct the directly
cache shadows really you just don't see
much I don't even see them at all here I
guess that's it right there but if that
wasn't there I I wouldn't even know
right like I wouldn't even have noticed
it not being there
honestly hardly at all in this scene I
think it's right there right other than
that I don't even see any direct
shadowing in the scene that really I
notice so I think like and this is true
of the real world too like I mean if you
just look at photos
you just don't see a lot of that I don't
know how to get just random photos so
here's a shot and again if you look at
what you notice in this shot in terms of
direct shadowing you know all I see is
some darkening underneath the the
elements right I don't see any direct
shadowing in that scene I don't see any
direct shadowing in this scene none in
that scene none in that scene none in
that scene none in that scene I mean
it's just not there so to the extent
where we really need to think about it
at all I really think the only thing we
need to worry about is darkening
underneath like where the player
standing so they can see what they're
standing on that that piece of visual
information the darkening I think is
important everything else I think is
just a waste of time cuz see real scenes
just don't have a lot of like oh I see
the long like shadow being cast again
same thing here right there's some
direct shadowing happening here it's
just darkening where there is stuff and
and I don't need like I can't even
perceive that those are cast by this
thing in terms of shape I just know they
are because there's stuff there so again
it's just like it's just a darkening
that happens underneath stuff that can
be easily faked it doesn't really
require any of that sort of solving and
so I feel like our soft shadows plus if
we want to darken something underneath
things passivity is really all we need
is the cause over brightness merely a
change in the algorithm makes the light
bright it's very different or is there
an actual bug
well again the reason is just because
we're doing an approximation of the
integral and we aren't approximating the
cosine term correctly in either case
because in one case we're under sampling
the Hemisphere but correctly multiplying
by cosine theta in the other case where
maybe sampling the atmosphere a little
bit better cuz we're concentrating
towards the points that contribute more
but we're under sampling the cosine
theta part so both of them are bugs in
accuracy they may not be bugs in the
Apes we had a line of code wrong sense
so well sprites be simply flat lighted
or do you plan to implement something to
give them fake 3d lighting if we end up
having normal maps as input I don't know
if we're gonna have any normal maps for
input then it will light with the normal
map otherwise we won't lucid frost has
similar is this letting mild to
something you would find in other game
engines it's fairly similar I think to
what you would find in like a high-end
radiosity based engine so I think it's
fairly similar to say how the Frostbite
engine does its indirect lighting Pass I
think so for example is that what it's
called
and I don't know I have no idea how
enlighten works
I know literally nothing about it so you
know take this with a massive grain of
salt because we are probably very
different in terms of how we work than
they are but so here's an example of
rate of how their system works sort of a
little bit anyway here's a direct
lighting pass from the engine which they
can do we can't do it because for two
reasons one we don't limit the number of
lights in the scene and to their direct
they have real geometry so they can do a
real direct lighting pass right so they
do a direct lighting pass and then what
they do is they take at various points
in the scene and they record what the
direct lighting was at those points
right and then here you go the main
runtime for a certain lightness to map a
point sample description of the lighting
over the target mesh surface which is
this - a light map or light probe output
this is the bounce
anything you could stress in these terms
has valid input to enlighten right and
so here's what enlightened outputs now
looks familiar right yeah I mean that's
a lot like what we get you know and so
then it goes ahead and reconstructs that
in a way which is what we're working on
now how to reconstruct our version of
this to something that's smooth for what
we want and you know I don't know how
they're doing that exactly but I assume
they're doing it roughly how we're doing
it
directional irradiance between first
full spherical output for the spherical
harmonics at a point so you know who
knows what's out with the ring but
anyway then they composite that with the
actual scene geometry and they get that
right so in terms of what we're like now
we're kind of just like a high-end
radiosity thing at the moment how well
would that work for our 2-d game I don't
know but it's doing nicely distribution
so I'm kind of happy with it why use in
citing the application for a toboggan
when you already use Visual Studio
proceed view code debugging why not just
use insight in Visual Studio because the
NSA
Visual Studio is really like finicky and
like I don't like having to deal with
the same panels I just want a thing
that's like laid out for graphics the
bugging only and it's optimized for that
so I would prefer an external tool if
possible and that's what that gives me
so I kind of like that I know a lot of
people like I des I don't know why they
like ideas I can't stand them typically
I like to have a tool for that job that
I can rely on and works reliably for
that job I don't like everything crammed
into one thing and then it's like okay
this view may be right for debugging but
now when I want to do insight all of a
sudden it's like jammed into it and
weird and it's using the same key
combinations which are wrong for what I
might want
I like having different contexts for
different operations
I'm not debugging code when I'm
debugging graphics almost ever right
because they're just not similar one is
running on GPU once ring a CPU and only
sometimes do the twixt meet so typically
I'm trying to do a specific task and I
want something that's designed just for
that test I switch to and is optimized
for that purpose right have you
considered baking shadows we cannot
really bake shadows in that way because
we are procedurally generated so we can
do some baking of shadows if we wanted
to have some static geometry or
something but I mean but also the lights
are all moving around I mean I just
don't even know what that would mean
right it see I don't really think you
could make shadows in this case
do you think there's a small number of
the number that the number of small draw
calls might be causing GPGPU occupancy
issues can't remember if we saw
occupation in sight
so that the small number of draw calls
is gonna cause a lot of unnecessary
driver overhead period and we should get
rid of it and we probably will so I
would say it's not really necessary to
look into it particularly much because
it's just a unnecessary thing that I
think I've decided I want to get rid of
anyway and so we probably will show what
the game looks like now oh dude were you
not okay I mean did we have been running
the game when we've been testing the
lighting so this is our little test area
that we're working on here and we you
know we're a 2-d game so it will look
only it will only be visible from this
perspective in the actual version of the
game but we can use the debug camera to
inspect our 3d scenes pretty easily like
so right and so what we're testing right
now is we basically just attach this
light to where the player would normally
be and as you can see I'm like moving it
around to test the lighting because
that's what we're working on at the
moment and so at the moment we've gotten
ourselves to pretty good lighting
solutions that we've got right here but
what we haven't done yet is and what
we're now moving to work on is we want
to reconstruct our lighting in a smooth
fashion so you know the lighting right
now is basically per block surface and
the block surfaces aren't shared
together in a way that makes the
lighting coherent and smooth and so what
we want to do is just make that happen
so that's the part that we're doing now
and you can also see out here so the
white blocks are blocks that are pulled
in to the simulation but that aren't lit
and so that's another thing that we
haven't really done too much of yet is
determine where the lighting solution
happens and where it doesn't happen so
we'll probably do a little bit more with
that and
future as well um I'm gonna go
downstairs just cuz I can again you
could see I'm really happy with how this
lighting is turning out I mean that just
looks cool you get this rim lighting
here from where the lights coming from
downstairs up here is all darker now
right it's just really Pleasant and we
do suffer a little bit from our
approximations you can see like probably
that shouldn't be lit right now but it
is and of course the reason is because
we approximate regional lighting and we
don't do a whole lot to fix that but I'm
okay with that you know it's still it's
still again it lighting any real-time
lighting is an approximation always and
you're gonna get glitches I don't mind
those kind of glitches I'm fine with
that
because it still does the right
character right it still it still
provides the character that I want in
this case right so all right I think
we're all done
all righty do you think like yeah I 3d I
was for things like HR drawers
I just want just blocks and the block
can have textures on the sides of them
but just blocks and sprites are the only
two things we'll have so in some sense
the doors will probably be blocks which
means they are 3d objects but they won't
be like special 3d objects like they
won't be modeled didn't like Maya or
something they're just gonna be blocks
so the only input to the game should be
textures there's not going to be 3d
models that get input if that makes
sense
all right thanks everyone for joining me
from the episode of handmade here at
some pleasure coding with you as always
if you would like to follow along with a
game at home you can always pre-order it
on handmade hero org and it comes with a
source code that I update every time we
do programming on it so that you can
follow along at home and do your own
experimentation maybe you'll figure out
interesting way of integrating the
lighting before I do if you are a
intrepid sort of programmer that's about
it for today I will be back here
tomorrow when I will try to do a little
bit of world gem code to see how we're
gonna place those lights and so we're
trying to start to streamline that
process because the very next thing that
we have to do after lighting is probably
start working on the world Jen and art
stuff to sort of build our worlds now
right and actually get some worlds in
there that we can walk around and really
start to clean up the engine to the
point where we're happy with it doing
everything that we needed to do because
we basically like got all the components
that we might need but they you know
could kind of benefit from now pushing
forwards and seeing what's going on and
so we need to start start pushing that
and so what I want to do is get the
lighting tied into that part of the
process so I think that's what we're
gonna be looking at tomorrow I hope see
you back there for that until then have
fun programming everyone and I'll see
everybody on the Internet take it easy
everybody