there we go hello everyone welcome to
handmade hero the show we code a
complete game live on Twitch no
library's no engines just us and a good
in-depth look at every last little bit
of how a game actually operates if you
want to know how that happens you have
come to the right place today we are
looking at normal mapping which we set
the stage for yesterday by doing the
plumbing that's necessary to kind of get
it in there and now today we are kind of
gonna trust we're gonna start the the
process well I guess what I should say
is we're gonna implement the basic
normal map operations but they're not
going to do anything particularly useful
for us because we don't really have much
lighting information to work with so if
we're going to centrally try to leave it
today with the normal maps working so
that next week we can kind of go on a
little mini adventure to figure out how
we're going to produce some kind of a
usable light field that we can sample
with the normal maps that where we're
going to be using all right so if you
want to follow along at home and you've
pre-ordered the game on handmade hero
org go ahead and download the source
code and make sure that you unzip the
source code today 97 because we're on
day 98 today and also I will be cycling
the the packs at day 100 so like day 99
will be the last one Monday I guess will
be the last one in this pack and then I
make a new pack so that way you know it
doesn't become infinitely huge archive
since I include every day source code in
there so be on the lookout for that
eventually when you go to your link
you'll see that you've got options to
download multiple packs they'll be like
a zero at a hundred pack and I'm sorry
$0.99 pack and then 100 to 199 pack and
so on all right off we go now I kind of
you know I'll be honest with you I was
kind of out of it yesterday it was not a
good coding day not sure exactly what
happened some days you're on some days
are off maybe I don't know I think I
didn't have any coffee yesterday and you
know
you don't have any coffee all day so it
was it was a bit of scattershot you know
I sometimes did get you're done with the
stream and you're like wow I didn't
explain anything very well and they're a
bunch of typos yesterday it was just it
was just kind of a lousy day so I don't
expect that we're going to have a
particularly smooth ride today while we
try to work with that code I added
because it was kind of in a daze and so
we're gonna have to pay a little bit of
attention here to what's going on just
to try and make sure that we don't have
any really stupid mistakes in here that
are going to cause problems for us but
anyway what we did yesterday is we added
this sort of normal map branch in here
that we're doing for every pixel again
this is highly uh that we're doing here
we're just trying to get all of the math
worked out properly so we'll be able to
see what we want to optimize when we do
a sort of a more optimal version of it
but basically what we've got here is got
the normal map version which is
happening per pixel and we wanted to
kind of sample these environment maps
that we have which we're sort of saying
are the things that we'll sort of
investigate next week to see what we can
do to generate interesting lights light
areas kind of sample from so what we
want to do is we want to take these
normal maps which we kind of had a
little thing in here that would generate
a fake spherical normal map for us we
want to take those do wanna do that
sampling now we never actually hooked
this up so I think the first thing we
want to do is actually cook up the
sphere normal map maker and then we can
try passing that's for a normal map in
and we didn't actually do the sampling
over here either we just sort of
returned what the color in the normal
map was and so I'm hoping that that will
essentially give us a way to just first
verify that our normal Maps look at all
reasonable anyway all right so going
from there here's our make sure normal
map and basically what you do is you
hand in a bitmap and you candid a
roughness and again that roughness value
is just a material parameter it's
getting packed into the alpha value and
like I discussed before we don't
necessarily know for really want to
store all three values of the normal map
in here because at the end of the day
it's unclear really what we want to do
in terms of that on the GPU we'd
probably only want to store two so maybe
we do that on the CPU side as well
because like I said our goal with the
CPU render is not really to make sure
that it's performant enough to run the
game it's more just so that we can learn
how everything works and show how to
optimize it as well but at the end of
the day CPUs really aren't made for
rendering graphics well they are getting
a little bit more with avx-512 when that
comes out at the end of the area that
was designed for graphics so you never
know but point being
for the most part CPUs have not been
designed for rendering graphics and so
we can't really expect to match what we
were going to be able to on the GPU at
any level of fidelity with the CPU
anyway so let's start by saying alright
we've got our normal map generator here
I'm going to go in and when we do our
load time stuff I'm going to have it
sort of generate one for us that we can
use just you know something that'll kind
of be workable and we were we were using
that tree I believe is what we were
using as our bitmap to test with so I'm
gonna go ahead and you know say that we
had a tree normal map here even though
we don't and then I'm gonna make it so
that when we you know when we load this
tree I'm basically going to make a
bitmap that will will be the the tree
normal map so I'm gonna say that we have
that here and the roughness for this
thing is gonna be 0 for now actually I
guess technically we can might as well
have the roughness be 1 which is to say
that it is perfectly smooth we'll start
with perfectly reflective that's the
easier one to debug so start a throatily
we'll start with one that's completely
reflected so what we need to do first is
we need to allocate space for this so
I'm gonna do a make empty bitmap call
since I think we already essentially
have that ability here we needed to pass
it in arena we need to pass it a width
and a height and the width and the
height are going to be off of whatever
the trees width and height were right
we're just kind of mirroring mirror near
roaring that and we don't need it to be
cleared to zero because we're gonna
right into it directly now I guess when
we do that I believe the way that we
said that we were going to do these guys
we we stored them in the transient array
and we could keep doing that like that's
where the ground buffers are
and I suppose we can do that here as
well right we can go ahead and say that
the tree normal map comes out in here
and that way you can use the same arena
that everything's using for transient
State so and then we'll go ahead and
make that sphere normal map in there now
I think that's all we really need to do
to do that
oops don't really need that arrow
operator there I think that's all that
we really need to do I can't quite
remember if there's any other wacky
misses let's see and that is also an
address oh so that'll make that sphere
normal map for us we can then start
passing the sphere normal map along
because we've got this thing here where
we're actually you know about to use it
so we can pass the tree no map in there
and that should actually allow us to to
sample from it now we have to now bounce
back to the other routine there and
actually do something reasonable with
that okay and I believe we didn't finish
doing any scaling on these either if I
if I remember correctly so when we
sample out of the normal map right here
all we're doing is we're unpacking it so
they're 255 they're like they're 0 to
255 and 0 to 128 in and I guess you know
I'd have to think about this but I guess
we also wanted to to change the way this
is packed this is not really correct
right this is should actually be 128
plus 127 normal Z right because it's
always a positive value I mean
technically we could just do it exactly
this way in fact I don't know why we
don't for uniformity sake
right we should just be packing it
everything the same way take whatever
that that normal Z is add 1 to it
and divide it by 0.5 multiply it out so
that that seems like a smarter way to go
that way everything is is in the same
coordinate space so so let's pretend
that never happened we'll just go ahead
and and get back in here
so now we've got this thing and like I
said I don't think we're actually doing
any real scaling of the values we just
unpacked them and we linearly
interpolated them but then once we have
our normal we don't really know what any
of it means right
we haven't scaled down to to the proper
range we haven't adjusted for positive
negative any of that stuff
so we kind of have to figure out what we
want to do with that and what's a little
bit confusing here and I feel like this
is one of those things that's that's
again it's part of the hacky nature of
the problem that we're trying to solve
where we're you know we're essentially
trying to do some 3d things that are
inherently 3d we're trying to do them in
a 2d world you always run in to these
kind of problematic barriers right but
it's just happen to be aware of if you
think about what we're drawing when we
draw something and we've got you know
like we drew that sphere in there and
we've got things that are pointing like
directly at us here we've got things
that are pointing up sideways you know
this sort of thing and they get smaller
and smaller right what's important to
note here is there's never anything
that's pointing backwards in Z whatever
the Z coordinate is relative to this
like what we're talking about here we're
never pointing back into the screen
we're only pointing forwards right and
so the meaning of these things is kind
of hard for us to really into it but the
meaning of our normals if we imagine
this was a tree really what we're
talking about is the x axis of our
normals is the x axis of our world right
and the y axis of our normals is really
more like the z axis it's the thing that
would blend between you know sky and
ground and then that middle thing right
so the top middle bottom that's really
what the Y tells us and then that Z
right the Z which is sort of saying the
outwardness of this thing that's that's
kind of saying you know where you are
and here is really more telling us what
direction in Y on the screen we would
actually be go
right and it makes sense if you think
about it because really when you have an
opaque tree like this that's facing us
there's no way a normal could ever be
pointing behind it
that we would see so there's no way it
would ever look upwards in y2 like you
know if there's another tree behind it
we'd never have a normal in this tree
pointing at that tree that was actually
visible on the front side of the tree
it's not a thing right and so it kind of
makes sense but really what it means is
that the X Y Z's in terms of this
texture map really map into this way
right they really map into x y and z
like so right for a tree now we might
also have things like the ground right
and the ground would have normals that
would be you know pointing in some
direction for the ground right for
ground it's a little harder to say what
actually we would do I mean you know if
these are kind of bumpy they're kind of
bumpy in all directions like the ground
actually is flat so it could point in
all the directions of the hemisphere so
in some sense we have like two types of
normal map right there's a front facing
normal map and it looks like this and
then there is an up facing normal map
right and it actually has a real XY Z
that actually means what it actually
means the X is the wise and the Z's are
all actually what they really are and so
we probably have to have two different
texture sampling paths one that handles
these and one that handles these and we
would switch between them based on
whether we were drawing ground like
things or sort of perspective sorts of
things right I know that's a little
confusing but that's kind of how that
works and it's worth noting that that
maybe isn't always the case here in
terms of not being able to see behind
you you could imagine in the
weird case of like the top down dungeon
a sort of perspective which I don't know
that will necessarily clone but let's
say that we did so here's like a Zelda e
style room you know that you see pretty
often in these sorts of games right
that's got you know you some brick walls
here and and you know that sort of thing
and it's got a slime mold in it
that's slamming around or whatever okay
anyway point being you've got something
like this these walls right do have
normals that point in that direction so
you know we it wouldn't it's not like
we're throwing away a bunch of
information in terms of here here it's
just for the for things like trees they
would never actually have normals
pointing that direction but it's
possible that we could have sprites who
do want to have normals pointing in in
those directions right that's it's it's
plausible at least alright so off we go
in fact let me let me just move us back
up here see this there we go so for
right now we're only gonna handle those
front facing bitmaps for now we'll deal
with the ground a little bit later in
having separate paths so assuming that
we've got our sphere packed in here when
we grab this stuff out what we want to
do here is take our normal and we want
to produce those scaled values right
so we want to take our X of our normal
and our X of our normal I guess we could
we could just sort of say that this is a
unpack normal here right so we have a
like an unpack or it's not really
unpacked but it's a scale and bias or
unscaled bias normal something that
we'll take in our normal for us and it
will give us out a reasonable value
right and that I guess I could even do
that per component I'm not sure what I
want to do there so we'll just leave it
like this so off we go that's one of
these guys like so
so this will return that v4 it'll do the
unskilled biased normal here like so and
what we want to do is we want to produce
that result which basically takes the
normal X it's going to it's it's right
now packed from 0 to 255 what we want to
do is we first want to change that to
the range of 0 to 1 right so we kind of
have we've got one of these inverters
again right so you want to do in 255 and
then we want to change that but from 0
to 1 to negative 1 to 1 right so what
we'd like to do is start at negative 1
and we'd like to go from there you know
twice the range of the 0 to 1 value and
that is just going to happen for all of
our components since they're all packed
uniformly at the moment the W which is
the roughness value is literally just a
value that goes from 0 to 1 so we don't
have to do anything special there we
just convert it like we were converting
a color value an old school color value
that wasn't using the linear packing or
any of that stuff I'm sorry the srgb
packing so doing that would will produce
at least properly scaled normals now
although that doesn't look particularly
good that's did I did I make some kind
of mistake there I believe that's right
you take the normal x y&amp;z we produce a
range of 0 to 1 to 1 we then start from
negative 1 and we add twice that range
in I think that's right I would have
expected half the tree to look that way
but I wasn't expecting the other half to
look that way that's that's a little
it's a little suspicious to say the
least
all right so coming back down in here
let me just finish the part we were
doing so after we do the lerp of the
normal which I believe is still probably
fine I have to think about whether
there's consequences to the fact that
we're using 0 255 to encode that range
but I think we could probably lurk and
then unscaled
and emboss it into real normal range
first but then we have our thing here
where we're doing a sample environment
which I thought
was going to just draw the normal as a
color in fact what I couldn't do here
just to start with let me go ahead and
draw literally just that normal so the
Texel equals the normal and like so and
we could also force the Texel a to be
1.0 so that there's no frisking so there
we go
so our color is always black so we've
got something nasty going on there so
I'm gonna go ahead and like I said since
I'm since it's been a little it's been a
little wishy-washy in here lately
I would like to step in and just verify
that all of my stuff is happening the
way that I think it's happening because
you know I don't have a hundred percent
confidence and especially the code they
got written yesterday but we're still
coming off of it today so you know how
it is alright so I want to step in here
and see what sorts of stuff we're
actually getting when we sample the
normal map because like I said we don't
really know what we're getting out of
that so I want to see it so here's our
normal a B C and D D so when we unpack
those I'm just gonna take a look at what
we've actually got in there so I don't
understand why all of those would be
zero that doesn't seem reasonable to me
so I kind of feel like that is well you
know I suppose that could be no I don't
really know why that could be I feel
like there should be no places in our
texture map except like like they should
always be normal right so I feel like
that's just that's that suits somewhat
implausible to me so I want to know why
that is the case I'm gonna go ahead and
look at the normal map directly I'm just
gonna take a look at no no this is
exactly what I was afraid of look at
this cut and paste yesterday did not
even change the normal map we were still
sampling out of the texture it's just
ridiculous I mean how does that help you
not at all right all right so we found
problem one let's let's go back there
now okay
so let's take a look at what our normals
look like now our normal B is zero
our normalcy or normal D our normals B
and D which are the ones that are one
away look like they're totally wrong
so that is not reassuring to say the
least I'm not sure why that is these
guys look not right either because
that's not a normal one one zero is not
is not actually a normal day oh so it
looks like we're still pretty janky in
here so I'm gonna go ahead and take a
look at what that normal map actually
has in it what did I just do all right
bad key combination there I invoked the
will of Visual Studio which really you
just never want to do never a good thing
if Visual Studio starts doing this thing
just always bad alright so if we take a
look at the memory here I'm going to
look at this as an int unsigned and so I
can sort start to see what's in there so
that actually looks like a fairly
reasonable value by comparison to what
we were getting let's take a look at
some set of those values that does not
look useful to me
yeah all right so I'm gonna step out a
bit here I'm going to take a look at
what happens when we call make oops
come on here I'm gonna take a look at
what happens when we call our our sort
of sphere bitmap generator which is in
here I just want to see what that's
doing Oh awesome yeah I was right to be
to be leery let's say of yesterday's
code it was just not good right I mean
how many times are we gonna write to
this pixel the answer is we're gonna
write to the same pixel width number of
times doesn't seem particularly useful
usually you want to go ahead and move to
the next pixel when you write one yeah
just just a thought
all right so checking you look at this
guy here let's also just check this math
real quickly if I remember correctly I
was totally out to lunch in the math as
well in fact I think of pseudonym 73
hasn't stepped in it would have been a
complete disaster let's go ahead and
generate this app properly so we've got
our bitmap UV which is just where we are
in the bitmap right that's going to be
the X divided by the width and so that's
fine and we want that to yeah to
generate a nice value there for our X
and our Y so this is going to be our NX
and our my I guess right and so then our
NZ as we were saying before that should
actually just be Pythagorean theorem
squared with a grain theorem solved
right so if we just say you know this is
the sphere situation if we just say all
right we've got a sphere so this is
actually you know this is actually one
of those three-dimensional fancy spheres
if we've got a sphere and we're looking
at this fear from above so we're looking
at it downward right and so we just see
a circle then at any point here we could
figure out we know that the you know
this is an orthographic kind of
projection so we're looking straight
down on the sphere we know what the X&amp;Y
because that's just whatever our our
bitmap you know wherever our coordinate
coordinate in the bitmap is it right and
so if that's the X&amp;Y
we know that that represents some point
on the sphere right where it's taking
the x coordinate right and the y
coordinate of this of this thing in
order to know what that Z coordinate is
we know that the sphere is supposed to
be unit length right so we know that the
radius here we know that the R is
supposed to be one right so we know that
x squared plus y squared plus Z squared
is supposed to equal one right that's
what we want to have be true so what we
need to do is solve that equation so
that we can figure out what the Z is so
squaring both sides right we get this
and if we want to know what the Z is we
just have to move the X and the y to the
other side right so it's that equals Z
squared right so then it's just Z equals
square root of 1 minus x squared minus y
squared right and yeah I believe suited
him probably did that yesterday for us
but since I was out to lunch it's good
to have know someone's got your back but
point being when I'm actually present I
would be able to think of such things
and there you go so we've got
essentially this happening oops
- and - right
just we want to square root one minus
the the square of the X minus square of
the Y that's our NZ so then we've got
our normal and we know that our normal
is just NX + y + Z all right so now
those values all range from negative 1
to 1 obviously our NZ never points
backwards because like we said we don't
ever really point backwards so
technically and only red ranges from 0
to 1 but we're kind of ignoring that
aspect at the moment so then we got to
pack those in here we pack those in here
by first changing them into the range of
0 to 1 and then multiplying by 255 which
should do the trick and then we go ahead
and and put that roughness value in
there at the end that should just about
do it we do the truncation and
shifting to put the ALF at the top which
is really our roughness and then we have
the our G's and B's value now that
packing is not probably what we really
want to see right you know if we think
about this when we do our unpack it's
gonna unpack is that I'm gonna unpack
into the proper order just want to make
sure here where's our unpack unpack that
unpack is is actually reproducing it
properly so that's that's okay so we're
good so that's fine so let's see if
we're getting any closer to having
actual normals coming out here that are
actually usable I hope I still have yeah
okay I hope I still have my break points
out there so let's see what these
normals are let's see what these normals
are I still like two to five two five
zero why are we having that as our
values that doesn't make a whole lot of
sense to me oh right
that is one other thing we that that's
the other problem that we had before
which is that we have to sort of take
into account the fact that we're
sometimes off the sphere so you know
when we're drawing this guy since we're
filling the whole bitmap we're gonna be
filling values in that are actually over
here so we're probably gonna want to
make up something reasonable for these
guys what we could do is say anything in
here just points like straight up or
something right
so it's zero zero one let's say again
there's really not I mean I guess you
know what the other thing we could do is
just say it's just whatever the closest
value was on the sphere right that's the
other thing we could do that seems
somewhat reasonable so what we can do is
say oh you know what let's take this and
we'll say this is our root term right
and so there's our root term and so you
know once this gets up to the point
where it's going to be greater than than
one so the root term goes negative right
so you know the case where
the case where MZ will say if root term
is greater than or equal to zero then we
can actually do this properly right
because the square root will actually be
somewhat defined
but once we get to to the place where it
would go negative we would be in
imaginary numbers which would not be
good so what we want to do is is replace
it with something more useful and in
fact that I might actually argue that
what I what I should do I guess we'll do
it like this first but we might do
something a little bit fancier later so
there so basically what we do is we say
all right we'll compute this using the
square root method assuming that we're
on the sphere if we're not on the sphere
we'll just assume that it just points up
for now but we probably want to do a
little something different later if we
ever wanted to use these four things so
let's go ahead and see if that helped at
all in terms of dealing with they're out
of bounds and there we go those are much
more reasonable so those are zero zero
one which is exactly what I would have
expected them to be at that point when
we do the lerp we should get a
reasonable result back course these are
all the same so you should have done the
same thing back and then when we take
our normal and we unbias and scale it
hopefully it will produce what we think
it will should produce which is zero
zero one which is roughly what it did so
that's good although I wonder why we've
kind of want 128 to map exactly to that
so we should probably take a look at
that I think anyway let's take a look at
what that looks like first just for for
starters here
oops there we go so that's not though so
now we're still we're getting basically
nothing is ever inside for some reason
which is a little bit odd like why are
we we're never getting any any
reasonable values in there we're just
getting pointing straight up right
that's all we're ever singing which
seems odd to me I'm not sure why we're
we're always filling in that same value
we do do the root term here where we're
saying 1.0 minus an x + y a-- that
should be you know that should be
computing that at least sometimes let's
take a look at why that is yeah so we're
never actually getting that value okay
let's let's switch back in there
all right could we run please thank you
so taking a look at these values n x and
y both negative 1 that's what I would
expect totally reasonable
let's bitmap you V should be 0 0 right
and it is so as we walk through here
what that doesn't make any sense to me
why is that negative man
yesterday's code was awful I feel like
this should have been shown this should
have been like on the stream this the
entire time yesterday just like it
should have been it should have been the
owl sitting there the entire time
Howie this is just ridiculous that's not
okay like how did that get there this
should be that right I mean that doesn't
make any sense that man when you're when
you're not with it you're not with it
that's just absurd alright let's try
that one more time okay that looks a lot
more like a normal map so I think we're
we're getting back into a more
reasonable space here if you will
looks a little janky so I think we've
probably got some stuff we still need to
work out but point being we're at least
in in you know territory that's not
totally absurd so that's good so you
know it's baby steps anyway so there's
are they're sort of our known weapon and
this is what we would expect to see
right in fact we we probably we could
just for the sake of drawing it we could
actually rebuy us and scale it you know
if you will inside the render group
where we're outputting it as the color
we could actually view something where
we say all right
don't actually
you know don't actually draw it in the
negative one to one range boost it up a
bit so multiply this by by you know 2.0
and and add one to it I'm sorry by 0.5
and add 0.5 to it just to get it back
into the valid range of colors so
basically we can see that you know in
and out where we're actually getting the
the proper stuff right and and that
looks about right so you can kind of see
how you get like the amount of red
increases as you come over this way the
amount of green increases as you come
down and so on and you know that's just
that's just more of a sensical that's
that's more of a sensible thing you can
kind of see how it looks like either our
lerp is not quite right or something
we're getting some weird like like it it
feels like we've done something slightly
incorrect somewhere in here and I'm not
exactly sure where so I feel like we
kind of want to take a look at what's
going on in there a little bit more
careful okay like we shouldn't be having
so much Genki 'no stare now if I turn
off the normal mapping if I just get rid
of this entirely you know my tree I
guess it might be hard to see if the
tree was janky right because I mean it's
not as clean as this is so maybe
wouldn't necessarily show maybe what we
should do is instead of using that tree
maybe we should use something that's a
very well-defined shape for testing
purposes that seems like a very
plausible thing to do just somethin
think about but I'm kind of interested
to know like is it well you know what
one thing I could do pretty pretty
trivially here right is if I go back in
here and I say all right we've got the
tree if I was to just say draw the tree
normal without you know just pretend as
a texture map what does that look like
right and so here's what that looks like
and
yeah I mean even looking at obviously
it's doing sRGB weirdness stuff I'm not
sure why this would be yellow exactly I
have to think about that oh because it's
it's 128 is the is the zero value but
you can see that the edges are not all
janky as well so I'm just I'm curious as
to what why our sampling was so weird on
the normal map I feel like it should
have not been so not been so odd right
so I feel like we've got to maybe do a
little looking at that coach to make
sure there isn't something really
strange happening as to why it looks so
weirdly banded like that basically so
when we do our lookups here we're doing
the lookups in the normal map the exact
same way that we're doing them in in
sort of the for further regular texels
right I mean there's really nothing this
is the exact same code right ah there we
go again Scott basically today is just
fixing all of the bugs that were in
yesterday's code so hey big surprise you
get the pitch wrong you sample out of
the wrong place in the texture so there
we go there's our normal map and that's
better and we could actually we could
probably turn this into a function to
just to make it a little less
error-prone right we could say okay
we've got an inline gear which is you
know something that takes a bilinear
sample so it's like you know bilinear
sample from one of these loaded bitmaps
right so we have a loaded bitmap that
you pass in and that's the texture and
then we have you know an x and a y right
x and y that you wanted to sample that
we can then do all of these samples
together and we could just return those
you know in a little struct that was
like a bilinear sample right like so
and so we could just say ABCD like we
did before and we'll just do this result
that a result dot B result dot C so
you'll be returned results so that is
that so let's take a look there there we
go
I'm gonna go ahead and change these guys
over to that so I'll do bilinear sample
Texel sample something like that no no
yeah call it by Texel or now Texas
samples good alright so we'll do Texas
sample we want to do that
by linear sample of the texture X and
the y like so and then in theory we
should just now be able to do Texel
sample a textile sample B Texas sample C
like so sample D right everything's good
and then we can do that here as well so
we got by linear sample normal sample by
winning your sample grab that oops
grab that normal map out go ahead and
get the X and the y same thing and that
should be it right just do a normal
sample a normal sample B from a sample C
and normal sample D ok so now we are
back to reasonable here I think at least
somewhat reasonable it does kind of look
a little odd like it feels like it's a
little clip to potentially so something
else I don't know if we want to look at
a little more carefully but point being
so if we now go ahead and switch back to
this path we would see our sort of
normal map kind of color stuff
modulating against the tree so we know
that both of them are getting sampled
relatively correctly so that's good all
right so I think we're in better shape
now we can actually start to do
something here so the next thing that we
kind of need to figure out is what we're
gonna do with these environment maps
right because we need to pass something
in there so that we could sample them
right and we also have to kind of figure
out how we want to modulate them in
right we have to decide what we want to
do in terms of actually producing the
colors here now what we could do is just
say that we add them together and that
might be reasonable I don't know I mean
we you know we could say this sort of
thing we just add however much life
there is to whatever's there you know at
the moment and obviously you know we
would want to make it so it would not
overflow so for a lot of these we'd have
to actually clamp them right we'd have
to go ahead and take after we were done
we'd have to to clamp all of the values
right so our our would have to be
clamped zero to one so there we go so if
we add the light in you know that's
that's what we're looking at also
obviously we well actually I guess so we
have another problem here which is that
the light color this is all
premultiplied alpha so our light color
whatever we grab out of the light color
is going to have to be multiplied by the
texels a value right because the texels
a value is what actually we're expecting
everything to be pre x so that's one
more thing that we have to do right so
now we have our thing which is lit by
our normal map but our normal maps not
actually gathering any light values so
we're literally just using the values
that are in that that normal map itself
to do the lighting which is pretty
useless right to say the very least so
we want to do now is we want to go ahead
and actually try to grab that lighting
out of something right
so so we got to start tackling our map
stuff let's take a look at here that's
sort of what we had yesterday we did the
unscalable enormo so that's all good hmm
excuse me we then we're saying we're
gonna see which n vac we were using by
grabbing the normal Z but like I say
it's really the normal Y that we want to
use for that not the normal Z the normal
Y is what tells us where we are and now
of course the normal Y actually goes
between negative 1 and 1 and so this
testing is not actually at all what we
would want it to be I think right we
probably want something more like this
again this is yesterday's code which is
all awful that's the that's what we've
pretty much learned so we want to do is
say you know whatever the the actual
pointing value is that we choose to use
and like I said we'll probably have
multiple modes that pick from different
values here but whatever we choose to
use we say okay we've got the T and map
if that's less than then then the
negative 0.5 then we're going to sample
from that bottom map and if it's if it's
greater than 0.5 then we're gonna step
it from that top map we then need to
produce how much we want to blend in
that top map and an bottom map so for
the bottom map if it's less than
negative 0.5 that means it's ranging
from 1.0 to 0.5 right so in order to
figure out what we actually want to do
we need to take the M map and we need to
you know base it off of that bottom
value that negative 1.0 value right so
it's subtracting negative 0.1 or adding
1.0 and then we need to divide it by its
total range which is just the the 0.5
right so that way like I said if it's
negative 1 we just end up with 0 if it's
negative 0.5 which is the maximum it
could be then it'll just be 1 the T for
our map will be
so similar we come and cured a TM map
greater than 0.5 so again same exact
math right we want to subtract where it
starts from essentially from it so now
it's ranging from 0 to 0.5 and then we
just again divide by that point 5 right
so that should be it I would think of
course dividing by 0.5 is the same as
multiplying by 2 so we could just save
ourselves trouble right and do it this
way but that should give us that should
give us what we want right that should
give us what we're looking for we then
go ahead and do our sampling and we
sample at least one of these guys if we
ended up picking one of these far Maps
the top or the bottom that we want to
contribute in there then we go ahead and
do our sampling for that as well right
so to do that sampling we were passing
the normal X Y Z it's a little unclear
if that's really what we want we kind of
have to think about this a little bit
because again like the X the Y and the Z
what do they really mean I guess we can
pass into the sample environment map
this way and have sample environment map
kind of know what they mean but
it's just one of those things where it's
a little confusing right so let's think
about this for a second because now we
actually have to do this math here what
we essentially have is we have we have a
circumstance where we're looking at a
point in the world and we've essentially
turned these into barycentric
coordinates right we're essentially
looking at something because I wanted
we've got our screen space UV which is
sort of telling a you know it's it's
telling us where we are versus our
environment Maps right so it's kind of
telling us like okay you know if it was
here then maybe that's a point too right
maybe this is 0.2 and that's like 0.8 or
something right
that's the screen space view screen
space V so we know we're like here and
then we have some normal which is
telling us you know in this sandwich you
know this is like the lowest layer of
our sandwich right let's say well I
guess it's really not it's the middle
layer right we've got here here so from
this point we then have a normal and
that normal is you know pointing in some
direction and so now what we need to do
is say okay
for the normal pointing in that
direction we need to figure out how we
want to do the intersection like we need
to figure out how to pick the point
where we were where we are looking at
you know in our environment map right
and essentially what I said before is
that maybe 0.5 we're basically choosing
a 45-degree I think well I guess that's
not entirely true if it's 0.5 then yeah
I mean basically what we're saying is
the deflection off of the Z is not going
to be more than 0.5 what to think about
what that actually is cone wise but
point being we sort of got a cone that
we're looking up in and a cone that
we're looking down in and we want to
produce like which pixel on the map we
would hit for each of the normal values
inside there and then when it comes out
and it's more a lateral we then are no
looking in that we are looking strictly
in this sort of middle plane where which
is kind of the problematic plane the one
where we don't really know what we're
gonna do about it so we've got to
environment types we've got the
environment type up here we've got the
umberto type down here we've got two of
those that are probably more
straightforward to answer and then the
one that's we don't really know we're in
deal with right so I think if I'm not
mistaken this middle sample here we
could just say for now if that middle
sample we know is is not happening right
we know that's not happening so assuming
that we actually have one of these farm
apps then we'll sample the farm app with
that and of course again since it's
yesterday's code it was garbage and it
wasn't even passing the actual map that
we picked but now it is and so we grab
that farm app out and then we actually
lurk between the colors based on on that
so what we need to do is make sample
environment map actually produce some
kind of value that we can use here right
so this up here so sample environment
map is going to produce it's going to
give us hopefully what we want
given some map that we have the first
thing I think we're going to do is take
the roughness out of the equation so
we'll say that we have logs here I'm
gonna get rid of this wit pipe power of
two stuff for now because we don't
actually care about it at the moment and
we'll just say that we have some number
of level of details here what I'm gonna
do is say okay whatever the roughness
level is that's what picks in into our
log levels and what we'll do is we'll
just set all the lot of levels to point
to the same bitmap at first so we kind
of take roughness out of the equation
right but it's pretty straightforward we
just say okay however many of those we
have write whatever this value is here
so the the map blog however many of
those we have we just want to
essentially quantize this this roughness
value to fall into one of those buckets
right and so what we're gonna do is say
and later we could
you know we could actually try to blend
between them if we if we really wanted
to as well
but anyway so what we want to do here is
say all right we take that roughness we
multiply it by the array count which
will give us back a number between you
know zero and whatever that level is
we'll do the rounding on it like before
right and we'll come up with you know an
integer roughness level here right so
this is our this is our roughness
integer right and or I guess we could
say our roughness index maybe are a lot
but it's called out a lot index right so
we do this and then we want to to cast
this guy down right so we want to say
whatever this guy was we are now going
to cast him down into the lot index and
then we can assert in here as well that
the lot index is always less than
whatever that array count was right so
we shouldn't ever be able to fetch
outside the array actually now that I
think about it this is actually supposed
to be array count minus 1 right because
we want produce 0 1 2 3 so ya think we
actually want to save that right makes
sense
so that gives us our lot index back and
then from there we can go ahead and grab
the law that we actually want so now
we've got a loaded bitmap and this is
our LOD so that's our map would be LOD
index oops so once we have that out
mm-hmm we can go ahead and take a
bilinear sample of that value right and
then actually compute whatever that
should be right so we can go ahead and
say you know we've got our LOD and so
now we just need to figure out what are
our texts our x and y coordinates will
be in the L in the map you know we can
take that bilinear sample
and once we have the sample then we can
actually do the loop on it right and
what we could do to here is say that you
know since we already know how all this
stuff works
we could also smack this down into a
thing which is that bilinear sample
could then
have a function that was like bilinear
blend so we could just say as well
bilinear blend here and then we just
kind of grab all this stuff up and say
that our textile sample can do that sRGB
bilinear blend let's say right that and
this will basically do srgb bilinear
blend that'll take a textile sample and
basically do all of the stuff it needs
to do to do the alert right so that's
kind of cool because then we can just
say bilinear sample sample so and right
we need the to the F X F Y values so
those are the percentage off that you
are so we need the FX and FY now we're
back to this so when we do this again we
would have to do to produce the actual
color in fact I guess I get rid of that
and say that the result it's going to be
equal to that srgb bilinear blend of
course it's only it's only part of it we
don't actually use the Alpha component
rank so it's really just that much of it
but there's our sample and so really all
we need to do is actually do that
intersection math now right we actually
need to figure out how we're going to to
intersect it once we do that we should
be just about done this guy has to
actually take the FX FY as well right
and let's see this stuff can all be
probably collapse down into functions as
well here yeah because this is all this
is all the same as what we would use to
sample the that bitmap as well right we
take the U and the V and we expand them
out I'll have to think about this a
little bit more to think about this a
little bit more
this stuff is all the same
as well I'll copy it for now but I think
maybe we probably just want to condense
that down all right so we're in here
I'll rename these to the this sort of
the stuff that we were using before
we'll call this XY so and so now we
really just need to know what those
values actually are
I think we're basically that time we
only have about two minutes left so I
don't think I'll have time to cover the
intersection math today we're just about
to push it till Monday which I suppose
is fine because that will put us into
when we're supposed to actually working
on the light stuff that we'd be sampling
anyway let me double check that we've
got everything here so here is our our
map right width and height
oops sorry our LOD like so and I think
all this stuff is fine so we'll just say
for now px and py or nothing like so
oops
turn salt there we go
and this should crash us I would think
um to be honest with you I do not know
why it did not because we aren't passing
valid environment maps oh I guess
because we do test it here so we do test
to see if our map actually is valid so I
guess it won't crash us all right so
we're all good we just need to actually
generate those maps now which is what
we'll do next week and do a little bit
of an exception math right here do
intersection math to determine where we
should be right so that's all good so I
think we're getting closer it's just a
lot of work to do here to get all this
stuff working but yeah I think we're
getting closer really we've got
everything that we need in place but we
need to do the intersection math to
figure out where those things should hit
and then we also need to go ahead and do
you know the production of you know
basically getting the ground and the sky
into things that we sample from if that
makes sense so we've still got a ways to
go it's true
you know next week should be pretty
interesting we should be able to get a
fair bit of stuff there so let's go
ahead and go to the Q&amp;A right and I
really like I really like whoever said
this should crash us never crashes
ambition work always crashes it's true
right it's it's like the computer
doesn't want to agree with you it's like
if you say that something's gonna be
okay then it wants to make sure that you
know that that's not true and if you say
that well it won't be able to handle
this then it wants to prove you wrong
and be like oh no it does it totally
works but yeah I forgot that we were
already checking for that normally you
know when we actually go to optimize
this stuff out there won't be lots of
ifs in here so look normally it would
crash us right but
do we have any questions again most of
today was I guess just kind of cleaning
up everything and fixing what we typed
in wrong yesterday and we again did some
nice collapsing here just to get this
stuff out and you know we'll probably
actually honestly have to uncollapse a
lot of this stuff in macro style or
whatever when we do the optimization but
while we're getting stuff working it's
usually nice to be able to pull stuff
out into functions that you know work
because that way you don't make typos
that cause you lots of pain you know
that makes sense
let's see I'm sorry when you lurk to
normals you probably won't get a
normalized vector there are a few things
you can do about that would you briefly
comment on your thoughts about this yeah
sure
so I about this a little bit I don't
know if was yesterday I think it was
yesterday you if you remember on the
blackboard actually it's it's up here
somewhere
that's where did it go where did it go
this is lighting normal Maps normal Maps
normal Maps there it is
this was the diagram where us talking
about it right I was like when you lurk
between them
you get like a stumpy one which is not
really normal and if you remember what I
said back when I was doing that I was
like well we don't really need to think
about that right now because we don't
know what we're actually gonna do
sampling wise and that is true so if you
take a look at what happens here this is
the slurp is the thing that might
produce the incorrect normal the
unscalable is well do we have to correct
for that and so what I'm guessing and I
could be wrong about this but what I'm
guessing is that when we do the math
here because we're actually doing an
intersection we will be able to do it
with a non normalized normal and just
bake that normalization into the divide
I think don't quote me on that but I
suspect we'll be able to do that so
we'll see if you can't do that and you
actually need an actual normal then yeah
then you've got problems now one thing
that we aren't doing properly here is
we're not doing the this selection
correctly right this is the blend and so
the lerp normal will get the wrong blend
amount there because we're just using
the normal Y directly and so you know I
I could put to do here you know and we
could also just say you know we want to
be totally correct for now and
you know do we really need to do this
and but we could do ok just always
normalize you know the normal that comes
in right and that's totally fine right
because like I said this is the slow
path right now we're just doing it for
correctness so we could just always
normalize right after you come out in
hardware nowadays especially if you're
on a PC like on a desktop part usually
they've got fast inverse square root and
so you will you almost always don't even
you don't even store both coordinates
you store just the X and the y and you
normalize out to get the Z so like this
thing that that we did that you in fact
recommended yesterday is actually you
just do it in the shader right so you
never actually you never actually do
this Z computation you just compute it
in here right
criminal dragon how are we going to
sample lights when calculating the pixel
values for each bright will there be a
list of all the lights or will that be a
parameter of some sort no it's in a
texture that's what I was saying that's
what the environment maps are the
environment Maps we're going to write
all our lights into environment Maps and
then pull them out that way so we don't
have a list of lights we just have a
texture that way it doesn't matter how
many lights we have we could have like a
thousand lights and it doesn't cost any
more right it's just one way of sort of
simplifying things in genera whatever
happened to your almond milk I was
drinking it today I just didn't put it
in one of those bottles I need a bottle
brush those bottles are getting kind of
nasty and I don't like drinking out of
them anymore
so I need a way to like scrub them in so
first well yank should be making normal
maps for the art now - I may generate
the normal maps as using offline some
kind of offline processing so I don't
know that she'll actually make them but
yeah we're going to basically try to
have normal maps included with the art
set but how they get created I'm not
sure yet will you cover more advanced
brdf or just simple Phong like lighting
equations uh I don't know that there's
so like brdf are not really all that
useful if we don't if we're already
totally hacked lighting like you know
brdf you don't really see much you don't
see much of that until you have really
obvious stuff happening right you've got
to have like real lighting a really much
more complex lighting environment to
really start to see the results of those
so covering up having a brdf inside a
completely hacked lighting model doesn't
seem like a particularly productive
thing to do right it seems like you're
just totally throwing cycles away at
that point but I mean again it's really
pretty simple if you have a notion of
what the incoming light is you certainly
could go ahead and do some line
combination we're not doing even Phong
here right yet all we're doing we're not
even accounting for the
viewing angle yet so you know if it's
something that people want to see we
could do something here where we're like
okay I actually do a lighting model
computation here to basically attenuate
that light based on the viewing angle
and so yeah you know we could totally do
something like that because right now
and and we also here actually compute a
bounce based on the viewer direction
right there so there's a bunch of stuff
that we're just not doing and I don't
really know if you want to actually do
those things
I'll put two dudes there in case we want
to talk about them but again I'm not
sure how useful that is when everything
is totally hacked to try and like fit it
into the 2d scheme hmm what if I don't
want my game to be just normal are there
other kinds of maps I can use to make my
game more unique so yes you can use
abnormal maps and abnormal maps so
basically like where that term comes
from is is essentially there's a so
there's a thing called an a/b normal map
right
short for and they're shortened to
abnormal Maps right and basically what
an a/b normal map is is it's essentially
like you take whatever you know mapping
that you wanted to do right
so you maybe take an oral mapping right
and what you do is you make up two other
textures an A and a B well actually to
draw them properly you'd put them on
this side right and a and a B and you
introduce operators between the maps
which basically totally ruin the good
calculations that you were doing over
here but get you a completely unique
result out this side right so one thing
for example you might do here these
could be convolutions for example they
could also just be straight ahead
like ads or multiplies so like
oftentimes one thing that you might do
is like an a times would be times the
normal map would be another one that you
could do and that's how you can produce
one of these abnormal maps and then then
your game looks very unique and awful
kronole dragons some games use a bump
map
in addition or instead of a normal map
what is the difference between these and
what are the advantages or disadvantages
well probably no one's using a bump map
for lighting instead of a normal map
these days I would think if you're if
you're using a bump map nowadays like
actually using a bump map then either
you're just trying to compress your
normal map more than you could otherwise
and so you're trying to reproduce
normals from the bump values you know
what I mean or you're trying to use
actual displacements or other kinds of
like occlusion in the map so like other
effects besides lighting you know what
I'm saying
but the relationship between these is
pretty straightforward right so a bump
map and this is not a joke like this was
this is actually serious so a bump map
and a normal map right what happens is
the bump map basically says height and
this says surface direction right so if
you look at what these actually
represent you know if I take a 1d
cross-section of it like a height map
let's say the surface goes like this a
height map is just that every Texel you
just store how high it was right so
that's a bump map a normal map on the
other hand for the exact same surface
right so these these Heights actually
you know just to make it totally
concrete it's this distance right that's
what gets stored into this map the
actual normal to the surface at that
point right is what gets stored into
this map so that is what gets stored in
here
now pretty much you never really want
one of these unless you're trying to do
something else with it like I said
unless you're trying to go for a better
compression because hey this only has
store one value which is that height or
you're trying to occlusion so you need
to know what the height was because
you're trying to do stuff like if you
view it from this angle you can't see
this pixel because this pixel occluded
it stuff like that there are schemes
that do stuff like this that's for 3d
that wouldn't help you in 2d but in a 3d
game like a texture like a brick wall
that had like little mortar you know in
skews mortar things that kind of stuff
so what what's going on there is
basically the surface Direction is
always a much higher quality way to
store this information than the bump and
the reason for that is a surface
Direction can store anything including a
perfectly a full on hard edge here it
can store like things that point
directly that way or anything else
whereas the bump map can never really
capture that information because the
bump map is not storing an orientation
it's storing like a delta it's sorting
like a height that you then have to look
at the difference between to compute the
lighting right because height doesn't
tell me anything that I that I need to
tight doesn't tell me what the lighting
calculation should be because remember I
need the tangent plane to do the
lighting calculation so what I have to
do for a bump map is I have to look at
what the surrounding values are and try
to decide based on those roughly what
the normal would have been whereas the
normal map just gives me exactly that so
the normal maps always superior if you
can swing it a bump maps usually if
either you need to save space so you
don't want to take up as much space as a
normal map might take up or you're
trying to get more bang for the buck by
getting other schemes out of it so
typically what you might think of is the
normal map is sort of like storing the
derivative of the bump map like if the
bump map is is this then this is is like
you know that and more technically at
the risk of getting ridiculous at this
point it's really this it's really the
gradient of the bump map right
which is to say that it's creating a
vector that says what direction the bump
map was changing in if that makes sense
and it's it's even a little it's even
not quite that because that actually
would point that would give you if I'm
not mistaken because this is explicit
function and soon m73 can can either
corroborate or deny this basically
you've got a function that's the height
right and technically I believe since
it's an explicit function like you've
got F of UV and it's outputting this
function I believe technically you take
the gradient and you'll actually get
this tangent right and you want the
perpendicular one of that so I think
actually timely it's not even really the
gradient what it is is it's the cross
product right of the gradient versus the
function right so it's it's it's that
weird it's like I don't know what I
don't even know what that's called curl
I don't even I don't even know but it's
like the cross product of of that
original gradient that you'd get but
that's what you actually want in terms
of you know in terms of taking the bump
map and turning it into one of these so
so they are related it's just that this
is a much more expressive version
because you'd have to in order to
express all the things you could express
with this you'd have to be able to have
like essentially infinite changes in
height to sort of say what the normal
should end up being at that point
because you can't really you know since
these are fixed
you can't ever represent the fact that
the surface did things like this right
because you can't put two sample points
at the same area right so we will always
think that if you showed if that would
always think it was this but really
maybe it was more like this right I
don't know if that makes any sense
hopefully it does
well the effect end up like a bump map
effect yes so it's basically normal maps
are basically the more powerful version
of a bump map right a bump map is like a
worse version of a normal map if that
makes sense
could we do reflections by using our
frame buffer as an environment map when
drawing the bitmap yes that actually is
what we'll be doing so that's basically
how we'll have things sort of reflect
the ground and that sort of thing again
I'm not sure how it'll work out but
that's just what we're going for
that's like what we're trying right if
you imagine the surface as an implicit
function it's the grating of that
function yes exactly like if we actually
had a function that instead of being
explicit so it's not this but it's like
an explicit function which I'm sorry if
it's an implicit function so you
actually have a value for it everywhere
and you're looking for the iso contour
then it's the gradient yes but but we
don't a bump map isn't that a bump map
is it's explicit so yeah you kind of
have to do the you kind of have to take
this guy you have to take the tangents
the actual tangents of these guys and
you have to take their cross-product
right so you know if you looked at it
this way it's like okay so we have for
any point we have a tangent for the U
direction and a tangent for the V
Direction right so we've got these and
we have to cross them to get that normal
right we haven't covered cross products
and we won't because it's a 3d thing
really that we probably won't ever need
to cover maybe we would eventually but
you know a cross product yeah so it
would be a gradient or it's sort of like
a gradient but unfortunately we can
actually do it that way because the bump
map is is again it's explicit not
implicit unfortunately
alright looks like we have come to the
end of the questions
alright yeah looks like we're done
lovely lovely okay so let me go ahead
and close everything down here and I
saved this right double check okay all
right thank you everyone for joining me
for another episode of hand made here oh
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always
I think we're basically finished with
the with the sort of normal map cleanup
stuff there it looks like everything is
working properly now so next week what
we should be able to do hopefully you
start to build those lighting sample
buffers and then actually sample out of
them using our normal maps that are
being passed through properly now it's
gonna be a little experimental next week
because we really don't know exactly how
you know exactly what would be good ways
to do all the stuff that we kind of want
to do here so yeah it's a little it's a
little wonky but you know we'll do the
best that we can anything with lighting
even in a 3d environment it's always a
hack
because simulating lighting correctly is
too difficult and so you're always
coming up with sort of these
approximations that are sort of what
you're doing because you don't have time
to do a full light transport solution on
your scene obviously you know oftentimes
those take minutes to do even today so
you kind of have this situation where
yeah we're not really at the point where
we can do real lighting transports so
it's always an approximation and that's
okay that's just where we're at and so
we will play with those approximations
next week until we get something or
maybe even for two weeks who knows how
long it will take us but we'll keep
playing with them until we get something
that we feel like we can use as sort of
the basis for our render setup right so
I hope you'll join me for that same time
same place on
Monday I believe although definitely
always check the Twitter for the
scheduled I believe it should be 5 p.m.
on Monday same time same places was
today so yeah thanks for joining me if
you would like to follow along at home
and want to access to the source code
you can pre-order it on handmade hero
ductwork and use the little pre-order
button that'll get you access to the
source code if you want to follow along
at home there's also a patreon page if
you want to subscribe and support the
video series it's much appreciated we
also have a forums site where you can
ask questions you can also look at ports
to Mac to Mac and Linux that the
community's done there you can also look
at the anti depe sewed guide which is
pretty awesome and we have a tweet bot
as well which tweets the schedule at you
so if you'd like to check that out
that's a good thing to subscribe to sue
but you know when essentially the this
shows gonna be live so thanks to him for
joining me hope see you next week have a
wonderful weekend and we will pick up
where we left off on Monday