hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we code a complete game
live on stream it is time for us to
actually you well I I don't want to say
use but have some fun with I guess our
we made a memory visualization so we
could see how we were using memory and
handmade hero and the reason I wanted to
do that was because our enemy structure
is super piggy and that was intentional
we just don't care about it right now
but I would like to move into a phase of
the product where we do care and have
some idea of what we're doing with that
and in order to do that I wanted to have
a memory visualization we could look at
just to have some idea of what was going
on there so I just to I guess give some
perspective on where that was at for
people who may have missed it that's not
high school remedy what we want to do
here also I don't I think I'm behind on
my remedy you know what
pause everything I just said do we need
to update our to bugger how do I update
my debugger update my debugger download
download I don't know how to use this
thing I don't know I've never known how
you're supposed to use this thing all I
know is I had to use it to get remedy so
I did it's there a remedy that there we
go remedy dot H dot IO alright so I want
to say there's have been a fairly major
update yah27 alright so let's get that
going
I think it has some some good features
in it too
he actually fixed he added a
cut-and-paste for us to in the watch
window just based on what we were doing
the other day he was like sorry there
wasn't one I added one for you so he
George always adds so much stuff for us
I I want to always keep up-to-date
because he's been so great about
updating it with with new features
whenever we run into stuff so yeah I
just wanted to get that get that going
okay so let's try that one more time
rewind now let's start remedy two seven
and you know what it also has that's
pretty awesome check this out it's got
this new layout feature where you can
save all your window layouts in here and
like switch between them real quick so
you can just like pull back you know oh
I want layout 0 1 2 3 and I can name
them different stuff so if we want to
have like a memory inspection one versus
like a threading one you can create
different layouts and switch and that
seems really cool I don't know how much
I will actually use it because I've
always kind of just stuck with this
layout I mean Visual Studio is crappy
and I don't think it lets you switch
layouts right quickly so I've never
really thought about that but maybe we
can try and think about that and start
to add stuff I do suspect as remedy
becomes more powerful there will
probably be other windows too and stuff
like that and then it really would make
sense to to be able to have a bunch of
different layouts either way I thought
that was pretty cool
um so anyway I'm gonna go ahead and open
up handmade hero and just show you what
I mean about the memory layout stuff so
what happens now is you know we've got
these like debug things I'm hitting the
F Keys right you can see it switching
between those and so if we go to the
memory view what it allows us to do is
see which arenas exist in the system
currently and we can name them so here
are some that have never been named and
I don't know that we care that they were
because it's only one megabyte but maybe
for completeness someday we should name
them but then you can see here we've got
for a permanent storage you can for
carrying you know allocations throughout
the game you can see that we've got 69
megabytes in use for the game itself
we've got two hundred seventy nine
megabytes used for just asset backing
storage which is just bitmaps and stuff
we keep in there for sending down to the
textures and sounds and that sort of
stuff and then
we've got a debug that's taking up 135
minutes so we don't care about that one
because that's just storing old like
debug information in case we want to you
know it's it's basically like all of
that memory arena stuff but then also
like you know this stuff here so that we
can pause frames and you know and look
at different pieces of debug information
right so we don't care about that
because that's not really relevant to
our games performance it's because it
goes away entirely but the part that I'm
interested in talking about now is this
part here the 69 megabyte number now 69
megabytes is child's play on any modern
computer you know the the Unreal Engine
game is probably a 69 megabyte
executable let alone the game but that's
not why I'm interested in it
the reason I mentioned in it is remember
our game is very minimal right now we
have only created a small number of
entities and we want to be able to
create very large worlds here and so I
want that number to be fairly small so
that I know when we create a world that
has a hundred times as many entities
into this one or a thousand times as
many entities and is this one we're not
gonna be in really big trouble and right
now we kind of would be if we wanted a
thousand times more entities than we
have right now which granted maybe we
wouldn't necessarily get to because that
might be just too big of a world for
anyone ever play but that would be what
a six gigabytes if I'm not mistaken is
that right I don't know how many that
would be but well it actually no if it's
six a nine megabytes if I do a thousand
it'd be 69 gigabytes right and so that's
just not feasible and so even a hundred
times to be 6.9 gigabytes or seven
gigabytes right so you can see why
that's a concerning number I'd like to
be able to get this down to something
smaller and more manageable and if we
look at our memory visualisation here
what you can actually see we can hover
over these guys and see who allocated
what and why what you can see here is we
have a bunch of things down here that
are probably pretty uninteresting right
you can see that these are like the
asset rendering
allocations just some basic stuff that
gotta come down here we could go figure
out what those are at some point and
take a look at them in more detail as
necessary what those arenas do and so on
but we probably don't really care about
this very much because this is the big
block here of all of our world data and
that's really what we care the most
about because it's the thing that's
going to scale up as our world gets more
complicated right so if you take a look
at what we've got here you can see that
each one of these things is sort of a
fixed sized chunk and there's a really
good reason for this the reason why each
one is a fixed sized chunk is because we
store our world in fixed sized chunks so
we pack entities into fixed sized chunks
and Buckett them away for future
reference right and so each one of these
chunks is a little storage for what's
being kept in some world data somewhere
that's what's going on right and so you
can also see we've got kind of a bug
here or at least something that's a bit
inefficient you can see that each one of
these things is about a 64 k chunk and
the last one in every block is like
fallow right there's nothing in there
and so you can see that either we have a
bug or and I don't really quite remember
exactly how we did this but this may be
how we did it when we did our we have a
block storage thing that we used in the
platform layer to like record like
pieces that got allocated it may be that
we can't store the last 64 KB cuz a
little bit of its used by that platform
layer right and so you can kind of see
that that creates a nasty wastage
situation here and granted that wastage
might go away if we turned off whatever
memory tracking is happening down there
in the platform layer but that is
something we may want to address at some
point just because we like the game to
run basically memory profile wise in
mostly the same way as it would be in
terms of layout inside
during shipping and and release so that
might be something we want to take a
look at fixing at some point if we can
but none of that is really all that
relevant the more important part here is
looking at how many 64k blocks are
actually necessary to store our current
entity load now there's one thing that I
think we want to do before we go any
further and that's just to improve this
visualization slightly and the slight
improvement that I want to do is right
now we do not differentiate at all
between block sizes they're already
always drawn exactly the same no matter
how big they are now what I mean by that
well take a look at this here right this
block is one big allocation that
somebody allocated you can see it's in
handmade asset rendering allocated it
right it's on
178 let's just go see what that is right
let me load up for coder and if I load
up and made Hiro and I go to 178 in Hana
main asset rendering here you can see us
pushing some lighting data and so this
piece of lighting data is what that
entire push is right and you can see
that it's written out in bytes it is
what is that we should probably some
commas in there huh but that is a 1
megabyte block it looks like right about
about a 1 megabyte block of data okay so
that's a 1 megabyte block of data and
this is a 64 K block of data and there's
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16
of them right so maybe 16 times 64 they
happen to line up in this case they do
so these are the same size and the
visualization is accurately representing
the difference between this block and
this block right like they're the same
size this this is the same size relative
to this as it should be right but if I'm
not mistaken there's no real reason for
that to be true and I don't know if I
can actually find a block here where
it's not true but we didn't enforce it
so we could just keep hoping that nobody
ever changes their block allocation size
but if anyone ever allocated a super
block right the the huge sub allocated
region if anyone ever allocated one of
those that was bigger than one megabyte
or smaller than one megabyte this
wouldn't line up anymore right in fact
that's a good example of it right there
so these two blocks although they are
the same apparent size on the screen are
totally different sizes
right so that one right there is like
1.7 megabytes and that one right there
is 1.1 megabytes but they're the same
size see I'm saying and again I think
that's just because the default
allocation is 1 megabyte but if so when
whenever you allocate things it's going
to allocate a megabyte block and
subdivide it up for you but if you
needed to allocate something bigger than
a megabyte it just allocates a special
allocation for you right here's another
example there you go right
that one's 3.1 megabytes so again that
that and that are all drawn exactly the
same size but they're totally different
size allocations and so while this does
let you know one piece of information
which is how each block is subdivided
accurately meaning this does show how
much of each block is used correctly any
given block size is not proportional to
how big it actually is and so what I
think we want to do before we go any
further just because we only just
finished this memory stuff
last weekend we just only barely got it
working at the end of the stream we were
like just finishing up and I went long
to do that what I'd like to do today is
just get our memory view into some more
stable state where it's properly drawing
things at sizes related to their total
absolute size so that we don't have to
inquire explicitly all the time to make
sure that we understand the sizes of
things and we can also potentially just
treat this thing as as one giant like
grid right and sort of place everything
so that we know you know one row is four
megabytes always or something right
so we can kind of see we could even draw
in markers that are like here's a 64
megabyte 64 megabyte 64 megabytes right
so we can kind of get that that
understanding more directly and you can
kind of see - why this is important like
if I go over here you see this asset
storage arena's got five allocations
right that that's that's a total number
of allocations that are in and I think
oh wait no what are these - it's so
that's the total number of allocations I
forget what these actual numbers are
we're gonna have to go back and look I
don't even remember they are I think
it's it's the total number of blocks
versus total number of allocations I
think so it's something like 67 blocks
with 1077 allocations 5 blocks with 1178
and so one of the things that I look in
here I see I don't really understand
what I'm looking at here either because
if I go through here
I don't see like I don't know where that
asset storage block is but I guess it's
this one we need to make those tooltips
not go off the screen like I can't see
what that is hole a second we can we can
cheat that though
so you can see there and and I don't
really again I don't understand why that
looks like it does so this is something
we have to kind of get we have to look
at right if you look at the asset
storage arena just looking at it here I
mean I only see like what one two three
allocations total right and so I don't
understand well for okay um I don't
understand why when I look at asset
storage if I only see you know if I only
see a few allocations and get it's
telling me there should be eleven
seventy eight of them what's going on
right so something's a little bit wonky
there as well so I feel like we just
that's what's on tap today get this
thing into a good solid state make sure
nothing weirds going on and then from
there tomorrow we can start on the
entity stuff that I wanted to do which
again we need for lighting and ground
cover just to improve the quality of the
visuals there so I'm going to go into
the debug system and just take a look at
that I the first I'm going to do is try
to look for why we're not seeing all of
those allocations I don't remember what
this is but I guess there was it was
around the profile bar stuff right yeah
here it is so if we look in here we're
not drawing suppressed arenas and so I
suppose it's possible that somehow those
arenas got labeled as suppressed but I
don't think so because again we are
seeing it show up so it wouldn't be it
couldn't have been suppressed because
we're seeing it show up we're just not
seeing enough of it show up so here's us
looking through each allocation and
here's us trying to plot that alakay
Shen has various rectangles so uh maybe
you know is this loop busted you know
what's going on let's take a look and
see what's going on with this this part
here and and why that's that's wrong so
what I'm going to do first is I want to
look at the memory lister because
essentially what I've got is two things
that disagree and so I should be able to
compare these two things and get some
idea of what am I doing differently
between the two I must be doing
something differently otherwise I
wouldn't be getting different results
right all right so let's start by
looking at the loops themselves what you
can see is that in both cases we loop
over the arena's in order this index
here I'm not sure what we're actually
using it for
oh we're just using it for sorting right
so we're not using any we're not sorting
anything in here so we don't need that
index right but otherwise these loops
are the same we check for suppression
here because we don't draw suppressed
arenas which makes sense we shouldn't
really be looking at the outlay of those
anyway and we couldn't because we any
arena that's suppressed we don't record
the exact locations of blocks so while
we could draw just the blocks themselves
which maybe you could argue we should in
fact we could just let those draw
because we do record how big the blocks
are I think let's do that let's just try
that
I mean hey we're in your improving this
thing let's see what happens in that
case so what I'd like to do here is say
all right we're going to push these rect
outlines here what I want to do is take
that arena suppression and I want to
take the arena suppression and move it
down to the place where we're actually
drawing the sub blocks like so and so
the sub blocks there will tell us
effectively like you know where all of
our subtle applications are in a
suppressed arena we don't know those
we should still know how big they are so
what I'll do here is say well we've got
this color for the overall block right
and that's what we're drawing the sort
of you know gray to indicate you know
that it's a that it's a block that's you
know been allocated and maybe not all
that's been used we'll see that gray
show through so what I'd like to do is
say well if the arena is suppressed so
in other words if this happens then I'd
like to change the color to something
else and so what I might do is say well
in the case where the arena is
suppressed maybe we make a much darker
gray so we know that just hey there's
some blocks being allocated here and we
can't really do anything with them and
they're not relevant to the running of
the game but we're still gonna show
where they are and that they were
allocated right just so we can visually
see them and know that they're there so
if we take a look at the arena's now
just looking through so I don't again
don't see any of those but I don't know
if that's because there's something
weird about the suppressed arenas that
doesn't allow me to draw the blocks or
if that's because again we've got some
kind of a bug where you know we're not
seeing the other we're not seeing the
asset allocation arena's working
properly
either so again I don't know what to
make of that that that could all you
know be more part of the problem as well
but anyway so I think I want to draw
this if I can and we'll see if there's a
way to make sure that that actually
works to some degree so let's go ahead
and keep going here so normally what we
then do is we loop over the blocks that
are in the arena and you can see me
doing that here in a sort of a block and
allocation sort of phase they're looking
at let's see so assuming that the
arena's not suppressed the looping over
the blocks looks exactly like it
normally does looking at the allocation
that also looks basically the same we're
tracking an allocation index here but
the only reason we're doing that is to
pick a color from the color table and
that really shouldn't be an issue I
don't think it's an unsigned integer and
it's getting modded by the size of the
table so that should just roll and I
can't see any reason why it wouldn't so
looking at this stuff here where we're
trying to draw them it could be that
something's wrong with the way that this
is being computed we'll have to take a
closer look at that a little bit later
but otherwise I'm not sure why we would
be having a problem here so what exactly
is this text buffer add line situation
so you know what else I'm wondering when
we're adding these rectangles is it
possible for us to run out of rectangle
run out of graphics space yeah I'm not
sure well anyway let's take a look here
at at just that tooltip thing I want to
take a quick look let's see what happens
in there
[Music]
so looking at the tooltips here well
actually but that's okay because this
only happens if you actually hit the
rectangle so that's fine too so I don't
really see any reason why this shouldn't
be drawing everything and yeah and so I
don't know I don't know what to make of
that at the very least at the very least
I would think that we should see the
blocks showing up for the other arenas
that we're not seeing and I'm not really
sure why we're not it could be because
also maybe they're too small like each
allocation is too small compared to the
size of the block I'm not sure but let
me just loop through here really quickly
and what I want to do is take a look at
the arena names there basically and see
if we ever what we are actually trying
to draw and if it looks at all sensible
you know I am to look at the names these
here I just want to see if it looks at
all sensible when we draw well you know
what why don't I just jump to draw arena
interval there so when we're drawing
this I'm gonna go to each arena here and
see you know cuz they've got names
associated with them I guess I've got to
be in debug mode there I never
understand why I restart when you could
just I don't have to restart I could
just build in debug mode but yeah I
never think of it let's try that again
so if I click on arenas now and we look
at the names so here's the debug arena
and this should still draw some blocks
right because even though it's
suppressed we should do these two we
won't do this interior bit but we should
still draw this rectangle and so my
question is like yeah what's the block
rectangle that we're drawing in this
case and so that looks like a totally
valid rectangle to draw
[Music]
right I mean and we should have been
drawing that in the sort of darker block
color as well so why why aren't we
seeing that because that should have
shown up we're drawing it in a legal
location as far as I can tell that
certainly looks like a reasonable
location to draw it and in fact let me
look at the profile rect itself just to
see what the min/max is there I mean
that just looks like exactly like what
you expect right and so I would assume
you know I think I should see a sort of
darker gray rectangle as the first
rectangle in the set right it should be
like right here there should be like a
dark gray rectangle right there and
that's definitely not what I'm seeing we
start off with the handmade world it's
not even the same arena you know what I
mean
so I've got a drawing bug here like
maybe my block Y calculation is screwed
up and I end up like over writing where
I was or something like this do you know
what I'm saying so I've got some issue
there that that just doesn't it doesn't
add up
ah so first things first this block
computation has to be outside the if so
that's probably all that was that makes
good sense all right so that should fix
the problem of why we weren't seeing the
debug blocks now we should see the debug
box because I just wasn't incrementing
the block counter when the arena was
suppressed just a typo when we added
that when we reorganized that
Loup boundary so if I go in here now and
look at the the debug version right
there you can see and you can actually
see it adding right that's it you know
we stack up a certain number of frames
of back debug information each one of
those is sort of like showing you that
we're recording more and more back
information until eventually we stop
recording because we hit our size limit
right so that's what's going on there do
we do and normally that gets hit more
quickly but because we're in debug mode
right the frame rates very slow so it
takes longer to accumulate I remember
how many frames we did 128 or something
like that and so it takes longer to
accumulate all of those frames we're
probably gonna have to make this
scrollable too because if we want to see
all of our memory and we want to draw
the debug which we could turn on and off
would also be a pretty reasonable thing
like to have a setting here that was
like one of the settings is do you want
to show suppressed arenas or not and
that seems like a good idea as well so
we should probably do that but do do do
let me see if I can do what I wanted to
do now by the way it's just compiled in
release mode
yeah so you can just switch between
release and debugging a problem which is
nice um so yeah like you can see like
we're gonna need some way of like
scrolling around this probably which is
no big deal either but you can see like
all this huge block of debug information
is we just have allocated here right and
that's the debug arena and then we've
got all our other arenas all right so
that works fine now and maybe let's add
a toggle so that we can get rid of that
just in a short term and we probably
want that to be the case in general as
well because you know if we're we don't
probably want that to be used in certain
cases so we know that there's we've got
sort of this idea of storage for our
different like here's the profile graph
for example here's the arena view so we
could have a thing here that's like hey
show suppressed or not right and so what
we could do is when you get called in
here and you've got that graph ID I want
to say that that dev you I there can now
access this information and have like
basically a switch that turns it on and
off that's my story and I'm sticking to
it
I don't actually know if that's true or
not uh well it's not mmm it's this thing
it's the graph ID
it's that graph ID used anywhere you
know what that may not actually be used
anywhere but surely you would want to
use it sometime like don't you want to
know that information
try profile bars total clocks well I
think we may have to pass it down then I
guess I don't know I'm not really sure
how we were meant to recover those
because it's been too long but when we
actually draw these we have that graph
information and I guess we just don't
pass it down maybe I'm not sure but if
you look here right when this gets
called you can see that we have the
graph available here I guess we just
don't send it but I think we want to
because it seems like something you
would want to have right
so I feel like we want these folks to
have access to this graph and so in here
we would just want both of those to be
able to look at it because that's where
we would put settings about what to
include in our various memory views the
example being whether or not suppress
arena show up but there's other reasons
why we might want to put that in there
right all right so what I'd like to do
here is say that inside this we want to
look whenever we're going through this
this bit here I guess I want to suppress
the entire operation of it so I want to
kind of do like don't do anything if the
arena is suppressed if the arena is
suppressed and show suppressed isn't on
so what I'm going to say is if it's not
suppressed run it or if suppress is on
run it right
and then the same exact piece of code
would be used up here so when we get
into one of these we would just suppress
like that arena entirely and not even
draw the blocks if it's you know got
that turned off and so then we just need
some way of allowing the user to
actually choose whether or not it is or
isn't and so we need to put a button in
there that basically says like suppress
or not you know show debugger don't show
the debug stuff so yeah if I look it for
draw top mmm list or whatever it's
called there in here we just need one
well there is the boolean button right
there
so what I want to do here is say let's
add another button and that button is
going to be like debug or something and
what I want to do is have graph show
suppressed and that itself is the
boolean we're talking about the
interaction is going to do what here
well actually so I don't know that it's
well I guess this is fine so it's just
going to take our show suppressed and
it's going to toggle it right it's all
that's gonna happen so we just want it
to be like not show suppressed I think
that's all we actually need right
I think coups
I meant graph
so all I'm trying to do there again is
just have a way of controlling whether
that chef shows up or not in case we're
interested in it and so then when we go
here you know the hope is though well
that didn't work very well did it
oh so it looks like I don't actually
count the arenas in that loop I assume
that all the arenas are actually there
and so hmm wonder how I want to modify
that so I guess the way I would do it is
say well we do the arena count here and
then I guess what I would probably do is
actually have the arena count get set
so whatever the index ends up being here
I would set the arena count to that so
when we're done I would just say like
arena count equals index so that we get
rid of the ones that we're not using
right and of course I actually need to
do this oops this has to only happen
when we use the index I could do it like
that as well
so I think that's good enough for that
and should take care of the fact that we
were then we were using some arena we
were using some things in our index Hort
that never got filled in so if I include
the debug arena you can see that it pops
in there right and I the reason I wanted
this in both because you're saying like
well why would you care if it was
including here these percentages are
based on the total that gets used so if
I turn on debug it changes my
percentages right because it includes
the debug in there when it calculates
what percentage is getting used so
having the above the app be off computes
the percentages for the actual runtime
of the game and lets me see that like
okay 80% is in the asset store and 20%
in the game entities right and that's
better that's a more useful heads-up
view if I go into the actual arena
layout view here same thing is true
right I can now see that with or without
the debug and that's nice okay so
problem number two now we've got that
out of the way why are we not seeing
assets
or allocations from the asset system why
are we not seeing them show up as
multiple blocks in here right so there's
a couple things it could be happening
and I have no idea which one is it seems
unlikely that the thing I'm about to say
is true but we're gonna say it anyway in
fact I know it's not true just looking
at this just just looking at this I can
tell us not sure so never mind so let me
say what I think the problem is just in
general so looking at this again I'm
worried about the difference between
these two you know I'm saying I look at
this and I see this allocation number
and I look at this and I can't find
theirs where are they right they're just
not what's going on and so something
something isn't adding up and we need to
find out what it is
so in here trying to think of like what
the best way to approach this would be
but if I go into the if I go into the
draw top mmm list there and we just look
in here at like what you know what is
the actual stuff when we're tracking
these allocations so when we print this
out we print out the total number
allocated and the total number used is
that right what does that mean
so allocated is blocks right so this is
the total number of blocks which is what
we thought maybe I'll do this
right so now just to underscore this
right and that's not a very pretty
printout
maybe we can just put it at the top in
fact that seems better why don't I do
that take this thing and then put it up
here I've got advance the line don't I
yeah I think we have tools for doing
this text out now I should probably be
using them but you know oh well so if I
want to just take this and print a
header here what I want to do is keep
this formatting essentially and so what
I need to do is say well we were
previously doing four spaces one two
three four right and then we had
megabyte which is one two and a space
and then we had some number of percent
here so Oh 5.02 is five total spaces for
it right so one two three four five then
we had a percent sign that's one and
space then we had four one two three
four and then we had one and then we had
eight one two three four five six seven
eight and that's the total width right
that's the thing so if that's the total
width oops I guess with virtual white
space I can't really line those up can i
that's a bummer
well let's try this again so if that's
the total width and I want this to be
lined up I can just do like blocks and
Alex right something like that
and that way we can just see what the
heck these things are because otherwise
I don't know oops
what do we do wrong allocated undeclared
identifier that's a good point
none of this stuff should be there there
we go so again this is just me trying to
make it so that we won't accidentally
miss read those or forget what they were
you know refer to because you know two
months from now we're gonna be like what
was that alright so I just need to push
those forward a bit yeah so much for my
poor counting abilities something like
that if you really want to get fancy you
dab columnar displays here so you could
just sort of say like here's the table
and here's the headers right we're not
gonna do that but you could alright so
that seems better now you can kind of
see where those are and what they refer
to maybe I'll move it back a little bit
and call it a day and so now we have to
go to do the actual debugging to figure
out what's going on here and why we
can't sort of tell why why we're getting
so many allocations recorded and and
what's happening so one of the things
that I would like to be able to do and
right now I guess we don't
super have a way to do this it would be
nice to merge by string where these
allocations are coming from and we don't
really have a way to do that right now
like we don't have a like a little
string combiner basically like a little
string hash thing although I don't know
for all I know maybe we do we have a lot
of stuff in here doesn't well so we sort
of hash by strings sometimes and using
debug elements I guess we do that
sometimes but it would be nice to have
something where we sort of summed up by
string which ones are which under each
arena because every arena has some
number of call sites that are right like
there's some number of call sites in our
code and each one of those call sites is
responsible for some subset of the call
of the allocations and when we look in
this mode we can see that by hovering
but when we're in this mode we actually
can't write so this just says the arena
but we have no idea like yeah we have
like no idea who is responsible for each
one but I want that back one and over
three
I don't know if that's quite right we'll
find out yeah sue
so yeah I mean I'm tempted to just say
like under each of those we should just
list the call sites so that when we
print it out we then just list like each
for each call site here's how much
memory was allocated how many calls to
that call site how much memory allocated
for that call site right and so like I'm
tempted to just write a little thing in
place and again this is the this is the
one place where like C and C++ are just
always crappy you have no choice but to
use some super terrible templates or
something if you just want like a
generic way to hash strings they just
don't have good meta programming support
so it's always a pain in the butt to use
any kind of generic structure it comes
out horrible but I'm tempted to do
something here where we can just keep
track of this in a trivial way and
thankfully like anything else and see
writing one from scratch is actually
quite simple
so it's no big deal but if we want to do
this we could just say alright let's
just create a it well in fact the debug
memory entry might actually be what we
want I'm going to move that out here
it's not quite so I'm going to make a
different one
so this is our like debug memory call
site and I'm just gonna say that we've
got some way of referring to like the
name of the call site and that's just
gonna be used for coalescing and then
I've got just a single statistic that's
like the Alec the amount allocated so
this will track the number of bytes and
the number of calls from this particular
call site right and so to do this
there's not really a lot to it all we
have to do is every time through each
one of these things as we're seeing
these call sites stack up we can just
remember them and put them in here right
and since I'd like this to be per arena
and I'd like that to be true even if
it's like remember call sites encode the
call sites themselves are I'm not sure
how to say this so an arena is an actual
thing that exists in memory right we
have a pointer to it and it's like a
chain of of like blocks that gets sub
allocated right so a single physical
location in the code like a single line
of code there's not out there doesn't
have to be a one-to-one mapping between
that line of code and the arena it's
using write because a single line of
code could just be have been passed
which arena to use for its allocation so
that means I've got two separate things
I'm trying to track there's the arena's
and there's the call sites and I want to
print out how much each call site
contributed to each arenas allocations
so I want to do this multiple times and
record separate entries for each call
site per arena makes sense and there's
really two ways I can do this and I
don't really know that I care which one
I do so I guess I'll just do the
more stringent one first so I'm going to
stick the arena in here
and I'm gonna stick the call site next
pointer in here for hashing purposes
right then I'm gonna go ahead and say
give me a hash table because why not and
so right at the top here where we're
taking temp memory up I'm gonna say give
me an array of pointers to call site
things right so there's my call site
hash and I'm gonna yeah I don't know how
many there's gonna be mm let's say call
site hash size is 128 then what I'm
gonna do is say the debug memory call
site with no click well actually I do
want that cleared so I want pointers to
those i allocate that and off we go
each time I come through here when I see
a particular type of allocation what I
want to do is now look up in my hash
table to find that allocation and I want
to find it keyed off of not only its
call site but also which arena was
responsible for that particular
allocation so that I match it to the
correct one if that makes sense
so what I'm going to do first is going
to compute its hash value and I don't
know we've got a string hash here
somewhere
so here it is right and these
allocations that we've tracked they've
got the grid right here and to be
consistent I suppose I should also take
a second to make sure that this is named
weed because name is probably not right
so if I take the string hash of this
grid at the time when I'm actually doing
the summation then what I can do is look
it up in my call site hash and I can
just try to find where it goes so
I need to mod by the call site hash
sighs and then that gives me my hash
value or really it's the hash slot index
right and so then I say in my call site
hash I loop from there and say for each
one of these things I might call this
test I'm just gonna see if I can find a
match so I'm going to say if the arena
equals the arena that I'm talking about
right now and the grid equals the grid
I'm talking about right now right so I
need to do a strings are equal here but
but since these grids come for me and a
call site really I don't have to do that
I don't have to actually test for
equality there I can just compare the
pointers because they're the same right
I'm gonna track the actual pointer to
the string so there's no need to compare
them I can't have two places that
generate the same string but different
string pointers that's not allowed in
fact we go out of our way to prevent it
by inserting a counter into each grid to
prevent this very thing right so if this
is correct then what we want to say is
hey we found the thing right so we'd say
we found it done so that allows us to
collect you know anything that's already
in the hash table and so if we didn't
find it we just need to create one here
if we did find it which we will have at
this point we just now need to make sure
that we record into its allocated
exactly the same thing we were doing
here so we're just gonna do this
statistic twice but instead of going
into this one we're going to go into
this one instead right so presuming that
allows us to accumulate for call sites
as well as arenas which is what we
wanted
and so then in here when I'm looking and
I don't find a site no big deal
all I have to do is push a new one on
right and remember we're in temp memory
here so we can do whatever we want I can
just do a push struct on to that
temperature temporary nough and we don't
care because it's all going away in a
moment so it's it's you know no harm no
foul
okay so I'm gonna push struct on there I
know that what I want is one of these
debug memory call sites and I know that
I don't really need to clear it because
well actually I might as well because I
gotta clear out the statistic it's fine
so to push one of those on and then I'm
going to set it up correctly so the next
in hash is going to be the call site
hash for that hash light right like so
the arena is the arena and the quids the
grid oops don't ask me why that isn't
there because I don't know and that's it
actually right and so then we just need
to update our hash table to record the
fact that we added a new one and then I
think we're done so that should now
build a complete attribution table that
says who is responsible for each portion
of this thing and that's next in hash
and so now when I run this we won't
really see anything different but if I
didn't screw anything up we are now
building that hash table in the
background and so when I come in here
and view this thing we should now be
able to add a new button here that's
like much like we can set debug on or
off we should be able to also set to me
we should be able to also set a call
sites on and off in yeah in in that just
like we did show suppressed right so
here we would say show call sites and so
in terms of show call sites what I want
to do is just again look for where we
did show suppressed
and previously yeah alright so just do
this all sites and show all sites all
sites like so and so now we have the
ability Jenny now we have the ability to
turn call sites on and off and all we
need to do is add a mode in here that
will display them as we kind of go down
the list so what I'm going to do is
we're going to print this thing out and
then what we're going to do is if that
call sites thing is true so if we said
show call sites then now what I want to
do is go through my hash table to me and
for anything that's in this arena I want
to print out those call sites one by one
now I could use a chain to do that but I
don't care so I'm not going to because
it's just not going to cost me enough
time and Plus this number this is the
top clucks this time in the wrong place
sorry about that I meant this one so
when I print this out I then after we do
this I'm going to go ahead and put it in
here you technically should probably be
here
if we said to show call sites I'm gonna
loop through and remember this number
yeah I don't this is just the size of
the hash table in terms of efficiency
the number of call sites is not that
high so this doesn't have to be that
high but I do have to loop over each of
the slots every time if I want to find
one of these and that is a bit expensive
so I could use a chain if I didn't want
to I just have a change for each arena
that's that threads through I don't
think it's worth it at the moment but if
it turned out to me we could so I'm
gonna have to do slot index equals zero
slot in sis less than oops call site
hash sighs and also I might just undef
call site hash sighs here so that no one
has to worry about it so with this call
site hash sighs in fact I could've made
that I you through - I don't know why I
didn't but with the call site half size
as I loop through there
I now can look at the call site hash and
well actually I can just copy this exact
routine here this is all we're doing we
loop over each of the entries in that
particular slot and we print them out so
for each site if the it matches the
arena that we're trying to print out at
this time right we don't want to print
ones that aren't then what we want to do
is just display something that tells us
what happened here and you know
something like that
right okay so we need something that
will print out the information for this
particular call site which is not the
same thing as we were doing before but
some of its the same we know that the
call site here is gonna get oops its
grid printed out
we know that the site has a track for
the amount that it allocated so we know
this piece of information right so the
allocated oops so slight allocated count
is how many of the things we were going
to do and similarly we've got the site
allocated some could be the same thing
as we were doing here right so that's
the total amount divided by megabytes so
that we can put that in there right this
percentage we could also do which is to
say that we can say what it's the same
thing right we can just say whatever
this allocated sum is we can put out the
percentage that it is of the total
allocations we could also make it be per
arena if we wanted to but yeah so we
don't have blocks in this case so we
really only have this one we don't have
them because this is already out of like
we don't know we can't say that a
particular call site caused a block to
be created because that's really just
chance it's like a whole bunch of other
call sites might have used a whole all
the block and you just wanted this
little piece of memory we can't say that
it's like your fault right so so I don't
think we want anything more specific
than just here's how much memory the
thing happen to use anything else would
be a misleading statistic and really
what you should be doing if you're
worried about that is looking at the
graphical display cuz that will actually
tell you who's responsible for that kind
of nonsense right so if I turn on call
sites now what we should be able to see
hopefully is that when we look through
here we should see call sites and who is
actually responsible for most of the
memory now what it looks like is
happening
and I guess this explains the behavior
that we were seeing you can see that
like almost no memory even though
there's tons of allocations being
allocated by these streams here nothing
is actually getting that they're not
using hardly any memory so that's
probably why we're not seeing it in here
because nothing's happening with it
right it's like tiny little slivers so
that's great it tells us what we wanted
to know and it Altus understand what's
going on I don't like how this isn't
lined up and so I'd like to push this
back further by inserting you know what
1 2 3 4 5 spaces in there just to get
that more correct right and then in here
I want to do something like this just to
make sure you can see that it's like
underneath it maybe that and so here now
we can see those call sites and really
have a better understanding of who is
responsible for each of the you know
things that in the memory map right
so here in my call site display now it
should be a little bit better yeah it
looks better so you can see all the
allocations listed here you can see how
much memory each of them is taking and
so when we turn on call sites we can
just immediately look and say well okay
so it's pretty much this allocation and
this allocation that account for all of
the memory the rest of this stuff is
just irrelevant anyway these three
malloc ations here the interesting thing
about it is why they're not going away
and so I think the more interesting
question asked would be do we have a
leak in here somewhere where we were
supposed to be freeing a stream when we
for example loaded something up I think
the answer is no my assumption is that
this is the error streams that we record
on import why there are so many of these
unnecessary
allocations though because presumably
there aren't that many errors getting
reported you know we looking here we
don't see much happening there so I'm
wondering you know why why is that the
case and so I'm interested to know if
maybe there's something something going
on there that shouldn't be going on and
I'd like to take a look at that and find
out why you can also see that there's an
exactly matched pairing of these two
here 106 and 12 are happening what
appears to be on the exact same code
path there's also a set in asset that's
a BP that's accounting for a lot of
those let's go look and see what these
are just so you can have some idea of
what the heck is happening right so I'm
gonna first start with the ones in the
asset system proper 735 and handmade
asset and so we look in here and we see
we've got a base name for the asset
source file so I get I guess all that's
happening here is it's just pulling in
when we were doing the import right when
we check for that import it's just
remembering all of those names right
and that's probably there's probably two
of those there should be back to back
right 735 and 734 yes so it's just
storing these two pieces of information
that's good news because that's actually
effectively debug information it's
information that doesn't actually need
to happen when you're running the game
so we don't really have to care about
that in two ways a we don't care about
it because it won't happen at runtime
and B it's not taking up much memory
either all right so let's see where
these stream ones are coming from
that's 106 and 12 the problem we're
gonna have there you know I think is
just that when we're calling these out
F's we don't really know you know on
whose behalf they're happening so this
is not getting the information it needs
to really know who was
responsible right and so it's hard to
say what we could do is we could
propagate that information forward we
could make out if arglist actually pass
through that information I don't know
and what's interesting is it looks like
it's sort of already is passing through
that information in which case if I was
to actually look at push copy I could
just start calling that with the actual
debug name there and that's kind of
interesting so let's suppose you know
just for sake of argument here if we if
we went into that that stream system and
instead of using file name and line
number for the chunks instead we said
something like hey there's a grid there
you know that gets associated with each
individual stream chunk then what I
could do is I could leverage the debug
system and say well let's make out F
conform to that same procedure that
seems like a pretty good idea I don't
know I mean maybe it's dumb maybe it's
not but if we went ahead and said you
know only put these in here if you're
actually doing an internal build because
otherwise the grids really shouldn't be
there and then I went and looked at the
debug interface and I just copy like
that same sort of idea where we where we
generate grids for everybody who's doing
that oh wait sorry it's the memory so I
don't know why I said debug system so in
here right we've got the internal memory
per am and the internal memory pass so I
think what we can do is just
kind of copy that idea so in here where
we've got art out F arglist and out F we
can just say look those are gonna take
one of these things and we'll just
piggyback on that memory system and it's
understanding of what's happening there
and then when we have the out F stuff
what we're gonna do is actually use a
debug name at the call site location so
here where we generate the debug name
and you know what why I'm not sure why
there's a comma there because really
there shouldn't be right oh I know why
it's because debug you we could have
done it this way if d by name had just
expanded to a comma but oh well so
anyway if I do handmade internal here
then what I can do is just have two of
these where we say all right in one case
we'll do an out F debug name there in
the other case we just won't do anything
and we'll just call it regularly then we
should be good to go for making these
things work correctly
in both cases hopefully also I think we
need the little doodad there not really
though because you're always actually
going to pass something but either way
so I think that's correct and now if I
go in and record inside here and make
this be the internal memory per am and
then here we do a internal memory pass
right we should now have this stuff
hooked up so that it flows through and
tells us who is actually doing these
allocations and why again not sure
that's the greatest idea but you know I
just thought it might be worth a shot
in here I'm going to lose
if handmaiden turn off otherwise so yeah
so that all seems good and then in here
if we want to dump these out then what
we could do is say well anytime we're
dumping the stream to the CRT like this
what we can do is just if we know this
we print it if we don't we don't so if
we're in handmade internal mode we know
that we have this tracking information
with it so we can just say show the grid
which has the file name and line number
in it which is exactly what we wanted if
it doesn't then we can't no big deal all
right when we do the error arglist here
that seems fine for out if arglist
we would need to generate a debug name
here potentially and it feels like that
wants to get that passed as well in a
sense but I don't know to what extent we
really want to go down that road so what
I may do here is just say
I may just go ahead and do it this way
so we'll actually generate a debug name
here for ourselves like so right in that
cubes that view the comma there or
should have yeah
and so now maybe we get a little more
visibility into this I don't know again
not sure that was really necessary or if
it was a good idea but we're gonna find
out
cannot open oh yeah I agree with that
let's try rebuilding that and so this
should just give us a little more detail
about when and where those stream
allocations are coming from Molly beam
come on up come on up there's a good
girl
that's my good girl it's a good girl
how are you doing how's it going
did you just have dinner
uf is at 6 o'clock yeah she has a little
automated feeder that goes off at
regular intervals I just feel like
that's better for her cuz she you know
there's no variability to it she can
rely on her meal times if I'm not there
or something you know it's for her dry
food her wet food still obviously has to
be done by a human but her dry food
isn't that right her dry food you can
give her so she can feed herself alright
um so let's see does that give us any
more insight into whether or not those
things are supposed to be happening just
in case there's an issue with them Oh
what are you doing baby what's going on
what's going on I'm just finishing up
programming it's just a little bit
longer actually don't know how much
longer it is it's maybe 45 minutes
longer which is actually quite a bit
longer I'm sorry we can play later if
you want to
I don't know what you want to do you can
sit here if you want although it's a
little hard to type around you you know
we have a problem with this every day at
work that's a good that's a good ok well
I don't know what's going on here with
Molly she's she's gonna make her own
decisions she may just sit on the
keyboard in which case the stream is
basically over we can try to put her in
the cat tree and maybe she'll sit maybe
she won't who knows
Gina good brushing I didn't brush you
yesterday did I did I brush you
yesterday I don't think I did I'm sorry
should brush you later will brush you
later ok right after the stream will
give you a good brushing you'll be all
nice and clean so anyway looking at the
call site there to see if we got any
more infor ok Molly Molly wants to
modify the mouse position as well as is
her prerogative ok those are my
headphones can we step over the
headphones look there we go ok so I
don't know if we got any information
about the call sites here that'll help
us figure things out there might be but
there might not be so taking a look in
here at the stream allocations that used
to be there you can see now that some of
them have gotten more detailed right so
for example these two we know were
previously allocations that are just
made to track source asset files of
which we have many now because there's
just even though the game isn't really
have even probably a tenth of the art
we'll have there's a lot of source files
a lot of source pngs for things like
fonts you know that that ups that number
really quickly and so if we look down
now we can see that there's 360
allocations still happening from stream
12 but now we've got some more
information about what's happening for
example in here this is coming from
import 1127 and so that gives us the
opportunity to go there and just see is
that something that should have stuck
around or
isn't it right here animate import 1127
right and so it looks like these are
error messages telling us that it found
information and something that was
supposed to be a blank tile so that's
like that's just an error we're getting
errors on some blank tile stuff
there must be something is happening
with our asset metadata so the
interesting thing about that is I think
that maybe an erroneous error message at
this point though because the thing is
that error message is probably wrong for
bitmaps because they don't have a type
ID if I'm not mistaken because they're
never referenced now maybe we should
they have direct asset references in the
font right so they don't get looked up
by their type and I think their type is
just set to zero now that may be bad
because it may be that that's sort of a
bit of breakage in the system that we
don't really want but I do think that
sort of indicates that this error
message is not appropriate because it's
erroring on something that's actually
fine
so I might go ahead and do this
I could do this and comment it out or I
can go try to fix that now and I'm not
sure which one I want to do I suppose
just doing an asset rebuild it's pretty
trivial and we could just add a type for
it let's see what that would entail
would it break anything else because I
would like to still know this piece of
information in the future when we sort
of refine our import maybe a little bit
I think that's a good thing to have in
there so we finally went to the file
format and just said hey we've got the
basic types here where did those go so
inside here you know
in fact there's font glyph right there I
think we're just not using that anymore
but we could and if we did then
presumably we wouldn't have that
erroneous error so like that would be
when we actually do the import font
right
in here when the tags for that font are
being created right so we come through
here we're parsing these things and we
get these various glyphs when we come
through here and we set everything up we
look for the asset data and we set the
code points all up in here right and so
this process every time we do this when
we load that bitmap which which is going
to be this call here update asset data
from file so if we're looking at this
we're passing it null tags and template
tags and I'm guessing that that's really
the issue here so when this thing gets
updated and it's going to look to see
right it does it does this update asset
metadata right and it passes those
template tags so the template tags
here are just never set right so I guess
what I would say is that seems like the
issue and maybe we should just fix it
yeah I don't know I think that's what we
need to do so if we look through the
template tags there it looks like nobody
else even uses them yeah
they don't and so you know that's
probably all we would really need to do
is just say well the template tags they
have in this is the tag grid or Ritter
whatever it is called their import grid
tags inside the first one of those the
type ID of this thing it's going to want
to be that long cliff right and so I
think that's all we really need to do is
make sure that that gets set everywhere
looks like that
did I I did that wrong sorry it's just
asset funk lifts now that was old news
um so yeah if I go ahead and go to the
import code and just change that to be
this I think now all of those would they
get imported would come in hopefully as
font glyphs and you wouldn't have that
error happening that's my assumption and
then that error would only occur on
actual valid prop you know things that
are actually wrong okay so if we go
ahead and do our asset rebuild now
hopefully that would fix the problem
so inside handmade
and that is in the data directory so
we've got the font and the font is in
the base game
HHA so I think if I just ask it to
rebuild that we should be good to go
probably and then we can see whether or
not we're still getting that airing out
where it's like looking and going like
hey man these things I'm importing they
don't have any types associated with
them do you care
all right and so that did the full asset
rebuild of the game assets so they'll be
more call sites in here probably right
then there would have been before
because we would have saved some
reporting about what actually got
imported but off we go so let's now take
a look and see although actually even
just looking at it now it does look like
maybe that already improve things a
little bit let's take a look so now on a
on a fresh run where things have
actually been built let's take a look at
what we've got here so we've got one
hundred and twenty two allocations
coming from asset ten twenty well
actually let's just start with one thing
that error is not happening anymore
right
so that was exactly what I thought it
was but let's just double check the rest
of these so
I'm not sure what this error is it looks
like we've got assets that are saying
they come from the same place in the
spritesheet yeah
so that seems bad hmm
I wonder if that means we're not setting
our annotations right for grid X and
grid Y although it's awfully suspicious
so I'm kind of wondering if this is also
if this is because of a way that we're
attributing names to things that causes
all of the font glyphs themselves to be
registered to the same file name so I
wonder if that is the problem let's take
a look so when we do parse font block
for each one of the glyphs we're gonna
call update asset data from file right
and we use this import file match as the
match so in theory that seems like it
should be okay to me because it's going
to create an asset source file for that
piece of information which should be
unique
yeah that seems fine so I don't know why
that would be having hmm so I guess what
I'm gonna do is say I don't really know
exactly where that's coming from
so what I'd like to do is dump this file
and see what's actually going on there
so if I run HHA edit I'm gonna use the -
dump call and I'm gonna dump base game
that HHA to base game dot txt and then I
want to run tab view on it so if I take
a look in here and just see what I've
got I should be able to get the
annotation for this thing and if I look
at these
[Music]
so I guess a couple things first of all
I'm not sure why this thinks there's no
type because I thought I tried to set
the type of each of these to be a font
glyph now it could be that HHA edit just
doesn't know how to do that and I could
look for that not sure where this
actually gets printed out that's in read
hij I don't care about that where does
this actually figure out what to print
things so this is where we print things
category name from ID is where we take
care of this in category name from ID
we definitely have a set font glyph so
it doesn't look like I'm actually doing
this properly because if I was we would
have seen that value show up here right
because it should have found it in that
run-through and it should have decrypted
it here well decrypted it should have
cracked it here and showed me the name
but instead it didn't what I will say
though is I must be looking at the wrong
thing because that prints out none and
this would print out unknown so I'm
still a bit of a loss there there's the
assets we come through here we efferent
out at present you percent counter
account category data
so I guess this part here I can see what
the issue is we don't add any actual
tags we just say what the type was and
since we don't actually add any tags
this still wouldn't be able to find out
what that thing was all right I can see
why that's an issue
um do I want to actually add a tag for
that I'm not sure I'm not sure but the
part that I was looking at more
specifically right now is the fact that
all of these do have a separate source
file name for them right
so as I'm looping through here you can
see that they actually are totally
distinct so what I don't know is why
we're getting this error message that
says that there's things that are
overlapping because I don't actually see
anything that's overlapping unless I'm
just missing it because I'm scrolling by
too quickly but it honestly doesn't
really look like it right so that would
be an example of it so it looks like
these because they're audio they're
chunked streaming audio so the chunk
streaming audio does have sort of a you
know it it has two things that that say
that they're coming from the same place
and so the problem with that is it's
really just totally ok that that's the
case you just want to take the the
earlier asset index in the case of
streaming audio so I think really all I
have to do is just always make sure I
take the lesser of the two I mean that
should be okay so in this case we're
we're going to look at it here what we
want to do is say if it's equal to zero
well then let me assign it if it's not
then we want to actually check to make
sure that we actually want to report
this in the case where it's an audio
asset that's okay so in other words if
this conflicted asset are what's the
actual
I want to know if it's a sound so an
haja set sound so if this thing is a
sound then I don't want to print out
that error message instead what I want
to do is assign this if it's less right
so I just want to say if grid asset
index is greater than global asset index
then you know assign it right although
since global asset index is always
ascending that probably isn't even
necessary but that's basically what we
want to do so we want to take the lowest
value that we can that we can get and
then we would know to replace the run if
we had to actually replace it right so
I'm interested to know does that help us
with our problem here so looking at the
memory read out here it looks to me like
[Music]
10 29 so no it didn't so it looks like
that unfortunately is not helpful so
we're still getting a bunch of these
errors I'd and I just don't know on
whose behalf we're getting them we don't
currently have a way to look at all
errors in all source files which we
probably should have because we would be
able to see that if we did we only have
the main error stream here that we don't
have the purse or file error stream
which would be nice maybe this should
actually go to that air stream but it's
hard to say
so I'm gonna do the poor man's version
of this just for expedience at the
moment that's probably something that we
should take care of in a more definitive
way later if I go set a breakpoint where
that happens we can look at which assets
are causing the issue and maybe get a
better sense of why so if I look at
source file name oops
of course we can't actually because it's
all been optimized out
so here's the actual source file in
question what so this is a case of
somebody not actually specifying which
source file that came from looks like
which is surely an import book right
that means that somebody's is not
setting their actual annotation to have
what the source file actually was let's
take a look at what that asset looks
like just we can have a better idea so
looking here we can see a couple things
so it's a type two I don't know if I can
that's a sound so it was actually a
sound
ah
we actually need to look at the HHA it's
up there that's what we're gonna let's
try that wartime okay so we shouldn't be
looking at sounds now hopefully right so
the type is Type three and that type is
a font so the font is saying it came
from a base name oops sorry
a source file name of base game and that
doesn't seem that doesn't seem useful
but I guess now I think about it it's
hard to say where else it would come
from so that's probably correct actually
however what else is occupying that slot
because I guess there could be one other
asset in there yeah
yeah I'm not sure what else we could do
because if these things are chained on
the actual HHA file then you kind of
have a nasty situation where what else
are you gonna do if you have like
multiple fonts they're all gonna be
using bass game as their asset source
file that doesn't really work it's just
a bad problem that we have here so
fortunately we're just down to the two
it looks like on there now so we've it
was the sounds that were causing most of
the problem it looks like but we still
do have two of those and that's probably
something we want to fix eventually
looking again at the call sites let me
speed this back up again but looking
again at the call sites here let me just
sighs the sound
now we only have three calls there which
seems more plausible so that's better in
fact looking now at the allocations they
look correct right so that's looking
pretty good
so we've cleaned up a bunch of that
stuff yeah and all that stuff seems fine
in general nattu one of the things that
these call sites do that's nice is
looking at the overall like if we just
saw that it's really important for us to
be able to name our arenas because we
have no idea who the heck is responsible
for these right but when you turn this
on now you can see right away like some
detail about what the allocations were
and it would allow us to not really have
to care if those things were named or
not right so we can go look and see like
okay so who's responsible it's one
allocation in hand-made it memory 2h 388
right like what's going on there and you
can see that that's a bootstrap and the
bootstrap allocation I guess in this
case is not passing through who's doing
it so I would say we probably do want to
pass through who's doing it for
bootstrapping it seems like something
you would want and I don't know if there
was a reason why we didn't do that but
for now I think I would like to so in
order to do that in the bootstrap stuff
what we would want to do here is say the
bootstraps struct piece here is gonna
probably get pulled up right and so
that'll go in here and do this and that
in this case it will do exactly what it
was doing but in this case it will do a
debug name here and it will be bootstrap
which size so I think that would allow
us to do the same thing we're doing
everywhere else so this would be
internal memory pram and this would be
internal memory pass and this would
actually be a underscored one and so now
in theory we can track that allocation
upward and see what's going on so inside
here you can see us calling this boot
strap push size directly
I couldn't really say why though
okay so if we do want to do that where
we're creating the frame arena here when
we call bootstrap push size it would
seem that we would have to pass the
debug name here and that's a pretty
weird way of doing things but I guess
we're doing it because we just want to
use offset zero which hey works but I
don't know that that's maybe the
smartest thing to do if we're doing it
that way though yeah we want to be able
to pass a debug name is the first thing
I again have to ask why debug name
itself doesn't just evaluate to
something smarter if for example debug
name always evaluated to something with
a comma after it then we wouldn't have
to make multiple versions of all these
things which seems like it would be a
lot nicer than what we have going right
now and so you know I'm just looking at
this and you know you've Oh you've
always got it so that it's doing this
right pretty much everywhere you have
debug name it's just always like comma
comma comma comma comma comma comma
right and so it feels like if we just
made it evaluate to a comma in the first
place
then we could have put this at the front
of everything and you wouldn't have had
to actually worry about defining it
differently in debug mode I guess here's
a case where the comma would have been
unwelcome so I don't know I'm a little
bit torn there but but oh well so I'll
just go ahead and keep going the sort of
not particularly fantastic route that we
have been going
and we'll just put it in here so that'll
coops that'll correctly track that push
by giving it an actual name as it wanted
and now if I run hopefully in theory
that will eliminate one of our mystery
allocations there and actually attribute
it to somebody
instead of nobody so now we can see
actually getting attributed properly to
handmade CVP 185 and hey of course we
now know that because we know that it
was here but you know it's good to see
it so that contributed to here that
similarly this one should now inside the
frame temporary that should get
attributed to 187 and it is so those two
are now nice too attributed attributed
we could also label this arena pretty
easily I think when these are created
here inside the game state I assume we
could if we wanted to label those
[Music]
it's just the gate it's just the game
state's total arena and somehow that one
wasn't getting labeled so like if I go
to game state this total arena like
didn't get labeled I guess and hey I
guess that's actually true so for some
reason
yeah I don't know for some reason we
just weren't labeling that one and I
don't know why and so now we have it
labeled as you can see so this one is
the only one that's a little bit
Squinkie now and we should probably go
take a look at that it looks like it's
you know it's part of the import system
so it's probably just the air output or
whatever that was going on there we
might as well label that and again this
the call sites really lets us jump right
to what's going on so 20 to 30 on the
handmade import and so in here we want
to go ahead and have this error stream
on demand memory stream is who's picking
that up and so probably we just want to
label that if I go in there and look at
how on-demand memory streams working you
can see that we've got that stream
memory here so what we probably want to
do is right after that just say debug
arena name grab that particular error
stream and say that that is the
synchronized asset file changes so
basically I mean that's what it is right
it's the standard out for the change
synchronization so I think that's what
we need there let's find out there we go
um so the name won't change here because
that path will not get called it's only
happens at import time so we're never
gonna hit that again but if I run it now
from the start again then we should see
that that name get picked up
hopefully although as I say that it odd
that's obviously not true because which
should have been there and it isn't
right um so I don't know what to make of
that is it oh wait error strip how did
that how did that compile all right
let's try that one more time I don't
know what was going on there all right
try that one more time so hopefully this
will name it now and it doesn't well so
much for that so I'm not sure what's
going on these are the allocations here
there's 22 31 right was that that site
we just looked at
[Music]
and I guess the problem so the problem
is probably that it hasn't had any
blocks yet and you can't label one
without blocks all right I guess that's
true
oh well so maybe we just need to do it
that way and then we're okay not the
cleanest solution but you know we don't
have a way of because arenas can get
moved around where you're tracking them
from and we didn't want to make it so
that people had to like be cognizant of
that so that was just yeah so now we've
got it so I think now we're properly
tracking everyone's memory we know the
call sites so we can see for every arena
who is messing with it and why and
that's really nice so I think all of
that is pleasant and good I would say
that now we can move on to the last
order of business in in what time we
have remaining and just take a look at
making this display make more sense
again so that it's not so that it
properly reflects the sizes of things
that it's showing and so what I want to
do there is just draw memory intervals
or whatever arena intervals all I really
want to do here is say all right when we
start creating these blocks I need to
start thinking of them less in terms of
subdividing a block and more in terms of
actually like rasterizing out for
however long you're going a certain
amount of space in this memory map that
where everything should be equivalently
sized right and so what I'd like to do
there is have some way of actually
mapping into this block directly so that
rather than thinking of it as block Rex
you subdivide you
actually just used your like absolute
memory location to create the lookup
into the block and then you have a party
right I think that's the saucy err way
to go here so in order to do that what I
want to create is some sort of a notion
of how to draw some range and I'm going
to need that to work as a function call
that can do it sort of based on the
total profile rect size so you pass me
one of these profile rect sizes or
something like this and then we say look
here's the total here's like your actual
address in there so I'm not sure exactly
how I want to do that but let's say that
we do this as let's say that we do this
is something like like this and then
we're going to go ahead and in fact
maybe like that so you pass us a range
and then we're gonna fill the range and
so we need to have the render group in
here and the UI transform with that
stuff so we're gonna have to take a
little bit of upstate and that's fine so
in here what we do is you know we doing
something like this
and we're gonna fill Rex and we can
obviously get the render group out of
here as well right so we're gonna get
the render group the UI transform we
need to know the block color but other
than that I think we're all good so in
here I would just say pass me the block
color that you want used and I think
that's probably all we need in there and
so then we're gonna do is we're gonna
say we have a way of mapping addresses
to page you know we have a way of
mapping addresses into this block and I
might might want to do this in you 64
[Music]
let's do it so you pass me your two
ranges and what I need to do here is I
need to effectively fill the number of
rows that you're going to occupy and I
need to fill however much of each row
you occupy right
when we do the push rooked outline
really eventually what I should do is
keep one side of that solid or not
depending on whether or not you actually
wrap around to the next row but we'll
cross that bridge when we come to it so
we need to do one of these for every row
that you that it encounters so we need
something here like a row index that
we're going to step along right we need
this sort of thing and then for each of
these we need to know like what section
of the row you actually take up I'm
guessing that I won't have time to quite
do this today just based on where we are
timewise
so I might just leave it here and then
tomorrow what we'll do is we'll go
through this stuff exactly so the when
we're going to draw the arena intervals
I'll go ahead and make that call out to
this and we'll do the memory mapping
into the range so that each of these
will just tell it exactly where it is in
the total size of the memory and then
that will translate into the correct set
of like rectangle fills for each region
and then that way we can also introduce
a scaling factor so that if we want to
be able to zoom in on pieces of memory
we can which I think we'll probably want
to do eventually as well so yeah let's
stop there because we did ton of stuff
today and let's move back to the Q&amp;A
here
did you code C++ turday job yes
all these with without common macros is
complete nonsense is there any better
way to deal with it yeah it is complete
nonsense and again like C and C++ just
aren't good languages for actually
building complex programs there are very
simple language features that would have
made all of that stuff unnecessary and
they just never added them and so
typically what C++ in particular does
because C was a fairly minimal language
C++ typically what it does is it says
well okay so let's suppose you wanted to
do that thing we were just doing they
have all these sort of like halfway
implemented language features that don't
really work but that would sort of maybe
help you address that problem and if you
end up trying to use them your codes
even worse than what we just ended up
with right and so it's always very
frustrating if we wanted to do something
better with our actual with and without
memories macro stuff I do think we can
do better than that though just with the
preprocessor and the reason I say that
is because if we just introduced another
debug name thing here like let's see we
just bit the bullet and say well we've
got inside the handmade debug interface
stuff we've got this one way that we
create debug names right here it is well
maybe we say all right so there's
another one which is like debug memory
program or something right like this
and what that does is it just says like
well normally when you say this thing
then I expand it to this right and I put
the comma on for you you know I'm saying
and in the other case I don't do that
so if you instead are not in the
internal build then it just goes away
right it just disappears and so if we
wanted to do that then I think what we
could do is simplify this quite
considerably right we drop that up there
hmm and drop that in here and now I
think you could just get rid of this
entire else set I think right because
now what I believe we could do is just
instead of using debug name everywhere
here we would just say debug memory
program as the first thing right and
then we don't have to have the two
versions ever although I guess I should
for posterity in case we ever do want to
re-enable it we got rid of it because of
clang I'm gonna keep I'll call that P
bug memory name
sooo if I just do this and then remove
these I think that's probably sufficient
and so that would be one way to make it
at least somewhat cleaner we don't
really need these pounds because these
all take arguments so there's no chance
that there are zero arguments there so I
think that should probably be fine as it
is so I think that's pretty much
everything and then you don't need the
multiple version nonsense anymore I
think that would just would just take
care of it right and so that's pretty
compelling by comparison
looks like my pushin mill terminate is
wrong there whereas pushing all
terminates pushin mill terminates
yeah um so that's one way and that seems
better like I probably should have done
that right that seems like an
improvement to me again it's hard to do
a good job in C C++ for that sort of
thing all of your options are sub
standard like none of them are great but
C++ is not a great language so you can't
expect to get great code out of a non
great language it's kind of
self-defining lis not gonna happen but
that's you know better than what we had
and keeps it a little bit more you know
concise you don't the two versions of
everything and it would also allow us in
other places where we did that to remove
them as well so you know if I go looking
for the places where we put those in
here
select right here for example we should
be able to also say well this doesn't
have to occur because we can use the
same trick right here so anyone who
wants to participate in that scheme can
just do it and it's not an issue right
same same thing here
I don't know that we had any more those
may have been all of that probably
should have just looked for debug name
in there but
yeah um I can also test and just because
we made that change there let's see if
we broke anything when handmade
internals off because there might be
some places now where that's busted and
we want to make sure we fix that so it
looks like bootstrap push struct is
still broken so let's just fix that real
quick yeah so that one's missing this
and what else you got
so there we go so now the non internal
version is working and you know off we
go there but if we want to turn it back
on now we can
I'm a web developer by trade and my
day-to-day code seems to abstract way
more logic than you do in your engine
could you explain why that is um I'm not
sure what exactly you mean by the
question can you be any more specific I
mean one of the things I guess is
obviously that this stream is about
doing low-level code so obviously we're
not going to abstract things any more
than we have to but that may not really
be what you're asking so if you could
explain that question a little bit more
I could try to address it more properly
what would you do differently if you had
to work with other developers on this
project I wouldn't really do anything
differently
in most instances but when I'm working
with other developers typically we come
to some sort of an understanding about
like where we're gonna put like fault
lines in the code base really and what I
would do is I'd spend more time
periodically creating interface
boundaries that were like clean
separations that other people could look
at and go oh okay here's the stuff that
like KC wants me to call to use like the
asset system or whatever so that they
don't have to wonder right I don't spend
a lot of time doing that with what I'm
doing now because I know so it's just a
waste of time but if I know that other
people have to be calling the code then
I treat it more like a public API that I
might be pushing out to the world right
and so I'm gonna stop and make those
boundaries clear and have a clear h-file
that's like hey everyone look at this
this is the part that you want to call
so that you don't have to know anything
about what I'm doing you can just call
the part that I told you was reliable
and do it right and so you know when I
used to ship licensable SDKs for example
that I would just apply that mentality
to the to the part that I wanted to wall
off at any given time right so like when
I am making a SDK for someone else to
use you know there's the internal part
that I'm working on and I don't care if
anyone else knows how that works but
then there's the part that I want them
to call and I want that to be like
obvious right I want to be like here's
the you know begin execute end stuff
here's what you can call here's maybe
some comments that say you know here's
an example code or whatever and so I
would you know take the time to push
that periodically when I wanted people
to be using a new feature that make
sense or a new thing that I added but it
turns the internals I wouldn't really do
anything particularly different I might
put more error checking code in as well
because if I put error checking code in
in places that I know I probably will
never make an error I'm wasting my time
but if I know that other people are
calling it and they I don't know what
kinds of errors they often have or what
kinds of errors they might make because
they don't know how I normally do things
in my code then I might put some guards
in to look for things they're doing
wrong you see I'm saying and that's to
help them save debugging time so that
they don't get something wrong and then
waste their time tried to bug what
happened so that makes sense so those
are some things that you want to do
differently when you know that the
person using the code in many cases
isn't you but when you're making code
for yourself
you don't want to waste your time doing
those things necessarily right
yes exactly this is better but it can't
do just one name and that's actually why
I made it debug memory name and didn't
change the one that's debug name because
debug memory name we know we always take
something right and so it's just a yeah
and again it's just crappy it's just
because you know it's crappy but you do
the best you can with C++ right
I'm wondering what language feature
would make what you have done with
memory tracking easier well it's obvious
right you should just be able inside a
function I mean right something like
this because essentially what happens is
you have a call graph at compile time
where the compiler knows everybody who's
called
right and for 99% of all functions
you're not calling through a pointer so
it's actually easy for the compiler to
just push that information for anyone
who actually needs it in the call graph
so languages could easily just add
something that automatically adds a pass
parameter if the person who's getting
called wants to know who the caller was
right and that creates literally this
exact code but you didn't have to type
it in
if someone we're looking to get into pro
game programming today would you
recommend starting with using an engine
like unity or would you recommend doing
this little lower programming um I think
I would say it depends on what your goal
is if you're trying to be like a game
designer I would say you want to use
something like unity or unreal and the
reason is because those tools are what
are the kind of thing you will be
expected to use so when you go to get a
job as a game designer they will expect
you to be working with something like
that it may not be one of those because
they may have their own in-house engine
but it's gonna be something like a
scriptable like unity style thing right
if on the other hand what you're trying
to do is get a job as an engine
programmer then what I would say is yeah
I don't know how useful starting with
unity or Unreal would be it might be bad
because they're very large and very
complex and so if you're trying to learn
engine programming I mean there's no
reason you couldn't learn engine
programming by downloading the source
code to the Unreal Engine which I
believe is public and hacking on it
right I mean you can do that but you
might be overwhelmed
whereas starting with some simple pong
game you make low level like what we do
in handmade hero there you might be able
to learn a lot more because it's so much
easier to grapple with that then this
huge multi-million line source tree
right and so I think when you're
starting to get into game programming
there isn't a right answer it's like
what am I trying to achieve and what can
I grapple with like you know what what
what do I get the most mental traction
on and that's probably what you should
be doing because you will learn if you
do it a lot and so the question is what
is your brain willing to do a lot of and
you should do that thing right and
starting with something like the Unreal
Engine might be too much
right and so you might want to scope it
down and that doesn't mean you have to
do like what we're doing you could do
other things start with the quake source
code that you download or something you
know I don't know but I'm saying like
try to find something that you can like
grapple with and go with that
don't don't be afraid to try a few
things to see if any of them stick if
nothing stick maybe you don't you
shouldn't be a programmer you know right
like you don't have to be programmed
there's lots of jobs that people do in
the game industry production art sound
designed regular design management's
marketing community management
programming is just one of them so don't
be afraid to experiment and see what it
is that you actually like and are good
at and go from there
off-topic question ender group what is
the purpose of this entity object API in
a few words nowadays is it essentially a
command buffer for a specific FBO for a
specific GL state I'm not really a
render group nowadays and let me just
bring it up here so we can talk about it
um so really what's happening here is
this is just saying mm-hmm that we know
we have some actual stuff that the
renderer needs to do like actual work
that we rely on the platform's
implementation of something OpenGL
direct3d whatever we have some mini
driver that sits on top of that that is
capable of actually doing the rendering
work like drawing quads and depth
sorting and all that crap right
but in order for the game to actually
stream out the actual information that
that mini driver needs right there's
just a lot going on there's all sorts of
stuff like okay where am I in the output
stream to to put like vertex data out
what's the actual transform that I
expect to be using here like just a
bunch of bookkeeping and so what the
render group does is it just packages
that up into one place so that all of
the people who actually use rendering
and throw stuff down to be rendered
don't have to track it all separately if
so that's all is is it's a bookkeeping
aid so that people who want to push
stuff to the renderer don't have to
remember every last Oh was lighting on
or off and and did I where was the
lighting going and how do I get to the
assets to like figure out which texture
I'm using it just puts that together so
that you you don't have to pass tons of
things down the pipeline and or find
that you're somewhere trying to render
something you don't have something you
need so it's a bookkeeping
simplification struct and you'll see
that happen a lot in complex systems
because there's so many moving pieces
you don't want to pass them all you just
want one pointer to something that has
all of the stuff you might
need in it and you just grab the one you
want right why are games unable to
saturate storage bandwidth when loading
with modern SSDs it seems like load
should never take longer than 2 to 3
seconds you're absolutely right and the
reason is usually just bad asset
processing right so typically what
happens is like they load things tons of
disparate tiny little chunks and then
they have to like wires I'm all up and
they're like matching strings like crazy
and like remap you know unbundling stuff
and just crazy bad code that's doing a
ton of work and so rather than just
issuing a giant set of i/o ops that it
can just like saturate the SSD and pull
it out as fast as possible instead it's
just this nonsense dance of like you
know grabbing little tiny pieces that
are not really fully processed and
checking whose name matches to what and
oh that thing reference this other thing
where is that thing I don't know let me
look it up in a table oh it's over there
issue an IO called a bat so it's like a
lot of these little serial bubbles load
this tiny thing what does it need o load
that thing that it needs oh that thing
needs something okay load that right and
so you end up in this case where you're
constantly waiting for the full latency
where as if you just knew everything you
needed for the next level and issued it
all at once it could just all come back
right and so it's those latency bubbles
of I asked for something then I need to
look at it to find out what to ask for
next that process is doing these big
round trips through the whole pipeline
and so even though the SSD can sustain
this really high bandwidth back if
you're just trickle asking for it and
then it has to wait all the time it's
constantly like stalling out right it's
like oh wait okay what did I this oh
okay oh this'll look right and so it's
just it's just sloppy programming
you've mentioned it with the engine
you're ready Frank 25 you're spending a
lot more time documenting your process
and decisions we're tackling a problem
problem do you have any tips or examples
of what you find useful to keep track of
yes I can tell you exactly how I do it
so specifically what I do is every time
I am not sure what the answer is to
something I'm doing that gets an entry
in the log so if I'm like well I could
do this thing by doing it X but I could
do it by Y and I'm not sure which one to
do or maybe like I could do X but maybe
X isn't quite right and I'm not sure
what is right that gets an entry and I
describe why I'm confused right so I'm
like well here are the pros to X and
here are the pros to Y and then I say at
the bottom I'm like I'm gonna go with X
for now but I'm not sure and then later
if I ever find out the actual answer
like I implement it and I'm like oh it
turned out X is really good or Wow X was
terrible don't do that let's switch to Y
then I go back in that comment block and
I say I put a little thing that says
resolved I'm like resolved you don't do
X because this happens so do Y because
it doesn't right that's what I keep
track of so any decision that wasn't
obvious that's what I try to keep track
of
if they're a good rule of thumb when it
comes to guard against errors in your
code is there such a thing as too much
handling I could imagine having many if
state mr. J conditionals could cause a
performance hit so a couple things the
first thing I'll say is on the
performance hit side of things it
doesn't really cause a huge performance
hit on an X 64 processor anyway to have
ifs for error handling and that's
because usually the if to check the air
condition doesn't require much work and
branches that are always taken in one
way are usually fairly cheap right so
meaning if you have a branch which is
like if everything is okay do this stuff
those are pretty cheap branches in fact
they're almost free branches if you
didn't have to do any work to compute
the thing that you're branching on and
so I would say I'm x64 you can probably
afford to have a fair bit of that code I
mean it depends on the context so
certain cases maybe not but in a lot of
cases it's okay but what I would say is
it's more about you wasting your own
time so don't waste your time adding
error checking in places you don't think
you need it
and so that guess was the first writer
question which is what's the rule of
thumb where do you need it and what I
would say there is that if you don't
know what kind of bugs you're likely to
make because you just aren't sure you
haven't been keeping track of that right
then what you want to do is you want to
start by saying every time I must set
aside this month every time this month I
get a bug in my code that I have to
debug I'm gonna write down what it was
what kind of bug was it right and the
end of the month you will know the kind
of errors you tend to have right and
that will give you some information
about you know what
what you should be guard against more
often the other thing you can also do
that helps is when you have bugs when
you debug the bug ask yourself how long
did that take if the answer was a minute
probably no need to do anything about it
if the answer was five ten and a half
hour then ask yourself what is the check
that would have prevented this bug going
add that check and remember it right
that's usually a pretty good rule of
thumb - so does it mean that you have
augmented this color information in your
metaphoric scheme so you can always
query who called you I hope that John
integrated these features in JRE um I
don't know if John has them in AR
already or not but it's not
metaprogramming really because all
you're saying is I want to be able to
have access to the call graph in a way
that generates something and that's just
regular programming really so for more
series on where you log do you have a
file for each function no I just have
one giant file called like devlog or
notes or something
render group thanks for answering it
sounds like an abstraction of GL API
plus the notion of render pass no still
not really and the reason I say that is
because a render group can actually just
get modified on the fly so look as
you're coming down and doing stuff you
can change like the transform as you go
so I really would encourage you to think
of it more as bookkeeping it's and it's
transient so render groups themselves
don't get handed anybody they go away
after they're used so they're really
just bookkeeping they're there to track
the state as it goes so it's more like
us a abstraction of all the state
necessary to issue render calls and it
updates as it goes as you change that
state but it doesn't record it anywhere
so the actual recording is done in other
things right that's what I would say
what are your thoughts on visual
programming languages do you imagine
good use cases for them and if so in
what context do you think they work
understanding is that it's challenging
to make a good visual language and that
usually the special-purpose ones work
better than attempts at general use ones
um first of all I would agree with the
with the back half of that the part that
you said your my understanding is I
would say that like the kinds of visual
languages that I've seen which tend to
look a lot like wiring diagrams those
are pretty limited in their utility like
when I see people trying to take those
in program really complex stuff in them
like when people use blueprint to make
complex stuff it's I'm like this is bad
right you it's way too complicated very
hard to read and so I think that's kind
of going off the rails there but when
you take a simpler example of something
that you do in blueprints or like more
to the point are shading diagram and
like Meyer something if you just have a
few things like oh here was the image
and I applied this modifier to it and I
can see that it got you know it
increased the contrast or whatever and
then I piped it to this detect this mesh
and there it is right you know you can
kind of see that being I'm like okay
that's not bad that's probably better
than if I had to type in some code for
that and didn't really know especially
if I'm not a programmer really and I'm
not used to thinking of things
linguistically like that you know it
seems like a pretty clear win um so I'd
agree at the back half of that as to
what my thoughts are on visual
programming languages in general I would
say that I think that the idea of making
languages that have visual components to
them as opposed to just a bunch of text
on a page is clearly good because a lot
of the things we program have a
geometric component to them and the fact
that we can't see any of it doesn't help
but I would say that the idea that
visual programming means wiring diagram
seems misguided there are people who've
done experiments with visual programming
that is not about wiring diagrams those
look
or promising to me and so I would say
that that seems like a better a more
fruitful Avenue for future progress than
wiring diagram which to me never really
made sense as a way to do anything more
than just simple image manipulation
stuff which is where those wiring
diagrams seem to work okay right
question is to touch on the over
error-checking
what about the case where you're making
API this is to be accessed by other
developers right now I'm making a
library for the twitch API that will be
constantly interfaced by users but I
feel like I'm holding their hand too
much with errors instead of assuming
that they have an idea what they're
doing to the point where a significant
amount of the library is just error
checking um well I guess what I would
say is obviously with anything including
that there's always still a balance to
it so I would say that you you you don't
necessarily want to go overboard but
it's worth remembering that when someone
else is using your code
they are coming into it completely blind
right I mean they have no idea what you
did in there and they are very much just
just feeling around to try and figure
out what's going on right and so you do
have to err on the side of being more
pedantic and descriptive and sort of
rigorous with your sort of error
reporting if nothing else because they
just aren't gonna know what they did
wrong a lot of times like they're gonna
do something and it's just not gonna
work and the reason and it would be
trivial for you to understand why it
doesn't work because you know the
internals they don't and so they're just
gonna be like I don't know why that
didn't work so the crucial thing that
you need to provide them is the way for
them to gain the understanding of why it
didn't work an error log is very
important in api's like that so they can
just see like okay this didn't work turn
on logging what happened oh that call
failed because
i patent it I passed a null pointer I
didn't realize that thing could return a
null pointer you know whatever or it it
failed and didn't produce an ID because
the server was down and I didn't know
the server was down so I thought it was
okay right bla bla bla and so having the
ability to look through an error log is
pretty important for people who are
trying to learn how to use an interface
and you do have to err more on the side
of being more descriptive putting more
stuff in there then if it's just for you
because you know the internals and you
know what's possible and not and so you
just have to respect that difference of
knowledge there
hmm I think I'm running out of voice
left to answer questions
going back to a question in the
beginning about Africa logic I think the
heart of the questions is due to a
discussion about what is clean code some
higher level languages seem to make
things look good but clean code is at
least to me isn't very well defined
maybe that they were looking for why
does this a complex versus something
that's a few lines of code but contained
in a bunch of little files my thoughts
review performance fine tuning and doing
exactly what's going on rather than
guessing I do that a lot using Python um
well I guess there's a mixture of things
so first of all the phrase clean code is
if someone uses the phrase clean code in
a specific way that usually concerns me
sometimes we use it in an offhand and
and using it offhand it's not always bad
like sometimes I will talk about
something being not clean and what I
mean by that is I know there's crap in
there that I haven't finished yet or
that I stuck something in it that's kind
of lousy and I want to go you know fix
it later and so in the sense that
there's you know clean code to me what
that usually means is I finished it to
the degree that I wanted it finished and
if I haven't done that then it's it's
probably pretty dirty in there right
like I haven't really had a chance to
quite polish it up and so I do think
that that that is a reasonable use of
clean code saying the word clean code
and referring to something like does
things have classes with private
sections or something that I think is
just absurd and silly those are people
whose opinions I don't respect and have
hate working with right and so what I
would say is you have to be careful
about what you mean with various things
and what they mean in a lot of these
different contexts right but going back
to sort of the meat of the question
which is whether things
take too many lines to implement it kind
of seems like what we're talking about
there then what I would say is yeah
there's a lot of trade-offs kind of all
mixed together
and you kind of have to pick what you're
going to accept right trade-off wise and
so you've got three things you can kind
of pick from and you really only get to
have one of them you can have code that
actually works well on the CPU and is
good like it runs well right and if you
want that you pretty much have to use C
or another fairly low-level language
it's very hard to get that you know
forget Python PHP you know it's it's not
even close to being acceptable when it
runs right and so you know if you want
if what you care about is the actual
quality of the executed code there are
very few things you can choose from and
they're all pretty verbose languages
right it's hard to find languages that
are good at making things concise but
which still generate highly optimal code
it's very hard to find that and that's
just a limitation so far in our ability
to produce quality languages for that
purpose okay so that's like one issue
another issue is if you want things to
be concise you can pick languages that
maybe
good having expressive power in terms of
the technical output you are looking for
but where you don't care how poorly you
get the result right so for example you
might find that in a language like ml
for example you can produce some very
nice things for certain types of
problems that allow you to in a very
small amount of code state something you
want to have happen and get the correct
answer even though the code is not
particularly good that comes out of it
right and so those are two distinct
courses you can pick there right and
once in a while if you're really lucky
you can find a language that can
actually do both but it's very rare for
most problems you can't write so we're
most films you have to pick one of those
two and then there's a third thing which
is like prefab code right and so for
example when you talk about something
like Python that has nothing to do with
the code
the only reason Python is useful at all
is because there's so many libraries the
reason it looks like something in Python
is concise is because you're calling a
bunch of prefab code that somebody else
made right you don't have to implement
HTTP yourself because there's a library
there to do that for you you don't have
to implement MSHA one because there's a
library for you right and so that is a
separate concern altogether it's whether
or not you have any particular access to
libraries that do the things that you
need that's a separate concern and
actually in many ways re-implemented
sometimes those libraries you might find
a really well-written library and then
you it doesn't matter that you used it
you still get really high quality
results because the library was written
specifically to do the thing you want to
do and was well written other times you
be like well I just care that this can
do it at all and the fact that this
library can do it is good enough for me
even though it's slow and piggy and lame
right and so I think you have a pretty
wide set of concerns there that you have
to manage the reason that on handmade
here oh we write everything ourselves
and we write it low level is because
there's already plenty of material out
there how to do it the other way right
grabbing someone else's librarian just
calling it is not something I really
need to teach people to do you should be
able to find right plenty of people
talking about that and I think it's
important that people learn this because
my daily experience with other people's
software is that it's terrible every
single thing I use on the web is
horrible
super slow and absolutely like so far
below the level of acceptable quality
that I just completely rage out at it
right and what's weird about that is
like you know I did the code for our
website and this when I tried to use
other people's stuff for this it was so
horrible that I just ended up writing my
own and seeing it was way better right
um so again like that quality bar is
like a real issue right now and I think
that is I think a lot of people are
lying to themselves about the quality of
the things that they're putting out by
not writing things from scratch and so
it's a little bit less to me it's not so
much that I think in the grand scheme of
things we will always have to write
things at low level I actually hope
that's not true but right now people are
using a lot of high level things either
libraries or languages that are actually
just terrible and they don't seem to
care that the products they're producing
are absolutely terrible to use their
buggy they're slow they're unpredictable
they're not very maintainable they have
erroneous weird transient errors a lot
of time and I hope at least that some
people who watch the series get a taste
for implementing things themselves
because I'm just hoping that people more
people will take quality more seriously
which is really just and you have to
start here right you have to start just
knowing how to do this basic stuff and
so this is just like a training ground
for knowing how to implement things from
scratch and once you know how to
implement things from scratch then when
you go to look at another problem you
can say oh I don't have to use this
ridiculous super piggy thing that takes
one point five seconds to add someone's
name to a mailing list on this website I
can write one myself it takes ten
milliseconds including the ping time and
it's like ten times better right and so
this is just a way to say hey it's not
that hard to implement things yourself
here's how it looks yes it takes longer
to write something that's good and from
scratch but it's also way better right
um and so I guess that's what I would
say I tried odeon no I have not
what you're seeing is really good but
opposite to what devs are being told in
schools um yeah but I mean that's true
of most things that occur in schools I
mean one of the things that's true about
schools is those are not people who do
production code for a living right
so typically what someone gets taught in
school is either completely uninformed
by reality which is often the case and
not just in programming or it's old
right
it's it's old knowledge that if it was
ever true is not true anymore right and
so you know it's a problem but that's
true of most things you learn in schools
right most things that happen in a
university are not particularly well
grounded in practicality right and to
some degree I think that's a bit of a
reason why they're not particularly
great for training people to actually do
stuff I mean you know that wasn't really
ever supposed to be the point of a
university in the first place like
universities were supposed to be places
people went to sort of abstractly study
things not where you went to get trained
to do something that's what a guild is
right didn't go to university to learn
to be a blacksmith you went to
university to just study about the
nature of metals or something right and
so nowadays we've kind of got it mixed
up you go to University learn about
programming but the people there aren't
production programmers you know the
people who are professors in programming
classes usually haven't done hardly any
really serious production programming
and if they have it hasn't been for a
really long time that's just not where
you want to get your information right
about how to be a production programmer
so yeah it's bad but that's the nature
of universities unfortunately and we've
that's a fallacy we accidentally created
and it doesn't just apply to programming
it's everything you know we the place to
learn how to do something is not in an
abstract studying scenario and
universities were supposed to be for
abstract studying
and guilds and apprenticeship was
supposed to be to learn how to do stuff
right and unfortunately we've lost this
dichotomy and it's a problem
Chavez still intro to CS and often times
C so us is barely covered why do you
think that is I think it's because a lot
of old corporate financial companies the
old guard was stuck with ooh
servile hand um yeah I don't know why
they prefer Java it's hard to say I mean
again like C C++ they're not good
languages either they're if you're gonna
learn something C is a good language to
teach instead of Java for sure but you
know there's really no language as I
point to today and say wow that's a
great language we should all be teaching
that right they're all bad C++ is awful
and so you know the reason I would say
why would you be learning jobs cuz I
just don't think you want to teach
people things that pretend that the
computer is not really a computer right
not a good way to learn but but you know
I'd be lying if I said that C++ was some
kind of language that I think is great
it's not I I complain about it every day
on stream and you know just looking at
any given piece of my code I can think
of 10 things C++ should have had that
would have made it much simpler and much
easier to write that piece all right I'm
gonna spend a long stream of talking I'm
gonna lose my voice I actually already
have lost my voice all right we all get
here
all right hmm thank you everyone for
joining me for another sort of handmade
hero - a pleasure coding with you as
always
if you want to follow along with the
stream at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade hero organ it comes
with a source code already so if you
want to play around with it that's the
way to do it I'm gonna be back here
tomorrow for more coding we'll take a
look at our memory window and try to get
that finished up so that next weekend we
can start on our entity improvements
that's about it until then have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the
Internet
thank yous everybody