everyone welcome to handmade marrow show
Rico to complete game live on stream we
are going to do some funny today we did
the implementation work necessary
yesterday to support large textures in
addition to our smaller textures that
are designed for use in the game which
try to get packed into a texture array
to avoid them being sort of expensive in
our dispatching so what we're trying to
do today is figure out what we need to
do to get opengl to deal with our new
implementation we got everything flowing
for the pipeline but we get black
textures when we actually try to use the
cutscene textures so we've got something
subtly wrong in there maybe something's
not get initialized right maybe we're
calling OpenGL slightly wrong we don't
know so we got to actually take some
time right now to go figure out what's
wrong in there and then once we do that
we can move on to a couple of their
touch-up things for our renderer which I
think at this point is now pretty good
right it's you know it's it's start to
be relatively respectable for what it's
supposed to do which is you know fairly
advanced 3d sprite plus cubes kind of
rendering system the quality looks
pretty good on it so let's go ahead and
load it up and today is for 80s so start
with day 479 source code if you're
someone who has pre-ordered the game and
is working with the source code right
now let's go ahead and refresh the
memory of what's going on here so if you
look at the code the way we have it the
key thing that we added yesterday was a
new pipeline for handling large textures
what we do is inside any quad dispatch
what we do is say the old-school way we
used to do things of having a texture
per quad you can still turn on so
essentially what happens is normally for
anything in the game you go through this
path where we just bind a texture array
and then can draw everything in one
batch which can create Lee accelerate
the rendering on a lot of GPUs because
they don't like to see like lots of
dispatches like that the old-school GPUs
again the more modern they get the less
they care about that so you know again
it your mileage may vary but especially
when you're using kind of old-school
OpenGL calls as well like we are so kind
of back compatible stuff getting the
dispatch count up high
I is bad right and a lot of there's a
lot of kind of new API and stuff that
you need to do if you really want to be
a large dispatch kind of a draw system I
so since we don't want to do that and we
don't need to do that and it allows us
to support older cards if we wish to
we've got everything condensed pretty
nicely down to just one texture array in
one call so you just bind and go and
that draws basically the entire game
right here right and we just do that
four times once for each depth peel and
then we're done so really the only thing
we're trying to do here is enable a path
that allows us to set up a texture per
call situation for unusual cases such as
the cutscenes where we have very
irregularly sized textures and we don't
want to try to pack them into an ALICE
or a text or anything else and we don't
want to do the extra work of gritting
them or anything like that
because it's such a regular thing that
happens and we know that there's very
few of them so we don't need to worry
about the dispatch overhead it's only
gonna be eight of them total I think we
counted in the highest use case so this
is specifically for the situation where
we know that's what's going on so in
order to do this what we want to do is
take a look at at how this loop is
working here figure out what we've done
wrong because we did something wrong and
trying to get it working correctly so we
looked into it a little bit yesterday
and we found that at least to first
approximation we found that it didn't
seem to be the actual texture passing
that was the problem anyway when we
looked at this texture it looked correct
it was an actual valid texture handle
that had been seen and it seemed like it
was all set up properly so we might have
to dig a little deeper find out a couple
more things did the texture get
downloaded properly you know maybe it
didn't is the texture stuff that's
packed into the texture itself correct
you know maybe it's not because some of
the things that could happen here is
like when we bind this texture I don't
know what happens if you bind texture 2d
and then like for example one really
easy thing that could be wrong is when
we bind this texture we don't know it
may be a simple
as we're binding a texture but we're
calling a shader that expects an array
right so it may just be that mismatch
that's causing the problem and we needed
to either set a different like have two
versions of our program one that's
compiled for texture arrays and one
that's not or maybe there's some kind of
finesse you can do here where these
texture we just create everything as a
texture rate but it's only one deep
right so my guess is that the actual
problem we're seeing just you know I'm
just guessing here but that's my guess
because right if you if you remember if
we look back at the texture rays itself
inside the OpenGL renderer
let me just pull that up here so if we
look at like the samplers as they're
defined in the theta Z bias program is
the thing that we're actually talking
about here so if you look inside the
program that we're actually talking
about which is the Z vias program here
what we want to look at is how we're
actually getting the textures out of it
you know I'm Sam and so if we look at
how we're getting the textures out of it
this is the pass through right and then
here's where it picks them up and so
when we look here we've got the 2d
sampler array right here this vertex
sampler my guess is that you can't just
find a regular thing to that right you
can't you probably can't just say I'm
gonna bind an on array texture to it
that's my guess right so I'm guessing
that if I was to bind a regular texture
to that it will just fail now what I
don't know is is that does that mean
that the solution is as simple as just
changing it to everything to 1d texture
right maybe it is I don't even know if
that's actually the problem right so I
you know that could just be fake news it
could be that if you bind the thing to
it that you end up in a situation where
it will just use that texture as a
one-dimensional texture array and you
don't have to worry about it right I'm
not 100% certain so what the
specification is there I don't know we
could look it up but I'd rather just
test it and see whether that's something
that's logical just at first just to see
what the situation is with that
so when I do GL allocate texture and
call in here we do a special texture
right you can see what happens here
where we do write a GL text image 3d if
I was just to say look let's keep this
exactly the same right and instead of
doing Jill text sub image 3d just do
text image 3d and just send the whole
thing down does it work you know I have
no idea right I'm just saying maybe
that's the case so let's take a look so
if I go look at GL texture 2d array
where we create it which is here you can
kind of see where we're actually
creating thing if I was to avoid
actually ever creating it and instead
just said like look let's do it this way
where we do a bind texture and then set
it up right what happens so let's just
see I'm again just totally speculatively
here just totally guessing have no idea
if it's actually game so if I was to do
this and I bound these texture handles
as a 2d array texture handles and then I
just go in and set them as 1d arrays do
we fix anything right again probably not
but I just want to know that that's not
the case because for all I know when we
have something that's expecting a sample
from array maybe it always has to be an
array you know maybe that's just how
that goes so if I come up and I look at
allocate texture and I you know change
this path here to basically do exactly
the same thing the other one does so I
say look you know here's the the bind
instead of calling GL text into D called
GL Texan mich 3d and when we actually
send that down we'll just specify the
entire image itself right so you know
we're we're gonna pass the actual
dimensions we're gonna tell it that
there's only one right that doesn't have
multiples right and off we go something
like this now I don't know if that'll
actually work like I said we're just
gonna try it and see what happens
because I'm just curious I want to kind
of eliminate that as a possibility just
from looking at it I want to see what's
going on with that we might want to make
some way if this debugging goes on for a
while half
to wait to switch into the to the
cutscene mode is pretty annoying so it
would be nice to be able to sort of go
in there and and have a more stable way
of doing that hold on one second here I
must have passed something wrong oh yeah
that's that's not obviously we don't
want to try to pass down an entire
sprite arrays worth of data I need to
tell if there's only one slice to this
particular one sorry but first why I was
saying is right now in order to has two
cutscene since we boot into the game
normally for testing purposes I would I
should go turn off the path that boots
directly in the game I should make it
boot to the cutscene like it normally
would it start up so that we can watch
the cutscene and see what's happening
right alright so we've got an error
message happening here that's kind of
interesting target doesn't match the
textures target oh yes right so one
other thing we have to do in order to
test that path is when we actually bind
the texture inside the drawing loop we
got to make that actually work so inside
the part where we do the Deaf peeling
here well let me do this part
so in here where we actually want to
bind the textures and use them this has
to bind the 2d texture array right like
this so again don't really know if this
will do anything just speculating and
want to make sure that we're not that
the only thing that's failing isn't just
some basic thing about you can't have a
sampler an array sampler bound if an
array sample in the shader if what
you're binding is a regular texture and
that's all I wanted to check in idea
other people who know the spec better
like Martin's probably know already
whether that's a problem but I don't
know got hit escape so yeah that's all I
want to check first and then after that
I don't know we might want to take a
capture and see if the textures are
being uploaded properly would be another
thing to check trying to think of the
other things we might want to check but
yeah I just basically start to go
a little bit more forensic ly and see if
we can find you know more errors there
so I'm still not seeing anything so one
thing I think I might want to do is boot
directly in here and see if we can't
capture frames in like the de butter to
see what we've actually sent down right
to see why this is like because for all
we know - you know this draw limits
maybe drawing things wrong I don't
really know so you know just just
getting this stuff right would be would
be probably part of it as well looking
in here you know something I'll surprise
you - is this like why not right
sooo again quad protects her as well so
we're getting the texture handle and
we're stepping through those properly I
think so each time we advance a quad
we're getting a texture out there and
we're getting a special texture handle
then we're binding it which is correct
then we're drawing and we're moving on
so I think again that should be proper
right I think all of that should be good
this right here should really be that I
assume because that's the thing we
actually bound at least it looks like to
me although really all of these should
be unbound as well
I don't know I guess it doesn't matter
if it remains found or not um so yeah
I'm not really sure there so the I think
the next thing I want to do is try to
validate what this is gonna be grabbing
for geometry and maybe like I said you
know maybe the easiest thing to do just
to make the debugging a little easier on
us to going forwards is let's boot
instead of booting into the game let's
actually allow it to because like you
see right here this this is what boots
into the game if we just get rid of that
and instead boot directly into the
cutscene system then that takes out a
bunch of sort of annoying stuff steps
that have to happen there in order to
get to the part where we're actually
trying to bug things so that you know I
guess one thing them don't quite
remember I'm pretty sure that the
lighting isn't a problem there like it
wouldn't be lit as zero or anything I'm
assuming but anyway
so let's try to boot up in sight and
just see if we can get any insight into
our into what's happening with our
cutscenes right so here's the the
handmade hero target executable stuff
and I think it's already set up to do
what we want to do so I think if we just
launch the game we should be able to do
capture once we get far enough into the
game where we think we should be seeing
the cutscene and you know we're
obviously not seeing the cutscene so in
order to capture a frame I think you can
just go back here and say capture for
live analysis right is that all I have
to do yeah so now we in theory could get
some insight into what's going on by
just taking a look at all the
information in the capture what's this
err says there's an issue but how do I
know what the issue is
oh right these are just like things that
don't don't change the state so we don't
really need to do them
yeah um so first of all let's just take
a look at what's going on right because
what we we should be able to see we
should hopefully be able to see us
trying to draw some stuff right and so
coming through here there's the multi
sample setup there's a frame buffer
I'm not really seeing our dispatch
anywhere
here we go no that's not our just
factually that that's just a final mix
down is there a good way I can jump to
places really dry race there we go
so triangle stripped this should have
that's also just a mix down so for some
reason I'm not really seeing sorry too
many windows open now we're getting
spammy here there we go
so some reason I wasn't really seeing
the draw elements that I was expecting
to see oh you know what though but the
cutscene graphics would also kind of
look like that
so now that I think about it that's not
dispositive so anyway let me just yet
write because I keep forgetting we're
not drawing a little sprites anymore I'm
like looking for little sprites on the
screen and I'm going oh this must be the
mix down where we do a full screen quad
but no no it's cutscenes so it would
look like that even if it was just the
cutscene stuff however when I you know
just again still looking at these
there's in terms of draw array calls
here and I guess I could I mean let's
look at oh that's that's really nice
in terms of these drop calls here I'm
also where they exist I'm not seeing any
actual I'm just really not seeing any
actual calls that look like they fit the
correct pattern
because there should be a bind texture
with GL texture 2d array right is there
a way to do a filter for vine texture
there it is
so there's GL texture 2d array so that
is definitely a bind to the type of
texture we care about so if I turn this
off
you know dear NVIDIA people this is
pretty awesome like that was just super
cool I don't know if there's anyone from
Nvidia watching but if there is like the
the fact that you can just like search
on like what you wanted to look look
which call you were looking for go right
there then go back to the whole thing so
you can see what happened around it
that's like exactly the kind of thing
that people often get wrong and then
it's super hard to use the tool like the
fact that that all just worked exactly
as I would have wanted to is pretty
awesome right so that's pretty cool so
yeah so if there's the bind texture and
there's GL draw elements base vertex
that's actually the old one right like
that's actually that's actually calling
this so it's not doing this path it's
doing this path you know so
just looking at the places so for
whatever reason like we're just not even
getting a dispatch so it looks like
maybe the problem has nothing to do with
the textures just yet we just don't even
seem to be drawn anything so that's a
problem I guess I don't really want to
quit let's just terminate if I can yeah
I sue and say it looks like it was
working pretty well there to me that
seemed pretty clean got the capture
looked at the logs everything went great
I'm gonna assume this is our fault
meaning that there wasn't a problem with
a capture and that we're just not
hitting this path somehow and so what
I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna set a
breakpoint in that path and make sure we
hit it now I thought we definitely were
hitting it at least before because if we
weren't hitting it then I don't know how
we were getting the error that we were
binding the wrong thing right in other
words we saw it issue an error before
because we were binding at extra high
with just Yelp to texture no array so I
mean it must have hit so maybe what
we're doing it so there it is right and
so why we're not seeing this draw
elements call occur I'm not sure now it
does take a little while to get there
but I thought we waited long enough and
maybe the answer is we didn't wait long
enough right I'm not sure so maybe we
just need a way of knowing when we've
hit there now there's something else
weird going on here so and I'm not sure
what it is now you'll notice so if I
like try to run this guy again I don't
really know how to do that I guess I
just do this is that the correct working
directory maybe that's the problem is it
can't load anything what's the correct
working directory for this gentleman
aha that's the problem
so just couldn't load eight textures
there we go
so cool okay great now let's try again
yeah cuz I I didn't see the fonts either
so I was wondering what was going on and
now we know all right so now that we're
running here we should be okay and now
we should be able to get one I knew
there was something wrong guys didn't
know what all right sue now let's see if
we can find an actual dispatch called
looks like the kind of call we are
expecting to see because hopefully now
we will in fact this one looks a little
bit like it right here and and let's see
what's going on
right so that actually looks a little
bit more like it can we actually see
this texture would be my next question
[Music]
textures
so
I'm guessing this is
I'm just assuming this is the texture
this is pretty cute by the way so I'm
guessing that that's the texture and
it's not actually being created properly
here's our sprite sheet I think
can we get some more information here
this is our spreadsheet right here 512
by 512 2056 slices great so I don't
really know it looks like it never got
so it's trying to draw with the texture
that did not work in terms of texture
specification now what's interesting
about that is it didn't give us an error
right
so I could just take one second over
here it didn't give us an error so for
whatever reason this call it's
suggesting that this call failed but
that even though it failed it didn't
produce an heir or maybe I'm gonna go
ahead and look up real quick on Doc's
dot GL what GL text image 3d has to say
just so I can see here so obviously the
level parameter seems wrong I don't know
why yeah that looks like that was just
wrong from before so and that might have
to do Martin's actually filed a thing to
get us so we could use text image 3d in
the place we were trying to use it
before and it didn't work and that might
be part of it too so that's what's
probably wrong with that height I
probably write the depth the depth
should be one because it's one wide
right border is zero so I think we're
okay with most of this stuff I'm not
sure let's just see if this makes any
difference sorry I got a
Connect insight here and who else is
holding Oh I disconnected it I did not
terminate it sorry let's just build this
and then I will run it okay so that's
better
[Music]
so we are now correctly getting imagery
and it looks like well I don't know
where correctly the imagery that may or
may not be correct there but it looks
like we are screwing up one thing which
is that our texture coordinate
computation it looks like it's using the
hard-coded to produce to use in V's it's
its encoding those incorrectly so what
we probably just need to do to fix that
is inside handmade render dot CPP where
we actually push the quad on you can see
where it does like its UV computation
here right this stuff so what we
actually want to do here is when we look
at the is special texture stuff that's
probably the place we want to actually
do this computation because we will
actually be using the entire size of the
texture not a mapping of an interior
part of the texture so the probably the
best way to do this would be to say
let's take those UV zero through three
which are being specified up in here
let's actually just correct those where
we go and I think I think that's really
all that we should have to do so what we
can do is say alright assume that this
is the inverse U and V upfront but then
when we come in here if we know that
it's a special texture
know that the UVs are not going to be
based on these DIMMs at all so at that
point presumably all we have to do is
say okay
it's the in view and V it doesn't
actually modify anything another way to
do this we could probably do it the
reverse way but either way is probably
fine
so in a view V dot X probably and that Y
probably can now just be one and then we
would not get that remapping of the
texture I think let's just take a look
there so we're getting closer to being
correct but we still have some issues
here so some kind of odd issues as well
like first of all we're getting no
actual animation there for some reason
so like the time step isn't applying or
something so like or well more
specifically could just be our our
offsets are not being applied so like
it's just mapping to the whole screen
always or something like this we're also
not getting any alpha blending so it
looks as almost as if the Alpha Bunnings
been turned like off or something so
this one is moving I'll be it only a
little bit so yeah there's some weird
weird stuff happening here and I don't
know exactly what it is so we're gonna
have to look into this a little bit
further like we're just definitely
getting kind of weird stuff happening
and like the edges are not alpha blended
for some reason which I don't know why
that would be
so that's a little bit peculiar so yeah
we're gonna need to go in here and and
take a look probably one thing we should
do is look at what we're actually
passing in terms of color information
and stuff like that because I don't know
to what extent those may be incorrect
now but yeah so the other thing I don't
actually know is how is this actually
pushing stuff on it's just doing begin
render group yeah yeah so it's also
doesn't have clear color clear depth on
but I don't is that because we got rid
of those
I guess because render default just does
that
so I wonder if it has to do with I
wonder does has to do with the depth
peeling or something I don't actually
know I'm just curious I'm gonna just
oops that's the title screen I'm just
gonna I see what's going on here I don't
actually know
so yeah that's a total non-starter so
I'm not sure where to start looking for
that particular piece of information
it's just trying to think it through
because it's trying to draw through the
same drop half you know the the other
stuff which is already working like this
is all drawing through that same drop
path and it works just fine with its
transparency right and the game works
just fine with transparency so right
like all the transparency just works
fine there so I don't really quite
understand why we would be suddenly
seeing problem with just the render path
involving the large textures I mean mmm
yeah like maybe yeah I don't have a
solid theory so I'm gonna just start
investigating see if I can come up with
some leads so I can figure out what's
going on cuz I really don't know and I
can't really think I don't need that in
there anywhere I really don't know what
would be causing that and we haven't
looked at the cut seeing stuff in a
while so I don't have a good idea either
of like what would be like logical to
suspect there so the focal length also
maybe needs to be changed I suppose for
possible things I don't really know but
again that shouldn't be affecting the
fading much so I'm gonna go ahead and
step into the where we actually push
these down I want to see what we're
actually pushing so I'm gonna go ahead
and set a breakpoint when we actually
push layers on so I can watch like what
goes into the actual buffer right so
here's the push bitmap call and let's
step into that they do an actual step in
two
okay step into specific push bitmap they
needed just a hotkey for step into the
last one and I I don't know if there is
one or not but that really needs to be a
high key so when we get the bitmap out
here we're going to do a push book map
call the push bitmap call is gonna do a
push quad at the end of things right so
here we go down to the very end where
we're ready to push and of course step
into specific push quad so when we walk
down here all I'm really gonna try and
do now is figure out like what we're
actually pushing on we know that this is
right now because we're seeing the right
textures in play the vertex and index
index stuff I think that should all be
the same through most of these so that
all seems fine and so the question is
now just what are we producing here so
the UVs should like look at least
relatively correct so I don't suspect
the UVs or the problem in a particular
sense and I don't know why they would
affect the blending much either way so
let's see here we've got
we've got color values well you know
what let me just push all these on here
and let me just look at the vertices at
the end of it so here are all four
vertices if I switch to hex we can also
look at the color of course we're
starting off at black because we're
fading in so probably we really should
wait let me go ahead and and and
actually step to this once things have
actually faded in all right now it's
breakpoint there okay so now let's step
in to the renderer same place and if we
look now we should see yeah so those are
you know color values we would expect so
that seems about right the light index
is being zero is I think correct because
that will turn the lighting off so there
will be no lighting so I feel like that
should all be correct so it looks
honestly I mean that looks like we're
pushing down proper values there now
texture index 0 I guess I don't really
know to what extent that would cause
problems for things it it may be that
the texture index wants to be 0 always
like I don't really know what will
happen inside the sampler if you pass
something that's out of bounds I would
have thought the clamp would just work
but maybe it doesn't so just to be on
the safe side since there's only
one entry in these secretaries I'm gonna
say that when we push a quad down that's
a special texture it needs to set the
texture index to be something else right
so it should always like floor it to
zero
so basically when it puts it in here it
will always be zero because we're
setting the texture manually so it
shouldn't ever use anything other than
sliced zero now I don't really think
that was probably the problem because it
should have yeah and it's not as I say
it should just clamp so I don't think it
should matter you know but I just wanted
to make sure that that was not weird so
yeah I mean as far as I can tell we're
just getting some weird like depth
occlusion stuff happening it doesn't
seem like it now that may just be
because the depth went like is the depth
lending just not working for some reason
and maybe like trying to think of why
that would fail
so when we actually let me actually draw
[Music]
cuz that's right when we actually draw
these I wonder if there's some kind of
bug like we're now gonna have more than
one render group entry type let me just
try to think out loud here so you know
what I'm sort of investigating or trying
to investigate
so one thing we do know is that because
all of our calls get aggregated into a
single call effectively for the game
when it's running we actually don't have
any that this only happens once in the
actual game render I think because
literally all of the sprites and all of
the cubes get stuck into one single
giant quad dispatch and the only time we
have two quad dispatches is if you use
more than 16 bits worth of indices now
we do use more than 16 bits worth of
indices in the test app the external app
but for all we know there might be some
issues with that one that we just can't
see so we don't really know what happens
when you call render entry textured
quads more than once so one question is
is there something that when we updated
the renderer that we did like some kind
of eye we introduced some kind of thing
where you can't call it twice without
having some errors what is debug set up
want to remove that
so I don't know that's I'm just like
wondering if there's like a texture
buying problem that it's like doing
something weird leaving something bound
that shouldn't be bound I'm just not
sure so you know in here we do like an
active texture one we bind active
texture 0 active texture to bind 3 bind
0 again we never bind texture 0 but we
do unbind texture 1 we don't unbind
textures 2 or 3 so I'm not sure why we
take that extra time to do that yeah I'm
not entirely sure this right here really
wants to just unbind the texture 2d
array which would be that but I don't
see that's getting rebound every time so
it doesn't seem likely to be anything
problematic I wouldn't think so yeah
so I don't know so I guess the next step
might be let's insight capture this and
see what's going on it really looks like
you know you can see to around those
edges like I wonder if this is just a
case of like hey the depth feeling isn't
meant to handle four things five things
that can top each other I don't really
know but it sure seems like it should be
handling it better than that you know
what I mean so one thing I'm curious
about is if we actually want to skip the
Deaf peeling all together and we do
begin frame I'm just curious like can we
just move this stuff outside of that
loop so you know you know maybe let's
hear it here's a question for you
suppose we just like have the render or
skip that part instead like all right if
we're going to run to the title screen
like first like do this thing to get the
DEF peels out of the way you know I'm
saying then
I guess just zero
so again this is just oh that's that's
the title screen
so this was just like pre you know sort
of push it to see if we're just because
we've changed the render around if
really it's just a case of like we
didn't quite really finish making it
support rendering without using the
depth feeling at all
so I guess we don't really need a
background color here
so again really strange so that does
work right and presumably these are all
going through the non depth feeling pass
now and let me just verify that they're
going through the non depth billing pass
because that would be where's the OpenGL
stuff that's not it that's it or not
there we go
so let me just verify that we're not
going through the depth filling pass
here so when we actually come through
here I guess I should actually set the
breakpoint here and say when we when we
draw these guys peeling should be false
and it is so we're going through the non
depth building pass now you know what
I'm saying
so that stuff should just accumulate on
top and we should get
we should just be getting alpha blending
but we're definitely not it's almost
like it's truncating our alpha down to
one bit or something
so I think this would happen if we drew
in the wrong order right because if we
have depth testing on and we drew in the
wrong order we'd get this result so I
wonder if maybe that's what's going on
here
not sure I understand so we were already
drawing backwards wise so it doesn't
seem likely but I'll try it
oh no we weren't so we switched to
drawing forwards for some reason not
sure why so all right let's suppose we
were to do this and draw on the opposite
order
all right
so this just gets weirder and weirder so
now what you're telling me is that if I
draw in the opposite order the amount of
zoom changes okay is there something
weird going on here where we like we're
getting some weird stuff happening now
so if you look at what's going on here
what we're saying is that just simply by
picking a different layer order right
because this was it originally right
just by picking a different layer order
we got movement
so we've got some seriously whack
happening right now all right
I'm gonna leave it that way and I am
going to go ahead and do an insight
capture and look at what the vertex
arrays are cuz I am totally confused
right now totally confused I would just
like it known that I have no idea what
that's doing which is often the case
with hardware rendering just to be clear
capture so now we can in theory look at
like what's going on here right as we
sort of come up through here so here's
the render building up each phase
so looking at this render let's look at
here so this is what's happening so
first we draw this bitmap and that looks
correct then we draw this bitmap and
what you can see is that we get no
transparency we only get an alpha cut
out right and I have no idea why that's
happening like I have no idea why it's
not blending with the background so even
just right there we've already hit a a
snag
so the first thing I want to know is
like why isn't an alpha blending like
what did we do wrong and there's two
ways it could be wrong one way it could
be wrong is the textures alpha got
screwed up the other way is we don't
turn on the right blending modes or
something so let's first look to see
what the blending modes actually are
right so looking through here we are
drawing multi sample so I don't know if
that's necessarily bad or not
this is the texture and I don't know if
I can see what the alpha so there is
there's all kinds of alpha in there you
can see it so it doesn't really seem
like that's likely I mean there's the
alpha right it should be really clear
you know so it doesn't seem like it's a
problem with the textures alpha it seems
like something we're doing to the
textures alpha that's a problem
there's the pixel ops so we we do have
depth testing on but that should be okay
because those are further away I would
think now maybe that's not true like
maybe we've got some bad stuff happening
there the blending states obscured by my
head so I can't see it so maybe we'll
just do this so blending States
Sarah where's the blending function
[Music]
there it is
so everything's getting written our
through a no multiplication happening on
the source which is correct for
premultiplied alpha destination has
inverse which is what I expect and it's
adding so I don't quite get how that
could be wrong unless what we're reading
as a color value in the shader is wrong
because that means that assuming it was
actually sampling from that texture it
should have gotten us the proper alpha
value we saw it in there right so if we
look at the fragment shader here's the
source code to the fragment shader and
we look at what's actually happening so
what comes in here we do textile fetch
on the lights and that should just be
ignored hopefully let's see where that
actually gets done
so we started out by saying if Depp feel
I'm assuming that deaf peels false in
this particular one because well it's
supposed to be because we're in we're
not in peeling mode I don't know how to
tell if that's true it isn't showing me
like a compiled version of this
unfortunately so I'm not sure if this
can tell me whether it actually got IFFT
out there oh well let me see
it should say it here yeah def kill is
zero so it's not gonna do that that's
not there so then we come through here
and we say all right let's get the array
UV going the frag texture index in
theory should be zero and when we text
your sample that will get out the
texture with the with the alpha in it
right
fear sim text reads should be zero right
oh oh no read the source should be is
one
that's not correct
so this graphics card supports srgb
textures so we should not be doing that
right
that's just straight-up wrong
hmm
mm-hmm so we need to look at what our
alpha threshold is although it shouldn't
really matter because again we're not
getting blending anywhere so no matter
what our alpha threshold is it's
probably worked but just looking through
things here so I would say before we go
any further this is not really related
to the problem at hand but since we see
it we should fix it that that srgb stuff
is is broken and I I thought we got that
right and we obviously haven't there we
go
so so this is this is bad
we have simulation for srgb in there for
cards that don't support it but I
thought these should support it I don't
know why that's happening that seems
really bad so I'm gonna look at sim Tex
right sRGB I'm gonna see what's going on
there why we're not getting any of that
stuff I so
do we like not define allow GPU srgb or
something is that like a mistake
was there a reason that we did that I
wonder how long that's been wrong I mean
I guess to be fair it's not necessarily
wrong in the sense that if we always had
it turned off then we probably weren't
submitting textures as srgb you know we
probably had that turned off because
well yeah I don't know why we had turned
up all right I it's lost to the sands of
time I must want to take a look at what
goes on here to make sure that that
actually still works cuz that that's
just weird
um so okay just gonna go ahead and it is
still one
hmm all right we're stepping in cuz yeah
I don't know why we wouldn't be getting
that so that's zero in both cases now
here's this compiling Z biased program
those are both now defined zero so
that's what we should be seeing now in
here right that was probably some old
thing if I just left that loaded let's
hope that's true
all right and so now I'm going to do is
gonna draw it again and I'm just gonna
look at that primer shader and see if we
can now verify that it's not yeah there
we go so I would like that to be working
properly so let me just verify that it
actually is in everywhere else so if we
run now oh we can't both open this
apparently
come on there we go so if we run now I
want to make sure everything still looks
okay
all right sue assuming all that's fine
and happy we're back to just our
original problem which is why are we not
getting alpha blending that it looks
like we should be getting what's getting
in the way of the alpha blending so
let's go ahead and go back to let me
close this down let's go ahead and go
back to a frame capture and watch it
build up and see what's happening there
because I really just don't know it
looks like it should be blending
properly but it's definitely not so all
right take that scene capture if we look
through here nothing gets done really so
this is the first time anything happens
that's important that looks fine here's
us drawing our next one and it's totally
not fine we're not getting any alpha
blending it all so I don't actually know
if we look at the fragment shader itself
let's get this out here maybe that can
be like on here because either I'm
looking at events or I'm looking at code
probably so looking through here when we
actually update this information it's
the output is blend unit color and by
the way this stuff can all be simplified
dramatically now because we don't write
to more than one year at a time
so we've probably should get rid of a
lot of this junk anyway but when we
output the blend unit color here it's
the surface reflect that we use so the
surface reflects alpha is what we care
about and so let's just look at how that
actually gets set
so basically it will discard anything
whose alpha isn't over a particular
threshold that seems fine inside here
we'll take the mod color which is alpha
amount which comes from the the fogging
times the frag color times to example so
you know it could have something to do
with the fog right it could very well be
so like so this stuff
let's take a look at the vertex shader
so in here the fog distance does the
inner product with the fog direction and
the fog direction is zero so fog
distance will also be zero
when it comes out of here right there we
go so when fog distance comes out as
zero in here that means the lerp will
not lurk so the so the fog amount should
be zero in both cases
so here is a particularly strange
situation the alpha start and end and
the fog start and end are both on the
same value which is definitely wrong so
I would say that alpha amount is
completely bogus right now that's just
old news and is wrong
once mod colors alpha gets set in this
case I'm not sure why anything is
getting drawn because if the fog
distance oh because it's negative 99 I
guess I guess because that's set to
negative 99 it will end up producing an
alpha amount of one probably so here's
what I'm gonna recommend first I'm gonna
set those values to known values to make
sure that that's not the problem and
then we're going to go from there
and then I'm gonna look a little bit
more closely at how we're computing
those because that Alpha clip start and
end should be based on the actual screen
Z more so than the fog z because the fog
can go could go in a different direction
right if we wanted it to so that part's
a little bit iffy but all right so let's
just take a look where's our Z bias here
it is so in this particular piece of
code here what I want to do is make it
so that these just get switched around
so the Alpha amount will always be 1 and
the fog amount will always be 0 and I
want to see if that has an effect on
things so that doesn't so it's not even
that
so the 99 does actually work in that
case so how is our alpha so let's try
some other things here in this situation
I'm going to set the surface reflect a
to be 0.5 so that means essentially that
every surface we draw should be at 1/2
translucency right
and so still nothing like if there's
appears to be nothing we can do to get
the actual alpha blend to occur right
even though we're saying you must alpha
blend at 0.5 it's like no I'm not gonna
do that you can't make me do that I'm
I'm going to I'm I'm I just I simply
won't
I simply refuse right
hmm
so why is that happening
why is our texture sample a wrong I'm
sorry why is our blend always wrong
because we should be able to get it to
show something of the background through
by setting the surface reflect a to
something else right I mean
you can even see it that it dimmed but
the alpha value has not been affected so
somehow we're not getting alpha blending
even though we're forcing the Alpha
Channel to be 0.5 and we know that
blending is on cuz we just looked at it
it doesn't matter because it refuses to
actually blend
can't say I know why that's happening
did I mention I hate hardware rendering
I do just make sure I'm not crazy here
so again looking at this draw call here
we don't really get any information
about it that would indicate something
went wrong and so if we look at all of
the information that we've got here the
the index and vertices and stuff seemed
good enough right
and I don't see anything particularly
unusual occurring right inside the
fragment shader we were sampling from
exactly the things that we think we're
sampling from and we can verify that our
texture sampler here does actually have
alpha in it of course we forced the
alpha 2.5 so we know that that obviously
doesn't even really matter right
all this stuff looks right I can't see
any particularly weird stuff happening
here right
I have no idea I don't see anything
unusual happening there that's exactly
the blend that I would have wanted right
I don't know how to see more of that
it's very way to like there yeah it's on
ad and it's one - source off of her
destination so that all is exactly right
so how can you possibly have that be the
drub of her settings and not blend
anyone
so what's this
what's this right here
tenshun buying zero
so the fact that texture zero still has
this bound to it
hmm that is a little concerning unit
zero has these two things bound unit one
has these two things bound
hmm
I can't say that it should matter which
one of those is bound because really we
know we're only gonna pull from the
array when we use an array sampler so
the fact that this is bad shouldn't
really matter
but I really don't have any idea what's
going on there
I am out of ideas so I think at this
point I'm probably gonna have to start
like making simpler stuff to see what's
going on because I have no idea what's
actually wrong here I'm not sure how you
could get a more straightforward thing
than this like it's literally just
drawing the thing and you get no alpha
even though we definitely set alpha in
here and it did not matter so like
somehow it's not doing alpha blending
even though it has a partial alpha is
set to the correct blending mode
I really have no idea how that could be
possible
this is a little interesting so if I do
insert clear everything becomes like
white and red is that a bug in insight
or is that really what would happen if
we were to clear the buffer you know
what I mean
so while I'm here because I don't have
any other ideas I would like to get rid
of the multi-target stuff
so like blend unit color for example
like I'd like to stop making that be
three things
so what is some of this stuff compiled
resolved multisample has like some weird
stuff in it
let's just get some of the stuff out of
here all right Gill tube lighting we
know that's gone so yeah I don't really
know what's going on so I want to
simplify this down a little bit first
just make sure we have no problems with
that
hey Krampus and also I feel like the
aspect ratios room so and and we when we
flip the order things they were wrong
there's some really weird stuff going on
I feel like maybe with our submission
process as well like the vertices are
maybe incorrect or something like this
additionally so I don't know like we're
gonna have to we're gonna have to go a
little bit deeper down into this but
that's okay but first I just want to get
rid of some of this cruft because it
makes it harder for me to see what's
going on when we've got a bunch of
legacy things in here that we don't use
anymore because then I'm like wait is
that something that we care about no
it's not so let's take a look here so
resolve multisample let me see here
so we've got a couple things here depth
appeal the lighting is gone
fake seed lighting is gone right so
resolve multisample who uses this how
yet that all looks fine so that's
exactly what I would have thought so I'm
not sure why it used to write to
multiple buffers so we don't have these
things anymore like emit simpler and NPL
right those are not actually there so
like emitting MPL are gone we do have
color and depth
but admit in MPL we definitely don't
right
so we really just have that one surface
reflect so I think the blend unit color
can just be one thing in this case and
it really can just be can just be that
right so can I just
can I just get rid of this entirely
everywhere and I think I can alright so
just taking a look at what happens now I
just want to make sure that we didn't
bust anything that whoops that was
working like you know our regular
drawing and stuff I don't think we did
so that just simplifies that down nicely
and you know make sure that also since
we have a render a test as well that the
renderer test works yep oasis so all we
really need to do needed to do to do
that with just take a little bit of a
Delete key to the situation which i
think is good because that stuff was
just kind of old crafty stuff that
really didn't need to be in there so I'm
glad we got rid of that okay so now let
me look to just to see what we had in
terms I don't think there's anything
else particularly that got removed
entirely like that but that just makes
it nicer so now in theory right if I do
an insight capture we won't have that
weird like there's sort of that weird
like multiple color target thing which
I'd like to make sure it's not a thing
because we shouldn't have it should only
be rendering of one thing in each of
these scenarios right so yeah so like
this like why is this still here
what is going on did we pass something
down in terms of the number of color
targets that we were that we're still
passing down as a four you know I'm
talking about that we should get rid of
because I would like to get rid of that
yeah we've got three color attachments
so that needs to stop
so let's find out color so when we
create a frame buffer we're creating
color attachments here for how many
exactly four color buffer count
where do we actually define them yeah
all right so what we want to do is this
I believe and when we actually bind
these things in here we don't really
want this in fact we don't want any of
this either do we
that's all not a thing
so again just trying to get rid of this
stuff because it's just gonna make the
debugging more complicated and we
definitely have a lot of things in there
that we don't actually need because this
was all from when we were doing other
kinds of letting experiments
so we are missing a little bit there and
why is that
this is reading from the light buffers
we may still be using that for lighting
I suppose no that's just wrong
so what was actually going on here that
made that important
so for each peel
I'm assuming fronted so this is for the
final composite so I think what's
happening here is just for each peel we
were probably skipping one of those NPLs
so let's look at the final let's look at
the peel composite program and just see
what's going on here yes so we don't
want the NPL samplers right because
that's just not a thing we're doing
anymore we do the lighting directly so
that's the problem with there is that
needs to be removed because those go in
order
right so the NPL stuff needs to just to
just die right
that all goes away
and I don't even know those were there
none of this is necessary so it's really
just that right because that's all we're
doing now we don't do lighting in there
at all so these are gone these are gone
and we're just left with the four depth
peels that we actually composite right
okay so I think that should now be clean
where it's only taking the def peels and
compositing the def peels together which
is all I actually wanted in the first
place now because that other stuff is
all just there for like old sort of
wedding experiments all right okay well
there is a lot of cruft in there from
all of our experimentation sometimes you
just got to go in and clean it up so if
I now do capture hopefully I can finally
get rid of our extra color targets which
I don't need anymore and we're just kind
of getting in the way so here we've got
a color in a depth target and that's
what we want so those are correct right
that's good that's what we should see
now if we get sort of clear beforehand
why that turns red I really don't know
and I'm not sure if that's is that
normal to have to have the R and B
channels flip like this that just seems
really odd I don't know if that's just a
bug in the system but we shouldn't be
seeing that like I don't know what is
causing that specifically so that's a
little disquieting I'm hoping that's
just a bug in insight if it's not we got
bad news so let's tackle
listen to you know we know this is
pretty darn nasty what we're seeing here
so let's tackle this in two passes or
two two steps here right so a couple
things we know first off I think we know
that we've got some kind of problem with
how we're specifying our actual drawing
data separate from the fact that the
that the blending isn't working at all
right which we don't have any idea why
but we also know that we're getting some
kind of weird like positional corruption
and the reason I say that is because if
we do some very basic stuff here that I
don't understand why it's happening we
can see okay sorry about that so if we
do some very basic stuff here such as
here is one pass through that scene
right where we where we're just drawing
the layers in the same order that we
were drawing them before right and what
you can very clearly see is that there's
very little movement now you can see
that there's some movement because you
can see some like weird work artifacts
moving through here like weird little
like it's almost like bilinear is also
not working properly or something so
you'll see some weird artifacts moving
through here and and I guess that's that
light just because we're stretching it
down too much like it could be not by
one IRA's fault in that case right but
it is moving however if we go in and
change the way that's rendering the
cutscene just to render them in the
opposite order so literally all I did
here was say look render them in the
opposite order all I did was change the
order right um if all I do is change the
order all of a sudden you get way more
motion
uh there should be no difference between
those two right like the order in which
we send the things down should not have
any effect on on the speed at which it's
interpreting those things like I have no
idea how that's happening so to me what
that suggests is that when we're
outputting those particular types of
quads
we're actually outputting the vertex
data subtly wrong somehow not wrong
enough to cause corrupted quads but
wrong enough to cause like the wrong
texture to be associated with you know
the wrong weight or something right so
don't know how that's happening but we
should be able to figure that out right
and so let's start by trying to solve
that and then when we get that right we
can move forward to try to for our alpha
blending is perplexingly not working
which must be something else because
we've looked at the Alpha voting and it
was on so it must be something that just
makes it look like the alpha blending is
not working but the Alpha actually is
working in something else is not working
which is the way it usually goes with
hard to rendering because you can't step
in there and see what the actual problem
is so if I look at push quad pure I know
all these are going through this special
texture path and so I know this is
fundamentally what's going on this quad
texture is quad texture campus with you
know texture that's actually where we're
setting that texture there and then it's
gonna output these vertices right the
verts and the indices and those are
gonna come from just whatever the
current index stuff is right now the
base index stuff here
I feel like that should always be off
the full amount so I feel like that is
getting set properly based on the vertex
array offset itself
and so really I don't see much of an
issue there so my question is is
everything okay here I'm wondering if
maybe this never gets used in fact that
sounds likely to me I think that could
be a problem so here we are in in
textured quads vertex array offset is
never getting used yeah so our draw
elements base vertex call uses that
properly our draw elements call does not
use that properly and that would do it
now draw elements
I feel like in this case we should just
be able to use the call directly
unsigned short you're the Jill right and
so we've got this guy here you know now
I'm wondering is that part of our
problem with the Alpha winning too
because it would mean potentially that
the depth was always wrong like it was
just Z fighting here and I'm saying
potentially okay so that looks a little
bit better let me go in and make sure
it's drawing in the right order now
because I changed that
all right so I do think we now at least
have the proper you know plates because
this looks like the cutscene again Alfa
Bunnings still totally wrong yeah I'm
saying so that didn't get fixed but the
pleats are now correct so that was
definitely a bug and that got fixed
which is good unfortunately doesn't
really change the fact that alpha
blending just looks straight up off to
me it looks like we're just getting the
alpha discard and it never a blend so
when it goes to try and blend its
blending with nothing or not blending
and just producing black instead of
actually producing the composite color
so we're still left with one GPU mystery
and we don't know what that is let's go
ahead and take a capture but I'm
assuming it won't really tell us
anything that we don't already know but
now that we fixed that problem I'd at
least like to look at analysis from the
properly submitted set so here is step
one here's step two what I will say is I
don't know why depth test is on
but unless I'm really misunderstanding
things which let's be honest could
easily be the case we were just looking
at the result like this is the result of
just building up the back buffer we like
this is the depth feel composite here
going on and so I don't understand why
we would get an alpha blending fail in
just building up a single depth feel
like if alpha blending was off right
here it would make more sense is there
some way that I'm just reading this
wrong and alpha Bunning is just off
right like that
that would be what I would expect but it
seems like blending was on and maybe it
wasn't really on maybe the blend was off
entirely and it just said this is maybe
what I was trying to say is this is the
blend mode that would have been on if
you had blending on I don't actually
even know where they list that hold on a
second
just trying to find if there's something
that says whether blendings on
[Music]
there it is alright so never mind
I take it all back that was a slight
that was a sake
I admit that okay I admit that was a
mistake
so I think I literally just wasted like
30 minutes because I didn't look at the
false that was in that category because
that's the entirety of the problem right
all of the blend function may be set
correctly but if it's not turned on then
it doesn't work now what I don't know is
why it's off let's take a look so we
disable blending when we're writing into
the frame buffer for the DEP Beals
however when we stopped appealing I
would like to then turn blending on I
believe so I feel like when we're in and
depth peels I kind of feel like I want
to do that right
I so hey good news is we were right
about the blending being not on turns
out the reason that the blending was not
on is because blending was literally not
on which eliminates a certain amount of
the mystery to be sure I guess we're
done that that was it
there wasn't any mystery to it the
reason blending wasn't on was cuz
blending wasn't on that was a colossal
waste of everyone's time well at least
we did find out why blending wasn't on
and the reason is cuz blending wasn't on
which is probably a good thing to check
more carefully that's probably just
chalk it up to me not knowing how to use
insight since I've only used it like the
times on stream that you've seen me use
it so far and I clearly was not used to
looking in the right place to find the
information we were needing to know
there the cutscenes look good now they
look they look right to me let's watch
them all the way through once I do wish
we had these guys snapping to the screen
I don't know when that stopped happening
probably they're like done in pixel
coordinates now or something but let's
just take a look to make sure there's no
obvious like weirdness going on there
Misty's supposed to put the hell out
there we go that's like where does he
put the hat on
it's always good when Krampus comes in
you notice that's gonna get good when
Krampus comes in
it's all looking good
great a salmon here I've said a real
hand-signs outfit already aggressive yes
absolutely like graphics programming is
always like which of these 100 million
settings that occur throughout the
course of this frame got set wrong and I
can't step into anything and see right
sometimes you get it gets better like
sometimes like they have things we can
just drill down to a particular pixel
and actually step through it on so like
you know if you're on like a console or
something and that's a lot easier but
like when you can't step through a
shader you're like well let me just
guess alright alright QA that was
annoying but on this on the scale of 1
to 10 of graphics bugs like something
that you can find in 30 minutes it's
even if it's stupid it's still great
right you're still really happy with
that because at least it didn't take you
like days and then you go like oh crap
it's this thing
I missed what was preventing the
parallax movement because you point out
that again real quick also is it just me
or is the gamma off a little on the
cutscenes it looks a bit washed out so
two things one the parallax movement
prevention was that we weren't properly
offsetting the base vertex when we
submitted the draw buffers so if you
went down the the per Tex texture per
quod path we never set the base vertex
so it was always using the first quad
which of course is the one that's in the
back and just standing still right so
yeah as far as the gammas a little off
it is because remember we have not
packed these textures as srgb so in the
future we probably should pack them as
actual srgb we packed them right now
squared so if you want to be a little
more accurate that was the thing that I
was playing with before I just wanted to
make sure it worked we can turn it back
off now if you want if if it's makes
feel better but this right here was
whether or not we were going to use the
cards version and you know we could
leave that off and just always use our
own squared square rooting this is what
the actual things were packed ass and so
I dunno if that might be what you were
sensitive to or it may just be that that
that you just would prefer more
saturated whether you just prefer it
more saturated to begin with
in OpenGL gate texture in the non
special education you're calling the get
texture index form to mass class when
the texture bit but at this point you
know that this bit isn't set or am I
reading this incorrectly no you're
correct I just want to make sure we go
through that in case we change it later
I want to make sure everyone always does
that do you have the story for the game
all written and thought out or you're
still working on it yeah no it's I mean
it's that's what the cutscenes are made
from
alright let's wrap it up shall we
all right thank you very for an episode
a handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you want to
following series at home you can always
peer to the game on handmade hero org
and it comes to the source code so you
can compile it and play around with it
yourself we will be back here next week
I believe yeah I think next week for I
suspect at this point maybe just a
little render or cleanup now that we've
done everything I think we have all the
features in there we may want to add a
little bit of a particle system fast
path which may be sex sets like a
texture once and does some fancier
things so we may want to do a little bit
of extra additions now that everything
seems to be working and we're in the
fast path now but I think we're back to
basically just why do tags so we can
decorate the world so probably the next
steps are if we want to do fast paths
with particles we could leave that to
later though when we actually have more
particle effects to think about but it's
really that and then I think the tags is
the is a really big thing so we got it
we got to come up with a good way of
actually being able to sort of more
closely tie the world gent to the art
assets so that we can decorate the world
put textures on cubes that you want and
you know put sprites in the world that
corresponds with specific stuff from the
imported art assets so that's really
what we got to do next decorate the
world basically put textures on
everything and we got some open issues
there to think about so we'll be
starting on that next weekend probably
this my guess hopefully see you back
here for that until then have fun
programming I'll see you around the
internet take it easy everybody