hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show we code a complete game
live on stream it is well it's time for
us to do probably a little work with our
with the way we're working on entities
right now we sort of got movement into a
place where it was kind of getting
pretty interesting and we want to kind
of continue down that road but in more
of the entity system side of it so today
I think we're gonna probably look a
little more closely at how we're doing
our entity type systems and start to
think a little bit more about what
that's gonna mean as we go forward so
today is day 286 if you would like to
follow along at home you want to do two
day 285s
source code that's what I'm starting
with today so let's go ahead and boot up
for coder here and and let's open our
project alright so so here we go
so essentially what we've got now right
and we and I kind of played around with
this in the Q&amp;A because someone asked
about it we have the ability to sort of
generate arbitrary additional little
dudes here right and those are all full
entities with the same motion controller
and everything else is the hero and all
that sort of stuff and you can start to
see like one of the things that I guess
I should emphasize here is the way that
engine development and game development
does tend to work is it's it's very
nonlinear in that way like you saw us
spend a lot of time on like little
detail things you know several days and
you know it's ours really so you know I
don't know think to three days of coding
of full time coding let's say we may
have spent on just figuring out like how
you know we were gonna place points in
the world and occupy them you know we
probably spent five six full days of
coding you know if you took all those
hours and put them in there thinking
about how we were going to do like
entity storage and world
storage right and in this course of
handmade euro which so far is only
probably up to six seven weeks of total
coding if you pack the hours into
regular work weeks that's a huge amount
of the project being spent on those
things right and so but when you start
to look at those at some point they
start to come together and you can just
do stuff like this where now you've just
got you know stuff that sort of becomes
an autonomous system where it's like oh
I just want more of these and I threw
them in there and and that sort of stuff
and that's sort of the curve that we're
kind of going to see unfold probably
over the next you know a hundred coding
days of handmade heroes the next hundred
hours or whatever it's things will start
to ramp up quite a bit and so you'll
start to see things slowly get into that
because we're kind of like right at the
cusp of that curve where all of a sudden
it starts to shoot up and adding things
now no longer is just oh I did X amount
of work for X amount of pay back it's
like I did X amount of work for x
squared I'm going to pay back and it
starts to be kind of good right uh so
that's that's really where we're
starting to go and I and I feel like you
know being able to spawn people it's
kind of just a simple example of that
right but we've still got a bunch of
things like for example these guys are
caught inside each other right now
because we still have the old collision
stuff which doesn't really know what
it's doing and isn't particularly
logical for the stuff that we're working
on right now and we also have like a
bunch of other stuff like we need to
figure out our Z stuff correctly so it's
a few things that we really have to go
through before we're it free and clear
but we're definitely starting to get
there so one of the things that I want
to take a look at now is I want to start
to get a little bit more of a sense of
how the entity system comes together and
so what I'd like to do is if start to
try and break down some of these type
based operations that we're doing in the
entity system so in other words right
now what you see us doing in the NA
system is is we basically special-case
everything by the type of entity so even
for example the way that we know how to
draw the little hero dude here right is
because we created an entity that had a
type of hero head and an entity that had
a type of hero body and those two things
are used in multiple places to determine
how it's controlled and how it moves and
that's not a bad thing
there are plenty games whose energy
systems work exactly that way and that's
not a problem so you know if you're
doing it that way that's great and
certain games where the entities are
very specific and each entity is
supposed to be very unique and very
different from all the other entities
that's totally the you know the
reasonable solution is just to write the
code for each of the entities that you
want and off you go and you can still
share like through functional
decomposition you can still share the
things that they use but in this game we
want a more of a continuous feel meaning
yes we want lots of very different and
interesting entities in the game but we
don't want those to be isolated points
in space we rather want the full concept
of entities to encompass everything
between those so everything from you
know this hero through to a boss monster
rather than just having hero and boss
monster we want to be able to say like
what's the thing that's halfway between
the hero on the boss master or a quarter
of the way between here on the boss
monster and that's what right we want to
be able to sort of think about this sort
of very very varied space of like lots
of different permutations that are
scattered throughout the possibility
space so that the game has a lot of rich
sort of texture to it in that gameplay
sense and again this kind of comes more
from you know sort of the roguelike
tradition of games not the zelda side
because you know like I often say it
sort of we want to kind of combine those
sorts of things and that rogue alike
side is very much about not having all
these hard-coded specific entities but
rather having hard coded little chunks
that assemble to create entities so that
they could be assembled in a different
way to create a different entity or
remove from one entity to make it to
turn it in to another end of your added
to an ad to give it that ability right
and so that's what I wanted to start
looking at today just because I feel
like now might be a good time to sort of
play with that a little bit I just get
that sense so what I want to do is take
a look at this entity type field and
start to think about if we want to start
to eliminate the actual use of this type
field what would we do right
so for example let's say we would now
like to have some other enemies in the
game which we we want to completely
reuse for all intents and purposes the
code for our hero and make them and
those two entities or couple and is
going to be an enemy whose movement
whose whose looks just like the hero
he's like the evil version of the hero
looks and moves just like the gyro but
he or she whatever it is the specter it
perhaps the evil whatever manifestation
of the hero but it has some kind of an
AI thing on it which causes it to jump
around attack the hero so instead of
using controller as an input it uses
some kind of artificial intelligence or
or it just walks around it doesn't even
matter something that is not what that
does not wait for keyboard input right
to move around another one would be a
floating head and it uses the exact same
code for the hero head only there's no
body another one would be just the body
right it hops around but doesn't need a
head to tell it where to do so right so
even just with a code we have for the
hero which is very little code right
it's like you know 50 lines of code we
wrote for that of something 100 lines of
code I don't know how many but very
little you can already see how in theory
we could have created a number of
entities right if you start to think
about different a ie controls of them
you could have dozens of entities like
different head monsters different
whatever that are all basically doing
you know that underlying code but right
now in our system that's would not be
obvious how we would do that right we'd
have to actually go in and change this
video what I want to look at in terms of
pushing the system towards that more
decoupled state where things are very
piece pieced together is what would I do
to start getting me to a place where
that would have just been trivial and
you can see that pay since entities
just have all this information in them
we've already done the thing where we're
just kind of doing the flat entity and
then we'll look at compressing it down
later we don't have a problem with the
data so creating the data for those
other entity types that we want would be
trivial right it just created entity and
it's already got we know it as the data
so we don't run until you the C++
nastiness of like having to like
decouple class hierarchies or
we did this wrong thing that's like
we're not gonna have any of that problem
because if the data is already flat and
so that'll just work no matter what
combination of things we want it to do
right but this type field is still
serving oh it's it's this type field is
still very much C++ object-oriented
nastiness in a lot of ways right
that type field is like saying this is a
particular instance of this particular
class of entity which really prevents us
from being able to do those mixing
things in exactly the same way that it
is difficult in C++ to do them right or
I shouldn't obviously reporting
receivable so I I guess I mean where the
C++ class interface inheritance model
which I already said I don't like so I
don't want that how do we get rid of
that well first things first
what I'd like to start by doing is
saying well we know that this movement
mode already exists in a sort of finite
state machine quote unquote kind of a
context where we have two types of
movement that an NV could be doing
planted we're standing one place or
hopping where it's going from one place
to another via a hop so the way in which
you might be moving is already has a
state variable so the fact that I have
coupled that ability to use that state
variable to the entity type is clearly a
mistake right I could just not do that
and then all entities could have had a
planted and hopping motion and any
entities that want more motions can go
in there right so that's the first way
we can start to attack that entity type
problem is by saying instead of having a
type that says what type is the entity
let's
focus on the parts we actually care
about and make those have identifier x'
right so saying what is the actual code
differences that I actually care about
at a lower level let's make those have
them and lo and behold we already did
that as part of the implementation so
really this first part is just going to
be an exercise in getting things off of
the type variable when they didn't need
to be there in the first place right so
let's start by trying that and we'll see
what unfolds so if I go into world mode
here and I take a look at the movement
mode and where that's being used and you
know what I'm gonna go over here I
always start for coder starts you in
this window or rather my for coder
config starts you in this window I
probably should make a start in the
other window for no reason other than
since this is a stream and the head my
head is down in the lower right hand
corner it probably would make more sense
to start so that I'm on the side that's
not obscured but anyway so looking at
the movement mode we can kind of see
here that there's a bunch of information
that's going on a bunch of things that
are happening but the movement mode what
if we were to just pull those out so
that they weren't actually in the inside
the switch statement right like doing
the very most simple possible thing
could I just move this out so that it
wasn't in the switch at all right could
I do that so let's start by trying that
and and let's see here
we've got what have we got here teeth
rest this whole thing so let's take a
look at this whole thing here the hero
body code right you can see here that if
the if the movement moves planted we pin
it to its occupying square right we we
take a look at this head Delta and that
head Delta thing that's obviously a
little bit specific two paired entities
right but the rest of this isn't so much
right like all of this it's really just
that Bob amount that has to do with the
head distance here it looks like the t
head distance it's really just that bob
amount that's happening inside planted
that's really it
and you can see that that hopping in
general doesn't really require the head
at all so I think what I'm going to
start by doing right is I'm gonna try to
take this out and see if I can make this
be its own sort of idea here and and if
you're thinking in the back of your head
well you know this does look like the
sort of thing Kaycee that you might want
to pull out to a separate function I
agree with you but not quite yet it's a
little bit premature to do so so we're
gonna leave it in line for now but you
can see that that is kind of a thing
that might be primed for pulling out
into something so it's easy to see what
it you know it doesn't have to it makes
make it easier to read so I'm just going
to make a note instead of making it a
function for now and I'm going to say
handle the end of these movement mode
and here we go with that and then we're
just going to go ahead and compile it
and see what our effectively our
problems are if you will so down here
you can see that we've kind of got this
computation for T Bob and B T Bob and
that sort of stuff and so what I kind of
want to do there is take that out and
and put it down in here right and what
you can see with these equations you're
like well you know everyone now is gonna
be using this DT Bob well maybe we're
gonna call that a slightly different
thing that has to only do with movement
but even so what we could do here is
notice that our we can have a DT Bob
which is like you know movement mode you
know inert or immobile or something like
this and that could just not set
anything right that could that could do
nothing at all if that makes sense and
so I could go into our entity structure
let's go here where we're sort of
defining these movement modes and I
could make the default movement mode
that you're just not doing anything at
all right you're not bobbing you're not
stretching you're not doing anything
you're just completely immobile and so
for something like a tree which which
never does any movement it doesn't even
think about movement you know it could
have something like that and and and
wouldn't ever set DDT Beauty Bob
although now that I think about it
you know maybe I'll just won't even do
that and just say that that's planted
for now because if you look at planted
it only only was doing something when
there was a head involved and a tree
would not have a corresponding entity
that's like a linked part to it in any
particular way so it seems to me like
that's probably okay right so let's just
leave that out of the out of the
situation for now so let's go ahead and
rebuild and you can see that our primary
problem here again is that this part
isn't really set up for working if
there's no heads so let's not try to
solve that just yet let's just go ahead
and comment it out and make sure that
we're okay
when we run okay so now you can see what
we've done essentially we have exactly
the same code running and we just don't
have the extra bobbing motion that was
happening before but we have most of it
right but when it's planted and you
stretch it doesn't go down I think was
the main thing based on it doesn't sort
of hunch down so really we have lost
nothing and one of the nice things about
this is it applies to you know all of
the entities in the system with no
deleterious effects except for one right
and of course you may have missed it but
I'll show you again well this guy right
here you notice goes off into the middle
of nowhere well why is that that's
because the DT Bob like this this whole
equation right is entirely predicated on
that DT Bob meaning sort of the
springiness of the characters motion and
we were using that bobbing motion to
actually control the floaty thing right
it's got this entity you know T Bob here
right so it's kind of getting added to
the position using that increasing
timing value and so those two things
kind of conflict right now I don't
really know exactly how we want to
proceed here and the main reason for
that is the floaty thing is kind of a
one-off and I don't really even know
what it means or should be so I don't
have much of an opinion about what that
really value like what I want to do here
right so you know
for now we could even just say let's not
bother supporting this guy at you know
at the moment and it's just another
point temporarily and we can sort of
look at that in a second when we think
about how we might want that to work in
reality right but either way you get the
point which is that we need to now make
solid definitions for things we don't
want something called t-bob because we
don't really know what that actually
ever means right we need to have solid
definitions of our variables so that
everyone can share them and again this
is not a deficiency of the system it's
actually a strength meaning the goal of
the system is to make single variable
points inside the entity for single
specific things of meaning so that
everyone can share them and build richer
interactions that build on top of them
right and the example here is like if we
have a value that's about how the bounce
is happening then other things can start
to tie in to that bounce value for other
reasons and that's what starts to make
the entity system rich and create a
variety of interactions that are
interesting which is what we want
okay so I'm gonna put it to do in here
because I do want to think about this
later I just don't know what it means
right now but platforms you know we'll
want to sort of support so think about
what this stuff actually should mean or
does mean or will mean right okay so now
let's take a look at the more pressing
problem which is that these entities are
paired and there's this concept of the
sort of you know related entity you know
like an entity to which you are attached
if that makes sense or that you're I
don't I don't want to I don't know what
we'll call that there's just this
concept that entity can be paired such
as the head in the body but you could
imagine other things being like that so
you know it's sort of a generic concept
of I have an entity to whom I am paired
and I have a certain behavior towards
that other entity to whom I impaired and
I want to you know make sure that I
support that right so what I think we
want to do there is I think we want to
sort of have a solid notion of what that
means so instead of calling this entity
reference head we'll call it something
else now what I want to do here before
we do anything else is sort of start to
create a section or rather a partition
between these two
a partition where we start to move
things up into the entity structure
proper by saying this is something we
actually thought about right versus this
is some stuff that we just did while we
were prototyping and getting things
ready right and so up to this point
right we've been basically trying things
out and it's you know being stored
getting the engine running you know
doing whatever software rendering all
these other things right well now we're
starting to think about this entity
system for real and so now it's time to
start saying when are we gonna actually
lock down variables and say this
variable means something and we thought
about it and it mean doesn't mean we
can't change it but it's there's a
difference right between one of these
and one of these other ones that we just
got through in there when you know we're
just like playing around so I'm gonna
start with by saying the first one that
we really mean perhaps is this one and
any reference and the way the way that I
think we might do this is to say let's
introduce a notion of like almost like a
geometry of of these creatures where you
can perhaps have some child creatures
and a parent creature maybe I mean they
don't know exactly how we want to do
this but let's just say that we're going
to have some notion of of this parent
right in any way pairing and I'm not
sure how far we want to take that but
I'm just thinking of things like you
know let's say I have some kind of boss
monster spider thing and each of its
legs is a separate piece that could
detach and sort of like move around or
whatever right it's it's there's sort of
this may be multiple entities kind of a
thing going on there so we're gonna want
something like that and the head body
case is a similar situation right the
head is probably the primary concept of
the entity meaning that if you still
have your head you are still technically
alive I don't know maybe that's not true
maybe either/or is alive you're still
technically alive I'm not sure the point
being you've got these these entities
and there's sort of this relationship
between them
and I think we're gonna see that a lot
and so we want some way of representing
that relatively generically right we
don't want to just say this is the head
of the creature this is the body we want
to say this is the parent entity and the
only question that I have right now is
do we want the notion of multiple parrot
in amis because it seems to me that
we're probably gonna want the notion
that I could be paired to multiple
entities not just a single entity if
that makes sense so I think we would
want to and I think what we would want
here is the concept that an entity can
have some number of paired entities so
we would want something like this right
where we sort of had the notion that
there was some set of parent entities we
know how many there are right and we can
sort of loop over them now the thing
that I'm not quite sure about obviously
is I don't really know whether these
paired entities have some kind of a
structural thing going on meaning you
know when I parent entity with another
entity is there some kind of a you know
does it is there a meaning to that
pairing
because you know maybe they're sort of
maybe and the more I'm saying it seems
like the answer is obviously yes right
and so when I attach them to another one
maybe I just have this notion that
they're paired they're linked would be
one way of just describing it and maybe
like a parent to child link versus a
child the parent link might be a thing
you know I don't know but it seems to me
like there's a little bit something
going on there and so you know the
notion of an entity reference could
easily be expanded to have some kind of
an enumerator with it that said what
kind of reference actually is this like
what are you trying to say my
relationship to this other object
actually is and I don't know like I said
this is a little bit premature
but that's essentially what we want here
and we're gonna want probably the
ability to make these be as varied as
possible meaning we'd like to know that
the the number of entities paired with
the particular entity could be whatever
it needs to be and I would suspect that
we probably want to have it so that it
could grow dynamically I'm guessing
that's my assumption so we would want
the ability for this entity reference
set here to be as large as we want it to
be right and if you want 12 paired in
bees or 23 paired entities or something
like that that's fine so I don't want to
implement anything with that yet because
like I said I haven't thought through it
enough but I want to sort of have I want
to take that and now look and see what
happens if I do you know again right the
usage code first kind of thing what
would happen if I was to say I can have
multiple paired entities so if I come
here to say movement planted and I know
that I've got two this was the code
effectively that I wanted to write how
would I deal with this fact here you
know what would I do
and you can see that this code is
essentially saying however far away the
head was from the body I want that to be
how far I crouch down because I'm about
to jump or something right and so if we
wanted to maintain that behavior let's
say that we had multiple heads or
something right what we would need to
know there is what's the behavior
supposed to be when we don't just have
one and there's a couple of different
ones we could do we could look at the
average distance away they are right we
could look at the maximum distance away
so whichever one's the farthest we could
look at the minimum distance that's ones
away right basically we could use the
set of norms norms are I don't even know
why I'm bringing this up
you know handmade here it's educational
supposed to be education so a norm is
essentially like a measure it's sort of
a way of taking something and asking for
a way of measuring it and they often
have names like the one norm 2 norm 3
norm infinity norm etc and you know
there's you know these are often the
Euclidean ones we're talking about right
so it's a bunch of terminologies here
like you could someone says the you
clinically an infinity norm or something
like this right well if we take a look
at what these things are you'll see
these in the literature they're really
very simple to understand actually and
what they are is they're ways of looking
at values that are when you have more
than one value and you want to take the
measure of them you get into like this
situation for example with vectors so
you know how we typically have vectors
for example in 3d we have an X Y Z
vector and oftentimes we've said well
let's take the length of the vector and
what did we do when we took the length
of the vector right what did we actually
compute well if you remember correctly
we essentially use the Pythagorean
theorem to compute the length right if
you imagine the triangle where we have
you know sort of the X and the y here
and we want this right this is our
length we said well the length squared
equals x squared plus y squared right so
when we said we wanted to figure out the
length was we said well let's just
square root both sides and we have x
squared plus y squared Square rooted
right and that's how we were computing
the length of say our two-dimensional
vectors and three dimension vectors are
the same it was just plus a Z squared
over here or whatever right so right you
can trivially keep extending this
outwards no matter what your dimensions
are it just gets longer
so that is actually the two norm right
that's actually what that is the length
what we were taking here when we say
length is actually the two norm what do
we mean by two norm well the two
actually refers to the power because the
definition for a norm generally speaking
is that the norm whatever it is when we
say say the N norm what we mean is that
it equals the enth root whatever that is
of the components raised to that power
right so the two norm is the square root
of x squared plus y squared the one norm
would just be the values added together
right because it would be the first you
know it would be a non square root
basically it'd just be nothing there X
to the first plus y to the first would
just be X plus y that'd be the one norm
right the three norm would be the cube
root of x cubed plus y cubed and then
the most mysterious one of them all this
one right here which is the infinity
norm is the infinite infinitive whatever
you want to call that the infinite root
of x to the infinity plus y to the
infinity got that done and so let's talk
about these real quick so you're very
familiar with the two norm already
that's just what we think of as
Euclidean distance that's the typical
notion of distance in Euclidean space
that we're all familiar with that's the
two norm the one norm is just the sum
that's the sum total of all of the
values right and you use the one norm
often in computer graphics as well
because for example when you want to
renormalize things like blend weights
right you want to normalize the blending
equation well you need all the weights
to sum to one so what do you do you
divide by the one norm add all the
values divide by that now you know that
everything sums to 1 right so one norm
two norms very common three norm not so
much infinity norm more common than you
might think
because
what happens when you take the infinite
route of a sum of infinite powers well
the answer is that actually everything
but the largest power draw I'm sorry the
largest variable drops out so what this
actually becomes is max X Y Z so the
maximum component of all of your
components is the infinity norm so if I
had a vector and it was 9 10 3 and I
said what's the infinity norm will be
infinity norm is 10 because it's 9 to
the infinite power plus 10 to the
infinite power plus 3 to the infinite
power to the infinite root now you would
need somebody such as perhaps pseudonym
73 to explain to you the number
theoretic basis by which that actually
comes out to be the case I don't pretend
to be a math proofs kind of a fellow so
I am NOT even going to attempt to tell
you about that it is way out of my area
of expertise I can simply tell you that
that is the definition of the infinity
norm and leave it at that ok so point
being what I was sort of speaking of
when I sort of threw that as a side and
I thought it might be good in chance to
sort of slip that in as a minor
educational topic so now that you know
what people are talking about when they
talk about norms in here when we're
talking about taking something that
expects to operate on one thing and then
we want it to operate on a number of
things at the same time but still only
produce one outfit output right if we
wanted to have n copies of this
operation well then we just have a for I
loop right but in this case we still
only want we we only have one value that
we're outputting we're still just
outputting one value for D DT Bob so we
need some way of actually rephrasing the
equation in terms of multiple inputs but
only still produce one output and one
way of doing that again is using a norm
on the input so that we're actually just
pre sum you know summarizing the input
down into something that's what we were
originally working with such as length
instead of taking just the length of one
thing can we now say what is some other
measure that would sort of make that
work right and so in this case I'm not
sure but let's say that that's what we
were going to do so imagine here we're
going to say paired you know entity
index or something like this and we
would say paired entity index is less
than paired and the count for the entity
that were on and then we would increment
that then we would look at which entity
that was in the pair identities and we
would grab out our pair from that as a
pointer if there is something in that
slot this you know meaning the slot is
valid then we could sort of do the same
equations that we were doing here right
like so and really the T had distance I
suppose could be clamped at the end so
it's only really the head distance part
that we're doing here and so we could
make this head distance initialize to
something go through here and sort of
take the that that length notion and
then at the end produce some final value
I'm gonna go ahead and maybe just say
let's take the two norm let's take that
that average we already know that we're
doing a length operation so instead of
square routing I'll just leave it
squared and then at the very end I will
square root it
so you can see what I'm doing there I'm
just some you know I'm just summing all
of those up so that as we get them I'm
summing the squares you know just like
the x squared y squared Z squared I'm
doing basically the sum of the squares
of the lengths and then I square root
those to get a final head distance then
we go ahead and operate on it like so
and in this case our head distance will
be 0 if there were none so we no longer
really have to check separately to see
if we had a head because where this loop
is effectively that check right so
here's the movement planted code now if
we did not know anything about what we
might be paired with and our rule for
how we wanted our bounciness to to work
would would have you know would go with
that essentially so there you go so
that's the kind of thing that seems
relatively reasonable I don't know again
like I think it's maybe a little too
soon to say for sure whether we need
additional things there but you can see
that it would be relatively easy to
write things in this fashion because you
know we we can respond to an arbitrary
number of attach entities at this point
and that's the kind of thing that we're
going to be looking to do as much as
possible meaning can we generalize these
things up into things that don't require
specifics that can work some sort of
more in generalities so that as we get
more permutations of stuff they can
interact with each other in a richer
fashion so if I go ahead and compile
that you'll notice that most of my
troubles here now come for the fact that
we no longer have that head entity to
pack and what you'll notice is when
we're doing this packing we don't really
have that packing operation doesn't
really do anything it just does a block
copy of the entity over into the sort of
the raw space and so one question that
we obviously have now is well what do we
want to do here during this packing in
terms of packing down things like this
array right
we the pair identity count part would
still pass through just fine but the
this part right here with the pair
didn't be pointer that
what we actually want to do is pack that
array however many entries there are
into the the chunk right and so now
might be a good time to start to think
about that part of the process there are
two things that we care about here one
is that we pack and unpack this array
properly using only the amount of space
that's necessary to hold the array right
because remember we could get around
this by just going like that but the
idea is that we'll eventually get too
unwieldy it's probably not on - and
really right now but as we up the number
of entities and up the number of things
in the entities that amount of data
throughput just gets more and more and
more and eventually might lead to
constraints on what kind of gameplay we
can have if we're not more judicious so
we want to do is say let's only pay for
the entities that were - with which we
are actually paired and so what we want
to do here is say you know just pack the
number that's actually there and that's
a pretty easy thing to implement with
what we've got right now that wouldn't
take much time - right now what's a
little bit trickier and something that
we haven't really seen yet is what we
want to do for essentially growing these
arrays over time right because what's
gonna happen is when you first create an
enemy there might be no pair identities
with it and so this pointer could just
be 0 later on you're gonna add a pair 10
B and maybe that's a time when you
allocate a little thing temporarily in
this image of store it or whatever but
what's our policy there how do we do
with that we essentially now have this
notion of a dynamically growing array
and we don't really have any way of
dealing with that yet in the system so
how do we how do we want to deal with
that right what do we want to do and
what's our policy there there's some I
you know people do like you grow by 2x
every time or other things like this for
something like the paired MD list I
think it's unlikely that you're gonna
have a ton of pair identities all that
often so I feel like probably what we
want to do is just allocate in like
blocks of four or something right
because the chances of somebody having
you know a hundred pair identities is
fairly low the chances of them having
zero one or two pair identities is
pretty high so we probably want to
optimize for the more simple case
they're right all right so let's write
this code because like I said I think
it's a good place to do that so the
first thing I want to do is I want to
take PAC entity into chunk oh and by the
way this might be a good time as well I
think we've got about 20 minutes left on
the stream here this might be a good
time as well to take a look and see if
it's now a good time to move the unpack
code over here into handmade world
because my goal is to have all of the
packet unpacked stuff happening in
handmade world and then all the sim
stuff can happen over in sim region and
entity but I'd like the packing to kind
of live in a place where we can see it
very clearly what's involved in the
packing and what's not because that's
the process we want to sort of
systematize and not screw up choosing
alright so here's our problem child pack
entity reference head is now an
arbitrary number of things that we need
to pack again not particularly difficult
we know we have to pack some number of
entity references now what's an entity
reference well an entity reference is
actually a pointer in an index but guess
what if we're gonna start packing these
things we actually don't need to pack
the index anymore right
and so what we can start doing here is
saying well we really don't need entity
reference anymore right that's not
really a thing we can just store entity
IDs by themselves and so you know we
when we pack we could leave the IDS in
here if we want to carry the IDS through
and there might be some valid reasons
why we might want to do that I'm not
100% sure that we will ever need to do
that but basically the the reason that
we would that we might need to have that
notion is we might need to have entity
IDs be things that you can look up and
keep even if you're no longer if they're
not nearby right because remember the
only things that could translate into
pointers are entities that
actually nearby so we may want to start
to to sort of break that notion right
and so if you have entity reference you
know we may want to make it so that I'm
trying to think of how we want to do
this exactly I guess here's the here's
the general problem if people ever want
to keep track of an entity long term
meaning let's say you know this would
not be anything that's frame to frame
simulation but let's say we wanted
something to remember a thing like I am
looking for some special gemstone that's
created in the world and so my entity
has the entity ID of that that gemstone
in it right perfectly standard thing so
that I would know if the gemstone were
nearby to me or I saw it I go that's the
gemstone I'm looking for I could match
the IDS or something I don't know I'm
just making this up another one would be
like oh I have a familiar and if I'm on
the same screen as the familiar the
familiar comes over to me and hangs out
if I'm off if I'm off somewhere else
I don't want the familiar to forget that
they're my familiar I when I come back
on I want them to recognize me again and
come over right so that's really what
I'm talking about here so the way that
we had the system set up right now you
couldn't really do that
because as soon as the person goes out
of simulation range it would forget that
you were ever it that ID would go to
zero that's just the way that it works
right now and so I suspect that what we
would rather have is we'd rather have
the ability to store any ideas IDs
permanently over time
the problem with that is how do we make
it clear in the pair identities that
that's what's going on right and we have
a couple different options so one is we
always keep the entity reference around
where we have the entity pointer and the
entity ID that's the index right and
then whenever you set it if you set the
entity pointer you have to set the end
of the index as well right because if
you didn't do that then we would never
know when we go to packet what we would
see is the pointer was set to something
and the index was set to something else
right in the case where the pointer was
set to something valid we would know to
overwrite the index with that entity
that pointers and the ID no problem in
the case where the index wasn't I start
where the pointer wasn't valid right and
and just to be clear I'm saying let's
say we did this right in the case where
it wasn't we sew the pointer 0 we
wouldn't know what did that meant clear
out the index because this person's no
longer looking at something or if that
just meant oh when we loaded this guy in
the index the entity index that he was
looking for doesn't exist in this sim
region so we couldn't find it right and
I don't know right because I could see
it doing either way but you know I mean
I guess what I'm saying is a bare
minimum we've got to do at least this or
that right where we only just can't ever
keep track of the index but if we kept
track of both of them so you can quickly
use the pointer and you don't have to go
through any kind of a hash table to use
the index so if you went this this route
with it
then I guess what we could do is at pack
time we could say oh is the index sum is
the is the this entity's index that we
have here is that in the hash table and
if it is
in the hash table then it's okay right
if it's not in the hash table then it's
not and I don't know there's a lot of
cons with that to the entity pointer
will appear to be zero so everyone who's
using an entity pointer will not get one
right but the ID will still still
secretly be valid so if someone wants to
say am i chasing anyone the thing where
you do like if edit ereference dot
pointer is not right because it's really
entity dot index that tells you that
because the pointer might be 0 if the
person just doesn't happen to be in any
sort of simulation range that you can
see so you can see why this is
relatively complicated but I do think
there's at least some merit to
essentially saying something like this
let's say that we made this structure 16
bytes long so we essentially said we've
got a relationship we have an index we
have a pointer that's what an entity
reference is you always use the pointer
anytime you're trying to do something
but you always check the index if you're
trying to throw something is correct or
not and we could say well let's go ahead
and make these extra hard to access so
that people know that they really should
not be accessing them and then we can
make it so that you're supposed to go
through some helper functions that do
the right thing right
I don't know you can see why this is
complex right it's a tricky pit bit it's
easy to implement no matter what we pick
to do the problem is just I want to make
something that's not going to cause too
many problems for the usage code and I
think most of the time the porter stuff
would just work but I'm just worried
about that one case where the pointers
Nell but the index is still valid which
is the case for long distance references
essentially and I just don't know if
there's any way other way I can really
make that be any more good right so I'm
gonna start sure another option would be
to make the entity always point to some
kind of a special dummy entity and you
can test for that I don't really love
that either
in short I just don't think there's a
lot of good stuff to do here other than
maybe try to have some helper functions
that make it easy to do the right thing
but it's it's basically a tri-state
condition right you know it's something
that looks like this it's like zero no
reference one is you no reference to
something in Sim range and two is
reference something out of Sim range so
basically everyone in the game who is
using entity references for things is
going to have to know whenever they do
processing on that reference they need
to expect one of those three states not
just two states because normally it
would just be like that right that's
what we would have in the simple case
where we didn't support essentially out
of course sized worlds which is sort of
what we do support now
I don't know I just don't know I just
don't know don't know uh so yeah
I guess what I'll say about that is I
guess we'll sort of have to see what the
code breaks down to look like if I was
to look at the one piece of code that we
started with just now and say what does
that look like right then you can see
this code right here this code probably
just is fine meaning it's not making any
decisions about this it's just saying
hey any entities that actually are
available to me you know right now I
will go ahead and take their lengths and
that'll be that right and so it would
work fine and and I and I guess maybe
the answer is just you know maybe really
what we want is it's just you almost
always use the pointer and you only have
to worry about the index if you're
talking about something that's that
you're about to like take you're about
to make a decision about it based on
whether there is anything there and
maybe there's a thing that's like b32
you know
reference exists or something I don't
know or reference references valid
reference I don't know something like
that and it passes the entity reference
so that you can always ask you know hey
tell me is this thing valid and that'll
always look at just the index it's never
gonna look at the pointer because the
pointer is irrelevant if the pointer is
zero it still could mean that the index
was valid in which case this reference
is still valid
so something like that right so let's
say that that was the case I'm gonna go
ahead and compile this what did I do
wrong oh right it's index top value
there we go so let's get back to what I
was talking about before so when I want
to store these things and I may go ahead
and also do now that I think about it I
may do a slight switcheroo here as well
and say let's have like an entity stored
reference so you know this is like that
something like this and that way when we
say hey are two references equal we
could also have a thing that's like hey
inline be 32
something like references are equal and
we say any reference a any reference B
which is a little confusing because we
it's hard to say whether that should
include the relationship or not but that
I guess will be something we'll have to
think about a little bit more down the
line right but okay so in here we would
say if references are equal we'd say
yeah we just say entity stored index
equals be stored index so I I don't know
why that was a bracket so you know we've
got a check on that we could also demand
that a stored relationship was be stored
relationship and yeah then here we just
say references are equal
I guess you know I might keep the
pointer around in this case maybe even
in the other case because you know we
really don't know the person may have
set and not set the index yet so I'm
just trying to think of how I would like
that case to proceed let's say I set the
entity reference and didn't set the
index yet you know to set the pointer
yeah so I think that's actually what we
want I think we want to say references
are equal a Titan B speed identity
something more like that okay so now
when we do our packing we've got sort of
our pack entity into chunk what we're
gonna do here is we're gonna make sure
that our indices are packed properly and
I guess I'm kind of running out of time
unfortunately that's unfortunate so now
what I want to do is say okay let's do a
pack entity reference what I want to do
is say how much room am I going to need
for the array of this particular fellow
right of this particular entity and so
we know that we will need to store a
paired entity count of them right so our
pack size is the size of the source plus
some data right however many pair
entities there are times the size of the
stored entity reference right so that's
how we actually would compute how much
room we need now which is more than just
the room for the for the entity itself
so now when we get down here and we say
oh we've you know we've packed this the
source in here we now also have to pack
where we packed the two traversal
references isolate we now need to pack
this entity reference array right and so
what we want to do is we want to do pack
entity reference the the array of entity
references pack entity reference really
doesn't probably need to be a thing in
quite that way anymore we could probably
just bring it down here and say all
right let's pack all these things
together right
I'm a little nervous about not having
named slots for these you know maybe
it's dumb to have them in an array and
not to have them named but I just don't
know how else we would support things
that kind of have arbitrary numbers of
things that connect to them and we can
always have more than one array if we
want right in fact you know what I could
do here is I could actually call this I
could leave it outside and say packing
may be referenced array right and then
you know just say the reference count or
even just just count we know what it is
there's the source right and then stored
entity reference why is that gonna be
stored reference stored entity reference
and then we'd say stored entity
reference destination then after we loop
over these we'd say all right the desk
we're gonna do exactly the same thing we
were doing here right we'd say the
destination index is going to equal the
source this is pointers ID but only if
the sources pointers ID is not equal to
0 so only in the case where oh sorry
where the source pointer is entered so
only in case where we had a valid
pointer do we want it to be equal but
we're gonna expand this case a little
bit and say well if it was equal then
you know maybe we're gonna do this the
other way where we'd say like we'd still
preserve that ID maybe we do that and
we'll do that if it's in the hash table
right so this is going to have to take
this is essentially going to need to
know the sim region nutrition and this I
guess this sort of begs the question -
now of you know just the packing live in
the sim region actually instead of over
here in the world
maybe this world thing you know will
literally just be for you know will not
you you get the idea
you know what I'm saying because we we
need that hash table to know whether or
not we would repack this right and so
yeah I mean the other thing we can do is
do that at is is do that at the you know
at set when the sim end closes down but
I don't know to what extent we really
want that to happen it just seems like a
little bit of overlapping work there
so anyway point being we're gonna have
to do this case I'll leave it for now
but instead I guess well do or say ok
we'll clear it in that case in either
case we'll say that their relationship
well I guess that's fine not true we'll
say that the relationship equals the
source relationship in this case I guess
we'll say
none right and we'll increment the two
so we walked the array and we just
basically remap those source it's the
source over to the desk and then and
then we're done we could also do this so
at least we know it's always initialized
and then in here it's like we could just
look at see if the hash table if it's
found all right and so then what we
would need to do here is we wanted to
pack these entity references skin all we
have to do now is say well okay we know
how many there are right we do the death
entity sorry we know in the source
entity we know we've got that that
entity paired entity count right and
then we know that the sources paired
entities is the array that we're coming
from and then finally we know that the
dest is the amount that we added right
in our pack size that's after the source
we know where that is as well and we're
gonna want to make this a little more
systemic but we know exactly where the
the entity store references live as well
they live here so that's the packing
code and we're over time so I got a I
got to wind it down here but you see
where I'm going this is all pretty
straightforward right let's fix that the
dot value-packed reversible reference so
a traversal reference I guess is really
just this though right and this is
really something we want to do yeah I
don't really wanna I want to do this
fairly correctly so I really don't
actually want to to wind down right now
which is kind of annoying
hmm well I guess I'll do the minimum to
leave it in a compiling state and then
we'll move on let's just say that this
is actually stored entity reference and
paired entity count paired entities
identifier not found Peck in the
reference array we have our load entity
reference and then we have our head
happening here
when we add the player at this point
yeah we're gonna need to be able to make
that array do its thing which is
actually relatively simple in this case
right because since in both cases we
just have one of these we can do and end
the reference which is like body rs13
reference head riffs one right and then
in here we can just say like oh okay the
body parrot entity reference turn
entities equals body refs head their
identities equals head reps yeah so body
rests zero duck pointer equals head head
riffs 0 dot pointer equals body and off
you go and in both cases aired the
account closed one head or an entity
chemicals one right so there you go
and in this case we can just do to do
re-enable and we'll say that the body
just doesn't exist at the moment
same here okay and this code we actually
could have done before the head Delta
obviously it's just the distance between
whatever that pair identity is and so
that's fine so yeah I think at this
point we probably would have a bunch of
bugs that we're going to have to deal
with and we haven't implemented half of
the things but I'm gonna leave it there
so we go to QA let's go ahead and do
that now and I'm not sure yeah like I
said I'm not 100% sure whether I like
the flexible array thing or not but
we'll see
and a/c a fairly simple way to describe
or understand the Infinity norm is to
draw the unit hyper spheres for each of
those common norms the one norm would be
a diamond shape the two norm is the
regular circle hyper sphere the three
norm gets more squarish hyper cubish and
so on
you'd quickly see that this series
converges towards a square slash
hypercube uh I don't know that that's a
fairly simple way to describe her
understand understand the Infinity norm
because first people would have to
understand the mapping of it to the
sphere but yeah I mean I can see that
FLE dulski have you seen Scott Myers
talk on CPU caches lesson one of
programming is don't listen to uh Scott
Myers talk he talks about how it's
better to stored you to have the same
type together in memory because they end
up on the same cache line which is good
for performance is this something that
you think about or will cover in
hand-made hero so that's not true right
obviously that's not correct the true
statement is that it depends how you're
processing it you don't want to keep
data of the same type together in memory
you want to keep data that is accessed
together together in memory right so if
you're accessing a b and c always
together but they happen to be
completely different types those you
want to put close together you know if
just because i have say a thousand
x-coordinates but i never both process
my x-coordinates there's no point in
keeping them close together that's like
worse right spacial locality is just
about keeping data that is used together
close together and sometimes you have to
make concessions to Cindy where you're
forced to process data in a bulk fashion
because of the way the floating-point
unit works and that can be true but that
is an aspect of the fact that the
algorithm worked that way not that it is
better to keep things it's still because
you're accessing them together and Cindy
forces you to process things in same
size bulk like that because you don't
want to transform right so no like if
that's what he said that's just wrong
but he may have said the right thing and
maybe he just wasn't clear about it or
whatever but yes we've covered that in
handy here Oh many times it's not
something you typically think about
until later in your architecture because
it's not it's something that causes a
lot of cost if you're constantly trying
to do it and most of your code doesn't
need it so you have to be judicious in
knowing about when you care about that
part of that is C++ is Fault C++ is
awful at data organization it has almost
no utilities it has almost no features
that allow you to organize your data
well if you've ever watched John blows
stream on Jay you can see that he's
already got some nice features for that
where you can twist the way things are
stored without having to rewrite the
code so that you can pick better
orientations of them for things like
spatial locality could you use the enemy
parent concept for a vehicle occupant
relationship like an airship and its
passengers and if so how would movement
work on it in our system probably not at
the moment because we already have the
concept of standing on so you would
probably just put standing on you would
probably just have them standing on that
the traversable points that are on the
airship steveod 1990 I was just
wondering why you don't have a
subscriber button for those that enjoy
your frequent broadcasts for when I
gather you were offered partnership but
turned it down to do something in the
contract can you tell me a little why
you made that decision and what options
do you have to donate sure yes so first
of all if you if you do look down in the
below the video in the twitch
information there are a bunch of links
but if you just want to remember one
thing you go to hand-made here org and
we have both a patreon and a way to
preorder the game so if you're looking
for to support the series both of those
are much appreciated either one or both
or whichever one whatever you want to do
is is up there on handmade hero org
certainly so yeah that's that's what
we've got as far as the information you
were asking regarding twitch yes I they
their standard contract has some things
that we can't sign such as prohibition
on uploading the videos to YouTube until
a certain amount of time has passed and
various other things like this and since
people a lot of people watch the series
very regularly and watch it almost
immediately after its broadcast maybe
within an hour
on YouTube I did not want to
disadvantage those people who cannot
watch the stream live and make them wait
extra days to get it potentially due to
a contract with twitch I did try to go
back and forth on the conical of times
but you know we kind of got a few terms
ironed out and there was a couple of
things left and then they just stopped
ever writing me back so I guess they
didn't care so I've never heard for them
I emailed them like three times after
that so I tried to get it set up because
people wanted it I
I seriously sent them like three males
like a couple weeks apart just being
like what you know how can I've never
heard back about this like what's the
deal and they just never talk to me
again
so that's that's the last I ever heard
of them was a month than a half ago
right if they didn't ever actually come
say no they just stopped talking to me
which I don't know it was kind of rude
actually but I mean I don't really care
because it's not something we need for
the series in any particular way so yeah
that's that's the situation in general
like I said that's not really a problem
it's not something I really wanted I
don't mind that twitch didn't want to do
it and their contract is their business
I just people had been asking for a
subscribe button so I figured I might as
well spend the time it took to read
through their contracts and see if it
was something we could sign it for it's
not particularly good or even useful
deal for us supporting us via patreon or
supporting us with by pre-ordering the
game is way better for us and it's way
better for you because you get the
source code to the games to play around
with at home if you preorder the game so
you know I would say it really is no big
loss not having that subscriber button
and if you just want there to not be ads
on this video I don't play the ads I
never play any ads on handmade hero ever
but twitch and search them at the
beginning I think and if you don't want
that you can go to get twitch turbo or
whatever so you can subscribe to twitch
separately and then you won't see ads on
the channel more so you can you know
give them some money in exchange for
that so so that's the full that's as far
as I know it that's the full story
your term it is it not possible to
subscribe to forum posts anymore now
since the new stuff was made I don't get
any post to my mail I don't know I am
not really involved in the forum suffer
at all so you can ask them about it if
you like there's obviously if you go to
handmade network.com there's a forums
for handmade network where you can post
feature requests or ask why something's
not there I that's all I can tell you
and yeah Omni Technomancer saying
subscribe doesn't make it that free
anymore twitch turbo makes it bad free
at least it does for me and ad-free
might not be true it gets rid of like
the ads at the beginnings of any one
stream like I like i subscribe to
twitter turbo and I've never seen an
addon like shawn stream or john stream
or anything so it got rid of all the ads
that i ever saw
now whether if it's on some big you know
super important stream of like you know
dota special tournament something or
other
then i don't know if that it maybe they
still throw ads and that i don't know
but on on everything else it got rid of
it whether it's subscribing to a
particular channel gets rid of the ads
that i don't know if that might not so I
would say if you're looking at rid of
ads go twitch turbo I can pretty much
guarantee you that at least right now
you won't see any ads on handmade hero
because I don't run any now other
channels who try to make money off of
their stream they run ads specifically
on the stream and so maybe that you know
is a thing but but for watching handmade
here without ads I never run any ads on
it and I never put any ads in our
YouTube we are completely ad free and we
generate no revenue from the streams or
from the YouTube ever and so if you
unfortunately twitch doesn't allow me to
say don't ever run ads on my content
which honestly is one reason I'd
probably like to not be on twitch
anymore at some point I'd rather be on
an ad free service if there was one I
don't know if there is but since I don't
make any money from it I have no
incentive to run those ads and I don't
want you to have to see ads so you know
there's not much I can do about that
are we done with the Q's no no we're not
there's one up here
this entity reference that feels
premature to me since I don't think we
have a lot of examples of how it will be
used are you doing it now for a
particular reason
yes so I'm doing it now because well
obviously the entity reference stuff I
assume you mean the the enemy reference
array not the entity references because
we already did a bunch of entity
references so the reason I'm doing it
now is I need some system in there to
start playing with the concept that I
don't know exactly what input I have
because right now I've been leaning on
the fact that I have an entity type and
the entity type just knows oh I'm gonna
use like a head pointer or something
right but I want to start trying to
write some code that doesn't really know
so like you know the example would be I
don't know how many legs I have right
like maybe there's just legs sticking on
me and I know that I want them to kind
of like wobble when I walked I don't
know how many there are and so I want to
start having a way of like you know
being able to say like enemies
when we say that I have a reference to
the entity I actually gonna have a set
of references right and I suspect that
I'm gonna want to play with that a
little bit so I want try it here with
something that only ever really has one
just to see how it looks if I'm sort of
doing discovery and then I'm gonna add
more and see what happens
and I suspect them and I have to like
fuss with it a little till it feels
right my suspicion is what I'm probably
gonna have is more than one array so
like the relationship part where it's
what the relationship in the entity was
I think that might be a mistake so we'll
see but I got a try both I don't know
we'll see what happens when I actually
play with it but I'm suspecting that I
probably want to iterate over the like a
couple of different arrays like or
something but I don't know I really
don't I have no idea so I'm just gonna
play with it but I need at least one
array example first to try
that make sense
all right so it looks like we're good I
don't see any other questions that I
need to address so I'm gonna close down
all right thank you everyone fronting
for an episode of handmade hero it's
Anna pleasure Cody with us always if you
would like to play around the source
code at home you can always pro2 the
game on handmade hero org and it comes
with the source code so that you can
yeah play around with it there's also a
forum site if you want to ask questions
there's a patreon page if you want
support the video series there's a
schedule bot if you want to know when
the series is going to be live and
there's a episode guide if you want to
catch up with past episodes that's about
it for today we'll be back here not
tomorrow but Friday for the last dream
of the week at 5 p.m. Pacific Daylight
Time hope to see you there until then
have fun programming and I will see you
guys on the Internet