so anyway start recording hello everyone
and welcome to handmade here are the
show Rico to complete game live on
Twitch no engine new libraries
everything is custom built from scratch
so we can see exactly how every single
part of a game works from start to
finish no mysteries we don't leave
anything up to anyone else we we go in
there and we do every last little bit
ourselves we basically are at a point
today where we were just about to debug
some stuff from that we did yesterday
and it has to do with how we're keeping
track of where players are where enemies
are in the world height-wise again we
wanted to kind of flesh out how our
system was handling Heights because even
though we're a 2-d game we want to be
able to stuff like multi storey rooms
that you can walk up and down in and
other sorts of things that have to do
with three-dimensional positioning even
though we're in a 2-d game and so we
were just about to debug the code that
we wrote yesterday to sort of treat
things a little bit differently in terms
of their 3d Ness and so that's what
we're gonna go ahead and continue with
doing today but before we do that I just
want to remind everyone that if you have
pre-ordered the game on handmade hero
org you should have gotten a link in
your email which allows you to download
the source code and if you want to
follow along with today's video what you
want to do is unzip day 76 is source
code out of the source code zip we're on
day 77 so we're using what was done on
day 76 as the starting point so if you
go ahead and unzip that into directory
you will be exactly where I am right now
and let's go see where I am right now no
during the pre stream somebody guessed
what they think probably the bug was
from yesterday and it did sound like a
pretty good guess so they could go ahead
and look there first but let's before we
go do that let's quickly just recap
we're you know what sort of the bug even
was like what was the actual problem
that we were seeing and what do we need
to fix and anyway what I started to do
yesterday was I started to make it so
that the entities would be tracked in
their Z so that they were essentially
they essentially had full-height
information in them and they were
supposed to be starting on the ground at
at the ground was supposed to be where
their position was and their height
extends up above the position now what
we would have expected to have happen if
we did that was first of all we're
seeing like the it does appear that the
guy is lower than he should be right he
should be stopping like he's kind of
sunken down you can see he's supposed to
hit this tree we're on the bottom level
here he shouldn't be able to go that far
into the tree so it looks like he's a
little bit lower down there same thing
was stopping here it looks like he's
stopping too early which means again
he's probably sunk down to the ground
since we don't have really a lot of 3d
rotation or anything that we can do here
it's hard to see that that's one of
things that we put on our to-do list
with to add some debugging visualization
stuff so we can debug this more easily
when we're actually developing the full
game so there's that and the other thing
is we're still colliding with the
stairwell properly in in all ways which
means that you know the guy is not
really where we think he is probably so
what I want to do is go ahead and look
for that bug and what the person
suggests on the pre stream and I think
is a very good suggestion was that the
problem is we haven't actually gone and
fixed are standing on the ground code to
take into account the fact that entities
have a height and so we are actually
putting their position down on the
ground but their position has to float
above the ground because their height is
sort of determined as a rectangle
centered about their position and so to
draw this out for you just to give you a
little bit of an idea what's going on
here let me go ahead and and move down
here to day 77 well the pressure is just
on the pre stream and what I think again
is a pretty good guess is that if our
entities look like this this is a side
view here right if our entities look
like this and they've got you know a
dimension the that's that's their height
here right this is their Z dimension in
fact I'll to stop saying width and
height because it's kind of confusing
what if I just said this is their their
Z dimension right that's how high they
are in Z
this distance here is going to be 1/2 of
that Z dimension right it's gonna be 1/2
of this and if that's the case then when
we say we want pretty people to rest on
the ground we really want their position
right minus 1/2 their Z dimension to be
resting on the ground so the effective
ground type for anyone is actually you
know the ground plus one half of their Z
you know what I'm saying that's where
the ground actually is the ground you
know is is down here but if we were
talking about what the ground was for
the center position it actually you know
if the the center would actually up to
be up here in the ground would be here
right you'd have to add that in so
anyway mm-hmm another way of looking at
that I guess would be effectively you
know we want to think of the ground as
being effectively up here right so
anyway that's a good suggestion for the
bug I think that's probably if not the
bug it is at least a bug and we can sort
of take a look and see we can fix that
probably pretty pretty easily if we go
down to where we're doing our ground
code here you can see that we've kind of
got the ground being specified as not
having taking into account and that we
have to do here for ground handling but
that was for other stuff or to do was
basically well it doesn't even look like
we did have it to do here this is just
something that was on our our our main
to-do list right which is which is how
do we do ground levels right so this to
do right here so ignoring even that part
even if this was the real ground level
you can see that we don't take into
account this entity rect at all when
we're actually dealing with the ground
level and so when we do our handle
overlap right that's not taking that
into account and when we do our our
stuff here where we actually do our Z
supported that stuff that's not taking
into account it either so basically
nothing is taking that into account and
so what I think we want to do is we want
to change this ground level into sort of
a synthetic ground
I just want to take a look at what the
handle overlap code actually does what
it does to the ground level yeah it
looks like what it does to the ground
level is it does this lerp here and so
what I'm gonna have to do is basically
adjust the ground level after we do our
overlap testing because the overlap
testing produces what the actual ground
level is and then we want to adjust it
based on the entities dimensions after
that fact right so what we want to do
here is basically say the ground level
equals wherever the ground level would
normally be plus we want to move it up
now right we want to move it up by
however big the entity is kinsey half
that distance right something like this
that's what we would want to do and
again that's just doing exactly what I
said in the diagram there nothing
particularly odd and so that yeah that
looks like that actually did put our put
our stuff back to back to reasonable
potentially although it does look like
now well that's still not quite right it
looks like now we're actually colliding
with the higher up entities so it's like
we have lifted off the ground oh well
you know what I wonder if we're actually
on the top floor that could actually be
yeah I think we are on the top floor so
it's hard to say I don't know that's
still not quite right I don't think I'm
gonna go ahead and step into that code
it's a little weird how we're colliding
here it's it's kind of a little
nonsensical I wonder if we will have to
add some debug code just to see this
because I'd like to see it a little bit
better than we're seeing it now let me
see if we're on the top level or not
yeah so we are actually on the top level
at this point and our colliding an up
and down is a little bit it's a little
bit odd you know I'm saying definitely
little bit odd but again we have one
other thing we need to debug which is
how we're drawing stuff so maybe I'll go
and debug the drawing stuff first too
and then we'll come back here and and
we'll make sure that things are kosher
but first before I do anything else I'm
gonna step into that code and see what
the ground computation is actually doing
just to make sure that it's somewhat
reasonable so let's go ahead and
and take a look at that so if we come in
here let me see what empty we're
actually moving I don't want to look at
the Monstar I want look at the hero so
when we come in here we've got the
ground level specified at zero which is
what we expect we have the entity's size
and that entity size is 0.62 so what we
want what we want to see basically is we
expect the guy if you know if if point
six 3/2 if that is sort of the height
off the ground that we expect the
position to be hovering what we want to
see is that ground level come up to that
and that is exactly what it does so
we're gonna go ahead and see that get
set properly so it looks like he is in
fact resting on the ground as we would
have expected so we at least fixed the
bug that the person the pre stream
suggested so let's go ahead and keep
going with that that may have been the
only bug and in that in the actual
collision side of stuff and it may just
be the fact that we haven't really done
due diligence with the drawing side of
things and if I go fix the drawing code
that will fix things but it's hard to
say so let's go fix the drawing code
since we know that needs to get fixed as
well now the drawing code is totally
placeholder at this point which
unfortunately does make it a little bit
harder to debug because it's kind of
helter skelter but you know again you
can't you got to sort of take some of
the good with the bad when you're just
kind of working out how things are
supposed to go you don't want to spend a
lot of time cleaning them up all the
time so you kind of have to deal with
the fact that it's a little bit grumpier
to go in and debug it but hopefully it
won't take us too much time so the way
that we're doing things currently when
we do our drawing we do push bitmap
calls in the push bitmap calls basically
say we want to draw a certain bitmap and
we want to draw it at a particular
offset from wherever the entities
position is so what we actually do when
we go to draw the bitmap let me go ahead
and load that up here
there we go when we actually draw the
bitmap what we actually do it looks like
is we use sort of the upper left corner
to draw to draw the bitmap right so if
you take a look at what's going on here
we pass in an X and a Y and we go ahead
and we take that X&amp;Y and we expand it
out by the bitmaps width and height and
that is how we determine the bounds for
drawing so that what we're passing in is
the min the minimum corner right so when
we're doing this here when we say draw
bitmap and we say Center X center Y it's
kind of a little bit I wonder if that's
just a straight up bug that we never
noticed just in general if you look at
how this is drawing it's not it's not
the center that draw a bitmap that the
drub bitmap code takes because this is
the call that we're calling here and
it's taking the minimum corner so really
what we would want to do here is we
would want to offset that now maybe yeah
because if you look here what we're
doing is we're offsetting by our our
center point like the thing that we
picked as the bitmap centering point for
whatever this for this piece was but we
really just we never account for how big
the bitmap actually was so yet this is
in no way the center point so I think
that's that's wrong just to start with
even just our basic stuff that we were
doing here for drawing was not entirely
correct so let's go ahead and think this
through a little bit more this code the
draw rectangle code looks like it's
actually working correctly so I'm
wondering now why did these things ever
line up at all did we bake in maybe we
baked in the offset for the bitmap to
get to the minimum corner into here
which doesn't seem maybe that's what we
did let's assume that's what we did
because otherwise we've got a bug there
so let's just take a look at what
happens when we do a push piece call so
when we push when we do a push piece
call it looks like we Tay
let's see your fix a little offset X
offset Y minus a line so yeah it it I
guess I guess this is our saving grace
here we're actually baking in that
alignment offset right in here so really
this is not the center X Center why this
thing this part of it right here
basically baked in that offset that we
needed to do yeah for for the bitmap so
that's that's pretty janky look I don't
like that at all
because that means that the rectangle is
drawing things from the center and the
bitmap code is drawing things from the
minimum corner even though they're both
called center and computed in the same
place that's pretty suspicious oh I'm
torn as to what to do here do I just fix
the bug do I just go find and fix just
the Z positioning bug or do I actually
pull this code out and start to make a
little bit of render stuff you know to
kind of clean this up a little bit it's
a tough decision it's a tough decision
I'm not sure what which one I should do
which means I probably shouldn't do that
good if it's a tough decision err on the
side of not changing things alright so
if that's the case then basically we're
baking into the piece offset there what
the actual offset is and so I guess that
should in theory mean that
yeah the entity's position since we're
treating the entity's vision as the base
point where the guy was standing because
that's what we set the alignment to
since we're treating the enemy's
position as the base point it does mean
that we would need to displace that
position downward by his height in order
to get the actual ground point right so
what I think we want to do here is our
entity P we really want that to just be
a different point altogether than the
point that it is we
want to do are like like entity base P
or something and we want that again to
be whatever that entity position was
plus half of the entities dimension in Z
that same thing that we were aligning
I'm sorry - that we were aligning the
ground with we want to align the drawing
with as well because that's what we had
treated all of the rest of the of the
drawing as being based around right now
it's unclear that everyone would want to
do that but I think pretty much everyone
would want to basically hit be about
ground points except for maybe flying
things so I don't know we could
introduce something later on which
actually does I don't know some kind of
does some kind of mumbo-jumbo that
allows you to specify where you want the
the drawing point to be based around or
something like this but it seems like
that's a probably a reasonable thing to
do at the start so let's go ahead and do
that for now let's take a look at the
empty key oops entity P and make sure
that's not actually being used anywhere
else it's not so let's take a look we
should maybe this guy should probably
use it as well for the shadow alpha even
though the shadow alpha is not
particularly interesting it's just kind
of a placeholder thing but if we want to
get the shadow alpha right we also want
this to be done in the exact same manner
so that's n TP Dib dot Z right
initializing what is the problem
entity base P o because we actually want
that to be this we only want to subtract
out of the Z all right so let's see now
that we're drawing things properly well
that does appear to be have been the
problem now that we're drawing things
properly we do seem to be correctly
stopping at the location where we would
have expected to stop we do seem to be
able to walk through things the way that
we would expect to be able to walk
through them so that is looking pretty
good yeah that seems pretty good yeah
yeah and so I think the only thing on
that I would say is we are now back
assuming that that actually is the last
of the bugs that we had there we now
have to deal with our problem that I was
talking about before with the stairwell
where the stairwells will never actually
collide with because they only go up to
the exact height of the ground above
them so yeah let's yeah yeah let's go
ahead and do that so one thing that I
would like to do is take those
stairwells though and I'd like to add
two rectangles to them so that when I'm
drawing them I draw one rectangle at the
bottom and one rectangle at the top of
the stairwell in order to do that I will
need some way of offsetting these which
I think we already did so I believe that
what we did with our push rect is
usually that there's a offset here so ZC
I forget how this stuff works as I
remember it was all super hacky stuff
that we did entity offset Z miracles
time offices Z so basically what's
happening in the push rect is we don't
allow an offset see in the oh no we do
there it is it's right there we do allow
the offset see in the pushback so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to take the
entities dimension in Z and I'm going to
offset a second rectangle by whatever
that is
and I'm gonna go ahead and make the
bottom one be colored slightly
differently from the top one and that'll
just let me I don't actually know why I
stopped the game that'll let me figure
out those should be moving that's that's
a little busted that's that's not right
what's going on there why why has that
happened so we're drawing this one where
the Z offset for push rect but it
doesn't look like that's actually
getting used because we should have seen
those moving in differently basically
that is because so that is because we
don't actually mm-hm
yeah you'll notice our Z fudge here so
the Z fudge is only used to compute that
ground point but we don't actually use
that offset Z to actually yeah to
actually do anything with the X&amp;Y
otherwise right that strictly lifts
things up off the ground I say well I'm
not sure what we really want to do about
that then what I really want to do is
make two pieces basically push two
different pieces for the stairwell I'd
like to push a separate piece that's at
a separate location but unfortunately
that's not something that looks like is
really super possible for me to do again
because this code is pretty pretty darn
janky and I'd like to leave it janky but
I just wanted to be able to get a little
more mileage out of it because I don't
really want to go digging around in here
I don't think it's super productive for
us to do that so let's take a look and
see if there's any way that I could do
something simpler that would allow us to
you know you know set things up a little
bit differently so the way that this
actually works I guess is when it does
that the set of pieces when it unpacks
them
it looks like it's sort of always does
the ground at ndu it could if we wanted
to we actually could
roll this in here like we could actually
put this in here right and we could
actually optionally use the Z offset
directly above so maybe we'll go ahead
and do that for now let's just see what
would happen if we were to do that so
let's assume that I took this out of
here
right and when we actually do the entity
base PZ for that Z fudge right I'm
actually going to go ahead and I guess
would leave this in here when we do this
Z fudge I'm actually just going to go
ahead and add that in here so that's the
effect of Z of the thing whatever the
offset C is it'll actually it'll
actually get used now again this this
causes some problem so I'm not really
sure that I want to always have that
work that way yeah so that's that's one
problem right that's hilarious
that's pretty funny so I still don't see
where did that yellow guy went I don't
know that's that's pretty funny there I
don't think that was not that was not
what I had intended to have happen that
was pretty funny so I'm trying to figure
out exactly why that is okay
is that that's actually because that's
in meters to pixels right I think based
on what's happening right now just how
much cruft there isn't here I feel like
this is probably a good sign that I
really if I probably am going to have to
go ahead and pull this out and actually
do some real rendering code because this
is kind of just piling hacks on top of
hacks at this point and you know it's
going to create more problems I suspect
for us then then it saves Russ Tanaka
dive in there but I believe what's
happening there right is meters to
pixels gets pretty x offset Z and we
want it
to not be right we want offset Z to
actually get x meters to pixels later so
that we can do the that multiplication
separately right so we would want meters
to pixels to just happen here oops like
so because me it's already that would
cause it to be multiplied twice like the
offset Z was getting multiplied by
meters to pixels but then it's getting
multiplied by miracles again when we
multiply that Z fudge in here to to do
sort of that that pseudo parallaxing
effect that we're using to see where
stuff is so there we have what things
are you know looking like I guess not
super sure how accurate it is there I
have to think about this a little bit
more carefully but basically yeah you
can kind of see what's going on here and
and if I were to go up the stairwell
which I guess I can't do at the moment
for whatever reason I'll have to go in
to bug the stairwell code Oh of course
the stairwell code is also going to have
to use that ground point as well so yeah
basically we'll have to debug that but
I'm not sure it feels like I don't know
about you guys but it feels like this
guy is still in the wrong place right it
should be hovering above that guy when
it's roughly in the center of the screen
so I do wonder a little bit I wonder
about yeah I wonder about how we're
gonna do this sort of drawing long term
look what happens if I just kill this
right now right and so that it's always
just using that Z fudge it's a little
bit weird because in theory that makes
it a little bit harder to do some things
but if I look at it yeah you know what
that looks that looks much more correct
so basically if we don't have the offset
in there if we don't have the offset
offsetting the Y anymore and we just use
it as a straight Z offset then it seems
to work relatively well but I just don't
know if that's gonna hold up because
it's all the art is isometric I mean
basically what that Z fudge is doing
right if you think about what's going on
we've we've sort of got a little
coordinate system happening here where
we're saying you know we've got
something and it's position relative to
the to the camera center is in a certain
location and what the Z fudge is doing
is that saying well the higher up in Z
the thing is multiply that vector by
some coefficient of based on that Z
height so as things get higher they
exaggerate their distance from that
center point right which is essentially
just a scaling effect so it's just
scaling making things more distant but
it's scaling them up when they would be
closer to the camera right and because Z
comes at you but there's kind of two
competing things here one is that but
the other is when we've got you know a
dude or something he is drawn up right
in Y right he's not really drawn in Z
meaning if he was right if if this is
the screen and he's standing right in
the middle of the screen you don't see
his head and his body directly under it
like hotline Miami or something like
that our art style is is this way which
is like sort of isometric right it's
it's rotated in this sort of false
perspective way because it lets you get
a better look at the character and its
face and so on and that's why you know
you do that instead of drawing
everything top-down so we do have a kind
of fundamental mismatch there but that's
just as something that 2d games have
always had to fight there's really no
wrong or right solution to it it's just
a problem that you kind of have to deal
with if you want to do the art style
that way so yeah so I think now I guess
I mean I think that is roughly correct I
mean and I can I can still hop up to the
next Z level just like we used to be
able to do there's no ceiling you can
just hop hop hop up there so things do
seem to be working relatively well so
maybe what we should do is just go ahead
and and finish our stairwell there get
it collision protecting properly and
deal with the fact that it needs to kind
of extend up above the ceiling a little
bit so that we can walk back down it so
let's go ahead and do that
that seems like a pretty achievable
pretty simple thing so if I go ahead and
cure two handmade sim region again what
I think we have to do is when we're
doing our hour calls here for a candle
overlap and speculative collides and
stuff
speculative collide if you remember was
there to let us go onto the stairwell
only in circumstances where we would be
entering from the bottom or the top of
the stairwell and not so that we
couldn't just walk right onto the side
of a stairwell and pop up to wherever we
should be or down to wherever it was and
so if you take a look at what's
happening here that's basically using
that ground tight again versus the the
movers peasy so I think basically what
we want here again is probably to just
go ahead and introduce for our sim
region since we're using it everywhere I
think what we probably want to do is did
you just a call like get entity ground
point right because since everyone is
using this and I don't want to keep
computing it in everywhere because then
if I want to change it how its computed
it'll be hard for me to do that later
and to really it's not even so much
gonna be hard for me to change it in a
lot of places because that's not the
problem if to know where those places
are so what I'd like to do is I'd like
to go ahead and do a get MD ground point
call so that I have you know an entity
and that's just going to return for now
that thing that we were computing in
other places right so that's going to
return the entity's position and then
it's going to offset that position by a
vector that just moves it it it down by
whatever the entities dimension was in Z
again multiplied by that half to just go
half way the distance down and so that
way I'll just call that a call get enemy
ground point everywhere that we would
have been doing that so like any time
that we have that that dot Z in here
like here we'll just we'll go ahead and
say that that get entity ground point
call gets us gets us back the ground
point right and so let's take a look at
where we were doing that entity
z sorts of things so in here I guess
it's a little harder for us to use this
this is actually something that really
we can we can use primarily here get
entity round point so and that'll be our
entity that is the entity is it not yes
that entity there so really what we have
to do here if we wanted to compute the
offset using get entity ground point is
we'd have to say get entity ground point
for the entity and we'd have to use the
entities position and say alright we
want to move the ground to where the
entity is right so we want to basically
move to to that location so what we
would do is just take the two Z's and
subtract them there right and that would
let us oh well actually I guess it's the
other way around so let me draw that out
so I wanted to rewrite this expression
in terms of getting the grant to be
ground point the reason I want to do
that was so that I wouldn't have
multiple places computing it in
different ways so that way if I change
this I know it'll work right and so the
way that I was going to compute that was
I was just saying alright well I
essentially have an entity position here
right and I have an entity ground point
which is here right and so what I want
to do is I want to solve for I want to
basically take wherever the ground was
right so here's where the ground is
currently and I want to add something to
it that moves it up to where it should
be for it for the enemy's position so
what I want to do there is I want to
take the position minus the ground right
I want the thing that goes from the
ground to the position and that's you
know that's vector subtraction right so
I want it to be in that order and that
will give me that ground displacement
that I actually wanted whoops that's not
entity that's mover
there we go what are you complaining
about sir oh right we need to know the Z
of the ground point so yeah that should
hopefully restore are going up stairwell
code and it does but going down should
presumably still not work because now
our collision section is actually
working properly or at least we've
debugged as many of the bugs in it that
we could find so far and so what that
means is that we will no longer collide
with things whose max is right at the
ground level because that is something
that's technically on the floor below us
so what I think we want to do and I get
I don't really know but it's the first
thing that comes to mind but I think we
want to do is we want stairwells to
extend up above the ground a little so
that it's clear that that's something
that you collide with when you're moving
along background and so when we add the
stairwell I'm thinking that basically
you know we just say all right you know
whatever that you know whatever that
dimension was maybe it's just it's a
little bit more so it extends up just a
little bit above how big a floor is and
and you know see if that if that helps
us out and so again it looks like our
stairwell is working properly now we
can't get at it unless we come at it
from the bottom and then when we're up
on the top of it well close but no cigar
it's now colliding with it properly and
against its that yellow one now right
it's the top of the stairwell it's
colliding with it properly but it wasn't
really letting me get on to it it was
too high up I wonder if that's because
it actually is too high up
what was our tolerance level there so I
think what we what we need to do and
this is something that I wanted to do
before I think I even mentioned it on a
previous stream is I would like because
you know we're sort of this step height
and in fact I did exactly the step
height so you can see what's happening
that's pretty funny yeah you win some
you lose some
so the way that we had our code written
was basically to say okay when somebody
is coming along and you know let's say
that
maybe I'll draw this diagram a little
bit isometrically
right like so so here is our stairwell
right when somebody is coming along this
way what we basically said is well
what's the distance here right what's
the step that they would have to take
from where they're standing to where the
stairwell thinks the height should be
and really I'm drawing these as stairs
but really they're ramps that's what
we've implemented we don't we don't
stair step down right now we've lied
down so really they're ramps but either
way it doesn't matter so it's a ramp at
the stairwell doesn't really matter and
what we were saying is well we're not
gonna let it if it's any more than then
a tenth of a meter you can't do it so
you've got to kind of come up here and
go where the stairwell is you can't just
hop down onto it right and I guess it's
arbitrary maybe we'll change that in
future but that's what we implemented so
I made the stairwell go 11.1 meters up
over the ground which meant that if you
tried to board it at the place where
you're supposed to you would be able to
it on but it does mean in theory that if
I left it that way you should be able to
get on it right at the sort of a little
bit further down it oh well I guess I
got to go up the stairwell first so kind
of right here on the side yeah and any
exactly what you can do yeah
so that's kind of busted and you get a
little popping there too when it kind of
goes up and down it so we want to fix
that and I think the way that I would
like to fix that something I mentioned
before I would like the ramping so the
thing that computes the position that
you're going to do I would like that to
be independent of the collision
rectangle so I'd like the stairwell
collision rectangle to be something that
can be conservatively large but then
that sort of you know so it so it to two
stories almost right but then when it
computes the ground it doesn't use that
it doesn't use the the position way up
at the top it just uses what it knows is
one story or some other value that we
could specify later like we could put it
in the entity if we wanted stairwells to
be varying distances right so what I
really want here is instead of minzhi
see I really want it to be something
more like Minzy and Minzy plus the the
tile height or something like this right
but for now since I mean there's really
no reason not to and this will be good
because when we're doing our ante
systems it's just another thing that we
can look at we could just say only four
stairwells only four stairwells and we
could just say you know a total like
like walkable height or whatever
something like that right and then
walkable height it's just this right
we're taking the region's minimum Z and
we're going ahead and doing that so and
in fact we could even write this we
don't really even need a loop here at
that point if we've got the very
eccentric Y we can just use this
expression to say we basically are going
to be however much up we go on the walk
we'll height right and so now when we
add a stairwell we can specify how far
up we want it to go and so we can say
that that just the best way to do this
entity sim dot walkable height that's
going to be equal to the gamestate world
tile depth in meters right so now it's
collision rectangle it's kind of
separated in terms of its height from
that from that walkable height oops and
that's got to be the region's light and
so I think that should should solve our
problem there I think let's find out so
we can still we're still blocked on all
sides of the bottom stairwell we walk up
it there we go
try to walk down it that's still a
little janky why is that
you can still see there's a lip what's
what's going on there that's crazy
check that out is that freaky or what so
something is a little busted there with
just just at the very end we've got a
bug I'm not sure what the bug is but
we've definitely got one so let's go
ahead that's funny
let's go ahead and see what's going on
there
oh wait is there any kind of so yeah so
we've got two different computations for
the ground type that looks like what's
really going on here yeah so we need a
function which is gets their ground
something like this right and again this
is really good I really like where this
is going because again we're gonna have
to do our entity system at some point
and you can kind of see that we don't we
don't really have much built up we've
got some stuff but like the soars the
hit points that stuff the more stuff we
can pile in here the fattier we can make
this the better it will be when we go to
do it like we want as much stuff
happening with these entities as
possible
because that is what's going to allow us
to make a good entity system right if we
try to design the entity system before
having enough stuff in here we'll
probably make mistakes and have to
constantly keep redoing how we're doing
stuff and so you know essentially that's
that's really the whole thing about how
about how handmade entity dot h should
continue to grow just we want to start
having you know stuff that's very
specific to all different kinds entity
types so that we can see later when we
want to break it apart and make it more
usable and maintainable right so let's
see here so the region rect looks like
do we always have that it looks like in
both cases we do have that although it
looks like this is essentially doing all
the same computations right these are
all exactly the same so I think we
really just want to make this whole
thing right am I right about that it
looks like we really just want this
whole thing to happen in here right so
we want the the entity to generate its
region rect
we want it to compute its very eccentric
coordinates we want it to
can you know compute that ground height
but I want this is the one I actually
want right I want to compute that ground
height let's see and yeah and I've got a
pass in here as well
whatever the sort of the the standing P
whatever the place is that the Erlich
entity ground point right oh and that's
a bug as well so we have yet another
problem right this mover P should also
use that in both cases and it's not
right
because the theory we would want it to
always use that ground point again yeah
so this is good this will get rid of a
lot of bugs for us because this was just
not very good code at all because it was
written in a different it was written
with a different set of assumptions and
we want to kind of solidify that quite a
bit also I suppose this should really be
in here as well right okay that's
actually the 15-minute warning since we
started 10 minutes late so we've got a
fair bit of time to play with still okay
so this is good get any ground point we
know it is pretty much correct gets
their ground let's walk through this a
little bit more carefully we need to get
whatever the stairways region is we then
need to get the barycentric coordinates
for whoever it actually is so entity
ground point will be done there we then
have to compute what we actually think
the ground is and then we have to return
it and that looks let's see let's call
this at ground point right like so on
yeah now I guess technically now that I
think about it that wasn't really a bug
I mean it sort of was but because we
were only using the Bary centric why it
didn't matter whether we were passing
the ground point or not right so it
wasn't really a bug
it was a little hasty there that wasn't
a bug that was just sort of a little
sketch but you don't really need to pass
that ground point I guess so really this
could even be a v2 right you don't
really care what it is and so yeah what
can I say
anyway so let's keep going
so let's convert these two routines so
handle overlap this is basically just
going to call get stair ground and for
completeness I'm still gonna just call
get entity ground point in case it would
displace it in X&amp;Y some day you know I
mean it could happen probably won't
happen but you never know so I'm gonna
I'm gonna go ahead and call call that
anyway so past the region will get that
ground point back this stuff can just
basically go away entirely we are in the
stairwell code again here don't need
this don't need that and we can go ahead
and I probably leave that needs work
comment in because it probably doesn t
work but anyway so what we want to do
here is is wonder why this why are we
testing both of these things
does anyone know why we're testing both
of these things was that just because we
hadn't worked out all the code before
and so we were just choosing it because
it feels like the only criteria for
stepping on tor off of the stairwell
would be how high you have to step right
I don't feel like that code needs to be
there I I don't get it so I'm gonna go
ahead and and if that out temporarily I
feel like that's the entirety of the
code right like it should just be that
it should just be that you've got to be
within the step light yeah I don't know
that that's that's all I got so let's
try that first so let's do mover ground
point people's get empty ground point
mover we will then say mover ground
point Z will compute the ground here
gets their ground and we will go ahead
and do move the ground point and pass
the stairwell we should also probably
assert here just for fun that the entity
that we're trying to get the stairwell
level for actually is a stairwell
because you know someone could get into
a weird situation where they try to call
out in some other case and we don't
really want that so yeah so that fixed
our problem that's a good thing and it
does appear to be working kind of nicely
now yeah that's really good actually we
have tons of stuff that we are still
doing kind of janky like I guess really
the ground height is the number one but
yeah that's kind of nice what happened
there that didn't look quite right
let's take a look at what happened there
I think that was a bug so we went down
looks like ah aha so now now we see what
the barycentric y was therefore it was
because this is why taking a week off is
rough I tell you it's hard programming
all day and then coming home and
programming it really taxes your mental
state but now I remember the reason for
that is because we haven't actually done
the work yet for speculative collision
to handle exits properly right so what
we want to do is know what the ground
level we want speculative collide to
know whether you're going onto or off of
the stairwell right because basically if
you're going off the stairwell then we
need to know what the ground type would
be on the outside of the stairwell to
know whether or not you could cross it
so you know do we want to fix that do we
not want to fix that and I'm not really
sure I guess I would say that's the kind
of problem that does seem a little
tricky to solve so maybe we should solve
it let's go ahead and say that tomorrow
looks like we did this today at least to
the extent that we knew about it it
looks like probably what we want to do
here is say and maybe we can we can do
these two things sort of together we can
say need to make a sod constant of
ground level so the camera can be freely
placed in xena multiple ground level in
some region that's the next thing we
want to do anyway what we also will say
now is concept of ground in the
collision loop so it can handle
collisions coming onto and off of
stairwells for example because I think
that's probably something we should
probably get right it suggests that we
want to move this into a little more of
a primal spot in the way we handle
collisions where we're thinking about
where things will go height wise and
disallowing movements that would be too
far height wise in transition so I feel
like that's probably the right thing to
do so maybe we'll look at that tomorrow
but I think we're pretty much done for
the day we did the thing that I wanted
to do today they did actually both
things I wanted to do today so we're in
pretty good shape here I just I want to
spend a little bit more time getting
that stuff right before we move on to to
anything else I definitely want to go
ahead and and make a solid concept of
the ground-level stuff and we could do
that you know we can we can make sure
that flying things to go over walls
there as well maybe we'll make ourselves
be able to fly and so that we can see
whether we can fly over stuff or not so
yeah I think that's pretty good
I think we should go ahead and go to the
QA let's take a look here I think we
should go ahead and go to the QA might
as well start it on time since there's
no point in starting something new let's
go ahead and do QA please fix prefix
your questions with Q :
so I will see them and please keep them
the stuff that we did on today's stream
programming stuff or on previous streams
if you want to talk about crazy stuff
like what's the best computer science
NASA take or what do you think about the
MacBook Pro those are the kind of things
we do talk about on the pre stream so
come 15 minutes before our scheduled
start time and ask those questions will
we'll cover them then but for right now
just programming questions please on the
stuff that we're working on or that we
have worked on
let's see not seeing much in the way of
questions about what we are working on
well I guess I will answer off-topic
questions since we don't have any on
topic questions but if we get any on
type of questions I will switch to
answering those do you use clang on
Linux yes I do on Windows I use visual
studios compiler around on on political
aids clang I suppose I would also use
clearing on the Mac but I haven't been
shipping anything on the Mac in a while
so I don't really I'm not super familiar
with it
what is the best way to learn C++ from
absolute scratch on my own uh hmm I
don't know I mean just spending a lot of
time programming in C++ is really the
answer you know you kind of got to start
with some basic training so maybe the KN
are the original C programming language
book from knr and you know watching this
stream and seeing the sort of stuff that
I do and trying to figure out how to do
stuff like that I don't I don't know of
a good introductory series because you
know was many many years ago when I
learned and I don't even remember what I
did to learn really like what my first
reading materials were I don't even
remember and I don't know what other new
stuff has come out since then
do you know anything about Vox pel
programming no I don't think I know what
a Vox pel is I assume that it is related
in some way to a Vox
all but I would I would not say that I
have ever even heard that term I do know
how to program a voxel engine but I do
not know how to program a Vox pel engine
what versioning and revision control
system do you use I use the one a custom
one that I wrote myself are you planning
on replacing the stairs in your house
with ramps so the interesting thing
about this ramp is it feels awesome to
go up and down it it's so nice I think
once we actually do some real rendering
here it's gonna be kinda awesome just
going up and down stairs it feels so
much better than any stairs I've ever
gone up in a game before I don't know
why that is but just something about the
fact that you just goes up it and
there's no it's just a nice slide it
just feels really good you're like oh
I'm gonna go down the stairs we I don't
know it's like things and games when you
do sometimes you hit upon something that
feels good so I wasn't planning on
having a ramps in the game I guess
that's just first time implemented but
it feels so good in the fact like a lot
of 2d games lock you into Z motion so
you you hit a stairwell and your guy
like does some canned animation and up
he goes and then it switches screens or
whatever this feels so good that I think
we got to leave it in so we'll we'll
definitely figure that out
because that's that's definitely it just
feels really good I want to be able to
go up and down floors like that I don't
think we'll be putting them in my house
but
how did you get the right side of your
visual studio debugger you to be split
vertically it's really easy basically
when you drag windows around so like if
you drag the modules window right if you
grab this tab and you start dragging it
around you get an actual window right
and when you hover over another window
it it shows you like this compass rose
thing and if you if you put it in the
middle it'll dock into that window but
if you if you do one of these other ones
it will split the window and so you can
just split you can split things in any
way you want you can you could have as
many different slits as you want you
could have like four panes or two on top
and one on the bottom or anything that
so it's really easy to do of course
there is a catastrophic bug in the
previous version of Visual Studio well
not for you sir in Visual Studio 2008
where on many machines trying to dock a
window crashes it and it's awesome
because in the Microsoft knowledgebase
they're like yes it crashes we are not
going to fix it don't do that and you're
like awesome but so but assuming that
you're using Visual Studio 2013 that
does not have that particular bug so off
you go
why do you so many magic numbers in your
code
what kind of magic numbers are we
talking about if you could could you
give an example of magic number and then
I could explain why I used it
that was d25 inferno who asked that what
do you think about friend classes I
think that it's a waste of typing I
don't ever use private so I don't need
friend
so yeah let's see is this turning into
reverse doom almost complete 3d rendered
in 2d instead of 2d rendered in 3d
no doom doom is basically doomed doomed
as a lot of sort of I mean do basically
did sort of 3d rendering of wall
segments right I mean it was like two
and a half D so it kind of did this sort
of 3d view of the world and it was
trying to approximate how the walls
would be work to fit on it we're just
splitting sprites so the sprites
themselves are never going to be angled
but you know otherwise we're using 3d
positioning so I think I would say we
are 2d rendered in 3d and maybe they are
3d rendered in 2d so I would have I
would flipped your statement whether
that makes it reverse doom or not I
don't know that's one way I guess you
could put it but I feel like it's a good
idea to get all the 3d fundamentals
solid because at the end of the day it
doesn't take that long for us to do you
know it's 10 hours 20 hours or something
of programming to do it and then we know
that we won't have any surprises when
we're actually you know implementing
stuff where we constantly will have to
hack things if we can kind of get some
semblance of stuff solid at the outset I
think it'll help us now maybe not it may
still turn out that because you know
when you're in 2d it just it's always
hacky and that may be true but I feel
like we should at least try because it's
not too expensive to try
let me see if there are any on topic
questions here he's the top layer going
to fade in if you go up the stairs into
a closed room so I don't know we've got
to do there for that you can see we've
got how is this rendered kind of sitting
there I don't know probably it will have
to fade in that's a pretty good guess
because I'm not sure what else we could
do so I don't know that's probably what
we'll do but you know we'll have to play
around with it so it's a little early to
say definitively when do you plan on
doing Z sorting with the sprites when we
do the renderer so probably not for a
long time probably not for several more
weeks d25 or no why do you use so many
magic numbers in your code why not pound
defines what's an example you've got to
give me an example of a magic number
first are you talking about this if
you're talking about a magic number like
this it's because it's not used anywhere
else and if something's not used
anywhere else then there's really no
point in putting it in a pound to fine
because then all you're doing is
polluting the global namespace with
something that should only have been
defined locally if there is a number
that I'm using in lots of places that's
probably something I shouldn't be doing
so you should point it out and I can
tell you whether it's just an oversight
on my part or whether there's a good
reason for it
let's see here are you planning to use
advanced shader techniques if so which
ones yes we will be using some but it's
a little too early to get into that now
it'll be you know a ways down the road
when we're writing the renderer
looks like I skipped an episode in which
you made a lower level visible from a
higher one do you remember when did it
happen is the floor going to remain
transparent in the future so no the
floor will not remain transparent it's
kind of handy to have a transparent at
the moment but we will put in a ground
possibly very soon actually I don't know
exactly how we want to do that but we'll
put in the ground pretty soon at least a
placeholder ground so it won't be
transparent but we will have to do
something like fading out the top level
when you go down to the bottom level and
stuff like that we've got to work that
out and that's you know a pretty big
to-do item that's that's sitting right
here and so when we start to work on
that will probably work on the we'll
probably add some ground in there at
that time but I don't remember when that
happened to answer your question I don't
remember when we did that exactly
let's see Dee Johnstone 5 my previous
question was on topic missed it maybe
let's see where is Dee Johnstone yes I
did miss it it's there's a bit of a
flood of questions to say the least
correct me if I'm wrong but it seems
early on we started with the bottom
center position for collision detection
in our hero we moved to a center
position which offset in both x and y
now it seems we use the center x and y
owner continues to competing the bottom
center position do you feel this needs
to be consolidated in any way so no I
feel like if you remember there was a
decision point I think was actually
yesterday when we thought about which
one we wanted to do and basically the
decision was it's just gonna be a little
weird if we constantly have to think
about all of our collision routines in
terms of x and y being handled
differently from Z right so we wanted to
do is handle all everything uniformly
and then only handle the the one
things especially that actually cares
about that Z offset which is the ground
placement right and so that just seemed
like a more sensible thing to do because
otherwise like when we did Minkowski
sums for example you would do Minkowski
sums on the X and y differently than you
did them on the Z and when we dude like
interference testing we'd have to do
them differently on the Z like we
constantly do everything differently on
the Z and I feel like that math is way
more complicated and we don't want to be
in a position to force that difference
on to the more complicated math of the
collision detector what we'd rather do
is have everything just be uniform in XY
and Z and then handle just the ground
point stuff especially so I think that's
probably the right decision but it you
know you never really know with
something like that it may be that we
look back on it later and go and that
was probably dumb right and so it's hard
to say what's with the floating head in
the middle of the forest well that's our
familiar it's a floating head it follows
us around
can you explain the line controlled
hero's a raid count game input star
controllers and hamate age because it
looks like you're casting a null pointer
and referencing yeah okay so you are let
me find the line you're talking about
first array count so this is just pure
annoyance it this really isn't something
that should have to happen to say the
least
it's just unfortunate so what you would
like to write let me let me show you
what you would like to write here's what
what was in there before right
what you'd like to be able to write is
this right that's what I want to say I
want to say oops sorry array count
that's what I want to say right I want
to be able to say whatever the size of
this thing is right which I'm not
allowed to do and see whatever the size
of that member is divided by the first
one of it right but I can't do that
because you're not allowed to take the
size of just a type you have of just a
member thing you have to have an actual
type or an actual variable like an
actual value so this is nothing more
than stick tactic nonsense to say hey
mister compiler pretend that the null
pointer is a pointer to a game input
structure and pretend that you were
going to dereference it it's controllers
array then do the array count which is
size of the thing divided by size of its
first element what would that size be
because since the compiler isn't doesn't
actually generate any code for a size of
it just looks at what the size would be
and then returns it the pointer doesn't
actually have to be valid the
can be completely bogus it just needs to
be the right type and so that's this is
just getting how to do a size of
something that you don't actually have
the value of I would like to be able to
just state it directly but see doesn't
provide a community to do that that I
know of anyway to work around the
mischief zoom issue how about you find
the zoom level you want then draw four
dots one in each corner then when you
come back you can align those dots back
to the corners yeah the reason I'm not
doing that so then we'd have to go find
the four dots all the time I want a
thing that just like sets the zoom so I
don't know
yeah and pseudo named 73 pointed points
out that if I wanted to I could use C++
here because you can use deco type or
type of I try to stay away from those
because they traditionally weren't very
well supported they're probably more
supported now but I still use a very I
still use only the subset of C that work
didn't like you know 1990 for the most
part and yes I know you meant I know you
meant deco type type of probably
wouldn't help you there but but deco
type although I don't even know if deco
type helps you that much they're like
how would you actually type it because
deco type yeah does deco type actually
help I don't know if it does I guess you
could do deckle type of game input
controllers something like that
does that work oops
does that work sighs Oh oops do that
okay so that's the way you could do it
you could do that end and and that oh so
how would you actually so I don't know
can you actually write it with that go
play I don't know if you can cuz you
need to be able to get the size of the
lower one as well I don't know I'll
leave that as an exercise for the reader
if then I'm sure there is some new C++
way that you could do it but that's just
fine for me for now so we'll leave it
that way
in C++ I don't think that works memo
Zico is saying that could you do it
array count game input controllers but
I'm pretty sure that doesn't actually
work does it yeah that doesn't that work
so that's not an actual that's not an
actual option unfortunately deckle val
is what you want so yeah so people were
close with deco type if deco valid
actually would work I don't know
again it's sexual NFS doesn't matter
this works and it will work even on a C
compiler so it's kind of dumb to use the
C++ feature anyway like it's like at
that point we could just a pound to find
a thing if we wanted to right we could
pound to find a thing that was like you
know type and you pass it the type and
you just pass it just does this right
right and then you could in here say
something like I want to reference the
type game input and it's controllers
member right and then you can do things
like array account of that thing and it
would work right so if we wanted to we
could do that pretty easily without
having to resort to anything in C++ that
may or may not be confusing as well so
it's not that big of a deal it's
probably just not worth even trying to
crack open the ginormous C++ back to try
and find the thing that maybe sort of
works some of the time or whatever so
yeah
all right so have we come to the end of
the questions where are we we got five
minutes left there were a bunch of
off-topic questions before I know if any
of them need answering
why do you plan on using OpenGL or
DirectX for hardware acceleration is
that something that you have to have
knowledge of actual GPU Archer to be
able to implement I'm not sure I totally
understand the question the reason if
you're just saying why do we plan on
using OpenGL or DirectX the reason we
are using them is because they're the
only way to access the 3d hardware I
mean you're gonna have to use OpenGL
DirectX or mantle basically they're the
only API is that you have available for
the most part and the reason that we're
going to use them is because we want to
be able to use the 3d Hardware to render
the game so that's about that's about
all there is to it modern computers
can't really render graphics entirely on
the CPU very effectively the CPU is very
very underpowered for that task and so
if you want to have a game that looks
competitive and good you pretty much
have to use the graphics card so we are
doing our own renderer as an educational
thing but we will not use it as the way
that the game typically runs for the end
user because there is no way to make a
cpu renderer that's nearly as fast as a
GPU renderer that's just not something
you can do so yeah
so what do you think of Cronos vulcan
well I haven't seen it yet I asked if I
could take a look at the spec but I have
not received one yet and so if and when
I get a copy of the spec I will be able
to say what I think about it but at the
moment I don't know I would like the
most minimal possible interface to the
hardware that could possibly be I mean
in my ideal world you just have ring
buffers that you're right to and the
hardware reads out of and there'd be no
driver at all that'd be my dream world
so assuming that Vulcan gets
significantly closer to that than modern
OpenGL which wouldn't be hard it would
be a plus so it's probably just a
question of how much of a plus would it
be if it's really well designed it could
be a very big plus if it's not then
it'll be an annoying but still plus
right so I don't know we'll have to see
let's see
anything else we got here what is the
best way to build a game when you know
how to program but you have no art
skills hire an artist to do it for you
that is my Achilles heel but I want to
make a game on my own well if you don't
have an arch to work with or don't know
how to work with an RS or don't have the
money to work with an artist make a
procedural game there's a lot of people
who have kind of done things that are
relatively programmer II art stuff and
they were so popular so you might be
able get away with it right so I would
say try to do something in 3d with a lot
of lighting so that you don't need this
good art and try to make the definition
of what the graphics are much simpler so
that that you don't have to try and make
you know huge dragons flying around or
something which you know it's gonna be
hard without an artist try to make
something that could be more procedural
something that you could generate from
code you know more directly I mean a
simple example would be you know if you
can do a game that's mostly with
geometric shapes for example - or you
know you can also steal someone else's
visual design like mini Metro would be a
good example right like I don't know if
you guys have ever seen this but like
the visual design for mini Metro is just
a subway map right and so you don't have
to be necessarily a great artist to go
steal the design of a subway map and
build a game around it that's a good way
to get around your limitations as of not
being able to do like high-end
production art or anything so that would
be my advice to you is that if you if
you can't swing the art see if there's a
way that you can define what the game is
and how it looks so that it will look
good without art such that art is not a
thing that it hangs on that's really the
only advice I can give you and with that
we have come to the end of another
episode of handmade hero thank you so
much for joining me if it a pleasure
programming with you as all
let me go ahead and close down things
here and save our mischief drawing so
it'll be in the in the pack so I think
we're in pretty good shape we've still
got a little bit more work to do before
we can really call our stuff solid and
on the ground side of things they're
still a bunch of hand waving in there in
terms of where the ground height
actually is and some things like that
but we're making progress we're getting
closer so I think that's good and then
we can spare men a little bit with how
we want to draw the things in Z and
maybe figure out a little bit the stuff
we want to do there we're starting
starting to look pretty good
I think we're getting we're getting down
to it and I'm pretty happy where things
are and it'll be fun to kind of move on
to something new we've been working on
this for a little bit of time it'll be
kind of be fun to move on to something
sort of different and so maybe you know
by next week we can try to set our
sights on being on to the next major
area to tackle as always if you would
like to follow along at home you can
pre-order the game on handmade hero org
and it comes to all the source code you
can download it every night right after
I finish coding in fact I upload it so
if you want to do that you can do that
here at handmade hero org also on hand
meteor or gar links to other things that
are good we have a tweet bot that tweets
the schedule which is horribly broken
right now it's still tweeting in Pacific
Standard Time even though we're on some
daylight time now which I realize is
very confusing for people because it
says 8 p.m. Pacific Standard Time but
really it's a p.m. Daylight Time so I'll
be fixing that this evening thank you
for people who reported it so that that
will normally be treating the schedule
in the correct time zone even though
it's time right now it's not exactly the
world's best made piece of software I
wrote it in like an hour and you know a
lot of that hour was trying to figure
out how to get curl to work so let's not
let's not pretend that it's a you know
it's not going to the moon although
apparently the software that they tried
to grow the moon with also didn't work
but that's a separate story for a
different time anyway tweet bot normally
free to schedule highly recommend
checking it out if you want to catch the
stream you could follow it or you can
just go to its page and take a look at
the schedule at any time that's pretty
much all it does so it's a low volume
kind of guy we also have a patreon page
that basically if you want to support
the video series you can subscribe to
it's always very much appreciated
we also have a news at forum site which
has a lot of great stuff on it it's got
an annotated episode guide made by
people in the community that's really
cool you should check it out it's got a
forums where you can ask questions about
the series and so on and it also has
ports to Linux and Mac and other stuff
in advance of us actually doing them on
the stream so that if you want to be
working right now on a Linux machine or
on a Mac machine you don't have to wait
for me to get there you can actually go
and see what other people have done for
the port's and follow along with the
series on those machines right now so
that's pretty handy however mint
recommend checking that out if you're
someone who's trying to learn from the
stream that's really great resource so
again I'll be back here same time same
place tomorrow 8 p.m. Pacific cent well
oh I almost see it's not the bots that's
wrong
it's me often times 8 p.m. Pacific
Daylight Time 8 p.m. Saturday light time
tomorrow here on the west coast I hope
to see you all there and maybe I will
finally remember what time zone I'm in
so I won't be as bad as the Bob the
bottle be fixed but I'll still be wrong
what can you do there's really no
debugger for the human brain yet thanks
very much for joining me I hope you have
a wonderful Wednesday and I will see you
tomorrow