all right hello everybody and welcome to
handmade hero today we are probably just
going to do
some experiments with collision
uh we need to
basically like we have uh we need to we
did all weird stuff with the glove like
you can see here a strange test case we
made where you can put in patterns for
the glove that have like
different speeds depending on where they
go
um
and uh that like we don't really know if
this is something we're actually going
to use but we were just playing around
with like move cues and how they might
work
um
this stuff's a little bit janky but we
only just sort of started playing around
with it uh and furthermore we don't have
a few things in there that we need to
have in there like for example when you
do one of these crazy glove patterns the
amount of time it takes the glove to
return to you is always the same right
now and i would assume that we
while we may want something weird like
that because you want it to feel a
certain way
um as we start to actually tune the
motion of things like the glove i'm
assuming we would want the return time
to be at least somewhat proportional to
how far away you are
so that the glove takes longer to return
if it's further away
maybe we don't but i assume we do
um
so
what i wanted to do today was make it so
that we figure out how we want or at
least get some
semblance of a plan
for how we want to do uh like the
collision so you know we've got this
situation here and we'd like to do we'd
like to start making it so you can
eliminate enemies
when uh you
when you hit an enemy we would like it
to do like a point of damage or apply
whatever random effects we want
and because we want this to feel uh like
tile based basically like we want it to
feel like um
we want it to feel like it's happening
on the grid we need to figure out what
we want our definition of hit to be uh
it probably still just wants to be
when the
boxes
of the two things touch
but i don't know like it's hard to say
so you know we we can do it in a lot of
different ways but i don't know which
way we actually want to do
we could make it so that it's when the
glove arrives at the square is actually
the um
like
you know the the punt like just the
punch
uh
that's when it does the damage so
whenever it arrives at the squares when
it does the damage
we could also do when the two bounding
boxes overlap is when it does the damage
and i and i don't really know um
i guess we'll just start with the when
the glove arrives at the square is when
it does damage so so if
if somebody's leaving a square and the
glove arrives at that square it does not
count
um
i guess i don't know i'm really not sure
how we want to do it i suspect we don't
there's just so many ways you could do
this and i really don't know what you
want so i think we just have to try them
and see what feels good because i i just
have no idea like for example
uh let's suppose that you have somebody
uh who's hopping from one square to the
next square
um
in that scenario when they're hopping
from one square to another and maybe
i'll turn this dude into like a thing
that hops from one square to another for
example just so we can
play around with it
um if you hop from one square to the
next square then
when are you considered in this square
if the rule is that the glove arrives at
the square it does the damage you know
what i mean
um
i just don't know
i don't know
uh
and i feel like that's something that
should have a a
smart answer to it but i don't know what
it is because i don't do game design
so
my guess is that we probably want
something like there's the halfway
transition point when you are considered
in the square
and at the halfway transition point like
that's
when
like something like at the halfway
transition point that's when you
become in that square
and on the halfway exit point so like at
point five on enter and point five on
exit kind of a thing you know what i
mean
so we could do it that way
i think that's just yeah i think that's
probably going to be not what we want
long term i think maybe just if the
bounding boxes overlap is what we're
going to probably want
i'm guessing
um so like you
you know you
you just look at when the old-school
collision like if the two bounding boxes
happen overlap then that's a strike
probably um
and the reason i say that is just
because that's what the player sees
visually right
so it should match what the player sees
visually because that's what they are
going to be most able to time if they
have to time something that's not really
like that like if they have to time
something that's more
[Music]
that's it's more like abstract like what
square you're in like that then i feel
like it's just gonna feel less
satisfying
um so i think we just kind of want the
old-school version of of that where we
basically say look
check for collision against some things
in the nearby area and if you if
anything overlaps
that's just what happens so it's it's
we'll be very akin to something like a
street fighter right so we define like a
hit box
and
we
just say that if hitboxes overlap then
then that's when it's a strike
right
i think that's basically it
uh so let's just do that
and
we'll call it a day um i don't
i don't know why we have a ray intersex
box
call
does anyone know what that is here for
it is here for hit testing
[Music]
okay so it's it's literally just for
debug we probably should have labeled
that debug it looks like it's it's
strictly for um like picking entities
with the mouse
right
because i was like what the heck we
don't use that anywhere um
so it was a little weirded out about why
i was there
um anyway
it doesn't matter point being
uh entities basically all move
and they can all always move because the
only restrictions we have currently on
moving
is
that if you are somebody who's an actual
like
uh
who takes up
physical space
then you had to use transactional occupy
to get there so no two people can occupy
the same square in that sense
but
for anything else for things that are
just moving uh that do not use
transactional occupy they can just move
wherever they want
and so then at the end i suspect we
just at the very end after everything
has moved
uh then we could go in and
do a hit test
uh
you know
not this hit test this is for cursor
picking um
but we should go in and just do a thing
where we go all right now we'll check
any bounding boxes versus each other
now again we would rather have an
explicit grid here the fact that we
don't have one is lame uh we had done it
in a very generic way so that you could
do worlds that weren't grid based
uh and we just don't need that so a lot
of stuff is over complicated now uh
things that we don't
you know we we easily should have
probably just put down that constraint
at the beginning
to make things simpler but we didn't so
it means that we kind of have a worse go
of it here
and so probably what we want to do is
collapse things back down to a grid but
i'm going to save that i think i've said
a couple times i'm going to save that
maybe just a little longer
um because
it's kind of something we can comb
through a lot of code and delete a lot
of code from the code base when we do
that
uh it will sort of massively simplify a
ton of things
uh but like kind of like how our
lighting got massively simpler and
faster when we
switched it to planar right
planar
uh is simpler than volumetric always and
grid based is simpler than planar oh
pretty much
um sometimes that's not entirely true if
the things you're doing are very sparse
but you know
anyway um so after we loop over all of
these entities then i think we just want
to do
a check for
collision
and the way that we would probably do
this in the future
is we would do it more based on the grid
right
but since we're not doing that here we
could do a second loop over entities
the problem with doing a second loop
over entities is that that's going gonna
touch literally everything a second time
which means that we kind of like
we'd end up in a situation where we're
pulling everything back into the cache
again right we've swept through it once
and now we're sweeping through it a
second time
and
it's just kind of
wasteful right
so my guess is that what we would
probably prefer here is that if we had
some way of just tracking what
projectiles
were active at a given time
that would be
the
more efficient way to do it so i'm going
to put this i'm just going to mark this
down because
this is something that we want to
think about more long-term and just say
like okay you know
this needs to become
a loop over just projectiles
and
grid accesses
once the grid is here
because really this is so i'm going to
do it in like the worst possible way
i'll do an n-squared loop here
and then this wants to be replaced with
inside here we track things that are
actually going to do damage and then we
resolve the damage here after everyone's
moved so this will just be a loop over
active projectiles and thus this will
just be a check for the grid squares
immediately surrounding those
projectiles
but
prior to that
i'm going to call this projectile
or project or maybe because we're
probably going to actually want to
change it into um
you know
an actual thing called projectile that's
part of the entity
uh and this is going to be like the
check
thing we're checking the projectile
against
so we have an entity um that's the
projectile
and we don't actually have to do this it
won't actually be n squared almost any
time because we can do a check
here that's the same check we'll
eventually do up here to save the
projectiles
into a separate list that's for faster
checking
um we presumably want to just check a
flag on the entity that says whether or
not this entity gets to participate
in this sweep right
and so the entity flags that we've got
and i don't even remember where those
are
in the game but we'll jump to them here
so um
you know we've we've got like some
things here like event on collision and
those sorts of things these are all old
flags
uh sphere collision that sort of stuff
um these are all really old flags and we
probably will update them at some point
at the immediate moment i'm just adding
another one because again
uh i'm not gonna simplify stuff until i
actually am done sort of sketching out
what i actually want
if that makes sense
uh so
don't ever mention new c plus syntax c
plus plus needs to die in a horrible
fire
um to say the very least
uh
so what it would really look nice
probably is ji syntax but i
feel like we probably shouldn't port
handmade hero to it um
no they definitely didn't so here's what
i will guarantee you
about c plus four loop syntax
i've not even looked at it yet i
guarantee you it's completely wrong
i can just promise you they screwed it
up entirely because they have never
added a single feature in the history of
c plus
the only thing i can think of we we had
a long brainstorming session about this
the other day
with other people
the only thing that came up was a line
nas
seems like it's sort of
they didn't screw it up
for loop syntax i guarantee you if i
went looked at it i'd just be like this
is the dumbest design i've ever seen for
for for loop syntax i guarantee you that
i just guarantee you they've never been
able they've literally never known how
to do stuff right ever
uh and and how to do that right is
trivial it's obvious how to do for loop
syntax right it's so obvious how you do
for a loop syntax right that it's a joke
if you can't but they
i guarantee you that they haven't i'm
just gonna guarantee you that
okay um it's like what john said on his
last stream about namespaces it's so
blaringly obvious how you do namespaces
correctly the person who uses the
namespace names the namespace that's
what prevents collisions right but they
did it the other way around the person
who creates the namespace names the
namespace
like
like they just have no idea
yeah so richard that's terrible that's
absolutely ridiculous right and and not
how you would do it
if if that's really what they came up
with that's absurd like once again they
managed to swerve
around the obvious answer to how you do
for loops because it's so
painfully clear
how you do for loops
i just i don't even know how you
have a language for 40 years and don't
do them but
anyway
so uh entity flags
we need something that's like
projectile
or you know i
collider
something like this
uh and these will probably be you know
these will probably be removed uh
eventually sphere collision might not be
because we might still want sphere
collision
um i'm not sure whether it will always
be
uh rust i think the exact same thing
it's it's ridiculous how bad it is given
that it's brand new it's like almost as
bad as c plus plus
but you know
that's not the bar you should be aiming
for if you make a language in 2020 right
we managed to be
maybe slightly better than c plus plus
although we introduced a bunch of things
that are actually worse than c plus so i
don't know that you would necessarily
say that but it's just a joke modern
languages are a joke that's all i can
say
like they're like barely passable as
languages from 1975 but they're made in
19 in
2020 right it's like it's a joke it's a
joke how
little improvement people have targeted
for their languages that they're making
literally 40 years
after the language they're more
languages they're more or less aping
it's just absurd
it's just absurd it's a joke it's all
just a stupid joke anyway
so projectile flags checked against
collider uh is what will tell us whether
or not we'll do a separate one here and
then for each of these we'll just do if
these two things collide right
so if these two things collide then
we're gonna go ahead and uh trigger
whatever kind of like collision
resolution event we want which at the
moment
i don't think we have anything other
than
projectile
right
um
like like in the game of the things i'm
thinking of there really isn't anything
else
projectiles might have a series of like
different
um
like they they might have different
things that they
you know different properties right
but they're not really gonna be like
there aren't like multiple things it's
it's really just that i think
um
so so here's a question how are we
currently doing
um
this because this this is something that
isn't that way
um there's like um
where is it
so when you hop in front of like a
character
like this
so that that
volume check
i don't actually know what that's using
um
hmm
so i don't actually know what we did for
that but i think we just created a box
that we check for which room you're in
right and that's like a separate camera
zoom kind of box so so even that
i mean maybe we want
this system to work
that way but
but maybe not
what's the obviously good for loop
syntax i would
i almost don't want to say it because
i'm just curious to know how long it
will take these languages to figure out
the obvious way you do for loops
i
like
if i don't say what the obvious way is i
honestly don't know like is the answer
like
10 years like how long would it take
another an actual language
to figure out how the frick
is the
it's so obvious i don't even know how
it's not the standard way in every
language but it's not so
i don't know there might be a language
out there with it
but i kind of now don't want to say it
because i honestly want to know
how it's
how long it would take
i don't know how long it would take
years
maybe jai has it i don't know it might
um
i don't know
jay i might already have it right
um john tends to do things in a way
where he's thought through it
which is rare
you know in language design normally
they're not really thought through
they're just kind of done
um
but uh
but i don't know i don't even know if
j.i has it i'm not sure i should go look
uh i don't know if there's
like um
i don't i don't know if if there's
a stream where john shows that stuff he
was he's was
like talking about some of the basic for
loop stuff
but
there's like a really really really
obvious thing you do with for loops in
my opinion
um
but
yeah i
i don't know
i do not know
anyway
when i release casey lang
it'll use that for loop syntax
that i think is the overwhelmingly
obvious for loop syntax
and then you can see you can tell me
whether you can remember today you can
tell me whether any language today had
it when i released that
so
uh yuka that's pretty close
um
that's pretty close
if jai has that
yeah as as expected right
you know you
it's it's not
it's not probably an accident that john
did what i think
is what
is good right it's because he's thinking
about
programming
instead of whatever the heck these other
language designers think about which i
don't know what it is
anyway uh so
we're gonna have a entity that we check
against and we need to see whether
they're
bounding like just their bounds overlap
so this is not like a collision detector
proper this is literally just it's just
a
a simple check
and i don't know if we have one of those
or not um
i really just have no idea if we've uh
you have
we've kind of got this sort of thing um
and i guess that's it like i think
i don't know uh there was like a sphere
collision thing and that didn't seem to
be that way necessarily
um
but
i don't know
i don't really know
it's not my it's not my
uh fault it's not my problem anyway
uh if these two things overlap then
we're going to do like uh
basically an application of you know
damage or something else to this
but we're probably gonna want some
things that prevent this from happening
uh in rapid succession and there's a
number of different ways you can do this
we'll probably do the action game style
one so the way action games typically do
this right is
when you
when a projectile of some kind
hits somebody
the
person who gets hit by the projectile
becomes like invincible for a short
period of time right
now there's two reasons for this
one reason
is
to
give you a chance to like
like to make sure that you don't get hit
by like 12 things at once and die right
or whatever
um but another reason is because it
means we don't have to disambiguate the
fact that on every frame you may be
colliding
and you would keep doing damage every
frame
so
there's multiple ways that you can deal
with that fact one way is you can
actually track
the going from
not colliding to colliding so you
remember that you weren't colliding on
the previous time
and then you clot you know when you go
to collide the next time you're good you
know that it's a it's a new collision
right
so you can do that
but
uh
it's actually easier and also maybe you
know you don't you don't really have to
write any code besides a little timer to
do the other way which is just make you
invincible for a little bit
and that has this sort of nice ancillary
benefit
um
of like
making it so that you you know
um
yeah i mean making it there's a couple
things i should
i guess mention here
so another way is the projectile gets
deleted or the projectile gets marked as
done right
in our case i don't really think we
have that
uh
because like with something like the
glove for example it's not going to get
deleted we could mark it as done so the
first time you hit something it returns
but don't like that idea because i like
the idea of there being gloves that
continue to do damage so you can hit
multiple things with one swipe if
there's multiple things in the way
maybe some gloves don't do that
but at least some gloves would right so
i don't want to presuppose that the
glove always gets disabled
when it hits something and and only gets
re-enabled when it returns to you right
i don't like that idea
so
so yeah um
on the other hand for punching enemies
while i don't really want you to be able
to punch the same enemy multiple times i
suppose i do want you to be able to
punch
yeah this is tricky
so i think i may actually want something
that that properly tracks new collision
like
yeah i i don't know this is this is a
this is particularly
tricky
for the glove
is i guess what i would say
because i want the glove to
properly be able to punch things
like when it is
so let's let's turn off this weird like
slow
test thing that i had there
um
and
because we we just kind of hard coded in
an attack pattern here just we just made
one up right normally you'd be these to
be specific to like the glove or
whatever and you pick them up
um
so uh
the thing that that i was curious about
here is like so let's say we were doing
like an attack pattern
like this
right
um and i can stop doing that little like
pattern draw nonsense we had a little
thing there that tries to draw the uh
movement
for
when we were like doing a little bit of
debugging there it was this piece right
here
and we don't actually need that for
anything now
uh but the point is
if you're doing something like this you
want to be able to repeatedly punch the
same enemy as well right
um
so
that part is a little confusing like how
we would want it to just be
you know as soon as it
yeah i don't know
so you know a trivial way you could do
it that would work with one glove is you
just
have a sequence number on the glove
basically
um
oh
wait a minute
that actually works for everything
doesn't it
huh
okay so actually yeah i suppose this
would work for anything now that i think
about it
so if you put a sequence number
that's a global sequence number for all
entities so every time any entity gets
an attack
the attack is labeled with a sequence
number and that sequence number
increments by one each time
all colliders so all other entities in
the world they just store the last
sequence number that hit them
and if the sequence number of the thing
that's trying to hit them
is greater than the sequence number of
the thing last thing that hit them then
they update their sequence number and
that's recorded as a hit
right
so that would work
just fine it requires all things that
can be hit to record one sequence number
which is maybe a bit much
wouldn't that mean a slow projectile
could be invalidated by a later
fast-forward yeah i think you may be
right
and also as i'm thinking about it i'm
like
it's too much storage because
you probably could have just stored for
each projectile the list of things that
hit in much less space
right
so that may be too clever
so i don't know
so there's one other way we could think
about doing this which is maybe more
specific to this game another way we
could think about doing this too i
suppose would be that there's a specific
time at which the hitbox activates
so that it only activates on one frame
anyway
um
that's more like a real punch in a
fighting game where like in fighting
games you don't you don't get credit for
hitting somebody
throughout the entire punch you only get
credit
during the specific hitbox activation
periods
right so i don't know i really don't
know it's a good question this
normally you solve this problem by just
not you don't really do this right like
you don't try to solve this problem in
most action games they don't actually
try to
but in this particular case i feel like
we actually do want to
uh because we want the glove to be able
to do those things
and we also have i mean we already have
in the game
the note like we can't just do something
just for the glove because we already
have the the notion that like like this
still works right
like i can still i can still create um
another
hero uh and you know i don't actually
know whether anyone will ever play the
game this way because maybe the game
won't really be fun to play with
multiple heroes or whatever
um
you
you can imagine that if that did work
you wouldn't want to not
ship multiplayer just because you didn't
have a solution for multiple gloves
right
um
i wonder how far out i can get that
because i don't remember what the
movement limit is is it three
if you just keep wailing on the button
um
i would like the simplest possible thing
that satisfies those constraints
so i don't really want to have to put in
something complicated here but i'm not
really quite thinking of what the if
there is some obvious solution
that's not complicated i'm
struggling to think of what it actually
is
furthermore like some other simple
solutions like oh colliders just store
who they're colliding with so that if
it's the same person as last time they
don't do damage
um
i feel like that fails if a collider
happens to overlap two people first in
like you know it's a somewhat rare case
but it definitely
could happen right
um so if uh you know if there's two
enemies right next to each other and the
glove happens to overlap both of their
bounding boxes because of like it's
placed just so
or something like that
then
you would it would oscillate between
them presumably and continue to do
damage all the time because if you only
store one thing that's in contact with
then that you know
it's not enough
you have to be able to store when you
become uncontacted with something like
so that there can be as many as
you might overlap have to be tracked
um
so i don't know i think we might be back
to
just basically we gotta track the list
there's just a list of people who were
overlapping on the previous frame
um
i honestly can't think of anything else
that you could do
um
if anyone has any idea of something
simpler
um
i'm i'm happy to to entertain it but i
can't think of anything that would be
that that's
yeah i can't think of anything that was
that's gonna be like
simpler and still
work
um
because if you have a list of the things
that you were in contact with on the
previous frame that's all the in that's
definitely all the information that you
need right because when you do your
collision pass on the following frame
you basically go well
anybody i
i'm colliding with now that i wasn't
colliding with before that's a hit
and that's just
that
solves all the problems right but it
does require you to store
all the
all of the people for with whom you
your entity overlaps returned true
like for whom
it returned true
uh you have to know that that
list and we could you know bound it we
could say like well that's never gonna
be more than four people or something so
we can probably keep it from being some
like arbitrarily complicated thing i
suppose but it's still
it's still somewhat
um
it's still somewhat fancy
right
um
so yeah i don't know i guess we're just
gonna go with that for now because i
can't really think of how else you might
do it
so um let's suppose that we did
something like that and in the future
maybe we can store those in some kind of
an active active projectile list that's
like a separate thing
because right now obviously our envy
stuff is pretty piggy uh and you know if
we want to get that down in the future
though computers are so freaking fast
these days you know
if you use web software you wouldn't
think so but they're so fast that
even though this stuff is totally
ridiculously unoptimized like
to the nth degree unoptimized
it still just runs just fine
which is absolutely absurd
but that's just a testament to how fast
computers are they just don't seem it
right
what can you do so anyway uh if we did
want to keep something like this you
know let's let's just sketch that out uh
so this is just going to be like an
entity uh collider list or something
like that
um
and i guess it's not even a list it's
it's really just an array um or a group
uh and in here we would just say yeah
all right there's an entity id for like
uh colliders and it's like we got some
in there
and that's it
you know what i mean
uh and
i don't really know
i
i don't really know that it needs to be
anything more than that
but effectively all we're going to do is
just store
that in there and check
if
the entity
that in question is is in there or not
right
so the way this would work is again
incredibly simple
uh we just have and
you know we would make a new one here an
entity collider group oops
not literally right here
every time we look at a particular
projectile
we would
make a new group here
and we'd probably have the old group
we'd we'd just like pull it out
like so
so we have the old group in the new
group
we'd cla well you don't even really need
to clear the new group because we can
just say uh
like collide count
equals zero
right
so when we go through here and we do
like
if this guy is a collider
and i guess technically all this stuff
can live inside here although that's
really neither here nor there because
nothing actually happens
but um
when we loop through all the people when
we find somebody who overlaps
we add them
to the list of colliders uh and we'd
probably do something like this if
collide count is less than the number of
slots we have
in
the
what is the name of this thing again
just colliders
i guess let's just do ids
um so if we have room in the ids for
this then we record it so we just do
like collide count
um plus plus equals
whatever this
particular thing is we're about to hit
right
um and maybe we assert here and we just
say like
collider overflow
so that we know um because maybe this
needs to be eight you know who knows for
our game
we don't want it to ever fail um so we
don't want this to produce like
a cr well it wouldn't really be a crash
but a corruption or anything so we want
to make sure we don't do it but we also
want to make sure we know if we've set
this value low enough that it ever
really happens in game play
um so that's just my way of knowing
what this you know so i can see what
this value reasonably has to be to
prevent it from actually occurring in
practice
you know what i'm saying
uh so then in entity when we get the
overlapping entity we're recording him
in this group and then we need to do a
check here to see whether or not it's
new um so we assume it's new then we go
through here and we'd set it to false if
it matches right
like this kind of thing
so we would say you know the
collide count is is just going to be
whatever the old group
ids are
and yeah you know what i guess we this
does need to be this way unless we want
to store the u32 of the count
which we don't want to and clearing this
if compilers weren't absolute garbage
every day all day
uh this wouldn't be a big deal anyway
because
this is literally just two 64-bit
values
right
it's four 32-bit values so it's like
it's two registers worth it's nothing
right
um of course compilers will do amazing
things like turn this into a freaking
mem set because they're
i don't know
because the compiler and the c plus
standard are basically written by the
same kind of people people who don't
know how to code
all right
so
when we actually look at this and we go
like let's loop through the indices here
and see if any of these uh were
existing ones
um for those of you who like cimd things
you will notice that we could probably
do all this thing with a single u128
register um but you know
we're not at that state this would just
be a move mask
we don't really do cimd here much on
handmade hero but but point being if
you're into 70 programming you you
should be thinking in your head here
about how this would be clearly that
um
when we find one we just need to do like
uh you know a check to see and when we
find one we just say that it's not a new
collision anymore but that's all we
needed right so so like it's literally
we don't even need to know what position
it was in this is why i say if you know
if you think cindy you can obviously see
how this would
uh be something that you would you would
uh cmd pretty quickly
so we look to see does it match if it
does match this isn't a new collision
and we don't need to keep looking
obviously uh and then here we finally
get to our collision resolution call so
like this is like collision resolve or
whatever
and in theory anyway because we're
checking these things we should this
should only happen on a new collision
meaning we stopped colliding with the
entity and now we recollide with the
entity or we've never collided with the
entity either of those two things
right
so this is where we would do the actual
collision event it would happen here
and it would get resolved
how we want it to get resolved is
now getting into gameplay code
unfortunately and you know
uh jonathan blow
conveniently
i might add is apparently on a plane
from san francisco back to florida today
so he's not here to tell us
what we would do in that code but
you know normally your game designer is
going to
have something to say about this and
what's going to happen in here right
like
engine programmer has to produce this
part
oh yes sorry not from san francisco from
ohio yes that's right he was that he was
at um
g dex
i've never heard of what that is
um
but it's
i guess it's a midwest game conference
of some kind
[Music]
something like that i don't know
hellman munster
start growing series on youtube
currently day four sisters you want to
tell someone just starting um
no not particularly
um
no not really
i think you know we it managed to
capture the process pretty well i think
um it's a little off because
it's a little bit weird programming in
such small chunks
you know it's hard to do much
600 episodes still ends up being
something like a thousand hours of
programming which is like almost no
programming
um so
it's a little
challenging
um to produce anything good that way
but
you know it sort of captures
something like it
you know
um
yeah
it captures
programming to a certain extent it
doesn't really the thing that it doesn't
do is capture the real like
the really good programming
you know
um
because like
it only happens when you like spend 16
hours like looking at something
continuously you know like you're just
looking at it all day and you look at it
all day the next day
you know
um
and
and you that you just can't capture that
on stream
your brain is only half
engaged so you're at 50
you know when you're programming on
stream
and
that's fine for simple stuff
you know
uh
but like
it's just not good enough for things
like complicated code like the lighting
code or the debug system
like getting those things to be good
is just i don't know how doable it is on
stream i can certainly go do it all off
stream
and do all the learning right
um about exactly how i like to do those
things and then i can do something on
stream and it comes out right but that's
because i already knew
right
i already basically knew the hard parts
of the answer
and reconstructing them again in code is
not hard if you have you know the
experience right
but like
the real like
extremely good things they they just
don't happen on a stream
i guess is what i'd say
um
some accidental discoveries do sometimes
uh like the way to do the perfectly
round
interpolated light source thing
by using negative numbers in the lights
that was an example of like oh hey i
accidentally stumbled upon this by going
hey i wonder if this would work and then
it does
we had a couple of those moments
um but the really like
insightful like
hardcore code stuff it just doesn't
happen on stream that's that's just and
i don't think it ever is gonna
you know i just don't because no matter
who you are or how smart you are
some part of your brain is required to
talk to do the stream
and that part
is not working on the code at that time
right
and so i think that
just means that whoever the person is
their best moments
will never be the ones that they're
streaming
you know what i'm saying
um
so
that's all i would say really
uh
otherwise i think yeah it's mostly
uh it's mostly what you would expect i
think
um
yeah
i don't think there's much else to say
about it
um because capturing mistakes and things
like that was like the point of
streaming the whole thing
you know what i mean
um
and uh so you know
you don't really want to say those up
front the point is to see how you
recover from things or try different
things you know what i mean
um so
so yeah
that's what i would say
all right back to our story i mean this
is basically the code uh this is
basically all there is once we're done
doing one of these passes we just change
the list over to the new one
right so we i mean hopefully everyone
can see how this works it's really but
simple we're just going over anything
that's a collider uh that's that's one
of these
things that wants to do stuff when it
runs into somebody
um and all we're doing is saying look
we've got a list of the things
that it hit on the last frame
we run through all the entities and
again like i said this wants to be a
spatial query so this is very
inefficient the way it's being done but
it'll be done exactly the same way just
with a more efficient query
iterate over the things you might
collide with
right now it's everybody but in the
future it would be a subset
you see whether or not you do collide
and if you do collide then you go ahead
and add it to the list of things for
next frame to track
and you use the list from the previous
frame to see whether or not this is a
new collision and should have an event
right
now we can also do another thing in here
if we want to we can have the an exit
collision as well
right
because
we could also say well at the end of
this compare these two groups and see if
you know if anyone who was in the old
group is now not in the new group that's
an exit event
i
can't think of anything offhand of why
we want exit events
right um so i don't think we need to do
that extra work but
you could trivially do it so you would
just compare these two and see if anyone
from old group doesn't appear in new
group that's it
all right
um
and as an assigned for cindy people just
you know so you
if you're interested in cmd programming
what i was trying to say here is like
you can kind of see what goes on if you
have an array of let's say this was
eight
right
which is the natural avx with so the avx
width in
so in x64 the avx uh which is the
processor you're likely programming on
has avx
uh the avx width is going to be 32 bytes
which is eight four byte values
this entity collider group if it was one
avx register large would store eight
entity ids
right
if you wanted to do the check to see
whether your old group and your new
group had anything in common right
it's just eight pairs of instructions
right it's broadcast one of the ids from
the old group to all eight lanes one
instruction second instruction is
compare
against the single register that holds
all eight ids from the new group right
that's basically it
um
you could do it a different way with a
rotate as well but you can do those and
then you you effectively just have a
very small number of
actual tests
right
um so instead of
8 to 8 being 64 tests
eight to eight is only 16 tests
right
um
you know what i'm saying
uh
and so like you know and and that's not
even probably the smartest way like i'd
have to think about
uh other ways you might do it
there's probably
ways that are smarter than that right
um in terms of just the efficiency of
getting things into the right places
in fact
yeah i'm not gonna overthink it but
let's put it this way um there's a bunch
of stuff you could do here right
so you can always be looking for places
where you can do creative stuff if all
you care about and and the same would be
true of this right so this code would
instead of a loop at all this code would
just be one load broadcast so it would
be load this 32-bit value and broadcast
to all lanes of the avx
register and then
one
comp
and one
mask move
right
or move mask
you know what i'm saying um
so rather than literally checking eight
times in a loop
it would be three instructions total
right
because the processor just has to do
those steps anyway you might as well use
the eight lanes
uh
yeah
uh all right
so um that's all i was gonna point out
is that you know these are the sorts of
things that nowadays i just kind of
write everything that way uh and but the
hand made here at co-base is not that
kind of a code base right uh so it's
still scalar
um
but point being this is all we really
need is what we have here that's the
entirety of the code and really uh all
we need to i mean we have to debug it
and make sure it works and all that but
that's really all we need
the optimization will have to come a
little bit later uh this is probably not
gonna work i mean it will because
computers are so freaking fast but it's
very wasteful
the number of checks that will actually
get done here is vastly more than need
to happen
so uh when we actually do also we should
probably check to make sure that
collisions are on for the second
uh person because i like
i assume event on collision or something
i i don't know like let's just look at
what these are but we need a flag that
says whether or not you're somebody who
actually does it so it looks like these
are not even used anymore right so maybe
when i say remove we actually just
remove these because they really are
remove a bull right
so if we do if we remove that flag that
collision flag no one cares if we remove
allows motion on collision
um that's a thing so what does that mean
uh
allows motion on collision
is there here
and here
but
i
so i think that's because we had yeah i
think we can just get rid of that as
well because we don't care about those
collision volumes at all
because they're not set uh
for the things we actually care about so
i think we want to set these things that
are going to get collided with
need to be sort of marked as such
so
let's actually take a look here
at how we want to do this i don't really
know oh let's take a look at sphere
collision as well so suppose we remove
a sphere collision
what does that look like
so it looks like the glove is set to
sphere collision um and so i'm gonna get
rid of that as well because i just don't
care about this stuff right now um so
we're just gonna leave it like this
so we got rid of those that we were from
the old stuff we now have a collider uh
i wanna i think i want um
like collision receiver
or receives collision
you know what i mean and like applies
collision or something like that
because we sort of have this you know
it's a little bit idiosyncratic in this
game
it's just kind of the way the game
design sort of wants to be
for lack of a better term that we've got
things that are supposed to be doing
hits
and things that are supposed to be
receiving hits and they're not the same
things right like sometimes in a more
like physics-y based game
you know what i mean
you don't have really that dichotomy
like everything is kind of just involved
in the physics but in this game it's
like very regimented like things hop
around on squares and that's separate
from like these gloves or bullets or
whatever there's gonna be that are
completely different um so some games
are like that and some games aren't in
this case i think our game is basically
um
it's the kind of game where you
you manually say in the design
specifically these things
are
going to apply collision they go out
into the world and hit things and then
these other things receive collision and
they're not the same right
so i think we effectively want it that
way where we say you've got to mark
anything that shoots it's an implies
collision anything that gets hit is a
receives collision uh and that's just
non-negotiable assuming those two things
are true then we call the like collision
resolve
with the projectile and the thing that
the projectile hit
and we probably want to pass the sim
region as well uh
i don't know what else we would
necessarily do oh we can eliminate that
now too can't we
um we can receive the sim region
and
i don't think we need anything else
um
so we'll just
tack that on there in case because we
might need that for like spatial queries
or whatever
so i don't know that we have anything
like this i think we did have a little
thing for a collision resolution before
maybe
um i it may have gotten removed
i don't remember
um
you don't
so this oh
yeah yeah
i was gonna say when we were doing this
i was like didn't we have a thing for
this already we did a long time ago the
pairwise collision rule thing
remember this
um i don't think we ever actually saved
that
like it's not it doesn't exist anymore
but the this part of it remained
you remember this
long ago like we had a little sword
thing long long long long ago
right
so we can't punch no you can punch trees
you just have to mark them as punchable
right
the designer chooses the designer
chooses whether you can punch trees is
what i'm what i'm trying to say right
like
if the designer says you can punch trees
then you can punch trees if they don't
then you can't right
it's not that
everything always gets punched
uh and
you know
then the designer sets the punch damage
to zero for the tree or something like
that right they literally say for every
type of thing in the game whether it's
something that gets punched right
but you can set the trees to punchable
that's totally fine right there's no
uh there's nothing wrong with that this
is this is all old code too particles
like we have a full particle thing now
so that's not
a thing anymore
um
all this old stuff
uh anyway so i don't know that we have
uh
the yeah the collision stuff
um
i don't know that can collide really
gets used anymore either uh so i'm gonna
sort of get rid of that
uh and it's just down to resolving
collisions
resolving collisions we don't really
have uh
anything
at the moment
i
you know that's this is going to get
complicated in here for sure
so assuming that we have an applier and
a receiver this is where the collision
you know resolution code would happen
it's going to get a lot more complicated
for right now i guess we would just
reduce the hit points
of the receiver
which
uh
you know
is some
simple
value here like
we don't even really know
what's going on here
um
do we already have code for this from a
ancient like day you know
show me all the hit point code
so this draws the hit points
that initializes hit points but no
there's no code for it
so basically we can just do whatever we
want here i have no idea how this code
is supposed to work or what it's
supposed to do
i assume that hit point max
so if we want to remove a hit point from
somebody
these hit points are like whether or not
they're full is like in their
filled amount
um
like who knows what the heck i have no
idea what any of this stuff does
so let's start with this let's start by
uh maybe we'll make one of those little
snake dudes well first of all i need
some hit points i mean i guess i want to
always win my own game right
so we should make me have infinite hit
points or something uh which is what i
have now but you know in order to make
the game any fun the hero's gotta have
to be able to die
um
so those snake pieces all have little
hit point
placeholder markers below them right
those are little like temporary there's
little boxes
that we drew
uh to show that there were hit points
on the stupid snake thing that always
gets stuck in the corner he sticks his
own self in the corner
um
so the stupid snake thing already has
hit points and so when i hit one of
those snake pieces there
uh we want to do something with the hit
points
right
and
i mean presumably we just start with the
dumbest thing which is that when you hit
you take away a hit point
and these are probably going to get a
lot more complicated over time i don't
know what the heck hitpoint sub count is
i mean what did i do right the game or
something
i
so what is it
so it looks like hitpoint sub count is
just the name that we gave to how filled
hit points get
i guess so it's like the subdivisions
right that's really what it is let's
let's name it a little more clearer
right
so it's saying that like a hit point has
this many like sub hit points
you know what i'm saying
um
that's actually true sagan
or sagia and sorry
i i literally tried to download people
watched me do it on stream i assume you
were there
i tried to download i was like i want to
play minecraft you know it's one of the
most popular games in the world i like
to play it i tried to buy it i put in my
credit card number it didn't work i
tried paypal that didn't work so i've
still never played minecraft
i've bought
dozens of games
since then with the same credit card
but like microsoft couldn't figure it
out they were like we do not know how to
charge a credit card to buy minecraft
like we're never gonna know sorry we
tried their own browser we tried edge
they wrote the browser
well they didn't write it they rebundled
it
but it's the one they shipped
like like if they don't test edge what
do they test it's the one they ship with
windows
so i tried it on both that and firefox
if i remember correctly and neither
could do it and i tried both paypal and
their built-in credit card thing and
neither of those worked so just like all
right
great
i guess i'm never playing minecraft i
don't care
i probably wouldn't even like minecraft
so it doesn't matter
but
it's just kind of lame because like i
wanted to just see minecraft
and microsoft couldn't do it like they
that was way too much for them to charge
a credit card and give you an executive
they had no idea how that would happen
right
um all right so we want to go to the
receive
the receive or guy here and this is not
really what we want to do all the time
because there's going to be plenty of
times when this isn't the case
um but like i guess i'm just going to
maybe i'll do like an apply damage call
just anticipating the fact
that i'm going to want to be able to do
this at different times it's a little
it's getting a little bit ahead which i
don't normally like to do
um
but i just kind of know that i i
you know will will want to be able to do
this right
so if i take an entity i want to be able
to apply some damage and we don't really
know how damage is uh
going to like
affect right this you know
we don't know how we're going to record
damage or store damage or any of those
sorts of things so we're still in the
early days of that sort of stuff because
against game design it's not really what
i do
but uh we know here we could just say
like
you know there's a count for now
just how much damage and maybe for now
the count's just one
because i mean
we
again don't know so we're gonna fill
this in
as we start to like add random gameplay
features i just go in here and you know
monkey with this until we have some
better idea of like what's actually
going on when you apply damage right
so now in here we go to the hit points
and i think what we do is we walk
backwards i mean i don't really know um
like i said before we've got these hit
points and there's flags the flags are
not defined anywhere as far as i can
tell so there's no actual
flags or anything like that
um and then we have this filled amount
here right
uh
and
i think the idea
is that eventually this is kind of going
to be like a thing
where
you
[Music]
you know like you can have
properties attached to the hit point
um
[Music]
that kind of thing there's nothing
uh
there's nothing there
uh yet right we haven't even we don't
even have like a guess as to what that
would be because again that's game
design not programming
um so
that's like more like what do you want
uh if that makes sense
so
we're only really looking at filled
amount
and presumably this goes from the back
for like downward
i assume
uh so we would do something like uh
the hit point max well i guess i don't
know maybe it's drawn in the other order
i guess i don't know
what order is it drawn in
if hit point max is greater than or
equal to one
otherwise known as greater than zero
um
the health index is less than the max
and we
plus plus it
we
draw the filled amount
um so i don't know
how we want to do this exactly i'm going
to just type in some garbage first
and i'm going to say like all right
hitpoint index is equal to the hit point
max
like -1
[Music]
and
in this case i guess we would have to
step back down through it this way
it's kind of ugly right but i think this
is roughly what you'd have to do i
which is why i say maybe it should be
stored in the other order so that it's
easier to work with this way
but we'll see
anyway so we have hit points
uh and these
is it hit point
it is
uh so we have like entity hit points
and we want to see like okay we have
some count that we're going to decrement
here
and
i guess what we would say is in here we
also want to say that count is not zero
right
so
because we're going to take off as many
hit points like by subtracting them from
the thing as we go applying it each
individual time
and another way to say that is we may
want this to be
like a more like a for loop um
i don't know we'll see because
if you actually want to do this you may
want to do it each time like in other
words
this supply damage
may be more like something you call
repeatedly because too much logic has to
occur so you don't pass like a number
you know what i mean
so it's hard to say
i i'm i'm
i'm not sure
uh
i i think i might say that you call it
repeatedly i think that's what you're
gonna do because this will end up being
very complicated with like a bunch of
flags and crap for each hit so if you're
applying more than one of those i think
they probably have to be called multiple
times to do different logic
probably
i don't really know this is not going to
be a performance bottleneck because the
amount of damage that gets supplied on
any given frame is fairly low
even if it's in like the hundreds it's
not going to be a big deal one way or
the other so i think it's probably
doesn't really matter
anyway
so we
look at the last hit point here we say
like if
um
hit
and there's this like filled amount i
guess
so if hit filled amount we subtract
right
and break and that's it
i think
so that's applying damage uh we applied
damage to the receiver always
um
and now in order to make this do
anything we would have to we probably
are going to you know need to do stuff
like apply some reaction stuff and spawn
particles and all that kind of stuff but
for right now
um we just want to get this to a point
where it does
the actual gameplay action so in
adblayor
with the glove
we would have to order in
um the entity flag
of
applies collision
and for something like a monstar
i
like in here
we would need
uh so okay
where's the snake there it is i'm like
we know there's a snake in here
somewhere uh so for the snake anything
in here we would need to add the
like for the head
um
we would put in receives collision
uh and for the segment same
so now in theory the glove can punch and
the snake can receive punches
again totally in theory
um but again just sketching out what
this should look like so we can start to
build like a little sort of system for
crossing
uh gameplay style events
right
uh and we should put a snake in the room
with us here so that we can not have to
hop around on tiles to open up the door
um but let's see if we can punch this
thing here
hopefully this guy will get himself
trapped in a corner again um
it was a mistake to make the thing
multiple times this thing doesn't draw
differently if you
if you uh
it doesn't look like it though like it
doesn't look like i'm getting any uh off
of it it doesn't draw until you would
hit four times right because those would
be set to four but doesn't look like it
so let me see if we're getting an
interrupt in the collision uh or not
so in
well
so in applied damage for example you can
see it's not triggering right
so we're not actually doing it and we're
not sure why let's see if we ever
actually process
any colliders at all would be the next
thing
so in here where we're doing the entity
update
um
so we are checking
right like someone's checking
because we're getting into this code
uh is anyone getting here
and part of that is i gotta go check to
make sure any of these things have
collision volumes because they might not
uh in which case that's kind of why
right
in fact we can do that pretty easily by
just turning on collision volume drawing
so in the world mode uh not world mode
in the nd code uh there's at the end
there's the thing that draws collision
volumes
um it's that
um
so
here are the collision volumes in the
game
and
that has collision volume
oh the glove's collision volume is
weirdly like not attached to the glove
i guess i know why that would be
but
it doesn't matter because that's still
obviously colliding
right
um
we'll work on that in a second isn't it
oh no it's not
yeah it is no that is that is
that's still obviously colliding i was
like i thought it was too low at first
there but it's it's fine
so it's obviously colliding so we have a
the overlap code is like busted or
something right like you can see that
that's obviously colliding and should
produce a collision somehow
i assume that means this isn't working
because i assume we set
this receives collision um
so that it would be the entity overlaps
entity code that's not working but i
guess i don't actually know that i mean
maybe that flag isn't set but i'm pretty
sure we just like we literally just set
that code
in the snake
you know that's
not supposed to be equals that's
supposed to be or equals
by the way
we should probably make an add flag
function so that i don't accidentally
make that typo
since we've already seen me make it once
you can certainly make it again uh
anyway
so i think
uh
we
need to go find out
uh maybe if there's something wrong with
that uh over entity overlap
code
i guess
um
that looks
extremely straightforward
so
that's
kind of weird
let's
double check
um
like that's very weird wouldn't you say
it sure looks like that should be firing
let's double check here
we've got this
this check here
um
what i'm wondering is like should we
just separate this out like so
that way i can see where we actually get
in here
um because because now i'm just not sure
so i'd like to know you know whether
this
we also need these to not be equal the
same person
so basically as long as this thing can
receive collision and
uh
we the projectile ids are set
right um
that seems like something we want
yeah is there an ad flags
there is i like that we should have a
function that does this
parenthesis we already do i just didn't
call it
that was pretty funny
i like that
you know that function we should have
that function yeah we do have that
function you just didn't call it
um
so
i suppose if i really wanted to do it i
could change the flags to be like flag's
underscore so that it's like
clear that you should not be using it
directly but i don't know that i want to
go that far
that might be a bit much
okay so what
is the problem here
i want to know forever getting in here
that's not a good sign
why can i not set any breakpoints in
there
what
is there something really
is there something really stupid going
on here where it is optimized the whole
thing out because i typed something
stupid
or is that just like a debugger trick
i'll have to go look at the assembly in
a second i mean i can do it a different
way than that as well but
i don't know why that was up
for what it didn't need to be but that's
not a problem
if the projectile id and the check id
are not equal which is true almost all
the time
right
it was a typo
good on the compiler for optimizing that
out bad on me for having the typo
uh alright so
[Music]
uh we really need to put a snake in this
in fact let's just do that because any
time i restart the game i saw they
didn't really need to restart the game
for that but
i do like to restart the game
now and again and i don't want to have
to hop
around to get all that stuff for no
particular reason
so in world
gen
i don't even remember like
why it's set up this way probably
because we wanted to hop on things
ourselves and not have the snake
hop on them
i'm guessing
um
i i actually don't even really know
but
um
so when we create the dungeon
i
i guess
the floor entrance room
is
well why yeah what kind of room is this
why is this room this way
also we need to stop having box index
down as a thing
because we don't have that anymore
but uh yeah i'm not sure
you can see what we do here we
uh
when we place
the hero it's in dungeon entrance room
right so the entrance room
uh
is this floor entrance room which is
this thing
and
i guess i'm not sure
i guess i'm not sure why it doesn't have
a snake i guess
because we only add snakes to the rooms
after it
so if we wanted to add a snake i guess
we would just do this
um
why is that able to hop
through me i wonder oh because it
started on top of me interesting we have
to fix that
all right so we should now be able to
figure out why we can't punch these
things hopefully i mean maybe
right um
right so that's
clearly going through
right so let's take a look at what
happens breakpoint wise here
so
pointer and check the two entities here
uh we want to see if we get here we do
now do we ever get here
we do
so
we're actually
we're actually calling the collision
resolution function apparently
but it doesn't look like that function
ever actually does anything
yeah it doesn't think it doesn't think
this is a thing
that it needs
ah
how did it
so
how did this work like
it's supposed to be that
what did the compiler do with that
exactly
do i even want to know i probably don't
and i still can't set a breakpoint here
so it still doesn't think it needs to
call that function
right
so what did it actually do
it has the notion that let's see if we
can just look at what the disassembly is
there like what actually happens right
here
like nothing
all right so something's up with apply
damage
right something's up with this that it
thinks so if entity hit point max is
greater than zero
hit point index equals the hit point max
minus one
hit point index is greater than or equal
to zero and you subtract down
[Music]
we look at the hit point if it is filled
we subtract it
doesn't look
obviously ridiculous
that's a bit odd
say that
say that much
all right so
i'm gonna look at this in debug mode
because i don't understand exactly what
the compiler is doing there so i must
have had a typo somewhere in there
uh we'll find out in a second
all right
uh so
you know slow slow debug mode
so here's collision resolve
uh
we step in
to apply damage and we look at the
entity
the
uh hit point max is three
right so we would go in here
we then set the hit point index so the
index should be two right
um
right
uh that means we'll get the
the last hit point
the filled amount is four
we subtract it to get 3
we break out
of the loop
and that's
i mean
that's exactly what we assume
would happen
um
so now i'm a little confused
because that's like the correct behavior
right um
so yeah
uh
what's up with that is there something
weird going on in there that i'm not
thinking of like so now
this should be
able to punch these guys and they should
be
they should go down
uh
four punches should remove one
of the little
uh hearts on there
and
you know in debug mode it's kind of hard
to do because the lighting
is too slow so it takes yeah so it works
all right so it works just fine i guess
let's see if release mode was just the
assembly was just done in a really
strange way or something i don't know if
i believe that but
so it works
all right
so i guess the assembly just i optimized
it into the loop in a way that was like
going to be kind of hard for me to read
i guess because i didn't immediately see
it but i guess it's just simple enough
that that's what happened
all right so you can
punch out these dudes here
um and that's fine
right uh
and uh
and there you go
presumably we need a thing where like if
the damage goes to zero
so like if
entity
hit point zero
equals
you know
or rather hit point zero filled amount
equals zero
then this entity has to die
probably
right
and
i don't actually know
i also kind of feel like this probably
was annoying so i'm just gonna do this
for now
because we're going to want to do this
this sort of crap
so do we have like a is
like some kind of way of testing if an
entity is still valid because we don't
really need to do any of this work if
the entity like already died or things
like that
um but i don't actually know we probably
want to introduce that now because
gameplay is going to care about that in
a lot of places but i don't know if we
really have anything like that um
so we should probably add something like
that like there should be a thing here
that's like
um if you know
is
active or something
so like these things
are only happening you know they have
these checks for whether or not an
entity should should be doing stuff or
not
and that would be
that the flags
are set a certain way
so like in the entity itself
you've got uh
if
entity flags deleted
and active
right
has to just be equal to active
i think that's basically what we want
critical hits
probably not um
because
that's very game designy like i don't
really understand like entropy in game
design
a critical hit is basically just a way
of
having a average amount of damage that's
not equal to
the
n like so
a critical hit is basically when you say
normally if i have 10 hits
and the average damage is
you know let's say 40
then each hit did four damage right a
critical hit is a way of making the
average damage still be 40
but some of the hits are worth two and
some of the hits are worth eight
right
so it's a way of
it's a way of making a non-linear it
makes it non-linear the fun the function
right of
the non-monotonic the damage over time
it goes like that right
um
which i'm sure is like very important to
like crafting certain kinds of
experiences and if you're like a really
like if you're a game designer who's
like really into game design stuff
uh you would know when you need that um
but i don't know
those kinds of things that's game design
not game programming
right um
and so uh
yeah
so
uh i probably wouldn't implement
critical hits because i wouldn't know
what to do with them right like
you know i mean i guess i could
implement them just to implement them
but i wouldn't actually have any idea
what to do with it i you know what i
mean
uh all right so we need on entity
deletion right now we don't de-occupy
their square it's like i can't still
occupy it right so we kind of need to
like clean that stuff up
right um
but but this basically works now
yeah
uh so that's good um
[Music]
when an entity gets removed i don't even
know uh
when we do that but i believe it's in
the sim region
maybe not is it in the world says stuff
so when an entity is deleted it the
remove from unpacked flag gets set and
that's that's when it
that's when it goes away
right
so in delete entity uh i would assume
like right there we would probably want
to free up
it's
it's traversable
so like in transactional occupy occupy
this part here
so i'm not sure
i like test wall
so much stuff in here from the old days
yeah test wall is not still a piece of
this code
um
so i'm not sure i'm not sure about the
how traversables we probably want to
clean that up too because i don't even
know if we really need them anymore
because when we switch to the grid we'll
get rid of them but for now you can see
what happens so we say here's where we
want to go
i
and
that's all fine but
what we really care more about here is
where we're coming from
[Music]
um so it's this one and it what we
basically do here is say clear
so i guess it's the clear function on
these these particular occupiers
um
which of course we can't find because
for some reason
uh four quarter does not like to list
the actual thing that you would need to
know um
which is what the parameter of the
function was
so
uh
yeah i don't know
is it just literally that
so what what that's like all that gets
cleared in transaction i guess that's
all that needs to get cleared
so i guess we would we just it's
literally this like
so in delete entity uh we just say
well
get the traversible for
uh
this sim region
and this uh
reference so the entity you know
occupying
we then say if there was one
uh
basically this is like
our vacate right we're leaving this now
um we just clear it
so entity traversable point
this thing
um
the preview occupier and occupier i
don't actually know what the heck prev
occupier
uh
why we need that
but
it's basically this
um now since that's used in two places
i'll probably make it just a single
thing
so
you know
maybe we just have a thing here that's
like vacate
um
where we just do this operation
so
the mover ref
is just the traversable reference i
guess so it's it's not quite that so
it's like that
uh this code can now just be used in
both places so we just say like look
vacate
this mover ref thing
right
um
and then this code is used in here
and can be used in here so we just call
vacate sim region
entity
occupying
now i don't know that we need to pass it
as an address because we never write to
it so i think it can actually be done
that way
so it would look more like
this
but otherwise it's the same
identifier not found
what
well fine then
meow meow meow meow meow meow meow
okay
so i believe we can now
properly play through
um and so yeah we're unfortunately we're
rapidly going to be moving into the part
of the situation where we have to do
some design
stuff now
um which is fine
but we can clear these guys now
right um
technically although we would want to
really like
do a much better job on the av of that
so that it feels good to punch people
but
so that feels good to punch people you
know just like in real life
um
so
uh we yeah we need to like um
do a bunch of work on the presentation
of it but
thus far
we now don't really have to worry too
much about getting through a dungeon we
can punch people
technically
uh we should probably
make there be a way for us to get hit
obviously
that's probably
the next obvious thing to do
which is presumably just getting hit by
enemies
that hop into the square with us
i guess
right
i don't know
um and there's another thing we have to
do as well which is that the glove
may not do damage all the time so when
the glove is returning from a punch it
shouldn't do damage right
um so we're gonna have to change the
flag stuff uh to be a little bit more
dynamic like maybe the glove gets its
flag set depending on what move state
it's in
or something like that right
um
so that seems fine
um we should also stop
stop the violence uh we should stop
drawing the um
we should stop
like having the box down stuff on
generation
like because we can't
we can't go up and down anymore right we
decided to we pulled that out so
the direction stuff
the box direction
um
i don't remember what it's called
direct no
it's like direction something
um which i don't remember what it is but
basically like the box down thing
uh
in
here box index down whatever that is
is not a thing anymore
this
right
so box index up and down
um
that
isn't a thing anymore
so we kind of want to get rid of it i
mean i don't know
who uses it exactly
but we probably don't want it
anywhere
anymore
maybe
not really sure
all right
um
so i think we can just pretty much
remove them it doesn't look like anybody
uses it right
so we can say those go away
uh and these go away
we can check this and say that it's
um
[Music]
not really sure why that was
checking against box index up when
there's already a box index count
but
yeah i don't know about that it's a bit
suspicious
um
get rid of this
i guess this is gonna be
down so if we're connecting the room
above and it's saying it's a downward
connection this would probably be a
northward connection and it's not room
above anymore
obviously
uh
this
is just
not a thing
you can't have stairwells
um and so now i think we have the
problem of our room packer as crappy as
it is is just gonna run out of
uh
to do right like it's not gonna it's
gonna assert that it runs out of room
because it's super terrible
um
which is not really a huge deal
where's our generate world thing
because we know we have to fix that
anyway but
uh in the interim so i just want to get
rid of those and then
i i don't know
i'm gonna set the floor count to one
because we gotta redo this code anyway
so let's see if it packs a single floor
correctly with a super crappy nonsense
no it doesn't
so
you can see like the problem here is the
layout thing being as dumb as it is it
just puts in the rooms and can't find a
place to put
the rooms when it can't go down
right um at least i believe that's what
that's
telling it right
um
don't quote me on that
so
yeah like
really just
the issue is this
system being crappy
it should be able to do this but it
can't
and we can make something a lot nicer
here now especially because it's not 3d
anymore
it makes that a lot easier as well but
so in the layout code
this right here
is
the
the test to see whether or not it was
able to place the room
i believe
yeah because here's it trying
then this is it failing
and basically like you know normally if
you want this code to work well at all
you need it to place things in a way
that if it can't place something it just
tries again or doesn't
uh do it right
and
in our case it's not so you could just
say like all right look there's no room
it doesn't matter
um
and that's fine for now uh but really we
we want to change the way this code
works in the future anyway uh yeah and
the other thing too is it has to check
to make sure that there actually is a
room to place it in later
i don't really like the way this code
works and i never have because it it's
maybe a little bit too much
right
like it's just
it's not explicit enough it's very like
vague like oh just here's some rooms
that we want you to like lay out
and it just doesn't seem
like it just seems too complicated so
you end up having to like buffer
everything into basically an ir like
there's this intermediate language for
uh what rooms you want like in this case
you know what i'm saying
and like i guess that's okay i don't
know it just seems kind
of it seems like it's going to be too
hard to get the results we want out of
it you know what i mean
uh and so i feel like something that's
just more immediate
would be better where you just like
generate stuff and it can do little like
look-aheads if it needs to but mostly
it's just hand-coded how it generates
things
it just seems better
because we already have to do we have to
do all this like buffering right and it
just doesn't it just feels like over
complicated for what it's going to
eventually do
i we don't
have this problem anymore
um
so like
the spec that whole thing like that that
sort of spec
thing
is is what i mean right like i feel like
we can do better than that
by just getting rid of those and doing
it immediately so like when you
start to do the layout you just actually
do the layout
in immediate calls so for example when
you're gonna do create orphanage instead
of having to do the spec first each of
these calls actually just generates the
actual room
right
and so the downside of doing that is
that you
need to have some ability to do uh
pre-knowledge
of where things might be
so that you can make connections between
them but
uh
that i don't think that will be that
hard
in principle right like we can do little
things that look ahead as necessary but
then you don't have this whole
nonsense there's so much right like
going on in here that's all of this
stuff could have just been
direct
you know what i mean
um
yeah so i i just feel like it's kind of
stupid is i guess what i'm trying to say
like like i feel like
we should be able to make it so that we
create what we need to
uh
at the time
you know what i mean
and
i feel like that was just a better
approach this is like too it's too
advanced and you could imagine doing it
this way
you're just you have a tremendous amount
more work and it's not entirely clear
why
like
won't we end up having to make this
really like powerful generation system
but why did we do that right because we
know we're only ever gonna do this one
thing
so it it's just gonna create a lot of
work but we're not gonna get like the
benefit out of that work you know what
i'm saying because just hand coding the
one we actually wanted to generate
would actually
be less work in total over time
is i guess what i'm saying
so like if you imagine just like
sketching this out
so that it's it's doesn't do
as stupid as it is right it's less dumb
um so
yeah and like all this stuff is the same
way right like
you could still
you could still do
this
meaning
you could still
defer placement of npcs until the end
because you literally just build that
list
right
um
and then randomly pick from the list
uh
but otherwise i think you can just you
could just do this more straight ahead
so i think i might just do that
right
so
so yeah like supposed
let me think about this for one second
so there is like one kind of weirdness
this has very little to do with
the actual
so one thing that's kind of a little bit
weird is
the generating the like sort of forest
area
is a little bit different than
generating dungeon areas in that maybe
we just want that area to be like not
room based because that area could
be
um
yeah
that that part's a little harder to
think through because if you didn't want
it to be room based you kind of have
this weird
notion of like where
i think maybe so
i think maybe this is maybe i shouldn't
start on this just and and we should
just do this is what we do next week
entirely
um
so it's been like two hours i think
right
um
i think that's what i want to do i think
that's what i want to do so i think what
we want to do next time
is we want to like do the world gen
because basically now we need that like
as we're doing game design stuff we're
gonna need to actually design rooms
because they're not gonna like
combat's not gonna make any sense
outside of the context of like what
you're actually fighting in
so i think we wanna do
is up the world gen next time
and massively simplify that down the
room based stuff i think is pretty
simple because there's just not a lot to
it
the thing that is tricky is the forest
because the forest is kind of just
continuous
right and we could
like we could make it still be rooms
and maybe we should
for just for simplicity's sake that's
the way like the original legend of
zelda was for example right
but
on the other hand maybe we don't want to
do that or maybe we want them to still
be generated as if they are rooms sort
of but the rooms are very large
you know what i'm saying
so i think we want to think
that
through
look i think we want to go ahead and
think that through
um
let's think about that over the course
of the week and we come back and start
programming next weekend
have some kind of an idea in our head
about how we want the forest to work and
that sort of stuff
um
so we'll do that
i think that's the plan
i don't suppose um
i don't suppose john
uh
got back yet
did he
no he's not streaming or anything he's
probably on a plane
um
all right so yeah i think that's
i think that's what we want
and that's what we're gonna do next week
that's my story and i'm sticking to it
okay
uh yeah all right so that's we're gonna
do i'm gonna leave this like this and
we're gonna basically delete 90 of this
code
uh in the
uh in the room gen stuff and take the
stuff that we do have and repurpose it
so that we can get that stuff working
more
uh like well
right
and have a clearer
sort of
understanding of how that's gonna work
but most of that
room gen code's gonna go away
uh because most of it's just not
necessary i think it was too complicated
and
like we could go down that route but
it's just not
i don't think it's what we want
so
all right that's it for today
um i will see everyone back here next
week when we will uh take a look at
at you know improving that room gen
stuff to something that i think is
usable
uh until then
have fun program everyone and i'll see
you on the internet take it easy
everybody