hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show Rico to complete game live
on stream uh we are just about to I
guess I don't want to say wrap up but
we're sort of coming to a junction point
here we we finished moving everything
over to this concept of these sort of
impromptu created controller structures
that we called brains and those seem to
be working ok now but we we have some
more like kind of entity partitioning
work that we want to do and you know we
started down a path at the very end of
last stream of like pulling out the
concept of how a particular entity gets
rendered as well and so we've kind of
you know we're kind of at a place where
we're starting to pull new things in the
mix so we want to kind of just continue
that process and we'll see what kind of
comes out of it in terms of what the
next major area we want to tackle is now
I want to address some things but let me
first say this is day 29 tso day 289
source code is the source code that you
want to start with so the first thing
that I'll say is in the pre stream busy
beever brought up a good point which is
that we have a sort of late a bug in
waiting let's say a bug that is waiting
to be a problem it's not a problem right
now because we are not real actually
doing like the stuff that would be
necessary to cause it to to to bite us
but it's definitely there and it's
because of the sort of changes that
we've made recently we haven't gone back
and revisited the way that we're
actually doing or begin sim and sim
steps so what I'd like to do here is
just go ahead and take care of that so I
what the bug is is remember we now move
to a system where we load chunks in we
pull in all the entities from them then
we simulate those entities and then we
write them back out to the chunks what
this means is that we destroy the chunks
as we go because of course we're
intentionally not going to pack anything
back into those chunks as we pulled
everything out of it but we left in
place the entity overlaps rectangle call
to sort of trim the bounds which now
means that certain entities that fail
that check
will not get streamed in and hence be
sort of silently deleted right they'll
just go away because we pulled them out
of there chunk but we never actually
record them and so the bug fix is
obviously trivial there really isn't
anything to it we can actually just
delete this code because it's
unnecessary code but it is important to
do so otherwise eventually we would have
this problem where we would suddenly
lose some entities on the periphery and
we would wonder why so a really good
catch by busy beaver there saved us a
bunch of time I suspect because we would
have had to hunt for that in the future
and feel like what's going on so that
really shouldn't affect anything right
now that's just like sort of going in
there and sort of trying to make sure
that we don't have a bug later I don't
know I should double-check to make sure
that identity itself always does uh does
like the appropriate add as well Matt I
pulled my shoulder and really bugging me
it's just it's always there you know
it's always like ah anyway so if i go
through begin same and just look at
what's happening here pretty much we go
through all the entities and we always
add them unless we hit our max entity
count cap and that's an invalid code
path for us so we're going to want to
make sure that that can never happen but
other than that we are always going to
add it so even if we if it doesn't
overlap our simulation rectangle we
still keep it we just marked this
unobtainable now I don't know if that's
still going to be a thing but it's at
least not going to prevent the entity
from being loaded which is all we care
about all right so that takes care of
that now we need to kind of go back to
what we were doing before now you'll
remember what we'd started yesterday was
we started making entities get rendered
in a more procedural way and less
hard-coded I shouldn't same procedure
maybe let's say data-driven way and less
about a hard-coded function that says
how they're going to be rendered and you
can see that the trees are back to the
to the way that they were and they are
the that's what we did the last dream
they are the only entities
now going through this path and so what
we want to do is now we want to sort of
move all of the other entities over
until we're left with no entities still
being rendered via the old path if that
makes sense so let's go ahead and see if
we can figure that out you know what
someone else mentioned by the way on the
forums I should also take care of
another bug while we're here it was a
real simple one it's in brain actually
there was a bug in this code that we
sort of haven't really we haven't really
gotten to the point where this code is
really doing anything at the moment but
we need to now use the DDP too because
we need a three dimensional vector here
and we were we were still looking at
this one which is only two dimensions we
were kind of reading off the end which
could have given us like complete bogus
results there right so yeah so that was
that was the only thing with that anyway
so yeah so anyway we got mr. mr. tude
moving around here but everyone like I
said besides the trees are still going
through the old render path so what I
want to do is see if we can get a you
know all the other people through that
same render path that we were using
before and you can see how that render
Pat path works right we've got it's um
this is all kind of dead code
I so you can see how that path works up
here it just loops through the number of
things that has to draw just like the
way everything else works pretty much I
might put draw hit points kind of here
so we have the other loops we could also
just move draw hit points right down in
here if we wanted to but anyway you can
kind of see how this works we have some
set of pieces for each individual entity
and we go through each individual piece
we get a bitmap match out of it and then
we push that bitmap onto the renders you
know into the stack we're using for
rendering and so what that means is most
of these people will probably be fine
like if we take a look at what Monstar
does right Monstar does a shadow and
then a torso right and that seems pretty
straightforward as well so I feel like
we could take care of Monstar and make
Monstar have pieces just the way that
everyone else does right and the same
would probably be true of hero head
right all we would need to do is have
the offset on there which is something
that i can add so let's go ahead and add
that offset in for now so here is right
here's piece offset and that's going to
be something that's probably going to
have to get a little more complicated as
time goes on but we don't want to be too
premature with it so I'm going to wait
till we have a little bit more
information about how we're animating
parts of things because that could
change a little bit so I'm not going to
get to hog well with that we're just
going to have a single offset for now
knowing that that will probably have to
get a little bit more complicating the
future because we're going to probably
want more than just a static offset as
we want to kind of make more more things
animate right so we'll kind of when we
do the hero will get a little insight
into that but we may need to go even
further than that to really know what
we're doing and what would be
applications in that scenario alright so
now we've got that piece offset
happening there and I'm just going to go
make sure that that's handled properly
so you can see here in ad piece what I
want to do is add that the offset part
in here and maybe that happens right
here I'm
sure but I'll just go ahead and say that
those for now oops so we'll say height
piece offset equals offset and then when
I compile i would expect an error here
because we're not specifying it so now i
just have to say well the offset here at
000 and that's all good now in that case
what i want to do is I want to start
expanding now that I know that that
that's you know all better i guess i'll
double check that it actually is and
remember every time we change the data
layout we don't have data safe reloading
so we just have to restart the game if
we change the data layout code week in
hot load but but data changes we don't
handle or Sega sized data changes so
anyway in this case you can see we're
still drawing the trees properly and
everyone else too let's go ahead and and
the Mon star in here so we'll make an ad
piece call for the Mon star and here's
that Mon star and what I need to do is
go into the monster our code that it was
using in World mode and just grab out
what it was doing here with this with
these bitmaps right so I should be able
to just say okay you know there's the
Mon star and we're going to say that
there's a push bitmap call which now
becomes an ad piece call and these
things are obviously based on the entity
and then we know that this is an asset
shadow in one case and an asset torso in
the other case right and then we know
that the offsets are whatever the
offsets actually are and you can see
that there don't appear to be any actual
offsets for the Mon star so we really
shouldn't have to to deal with anything
there now I don't know where shadow
alpha was defined must be somewhere up
here okay should be computed after the
update yeah so this is shadow alpha I
don't know what exactly we want to do
with that probably this show
ohs are going to have to be special
cased and so I'm not going to super care
about that right now but eventually
we're going to care about that so I'm
going to say that the Monstar since it's
on the ground at the moment is going to
have a no point five but i'm going to
say here something like to do casey
shadows should be handled especially
because they need their own pass
technically as well so we're probably
gonna have to tag things that are
shadows on the ground because that's
going to be something that is the
renderer eventually the final very final
version of the renderer with all the
tweaks will need to know that that
things are shadows especially it won't
be able to just treat them as normal
objects because there's you know if two
shadows overlap they don't necessarily
double darken it will depend on like how
what the rule is and what's actually
happening there we may need to do more
complicated things to get the look that
we want in those circumstances so yeah
that's all we really need to do here
we've got we don't need the tree
obviously so we've got the shadow and
the torso I is it true that the shadow
is 4.5 is that actually what that is I
don't know we'll find out in a second
here add peace um well you know what let
me just double check with that actually
was supposed to be a bit maps asset
shadow yeah so the shadow is also 4.5 I
guess that's just because hey it should
be the same size as everything else I
guess that makes some sense
who knows alright so we've got our ad
piece call and I just need to make sure
that it's it's right it's the trees
let's see so the entity the type the
height the offset and the color so I
just need to put a color in here and
then we should be good to go so now we
should see a Mon star and we do see the
monster that is the monster right there
that's the monster and yes since we're
not really doing collision at this point
on because we turned all that stuff off
we need to start and this will be
actually a very good thing for us to do
next we need to start having the monster
go through the new movement controllers
as well so we take so he takes ownership
of the square that he's on and so that I
cuz right now I can move right into a
square if i want to write so that's a
not good whereas if i have one of those
like if i actually had someone who is
occupying the square properly that
wouldn't work alright so let's keep
going on that same you know the same
clean up route the Monstar case is now
gone let's go ahead and take the hero
head and and turn that into something
that we can work with as well so when we
do an ad player that's going to have a
thing where we can add the construction
here to make sure that the player also
has render information so here's the
head entity and we have the asset hero
head or just head I guess we've got the
hero sighs see I don't really know what
the hero size even is but I guess we
just kind of made it so it was easier
for us to scale and so I'm just going to
say that that can come up here now and
we'll leave it there temporarily but
i'll do a little to do kc delete this
because once you move everything out of
there the hero size could be something
that's a property of when you're
constructing it and doesn't have to be a
property later right
so we can add this in here and this is
all exactly what we want right all we
need to do now is just have sort of a
color a dummy color that's in there but
otherwise that's all we need to give our
hero a headpiece and so now when we run
hopefully we'll get ahead and there's
the head and it does respond to
directional changes correctly so that's
good too and so another case down which
is cool alright so we're it slowly
winnowing away at these edit e cases
slowly slowly but surely and so now you
can see in here we were down to only two
there's the familiar and there's a hero
body now the familiar in the hero body
are the tough cases for us because the
familiar in the hero body are the ones
that have actual animation right so you
can kind of see in there that there's
sort of been you know there's there's a
certain amount of bending asst that
happens with these you know one of them
one of them kind of was meant to bob up
and down and one of them is meant to be
bendy and so that's information that we
need to capture right we need that to be
reactive and we can't do the same thing
that we were doing for the other
properties of these pieces because the
other properties of these pieces we're
such that you just create a static idea
of relative to the entity what do I need
to know these are actually dynamic than
they have specific ways in which they
kind of need to work right there's all
this logic in there and so I don't know
exactly how we want to deal with that
yet but I suspect what we want to do
here is create sort of a like an
infrastructure for saying when people
move we have a certain sort of armature
understanding of what their parameters
of motion are and then we have ways of
constructing the pieces so that they
latch on to that are mature in a useful
way right this is when people are always
saying about the skeletal animation
stuff like I saying what we're doing is
already skeletal animation for all
intents and purposes we just haven't
systematized it yet so we're just
doing it but you know like the fact that
the the the two pieces of the hero can
bounce that is exactly what skeletal
animation actually is right and so
slowly I'm just kind of moving it out to
see what kind of system we actually want
so what I should be able to do here is
for starters I can i can probably get
rid of this situation like hero bitmaps
we can probably get rid of because you
can see that it's just head caped torso
that's the stuff that we're just putting
in here at that piece of information we
definitely know that we would have so
that's not particularly interesting
right and so I'm going to f0 these guys
out and then I'm going to start by
making pieces that are actually what
should I put it I'm gonna start by
making pieces that are just the static
versions of these guys without the
animation and then we'll figure out how
to get the animation back in right
because we know that part of this is
working the part where we just say that
there is a shadow in a cape or this and
that that stuff will work just fine it's
the rest of the stuff that won't write
it's the movement so we've got the
player we've got the Monstar so inside
the player now this is the head
information i should be able to also now
do add piece on the for the bottom right
i should be able to say okay the body
got has these three things and again the
only real difference here is going to be
the fact that when I'm what I'm creating
these I'm leaving out the animated
portion of them right so this is all you
know this is all the same this shadow
alpha I don't know for now i guess i'll
do a pound to find for it so that we
could find it later because we're going
to pull it out later into something else
so i'm gonna I guess I'm leave it so
that shadow alpha is a is a known
quantity here there we go uh so we
so we know ok so in here what we want to
do is add the pieces out the animation
shadow obviously doesn't have one the
torso does I believe right you can see
that it's right here x-axis and y-axis
so that's the part that we won't be
handling properly right here I don't
know what why color I guess we just set
it to 111 well you know what i could do
i can replicate that it makes sense for
me to replicate that I think and so
again same exact thing that we were
doing before we've got the everything
copied out except that x axis y axis so
we lose that bit of information and
that's one that will have to put back in
and then we've got also here the cape
and the same same diff deal here you can
see that it's got the x-axis y-axis we
don't have that piece of information at
the moment and then we also have this
this notion of this offset here and that
offset with the tea bob is is not going
to get it's not going to get properly
respected either ok so we lose a bunch
of stuff but we can still basically
recreate the thing and so our job will
just be to put it back oops it's not
head so yeah
they go ahead and delete this there we
go okay so now we should have a pretty
much everybody but and you can see that
they're not down there everyone but the
familiar is represented and you can see
that everything still works just fine
it's just we lose that animated those
test animation things we did for our hop
right and it looks a lot stupider now
right so that's you know not good but
that's fine that's what we expected and
so now we just need to finish off the
the the familiar and here's the
familiars code so i'll go up to add
familiar and just do exactly the same
thing that I did before so we'll put
familiar in there this is going to be an
ad piece so is this and in here we just
have entity and this is one of them
shadows nothing particularly teresting
there we lose again the bob sign and
then here we've got again the entity I
don't what does be ID in this case why
were we what was what was that it's just
a head alright and yeah again exact same
thing here so you know we just we don't
really know where it goes all right
um that's really it oops so now
everyone's being recreated properly and
we've essentially gotten rid of that all
of that code right that's now all
procedural and just created so now we
can create any combination of those that
we want right and so what I'm going to
do now is go figure out how to get the
stuff that we missed and put it back in
there now I'm going to do that in the
simplest possible way at first but like
I said as we get a little further down
the road and have some more animating
objects will be able to find out a
little bit more information about how we
want to construct this system to go
beyond just simple pieces right okay so
inside handmade world mode or actually
sorry inside handmade entity I'm just
going to add into this piece the the
most basic thing right which is a look
at entity visible piece sort of I don't
know let's call it a movement or
something and in here we'll just say you
know peace move and you know we'll just
say nun is a rigid it just means you
know it's it's just attached directly to
the frame we could say that there's like
a access to form right so if the entity
axes to form it would deform the thing I
axis X is deform or something like this
and then we should also have one that's
like a bob offset right and these should
probably be tipped you know to think
about these could easily be flagged so
we could just say like hey whichever
ones you want you can have so I can just
say like movement flags and care right
and then we can just so all I'm doing
here is being able to pick up parts of
that code and essentially use it for
what I was doing before so here's my
access to form I know that basically
the familiar had a bobbing head right so
I'll put that in at the end for the
flags on on that guy and similarly the
hero needs both a bobbing torso and a
what was the other one access actually
deforming well I guess it needs the
access to forming a cape and up both of
them you'd axial the form of I member
quickly but only the Cape actually does
the Bob offset right that's my sort of
recollection of it anyway so I'm gonna
leave it at that and assume that that is
good enough so then I'm going to go to
the add piece call and I'm just going to
say okay you know if you add a piece you
can have some flags on the end of it and
then we set it up and so that's all good
and sorry movement flags so that's all
good that's not going to do anything
just setting the flags texture upload
that's not gonna do anything just
setting the flags right because we're
still not obeying those flags but
everything should now be set for us to
actually just use the equations we were
using before base on which flags are in
there right alright so now we can go
ahead and say alright I in this code
where we're looping through the pieces
when I do push fit map I now want to do
essentially the full version of the call
you could see this this one right here
kind of has a full it's everything that
we had been doing previously right it's
got the entity transform it's got the
offset it's got the y bobbing and it's
got the x and y axes right and so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to keep for
now all of these things when I'm going
to grab these guys on here
and I'm just going to say okay so we've
got all of this stuff as the optional
ways in which these things can can
behave and so what I'll do is I'll say
well alright if the if this piece is
flags well here's the easiest way here
we go so to say all right I'll
initialize it and soon that our x and y
axis is our new to our x and y axes are
neutral right then i'll say well okay if
the pieces flags in this particular case
say that we do access to forming then we
want to we want to overwrite whatever
the default axes are with the axes that
come from the entity right otherwise it
won't do that deformation similarly will
say okay we've got this offset here and
we'll say that if and also similarly
Artie Bob value those will both get
initialized to nothing like so and then
what we'll say is well if the piece
flags were supposed to be Bob offset
then we will will use them
and then we should be able to call
essentially the same parameters we were
calling before for everything else but
now right we've got this happening and I
guess that offset value should just have
that some din right okay so there we go
I don't know if we really want to call
those movement flags because I feel like
we'd want to pack all our flags into the
same place so I feel like we should
probably just call it nad visible peace
flag I'm just call this flags and then
everywhere that we were calling it
movement flags which I obviously didn't
even want to do because I never typed
that I always typed it wrong on how to
correct myself we'll bring it back
alright so now you can see we're getting
that hop back in there we're not getting
the torso is not actually deforming
though for some reason I don't know if
you notice that and i'm not sure why so
let me go double check whether it is but
now we can get rid of this switch
statement entirely which is good I know
where I want to put this I'm constantly
not sure where okay so let's go up and
see what I did wrong I assume I did
something wrong I don't know but we'll
find out in a second so both of these
guys have axial deform deformation the
torso and
cave right they both have access to
forum they both have Bob offset so let
me see did I define them correctly I
assume I did yeah and so the way I'm
looking at this is saying oh let's see
if we do access to form x and y and yeah
so that should that should deform both
of those right I'm not sure why it's not
but it's definitely not right you see
the torso is straight up and down oh you
know what it's not deforming I'd room
it's just moving the other one so the
axial deformation is just plain not
working so the question is why
so there's two possible reasons one is
that something is wrong with this code
that's not obvious and the other one is
that we're just not setting them in the
brain or we're setting them on the wrong
person so let's find out
so here we set I don't know why we have
to do set the set construction and then
we don't set it at construction probably
should actually we should probably
actually use our actual comment but we
want to actually have that work so why
did we accidentally delete it I am
confused it looks like we somehow
deleted it right because it's not here
anymore so I must have deleted it at
some point but I'm not really sure when
I did that
hmm I assume this would be a good time
of course I don't really use get usually
so I guess I don't know how to really
figure this out but I'm assuming that in
here I could ask it when we deleted that
line of code but let's let's at least go
back in and see what it was so let's see
here we've got world mode and I'm
assuming that I can get the history for
it so yeah so if I if we go back to
something like you know this code where
we weren't touching anything we should
be well how do I get it to show me just
the file that's not what I wanted oh boy
I just want to see this file at that
version is that this one of those like
oh you wanted to do something that's the
default thing you'd want to do you can't
do that thing what do you get who you
get in here we go this is what I want
browser positive Tory at this point all
right so this is handmade world mode and
so now I can go look at that piece of
code and I don't know why it got deleted
here it is I guess it must have it was
probably sitting down here and it just
got the best they've got I must have
accidentally today just at one point
accidentally so oh well alright so in
the brain here oh no it's right there I
was okay i was just searching for x axis
that's the problem okay that's why it's
gone so i didn't delete it it's right
there alright so the question is why is
this not
to be happening right first of all this
needs to be inside the head code so
that's a bug to begin with oh wait no
that's I guess that's not true never
mind because it does have an if around
it so we compute the head Delta and then
we're setting the body y axis here so I
guess the only bug is that this this is
the bug the fact that this server rights
is every time so really what we have to
do is just go back up to the constructor
and do what we said we were going to do
in there which is when we do begin low
entity and we do the 0 struct we got to
set these to the correct values and
that's really it I think and by the way
why do we still have entity low we got
rid of all that that no longer has to
happen ever okay all right so now we're
properly deforming with the deformable
axis which is good as well and so now
we've gotten rid of all of the things
that were specific to a piece of an
entity in the render code right so the
render code no longer needs the entity
type so the next question is what does
anybody else need the entity type right
so let's start by just going into the
entity and deleting the type and we'll
just see who notices right and we'll see
if anyone cares so it's like all right
gets their ground Wells get stared
around isn't even a thing we're ever
going to have anymore so that doesn't
matter let's see what this is entity
overlaps rectangle oh that must have
been one of those I for kodir has a
weird bug these days where it can't go
it doesn't the first time you try to
jump something it doesn't jump to it for
whatever reason I'm not quite sure why
ok so in handle collision this we're not
really using at the moment so I'm going
to just go ahead and say that these
things can sort of be nerfed for the
moment
because we're going to go ahead and play
with those a little bit later on all
right don't know that I used to still be
there get rid of that rid of this can
also take the opportunity to get rid of
begin low entity okay and let's see we
can ground identity does not need any of
this stuff let's keep on going
nothing to really see here you can see
what I'm doing I'm literally just
cleaning this up so that it's not taking
that anymore all right so now we have
the game running and it literally just
doesn't have any types at all right
which is what I wanted so that's like a
good big step we still got a ways to go
but it's a pretty big step because now
like I said all of those all of the
information that sort of type knowledge
has been decoupled which is what I
wanted right I don't want a notion that
this entity is type X where X defines
everything about it I want that
splintered into dozens of little types
that are like what type of collision
does it have and what type of body shape
does it have and what type of brain is
it using and what type of this so that
they can be mixed and matched freely
without having to think of something as
up being a particular whole type of
enemy and so now that that's done i'm
pretty happy camper
okay so that's pretty good and I'm going
to say that that I'm willing to promote
I think the way the brain was working
was quite good so I'm willing to start
to promote that up to here where this is
the thing we've actually thought about
and want right like I feel like that
system is is it a place where that's you
know that's doing what I wanted to do in
the way I wanted to do it for the moment
and so I consider that to actually be
our first thing where we kind of thought
it through there's some it'll probably
still need some improvements down the
road but I think that's an actual real
thing now that I want to keep so entity
ID updateable is not something we've
thought about but entity ID definitely
is and obviously that's also something
we need so that's our actual part of the
energy structure that we thought through
pretty carefully and so I feel like
those are going to stay there for a
while all right so let's go back and
take a look now at what the world mode
code looks like now that we've got rid
of that part and you know what what this
sort of straight line code looks like so
you can see that we loop through the
controllers here to see whether anybody
has tried to start playing the game we
then loop through all the brain code and
Allah give each brain a chance to think
right essentially and tell its component
entities what he wanted them to do we
then have a loop through all the
entities where we you know duty but
could if we need to assuming that it's
an updatable entity we kind of have this
global alpha stuff having here I think
this is you know something we want to
pull out and into sheep rendering like i
said before but then we've kind of got
this notion of the movement mode and
then the physics update right and all of
that is good but it needs to start being
factored for real into actual you know
this isn't really all that thought
through yet it probably needs a little
bit more refinement but on the whole
it's okay and then we get to move entity
and move entity is
the weakest link at this far because
that's still our old standard physics
stuff and that probably needs a good
good dusting right then our render code
is now pretty reasonable I mean it's not
great it's not going to win any awards
but it's actually starting to be a
little bit more straightforward and on
you know unencumbered by notions of what
entities are anything like that you can
see it just kind of goes through and
says well I just got a list of things I
should render i render those and if I've
got other things like hit points I draw
them on top you know and debug data on
top right and then we just got a bunch
of debug code so overall there's really
not much there at this point and that's
good so I feel like we're kind of
getting we're kind of getting to a good
place so really I think we need this to
be like the physics section so we've got
our physics and then we've got our
rendering down here right i guess i'm
not sure if an entity is updateable i'm
not sure why entity has to be updateable
for it to be rendered like I guess it
makes sense because we'd only want to
render something that we that is
actively and well I don't know it's a
little weird because I'm not sure that
really is what that means but okay so
yeah if we take a look at what's
happening here we kind of have the Bob
update and the movement mode hopping
update and so on and so forth
I'm not sure exactly what we want here
hmm i say hmm
so I guess here's something that I i
guess i would like to start to do then
I'm going to say let's create a brain
type well we don't really have to create
a brain tab because I think we've got
one yeah so let's let's start playing
around with this I'm going to I'm going
to have a brain Monstar test here right
and the brain Monstar is just going to
be a thing that utilizes the movement
spec and maybe uses hopping as a thing
and so the way I'm going to do this is
going to say ok a monster brain at the
moment I guess really just has just the
body right but it you know probably
eventually have some real stuff there
but in here we've got these are sort of
our types of brains right if that makes
sense in fact what we could do here as
well as say all right you've got brain
IDs and brain slots and brain types and
those sorts of things and maybe all of
that kind of lives down here and that's
the definition of the brain and then in
here this is brain types
right something like that so we've got
brain hero parts we've got brain and
maybe it should just be brave hero
instead of parts this is brain Monstar
and this is brain familiar and again I
don't know that these are actually I'm
not trying to suggest that these are
actually the types of brains we would
have they the brains themselves might
want to be a lot more fluid to as we go
further on but for now i'm basically
taking the same approach with brains as
i would took with the entities first
hardcode them to what i want them to do
first and when i start to see the places
where things can be pulled apart pull it
apart then rather than try to guess
ahead of time and this is sort of the
you know a very much a compression
oriented style thing that I'm suggesting
here I think that's going to be more
useful so a familiar just has a head at
the moment I believe and a monster just
has a body so there's that but you know
that's just how it goes i guess so let's
go ahead and reenable some of these
things just to play with them a little i
just want to see what happens so i'm
going to go ahead and and put this in
here i'm going to set the config for now
to the AI follows here at a true so i
wanted to fall to it actually working
and then we'll just say alright we've
got our our brain familiar we've got our
brain familiar this is essentially just
want a mirror like you can see what we
did here I just want to do this
I so we just grab that out and we say
well familiar only has a head so that's
fine inside here we've sort of got this
loop through and we need spatial queries
that's true but we don't care about that
for the very moment but what we want to
do here is say well we want to find I
guess the closest thing that has a brain
that is a hero if there is one so I
guess we would say if the brain type is
brain type hero or brain hero then
that's then that's it yeah I think
that's pretty much all there is remember
how movements effects work I'm going to
go ahead and assume that this is how it
works at the moment and then in here
everywhere we're doing entity is going
to be head right so head head head head
head head oops
okay um so I don't expect anything to
happen now when we run this and the
reason for that is no one should have
that brain look we have not installed
that brain in anything right so what we
need to do is when we do an ad familiar
to the game and familiar we need to do
this this piece of code oh I just had an
idea we need to do this piece of code
right and we need to say brain familiar
for this entity the brain ID in this
case we're going to have to get so we
need to do an ad brain and that's about
it
well that was anticlimactic mr. familiar
not following me now I probably have to
set his movement mode he's a separate
issue but I gotta go first check to make
sure some other things are happening uh
what I did want to point out those I had
an idea here which is what we might want
to do to make things easier on ourselves
is we might want to make these like
brain hero or whatever and bring monster
or whatever I we may want to make it to
the brain type and the struct are the
same right I so it would basically be
like hey this is just like you know type
brain hero type brainsnake that sort of
thing type brain familiar type brain
floaty thing for now type brain monstar
type rain and the reason I suggest that
is because it gives us a little bit of
opportunity to protect ourselves to you
know sort of overcoming again the C C++
language shortcomings that force us to
do some weird macro things this brain
slot for we could sort of make this into
a more extensive macro set that would
sort of reduce the chances of us making
an assignment error so you can see like
for example in this case we have the
brain type and the brain slot and there
are signs together and that's a very
common thing so I'm starting to think
well maybe a brain slot and a brain type
should sort of be bundled together into
some single thing
you know so maybe there's something more
like oh okay there's a brain type and a
brain slot and since anything that gets
assigned to bring type has to have a
slot into which it goes instead it we
could say Oh in that case you know its
brain type in slot right makes sense so
maybe brain slot is a very is a totally
different thing maybe it's something
more like this you know I'm saying so
brain type actually doesn't appear
anywhere and brain slot for is a thing
that you actually gives you back both of
these so what I do is I say well okay I
know what the type is that we were
talking about and I can get the
enumerator for that type just by pacing
on type underscore at the beginning of
it which means that now i can say that
just takes a brain type in addition to
whatever the value i'm supposed to be
packing in right so then when i do brain
slots i can say well the slot is the
type and then the pack value and we
could also warrant that this is going to
be a u16 because we know that we're not
going to have more than that number of
slots right so that seems pretty
compelling to me and I think that I like
that because now what we do is we say
that the brain slot is just that and now
you can't mess it up you can't use an
offset for one type of brain but assign
it to a different type of brain just
threw a typo which is something I could
easily see us doing right and so it's
free it doesn't create any cumbersome
this for me so it seems like a freeway
there's a purely free way to prevent
some errors so I'm going to take it I
think I have five minutes left on the
clock so I'm going to use them to finish
this up and then we can worry about
familiars and stuff like that tomorrow
okay so in here we've got a brain slot
brain type so now we just get rid of
brain type and it's gone and then I just
have to deal with the fallout from that
and we should be good and can you not
convert brain type 2 u16 possible loss
of data what
how on earth with that enum ever be
greater you're staring right at it all
right well I won't ask I won't ask my
friend okay uh so get a rad brain let's
see here so get our ad brain is looking
at the desk brain type but now it needs
to be the brain slot type right what's
going on here bring ID right its brain
slot type is it not cannot convert
argument 3 for me 16 to brain type
alright fine we'll just say great type
and so all of these now have to be type
brain hero type brain snake type brain
familiar and type brain floaty thing for
now type dream monster aah type brain
era
okay so hopefully nothing has changed
that should just be the same and so we
still have to go get our familiar
working but we can do that tomorrow and
I can go to the QA
man then that kink not fun
quarter were you trapped in an elevator
today ah no was there a risk of that I
mean I guess I did use an elevator today
but I never became trapped the marsala
if you are nuking the constant any type
but still keeping everything tightly
bound in the brain what real gain does
all this work give us didn't we just
shift responsibility into the brain no
right because now you can assign any
brain to any collection of entities and
use any movement type with any brain
type it just allows us to decouple all
of those systems before everything was
on the env type how you moved whether
you were controlled by a controller what
your actual render pieces were what your
movement speed and even was was all
bound into that right and so now we have
the ability to just mix and match so we
can have something that's created out of
totally different renderable pieces but
uses the same brain as a hero we can
take something that appears to look like
a hero but uses the you know Monstar
brain or whatever and those are just
separated so similarly I would assume
that as we go a little further we may
have brains have quite a bit more
parameterization to them as well but
again the point of moving things out in
two brains was to vet the other thing
that we gained is that brains operate
cross entity so that solved a big
problem for us was like oh we have these
multi entity assemblies that want to
think across multiple entities Weeden
have any way to do that now and brain
solve that for us too right so now we
can have the hero head in the hero body
can both be controlled by one controller
for at some point and then we can make
it so they're going to control
separately at other points and we could
even have it so you can you know
dynamically switch as you sort of maybe
get into situations where your head
could detach or other stuff like that
Abner after all this time are finally
you used to programming live is this a
comfortable habit now I know it's always
not great I mean it's always a lot
harder than programming not it's not the
live part that's the problem it's the
talking and the little bits is also
problematic and having lots of products
at once is also not great I don't love
that either so it's a lot harder than
programming normally like a lot harder
lung boolean could you explain again
what you just did with the brain slot
that went a little fast for me well I
was just saying I so if you take a look
at at what was happening let me see if I
can pull that up in here I want to open
brain dot H so if you take a look at
what happens in here we've got this
nation of of these brain slots which we
haven't really you know we haven't
looked into too much how this is going
to work this might get a little more
complicated later on right but the way
it works right now is a brain this is
just something that's got some slots in
it that you can stick things into but we
don't really know what they are and then
what happens is depending on what type
of brain you are we've got some
different understandings of how those
are laid out whether it's a hero a
monster are familiar right oops undo
that and so we've got these layouts here
and those layouts are important right
there you know at the moment we could
probably just do it all with just head
and body and having two slots right and
maybe if in the end that turns out to be
all we need then great but assuming we
start having crazy stuff like weird
spider creatures that have eight
different pieces or you know sets of
pieces or who knows what else if we
start to have stuff like that or like a
snake thing that's just a bunch of
different pieces that follow one after
each other you know I don't know what
we're going to have and so to make sure
that while we're experimenting with it
right like if I knew we're going to have
I could just say here's maybe the
sperry do it but since I don't know
we're going to want to be able to play
with this and just see what happens as
we go I wanted to make sure that we
would never use the wrong template uh
with the with a different type so if
we're saying that a brain is of type
familiar I want to make sure that
everyone is using brain familiar to
assign themselves a slot index right so
I want them to say I'm you know the head
of a familiar and make sure that the
type is marked as familiar I don't want
them to say I'm the head of a familiar
and then mark the type as floaty thing
for now or Monstar right and so before
what was happening is when we assigned
in India brain we assigned it a slot and
a type completely separately so you
could have easily just said this is a
snake but then assigned it the slot as
if it was enumerated like a hero which
would give totally nonsensical results
potentially right so what I did instead
was say hey let's use a macro to make
sure that whatever struct you use to
measure your slot location you will then
use that as your type as well so I just
named these the same things as the
struts and so you know that that is just
a little trick to make it so that you
use a preprocessor to prevent you from
making a typo
sighs acai would you handle something
like mind controlling other entities or
having your own or sorry having your
mind swapped into a differently
structured body um well at the moment I
guess there's one thing we might have
well no not really I guess I I guess I
think there really isn't much to do for
that you know all we would all we would
need is to just all we would need is
just to take whatever that other set of
entities are and set them to our brain
ID and then jettison our own right again
this is why I think it's so important to
have these things decoupled I mean maybe
maybe it's it's a little obtuse right
now just because you know I have
everything in my head pun intended and
and everyone else doesn't but like so
like for example the marsala said
player-controlled flag but no you don't
need a player controlled flag like
that's like the whole point so for
example you know let's say I wanted to
have that exactly what you just said
happen so if I came and said well we've
got you know the start button down or
something I don't know what the start
button is I guess it's the spacebar I
think so i think i think this is it
right
let me just see here so if I came over
here to see where that was just wanna
make sure this is the correct thing wait
what oh that's ended down I want was
pressed of course it's going to be stuck
ended down because I get the spacebar
and then went into it and it wouldn't
have been checked again but cannot go
right one from bulleted game button
state that alright so when I hit the
spacebar yeah there we go okay uh so if
I for example wanted to do the mind
control thing like you said then what i
could do is go okay let's let's actually
make that scenario happen right so when
i do was pressed i'll just make it so
that i take control of whoever the
closest entity is right like literally
is like even if it doesn't have well i
guess i don't want to take toiletries
but i'll just take care I'll take care
of anyone anyone with a brain I'll take
control of that person right we really
need to make find closest entity we need
a call for that that's got to be done
soon so if I search through here and I
just say hey if rain slapped slot type
or i guess i should say brain slot ID is
you know is nonzero then whatever this
test entity is I'm going to take it as
my head and jettison the head that I do
have right so I'm going to say like if
head head gut brain slot equals brain
slot for or I guess clear
no brain slot like that or just no brain
right so I'll get rid of of the head
that I do have and I'll just assign me
to to this to this brain yes now I think
about I want to do it out here star
closest 0i so we've got the closest hero
here and so when we come out of here
we'll just say well if I had a head the
head's gone now and the the closest hero
whatever that was I guess I should check
for us to see that we found somebody so
we don't end up headless will save the
closest here is brain slot is just going
to be brain slot for brain or brain hero
head so this just like installs a
different head right and so all I have
to do is is actually make that groups
all I have to do is actually make that
no brain which is something we would
have wanted anyway and so in here I just
need a way of returning zero so it'd
just be like brain slot you know no
brain brain slot result results
uh and I guess oh you know what I don't
even really have to do that now I think
about it it's just I guess it's just no
brain it only affects the ID now that i
think about it right so it's actually
just it's only the ID nid result return
result so really I guess I don't have to
do the brain slot I it's really just
brain ID right so--okay so closest hero
bring an ID equals whatever my brain ID
is and off you go so I think that should
work but again this is kind of early and
testing but so maybe I try to go pick up
the familiar head we'll see if it works
I don't know if it will or not let's see
here okay can we find one
oh you know what I just realized we have
to make sure it's not somebody we're
going to just pick ourselves because
we're the closest so we also have to say
the test brain ID value is not zero and
is not us right because our brain ID
would count so we don't want to take
control of ourselves because we're
always the closest thing all right try
one more time so let's see so that was
me taking control of that head right and
now take control of this head back again
I guess not sure if I can actually do
that like that should have worked why
doesn't that work
my set a breakpoint there because it
should work to swap back as well jump
down to hear it could not find one brain
ID value is not equal to the head brain
ID value and I guess this only works if
we have a head as well should make this
as if head but tests inity brain ID
value ah that's why because we need to
give it some kind of a different brain
ID so when we when we leave it I don't
really know what we would do here
exactly but there's this notion of a
thing that is is it an animate or
inanimate like can I possess it and I'm
and I don't know how we really want to
describe that but I guess I guess we'd
want to swap does that make any sense so
the old thing should have become us
probably so let's say I mean just
because we could assign it some other
thing but yeah I don't know so so let's
say that we just swapped these directly
like maybe we just say brain ID you know
old brain ID equals head grain ID and
and this would only be if we have a head
right so we have our old brain ID and we
have our brain slot our old brain slot
equals head brain slot and so what we
need to say is like well the heads brain
ID becomes whatever this thing's brain
ideas and the heads brain slot becomes
the closest heroes brain slot and then
the closest hero brain ID just becomes a
the old brain ID and the closest heroes
brain slot comes the old brain slot that
way we don't make it in an animate that
we can never really use for anything
again it just becomes it become our head
becomes whatever it was and vice versa
right so like if I you know toggle this
guy right now I've I've sort of taken
control of this dude I got to fix our
collision code here in fact a second I
want to do this temporarily let me see
here world mode that's the P collision
because we we still the collision is
definitely the the elephant in the room
right now both not ideal for the rich is
something that you know you're kind of
gotten rid of it but we haven't actually
gone in and finished that the done any
of the actual work to make sure that
it's still happening there so I'm just
going to make these guys no collisions
for now so that I don't have to worry
about them while we're playing with
other things
okay so so now i can like tool over here
right and let me swap to this guy and
then I can you know swap back swap swap
back and then i can swap this thing out
presumably so if I moved away I think I
could swap to this thing can I does this
thing have a brain I don't know if it
does or if it doesn't it doesn't seem to
want to recognize that guy as somebody I
can swap to it always won't it always
fix the one who's way far away so I
don't know what that guy is due mon
stars have brains right now mom stars
might not have brains and so let's just
give our monster our brain yeah mansour
doesn't have a brain that's no big deal
right here's a monster or brain I so we
can just say like oh there's a monster
and that's got the body
so now i can i can swap right and i've
picked this thing up as the head which
is not appropriate because the torso but
it's okay i can do it and then i can
swap back right if i want to i got to
fix the movement code now to be back to
the way we had it before but yeah
so yeah so hopefully that makes some
sense right hope you that answers the
question
let's see
when will we implement the zombie brain
well honestly like a lot of monsters are
kind of zombie like so probably that'll
be one of the first things actually that
make sense so let me see if there are
any other q Collins here
alright so looks like I've got all the
cues all right so I think I've all the
cues that are relevant to anything that
we're actually doing so I'm going to go
ahead and wrap it up close this down and
this as well all right thank you
everyone for joining me from those set
of handmade here it's and a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home you can
always go to the game on handmade here
or get it come to the source code so you
can play wrath it at home and experiment
we also have a forum site you can go if
you want to ask questions you have a
patreon page you can go to if you want
to support the video series we have a
schedule about that tells you when we're
going to be live and we have an episode
guide that you can go to to catch up on
old episodes that you may have missed
that's about it for today we'll be back
on Friday I believe tomorrow's Thursday
which is a day off for us if I'm wrong
about that then I apologize if I believe
it's tomorrow today is Wednesday but we
will be back on Friday 5 p.m. pacific
daylight time until then take it easy
everyone and i will see on the internet