hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete-game live on
stream I am going to take a look at our
Rick casting today we actually aren't
running that poorly if you take a look
at where we're starting it's actually
not that bad
I thought we were gonna be worse off
than we were but when we actually made
the bounds of our of our lighting
solution a tighter fit if you will for
what we were doing so if you look on
here oh I forgot I haven't actually run
Oh actually do I save this I probably
save this let me open it I mention that
we're trying a new version of remedy
today that I have not tried yet let me
go ahead and load that up here there we
go yeah there we go so I was about to
say some stuff about handmade hero but
I'm actually going to pause and say what
I really should be talking about first
is the fact that we now have version 3
of remedy which is the debugger and I
don't know for those of you have
followed the stream for a long time you
know that we used to use Visual Studio
for debugging that was because it's just
a better human factors debugger than
pretty much anything else you can use at
the time on Windows it's not a good
debugger but it's it's good at
displaying information and it's good at
quickly restarting your program and you
know it basically had all of the like
good user interface that you would need
by comparison to other debuggers on the
platform so that's why you know that
that's what we were using when we
started handmade hero now in that way
that that Microsoft generally I mean
pretty much exclusively for the past 20
years only ships worse versions of their
software each time so if you were using
you know version 5 and you get version 6
it's worse than version 5 and you get
version 7 it's worse than version 6
sometimes it gets dramatically worse you
know like Windows
7 to Windows 8 sometimes it's only
slightly worse like each update of
Windows 10 where it just gets you know a
little bit worse each time until you
know eventually it's gotten dramatically
worse over the course of several updates
etc so Visual Studio had been decaying
for many years the last really good I
mean I'm really good but the last like
version you probably want to use was 5 6
was ok and then everything after that so
2005 2008 and so on have just been
getting really bad and now it's it's
really pretty bad it's very slow it has
a lot of bugs in it it's it's bad it
crashes a lot and so on uh so we had
kind of been struggling with that and I
had said multiple times on stream I'm
like somebody needs to make a deburr to
replace this thing it is garbage and not
to mention the fact that installing it
is a huge chore it takes it oftentimes
you know are just fails you you know you
you get inexplicable errors that don't
work you have to create a Microsoft
account to install it even if you paid
for it it's a it's a disaster and it
installs like sequel server on your
machine it's it's it's unfathomably bad
in terms of the installation process for
a debugger right because you can only
get it as part of the IDE and the ID has
all kinds of crap you don't want so
eventually actually somebody and it's
it's X 13 pixels on the chat was like
alright I'm gonna do something about
this and they started writing a debugger
and eventually they actually got it good
enough a 1.0 and we started using on a
stream and it you know was missing a
bunch of features but it was just plain
better to use than Visual Studio and
it's it's remedy BG it's this debugger
right here and we just started using it
and it's like it's super fast it steps
and updates the watch windows so much
faster the visual studio it's got the
same kind of clean easy-to-use systems
that Visual Studio had that made it
preferable where you can just quickly do
what you want and you don't have to wade
through tons of command line parameters
and and hard to view windows like it
actually shows you what you need to know
when you need to know it but didn't have
all the crappy bad
individual studio it's one eggsy you can
literally just copy the EXCI on your
machine and it and it works loads
instantly it runs instantly it's great
and then steadily since that version 1.0
it's just been getting better and better
and better
now in this version 3 which we've just
upgraded to and X 13 pixels in the track
and correct me if I'm wrong but I think
he actually did something that I
literally don't know if any debugger has
ever done and it's kind of a
breakthrough feature for people who use
this so I'll describe what it is correct
me if I'm wrong X 13 conditional
breakpoints were added in this version
of the bugger so a conditional
breakpoint is like if you have a
breakpoint and you want to change it so
that it only happens like sometimes
right so you want to say look I'm a type
a piece of code in here you know like oh
if X equals 5 or something right um if
you want to do conditional breakpoints
obviously that requires evaluating C
expressions while your program is
running because every time you go and
hit that particular breakpoint
traditionally what was done in say
Visual Studio is it would actually use
an actual breakpoint so it would you
know use an int 3 or something to
actually stop the code when it hit there
it would then branch to Visual Studio
which would actually go run its
expression evaluator and then if the
expression evaluated it true it would
then actually break the program into the
debugger meaning it would show you that
break otherwise we just resume right so
what that means is that anytime you ran
with conditional breakpoints you've got
a massive slowdown because every time it
hit that break point it was going to
have to do this whole process well I
believe what X 13 pixels did and correct
me if I'm wrong is actually it compiles
the actual expression into your
code like into your executable and jumps
and patches that with a jump am i right
about that
let me check
didn't know today so how is it so much
faster
okay I'd take it back so X 15 pixels
tells me because it's 15 times faster
than visual studio and so I assumed he
was actually trying to do that but
because he had talked about doing that
before he's saying that it's actually
just 15 times faster even doing it with
the interrupts Wow okay so I take it
back I guess he didn't have to do
something no debugger had ever done
before he just actually I guess wrote
much better code than the visual studio
team and is 15 times faster so all right
I guess there's not much point in doing
the compilation thing although maybe if
you have enough threads there is I don't
know anyway never mind so separate from
all of that it's 15 times faster than
visual studio which means that now you
can actually use conditional breakpoints
in places that probably you couldn't
really use them before because
previously you know if you were trying
to set a conditional breakpoint on
something that got hit often it was not
really plausible to do that because
Visual Studio would run so slowly that
you would really want to try to avoid
that if you could I mean if you had to
you could and you just kind of let it
sit for awhile but you wouldn't cuz 15
times slower is a lot slower right if
something would have run for a minute
before it's running for 15 minutes now
right and that's you know not great or
whatever right so remedy now has really
fast conditional breakpoints and I feel
like that's kind of a game-changer for
people who use breakpoints a lot with
conditions on them I don't actually do
that but for example John Blow talks
about this he uses them all the time
so for people whose workflow relies on
conditional breakpoints remedy 3 is
gonna be a huge deal for them like a
huge huge deal for them for us I don't
know that 3 is all that important to us
because we don't actually need
conditional breakups I don't tend to use
them probably I should and maybe I will
now that they're so fast
but either way remedy for us like just
the 2.0 branch was a huge win like we
you know use it all the time on stream I
use it as my pretty much only debugger
at Mali rocket it's just it's been a
huge huge huge win and so anyone who
hasn't been looking at remedy because it
didn't have like all the features that
you needed I would really highly
recommend checking out the 3.0 branch as
it develops because there are a lot of
features in remedy BG right now and it
may have crossed that threshold for you
where now it's got everything you need
and man if it does switching to it over
Visual Studio or Visual Studio code or
any of the other like things that people
have been using for debugging windows is
a massive massive massive win just being
able to do single step as fast as you
want we didn't hold down the single step
key and the watch window just updates
accurately the entire time there's
nothing else on Windows that does this
right I mean you look at visuals to
reveal sugarcoat it doesn't even update
at all when you do that you have to let
go and wait you know a second and then
it pops in or whatever it's just way
better so I would really really highly
encourage everyone to check this out it
is not expensive I think you can just
literally type remedy B G dot h io into
your web browser of choice and it is
literally 30 bucks and it will be the
best 30 bucks you've ever spent if you
know Visual Studio or something is
bringing you down it is just way way way
way way way better so highly recommended
I don't know if the 3.0 branch has
settled down completely yet cuz it just
came out so I don't know much about that
but at the very least a two point eight
branch which you could also be on if you
want to has been very stable for me the
latest version so you know 3.0 I don't
know if it needs a little time to settle
down or not we haven't used it it may
already be completely stable but even if
it's not the
point eight branches completely stable
for me that's what I use and 3.0 will be
there soon enough so you know either way
check it out both versions are up there
will be play with a 3.0 branch and
kicking the tires so you can check it
out on stream obviously but I would
really encourage people to get on there
there's a github that has an issues list
so if you find bugs get them up there
that's the way it gets better by people
reporting problems so you know check it
out but I think it's something that
should be on every programmers machine
at this point if you program on Windows
it just it saves you so much rage
compared to using Visual Studio or
Visual Studio code all right all of that
preamble aside let's take a look at
handmade hero basically the you know
performance level of handmade here right
now is actually pretty acceptable which
was surprising to me because we're now
doing fully raytrace lighting on the CPU
which normally you wouldn't really
expect to be running this quickly at the
stage rat but I'm pretty happy about
everything we did to it we did a really
good job there's quality issues we're
gonna want to address we haven't done a
quality pass so a lot of things in here
enterings including some feedback loops
making the edges a little rounder of the
voxel interpolation getting the
occluders to be set correctly for
bounces there's a lot of stuff like this
that we have to do and that'll be a
secondary pass maybe starting a weekend
or two from now and that's just visual
quality and a separate thing right now
all I really want is I want to be able
to do just due diligence pass over the
performance right now and make sure that
it's up to at least a reasonable level
and so we're gonna take a look at that
our current performance metric if we
look at it we're running it around 30
milliseconds
if we take a look at our actual thread
performance you can see that actually if
we turned off debug we'd get some of
that back in fact just you can see like
even just the the act of printing out
like lots of text for example the debug
system slows things down quite a bit so
if we actually take a look at what we're
getting for our speed here you know it's
more representative this number so we're
edging in on 60 frames a second even
with the the CPU side ray-traced
lighting which is pretty great and yeah
and you know something I'm pretty happy
about I don't really understand why I'm
not seeing are we did we look into
something so there's a little bit of
weirdness here oh you know why I know
why I never mind we're actually not
timing the separate thread parts anymore
that's why we're not seeing any thread
behavior out here that's actually why we
probably can add something back in when
I think we probably should for that real
quick that wouldn't actually be a
slowdown if we just time the actual if
we time the actual thread dispatch
themselves I think we would get that
although well you know um I guess not
necessarily now that I think about it
that isn't actually the case
so because we split up our slices the
only way to really do it is to put a
time in here and the reason that's a
little bit iffy is because the is it not
timed function oh it's just the reason
that's a little bit iffy is just that if
you take a look at
how many work QD Q's we do there's
there's maybe a little a few too many of
those at the moment and so if you take a
look at what happens when we do our
timing there well okay no that's not
that about 24 is not that bad nevermind
so if we actually time what our threads
are doing here you can see the work
units for the actual ray tracer getting
distributed out here and you can see
those being done sort of as as separate
pieces right and so you can kind of see
we've got our extra threads here we got
six of them that's because this is an
eight virtual core machine so you can
kind of see here if you look at the
performance measurement for the the CPU
you can see what it's doing here
and we are intentionally not using 100%
of the CPU we leave one core idle or I
should say we you know we don't schedule
one threads worth of stuff so if we
detect there's eight cores right now
you're gonna have one core which is the
main core that's running the game loop
and then it's got you know a certain
number of worker cores and we won't
generate seven worker cores will
generate six so we leave one idle the
reason for that is the operating system
needs to do stuff and also we do loading
in the background there's two loading
threads that'll that happened here and
they happen infrequently and just
basically block on the OS that's to keep
us from like over subscribing so we're
trying to you know not absolutely you
know tank the machine that said when you
actually look at what's going on here
you can see we're not stressing this out
at all and I don't actually know why
that's happening but my so my kind of
suspicion there is I do wonder if we're
getting you know if we're actually a
little bit blocked just now by the fact
that look we can't quite yet sixty so
we're gonna end up running at thirty
kind of a thing we tried to turn
v-sync but you can see that there
actually is a fair bit of stalling that
seems to happen there we we wait for
quite a few cycles in the frame display
and we never really were able to fare
exactly what was going on there
I do suspect that part of that is just
because we're running on a streaming
machine and it's locked to stream out
the the HDMI port while also rendering
the screen so I don't know to what
extent Windows is compositor is kind of
the thing that's that's causing us
issues there right so we're not gonna
try to attack that part because it's
sort of a separate issue from how fast
our stuff goes our goal really is just
to make sure that to the extent that we
can we we reduce the amount of time
spent and rate racing and the reason for
that is even if we don't want to
actually speed things up at all even if
we're happy with the speed things are
the faster we can make that ray tracer
the more rays we can trace and you can
see there's some flicker in our lighting
right now that's like variance we can
attack some of that with sampling with
better with basically better handling of
the samples we collect so there are ways
in the quality pass we'll be able to
direct to improve that but regardless
the more ways we can cast the more
accurate of solution we can construct
anyway so we kind of want that
performance either way so what we you
know end up with is we end up with a
situation where we know that our ray
casting is is the main you know thing
that we're is the main like speed bump
that we have for how many Ray's we can
cast like this is the thing that makes
us have to worry about cranking up the
number of Ray's to you know
significantly more let's say than it was
and so what we really need to be able to
do is we need some way of of making sure
that we're doing a reasonably good job
performance wise inside this code
right so inside the code where we're
actually doing our ray casting we kind
of want to know that we're doing a good
job in here and we want some way of you
know guaranteeing that that that were
you know if efficient through this this
part of the code now there's two parts
to this and we don't really know very
much about it quite yet right
the reason I say there's two parts you
can actually see I've gone ahead last
time and split them into two if two
branches of an if one is doing actual
collision detection on the Ray and the
pieces of geometry in the scene and
that's one right here so this right here
loops over actual blocks and it collides
against those blocks right so this piece
of code actually records kit tests and
it just you know is designed to produce
the Ray casting against rectilinear
volumes that you would expect so this is
very like straightforward this piece of
code on the other hand is a little bit
different this piece of code is instead
just trying to call volumes using a
hierarchy so this although it's
basically the exact same code like you
can see here that's going to do the
exact same thing
in either case for the first part which
is just computing a box intersection
it's actually going and trying to
determine whether or not it should go
down one side or another of a bounding
hierarchy right and that's what this
piece of code is doing now there's a
reason that I separated this out we made
this code generic originally just
because that's what we were doing we
made a hierarchy of boxes and we just
said look eventually you get down to the
bottom and we say there's you know
certain number of boxes here or whatever
right well if you look at what happens
here the intersection to try and
determine
or not we hit a particular box and then
selecting that box you know it's
actually quite a lot of code now it
doesn't look like that much code but
each one of these v3 Forex operations is
relatively expensive if you take a look
in the sim design things I guess so yeah
so if you take a look at how this is
actually working if you go and check
like you know just this one well you
know what actually here's an easier way
to do it let me just show you what the
assembly language code looks like I mean
because you can see it gets expanded
from here let's say you have something
like an operator - that you're seeing
there that's just written in the code it
just looks like a subtract if we
actually look at how that's implemented
so here's operator - on like 2f 32s it's
gonna issue a subpoena the v3 version
right it's gonna do that on several of
these so it's gonna be three of those
sub pieces so each one of these lines
here is three instructions long right so
that's gonna be three instructions
that's gonna be three instructions right
three instructions three instructions
another three instructions three
instructions right so the number of
instructions here is actually pretty
high right and it's not like we can't
afford to do some instructions or
anything obviously
in lighting there's going to be several
instructions how to actually get to what
am i looking for your lighting there we
go oh and I can do a control F now can't
I so I can actually jump right here if I
want to look at that alright um so
inside this code right if we actually
look at what has to happen if I go ahead
and set a breakpoint here and we go
ahead and and look at the the
disassembly which is what I actually
want
let me looks like that one does not open
there it is so if we take a look at the
disassembly here what you can see is you
know there's a lot of of code that's
going on here there's chef PS is there
you know there to sort of distribute
things out like this sort of thing right
here
I lost this single value up to two
replicated stuff so there's chef PS is
for that then there's the sub pieces
that are happening right chefs subs
there's mobs that are moving in the data
right I don't know why this is storing
this out some stuff there doesn't make a
whole lot of sense but doesn't matter
point being you can see Mull max min
chef right there's tons of code
happening in here and to some extent we
could start to minimize this because on
certain things like for example the
boxes we know we can control how those
boxes are created so we could for
example just pre store them with some of
these things computed and that's
definitely something we're gonna want to
do right but the point is it's fairly
expensive if we look down here right and
we look at what's going on here you can
see that we do this box intersection
test but the only thing we're ever going
to do when we intersect the box is we're
just gonna determine whether we should
go and look at the children of the box
right that's it and so that's just not a
particularly useful way to construct
this tree instead what we could do is
because we've basically constructed it
for example like a KD tree this is way
more expensive than it needs to be if
you look at what we're doing in our
split box right here's where we
construct the bounding volume hierarchy
we're basically doing a KD tree here but
there's no reason for it to ever like it
doesn't actually ever use that knowledge
in here right it does a bounding box
check even though the only thing is it's
just a split plain right this is
basically a BSP but instead of testing
it like a BSP we're testing it like an
ABB AABB hierarchy Agis we're just
throwing cycles away so this piece of
code it sucks right there's no this is
not smart at all and we don't
know that we can save time by improving
it because we don't really know to what
extent we are you know we don't know
exactly what we're limited by we don't
know if we're limited by cash concerns
we don't know if we're limited by branch
mispredictions we don't know if we're
limited by math ops right
we just fundamentally don't know and if
we wanted to know for sure we should
probably take some actual measurements
right and that may be something that we
want to do meaning we'd pull this code
out we'd run it in a more controlled
setting and we look at what's going to
happen there but at least as far as we
can tell here there's no reason to
believe we wouldn't get a win on
basically all of those fronts by just
not using a abs for this if we're going
to use a KD tree anyway which is how we
did the splits here and generally
speaking KD trees are what people use
for ray tracing most of the time we
could reduce all of this just by using a
different type there right so if we
actually look and plus you know let's
take a look at get box right so get box
for you know even this we don't need to
call right this is just doing a straight
ahead lookup so it you know what and
this is even worse this is a double
indirection right for no reason although
that may make sense up here because
we're trying to use the existing set of
boxes that we got handed so that we
don't copy them the initial time even
that's a little questionable we should
probably just flatten that down even if
we weren't going to do that looking here
there's no reason for this because we
created these boxes that are the sub
boxes in the set they should just be
continuous in memory so before we get
too far down the road of trying to
actually collect information about this
I feel like we probably would want to
just fix all that right but it may also
be instructive I don't know to sort of
say look well maybe we should create the
test harness for that first right so I
don't know I'm gonna go ahead and say
maybe I'll look at how much work it will
be for me to isolate this piece of code
out and then look at its performance
separately I want to say that I
installed vtune already on this machine
let me see if that's the case looks like
it right because I believe we were using
this one time I did a meow hash stream
and I remember a few folks who watch the
stream regularly remember that but we
were using to be honest I don't actually
know that there's a way to do
command-line performance analysis on
windows on Linux there's a executable
you can call called perf that allows you
to actually get your performance
counters without having to go through a
ridiculous tool like vtune which I don't
super love but on Windows the only way
to get access to like the more sort of
specific performance counters that
you're going to get those only really
come through vtune so if we wanted to
take a profile of this particular
application we really kind of need to
know what's going on vtune why's there
and so what we could do is is break this
out into a piece of code that we can
then look at and be a little bit more
specific about and that might be worth
it because then we can take some actual
timing you know pieces of timing
information that are more specific and
get a little bit more information about
what's going on right now in order to do
that we kind of need some way of
actually getting information out of our
system we need a way to sort of do this
procedure offline thankfully the
lighting system really just works on
sort of these these box inputs and so
here's what I'm gonna say I'm gonna
actually say let's just let it take a
capture okay
and we'll you know we'll just let it
right to a file if we look at our
handmade platform code I want to say we
actually have the facilities already
built for this so let's just capture
some of the data use that you can write
you can see we got platform write data
to file here right so we should be able
to actually just open a file blast some
data out to it and then and and and use
that an external test app so it's nice
because again you know and yeah I don't
want to go down the rat hole of why you
should always program simply and why I'm
I'm just oh wait I don't even bother
arguing people about this anymore
because I feel like the shark has been
jumped so you know you get these modern
C++ people and then they're just off in
la-la land or whatever right but again
when you just program sensibly and you
just have like a basic array of some
data stuff like this is just a non-issue
right if I want to capture the input to
one of my things I could just write out
the array right it's not some giant
rat's nest of ridiculous Aria I classes
at all point to each other that have to
be crawled and just like who the hell
knows and then there's like you know all
serialization and oh do I use a
libraries right you know it's all just a
waste of time right it's all just a
waste of time because begin lennie
computation we go through here we get
this we get this input that's just like
look this is what you're gonna do our
split box call like when we call build
spatial partition for lighting that just
comes in in a very simple array right
you can see this is all we do right we
just loop over the boxes we got as an
input and then we build it we can just
write that out as one flat piece of data
and be off to the races right so again
really really simple and the reason for
that is we just weren't dumb right all
we did was just we didn't over
complicate our lives the bunch of
nonsense that doesn't have any practical
benefit right so what I can do here is
inside build spatial partition
relighting if I want to I could go
and use the platform IO stuff to just
say why don't you just write out that
flat array I'll load that flat array
back into my program in just a
standalone exterior program and then we
can actually run the lighting on an
actual scene so we're not making stuff
up and taking timings on something that
isn't really appropriate so if I want to
do that what I should be able to do here
is just go ahead and say look if I call
the platform API so I'm doing it you
know something like this I should be
able to do like an open file and then I
should be able to do like a write dated
a file and then I should be able to
close it right like this just closed e
and then I can you know dump out this
thing that I was using the solution box
is here and then I can just do the same
code that I was doing before and and in
theory that will give me but like
everything I need right so let's go
ahead and try to do that if we look at
the API for that open file right if I
you know for trying to actually get a
platform open file there I think I
should be able to do that with this is
this only for iteration I don't know if
this Creek there is a way to create
files I just don't remember exactly what
it is I think it's this platform get
filed by path so I think maybe that's
actually what I want their platform get
file by path and then what I have to do
is I have to pass it like some
information and I don't know if that's
the right way to it's been so long since
I've done any of this stuff and this is
made for our asset system so I'm not
what I'm sure that's the smartest way to
do it but I think that it is so if I go
ahead and do it this way one of the
other things I need to use there a
platform file group which is which is
just this I don't remember
I'm gonna go look at the win32 code
so in here where we have like win32 get
filed by path I think that's really what
we want because I think it works pretty
much yeah I think it works with whatever
we want so we can pass we don't have to
open a file that exists you could see
here that like if we specify open file
right it will create the new file for us
right so that seems like what we want as
far as I can tell when three do you open
file we should be able to then just pass
that file info that we got back and off
we go so I think we're okay that's
that's my argument you know that that's
what I'm that's what I'm gonna claim so
here if we look at what happens when we
actually call that get file by path that
gives us the like you know I don't know
we call this the dump file or something
and I know we're gonna call this this is
where we're gonna dump our data to we
should be able to open that file and
oops I put think this get filed by
pathum advice no that's fine all right
so open file like I think all that open
file needs is to no open file right
looks like and then the file group
that's the only thing we don't have so
there's the file group I think they get
passed to everything does it
so here and then when we do write data
to file we just pass the handle we got
back right so it looks like that and the
offset the size which left compute and
the source which is just the boxes right
and then I guess we close it I don't
know that we need anything there so I
think this is literally all we would
have to do but it looks like we'd have
to open a file group for that I like
this and so if I just said like okay you
know platform Open File group and then
platform close file group I think that's
everything and you know if we were gonna
do this a lot that's that's too much
work right like we shouldn't have to do
that much so there probably should just
be like a debug dump file kind of a
thing like somewhere that we would have
and we don't have that at the moment can
see we don't you don't have any any of
that as far as I can tell so you know
this should probably we should probably
wrap this up in like a dump thing like
it should probably be something like
this that we can use anywhere we want
something like that so that way if you
want to do just like debug dump data
something like that you can basically
just say you know give us I don't know
like a name for the data that you
actually want right like you know data
name or whatever and then it will do
this work for you you just give it like
how big you know was that supposed to be
and what was the data you actually
wanted to dump and off it would go
something like that no I mean
so I think that's all we really need and
we can also then use this in other
places so it would take less time next
time to do the dump because we you know
would have a purpose-built API that
opens and closes and stuff for us so
what I'd like to do there as well is
like I'd like to then say we've got a
platform file type for dumps right
because basically like that's the thing
that's gonna you know we'd want to have
like a directory where those go or
something so exactly what this was
previously used for we would we would
want that to happen here as well so in
here like I would say you know we've
we've got our handmade hero directory
and you know we've got a debug directory
that stores this stuff so actually I
would say that's probably where that
should go right so inside the debug
directory we should be able to open that
up for dumping dump files there and
again this will do I think like roughly
what we won't want it to do right
oops that should be dumped or something
right so when we do get filed by path I
don't know if it automatically adds the
dump prefix in there it seems like it
probably wouldn't I don't actually know
though so again I'm just gonna use been
so long since I've looked at any of that
code I'm just gonna take a look to see
whether the you know the get file by
path stuff actually pens anything I
don't think it does yeah so it doesn't
so I think what I should be able to do
is in here like you know maybe say file
name again it's a little weird does this
use I'm not sure how this figures out
where stuff goes because it feels like
this should actually create a path that
it just feels a little bit buggy like
like who puts this path together
so that it's in the right place you know
this this filename here like you know I
feel like what I'd have to do I think
what I'd have to do here is say
something like debug slash lightbox dump
and then I just say oh yeah the size of
that is like you know size of solution
boxes times however many of those were
so you know this thing right here and
that would do the whole dump but I feel
like I shouldn't have to do that like it
would be nice you just did that
and then when you did an open file with
the path in there it would say well
whichever file group that was under it
appends it right so I kind of think that
shouldn't I be able to not use debug
slash here like
I don't know it's it's not a super well
thought-out API the file stuff it's just
for the asset processing so it's not
something we really know is particularly
great so I'm not super concerned about
either way but I just wanted to drop a
note there so I'm like yeah that seems a
little bit Squinkie to me so you know
maybe not anyway so I think we have a
global platform handle for that in hand
made out eh
I want to say or something like that
we've got one that we we actually just
store it because that's accessible it's
it's an API that's accessible to
everybody you don't need a particular
thing for it you can see that it's right
here so I guess what I'd say is maybe
let's just put that in here and make
people call through it which which seems
good to me actually as well so in here
we would just say okay I guess I don't
know I don't know if that's ex turned
anywhere I guess it sort of is so I
guess I can really put this anywhere
right yeah I can so I can put this
anywhere so I think maybe I'll just put
this in here right
and I'll just export that as like a
function that people can call like this
and you know we'll leave it at that so
now anyone can dump data out to our
dumps directory I don't know what that
Open File group call was actually called
let's look at it here
I guess it's this get all files of type
begin get all files of type end and we
now know we've got a type of this which
is the platform dump and there we go
alright so get file by path wants
another parameter not sure what that is
so let me just look at the actual let me
look at the actual call for that so
that's get file by path it means
file group oh and we need the path we
didn't pass it and that's an address of
I think that's it so I think that's what
we wants and I think that should dump
the data and if I run the program now
well actually I guess I don't remember
if I actually put in here an actual call
I did if I run this now I think that
should just constantly be dumping the
data to it right and so yeah if we want
raw dumps I think that's all we really
needed to do and that gives us the
complete set so what I need is just some
way of actually triggering this I don't
actually probably care much about it so
maybe I'll just do that and then I'll
just change that to a one if I want to
make it go right so and you know the
other way I could do that here is I
could say something like okay you know
maybe we've got a global you know light
box dump trigger right and then we could
do this and that way if we just set
light box dump trigger to true it will
dump the data so that would allow me to
like walk to I don't need this anymore
that would allow me to walk to where I
want to be in the world so maybe I want
to be in someplace that's like you know
got lots of stuff in it or whatever I
mean I don't really know what the best
place to be is for it maybe I want to be
like out where there's eat more like
layers to the thing like out here you
know where we start paging in more world
stuff from like dungeons and stuff right
like that's a lot of boxes right in the
system I would think
so you know if we wanted to we could say
alright let's go ahead and take a debug
dump in that location so whoo I guess
all I really have to do is look for that
variable and set a breakpoint so if I
set the breakpoint here and then I I
don't know can I set this variable to
something I don't know if I actually can
where is this thing I'm not sure they're
editing values in remedy I don't
actually know it's a good question
for that would be a good feature to add
to the list I've I don't think I've ever
actually tried it so I'm not sure at
this location memory
that was cool I'd like that send memory
to watch window am I allowed to change
this now I'm not alright so I have my
first feature request for uh for 43.0
branch can i edit that that's my request
alright so if I want to change this then
I guess I'll just do it this way
because I don't really need to do it the
way I was doing it I guess I will just
go to here and say true and then in
theory like I should watch this it
should stop on that line now and if I go
in here I should like open something I
mean I don't really need to walk through
this you know whatever it's gonna do
what its gonna do
and then in theory I should now have if
I kill the program I should now have a
dump of that if it actually worked right
so if I look at the debug data there's a
lightboxes dump hopefully it actually
has the data that I actually want in
there but that's like what we would need
to read in an external program so if I
want to what I should be able to do is
actually create sort of a standalone
thing that's going to load this and then
use the you know the lighting system
separately so you know if you if you
take a look at you know we've done this
several times before like ehh sphere for
example in the build up that we have
there's a sphere builder right that we
use for our lighting and if we look at
that it's right here we could just make
another one of these which is like
lighting profiler I don't know and all
that would do is we'd build HH like
light per for something right HH light
prof and that would allow us to create
some other executable that is there
solely for the purpose of profiling the
lighting system and it doesn't do
anything
else right so we do h/h light prof
that's cpp here we open that up we
basically you know copy this exact piece
of code that we had before and so that
we can you know build handmade here oh
we looking things with handmade hero
actual code rather than all of this
nonsense about the spheres all we would
actually do is stuff in here excuse me
I've got the UH something in my eye
we would just say all right when we run
this thing we'll grab an argument that
is the lightbox dump name or something
like that right we don't care about any
of this at all
we're gonna RB this thing like Arby's
you know like a roast beef we're gonna
open up the lightbox file will read the
entire file here if we can't we'll just
let people know and and that'll be that
right so this is all we really need to
do here and we'll just use this as our
way of debugging the program I don't
know if I can include the lighting here
so let me just go ahead and do a test
build first and see if we can make sure
that this works like so there we go OOP
I don't know if that's about is that a
bug
all right uh anyway so I want to be able
to do this like I want to have the
ability to call our lighting functions I
don't know if we can actually do that
you can see that there's some stuff
that's missing in this case so lighting
box is actually in it's in the renderer
code right and we also need H file so
world position think that's just in here
that's not how you spell that
yeah and debug dump date it can just be
stubbed and I think that's what we
really need there that's gonna have to
go up above the actual lighting code
because it needs to be able to find it
what else we got set light bounds enable
lighting dev mode lighting global anxa
probes so some of these push line
segments some of those are just in the
renderer code I don't think we want to
do that but we could dev mode lighting I
don't know what that actually is
I think it's in the editor
some we're not actually sure here's what
I'm gonna actually do alright so some of
these we actually have to bring in
probably I'm just guessing are in same
chunk for example he's a bit of an issue
um maybe I'll just grab that are in same
chunk because it's not important here so
I'll just say like and again this is
just me compiling a separate executable
sort of out in the you know out in the
wild here there's another way I could do
this and we'll see if I have to do too
many of these I'll do it the other way
but for now I'm just gonna do this and
basically stuff these out cuz I don't
care about them right all right so now
at least in theory I can go and if I
want to in the debug directory I should
be able to do something like HH light
perf light boxes dot dump like prof.
sorry
uh I Shh there we go I should be able to
do it that didn't that wasn't happy what
happened there
that's what happened there so I should
now be able to debug this program it's
like a separate program if I want to I
should be able to create a remedy debug
profile for it as well so hopefully I
can just you know go ahead and oh you
know what this is something we meant to
fix as well let's fix this because I
feel like I forgot to do that many times
here so in our mist directory we have
our remedy batch file this is like not
supposed to happen this way right the
start needs to get removed I think so
let me just see if that fixes that wait
but we still need hmm but we still need
to call that start call what am I doing
wrong here do you have to do that maybe
nope so I thought there was some way
maybe extra teen can tell us I thought
there was some way to like get remedy to
use the things that I just passed to it
as oh I like that as the as a startup
stuff here but I don't know if that's
true it doesn't really matter to me but
I figured I should probably fix it at
some point
might have to Appendix II but I thought
that worked okay so apparently no yeah
it does work so I guess you need to
actually say eggsy cuz it probably just
couldn't find it so nevermind I didn't
need it looks like I actually did fix my
batch file so that's good I thought my
batch file was broken but it's not
nevermind alright so yeah so I can now
create a debug profile for this and I'm
just gonna save that off so that we have
it HH light prof so that way we can
quickly like run the thing and debug it
in whatever right so here we are in here
and you know we did some stuff and
whatever no one cares anyway so now if I
want to do this I should be able to say
like look split box is a thing right and
I should be able to actually call
exactly what we're doing so I can build
a spatial partition and then I can test
the spatial partition and all that good
stuff right so I should be able to
basically run exactly what I am running
here almost verbatim right like I should
be able to say all right like let's go
ahead and and run the spatial part you
know let's build the spatial partition
for lighting using an actual lighting
solution right so I should be able to do
something like this where I say like
build a spatial partition for the
lighting and I'll have to obviously and
in fact I suppose I could do that here
so if I pass a lighting solution to this
I should be able to then call bills
based purchase relating to build the
spatial partition that we actually have
I should then be able to also like
effectively just do the work
distribution so I should be able to say
look if I create a bunch of these work
units I should then be able to actually
call the ray caster right if I wanted to
now I don't know that I actually want
that per se what I might want to do
instead is say all right at the moment
you know maybe we want to do that
eventually at the moment I may just
literally only want to test the ray
caster like in a loop right so I may
instead want to say look I just want to
call this thing right so I want to call
this thing here so maybe I'm just
actually going to create a lighting work
structure and then I'm going to call ray
cast on that lighting work structure
with you know all of this garbage right
so if I wanted to do a raycast this way
I could just test this manually and not
actually do the work decision and I
think I might want to do that because I
want to be a little bit more specific
about what I'm testing like right now I
don't want to look at like the diffuse
texture builds and stuff like that so if
I actually went through the whole work
distribution pass it would do a bunch of
other stuff and I want to kind of just
look at the raycasting so kind of my
goal here is to get a little sign
program working that only is gonna cast
Rays that's all it does and then we can
profile just that you know just that
particular thing you know so if I'm
gonna do that I need a couple things I
need the spec and diffuse atlases and I
need the spec Texel right so if you look
at what's gonna happen in here and we
take a look at what's going on
we can sort of go through the lighting
solution and see everywhere it's
actually used so you know there's like
the root box index that should it filled
out there's a tee Update blend we're
gonna need right so up here we should
start setting those things like the T
Update blend and we don't really care
what that is as long as it's not a weird
singular value we should be able to set
it to anything we want since it's a
constant in here that I think we can
just set it to the exact same thing it's
like 8 over 60 or something I don't
actually remember what it's set to but
we should be able to basically say look
it's it's just this so you know we'll do
the same thing might as well know no
reason not to so if we take a look at
what's actually in the letting solution
up here and we take a look at what all
these things are we're gonna want to
actually set like most of them to be the
correct proxies of things we actually
would need for anything that actually
matters so like the Vox will have to get
set up the rest of things probably not
so much the fuse weight map should
probably get set up well actually no
we're gonna look look at that so the
sampling spheres should probably get set
up that's about the only thing I guess
that we would need there so let's make
sure the sampling spheres are up there
and then we need to set like all of this
stuff up right and that's going to come
from the file that we actually saved so
this stuff should get set up in the file
like from the file like here so we're
gonna set the box count and and this is
where we'd actually get you know we're
gonna we're gonna need like a malloc
here right to get to malloc and an F
Reed to get from the file the stuff that
actually goes in in the actual boxes
right and so we're gonna need to load
that up and that's totally fine we also
need a couple other things here probably
I would guess do we really know I maybe
we don't really need much that may be
mostly it so I think the only thing we
really need beyond there like I said is
the the lighting spheres we need
obviously but we can we can just get
them from the include file so the
lighting is spheres and then just the
voxel information and I think that's
that's most of it so let's go ahead and
set that so there's the Chi update blend
here's the random series there's the
sampling spheres we don't need the work
distribution array it's not necessary
the voxel dim and the in of Excel dim we
we probably do want right and hopefully
we can work that out fundamental unit we
may not have them not sure right let me
go ahead and if this out for one quick
second actually and this as well so
fundamental unit is something that gets
passed in probably yeah so I don't know
that we care about the fundamental unit
mmm at all probably won't matter other
than to profile our voxel lookups so
when we call in it lighting I suppose we
should probably double check and and
okay so it's 1.4 is what we were setting
so you know sure it doesn't I don't
think that actually matters like at all
what we set that to for the most part
but you know just to make sure profiling
as close as possible will keep the same
constants but you know there I don't
know that that's gonna make a
particularly big difference either way
alright so I think that's mostly what we
need to make all this stuff work so now
we're really talking mostly about spec
atlas diffuse atlas i don't know where
those are going to be coming from here
and so we're probably just gonna have to
set up fake versions and we're gonna
probably need to actually allocate the
memory for those just to make sure that
because you know this code writes in to
that so we kind of need to have that
backing buffer there so you know this we
can nerf temporarily just to get it
compiling but then we're gonna want to
actually generate raise the spec atlas
and diffuse that lists those are gonna
have to get passed in here like so so we
need those
and we can just use weekend to knit
those by doing and make light out let's
call so that shouldn't be a huge deal
and then we can just do it a test or a
cast call and this should you know run
the right caster right so I think that's
the setup we're looking for oops and I
don't know that we need to actually go
so far as to pass an actual spec Texel
at least for the kind of testing that
we're doing right now doesn't seem
particularly necessary so we should be
able to do is a get Texel call on it
more directly so when this thing
actually like if we look at the way the
lighting code was doing that when it's
actually doing the distribution on those
texels in the work callback which is
right here when it gets a Texel it does
it like this right so we should be able
to actually just do that right we should
be able to say look just get it I don't
care which one we're not profiling the
rights to the Texel at this particular
time so just give me something and we'll
pass that down and that you know that's
what you'll use so hopefully that gets
us to the point
oops hopefully that gets us to the point
where we're really just focusing on
loading up this initial data when we
look at those light Atlas calls again I
can if I want to and I you know I might
as well just go ahead and take where we
were doing the light Atlas generator
which
probably this right what I can do is say
look let's just do this so here's the
thing that oh that was not what I wanted
at all why did I paste that in there all
right
I meant to paste it in here so let's
just do this we'll actually use the
constants we can tweak these if we want
to but again I don't think we care so we
should then be able to say all right
here's the diffuse Atlas here's the spec
atlas and now they're initialized with
the actual settings that they should in
theory have right and then we would want
to I think and you know give them some
backing memory because otherwise it'll
write into nowhere so we probably do
want to do a thing where we at least do
call this so we probably do want to set
that a few setlist texels to some malloc
thing right so what we want to do here
is get the entire set we might actually
need and I think you can just do that
with a call that's like the give me the
size I think it's this so all that's
doing is saying look just allocate
however much memory this thing says it
needs and give it to it so that creates
a fake environment that's similar to the
one that runs in the game without too
much trouble all we need now is those
actual boxes so what we want to do here
is you know get a file size so we'd want
to do something like this for some
reason C runtime library and never
thought the size of the file would be
something you'd want to know um so if we
go ahead and do an F seek on this and
just do like a seek set
what seeks that seek end into an F tell
on it that should give us the file size
and then we can malloc the file size
right and I freed it I don't know the
box count in any particular way but I
can get it pretty easily just by saying
whatever the file size is that's how
many boxes there were right and it looks
like this has to be 16-bit because we
don't allow bigger than that right and
that's it that's our test app I think
that will literally do the whole thing
right now I don't actually want the
global debug table so I think what I'll
do here is turn that off so in here I'll
probably do it like a pound to fine like
handmade like undef handmade internal so
the debug code is gone I'll also turn
off handmade slow so basically like the
certs are gone the internal code the
debug code is gone and off we go so I
think that should recreate our test
scenario I don't know why this is still
here shouldn't be and now I think we can
save this highlight prop up so now I
think if we just load remedy it should
just be in our drop-down list we can
select the light prof and run it
right so I think we're all good I think
that's all we substituted and we should
be in good shape this I don't know if
there's a size issue there so if we look
at at the lighting solution here I don't
know if that's too big I want to move it
out for the stack I think it probably is
yeah
so there you go we're running our test
program everyone's happy
that actually in theory does an actual
rate cast I think so if we come through
here I mean in theory I this is a
release build you know what let's
actually step through it let's just do
it
so that's gonna be in work directory and
debug right step in open the dump file
how many boxes are there oops
not the best spelling in the world zero
what
did I flip I did I had dollar for every
time I did that typed enums it'd be nice
alright anyway let's go ahead and try
that one more time I'm like it ain't two
boxes fellas much better much better so
in theory if we read in these boxes now
like I should be able to sort of like
look at them and see that there's
actually some data in there that maybe
it's theoretically plausible right so
like you know those are good floats
right so you know looks look saying it's
kind of what I wanted and if I looked at
more of them so I could do like solution
boxes I think I can just like say I want
more of them right and then you know
still looks good so so you know that
looks looks reasonable if the Box had is
three for three
then maybe I want to look at box three
for two which is the last box just to
make sure that it doesn't get weird at
the end it doesn't appear to so that
seems fine so off we go so all right
that all looks fine now we have the
problem I think this should crash
immediately though because it doesn't
have room to create boxes right
shouldn't it theory yeah so we need to
pad out that box array and I don't
actually remember much about how that
gets done so I'm just gonna do it in a
sort of you know arbitrary way look you
know don't use four times more boxes
then you get inputted all right which
should be impossible because since it's
doing a binary split tree basically in
theory you know you shouldn't have more
than log n boxes added to the box set
right something like that you
order login it doesn't matter point
being I just want to give it some
Headroom and then I think we can run it
um so that looks like it's having
trouble with a box which I don't know
why it would here's the solution these
are fine obviously
[Music]
so what's it having trouble with box the
box that got must be a non not real box
yeah so what's the box index so that
does seem strange because we just saw
the box index set to something oh yeah
we want to allocate this many but we
don't want to tell it there's that many
so what we actually want to do here is
just allocate more boxes right so just
give it some overhead right some extra
space at the end to use which we're
gonna undo that in a minute anyway but
you know off we go
so let's see what's going on here so one
more thing we got to do it looks like is
we've got to fill out that work order so
I forgot to do that let's fill out that
work order so in the work order I don't
know that we can fill it we can't fill
in the commands really so we'll fill out
the solution voxel X can I think all the
rest of stuff could still be zero so I
think that's fine oops
and now we're all good so now we're
running the test and we're running the
test pretty reasonably right so we
created a you know fake environment we
then actually you know start we do ray
casting and so now all we really need at
this point I think is to actually put in
the sampling sphere randomness so
instead of calling ray cast like these
are two garbage values right
like that's not not sensible right so
think what we need to do now is actually
make some way of calling this with some
real code so if we look in here at where
the lighting is actually doing that call
you can see us getting the sampling
sphere out of here let's go ahead and do
that right so this sampling sphere pull
and then the pull out of the sampling
sphere I'm gonna copy that into the
light perf it'll look something like
this
right and that's how we'll get the Ray
origin in the rady now the origin I
don't care what the origin is
particularly much it would be nice if we
were using an origin that's like similar
to something that would be used in the
game zero zero zero isn't ridiculous so
maybe that is just what we'll use but
Ray Direction needs to actually be set
so we'll say that Ray Origin still that
will then say all right let's make a
four I loop here around the Ray casting
where we're gonna do it like over and
over and over and over and over and over
right so we'll say like der sample index
equals zero
Duras antal index is less than you know
some really large number of of things
we're doing here so we're gonna rake a
stand ray cast and ray Kasten ray cast
and then we're gonna ray cast some more
we'll go ahead and say oops I said this
just be empty index sorry
we'll then figure out which sampling
sphere we're trying to actually sample
here as you can see and then we'll pull
out you know the Ray bundle index off of
off of that right now the Ray bundle
index I don't know where that actually
gets set it looks like so that's a
separate loop inside of here that loops
over the total number of Ray bundles
that there actually are and so we should
probably mimic that behavior right to a
certain extent so we should probably say
that we do it like this and the Ray
bundle like that like index thing will
just go over every single one because
that's sort of what would be happening
in the actual app so we then pull out
the sampling sphere for whatever a
directional sample we're looking at and
I guess we could do that here and then
we pull out the Ray bundles for each
particular bundle yeah that seems
reasonable and so now if I run it it
should sit there for a while do a bunch
of ray casts and exit and we're probably
gonna have to like lean on it really
hard to make sure that it just does a
crap ton of ray cast like rate castrate
castrate castrate castrate cast and the
reason for that if we want to analyze
the profile of this and we want to look
at how expensive it is to do these ray
casts we're gonna want to look at a
representative slice in the middle and
as you'll see it when I go to use vtune
the sort of bloated bilious vtune i'm
gonna need a way of not having it time
or a bunch of random crap and so a bunch
of that random crap is stuff like how
long did it take you to load the file
right like the dump file you know I
don't want it to count any of that stuff
because if you're getting a bunch of
cache misses and when you go into the
kernel load a file well that's not gonna
give me any information so what I want
to do is I want to make sure the program
that I run and there's different is you
can you can actually like include a DLL
and in in your building where
and include deals wrong you luteolin
tell use you know do a get proc address
to vtune to say here's where to start
pro flying here's have to stop but a
much easier way to do it that doesn't
involve any like you know poison the
code in that way is to just actually
make sure your application does a
crap-ton of the thing and then just tell
vtune to start profiling ten seconds in
or five seconds in right because at that
point you know that all of the cash
stuff and all of the kernel transitions
for a like loading filed on all that
crab already happened right that already
happened and you don't need to worry
about it it's not gonna get counted in
the profile and it's just gonna jump on
in and start profiling the part that's
the actual mead the algorithm that we
care about so that's what i want to
happen here and so you know this piece
of code would just would just do that
right so what i want to do is make sure
that i have enough of these let's say
that we're just gonna keep on doing this
until you know a heat death of the
universe and all that and so i run it
and you know it stays up for a good long
time ray casting and doing its thing you
know ray casting red cast and red
casting ray casting and then eventually
it will actually exit that's maybe too
much let's back off a little
still maybe longer than I need
seems pretty good although I might even
drop it down a little bit more so I
didn't really need to spam it much it
was pretty good alright so now we have a
single threaded standalone app if we so
if we literally just want to look at
sort of the fake theoretical behavior of
our routine we now can do that because
we have an isolated fake case that shows
us theoretically what's going on now
it's not an exact replica and we don't
actually want it to be because the exact
replica is the thing that runs in the
game what we're wanting to do now is
take away some of that variability and
just look at like theoretically if we're
just trying to push this crap through
the processor the way that we were on a
single thread so we don't have multiple
threads contending not to hyper threads
none of those things can you just tell
us sort of what's going on in our code
so we can start to tweak it and just see
what the what the result is behaviorally
that's what we're trying to do here and
you'll have to forgive me for my I am
not good at vtune I normally just use a
Linux machine and run perf which I find
much easier to use the the vtune kind of
weirds me out and it's got all this
weird like like trappings that just I
don't know it's I don't understand why
it has to be so complicated I just want
like Intel out there if you're listening
you're not but let's say you were I just
want something where I can just like do
this in my coat I don't want any of this
like I wish I could just I don't know it
doesn't matter point being inside vtune
this is what it looks like I they made
it free and thank you in television that
used to charge exorbitant amount of
money for vtune so nobody used it but
they eventually made it free for like if
you don't like there's some part of it
that you don't get I don't even know it
doesn't matter the point is it's free
now and you can just install it on your
machine you just make an account you can
install it and that's good and so if you
want to I can create like like I'm doing
here a new project I could create a
vtune project that I can store and I'll
do it in this work temp directory
because I don't know
if I don't really want to pollute all my
stuff but will basically say like
alright let's call this like ehh light
Propst
HH light prof create project and what I
should be able to do now is you know
just tell it I want you to take a look
at this application and start to tell me
stuff about it that are based on
profiling counters that are in the cpu
right so normally I just want to access
that stuff and you see me do that in
handy here before our entire ProFlowers
built on the fact that we could just
call our TTS C which is read time stamp
counter which basically says get me this
particular performance counter that's
inside the Intel CPU that just basically
tells me how many roughly clock ticks
went by at any particular time great
there's a whole other set of performance
profiling counters in there and when I
say there's a whole other set I mean
like you have no idea if you've never
done this kind of profiling before so
you've never looked at the perf counters
on a modern axis or a processor you are
in for a treet slash headache because oh
my god you have no idea how many things
you can profile in a modern X's for CPU
there are so many that I'm willing to
bet that there's almost nobody on planet
Earth who actually knows what they all
are it's gonna say that there's probably
very few people I've actually done
passes where I profile every perf
counter that I know of it's like in the
hundreds and I only know what some of
them actually measure like there are
probably I don't remember how many there
are
I actually did know exactly how many
there were that I that I could find
documentation for I want to say that out
of those there were probably 10 maybe 20
that I literally just have no idea what
they actually count I just don't know
a lot of them you can tell by reading
it's like oh this counts any time like
you know the CPU missed the l2 cache and
this happened or whatever right but some
of them I'd like read and
I don't even know what this counts there
are so many of them so anyway with that
out of the way we're just gonna be doing
some basic work with this we're not
going to try to do anything that fancy
at all so we're gonna go to HH light
prof here we're going to pass in that
light dump or sorry I just want exactly
this right I want to run exactly what
we're running so I want to run that and
I want the working directory to be the
same working directory so we know that
it will work right we don't need to set
anything else up in here because nothing
particular is happening the only thing
we need is this bit here that I was
saying we want to that's not it
where is it
here it is here it is okay sorry I'll
automatically resume collection after
sec and automatically stop collection
after sec that's what we want to
actually look at here so what I want to
be able to do is say all right I want
you to I want you to basically start the
app and for like two or three seconds
let's say maybe five seconds or
something like that right
don't take any profiling so I think
that's all I probably have to do I like
I said I haven't used this in a while
and it's hard for me to remember
sometimes exactly what I have to do I
think that should do it right so anyway
that's what we need here to have a way
to launch the application and then what
we want to do up here is you can see
like I want Hardware of a event based
sampling that's just saying it's gonna
take a look at what's going on in the in
the hardware to count the the counters
that I asked it for right and I don't
remember
analysis type ok wait the duration time
estimate option is deprecated use the
CPU sampling interval option on the
analysis type configuration pane okay so
you're telling me don't set this wait I
don't understand I can't not set this
okay I don't know what to make of that
but okay so in analysis type which I
think is in here yeah okay
so what we want to do here you know and
and there's a couple different things we
can do obviously we can start checking
the hotspots just to see what it thinks
are the performance bottlenecks which is
also good but microarchitecture
explanation is what I want apply do
eventually and that's just the thing
that lets me look at the actual code and
see what we think is going on there
let's just see what happens here I like
I said I'm really bad at using vtune so
we'll see I'm gonna go ahead and start
it let's see if it works it should
unpause the collection automatically it
does and there we go right so hopefully
now I will get some actual information
here what you can see in terms of what
it's telling me about what it saw the
the I don't think we've ever talked
about a lot of this stuff on Hanneman
here so I'm not sure where to start
there's a couple different things that
we now need to start looking at to start
to make this code run high-performance
right so there's two separate things one
thing is making sure that the code
itself is doing the smartest set of
operations that it can do right this
tool will not tell us anything about
that so the thing that I was talking
about before that we're gonna want to
look at possibly even first and so I
just wanted to get a run of it with the
existing codes why we're looking at this
I don't necessarily need this
information right away but so we have to
go think about whether we're actually
doing the ops we should be doing in the
first place and stuff like that
this tool can't tell us anything about
that right the second part is saying for
the ops that we're actually doing right
like when we actually decide we need to
do this stuff how close have we gotten
to actually utilizing the chip with
those ops right and sometimes we may be
in a situation where like there's really
not much we can do so we look at the
code and we're like well we have to do
this stuff there's no way we can really
utilize a chip very well with this stuff
so that we're just we're out of luck
right but other times we can look and go
oh ok I see using it too like this we
can say I see why we're underutilizing
the CPU and there's ways we can fix that
right so you know looking at this you
can maybe starters make some
translations it doesn't matter right now
because we're not even in a release mode
built right so this you know we don't
really care about right so let's start
by just saying all right let's run a
build I think I can just I think I can
just run a builds right let's just run a
build that's with optimizations on so
this should be some reasonable code in
theory let's see what the hospitai asks
this looks like just to make sure we're
actually getting that although actually
Oh
so the problem is that's now running so
fast we're gonna have to add more delay
to it so let me go ahead and and and
just up that
that's that's still not long enough all
right so my estimate before was actually
accurate it's just I forgot we were in a
debug build so that's better so now I'm
gonna go ahead and say alright let's go
ahead and rerun this I think I can just
do this again in the the porgy of
windows in here I did I don't even know
but anyway there's the yeah there's the
sort of information that we got this is
not a diagram we can use because this is
talking about multi-threading if we want
to go profile the work completion and we
start multiple threads or something then
we can start looking at this but this
doesn't really tell us anything because
this is just looking at core utilization
and we know we're only looking at the
single thread right now so this is
actually the number that we care about
right here right the micro architectural
usage and if we look at that we can kind
of see that the disk pretty it's
actually pretty high 80 percent of
pipeline slots filled is is not terrible
right so you know I it looks like the
code itself right at this point is not
super bad I forget how you get all this
stuff you actually want here so you know
if we look at what the code looks like
let me see if I can
I'm not sure I thought you could see no
I thought you could see more than that
maybe it's this no there we are
um yeah okay so you know if we take a
look at the code in terms of hotspot
analysis so this is kind of it's it's
not really very good necessarily so you
you don't want to put like too much
faith in it but if you take a look at
the raycast routine you know this on the
side the cpu time like list here on the
side is sort of maybe kind of a little
bit possibly sometimes trying to tell
you like where you are seeing like more
you know more or less time spent in the
system and you can see it's sort of
correlates like they look there's a lot
of total time was estimated was spent
you know through this you know branch
here which makes sense I I don't know if
this maybe compiled in a weird way cuz
the fact that this isn't shown it all
doesn't really make any sense
but I'm assuming it's because this got
collapsed down in some way or something
I don't really know what the cloud did
we have it looked but again you can kind
of see like yeah in this code is super
crappy which we kind of expect this is
you know makes very good sense when
array misses it's doing this kind of
assignment to a you know v3 it's not
particularly smart about it's doing it
scaler not in the ssee
and blah blah blah blah blah right so we
you know that makes sense to see that
and so on I don't know I tend to not put
a lot of faith in this because sampling
based profiles I don't really know
I don't know that I really trust them so
I tend to not use this view but I just
wanted to show it to you so what we
actually care about here and what we'll
probably be using it for we're at the
end of the stream for today but you know
tomorrow when we start actually working
on optimization what I actually want to
do is go to the micro architecture
analysis so in here what we can do is
say all right hotspots we don't really
care about that I don't trust you anyway
we know it's just that one routine or
optimizing it's not a big deal we're not
asking you to tell us you know find the
trees in the forest kind of a situation
or the needle in the haystack this is
more what we want to do you know memory
access or microarchitecture exploration
so in here if I say micro tech micro
architecture exploration this is where
those performance counters I was talking
about come into play this can tell us
stuff like how long were you waiting on
instruction decode how long were you
waiting for a cache to come back filled
you know how many times did you stall on
that how many times did you go to try an
issue a you know an ad and there was
nowhere to put the ad so you have to
just wait till a nail you finished you
know these sorts of things right and so
this is where we can get that
information from right and I don't
actually know so these are the actual so
this is why it's remember I said there's
a lot of them this is and this isn't
even all of them here's an example of
some of the of the things that can count
right like these are all on the chip it
can count these things it's insane right
um so anyway if we run a mark
microarchitecture exploration and you
know we go ahead and let this let this
do it do its thing
area now what we can see is if we look
at the the way that the trying to think
of how to explain this so now if we look
at the way that the CPU was actually
chewing through our instructions then at
least if this summary is to be believed
which like I said you you have to take
some of these things with a grain of
salt what you can see is look here in
the here in this breakdown
on the back end you know part of the the
CPU what you can see is how much use
were we getting out of our al use okay
and what you can see here is that one
the the ALUs are based off of ports the
way that the Intel architecture works
we've talked about some Hamming here
before there's port 0 port 1.2.3.4 port
5 6 &amp; 7 are not as much what we were
looking at here but there's a set of
ports right and you can see them listed
here
each of these ports corresponds to a
certain set of instructions it can
execute each instruction can be executed
on only specific ports to support that
instruction so when we're looking at the
performance of the CPU we have these
instructions they're going through the
front end right which is taking the
instructions that we give it decoding
them into specific things can be exiting
the port's handing them after the ports
and our goal to make sure that a piece
of code runs as fast as possible if
we're not going to change the sort of
actual algorithm that uses is to make
sure that we try to utilize as many
ports as possible as often as possible
right now a modern x64 chip can decode
four instructions per cycle that's it so
on any individual cycle there is
literally no way you're ever going to
execute more than
for micro tech micro architectural
actual true operations now some
operations aren't actually operations
something like a move from one register
to another isn't an actual operation so
we're talking about things like port
utilization there's some things that
happen up here in the front end that's
the thing that decodes the instructions
remaps things around that sort of stuff
right so we don't really care about that
what we care about is this at the moment
and that's adding things you know
multiplies that stuff that's what's
happening shifts all that stuff that's
what's happening on these ports we want
to see every cycle several of these
ports used right we wanna we wanna hope
that when we look at this thing
lots of ports are being used every cycle
because if no ports are being used on
lots of cycles right this number right
here that's terrible that happens when
you stall on memory or something else so
you're literally just sitting around
doing nothing if you only have like one
or two ports used oftentimes like just
one I'm sorry one thing if you have like
one port user to port used that means
well you're doing work but that work is
like serially dependent so we can't
issue like an ad here and an ad here and
have them going at the same time we have
to wait for like the result of that app
we're get to another one right when you
see three or more ports utilize you are
happy days right because that means that
you're actually doing a lot of actual
work right so that's great right when we
see that that we have like a high number
of our port utilization percentage
breakdowns ends up being in the the
three plus we're happy about that that's
what we want to see we don't want to see
a lot down in here right so if we take a
look in here and we see some
so if you take a look at hearing me say
like okay you know a hundred percent of
the time was spent retiring slots right
like what is that even trying to say
right and you can see like each of those
things like what I just said if you
hover over this it says something so
some of those like that may not really
tell you much you probably need an
explanation more like mine but some of
them like this is more explicable right
like pipeline slots fraction use my
useful work meaning the issue do you ops
that eventually got retired ideally all
pipelines slots would be a tribute to
the retiring category retiring without
set right whatever
so this particular metric here right is
just letting us know it's basically
another way of saying we didn't we
didn't have this problem right because
basically what happens is when you issue
all these instructions if you have lots
of branching that fails or if you have a
lot of situations where like it thought
it was gonna do one thing and it
actually ended up doing another you can
end up throwing away a lot of work and
so what you don't want to see is that
like you your actual retire rate was
very low right your actual number of
instructions that you actually then used
you don't want to see that going down so
I in this case I guess it's basically
just telling us like we didn't have a
lot of misprediction problems or things
where stuff got thrown away which which
is good right okay so when we look at
what's actually going on here the only
thing that I don't quite understand what
I'm looking at this is like that doesn't
add up to the right thing and this is
why I say I'm bad at vtune so when we
look at backhand bound right you know
like you would expect to see something
that told us we were bottlenecks
somewhere right so you know in this case
it's like you're looking at this and I'm
going well
you don't think I'm front-end bound and
you don't think I'm back in bound
so like what do you think is happening
and so I'm not sure I understand it
right and another way to say that is
like because I'm not you know I don't
normally use it vtune when I look at
this and I look at the port utilization
here right and I and ice and I look at
the breakdown of that number so it says
like the port utilization is like you
know something like 50% total right like
the dividers at 10.5 and you know 20 I
mean we just look at that number right
so I have twenty nine point eight plus
ten point five that's that's like you
know forty forty percent I don't
understand why I'm only seeing that and
it's not telling me where the rest of
it's going right and so you know we can
look up here cycles per instruction
retired
that's a weird metric I usually like to
think of it the other way around right
which is how many instructions per cycle
I did retire so if we invert that number
we get 3.2 that suggests to me that like
again this number is really the number
that should have been like shouldn't
that be like close to a hundred percent
right because what I don't understand is
like if this is our actual CPI rate what
where's the extra clocks going so I
don't know I've always had this problem
with until you I don't use it I mean I
should use it more because it's you know
that way I don't have to go over to
Linux machine to do the sampling but so
I often have this problem where it's
hard I don't understand how they're
choosing it rather there's like stuff
like this always confusing me actin
mainly read it myself then I see that
it's like oh it's close to 4 which is
the max we could possibly get yet these
numbers do
suggest the same thing right this should
be like 90 right so I get confused about
that right
I just don't know um so you know we'll
pushing this maybe before tomorrow I'll
take a look at some of the docks or
vtune and try to get a little bit better
at understanding this but that's what
we're looking at right now stimuli like
I said before and we can set which
things we want to look at there as well
I believe there's a way so if you go
into microarchitecture analysis I think
you can do something that allows you to
get access to this I just forget what it
is
so I really just can't remember how you
unlock that maybe you have to buy the
season pass
[Music]
so I don't remember how you get this
thing to turn on oh do I have to run it
in a special I don't know we'll look
this up before next time because I would
like to know because I've got to get I
basically have to get to the point where
I can do the same thing I do with Linux
perf on this if we want to actually look
at stuff so I'll look it up but either
way so the other thing you can run in
vtune right is the memory analysis thing
and the memory analysis thing is just it
collects different data on the run right
so instead of looking primarily at the
performance counters that are about
back-end usage and stuff like that here
we can get the information about things
like cache misses right so here you can
see like look here's when you were bound
on each of your particular types of on
each of the things that you've actually
got so in l1 cache l2 cache the DRAM
right so this is telling us how our
memory profile looks and as you can see
it's pretty squeaky clean right
according to this we basically never
miss the cache in theory right so you
know optimizing for the cache
wouldn't presumably help us much here if
this is to be believed so anyway that's
you can see why I did all that
that's the isolation process we now have
a clean way to measure the performance
of the program so tomorrow we could do
is we could start making some targeted
changes to it we could see how the
profile changes we can also put in a
little counter in here so we can just
run the program and see if we get faster
or slower so there's a little bit of
that we can do this just sets us up for
success okay so you could see why I did
that so we could just take targeted
evaluation and we can see by metrics
whether we're getting better or worse
let's go to a brief QA and I'm gonna
have some lunch
and I want to say I want to say that
there's some jomblo Sean Barrett action
going on later today if I'm not wrong
about that so we'll try and skip over to
that after this stream is is done
might be a good idea to explain the
difference between sampling and
instrumentation ProFlowers and how they
work on some basic level and why
sampling profile is not a great idea
despite most people believing and
telling you that it is very good yeah
sure I'm happy to do so so you heard me
say the hotspot analysis I showed you
that thing and I said like an early
trustees number like like I said some
stuff that was dismissive of the hotspot
analysis why did I say that well the
reason I was dismissive of the hotspot
analysis is the hotspot analysis does
something called sampling based
profiling and what that does is it says
look I'm just gonna randomly interrupt
this process periodically and I'm gonna
see where the instruction pointer is and
I'm gonna assume that that is where the
program is slow and the reason for that
is because typically you're sitting
inside your hot loops most of the time
so if we just go ahead and see where you
are most of the time periodically that
should tell us where you're slow this is
not a bad idea in principle and if it's
hardware-assisted meaning your hardware
has good capabilities for collecting IP
logs without actually affecting the
runtime of the program which actually
x64 is due for certain things for
branches for example it can be okay
I don't know that vtune actually does
any of that I think vtune literally just
interrupts your process periodically I
could be wrong about that so as a result
it's actually not a very good measure
for the performance of the program
because it's actually changing the way
the programmer runs quite a bit it's
just not a great way to look at it so
the way that we do profiling handmade
hero and the way that will do profiling
here for our actual speed is we just use
our DTSC around the block we're trying
to time right and you've seen me do that
multiple times that's how I like to find
hotspots now again like I said hardware
assisted sampling base profiling is not
necessarily a bad idea but I don't
really trust me tunes hot-swap profiler
so I don't use it and it's because I
just don't trust the sampling that does
so sorry if I didn't explain that
vtune organizes those metrics by
something called the top-down before its
analysis methodology there's a pre
detail paper that introduces this that
would likely help maybe I'll take a look
if you're tried using clang CL to drop
in placement drop in em SVC can paddle
compiler there's much better code gen
than MSB CCL it's compatible with link
tag C but even LOD link will give you
usual PDB so I tried it my retrace where
it ended up being 15 times faster than
with regular my c CL it sounds like your
ray tracer was a little bit busted but
ok um have a meow hash the distribution
of your meow hash compiles on both clang
CL and M SVC um I would caution you to
so the thing you said which is it has
much better code done Jen that MSV CL is
false so clang CL has better code gen
for some things and worse code gen for
other things so for example clang CL
compiles meow hash worse than ms v CL ms
v CL is better the MS v CL compiled code
is faster than clangs that's how it is
so I would caution you to say it like
clang CL is not better than ms v CL it's
different and if you really want to know
which one compiler code faster you have
to test it some cocoa bio much faster
thanks yell some will compile much
better in SPL one thing that I can tell
you is clang CL is a minefield of
undefined behavior nonsense one of the
reasons they do better coach at some
times is because they screw up your code
and introduce a bunch of bugs right so I
would also say be very careful of that
clang CL is very bad at being
trustworthy about producing good quality
code because anytime they can use a you
be trick they do which will introduce
like security bugs or regular bugs and
so on
and so I would just warn you about that
so clang CL yet not bad I have used it
it's a totally reasonable it's not
better than msel
it's different sometimes the compiles go
better some is compiles code worse
and you could pick the one that seems to
be better for your project games like
csgo go up to 300 frames per second are
they pretty good optimized seems like
getting him here because this would be
hard actually getting him here up this
would be trivial you just put the Ray
casting on the GPU or pre compute the
lighting so you know counter-strike go
doesn't have real-time lighting you know
it doesn't doesn't do that all the
indirect lighting is baked so they just
don't run that pass and hey if we didn't
if we just pre baked the letting him
handmade hero that would just go away
and currently that's where all of our
time goes basically if we wanted to
speed up the render side of things
there's many ways we can do that as well
so 300 check in to him here would
actually pretty easy if that makes sense
oh we left an extra you're right we did
thank you for that catch
what's to say Samuel hatch will be
reaching a new version soon uh probably
we will release an 0.6 sometime soon
yeah I just haven't had time to do so
Oh point five is still I think the best
hash that there is it's a very fast hash
that's much more secure than any of the
other non cryptographic hashes you can
use so I think 0.5 is already great but
0.6 you know we're just trying to
finalize a few things so that we can
call it standard
have you tried it buggin by the stream
there's so many frames to move the
character around it's just because I'm
recording it's just OBS being dumb you
know it's got a hard job to do it's got
a record video and stream video and it
it just can't handle recording and
streaming at this at the same time at
60fps because the stream I think goes
out at like 30 fps or something right
what should me I'll hash not be used for
um it's there's a very very clear
explanation if you want to know about
that so this page so meow hash is by
Jacob and myself and this is no hack
coder is Jacob this page explains
explicitly what hash levels are right
and basically like meow hash is a level
three hash level four and level five
hashes are like what you would typically
call cryptogram while level 5 hash
really is what you would typically call
a cryptographic hash so that's one where
you need it to be very strong against
adversaries who know the seed for
example level three is a reduced level
of security but it's not like most
hashes that are non cryptographic are
like this right they're not even this
most are like this they might not even
be level one sometimes but anyway so in
the case of a level three hash what it
basically tries to guarantee is that if
you use it an attacker who doesn't know
the seed can't generate a collision
right and you know it's based on
probabilities and stuff like that so you
know you have to figure out like okay
what was the bit depth and all that sort
of stuff but a level three hash is
basically a hash where if the attacker
doesn't know the seed they cannot
generate a collision
you can't that in my ass is one of those
you can't for example use that kind of a
hash for something like digital
signatures because in that case everyone
knows the seeds the seeds public
so in the case where the seed is public
you can't be using something like a
level three hash you'd have to use
something like a level five hash right
what you can use a level three hash for
is anything that might have an adversary
still but where the seed isn't known a
hash table at the front end of a server
for example there's been a lot of denial
of service attack kind of stuff that
happens because people used a crappy
hash and the hackers figured that out
and were able to craft all their packets
to hit the same line of the hash table
which takes down the server right
similarly you can use it for something
like meth message what are they called
max message authentication like it's for
like message authentication codes
between two people like stuff like that
can use it for that so there's a lot of
uses for meow hash cuz it's a lot better
than a normal non cryptographic hash and
it's the fastest hash so it's faster
than all the other non cryptographic
hashes and it's stronger than that but
it's not a cryptographic hash so you
can't use it like the kind we typically
call cryptographic hash you can't use it
in circumstances where you circulate the
key either the seed
are you sure the hash is secure people
have previously pointed out some issues
with meow hash Jenny collisions yes
we're quite sure it's secure so nobody's
ever found a collision in Maya hash 0.5
that wasn't standard birthday paradox so
basically the 128-bit the full 128 bits
meow hash
no one's ever found a collision ever in
0.5 and in if you just look at the
bottom 64 bits you would expect to be
able to find collisions if you tried if
you look at the bottom 64 bits and you
try more than 4 billion random attempts
then you should start to be able to find
collisions based on the birthday paradox
right it's very hard to do that because
you need a machine with a lot of memory
to do it but it was recently done and we
performed better than anyone else on the
test
amusingly so you can actually look at it
here
so here you go so our old version which
was not a level 3 hash you can see that
there were collisions when you run
randomly a hundred a hundred million
hashes and check if any of them collide
with each other right um for 40.5 we
were actually below the expected rate
and that's basically as low as anyone
got besides like I guess its ex ex age
64 but this is edit but we're basically
the same and that's a meaningless number
because it's really just random it
should only be it just has to be at like
the birthday paradox level so that's if
you only use the bottom 64 bits of meow
hash if you actually is the whole 64 bit
120 pets no one's ever found one right
so yeah so meow hash five is so far
rock-solid
no one's ever found a collision in it
and if you go looking for collisions in
the low bits by truncating them down to
a point where you know you should be
able to produce collisions in any hash
even a cryptographic hash we perform
exactly like a cryptographic hash in
that case we produce exactly the
expected number of collisions what do
you use me I ask for everything it's
like the only hash function I use now
would hand me here run a 3G bit system
or it needs some porting it probably
needs a little bit of porting right even
security well like I just said I don't
use meow hash for public message signing
but I don't write any code for public
message signing so the things that I
wouldn't use the the things where I
would need extremely strong
cryptographic hash where you can
circulate the seed I don't have that
case but yeah meow hash we believe it to
be secure for the specific case we
talked about which is if you are not
circulating the seed then we believe it
is a strong hash oh crap that we didn't
finish this I'm glad I'm glad people on
the chat are watching
thank you
miss Miao has cross-platform that's one
of the things we're putting it in 0.6 so
it is in the sense that forearm and x64
they both have acceleration for AES so
you get very good performance on those
platforms PowerPC I don't have so I
don't know anything about the
performance profile on a PowerPC I just
have no idea we're not targeting that
and we really don't care
we basically only care about consumer
hardware that's what it's for
so I don't care what it runs on a
PowerPC
but that said it might be fine I don't
know anything that has a AES support in
hardware which is a lot of hardware
these days can be accelerated on me on
hash quite a bit anything that doesn't
will be slower but how much slower
hard to say
any reason we're not using the
checkerboard rendering yeah just because
I think we're B I think we're fast
enough without it so I don't think we're
gonna need it are you talk about our
lighting we did the checkerboard
lighting thing and then we turned it off
is that what you're talking about you
talk about something else
you don't actually check our board like
rasterization or something you know I'm
overtime anyway I should I should go um
alright so I'm gonna I'm gonna wind down
the stream here right and I just I don't
know what's going on with the stream
[Music]
so this specifically says like 3 p.m.
Pacific time which is like 30 minutes
from now John and Shawn are supposed to
have a stream so it's not up yet but
[Music]
yeah rational coder you use meow hash
for normal hash tools in your everyday
code oh absolutely yeah yeah yeah
all right so I not hearing anything
about when this is going up so look
here's the thing I don't really know
exactly what's going on but in theory in
30 minutes
there should be a stream with John and
Shawn talking about compilers if you
like the one that John and I did then
this is more of that so you should check
it out I don't actually know how to make
it easier to get to it but you know
twitch TV slash naysayer 88 or go to
Twitter Jonathan Blow and and watch that
that's that's about all I got so please
check that out I'll try to raid the
channel after but you know I'll be
honest I don't think that's gonna work
because since they're not live people
probably won't stay there but so I was
kind of hoping that they were at least
running a like nominal stream so anyway
thanks for joining us for another thanks
for joining me
further episode of handmade hero it has
been a pleasure cooking for you as
always I'm glad we got a little test app
setup tomorrow we can start to tweak
that and actually take a look at the
performance characteristics of a red
caster and optimize those to where we
think we need to be that's it for today
until tomorrow
have fun programming everyone and I'll
see you on the Internet
check out that John blue Shawn Barrett
stream if you get a chance should be
happening at 3 p.m. Pacific Standard
Time again that's a half hour from now
the webinar so that should be twitch.tv
slash naysayer 88 alright take it easy
everybody