start groaning hello everyone and
welcome to handmade Hero the show where
we code a complete game live on stream
we are doing some animation coding
basically showing how to do some some
handmade animation code and it's really
good you know learning to do handmade
animation code is really a pretty good
idea to do before you ever implement a
general animation system like loading
and playing back animations is a fine
thing to do and you typically want to do
it if you're on a team that's got a
bunch of artists who have tools they can
use to make animations you obviously
want that but it's always a good idea to
first cut your teeth on some hand coded
animation and the reason for that is
because it will get you familiar with
the concepts and how to do sort of the
sets of things you might want to do in
animation code and it allows you to make
much more dynamic stuff and so then in
the future when you do use an animation
system or however you're doing it where
they're externally authored you can
still jump in and times when it's it's
the right thing to do to have something
procedural kick in you're not like I
don't know what to do right so it's kind
of nice it's a good thing I think that
most programmers should know how to do
now like I said we're kind of right in
the middle of it today's day 275 so if
you want to follow along day 274 our
source code is the one that you want to
work with I'm gonna load up for coder
here and and made Raj let's go get this
going on and run it all right
so essentially what I was working on was
I was making this sort of code here
where I could I could make the dude hop
along and we're sort of getting to a
nice place on it but we have a big to-do
left which as you can obviously see at
the moment the the head we just worked
on the body animation and we let the
head go wherever it wants now that would
be fine if this was some kind of ghost
child and you know the head of the child
is supposed to be able to float around
just like a separate thing but that is
not at all what the game is the game is
actually supposed to have a child who's
head is attached to his body so we need
to
figure out you know some way of of
starting to make the body part stretch
up towards the head so even when it's a
bit far away it can sort of reach you
know what I mean
and so how exactly we're gonna do that
I'm not sure because obviously there are
some considerations with how it's going
to look but we don't have a whole lot of
options one of the things that you have
to remember about games in general and
it's kind of just unfortunate but it's
the truth is that responsiveness is very
important and so when you're coding the
interface you know you're gonna code if
you're a responsible game developer
you're gonna code it so it feels good
right and you're not going to sacrifice
that feel just so the animation looks
better because that's just a bad idea
now if you want to know what that feels
like go back to the very original say
Prince of Persia or Cara TECA
for example the original Jordan Mechner
games there those were examples of games
that decided to just let animation
determine entirely what was going to
happen and the controls feel absolutely
100% awful as a result you basically
like you know you hit jump and your guy
like runs for a while and then jumps
because that's what the animation did or
whatever right and it just feels awful
to play and so that's the kind of thing
you want to steer clear of in my opinion
when you're programming the game you
want to do the opposite you want to let
the design or the designer make whatever
is what to feel good and then you do
whatever you can to make the animations
not look bad as a result but you don't
ever go well this animation kind of look
bad because of this you know the player
could turn too quickly so I'm gonna like
force them to turn more slowly
that's just rarely a good idea at least
the games that feel sluggish and the
controls don't feel responsive or so you
know if your designer tells you to do
that that's one thing but as a
programmer if your responsibility to not
get in the way of the design like that
so figure out how to write your
animation systems so that they respond
to what the player must do not so that
they force the player to do things that
they didn't want to do in the first
place I feel pretty strongly about that
and I think most players probably do too
so that's what we're gonna do here we're
gonna go ahead and say well you know if
it looks kind of weird and stretchy
that's okay we'll just say that's part
of the style and we're not gonna try and
fix that by forcing the head to not move
too far or anything like that all right
so as this hops along what I'm gonna try
to do first well there's a couple things
I want you first I want to do a little
bit of cleanup first and maybe I don't
know if we'll get to the body stretching
thing today that's our next major to do
but I've got some smaller - duze mm-hmm
that I need to work on as well and one
of the big to-do is that I need to work
on is already the head doesn't I'm sorry
it's not only big to use one of the
primary minor things is it feels a
little bit I don't like the feel right
now and the reason for that is that
spring that we added on that brings you
back to the body that spring should not
be springing to where the body is it
should be springing well two things
first of all it should be only springing
if I'm not using if I'm not actively
trying to move in direction obviously
which i think is okay at the moment like
I think that's we turn that off but when
I do let go I don't want it to suck back
towards the body I want it to suck to
wherever the body's gonna end up right
so I essentially want the head just like
to snap to a point whatever the closest
point is to the head regardless of
whether the body's gotten there yet
right so all I'm really gonna do there
and don't ask me why I closed the
program I always close the program for
no reason that's just what I do
apparently let's launch that back up
again all I'm gonna do here at first for
that is I'm gonna go into world mode
where we're doing that sort of closest
point thing and I'm going to take the C
here oops
and I should be over here what I'm gonna
do is I'm gonna go into this code for
the hero head and I'm gonna pull out the
code that I was using for the hero body
so that I can search for the closest
point in both cases right and this is
actually an important step for the code
anyway because eventually we're gonna
want you know we don't really want to do
all of these tests we want a spatial
query you know we've got to do right
here for it so it's true in general that
I'm going to want to be able to issue
some of these spatial queries and
accelerate them so I'd like to get in
the habit of calling a function do that
anyway because that function is gonna
get a lot more complicated and I want
lots of people to have access to however
it's going to work all right so I'm just
gonna pull that out here into a little
thing that you know Jimmy that goes
through and does its thang something
probably like this sort of a thing
because I'm just computing well I guess
I really only need the closest p-part so
I'm going to take this out I'm gonna
drop this here and I'm gonna say all
right internal void get closest
traversable and that's gonna go ahead
and that's going to go ahead and say
well from whatever point I'm starting
with and we'll just assume that that's
gonna replace the entity point that we
were using before well I guess we should
say really frumpy and default P might be
the better way to do it something like
that probably although the other way I
could do it is like this maybe we we
have a pool that says whether or not we
found one and then we write the result
if we did so we'll basically say like
found equals false and in here we would
say like found equals true because we
got one
and then we'd write closest P to result
although really I guess I can just sort
of say well get rid of this and just say
that this is result equals that like so
so what comes out of here I don't know
if I need a struct though because I
don't know whether I used closest
distance it looks like I didn't but you
know we probably will need to augment
this function as we go further because
people are plugging a lot more when we
do these facial queries plugin I have to
provide more information than what we're
giving here but you know I rather than
be premature about it I'll just let that
happen when it happens
obviously I need the sim region here
because that's the thing that we're
looping over and that'll be the thing
that eventually has a spatial query
inside of it we've got the from P which
is what we're actually testing so in
here instead of head P we're talking
about from P and I think that's roughly
everything there is to it
so I'm gonna then go ahead and change
the hero head code in here to use that
well I I guess I should do the body one
first obviously so I'm gonna say here
that we've got that closest P and the
closest P is going to be like get
closest reversible and it's going to
take the region and it's going to be the
closest thing to the head and this is
going to be oh I guess should do it like
that and so it's gonna move over right
closest P if it finds anything and I
also get a blue back that tells me if I
did find it but I don't actually need to
know that in this particular piece of
code at the moment right so then what
I'm gonna do is gonna say okay there's a
closest traversable in here as well
right so when i go to call when I go
step into the hero head code I want to
know that as well and you can see in
here that when I go to do this
simulation currently what I'm doing is
I'm looking for the body and I'm
snapping to the body but I don't
actually need to do that right now
anymore what I can do instead is say
like hey let's take a look to see
whether we got one of these traversable
x' like so and assume
that I did then instead of using the
body we'll just we'll just use that so
I'm not going to use the body you pee
anymore I'm going to use the closest fee
and the only thing I'm gonna do since I
don't want to adjust the Z is I'm gonna
say that let's let's not match in fact I
guess I
hmm nope nope nope nope nope I'm gonna
do it I'm just gonna keep I'm gonna do
the Z as well so I'm just gonna entirely
replace the head P with the closest P
and that's it
or sorry the body P that's closest B and
that's everything and then a memory
button so a head is not relevant here
we're actually looking for the closest
thing to us because we are the head and
so that's much nicer now yeah so the
other thing I want to do too is I don't
really want the facing direction at the
moment is based on the movement and I
don't like that at all the facing
direction should be based on the last
direction I push because you can see
what's happening here if I overshoot and
come back the head because it faces in
the direction it goes flips but I don't
want it to flip I just want it to use
whatever the last direction I pushed was
and so I'm going to take a look at where
that face Russia said I think it's set
and move entity and that's just stupid
and I don't want it
my head appears to be blocking this but
I'll just zoom down a little so leave
facing direction whatever it was or face
direction you'll is a tan - so these are
just not I don't want this right I don't
want this at all so really really I'm
just gonna say this code gets nerfed out
and probably what I want to do is I want
that to be based on what direction you
were pushing with the controller and so
since the DDP code here the con hero DDP
is really the code that I'm looking for
then setting the head at least I guess
we can do this right we can say like
let's take that DDP and use that so
that's like what direction I was trying
to accelerate in and that's that's
almost sure they're gonna be better yeah
cuz that's what I want I just wanted to
kind of slide back I don't want it to
turn or anything like that and the other
thing I want is I probably want that to
be pretty quick so right now it's not
particularly tight the spring is like
relatively weak also we don't need that
good anymore so I think I want this to
be a little bit beefier
and so yeah like I guess the only thing
that feels odd to me about it now I mean
other than the fact that we need to fix
up the fact that the head in the body
are totally except to segregated the
only thing that feels particularly weird
about it now
is that when I move if I'm off-center
and I stop it feels good like that feels
fine like that actually feels totally
fine you know what I actually want to do
too you know what I'm gonna talk about
that in one second that let me let me
let me do one more thing I actually want
to be able to hop straight hop and so
you know the sword stuff is not what I
ever wanted really that was we were just
playing with that that has nothing to do
with the game design we were just doing
some stuff so I'm gonna get rid of that
and it's really the distorted stuff
that's what would I would want the
determine the facing direction it's the
last direction I attacked in is actually
what I would want
so really it's like con hero D sword or
yet D sword he's actually what I want
and so I think putting that in just
temporarily even though we're not
dealing with attacks or anything at the
moment I wanted to see what that feels
like because that's more that informs my
decisions a lot better if I could
actually see the hopping using that
methodology and of course I close the
program why they close from I have no
idea
force of habit so this is actually what
it will look like so I'll be like
strafing around like this and then maybe
I will like start attacking something
below me and I'll go like this right and
then I'll attack something here or here
and so this is actually what that would
be like so okay so stopping on to a
square feels fine to me now because once
I let go I don't really care so much
about what happens it's like it's like
it's like the you know what on an analog
stick you know I'm fine with it sucking
back to the center right but what I
don't like what does not feel good to me
is as I'm hopping along if I'm right in
a row it feels fine
if I'm below the row the fact that it
sucks me up like that feels weird so
like when I'm hopping this way and then
I go up that re-centering
doesn't feel great and so I wonder if
maybe I just shouldn't do that maybe I
should say that when we do the the sort
of spring back to the center maybe I was
premature and I said we don't need that
code let's delete it maybe I really want
to make sure that all of the things are
in fact zero look I'm not
I only want to spring back when I'm not
pushing anywhere so if I was to do that
I would just say like what's the length
of the DDP so let's do should apply
equals length EDP less than dope one so
basically if I don't have any
application then I'll just do should
apply here
and that definitely feels better so even
though it's kind of wonky and it means
that you don't really go into the
channel I guess what I could do is make
the spring stiffness based on that so
what I could do potentially is say well
okay so I'll keep this code here which
is to say this is the code to tell me
whether I want to apply anything at all
but this is the code which says what the
factor is so really this is an r32
that's like my my coefficient for on the
position of the spring and what I'll say
is like okay if if you're not pushing it
all then it's the super stiff spring if
you're not if you're if you are pushing
in some direction but not in the
direction of correction at this
particular point like for whatever acts
we're talking about then we will use a
weak force to gently guide you back but
in a way that's hopefully so subtle you
won't know or won't be bothered by it
right so then it's kind of like just
feels a little bit more debt like
diagonal you know what I mean
to kind of catch you back in there
and I don't know how I feel about that
still doesn't feel great I think the
best feeling thing is just not to do it
I don't know it might just be that it's
only it only should happen when you when
you land yeah I don't know easily to any
push equals this and I guess really it's
just like hey yeah that's not so much we
can always change back but it does kind
of seem like does kind of seem like it
wants to be free floating
I'm gonna leave it like that it's
obviously a decision that we can make
later on when we play the game and see
how it feels because again it's not
gonna make a huge difference in terms of
any other sort of design thing but it's
just like hey you know you gotta tune
the game so that it feels good to you I
mean you know whoever the person who's
responsible for it has to tune it and so
I think in this case it just feels
better when I don't do that
so I think that's what I'm gonna stick
with for now and because that's starting
to feel much better yeah so even though
it'll kind of be like a little weird I
think that's just what we want to do
because in general like any game where
you have a grid-based thing that people
have to work with there's a number of
you know I mean the best possible thing
for clarity is always if the person is
just directly on the grid but the bottom
line is it just doesn't feel good in a
game to lock a person to a grid like
that usually especially not in an action
game and so you kind of have to be
careful about what you do and so I just
want to make sure that we don't
compromise the feel of moving the
character for the grid so the grid is
supposed to be something that sort of
like happens but that's why there's the
body and the head as separate pieces
it's because I want to make sure that
that works and that's something we can
do so that's starting to feel pretty
good there so let's I guess let's go
ahead and start tackling that last part
which is just making the the two things
connect and then once we've got that
going I think we're kind of at the point
where I think we want to go revisit the
renderer a little bit and tidy up all of
our stuff so that everything's sorting
properly probably fix the hero bitmaps a
little bit and and just do the assorted
kind of assorted little to do's that are
stopping us from having a correct
looking character like the fact that
those are sorting in the opposite order
and stuff like that so we want to have
to fix all of those and make sure that
those are correct so in this scenario
what I need to do is I need to start by
exposing some of the capabilities of our
renderer because one of the things our
renderer can do is our renderer can
scale things our render can shear things
and our renderer can rotate things but
since we have done literally no
rendering of that name
sure we don't have any way to actually
specify that as part of like when we
specify a bitmap so what I need to do is
open up the code in the renderer so that
I can actually send it the ability that
you know I can actually send it
information about the fact that we need
our our body to to scale or you know
stuff like that right I need I need to
sort of have have that work so how am I
gonna do that let's take a look here we
go to handmade render group and you can
see that in handmade render group we've
got like a render entry rectangle and
that's got you know the ability to scale
I guess but no rotation and no sharing
so there's no axis Pesa fied there's
just the dimension and so what i would
like to do is have some way of
specifying additional information and
probably i want there to be a whoops
and then probably search for bitmaps so
I probably want another type of render
entry that's like render entry like
flexible bitmap or something like that
and in addition to the color the P and
the size instead of specifying size as
to just to like sort of distances what
I'll do instead is specify the x axis
and the y axis and those will come out
of the point P right and so in order to
do this I need to add the ability in the
renderer to do a push bitmap call that
actually has this information associated
with it now I could make it so that we
always specify this but I feel like it's
probably a good idea to keep this in
case we ever want to increase the
rendering throughput of stuff that
doesn't have to be rotated we might want
to do that now obviously well you know
what honestly that's probably not all
that necessary because it's easy to test
if the X and the y-axis yeah it's easy
it's
the X and y-axis and jump so I feel like
probably actually what we can do is just
change this I feel like we can just go
with a single one hey how many times I'm
gonna do that hey it's like a pair of
zircon encrusted tweezers let's go ahead
and just do the corrections necessary to
make this work not changing anything
just gonna render the exact same stuff
but I'm gonna now instead of just
encoding a size I'm going to encode that
that directionality as well all right so
I'm going to start with the OpenGL
renderer because that happens to be what
we're using and then we'll switch over
the software in or make sure that
handles the two because we might as well
keep both working it'll be pretty
trivial to do so since our software
rasterizer does already handle this case
so it's not like it's something we got
to go right rendering code it's just a
case of setting it up properly so here's
the way that we were rendering something
and you can see us calling OpenGL
rectangle and that's not really gonna
come to any more because OpenGL
rectangle is something that draws
something rectilinear right and you can
see that happening here so what we need
to do is we need to actually have this
this little fellow here do a more
explicit thing where it's not going to
be rectilinear like that so I'll drop
this in here for starters and then we're
gonna change how it works so menu v-max
would be obviously will just flow
through properly and then we've got the
max P and the min P and those are here
and those will flow through properly so
if I were to do nothing else right if I
wasn't if I was to do absolutely zero
out here then you know what I can also
do here I can do this there's a you can
point to it you can pass a pointer to a
color and have it loaded soon so if I
was to just do this I could delete the
OpenGL rectangle call I believe and be
fine so I'm gonna double check that
that's true and then we'll go from there
let's see size is not a member of that's
true you know what I probably should do
I should probably do these changes one
at a time
render group that hb2 size
all right
connect everyone from from vo to class
oh oh sorry yes you need the pointer to
the floats don't you so I'm going to go
ahead and run and I should see exactly
the same thing on the screen as I did
before which is what I want and then and
I do have to restart the app now because
this is not in the reload section this
is in the rendering code so now what I
need to do is I need to make this code
actually work with sort of a stretched
version of the bitmap and what that
means is that instead of being able to
use the the kinds of a min and a max P I
actually need four separate points right
I need each quarter because they can be
sheared and rotate there's there's notes
there's it's not like two boundaries
anymore I need to know the different
points so just to be explicit about this
right if I'm just drawing something
that's that's rectangular and aligned
with the screen then it's pretty easy
well I guess I'll do it this way it's
pretty easy to send down a minimum X Y
and a maximum X Y and that specifies
obviously the entire rectangle because
it's just like it's like bounding this
by a set of four planes right the min
and the max in each axis but as soon as
I move over to something that could be
rotated scaled and sheared let me see if
I can draw something kind of crazy that
illustrates that so right this is now a
totally legal shape for our renderer to
output and the the bitmap will just get
kind of squashed around in there and so
if that's what we're gonna do then you
can kind of see that like hey we can't
really specify it to the renderer
anymore as as a min and the max instead
we're gonna need something else and so
what I was saying is well let's just
pass in you know here and here okay and
then I know we can produce these other
four points because like we just take
the center point that we have and we do
we subtract this in this to get this guy
we add this and subtract this to get
this guy we add both of them to get this
guy and we add this one and subtract
this one to get this guy right so we can
produce all four points and so then what
this becomes is this becomes us
sort of having to generate those four
points from what we're given and to
generate those points you know what we
could also do here because both render
paths are probably well known I guess
they don't really need it so what we're
gonna do here is just say okay assuming
that we've got the other information in
there let's let's jump over to render
group that H assuming that we've got
these in their x-axis and y-axis and
these are scaled in fact I'll note that
so if we want to go through and do this
code what we need to do is produce like
the midpoint so this is min min this is
essentially min min P it's min X min Y
right in fact we could do it this way
well I'll just do min min and the next
minute Y so that's been X min Y this is
max X then Y and again I can also do
this with the with the floating point
passing I want to this one is max X and
I'm just like I said just reading these
off here max Y min X min Y max X max Y
and min x max Y okay so if we take a
look at what happens here all of our UV
coordinates are going to be exactly the
same and now we're just computing these
points a little bit differently so what
we can do now is say well we have our
min X min Y point our min x max Y point
our max X min Y point and our max X max
Y point those are our points we know
that these are all going to start at P
you know at our at our main point and
then we're going to need you can see
here we've got this x axis Y axis thing
this is literally the equation in fact I
guess we can just
I'm interested to know oh so our entropy
oh so our entropy is already based in
the lower left corner so these can just
be scaled by the actual dimension are
already scaled by the dimension
apparently I don't know if I like that
but we can always change it there no big
deal anyway so if I want to move on from
here I can simply say all right we've
got the P which is that the MVP and I
guess we could still call it min P
because that makes sense and then this
is really the code this is the entirety
of the code we need is this exact code
it's now what we're doing is saying hey
we don't need to multiply by the size
anymore because these are multiplied by
the size already we don't need to
construct them in place because they
actually exist in the entity itself and
then all we have to do is construct each
of the points by doing exactly what we
just said so min X means subtract the x
max X means add the X min Y means
subtract the Y max X means add the Y and
so there's our four points on the
corners of our parallelogram which could
be rotated you know two rotated and
shared square right so it becomes a
parallelogram of arbitrary dimension
arbitrary size dimension I guess we
could mean something else's context so
we won't use that and so then we should
be basically all set now all we have to
do is actually record this information
in the actual renderer and we should be
good to go now if I switch back to the
renderer the regular software renderer
which is somewhere where is that here it
is in the regular software renderer when
we're rendering a bitmap you can see us
calling draw a rectangle quickly now the
same stuff applies here right you can
see that we basically already set
ourselves up for success really all we
have to do is is pass these along and I
think that's it like that's all we need
to do to support what we were trying for
so I think that's the entirety to
modifications so really most of the work
we're gonna have to do now is going to
be about actually passing this
to the renderer it's not about the
renderer code handling it because it
will just handle it so okay we can start
by supporting the existing push bitmap
call this is not going to be
particularly difficult because we know
what the size is so if we instead just
keep the size as a v2 real quick real
quick like then we know what the x-axis
is and we know what the y-axis is right
because all they're going to be is just
whatever that size X was that's that
goes into the X component and whatever
the size Y was that's what goes into the
y component so that'll do our that's all
we were doing before so we can just do
it now so then if we come in here and
wait what am what's the problem Oh
entity I spelled it wrong so now if we
come in here we just have to clean up
these calls where I'd forgot the V and I
think we should be good to go when I run
this code hopefully if I didn't mess
anything up
and I obviously did that's kind of
spectacular you have to admit that's
awesome we should get a basically exact
same thing on screen so it definitely
messed something up there and that's not
a good thing oh you know what I just
realized
whereas render group there we go -
x-axis + s up so men men we don't
subtract anymore so we just have I don't
know why I deleted all that so we we
don't subtract cuz that was I did that
as if we were doing half dimensions but
that's not what we're doing we're doing
whole dimensions so I doubled the scale
of everything right I was still thinking
this in my head but really what we have
is this right so all we do is start at P
we add the x-axis we add the after we
add the x-axis we add the y-axis you
know so that's it we don't do
subtraction so since I was doing it I
was essentially doubling the size
because these were the whole size of the
other side and I was doing that which
was just dumb again had the wrong mental
model stuck in my brain for some reason
so now I think we're good and that
allows us now to render anything that's
like scaled and sheared and rotated
which is what we need so now we just
need a cut like I said most of the work
is getting it down there now we just
need some code that can actually specify
some useful things here when we call
push bitmap so you can see that we've
got a couple different ways of calling
it here and I think what we want to do
is we probably want again this to sort
of get one more step removed so that
these are you know kind of again
inlinable we hope and what I can do here
is say well okay so the sizes that come
down on these we can just multiply those
by maybe two vectors that we end up
getting that we pass in right so maybe I
can just say like okay
Oh
we think about this so see a line we
just have a tunt we just have so many
things that we passed a push bitmap it's
kind of annoying but you know like if we
wanted to write we could even stick
these on the end here right this could
just be x-axis y-axis if we want to and
again not it's not great but we totally
could do that because then what we would
do is just say well whatever the size X
is times the x axis and whatever the Y
the size y is x will axis now the other
thing that I'm not sure is if that we
have would have any problem with that as
far as the scale the nonlinear scale is
concerned and I have to think about that
because if you think about what happens
here right when we go through and say
get bitmap dimensions we get back some
scale values that are based on
projecting those sizes and so that
projection is nonlinear which means we
can't just multiply it on the outside so
I feel like we kind of need that to be
more respected now if you always pass in
non scaled axes
that would be fine
but at some point I think that's just
not what you want if that makes sense
so I'm gonna take this back a bit and
think about this
so inside kept it mapped in well I guess
it's actually getting render MV basis P
I suppose because we get the base of
scale oh well I guess it's okay because
we have it as a separate scale and so I
guess we baked the non-linearity into
that is that correct though does that
actually work how does our how does our
get run our energy basis code work let's
take a look so where I produce the scale
it's the meters to pixels the projected
XY dot Z so the projected XY dot Z which
is the 1 over 2 focal length times raw X
Y so it's definitely dividing that value
by its month well so yeah that that
actually is gonna be totally fine all
right
I take it back I guess that would just
work I think that just works
conveniently for us we can just do that
so the way this is working in here is we
pass in a height value right and the
height value it does some like monkeying
around to sort of get that to to be
scaled properly and so what I could do
here is just I could say and probably
what I would want I'm guessing is to
specify sort of the x and y axes we're
like let's see here where the height
actually yeah like the optimal thing I
think might be just specify the XY axes
as constant AXI
so the X and y axis would be unit length
and we still specify the height and then
you know I would just grow the height to
figure out how high I want to be and it
would stay uniform and then if you
wanted to you could shrink the width by
shrinking the x-axis so that way you're
shrinking it proportionally I don't know
it's really tough to say it's real tough
to say because the other thing we can do
is just specify those two axes directly
and just have them multiplied by the
scale and you never specify like that
size
and the width over height that just
never gets actually used
I guess I should think about what I
actually want to have happen here at
least in this one specific case so that
I baby can say that at least work for
one thing so what I would want to do
here right is we've got the the hero and
he's kind of a you know a trapezoidal
looking thing and he's on top of another
trapezoidal looking thing and then he's
got a point which is that where the head
is
and so what I'm sort of saying is well
okay if the head shifts over to the side
what I've currently got going on is
something that looks like this right and
so what I'd like to do is I'd like to go
ahead and correct this vector so that it
points back towards the where the head
is right now there's different ways that
we can do that we can leave this so that
it we could shear it so we could make it
so that it just goes like this right
which might make some sense we could
also rotate it this way
and then scale it right and that would
be a little bit different that would
look more you know like like that and I
don't know which one of those is going
to be the right thing to do but the
reason that things are slightly
complicated is because when we know you
know if we have this thing or I should
say what we actually have is we just
have a notion of where the bitmap
actually is and it's its width that
height are determined by what the input
art file is right and that makes things
a little bit complicated because it
means that we don't really have a stable
sense in the external code of what the
wit is so I guess we want to just keep
doing it off of the height and we'll
just specify some height stuff and say
hey did we want you know if we want to
bend that height around we'll just
change what that y-axis is
and that's it I think that's probably
what we're gonna want to do now we're
gonna have a problem here and that
problem is going to be that like the
pivot for the object is what we have to
kind of work around and I don't know to
what extent we're already doing it so
here's our our alignment and the
alignment gets baked into the offset so
I guess that will probably work
correctly but it's a little janky here
because we've all you know we've kind of
also got this concept that you know
we're trying to talk about something
that's based here and stretching to some
point but the actual bitmap is being
rendered you know something more like
this because remember we haven't even
gotten rid of the empty space there so
the actual bitmap is something that
looks like that you know I'm saying so
when we actually start here and we want
a displace to there then what we're
essentially doing is we're having to
sort of do the whole thing this whole
thing has to kind of happen like that
right but it has to counter move if it
just did that then this point would
slide as well which we didn't actually
want we wanted this point to remain
rooted so we have to counter slide this
point by however much is necessary to
keep this point in this Innis the same
place right
essentially the pivot has to be
respected so we've got some work ahead
of us to make this happen the way that
that's working now is inside get bitmap
dim you can see that we're using this
align thing and that align point that
sealion times Hadamard nonsense right
that code is actually aligning us to a
bogus alignment point if the alignment
point that we set in when we packed the
assets and those alignment points are I
think based on the ground
like where the ground is and that's not
something we actually want because now
we're animating these three pieces
separately what we actually want is that
point to be specific to like basically
the the sort of wrote the part around
which we rotate about the imaginary part
that it connects to the the legs well
they're not really legs because there's
no legs
it's a legless child the stump
so wherever connects to the stump is
what we actually would want that point
to be and that's not what that point is
at the moment now we can always override
it so that's not that big a deal but it
is worth noting that like that's
probably saying when we bake the art
assets you know I'm gonna have to make
sure when I produce some of the final
art packs for this we want to get those
things right yeah so this is kind of
complicated we're gonna have to do a lot
of work to sort of get this into the
right it to get this into shape but what
I do think is true about this is I do
think we want to just go ahead and say
that you can pass x and y AK axes and
we'll just scale those as necessary so I
think we probably keep roughly what we
had I think it'll probably work okay and
then we just say like okay yeah when you
pass one of these down we'll just go
ahead and say it's size x times the x
axis and size y times the y axis and I
don't know so where is get bitmap dim
used is it only used in this function
so where else is it used get bitmap Tim
is in text up so get bitmap Tim is used
for text rendering and block work so
that's basically all that's used for so
I'm relatively free it's only even using
the debug system I'm relatively free to
make changes to that and it's not a big
deal so if we take a look at what
happens here where we've got the dim dot
size that computes this information and
we've got the dimensions dot aligned and
all that nonsense so in here what I can
do is say well this offset needs to be
computed now based on those axes right
because the alignment is going to be now
is not gonna be done in flat 2d
rectilinear it's actually gonna be like
in the near sheared rotate escape face
so maintaining that alignment point
which of course is wrong at the moment
but if it were right maintaining that
alignment point has to be done in a
different way with this that with this
p-value and what we have to do is take
that alignment and multiply it by the X
and the y axes to get what we actually
need I'm gonna change the way that this
function is working I'm gonna say that
it's since we don't touch the Z I'm
going to say that the Dimpy Z equals the
offset Z and then I'm going to say that
the X y equals basically the equation on
the XY itself
and then I can't be got it actually
change my underscores back to not
underscores okay so that is step one and
again we're not actually asking to do
anything yet so we'll see the same thing
so after I do that after I get the entry
x-axis and y-axis stuff I need to then
pass them down in here and this needs to
be something that looks like this
right so this function now has to take
an x-axis which again can still be a
default so anyone who was calling this
thing can still call it the same way
that they were calling it before and
that's totes fine but it needs to know
now again hopefully that will produce no
change and it doesn't so that's good and
so now what I want to do is just see
whether we can get some kind of a
stretch going on here right something
that's sort of you know moves the kind
of moves the stretches the body out in
some way and it's gonna be a little bit
wrong I think but we'll do what we can
because like I said those those pivot
points are in the wrong place
unfortunately so now if I go down to
handmade handmade world mode and I come
in here to the hero body what I can do
is take a look at the distance between
the head and the body
that's this head distance here so I'm
going to take a v2 or I guess we'll do
it v3 which is the head Delta and I'm
just gonna take a look at what the
difference between the two of them is so
where is the head versus where it
where's the head moved relative to where
the body is that's the displacement off
of those and then I'm just gonna try
driving a little bit of change in that
y-axis based on that so you know when we
kind of compute that we'd come down here
I think we have the render code for the
hero head and then here's the code for
the hero body so in here what I can do
is say well the torso and the Cape let's
use a different you gotta take a look at
all my parameter let's use a different
thing for them let's use a different X
and y-axis for them so at the moment I
don't have any needs for color although
I feel like eventually we will probably
want to change the
color of things on the hero that would
not surprise me but anyway we've got the
color that we're passing the CTU line is
always going to be 1.0 that's not going
to change and then we've got our x axis
y axis so x axis to start at and the
white said before there when I didn't
have to our x-axis and a y-axis can
start out being what they were
previously and looks like I didn't quite
get that right notice here that our ties
could be well trying to match the are
here lose
okay so render group have a transform ah
right I missed one of my functions since
we can pass the bitmap ID to these guys
this push bitmap call also needs them
okay and so this should do exactly the
same thing was doing before because
we're passing it through and we're fine
and so now what I would need to do is
inside the world mode code I need to
actually have I guess I'd probably
because because we're doing rendering
and in updating separately I would need
to store this in the sim entity
structure as well so inside here in
salinity I will need to add you know
x-axis y-axis and the x-axis y-axis at
the moment because I don't really have
any particular desire to fuss with it is
just going to be set to the default
might as well set it on everybody PI
step that's a construction someday
alright so what I want to do here is I
want to actually compute different ones
for this for the hero's body here I will
just use I will now get it out of the
entity so that it can be stored by the
entity update routines to be whatever
they want based on how they were moving
and yeah pretty straightforward so now
we just have to actually compute
something and that's the part that think
we're probably not to put off till next
week because there's this is gonna be
fairly complicated and we have to figure
out how we're gonna deal with the fact
that the hot spots are in the wrong
place but anyway when I have that had
Delta there what I could do is say well
okay whatever they had Delta is after I
figure out where my new location is I
can go ahead and take my entity x-axis
and I can compute I suppose that in the
y-axis I can go ahead and compute that
by displacing that axis
relative to where the head is right and
so if I'm gonna do this I could I could
do this fairly straightforwardly by
saying hey what the x-axis is just
whatever it is or we can even leave the
XS is the same in fact maybe let's do
that first
and I could say that the y-axis is just
going to be whatever the y-axis would
have been plus some coefficient times
the displacement now this is going to be
grotesquely wrong but like I said for
the time being I think that we're gonna
have to live with that do not know why
I'm not seeing any results there
why not doing anything well I guess we
can start by saying hey this should make
the guy be twice as big right twice as
tall and it sure doesn't so something's
not happening
so here's here a body it's getting those
things out it's passing them down oh
right got to actually pass them so
that's getting passed there this is
getting passed there Thanks fine and
dandy there we go that's what I was
expecting
okay good all right so let's actually go
and try that one more time so here we
are in world mode I'm gonna go up to our
y-axis and I'm gonna say I don't know
why I made that in x-axis there we go
so that now does what exactly what I
think it should do so now we're
operating at least properly so now I'll
put this back in here here we go and so
now well that's that's great I did it
again there we go
so now you can see I'm already starting
to do that stretching which is all fine
and dandy it doesn't look particularly
great though
right you can it's it's not it's it's
better than it was to a certain degree
but it's not fabulous right like you
probably don't want the game to look
like that like that's not going to be
that's not gonna be great
so we'll have to start dealing with this
next week as I said we're out of time at
this point but at least we now sort of
have the renderer supporting us if not
our art assets since our art assets are
not really aligned in the way that they
probably would need to be in order for
this to work properly
so I sauce the kid
zircon encrusted tweezers are you moving
to Montana soon yeah
just me and the pygmy Pony man over by
the dental-floss bush frosty ninja why
does our limbless hero need to suffer in
such gruesome ways well you know it's
tough being a video game character you
get squashed you get stretched you die
repeatedly in a lot of games
do I need the pay version of mischief to
change the background-color yes I think
so but I would hold off on that because
somebody on the handmade who was a
handmade hero friend
they made a replacement for mischeif and
it's supposedly almost ready so we're
probably gonna switch to that pretty
soon now so there's that will you try
rotation to visually compare against
shearing before deciding probably what
we'll do actually is a combination so in
order to get it as minimally messed up
as possible we'll probably do some
rotation and some shearing and that's
you know I think probably the best that
we're going to be able to do we might
also try having one more frame of
animation in each direction or a rather
frame of imagery so that when you're
really far over it like splays out it
like changes to another image
let's see
see you got sure you wrote the scales
for this way because it's already done
in a software renderer but these
transformations would usually be done in
a vertex shader right no these these
transformations have nothing to do with
a vertex shader if you were trying to do
these sorts of transformations you would
do them in a geometry shader is the way
they would actually be done so this
piece of information here here so what
you would do is this concept right here
this render entry bitmap this would
actually be what you would send to the
card and then the geometry shader would
output it well the geometry shader would
literally do exactly what you saw me do
here so this code would be in the
geometry shader like literally all of it
like right here and down all of that
would all be in the geometry shader if
you wanted to pass this width and height
somehow otherwise you'd do just this one
part and you would the thing that would
be that you'd pass them in menu the max
UV to the geometry shader
some other games have similar moves
styles but they use a floating indicator
instead of separating the head from the
body your thoughts yes this games
designed very specifically requires you
to not do that you have to move the
actual head so I sauce the kid for
collision detection will there be skewed
boxes as well or will it just be a a BB
so I don't think we will probably have
any actual collision detection on the
hero anyway it will probably be mostly
semantic if that makes sense so the body
shirred body will not really be go
undergoing collision detection probably
garland Oh bloom so we moved how that
I'll haven't seen the new movement yes
we moved house tile
bird Amina are we eventually going to
move these over to shaders if we had to
for some kind of performance reason we
would if we never do have to do that
though that no because basically OpenGL
programming is it's kind of useless
programming right it's programming that
won't be relevant in five years it's
oftentimes not even relevant in two
years because it's you know completely
different it all gets changed around
repeatedly so you know my preference
would be to teach as little graphics API
specific stuff as possible I would
rather show how to code it in software
so that you know how it works and then
you know if for some reason you can't if
if you actually go follow hey I made
Hiro to the point where you've written
the software rasterizer it should be
trivial for you to go like learn how to
drive a graphics API do it cuz that's
just like looking up the API is stuff
and going how do I call it to do this
right because you already know exactly
what happens there just a question of
like okay how do I call these things and
those things change frequently and so
teaching them on the stream is like
literally complete waste of time so I
try to keep it just to the parts we
actually need to do to make sure that
the game runs okay on GPUs
any word on the new debugger a new
debugger I am not working on a debugger
if anyone thought that that was
happening
courage against and you have a stream
about someone counting you about making
butter no not contacting me
it was contacting oh I know what you're
talking about now you're talking about
the the folks who were looking to put
the debugger into for coder all right
now I know we're talking about I have no
idea I just did the stream because I was
like if people are trying to work on it
then I'm gonna give them as much
information about it as I can because I
would love to have a debugger but
unfortunately I you know I don't have
much time to look into stuff like that
so I I have no idea what they're doing
with that I know that that Alan Webster
has to finish up the UI upgrades in for
coder before you could have like
debugger looking things in it and I
would assume since I haven't seen any
for coder updates in a while that he is
the middle finals and stuff since he's
in school so I'm guessing that that
probably until there's some free time
for Alan I'm guessing that we won't see
anything but you know maybe once school
is out that that will happen if that
makes sense
and insofar as you say I doubt the
concept of shaders is going anywhere
soon I disagree
right like and this is you know this is
I guess a point where I sort of separate
I guess from the credentialism maybe
it's just my wishful thinking but I
don't really think like shaders are
obviously stupid right they don't make
any sense because essentially what they
are is a way of having sort of like a
way of pigeonholing a particular type of
stuff that you might do in code whose
has a very irregular boundary that's
based on a strange overlapping set of
things that you that different Hardware
did or did not do at certain times or
whatever and because of that rather
disgusting architectural artificial
architectural creation it means that
it's constantly undergoing drastic
revisions like it first started out it
was a bunch of API calls that you used
to set up like some blending things you
could do then it moved to an assembly
language thing that you programmed that
was like DirectX like certain you could
do a certain number of ops and those
would be baked down right or whatever
then it became like a sort of see like
thing that get compiled into these
things
now it's bifurcated so there's like many
see like things each of which can do
certain select operations or one
general-purpose see thing that isn't
really meant for rendering and you can
sort of call that separately but we
don't even know where it goes in the
pipeline
it's a non-sustainable system and you
know it's not sustainable because it
hasn't ever remained the same for more
than like a year or two in a row right
and they're constantly having to add all
this nonsense about like oh we added
this new wave actually texture so we had
all these API is for it and then those
get routed in through the sato-mobile
it's like it's stupid it's just it's a
dumb dumb way to do things the correct
way to do things is to like create an
actual programming model just like a CPU
export what that is as an ice ax and
then we code to it
like just get there right and so I kind
of feel like it's inevitable that we
will get there because if shaders were
the right model then that's how would we
be programming actual code like that's
how we would actually be programming
computers is all shaders you wouldn't
have like the ability to write a program
you would write a collection of things
this is a piece of string code and it
would be in string Lang right and like
this thing over here oh well this is
written in blah right and so I think
it's got to get there eventually because
it's the only actual sustainable model
that I know about so and the fact that
shaders have changed so radically like
every 2 3 years since their inception I
feel like it's got to go there
eventually now unfortunately it will
probably still be super janky but I just
don't think the current way that shaders
work is gonna be relevant to anybody in
like 5 years let's say I just I just
don't think so
I think at the very least in five years
we'll be on some different
conceptualization of shaders that's not
like the one that's that's now right
like they're not separated into five
stages anymore there's like they've been
reorganized or something like this right
and so I kind of think that's gotta
happen and I hope it happens sooner
rather than later but of course it
probably won't and we'll probably have
another ten years of every two years you
have to relearn how shaders work because
they've been completely modified you
know
may blow do you think you'll use the
spring code from the other day on the
camera movement I'm imagining a
critically damped spring would be the
thing to use for that pet peeve is non
critically damped Springs on camera code
so we would definitely not use a non
crude of your damp spring I don't know
that we would ever use a spring we would
probably use a b-spline maybe I don't
really well you know what I don't know
you might be right critically damn
spring could be good just never use an
under damp spring for camera there are
so many games that use it under dance
together it makes people nauseous I
often times get sick trying to play
Stephen sausage roll because the the
camera is an under damped spring so it
shoots past the guy and then goes back
and you feel like you're getting like
you know like your your heads going
crazy I see tons of games to do that
it's awful
super nauseating
so it looks like we got really no more
cues about where we were doing your land
of them for camera stuff I just do X
plus equals X minus deaths divided by 10
well where's the time where's T in there
Matt where's where's T in that equation
there is no T where is the T
Orlando Bloom that's not accounting 40
that's if it was instantaneous well so
you you just apply that no matter what
the time step was so it takes you know
in one frame you are going to move one
tenth of the way to the destination no
matter what is that the idea or it's
like I move a tenth of the way of the
destination every time which also means
you'll never actually get there I mean
you will cause a floating point but
that's a Zeno's paradox kind of thing
right it's like I'll never actually
reach the destination point
and yes Allen I think you're correct
like if it's actually X - desk then it
would be moving a tenth of the way away
from the destination this is like fixed
FPS so it was fine but I've changed hold
on look it up well so yeah if you're if
you're wondering what that would be
that's that's basically a like a
logarithmic or exponential however you
want to look at it so if what you're
doing there is this is distance and this
is time I'll say this is distance from
Target then what your site effectively
doing is saying well I'm always gonna
start off by moving the most right off
the bat right because you've effectively
got distance over ten right or stated
alternately distance divided by
something right is your amount and so
the higher the distance the more you
will move and so the very first move is
the most is most of the move right is
that is the most you will ever do
everything after that move will be less
right and so what you're gonna do is
you're gonna look like this right so
this is what your approach curve looks
like it's like an asymptotic you know
kind of thing that that looks like that
so you know like a hyperbola or
something like this is what you would
think of for that kind of a curve and
it'll never get there right it'll never
actually get to zero distance other than
the fact that floating point will
eventually round it but that's what
would actually happen and the reason
that I wouldn't do something like that
like I wouldn't really recommend that is
there's no acceleration right it's
instantaneous so it immediately jerks
the camera as hard as possible towards
the target
if the target somewhere else and you
know you probably want a little bit of
acceleration there right like I would
argue the correct curve probably looks
something like this
you know because you want that camera to
like start moving a little bit just just
even a little bit doesn't have to be
huge and you don't want to feel sluggish
necessary but it's like you want a
little bit there you don't want to just
have a massive instantaneous
acceleration and then everything else is
deceleration right because this is
basically like instantaneous huge
acceleration and then every other point
is deceleration right decelerates here
decelerates here decelerate zero so it's
here right so I wouldn't you know I mean
there might be a reason why you would
want to do that but I wouldn't recommend
it because it really doesn't have a very
flattering curve there I think and also
obviously it's time step dependent but
you could make it you can make a time
step independent one of these so I still
just wouldn't recommend Nestle shaping
the curve like that
necessarily
plants are adding camera shake or blur
are similar if the hero gets hit or a
boulder hits the ground near the hero
yeah I mean probably I don't know those
are kind of polished sorts of stuff that
I'm not sure how important it is to
think about like now but but they're
definitely things that we might want and
they're pretty trivial for us to
implement right because we can shake the
camera without having really to do much
all right
I'm gonna go ahead and wrap it up
so silly looking now
that's just really silly all right let's
go ahead and close that down thank you
everyone for joining me for those sort
of handmade here at symmetric coding
with you as always if you would like to
follow along at home you can pre-order
the game on handmade hero organic come
to the source code so you can follow
along with the daily programming we also
have a forum site that is hosted at
handmade network now which is pretty
cool you can check it out if you want to
ask questions or hang out with other
people who watch the series you can also
go to our patreon page if you want to
support the videos you can also check
out our schedule bot if you're trying to
catch us live which we'll post this
weekend the schedule for next week as we
often do and we also have our wonderful
episode guide maintained by the fabulous
may blow that allows you to catch up
with past episodes with ease with ease
unprecedented ease I might I might say
so check all that out we'll be back here
probably Monday again check the schedule
box the schedule if you want to catch
the next week until then have a good
weekend of programming and I will catch
you guys on the Internet
take it easy everybody