hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we are gonna I guess
start debugging our code today we've got
some stuff we want to do regarding asset
reloading and we've implemented most of
it we really just now have to go through
a little bit of plumbing and a little
bit of debugging to make sure that
everything works cleanly the two things
that we need to do are one finished
right backs which we mostly did already
and then debug everything the other
thing that we're going to want to do and
after we get this working is we're gonna
want to add something to store for lack
of a better term some edit data and what
I mean by that is if you take a look at
how we implemented the sort of on-demand
asset packing and we kind of go through
and take a look at it here
so if we take a look at how the asset
packing stuff actually works here when
we go into the check for art changes
stuff right when we're loading these
things in whenever we find a PNG we find
one of these like little match guys
which keeps stored in the in the header
files it motion signifies in memory
it keeps stored what the asset the what
the assets were that these PNG is
represented right so we have this asset
indices already here that says like oh
for each tile in like the group of tiles
that this PNG had here's the assets that
those correspond to when I imported it
last time these will not get saved
anywhere so when you run the game you
import all these pngs
you close the game down you launch the
game again they'll all be gone right and
we don't want them to be gone we want
them to remain because if they remain
then what will happen is we will be able
to prevent the asset file from growing
unnecessarily right every time we launch
the game we would reinforce the new
assets again because we would not know
that we didn't ported them before and we
wouldn't know when they changed which
assets to rewrite because all that data
the the file date and the ass indices
has gotten lost so what we can do is we
can write this data out to a separate
file that's just like a little cache
file sits in the you know directory
along with the game and just says hey
here's all the stuff that I imported on
this machine and you know when you
launch the game again you just load that
in and you prime your asset source file
hash table with the information from
that file that then prevents any future
accidental over over importing basically
like bringing in PNG s that you already
knew about but just only happened on a
previous run of the program so we need
to save
and we need to finish the the right
modifications to HH a part of things but
we don't actually need to do that part
yet because that's just about making
subsequent runs of the game work
properly right and so for subsequent
runs of the games to work properly we'll
take care of that for right now we just
want it to import assets properly for
one run of the game and so that's what
we want to do here and the two things we
need to do for that are inside right
modifications to HHA when we go through
the assets we need to pull the
information out right and pulling the
information out of the assets to write
it back to the file is what we're gonna
do right now and then the other thing
that we need to do is we need to decide
on some tags to give these assets right
now we just don't so when they come in
they'll never be used we will import
them correctly but they will have no
tags attached to them so no one will
ever find them for any purpose you won't
be able to use these assets right so we
need to find some way to give them some
tags we can give them some test tags to
start with or you know whatever we want
so that's easy enough but we need to
eventually get to a place where we have
some idea of what tags we're gonna put
on there right okay so if we come down
here and we loop through the asset
indexes here are the assets themselves
oops they should have been there is my
struct asset there it is
so each asset has the information we
actually want in it right
it's got like which asset it was in the
file what file index it was in and what
the AJ was and all that sort of stuff
right so what we want to do here is we
have because we're running the game has
all of the assets known to it across
every HHA what we want to do is look for
the ones that pertain to this HHA
specifically so for each asset we want
to check to see if the file index in
this asset is equal to the file index
that we're actually looking for right if
it is
then we go ahead and write it out and if
it's not we skip it right so in both
cases we're going to be doing something
that looks like this we put that over
here and that over here so in both cases
we're going to be looking to see if this
asset is one that we actually should
process if the asset is one that we
should process then what we know is
we've got you know to make space for it
in the file so this file is gonna have
one more asset than it had before
because we found any one and then for
the tag count we just need to know how
many tags this thing had now in the HHA
file I believe that I'm sorry not the
HSA file in the HHA struct
I guess I should say we actually have a
sort of a list here that says hey this
is the first tag that I use and this is
the last tag that I use right so we kind
of know how many tags we're going to
need for this particular asset because
the HHA asset itself says that
information right so it's pretty easy
for us to figure out what that should be
so what I want to do here is say ok this
assets sorry this tag count is gonna add
however much this asset says that it
needs maybe I could do well
so that's you know a example of grabbing
out the range adding the tag count in we
now have the asset count and the tag
count so we're ready to write it out
similarly then we get here there's not a
lot of there's really not much to this
right we can just write the HHA out
directly and off we go so in this case
we know that we've got this source asset
we then know that it's matching the file
index that we're trying to write out so
what I want to do now is go okay we've
got a target HHA asset right that's the
destination asset and what we could
probably do here is also say hey let's
just start at the front of the asset
array right and let's also start let's
do a death type at the asset types right
so with these here what we could do is
just write these things out
incrementally now because we're writing
out the HHA asset the asset type thing
here because this is a little bit weird
I suppose what we want to do in this
case is keep track of the asset index
like in the file so maybe we don't
really have to do that we can just do it
this way and so once we grab that piece
of information and we then have a
destination to write into we can see
what the type ID of this asset was we
can say what the first asset index was
we can say what one passed last that
index was and so on right and it's just
going to be sorry this is just tight
it's just gonna be whatever the asset
index was in the file and the type ID
right just whatever this assets was
supposed to be whatever type this asset
was supposed to be so if we go back into
handmade asset in here one of the things
that's a little bit of a problem is we
don't
record that information anywhere so the
asset memory header has the asset type
in it but we really don't record it
anywhere else if that makes sense
um I'm not 100% sure yeah like like we
don't we don't store that data anywhere
at the moment and so our ability to
write it out is kind of compromised and
I feel like we're gonna probably have to
augment like I feel like we're probably
gonna have to augment that structure to
say which one it is now we could get
around this if we wanted to
[Music]
by using this linked list I'm not sure
necessarily why we wouldn't bother
storing the type in there but we could
just not do that right so for example if
we wanted to in here we could just say
hey here's all the asset types right the
asset index globally speaking is just
first a set of type for that type ID and
then we just know the type ID right so
yeah I mean we can get around storing
the type ID because we actually sort of
have it stored implicitly but you know
we may want to just store that in in the
actual structure now that we're doing
updates because it's not like it's a
huge deal to keep that information it's
pretty minimal so I'm not sure that's
really a smart idea long term but we
don't need it for this so I suppose you
know I'll just say note we loop through
the type of the first asset of type
lists here because we don't store the
type ID
so you know not sure what we want to do
about that
anyway what what happened there
handmade asset oops didn't mean to type
an a in there we go
so yeah moving on here we have more work
to do though and again this just gets
down to the tag situation so when we
actually have a destination asset here
really the destination asset is just
going to be whatever we had stored in
the file for in the asset struct for its
HHA so we we don't really have to do
anything at the moment and again that's
just because we stored the HHA asset
information here so we can copy it into
the array like so just directly but it's
a little misleading because it's not
really going to be correct and the
reason for that is like we just kind of
nerfed the tag array here like it's not
really correct and so I again I'm not
sure how we really want to approach that
going forward for right now I'm just
gonna say okay let's actually just write
out the tags as if we were preserving
them exactly the way they used to be and
we'll just go from there
so what we want to do there is say well
we've got this tag array and so I'm
gonna have a desk tag I guess that I
write out here although I guess again we
want to be able to refer to index so I
guess I'll say tag and Nixon file right
and what we'll do is we'll write out
these tags one at a time and I don't
know if we skip the first tag in terms
of the when we actually read them in I
don't think we do
yeah I don't think we do so when we read
them in we assume that the first tag is
actually valid we leave space for a null
tag and then we move we continue forward
with the tag array so when we're
actually writing out one of these what
we want to do is just write out all the
tags that we see so we want to do a four
I loop in here for like a tag index the
tag index needs to loop over the the HHA
that we're going to write out so the
first tag index and the one passed last
tag index oops
so as we loop over the tags here what we
want to do is we want to take every
individual tag that we see and we want
to copy those tags into our tag array so
that we have them all in a nice flat
structure that will get rid written out
right so what we do here is we say well
we know we have the tag index in the
file that was the last one we wrote to
so if we take the tags array right into
the next position whatever the tag is
that we see for this particular asset we
should be good to go
now where do we get the actual types
well the actual tags come from in
handmade asset the game asset struct has
all the tags in it right they're sitting
here so if we just look at the tag in
question that's the one we wanted I
think right so we're just pulling out
the assets tags and off we go
now what I'm not quite sure about is I
don't really know I assumed that when we
took the HHA we offset the HHA right so
like here just to double check when we
loading in HHA from the file and we
assign them all right I'm assuming what
we do is we yeah
oh that's interesting
so actually though that does look like
the first tag is skipped so what am I
saying when I said the first time I
thought it looks like it was loading the
tags oh it's not loading the tags it
does skipped it okay I apologize I
apologize I made a disgusting error so I
take it all back
so the first tag is in fact skipped and
that means we could zero struct tags
zero right although these are all
getting cleared I don't know that we
really need to clear all these to be
honest because we're gonna write to them
all but you know anyway so when we write
through here and we write everything out
what we're gonna find now is that all of
the tags that we have are packed into
the file it looks like if it's a tag if
it's a zero tag we don't want to write
anything but that's already the case
right so because we're not gonna be it's
going to be zero and this is going to be
zero and so it's fine so we should this
should write out all the tanks for us
and now once we have all that we'll have
the header the tags the asset types and
the assets all of those things can now
be written to the file and that should
conclude the updating of an HHA right so
that's all good now one thing we do need
to check and this is sort of a separate
issue that's just about the platform
layer and has nothing to do with
anything else is that the platform
layers ability to write to the file is
predicated on having opened the file
with the ability to write the file right
because the operating system maintains
those handles so when we have like write
data to file and ask me why this is not
that so when we have write data to file
what we need to be able to do is ensure
that this handle that we actually
created up above here
as the authority to write in the first
place so what you can see is it it's got
to well I guess certainly that's three
it has three sort of places where that
comes into play one is this and that
generic read handle I'm sorry that
generic read flag is just telling the
operating system that's what we plan to
do with this handle so if we lift that
as is when we tried to write to this
handle it would tell us that we couldn't
the right would fail and the reason is
because we didn't ask for permission
when we opened the handle so what we
really want is we want this to be open
with permission to write to the file as
well if we are actually a like if it's
actually the case that the handle not
sure how to say this we want to have the
option of doing this I guess is why I
wouldn't want to say we want to have the
option of saying that we want to write
to the handle as well as read to from
the handle right so what we kind of need
here is the ability to specify some
information about what we're going to do
we sort of want to do something like
this
we kind of want to start and we want to
see what kind of a handle we're trying
to make here is this something we plan
to write to or is this something we plan
to read from or both right and then we
want to actually apply these things
sensibly one thing we could say here is
something like this you know if we plan
to write to this and all right then we
know that the handle permissions have to
be generic right enabled if you know we
plan to read from this handle will fill
those in in a second
then we want generic read now in terms
of how we want to share access to the
file we probably will allow people to
read from it at all times because
whether we're writing or reading from it
or whatever if someone else wants to
look at the file we don't care we don't
have any specific reason to prevent
people from reading from it we do
however probably need to prevent people
from writing to it because if they wrote
to it it might change the file out from
under us and then we'd get really
confused and crashed and do all sorts of
bad things right so we want to make sure
that we're the only people accessing it
and if anyone's gonna write to it it's
gonna be us so the other thing that we
need to deal with is this open existing
thing here so what happens here is when
we have handle creation we need to tell
the operating system what to do with the
underlying file in the case where it
exists and the case where it doesn't
exist
so when we call create file W we're
gonna pass a file name that file name
may be there or that family file name
may not be there right and it depends on
which to which of those it is it depends
what we might want to do with it in the
case where we're trying to read from a
file we want to open an existing file we
don't want to have the operation create
a file for us to read from because
that's not going to help right so when
we open a file that's for reading only
we kind of want to
say open existing because if we're
seeing that it's for read and I put
these in this order specifically if
we're saying it's for read then we want
to make sure that it exists if on the
other hand we planned to write to this
file potentially then it may be the case
that we can just make one because we
might write to it right so in that case
we should probably say hey in addition
to opening the file if it's there maybe
we want to create it if it's not there
and so what you can see this is a little
bit different than if you're familiar
with the C runtime library it's a little
bit different the different modes that
you have available
those are like you do parentheses like R
plus and W and WB and all those are a
little confusing and not always the best
so what we want to do thankfully is use
the more direct Windows stuff and that's
what we're using right now this is a lot
more clear right and you can see what
the modes are there's create always
which means throw away anything that was
there and make a new one there's create
new which means create a new one but if
there was one there just fail so don't
over anything there's open always which
means open existing one if there was one
there but if there wasn't one there make
a new one and then open it open existing
which means if there's not one there
than fail but if there is one there open
it and then truncating existing means
open a file that happened that has to be
there but once you open it get rid of
all the contents right so pretty good
actually set of flags here good on the
win when old went through two folks for
that and what we want in this case isn't
open always right because we want to
write to it then what we want to do is
open it if it's there but if it's not
there then we just want to create one
right so that's I think how we want to
construct these and from there we can
now figure out how to actually put some
flags in place for that to occur in the
platform layer itself so when we have
open file which is this right here
the prototype for that should now have
in addition to the info to open we also
want to have like mode flags right and
the mood flags are just going to be this
for now and so now we can do is say okay
those mood flags we can test and what we
can do is just use those mode flags
figure out which one of these you want
to do then we can pass those like so and
off we go
so it's pretty straightforward right
there's not a lot to it
that just allows us more expressivity in
this now one thing that we also have the
ability to do now that I should mention
is now that we've done sort of a more
robust version of these things we can
probably just finish off this API here
because it's pretty good there's maybe
one or two other things you might want
to do but we could probably get rid of a
lot of this stuff right so this this
this
[Music]
I don't really know what get process
state even does what does that do
oh that's just for running external
processes right never mind
so basically like we can get rid of free
file memory read entire file and write
entire file because we can now just
implement those inside the game as debug
functions and not have to have the
platform layer worry about them anymore
right so I think what we want to do is
something here which just says you know
to do KC get rid of these eventually
make them just go through the open file
read data from file write data to file
close file API and like I said it's not
quite there yet because you know we
haven't looked at doing that but these
would be pretty easier place now and
that gets the debug stuff down to just
these and we don't really use this
execute system command 1 anymore anyway
we were using that for some debug stuff
where we were kind of playing around
with it so we don't even know if we
really want that or we'll need that in
the future so we may be able to really
slim this down eventually to the point
where we're just looking at this stuff
up here at the top and this is a pretty
good platform API now in terms of being
pretty minimal but getting most of the
stuff that we actually need now again
could it be refined yes we'll refine it
possibly but it's just worth noting that
like at some point you get when the API
gets a little redundant you might as
well just consolidate it down because
every time we port to a new platform we
have to port all these functions if we
simplify them down to fewer functions
it makes porting to new platforms easier
and more consistent because more of the
code lives in the shared part of the
code base which means that you have less
platform variability as well which is
also you know a very good thing
all right
so let's see I think we're all good here
we just want to pass now open file read
because this is only reading at the
moment and we'll switch it to open file
right eventually now these these will
always be open file read because we
don't write to the pngs for example that
was mode flags not mode flag and then
one other thing when you do we just
haven't done it yet is win32 close file
where do i set the platform handle we
don't open there it is so we added a
bunch of functions we now that we're
gonna actually start running this stuff
we need to make sure that we actually
set up these platform calls so that they
can be accessed by the game
all right
so I think that's really it in terms of
the writing stuff I don't really think
there's anything else we need to do so
now we should kind of start we should we
should start down the road of trying to
actually put the assets into the game
and to do that like I said requires us
now starting to work with the tags
because basically everything in here is
going through tags in one way or another
and so if we want to have the the actual
assets available to put them on these
walls or you know change with you know
the sprites of the character stuff like
that we need some way of setting up the
tags so that those tags actually get
used when the when the game is searching
you know for art assets to use so I'm
going to borrow the same trick that I
did for the assets themselves and I'm
just going to make it so that we can add
tags to the system like so when we look
at max access count here here we go I
I'm going to do the same thing I did
before so I'm going to say that max tag
count just equals assets tag count and
then I'm just gonna bump it and again I
think we're gonna change the way we do
this stuff eventually because we can
simplify those tags down I think we
could pull some of the complexity out of
that probably we'll see depends on how
we want do it but given that we sort of
have that basic situation now what we
want to do here is just give ourselves a
way to add the tags you already have
just for testing purposes so by doing
that we could now that we have a reserve
asset that uses Headroom in the ass
I can also do the same thing with
reserved tag so in here what I would do
is exactly the same thing I did with you
assets like so but instead of reserving
a single one at a time since we know we
typically want a raise of tags I'm
actually gonna just have a tag count
that gets passed in here so what I'm
gonna do is say well if you could have
reserved all of the tags that you asked
for don't ask me why this oh wait no it
should be less than mine yes uh there we
go I will just reserve all of them in
bulk right so you tell me you want a
certain number of tags I give you back a
block of that many tags or zero if there
was no way to do so because we're out of
tags so now we can assign tags to any of
these things that we want to assign tags
to but the problem that we have is now
we've run out of stuff we know what to
do and we're in to the place where we
have to start making decisions so the
first thing I'm going to do is I'm just
gonna assign the old-school tags in some
kind of hacky way that just allows us to
debug the asset importing itself because
that will at least get us so that we can
say that our PNG import path is now
complete and then what we can do is
start on the next leg which is putting
the assets into the game that we have
and in doing that the goal of that will
be to figure out how these tags should
work for once and for all so that now
we're just gonna say this is the final
way that tags are gonna be specified
right
okay and again my suspicion here is that
really what we want to do is the tags
are probably going to be streamlined
down to correspond a little bit more
with the asset the way that the assets
are set up we'll probably just have a
bunch of things that are sort of like
constant tags in some way that's sort of
like I'm guessing I'll be like the asset
type tells us something about which you
know group of things you are and then
the tags actually just tell us like
which kind of grid square you were and
or something like this and we just know
exactly which ones to jump to it's hard
to say but I don't know I'm thinking
that we're gonna have a simpler way of
doing it just because now we're coming
in with sprite sheets in a pretty
straightforward way all right so I think
that's it so I'm gonna go ahead and just
see what the easiest way is for me to
add something in here so if we go into
the entity system I should say
placeholder introduce the entity system
obviously we don't really do much with
entities at the moment but if we go into
the stuff that does entities here and I
actually just create something that you
know like like we don't have the hero
doesn't have a hand right here doesn't
have a hand yet so let's suppose I went
into the hand made asset stuff and I
added the notion that there is a hand
right
so in the table of assets I have a thing
called asset hand and asset hand is a
new thing that you can have right well
we know that we have one of those
actually we have two of them I think in
the test assets that Anna sent us we
have now we have three we have like a
flaming paw thing we have an actual
glove and we have a skeleton hand right
so we know we already have everything we
you know everything that we need out of
these we already have the notion of what
this is it has four different directions
right and I don't think I think it's
just a base item template so I think we
don't I don't really know how the hand
files are set up there is no hand
template file I should ask what that's
gonna be
let me actually send a mail real quick
just so we know because I don't want to
forget okay so when we load in one of
these hand files we can assign it the
new asset hand type ID and then we can
use the existing tags we have which is
facing direction right we can take the
facing direction and assign it properly
to correspond with with these directions
right and that one's a little bit harder
to see but it's right up left down just
going around the circle exactly as we
would expect so if I wanted to do that
what I could do is say alright let's
start by only importing hands because we
don't want to waste our time importing
everything because we don't have tags
for everything and we don't know how
wants to be imported yet we're just
gonna do hands and we're gonna see how
that works and debug with just the hands
so when we come through here what I want
to do is filter out anything that isn't
a hand file now what you see is we've
already sort of done this which is that
this piece is here this this part that
pieces array should have just the names
separated by underscores so if the first
name is hand that's a hand file and if
the first name is something else it's
not so that gives us a pretty
straightforward way of dealing with this
right okay so what I can do is in here I
can sort of start by saying where's
those little pieces things there it is I
can just test for Strings being equal in
the pieces I can say if strings are
equal pieces zero what is it and then do
this and that's will tell me whether or
not we have one that we actually want to
process all the rest of them I will
simply skip right and that'll be that
so let's go ahead and and do that I
don't know that we have one of these for
a counted string okay so we do so if we
want to write take one of these things
here we can actually make a little
simple utility function
and all we're doing here is just calling
a function we already have and we're
gonna pass the stuff that we have here
right so we know we've got a count like
so and then we're going to return it
similarly we can also do this this way
because we have this one too so we can
do the same thing that way right I think
I claim
that was a you eight pointer and it
wants a care star enough so now what we
should be able to do is call that change
function and what I'm going to do is in
handmade asset when we do I'm going to
put this into the header file so we can
call it whenever we want here so what I
want to do is I want to check for art
changes once we load these files now
what I'm going to do is when we start up
the game here right I'm not gonna bother
updating existing files yet what I'm
gonna do instead is I'm just gonna have
a dummy file that we use for appending
new assets to and we're just gonna start
there so we're just gonna start simple
so I'm gonna do check for art changes
here and what should happen is nothing
because this won't be set to anything
right so what I should be able to do
return value there compiler doesn't warn
you on the visual studio compiler
doesn't warn you on a missing return
value if you never call the function I
don't necessarily know why it may be
because of template things I'm not sure
sometimes to support like template-based
stuff they have to do things like don't
require a return value if the function
has never been called because the
function is never called then it won't
have had to been stan shaded which means
you know but you know it may actually be
a requirement for all I know I don't
follow that stuff anymore but it makes
you be requirement so who knows but
point being typically the compiler on
Windows will not warn you about a Miss
and return value till someone calls the
actual function whether that's just
because it doesn't bother looking at the
function or whether that's because it's
actually required not to do that I don't
know so I you know that's that's sort of
a separate discussion but either way it
doesn't so that's all that was right
there is kind of reminding us so now if
we set a breakpoint there we should be
able to run the game we should check for
our changes and what should happen is
since there's nowhere to append a new
data to it should just skip right and so
our game should run basically the same
way that it was running before oops
we still have to fix that weird we have
some camera bugginess things there where
it will it will like give us bogus
values and I've know that if we wait too
long like there's a yeah
it's it's just a stupid bug but anyway
I've does nothing to it checking for our
changes so when we do our check for art
changes there you know we should
probably just debug that since I now can
do it pretty easily it's it's pretty
simple I think it's just the the way the
camera updates is and the way the frame
update is is just kind of a little bit
busted so if I if I come in here you
just take a look
gain input so do you see this DT for
frame it's like 14 seconds right this
what we want to do is we never want to
run the game forward 14 seconds because
if you pass a high enough floating-point
value in there no matter what we do
things will probably blow up right
similarly if you pass too small of a
value there things would probably blow
up because we'd run out of precision at
the low end so what we probably should
do just in general is we should have
that capped now we should also fix our
camera code because there's no reason
for the camera code to be that bad but
we don't really want to do that right
now
right that should wait for when we're
actually doing some finalization of the
camera code but what I want to do here
is say okay if we have the DT for frame
input we want to cap it
all right so what I want to do say all
right if input DT for frame and I guess
you know I can also look a little bit
here to see who else uses it but if the
DT for frame is going to be greater than
let's say you know I don't know a
hundred milliseconds then that's that's
the slowest we will ever run and if it's
less than one millisecond that's like
the fastest will ever run right and so
you know it's hard to say what those
should actually be but what we want the
platform layer to do is to keep those
refresh rates within that rate and if it
can't we should probably warn it right
so the other thing we could do there is
is maybe have some kind of a warning
and maybe someday when we sort of do
some code about that sort of stuff we
could add something in there right so
now what I should be able to do is sit
around waiting here for as long as I
want to and do whatever I want and then
if I run the game it should still work
right and again that's just there so
that if something weird happens in the
game like it's stalled for a minute it
doesn't come back and tell the game to
do one minutes worth of updating which
will completely ruin everything
right because we simply have never
architected the code to advance things
by one minute and so it would compute
like really long trajectories for
everything and even if we made all that
code stable in the sense that it didn't
crash it just moved people to where they
should be the game would still be in a
nonsensical state so the design of it
would suffer greatly from that even if
we made all the code 100% robust to it
so you kind of want to do that no matter
how robust we ever make the code we
probably still need to fix that part
okay so moving on we would like now to
have the check for art changes code
actually get run and in order to do that
we now need to have an HHA that we're
actually going to use we're actually
going to work with write some something
and HHA that's set up specifically for
this purpose right and so what I want to
do is test to see if we're in the
internal mode and if we're in the
internal node then I'm going to grab
these HHA files for writing as well as
reading right so when we come through
this loop here and we're reading them in
I want to actually do an or right there
in the case where we're gonna be
actually having in the case where we're
going to actually allow writing back to
the files so what I'm going to do here
is say yeah let's just go ahead and
specify will say open file read will say
if handmade oops eternal open Flags
or equals to open file right so what I
would like to do here is I would like to
just say well once we've word these two
things together now I'll just open all
the files with that because if we're
assuming that we're gonna allow write
back so we can write back to any asset
in the system so off we go what I'd also
like to do now is say well we need to
pick a file to append to and it's tough
to say what file we would want to append
to so we kind of need some rule here
right if I go to handmade data here what
I kind of want to do is I want to make
an HHA that's for appending and I want
to have some way of indicating which one
I want to append to right and I I feel
like I almost want like a command line
flag or switch or something so when you
run the game you can tell it like I'm
editing art assets and here's where I
want to put the new ones you know what
no I guess I don't want to do that I
think what I'd rather do is I think what
I I think I would rather create a file
if I haven't seen one that's called like
new assets that HHA something like this
I mean they just it seems like what I
would like you know
hmm hmm hmm I'm just not sure how I want
to do that specifically I mean one way
is there's just always a file called
like new assets HHA or something and
they all just get appended to that and
then if you want to stop if you want to
lock down one HHA you then just rename
it to a new file name right and it will
then create another new assets that HHA
where new assets would go so right I
mean that seems fine
[Music]
it's just I'm just not sure
yeah I I I don't have a really strong
opinion about this I feel like there's a
lot of options but there's not a clear
like right answer to me I just need some
way of knowing which one of these files
should be accessed in that way I guess
maybe what I'll say is
I guess maybe what I'll say is that you
can yeah yeah sorry I just not feeling
it
I'm not feeling an obvious right answer
here so I'm not sure
I mean I guess I'll just say the use
case for this is generally speaking you
run it on an artist machine and they
want to basically just make you know
they're just putting p.m. G's down and
you want to capture all those pngs into
an HHA which you're eventually would
ship or something right but you really
don't care because you you can always
rebuild it all from the PNG s anyway so
it's not like you really care what HSA
it's tucked them in can stick them in
Naha it actually wants to because that
has nothing to do with how you actually
build the distribution hhas you could
build them any way you want from the bit
from the PNG to get imported
so the hhas are really just a cache and
you really just don't care
hmm
so I think what I'm going to say is I'm
just gonna say like look it creates a
file I guess called like local HHA or
something like that and that's the one
that it will write to in that case so
like this
you know what I mean so we basically
have like one local one that we just
sort of have around and we go from there
seems reasonable to me I guess I don't
know I mean another way to do this would
be to say that that just automatically
gets created somewhere else like we
could say look at startup there always
has to be one of those and if there are
we go from there so like we say all
right we loop over these files if
handmade internal is set then we do this
mumbo-jumbo here and when we have you
know when we do like looping over the
file info and we do platform Open File
and that sort of stuff what we do is we
check to see at the end of it all if
handmade internalist set then we do if
strings are equal and we test to see if
this is local HHA right we can look at
file info I assume we have some name
here that we can trust
it's called base name I think right yeah
so if we just look at the base name and
its local then whatever the file index
is that we have right now that's the one
that we're going to use
so I'm actually okay with that and then
if we want to we can do something that
creates one of those and if we don't we
don't so when we run this it'll still
skip this right
but then in the win32 handmade directory
at startup if we wanted to we could
create one of those right so we could
say you know
it's debug platform right entire file
you could just say like yeah right this
file out if it doesn't exist you know I
again not really sure this is a great
idea but I'm just saying like you know
what else we could do actually now I
think about it I kind of like this even
better if you want one of these you
create one using some alternative method
so like maybe we take simple pre process
or here and simple process or normally
like here's the that's a sorry test
asset builder so maybe like we take test
asset builder and say well maybe we
should have one of these that writes in
HHA out with nothing in it so like we
could do something like
like this
actually you know what so now I am
actually getting a plan yeah I think I
know what I actually want to do here
okay okay here's a proposal for you cuz
I just I haven't been feeling good about
any of the options there it's didn't
like them but now I think I have one
let's just make a little utility that we
can run and we call it like HHA edit or
something right or HH edit dot cpp right
something like that and then this thing
just allows you to do stuff with hhas
maybe right that actually seems pretty
good to me so you know we basically say
if you know if argh count equals yeah
this is really stupid
but it's just a base of command-line
utility that you know choose C runtime
library it's standard nothing weird
going on just basic basic stuff we would
say look if you know args one was create
or something right
then create one of these things maybe
let's say and like this will just let us
do stuff so maybe in the future we'll
have things to come like merge to hhas
or dump hhas or do whatever we want so
it seems reasonable right and so this
could include the same stuff that we
included here in fact I'll just grab
this directly and then I'll put that
into the compile path for us
that should be about it and then I'm
happy camper right so then yeah so then
I could add one of those to our to our
misc directory where we have like our
batch files you know and so in here I
could make an HHA edit bat that go off W
build HHA edit eggsy pass all the stuff
to it right and now it's in the path so
I can do stuff and what I can do here is
say alright if you pass - create then
we'll make one of those and we probably
want to make sure it doesn't exist yet
so I might do like dest equals F open
file name read binary if test that's an
error right so something like this maybe
so that I can do
that so that it won't overwrite a file
you would have to delete the file first
just to make sure you're not actually
overwriting something when you ask it to
do one of these things so just test to
see if the file exists and and that's it
right so then assuming that we can open
one here uh then what we want to do just
write an HS a header to it we want the
header to be blank because we don't want
anything in it right so the only thing
we want to set is the things that are
required on an HH a header so for
example magic value inversion and
everything else to be no there's nothing
else in the file by the way we figured
out the awesomer way to do this didn't
we when we did the PNG reader
remember when we did the like
oh right it was like crazy you can just
like put it in single quotes so nuts
anyway um that's so nuts anyway sorry I
just wanted to remind myself that that
was crazy but that I had never seen
first so anyway we need the magic value
the version but we don't need anything
else that should just create one of them
right um so here it let me do HHA edit
if I do create it still doesn't have
enough arguments for it so it tells us
we don't have one if I do food eh eh and
now I do it dirty HHA it should have
created one of those well and in theory
if I run it twice it should tell me that
it already exists so then if I go to the
data directory and I want to make one of
these for the local cache I can just do
hij edit - create local HHA and now
there is one so now in theory if I did
the rest of it right it should actually
have it should actually have one that
can write you now that looks like we get
an assert here so
I'm not sure how this got in here since
asset count for type is zero something's
weird I think maybe this was just why is
that we take a look at the file and so
I see that I'm not in a debug build that
is just right out of the question sir
okay now I can actually look at stuff so
it says that so this stuff is all
actually filled in
I'm not sure what it's complaining about
but I should probably look here to see
what's going on
when it initially loads the files so we
can determine what actually happened
here which file is this by the way fund
x6
so here is my assumption these are not
properly guarded so probably what's
going on here is the tag count and the
asset count are actually erroneous
because you're not allowed to have zero
if that makes sense
so I'm not sure how that would have
worked anyway because the it should have
produced an extremely high number for
these because it should have been 0
minus 1 and s and 0 minus 1 in both of
those cases so I'm a little weirded out
by that but let me just I'm just gonna
step through this and see what happened
there so that does seem a little strange
so we're loading test fonts
and we're loading test three antis -
just one and now local
oh so it basically just wrapped a
reduced negative one so I'm not sure
exactly how I want to handle that so it
seems like maybe that argues that these
should produce those properly but I
don't know I kind of don't love the fact
that that's how that works so I don't
know for now I think what I may do is
say that we actually handle that case
but I don't quite love it because it's a
little bit too much thing going on there
and it's not great let's jump back to
that yeah
so I think it was just the fact that
those are subtracting one was probably
the problem there we now have a default
HHA to a pen too so this code can
execute and so now we can start to look
at the situation as we had it before um
so let's take a look at what our pieces
array says so you can see here we've got
title and you can see that the count of
the string here tells us how many
character read the the debugger doesn't
know that these are counted strings it
thinks they're null-terminated strings
so that's why it says title screen but
it's actually just title right because
it says there's only five characters so
it's split into title and screen which
is exactly what we want it's not going
to find one of those so it's going to
create one of these on you know matches
for it but then it's gonna punt it's not
going to actually find that it because
it doesn't have hand as the first thing
I'm so you can see again we get
obstacles orphanage which is good
obstacles forest item template blah blah
blah
so it's going through everything like we
wanted here we found an actual hand one
of these so now we can actually look at
what it's going to do so it should match
and it does so now we start our import
this allows us to open that file this is
the file in question right this platform
thing here okay that's not what oh yes
it is
those are wide characters I believe
right hmm I thought handle platforms
should have had oh that's why I'm an
idiot
you file into a platform that's what I
was looking for right so what was that
thing here we go there so that's the
actual file that it's going to be
grabbing there which is what we wanted
so that's good so we come through here
and we say although okay nevermind so in
here we we loop through the file buffer
stuff we read in the the data from the
file so that should get us the entire
file hopefully there's no error on it
which we should probably check that but
we didn't we match the file date and say
okay now we've got the latest data we go
through update art pack update our
packages we start to reap we start to
read from the the buffer that we were
given which is you know as you can see
it's the constant of paying so we ask
the PNG reader to read it so they're the
PNG reader did read it in here's all of
our ping that was the work we did before
awesome we go through process tiled
import process tile import comes through
and says alright here's all of
here's all of the tiles that we might
want to look at let's go ahead and look
at which one of them contain data so I'm
gonna go ahead and jump till we get to
one that does so we've found one that
contains data and so now what we're
gonna do is we're gonna initialize what
we think the hij asset should be we
should find that we don't have a backing
store for this yet because its first
time you ever seen it and we aren't
storing backing stores to files yet
anyway so even if we had seen it before
it's a fresh front of the program so it
wouldn't find anything regardless so we
try to reserve the asset here so we come
through and we say well alright how many
assets could be happy of that many how
many do we have only that many so we
easily can let's say put it in this
asset we now have an asset index for it
we can go through and set all this
information since we haven't seen it
before we're gonna put it in this file
which is good we can reserve data for it
this is how much data we need for one of
the tiles right so we can set that
information up record the HHA now and of
course it doesn't have tags which is the
problem so it won't be able to be seen
that's the part that we need to start
working on we have the asset indices
here we record the fact that the first
tile has that asset index now and then
we want to write the data back right so
we want to say okay write the data to
the file the offset should be just after
the header which is exactly where it is
right now so that's that's perfect and
we want to write this data in so now we
should see is we should see this file
expand this file is a 44 byte file it
should now go to a four megabyte file
when this gets written out to it right
well
it hasn't gotten written back yet so
hopefully okay
I assume that means the handles still
open not sure how to really get any
confirmation as to whether the right is
pending or not hmm so it looks like that
right failed actually all right so let's
try that again let's see what happened
so here we are we check for oh it
already has errors so at some point we
actually just already got an error on
that file before we ever tried to issue
the right
all right so let's take a look
here's local we issue read the issue a
read we're still fine
okay so let's come through here let's
see which file we're on now
so the that file is number five oh I'm
not even look at the file index five so
there's the file says there's no errors
so we come through here we're gonna
issue a read so that read doesn't work
yeah oh and of course it's the same
reason right so do you see this is why I
was saying I don't like that thing
because you have to guard against all of
these minus ones and it's just not it's
not you you want to be in a situation
where those just work right and we're
definitely not in that situation so I'm
not sure what the best way is to get out
of that so I'm kind of just perpetuating
a bad situation here by by allowing
those code paths to work I'm just not
sure what the right solution is to fix
that so what we really need to do here
right is if we look at the tag array
size it's something that only gets used
here so you know what we're doing is
basically look if the file had our tag
count is valid then we go otherwise we
don't and again that's just I don't
really like it the rest of these I think
should work because they use
differencing to tell what what range
they should use but
well let's let's not count our chickens
before they hatch so we skip that one
and we have nothing to read so I think
we're fine
yeah so then we can jump down to here
and see now if yeah now we can see
whether we have errors on that feller or
not but you can see why I didn't like
the way that is just error-prone so now
we will actually issue this read this
right and looks like it worked okay so
now I should be able to see the file
expand but it might not cuz the file
hasn't closed yet necessarily right so
if we do a derp on this you know the
local hij against it might not actually
be updated and so we may have to wait
until we close down to actually see the
results of that flush out but we'll see
okay we should also close these file
handles now I was going to let this run
to completion pulling out all of the
hand data which it did right and then
I'm gonna disclose so that will close
all of the file handles for us and now
our local HHA has 50 Meg's of
information in it and we know that each
of those hand pieces was about 4
megabytes right well not about exactly
so if we do 1024 by 1024 by 4 if we take
50 megabytes right and divide it out
like so we get 12.5 right if we think
about how many hands we should have have
should have it was 12 so we're basically
right on the money in fact if I put in
this exact number we have exactly 12
effectively plus the overhead of like
the header and stuff right so that's
exactly how many hands we should have
had so we pulled in exactly the hands we
wanted everything was fine and dandy and
now our local HHA has that
affirmation in it right so now when we
actually run that those assets will be
there they just won't have any tags so
you will never know what they're there
for whatever that's worth right all
right so I thought there was one of the
thing I wanted to do there but I
forgotten exit uh so I thought there is
one of the things I want to do there but
I cannot remember what it was
so that's not great but you know I guess
whatever it was when it rears its ugly
head later I'll remember because I'll
have a pug and we go anyway so that all
is reasonable now right and all of this
stuff is getting updated pretty much the
way that I wanted it to and we're all
good so we now have to do something with
actually putting those tags into place
and what I want to do here is assigning
asset types to these guys oh that's what
I wanted to do that's what I wanted to
do yes yes yes yes yes thankfully I just
remembered what it was so when we come
through here and we're going to look at
one of these assets we never assign the
asset a type right eye so we want to
pull out that code that we're assigning
that we're using to assign types to
assets right this code right here we
want that code to be used up here as
well so we need to know the type of the
asset and we need to be able
put the asset into that type list so
this should be a function right that
does this and we should make sure that
it I mean we would ideally want to check
to make sure that the asset had never
been this type before or something as
well but or we want to make sure it's
not already in the list but there's not
a lot we can do about that
we can't assert that it doesn't have an
X of type field but yeah I don't know I
mean that's about all we can do right
that's not conclusive because it could
just be the last in the list and then it
would still have that set so again the
type stuff probably should be done a
little bit differently than this but
we'll keep going with this for now one
thing that time so if we have an asset
we just say this is the asset and then
we need to say what the new type should
be right and then so in here it would
just be hey okay I guess we need asset
index here now we know we've we've set
it I need a thing here to say that you
know and I get I guess actually I can do
it just like this
no I can't I lied so if I take that list
I can then say okay yeah make sure we
don't already have one of those and then
set it to whatever is in here right so
if I do that then I can do set asset
type here and I can pass the assets and
I can pass the asset index right so when
we're grabbing this one I can say that
global asset next has to be this type ID
right then I can get rid of those and
now I have a function that can set the
type ID of an asset outside of that
context because we're going to want to
do it down here as well so what I want
to do is I want it in here I want to
call that thing to set the asset type
right and so when we come down here if
we reserve a new asset then what we want
to do is we want to set that assets type
when we reserve it to this type ID right
and I could actually do it this way
so what we need now is we need an
understanding of what the type ID
actually is for this asset and in order
to do that we need some kind of a coding
in the system for so that when we're
like getting these tiles out we
understand that so I'm gonna this now
becomes the tag problem the asset type
problem a tag problem so I'm gonna call
this import grid tags or something
and I'm just gonna say alright there's
an asset type ID for each row and then
there's like some tags or something for
each row and column right trying to
think of how that should work here but
you know for now we'll just say ok
import good tags and and you know what
we'll just do one tag let me grab out an
asset tag thing here where's our tags
should be your summer tag ID
that's so it's just ID value right so if
we imagine we just have like some HHA
tag and here we've got so when it does
this this import right and it's looping
over these things that X count the Y
count and the you know the X count max
and and all that stuff what we want to
do since these are now kind of linked
together right we probably want to just
define a grid max for this like an
import grid Max or something right and
then they'll just be so this will
correspond the same way so you can index
them both and here's the tags right and
what I need to do I probably should do
import grid tag or something like that
what I probably should do is say all
right here's the type ID I'll just make
it so that it can be for everything
here's the tags here's the tag count
right and then I'll just say import grid
tag and we have tags that's how many we
have right so then when we come through
here we can just say look you've got to
give this thing an import grid tag so it
knows where to get its tags from so when
you interpret this source file I want
you to use this then when we come
through we know what the type ID is
because it corresponds to the x and y
count so I can then say you know maybe
this is grid tag array and then I can
say this has written tags
[Music]
let's lock that up into our structure
okay
and so in here we'll just look at what
the tags are for this particular one and
so again we said it's YX so in this case
we want to put the Y index and then the
X index right so when we get those tags
out now we can assign a different type
ID to each one of those right so each
tie on the grid can get let's own type
and then similarly when we actually go
to define the tags we can do the same
thing there and what we could do if we
wanted to is actually just set these
based on some stuff that we sort of
prefabricated Lea made so we don't have
to copy them either they could just be
in the tag array so we could say like
hey first tag index one passed last tag
index like that and then what we could
do is just go oh so when we set one of
these we overwrite the tag array so the
HHA asset first tag index equals the
grid tags first tag index like so and
off we go
so yeah
keep going here
what is the Kush you got this is set
type ID that's an ampersand oh no it's
not
and then I'll we really would need here
is to actually assign some of these
right so when we do our update asset
package from ping now again same same
deal we can just pass in the the tag
array that we expect to use like so and
[Music]
what we need now is something to pass
here right and that's really what we're
gonna do next weekend I think right I
would just say
that we're gonna pass that and that
would be it right and what we want to do
here eventually is just say like alright
we want to actually set these tags to
something useful so let's suppose we
were going to do it and so in that case
we would say all right the tags are
gonna be the type a ID is asset and the
first tag index equals something here
and the one passed last tag index equals
and new it let me just go ahead and grab
this out here
so the type ID equals asset hand one
pass the first tag index and the one
pass last tag index right these we need
to set to some tags that actually mean
something and so what we would want to
do here is when we're doing this import
grid we only want to do the first row
everything else we want to be zeroed out
right and so we could actually check for
that zero out a little bit earlier on to
so what I want to do here is say all
right the X index had better be zero and
we won't be just at the moment we won't
do anything for the other ones right and
when we go down here we'll use the Y
index to determine which tag we should
or should not be now going back up here
I feel like that gives us a way to knock
these out where we should skip ones that
aren't allowed and so what I'll do is
I'll say if the mean equals the max when
we come down here I want to make sure
that the grid tags type ID is actually
valid and if it's not then I want to
error out I want to say get map found in
or maybe sprite fan sprite found in tile
that doesn't have or found in what is
required to be a blank tile right
so we're just saying hey we saw
something but it's not in a place that
there should be anything because we
don't understand how to interpret
something being there in the sprite
sheet so that's an error right then what
I can do is I can say oh hey
yeah as far as the tag stuff is
concerned then what I'm going to do is
I'm just going to temporarily and I
think again I said this will probably I
want to have tags here that are like
just the four directional tags and we'll
just stick those in there so like der
tag for right so I'm gonna say is the
first tag index is just the the four
it's gonna be the four directional tags
in you know you know in a ring or
whatever and I'm only gonna do it for
things where the Y index is less than
four right so that's the entirety of it
and why
there we go that's the entirety of it
and all we would need for this to work
is in fact we can just do this is inside
the when we actually create what we're
creating I can at the end of this just
reserved some tags for those basic types
so when we come in here I can just say
like okay right so I can go through each
of these I can say that the dirt tag
index in question is going to be
reserved tags one tag so that gets me
back that particular tag and then I can
set that tag
I can set that tag to be the direction
tag that I wanted it to be so inside HHA
and and I guess I don't really remember
what these are set to if they're zero to
one or what they were so we'll have to
take a look at that it's been a long
time
and so in here we'll just do ID and
value right so the ID of this particular
tag is the HS a direction or sorry the
tag direction facing direction and the
value of the tag is would just be Tao 32
and we would go up to the the value of
tau 32 the portion of tau 32 for each of
the steps in the angle right so we would
do F 32 der tag index times tau 32 right
so we just like facing directions
winding around the circle so that
actually gives us now actual tags to
reserve their this and this stuff has to
actually be placed kind of more up where
it can start to be accessed by anyone in
the asset system so there we go and and
so now we should actually have labels
and they and on the hand sprites and
they should actually be you should
actually be able to find them what that
also means is that in theory anyway we
could add a part of the hero now that
referenced one of them and it should
work so for example here where we do
asset glove and we put asset sword in
here
we could instead put asset hand in here
right and that should now be able to
find it it won't actually find it in
this case because the
because we didn't import the things with
the type IDs yet and I believe this
asset count will be missing the assets
we imported right yeah it will because
those assets that we imported have did
not actually have types assigned to them
which we have to fix now so now we
should be able to test the entire
process what I can do is delete this
local that HHA file right use hej edit
to create a bear one and in theory now
when we actually run the import those
things that get imported should be
tagged with actual information now don't
quote me on that because that welp there
yep there it is right um so it actually
was however it looks like we've got our
it looks like we have our our our
jeebies reversed there so I think we're
not doing the RGB flip because it looks
like we store our handmade hair assets
in in the opposite order in RGB order
right but it all worked right so those
are now loaded on the fly and integrated
in I mean surprising right but it works
now we probably aren't quite done yet
right because on reload like if we
didn't get all that stuff right on
reload it won't work so we probably
aren't really out of the woods yet right
yeah right you can see like these assets
aren't probably getting loaded so we
didn't correctly rewrite the counts in
the file or something right so that's
our job for next week but we're almost
there so I'm gonna go ahead and delete
that and if the HHA isn't there we
should still run properly like when I
run the file here it shouldn't do
anything right because it's it doesn't
find that extra file so we basically did
it
we now have asset reloading in place
we'll be able to refine it over the next
few weeks and we'll put all our assets
in and have a little party so there you
go
I've been looking into existing
approaches to assign items to cells for
clustered shading okay that sounds like
that's pretty off-topic but okay it's
game development
I've already implemented two of them but
now I'd like to try an ID based approach
they mentioned in their SIGGRAPH slides
an item shape can be an OB b or a
frustum and they test its planes against
the cells and clip space since a cell
will simply be an ABB there I should
really improve my math novice skills but
I currently don't know how to do this
can you point me in the right direction
so I guess what I'd say is if your
question is just what is an ABB and clip
space mean we actually did this in
handmade hero so if you remember when we
do the projection so when we do the
perspective transform stuff remember we
make the matrix and we have a projection
matrix that is what's you know makes
perspective foreshortening work so what
happens with that is is when you have
not when you have done your matrix
multiply to put your objects into two
two two when you've done your matrix
multiply you you have your matrix which
includes the projection part it's going
to put the amount of perspective divided
that should happen into the W coordinate
of the resulting vector right so a
vector comes in with the W coordinate
usually the W coordinate is one it goes
out with the W coordinate that's
actually a value that will get
everything will get divided by that
value right well when you do that
transform that multiplication you're now
have one additional space once you've
divided by W right
you have made everything perspective
foreshorten that's what the / w does but
before you've done the / w you actually
have another space that you've
transformed things into so if you go and
look hopefully there's an article about
this summer I'm just kind of hoping here
we go oh man that's not so I mean this
isn't what I was hoping for like maybe
some a little bit more than that but
okay um so that was useless let me try
explaining something again and I'll use
the whiteboard this time I was kind of
hoping for some diagrams there but
doesn't look that's gonna happen all
right so hmm
suppose it I take a look at what's gonna
happen to all of my coordinates
throughout the 3d pipeline right and
again this happens in handmade heroes so
this is not something that's like just
only for high-end 3d or anything it
happened it's everywhere anytime you
have anything 3d at all you're doing
this so we have a matrix right and we
know that there's a 3x3 upper component
of the matrix that's the rotation and it
also has scaling and so on rotation
scale and shear all happens up in here
right then we know we sort of have
nothing in the rest of the 4x4 if all
we're doing is manipulating an object
with rotations and scaling right if we
want to add translation then we end up
with a vector here where this becomes
the txt ytz right
that moves things around and remember in
hammy here we went over why all this is
true as well so don't just think this
way actually go learn this if you don't
or if you didn't watch a meteor I
explained how this matrix actually does
its job as well okay but then we also
have additional elements down here that
can be used for perspective projection
why can these be used for perspective
projection well when a vector comes in
it comes in as X Y Z W usually W is set
to one it can also be set for 0 if this
thing is just a direction and doesn't
want to have movement applied to it
right but it's usually set to one so
what ends up happening is this bottom a
row can move things into the W
coordinate based on things like the Z
coordinate for example if I put a 1 here
and a 0 here all of a sudden what I've
done is when this matrix multiplied
happens the W coordinate will end up
equaling Z right and if I then
furthermore create more sophisticated
things in here I can move Z with an
offset in there I can move Z with other
things right I can do whatever I want so
I will end up creating a vector that has
a transformed x y&amp;z the way that I want
to for my world coordinates of my Z
buffer and all these other things and
then a W that's proportional to Z
somehow and it depends on how I'm trying
to build my matrix but I'm gonna have
time proportional to Z somehow right so
when I do this matrix multiply if this
right here is my entire transformed
matrix M right and this up here is my
input point P and this here is my output
point P prime you know I've got P prime
equals matrix times P right that's what
I'm doing this action right here this
very simple equation doing that well
this is my input space it's where I'm
storing my points this is the transform
that includes the camera transform
possibly the world space transform to
move the object somewhere as well right
and the perspective projection that
perspective projection means that this
right p prime is now in sort of a
perspective
space now it hasn't actually had
perspective applied yet why because we
have not / w remember your similar
triangles again we went over all this
I'm handmade hero remember your similar
triangles here is the screen here is
some point in the world we are
projecting that point down onto the
screen those similar triangles here this
right triangle this right triangle here
that divided that perspective divided is
what's giving us the foreshortening so
things that are further away project on
to smaller spaces on the screen right
this is much bigger than this but it
protects to the same point another point
out here that's actually higher than
this point
projects to a point that's lower on the
screen than this point right that's what
gives us that shrinking effect as it
moves away that's what makes the
perspective projection a perspective
projection and not an orthographic one
so when we do this we have a new space
that we've created it's not yet screen
space because we haven't / W we haven't
actually projected we're just in sort of
a new space that's ready for projection
and that's what we call clip coordinates
now why do we call them clip coordinates
we call them clip coordinates because if
you were to divide by W before clipping
everything blows up why sometimes W may
be very close to zero what happens when
something is like right next to the eye
right it's unstable so we must clip out
everything on the nearside of the near
clip plane before dividing by W or all
hell will break loose numerically so
these are called clip coordinates
because we clip in them now because we
have done a bunch of work to put these
things in to clip coordinates and we've
multiplied and divided and we've
multiplied all of the components to
shift them into the camera space in
ba-ba-ba-ba right there are operations
that you may wish to do here
that are easier done in the clip space
than in other spaces now why is that
well it's because all of our coordinates
have been scaled around and modified by
this matrix to fit into the region we're
going to view so clip space is basically
the view frustum we've mapped everything
into a unit cube inside the view frustum
and we've made sure all of our
coordinates have been multiplied
stretched warped compressed pulled back
moved slid so that the things we
actually want to view fall into a very
specific space right in between the near
and the far clip planes and if we looked
at this sort of projection sort of
head-on so here's the eye and we're sort
of looking down at it we've made it so
that things fall between 0 and 1 in x
and y as well so what happens when we
make everything be between negative 1
and 1 or 0 &amp; 1 depending on how you're
set up your transform let's say negative
1 to 1 in all cases right well if
everything we're going to be able to see
falls between negative 1 and 1 in X Y &amp;
Z because we've stretched pulled and
squish them all in there and then what
we're about to do is divide by W to make
everything build like that right well
instead of doing this before the
transform where everything's in world
space and it's all confusing and weird
like you know angled planes and instead
of doing it after when we've divided by
W and everything has gone back to all
wacky planes right why not start doing
some operations in clip space where any
individual cell is a regular rectangular
tile so if I want to once I've done that
transform I've a sect effectively taken
this clip space and I've turned it into
just a rectangle because I already
stretched everything out and warped it
so that it fits
- this unit just right you and I'm Sam
so if you look at what's actually
happening here in terms of the math
that's not what I wanted so here's that
perspective projection right and what
you can see here right is that we've got
the the forward projection matrix here
and you can kind of see that the action
that's going to be taken when we the
action that's gonna be taken when we
actually you know pull these things
through you can see that we actually
even do work to prep the Z coordinate so
that it falls between negative one and
one right and then the same thing
happens to all of our x coordinates
right so what we what we do with all of
them is we make sure that all of them
are are corrected by like the aspect
ratio and the focal length of our lens
right so that they all get squished
properly so once we do this transform
we've preconditioned all of our
coordinates for clipping so what people
are seeing when they say do this in clip
space what they're trying to say is the
particular operations they want to do
can just be most efficiently handled
right after you do that transform but
before you actually turn things into
device coordinates by like dividing by W
and stretching to the screen size stuff
like that does that help
is the warning and the C timecode
supposed to be taken lightly no it is
not supposed to be taken lightly you're
just supposed to say that I absolutely
do not warrant that it has been tested
or debugged so it's entirely you know
your problem if something wrong happens
you should inspect it and see if you
believe that it will work the way that
you're using it and if you are confident
that it does you can go ahead and do so
at your own risk if you are not you
shouldn't use it I see that transient
state doesn't leave for tasks with
memory and game uses much more thread so
the threads may sit there without work
because you can only submit at most for
such tasks for frame two q isn't for
test a bit low or am I missing something
here yes so what you may be missing
there is that tasked with memory are
very special we don't actually use those
for very many things they're usually
used for stuff like background loading
that doesn't really require and we don't
really want many threads working on so
actually we spin up a lot more work that
doesn't use memory in that way you can
actually see this happening if you look
inside the profiler so for example
inside here if you look at the thread
view you can see that we actually have a
lot more than four threads running at a
time anyways right so one two three four
five six seven here are running and
doing with lighting calculations so we
typically want lots of threads available
for doing work we don't necessarily want
a lot of Fred's threads doing work and
using memory
sliggoo meaning TV thanks for answering
the way I understand their slides they
have a convex shape defined by its
boundary planes either a six plane OB b
or a five plane frustum and they test it
against an a BB in clip space the a a BB
is already in clip space and the planes
come from world space I have no idea how
to test for intersection in clip space
what even happens to the planes when
they are transformed well I'd have to
think if there's any shortcuts for doing
I mean I don't really know exactly what
they're doing since I don't know what
you're referring to but if you want to
transform a plane you can transform a
plane just the same way that you would
transform anything else right so a plane
fundamentally speaking is can be defined
for example by a point and a normal you
could then transform the point and the
normal into clip space and that would be
the correct plane right so the problem
that you will have is that there's
there's nuance involved in transforming
things like normals by matrices that are
non orthogonal so inverse transpose is
actually the matrix that transforms
normals so if you just want the simple
solution probably the easiest way to do
it if you didn't want to go learn the
math is take three points on the plane
transform the three points and
reconstruct the plane because that's
fool proof points always transform
properly through the projection matrix
you don't have to know any math to do
that
you can just put them through it then
take those three points subtract them
and generate the normal and then you've
got the plane right so I could go into a
lot of other math about how you could do
this more efficiently but that's a
pretty basic way you could do it
and depending on how much more math you
want to go into you can do things that
are better than that right but the most
straightforward way is to realize that
since you already hopefully understand
how to transform a point through the
projection matrix you can always turn a
plane into three points transform them
and turn it back right so it's pretty
straightforward to lean on that and then
you don't have to you don't have to
worry about the other math minutiae if
that makes sense hopefully it does
I mean in case that part wasn't clear
you know so a plane let's say that you
know you could transform a point but you
don't know how to transform a plane
right you just you don't know and you
don't want to think about it right well
a plane
he is just three points right for any
plane in the world I can just take three
points on that plane and now I have
points to finding the plane right so if
I transform those three points through
some matrix I'll get three other points
that are the new transform points I can
now reconstruct the plane by just taking
the cross product of the two legs of the
plane right so if here's P 1 here's P 2
and here's p zero right p 1 minus p 0
cross p 2 minus p 0 right
he isn't normal for the plane makes
sense it's not really the normal it's
hard to say the normal for the plane
it's the tangent to the plane you don't
care if it's normalized right so it's
the tangent to the plane there and now
you know a point on the plane plus the
normal that's enough to test right
that's the entirety of the information
right because if you want to get back to
ax plus B y plus cz Plus D equals zero
which is the equation for a plane well a
B and C are this right they are n x and
y and z they're the tangent to the plane
and the D value can always be found by
simply taking the dot product of a point
on the plane which you have p0 right the
dot product of that with a tangent to
the plane equals your D value so you can
always reconstruct from three points a
plane
all right looks like we're done I'm
gonna close down
all right thank you for joining me for
an upset a handmade here it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along the
series at home you can always do so by
pro to the game on handmade hero org it
comes with a source code so you can play
around with it and do your own
experiments we also have a watch page
you can use to watch the series it
actually has some hot links on the
bottom for things like joining the
mailing list or exploring the forums or
any of that stuff and if you want to
view any of our other Molly Rocket stuff
you can always click on the little
handmade hero head and there's links to
all the rest of our sites there we also
have the handmade fun which is a place
you can go to contribute to community
projects such as the drawing program I
was just using we would like to start
contributing more stuff to those so if
you want to donate to the community fund
we will find new places to send that
money to right now we're funding
handmade network and the annotated
episode guide which is a pretty cool
thing can use to search through old
episodes of handmade hero that's also on
the watch page so check those things out
if you haven't already I'll be back here
next week we're only doing one episode
because I'll be off one of the days but
we will start next weekend actually
pulling in art assets and trying to
assign them to things in the world using
the sort of reloading system that we've
made now so that should be fun and we
can debug all the stuff that we created
these past couple weeks it seems like
the PNG load is working fabulously but
that all the stuff we put in for the
updating the hhas you know that probably
could use some work so we'll be doing
that and we'll go from there so thanks
for joining me see you here next week
until then have fun programming and I'll
catch you around the Internet take it as
everybody