hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we are doing some Katy
tree stuff and this is really just
because we want to make sure our
lighting runs as fast as possible and I
had also some ideas for that it's like
we're booting here for the first time I
had some ideas for that and I kind of
wanted to try some stuff that I thought
about in terms of reducing the variance
in our in our code currently like in our
lighting solution because it looks
pretty good but it's got a little
flicker to it which I don't actually
mind as a effect but I kind of wanted to
know to what extent we could make it
more solid and I had a really good idea
about how I think we could do that and
so in terms of looking at our lighting
again like I wanna I have an idea I want
to try for that I think I just want to
keep on the Katy tree thing this weekend
just because we had started last week
and I'd like to finish it so I think
we're gonna do today is is just take a
look at implementing that KD tree loop
that we sketched out and then from there
probably that'll take us all weekend
unfortunately and then from there what
I'd like to do is probably next weekend
try a little bit of the thing that I was
thinking of before we start optimizing
the KD stuff because I before I forget
what I wanted to try I wanted to you
know to put it in a little bit of of an
experiment there where we we take a look
at what we can do with in terms of
reducing the lighting variance that we
get from our lighting so I'm gonna take
a look at that and see what happens and
we'll go from there so we have our
routine sketched out from last time
where we had our ray cast and we were
sort of talking about how are we gonna
do a KD tree traversal here that's more
direct and like less about just sort of
shoehorning it in when we put it in
originally we just kind of shoehorned it
in and this is the original
here that's the one that's running right
now and then now we've got this sort of
other one here that we sketched out
that's like okay this is how we think
the Katie tree might run and it's kind
of confusing because there's a lot of
ways we could structure this and it's
unclear really so we kind of I think
just have to like implement one and then
sort of like push forward on it because
I don't know that there's any way to
really like into it up front exactly how
this should work so if you take a look
at how this is going what you can see
here is it's we're expecting to do
something where we pull something off a
stack we look to see whether or not we
need to test it for collisions if we do
then we loop through and actually test
it for real collisions of the Ray with
our boxes and that's just a loop through
all of the child leaves right then after
we're done checking all the child leaves
then we hunt back up the stack to see if
we can find any buddy who we haven't
processed yet that still needs to be
processed and the reason that I say
still needs to be processed is because
when we find an actual collision with a
box which we're doing inside this leaf
testing here as we look at the sides of
that we've pushed on the stack that we
haven't tested yet we know that if we've
already found a hit on our array that's
closer than the closest box could be
because of the plane division in the KD
tree then we know that we don't actually
have to do that test right we don't have
to walk down that side of that tree
so this n side bit here is sort of the
early out that says look if this is not
true meaning if at least one ray is not
on the other side of the KD tree
separating plane that we're looking at
then we don't have to continue you know
I'm saying
now we do have a bunch of issues we have
to work out here because we have to make
the math work out right and we'll talk
about that in a little bit but that's
basically what we're talking about and
what you can see here is the other side
of things where we're not doing a leaf
container so again this is just what
happens when we're when we've bottomed
out when we've gotten all the way to the
bottom of the KD tree and we are testing
the actual boxes that are contained in
the node and then we're walking back up
the tree to see where we should start
descending next right so that's what
that's what this branch does this branch
is when we were what we're in the put
thing we pulled off the stack and it's
not really off the stack because we we
like I said we changed the sort of
recursive pulling off of the deb stack
to being something we only do when we
finish with the leaf because we know
we're just going to send down all the
way to the bottom when i'm not explained
as well we know that we need to go all
the way to the closest thing in the KD
tree first and then we want the next
closest thing in the next such thing in
the next thing so when we descend which
is this side here because this is what
happens we know him to leave container
we don't push but the the things on the
stack here that we're going to test
immediately instead we just take them as
our next stack value to use so we just
take it immediately
the only time we start pulling things
off the stack is when we've bottomed out
cuz now we can't go down any more so now
we just pull something out a second to
figure out okay who should we test who's
like above us right and so that's what
this part does here now I think
I haven't thought about it too hard but
in theory because we know what side we
always know how to classify ourselves
relative to one side or another of a KD
tree in theory we could also do this
traversal stackless li because and and
we may want to because if we know that
we can always just do a piece of math
that's relatively straightforward like
maybe it's actually fairly quick to do
we could actually get out of the
branching altogether for putting things
onto the stack in the first place now I
don't actually know that we're ever
gonna have to worry about that because
with this new tree structure we could
conditional move these on there and
because we're no longer pulling things
off of the stack immediately anymore
those C moves might actually just work
now I don't know that that's actually
true but I think it probably will be and
this right here where we take the curse
tack value that's gonna be used next
time that's actually the one that's
gonna cost us the most I think because
it the next loop is gonna be completely
dependent on that finishing either way
so the fact that it doesn't come out of
a stack doesn't really matter that's
gonna be this as a conditional move or a
conditional is really gonna be the part
that we probably stall on either way but
ignoring all of that like I said this
part here can probably just be two
conditional moves now because we don't
meet we won't be looking at it for a
long long time so those C moves can
probably just happen and they probably
won't cost us much because nobody's
dependent on them at all the next time
anyone could even think about looking at
them would be after going through this
entire loop and testing at least a few
boxes and then getting in here and
starting to pull things off the sack
right so because there's so many
intervening instructions here you know
that you're not going to line up people
see really dependent on this thing until
after it's probably a completely known
quantity would be my guess I could be
wrong about that
so I don't think there's gonna be much
of an issue there but I could again
could totally be wrong but that's the
basic sketch and so if you look at the
things we need to actually do I think
one of them is just correct already like
I uh or we will scrutinize a little bit
but I think one of them is just correct
already basically and the others the
other one is the one that we actually
have to probably do a little bit of
engineering on because I don't think
it's quite right so if we take a look at
what goes on here when we're actually
processing a node in the KD tree that is
not a leaf so it's an interior node of
the tree and divides the boxes we have
into two halves one that are on one side
of the split plane and one that's on the
other side of the split plane the thing
that we need to do first and the slowest
part that we have like I said I don't
really know if maybe there's smarter
ways for us to do this but the slowest
part that we have is this part here now
one thing that I'm not sure about in
fact I think we could do this much more
efficiently than we're doing it here and
actually we probably just should so if
you look at what has to happen here
you can see that we're effectively doing
like masking operations and I think we
probably don't need to do those here
like the reason we're doing this so you
can imagine this side where we're
talking about the Ray direction there
are four different ray directions that
are you know slightly different and
that's because we're casting for rays at
a time right and if you look at what's
going on here we need to produce a XY or
z value from these Ray directions so we
need to select just those components out
by using the masks here to produce a
vector that's just the X's just the Y's
or just the Z's of our directions right
and since we don't know which one it is
we're doing it this way right now
there's other ways we could do
like we could do that as a load and in
fact yeah the more I think about it is
why aren't we just doing that as a load
so I think this code is dumb and before
we go any further I'm just gonna replace
it with something that I think might not
be as dumb don't quote me on that fact
because it may still be as dumb but yeah
I'm just gonna go ahead and say that I
think that's probably a little bit dumb
the reason I think that's a little bit
dumb is if we take a look at the v3 4x
struct here so I'm just gonna look up
the actual structure what you can see
about how this is actually created is
it's just X is wise and Z's anyway and
here's the III element access or so we
can we know that they're sequential in
memory so I'm gonna say like can't we
just do 128 bit load with an index and
we know that index is low can't we just
do that and not have this problem so
meaning instead of this if we actually
just do if we actually just do this as a
load of the Ray Origin using an index I
mean can't we just do this
so if we just take the dimension index
of this box like or like you know the K
dimension index like the thing we split
or payme what's called a KD index the
thing we actually split upon we
shouldn't actually have to do those
masks because we can just do one 128-bit
load of the value and it's since we're
loading that those three values from
that cache line they'll all be packed
together we should hit the cache line
every time it should be in l1 cache hit
and we should just be able to do a load
directly so I don't think we need to be
doing sequences of operations to do the
masks because I don't think there's any
reason we can't just load it directly
out so similarly a like here where we do
this I think we can just loops I think
we can just load that and I don't think
we will pay a penalty for it now this
wants to be done slightly differently
instead of actually doing the Ray Origin
part here what we want to do again is
just do both loads and then the ad right
so we want to do we want to load the the
start and the end and then when we do
our hit P we want to just add those
together by doing the the add of just
the components right so I don't really
know why we did it the other way round
it's way more expensive to do it that
way and probably we were just not
thinking about that part yet we were
just kind of sketching things out but
now that I'm like looking at it more
closely like that seems more stainer to
me right so this is like start D and end
D right and then the place where this
thing would would end like the place
where this Ray would actually end is now
just going to be if you
did a hit the hit P it's just gonna be
the start plus the the end D right and
and this is actually sorry this is
should say dirty right so this is the
Ray direction so all we're doing is
instead of actually computing the actual
end point we're just computing one
dimension of the endpoint because we
know that the split plane is
dimensionally aligned so we don't have
to test y&amp;z we can just test X if it's
an excellent plane we don't have to test
X and Z if it's a wise LaPlante right so
start D and dirty here right we combine
those two together and we end up this
tier a value here can just this is now
just a scalar multiply and we end up
with whatever the hit P is for this
particular dimension and then what we
can do is say well whatever the whatever
the actual plane D value was here again
we can subtract that out as well and
then we can do our test on it so to do
that like in here we could probably just
add that in so if we want to we can just
do something like this right and then we
can just see whatever the the hit P or
the I should say this this is the end P
right and maybe we call it nd that makes
more sense so here we can just do a move
mask out and take a look at what the end
sign bit is and then we know and the
reason that this is not quite right as I
said is because we don't know which side
we're looking at here so there is a
little bit of an issue this we could
take this value the plane D value we
could try to figure out something to do
there and it's possible that we could do
that on the push side of things so you
know we this that's the this is the one
part we've got to figure out is how are
we how are we making this end sign bit
thing work right so we could imagine
having some piece of information here
that tells us I don't know
but this ensign bit when the move mask
comes out what we're gonna end up with
is we're gonna end up with a mask like
it's gonna be you know zero one one zero
or something and it's going to be ones
in the place where it was on the
positive side of the plane so for each
lane for each of the four lanes gonna
have once the Paz side zeroes on the
negative side but the question is which
one do we want right so if it's all if
it's a mix if it's zeros and ones mixed
together then we always need to do it
because that means somebody at least one
of the Rays actually doesn't early-out
but the thing we have to know is if it's
all ones or all zeros we don't know
whether we do or don't do it right so
the thing we have to disambiguate is if
we pushed on the close the positive side
right because we're gonna descend down
one side negative side positive side
we're gonna push the opposite side but
we don't know which side we pushed right
so what we're gonna have to do in the
start side code so here where we push
these on we're gonna need to push on a
value that tells us something right some
piece of information that we can use so
that we know which way to test this
thing right and that's the tricky bit
now there's two ways to do it one way is
to always do the test the same way and
to add a multiplier in here so for
example if we pushed on a one or a
negative one we could load out of the
stack the one or the negative one there
and then we would multiply this result
and D by the one or negative one and off
we would go right now that doesn't seem
like a very good idea to me because it
requires us pushing probably more
information on stack than we need
because I
to store it one or a negative one we
just we only need one bit right so we
should be able to stick that bit value
into our stack in a way that's more
convenient so that our stack can still
be just 32 bits wide and not have to
store entire floating point values for
no reason right so I'm assuming that we
probably want to do something smarter
than this and like I said I don't
actually know that that's true
but I'm assuming so what I want to do is
think for a minute about what we would
store and maybe I'll go to the black
board for this which I have to like
reload because since we did a separate
stream I had had a separate black bird
up here so I didn't actually need it
because I had enough diagrams last night
when I was talking about graphic novel
pre-press but so let me try and open
here a Milton canvas and I don't even
know where this thing is but I think
it's an archive here does this look
right
this does not this looks like I don't
know where this is
come on second this looks like not
recent day 420 all right um TAFE for 33
like this doesn't look recent this looks
like it's off somehow
TAFE 469 I don't know what that just did
accidentally drew into it so wait that's
where the Milton canvas was I thought so
where what's the deal all right
maybe our canvas has gotten destroyed I
have no idea what happened I tried to
switch last night and I did not
understand what occurred at all it was
very unintuitive
I feel like probably there should be a
different way that this works because I
don't understand what it means to save a
milton canvas like when I closed it like
when I closed it I don't know what it
does you know what I mean like I don't
know where it saves it to so I'm not
sure what's going on here exactly so
we're just gonna go up to the top of
this canvas which may or may not have
ever been saved and honestly I wonder if
that means this whole time it hasn't
ever been saving our canvas it like
saved it to some temporary file that we
don't even know about or something like
this which could be the case I don't
know I really just don't know I have no
idea how Milton works at all in fact
maybe we'll just create a new canvas
because I just don't even know what that
means
all right doesn't look like I can do
that because it resets all my settings
I really just don't know I don't
understand I think there probably should
be some like thought put into how that
system works cuz it doesn't really make
any sense to me alright so let's move
over here a bit and we'll just start
again that kind of sucks as that's the
case because I've thought that I've
always included the canvas the Milton
canvas with the distribution it gets
packed up in there but I guess if that's
the case then I haven't been since like
day 4 33 because it just hasn't been
saving it I guess it just saves it to
some temp file that I don't know about
and I have to manually tell it to save
it or something I don't know I'm super
confused right now if anyone understands
Milton at all and wants to tell me I'm
happy to to try and fix it I guess but
also you know it's realized we don't
have our little overlay on either Dewey
but this all days have been a bit of a
disaster here we are five I don't
remember what we are either 595 okay so
yeah I don't know if the milton canvas
has been destroyed it may have been
that's okay my handwriting is so bad no
one's ever going to be able to read it
but the point is let me explain what I'm
talking about here in terms of side bit
masks so what's going to happen is we've
got a KD tree split plane here and we've
got array and it's on some side and it
goes in some direction and what we're
gonna do is we're gonna produce another
point and remember we're doing this for
wide so there's actually like it's more
like this is happening and so we're
gonna produce four points and some of
those points are gonna be on one side
and some of those points are gonna be on
the other side now in a particular
direction let's say we're using the
x-axis here there's the negative side
and the positive side relative to the
plane and since we subtract away the
plane D value which is this we're going
to have negatives for every one on this
side and positives for around this side
we're then going to do a move mask to
move out of the vector registers just
the sign bit of those four four
floating-point values and we're putting
those into a general purpose register
that's gonna leave us with one of
sixteen possible combinations right like
1 0 0 1 or 1 0 1 1 or 0 1 0 1 right and
these correspond to the signs of like
basically which side these are on so
anyone who is on the positive side is
gonna get a 0 and anyone who's on the
negative side is gonna get a 1 I believe
we can double check that
but I think it moves the sign bit and I
think the sign bit is positive if it's
not it's is one if it's negative and
zero if it's not if that makes sense
um but either way we can obviously
verify that so we're on about this
matter point being we know that we're
going to have a bit value in here that
corresponds to which side of the plane
it's on problem is we don't know which
side we want to actually measure we know
that in the place where we actually
determined which side the start was on
that as we descended the KD tree we did
push one side or the other so we know
which side we want it to be so what we
need to do is when we do the push we
need to record something that tells us
which one we were going to do right if
that makes sense and in order to push
which one of these we're going to do we
need something that will go from this to
like a yes or no value right that's
whether we need to descend so what we're
trying to do is determine whether any of
the rays are on the far side of the
plane so in other words there is going
to be a and that's your answer right
there so as I'm singing it out loud I
realizes that what the answer is the
answer is it's just equals is what we
need what we need to push on is one one
one one or zero zero zero zero and all
we need to do is say if it equals one of
these or I should say not equals one of
these so if it's not equal to the
pattern that we push then we have to use
it so that's actually what we're going
to do yes yes
oh my god everything is so tangled I
hate having to have a streaming setup
it's the worst there's so many cords
it's a disaster there's like 12 pairs of
headphones never stream folks it was
gonna be so nice when I don't have to
stream anymore okay it's like such a
disaster if you have OCD you can't
stream like basically that's that's the
thing you should know okay um so anyway
if you take a look at what's going on on
here that should priestly give us what
we need to know we're gonna have to say
look in any case if there's anything
other than exactly the one pattern that
says we've early outed then we're gonna
have to continue so this is basically a
not equal to some stack match pattern
so this curse tack value thing that
comes out here is actually going to be
sort of a calm composite and so we're
going to want to to do something like
this where we do the stack push the
curse stacked value here this u16 that
is actually the correct thing but the
stack itself is not going to be a u16 so
what's going to happen here is when we
record this curse deck by we push the
box stack on here what we're gonna do is
when we push this on this will push a
32-bit value that's properly encoded
because we actually did look out the
sides and then on here when we pull it
off we're actually gonna get a like
stack value or a stack a packed packed
stacked value here and then the curse
stacked value is going to be the packed
stacked value probably and it off and
then the the stack match pattern right
or the the are the plane test pattern
maybe let's call call it that is just
gonna be masked off of there right so
the plane test pattern in this case is
going to be whatever the cursed stack
value is and it's going to be shifted
down by the sixteen bits so we're gonna
like slide it over right now there's two
ways we could do this and I'm thinking
that maybe this is the wrong way so I'm
thinking maybe what we
since we know we always have four match
values we're gonna go ahead and slide
those this down and then we're gonna end
this with oxf to get those out so I
think that's probably more what we're
going to do right so we're going to do a
thing that looks something like this
oops and then the plane test pattern
gives us exactly what we need to know so
that's it now I want to say that's
actually the entire code actually we now
no longer need this so that's gone so
really the only thing we need to store
in the lighting boxes to support the KD
tree is we need the plane D value and
the KD index right
something like this so there's which
dimension we're using we would load that
out there's the plane D value which we
need to load out and then I guess
there's the two sides and that's it so
if we take a look at the lighting box
structure which is that if you take a
look at how that's used really what
we're talking about here is just this
top part would get fussed with right and
that's if we want to store them in line
which I don't know that we need to do
anymore
so I think we can probably get out of
that business entirely and just store
this exactly so in the lighting code
where we actually create the tables and
all that garbage I think what we can
probably do here is say let's just have
a table that we're going to use that has
all of the that halls has all of the KD
tree stuff in it that's what I think we
would want to do now the tricky part
here is that if we actually want to do
that we we do have the problem of
looking up into two separate arrays and
so looking at the light box which is
here we have that problem that this pack
structure right is the thing that tells
us that piece of information so I'm
going to go ahead and say that probably
we want to figure out a way to do this
loop without without checking that
so I'm guessing what we want here is to
put the leaf container flag into
something saner so I'm going to go ahead
and say something like
this and I realize I don't really know
what I'm doing exactly here but let's
say that we have is leaf container and
it's a separate thing so we just know
what it is when we are going through
here and picking things off of the stack
it probably is fine for us just to use
one additional bit for that right and so
for example like maybe it's something
more like this so whenever we push
something on the stack we actually know
which one it is or something and so we
can actually just find out what is leaf
container should be by shifting it and
masking it off right now because this
leaf container is just gonna be used as
a boolean I'm gonna go ahead and say we
probably don't even have to do that we
don't need it to be zero or one it can
just be nonzero and it will be fine so I
think if we do this that's the entire
decode and we no longer need to actually
have his leaf container encoded in here
anymore
so that would go away so like for
example
so we don't want to remove it yet
because I still want to be able to test
against the old version of these
routines so I'm not gonna vape that code
out and put like you know the new path
in yet as mandatory so we're gonna we're
not going to do that right so yeah just
to keep that in mind what I do want to
do however is we have to think a little
bit harder about how we're gonna run
these tests now is this how we are
typically running this I think yeah so
we do need to think a little bit harder
about how we're gonna run these tests
now though because I need somewhere to
put the KT box information and we need
that to be something that the Lightning
code can actually work with I think what
I'm going to do for now again is just
sort of take advantage of some facts
here that we know we can use so if I
were to Union this in here like so and
I'm I'm only doing this so we can still
flat load the structure from our old
data files that's all I'm doing because
I want to keep that load in place all
I'm doing here is just saying look we
had this before overlaid on top of it
because we don't need that anymore we're
never touching it and aren't going to
use it I'm just gonna lay in the actual
thing we need here which is the tree
Katie tree count and like Katie tree
node right something like this
and so what we'll do is we'll figure out
how many of these we might have
maximally we'll have an array there that
we can use as scratch base so we just
build them in there and then off we go
and then we can have like literally a KD
tree node here for lighting that we can
use and that KD tree node will just
literally only have exactly the things
that we need here so it needs the plane
D it needs a u8 for the KD index and
then it needs the two sides right so it
needs basically this now I don't know
that it needs anything else and as far
as I can tell this KD index is probably
not actually something we can store as a
u8 because I mean yeah there's just a
bunch of extra padding there so it
probably looks more like that yeah the
good news is if I'm reading that right
this is actually like 4 by 4 or 16 bytes
right so in other words we've got to you
32s for the side so that's 2 we've got a
plain D which is an F 32 so that's 3 and
then we've got 16 8 8 which is another
32 bits so that's four 32-bit values or
4 4 byte values or 16 bytes total that
means 4 per cache line which is a nice
compact structure so again the reason
that I would just point out that I kind
of like that better is because if you
take a look at how much memory traffic
we were going to have to have when we
were using the lighting box structures
well if you look back at the lighting
box structures how many things are in
there you can see that there's a 32-bit
value here in the lighting box pack so
that's 4 bytes but then we have 3 ty
three times four so that's to write out
the entire equation right we've got
three VIII's which are three four byte
values plus one four byte value or 40
bytes per right which I believe is how
big this is
so 16 per node is a lot better than 40
per node for obvious reasons it's more
than twice as large if it's at 40 so in
terms of the total amount of stuff we're
moving through the routine if there were
any cash issues we were having this
would definitely have helped them now
again we're doing this to do less ops
here as well so we haven't really
measured the cash effects we're just
trying to simplify the ops we're
actually doing for what we have before
we start optimizing so unfortunately
we're not going to necessarily know how
much the cash affected us here because
we're also going to be doing less ops
right so sometimes you can't yeah I mean
it's hard to really know exactly how
good that would be we could try to look
at some cache performance counter values
but again because we're changing the ops
at the same time I'm not sure to what
extent we could really make a firm
statement about that because you know
who knows what'll happen we don't even
know who's gonna be faster it could be
slower right so what we want to do here
is say okay when we're getting this
stuff out we actually don't grab the box
early on in fact what we're mostly going
to be doing is looking more specifically
at we're gonna be looking more
specifically at individual values and
how we're gonna pack these in and so
actually you know what it turns out that
there might be a real good reason oh you
know what there is okay okay okay cool
there's a really good way that we can
actually use these cage-free nodes
because of what we're gonna have to do
in here okay so actually this is fine
we're gonna need this right because
we're actually going to need the leaf
count and the first leaf index right now
we could just snuggle those into the
sides because we know the
not use them but we might as well just
use the two values we actually have for
the padding because there's no reason
not to right so yeah turns out we can
use those and and you know it's all good
I think at least as far as I can tell
that that seems right yeah okay so yeah
what we would do now is we'd always load
Katie tree nodes here so we'd actually
load a Katie tree node out of this thing
and we'd always load those out of like
KD nodes and it would come out using her
stack value right then what we would do
here is we want to load out the
information we actually need and in this
case I don't think we actually need to
do it this way because there's no point
in actually loading it out anymore we
can actually just use it when we
actually need it because it you know
they don't get reused it's it's pretty
much it's pretty clean actually the way
we're doing this from what I can see
so we'll load up that here the KD index
will load here like so what do we call
that just put ad index and then we also
would load it here although here we
actually only needed once so it would
literally just be in there right there
so yeah
[Music]
I don't think we've really addressed
this yet I I said I think we've that's
finished I don't actually think it is we
probably take a look at that a little
more carefully but we'll see
so yeah I think that's all we need so
then instead of looking at say like box
pack and this nonsense right we would
just use first leaf index and we would
look off of the KB note here since I
kind of been doing it this way maybe
we'll change to do it like that
so for the leaf index we go first leaf
index like so pretty sure the rest of
this routine stays the same and then in
this case we can actually just have a
stop value here so this is going to be
like while leaf index is less than one
passed last leaf index and we're gonna
generate that value up here as an unpack
operation so one past left these last
leaf index is just going to be the leaf
index which is the first one and then
the child count right so the Katy arrow
leave camp so we unpack those in the
case of a leaf container we loop over
all of them and we stop when we get to
the last one and error and out right and
then we could actually shove that in
there for good measure if you wanted to
I don't know that we do but we could so
we can then look at this part of the
routine that all looks fine it's using
the pack stacked values here to extract
what we need to extract out of those and
doing the test then it knows whether
it's a leaf container or not obviously
as necessary and I suppose
I suppose this actually looks like this
so we set curse stock value to 0 because
we have bottomed out we look up the tree
to see whether or not we can find a new
one if we do find a new one we break out
and then off we go otherwise we don't
and we just leave it at zero when the
depth bottoms out yeah I don't know
probably not the best way to write that
if to think about that a little bit more
but it's something like that
ok so on the other side when we're
actually processing a node for the first
time what we do is we say okay which
side is the origin on and this right
here is going to give us that piece of
information and so we could actually
just say look it's whatever the origin
actually is - the the plain D we don't
really need to belabor that point we're
going to move the mask and we're gonna
end it with just the bottom bit to give
us a 0 or 1 value right then what we're
gonna do is say alright whichever side
we were on so from the 0 side of the 1
side we're gonna push that on and I'm
sorry we're going to descend to that
side and then on the Box tack we're
gonna push whichever one we didn't do
right now if we do want to do a see move
here again I'm not 100% certain about
what this will look like but let's set
it up to do a see move for now so we
know that M s VC won't generate C moves
even if it probably should so I'm gonna
just say like the box stock at Value you
know is is this thing and and so we're
gonna to take the box tack value is a
reference here if that's where it would
get pushed on and then we're just going
to say
we're always pushing something on in
this case too so I can do the increment
there right
so we don't need to see move that so
this will see move oh wait what am I
talking about I'm just I'm ridiculous we
got rid of the conditional it's not a
conditional it's just a different
address for load great never mind I'm
still thinking see move
we don't have C moves anymore no issues
oops rid of that awesome so we don't
actually do any conditional moves here
we just do moves they're just straight
moves right with a different offset so
it's just an address load thing perfect
okay I think we're good
I'm sure there's so many bugs in there I
can't even imagine because this is very
complicated but I think that that is the
end of the bugs my brain can find so now
we have to do the unsavory pasta process
of finding all of the bugs my brain
didn't find and in order to do that
we're gonna have to first start by
introducing a bunch more bugs because we
now have a different format right then
we are like we're not storing those
we're not storing these Katie nodes as
Katie nodes yet so in the split box
routine we need to be able to write
those out you know I'm saying so the way
I would like to do this is if you look
here split box always has two routines
here right this is what happens if it
actually split the box into two and this
is what happens if it didn't actually
split the box into two and so we should
be able to create both trees
side-by-side so that we can still run
both versions of this code and that
should be pretty straightforward I think
you know don't quote me on that so when
we actually run the split box routine
and we're passing a lightening box down
so you can see like how this works right
it adds some storage then called split
box and says here's the box that you're
actually working on what we should be
able to do now is also pass in here in
addition to the parent box that we're
working on we can pass a parent node so
we'll just build both at the same time
we'll call that I guess parent KD or
something like that and that way we can
actually set these up properly so what
we know is if we're working on one of
these parent KD things here and this is
possibly going to be a little bit more
complicated so if we actually split
we're going to need to do if we didn't
actually split then we ourselves are a
leaf container right if we didn't split
then we aren't so what we need to do
here is we need to know some additional
information like for example when we
return here we're going to need to
return the the actually split value so
that we know which one are our children
were right like if they're leaf
containers or not now we don't need that
for the current system but we do need
that for the new system because we load
up the sides value the two sides values
that are packed into our parent those
side values in code whether the person
that they are referring to is actually a
leaf container right if that makes sense
and that's to avoid us having to pack
more values in the stack which maybe we
should do
oh man now what I'm thinking about it
I'm thinking maybe that's actually
something we should just do yeah we
should never mind forget everything I
just said every time I say that I think
about there's a key and peele sketch
where they're at like a diner and
they're each trying to outdo each other
about how like it starts off with how
like authentic Lise other and their
order is going to be like how how true
to their roots the the the order is
going to be but it quickly degenerates
into them just being absolutely
ridiculous with their orders as most of
those kind of key and Peele sketches do
and at one point like when they're
really heated and I can't remember if
it's key appeal actually I need to go
watch the sketch again it's been too
long one of them goes like forget
everything I've set up into this point
to like erase all the previous order and
then goes you know to order something
absolutely ridiculous I need to watch it
again like most key and Peele sketches
it's very good they do that sort of
escalation kind of comedy where each one
is trying to up the other one in us in
like a sketch like better than anybody
else it's it's so good they have so many
of those they have the like facial hair
at the office one they have the hats
where they do the different hats I can't
even remember all the ones they've got
but they have so many of those good
escalations sketches where they keep
trying to do to outdo each other alright
it doesn't matter if you don't watch key
&amp; peele you should it's really sucks
that it's not a show anymore I
but subside point anyway like what I was
saying is that when you come through
here and you do like is leaf container
that implies to me that you could have
just packed these values so I think
actually what we could do is like we
could have is leaf container and we
could have is leaf count or actually
just things that we unpack off the stack
so I think what we could do is say we
don't actually need this because when
you actually do a curse stack value here
this doesn't need to occur anymore I
don't think and I could be wrong about
that but I'm just gonna say that I'm
right because maybe I can just claim
rightness and not care so what I'm
thinking here is that like look we
actually load the cursed act value here
if we're in a place that we know we're
processing a node but if we're not
processing a node in which case we're in
here then we don't actually ever need to
do that because the leaf index can just
be the cursed act value and then the one
past leaf index can just be that plus
the leaf count right so those can
actually be things that we just load off
the stack so in this case we just run
through the boxes like we do here in
this case when we start packed when we
start popping things off of the stack we
know that anything that we pushed on the
stack here we can identify whether or
not it was a leaf container and in fact
in fact I guess that's one wrinkle in
the whole plan that I hadn't been
planning for here so that's one bug I
already just thought so when we're
popping the curse tack values out we
need to know whether they're leaf
containers or not now you know what I
could just do that determination at the
top of the routine like so what we could
do here is say all right the cursed AK
value is something that we pre-prepared
that has all the information in that we
need right so it's not actually that we
determine whether it's a leaf container
what the leaf and what the leaf count is
as unpacks on the cursed AK value which
we do not use directly right and so then
the part where we unpack the stack here
is actually this part is only gonna
unpack those two values of course yeah
but then if so hard to get this right if
I'm guess I might as well do it because
I already have to unpack it there right
it's like an alpaca it unpacks it gets
unpacked so yeah I don't know so anyway
as we roll through here what I was
trying to say is like okay so then
there's like a leaf count value that you
would unpack as well right that's gonna
be zero here and in fact I guess one
thing we could do is say we don't need
his leaf container we can just use leaf
count at that point right so we could
just say look there's a leaf count if
the leaf count is non zero that's how we
know we're in the leaf and then we start
loading out so in that case we use the
curse tack value as the leaf index and
we run through them all right when we're
doing one of these and we load these
values up out of here we need to do the
unpack here right so we need to set the
leaf count and we need to set the
I think that's it right
when we load one of these up we just
need to set the leaf count and the curse
tack value I think that's all we have
yeah so this is going to be a packed
valium and then I'm just going to go
ahead and do the unpacks here so I'm
gonna have an unpacked leaf count and
unpacked note index here we're gonna
take this packed value and we're just
gonna say like look we unpack these two
things and off we go right up here we're
gonna need some other stuff because in
addition to the curse stock this one
only needs to curse like dying the leaf
count that's the only two things it
needs this one needs in addition to
those it needs the it needs to actually
load up this index so we need to do an
actual KD node load here where in this
case we're loading it off the cursed AK
value and that's true
in this case we're loading it off of the
thing we just unpacked so this is going
to be an unpacked node index here so
that we can load up this thing that
we're gonna test right and then we just
need to know which thing this is so we
need to know whether or not this is
actually
so this is a test note index rank oops
so off of the stack that we popped we're
gonna see which note index we're working
with we're then going to look at that
and we also need to know the plane test
pattern that we're going to use right so
so that needs to happen right yes so in
this case the test note index gets
assigned back to Chris tack value and
also the leaf count gets unpacked
so we pull one off the stack we see
which one it is we load the test pattern
that we're going to need to use to see
whether or not it's something were going
to actually test against we take the KD
tree node and we load it up so we can
get it's KD index yeah so I guess
another thing here is that this doesn't
actually have to come from here it could
come from here if we wanted it to
actually so we wouldn't actually have to
pack that on but I guess I don't see any
reason not to at this point but anyway
so we're gonna load out the test node we
look at what the index is and the start
D dirty nd we do the test and off we go
right hmm actually
one more wrinkle so actually no that's
not quite what we do so when we push
this on here right we're actually just
going to push on this same one again
actually right because we're testing the
same node again but just against the far
side so I think when we push this on the
stack what we're really doing is pushing
on a different packed value right so
we're doing like a PAC value here where
we're saying oh like and I mean I guess
we can just we can still do it this way
meaning we can still actually have that
being coded the value we actually push
but it's actually gonna be the same node
again is what it would be and I guess
you can't really do that now I think
about it because you wouldn't want this
to be loaded that way
hmm so that's tricky because that means
the thing that we would have to push on
the stack is much more complicated if we
actually didn't want to have to load the
KT node there right we could push the
index so in other words this value could
be on there so that could definitely
work all of this would work it's just
this one thing that would cause the
problem right and so the question is do
we make the stack 64 bit and push the KD
plane D on there right
or is there something else we can do
so I don't see any other options I don't
know if you folks do but it seems to me
if we really wanted to do this where we
don't have where when we walk the stack
we don't have to load which I would I
think we wouldn't really want to if we
could avoid it I don't see any way of
doing anything other than like this so
we would need a 64-bit stack in that
case where we have both a you know a one
single floating-point value that's the
plain D we need to test against to
figure out whether we're gonna do this
side or not right and then we need the
packed bits for first leaf index first
count and the plane test pattern which
easily fits in 32 bits it's just like
1688 and you're done
but I don't know is it worth it is that
the right decision it's tough to say am
I missing anything is the other question
cuz that's like there's a lot of
complexity here very simple set of
routines actually there's not much here
which is great like the entire code for
the KD tree walk is between there and
there right so very little code but does
it actually do the right thing because
it's so complex in your head it's hard
to think through is that actually a
correct walk of the tree you know what I
mean
like is that actually right
and I guess the only thing I mean
looking at it it sure does feel right
the only thing I'm not sure about is
when you actually push the other side on
if the other side was a leaf does that
work properly so let's suppose the other
side had a leaf count and you came
through here and you did the test this
test is testing the parent actually not
you and then you would unpack the leaf
count here if you were gonna do it so I
think it does
this is incredibly small for a KD tree
but then again it's probably actually
still crappy like I bet people have
worked it out too much better than this
but it really looks like it doesn't do
much what do you think of this does this
look right I'm wondering if anyone on
the stream thinks this looks right or
not it seems fun but at this point like
yeah yeah I don't know there needs to be
a data structure named after key and
peele I totally agree with that
KP tree kind of like that idea all right
if this turns out to be an interesting
walk of the KD tree then we're gonna
call it a KP tree after key and peele
all right so this is what we need to
actually build here and so we just have
to go through and do the encoding now it
means that our stack is not quite right
so if we look here at this box stack
that we've got that's not gonna do it
[Music]
it's got to actually be you 64 and so
again I'm gonna actually just create a
new one here that's going to be the KD
stack and we're gonna use that instead
again we'll clean all this up once we
actually verify that this is something
we want because this is all experimental
codes so don't want to
remove the other code until we verify
that we're actually faster and better if
we're not then we just shouldn't be
doing any of this stuff right it was a
good mental exercise but we don't know
that it actually helps so you know we
need to verify that first so we're gonna
do the KT stack there and then the KT
stack here and when we're actually doing
these unpacks these are 64 's now and
this here needs to pack the plane D in
there so this is gonna be like a packed
node pack KT stack where we pass these
two in and I think I think that's what
we're doing bound bound I think that's
what we're doing for the encode and
decode side of this right so then I'm
just gonna drop this crap in the top
actually I guess I'll drop at the top of
this particular routine as well so like
right here I'll do a pack KT stack and
I'll do all the unpacks as well and this
is just there's you know this is just to
make sure that we can easily modify
these things and see them all happening
in the same place because otherwise if I
in lined all of the packing and
unpacking that might be a little bit
Squinkie right okay so what we want to
do here is is have these unpacks work on
probably the low 32-bit values so that
we can actually run them well I don't
actually know that that's true
forget what I said
so this is going to be the plain D and
this is going to be the like packed side
value and so when we do pack KD stack
here what we're actually doing is we're
just saying look we're gonna convert
hmm excuse me we're gonna convert the
plane devalue into a 64-bit value that
we can shift up and we're gonna or maybe
we'll just do the packed side by that I
don't know which one we should slide to
the high side but we waste we want to do
this so we want to move the plane D up
to the high 32 bits and we want to move
the packed side or we want to or the
pack side in now Jimmy the problem is we
want it to treat this thing as if it's
au 32 values so what we really want here
is more like this so we want it to load
this thing as if it's a u32 value even
though it's not and then we want to
convert it to you 64 value to shift it
up which is really wonky personally I
hate the way C does this stuff I've
never liked any of this stuff and C++ is
like even worse what you want to do is
say look load this thing into a 64-bit
register slide it up 32 bits and/or the
thing in okay it's like three
instructions why does it look like this
ridiculous garbage right and again it's
just because the priorities in a
language like C++ are completely
backwards
but we'll work it out and get something
that looks okay for now we just need to
do some unpacks in here so we know we're
getting a 64-bit value in here and we
know that these things need to come out
for smaller values so I'm just gonna
have the downcast in here isn't there
one more thing we need to unpack is it
really just two things
is it just the note innocent leaf count
I guess just to know wowthat's
know the plain deed the plain D the
plain D the test pattern yeah I'm like
there's I was like there's more stuff
what are we talking about like that's
that's way too few things alright so
we've got the leaf count in the note
index then we've got the test pattern
the plain D and the KT Index now the
plain D is like totally separate because
it's literally just the thing shifted
down right
and again like unpacking this thing I
don't even know how we're gonna do this
because it just doesn't work and C
correctly we may have to use like a
struct to unpack this but I'm worried
about doing that that it won't know what
to do you know and I'm saying
yeah I don't know so again this is me
just trying to give the compiler
something that it will do the right
thing with which shouldn't be a thing
but it's what you often end up having to
do for no reason okay so in here what we
actually want to do is we want to take
this pack value which is used 64 and we
want to be able to access it as if it
was an f32 and we want the high F 32
right so what I want to do here is say
like alright pretend this is an F 32
star and then I want you to give me out
of that F 32 star I want you to give me
the the next one right like I want you
to give me the high F 32 not the low F
32 I have no idea if that is something
that the compiler will generate the
right code for in fact I have no idea if
it's gonna generate the right code for
any of this maybe we should actually
have a struct for it I'm just really
really worried cuz we've seen MSD C not
be able to push Struck's on a stack at
all so it kind of needs to be you 64 but
I don't know ok so here's here's a
thought maybe so one thing I could do
here is I could introduce a struct
that's like this you know what I'm
saying and so I could do something like
this where we just say when we have a
pact one of these like we're just gonna
treat it as this thing and see if the
compiler understands that so for example
I could say look this is gonna be one of
these right so we take the address of
the pack thing we're given we treat it
as if it's a KD stack pack maybe that
helps the compiler maybe it doesn't I
honestly have no idea if it will or if
it won't and then off of that we just
get the the D value right and then here
we do the bits values equivalently and
and like I said I just have I just have
no idea I mean like I said this stuff is
so easy in assembly language it's it's a
joke
and yet in C which is ostensively
suppose to be easier to program it's an
absolute nightmare if that makes sense
and it just yeah I mean it's just stupid
it's the only way you can say it really
okay so assuming we unpack that and and
maybe the other thing I can do here is
introduce a helper macro that's just
like unpack and it's just this so the
only thing this thing does is it takes
one of these like casts there and gives
it back to you so you can just do like
you know this is unpack the pack value
and get the D value this is
unpack pack valium and get the bits
value and so for each of these things we
need some way of actually producing you
know the correct set of bits out of the
pack that we want mm-hmm and so that's
the last thing that we need to actually
put in here so in order to do the unpack
I mean sorry or in order to get the
correct bits so we need to just assign
each of them a location right and so for
each of these we just need to like shift
and mask it to the part we actually care
about so the plane test pattern the KD
index is like zero one or two so this is
two bits right this is four bits so
that's six bits this is eight bits and
this is 16 bits right so this is like
these to make eight bits together
broadly make six but rounded up to eight
these to make eight bits this is eight
bits and this is 16 bits and that's our
32 right okay so let's suppose that's
the way we want to do this is the node
index is the bottom 16 right the leaf
count is the next 8 from there so like
this
maybe the KD oops
no that's right the plane test pattern
is going to be the I guess we'll just
say the plane test pattern is the next
four and then the KT index is the top
seam right I don't know if that's the
right packing or not but anyway so if we
actually go ahead and say 32 minus four
right so it's gonna be what 28 so if we
want to grab the KT index we just shift
down those 28 bits if we want to grab
the plane test pattern we just grab the
24 bit version and mask off
all right so this is 16 bits this is 8
bits this is 4 bits and this is actually
not for a bit we're giving it 4 bits but
it actually only needs 2 so we actually
have 2 additional bits in there right
I'm going to call that done and we'll
see in here we need to pack a KD stack
value on here for the root box to start
with and in order to do that we need to
have so the way we're gonna have to
start to make the root box work here is
actually we're not really gonna want a
root box index we're gonna want like a
root box value so inside the lighting
code here like we're actually gonna want
like root box value it's just a thing
set up to like start the routine right
and I guess it's technically just it's a
leaf count of 0 with a box cursed act
that we pull right which I guess this is
the same I mean we can just use this we
can just use the root box index where is
that from
it's here so I guess we can just tell
you the same guy that's fine so we know
it doesn't have a leaf counts so we know
we're gonna jump right down to here
we're gonna load the Christic value out
and then we're gonna start like
processing that box right
now we need to fix all our macros which
are probably all broken this is supposed
to be unpacked capital like so and for
all of these after we're done with it we
probably also want to just undef these
macros okay and that is maybe the
routine ooh
unpack clean test pattern is a problem
apparently because of why exactly oh
yeah so
well no that seems right what's the
problem is it cuz we have an unbalanced
parenthesis here let me take a look so
unpack packed bits then we've got this
then we got that seems right for this
one and seems right for this one what's
the problem
so we've got that enclosed we've got
that and closed ah yes we need one more
there yeah
and this one shouldn't this one need it
too yeah it says we've got a right shift
by too much for Daedalus does that mean
I'm casting in the wrong place there I
might be yeah this one needs one more
Sam we're gonna have to check all those
okay so here where we've got the Ray
direction I'm assuming that's just raid
D right yeah
unpack lief count is probably a little
bit worked so there's that bracket
there's this bracket am i right so there
okay and then finally these are just
lowercase D now
and so the KD plane D value needs to be
lofted up to do to a 4x to do that
subtract now interestingly enough we
don't really need to do this for wide
it's just that's the only floating-point
unit we have so I guess we're gonna do
it for wide just because why not right
oops so yeah now Pat Cady stack
I guess I'm not sure what else to do
here other than I guess this just this
cast needs to be the problem I think
here is that this needs to be like
isolated in here this needs to get cast
usage before first then shifted up
before so it's justification more
parentheses again this is so annoying it
should just be assembly language like
it's so annoying
anyway um this is supposed to be dirty
Thank You compiler that was a good catch
all right so now I think we have the
full sketch of the routine it's all done
and so the only thing we really have to
do now is build it right and that maybe
waits for tomorrow but that looks like
roughly what we need to do and we should
be able to take a look to see if the
code that was generated for this on
these unpacks were sane or not and I
don't know what we're gonna do about
that if they're not we could split the
you 64 into two values first using au 32
split and then pull the plain D out that
way so we may want to hand code that in
in a little bit anyway we'll see
but we need to like analyze that first
either way if that makes sense but I
think we're good I think I think that's
pretty good
I don't know what I should do now maybe
I should go to questions or maybe I
should start the split box modifications
and I'm not sure exactly how I want to
do that but what I think I might do is
just make something that reads the old
tree and writes the new tree or
something like that for testing purposes
I'm not sure but yeah like what you'd
want to do here is you'd want to say
okay anytime like I think we just yeah
we probably do
want a totally different split box call
because we're gonna do the same testing
but we're not going to write the same
kind of values so what we're actually
gonna be doing is on either side we're
gonna look to see whether or not we
split the child and if we do split the
child then we don't write a new index
right for that thing and so yeah so I'm
gonna go to the Q&amp;A and we'll take a
look at building it we'll take a look at
building it tomorrow that'll be our
tomorrow job that's a tomorrow job and
then I think we're pretty home free on
the KD stuff it's just gonna be a big
debugging nightmare
but we're home free on the on the
implementation side because the split
box follows everything we want we just
have to reorganize it a little bit the
hair is getting so big like it's insane
how much hair there is now I know
someone's saying nice hair it's crazy
you probably can't even see just how
much it's kind of like flattened out at
the moment but like if you actually poof
it out like it's insane how is the
seeker coming it's coming it's a lot of
work but it's coming
what about writing a plugin for fur
critter that highlights and close
parentheses um so yeah I already did all
that and but then I moved all the code
to my own editor when I did that jump so
I just haven't gotten around to like I
only use this editor set up on stream
now that you're looking at here and I
just haven't been motivated to clean it
up
I should at some point but for code
already can do that like if you want it
to
stay finest oh yes that's a good point I
said it wrong didn't I
yeah
looks like you can recover the milton
temp file from app data and Milton Paint
data
yeah only probably if you haven't
started a new one that seems like a
really bad way for this program to work
I would strongly recommend changing that
if anyone cares like it should never get
rid of the old canvas like just move it
to a different file right because I
thought it was saving it to that file
like I didn't understand that it wasn't
ever saving my thing like that was not
something I understood at all looks like
you're gonna recover the Milton temp
file yeah oh sorry no that room we're
kinda getting free over the seahorse
just add yourself to the mailing list so
if you go to Molly Rocket calm slash
follow put your address in here as the
very as soon as it is on early access on
Steam I will send out a mail so everyone
will get notified when you can actually
purchase it but but it is not up yet but
add yourself to my rocket comm slash
follow and you'll get a mail when it's
ready today John said that deferred
rendering is a bad idea why I you would
have to ask John deferred rendering is a
bad idea
I don't know deferred rendering is a
good idea isn't it I mean it's not
always appropriate like for the most
part I would say that like deferred
rendering is a technique that you use
when it when you have favorable
conditions for it right but I don't know
why anyone would say it's a bad idea
it's a good idea it may not always be
appropriate to your particular task that
you're doing for rendering but that
doesn't really make it a bad idea it's
possible if John literally said it's
just a bad idea across the board like I
should never be used that seems
confusing but what he may have just
meant is this not appropriate for
something he was talking about
didn't he just mean that almost no one
uses deferred rendering anymore
is that actually true I don't know I
don't know if anyone's in fact what's
the latest one of these so like
I mean this is deferred rendering right
here right unless I'm just reading that
I'm just reading this really quickly so
it's hard to say for sure
this is a deferred rendering right here
like does anyone not use deferred
rendering would be the way I would say
it like
but but they do do that right I mean
this is what that that is what this is
like this is how these renderers work
they they write the diffuse channel the
normal channel the specular channel
irradiance channel and then they combine
those later right I mean that that is
how that works maybe he was talking
about some other technique I'm not sure
what it is necessarily but like maybe
this is not
I mean he's calling it deferred
rendering the person who's doing the
breakdown but I mean I don't know so I
don't know I guess I would say like yeah
I'd ask John who he thinks isn't using
deferred rendering among the main
graphics engines because I think they're
all using it I think maybe not like
unity or something cuz you know it's not
really a high-end kind of thing but like
I would assume that like everyone else
is this is not an actual whole thing of
unreal so this is only they guess the
post pass but I mean I just thought
everyone does it like I don't see how
you would get away with not using it
most of the time in a modern high-end
rendering I'm not sure you wouldn't use
deferred right but so yeah I would say
just ask John what he who he thought was
not using it because I everyone does it
right if you're if you're high-end I
think I mean maybe I'm wrong maybe I
don't understand what he means or what
they mean I don't know but that would be
I would say that's very counter to how I
think about graphics you oftentimes have
multiple deferred steps on on high-end
on low-end you probably don't want to do
that because like if you're a 2-d thing
or whatever you probably don't want to
be doing a lot of deferred because
you're trying to run on lower end
hardware and stuff like that or
something I don't know could you explain
the zero zero one one one Katie's side
testing again yeah
and again when these are just my guesses
about how to do this right because we
haven't looked like I said out handmade
here I was try to implement something
once myself to demonstrate how I would
go about doing it if I couldn't just go
cheat but we'll probably eventually go
look at how other people are doing Katie
walks and see because it's a very well
studied problem and we should be
to get some national stuff there but all
I was saying is let's suppose here is
our KD split plane and here is our Rea
origin we know that the Ray origin is
fixed so all four rays are coming from
the same origin because we use this to
gather light from a light probe and the
light probe is in one place when we're
gathering it so we've got a fixed rate
origin but several k ds rady's rather so
the rady value which is this there's
four of them
so this is a sim D Lane that's four wide
right so there's you know it's packed
it's like four or you know three two one
zero
right and we know that we've got three
times that because we've got x y&amp;z so
we've got you know x y&amp;z so we basically
have like three registers or an array
with three values in it and each value
is four wide right so this is you know
the this is three X this is 2 X this is
1 X this is 0 X this is three Y this is
two Y right and and each of these is 128
bits wide you know 16 bytes right and
that's because each of these is 4 so
that's the data we're working with my
hypothesis for the KD tree and I have no
idea if this is correct this is just
kind of what I whimsically came to in my
head after trying to look at the problem
a little bit on stream is that we know
we can always classify the Ray Origin
fairly trivially by just going look
let's load the X Y or Z which ever one
the KT split plane is splitting because
we know that it only splits one
dimension at a time so we load whichever
one of those it's actually splitting and
then we can say all right take the value
and subtract the plane D value right
that will give us a positive or negative
value too
pending on which side it's on and we
know that the Ray origin is the same so
each of these values in the range is the
same the radii value is different but
the Ray origin is the same so all we
have to do is just look at one sign bit
from any of these four and so that's
what we do we just look at this low sign
bit we just look at and one and that
tells us whether on the positive or
negative side when we start right now
then what we know is we're going to
recurse down that side so whichever side
the origins on that's the side we're
going to do but there's another side
over here right and there's stuff over
here because it was a split plane so we
know that there's things on the side so
the question is after we test what's on
this side do we need to test what's on
this side and my argument was look if I
add the current rate eval you two from
Ray origin plus the T value times D I'm
going to get the location of each of
these that of each of these Ray's as its
current best hit so it's either gonna be
here here here or here depending on
which one of the Rays for Ray's you were
talking about but I'm gonna get four
values that tell me where the Ray would
end right and what I want to know is are
any of them past the split plane because
if none of them were if it was like here
here and here then I just don't need to
look at this side right why bother
like I don't need to look at the other
side of the KD tree because I know that
I can't ever get to the other side of
the cage a tree so just don't bother so
what's that gonna look like well when I
actually do this you know origin plus T
times direction right I'm gonna get out
four values that have a sign it will and
then I subtract the D the plain D value
right I'm gonna get out for signs again
just like I got out when I did the
origin and I only needed one in the case
the origin because I know that's always
the same but for the rate for this that
they're gonna be for different values so
I've got four sine values all
I need to know to determine whether to
go down this side of the tree or not is
are any of them the wrong value so if I
was on the positive side and I want to
know do I go to the negative side I just
look are all of the signs positive if
they are I don't have to look at the
negative sign if any of them are
negative I have to still go down it
right so that's where you get that not
equal to you just say look if it's not
equal to the exact mask I'm looking for
I do have to descend right and again I'm
sorry if I typed it in wrong we haven't
debugged this so I'm not even complete
claiming that this code is correct I'm
just walking you through what my idea
was right so here what you can see as I
said look if we're gonna take out the
sign values that's what move mass PS
will do so this is gonna take out the
sign values
we're then gonna look and say if the
sign values are not exactly what I
expect them to be for it early out then
I have to then I have to walk the far
side the tree does that make sense
yes what is the initial T value the
initial T value is the farthest you want
to go before you consider there to be no
hit so basically what we would set that
to is the lighting region we just set it
to like and right now we kind of set it
arbitrarily but if we wanted to be
completely conservative we could set it
to the total maximum diagonal distance
from one end of that volume to the other
and we know that we can't ever have a
hit that's further than that because
that's the entire geometry we don't have
any geometry that is further apart than
that right so we can do that but it
doesn't really matter just at the
initial T value is whatever you wish to
pick as the furthest you can consider a
hit before you just say look look we
know we can't have hits that are further
than that because our geometry is now
out its and we're not there anymore and
something also mentioned learn OpenGL is
tutorials about deferred rendering and
he said be careful you learn from is it
deferred rendering has some pitfalls or
something bad that only programmers know
about again I just I'm sorry but I do
not know what what he means you can't
ask me questions about what John means
because I don't know what John means
everyone uses deferred rendering as far
as I know I don't know anyone who
doesn't use deferred rendering but I
don't I'm not a rendering person so I
don't know
you give theoretically go full forward
using clustered shading yeah but they
don't like do muses clustered shading
but they still defer right I mean that's
exactly what this was if I remember
correctly like didn't we just have this
up on the on the screen so Doom is a
clustered renderer it uses a screen
lined like voxel basically grid to break
the screen up into sections and then
when they go to render I mean like here
you go I think they still use G buffers
so I don't know I mean it's possible
that maybe you don't have to use them if
you do some stuff they didn't do yet or
didn't have time to do and maybe now
they don't like maybe they use in the
new doom renderer which I don't know
anything about look I haven't seen a
study of them maybe they now no longer
do defer any of the values but I mean at
least the last time this is the only
clustered renderer I know of it's like a
highly optimized cluster renderer I
don't know who else does highly
optimized cluster rendering there
probably are some people who do but this
still used a deferred pass on two of
three of the components right so I don't
know I mean it is true that people still
use a depth pre pass as well like you
can see all of them use a depth free
pass because it's pretty much always the
case that people do a depth free pass
right so you also do a deputy best but
that doesn't mean you're not deferring
anything
you
oh so there's a new quality which Call
of Duty does Z binning or clustered
right now I mean you know whatever they
want to call it which Call of Duty does
it
I mean not that it matters because it
doesn't look like we've got a graphics
study of it there but
anyway
so Call of Duty infinite warfare which
is whatever that is alright so here's
the Z binning whoa
yeah you're right that's a lot crazier
yeah so clustered renderer still but
yeah that's that's an interesting
cluster thing
yikes all right all right
I would agree this this looks pretty
pretty nutso
this looks kind of ridiculous is this
really a good idea though I mean man all
right well this has nothing to do with
with deferred or not but just like man
that is some much more nutso bidding
than than the normal one
I mean when you say it's faster but how
do you know it's faster you sure it's
faster than the one that they use in
Dhoom I mean all right I have no idea
what John meant by that but you should
ask him not me because I don't know what
he means when he says things he knows
what he means when he says things so I
can't help you
what I can tell you is as far as I know
deferred rendering is still used almost
everywhere in high-end engines but
that's all I know
so that's that's what I've got for you
I'm gonna go ahead and wrap it up okay
so you actually did what the crazy
render in your engine to the crazy call
of duty one that's all right well good
for you
I mean that did look pretty nuts but
problem is we can't ask him because he's
angry about it okay
well that's fair - then don't ask John
about it
just go figure it out yourself right I
mean you know you'd you know what it is
now you can go read like those graphs
breakdowns and you know what it does and
you can figure out whether it's good or
bad for what you're doing you know step
up to the plate
you don't need John to tell you one way
or another right so I think Carmack's
had deferred running doesn't work well
in VR like who cares about VR VR is just
totally such a waste of everyone's time
and so much money got poured into it and
no one cares like nobody cares exactly
like I knew no one would care it was
just a gigantic way to set literally
billions of dollars on fire and never
see it again so yeah great anyway I'm
gonna wrap it up yeah like I've said
this many times like AR is something
that will probably catch on VR no one
will ever care about ever it's never
going to be something people care about
it's it's only AR right it's only once
you get it to so people can still feel
like they're actually still in their
real tangible environment like it's it's
just not the case that like people are
actually still social they don't want to
feel like they've been completely
alienated from the real world like that
I mean if they were they would all love
coronavirus they would love being locked
at home without ever be able to see the
real world ever right but that's not the
case like very few people actually want
that and while it's true that it's a
good little like
fun crazy thing to do once in a while
like oh that was cool like I put on the
VR goggles and I was down with the
whales for a minute like sure but that
is not a revolution that's just it's
like the Nintendo Wii it's a little
thing you do once and some friends come
over and you try it one time and oh well
that was weird and then you never think
about it again right so it's just like
we are not necessary it just we
shouldn't have bothered it's a necessary
step to a are perhaps but say that and
that's what you're doing you're just
going down the road to AR and till you
get there it doesn't matter so you know
call me when you're at a AR and then and
then I agree there's probably people are
gonna start liking that cuz when you can
just put on like you know glasses like
I'm wearing now and you can actually
just see extra stuff augmented into the
world that seems like people will use
that like they like they use the
smartphone you know so anyway that's it
for today thank you for joining me for
those sort of handmade hero it's our
pleasure coding with you as always if
you want to follow along the series at
home you can always go to handmade hero
org and pre-order the game it comes to
the source code so you can follow along
with it you can go in modify the split
box routine before tomorrow try to beat
me to it
everything is there we just have to
reorganize the data so no no real new
thing happening but give it a shot
also we've got a Kickstarter going on
right now for our comic it already
succeeded but we want to try and get as
many people comics as we can so please
check it out we're gonna add a stretch
goal in there another stretch goal
because I think it hit all the stretch
goals already or almost did so we're
gonna add another stretch goal and there
soon too so check it out and yeah if you
like cats or you like space or you like
cats in space you should check it out
I'll be back here tomorrow when all
right that's the box routine and then we
can start seeing first of all debugging
this thing does it actually work like
did I miss a case somewhere highly
likely but then we can look did it help
just reducing those opps the number of
opps does that help us and we
so we'll see hope see you back here for
that till then have fun program everyone
and I'll see you on the Internet
tickety's everybody