hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show we code complete game live
on stream we i believe are just left
with debugging today we actually did
some nice reorganization last weekend
and we cleaned up the lighting code so
that it was easier you know because we
it had been gone through so many um
experiments with us because you know
lighting as i've said many many many
times on the series
is probably one of the hardest things
you're likely to encounter in real time
rendering um
it's the it's like the one thing that we
can't really do
um basically real time lighting
is just always a hack there's no actual
good solution to it
uh obviously folks at nvidia and so on
are trying pretty hard to
get to a real solution because you know
their job is to improve rendering that's
what they make money on and so you know
maybe someday we'll actually get
graphics cards that are so incredibly
powerful that you can actually do like
fairly
real lighting computations every frame
and it will actually work
um you know with some amount of
denoising obviously but like you know
it'll be casting so many rays to do
actual real light transport that
all of these hacks that we're looking at
won't be necessary anymore but
at least for the foreseeable future even
the next five years that's not going to
be the case
we just have way too far to go for at
least the indirect lighting part
direct lighting is probably going to be
solved because that's
a much more bounded number of rays
indirect lighting were pretty far
and so most indirect lighting schemes
that you see in games and certainly the
one that we have here
are just based around some hacks you can
do to try and
take the number of rays you can cast or
the amount of lighting work you can
actually do
and turn it into something that actually
produces a visually pleasing and
plausible result even though we all know
full well that it's not correct and
isn't going to be even close to correct
because we simply don't have
enough computing power to make it
correct in the 60th of a second that we
have to do it
so taking a look at where we've come at
this point in the series
for our lighting we've got sort of two
methods and i believe
we just can switch between them pretty
trivially now if you take a look at the
game running
what you can see is that if we run the
old system which we are trying to
improve the performance of
you can see that the lighting works
relatively well it's a little bit
flickery
but for the most part it is generating
we have some work we want to probably do
on quality and also on interpolation to
improve
the shaping of the lighting and so on so
there's things that we'll definitely do
kind of
downwind of the lighting computation
but the thing that we want to do before
we go any further on that is we just
wanted to try and get the highest
possible performance
for this level of light transport and
what we did there is we tried to improve
the ray tracer and if we switch to the
new one
you will notice that we don't actually
get any results that is because we have
not debugged it yet
and there are a lot of problems so
what we want to do today is just take a
look at that i believe this needs to be
looks like we've removed these values i
gotta
nerf them out here we just want to kind
of take a look and say
what's wrong with the routine that we've
written so far
i can get rid of this what can we see
that's buggy about it
can we just do the basic amount of work
to get it you know nominally working and
go from there because you can see here
if we run it
um what we what we actually see
happening and i know it's a little bit
hard to figure out exactly what's going
on there but
what we see happening here is that
everything get
every ray that's cast just gets full
moonlight
so our raycaster is returning the result
for
every lighting location um
it's just returning the result that it
already
left the the sampling volume and it's
just
it didn't hit anything right so so no
rays are recorded as ever hitting
anything
ever so obviously we know that's not
true because if this was working we
would see a result sort of at least
somewhat similar to the result that we
had with the previous ray tracer
and so we know that it's it's just buggy
right it's like
something's buggy about it but since we
only just finished it we haven't had a
chance to really
carefully go through the whole thing we
don't really know what's buggy because
there's
three separate pieces and any one of
them
or all of them could be buggy and we
have to start pairing it down
and getting each one working reliably so
we probably want to go through them
piece by piece
doing more testing seeing if there's
assertions we can put in seeing if
there's any kind of like
actual testing we can do to try and
isolate each piece and get it working
reliably
and the three pieces are one there's the
spatial partition
which we use uh it's a grid it's sort of
like the voxel but it's a little bit
larger it's one voxel unit larger
around the entire sides of it
so we want to see if we can make that
work uh reliably to partition
the things we're casting against into
that grid we don't know if that works
currently
it could just be wrong so you know one
one very obvious way
that we could be not hitting anything is
if we don't correctly
insert the boxes we're trying to
collision detect
into the grid we could have a thing
where you know you never hit anything
because the grid keeps telling you
there's nothing you can hit
so there's that the next thing we have
is the walk table
the walk table is the thing that tells
you which grid squares you sample for
any particular array
that could be totally wrong it could be
telling you to sample
all erroneous grid squares
and obviously that would cause you to
not hit anything and then finally what
we would have
is the actual raycast routine itself we
did some additional work on that
although the core of it still does do
testing the same way
meaning it does actually test for rays
using the same algorithm
when we do a comparison between the aabb
and the ray the actual structure does a
different
and the way it loads the data is
different and the way it finalizes
is different as well so all of those
things could be wrong
and there's actually part of that that
spans two pieces
when we build the spatial partition we
also pack
the aabbs we're testing against into
individual like cmd units that are easy
for our code to
work with and so that part is also
worth examining because if we packed
them incorrectly
then when we test against them they will
not test correctly
even if the testing code was correct so
again
three moving parts there and two of the
parts actually have like a relationship
with each other
through that packing structure that we
have to look at closely as well because
that wasn't even though the a
b testing hasn't really changed
we're using the same algorithm the way
we're doing the algorithm
is different because the data input
has been changed
so we have our work cut out for us
certainly so it's going to take a little
while for us to actually make this
go let's start by looking at the spatial
partition
and figuring out if there's any way that
we could sort of
test that right
and i think there is a pretty simple way
that we could do this
since we know that we can draw debug
boxes we've already done the work in
fact we even inside the letting system
have a very specific thing uh called
push debug box
it seems like we should be able to do
something where
we draw a particular
spatial cell so we could for example
take a particular voxel cell in the
world
and we could draw what that voxel cell
thinks its aabb contents are
and that would allow us to visually
inspect it to see whether or not
the contents of the space position
appear to line up with what we think
they should
and again the reason that i typically
take this sort of approach
is that you know
in fact we get asked a lot of time so
i'll mention it again people always ask
me like what do you think of unit
testing
what i think about unit testing as well
unit testing is fine
for very simple programs that don't do
very much interesting
for complex programs like a game you
really can't unit test because
the definition of what it means to be
correct
is very difficult to actually test if
you have
an input and what you want in your
output
is that you want a grid that contains
clipped versions of the input for each
grid square
well the routine that you write
in order to generate that is the same
routine you would need to test it
right there's no way to write a unit
test that tests that
without doing that right
there's no other way to do it so if you
write the routine
and then someone says unit test to see
if that's correct well there's no
definition for the output
other than run that same algorithm run
that right now sometimes you can still
do this if there's for
example if your performance like for our
raycaster
that's something that we could unit test
and maybe should in the future because
it's easier to write a crappy slow
raycaster
than it is to write a really highly
optimized cmd1
so we could use a brute force raycaster
to test
the total result of the raycaster
that's something we could totally do and
probably should eventually but to
actually test any individual piece of
the algorithm is quite
difficult because the only way to know
what the result
should have been is to have a properly
working version of the routine
and if we had a properly working version
13 i'd just
use it right now sometimes you can look
at unit testing a little bit differently
and say well
we're not really going to think of it as
a unit test but we're going to think of
it as
sort of two wrongs make it right we're
going to write the routine once
and we're going to write it a second
time a completely different way and then
we're going to keep working on them
until their answers match
right and that can be a valid strategy
if you have something that's really
difficult to test and you don't really
have a way of testing
the answer but you really need some way
of finding the bugs in it and you don't
really have any other options
you can definitely try to go that route
but with something like raycasting it's
inherently very visual
your eye immediately knows whether
something is correct or not in a way
that
writing a test is very difficult to do
if i can pick
a node of the voxel see the outline of
that node and then see the outline of
the boxes that it included
it will be immediately obvious to me
what it is doing and more importantly
and this is something that's important
to understand that unit tests often
can't tell you
it will also tell me how it's wrong
because when i can visually see
what is getting included in that box and
how it's getting clipped
i immediately also know what's wrong
with it if i don't see what i expect
if boxes protrude too far outside of it
then i know they're not being clipped
properly if boxes that aren't inside it
are included
entirely then i know that the bounce
checking is wrong right there's a lot of
things i can intuit from seeing the
visual version
that a unit test simply doesn't tell me
a unit test just tells me whether the
results agreed or not
but it doesn't necessarily have any way
of telling me in a intuitive way
how those results were incorrect and so
again
especially for something like a game
where you do not actually have correct
answers sitting around
you don't have a corpus of testing a lot
of times
visual testing is much better than unit
testing because visual testing
both provides you a way to quickly see
whether the results are correct without
having to try and figure out another way
of doing the algorithm that will somehow
magically be more reliable but just
slower i guess so that's why you're not
using it as your actual algorithm
but it also provides you an intuition
that you don't have otherwise
and finally it also gives you something
else that you don't have with unit
testing
which is insight into the problem that
you may not have had otherwise
so once you start drawing things there
are visualizations of the problem that
you have
you may actually gain insight into how
to solve the problem better
and a unit test can never really do that
for you because all a unit test is going
to do is tell you whether or not
the code worked properly it's not really
going to tell you anything that you
didn't already know about the code
because you're the one who had to write
the unit test for it
so obviously you knew what you were
doing when you wrote that
so having a visualizer that can draw the
various aspects of the algorithm
to help you find the bugs can also help
you improve the algorithm and that's a
really important thing to keep in mind
so when choosing between doing something
like unit testing and doing something
like visualization
i would argue that visualization is
usually where your time is better spent
especially in a game environment where a
lot of things are very poorly defined
and don't have really good right answers
to them
a lot of times if you have success with
unit testing it's usually because your
problem is very simple and has a very
simple definition of what the answer
should be
and in those cases it may be totally
fine to do so but
a lot of times that's just realistically
not what you're doing games are much
more complicated than the things that
people typically write unit tests for
and have much more fuzzy definitions of
what is correct
so it's much harder for you to do things
like unit testing on those
um all right so
let's go ahead and try to uh
put in some visualization for what's
happening with the grid raycaster here
so i think what i'd like to do is kind
of uh
re re reinvoke if you will
the debug idea that we had before where
we would sort of say
look we know that if we drew
everything you know the raycasters
raycasting tens or hundreds of thousands
of rays
every frame it's we can't draw all those
it would just be a giant
mess on the screen that wouldn't tell us
anything but what we can do is just
randomly pick
one location in the world and say let's
look at one of the rays or a couple of
the arrays that are coming out of that
one location
and then we can sort of get an idea for
what the raycaster is doing by looking
at
that specific ray or that specific grid
so what i'd like to do is something here
where we'll just say okay
let's go ahead and say if you know or
maybe we'll make
a boolean value that's like debugging
and we'll say if the initial grid index
equals some value that we
set so we can set this grid index to
whatever we want right it can be
anything
we'll just set it to something and then
we'll look at the rays that come out of
this specific grid index and this
specific grid index
only and furthermore we can do some more
specific
testing here if we'd like to and limit
the actual
number of rays we look at but for the
moment i'm just going to draw them all
from
one specific thing and then we'll start
pairing that down
as necessary
so what i'm going to do first is i'm
going to draw
for our debugging purposes i'm going to
draw the ray
itself and i'm going to do
also draw the voxel region that the ray
exists inside so we cast this out of the
center of a voxel for a specific
reason we wanted to compute lighting
that occurs within that voxel in the
center seems like the best place to do
that since we can only compute it out of
so many places we're going to draw what
that box is and then we're going to draw
the ray
and so what i'm going to start with here
is i'm going to call
the push be the push debug box call
um and i'm probably going to get rid of
this if here it's probably just there
for some quick testing where we didn't
want to draw too many boxes or something
like that but
we want it now and so what i need to do
is i need to produce a few things i need
first of all the color
which i'm going to use i think cyan
for this particular like the starting
box area
and then what i need to do is i need to
produce a voxman uh
i'm sorry a boxman and a box max for the
voxel
and in order to do that i'm going to
need some way of asking the voxel
what those bounds are and fortunately i
actually have a way of doing that
which is get cell bounds now it's a
little bit difficult for me to produce
that because we currently don't have a
way to reverse engineer an index
we have flat index from but we don't
have um
sort of the reverse of that so now would
be a good time for me to write that i
didn't write it before because i was
like well i don't know if i really need
it
i do think we need it for debugging i
don't know that we ever need it for any
actual work but that's okay
um you know building debug things into a
game is important so i don't mind doing
that
at all so what i'd like to do here is
i'd like to say you know okay if we're
doing the debugging
i would like to get the cell bounds here
i also don't really understand
why i need to pass a boxman into box max
to this when i have a rectangle so i
think i'm going to
have a voxbox there that i can just pass
and then i'll have there be a push debug
a version of push debug box that unpacks
that for me just makes my life a little
easier
which seems good so in here i know that
i want the spatial grid that's the grid
that we're actually looking at
and in terms of the index again this is
not quite correct
so what i want to do here is i want to
say
triple index from or however we want to
look at it
maybe x y z index frame or dim index
from maybe
and then i'll pass the initial grid
index so this way i can
figure out where i am in the voxel like
so
and that will help me out right so i'm
going to go
now look at how i would write that
function so we have flat index from
and we know that that's how we produce
the answer
so if you look here we go okay
we take the cell count x and we well you
can see what we do right the x
is the is the you know the step by one
the y is step by one whole x row
and the z steps by one entire x y sheet
right so what i want to do here
is i want to you know produce a version
of of this that does the opposite thing
so i'm going to call this dimension
index from
that gives us back the v so i'm just
going to swap these two right there's
the v3s
and here's the flat
so my goal here is to take the flat
index and somehow
produce the dimensional index from it
well i know several things about this
first of all
i know what each of the sheet dimensions
is
right because i know that for example uh
the z
sheet size is just going to be the cell
count x times the cell count y
so i know how many there are on a z
sheet and i know that the only way to
get
that far into you know to get one whole
one of those forwards is to move in z
because between moving in just x and y
if z was zero i would never get out of
that initial first
z sheet so what i can do here is just
divide
uh and get the answer so if this is how
much is in
a z sheet and again i pull this out
for convenience so i don't have to creep
using the arrow
so what i can do here is say all right
whatever the input index is
so when i look at this index if i divide
it by the z sheet count
that's going to be my z right
because however many full z sheets i
went forward that's my z
answer now if i then want to take
and decrease the index as we go
i i don't really know that i want to
modify it in place so i think i may
create a new one here that's like index
remaining
right so what i can do here is say okay
let's take the
uh the index remaining here and we'll
divide it by z
sheet then i'll take the index remaining
and i'll subtract
whatever that value is that i got times
the z sheet so that just gives me
however much
i have left now what i can do is say all
right finally we know there's a result
y right and the result y
is going to be just however many y
x rows you know we went forward that's
the y value so i can again take index
remaining
and see like how much is a y row
and a y row is just going to be cell
count x by itself right
and so then i can say index remaining
minus equals that value
and then finally i can say okay the
remainder of that is just going to be my
x because whatever i have left after
removing
the sheet motion and the row motion all
i'm going to have left is just
x right so now
this is not particularly efficient way
to do this um
i could probably do a better job of it
because i don't
really need to probably do full divides
on these i could be a lot more clever
furthermore i could just demand things
like that the grid was always powers of
two in which case i just use masking and
shifting
to get the answer but again we don't
suspect that we'll ever
actually call this function in any real
like
sense it's just for debugging
as far as i can think so anything that
gives me the answer
is good enough and in this case that
should give me the answer
so i'm going to call that and i'm going
to push the debug box in this case
and then i'm going to go ahead and say
look let's make that debug box
function a little easier to call by
taking a rectangle
and then we'll see how where we get with
that
okay so this just calls push debug box
solution
box dot min box dot max box color
um and then this instead of taking a v3
is just going to take a rectangle
and so that's just like a semantic
improvement for
my own purposes right it doesn't really
do anything else
okay so now when we look at this uh
what i want to try and do is make it so
that i can you know pick out where the
heck this
debug box actually is and there's a
couple things we're going to have to do
with that like i don't see it right now
right for example
um so what i'm going to have to do first
of all is we have to make sure our debug
line drawing is still working
because we made some changes to that and
we don't even really know if if that's
working properly i also don't actually
know like
what initial grid index 47 if i assume
that's something
we should be able to see anything that's
not larger than the total grid or
whatever right
um oh actually no that we have to make
sure we're at least not on the apron
though because the apron never gets
casted from so
actually we do have to make sure it's
something we could
very well pick a number that never gets
drawn so i'll just set a break point
there to make sure we do actually draw i
didn't think of that um but we also
don't really know if we're still going
to draw that because you know looking i
don't see it it could be that i just
don't see it
but it's also possible that like you
know we
messed up the debug line drawing so we
have to make our debug system work
reliably here
and we have to make sure that anyone's
actually casting this um
while we do that debugging work i'm
going to switch to debug builds
so i'm just going to set this to an od
here and then we're going to
step into there and make sure that it's
you know working at all
uh if i grab
where's the lighting file
hello remedy there we go
so if i take a look at this code here i
just want to know like do we ever get in
here
right because if we never actually get
into this piece of the code
then i know like whoops we must have
picked something on the apron or
something like this right
um and so we're never actually stopping
here so it looks like
uh i gotta go find out like why are we
never hitting this path like why is
initial grid index
always weird
and obviously that could be a bug but
so here's our grid indices here
i guess now that i think about it like
the initial sheet
would be like what 24 by 16 or something
so if we're not above 384
you're not gonna hit here right it's
weird that that's the first one that hit
but that could just be a multi-threading
thing
anyway we know that 466 is
is a valid thing because i just watched
it come through there so let's start
with that and now let's make sure that
we're actually getting back
something reasonable and trying to push
a debug box on
so here we go we should now hit the
inside of this routine properly so if i
remove this one here
we should hopefully get to the inside of
this at some point
there we go and when we uh
ask that thing for the cell bounds we
should get a voxbox here
and you can see that we actually do
right so that's good now there is
something that i don't know if we ever
actually addressed
so in this code when we call push debug
line
um yeah so you can kind of see here like
there's some problems we're going to
have if we actually want to run this
because we are running it multi-threaded
now i'm pretty sure that only
yeah in fact i know for sure so only one
thread can never process
a particular voxel region so i think we
don't have to worry about the fact that
this
is not thread safe you can see here that
we're just incrementing this thing
and we don't use a locked increment so
two people could overwrite each other
i think we're fine there because again
we're not really calling this from
multiple threads
even though multiple threads are running
um
so i don't anticipate an issue there but
i just wanted to point that out because
if we were
going to call it for multiple threads we
would get some dropouts
potentially as two threads hammered on
that value and
didn't sync up right we would want that
to be a locked increment
so if we go ahead and run this program
now
now we want to do is try to make sure we
can actually see that okay so we do
so here's an example of a place we're
casting the rays from and again
remember we've done absolutely no work
yet to make sure that we only cast rays
from voxel cells we actually care about
at the moment we're actually casting
rays from the entire voxel region and
in the future we may decide to try and
limit that but
we might not and the reason that we
might not is simply because
uh we will have cases where we'll be
pretty dense
throughout that region with things
stacked on top of each other and we
don't want the game to like have
too much of a variable frame rate so it
i'm not certain that we'll ever
make that change we may we may not but
that's okay so now we know that we're
able to draw our debug lines properly
so now what i want to do is inter
instrument uh the rest of this code
with uh actual you know
augmentation of the ray casting so
what we're going to do here is first of
all we want to draw
in addition to this debug box i'd like
to draw the actual array and what i'd
like to do is sort of draw
it uh in two parts i don't think i want
to draw it here i'd rather draw it sort
of maybe
um down here more after the hit
detection has occurred
so maybe like more down in here
and what i'd like to do is i'd like to
draw two debug lines
where i show the
in one color i'll show where the ray
starts
to where the ray supposedly hit
something and of course
in this particular case we know it won't
hit anything because that's the bug
we're looking at but
eventually as we go we'll probably one
debug actual
hits as we get closer to having the
routine work properly
so i want to draw one thing from where
the ray starts to where the ray hits and
then one from where the ray hits
out kind of further just so we can see
where the ray actually would go
in case it hits really close and we
can't quite see the ray
like we get like spurious it's i want to
see where it would have cast out to
right so it's just showing us those two
things
all right so let's go ahead and push the
debug line on here and you can kind of
see
that function just allows us to pass two
points in right so we'd say what color
we want and the from and the two
so here's the you know
the ray origin to the hit p right is one
thing we want
and then we want the hit p to like the
far p right so that's what we actually
need
and the colors for that um let's say
that the hit line is like
yellow right
uh and then maybe like we'll do a dim
version of the yellow uh kind of going
far from there or maybe
it's like kind of more of a of a red
line i don't know we'll see more of an
orange
so what we need to do is we need to
compute these and obviously
the grid ray caster is easier because
it's it's casting one ray at a time
which is really nice
because that's the way we structured it
it's one ray against multiple bounds
the old way was multiple rays against
one bound
so this is easier for us to work with
two which is kind of nice
all right so it's ray origin single and
then the hit p
we need to know what the actual p-value
was here
and so i believe if we look
when we terminate out of here you can
see that we have a t-ray value
and the well in fact
when we actually call the probe and
single probe p single that's actually
produced the hit
right um so i think we actually can just
piggyback
on top of that i guess we don't really
have to compute it ourselves
so it'd be probe p single
is actually the
is actually the value at least for now
and then when we want to draw the rest
of it we just draw from there to
something like that's just far out
so like far out man so you know 50 units
or something out in the uh
direction of the of the ray
i don't actually know what the ray
direction
is here it's going to be
so ray d single is the actual value
so that's just me trying to draw the ray
and so now what i should
see is if i run this i should see the
rays casting out
but only from that particular one yeah
so here you can kind of see those going
now one really interesting thing you can
see
is we obviously screwed up right right
off the bat
and this is why i say it's so good to
have visualizations
you can see like right off the bat we're
only casting
rays in one sort of conical direction
and
that was definitely not part of the
algorithm
so we're not we're supposed to be seeing
a full sphere here
of things happening and we're
not seeing that at all we're seeing some
kind of a of a
like you know restricted to only
kind of hard to say it looks like
looks like maybe we're getting kind of
like only positive
directions in
one in in y but
you know it's really hard to quite read
what the bug is there but you can see
like very clearly we've got a bug um
where we're not actually getting
spherical results here
right and we should so before we go any
further
it's pretty easy for us to start looking
at what that problem is
okay um and remember we're drawing these
rays
no matter what so when we come in
through here like we don't care
whether this loop terminated with a hit
or terminated on cost or terminated
because it ran out of space
in the grid we don't care we're always
drawing it so
in theory we should see the full sphere
of casting
because we draw all the rays that there
are from this particular voxel
and we're totally not seeing them right
so we know there's something bogus going
on
so we have a couple of different things
we could look at
if i look at the sphere generator that's
obviously the first thing that
could be busted and if i go look at how
it's actually outputting things i can
just maybe start to look and see if
there's any uh obvious errors here
so you can see that the way this is
working is we step through the
octahedron
and we look at the number of rays per
that we want and we just output those in
order
right so we just kind of go through and
we output all of the octahedrons kind of
just packed
right
um and there's a couple of different
ways that we could be messing this up
one is that it could be that like none
of the rays
in this entire array are
actually pointing in the correct
directions right like there's just
they're all sort of pointing down in
that sort of one direction and so it
doesn't matter where
you're sampling in the array you're
always going to get something pointing
in that one sort of general conical
direction
that's possible but the other thing
that's possible
that we have to consider while we're
doing this is that maybe there are
correctly distributed arrays in this
array and
we're actually only sampling a few of
them
so we've got the range wrong right
so there's two ways we could have
screwed this up and so we want to kind
of look at both of them now since this
produces an inl
file i should be able to go in here and
look and say all right so
here's the total light sample direction
if i look through these i should see a
fair
distribution of signs
and specifically for why i should see
like a distribution of signs
it didn't look like i was getting that
and when i spin through here i do
you know i do see a good balance of
signs in here
like i can't tell from visual inspection
whether these are properly distributed
around the sphere
according to the octahedral map but what
i can tell you is that
there do exist some positive and
negative y's
right you can see them very clearly as i
kind of move through here
and so if i was seeing a biased
distribution
i wouldn't necessarily be able to say
that it was broken
um or correct just by in visual
inspection
but when i look at this i can see that
i'm literally
never casting anything out in this
direction
so i pretty much know that it's not just
the values in the array that that are
wrong
there's something else wrong and it
could still be that the array is
constructed improperly like perhaps
there's too many of a certain kind of
value and we're only sampling from one
part of it or something like this but we
at least know that the values in the
array do contain
other directions and we're just not
actually using those directions
let's take a look and see what we're
actually getting here for that and also
by the way
you know when i look at this there's
another thing that i wanted to kind of
point out
as we're going here
so one kind of bizarre thing if we look
at this
i'm not sure why we're getting like a
black
versus a yellow
that's just really kind of
nonsensical to me because i put in
you know a totally valid color value
here
but i'm not really getting one
so i'm not sure why that
oh i know why uh so
that may well just be because of
lighting
i suppose so if i look at where this is
yeah you know what that probably is what
it is so
this may just be because the lighting
itself
is right you can see i'm i'm crossing
out into the unlit
region right so that's why the lighting
changes there
that's what's actually happening right
um
which is kind of just yet another
indication that we probably need to go
and actually put lighting first on and
off into the renderer
because we don't have that ability right
now everything always gets lit
okay so what i'd like to do now is take
a closer look at why we're getting that
but
that particular bug um
and you know i guess it it's
it's an important bug for us to do first
as well because if we do want to use
if we were gonna look at why this thing
was never hitting anything well what
it actually isn't we need this thing to
cast a ray up in that direction before
we can figure out why it's not adding
anything right
um so so actually for this particular
grid cell we happen to pick at random
the reason it's not hitting anything is
because it actually isn't
like it's actually getting the correct
answer oddly enough
so let's try to figure out what's going
on if we
look at where these rays are coming from
inside the grid raycast routine
we're actually feeding them using this
sample dir
here right and the way this works is the
sample direction
comes out of this octahedral table
and then what we're doing is we're
looping over these
now
i mean if i look at what's going on
there i can sort of almost already see
that it seems a little bit broken um
because if you come through here
remember we're going to be casting
four rays at a time and so
we're going to be taking the sample
direction and indexing four of them
then this passes
just that same thing plus one which is
not going to cut it
right so for sampling four arrays in the
grid cast
that needs to be a plus four and this
would need to be a plus eight
right because that's the actual striding
that we're using there
now that might completely explain the
bug actually let's see
because that would be enough right there
to screw it up
okay so now if we look at it we're
seeing a much
more sensible uh ray casting
distribution
right um there's some issues here and i
think these are to do with our generator
table just
uh running out of picks and it's
probably producing the non-jittered
version there's actually to do
in there for it so you can see there's a
little bit of bias in a couple
of these rays that we probably would
want to get rid of
um but on the whole it it now
looks relatively good i mean that's not
a horrible distribution
of rays you know maybe there's some
things we would want to change about
that but on the whole
that's okay and so now we just need to
start wondering
why do these rays never hit anything
and in the region where we actually have
full lighting happening
you can actually kind of see uh that
we're pretty clearly not hitting
anything either because
these are still bright yellow going up
through here so even before we've added
any of the other debug rendering stuff
that we want to add
we can kind of see very quickly that
this isn't working
that should produce a pretty obvious
result so what i'd like to do now is
i'd like to just take a look and see if
there's an
easy way for me to sort of
limit the number of rays that we're
actually casting and what i'm going to
do here is
maybe just control say the direction a
little bit more
so what i'm going to do is say look if
we're debugging
i want to take uh the inner product of
the array direction
uh and i guess i kind of need to do this
a little bit further down now that i
think about it
so i probably want to do that in here
and i probably also want to
so i guess i'm going to call this ray
debugging
and what i'd like to do is i'd like to
make the drawing of the ray itself
be specific to this particular raid
direction basically
so when we get down here i'm going to
look at ray debugging as opposed to
the regular debugging flag and that way
i can limit the number of rays and the
way i'm going to do that is right now i
kind of want to look at rays that are
casting upward
so i'm going to say that like if i take
the inner product of the ray direction
and i guess i really don't even have to
quite do that maybe i'll just say look
let's look at the z and if the z is
greater than like 9
we know this is a fairly straight up
cast and we'll look at that
right um
let's do it like this
so this is just me limiting the rays i'm
looking at
a little bit more and so you can kind of
see now if i go look at this
i'm just kind of looking at the rays
that shoot upward
and so that just gives me a better
you know a more focused way of looking
at how these things are being cast
right and now what i'm going to need to
do
is add a little bit more debugging
in here so i can see what we're actually
doing
so for starters i'm going to expand on
this code here
where we're actually drawing boxes to
draw which boxes we visit
so when we look at
this when we get these nodes here
the lighting spatial grid node is
looking up off of this grid index so
what i'd like to do
is i'd like to just draw for every time
that we enter here
if we're doing ray debugging on this
particular array i'm going to grab
the voxbox for the grid index we're on
and i'm going to draw that as like you
know a candidate
and so what this is designed to do is
this is designed to tell me
are we walking the grid at all correctly
right and so one of the things that you
can see
here is right off the bat like
unless i just did something stupid in
that code i'm not
getting any actual drawing
so what i'd like to do is take a look at
this piece of code
and find out why i'm never getting in
here
because we know that ray debugging is
set to true sometimes because i see the
rays getting drawn
and so either this code
is somehow erroneous
or we're always terminating this loop
immediately
meaning we never like go past the
starting node
right um
so let's take a look at what happens i
could also do sort of
one other thing here uh which is i could
choose to draw the starting node
a little bit separately a little bit
differently
so let's say for example that i do an
add radius to
on this particular voxbox and i just say
you know what let's go ahead and
shrink it in a little bit by you know
some by you know a quarter unit
and that would allow me to see whether
we're even looking at the first one
just just visually i can see right away
like are we even looking at it
and so what you can see here is when
we're drawing this
you can see pretty clearly that i'm
getting both of those two things
so i'm drawing both the
um the starting box
and i'm drawing that box again in here
so we do
correctly come in to this piece of the
code
and what's obviously happening here is
somehow we're always terminating
immediately so
in the actual square we start from
we're terminating and we're terminating
with a no hit
so for some reason we we terminate
uh prematurely for sure and i'm not sure
what that is right like
um
so yeah i i don't really know i'm just
going to step in it because it's you
know it's pretty
easy now for me to do that so that's
what i'm going to do
but yeah i'm not sure why we're getting
that result but it should be pretty
obvious hopefully
if we just step in here
and uh and check
so let's go to the first time that this
happens
uh you know and one of the problems
we're gonna have i should probably
switch this up is this is running
multi-threaded it's gonna be a real pain
in the butt
um in fact you can see it being a pain
in the bet right there
so i may need to go uh to the
internal core uh here and turn off the
multi-threading
at the moment um so you can see this
lighting cue value here
if i don't pass a lighting queue to
internal core
it won't run multithreaded so
if i want to here right instead of
passing lighting queue
i can pass a zero
that would allow me to not deal with the
whole like
n billion threads are coming through
this path right
although
it is a little odd because no other
thread should have had raid debugging
set to true
so that's a bit weird to say the least
so that makes me a little nervous
because that shouldn't actually be the
case
um it still would have been a pain in
the ass to
sorry pain in the butt to debug but i
wouldn't
actually have suspected what i saw to be
true which was that
i wouldn't have expected to see a second
thread
hit the ray debug unless that's not what
actually happened
[Music]
um
so that's a little concerning and we may
want to keep that in the back of our
minds
something to investigate in a second but
i want to keep investigating i was going
to investigate first
just so i can see so when we step
through here we see that there are no
leaves and that's exactly what we would
expect because
there shouldn't be any leaves right
if there were leaves in this particular
box that would be odd because we just
looked at it and there was no geometry
in there so there shouldn't be anything
to test against
we also don't expect something hit to
happen because we didn't hit something
so that's good
and then it looks like the cost metric
has decked down to zero
oh all right that's just a typo
um so this should actually be if cost
metric
equals zero right or is less than zero
um that was just the wrong way around
right so that's just stupid
all right so that's one bug down not a
particularly interesting one
but at least it is one um and now we can
see i suppose
uh we should be able to see this thing
actually step through something for real
let me run through here so now we should
see it like yeah right
it should be moving forwards correctly
and it does okay
so let's switch back
um to at least optimized
and probably also unfortunately we gotta
switch back to um
to uh
the the fully threaded version just
because lighting is so darn slow
there we go and let's take a look at now
if we're actually drawing
a grid walk because that would allow us
to figure out if our grid walk is busted
so that's one of the things
oh gosh okay well
so i guess what i would say is yeah so
we can obviously see something wrong
with our grid walk
which is great because again like i said
visualization tells you what your bugs
are very quickly
it's another really great part of
debugging with visualization
so what we can see here is we know that
we should have been walking
upward but instead we're walking
downward
so what i suspect is we have some kind
of a sign bug
in our walk table generator um
and you know we haven't really looked at
this routine remember i said there's
multiple routines involved
uh and all of them or you know
at least two are probably buggy and
they are so what we should see here if
we take a look
um we should be able to figure out here
why we're getting the wrong stepping
so let's take a look so
here we are and you can see us walking
through each sample direction
and we pull out a particular sample
direction right
uh and we set and say well wherever we
are we're gonna start writing to that
particular part of the the walk table so
that seems reasonable
um i mean we should we're going to have
to double check that part too because it
could also be that we're picking the
wrong offset in the lock table for a
particular array so
that's also you know something we could
try to verify
so in here what we see is we've got this
step value
and we've got this dim step value which
is how much we would
step in any particular direction and
what you can see here is we go through
the dimensions
and we look to see whether the
ray is going in a particular direction
for that specific
dimension right and what we do here is
we say if the ray
is going in the positive direction then
we set the step value for
that dimension to equal to the step if
not
then what we do is we make the ray
be positive anyway so that way we don't
have to worry about
look you know different ones but then we
set the step to be negative
right um we then multiply
the step by whatever the voxel dimension
is in that particular
direction and the reason we do that is
because obviously it's a step by more
and more each time as it goes from x to
y to z
stepping to be honest that seems
fine um
i can't say i can immediately see what
would be wrong with that
um but let's keep going there
there might be a bug in there i'm just
not sure what it is
we start at the starting location and we
look to see
if we've gone how you know how far we've
actually gone
we don't want to go past what we know
the raycaster will never actually use
we start by figuring out what the best
stepping would be and which
which dimension that would be we go
through the dimensions and we say
if we were going to get um
so we take the the cell dimension so how
far
we have to go for a particular cell
and we subtract the
location that we're actually at so far
in the cell which i believe gets
initialized to the center of the cell
yeah
um we then divide by the ray direction
which is the stepping rate right and we
see
how far in t we'd have to go before we
were to cover that specific distance
um figure out which one
that is and
we set the delta to
that step right which we pre-computed
before
and we move the ray by that much
uh which is wrong
so
the problem with that is we
aren't removing that element
of the cell dimension from our position
so
i don't think this actually would cause
the bug
so we have another bug that is not
related to this
but because we're just solving this
locally
we need this at value
right to
we need that to constantly basically
modded
by whatever we're stepping right
so um
not sure how to say this right but
basically we need this
to take whatever the dimension
that we chose so like the best dim
and we need to subtract the cell dim so
that we
re-center ourselves right
with respect to that that way we're
constantly just
inside like one cell and we when we do
this comparison it will actually work
um i don't think that will help
here that's just a separate bug right
um but this is like a directional
problem so
the reason i didn't think that would
solve this bug and i was right
is because this is a problem with even
the very first step
which which this fix
only handles would only address bugs
that happen on subsequent steps
so the question is for a ray that's
clearly going
upward which would be what positive z
um why are we stepping
backwards right and
i really don't know
we're taking the ray direction from the
sample direction
for each one of these
and
we're writing the walk table offset as
whatever we're actually going to write
into correct yeah
so i'm not sure what's wrong there the
dim step
here is set to 1 and should only become
negative in this case
i mean it should only become negative if
if the ray
direction is negative but
you know we're we're sure that it's not
for this ray because we literally are
only looking at rays that have
a z greater than 0.9 so no way for it to
be negative
pretty obviously so how
is it that we're getting a negative step
is the dim step part of this somehow
wrong that's one thing
or am i overwriting or writing to the
wrong place in the table
right because if i'm looking up the
obviously that would also be an issue
so let's just see how we pass the table
around in this particular case so we can
see
if that feels right at all
um
so if i do a search for
the yeah just for the
walk table
so you can see here i'm taking the
walk table offset for my particular
sample direction
right which is the thing that i in
theory wrote
right here and
i mean
it sure seems okay um
so i guess i'm also
just gonna have to
maybe the best thing to do here is to go
look let's watch the walk table be built
for this particular array and we'll just
see what it gets
um
because yeah i don't know it looks fine
right i mean it looks it looks like
what i would think so let's
do this let's use
our um same method before for debugging
so
[Music]
so in here i'll just
nerf this out and
i'm going to go ahead and watch
the walk table get built
and what i'd like to do is be able to
you know just
see which you know for for one of these
guys who's
somebody who's um
one of the rays that we're actually
debugging and i don't know which one it
would be
right excuse me
uh so for one of these rays we're
debugging i just want to see
what the direction index actually is so
that when we pull out
you know when we pulled out this walk
table like what
what was the actual walk index so if we
look at sample directions ray index
what is the walk table offset okay
it's zero
so i mean that's
pretty obviously wrong like why is the
walk table index zero for everybody
so something's up here um
wait a second
yeah that's just that's just really
bizarre so let's let's take a look at
how that's getting initialized so
something's really busted here
uh and let me let me just remind myself
how that
is there an obvious bug in here
somewhere so here's dust index
nice
so yeah we were just never generating
any of the walk table
actually
let's see what it looks like now
um we're never gonna run here because
we're running
single threaded debug which is about the
slowest possible thing
one can imagine um so
i should probably
switch that up but
wow that was kind of crazy right
um
should probably make a switch for this
that quickly turns off debugging for
this purpose
it's just dumb like this is the kind of
you can kind of see why it's so annoying
to do engine programming
is because if you think about how many
tools people have built for like crappy
lame programming like javascript or
something
there's so many things they can do
because people actually built tools for
it
whereas really basic stuff you would
want to do
so for example one of the obvious things
you would want to do
is write your compiler so it's not
terrible
so that when you're debugging you can
swap
in the debug version of that routine
to step through instead of the optimized
one
this is actually very easy to do if you
actually cared and it would make it so
simple
to do this kind of debug work you would
just literally have a button in the
debugger that would be like
patch the ip address over to the other
routine now because i want to step
through it right but of course like
forget that like i'm talking about space
age technology you know
as far as clang and microsoft are
concerned um
anyway okay so now at least
we are properly getting some walk
stepping here but you can see that it's
still
wrong so it's always picking um
to step upward but upward is not correct
um so we've still got some
additional issues i don't know if that
is actually a bug in the stepping code
though so let's just take a look
at the grid raycast code um to see
you know like
how are we actually stepping
so you can see here like the walk table
is not getting incremented right so we
need
our walk table to actually update and so
this
might just be because after we use it we
need to do this
and we aren't all right
um okay so now that's actually looking
quite
nice right so now we can actually see
that we're getting you know a variety of
rays cast here
and there's some weird things happening
with
i don't know why that's occurring right
so that's a little bit strange
and probably merit some attention
could actually have to do with with uh
if that's part of the drawing of the
of the hit p value or things so that's
fairly disturbing right
um if we look though at the
actual way in which we're stepping
through
uh this particular part of the grid
it actually like at first blush and
we'll have to pause this later so we can
watch
these things more carefully but it
actually looks quite
nice it does appear that the rays
are aligned with the grid stepping
that's occurring
and i'm pretty happy with that
so i feel like we've at least debugged a
significant
set of the bugs in here that we had and
we're now kind of getting down to uh a
difference
you know a separate wave so i'm pretty
happy with that i think that's pretty
good
so what we need to do now that we can
sort of see that our rays are casting
relatively correctly and we're walking
the grid relatively correctly the
the sort of final thing i want to do to
let us start to debug the actual
literal raycast part of this is i need
to now kind of be able to
focus in on on only just one ray so if i
want to focus on literally just one ray
i'm going to need some way of
maybe passing in the debug value from
the outside because by the time i get in
here
i i know where i'm casting from but
that's
really all i know and so i need some way
of
of um yeah making this a little bit more
uh
i guess i could make this part a tighter
bound
and maybe it would be sufficient um
i'm not sure so maybe if i did this
you know we can just kind of pick some
arbitrary stuff here
um and grab one that way but
passing in from the outside might be
like the better way to go right
uh and so here you can kind of see it
you know doing the
the debug cast but again i think that's
kind of a
fool's errand uh at some at some level
so i think what i would probably rather
do is just do a forced debug call
at some point so rather than do this
uh i think what i would do is i'll leave
this in place
i'll turn off ray debugging as a thing
so this will just again use the
debugging call
um and what i'll do here is
i will uh kind of go
i think i'll kind of go with maybe
like
just do the first ray from the bundle
so you know in here we'll just say
debugging equals false
right and in addition to just doing the
first array from the bundle
rather than using this i'll pass in
debugging as
a thing then
i'll just pick one to do in the outside
as a separate part of the routine right
um so in here i'll just go ahead
and as part of the
let's say part of the
main raycast i guess
i guess i'll do it as part of full cast
so as part of full cast
i'll do the check there and in here so
you know you can see us kind of looping
over
um with the vox center p stuff here
right
um i think what i'll do is i'll do an
additional one here
so i'll just say all right you know
like we'll we'll let it erroneously
write
um so this is just like a debug system
thing here
i'll let it erroneously write into
something here so we'll say like
uh sure like whatever the
the tile that we're writing here is just
you know this random spectile
and then we'll pass the rest of this
stuff
by picking out a specific one of these
so
down here i'll say all right there's
going to be like a
debugger and it's going to be
like something out of the
out of the set here i don't know which
one we want to do we can pick anything
we want for this
uh and then we can pass the
you know all the stuff here so i can
pass the ray origin
i can pass the ray direction which
actually take it back i can actually
just do this
we go um
and all this stuff should be roughly the
same so i can pass the the array origin
single which we know will always be the
same spec outstanding
atlas are the same spec text the same so
now i just have the debug der
is what i'd pass here right and what i
can now do is just wrap
this in the if initial grid index equals
something right i don't remember what
the value was but we probably want to
pick one
that we actually want to test this will
do one raycast with debugging turned on
just one and it can do the same one
every time
so up here you can see that we use the
entropy index for the octahedron that's
what gives us the jitter
so here instead what i can do is
set this to something right um maybe i
use zero for it i don't know
we can pick which one um but you know
we'll we'll see as we go
so if i run this now uh what i want to
do is pick
one of these grids and pick something
that's act
i want to pick something that's actually
going to hit
right and so what i can do is try to
like find that just by trial and error
because we don't really care
but again we just need something that's
going to do like a proper hit here
so when we take this debugger i could
just say look let's
add something to the debug dirt debug
dur you know
plus i don't know 20 who knows right but
we can just
pick random numbers until we find
something that actually casts in a
direction
that we can use right
so there's that's almost good right
it's not quite right but it's almost
good so let's
maybe try a little more here
um so that got worse let's let's try
backing it up
yeah i really have no idea what the
correct thing is to cast on here
not sure why that didn't give me
something useful
i need to add this to like some kind of
hotkey probably right
maybe i should just move which grid
we're doing since everything i'm picking
seems to go downward
i think there should be what like if
there's an eight by eight
right there should be 64 of these light
samples
is that right
and yet literally like no matter what i
pick it seems like it doesn't go that
direction
how is this possible
this is really annoying
i don't even know why that would work
that way because if it's the octahedral
map it should be
walking along an octahedron right
i mean each one of those should be right
because if you remember inside
hh sphere right the
way this thing was lined up is
it generates a poisson distribution and
then
it comes through here and says well
as i'm picking these we
pick a specific txty each time and step
through right tx
right we go through those and we
we look to see you know as we select
them
it's the eight by eight right so
there should be 64 in each octahedron
right and
we should have them correspond to the
actual
like to the actual octahedron map
layout t x
and t y now
it should be such that like
four times eight plus four so it should
be like
probably something like 36
should it be sort of towards the center
right of the map
all right i guess thinking it through
paid off in this case
um yeah
uh so
let's try that again now one interesting
thing about that is like
i'm sending that down but it looks like
it's not correctly
getting the uh the walk index there
right did you notice how that was wrong
it looked like it's still going downward
so this will be interesting to see but
anyway
so looking at number 36 uh
and then telling it to to debug that
good raycast um
that gives us one that should hit and
that we can walk through but
why we that looked wrong again right
like that looks like an
incorrect um
walk value and that that may just be
because it didn't like generate
uh the table or something because we
haven't really looked at that yet okay
so it's fine
uh because doing the code reloading on i
don't know what happens with the tables
on there we haven't really looked at
that
so if you take a look here you can kind
of see
the the ray as it is
passing up through geometry now and so
what i'd like to do
next is just see what geometry it
actually is trying to collide against
so i'd like to see you know
uh for each one of these boxes
i'd like to see which ones have leaves
first of all
and then go from there now again i think
i'm going to have to do
i might have to make the remainder of
the stream rather than debugging
actually just be fixing our lighting
code in the pixel shader
because like this is not useful
you can kind of see here like well
those two things were sent with separate
colors
and they look the same and that's going
to be a problem because it means we
can't use color as part of our debug
information really
and we kind of need to be able to so
like
if i just look you know uh
at what i've got here
0.5.250
and 1 1 should look different
and similarly
a
oh wait no that's okay never mind let me
go ahead and
and see what happens if i
change this oh no i did and so 0.5.5
should look different than 1
1 but it doesn't right
so it's just kind of busted like
you know it's not it's not working
correctly
and so i think we're gonna have to
figure out something to do here
uh now you know we've been avoiding this
for quite some time
and i don't think we're gonna be able to
get away with it uh forever
so like you know that's just not
sufficient
so maybe that's what we have to do now
before we go any further because without
being able to push debug stuff on there
you know so i think we kind of need that
what i'd like to do is let's go ahead
and
go to the pixel shader side of things
so in the open gel like z bias program
which should be here
you can kind of see like all right as we
come through here
and we uh
and we do our lighting calculations
really all we need
um is just a constant that turns this on
and off
right since it's really only for debug
purposes we don't
really have to care too much about it in
terms of performance
probably but so when you see here when
we've got like if lighting disabled
else and you can see the surface reflect
times thing
so this world z this was the hack that
we had in there from before
and that was for this stuff right so
that we could overlay this stuff
on there right and that works well
enough but it's just it's just was just
a hack that someone suggested and i was
like okay
i'm fine with that but i think what we'd
rather do here is we'd rather have a
constant
um that lets us determine how much
lighting you actually apply
right so what i'd like to do is maybe
something that looks like this
so let's suppose we say
you know we have
surface reflect is the value we're going
to actually have here so we have the
like the lit reflect version
is going to be oops the sum i deleted
the sunlight by accident there
there we go so what i want to do here is
say
okay surface reflect is going to be
times equals l
but what i'd really rather do is just
have one multiply in there
or one lerp in there that lets me
control that
there's two really ways we can do this
it's really hard to say but based on the
way
graphics cards work now i'm going to say
we just want a constant that controls
that
so we probably want just like you know
lighting enabled
is an actual boolean that's probably the
fastest way to do it these days
because usually what will happen i think
is that modern graphics cards will
actually look at those constants and
use them as actual switching on and off
if it's entirely one way or entirely the
other way
i think they'll actually handle that
don't quote me on that i don't
really do much with this kind of stuff
day to day
so i'm the wrong one to ask but
i think if you want to say like okay
there's a uniform
oops there's a uniform
int that's like lighting enabled and
you pass that in and if you have that on
you get lighting and if you have that
off
you don't uh then we could do it that
way
well okay you know what though i take
that back as well because
the problem is we kind of wanted these
to be slip streamed
into our
uh
we kind of wanted these to be slip
streamed into our actual
render code so that probably
actually isn't the best idea
so i think probably what we would rather
do now that i think about it is we're
going to be sampling textures in here
so you can see in here right that like
we do a
texture sampling for the reflection
value so
like um that's the octahedral map
sampling which we don't really care
about
here we go so you can see us doing our
array uv
like you can see the frag texture index
thing
right maybe what we do is say if frag
texture index is zero
right
or we could say a frag index is greater
than or equal to zero and then we just
pass a frag texture index of negative
one for things that aren't lit or
something like this
that's one way we could do debug
now the problem with that is if we did
do that
it would cause a problem where
we wouldn't
it would cause a problem because we
wouldn't be able to do textured things
that way
so again hard to say let's take a look
at what that value actually is
so here's our textured vertex uh and you
can kind of see like
you know how this is working
for the texture index we can have a full
16 bit value
um
and it looks like actually we've got
extra space too so i suppose we could
just in our vertex have a code
for lighting or not
in fact emission would be fine
right um
all right so maybe what we do is we just
pass it in there
right so we know that we've got a
reserved value in there and we actually
know that there's an emission value too
i just
i don't know that we're actually using
it so we could just try to make that
work
so maybe we don't have lighting enabled
that's not a thing
right
um and you know maybe this um
maybe this lighting disabled value also
is is not really a thing either
because we can disable it now when we
pass things down
so what we really need is some way for
this thing to get
in addition to these other ends like
it's getting that vert texture index and
all that stuff right
what we kind of need here is a way for
this to get the emission value
you know what i mean um
and we just stream that in
and then the emission value would
control whether you lit
the vertices or not so basically like
the l value here
i guess we would just kind of do a lerp
i don't i don't really know um
like that part's a little bit harder to
conceptualize
because we're doing like a a sum here
and
so i guess we probably just want
something like
this we go
between the like lighting
that we would compute and the one one
one
by just doing a lerp
i guess
i mean it's not great um but
i feel like it's something for now and
when we're trying to optimize our pixel
shader later
maybe then's when we would test to see
you know what we think about that
so i want to in here then say
that the smooth value in
there is just going to be like an f32 of
like
the emission value um
and that anymore
did i have these lined up right so
simmering the depth peel
light intensity light floor the voxels
and the diffuse yeah all right fine
um
so i guess i'm okay with that
it does mean that when we use the
z bias program
we're going to actually have to set up
the
attribute arrays correctly so
like in here you can kind of see where
we've got the attribute arrays
when we do use program we do like the is
valid
garbage here so in there what we're
going to have to do is
after texture index we're going to have
to do a similar thing
we want to do basically the same thing
as the color array so in here we want to
say like look
if the emission array is valid
then we'll use it
and we basically want the same thing
that we were doing for our
color but we want to unpack it the
unsigned bytes
we want to um
unpack those right and we want them to
be
zero to one floats so
i don't actually know
i did i don't think we need to do
anything other than to just say that's
not an
i so i think if we just say it's an
unsigned byte then it will
unpack it to zero to one automatically
because that's what it will always do
with an unsigned byte
um so although it's really kind of
squinky and weird
and we didn't really say that
i think that's what it will do anyway
right um
and so here i can also do the exact same
thing
which is that i can just disable it when
we're done with it
and that should be it we now have to
actually
look up those values so like right now
like that we'll use them if they were
there but
at the moment we don't actually have any
way to actually do that
i like to actually put anything in there
so although we have sort of the vert
stuff here
i guess this is actually should have
been vert emission
somebody's gonna have to actually do
something with it right
so we'll do that in a second but this
should at least give us the ability to
use it if anyone actually
sets it and no one is
all right so if we run the code now in
theory it should
uh still work of course i've got some gl
error stuff happening here but
we just won't get any of that because no
one's actually doing anything with those
emission values but
you know so let's take care of the gl
error messages first but oops
message there we go
index out of range really
what do you mean i also don't know
like for when we do these prague values
let's
let's take a look at the where those are
coming from at the moment
so this may not get cleared would be
another thing so it may just be because
we're never actually doing this
we'll see
um so if i go to the z bias program i
should probably make this actually
be properly called vert emission there
um
because at the moment i actually wasn't
doing that so let's take a quick look
and just make this a little bit better
so you can see here where we're passing
emission here
i might want to call that frag emission
actually and so in here
where we actually do the vertex stuff i
kind of want to do like an int
f32 vert emission like so
and then i want to do a smooth out
f32 frag emission
and i think i just want
those to be direct assigned so in much
the same way we just
do the vert uv directly there
we would do the vert emission directly
so i'd say like frag emission equals
vert emission
so it's just a pass through because we
don't need to change
it right
all right so let's look at the compilers
there
so i guess i want to look at vertex
errors if i can here
and fragment errors
just to see um i think i can use remedy
here to make that easier yeah
remedy the rescue um
so it looks like emission i just forgot
to rename
so like down where we actually use it i
was still calling it emission instead of
frag emission
so let me not do that
all right so if we now run uh
let's see what we get here
why why am i not getting anything
[Music]
what is happening something bad is
happening but i don't know what
access violation inside the ogl
nvidia driver so
i've told it something bad i'm not sure
what
what have i done so my vert emission
is like not right at all but i don't
know why
so in here somewhere i said let's get
the offset of the emission value
of this unsigned byte i say oh
that would do it
all right
all right so now um at least in theory
we should get a value you can see that
since i removed that these would have to
be having their
emission values set and they're
currently not um
what i can do here is now take a look to
see if
that's working at all and so one way
that i could do that
is inside where we do like a push quad
so you can kind of see where we do our
um
our quad you know writing here where
we've got our vertices
here's us writing our vertices out here
we could write emission values based on
whether the lighting is on or off
right so inside here we know whether the
lighting's on and off because
inside the render group it tells us so
in the render group itself
we have this value so
we should be able to in here handle that
properly
now i don't actually know if we always
use this
so if we look at all the places where
we're doing that
you can see that there's
at least two places so in handmade
renderer there's some of this
and in render geometry so here's a right
quad
right so there's a couple of people who
actually do this
and
we kind of need some way of
making that be congruent so
if we take a look at where the geometry
output stuff happens
that would probably be a good place to
think about this more
i think probably most people want this
emission value set to zero
so i'm just going to do that
and then only in like the debug code
will we set it at the moment
to anything else so
that's one place we write them and the
other two places we write them really
so very very few places we actually look
at this
but one is here and one is here
so in output quads
doesn't ever write it's just sort of
keeping that in mind so it's really just
only here
so what we should be able to do here is
set this to an emission value so all of
these
should be settable to like some value
right
um
um and so now what we can do is just set
this value like
our emission value can be a look to see
is lighting enabled and if it is then it
can be
you know zero zero otherwise it can be
ff
um and that should in theory give us
something we want
um we'll find out so
wait what
oh we actually pass in an emission value
here
um
i'm not going to use that at the
immediate moment
but we may want to use that later
because we could actually pack that
value down
actually
all right um so now
actually we can see that this already
works which is kind of cool
so you can see that now our code that
previously had lighting turned off which
was like the debug overlays actually
works now
with no hack right and that's nice
um and so now
uh what we need to be able to do is set
it to be off for
certain things like for the debug stuff
there right
and
i guess the easiest way to do that would
be to literally just use the packing
so when we go to
i mean this yeah there's a couple
different ways we can do it i'm not
really sure which one we want to use
um because this is not really the part
of the code that i really want to be
working on right now so i'm not
motivated to like do
um like a super
fancy solution but if we take a look at
how push line segment works
you can see that it just falls through
uh to push quad here and
probably what i would assume is that in
this particular case the push quad that
it's calling
we probably just want to pass a full
emission value down right
so we just say that emission was one
there and then when we do an
the actual push quad
yeah which is here uh what we want to do
is pack the vert emission
so probably what we want to do is say
like look if group lighting enabled
um if that's not on
then the emission value is one always
because
it just it's automatically going to not
use the lighting
but otherwise we should actually pack
that value
down so we should have a like
um
we we sort of want like a clamp by
normal pact
but i don't know if what we've got so
it's like it's basically you know the
same
as a bgra pack but we're only doing it
for one value so like
we want the ability to pack one of the
one of these
you know just one
and i don't know what we've got for that
at the immediate moment right like i
don't actually know
what's going on with that but somewhere
in here what we want to do is say
okay like clamp zero to one
emission times 255
right
basically
so we're just packing to 255 just
because that's what the graphs card
can read more efficiently like there's
no sense storing a whole float because
the emission just doesn't need to be
that detailed
um and so now in theory like we should
and
and do which is great um we should be
able to see our debug colors properly
right
and so you can now see like it's kind of
nice and clean coming through here
uh all of the colors are as i asked them
to be
so now it should allow me to do
something um
with my existing code and we'll
basically be stopping here for today
i don't know how much time we have left
but probably very little at most 15
minutes but
possibly like as little as one minute i
don't actually remember
but anyway what i was trying to say was
now i should be able to do stuff like
change the lighting
how bright like one of those cubes is
based on whether it has leaves or not
and other things like this
so inside the grid raycast code uh what
i can do now
is take a look and say okay
when we actually do the leaf hit testing
so you can see us looking at the cell
bounds here right
i can look and say you know are these
two different
so i can do something like
uh you know v3 color
or box color
equals you know
these two things
being equal to each other and then
produce two different colors based on
that
right so then i can say
you know
i'm gonna make this thing be dim
uh cyan in the case where there isn't
and bright cyan
in the case where there is um
and then that way like when we
just
don't why i did that um and that way i
can just have a little bit
better understanding of as we're
traversing through
like did it ever test any leaves at all
and then eventually we'll draw the
actual leaves themselves but i just kind
of wanted to see
um and what you can sort of see there is
some
sort of semi-nonsensical uh results
so it looks to me and i could be very
wrong about that but it looks to me
like these are actually in and maybe
this was too subtle like
maybe this should have been like
this so we can really see what the
difference is right
um and that way there's like no
ambiguity whatsoever
whether we've uh hit one or not
and so when i run this now i should see
like which ones have leaves yeah
so you know this gives us i'm gonna go
ahead and wind down for today but this
gives us a great place to start tomorrow
we've got our ability to draw things
clearly we now
know like definitively that
some weird stuff's happening with the
spatial data structure because we're
these all supposedly have leaves which
they obviously don't
only this one should have a leaf the
rest of these should like at least
these two and that one like so these
three right here are the only ones that
could plausibly have
colliders in them these obviously don't
i mean we're looking at them there's
clearly no colliders there
so that's great too because that allows
us to sort of
uh give us a great place to start
debugging from our we already know we're
going to do so we'll go to a brief q a
i agree that the hair is getting
very cartoonish i'm uh
i'm kind of thinking uh
let me just uh see if i can find it here
i uh i thought there was
a um yeah so like
i feel like i could kind of start going
down this route
a little bit like like i feel like i
could
i could do some wilson cosplay pretty s
pretty cert uh soon here
okay somebody needs to capture that in
sobot comment and send it to abner
coimbre
because five plus hour majora's mask
sounds like something that he would be
very interested in
performance might have changed since you
removed the early out oh yeah definitely
i mean
we have no idea what the performance of
this routine is
at all right we have literally no idea
because we have to get it working
properly first
and then we can actually benchmark it we
have we have no idea what it's doing
so we'll get it working first then we'll
do another capture
and then we'll run the two different
routines
um together to see which one
performs better right and we can also
take some v-tune testing
to see whether there's obvious things we
can do to improve either of them
i love right
looks quiet so i guess we can just wrap
it up
all right thank you everybody for
joining me for another episode of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coming with you as always if you would
like to follow along with the series at
home you can always
go to handmadehero.org and pre-order the
game it comes with the source code
so you can follow along with it um i
will be back here tomorrow to
do the next phase of debugging um i
think today pretty much went exactly as
i hoped it would meaning
what i said at the beginning about how
visualization helps you zero in on bugs
very
quickly much faster than say unit
testing or things like that for
algorithms of this kind of complexity
and
geometric sort of you know orientation
and i think that's exactly what we saw
right we were able to
find at least three bugs very quickly
um by doing nothing other than just
drawing
and so for something like lighting where
it's such a visual problem anyway it
just works really really well
anyway now that you have the ability to
do that if you are following along with
source at home you should be able to go
find
some more of the bugs before i do
tomorrow uh
because i can't program until then and
you can so you should try that if you're
interested in an exercise
but i will be back here tomorrow um
hopefully i'll remember that the time is
11 not 12 tomorrow
uh to do the next round of debugging
hope to see you back here for that
until then have fun programming everyone
and i'll see you on the internet take it
easy everybody