hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hair I sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we would like to we would
like to further debug and test our work
from yesterday today and that's gonna be
good because as we get everything that
we worked on for the past couple
weekends up and running for real it will
mean that we can work with our art
assets now in a lot of ways that we
couldn't really work with them before
like it will open up the ability for us
to put a lot more art into the game than
we've been able to in the past and
that's really fun because it allows us
to you know just dress up the world in a
lot of ways that makes it feel nicer I
mean at the end of the day the thing
that makes a video game a video game and
not a board game is that you've got all
this audio-visual stuff that you know
reacts to you and is instantaneous and
stuff and and feels you know very
immersive and so you know the art and
the sound and the music and all of those
things coming together is is not just
set dressing you know people like to
harp on gameplay and say that gameplay
is always the thing you really have to
care about and you know it's not it's
not wrong meaning you know gameplay is
very important because that's what gives
the game its longevity it's what it
allows a game to really be more than
just something you do for 10 minutes but
without that solid presentation and feel
a game really isn't you know it's it's
nothing really right because that's why
you're playing a video game instead of
something else if you want that
continuous audiovisual feedback that's
part of the immersion part of the game
and so it's always really rewarding well
when you get to spend time integrating
assets that you have into the game
because it's what makes it start turning
into a real immersive experience as
opposed to just like a tech demo or a
prototype you know that just kind of
feels sparse
and bare bones so you know it's usually
a pretty rewarding thing to do so I
think we'll have a lot of fun doing it
and and yeah I instead of just just
talking about it let's let's get started
here so I'm gonna open up handmade Hiro
on the pre stream I think it was was it
who was it said Oh frosty ninja frosty
ninja boy brought up the fact that we
didn't quite finish typing the stuff we
should have typed in yesterday and you
know that makes sense we ended the
stream kind of right in the middle when
we had literally just finished up and we
hadn't really gotten a chance to to
validate anything other than just going
up it sort of seems to work what we need
to do he pointed out is I added this
this this flag consumed semicolon to
make sure that the the system would know
not to try to eat a semicolon a second
time right but we never actually said it
so here where we do consume semicolon
when we actually eat that semicolon we
want it to say that we did consume the
semicolon right so here's an idea
another a different idea to we could do
instead of setting consume semicolon one
thing I was thinking is we could make a
thing called semicolon which is a you
know something like this and what I
could do is make it so that instead of
setting consume semicolon you just
consume the semicolon into the semicolon
token right like so and then here
instead of checking that and using a new
one it could say just look I you know if
you haven't gotten a semicolon token
right so if this hasn't actually
happened I don't know if we've got one
for tokens yet but I can certainly make
one in the tokenizer so you could see
here like right when we've got these
different functions I might just add one
for you know much like token equals I'll
do it like is valid
and that's just something that will say
hey does this token actually have any
text in it you know something like this
I assume we've got one for buffers I
don't know if we do or not Wow we don't
even have one for buffers what what the
hey what the hey how's that possible so
basically just something that will check
that I'll probably add this for
references I would like this for buffers
as well that way we don't have to have a
separate boolean that's maybe a little
bit easy to mess up like I did where we
just don't set it or something if we
just remember look if you're gonna
consume this cynical and put it into
semicolon and that way you know it'll
automatically trigger on the way out
that would be pretty good so that was
one thing the other thing that was
mentioned is checking the HTTP out hht
out multiple times I don't actually
remember where that where they were
suggesting that is because we have more
than one I guess I don't know where that
is exactly I'm not seeing that oh here's
one okay so it's the second time we loop
through so on here this is just checking
this again for no reason that's not
really a bug it's just stupid right
because if we if this was true by the
time we get here it can't have become
false because we literally don't do
anything that has anything to do with
hht out being set or unset right so if
it's set there it's gonna be set here
because it's set to its it's valid or
not for a whole pass through the code it
doesn't oscillate right so we don't need
to check it per time obviously so I
think that's the only two things there
so we kind of need to make sure as well
that the loading of these alignment
points actually works I don't think
we've checked that at all because we
don't actually have to do any rebuilds
here like imports you know what I mean
so loading something in from the drive
and wiping out what we currently have
set we don't really have any way to do
that currently so we should have that
and test that as well as delete our
files entirely and rebuild the H HDS and
make sure that that also produces NH HT
with all the right alignment points set
so we kind of want to do both those
things I think I'll start with the
in-game editor part where we don't
really have at the moment anyway to do
that called reload so let's take a look
at that in here we've got two buttons
there's an import button that does
synchronize asset file changes and we've
got a important Save button that does
synchronize asset changes as well it
just does it through this call which is
something separate meaning it first does
a look at our undo list and stuff so
those two things
looking at these here the names are a
little bit hard to describe I think we
want like something like import hht
changes and save to hhd something like
that I don't really know how to describe
it particularly well but it's something
like that and in here you know when we
test this this this is not supposed to
be on is dirty anymore because pretty
much you always want to do it when we do
save H HTS again we we really want these
available at all times because we don't
actually we'll never really know like
before we did it there was an is dirty
thing revert makes sense because that
doesn't actually touch the HTS at all so
if we haven't made any changes revert
doesn't need to be active but reload and
save H HTS are things that we might want
to do at any time because they happen to
be things that if the h HT changed on
disk we may want to use or you know
merge like so we kind of want that
ability to be available at all times and
again it's a little squeaky and we may
like sort of decide at the end of the
day that we want to make a cleaner idea
of what loading and saving means because
it's kind of a little bit confusing
right now since we always process the h
HT file whether we're loading or saving
because one like does the reinsertion
and one does the actual like importing
of art assets and they're sort of both
happening at the same time now so some
stuff like that is a little bit hard and
you know again we could make those a lot
more delineated right so we could have
one that's like save these alignment
points out to the h HT and one that's
load the alignment points in from the
hht as separate things and import new
bitmaps as another option because when
we're doing the parsing we have the
ability to just not do things like we
could just say look if the users not
asked us to do this particular type of
operation don't do it now when we're you
know when we're processing this hhd so
you know I don't know so there's there's
stuff like that and I'm not sure exactly
how we won't do how we want to deal with
it but that's how it goes wait so I
thought I enabled both of these and
change that did I not I probably didn't
get a successful build here I didn't so
let's take a look at what we're what
we're looking at here oh right so I need
the is valid to be to I need to actually
write those for the buffers and I need
to actually post these so this is valid
here wants to come up as something that
you as something that you can call token
just to find that everywhere and then if
I go over to where these buffers are
defined this right here I probably want
something in here as well so if I go
dopes I actually want to create a new in
there so this is the the types file and
I don't really know I don't really know
the most appropriate place to put those
but I thought we had a like a helper or
shared yeah I assumed the best place to
put something like an is valid for a
buffer would be in here because this is
where a lot of those kinds of questions
get asked but I guess I don't really
know I feel like this is probably the
best place for it because we don't
really have a dedicated place for buffer
operations
maybe we should we just at the moment
don't and so again that's something that
you know I'm not gonna think too hard
about at the moment but you know in the
future we might do some cleanup where we
decide to you know regularize some of
these things a little bit more
dramatically alright so I'm gonna do an
is valid
call here on this buffer that's just a
you know a check to see is the buffer
count greater than zero if it is it's
got data in it if it's not that it
doesn't so that's a pretty easy way for
us to determine whether or not it's
valid as far as the tokenized is
concerned you know I was thinking I was
gonna call this I want that call
regardless but I think maybe there's
actually better way to do this because
tokens star type it means that if you've
got a token of zero length you could
still technically it could be valid like
end of stream that's technically a valid
token that has just nothing in it so I
think the better way to do this would
probably be to say look that's what it
would you know if token type is unknown
then it's invalid but anything else
right would be valid that seems a little
bit better to me because it just it has
that flavor of allowing this one extra
case that really could happen sometimes
I doubt it would really come up in
practice much but you know it could and
I don't really want to like leave a
little surprise for myself there that
that ruins our day sometime in the
future so anyway let me go ahead and
[Music]
give this a shot here if we look at the
yeah okay if we look at the editor
buttons now you can see we've got reload
and save here so what I'd like to do is
I'm gonna hit reload hht to just see
what happens
right because I have no idea if I click
on that does anything bad happen right
and it doesn't look like it does at the
moment which is a good sign and so I
don't know you know maybe we're okay
maybe we're not we have some work to do
so we could we'd like to be able to see
general errors in here a little bit
better so that's something we probably
want to look at a little bit in the
future as well but let's now try a
slightly more involved test which is
just to get rid of the data files all
together and see if they can be rebuilt
properly so I'm gonna go ahead and build
in release mode also for a little while
till we actually want to step in and
look at some
thing because that just makes things a
lot easier on us since everything's
faster so I'm gonna go in here and I'm
just gonna delete base game HHA and I'm
gonna delete intro cutscene HHA so that
those are just gone and then I'm gonna
go ahead and run the game and I'm gonna
let it try to rebuild its art assets
from scratch and see if it can do it or
if it just fails right and so we're
gonna try that see how that does and
then when I think I'd like to do is go
add a thing that just dumps all the
errors from all the files that are
currently being that that we have on
like I don't know how to say this dump
all the errors that currently exist and
see what happens okay so you can see we
we do have a bug right it's not quite
working yet because deleting the file
and making it rebuild the alignment
points it didn't get the alignment point
right there's no it's not there right
and so we don't really know where that
error is coming from right we don't have
a real way to look at that now again we
have a lot more information than we're
getting here too because like every one
of these things has an error log on it
but we can't see error logs for things
that aren't on the screen right because
we can't select them or anything so that
makes it pretty hard to use and so again
what I would like to do here is I'd like
to have some way of showing all of the
errors that happened in the file in some
way that makes it clear what's going on
right and so that because for all we
know there's like some good error
messages being produced by our parser
that that tell us exactly what's not
working and we're just never gonna see
them so we would like some way of
displaying that error information in a
way that actually makes it easy to see
if we go backwards a little bit and say
let's take a look at for example the
asset system
where are those things getting stored
what you can see here is inside asset
source file there's actually a stream
for errors that's written here and you
know that stream is a self-contained air
stream it just gets dumped too and grows
so I feel like if we wanted to we could
just go through here and show these
errors directly and we would be able to
to just list those for all the source
files that we've got pretty much at all
times I think that would work the only
thing that I don't necessarily know is
are we actually properly tracking that
using the error stuff that we've got so
let's first make sure that the errors
are actually getting attached to those
source files in some way and then we'll
move on from there so if you take a look
here we don't actually open up the
tokenizer when we first do synchronize
what we actually do is we wait to get to
parse hht and then we open up the
tokenizer right and if we look at what
we're doing with the tokenizer here you
can kind of see that the error context I
think is never actually getting set so
if we actually go to the tokenizer in
here you can see there is an error
stream it's never actually getting used
so if we come back and look you can see
that there's really no error stream even
being mentioned right so into the asset
errors we do pack all of the errors that
we got for that file into the asset that
that we're actually exporting at any
given time but we're not actually doing
anything with the with the error stream
in terms of saving it in memory like we
said we were going to do right and so we
really need some way of doing that sort
of a thing like we need some way of
putting those errors into we need we
need something here that will allow us
to take those errors and and make them
work make them be tracked
across the tokenizer and into something
we can display so I'm not sure how we
want to do that there's many ways we
could do that I also am not sure about
storing the errors into the file like
we're doing now whether we actually care
about doing that or not it seems like
maybe that doesn't actually need to
happen and we probably don't really need
to worry too much about doing that I'm
not sure I mean maybe we should be doing
that I'm not sure but I think a more
interesting way to do this would just be
to say look when you do an import we'll
just take that Airstream and now we can
just show the entire Airstream as
something that can be displayed on the
you know on like the readout of our say
the the editor panel I guess we can just
take the Airstream
the last time you did an operation it'll
just show that Airstream that seems
reasonable to me right and I don't know
that we really need to do much else
right so if for example I came in here
and said all right let's suppose that
the context has an Airstream on it so
there's like you know something like
this and then here we would just do like
all right the Airstream is gonna be
something and we'll set it here right
then any time we create one of these
tokenizer x' so when we call parse hht
like this I'm just gonna say alright
from there we'll just set the the
tokenizer x' Airstream to be you know
the airstream that comes in from the
context that way whenever we have an
error it'll now get piped in there and
now I'll just hopefully let us you know
do something more productive with those
so then any time we do this I would say
well that probably should just be like
this right and these buffer these
starters these streams you can see how
these work we've got the ability to disc
our
stream you know total size that sort of
stuff
what I think I'd like to do is just
allow these things to have like their
own ability to grow this Airstream and
that's pretty easy to do because it's
got a memory arena right and so I think
I should be able to just create one of
these streams with the memory arena and
just clear the memory arena every time
I'm about to do something so for example
in this case what I could do is say
every time we go to do one of these
things right we're gonna reset it so the
assets Airstream is just gonna be an
on-demand memory stream of assets like
Airstream memory like so and the way
that that's going to work is the assets
era stream memory is gonna just get
cleared so we'll start off right excuse
me um
we'll start off with era Stream memory
clear and then we'll put everything into
it and then the next time we do a
synchronized will clear it again that
way we always have an Airstream that's
available for us to display if you never
use it
it won't take up any memory so it
shouldn't be a problem and off you would
go the asset source file currently keeps
these per file I don't know that we
really want that for any purpose so I
may just pull that feature out entirely
it just doesn't seem particularly useful
so here is our or stream memory and here
is our error stream I think that's all
we would really need to do assuming
these are cleared to zero at this the
outset which I believe we do but don't
quote me on that although I guess this
memory is allocated from the zero clear
pool so it proud
would be fine so yeah let me take a look
here yeah so I think this would be fine
and we would end up with a nice clear
stream at the start and then anytime you
do an export of any kind or an import
you would get errors piped to that
stream now if I go into the editor we
already have a thing that displays the
errors for from like individual files I
don't really remember where we did that
but we did have it isn't there another
file besides in-game editor maybe there
isn't
anyway an update and render editor we
should be able to track this down so at
its the asset editor that was doing it
in the asset editor the bla bla bla bla
bla here we go so we've got this
annotation label here that says errors
and that's kind of crappy like that
label F I don't think would even do line
feeds properly so we're probably gonna
have to do a little bit of work here to
actually make this thing work but that's
okay so if we were to actually do this
thing here a little bit more coherently
we're gonna need some way of like
dumping a stream out right but that's
okay right again not that hard so let's
go ahead and make that happen so instead
of like annotation label there I don't
know where where are we right now in
this file so in-game editor
actually has all that just built in
alright so when we do like annotation
label we need something where we can
actually display the whole stream in
there so when we call asset editor I
think probably right here for the HHA
bit that's probably where we would put
it so like right here
would want to look through that stream
so you know we've got assets Airstream
and this is what the thing that we're
gonna actually want to loop over if I
look at what a stream looks like you can
see that it's just a series of chunks
right and so if I just loop over the
chunks I should be able to print them in
order so here's a chunk I'll start with
the first one and go through them and
then each chunk has a file name line
number and a set of contents there the
file name and line number in this
particular case I don't know if the file
name and line number that are being
recorded to the stream chunk are ones
that reflect where the error came from
or whether they're ones that reflect the
actual source of the error if you look
at the tokenizer we should be able to
determine that so it looks like yeah the
file name and what we actually just
print out the whole thing so in here we
can just kind of go and imprint right
alright so you know there's a bunch of
different ways we could do this I'm
gonna go ahead and jump to the
annotation label F thing so this is how
we were printing that stuff out and you
can see that it basically just does the
formatting and then calls label so if we
actually look at what label does you can
see it calls basic text element which
does its own thing in terms of producing
a text element I don't think this ever
wraps lines or anything like that you
can see it just doing text out at and so
yeah like and it's got like the
interactions
kind of along with it and all that
nonsense so if we wanted to make this
work for what we're doing we kind of
need to do something a little bit more
direct we probably want to do something
here right where we're calling texts out
at 4:00 you know things a little bit
more specifically and you know passing
some strings
the I'm not crazy about how that's
working you know if you look it's using
care stars here which I don't love
especially because I'm assuming that
techstop doesn't actually need that like
you know right here this for loop could
have been over a number so I don't know
like I'm not thrilled with that and that
would make it harder for us to print
these things out so I kind of feel like
this wants to be upgraded a little bit
to take a length instead of a care star
right so in here where we do tech stop I
think I'm just gonna go ahead and say
let's make that happen
I might if zero this out temporarily
while I make that work I'm gonna go
ahead and hit build there all right so
let's take a look at the errors we have
context Airstream
is wrong aerostream memory that should
be an ampersand oops
and what else was it ah I see what it's
complaining about this also needs to be
an ampersand okay so that compiled just
fine and what I need to do now is just
make that change that we're it's
possible for us to pass strings to this
thing anytime we want to and so if I
just do that compile the the compiler
will guide me along there I think and if
you look at the way this code works
unfortunately yet another one of these
kind of like crappy parser things that
we just I don't know why we did this I
think someone just wanted to know what
would happen if we wanted to put stuff
in here for color syntax slurring which
I think we've literally never really
used like ever but that's okay you know
like I said not that hard to really to
fix that so if we want to fix that what
you can see here is we've got sort of an
app pointer and we want to be able to
treat it like a regular parse I can do
the same trick I did before if you want
to sort of change sudo parsing code like
this in place you can just change the
places where you're looking at those
values to refer to temporaries and those
temporaries can do the check to make
sure they don't read off the end of the
buffer and then you're pretty much done
right
it's not the most elegant way to do it
it's it's kind of it's inefficient
potentially it's hard to say that
without timing it whether it really is
all that inefficient in any particular
case but you know it's it's you you
could imagine doing a better job
certainly um but it is very simple right
it takes code that was written as if
there was a mill Terminator and turns
into code that doesn't need the null
terminator without really introducing a
whole lot of variants so it's easier to
get it working in debugged more quickly
so it's kind of a nice trick but yeah
you know isn't the best thing ever no so
if I go ahead and take the string here
and loop over it this way instead then
what I can do is like I said here we can
be a little bit more specific about
what's going on you can see the way that
this is getting processed here is at
always gets updated it's at particular
points in the code so it actuality we
don't do that we actually do this right
and that's fine so you know no biggie
and so these pieces of code all know how
far they would like to move the read
cursor along for their like pseudo
parsing right i I don't know what oh
this this is so I guess the other day I
said you know someone was asking about
utf-8 and I said we didn't support our
rig list I guess we do technically we
don't really read utf-8 but we do read
inline glyph numbering so yeah I forgot
we had that but I remember yeah that was
because we did actually we put in like
the glyph for owl or something as a test
to make sure that we were supporting you
know Unicode code points right and it
worked so that was cool
anyway ignoring that for a moment let's
keep going so yet all I want to do now
is make it easier for this code to parse
and so I kind of want like all of these
things to be there and accessible and so
to do that what I'm gonna do is again
just initialize the amount of look-ahead
that I need two zeros and then I'm just
gonna do you know something that looks
like this if you know I guess what I
would say is probably the easiest is to
say look if at index plus some number is
less than string counts then we can read
it right so if add index plus 1 is less
than string counts then I can read at
one right I know I can always read at
zero and it's just gonna be this right
but if I want to read these other ones
which would look something like this if
I want to read each of those I have to
look and see you know as I go which one
of these are actually valid and this is
what would tell me right
so if I said this add index plus one if
that's less than string count then I can
read the plus one value that is all I
would need for reading all of these
right
so as long as each of those in this
indexes remains in range
I can read from it otherwise I set it to
zero and then the rest of this code like
I said it's again not the you know
there's there's better ways of writing
the code than what I did but that's the
way that does the most straightforward
transformation on a parser that was
trying to that was counting on being
able to read off you know as far as it
could without hitting a null Terminator
and stuff like that and turn it into
something that that doesn't require the
null terminator anymore it's just a
simple way to make that happen this
should be that and this should be that
anytime we had a text up here from
something that was a care star string
that should really do a string length
string like this or a oh sorry we
already have a way to do it's just a
wrap Z so that will create the string
length and go and then we can now say or
when you're doing text out at you could
just pass her regular oops a regular
string here and it'll thunk through with
the same default parameter stuff to the
the text op right and so that's a lot a
lot nicer there let's take a look here
we've got for a get text size we're
doing the sizing call again that needs
to just do a wrap Z on the string here
and the same thing would be true here
although wait shouldn't that of just oh
no nevermind
let's see what else we've got
looks like that was it actually and so
now we just need to debug it did we
break it and so on right so it looks
like that's working fine the debug
system appears to have remained intact
no issues there that I can see all right
good deal and so now that I can do that
it makes it easy for me to use the
printing you know use what we've got to
print out sections of the stream and
that's really all I wanted so you know
in here now we we can take those
individual chunks and print them out as
separate pieces I'm gonna do nothing
particularly fancy at first I'm just
gonna do in fact I can't even do this as
a label if I want to essentially so four
texts out at where we're doing yeah in
fact here if I was to do something
really weird and stupid I could actually
do it this way
right and so if I go over to how we're
doing labels you can see they take a
care star sometimes would rather again
I'd rather change these now to sort of
doing things with a you know with
strings because like I said I just we
didn't do that at a major because I was
trying to keep things simpler but really
I just hate it
and any time I ever try to write
anything with with no terminators I
always get sad and so you know I should
have I should have just have said all
right we're not doing all terminators
sorry everyone and gone with length
strings at the outset but you know I
just I just didn't so in terms of basic
textile element here I'll just do string
text so when we go forwards with that
it'll it should work we'll have to make
sure the get text size call supports it
but otherwise we're good and then
through here right I can just change it
like so this always just works with
strings because we always have the
strings so it should be pretty
straightforward right like so and yep so
like for example here you know we've got
this temp and we're doing this label F
for printing it in again really easy to
make that work you know we can have temp
string and we just do time strand count
equals this temp string data equals the
temp buffer and then you're done right
so you don't even have to look for the
size because you get it back from format
string list and off you go
looking here basic text elements this
again should just be taking a string
there again button F same field that's
just going to do a temp string
and you're done
same thing here and here so again just
kind of propagating that change through
looks like we got a couple other ones
that get text size I should also just
make one for that so get text size right
you can call it a couple different ways
but yeah that's the wrap C version so
you just need a version without that and
again I really probably just don't even
want those the the null-terminated
versions eventually i would just get rid
of those entirely but since you know i
don't want to go doing large changes
right now for no particular reason i'm
just gonna change it in the editor and
leave it that way let's see that's that
this is this and
that all looks fine so all I need to do
here is just say look these are gonna be
six do we have there it is constantly
I'm like do we have a way of wrapping
one of these things I think we do and we
did so yeah can't see is all we need to
do to turn one of those into a proper
string I'm not sure what is button is
complaining about here it's
it's the void star classifier that's
having a problem with so that classifier
that it needs there it can't pass the
string because the string is not a
pointer obviously right but it can pass
the data of the string just fine so for
classifiers
that's totally easy as well and there we
go so I think that's all good
this again is the temp temp and temp
that's all fine all of these are just
constants ease now you just have to I'm
sorry
well I guess they're wrap see current
currently see what we've got here so you
can't actually pass this because C is
stupid so this would be a wrap Z sort of
I mean you could put it outside and not
do it that way but yeah so I don't know
exactly how we would want to do that
wrapping probably actually want to have
a separate builder so you know basically
this something where we can say that so
that we can actually pass the count
directly so you know I would often call
this like bundle string or something and
then you define some macro bits like
well if you know what you're going to be
putting in here you can just say you can
just pass these two things to it like
that right
so you still can
avoid doing work you can make these
things be packed correctly and so I'll
again it's just annoying because since
since C is so crappy and C++ what you
would want to do is have something where
you could just say that your strings are
always these kind of strings I feel like
they were gonna add that to C++ 20 20 or
whatever I'm sure they screwed it up and
it's terrible because they always do but
they were gonna have you know strings
where you could finally say you know
here's what I mean when I say a string
revolutionary idea I know but I don't
know if they ever got around to it
I'm sure it's real great if they did but
you know you can imagine in the same
language you would just say look here's
what a string evaluates to it's not null
terminated anymore it's gonna be the the
data with a count in front of it as this
lay out you know and then that's what
we're talking about from now on that
would be how a sane language would work
right because why why would a programmer
want you to predefined what a string
looks like it doesn't make any sense
right but that's you know how people
still think for some reason so anyway
moving on let me just finish this port
here
and one more it's like two more probably
have a utility function for this you can
see how many times you have to do this
little shuffle it's just a little bit
hard to do the there's some there's not
a lot of logic to it so it's not it's
not that easy and C to write the thing
that actually does what you want here
any more brief than that
sadly all right so let's see what else
we got a bundle string can I convert
from you it took care star that's fine
there we go
and what is the problem I was a little
overzealous there I admit that it's
edible P X did we not make this take a
string we do not I could not so label
texts is there this is a bundle yeah
again just busy work at this point doing
the conversion there's really nothing to
it all right
just a few more here to go so these guys
again are just these are just everyone's
taking a string properly sized string
there and like I said because it's
stupid
you can't just define your language when
you start to tell you that you wanted a
length string and not a null terminator
string military no strings being pretty
much the worst way to store strings but
they're not only the default and see
they're actually the only way so you
have to insert your own code to deal
with it which is not fabulous and like I
said I don't actually know if they ever
really did fix that I thought they were
gonna at some point I seem to recall
seeing something but don't quote me on
that
all right and so if we took a look over
at format string you can also see like
the way that it works we could have made
you know we definitely could make one
that returns a string and maybe that's
something we should do going forward
because that's just now that we're sort
of I'm in for a penny in for a pound on
that I'll probably want to just go the
whole way and make sure that the whole
thing works that way in the future but
we'll see
so these are what's the problem
editable pxy
still taking this fix that and keep
going editable type editable type looks
like it takes strings what's the problem
label text ah so this just wants to be
like not a string right but that's fine
and the label is calling get name a
debug state in the tenth name so get
name returns a care star which is fine
but we can just wrap that right you can
see pretty much in all these cases it
would know what it is I'll make it not
do that at the moment well maybe I'll
just have it wrap it on the outside like
really that thing should just return a
string but I probably won't do that
and so if we want to bundle this one
then we can do that in place as well
what else we got here
these are just for our profile and stuff
like that again these are just directly
bundle Bowl so it's like other profiler
stuff and
all right and I think we're done that
was more than I wanted to do but just
make sure everything's kind of working
so at the moment we have to go back and
check now to make sure we didn't break
everything converting everything the
strings because we may well have at
least all that stuff is working okay we
can look at the profiler seems like
that's working okay so I you know it
it's a pretty straightforward change but
you know we could have slipped up
somewhere certainly so let's go ahead
and and now put in display the trunk
content so if I look at the label call
it just needs a layout and then a string
I think that is all we really need there
and now we should be able to see those
errors each time as we go so when we run
the code now we should be able to see
all of the errors and you know here they
are so we know that we've got a bunch of
crap happening that's bad and we should
start by eliminating those and this is
exactly why I wanted to do this so you
can see our parsers hopefully pretty
good here where it tells us like exactly
where we need to look it's a real you
know parser with actual information in
it this printouts not particularly good
it's not even scrollable and it doesn't
really assemble strings properly so we
probably want to do a little work on
that too eventually but at the moment
this gives us what we want so it's
totally fine
if we were going to be the types of
people who do things unnecessarily we
could also be funny about this since we
did the work I'm gonna demand that we
actually use it and say that because we
did like the color stuff we should
actually put something in there like
just to see if this works
cuz I'd forgotten about that yeah um so
like you know we've got the syntax
colouring um so anyway 3517 in bass game
let's load it up and see what we're
screwing up so in base game h HT h HT
what was at 35 can't remember 37 what
did it say I read it and then I forgot
what it said 35 17 so this comma is bad
is that right
so it's f3 I remember too I wonder it so
this is this wrong did we screw up the
the line number because there isn't one
of those on on that line I'm base game
35 right so I think we're gonna have to
do some bugging there right cuz this is
line 35 and it looks like it's
complaining about something else unless
you know where I guess we could be off
it's hard to say like I mean you would
think it's probably complaining about
this line because this is the line
that's being parsed weirdly right this
is the new thing that we we added and so
if you look at what's going on there
this is 35 it really means this so 1 2 3
4 5 6 1 2 3 4 5 6 it's not exactly the
size of the comments I'm not sure who's
who's getting that wrong so let's take a
look at our tokenizer because we wanted
to bug this part of it like I said we'd
like it to be accurate because it just
speeds up our ability to find the errors
when we do the tokens we just set them
to be whatever the tokenizer thinks at
the moment that that thing should be so
in here when we do get token raw
[Music]
it looks like anytime we see and is
end-of-line we do do a plus plus
tokenizer line number so I'm not sure
why we would be having a problem with
that because seems like that should be
pretty accurate but do we actually track
it inside the comma comment
we don't so that looks like the primary
problem we just aren't tracking line
numbers through compound comments so in
here we would have to do this we would
have to do this every time when we look
and see if we've got an is end of line
situation presenting itself so you know
something like this would actually have
to occur every time so we would need
here to say something like look if
tokenize are at zero if we have either
of those new line conditions occurring
we need to go an extra one so we don't
over count the line number right and
then we need to actually advance what I
could do to there is just do it like
this
so that would allow me to like look any
time we see one of these things we'll
skip it if it's a double we'll skip one
ahead and then we'll just check any time
we see an end of line character we'll
make sure we track that as a line member
increment so that may have been our only
book because we were pretty accurate
otherwise so it's like we were skipping
the comment and hey lo and behold that's
exactly what we were doing so looking in
here you can see change now 41 let's see
if that's any more accurate and correct
all right so now our line number
tracking is accurate you can see that
it's upset about this curly brace so it
says it's unexpected which means it was
trying to it was trying to get something
else in its place and we should try and
figure out what that thing is also now I
think about it when you look at this
error message it says unexpected token
type is that actually the best error
message that we could be giving there
because if that's actually coming from
require token instead of saying
unexpected token type what we probably
should say is you know unexpected token
type you know expected something else
right like whatever it is that we
actually expected now the tough part
about that is that token type I don't
know that we have any way of actually
outputting what the token type is so
like if you look we don't have a string
for any of these token types but I'm
willing to go the extra mile there and
say look let's actually put that in here
so let's do a table in the way that
supercilious makes you do because it's
horrible and shouldn't be doing
automatically if we said get a token
name and say type name and we said token
type pass me the type and then you know
we'll just do a switch statements on the
type and have a case for each of these
that returns a string so that's what we
would do in this case and I'm gonna go
ahead and and do it we've got open paren
close paren colon semicolon asterisk
open bracket oops
closed bracket brace close brace and
equals four pound string identifier
number spacing oops
spacing and end of line comment this
game so now I just need to give those
things some names and a lot of them are
pretty simple right
it's weird like open parentheses in
closed parentheses for something that we
have to say so often it's such a
horrible phrase I guess we should just
rename them to paren period like there
is no word parentheses anymore we will
never use it again so now what I could
do is actually make that require token
printout something more useful so when
it says unexpected token type it can say
like I actually expected this other
thing right and so that's pretty handy
because now when we look at those error
messages it'll give us a little bit more
information about what we actually want
so you can see here now we got this but
it was expecting to see the actual
number there and so if we go into the
code where that's actually happening we
should be able to see that we got our
our tokens stuff wrong and off we go so
you can see it's pretty obvious right we
had an equals and we we just never have
those enclosures so what I would say is
we aren't using enclosure anywhere else
so I think maybe that's actually just
because this is wrong and it should just
be that so I think maybe our parsers
actually correct and really what we
should be doing is is none of that
so that may just be a case of our parser
being right and our output being wrong
and that's what it actually should look
like right so I deleted that here and so
now if I recompile let's see what we get
for error messages now so now it's
actually running the import it looks
like so that must have been the that
must have been the errors that were
stopping us from really taking the time
to import more stuff we're probably just
importing just down to there and
stopping and this is great so it looks
like it worked exactly right because now
we've got we've actually got those
reloaded and they're correct so that
certainly seems like now we can rely on
those H HTS to be reasonable and
actually have the data we expect so the
next question is you know we did look
and see you know there's our there's our
stuff that we've reproduced looking at
I'm gonna close this looking at the
signs as they look about right now you
can see it doesn't update the size till
after the file handles get closed um the
only thing I'm wondering about is you
know let's take a look at what happens
we rewrite those Haq T's again so here's
our tags and I'm gonna go ahead and copy
base gamedev hht to base game backup and
overwrite it and what I'm going to do
now is force it to resave that file so
I'm gonna go ahead and say save hht s
here and then
close it and what I want to see is did
it change the file at all right did
anything happen so I'm going to load
milled and I'm gonna ask it to do that
diff just to see what it comes up with
so if I go into handmade and I put
inside the tags directory I say here's
the old one here's the new one give me
the comparison and see what it finds
there's nothing that's what I hope for
so now let's go in and try something a
little more audacious here so if I was
to select one of these guys and say all
right here's let's edit the tags on this
thing so here's the the default base on
this guy you know I don't where is it
though I don't actually see this why
don't I see it
that's a little weird right hmm so we've
got some kind of a bug there even though
this looks correct like it's a default
alignment point and the sprite is there
there it is
for whatever reason no matter what I do
I don't actually see oh just because the
head was just too large to see weird all
right so anyway let's let's see what we
can do here so if I go ahead and and
start by trying to edit these guys a
little bit down I'm gonna add the base
of neck point I think that's how these
guys snap together it's top of head
snaps no it's just default
I guess there's and this goes to the
parent right so anyway yeah the
alignment point on this dude and the
alignment point on this dude are
supposed to line up so if I set the
basis neck it's that green point it
would go like something like right there
right and then if I set the default
point on this it would go something like
right there and so I think everything's
fine right and then the fact that that
sticks into the ground is something that
we're gonna have to now look at because
we want to actually make our sprites
have the correct Z bias to prevent that
from happening right but it does look
like that's pretty straightforward
I think we need a better way I think we
need to be able to turn off temporarily
some of this stuff because it's hard to
see when you win everything stacked on
top of each other we would like to be
able to look at the points in isolation
little bit better so I think we want
something that says you know don't draw
you know when I turn this off don't draw
the things that are attached to it
suppose there's an easy way to do that I
can just set it to default right and so
then as I as I set this you know I can
set my my ground point which is
somewhere like there and then I can set
my my attachment point which is you know
somewhere like like there and then I can
turn this back but that's a little bit
of a janky way to do that so I don't
know you know we'll see
so anyway if I was to set all of these
so the hero would be proper now what
would we get oh and you know what that's
the wrong direction to that's so if I
push the right direction
I'm getting this if I push the left
direction I'm getting that so the head
looks like it's also incorrectly coming
in there so the fist is correctly
updating the direction and I think the
body is too but the head isn't do we
have a bug in our head import code or is
that just wrong in the file let me take
a look
so here's the oops sources directory for
bass game here's everything that comes
into the base game the art files here
and so if we look at these we've got the
head hero is what we're looking for
they'll load that up
so here is the hero head it's oh so it's
just wrong so the files wrong not us
looks like and so if I go in here and
and look at that what you could see is
that if I were to open a different head
file so if I were to go load like head
orphan a one for example you can see
it's it's supposed to be right up left
down so this is actually just backwards
so we just need that art file to be
fixed I'll make a note of that so we can
get updated art files which we're gonna
want to do at some point here anyway let
me go ahead and just put that in here
and we can deal with that later okay so
that's good that's not our fault so we
don't really have to belabor that any
longer that'll just be an art file
update that will fix it and so the rest
of the stuff we should be able to do now
- if we wanted to so for example well
you know what let's not push our luck
I'm gonna hit save HH tees and now I'm
gonna see whether or not that actually
worked so if I go over to meld and i
refresh it I should have gotten some
updates although it doesn't look like I
did all right so we so we are still
screwed up a little bit here am I am I
wrong meaning we we did not see these
files change and these files should have
changed so what so we're gonna have to
step through that code path and see why
we're not updating a little lineman
points there in that case I guess is
what should have happened did we even
rewrite the file or maybe I maybe those
buttons don't work so we didn't even
rewrite the file so it looks like those
buttons aren't quite hooked up the way I
would expect so let's take a look so
when you hit save all changes which i
think is what would happen there yeah so
when you hit save all changes it should
call synchronized asset file changes
which when passed true will would do
save changes to HST so that should
happen I would also like let's also make
this be a little bit more explicit here
like some kind of positive confirmation
that we saved the thing out
we basically need some way of getting
like a time or something
so I don't really have any good way to
mark this but you know what I'm saying
right like I want to be able to do
something like this so that we can
actually know that we wrote something
like the time and then we say later
something else right so yeah not quite
what I would have hoped for I really
don't know what to put in there I guess
for now I could do something stupid like
this and maybe in here we could have you
know some kind of thing that we
temporarily I don't know I'm just making
this up and that way every time we save
it will give us positive confirmation
that we actually did save you know what
I mean
that seems like a good idea
so in here when we do Save Changes to H
HTS maybe I can you know and you know
what I could do to is like this so right
now this is just a really crude way of
me making sure that I know when I click
that button that it actually did what I
think it did
so that we can start debugging it so
yeah when I come through here and you
know it told me it loaded there's no
errors which is good I do save it did
save right and so I want to know now why
I'm not getting any meld ifs there let
me actually reload that don't know why I
got rid of that it would be nice if it
remembered what my previous ones were
doesn't have a recent menu does it there
we go
so I'd like to know what's going on with
this and why it's not receiving those
things if I go through here to you know
one of these things for the alignment
points let me just go ahead and and do
sort of similar operation to what I did
before right I'll just moving this
around like that or something so now I
want that to save I hit save and it's
not saving oh wait
that's not true we just don't increment
that number so there we go
so yeah for some reason that's not doing
anything and we want to step through
there and now find out why we're not
getting those updates that we had gotten
before
so something weird is happening where
it's not actually updating the alignment
points the way that we would expect
now in the code where that's happening
it is a bit subtle right because the way
this works is it's actually doing a diff
like this to see if the memory is equal
or not between what we read in and you
know yeah well what we read in what we
need to output I interestingly enough
looking at the way this code works it
does we're not actually outputting the
point here which we should this should
be causing a different bug than it is I
guess it's one way to say it it should
be deleting the alignment point and not
replace you with anything but that's not
what we're actually seeing so that's
kind of weird
I do want to actually fix this bug as
well but this is not gonna actually
affect us at the moment because we have
a different bug than this right but what
I want is this code to be reusable so if
in here you say this I suppose and then
you give it an alignment point it'll
output the alignment point that way I
could just recall that in here and add
the one thing that was missing which is
after you do the ignore I want to output
the alignment point afresh right that
should have been what it was saying
before
[Music]
and off you go
so when we read one of these things in
like this we want to test to see whether
or not we should write it out or not the
only thing that I'm not sure how we want
to do here is when we read this thing in
we also have one other thing to do which
is we need to test and see whether or
not it should be deleted so if the one
we if we're writing the hhd then we want
to look to see whether this one is right
or wrong so it's basically a merge
operation we look to see if it's exactly
the same then we just use it exactly the
way the user inputted it if it's
different then we want to do is say look
is the point type actually that we have
like our point type is that valid
and and so you know this right here
actually would be the thing we would
want to look at right so if that's valid
if the memory is equal right out if it's
not what we want to do is say all right
let's let's overwrite the one that we
read with the one that we have and then
we would say if that is an actual point
out put it otherwise don't like that
right I think that's what we actually
want to say again shouldn't have been
the bug we had so something's still
wrong and I just don't know what we're
gonna need to pass the grid X grid Y and
point index here but that's pretty easy
to do for obvious reasons good X Y point
index because in both places we know
what that is
so yeah really kind of weird because you
know yes there was a bug there no that
bug is not the bug that was actually
happening the bug we're getting is
nothing happens right
so it's parsing these and deciding that
it doesn't need to change them or that
it doesn't need to insert any so for
example it's it's getting here and it
doesn't have any unprocessed right so
it's like you never set this or
something yeah so I don't know so we're
gonna have to debug that let me just run
it one more time and get the current
state now that I've changed the code of
of what the bug man if it's so fast and
with that but then we gotta fix that
right I figure out what's going on there
so if I come through here and should
really change the way this works to and
tweak this right so you know I've set
this to something totally different
both of these are you know totally
different now and I asked to save it it
saves and you know let's see what we got
so not sure what to make of that so
fixing that other problem appears to
have actually changed it which I don't
know why it would have because that
wasn't really the bug that I was seeing
so I'm not sure what's going on there
makes me a little bit nervous I will
also say for some reason we're getting
extra whitespace in here I think that's
because we're not sort of eating up that
whitespace it's getting doubly copied in
so if we look at the the code here that
that copies that out we should probably
do is when we do this this output point
here we should probably say look since
there was already going to be whitespace
after the semicolon if the user wanted
it
we should not output whitespace
ourselves and so the only time we should
actually output whitespace in either
case I suppose is also I guess is it
should also be further over yeah that
should be actually something that's
controlled by insertion only so in the
places where we go to output these like
this here's where we would actually do
that something like that right okay so
let me close this let's save this in
here I'm gonna go ahead and and re save
the original and so now we should be
identical again and I'm gonna run the
same test where I go in here and let's
grab this dude and and mess with this a
little bit and then I'm gonna go here
and hit save HH tees didn't get any
errors and so now if I come over here we
get files identical right so again bug
is back so what's going on there right
why is it that something like why did it
work last time and not work this time
right that's very confusing and I'm not
sure what's going on there it doesn't
make a whole lot of sense to me
similarly if I reload it looks like it
snapped back so we we can actually
verify that you know it's not just some
kind of weird other situation it is
actually oh not updating the HH tees
with my changes
all right so let's go in there and find
out what's going on I'm gonna go do this
in debug mode and step into that code I
wonder can I just switch to debug mode
directly so if I do this I've changed
those values right
if I now rebuild the code in debug mode
so I just say look the build it's debug
now thank you can I and like the frame
rate slows back down again Network Oh
I had compiled error there
so what did I do wrong
[Music]
aha much better
all right sorry about that I
accidentally yeah one of the problems of
using this interim build a for coder
that is it doesn't make it easy to know
whether you've got errors all right so
let's say if the h h T's again and see
what happens
there's my save h HT let's look at here
so that time it actually did work I
don't understand how we're getting that
bug though it doesn't make any sense
how is it that it works sometimes and
not other times doesn't really make a
lot of sense I'm still nervous we just
have a bug like why did that work let's
try it fresh again because I'm just
trustful I'm very distrustful now with
that so if I do reload oh cool yeah out
of tag space that makes sense too that's
a bug we'll have to fix I'm just
trustful now I feel like that's kind of
buggy but all right you know whatever so
let's double check and see what's going
on here if I grab one of these now and
change it around
so yeah it definitely didn't save it
right because that should have produced
a difference so it's almost like the
first time you save it it doesn't do
anything in the second time it does or
something weird like this right so now
it's actually updated to be what I said
so it's kind of but it's kind of busted
we're not quite there yet right I
thought we were sort of there but we're
not quite there because something weird
is happening with the way that we're
merging these and to be fair we're doing
something fairly complicated here
probably we shouldn't have done but it
was just an experiment to see if it
would work and it kind of does so it's
not like we're completely failing but
we're just not doing a very good job so
for some reason we're not able to
actually get a reliable change occurring
there when we go through and process
these HH T's and we're supposed to be
saving them out we're going through here
and we're getting to the point where we
should be triggering this memory is
equal false case so in here and we
should be calling this out point every
time but for some reason that doesn't
seem to happen and I don't know why
right so this is the H HT and you know
if I go ahead and and overwrite the one
that we've got right so now they're
identical I run it I select one of these
pieces here I modify it somehow right I
go back and I hit save and that first
time it definitely doesn't save right I
click it again nothing
so it seems like there's some kinda like
uninitialized variable or just ran up
thinking it right because I didn't touch
anything but I saved the thing like a
couple times and then this time it works
right so if something super weird is
going on there and I have no idea what
it is
and so we're gonna have to drill down to
find out what's the you know what's the
magic they're like what's causing this
to occasionally work properly in other
times not right and we're printing out
the errors so we're also not getting any
errors there as far as I can tell
meaning it's not like something
sporadically failing like like rewriting
the file or something which would be a
pretty reasonable thing to assume so I
don't know what we probably should do is
but we're not you know it could be that
this is airing out we just don't know so
that might be something to try as well
right
so I'm gonna go ahead and add a little
bit more verbose stuff there and see
what happens I'm gonna look at write
modifications to AJ as well I just want
to see what goes on there so that just
calls a bunch of write data to file that
part seems to be fine it's really the
hht that's the problem so I'm gonna put
an F in here
might do this as well so this way I'll
say look when we actually produce the
final versions thing I'm going to go
ahead and look and see if the changes
need to be written back then I will I
will do that if not I'll say so when we
go to replace a file if it replaces the
file I'll say we're done otherwise I'll
say that it failed that will just give
me slightly more information so I make
sure that I'm debugging the correct case
and not actually looking at pieces of
code that have nothing to do with the
error right so I'm going to go back to
the hht here and once again overwrite it
so that we get back to the known bad
case that seems to be failing a lot so
it should be easier to debug hopefully
I'm gonna refresh this worked right -
there we go
I wonder if meld is just bad that could
be as well let's find out that would be
depressing um I'm gonna assume it's us
but you never do know all right so we
rebuilt and now I'm gonna run and I'm
gonna go in here and just well you know
what let me save first no changes hmm
so that's
oh right because there's 2h h DS so let
me actually be more specific - well when
we say that there was no changes in the
import I'm gonna go ahead and actually
say who write so in here we'll do a
printf of whatever the what was the file
name so looking for that don't actually
know what it was
so in here when we've got the HH tees
hmm so I guess we don't really a store
that though well we do kind of know in
the file info though so the platform
file info itself would actually tell us
that piece of information I think
because base names there so we could do
that that seems reasonable so I could
just say yeah when you update this here
file info base name will say what was
supposed to add in there
right
uh so maybe we play with the color stuff
because why not and and there we go all
right let's see what's up
oops again let's see what we're getting
from our readout there and whether or
not it makes sense
so it did not like something in this
stream the percent s perhaps I'm not
sure
it's trying to take the length
of this string
but that should be fine because we're
just using base name which should always
be valid right and there shouldn't be
anything weird like there it is
so I'm not sure what what word would be
going wrong
hmm
so taking a look here at looking at the
size of the string the string that it's
getting is not valid right look looking
at out F here we've got we've got a
couple different things let's look at
the format specifier well of course it
is alright so it is a valid string
that's on there but it looks like when
it gets it it ain't valid
hmmm I'm gonna go ahead and go to debug
mode and see if I can get something a
little bit more specific there but it's
kind of a little bit weird that it's
having trouble parsing base name
I know the base names accurate because
we just looked at it it is null
terminated as far as I can tell so that
seems fine too and it should be valid
for the entire life of this function
there's nothing weird happening there
that I could think of so I'm not sure
what the problem is there it should be
totally fine to read that and yeah
III don't I don't quite see I don't
quite see it let's take a look
at least it's reliable and not transient
if we look back here now we can kind of
see what do we end up getting just just
total garbage out of the string there
which is a little bit weird am I just
doing something really stupid that I'm
missing if I pop out one where you can
see the format string percent s note
changes and the arglist seems right
[Music]
I don't get it right that seems correct
is there some sort of
let's just step through it I don't have
a better idea at the moment it's
probably just something stupid that I
have you know it's just a slow morning I
guess so if I come through here and I
look at what we're actually what it's
actually gonna go on in out F right here
we are
we passed the file name and line number
we got the destination stream there's
our format and then we're gonna look at
the argh list here
well actually no so that's wrong what
are we doing here wow that's really bad
so the one that takes the argh list is
getting called instead of the one so is
a VA list a care star pointer or
something did you see what just happened
there I don't know if if you caught that
but what just happened was it preferred
to call this when the final parameter
was a care star like that's what just
happened right so a VA list in this case
is apparently the same as a care star is
that really true
can we get some validation on that
please
where's our test project we don't have
our test project let's see I know we
made one it was called like search or
test or something right
like we had one here I just don't
remember where it went
nope
where is that we have one that we made
it was like you know just a stupid misc
project temp thing
yeah I don't know where it went I wanted
to do a search on that file you know
what I can do let me just find standard
aargh and see where it is because I
think it should be able to know that but
yeah I'm curious to know what that
actually is
so that's not interested oh my god
that is really really dangerous and not
what you should be doing that should be
a struct guys like seriously all right
now we know Wow
well that was an interesting bug not
what I was expecting to find certainly
so let's take a look here and make sure
that that was the only problem that we
were having there where is out F define
it is right here so I need to make sure
that you can't ever call those by
accident with overloading now we know
and let's try that again
lovely so now we can at least see what
we think we're writing out so we say no
changes in the case when there is no
changes and we should also now say
definitively if we try to save the thing
and there are changes you know what
those changes are so let's go ahead and
and and do that they're safe changes let
me go and ahead and pick one will you
know kind of move this around and then
I'll hit Save Changes it'll say base
game replaced so it thinks it wrote it
out and hey this time it did if I say it
again no changes so nothing nothing got
changed on disk so unfortunately now
we're at a point where I don't know if
things are actually getting changed
let's let's try again so here we'll
adjust this thing around like that or
something and then I'll hit save thinks
it replaced it all right so now it seems
to be working which is troublesome
I guess we'll leave it there for today
and we'll pick it up next weekend
because we're out of time but again it's
a little bit weird and I'm not really
sure exactly what's going on there so
I'm not I'm not psyched about that yeah
I don't really know what what we're
looking at so we'll have to we'll have
to be a little bit more specific going
forward
but that's okay we could do that next
weekend that's fine let's go to any Q&amp;A
as we have there that was a weird bug at
the end there and yeah okay V a list I
wouldn't have done that that way but
okay
Kevon be and this is why I don't use
overloading functions yeah you know
you're not wrong
wouldn't it be nice to move the old file
to a file name that back in the atomic
fireplace yeah it might be the problem
is what you do with the other file name
dot back that's there delete that I
guess you know I don't know
how awesome would it be if windy but
preview had trace diffs do you mean if
you run the program two times and then
it tells you what the IP difference was
between the two or something what's a
what's a trace diff in your world like
what do you mean frosty ninja read this
in game engine architecture by Naughty
Dog's guy I can't remember the name of
maybe I mean Jason Gregory but the you
C++ user defined literals to do compile
time hashes on strings at Naughty Dog we
permit runtime mashing of strings but we
also use C++ 11s user-defined literals
feature to transform the cindex any
string underscore s ID directly into a
half integer value at compile time that
seems good I mean I guess you have a
problem which is your integers could
collide if they literally mean integers
so just to put that in perspective so if
you mean 32-bit integer that's probably
a bad idea if you mean 64-bit integer
that's probably not too bad if you mean
a 128-bit integer then yeah you're all
good 32-bit integers will start
colliding once you have you know
somewhere around 65,000 strings even if
your hash functions perfect right like
even if it's exactly what it should be
and if it's 64-bit it'll start colliding
around four billion strings and even in
a place like Navidad getting to four
billion strings seems pretty unlikely
right
so it's probably okay that's 64 bits at
128 bits of hash if the hash is actually
a high quality hash then forget it
right you're fine you will never ever no
matter how long you developer what you
do will you ever be able to collide that
unless you hit pure cosmic unfortunate
chance and if you're having that kind of
bad luck your string hash is probably
the least of your worries so yeah a 64
bit hash the string seems reasonable
right and yeah I would think that would
be fine you you can also probably
provide some error checking if you
wanted to maybe that you to prove you
didn't collide
yeah I mean it's hard to say right
what happens when require tooken fails
yeah just it's just an empty string with
a none as the type so you never really
have to check the result because
everything should just not work like if
you try to open a file it won't work
because there's no file name if you try
to match it against something it won't
match cuz there's nothing there
right so you should be able to just use
it directly as you go
off-topic just an idea and for cooter
you could do the block orientation after
exiting the insert modes of life that
has nothing to do with it the reason
that it's jumpy is because of virtual
white space is on which means that it's
always refloat there is no such thing as
not reinventing the block I ended up
turning virtual white space off I just
don't it's I tried using it I try using
it periodically and it's never quite
ready yet
and so the version I integrate in
probably next weekend
if we switch over it doesn't have
virtual workspace on at all because it's
just not ready it's still not ready
I keep trying and it still keeps not
really being ready so I think it's just
it's one of those features that's going
to require concerted effort to get ready
and maybe Alan and I will have to do
like a four code or white space jam at
some point to finally get it ready but
it will be going away entirely when I
read eight
what are your thoughts on persistent
structures like used in cloture I don't
think I know what cloture has in terms
of that like what can you describe the
feature and I could try to just say what
I would think of it because I don't
firmly err that with that off topic this
probably isn't relevant to you working
in a small so company but as you get
older in thoughts on Aging as a
programmer in a large company it seems
mini me come managers but irrespective
of large organizations teams anything
you find it really interesting about
your day to day as you get older not
particularly much other than the fact
that I think it's not a very good time
at the moment to be an older programmer
not because it not age is really not it
it's the amount of time even programming
it's not a very good time to have been
programming for you know 20 or 30 years
and the reason for that is because the
like quality of programming is that like
an all-time low and so it's just
depressing right like it's it's really
depressing to go you know like if you
even compare what it felt like to
program when I was you know seven and
eight years old or whatever right back
when I was little there were so many
really good programmers doing so many
really impressive things with what they
had you know it was a pretty great world
and you know I just remember how
impressive it would be to you know use
like when I got an Amiga 500 or
something and how crazy that operating
system was just it's nuts that they're
able to get so much out of so little and
then looking at today it's the exact
opposite like everywhere I look it's
just complete garbage you know it's like
extremely powerful hardware that barely
is able to do anything at all because
the programming is so bad and so that's
really annoying because it's you you
would you you don't tend to
to excel I don't feel like it's easier
it's hard for programmers to excel in an
environment we're literally like
anything they do is good enough and
that's kind of where we're at now
like no code that I can ever write in
handmade hero could be bad enough that
it isn't significantly better than the
stuff that I have to use when I like
open up Gmail right like there's no way
we will ever write anything on the
screen that's that bad
and that creates like a really bad
precedent and environment because it
really brings everyone's standards down
like I'm not pushed to be better every
day like I should be and neither is
anybody else because the stuff that you
are used to is so incredibly awful that
there is almost no way you can be any
worse you know another way to say it
would be the worst programming that you
can do is the average programming that
you are using like we're at the bear
we're at the bottom right and that's
really bad and I feel like that's the
most heart the hardest thing about
having program for a long time because
if you started programming today he
wouldn't know that right he wouldn't
know how bad things have gotten because
you didn't go through any time period
where things were at least somewhat
better and it's not to say that software
was somehow awesome back in the day it
wasn't but the amount that people were
able to do with what they had was just
not even it's not even comparable to
what you see you know what you see today
is just is just just terrible
[Music]
let's see
I asked the priest mystery about a sperm
you didn't enjoy and you mentioned no
speck or unrespected problem domains
often being annoying I was thinking that
may well be young man's game at least
doing at multiple producing rail
no I I've always disliked it it's it's
just it's not really an age thing
they're the reason that I kind of think
it's that way for me is I like to
accomplish new things when I'm
programming that's like really why I'm
doing it I don't really do it for other
reasons than that usually and so working
with unrespected stuff just takes it
longer to make the new thing whatever
you're trying to do it's it's just a
waste of my time if it had been Specht
properly would it wouldn't have wasted
my time right so sometimes I'm okay with
it and don't mind as much but most of
the time I just find it annoying cuz
it's just wasting my time it's the same
reason like when I was younger I didn't
like it either and I didn't get into
things like security research and stuff
for that reason like I don't care about
investing investigating other people's
binary Zoar something right like I just
I just don't want to spend the time
because I like making new things and I
would much rather just have stuff
respect properly so if I have to use it
I can just know what it does by reading
a short thing that it says what it does
and know that that is correct that's way
better
right and so under spec stuff is just
wasting my time and it's not you know
it's not really a an age thing for me
for other people it might be if you
liked it when you were younger I could
absolutely see you getting tired as you
get older because you just don't care
anymore something or you're tired of
dealing with it for me it wasn't that I
never really liked it it was it's never
really been something that I I like I
always find it kind of annoying but
all right so here's an explanation of
the closure thinks the structures are
like lists in Lisp where old versions
are kept around because new ones
reference the old with sub parts
containing the new data appended on so
like it keeps effectively versions of
your structures again I'm not really
sure I understand what the feature is
per se
it's building up diffs yeah I mean so I
guess I'd have to actually use it to see
what I thought of it but in principle I
like things like that might be a way to
say it - waffles said hey Casey I just
started working on a super oop open
source project and C++ and one thing I'm
noticing is that it's so hard to find
the code that actually does the thing
I'm looking for can I expect this with
monitors he was blessed because it blows
literally all I'm trying to do is add a
menu option but my exploration is so far
looking at eight different files and
then of which actually contain the thing
that I want which is from what I
understand literally just adding a
boolean flag in the metadata um yeah I
mean this is why I don't use that
programming style and I would have
thought it should have been obvious to
any programmer worth their salt that
it's bad right and the reason for that
is that the further away your code is
from a literal reading of what it is
doing at first blush the worse it is end
of story
for many reasons one other people will
have a hard time reading it - you will
have a hard time reading it after you've
forgotten what it does 3 if it is not
clearly showing the steps it does in the
order it does them in a way that's easy
to read chances are it's generating a
ton of extra CPU code because the
compiler is not smart enough to
magically determine you were only doing
something simple there for it's
extremely hard to debug because when you
actually step through this you're gonna
be jumping all over the place and you
it's gonna be very hard to follow what
was actually happening in the code 5
it's very hard to maintain because any
changes in all of that random code
that's all being pulled in and and
crazily being munched on to do this
simple operation could all have bugs in
it and it could all get changed at some
point out from under you accidentally
you end up in a left pad situation right
on and on and on and on it's terrible
it's just a very bad way to program
objectively I think there is no real
subjective to it it doesn't work
it makes things slower to compile slower
to debug slower to write and harder to
maintain there there's no upsides to it
at all that I've ever seen
so yeah it's horrible don't do it don't
go down that road it's bad it is just
not good code by any metric you want to
apply that actually measures something
yeah ginger bill I'm looking at the
counter turn amount of LOV I'm Cochin
you know I took a look at that too at
one point and it was just like I don't
know what ends up happening because it
seems like it shouldn't be that hard to
write something that's like mmm here's a
description of what I need to CPU to do
please generate the code that does it
you know and yet when you look at
something like LLVM it's just an
absolute train wreck on the inside right
like you just are like alright forget it
by the time I even can do a small amount
of thing to this I could have written my
own code Jen right and that really
shouldn't be the case and so I think
again that I think that's probably just
another situation of just C++ nightmare
because the LLVM code base is all C++
tout them you know it's just ridiculous
about slitting the code into microscopic
files my co-workers love it because it
makes the code quote unquote easier to
read for them okay it seems like they
get lost a file has more than 200 lines
yeah I know probably because they don't
have this something that can jump
quickly to functions maybe I don't know
well moving away from Moodle and for
coder effect your wrists or have you
found that it won't sorry I think maybe
the phrase modal's tripping up there
it's still modal from the perspective of
the person using the tool to switch
around what the hotkeys are doing the
difference is that there's no entering
or exiting of operations right so
meaning I still do this right I still
have this in there but what I don't have
is like when you hit like let's say this
for list locations for foo right this is
a modal thing now that if I was to do
something else like for example switch
to a query replace or something like
query replaces this modal thing right
here's the thing we're replacing and
here's what we replacing it with and now
it's done right that's totally modal
it's gone I can't like I can't just
apply it anytime I want or do right so
what I mean by getting rid of that
modality is it's just all of those
things are now just part of the edit at
anytime so like search and replace isn't
like a mode I go into to do search and
replace it's just part of the operations
that are available at all times does
that make sense so the the the hotkey
mode is still something you control
to again be easier on the wrists so you
don't use the ctrl key that's separate
though the day I heard someone make a
claim that programming without syntax
highlighting is more error-prone what
would you say I guess I would say prove
it it could be right it could be wrong I
don't really do it for errors or not I
do it because it's just more pleasant to
have something a little more colorful
than just the the straight its
monochrome right so I do it more for
visual pleasantness I don't consider it
to be a particularly important feature
for for quality its its its for its to
make the graphic design not too boring
right
yeah and you know I guess on the air
profile let me say one more thing the
air pro front so I could actually
believe a claim that not using syntax
highlighting led to more errors if the
syntax highlighting highlighted
different stuff that it's currently
highlighting right so like the normal
syntax highlighting like this I'm not so
sure some of the stuff I added too for
coder recently I could easily see it
leading to less errors for example one
of the things I added to for coder
that's super baller is it auto annotates
your pound ifs so for example like if
you type so if you type something like
this right it's like who the heck knows
what each of these blocks are right like
what's this and that what is each of
those I have no idea right and you have
to start following it through and so one
thing that you'll see people do fairly
frequently is they'll be like oh all
right like this part here is the end if
for foo or whatever right but those can
easily be wrong like you can because
it's just a comment and so what you know
what I did in the new version is it can
annotate all your scopes for you so we
can just tell you like hey this block is
the block that corresponds to this
expression or this endif is the one that
closes this pound if right and it'll
just it puts it right in line there for
you to see so a bunch of stuff like that
could actually prevent errors because
you'd be like oh whoops I must have and
it's thing here that that made it end up
being a block I didn't expect there's
some of that that would be good right
so I think I think that's you know I
think that's good
try and think if there's anything else
but yeah so I guess what I'd say is I've
put some new features into four critter
that I think will prevent errors they
aren't the kinds that people are
normally talking about with sind exiling
and certainly weren't the things that
you heard said because no other editor
has any of the stuff that I know of so
we'll see but like another example would
be I have a thing in for coder now too
that shows you things like when you put
in a character or a hex thing it'll tell
you like what that color is or what the
characters integer value would be again
those are things that could easily be
preventing errors because maybe you
thought you knew what backslash-n was
but it's actually slightly different and
just having it show you there'd be like
oh wait right it's not that just stuff
like that you know another syntax hiding
thing that would prevent bugs in for
coder that I added is it will auto color
decimal and hexadecimal numbers so you
can see how large they are so for
example if you have it'll it'll block
out every four so if you fought you put
six hexadecimals in but you only put
five or you thought you put 12 but you
only put eleven you would know because
you can see the demarcations very
clearly so I've put in a bunch of stuff
now for syntax highlighting as you'll
see when we actually update it that I
could believe all of those could find
bugs but the normal cindex I know sounds
just like is this a function is it a
string constant I have a hard time
believing that's gonna help you find
bugs much I mean there's just not a lot
there so I do think we've added a bunch
up to for coder that'll be in the in the
new version that that is does have the
potential to really improve your coding
not just for decoration but a lot of the
syntax having stuff that we currently do
and that's in most other editors not
really the kind of thing that I would
say is gonna like help you find errors
particularly likely
[Music]
I really yeah I really couldn't couldn't
say can't can't think of a reason why it
would I would have to hear some
arguments as to what sorts of errors
people thought it was preventing you
know like what kind of a bug do you
think it's gonna prevent and and maybe
that then we could have a more
constructive inquiry into it cuz I can't
even really think about what bugs
someone would argue it could prevent
yeah
alright I'm gonna wrap it up
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for the episode a hand made here out
sort of pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
the series at home you can always pier
the game at hand made here org it comes
with all the source code so that you can
build it at home and play around with it
that's it for this week
we'll be back next week with more
streaming I'm not 100% sure we actually
debug the thing today by the time we ran
out of time I you know it was apparently
working but I'm not confident like we
haven't really done the testing that I
would like to do in order to determine
that it's actually correct now because
it's kind of subtle piece of code and we
did a little bit more than we would
normally do in there and so I seemed a
little iffy so we'll check it out next
weekend we'll put it through its paces
and make sure that there's nothing weird
going on there and try to clean off some
of that stuff and then hopefully we
could finally say all right now now
we're good to go we can mark up all our
assets and I'm not going to be nervous
about it losing our work or anything
like that that's about it until next
time have fun programming everyone and
I'll see you on the Internet take it
easy