hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete game live on
stream we finished up last week with all
of the code in place but we haven't had
a chance to really work through it and
make sure that we've actually got
anything working correctly so we've
definitely got a bunch of debugging work
to do this weekend
and when I say debugging work I kind of
mean two things one I mean like the
actual act of debugging to fix problems
in the code but also because we've done
such a wide swath of stuff like we
basically completely replace the Ray
tracer and how it works almost
completely like every last bit of it is
different now we also kind of want to
spend a little bit more time stepping
through it just for our own like
educational purposes when you write a
bunch of code like that and you're like
okay here so each piece is going to work
and you do a whole replacement and now
you've got different things happening at
each stage of the process that you had
then what you had originally it's pretty
easy to miss a few things or to think
something's working one way but it's
actually not working that way and it's
working another way and you may have
forgotten especially when you're doing
stuff like when we are where it's every
week we program for like you know four
hours or something that's it's not like
we did this all in one day right and so
what we really need to do is we need to
make sure that a we understand that
everything's happening that that we
understand how everything's happening
and we're not like missing some crucial
things or failed to take advantage of
certain synergy that would have been
like brought about by these changes that
we can then leverage in other parts of
the code because we didn't really think
of it you know or whatever because we
weren't paying attention to that part at
that particular moment and then we also
need to get the basic flow correct so
any bugs that are happening because we
just like you know we put some lot of
this code is very performance critical
and it's very like TWiki right it's like
okay we're doing all these crazy bit
manipulation things and we're trying to
make everything run as efficiently as
possible so everything is a little bit
delicate as a result it's it's not as
simple as it could be it's it's more
complex due to the performance concerns
so everything's got to be happening wide
and we have all kinds of like things
where we're trying to minimize a number
of operations we're doing so we're not
doing things in the most verbose way
possible and so on so all of those
things also kind of combine right
I don't know what
so we basically need to do all of that
process so let's go ahead and and see if
we can't see if we can't get started on
that process today and just sort like
get through a little bit of that that's
sort of slow process of just like making
everything work properly and making sure
that we understand it so let's start
with the walkthrough of how the code is
now supposed to work which again is a
little bit different than it was working
before so what we intend to do now is in
addition to building a texture like two
textures really but as far as the
raycast is concerned we're talking
primarily about one particular texture
which is the diffuse texture that we
sample from although we do write back
into the specular one so both are in
play so in addition to the voxels that
these textures represent because each
texture represents a voxel ization of
the world I believe it's like 24 by 16
by 16 or something like this right now I
don't actually remember what it is but
it's yeah 24 by 16 by 16 so if I take it
back I do remember what it is I guess so
each one of those textures represents a
voxel ization of the world and each
place in that voxel records an
octahedral map that is the lighting
either the specular or the diffuse
lighting the specular is what we
actually compute because specular is
what happens along Ray's the diffuse is
something we generate from the specular
and that's just a way of basically
convolving the specular map into
something that has the sort of cosine
reflectance fall-off that you would
expect from a diffuse surface
so when we get to that point we then say
all right we need to be able to trace
rays and so what we're doing here is
we're saying we need to go through all
of the actual all the actual locations
in our voxel we need to cast rays out
along the directions of the octahedral
map and because we want to cover the
whole area of the octahedral map since
we don't really have a way of ray
casting into the world and collecting
all the light in an actual like frustum
that would be implied by being able to
cast out from the octahedral map what we
do is we point sample it with rays and
each frame we cast a different direction
out of each place in the octahedral map
so that we hope we cover the map in in
general so this is the loop that does
one slice a Y Z slice and we distribute
X slices which of which there are 24
across all the threads we have so you
know in a perfect world we'd have 24
threads one each one doing a different
slice and if you happen to run this on
like a thread ripper or something that's
exactly what would happen but on most
machines especially like Intel machines
where they have a really hard time
getting the core count up because they
didn't go to multiple chips on one
substrate approaches early enough you
only have say eight cores to deal with
most the time sometimes only four and so
what we're actually doing is we're
probably having each thread do several
of these X slices in series so a thread
will basically wake up at the lighting
time it will start chewing through the
list of work units that it needs to
process in each work unit will be one of
these slices it's an entire slice it
rather than a single voxel cell just
because we don't really want to spend a
huge amount of time banging on that
queue it's a single queue and you can't
really have lots of threads banging on a
single queue often if you do you will
simply lock up the threads waiting for
the queue mutex or
the cash line if it's lock-free so again
it's just worth thinking about this as
you get more into multi-threaded
programming it's just worth
understanding what's going on there
there's a single work cube and all of
the threads just pull the work off that
queue that's a model that only works
when the work is heavyweight if there
isn't a lot of work to do on each work
unit that you pull off this would be a
horrible design because everyone would
just lock up in order waiting for that
cache line to become unexcusable you
would be doing for that so that's why we
have a fairly large work unit if we
wanted to start to generate a more
granular approach to something like this
we would do it differently so as we come
through here we're pulling off entire
slices and what we need to do here is we
then need to say okay we're actually in
our grid is this particular starting
point because we're going to cast out of
the center of these cells and we need to
know where the starting point is so we
create this thing called the initial
grid index and what that is is it says
all right in addition to the voxel
itself which is the thing that's all
right the textures themselves which is
what we're writing and retrieving light
data from we also in gretta have a
spatial partition and because of
constraints on the way that we're
walking the spatial partition and the
fact that we don't want to go outside of
it not so much because of fetching out
of bounds because we could easily
protect against that but more just
because we'd get incorrect results when
we wrap around the voxel what we've done
instead is we've said let's make a
slightly larger voxel and this slightly
larger voxel will have a one voxel cell
apron around the outside that is just
there to show you that you've walked
outside it and that way our actual voxel
casting routine can just go ahead and
have us you know a simple exit criteria
so what we do is we create an initial
grid index that says okay let's take the
voxel dimension with the apron which is
that sort of extra piece that goes
around it
and let's go ahead and see where we'd be
in there and of course we have to have
plus one on each of our coordinates
because this thing has a 1 wide apron so
if you want to be in a specific tie a
specific cell it's going to be plus one
in all the dimensions to account for
that apron as compared to the one that
doesn't have the apron which is the way
we're storing our textures and of course
the textures don't need an apron because
they never its size to the screen such
that you never sample outside it anyway
so we don't really have to worry about
that and if you were to sample outside
it we wouldn't care you could just
return whatever you know the closest one
was and it would be fine so we have that
set up and we create this initial grid
index we then go through and say alright
there's a should compute here which is
if we want to turn on sort of like a
checkerboard based tiling to reduce the
computation cost by further reducing the
frequency of updates that we do we can
we don't have that enabled right now but
you know we may want to enable that
especially on slower machines machines
with less cores things like that so we
leave that in there for now because
we're not sure what we want to do with
it we then go through and we have some
test code here that we can do like this
test sphere and so on that we were using
for testing lighting but really we don't
do that anymore
it's just sort of a this digital remain
that we don't maybe want to pull out
just yet because we're still not quite
sure we've got everything now down but
we've got the tester in there but what
we're really calling mostly is the full
cast call the full cast calls what does
the the actual ray tracing for a given
octahedral cell so that's what we're
going to be looking at primarily we then
go on to this diffuse tile bit here
where we take the diffuse texture and we
write to it so you can see here we're
writing to the diffuse texture and this
is our single update step it's the only
time we actually update the diffuse
texture normally what we're doing is
we're actually updating the speck
texture because the specular texture is
what records the result of raycast
it's the thing that records the thing
you see directly out in a line and
that's what we can determine with ray
casting we really have no idea when we
do ray casting that doesn't give us any
information about the diffuse
reflectance in an area because diffuse
reflectance is going to be blurred right
it's going to be a summation of lots of
specular casts so we compute the
specular casts and then we produce a
diffuse map by averaging specs the
specular cast that we've done and we
average those using cosine weighted
fall-off and that's what this routine
well it's not really a team this is what
this loop here will do we then fill the
borders and those are just there to make
sure that we don't have wrapping
artifacts so this is so that when you
sample towards the edge of the
octahedral map it properly samples
basically around back to the other side
which is what you would want it to do
because you know this is supposed to
cover a spherical region it doesn't have
any actual seams so that's to hide those
seams so we don't really care about this
part of the code right now in fact we
may change the way this part of the code
works later it's totally separate from
the raycasting part but that's what
happens here right so all of that is
probably working properly the only part
that we've changed recently is this
initial grid index is something that we
added that could easily be a mistake or
something wrong happening there but the
rest of this code is the same for
regardless of which raycast
transport you tend to use so and we know
it was working fine with the old one or
at least it seemed to be working fine
meaning we there were no visible errors
with it so we wouldn't expect to be
visible errors with this one either
if the raycast is working properly so
really what we're looking at although
this initial grid index is something
that we do have to take a look at and
make sure that we're working with
properly other than that one line
everything else in this function could
probably assume to be working well
enough at the moment because we know
that it worked okay with the previous
ray transport so it's really the full
cast routine that now we have to
scrutinize and there's two parts to that
there's what it calls because it calls
this ray cast function and we have the
new grid ray cast function which is what
we replace that with and then we also
have the full cast itself now again the
full cast itself is not that suspicious
because we know that it really doesn't
do anything in particular but we do have
to pay a little bit of attention to how
it's working because we we have to make
sure that things get passed through
properly right so we have the initial
grid index here and it eventually calls
ray cast to do its work and
can see that we've got initial grid
index here getting passed through
everything else gets passed the same
regardless of whether you're using the
old ray cast or the new one and in
general this particular function will
probably want to be modified in the
future as we collapse things down we've
got too many layers of cruft at this
point and they're mostly there because
of the experimentation so at some point
we're going to want to collapse these
down now is not the time to do that
because we want to leave all of this
sort of goop in place as we sort of work
with different systems until we settle
on exactly what we're doing hopefully
that will be soon because hopefully our
grid read caster is actually good and we
can just standardize on it and then be
done with it but you know you never
really know when you're doing
experimental code and trying to figure
out the best way to do something you
don't know ahead of time which answer
you're going to end up with so you can't
remove cruft too early because you don't
know what is cruft and what is necessary
that's just a basic problem with
experimental code so if we take a look
at the raycast call here you can see
what we're doing is normally in the
raycast call we actually kind of do the
the work here and this was our old ray
caster that's sitting here in place we
actually had multiple versions of it
that we tried we tried a KD stack one we
tried a bak stack one and then right
here we've got sort of if zeroing of
them out and you can see that we sort of
have a different version that will
actually do a grid ray cast instead and
so this is actually the code that we're
running now and all of this code we
expect or I should say we hope we will
just delete meaning all of that code
that was experimental us trying to get a
good ray caster you know hopefully we'll
just be able to settle on just this one
here and we will just weld this grid ray
cast into place at that point but again
we don't know that that's just you know
that's just our hope that's what we're
hoping will happen as we test out the
various algorithms so what you can see
in here is what we do is we basically
initialize the transfer PBS value and
that's basically the photons per second
which is a rough sort of arbitrary
quantity we've defined as the thing
we're gonna have to measure our light so
it's basically a measure of the rate at
which light is going through the system
inside here where we have the grid
raycast
we are saying look please write to the
transfer PPS for this so tell us you
know what you think we are actually
getting in terms of red green and blue
wavelength photons coming back through
here and then we pass in you know the
basics we pass in where the origin is
for the race or where we're casting from
what direction we're casting what grid
index we believe that to be in the table
and then a table that we look up which
says how to walk through the actual how
to walk through the the grid as we go in
the actual grid vidcaster itself I think
we did a pretty good job of keeping it
simple there's not a lot of code here
and so what ends up happening to do a
single array cast there's some
initializations to record the values
that are in question that we need to use
to actually process a hit there's a
shuffle table that we use which is just
what we load constants from and we use
this to actually do broadcasts to we use
this to do broadcasts oh right right
okay that's like but why and then I was
like right because they're dynamic so
one of the problems that you have when
you're writing SSE code it's kind of a
bummer is just that when you do an SSE
dispatch you don't really have any way
of doing any of the normal operations so
shuffles and unpacks and all the things
you would normally use to move data
around they can't be dynamic in other
words when you do a shuffle with the
original say SSE shuffle or the SSE two
shuffles those shuffles don't actually
allow you to pass in any information you
just have to say I want to do this
particular shuffle because the shuffle
pattern is an immediate that's welded
into the instruction so short of
self-modifying code or some other kind
of really problem
child things you could do there there'd
be no way to say look based on say a
comparison of elements inside one of my
vectors I want to do this particular
shuffle pattern the only way you could
do that would be using a branch right
we'll be using a switch statement or
something like this let you know a jump
in the assembly code and so what we've
done instead is we've made a shuffle
table because one thing that you can do
in sse in I don't remember if it's SSE 4
or 2 but I think it's for maybe 3 is
there's a byte shuffle that does take a
Scheffel input so basically what it does
is it takes a it takes the the 16 byte
value to shuffle register to shuffle and
a 16 byte input that says where what to
shuffle where and so you can have a
dynamic input with that and so that's
why you see us using that here it's
because we don't have any other way of
telling it to shuffle this is a very
simple shuffle
it's a shuffle that could trivially be
done with the shuffle with the immediate
the problem is that immediate SAR welded
into the code if there was something
that was simpler we could have done it
we wouldn't have needed a whole table
either way it's not the end of the world
it's one cache line worth of stuff so
you know it's not a disaster but that's
why this is happening here ok so what we
do is we start out by initializing the
shuffle value to whatever the first
shuffle is and the reason for that is
because we don't know that we'll ever
actually find a hit
and we don't want all of our code at the
end to fail if we don't we start at the
grid index that is indicated by our
caller so that grid index that we were
we know we were stepping through that's
where we start we also initialize a cost
metric value and a t-- terminate value
these are just there in case we run out
of grid to walk or we feel like we've
done too much work and want to stop
early so these are here primarily for
early termination in the event that we
actually hit something we don't need
these but we don't know that we actually
will hit something or we don't know that
we'll hit something within the
computation
budget that we allow we start by looking
at the node that we start in and that's
why grid index is initialized to initial
green index and what we do is we say
look if we hit a spatial node Terminator
a grid node Terminator that just means
we have hit the apron and we don't need
to walk anymore because we're just
walking out we've left the grid area so
this is our termination condition for
out of bounds we then look through all
of the leaves that exist in this
particular location so we look up the
spatial grid leaf table the spatial grid
leaf table it just is literally a table
that says excuse me
here are all of the things that exist at
particular locations so another way to
think of it would be it's basically a
packed array with all of the boxes that
you can hit all the occluders and the
lights as well and then each of the
nodes that we walk just says what chunk
of that leaf table to use so we're
looping over that leaf table and we're
just pulling out all of the the things
we might intersect with from there we're
then doing the Box intersection and this
code isn't new it's basically exactly
the same as it was before so the box
intersection code has been preserved it
doesn't it didn't change because we
already thought it was reasonably
performant before we didn't think there
was a way we could really make it go
particularly faster so the only thing
that we did differently here is we just
preserve different values in the case
where we do hit previously did we invert
preserving the box min and box max
instead now what we do is we preserve
the T value that we thought was the
actual hit and the reason that we're
doing this is because this will let us
pick out the correct value using our
shuffle table later so that's what's
going on there so as we come through
here you can see that all we're really
doing is we're just recording them
information and we also build a mask
over time that we can use for a future
jump that basically says did we hit
anything at all so if we did hit
something we know that since we're
walking the grid in order we can
early-out at that point because we don't
need to look any further if we've
already
something we can't possibly hit
something sooner in a later grid cell
and we ensured that when we built the
actual grid because what we did is we
clipped each of the boxes to the grid
cell that it's in and so we know that
there isn't any cases where you can go
to a future grid cell and get an earlier
hit that's no longer possible so we look
to see whether or not we did hit
something and if we did we're gonna
terminate and the way that we terminate
is we first say all right we need to
look up to see which kind of shuffle
we're actually going to do and you can
see here that when we actually do this
to to do the I'm sorry we don't quite do
that yet that's actually happening here
the first thing we have to do is we have
to put all of our data in place to do a
horizontal comparison so the way that we
do this is you can see in here we've got
our our data set up so that we're going
to take the second and third the sixth
and seventh the tenth and eleventh and
the 14th and 15th values out and then
we're also going to replicate this to
the second and third values into the
rest of the table we're gonna do that
one shuffle and what that shuffle is
doing is it's taking the highest part of
each of our of each of our
floating-point values
so actually here's a question where we
overly were we overly clever here though
so so if you look at what's happening
here we're trying to extract the minimum
value so you know we just want to know
which one of these 16-bit values is the
lowest is what we're asking it for I
mean that's what this is right and the
thing that I don't quite understand is
that we should have to compare the
entire floating-point value in order to
do that right
I mean basically this is just ignoring
16 bits of mantissa which I mean I guess
is maybe you would just say that's okay
because we just need to know roughly
which one is the closest but it's a
little odd right I mean it at the very
least I think we probably needed to do
in there because it just doesn't seem I
mean out of the 32 bits of the
floating-point value that we're
comparing we're obviously comparing the
best part to compare meaning we're
comparing the part that's the exponent
and the most significant bits so you
know we're comparing like 8 bits of
mantis or something and the exponent but
I'm not sure that we're is that enough
like I don't know that we know if that's
enough or not you know what I mean
like it may be that there's those
remaining 16 bits of mantissa were
important and we don't seem to care
about that and I'm not sure that we
actually did the work necessary to know
that we don't care
so it's a little odd
I'm gonna just put it to do in there
the downside of it it's not a
catastrophic failure because all it
would mean is that you pick a slightly
different position to sample your
lighting from but you know I don't know
if that's again if we haven't really
done any kind of analysis to determine
that we don't care then we don't know if
we don't care so I am a little nervous
about that and I just want to put it to
do in there because I'm not sure we
really thought that through all the way
it definitely will work I mean that's
it's never gonna give like a completely
ridiculous result doing that it will
always give you roughly the correct hit
but in the case where you had two hits
that were very close together it will
not correctly pick the closest one all
the time it will just be kind of random
which one it picks so sometimes it will
pick the closest one and sometimes it
will pick the one that's slightly
further away and I don't know to what
extent that could have a significant
effect on the quality of the lighting in
our particular case maybe it just almost
never would because you don't really
care about those kind of fine grain
details in a game where you just have
large sort of blocky Minecraft you
looking sort of geometry that you're
casting against so it's possible that it
doesn't matter but I would least like to
note this so that we could maybe take a
look at in the lighting quality pass and
see whether this is actually valid
so it's really difficult to say and I
think that's just a case where we should
do some analysis on the actual numbers
and see whether or not we have
situations you know another one would be
if we just wrote the laborious code here
which tests it exactly what the right
answer was and then counted how many
times we were wrong I think that's
something we should probably do just to
make sure that we know exactly how
inaccurate this is making us right
that's really all I want to do there and
then if we're sure that it's fairly
minimal then it's probably still a great
idea to do it this way anyway because we
want to minimize the cost but it's just
I don't since I don't think we really
did that I'm not sure I'm comfortable
with it anyway once we do do that if in
fact that is okay then we get back a min
test value here by using the min posi PU
16 which will do the horizontal
comparison of 16-bit values for us
automatically and that's the entire
reason that we did this was just because
it's the one way we had that could
actually do that comparison we didn't
have a way of saying compare for
floating-point values and give us the
minimum the index of the minimum that
wasn't a thing that that was available
at least not that we could find and so
the reason that we had to do the 16 bit
compare was because it's the only thing
we actually have that will do a
horizontal compare across the lanes we
then have this shuffle index which is
what we extract out of that that's gonna
tell us that answer we verify as we're
running that it never gives us an answer
that isn't less than four and the reason
for that is just because we've padded
this out in such a way as to make sure
that we can't get it has to be what zero
one two or three these are just copies
of the original two values so
you can't ever have one of those being
less than this one and we looked and it
does go in order so in the case where
this is equal to this it should still
return us the lower one which is zero so
we just asserted that that's true
because we wanted to make sure and then
we go ahead and we look in the table and
we grab out whatever the thing is that
it told us it should be and that we grab
out the shuffle that puts that thing
everywhere so we then do our P chef to
make sure our T ray just now has the
correct value in all four positions and
then we go ahead and do our computations
to figure out the normal we take the
sign bit of the ray direction and the
reason that we do that is because we
know that the normal has to be pointing
in the same direction as the Ray or I
should say in the opposite direction of
the Ray because we can't hit something
that's a back face of the of one of our
occluders and then we go ahead and do
our selection of x y&amp;z and this is why
we changed what we're storing is because
we figured out that if we just use which
T value got selected the X one the Y one
or the Z one we can then know whether or
not we're an X normal a Y normal or Z
normal so we can get the sign directly
from the Ray direction and then we get
the Y X Y or Z which one it is just
based on which of the T values we
selected and this was a very efficient
way to create the normal compared to
what we were doing before it's just a
few bit operations and we get we get
some accurate values out of it we think
however we haven't tested it we could
have slipped up in here we could have a
typo or a bug or something and so we
need to check check that we're actually
producing good normals with this process
when we actually finish producing the
normals we extract them here down to
singles in order to actually use because
when we fall out of these loops we're
going to do radiance calculations that
need to look up into a specific place in
the grid so things have to be dropped
down to single so you know we can you
know we can just see it's that to do
still relevant it's not so we actually
did the thing that this to do was
talking about
if you look here we now only have one
irradiance computation not two so yeah
anyway what you can see here is
regardless of how you exit the loop we
fill out these values and the reason for
that is because these are the values
that I actually get used you can see
that in the case where we hit something
we produce you know the normal and the
sample direction and that sort of stuff
we drop them in here and in the case
where we just run out of time then what
we do is we step the array forward to
where we ran out and we just say this is
where you're going to probe in the case
where we hit nothing at all so we just
miss entirely and we were still under
budget at that point we just kind of say
like hey we don't really know which is
probably wrong I mean I would say that
it might be the best idea probably you
know possibly to just exit on the cost
metric drop out and say you know we
probably just want to do this operation
when we run out of space as well
hard to say that's kind of a to be
continued I think when we do the
lighting quality pass and we decide how
we're actually going to be putting
moonlight in here I think we're gonna
probably want to say that if you leave
the grid
I mean ideally we'd just do like if you
leave the grid I don't think anything
happens so yeah I don't know this is
probably fine so we then go and compute
the voxel irradiance and we use where we
are sampling which is what we determined
up here right we pass that in we take
that fall-off and we actually do the the
fall-off based on the normal that we're
reflecting off of and whatever the
emission would have been we do some
computations to get the RGB and emission
to work properly and then we we pass
those out so that's the complete rate
caster and we want to step through here
and verify that those things are
actually working the way we think they
are because like I said there's a lot of
intricacy in there we've smacked a lot
of things down to very few operations or
I should say very few I'm sure we could
get it lower than this but it's still
pretty small I compared to what the
verbose version would be and so we want
to step through that now and see if it's
actually working the way we think it is
similarly we also have the grid
construction code and that replaces the
KD tree builder that we used to have so
in spatial partition for lighting what
you can see here is we had these things
for building them we're now running this
separate path we don't really care about
any of this stuff anymore and eventually
we will remove it entirely but what
we're actually concerned with now is
this part what we do is we say all right
let's take a look at what we need for
our array and we basically build the
array on the fly so we say however big
the lighting box is going to be let's
build that we then loop through and we
count how many leaves go into each
square so this is literally just a pre
pass for sizing so that we can keep
everything aligned nicely where you
don't have to jump around to figure out
what you're intersecting with you'll
actually just always have for every node
in the grid you'll actually know exactly
what the leaves are in a tight array
excuse me I've been pretty sick lately I
got some um antibiotics from the doctor
because of course with kovat 19
situations you actually can't safely go
to a doctor and a lot of doctors were
actually shut down so you can't actually
get things like a throat culture or
something so they basically were like
well let's try to treatment things and
see what ends up happening because that
will be effectively a test right which
normally you wouldn't do but in this
particular case if you don't want to
have to go to the like one or two
clinics that are open where tons of
kovat 19 people actually already are you
don't really have a lot of choices yeah
kind of annoying kind of a really
annoying aspect of the way we do
medicine where we don't trust people to
do medicine so like a throat culture
isn't a thing that would be that hard
for people to do at home but of course
we don't really not only do we not trust
people but our society set up so that
people who screw things up because
they're stupid or incompetent like we'll
sue you and create like litigious
problems for circumstances that make it
so that you'd never really want to be in
the business of doing health care at
home so even though really my problem
could just be solved by me having
someone like take a throat culture here
and then mail that to a lab of course
that's not on the table yeah
medical science always a hundred years
behind all right so let's go ahead and
it's not the science it's the medical
practice always a hundred years behind
so let's go ahead and take a look at how
this is built so you can see here that
what we do is we grab the min and Max
node for the place that this thing needs
to be inserted and then we loop over the
x y&amp;z of the spatial grid nodes and we
basically say we're going to take this
particular relief and we're going to
insert it into this particular AABB so
they include ER and we're gonna inserted
into every node that it straddles so you
know all the nodes that it possibly
touches we're gonna put it in there so
we're just counting and when we're done
counting we then say okay we now know
how many of these things were going to
have so we loop through and we produce
an actual total count by rounding up to
four because we know we pack four at a
time and we produce the count here and
we produce the count
Undivided by four so it's actually just
the raw count right so we say here's
where it would start and here's where it
would end though I shouldn't say that
here's where it would start and where it
would end is set to zero so it's
basically like a start in account we
then go through and after creating room
to store these we do the exact same loop
as we did before but now we actually put
each individual box in there and we do
that by creating what we think the box
actually is by creating the cell bounds
for that particular location and then we
clip the AABB to those bounds using the
intersect call we put it into the leaf
at the location that we believe it
should go thus creating basically a
packed xxx yyy ZZZ for later use by
inserting into you know subsequent
entries in that order when we're done
with all of that
we also loop through and do a post pass
to correct all of the information that
we had here so the first thing we do is
we divide this tardiness by four because
now we've packed everything in so
everything is by fours and you can see
that we sort of did that here as well
right the primary index was always
divided by four we actually inserted it
in we then also come through here and we
take the one passed last index and we
also like put that in using the divide
by four and we round it up so to make
sure that we capture the correct number
in there we then also say anybody who
was actually erroneous so they were an
apron they weren't actually supposed to
contain anything we actually go through
and check for any of that and if you are
on the apron then we put in the grid
Terminator bit or special value in the
start index so that the routine knows
right so that the grid that's how the
Ray Kassar knows it's hit the end so
again I think the logic is sound but we
don't know we could have some bugs in
there there's a fair number of
operations that have to occur and we
could have some part where we've got
issues this part here is it to do that
you know we now do and so I'm going to
turn this to do into just a note I'm
going to say we need to use intersect
here because we cannot allow boxes to
extend outside their node region
otherwise early termination of the ray
caster would not work since earlier T's
could be worse or farther I should say
farther hits compared to later T's so
anyway so that's just a walk through the
entire thing so let's go ahead and just
start stepping through I'm gonna use
debug build here
mmm because I'm not so concerned about
speed at the moment what I want to look
at instead is just the behavior of the
functions and to start looking for
problems or issues that are not like
where something's behaving contrary to
how I think that it should have and so
this is just for my own edification
before I start debugging specific
problems I just want to take that walk
through to see that we're not doing
anything obviously stupid what happened
there so a reason internal lighting core
did not get hit what's going on
do I not call that anymore what's going
on here
I mean here's internal letting car right
okay Wow not a great day for spelling
huh let's try yeah there we go
alright so here we go into the actual
ending code that we care about so this
is the actual spatial partition builds
that we just said this part is not
something we actually work with I don't
think but this part is so let's take a
look let's see what the max grid index
is just for our notification so there's
about 9,000 cells in the grid including
the apron the nominal size is 60 144 and
then if you look at like you know what
happens just to illustrate the +1 oops
it's 2 because on either side there'll
be a little bit of the apron you can see
what we would get up to that doesn't
seem right does it
hmm so that's a little wonky let me take
a look at what voxel dim is there so if
we did 26 times 18 times 18 yeah it's
doing the math right so where is 89 18
coming from voxel gym with apron
oh well not mm-hmm so I think that's a
little confusing
let's might just be a slow morning but
let's take a look at what's going on
there because I don't know all right so
here's the equation that we're actually
computing we're taking the X and we're
multiplying it by well I mean if you
pile this out it's x times y times z
plus x times y plus X right and I'm
wondering if maybe
so I guess the problem with that is this
is computing the actual cell like this
is if you could actually get to the
count as an actual index so really if
you wanted to know that count you'd have
to subtract one from each one so this
trick I mean it sort of is still okay
because when you do this you're just
want a value that's large enough right
so it's not an issue but it's also not
really what you would want right so
probably in order to make this be at
least a little less confusing for anyone
who was reading it you know we probably
want to do this at least you know what I
mean
oops so let's just do that just to make
sure that you know everyone understands
what's going on because it threw me for
a loop there real quick
and it was like you know it's not a
problem but it's just like you might as
well be clear so I think that's what
you'd actually want and in order to get
the count you would need to do plus one
so this is the max grid index but here
we're actually doing a grid count right
so I think you would want to do max grid
count or grid count something like that
and to be honest I'm not sure why we
just wouldn't do this with a get dim
call I guess we don't actually have one
that does this but you'd kind of just
want like get total size to happen with
this it's let's just do this
I mean that's just better right so I'm
gonna change this to grid camp so that
when we roll over these we're a little
bit clearer about what's going on and
you know I guess I don't necessarily
know that we care what type that is but
we do want to never have larger than we
can fit in 16-bit indices because we
don't really want to store large indices
into these things so now if I look at
the grid count hopefully I get an answer
that's more congruent there we go so
that seems better to me here's me
allocating those and then we're going to
loop over all the things we got to
insert in and so if we take a look at
what we actually get back when we do
these insertions we should be able to
see sort of how this works so you can
see here like it's basically getting
this is one that straddles you know as
you would expect most things will
probably straddle - it'll be a two by
two by two right I mean that seems like
mostly what will happen here right so as
we multiply out the two by two by two
you can see we just like adding it in
there right and we're just putting these
into the spatial grid nodes as they go I
don't think there's much to worry about
in that particular computation I mean it
seems like it should should just be fine
right
but I guess what I would say though is
this looks busted right so we need these
things to be inserted and that's just
gonna be garbage right I mean if you
look at what happens in here
this is expecting these to be inside the
voxel so things that are outside the
voxel cannot be inserted here and we're
not checking for that how this wasn't
absolutely destroying memory I have no
idea but I guess it's just because we
allocate things in a fairly consistent
way I mean you know right like this
should just been completely complete a
complete disaster let's make sure that
doesn't happen by protecting ourselves
from it so I'm gonna do an asserts that
the p-value is greater than zero in each
case greater than or equal to I should
say and I'm also going to assert that
it's less than the dim
so I think that's roughly what we want
to do now there's different ways that we
could go about doing this we could make
this voxel larger so like we can allow
casting outside and I don't know if we
actually do want to do that right so if
you look at what's going on in here when
we do these get voxel index for P we
could choose to have the Vox will be
offset so I'm gonna put it to do in here
that says do we want to support casting
on a wider voxel area than the lighting
because my my hunch is we probably do
meaning the lighting bounds are fairly
tight to the world and we probably want
to support lighting further out than
that in fact I'm just going to go ahead
and say like we do want that right so I
think what we want to do here is we want
to do some adjustment I mean you know we
probably still want something like this
but
I think what we want to do here is say
look we know that we have a specific
region that's covered by the lighting
voxels themselves but we probably don't
actually want to use that for the
collision because we want to be able to
capture things that are outside of that
and still be able to cast so that we can
capture lights that are off-screen and
stuff like that we don't want those
things to disappear just because they're
off-screen because the lighting will
behave in an obviously erroneous way
that we probably wouldn't like so what I
would say is voxel dim with apron
probably is going to be something
slightly different than it's gonna have
to be larger so if we look at voxel dim
with apron and the table
yeah so if you look at where this is
actually being used right we probably
just want this thing to be larger so you
can see here that we enlarged it just
with an apron but the apron is not
probably what we actually want so we
probably want to do another thing here
which is like the extra occlusion bounds
right
probably extra collusion radius and what
we would say here is like look maybe we
want to go you know an extra two grid
squares down and extra like eight grid
squares to either side and up and down
or something you know and so what we
want to do here is say like you know
let's make sure we build a much larger
thing and let's make sure that instead
of using like the hot corner which is
what we would normally use we use some
other corner right so we have like
occlusion corner or something like this
or what is this called
it's called spatial grid corner so we
would want that where we could say okay
the spatial grid corner is this thing
that we're going to be able to look up
in here and what we want to do is we
want to compute where that should be
based on the apron so when we compute
the hot corner which we've already done
at this point when we go to do the
spatial grid corner in the solution we
want to go ahead and compute that by
taking the hot corner so this thing here
and I guess I'll make this called a
midden corner as well just so it's clear
which one we're talking about
and what I want to do is I want to take
the voxel cell dim and I just want to
step backwards by the occlusion radius
right so we want to multiply whatever
the Vox seldom is buy that extra
occlusion radius and then we've aligned
this voxel so that it's just like a
larger version of the same right we
probably need this value because without
the extra occlusion radius and so on we
also wouldn't know I guess technically
the voxel dim with apron
I might roll that in there too because
at this point since now they're
basically separate voxels we probably
just want to say look here's the radius
and that's going to be the same value as
the offset right so in here we could
store this as that radius so I could say
like okay
you know this is what the offset
actually is and that way when people are
doing computations on it they'll use
that and they'll be correct so I think
most everything else stays the same we
just have to change how we're doing that
indexing so that will be a little bit
different now than it would have been
before so now when we come through here
and we do this spatial grid news grid
index from like this but here the
problem we're going to have is get voxel
index for P is not determinative anymore
so there's a couple different ways we
could choose to do this and it's unclear
like exactly which ones way we want to
do it but what you can see here is this
will adjust to the min hot corner but we
now know that there's like a different
corner that we might want to use
sometimes and so possibly what we should
say here is
instead of you loading that stuff up out
of there maybe we pass them in corner in
I don't know and we say something like
okay
send us the min corner and then the P
and so here we would say look at the min
corner and off we go
now we don't need to actually do this we
can just get the P directly it was
that's not what I meant
I just meant that right so in theory now
we should be able to just do get voxel
index for P and we can pass the min
corner that we actually want which is
the spatial grid min corner and you know
it it occurs to me that we probably
should have a data structure that's like
voxel that has like these things in it
and then you just pass which one you
actually wanted so we may want to make a
utility for that at some point I just
don't know that now is that point but
like you know
we'll look at that a little bit later so
now we come through here and we step
through this will now get grin as sees
that should always be in line if they're
inside the problem is we do know that we
can have geometry that could be outside
and so we really want to do is just say
look this stuff should be clipped or
clamped to the minimum and maximum
places that this thing can actually be
and so I think what we want to do first
before we do this is to take like the
box itself and clip it to the entire
voxel and if it's outside it will get
clipped in if it's literally like
completely outside we'll end up with a
box that doesn't have any volume and so
we can just kind of discount it right
[Music]
there are other ways we could choose to
handle that and I don't necessarily know
that any of them are good so I think we
probably just want to do that but it's
worth noting so for example if we wanted
to we could just say hey anyone who is
outside just gets thrown into the apron
because we know that we're about to romp
over the apron with a terminator start
index anyway so that would be fine
but it just doesn't make sense to spend
a lot of time on geometry that's outside
what we're looking for anyway
so I don't think I'm gonna do that but
it's worth noting that you could write
so what I'd like to do now is I'd like
to just go and create a rectangle 3 for
the actual voxel and you know I'm just
going to do it let's just make an actual
function in here I'm an actual thing you
know we've got the Atlas the hand made
light atlas right let's just make like a
handmade like box all right
and if we wanted to do this we kind of
already know what they would take right
I mean this is what we want in there and
so if we have a voxel grid or a voxel
dimension I guess you might say voxel
spec I don't know what do we call it in
the Atlas case we just called it light
atlas so let's just let's just say it's
a voxel I mean voxel is it's not the
right term stocks as a pixel so I guess
this is a voxel grid and I'm going to
say it so in here we could just say look
there's a rectangle three that's the
total bounds of the voxel and then
there's the actual dimension in the
inverse dimension and I think that's all
we need to produce like the correct
calls that give us all the information
we want to know you know out of this
I mean I think that's that's just
everything we need right so then if we
like take a look at all the things we're
actually trying to do here with these
voxels so you know we've got this sort
of stuff all of this is stuff that now
we should be able to to just put in here
and compute so all of the the previous
you know voxel II sorts of things that
we were doing we should be able to have
them all work off of one of those trucks
and that's better because then we're
just not sort of spamming those
calculations everywhere and possibly
getting them wrong you know which is not
what we want so I'm gonna pull these out
and I'm just gonna take a quick look
through the code at that point to sort
of clean it up and make it all call
through here directly and this probably
will break our ability to load our
lighting stuff so we're gonna have to
probably take a new lighting sample but
that's okay because that's kind of been
a long time coming anyway so let's see I
don't see anything else particularly
suspicious in there so you know assuming
that this is what we think we might want
to do here I'm just going to like sketch
these out so we think we have one that
wants to take the center for a
particular index and in all of these
cases we probably want to versions of
this like an absolute index and a
regular index so we'd probably have
something that does like these two
different versions you know and I mean I
guess another way to do that would just
be to say
I'm gonna hold off on that because it is
harder to do so I'm not going to produce
ones that we don't actually know if we
need right so so yeah let's let's not do
that quite yet so each of these works on
the blown out coordinates like XY and Z
and then this can be a world P and then
just this one produces the flat index
right so
so get cell center P get cell bounds get
index for P flat index from and then
maybe like a utility function to get the
total bounce I think they can just go
ahead and reach in there and get it
because I'm not going to want to change
that storage so I think we're fine so
let's go ahead and and put these in
place so get cell center P here all we
really need to do is say all right we've
got the total bounds oops
dot min and then the grid box seldom
times the index and the centroid offset
get voxels cell bounds is now just plain
get cell bounds because we know since
we're passing grid is the first
parameter that we know exactly what we
are asking for there so get cell bounds
just says look produce the cell bounds
by taking the grid total bounds min and
adding these two now I don't know why we
wrote it this way that doesn't really
make any sense
because after you've computed this why
wouldn't you just add hit him huh that
was a really convoluted way to do that
and doesn't really make any sense so
we're just not going to do that anymore
so this gets the cell bounds for us here
and then we've got the get index for P
this one is the reverse mapping so this
one is trying to figure out based on the
world P that you give it so in order to
do that we need again that minimum
corner total bounce min and we're using
the inverse dimension here and then
again we subtract out that center value
[Music]
which I thought we fixed this I guess we
didn't fix it because we were doing it
in two different places so kind of
another reason why this is you know
something you probably want to do a
little bit more centralized but if you
take a look here right this is wrong
because when you do the floor it's not
rounding its flooring so to create the
correct center value it should be that
right so we must have had some other bug
in there that's why we put in that
correction and we just didn't think it
through or something because that
shouldn't be the case once you subtract
them in then until you actually go up
above the seldom number until you go
above one you're in that cell so the
correct cell index in this case is this
and it may have been because we were
doing something else with it at that
time but you know the actual index for
the cell is always this so so I think
that was just you know again just a
screw-up on our part so we now have the
grid index from this is again something
that just needs to compute it needs to
be in bounds we can also produce a thing
that tells us that value so we can say
like is in bounds and we can use this as
the actual check and then here we can
just say assert that it's in the bounds
so we would just say for this Fox little
grid and this p-value this is actually
an index value not a p-value
so for that particular p-value off you
go
oh you know what else we need here is
the count so we need the cell count
right so these are the dimensions of the
thing that we didn't actually store how
many cells there were we do need to do
that
so in here this is actually cell conex
cell count Y and when we do in bounds
we're gonna be checking the cell now so
I'm going to pull the cell count out
here just for ease of my own referencing
so just grab that value like so and we
can now test if things are in bound by
testing the index and instead of
asserting these I'll just pull them in
to a function so the result of this
function is just going to be the ending
of all of these so if all of these
things are true
so if all of these things are true then
you get the results of it being inbound
if any one of them fails it means that
one of the indices indices is out of
range at which point it will return
false and fail so we can assert that
it's inbounds here and people can also
do the check for inbounds later we now
produce the flat index this is supposed
to be flat in next round and I think
that's what we want so now what we want
to do too is say okay we need a way to
create one of these so this is makefox
look grid it's going to return one of
these and what we're going to do is
initialize the values in it to various
things and we're going to make it as
easy as possible for people to construct
by computing all of these values based
off of just a few basic values that they
pass in so in terms of these actual
values all we really need is to sell
them so if you pass in the seldom and
then the count right so we have this
many of this thing or something like
that then from there we can initialize
this cell count and the seldom directly
also I don't know why I didn't just call
that seldom let's fix that
the other values can be computed from
that so you know the inverse seldom is
just one over the seldom right and the
total bounds is just going to be the
cell count times a seldom right so this
is a Hadamard product now we do need one
more piece of information because with
only this piece of information we
wouldn't actually know where it is so we
need to know what the minimum corner is
and we can add that in here so here they
just passed one corner how many cells
there are in it and what the dimension
of each cell is and then we'll fill in
all the dependent values based on that
okay so like the max and the inverse
which are computed off it we don't have
to they don't have to pass this in
because we can tell what those are so
that will make a voxel grid for us and
this will presumably allow us to you
know write some utility functions as
well that you know if we have two
different voxels and we want to
translate between indices and from one
to the other things like that presumably
we should be able to do that as well
we'll see so let's take a look at now
what happens in the lighting if we were
going to do this and move from here
what I want to do now is take a look at
how we would actually place this in the
lighting so let's go ahead and destroy
our ability to run the current sample
code because I mean let's face it it's
it's not gonna happen the box ref count
in the box of all this stuff is gone so
I'm gonna go ahead and say look we're
gonna end up with just this now I would
also say that like the scratch ABC
nonsense we can pull that out of here
too because even if we want to run the
spatial partition stuff that is still
using that information so you can see it
like using the scratch stuff what we can
do instead is just now push those on
here as array pushes
because they don't need to persist
outside
right so when we go through here and we
need like scratch a and scratch C and
all this garbage we should be able to
make that work without ever actually
having those you know having to keep
those inside the lighting solution so we
can have you know an effect I could just
do them like this but I probably don't
actually want to because of the size of
those I don't know if there's any
downside to me just doing a push I don't
think anyone does an array count on
those do they they don't so I should be
able to just literally do this where we
just do a push array here and each one
of these oops just creates the same
table that we used half but now it's
actually you know actually if it was me
which it was I probably would have put
the type second so we can just use the
temporary nough now that we passed that
through properly to for all of our
scratch space because we know that
doesn't need to persist frame-to-frame
so that's just you know a handy little
thing it looks like we accidentally
deleted something here though yeah we
did Miriam
so now we can start to collapse this
down a little bit so the scratch buffers
go away eventually like a lot of this
stuff will go away so the box count and
the boxes and the root box and all that
stuff
this will all go away as well none of
this stuff is necessary I don't think
because the boxes can just be passed
through directly so I think a lot of
that stuff will just get will just get
removed okay so looking through what we
actually have here again the the Vox mid
corner Selden this stuff here so we now
have two of these right we have the
Atlas grid which is how we're actually
storing the lighting information and
then we have the occluder grid or the
spatial grid I guess and I don't know
that those are the best names so we
might want to think about this a little
bit like there's the lighting atlas and
that has a grid associated with it and
then there's the like actual spatial
queries and so I don't know Atlas and
spatial might be the best or they might
not be so we'll see and I think that's
probably all we need so if you look at
like these things here we probably still
need that one because it's a non-obvious
thing that's a little bit difficult to
derive you wouldn't necessarily know
that these things are exactly offset
just by looking at them and you'd have
to do a floating-point comparison to
term and that's probably don't want that
to happen we don't need this we do need
the light sampling walk table and the
rest of this stuff looks like pretty
harmless right
the diffuse weight map is probably
something we want to generate offline as
well but you know
I would say nothing else here looks
particularly suspicious so I think this
is okay now all that looks fine and so
when I'm actually initializing this
stuff now I'm gonna have to change where
I'm actually asking for it right and so
I'm going to go into handmade well I
guess at the moment it be HH light prof
and I'm going to include that voxel and
we also need the CPP for it so we'll
include both of those and now we need to
just debug anything here that is
incorrect
I'm not sure what the problem is Oh so
the flat index from in this case I've
got the safe truncate to u16 I mean I
guess we'll let the person on the
outside do that because I mean hey if
someone does want to use this in
someplace where they've got like a
really large box or something there's
nearly no reason we have to do that here
because everything else in the system
supports it so it seems pretty
straightforward to just return it this
way and call it a day so I'm totally
fine with that the person on the outside
can verify the value so in this case
cell count we didn't actually pull it
out we should have in here we've got the
cell count and seldom Hadamard product
this needs to be lofted up to a float in
order to do that multiplied so that's
got to happen there and this total
bounds here I didn't quite specify it
properly but so what we really want to
do here is say that this is a rectangle
min dim so you know here's the minimum
corner and then here's the dimension of
it and that will create it for us I
believe so at that point now all the
things that we were calling before so
all of this stuff all wants to be
calling our new system now so we pretty
much just really you know honestly we
just want to vaporize this
thing and then we've got to think about
what we want to do for this and so the
reason that this is a little bit tricky
is because it actually needs the F chord
to produce the remainder and so I think
what we probably want to do here is
actually have a composite return that
gives this information back because you
know that this is something that you're
going to want
so like the UVW coordinates for example
are things that you often want to use
there and so although this B chord is
something that is unique to what's going
on here this is actually a computation
that's probably what you would want to
do anyway so I'm going to call that
something along the lines of like
I'm gonna call that something like Vox
soul relative P and it will just have
this information in it so inside here
what we'll do is we'll say alright so
there's an index that we're going to
return to you
and then there's a UVW and the beat
chord in this case doesn't get used
outside so we probably just won't return
that for now if someone actually ends up
needing it then we'll start passing it
so then in here where you actually call
functions like get index for P those
will actually go through a separate
thing that's like get fox or relativity
so when you when you call this function
to get the relative p value it's
actually gonna do this instead in this
case we know we're always filling out
the entire results so it's probably fine
to not initialize so here we're gonna
say look the result UVW and the result
index are computed here oops and we know
the in voxel dim and we know the total
bounds men and the world P goes here so
that's our entire think our entire thing
and now forget index for P what it can
do is just say well you know the result
is just get relative P
of this thing and just only take the
index so it's just a utility function at
that point which we don't really even
need to provide if we don't want to but
for now we just will keep it so people
who were calling that can still call it
all right so now this function can just
do voxel voxel relative P to get out the
like a rel p-value or a vox r LP - and
it'll pass the atlas grid which is what
it's using and the sample p which is
what its sampling it'll then have the
values it actually needs and we probably
want to leave those we don't have to
rewrite the rest this function because
they're just different names for the
same thing so what we can do here is say
well what we needed was a voxel index
and a UVW we have both of those two
things and here they are and the rest of
the function should be able to remain in
theory unchanged all right so that's all
fine and good later on in here what we
need to do now is figure out how we're
actually going to get the rest of these
values that we need so in this
particular case where we have voxel gym
with apron that's not going to exist
anymore in anything that we actually
need to look at what we're gonna do
instead here is probably just offset the
grid index value directly so probably
what we do is we'd say okay the grid
index that we're going to have what was
it called flat index we're gonna ask for
the flat index and we're gonna ask for
that in the spatial grid and what we're
gonna ask for is specifically the voxel
index that we're at in the voxel dem
we're actually using for our atlas right
for our spec atlas and we're just going
to go ahead
and take that and offset it by the
offset value we stored here right so I
guess what we'd call this is like Atlas
two spatial grid index offset so we're
going from the Atlas to the spatial grid
right so that would give us what we
expect this is going to have to be a
safe truncate because again the voxel
routines don't this is what is happening
there what the heck I do not know what
is wrong here okay
so I believe we have got rid of the bugs
but I don't know if or coder is very
unhappy about that so let's do it this
way so this way the initial grit index
is computed and stored as the 32-bit
value and then what I'll do is when I
was going to go use it which is here
I'll do a safe truncate there so that
way we just know like hey we'll down
shift to 16 and if somehow we blow out
the that outer space it'll assert and
we'll know so then we want to do the Box
entropy here you can see us doing like a
computation to get that this is not
necessary anymore so Vox Center P
presumably isn't a thing yeah so all we
need to do here is like get cell center
P and pass the Atlas grid and
so yeah like interestingly enough let's
look at this for a second so you can see
here we were constructing this index and
we needed this index up here so I think
what we want to do is like to say like
box index and I think we just want to
have this right cuz it looks like we
need it in a bunch of places so here's
our box index and what we can call us
this our Atlas index maybe so that way
when we do this we can you know just say
get cell center P solution Atlas atlas
grid and then use the Atlas index right
and that gets rid of all this code now
what you might notice is that like the
speck Atlas itself also has the
dimension in it so it feels like maybe
those things kind of want to be
regularized a little bit but
unfortunately I don't think you really
want to do that because they're sort of
a little bit separate it only cares what
the dimension of the voxel is in the in
the actual Atlas ease they don't care
about min corners so it'd be a little
bit weird for them to have their entire
voxel in there and you just have to
update them all the time which I don't
know that we really want now maybe we
would say well okay what what if we
maybe wanted to store them aligned
separately I mean I don't know that that
would even work because they need to be
transferred between but so it's hard to
say like maybe unify those eventually
maybe you don't certainly haven't seen
enough quite yet to know so I'm not
going to do that just yet but looks like
this is a u32 for some reason and I
don't know why because the rest of these
aren't
so let's keep going okay that doesn't
need the second close quote anymore
so okay so in here we've got the spatial
partition build for the KD tree in here
and we're building both of those I don't
really want this anymore I'm pretty sure
we're just never gonna use these again
so I'm not gonna port the KD tree build
it all I think it was just it was the
thing we went down that just didn't pan
out and isn't actually as good as the
grid version okay so in the box index
stuff here where we're doing the get
voxel in extra P these again are just
going to be get index trapeze and
they're going to be passing in this case
the one that we actually want so it's
going to be solution spatial grid and
now that's a lot cleaner like we can see
what's going on there and it's not weird
right
I'm not sure what the I'm not sure what
it doesn't like about that though why is
it complaining about that no it's not it
was just kind of old news all right all
right so now what we need is we need to
do the flat index from here where we say
that we want the flat index in the
spatial grid you know from this index
that we actually have I'm gonna make
that be a box index here right for
spatial index just so it's clear what's
going on there and what I'd like to do
here is I would like to add the code
that we were had been working on when I
went down this road of cleaning up the
voxels what I'd like to do here is just
make it so that these things are
properly clamped right so you know I'd
like to do something along the lines of
rectangle three clipped box equals you
know box box min box box max correct min
max so if we build a spacial rectangle
here and then I intersect this with the
solutions spatial grid total bounds now
I will have clipped the box so that now
we get you know a box that's guaranteed
to be inside our voxel and I can also
just do here like hey if this box is
actually didn't get entirely removed by
that clipping operation then we'll
insert it
and that to me seems like way better I
thought we had that guess we just still
call it has area so I think that's all
good let's try that again I'm not sure
I'm not sure why it does that double I
think that's maybe because it's later
compilation so I think the problem we're
having there is like we haven't actually
included this in here right in the
handmade build so it doesn't know what a
grid is when we get there so let me just
even though we're not working on the
handmade hero actual main body of code
here let's just put that in there okay
so the getfox will index 4p where we
where we pulled that out before we want
to do the same thing again so it's a
little annoying that we do this code
twice but I'm not really sure how else
we would do it because we do need to do
that counting procedure we've already
produced the box bounds here so another
thing we might do is just say well let's
make this unified so that it looks the
same right so now what we want to do is
we want to do the clipped box version
and you know we could just make this
here be box bounds in fact maybe that's
how we'll do it
so we'll just actually say look box
bounds is is this clipped version so
then in here where we do did box bounds
before we're not going to do it that way
we're going to do clipped bounds and
then we're going to check for the the
has area right and we can also do this
and this and then we just need to close
out that check so now I think it's okay
so we've got the box index we checked
the clip box make sure it's in there we
go through the loop to figure out where
we might actually hit oops this is box
bounce now and then assuming that it
actually can hit somewhere will actually
go through and insert it in right okay
now there may be some issues with
efficiency in that code because we're
not telling it about point or a listing
or anything like that but I don't really
care about the performance of this code
at the moment because this code probably
isn't really implicated much in the
performance just yet if we actually see
that it starts to be implicated in the
performance which it might then we would
look at maybe streamlining this because
it's not very well written at this point
for speed it's just kind of doing what
it needs to do and that's the end of it
all right so now as you can see we're
kind of going through doing this spatial
index one last time to clean some things
up so we want to do sort of the same
thing we were doing up there down here
rather than doing it this way otherwise
there isn't much else to say when we do
our letting initialization now we
actually want to do initialization of
these values properly so we want to be
able to take like the voxel dim and the
Inbox seldom and that stuff and set that
properly now to be honest at this point
I don't really think that we probably
need the init lighting code almost at
all really all we probably need there is
the random seed because the voxel dim
and the end of ox seldom are things that
we can just get every time we run
through
so honestly it's unclear how much the
innit lighting call really needs to
happen yeah that it just doesn't it
doesn't make a lot of sense so I think
what we probably would do here is we'd
probably pull this stuff out and we'd
probably go ahead and roll this into the
lighting computation stuff the solution
works here even I don't even know that
that needs to be there
so I think this comment is also correct
so if we go down and look at where we're
actually doing the dispatch I don't know
why we would not just do it here using
the temporary now before we didn't have
a temporary no we just hadn't thought
about that and we hadn't really done
that but it seems pretty clear at this
point that that's what you would do
right so like for example in here if we
were to just say look the there's just a
work array and we know how many there
should be because we computed it we'll
just push that on right here right
that's like way way better
it doesn't pollute the structure with
garbage doesn't need to stick around
because those values are only valid when
you're actually doing lighting work
anyway there's literally no reason for
them to ever actually be there in any
other circumstance so that totally gets
out of the business of bothering with
that garbage which i think is way way
better so I think that's good
and so again I think a lot of this stuff
can just go away the light sampling walk
table is is not so in they can go away
that's something that has to get
computed probably only once because it's
expensive to build and we don't probably
want to build it every frame so taking a
look at an init lighting now I think I'm
going to go ahead and move this stuff
all out of here so I don't know why
update debug lines is set to true I
guess just because in general we
update those we just don't put any on
there for not actually using it but
we're gonna leave that as it is and I'm
just gonna say alright this stuff is
gonna happen in here right oh well I
guess you know what the fundamental unit
though getting passed down I mean really
yeah again that can just be something
passed you know it really could just be
passed every time it doesn't need to be
in a nit lighting right like the
lighting doesn't really care what the
fundamental unit is it can change the
voxel dimensions if it needs to yeah so
I don't know that's a good question and
I'm not sure what should happen there I
guess I'll
I mean I guess I'll just leave it in
there
[Music]
let me go ahead and see where that's
actually called so here's where the
world mode fundamental unit thing comes
in and you can see it you know making
this call here and so you know if the
world mode fundamental unit is just is
just sitting there then you know we
could just pass it to begin lighting I
mean there's no reason not to so when we
do begin lighting computation we could
just say like hey yeah like you know
here's the fundamental unit and you can
have that so there's really no need for
this routine at all and mm-hmm I guess
mostly you know the only thing that's
really using here is is the random seed
so that that entropy unit you know needs
to be set somewhere but again I don't
think that's something that really would
weren't actually calling this so you
know maybe we just do something like
this
so the hoops that's not good so the
random series here where we do the the
random seed out I would think that we
could just do some kind of an
initialization check here like I mean
you know we could just do a thing where
we said like you know if we were gonna
initialize the voxel dim then we
initialized that stuff too right because
it just it's just like it's dumb to have
an init call that you have to make for
no reason
like who why bother making the people
who use this call init when we don't
really need to you know we can just
check some parameters and when we think
that we have to update we just update
everything right so let's let's do it
that way and let's say like ok so when
we come through here and we want to know
about the fundamental units and maybe
what we do is we just say like what's
the fundamental unit and we say if the
solution fundamental units it's not
equal to the fundamental unit then we
now make it that way
and we update all of our base
information right we could also make
this be sort of like a giant like
recompute kind of thing so we could say
it's like alright so if you change any
of the parameters of the lighting system
that are fundamental so if the
fundamental unit isn't the same or you
change the dimensions of the voxel so
now we're computing like higher
resolution lighting or something then we
just do you know all of this stuff over
again and I like that a lot better
because now we can just say look there's
one in it place that even if you know
you know if you're running and you
change you want to like eventually
support things like changing the
lighting resolution on the fly
this way we know that all of the reunit
stuff can just be done in one place and
we don't have to worry about exactly
what the heck is happening there right I
think that's way better that just seems
a lot nicer to me so then we can say
that we've got our table memory and our
temp memory those are basically sort of
split there and then we can just focus
on the rest of the stuff and make sure
that works alright I'm gonna move demote
all this old stuff down to the bottom
because that's going to go away so that
we can just focus on the things that we
actually have I don't actually know that
debug light P is really gonna be used
much at this point either so that'll
probably go away eventually but the rest
of the stuff here is stuff that we
actually believe we will probably be
using at some point the debug lines
obviously maybe will be a separate thing
but you know we'll we'll deal with those
a little bit later so the rest of this
stuff is stuff that we would expect to
actually preserve and so let's try and
put these where they belong so the light
sampling walk table and like the grids
like all this stuff is stuff that we
expect same with the series I guess in a
sense all of this stuff is stuff that we
expect to sort of have persistent and
that's initialized when we start up all
the rest of this stuff so like from here
down is stuff that we don't and I guess
the diffuse weight map would also be a
thing that would be that way and the
sampling spheres and that stuff so any
of this stuff would also be initialized
only once the rest of this stuff is
stuff that's kind of in flux so this is
all stuff that can just vary or that's
done temporarily the spatial grid nodes
and the leaves these are values that
don't persist over time but we don't
really necessarily want to have to pass
those around everywhere
so in other words normally what we would
do is we'd pass these down
and at the moment we're not doing that
primarily because it just seems like an
inefficiency to constantly be passing
them everywhere but what we could do is
say to do you know wrap these in in
their own things so we don't leave them
in the lighting solution since they're
allocated in the temp arena anyway you
know so that's kind of a separate issue
that we probably want to look at at some
point one way or the other
all right so looks like we're just about
out of time I'm going to go ahead and
just finish up a few more the compiler
parts here and then we'll go from there
so the table of oxygen is now really has
to be the same as the spatial grid so
what we want to do here is say look if
the voxel dim for the spec light atlas
we're gonna have to produce what we
would expect the spatial grid to be and
I thought we had that in here somewhere
we were doing the apron offset but I
don't know where that went
for Atlas - spatial
here so here in the internal letting
core like this is that stuff right and
we have the Vox of Timnath apron so this
stuff doesn't want to be done this way
probably now right so what we want to do
is we want to move this stuff out into
the begin lighting because everyone
wants to see it and then we want that
voxel dim with apron part to go away so
if I go back to begin lighting
computation then in here where we've got
this stuff happening we want it these
computations to happen upfront so that
we can then compare them and see whether
they're correct
so in bids fields for taste in builds
fish position for lighting the Fox
lagoon with apron should not actually be
happening anymore and so in begin
lighting I'm sorry in build it is in
build spatial partition box loading with
apron should just be something you now
get out of the solution because it's
like a known value right so in here when
we're talking about box loading with
apron everywhere that's just not
necessary anymore when you look at the
grid count here this could also be
something that we just call and get the
voxels so we could just say like get
total cell count and in here we wouldn't
be using box littered with apron we just
passed the spatial grid and so then in
our voxel code now we can just say hey
get total cell count and this will just
tell us the answer to that question
directly and again this is very simple
it's just the cell count next time -
cell count Y times cell count Z
right no big deal so at that point the
apron should not really be used in here
I don't think yeah so now the only thing
we need to adjust is when we're actually
looping over these this needs to loop
over the one from the actual spatial
grid so this is like solution spatial
grid and in here we have to do the cell
count Z right and it's worth noting that
there's like other ways that we could
actually do this so we don't need to
actually write the loops this way if we
don't want to we could instead write the
loops over the spatial index by just
declaring a thing that increments the
spatial index by incrementing the X and
if it rolls the X increment the Y
instead and so on and it's hard to say
like one of the things that si makes
very difficult is injection of that kind
cleanly it's kind of a long story it's
not worth going into right now but
languages in general do a bad job of of
loop insertion and you know so I'm
probably going to leave it the way it is
at the moment and just chalk it up to
kind of one of those unfortunate aspects
of things okay so moving along this
again is just the spatial grid cell
count and you know what I could do here
is just I could just pull cell count
just so this is a little easier to read
okay so now we just are left with the
anit code and we have to get the init
code right so what we want to do here is
say well alright the spatial grid index
offset also by the way like now there's
should be no calls to init lighting so
you know in a lighting that doesn't have
to occur anymore and that's nice too
alright so in here we're we're to me in
here where we're doing our pre
computation and we just want to make
sure that all of that works properly and
you can see that there's a lot of places
here where we're doing operations they
were previously looking directly out of
the that we're pulling values directly
out of the lighting that now should just
be based off of the voxel so the spatial
grid index offset now is not called that
but it is still a thing we want to keep
it's this right Atlas to spatial grid
index offset and so then what we want to
do is we want to generate our two grids
so here we've got an Atlas grid and a
spatial grid and we want those two to
both be initialized now the tricky part
here is that we want to make sure that
we detect changes to the grid so in
situations where we are getting a
different voxel dim than we had last
time we want to be able to detect that
and we should be able to do that fairly
straightforward by just saying look if
the Atlas dim from last time it's
different than the you know one that we
used last then if the thing we would be
using for the Atlas Tim is different now
like if it changed then we need to
trigger a readjustment of everything
just like we were doing before otherwise
we're fine so we do need to know the
Atlas spatial grid offset and we need to
set that but we don't need to set that
unless we're actually updating things
right so in here we can set this and set
these and let's just go ahead and make
those work so we need to initialize
these two grids
so we want to do that at some point here
you can see us computing a lot of the
dependent values so we want to do our
atlas grid that's the easiest one
because it's in line with what the
lights actually are and then we have the
spatial grid which is like the larger
one now if we look at what goes into
calling makefox LED red we've got the
min corner of the cell count and the
seldom so for each of those we have to
be able to figure out what that actually
is
now the min hot corner is actually
something that gets adjusted like as we
go to so it moves around right and you
can see here like how we're actually
creating that value can actually see it
getting computed here by using like the
origin positions and such right so we
still want this code to actually execute
and so what we're kind of going to do
here is probably just make it up as we
go because anytime that the solution
itself changes like this we kind of just
want to clear everything and restart the
lighting because we know that like we
can't really use any results that we had
from before because they're not going to
be valid anymore anyway so it probably
should be fine
so I'm guessing what we want to do here
is we want to set the Atlas grid and the
spatial grid but probably since the
spatial grid is always dependent we can
probably do that after we determine
where this grid at where the Atlas grid
actually goes right
[Music]
and I think for purposes of computing
the lock table we should still use the
old space the old Atlas grid dimensions
and the reason that I think that is
because I don't want anything to cast
all the way across the larger grid I
want the maximum size that you're ever
going to walk well so that is a bit
tough
these walk tables are just going to be
huge is the problem and I don't love
that so I guess for now all right so
here's what I think what we probably
want to do so looking back at the grid
ray caster right so the cost metric when
we run through here we Dec the cost
metric once each time so like the
maximum cost metric here is bounded so I
think actually this we could get rid of
when we go to compute walk table what we
can do instead is just have the maximum
cells visited as a thing so instead of
ever checking that value like instead of
this what we can do is just say did we
ever go that far right so that seems way
better because if we have that cost
metric in there then I think we because
because before we were thinking that we
wouldn't have to check the cost metric
and now we kind of do
so I think we'll be okay yeah so I think
what we want to do instead here is is
actually say what that's going to be so
I'm gonna say solution like max cost
metric here and I'm gonna set that to
something and you know at the moment
when we did our grid ray cast you know
what did we set it to it was like 16 or
something yeah so the cost metric here
so I'm gonna say like max cost you know
per Ray that sort of thing and we'll say
okay the max cost per Ray is going to be
16 and then we just need to tell the
walk table that that's what's going on
so it's gonna get that max cost for Ray
and it's going to go from there so
that'll be good because then we have
unified those two code paths and we know
what they should be so the max cost per
Ray it's here all right so I do want to
take a look at the compute lock table
code I also don't really know what it's
doing that for so that's kind of stupid
[Music]
so this is dumb and so probably what we
would rather do here right is do this so
that way you know we're we're just
computing the table and then returning
the table right so that way this doesn't
ever take the solution and it doesn't
even know what a solution is it just
takes some information and goes from
there
and then I can also
returned that tests because I don't
think desk gets updated right so it
should be okay so I think that's all
fine and now we can compute that table
and it'll work with the cost per race so
then what we'll do is we'll say all
right instead of the Vox seldom I'm
sorry instead of the voxel count we'll
just say what's the max cost per Ray and
when we loop through these and we try to
determine when we should stop what we'll
do here is instead of tracking span
which I don't know that we ever actually
need to track just take a look yeah so
span is only ever used in for that count
instead of that all we're gonna do is
say look if the cost at this point has
exceeded the max cost per Ray then we
stop
so in here each time as we go we'll say
like if the cost is greater than the max
cost per Ray then we stop alright so
that feels way better and it gets that
dependency out of the mix which i think
is good in the max discount now we know
it's just the max cost per Ray so we now
could just say look it's however much
that max cost is because that's what
we're stepping up to so if we ever
exceed that cost then we're done I guess
I should say if it's equal right so if
we're I mean I guess another way to say
this would be actually this is just a
while loop so this is
you know while cost is less than max
cost per a keep going
and we may want to pad that I don't know
so so like patted max cost per Ray or
something so we may want to let the
tables go a little bit further I don't
know if we want them to be exactly that
tight so let's just do it like that
wasn't quite done there here we go okay
so yeah
Oh No yeah all right so I take it back
because we use the step we flatten the
step down to just be a direct offset
there's not going to be any way around
it
[Music]
yes so that is going to have to be
dependent on that voxel dimension right
because there's because if we want to
bake the offset in directly there's no
other way to do it yeah hmm so that's
unfortunate but do ya I mean that does
look like what we would have to do there
so I guess voxel dim does have to be
there right and so when we actually pass
this in we're gonna have to be able to
we're gonna have to know what the total
cell count is right and that's pretty
much all there is to it I mean it's not
the end of the world but yeah it'd be
nice with us through things were
independent but I don't think they're
gonna be all right so we now know we
know what the voxel seldom is so we know
that whenever we set the fundamental
unit we can then make our voxels so our
atlas grid the Vox seldom and the inbox
seldom is at the moment anyway going to
be the same for both of these so the
voxel dim can be passed to both of these
functions and it's always going to be
the same we don't have to do anything
weird there the Vox will dim on the
other hand or the cell count as it might
be called is going to change so
basically like the the difference here
is going to be this fox logged in with
apron so you know these two are
different there so the
I'm gonna call this the cell count
instead of oxygen and I'm just gonna say
the cell the spatial cell count and the
Atlas cell count right are gonna be
different values so in the case where we
have to recreate these we know what the
cell dim is because it's always the same
and that'll never change just based on
the fundamental unit when we come
through here and we set the Atlas
spatial grid offset that is actually
something that's always the same so we
don't really need to initialize it here
although we might as well because why do
it more than once when we get the
spatial grid count we know what that
actually is it's going to be the Atlas
cell count plus that that spatial grid
index offset so it's plus this value
here and we want that on both sides
because it's a radius expansion
basically and then when we compute the
corners the corners are actually going
to be specified sort of down here right
so when we compute the corners those
that's probably going to happen in a
different place which also suggests to
the suggestible listener that make voxel
probably is not exactly what we want
right and again right the usage code
first this just happened to be something
that I threw in there it doesn't really
seem to be right so if you take a look
at how it actually works we want to be
able to rebase that fairly frequently so
probably what will actually happen is
this and the total bounds will actually
be recomputed fairly often so the min
corner will come in here and it won't
come in there that seems a lot more like
it's and again that's just based on
looking at how the usage code was
working and we want our API to like play
well with that usage code so this is
actually what it should have been and
now we know
so make voxel we'll only take the cell
count in the seldom and hey guess what
that's exactly what we happen to have
and now these two things have converged
nicely so I think that's good the rest
of this I'm gonna ignore real
temporarily here so the Vox seldom here
we can actually we can actually loft
this value like this is always going to
be the same so it's totally fine if
these all want to use the Vox sold in
like this
well this since are using in as well
like I'll just have it get them out of
here so in this case we're gonna talk
about the Atlas grid cell Jim and the in
Vox seldom is the Atlas grid in seldom
and again these are probably things that
we will want to play with a little bit
more later but I'm just gonna leave them
for now since I don't really want to get
into this part of the code at the moment
but all this is is just using those
values right
don't actually delete that okay what the
hey what the hey man okay so that just
about does it for the unit code let's
take a look at this now so what we want
to do now is call set min corner on our
two voxels so basically each voxel wants
to sort of have the ability to be placed
now into their correct location you can
see here that the spatial grid min
corner is going to be slightly different
because it has to use the extra
occlusion radius there so we know that
that is something we actually stored so
that's solution atlas to spatial so we
know what the offset is supposed to be
it's supposed to be this and so we know
how to produce the corner when we have
one and you you know we have one in the
other we're gonna want to be able to get
the minimum corner here
so in this voxel grid we want to be able
to do something like this so anyone who
wants to work with the min corner can do
that so we're gonna set the min corner
by getting them in corner you know of
the other one so the Atlas grid and then
we're gonna subtract that offset like so
I do not know what's going on here for
critters definitely having issues with
the indentation today for whatever
reason which is unusual because I don't
normally see a lot of that but
it's kind of weird I might also do this
so let's do spatial mid-corner and we'll
just compute that like so yeah and yeah
so that should be fine so if I want to
set the Atlas krinsman corner and the
spatial grits min corner I'll just do
spatial mid-corner and Atlas min corner
and I'm not sure what the hot voxel rect
is actually for I guess it's just to set
the bounds and you know in this case in
this case that stuff is probably stuff
you would just get from the voxel
normally right so I mean we can do it
this way if we want to but it's not
really necessary to do it quite this way
so we probably want to streamline this a
little bit but either way here's where
that Vox corner this is the actual value
we care about here so the Atlas min
corner is this
and this value is actually just going to
get done here automatically so we really
don't need to be doing that but again at
the moment I don't know that I actually
want to touch that because there's just
a lot of stuff going on here so I think
that's all good in here where we're
doing our test work here this this stuff
for the internal lighting core stuff in
this particular case where we've got the
work I don't know if we want to pass the
work into the internal lighting core
just so that we can sum it on the
outside that I really don't know I
suppose that's probably fine meaning the
work array would be passed in here but
[Music]
hard to say
since the work count is kind of comp is
kind of like computed in here this is
seems like a better place to do it and
since all you really want to do is take
the summation of these things it seems
like it the better idea would just be to
pass the summation out so that this
stuff is not happening in sort of
arbitrary and weird ways right so if
this is the actual summation that you're
trying to take like you know if this is
what we're actually trying to do then it
seems like a smarter thing to do would
just be like instead of leaking this
information out and having it be kind of
you know unpleasant right I'm not even
sure what I'm not even sure why we're
quite doing it this way there's a lot of
weird stuff happening in here we could
clean a lot of this up
yeah so this this should really look
like this right and really what we
should be doing here saying all right
this is doing a repeat where it's you
know
initializing these work things and
sending them off which it may do in a
loop or it may not right and what I'm
not sure about is why we did this I
guess the reason we did this is because
if we don't have a queue like calling in
the external code we don't want this
because otherwise you could just add the
entries and then this would just work
whether you were a single threaded or
multi-threaded right so kind of annoying
but it's fine
so anyway when this happens then this
will get some Aidid and then we'll we'll
end up being able to return that so the
only thing that I would say here is
instead of this internal lighting core
returning what its returning now we can
do instead is just take the work stuff
here and make this be like a stat
and that way we can just you know return
a lighting stats structure from this
routine and we can make this a little
cleaner later but for now we can just do
this right so now that data will just
come back automatically and we don't
have to deal with this weird like
nonsense where we're returning out the
work count and then like they're looping
over stuff that they don't have
necessarily I like this that was just
dumb right okay so coming back to the
way this was working before so now we
can just say alright the lighting stats
come back through here in a nice clean
way we can then just use those stats
directly as we were about to report them
so all of these are just spats dot oops
right and all of these are just sad stat
that seems like way better then in here
where we're actually like lofting up
these these things in order to basically
make stand-ins
we don't have to do this anymore so we
don't have to fake initialize the work
structures and furthermore we don't have
to do the computation after the fact so
this rolls up in there which is actually
a great that's way way way better
because now we can just do lighting
stats stats and off we go we can also
just pull these out and then not touch
the rest of the code if we want to which
also seems good
okay
the Katie nodes are going away we're not
going to touch that
and the table voxel dim stuff again
don't care about any of that and
shouldn't have to do that anymore
actually Shh
so we'll probably have to call no we
won't because all this stuff will
actually be in there I guess it won't be
because it won't quite be saved so yeah
this stuff is going to be a little bit
trickier so yeah one problem we're gonna
have a little bit here is calling the
begin lighting thing
[Music]
we may want to call the begin function
and let it do what it's going to do like
in other words we may want to call big
you may want to instead of calling
internal i t'ink or directly we may want
to actually call the full thing right
and maybe like this collapses down into
something that you know maybe this
collapses down into one call anyway
eventually effect let's take a look at
that so here's another question so the
other question is just yet so you can
kind of see here so the reason that we
need it the reason that there's even a
begin letting call at all is because of
the set light bounds saying so the
question is is like did we really need
that to be the case and I guess the rete
the thing is like the reason that has to
occur is just because if we don't call
set light bounds then the the pixel
shaders that operate in this part of the
code you know won't know how to look up
their lighting in the voxel right that's
the actual problem and so that's the
reason that this stuff is happening in
here but it seems like you know we could
just track the inputs to this and
actually just let all of this stuff run
that would be a better way of testing
this code I think
yeah I mean that would just be way
better right and that way you know we
can just we can just make this code be
like run in its entirety so I feel like
internal lighting core can just be
simplified into end lighting and we can
just call both of these so and what we
do is we just so if you look at what
would happen here where you call if you
look at where the render group actually
gets used in here it's just to figure
out what those what those basic values
are so it seems like it should be fairly
straightforward to do and it's a little
bit of a bummer like it does seem like
maybe the set light bands and enable
lighting stuff maybe should happen kind
of at one level above this in other
words it would probably be nice to sort
of separate these things out a little
bit and not have them actually be
retrieved directly from the game render
commands to keep this and the renderer
separate right because we're almost able
to do that and really all we need to
know is the atlases that we're supposed
to use we don't really need anything
else
and so if we were to move these things
up
that seems really desirable to me so I'm
going to do that so I think what we want
here is like set lighting values or
something so these things here where
we're calling into the group so this
stuff here this is what we would
actually do where we would set the
lighting enabled up here and then we'd
actually make the calls in this and
similarly like all of the stuff that was
operating on the group would happen in
here so that way you'd have the render
group in here and the lighting solution
you'd do these operations anytime you
wanted them done and you'd get the hot
voxel rect you'd actually get that in
here instead right and
yeah yeah yeah so in here what we do is
we'd say okay we can get these things we
we actually know we can get the total
bounds by just looking at the Atlas
itself so if the Atlas grade we could
just say what's the total bounds that's
that box we already know what that is
and then in order to get the actual
dimension of it because we need the
inverse then we can just say to get the
dimension of the hotbox lurex and then
we're done right so this can be a
self-contained function and we don't
actually need surprise that compiled we
don't actually need the render group
anywhere so then in here where we look
at what we actually needed the commands
for you can see that basically what we
need is we just need the two atlases so
what this actually should be doing here
instead of passing the render group at
all is it should probably be passing
more specifically it probably would need
to pass the the two atlases so we would
have one lighting Atlas it's a speck at
least one Atlas that's the diffuse Atlas
and so these are the two lighting
atlases that the renderer is using and
this will update that them so then you
wouldn't need the game render commands
you could just look at the spec atlas
and then down here where you actually
have to operate on those
you just do I think that's what we would
want so now that's kind of like you know
separated out and you need to call both
of these things right so you need to
call begin lighting computation because
you need to be able to you know figure
out where things are going to be and
really it's not begin lighting
computation that's probably a misnomer
right it's really like setting the
location of it
so what you're really doing is saying
more like set lighting region or
something or like compute lighting
region or change lighting region update
lighting region I don't know what you
want what it would be called set
lighting region bounds I don't know so
really what we're doing here is we're
we're doing something more like this
which is like setting up you know set up
lighting region and like you know push
lighting render values or something like
this you're not good names but I'm not
sure how you actually describe what's
happening here one is setting up sort of
where lighting is happening right and
the other is actually telling the
renderer what it needs to know so this
is just saying where the lighting is
going to happen we've got the render
group and this where we're pulling out
those lighting values in here right so
it's it's really this process where we
need to be able to send those things
so we need to be able to say here's the
diffuse atlas and here's the spec atlas
right and we need to send those down
because the lighting region needs to
know about them unfortunately so I'm not
sure what this is complaining about is
the render group that pointer yes it is
so getting closer to good still not
entirely fabulous you know but better
and then for end lighting computation
you know this has sort of the debug
output which could be split into a
separate path and the diffuse atlas and
spec atlas here could be passed again or
could be cached and i assume that may be
the right thing to do is to actually
cache those values when you set up the
lighting region because they can't
change like it would be very bad if you
switched which ones they were in the
middle of that so yeah like hard to say
but anyway when we do the end lighting
computation in here just taking a look
at what's happening this debug stuff
could definitely be in a separate piece
it doesn't need to be in there at the
moment so I'd also say maybe we could
have like push lighting debug values is
a separate thing and that way anything
that was operating kind of on you know
debug information and pushing that out
to the renderer can be done in a
separate place as well so basically like
push letting debug values oops
would be a separate thing I don't know
where the and letting computation is
there it is
so in here we'd say like yeah okay hmm
that's a separate thing you can do if
you want the debug stuff to happen but
it's not entirely necessary and I'm not
sure where the setup part comes in does
this actually use that it doesn't so
that isn't really necessary
and again the disputes out the suspect
list I guess for now I'll pass them in
but if we should like see what we
actually want to do about that because
I'm not entirely sure
maybe those just get cached those are
things that are kind of that bridge to
systems and so it's always a little bit
delicate when you have a situation like
that and as we're starting to clean this
code up it's something we can think
about how we really want to do that so
instead of an letting computation I'm
gonna call this update lighting because
that's what it actually is and off we go
so now we shouldn't need the commands
anymore here in terms of the boxes that
get passed through this stuff is now
part of like where we're actually doing
the yeah like all of this stuff where we
have the the boxes that come through
here that should actually be that should
actually be what gets passed to update
lighting right so these bits here
yeah
so these bits here we say update letting
so we say set the render region above
and then we say hey update the lighting
for this set of occluders and all that
stuff right and I think that's more or
less how that has to go if there's any
other way it's kind of nasty but you
have this like split problem where you
want things to be flowing in a
particular way and I don't think there's
any other way to do it okay so you get
the two atlases and then you get the
occluder account and the what are these
lighting box and the occluders you know
for now we're storing these but I'm not
sure they really should be in there
so as we clean this up though those may
go away as well
there's the occluder count in this case
render group it's never just called a
group and it looks like the platform
lighting queue for some reason didn't
get moved down to where I actually
wanted it in the parameter list which
was there all right
so I think that's good this is starting
to get more towards good I think that's
much better so I think these functions
at least now properly reflect what they
do which is good now we've got a bunch
of work left to do we'll pick it up
tomorrow we can go to a brief Q&amp;A for a
few minutes but we're already over time
so I'll keep it pretty brief
anyone have any on topic questions
oh yeah so we kind of didn't finish that
code yet unfortunately
that you're talking about there with the
Atlas min corner so I can kind of button
it up a little bit now but we kind of
need to to do it a little bit
differently
so this part is probably fine because
these will be set to zero initially and
then when we move through here yeah
you're right so we just want to use
Atlas min corner here like so
thanks for that catch that saves us the
trouble of finding him tomorrow I think
that's probably correct now in sohbat
that's very good in sohbat
yes so the reason that 603 and 604 are
not on YouTube yet oh sorry so 601 and
602 is because OBS is amazing and messed
up the recording on one of them and I
have to like go extract it from the
twitch stream properly so and OBS is a
real treasure I mean you get what you
pay for
right
max node in well max node index doesn't
exist anymore but I I know where you're
talking about you're talking about this
is this the part you're talking about
was the assert in bounds
this part
I'm not sure I know exactly what people
are asking here so you'll have to tell
me I think both parts both pieces of
code that you're talking about are now
on the screen so I'm not sure
it's missing the grid pointer you know
you're right how long have we left it
like that unbelievable that's a bit of
an owl shame there so hey now we have
our certs back they were turned off
there for a minute I was like how was
that compiling that's how it was
compiling yeah
so another thing I should do before we
go any further is I'm going to delete
the lighting record that we had so in
handmade debug we've got all these dumps
I'm gonna delete those because they're
wrong now so we're gonna want we're
gonna want to recapture and retest
everything tomorrow starting from
scratch right so I'm just gonna get
those out of there real quick all right
we'll pick this up tomorrow okay thank
you everyone for joining me for this on
handmade hero sort of pleasure coding
with you as always if you would like to
follow up series at home you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hear it
out or gonna come to the source code so
that you can follow along there's a
whole bunch of like debugging and
streamlining work that we're doing right
now so it's totally stuff that you could
try if you're looking for something to
practice at home that's what I'll be
doing tomorrow and you can try it
tonight and see how far you get that's
it for today I'll be back here tomorrow
until then have fun partnering everyone
and I'll see you in the Internet Dicky's
everybody