start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade hero the show recode
a complete game live on stream we did
well I guess we did much of the work
yesterday but not quite all of the work
necessary to start having the concept of
separate layers for our rendering in
terms of Z so that we actually have
specific layers of graphics that operate
in Z and then we've got sort of a a
separate Z that's used inside those
layers to do y displacement and this is
relatively important for a number of
reasons because do the 2.5 d nature of
this game or maybe i don't know if you
would i don't know what you would call
it the 2.2 d we're basically a 2-d game
but we do have this concept that rooms
can be stacked on top of other rooms and
you can see those other rooms by looking
through holes in the floor or otherwise
so given that fact the question is you
know how do we present this in a
reasonable way to the to the viewer and
what we found on handmade hero is we
kind of wanted there to be a Z which is
just y base so it just kind of moves
things higher or lower on the screen
based on Z for kind of a standard
orthographic z feel but then having a
sort of scaling effect was very nice for
rooms above other rooms or rooms below
other rooms to kind of give that nice
feeling of depth and so we wanted both
of those and that means that we have to
have this notion that there are sort of
two kinds of Z values one that creates
that scaling effect and one that just is
a y displacement and so we never really
got that nailed down and so here in our
sort of waning time when we're winding
down sort of engineers and transitioning
into gaming things it's important for
this I think to be nailed down so we did
some of that and today we need to kind
of finalize some of those decisions or
at least try to get as far as we can
towards finalizing how we
Phi Z down to the rendering system
alright so today in case you missed it
is day 2 98 so if you want to follow
along at home unpack day 297 source code
into a directory somewhere and that's
when i'm starting with at the moment as
they say they don't probably actually
say that all right so let's see where we
were at at the end of yesterday's stream
in case you don't remember where we left
off what we did is we actually put in
all the code for doing those slices and
we just haven't actually worked with the
Z yet and so what's happening right now
and what's kind of very confusing
actually and you can sort of see this
happening directly here if you'll notice
we only put one Mon star and one snake
in each room that's what the startup
code was programmed to do and yet you
see two snakes and two Monstars as well
as a weird split stairwell so what's
going on here well what's going on here
is at the end of yesterday stream we had
just finished the code which splits
tiles into layers and then assigns those
those are strings with style splits
entities into layers and then assigns
them their Z within that layer as the Z
they send to the render and what you can
see happening right now is exactly that
sort of flattening down to a single
layer that's happening because of that
since we have nowhere to put the layer
part of the Z that we extracted right so
what you're actually looking at right
here is the first floor of the game that
our little test generator generated and
the second floor that's stacked on top
of it both drawn on top of each other in
the same place hence two snakes and two
monsters right you can also see that the
snake and the Monstar one of the sets of
those is highlighting the tiles and the
other isn't and that's because those
tiles that the other snake in monster on
are being drawn underneath right this
set of tiles they're right on top of
each other but underneath you know as a
different layers because someone's going
to win that fight right and so the ones
that they're stepping on are getting
highlighted underneath but you can't see
them because they're going to cover it
up immediately right so that's what
you're seeing you're seeing that's that
kind of smoosh so our job today is to
sort of continue forward with this and
start actually doing those assignments
and clean up the renderer path so that
it understands the difference between
layers e which will be something
specified separately and a the regular Z
value which will always be used for y
displacement and which isn't getting
used for y displacement at the moment
and again this is of course trickier
than you might think because it is
inherently a non-systemic concept you
know I'm a 3d graphics programmer if I'm
a graphics programmer at all and so I'm
very used to deliver things in 3d it's
always a little bit challenging to then
go down to 2d because we're faced with
all these weird decisions and weird kind
of pipeline cases of instead of
everything just being handled in the
uniform 3d environment we've kind of got
this weird thing it's like oh well we
want Z to mean this sometimes in this
some other times so it's kind of this
gradual winnowing process of trying to
get things to flow down the pipeline in
a way that preserves the information
that is necessary while not saving more
information that is necessary and blah
blah blah blah blah so let's go ahead
and start taking a look at that like I
said it is a little more challenging
than you might think simply because we
can't just go to an established math
book or an established standard and go
here is how we represent these things we
have to make it up as we go along for
and get something that will be
appropriate for our game in our
circumstance so I'm going to go ahead
and go to the handmade render group here
and you can see as I look at this we can
kind of take a look at what's happening
in the current Z state we know that we
set up perspective or orthographic
transforms we know that we call get
render entity basis p and that is what
does RZ work here and you can see
already there's some shenanigans
happening in
here right where we've got our x and y
and those are kind of coming through in
a specific way that that the Z does not
right and you can see that the offset p
which is a separate thing does get added
in there from the auto transform in a
way that does preserve the Z and then
the pee comes through in a particular
way blah blah blah blah blah right so
you can definitely see that there's a
lot of janky pneus to this transform
right there's a lot of like kind of
special purposes to transform and so our
job here is just to try and streamline
this as much as possible and try to make
it coherent what is going to go on with
Z here and as you can see from you know
this this a straight line through the
code know where do we actually put Z
into X or Y what we do instead is use a
regular perspective modification to
actually just do the correct XY
displacement so we never have a manual
assignment of Z to X or Y even though
what we want to do now is have a manual
transfer of the Z of something to be
inserted in that gym name we want sort
of that that XYZ we want to make sure
that that works the way we would expect
now we do have won overwhelmingly I
guess one overriding concern and
something that I'm not exactly sure how
we're going to handle it's the one part
that's kind of a little bit like now I'm
not sure to do with this right and that
is the one time we actually care about
the difference between these two ways of
handling z &amp; 2 I guess put a sort of
phrase on it it's it's the you know the
changeover point
so what you can sort of if you can
envision it right we have a situation
where we've got you know a we've we've
got slices in the game that want to be
doing they're sort of 3d transform and
we've got these situations where I can
like have a floor and I can see down to
potentially something on the lower floor
right now I'm assuming that what we want
to do is to try and enable stuff like
somebody who might hop from one thing
down to another one we want to make that
be something that is you know possible
or plausible right and we need some way
of drawing it and the problem that we
have is that if down in here you've got
this situation where things on the lower
level are scaled differently right then
things on the upper level at some point
we need to linearly interpolate between
those two scalings right and because if
we don't it'll just pop right as the
thing jumps it'll go from being that
size to being that size instantaneously
whereas what we would much rather it do
is to scale down more gradually or at
least it has some kind of smoothing
period that would make it less jarring
now if you remember what we're sort of
saying if we look at this from the side
right so I'm going to tilt these like
this so we can kind of see both of them
in in a prospective II kind of way right
so if I've got an object like this and
it's going to pass through here then
what I'm saying is that somewhere in
between these regions scaling must occur
right for this thing to get smaller if
it happens to be drawn this size down
here and this size up here right so
there's got to be some kind of a
transition region below the floor I
guess or something like that that is
where that scaling occurs now
furthermore
has to be some area where the scaling
wouldn't occur and the reason that that
has to be true is because if we want
displacement by z2 just yield a y
displacement then what we're going to
see on the screen if something is
supposed to be floating upwards and then
downwards again is just a little bit of
an upward motion and then a little bit
of a downward motion and it's not going
to change scale right it's not going to
get bigger or smaller so that is the
problem that we're facing and I suspect
although i do not know that the most
straightforward way to handle it would
be to do almost exactly what I have
drawn here and really don't try to be
any fancier and see if that's enough
right and that is to say that there is
going to be a certain definition of what
the floor height is right now we've got
a parameter called typical floor height
and will probably change that to just be
called floor height because that's how
big one sort of slice is and what we
will do is we'll take the top part of
this and we'll assign this this top part
to be the scaling region and then we'll
assign this this part here instead of
this instead of this being scaling will
assign this here to be the the
displacement region and so when we look
at a Z we know that if it's in here it's
going to have its scaling interpolated
right and its position so in this region
it's actually changing its Z right and
in this region it's not another way to
look at this right would be to say that
there is a you know there is the actual
world space Z transition between these
two things this is the full floor height
and if we were to just pump Z through
normally we would get that full sizing
and displacement that we were getting
before that we said we need to get rid
of inside a single floor what we
effectively want to do is map this
entire height of Z displacement into a
much
mahler region right so that what we will
do is will hand the renderer Z values
for scaling and and XY sort of standards
each changes will hand it a much wider
varying Z then it would be normally
warranted in this area and then we'll
lock the Z and not very it in here and
instead use some kind of Y displacement
there right so that's what we want to do
and like I said it's it's a little
tricky to get right and we have to make
decisions about who is making these
determinations and when so it's it's a
it's a little bit of a it's a little bit
of a tough one but that's the that's
what we have to do okay so at the same
time I think we want to be cognizant of
one other issue that we have and that we
need to keep keep under control guess is
what I would say and that is that we
have a a sort of a notion of blocks that
you are going to be on and we haven't
talked too much about this because we'll
probably wait to sort of do this fully
until we've got an art pack in place
which will probably send out at some
point over the next month or two we have
a sort of situation where we're going to
have like blocky pieces because like I
said you're going to have these things
that you jump on and they could be
displaced in Z right and you know we've
got sort of it an emulation or not an
emulation a sort of simple version of
this here you can even see it happening
like here we have a problem with this
which is that even after we get Z slice
stuff correct you're still going to have
this concept of of the floor kind of
fighting with with characters to know
who to sort and as humans we always know
who to sort because it makes a sort of
concrete sense to us how we might do
that right we
kind of know that well let's suppose
that in this situation I have a
character standing up on this this sort
of pillar here right and I'm going to
kind of draw a little shading here so
you can kind of see what I'm talking
about right if there was a sort of a
tower if you will right in front of the
sky that extended all the way up here
right and this tower was like obviously
in front of this person you know we know
because that thing is closer to us we
know that it would draw in front of
these people right so all of this stuff
is all in front of this individual and
if there was a tower like that that was
behind him right even if it was the same
height right exactly the same height it
would be behind him yeah and that's
again because we sort of have this
notion of a of where things are in the
wat out in the Y of the world as well as
where things are in the Z of the world
and we're only sorting by the y right
and not only are we only sorting by the
Y but we're sorting by the Y in a really
really weird way which says that like
the thing that I'm standing on here you
know is underneath me at certain times
and and it would be in front of me at
other times because even though it's why
is technically in front of me or behind
me or whatever I know that it's a talent
i'm standing on in blah blah blah so we
need to have some coherent system on how
these are sorted and my suspicion is
we're going to basically need to do this
with some kind of a like you know
hotpoint rule which is to say that i
think we want something where we can
strictly sort by a real value look we
probably want to do like sort by you
know why then Z or something like this
right we want something very
straightforward like that and so what I
think we're going to have to do because
you know right now we got a hack in
there that does like is this tile
right or is it flat I don't think that's
going to last I don't think that will
actually work right so I think what we
need to do is we need to start doing
something where whatever the points are
that we're sorting their place to make
sure that they will produce the correct
results in all cases so for example what
I think we need to do is we were
previously taking tiles and we were
saying that their center point right was
the Y value that they were getting
sorted on now that's a problem because
what that means is as soon as the hero
is here right if this is the basis point
for the hero he's now behind the tile
and the tile will draw in front of him
whereas if he's here he is in front of
the tile and he'll draw in front of it
as he should so I think the answer to
this rather than setting the thing to be
upright I think what we want to do
instead is say let's always make the
rule that we set the Y placement for
sorting like we could even have a
special point for sorting that that
bitmaps have the Y placement for sorting
for a bitmap for a title we could just
place the Y back here because then
that's always correct right if this is
the placement for the Y then anything
behind this placement will be drawn
properly behind it which is what we want
if this thing can get below it right now
there's a slight caveat there which is
when something moves behind something
else it doesn't do so on a strictly
point basis right so we probably need to
say that the point for sorting for this
guy maybe is even further back than that
I don't know because they're sort of the
concept still that shadows have to be
placed on here and that sort of stuff so
you know that if if we use the strict
strict why a sorting system we would
definitely be able to make points sort
properly but things with size are not as
easy right they're still a little
trickier and so that question
unfortunately is not one that I really
no I I don't know what the
I don't know what the easy answer is to
it right I don't know what we would do
specifically for that because sometimes
like I said the hero would be behind
this floor right and the example there
is suppose we were looking from the side
and the hero is standing here if we are
viewing that from this direction right
then clearly this tile should sort in
front of the hero right we would not
want to see the hero because all this
stuff should be blocking him so this
part should all be blocked however take
the exact same circumstance the exact
same one and it looks like this so all I
just move this tile and put it down so
exact same circumstance and all I did
was lower this tile well now when I look
at this this tile probably should not
appear in front of the hero and the
reason for that is if there was a shadow
blob here that shadow blob would get
clipped by this tile which is not what
we want we want the shadow blog to
appear on the tile right and that's true
for any part of the hero that extends
past the sort point form as well now if
we cheat this and say well ok a que si
you probably can get away with with
adjusting the sort point on the hero as
well so let's say that it's got sort of
this shadow blob or or you know the feet
or like this whatever instead of placing
the point for sorting there you know
maybe you place the point for sorting
here well if you place the point for
sorting here then you have the problem
where this now we'll show the hero in
front of this tile right because the
fact that this point for sorting is
moved up to the front means that I can't
actually count it to do the right sort
here
so you can see why this is a really big
problem and I I I don't really know what
the most effective way is to solve it I
think what we you know it's plausible
that the most stable solution and I
don't know if this is true or not
because I haven't thought about it for
very long but it's plausible that we
might get some mileage out of actually
using the 3d nests of the scene to help
us and I'm not sure one way or the other
if that's an improvement or not but
obviously you know the sort of the the
fact that we can take a look at what
we're actually looking down at this
thing the fact that we know where these
things occur relative to the view
direction in actual 3d might help us I
don't know if it will effort won't but
it's possible that's something we need
to take into account the other shoe me
the other thing we can do here is we
might be able to do something where we
use against some sort of Z biasing you
know maybe the upright thing that we
were using before maybe we can still use
that for handling the shadow case I
don't really know but yeah so this is a
really nasty problem like I said I don't
feel like I have a really great solution
to it it's a kind of thing we don't
super have to deal with a whole lot in
real 3d because you know this is
something that you can use the actual
geometry to sort of figure out although
sometimes to do get nasty stuff like
this when you're trying to do relatively
precise things or shadow buffers or
those sorts of things where you end up
actually having some nasty cases where
you're trying to figure out what's in
front of what and it's not as
straightforward as it might seem but on
the whole we don't have to deal with
this sort of thing where there is a
conceptual sort that we know that we
want and we have to figure out how to
get that conceptual sort
and yeah it's a little bit tricky so I
don't have a solid solution for this all
I know is that we are definitely going
to have to address it and it's something
that the renderer has to be aware of or
perhaps not really that aware of and
it's just something that we use sort
keys for on the client side but I mean
on the you know not client side but on
the user side of the renderer and we can
just say well you know it's going to
produce sort keys that magically make
this thing work but no matter where we
push that problem to ultimately since
I'm the only programmer you know we're
going to have to deal with it
unfortunately we can't just pass the
buck so and now I think about it since
I'm drawing these cases out here I
wonder if we should spend a second
thinking is there is there anything
smarter to do before I go typing maybe
there is some kind of an insight we can
gain here I mean what's the difference
really between these cases that makes it
true right so what we're doing
effectively is we're you know we're
saying that there's sort of this
variability that comes in whereas as I
lower this thing down as soon as I reach
a z-value that's lower right then then
then here i want to draw the stuff on
top of it still and since so if there's
sort of this notion that the z value is
the thing that determines whether
something goes on top and
stated sort of a little bit alternately
right if this if this thing is above the
sea level of the of the hero we would
not draw the shadow on it and if it's
below the the sea level of the hero we
would write so what's interesting about
that is in the case of the shadow it's
really just the Z value that determines
the sort order of the shadow against
pretty much anything in the scene I
guess everywhere because since we know
that these things are all on the same
plane any right there they're all
they're all in the same they're not
tilted right and so it's sort of like
you have this notion of Z planar sorting
and anything that's you know in that
sort of screen plane whatever the Z
value of it determines who draws first
and then I guess the other people there
Y value determines who draws first so I
think that does sort of suggests that
the upright the concept of whether
something is upright or not does sort of
seem to be a lot about what's you know
which one of those two kinds of bitmaps
you are does seem to have a big
implication for how you're supposed to
be rendered right
so let's think of a few more cases here
so let's suppose that I've got this
situation
so I have hero and hero is standing on
something back here and then something
up here is obviously shadowing like not
shouting but occluding the hero so you
can't see the hero because there's a
giant column in the way right so how do
I know to sort the hero behind this
column right well the Z value would tell
me that but if I had an equivalent
column here it's z value would also sort
from the hero and obviously that's not
true right obviously the hero should not
be drawn in front of this but it should
be drawn in front of this and so here we
have the y value telling us what gets
drawn in front of of what right so the Y
value does does give us that piece of
information right and it seems as though
in this case when we're trying to decide
how to draw the hero when we're trying
to determine the sort order of these
things we want them to draw in Y order
but when we are trying to draw the hero
relative to one of these right this is
where we actually start to care about
the Z so once the Z value comes down
below the Z value of the hero we now
want to pesum eyes this so it looks to
me kind of like what you would say is
you sort in Y and then the Z if you were
already less than this then whatever the
thing was and why then y or z value
determines
whether you will sort in front of or
behind if you aren't right so if I
compared to people if I compared to
Emmett to render instructions I would
say well when I compare these two if one
has a y value that is greater than well
you know what this is not why this is
actually why I cuz i think i was saying
the camera was looking here right so y
goes up the screen and perhaps more
accurately this is the camera but yeah
so if I'm looking at this I would say
well if something has a lesser y value
then you know if we have a and B right
if and you know a this is a and this is
B if a has a lesser y value than B then
it's going to be drawn first unless it
has a lower Z value right
so that unfortunately seems to still
give because that I mean if if if i
phrase it that way exactly then that
just means you sort by z first and then
why right i mean that's what that would
do and if we did that then we have that
same problem of of this thing isn't that
going to sort this thing wrong because i
look at these two things and I say well
no but I guess his Z value is still less
so that seems fine too
so I'm trying to think of cases where
that doesn't work sorting by Xion than
my why because it seems like that still
would work even in this case because as
this thing gets lower right right if I
sort by Z first
if I sort by Z first then this guy would
draw second in these cases so that's why
this doesn't work I already enumerated
this case right so my brain is really
slow today so if we're looking at this
guy we'd say well you know kizzy is
higher so he'd sort in front of this guy
which is not correct he needs to sort
behind him because of the y right so we
have this problem of the Y sort still
needs to be effectual and we just have
these a couple cases in where we where
we would need to look at Z to say we
want to override that behavior so that
we don't accidentally sort incorrectly
in this case right and I'm really just
not sure how to make that happen without
causing other cases to be wrong because
it seems like you know either when we
pick that's obviously not going to be
right but if we do why then Z which does
everything correct most of the time we
then end up with this problem of you
know we end up with this problem for
having trying to have shadows fall on
other things and stuff like that so if
we were going to try and fix that uh how
would we do it you know what would I do
that would make that work and I don't
know I guess one way to do it would be
to make shadows be something that we're
handled a little bit separately so
trance things that are transparent like
that like brown shadows would maybe just
have to be handled separately so you
just wouldn't ever have that case you
would always handle shadows as things
that fell on to specific bitmaps and you
know maybe that's a smarter way to have
that work so there isn't one shadow for
the hero there's one shadow for the hero
for every tile and it's adjusted per
tile so that we know that it's going to
be sorted correctly on to that tile I
could see that being reasonable
similarly we could ask the question how
do we know that the hero sorts
above the tile right and right because
the Thailand and the hero would both be
at the same kind of point to a certain
degree but I think that could probably
be handled by the fact that these would
have higher Z values now so these would
all sort in the same y effectively but
the Z would be the thing that would
would tell you that and well or the
other thing would be placing the sort
point back further
so let's suppose that what we did was we
placed for things that are flat we
placed the sort point at the back and
for things that are standing upright we
place them at the base right that would
appear to always work properly if you
take out shadowing right if you take
shadowing out of the equation I feel
like that works correctly because now
you are always going to sort these in
front of these if they're on top of each
other but once it moves behind it will
sort behind it as it should right and
that might be workable that might be
workable
and then you really like I said you only
have one thing to do at that point you
just have to sort by the Y and then
inside why I don't know if you have to
sort any more than that but you probably
want to sort by Z after that just in
case right so like with the hero you
know where it's stacked on top of each
other you want the higher things to be
drawn first typically but that could
also just be a fudge value that we use
because typically that's going to be
more subject to just whatever we want
since that you don't really move in Z to
occlude very often
I think I'm pretty happy with that I
think that's all right but again what
this requires is is that the sort key is
computed in a very specific way it
requires the sort key to be computed
separate from what might be like the
pivot point of an object or something
that relates to its placement in the
world we need a sort of separate notion
of here is the sort handle and that sort
handle this placed you know very
specifically but that doesn't seem to
owner asst I'm trying to think if there
are any problems with that and that
would also get us out of the business of
specifying whether something's up right
or not because it's basically just
whatever you set up initially as that as
that sort point is what would determine
whether things sorts in a way that's
similar to the upright versions or
similar to the lying flat versions yeah
so let's take a look in our code here so
I kind of got off on this tangent of
fixing that problem I kind of want to
take a look here at what's going on with
that as well so in here when I do a
where am i where I do a push bitmap call
in here you can pass the sort key
through can't you or at least you could
before well it's computed by the render
basis so when you do a push for under
element you do pass in whatever the sort
key is that you actually wanted to use
and so what I could do is I could make
that so that when we do a push bitmap
call we sort of compute that that sort
key here based on what I just said so
the inputs to the to this system could
be that and I don't see so the c-line
value I'm curious to know where we use
the c-line value
I think we use the C Line value mostly
for debugging purposes right we use that
so that if we want to show a bitmap it
doesn't get displaced by anything I
think that's really the only thing we do
there and I'm not sure that that was the
most efficient way to do that but that's
yeah that's how that happened so the
question is here all right if we wanted
to make this be more explicit on the
sort key stuff we would have to sort of
pass a sort key through here in some way
and this this basis sort key stuff of
course is also problematic because
presumably there's information in there
that we wouldn't know else otherwise
right like for example meters two pixels
effects this from the camera transform
although in theory if everything's being
multiplied by meters to pixels then it
doesn't really matter this is going to
be real tricky it's going to be real
tricky to get right
all right well anyway so if we want to
to take a look at this what we need to
do is say well there would be a
secondary point passed in here really
and the secondary point is the one
that's actually used for sorting that
makes sense and so we kind of need to
transform you know to do like to
transform one to transform the point
that we're actually using and one to do
the transform for whatever that sort
point is now since we have the concept
of a scaling value we should though
probably we could probably fake this by
saying after you perform this transform
if the second if the sort the part where
we're passing down the sort if that's
just expressed as a delta right because
that's all it's ever going to be it's
just it's just a delta off of the actual
point that we're projecting we need some
way of applying that Delta after the
fact and the scale value kind of gives
us that ability right so what we could
do is say well you know whatever the
sort key is would be something like a
displacement and we know that the
displacement in X doesn't matter so we
really just have a sort bias at the end
of the day right there's really just a
sort bias and the problem is that before
we were doing when we're applying this
sort bias we aren't scaling the sort
bias by the scale that comes in here but
if we were to start scaling the sort
bias then that would fix the problem so
if we scaled by the sort bias and placed
those those biases so that they were at
the tops and bottoms of bitmaps in why
this would then presumably work
similarly we could then say well this
whole nonsense here with the original pz
in the two x pz and the blah blah blah
blah blah blah blah write that stuff
should also be able to be handled
directly now where we could say well
object transform upright is is not
necessary anymore right we know that Y
is being sorted on
as sort of a separate entity but here i
guess and this is a little bit weird it
looks like we're sorting by Z it looks
like we're sorting by Z much more
strenuously than x y which is the
opposite i think of what i said should
happen so that's a little bit tricky i
think that may have been a slight
mistake I think I don't think that's
what we wanted but i'm going to name
these things a little bit cleaner here
so we have two things we have the layers
e or the prospective z you might say and
we have the displacement z right and
when and we're going to have to know
what those are and so when we do our
transform here those two Z values are
going to be used in a different way so
our perspective Z is definitely you know
is the one that is the most important
sort value because if you have another
layer that layer is definitely going to
cause the sorting to be predominant
right so that's always the case that if
you're going if you're on a particular
layer you have to have that as your most
important sort criteria so that's true
but then in addition to that we have the
matter of the the actual Z values here
where we've got the displacement Z and
then we've got the py value so the P the
P Y value is going is what we're saying
has to be dominant over the displacement
Z so that is going to have to be you
know again another sort of power up and
then the the displacement Z is the final
bit of information there that we have
where we're trying to we're trying to
figure out how this would be factored in
and I think the higher that Z the higher
up you want to sort right so I think
this is close to what we said we wanted
to do on the blackboard but like I said
we have a slight problem here which is
to say that the the Y value that we're
using in the sorting that wants to be
adjusted by the fact that we may just
place it from the center of the bitmap
or wherever else right so the the sort
bias i would say in here is a modifier
on the y value so i think that is
perhaps the more the more correct full
transform so i would say there's the
there's basically the perspective sort
term and that's this there's the y sort
term
and that's this and then there's the Z
sort term and that's this and so our
final equation is just the perspective
of times the sort of the why I'm sorry
plus the y plus the Z so I think that's
what we want and this particular piece
of information here where we have that
sort bias so it's not really a
quote-unquote a sort by us anymore but
you know whatever we can rename that
easily so the point is we have this
other piece of information here and
that's that's what we would use to
displace the sort properly but now the
question is well we've actually got to
get these other values from somewhere
and that's easier said than done
certainly right and so when we find
ourselves in this routine with a sort of
an object transform coming through and
then this placement transform and that
kind of stuff what we have is we were
sort of cheating here by saying well we
had an original p and we got we sort of
stole the we sort of since we had two
separate things we were specifying an
object transform and then an offset off
of that object transform we kind of
cheated and said well one of the Z's
will be a displacement see and one of
the disease won't but that caused a lot
of problems and it's just not very clear
so I think what we want to do instead is
pass the layers e separately right and
we're just going to have to extend our
notion of what that means and just make
that work we're going to have to have
that in addition which means we probably
will have to say well the original p is
maybe now a v4 its XY displacement Z
layer Z or something like that right
that may be the most straightforward
thing to do so then when we say that
we've got a v3 P here we would no longer
be doing we would no longer be doing
this sort of thing instead we would
treat these as the same and produce our
perspective p from the actual XYZ and
then there's sort of that displacement
see that's additional on the end right
now again that's still a little bit
confusing because it's unclear which you
know which you would want to do do you
want the third you know we've got four
elements in a vector if we were doing it
before do we want the third element or
the fourth element or I should say that
third the the the tooth or the third
which of these do we want to be the one
that does perspective and which of these
we want want to be the one that does
displacement now I'm going to go against
what might be the most intuitive thing
to do here simply because i feel like
the way i would remember it better even
though it's less intuitive is to put
displacement on the affine part because
i think of a fine is displacement and
put the perspective on the z part
because that's what I tend to think of
as Z so we would create the P that we're
going to use in this fashion and then
all the other things that are going to
happen here will happen here and then at
the end we would say well okay so now we
know what our perspective Z is our
perspective Z is just whatever we
actually output it as the Z value right
so whatever we actually transformed
through as our Z is what r z would be
and our displacement Z really is just a
value that gets scaled by whatever the
projected Z is but then is just treated
as a normal value right so whatever this
result scale is here
that result scale is going to be the
thing excuse me and I guess that
produces honestly that's going to
produce this this term here so the Z
short term is really going to be well
we've already got it set up to do this
but anyway point being we've got the
result scale we're going to multiply
that by whatever the displacement Z is
so we would just say displacement Z or
it's the unscaled no I guess I'll do
this way GW since it's the W coordinate
is going to be that part so we're kind
of breaking it into two parts for
purposes of this so if we scale the the
resulting value by whatever we would
have scaled for the transform will get
the displacement see out of it then we
have our prospective sort terms like so
I'm sorry are our sort key we have to
protect us from the y term the z short
term and i think that's really all there
is to that right and so now we don't
need a
we don't need this i'm sorry i just
realized i did this slightly wrong no i
didn't know right so now we still need
to pass in the object transform what
that sort biases which I don't know if
that's the most intelligent place to put
that right because it's the something
that varies / / / actual bitmap right so
when you pass through this original p
you kind of want to pass through what
you want that displacement for sorting
to be that why displacement for sorting
to be and I mean like I said I could
make it so that that's actually the p
value that actually gets used always and
then you wouldn't have this right
because we could just say well you're
always supposed to pass the actual value
down right you're just supposed to place
that Y value at the correct location and
the bitmap should always be centered
around it properly and I can't say that
I disagree with that right and that
seems a little bit better potentially
because that way the sore pious stays in
actual regular bias that you know and we
just assume that the the hot spot of the
bitmap is just placed at the sort
location
that I don't really have a strong
opinion about either way
I really can't say that there's anything
yeah I really can't say that makes me
care specifically much about that in a
real way I feel like the the risk there
is that we have two concepts of
important points on a bitmap one is the
one that's used for alignment and that
would be important in terms of rotation
and scaling and the other one is
important in terms of sorting now I'm
trying to think to what degree those
tend to line up
I mean here's some other things to think
about suppose I have a multi-segment
body and these are like a jointed this
is like a jointed figure which we
already kind of have right and are only
going to have more of if I want to
rotate this about this point that it
makes sense for that to kind of be the
alignment point for the bitmap and I'm
going to do that sort of rotation that's
all pretty clear and that's all good
however this whole thing pretty much
wants to be sorted as one entity right
we want all of these bitmaps to be
sorted based on this point and then
inside of this all of these things would
then be sorted kind of just relative to
each other in a predefined way right we
know whether you know the what the sort
of composite order is it's whatever the
artist wanted it to be and it really
doesn't have anything to do with these
points right there not important so it
seems to me that that suggests that the
sort point actually comes out of a
completely different place right so in
other words when we come through here
and we do perspectives the displacement
Z and all this sort of stuff the sort
value is actually going to be something
that got computed along with in us in a
separate way right it's something that
you did you know you did like sort key
and you know you passed that right you
got one of these back whatever it was
and when you got it back you set it as
part of like the object transform and
just used it for all the pieces of this
thing whatever this thing is right uh
that to me seems like what would
probably happen because most articulated
figures are going to need to set the
sort key once and have all of their
components sorted with that key and then
each of the things on that key would be
assigned a specific location relative to
each other yeah I think I feel like that
is definitely what has to happen all
right so I'm going to I'm going to play
with with this a little bit here I guess
I should since we're at the end of the
day I should I should back this out for
the time being
projected XYZ so the perspective Z term
there I do I want that scaled I guess
since everyone else is scaled
I'm not sure I mean it sort of seems
like that's just this this is going to
wreak havoc but what are you gonna do uh
so anyway we um so yeah I think that's
what we probably want to get to and I
feel like starting next week maybe the
right thing to do here is come into
world mode where now we've got sort of
the peace stuff working and make this
figure out what exactly oh wait sorry i
forgot removed this out what we want to
do here is like when we do these these
pieces make this actual routine here
work the way we think it should where we
say let's start a sort key and this
group sorts together and off we go I
think that's a good idea so I'm going to
basically put it to do in here for what
I want to do next week and I think it
might take couple days but then I think
we can finally have all this stuff
straightened out let's say that this is
what needs to happen so this is where
articulated figures will be happening so
we need to have this code look correct
in terms of how we want rendering
submitted it should take a it should
begin by creating a sort key for the
entire armature
and then it should be able to guarantee
that each piece will be rendered in the
order it was submitted after being
sorted into the scene at large by the
key right and at the same time I feel
like we should also try to make the well
I guess so i think we do the pivot
points correctly with with bitmap
alignment here so that should all be
fine i think and that means that our
displacement we don't need a
displacement or a sort bias because that
can just happen outside now right so
yeah this should eliminate the need for
render group side source bias as well
since now the user is in control of
setting the sort value specifically this
also means we should be able to call a
sort key transform routine that does the
entity basis transform and then reports
the sort key to us
yeah and probably we will want the sort
keys to be you 30 tues now so we'll
convert from float at this time and that
way we can use the low bits for
maintaining order or maybe we just use a
staple sort yeah ah so let's see here
I'm going to go to the QA
canoe kohls kind of didn't get it from
the email are you still up to putting a
break sometime soon and make a little
interest rates programming still up to I
don't did I ever say I was going to do
that I definitely am NOT going to do
that but I don't recall ever saying I
was going to do that either
another use case to consider for the YZ
sorting flat things laying on top of
other flat things like a rug on a floor
how would the zy sort position be set in
this case especially at the thing on top
was larger than the thing it was laying
on well I don't think we quite have that
situation but i would say that should be
treated the same as the articulated
figure case kind of but i don't know i
guess i would say i guess i would say if
something is lying on the floor then as
long as it is as long as it is broken up
in terms of floor pieces
yeah I don't know I mean I think what I
would probably do is I would say that
it's z value should always be a little
higher than the other Z values right but
the fact that it's it's one piece that
goes over a lot of them I'm not sure how
you really make that work properly
canoe cools you wanted to go a bit more
serious than introduced here early on
maybe change reminds us no I I want to
do that someday but that's like after
handmade heroes done right that's not
any time during during hand material
Gary Johansson what do you think of
representing ends is 3d objects to keep
things simple like cylinders for
characters and cubes for tiles and rooms
it's not a bad idea just based on the
number of things that's hard to get
right with straight to D bitmaps I could
see using just plates in 3d as being
good idea because sorting by why seems
to be really temperamental and so you
know I'm really just not sure if maybe
there's something to be said for
actually just having plates which have a
z-value this is kind of standard in
modern games where you you know you have
each sprite mapped onto a plate you
actually can still put them in 3d and
you know use a z-buffer to sort them or
whatever and you know I think that has a
lot of niceness to it and I don't know
maybe we should do that the idea for
handmade hero was to try and stay away
from having to do a lot of 3d stuff
because I feel like that's kind of a
jump that's harder for people to make so
i don't know like it may be that this is
good enough and then it's okay it may be
that it's not and then I don't know like
maybe you have to have to do 3d
yeah I'm not sure the case that we were
talking about with the rug is an
interesting one because I do think
that's problematic and maybe it's not
clear why I think it's problematic but
I'm assuming that the person has the
question knows why is problematic
because otherwise they wouldn't ask the
question but the problem that we would
have with that is that you know if
you're sorting by why then you've got
this problem of I've got a rug and then
I've got some tiles under the rug
clearly none of these tiles should sort
in front of the rug right because the
rugs on top of them so I can't very well
put the sort for this thing here and the
reason I can't is because if I did all
of these would actually have sort keys
that were in front of it right on the
other hand I can't put it here which is
what would allow it to sort in front of
all of these because if I put it here
then a hero who is standing here would
sort behind the rug right
uh
so I'm just not really sure
I feel like this is the kind of thing
where I need to work out more explicitly
what would happen in 3d that makes it
work okay and then make sure that that
gets reproduced and I think that the
answer is that you need to be
interpolating if that makes some sense
like the reason that this works is
because I know that it was flat and so I
know that the value from here to here is
not increasing right whereas this guy I
increasing in terms of its closeness to
the camera
but even that doesn't really answer the
question for me because at no time are
we contemplating a case where these
things intersect so we shouldn't really
ever have to consider the fact that they
change they should be able to be
represented by something but I just
don't know what that something is yeah I
feel like this just needs to be worked
out in 3d a little more carefully right
you know in 3d we've got the situation
where we're looking at this and if we
had something like this we would know
that this is in front of this because
the actual time when we encounter it
right the time when it gets encountered
is earlier on this ray then then on here
right if we were to take a look at where
these things come on the camera and I
guess that's a good you can kind of see
its incidence here being important like
as I come down where this this
intersects on the camera plane continues
to kind of be you know it's a line going
this way right as opposed to a line
going that way and so this does
eventually right if taken out far enough
get to be in front of this same here
so this part of this wall would have
been in front of this but this part of
this wall isn't and so I think that's
the important part is that these planes
actually are relevant right and it's
tricky because you care about which part
of the plane you're talking about
well technically the stream is over so
I'm going to have to end but this I
think we're not done here I think this
is definitely there's more to this it's
there's got to be more to it than this
and I think we need to figure out what
it is so I'm not satisfied with my
understanding of it and there's more we
need to go further
cocho 87 maybe you need to sort the
object separately in both y and z and
then solve the conflicts if an object a
is before another object be in the Y
sort but in the reverse or in the Z sort
that's a very interesting idea I don't
know again like I said I don't feel like
I have a complete understanding of it
I'm not sure if it's an idea that
attacks the problem in the place that it
needs to it to or not but it's a very
chewing idea what what he's suggesting
or she whoever akoto 87 is what they're
suggesting is that if we have an object
that is in front of somebody both in
terms of X in terms of Y and in terms of
Z then presumably it can never be wrong
but if it's in front of it in X I mean
in front of it in why but behind it in Z
then maybe that is the cases that we
have to resolve and maybe we have to
resolve them in some special way still
though I don't know I still think that
doesn't really help us and the reason
that I think that doesn't really help us
is because part of the problem is that
objects don't have just one y value
right so we still have that weird thing
of like you know do we cheat and place
the thing in different ways I feel like
we shouldn't have to be doing that
I'm kind of also wondering if maybe I'm
not missing a bigger picture here which
is that I wonder if I out was out
thinking myself and actually the Z value
is the only thing you really care about
I'm gonna finish you and I we need to
spend a whole episode working this out
mm-hmm well I don't see any more
questions really so I'm going to go
ahead and close down and just say that
this is to be continued because I'm not
satisfied with it and I think we need to
look at it more closely and figure out
what actually should be going on here
because I feel like there's an answer
that's just a little bit out of reach
because I'm not understanding them right
and I think what I want need to do is
rather than kind of like get to it
roundabout way and be like oh let's
think about this to today we need to
spend the day and say we're just going
to spend all day to day drawing out
cases figure out what would actually
happen in 3d and then figure out how we
correctly capture that in the 2d setting
to our satisfaction so I think that's
going to be what needs to happen so I'm
going ahead and closed down thank you
everyone for joining me for lep's on a
handmade hero it sorta pleasure coding
with you as always if you would like to
follow along with the stream at home you
can always peer to the game on handmade
hero org it comes with a source code so
you can play around with it we also have
a forum site you can go to someone asked
questions a patreon page while support
the video series a schedule bot that
tweets the schedule you and an episode
guide if you want to catch up on old
episodes that's about it for today I
will catch you guys next week there's no
stream tomorrow so until next week have
fun programming and I will see you guys
on the internet take it easy everyone