hello everybody and welcome to handmade
hero we
are back i uh wanted to
take a look at some collision detection
stuff today because we just
just just just did uh collision
detection
um over the past couple weekends and
we are at the point where we
have to so i'm actually pretty
i guess i haven't run the shell.bat here
we go
uh we actually haven't uh looked at
one aspect of collision detection we did
some kind of interesting stuff with it
um and you can sort of see if i go ahead
here
uh and and run the actual game
uh what you can see is we actually had
uh some reasonable collision detection
stuff working
you can see here that like i can i can
now move the glove around and it will
it's kind of on a very loose spring
right now uh which is probably not great
like we probably don't want it to be
on that uh indefinitely but
uh what you can see here is that like it
it works pretty solid now the glove
doesn't really get stuck in things
um and it's it's pretty good uh in terms
of collision detection
uh so far we can we can sort of get it
like lodged on the other side of stuff
usually and and whatever
uh like trees currently don't have
collision detection you can see that
there's no
collider on trees which is probably
something we have to fix because we
probably don't want the glove
going through trees i would assume
but anyway you can kind of see that it
works pretty good and it doesn't really
have a problem but
we do have some some issues with it that
we'd like to address
uh and the issues
well they're not really issues they're
just things we haven't implemented yet i
guess is the way to look at it
um and there's there's a couple of them
so number one
uh is that we don't have a way for
something to get unstuck
if it's created in a stuck position so i
think we're doing a pretty good job
right now of not
getting them something stuck um it can
get stuck in the sense that like
when it's trying to move let me parse
all these out
so things are currently squares or
right rectangular prisms right and
the problem is so you can get stuff like
this for example so that's not stuck
it's just it's trying to move straight
and it can't
right um so for things like the glove
we want to probably switch to a sphere
so that it will roll off of
surfaces right because like there's no
amount like if you zoom in on what's
happening here
right there's no amount
of moving in this direction that will
ever
cause that thing to move forward it will
always hit this thing
right so you have to move it sideways
first before it could move forward
so it's not stuck in any kind of
numerical sense if i just hop
ooh the heck happened there why is my
camera
that was weird my like debug camera shot
to the side oh cause he moved over a
threshold yeah all right
the debug camera is its own thing um
all right so let me switch back to
regular camera so you can see
so you can see here the glove can't move
forward right because it's
it's pushing against a block but it's
not stuck if i move
over here it can come out just just
nicely right
so one thing that we want to do that has
nothing to do with the numerical quality
of the cushion sector is we'd like to
switch
uh like at least the glove but probably
enemies as well to using something like
a sphere or a cylinder
um so that it can roll it can sort of
smoothly roll off of things
easily which just feels better to the
player usually
the reason we do this in games the
reason we use
cylinders or capsules or spheres is
specifically for that feel it just
feels better regardless of the actual
shape of the object is the player would
rather feel it smoothly roll off of
things rather than sort of the stuck
nature that you get with with right
angles where they
can't glide off of each other right
um so anyway uh what we what we want to
do is a look at that
but b um that's just adding a collision
type to our system which is sphere
uh which wouldn't be that hard um we
were already set up for that
but uh what we don't have is any way of
getting unstuck if you are created stuck
and at the moment anyway
i guess i don't know if we have any test
examples of this
uh meaning an object that is stuck in
geometry when it is created
um i just feel like we want to support
things like that
because they create bad situations in
game design
where if you accidentally screw up the
game code and some piece of game code
accidentally creates an object which is
easy for it to do uh if it doesn't have
really advanced placement logic or
something
if it accidentally creates and two
objects interpenetrating
we don't have code that would really at
this point allow uh
those things to become unstuck right
um there's a little bit of a way that
things can become unstuck currently
um and uh and right now you know there's
not much of that
right so there's two things there's the
one that's getting stuck like this this
glove can get stuck in between or on
things
again not stuck in in the uh in the
numerical sense but you can see
it can kind of get pinned between things
or trying to move in a direction
uh that it simply can't and it won't
really roll around
on it so that's one thing we'd like to
fix um similarly like you can see
uh in this particular case right it's
wedged between two things at least
um and can't necessarily get out so we
have like all sorts of things like that
that we would want to fix uh for with
with spheres potentially or
um where we have an a uh
so i can't really demonstrate this one i
mean i can sort of demonstrate it like
there
that's good um probably
i'm trying to see if this actually is
true or not yeah
okay cool so the other thing we've got
is so in this example
right this is a perfect example of the
second thing i'm talking about that's th
that is an actual um
it's not a numerical problem i suppose
but it's an algorithmic thing we want to
fix
so this rectangle here right that's
attached to the player
is moved mandatorily on every frame
meaning the collision system doesn't get
to reject movements of it
so what has happened here is it has
placed itself
directly on top of the glove's bounding
box
right now this is not a big deal in
practice because hey the player can just
move or something
and that will unstick the glove but we
don't really want that to be the feel
right and similarly this is exactly the
kind of thing that would happen
as well in a situation where two things
were created
overlapping so in other words once two
things are overlapping
some some system that has nothing to do
with collision
so it's not a numerical error but just
some system such as the mandatory player
movement system
places two things overlapping like this
it then locks up the collision moved one
because it's like
there's nowhere it can feel to go that
isn't also colliding
right and so the reason i say we want to
handle that
is because i don't actually want to have
to care about that
i don't want the rest of the game code
to have to avoid consciously avoid this
problem
i don't want to have to put things under
physics control
to avoid this or anything like that i
want to be able to keep doing what i'm
doing which is just
hard moving the player wherever i want
and then having the collision detection
have the slop
in it as necessary to unstick those
and so i have it to do in the code and
that's what i want to look at today
uh before we add like spheres or
whatever i want to add a thing
that basically says if you started the
frame
intersecting then we will let you try to
get
out of that intersection right
and this is a little bit difficult um
it's a little bit difficult because
i don't know that we have particularly
good ways
of concretely measuring your
separation directions necessarily um
but we probably can invent some so
that's probably not the hugest deal in
the world
but other than that it doesn't seem like
it'll be that hard and the reason is
because
we already know that we're in this case
so it's not like this is a mysterious
thing that we're not aware of
we literally know that this is the case
because if we test
the original starting configuration for
intersection we will get back true
like we will get back the fact that it
is in this thing
and so it's easy for us to take action
based on this scenario specifically
because
this scenario itself is easily
detectable
right so that's what we want to start
taking a look at today
okay um
so as you can see from this
configuration right
i can move the glove target that's that
little white uh thing there
right i can move the glove target around
uh and it's kind of crappy uh like the
glove target
uh we have to we have to work on our
glove movement code
uh that's gonna be a big thing we do but
we wanted to get the collision detector
solid first because obviously that's a
big part of it
um but either way you can see like i try
to move it here and it can't get out
right it can't figure out how to get out
now one of the directions that direction
it probably shouldn't be able to go in
because that would require it moving
through that object
but another direction intuitively
speaking like that direction
we probably do want to be able to go in
because it's just sort of unfortunately
overlapping
based on the movement of the player the
player kind of stomped over it and is
now
uh overlapping it and we would like to
have it
now so that it can get out of that
situation
right we'd like it to move out because
that's the that's the least
moving out in that direction is the
least amount of motion
to get it unstuck right um so if we look
at the way the collision sector
currently works
what you can see here
is that it's a pretty straightforward
right you can kind of see
like how we've got it going there's a
pretty straightforward to do here
handle getting uh unembedded that is the
to-do we want to do
uh today and you can kind of see here
the way that the algorithm works uh what
it does is
for those of you who who haven't watched
the entire collision section
uh series where we're doing it is we
use sort of a voxel model where we say
let's
test the squares in a aligned voxel
around where this thing is let's see
if any of the corners of it would allow
it to be placed there
uh and then based on that what we do is
we allow it to move
out of that voxel into a neighboring
voxel
if the corners of the voxel
in that direction would indicate that
that move
is legal and that's what these four
things are doing here
they test the four directions
that you could move in a voxel that go
towards your target so if you think
about a
voxel cell a voxel cell is a cube
right there are uh
you know depending on you want to look
at it there are eight vertices of the
cube
six faces of the cube if we pick a
direction to go in
then there are at most four
different voxel cells you could imagine
going into
in that direction the one that goes out
the
um the three faces so you know let's
suppose our direction is
you look at the sign of the direction
you get like positive positive negative
right so positive x direction positive y
direction negative z direction or
something
is the vector of motion so then we we
would look at the positive x face the
positive y
face and the negative z face right we
look at moving into
the cells on those sides and then we
would also take that vertex the vertex
shared
by those faces and try to move into that
now there are other things we could do
there
uh we could look at more cells
there's a bunch of things we can do but
that seems to be a pretty reliable set
of
choices and then we just take whichever
voxel cell produced the closest point to
the target
and we move into that one now another
thing we could do is consider this more
of a search
and go uh propagate that search out
we're not doing that right now we just
propagate always just to closest you
could think of this sort of
um as like an a-star search without the
search so just always going to the
closest thing
never backtracking when we then hit uh
the
the end of as far as we can go um
so this might be fine and this might be
all we want but like i said uh so
now and i'm pretty pleased with how it's
working it seems pretty stable and good
to me
uh and when you look at its performance
so far i really have never seen it get
stuck
on something that itself wasn't placed
on top of it and if you can place
something on top of it then obviously
it'll get stuck because like i said
everything at that point is colliding so
it seems pretty robust and good we
haven't done like extensive
uh attempts to validate it yet so you
know don't want to say anything
prematurely but
it seems pretty good so what we really
want to do now is look at how we would
modify this routine
um because it's written with the
assumption that the
uh if we did this for example where we
checked
uh collision at the start um we would
it's assuming
a priori that we would not be in a cell
that was completely embedded
okay now i don't think we really need
this
we don't care about this it's not
relevant
we want to do and this is a little bit
of collision detection philosophy here
collision tech is something i've done
a lot of work on in the past so i have a
philosophy about it as opposed to things
i don't work on a lot in which case i
don't have a velocity about it
uh in my opinion when you're doing
collision detection work one of the
biggest things that you want to do
to keep them robust is you always want
to test the same thing every frame
so what you really don't want to do is
introduce a lot of things
that vary based on the person's position
right the cells uh the cells themselves
want to be aligned
uh to the world so they're consistent
and you typically want to test things on
the cell not the individual things
because the more you can keep things
regular the less
room there is for um
weird error to sneak in based on the
specific locations of things
and so it helps keeps things reversible
in this particular case
because we know we have a game where
we're cold setting the position of stuff
just in game code it's less important
because we know that we'll be getting
those
bad situations because the game code
will just produce them and there's
nothing we can do about that
no matter how precise our clinton code
is but again philosophically speaking
i approach this kind of code usually uh
by saying
i feel like my life will be easier if in
general i minimize the
number of things that can be different
from frame to frame
and using a coherent testing methodology
where the points that get tested are the
same all the time
can help with that a little bit right so
anyway
um so i'm going to get rid of this uh
because that's what we're working on now
and i don't want to do this things what
i'd like to do is focus more on this
scenario so
one thing that i would like to observe
about this code as it exists
at the immediate moment is if you take a
look at how the voxel occupation code
works here
where we compute the occupiers for a
voxel um
what you can see is because you are only
allowed to move out of a voxel
if the occupation criteria for that
voxel says that you can
it means that that like um i i would i
would argue
that therefore
there should be no way for us to be in
a voxel where we are not
colliding on some of the points and then
we move to a voxel
where we are colliding on all the points
the reason for that is because each
voxel
shares at least one point with all
neighboring voxels
right in the case of moving through a
face we know that we share four points
in the case of moving through a vertex
we knew that we share one point
so if we are in a voxel and we look in a
direction and we say there are points
that are
occupiable in that direction we know
that then the voxel that we move to
cannot have all eight points occupied if
it
could then that means one of the we
shouldn't have seen any unoccupied
points
on that face right
so to me that means that we have a sort
of
nice ancillary thing here uh which is
that if we take a look
at these um
results here so this this occupied stuff
and i'm gonna write this in the
sloppiest possible way we could just be
summing these with a counter
for example and avoid all of these but
we're we're not even a little bit
concerned uh with the performance of
this routine right now
um at all this this is not a
performance oriented uh piece of code
yet we're literally just doing it
um just just for correctness first
like so uh and so all i'm gonna do here
is
say uh that there's a embedded and i
look and i see
look um oops that's not an or
that's supposed to be an and wrong
boolean operator
um so i'm just trying to see look
if all of the points of this voxel
are all occupied then that means that i
have
embedded this object that i'm looking at
is completely embedded right it
can't get out
and so what i'd like to do here
is i'd like to have some way
of determining emotion
that i can do um and you can see here is
essentially what i'm doing is i'm saying
hey i'm gonna determine whether i'm
embedded
if i'm these are in the wrong side of
the branch
there we go a bit of slow morning
there you go if i'm not embedded
then this is probably okay and the
reason that this is probably okay
is because if i'm not embedded then i'm
by definition not stuck in anything
so i should just do my regular series of
moves because if i can't do them that
just means that the player or whoever
is controlling the motion subject is
trying to push through
something that they're not allowed to go
through and i should
just not let them right
meaning either this will succeed and the
object will move somewhere or
it will fail and that's what should have
happened because
the only valid movement is behind is in
the opposite direction from where it's
looking
and therefore we should prevent it
because it's trying to push through a
solid object
and that's not allowed right so we want
this to happen any time we started off
in a place where there was
where there were uh unoccupied vertices
of the voxel
but in the case where all of the
vertices were occupied we know that
we've
effectively gotten ourselves into a
situation where we're embedded
in another object so what we need now is
a solution to this problem
we need a way of moving from this voxel
to another voxel that doesn't have
that um uh
what's the word i'm looking for that
doesn't have that problem
okay so
couple things about this
obviously there are limits to what this
probably should or could correct
and we have to think a little bit
about how forgiving we want this to be
we could make it extraordinarily
forgiving
which says that if you're embedded in
something you can just go wherever you
want
right um and for example
um just to
to give you some
perspective on what that would look like
i could literally just say if you're
embedded you get free motion and then
i'm going to tell you why i don't want
to do
that um but obviously that's one
quote-unquote solution to this problem
now remember
i held the game open here it's still
running we're in this kind of
state here right and now i'm going to
compile it
and then we're going to so it's going to
reload in the middle of the code here
i don't know why there's a breakpoint
set there but there was
and now what you can see is i'm unstuck
right
and that's exactly what expected because
now it's allowed to move
out of there um and i'm pretty sure that
this would just work i don't think that
was a
very complicated scheme there but you
can see uh
like pretty much now any time this thing
got stuck
in the middle of something it will just
get unstuck probably just did it just
then
for example and so on right now the
reason i don't really want to do that
is because i believe this would create a
little bit too much opportunity for
speedrunners
again because we know we have this
sort of scenario of there's these things
like the player's head
that gets moved at or like these things
right
that get moved programmatically that
aren't subject to physics
they're literally they hop from square
to square with gameplay logic
that's required sort of a hybrid we have
a hybrid engine right
some of things want to be on on a
mandatory game logic it has to go from
here to here it's required we check
occupancy we only allow one thing per
square for gameplay rule reasons
um kind of not that dissimilar from john
sokoban game
right there's a transactional move
system underlying this game that
means that things that aren't projectile
or floaty
they move with a rigorous game logic
that cannot be
broken it has to go the way it goes
but floaty things like the glove it's a
hybrid because they are
built on a physics thing and they can
physics themselves around
but we could change that right i mean
another thing we could do is say
no let's not do that and let's actually
make these things transactionally occupy
squares
you know that's probably smarter
who knows um but we don't do things
smart here on handmade hero we do things
just to have an excuse to do different
kinds of programming so people can see
how to do it right uh and so that's what
we did and you can see like
you can see how cool this collision
detection system is
it's so darn good right it just hugs the
wall that whole way it does like look at
how
smooth that is very good um so pleased
with it's such a small simple routine
you saw how simple that routine was
produces excellent results um
really very happy with it anyway um so
when we uh look at this what i was
thinking is like you know it suppose i
do that
um now the collision system knows that
it has
like effectively two uh pieces and and i
guess i didn't do a very good job here
so it kind of snuck underneath so it
didn't happen
but i feel like it wouldn't be that hard
for me to push the glove into the wall
um especially let you know using
something else and the speedrunners will
find anything
right i mean they'll find everything i
feel like there should
there's yeah like that right so did you
see how i kind of was able to push that
into the wall
and it's because it was up high and then
it the the blocker pushes it into the
wall
um and now it's embedded in the wall and
once it's embedded in the wall
because my rule is if you're embedded in
the wall you can do whatever you want
you can see i can just move straight
through the wall now right um
if i rerun the game because it's hard to
see with the camera in there because
there's stuff in the front
if i rerun the game and so you can see
it in there to see see what i've done
now the the glove gets to move all
through that region
again not a bug it's literally what i
told it
it was supposed to be able to do when it
was embedded so you can kind of see why
i don't
want that specifically
and the reason that i don't want that is
because
i don't like the idea of speedrunners
having quite
that much ability uh to screw with the
game's collision rules
right because at that point they can do
all sorts of like intentionally embed
something into a wall
because they know that the collision
detection will be forgiving and then
they'll
use that right and you know a part of me
just says like just do that anyway
because speed running is cool and you
want to give
speedrunners a bunch of cool things to
do because it's just cool
right so believe me i'm sympathetic to
uh the idea that maybe we should just do
it that way
but um on the other hand i'm like it's
just it's a little
too much i feel like we sh yes
give them some things to work with but
that's a little too much in my book so
that just i'm not comfortable
with that level of a gimme to
speedrunners
so what i want to do instead
is i want to do something where if we're
embedded
we create for example maybe a new motion
vector
and that motion vector is based on some
kind of displacement
uh that would try to get things
unembedded
uh in a way that we hope will be
reasonable there's a
bunch of risk involved in doing it this
way to be sure
but i want to give it a try so let me
motivate this
um for you a little bit just you can
kind of have
a little bit of an idea about what i'm
talking about so
if you uh take a look at how this is uh
working here you can see that you know
what we're expect what we're
what we're planning on doing here uh is
we're detecting
embedded by saying here's the eight
vertices of the voxel cell uh that the
player
currently finds themselves in we know
that they're all occupied so we know
that in order to move the player or
shouldn't say player the entity like the
glove in this case will have to
go in some direction that is clearly not
indicated by its occupied
status but allowing it to move in
whatever direction it wants to move
is probably too permissive what we'd
rather do
is only allow it to move in a direction
that would get it less embedded
right like we want to
we want to produce
a some idea
of the direction of motion
that is moving out of the embedded
of the embedding that this
um that this entity has
has found itself in right
now the most straightforward way to do
this uh
would be if we were to take the position
of the entity
and try to come up with a unembedding
direction
from there and
the reason i don't want to do that is
because
since we're we're basing our decision
about whether or not you can move
on vertices of a voxel if i then
say well we're going to base our
direction of how you get unembedded
based on your actual position we run the
risk of your actual position
not colliding whereas the vertices of
the voxel do collide
right and i realize that that's kind of
a bit weird
uh because you know in theory you'd be
like well wait how the heck could that
happen
right but numerical precision wise it
certainly could if you imagine the voxel
cell
maybe you can stand just like
all of the colliders are just such that
if you were to stand on
any of the vertices of the cell you
would be intersecting
the ones on like the left side or the
right side if you sit on the the left
side you'll attack the left side ones
the right side right sides but right in
the middle
you could actually stand there and the
player
or the entity happens to be right in the
middle
right so i one of the things that's a
little annoying about this
is i would like to be able to just test
one position but i really can't quite
do that um because in order to do that i
would actually need
to know that they were themselves
embedded which they might not be
so i need the check i need to be able to
to produce
a motion vector that gets me that hopes
to get me unembedded
based on on something else
now
the easiest way to do this is just to
produce that motion vector
for each of the voxel positions
and
if i did that and then i just kind of
use i could i could try linearly
interpolate it
um
[Music]
i could just use the average of it
um i mean really the only
there's all sorts of things most of them
will just work fine
except for the fact that they probably
all
have some bad case where you could
imagine
them not producing a vector that will
actually get you unstuck very
effectively
right
so
i can't say that there's anything that
i'm
coming up with magical here in my head
it just kind of seems like probably
i mean i'm tempted to just wing it and
say look we'll do one of those and we'll
see how bad it is
um i don't know how rigorous we want to
be
about this particular thing like i don't
know how much validation we want to try
and do here and say
how bad of situation should this thing
be able to recover from
and i don't know you know i don't know
the answer to that question
uh but either way i'm pretty sure that
i'm gonna want
i i'm pretty sure i know what i'm going
to want here
um
in terms of sort of like basic routines
anyway
so i think i'm just going to go ahead
and write those and then we'll see
so if you look at like collides at p for
example
um really what i want to do is modify
this collides at p
function to produce more than just
the fact that it collided or not and
what i want to do
uh is produce sort of a
a repulsion field if you will right
so when i'm looking at collision
anything that
this collides with i want it to produce
a repulsion field
that basically says look we're going to
push you away
from this thing if you're embedded in in
it right
and then maybe i even want that
repulsion field
this is hard to say but maybe i even
want that repulsion field
to reflect
how far embedded into something you are
so
if you get more embedded into something
it tries to push you
out of it harder than if you were less
embedded in it
and
the reason that i'm a saying that
is not because the actual code on the
outside
will push you any harder because it's
literally just talking about a move from
a voxel to a neighboring voxel so it's
not
trying to push you with any particular
amount of force
high or low it's just a basic movement
it's not affecting your velocity it's
not affecting anything
however what i'm actually
talking about when i talk about that
amount of push
what i mean is that we are going to be
looking at
situations where because any time that
you are embedded in something
you don't have to just be embedded in
one thing
for a very simple example if i go back
to the game here
and you look at some uh place let's say
that you embedded yourself
right in this area right here well
there's one two three
four at the very minimum there's four
separate like colliders that you could
have
embedded into right and so if you
embedded
very far into these two
but not very far into these two so
pretty far to the left but not very far
down right then you may want the
resulting
push like the direction that your that
the thing is saying you should go in
you may want that to reflect
a more rightward push and a less
upward push just so the outer routine
knows
it's trying to get things further to the
right than it is trying to get them
up right so it's more about producing
a vector that captures the direction
we're trying to go
to disembed things um so
it's more about that and not so much
about how
hard the outer routine will actually try
to move you
because it's not really about that at
all right
um
and again i really just don't have a
strong opinion about that
uh off the bat i'm not sure i can really
think of much um that's important there
so it's just a little bit hard
to really consider so i don't know yet
but anyway i am probably going to do um
a little struct here
that we're going to say like uh
i'm going to call this a collision field
maybe
um and for right now i'm just gonna do
like
an occupied flag like we had before
meaning the point is
um and then i'm gonna put a v3 in here
that's also uh a product of the
collision detection
that just says like the uh
repulsion right uh
so this is basically just a vector that
points in that direction so what i want
to do is take collides at p
and i want it to produce one of these
collision fields so the result now
um is going to be
about occupation in this way uh we're
going to remove this break statement
here
because we now need to do some summing
up of
the uh of the occupied colliders
but otherwise that's all we're going to
do and then here what i'm going to do
is take this
code that was previously calling it and
i'm just going to reduce it to just
doing
exactly what it was doing before by
pulling out only the occupied
field which means now we should run the
game
uh and get identical behavior to what we
were getting before
with no changes because the code is the
same i can still push into that wall
just fine
and so on then what i want to do is say
okay
when we get this embedded situation here
and then we we see that we are embedded
what i want to do is i want to change
and you can see uh out here we we set up
these best things here right
distance squared and all that stuff
right
so what i'd like to do is say well maybe
i'm going to go back here uh and
i'm going to take this well
i'm not quite sure yet so let me hold
off on that thought
so what i want to do here is say like
okay if i was embedded
uh and i want to turn this stuff on
uh what i might do is just say okay i'm
going to clear out the occupied stuff so
that you can move
in a direction but maybe then i'm also
going to
clip the motion direction to
have to go in the same direction
as the uh repulsion field
right so
i
[Music]
this is i feel like it's not worth me
going over to the light board just for
this but this is a very like
diagrammatical sort of thing
um so i have two vectors
one of them is the motion vector
that says i want to go from here to here
uh and you can see that that's just um
you know a from p2p thing where i say
this is the entity position
and i want to go to this um
i want to go this displacement so then i
end up
with this new target is you know
is that that displacement right
so that's pretty easy to understand but
what we're doing here
is we're saying okay if we end up in a
situation where we start off embedded
which is what's going to happen here
and this can pretty much this pretty
much only is ever going to happen
continuously or not at all meaning
either we're going to start
embedded and then we may have some
series of cells we traverse where we're
embedded
or we start unembedded and we will never
traverse an embedded cell
because we wouldn't be able to move into
it in the first place right
so we know we start off with with this
being something that only happens
from the very first cell and then may
continue onward
but we know it's never gonna happen like
in the middle of a series of cells like
we're never gonna
be like unembedded unembedded embedded
unembedded embedded right
it's either a series of embeddeds and
then unembedded or
a series of unembedded that's all we've
got uh
if something else happened then the
routine's gone haywire and we need to
debug it right
so we know that in normal operation with
no bugs
that will not happen so
um what we need to do here is say look
if the if the thing was embedded
then we know that that uh 2p so the
place that we're trying to move
we need that to be adjusted right we
need to adjust the the
place that we're going to to say we're
allowing you to do
motion in embedded space we will not
allow you
to go hog wild we are only going to
allow you to move it
in the direction that would make it most
closely resemble
an a a removal motion an unembedding
motion
right uh and so in order to do that
uh we would need to say look
the uh we know that the
movement right so this
best 2p here um we know
that the movement which
i want to say we don't yeah we don't
really care
so when this happens
we know that we have our uh from
direction
right and we now want to take
and uh apply that delta to it we want
that delta
to now be effectively clipped
like we want to clip that delta
so that any motion that isn't in the
same
uh direction that that would go
against the direction of unembedding
is removed and
i mean i guess another way to think
about this would be do we want to
just force it to go in the unembedded
direction even if that's not the
direction it was trying to go
and that's a good question
you
that's a good question and i don't know
the answer to that question because
there's a lot of different ways that we
could play this and i'm not sure which
one is the smart way
right like one way to play this is that
we just
i mean there's so many ways to replace
we could actually not update 2p at all
and just update the occupied
stuff in that in that direction
i might try that first it's a really
tough call
and i'm not sure i really don't know
um but like so this
basically is what i'm talking about um
we would we would say
okay so like if you're embedded in
something
um then what we're gonna do is we're
gonna create uh
some side values here for uh
an unembed direction
right um and then what we're going to do
is we're going to take and set that
vertex
right um
[Music]
so that you can move in that direction
um
and and maybe we could even do like
right
so we would say okay uh
whatever side
x we're on um
this kind of thing you know what i'm
saying
so we're gonna allow you to move out the
unembed direction
there uh maybe we allow you to move out
of the face
um we could take the strongest face and
allow you to move out of that
in fact
that may be the best
right like like i don't know we have to
sort of think about how we would want to
code this efficiently
but you can imagine like um
you know if unbed x is greater than
unembed y
um
you know we're just basically picking
the the direction that's strongest
you know what i mean um and then we
could just say
that will set we'll set these up
in one in a specific way
uh
so something like this
and so you can see it's like okay if x
is greater than y and x is greater than
z then x is the face direction we're
going to move
um out of right and so
we would in here i guess we still need
that side one but we so so here we would
just say like whatever the side x is
we use and then everything else is just
set right
um similarly here if we have
a um
if we have x is greater than y
uh but x is not greater than z
then that means this would be the z side
and then finally we have the exact same
case over here so if this is not true
then that means
y is greater i don't know why this is
set up this way
um so if y is greater than z then
we do the side y one and if it's not
then that means
z is the greater so it's it's really
just this case again
right there's only three possible cases
we just can arrive at that same case
in two different ways um so this one's
the side y
case
and that's mostly what we want
right so if we assume that this happens
as well
where we just take a unembed
direction and we produce the side
for that uh and then we clear it
and again we we're gonna probably
eventually need to think oops size
that's good
we're gonna need to think about how we
wanna do this maximally efficiently
because like a lot of this code is you
know just i'm just kind of
sketching it out just doing it directly
um and i think that's roughly what we
want
minus the spelling errors
right um so now all we need to do is
actually produce that unembed value and
the unembed value
uh in this case i will probably just
take as a sum
so i'll probably just do unembed d here
uh i'll sum it up so at each one of
these things
we'll take the collision field and we'll
actually record it
uh and then what i'll do is if the field
oops we actually want that uh if the
field is occupied
then i will take the unembed d and we
will add
uh to it and
there are sort of two ways we could do
this i think what i'd like to do
is like embed count equals zero
so i'll count how many times i'm
embedded here
i'll take the unembed d and i'll do the
uh repulsion fields addition here and
then when i'm at the end
embedded now will just be in bed count
um if the embed count equals eight then
you know they're all embedded we don't
need
uh to study that any further so this can
just be
directly placed in here um and then
what we do is for the unembed d
we know that at that point we need to
normalize it so it's it's had
eight things added to it or
well i guess so to be honest we really
don't need that i mean we know that we
only use it in that one
case so actually we can just do
this which is probably better
because then it's not anything
conditional
uh
hmm
all right well anyway
so uh
point is hey we're only going to use
this if all eight were in so that means
we know we can just take the average by
doing
one over eight times the value when we
accumulate it and then it's just
known to be correct right it's just
right
just right at the time so at that point
our main problem now
other than maybe logical errors we made
in typing in that code
uh is that we don't actually set it so
it's always going to be zero
right which means that
it'll just kind of let you move out of a
random one of the faces
right it's not really going to give any
actual information
it's going to be i don't remember how we
wrote these ifs exactly but it's going
to be
all of these are going to be false so
it's going to be false
false so it's basically going to say
look you can move
um out of the out of the z
positive face so you can move upwards it
will always let you move upwards only
um and then we also have to remove the
else claws because now
we're we're always going to still do the
movement
so all we're doing is reconditioning the
occupy
the occupied uh checks to to prevent
uh you from going in a direction that
you wouldn't already be able to go but
that's the only thing we're changing
so if we run the code now it should
still work
um and it should allow you to get
unembedded in the upward direction right
um and so what that means is if i embed
this in the wall like before
i wouldn't have expected it to do what
it just did oh
but no it kind of does notice it allows
you to move
in the upward cell it looks like that's
sort of what it did
hard to say though so that may not be
quite correct
let me see if i can get a better
so you know what that is correct based
on what i wrote okay so that's a good
piece of information
i hadn't thought of so if we do this
conditioning
that means that you could still move
like laterally because if you
right you would still be able to move
laterally if you always consider those
cells were out
so i do think this this is a dumb idea
this won't we do need to do the thing i
said originally which is
condition the target vector um
i think we do have to condition the
target vector so we we have to adjust it
so that it's pointing in the direction
of unembedding
i think that's pretty much what we have
to do uh so i'm going to change
i'm not going to do that like i said
from before
uh not gonna do that what i'm gonna do
instead ignoring this
so that was a good piece of information
right
um
so i'm gonna take this uh
embed count here and i'm going to say if
it equals eight then we're going to do
the full wash
right
like so uh and that should be fine
so now you can move in all directions
and what we need to do
now is say okay and when you get in this
state
we are going to require that the place
that you move to
is going to have to be the unembed
direction
period right so you have to move in that
and you don't get any choice in the
matter um and we may say that okay
uh we have a certain amount of distance
here
because i don't know like what we
actually want that to be
uh but we're gonna say that like for now
we're just gonna say
it's it's you're trying to move one unit
in that direction
right like like that's that's where
you're trying to get to
um and what we probably want to do is we
want to say
uh as soon as you get to
a place where you're out again we would
stop doing that
now this is not um
it's a little bit hard because i'm not
sure
i mean so i'm guessing i probably want
to do this
right
so try to get the person unembedded for
a while
um and if if we do ever succeed in
getting unembedded then we revert back
to trying to get
towards the actual goal right
i could i could believe that okay so
this should do some weird stuff
currently
because it's always going to hap well no
so this will just freeze things in their
tracks because
that vector is zero right so things
should not be able to move
once they get embedded in something if
they get significantly embedded
they presumably couldn't move although
weirdly enough
that does so that's a little surprising
how is that able to move
so you would think did i mess something
up you would think
that this would mean that it
wouldn't accept emotion here
because
oh no it would though
because this
hasn't been updated
interesting
so
this seems very wasteful
um
this seems a bit wasteful so i'm not
thrilled about it
um
uh but it is what it is at the moment so
i think we're gonna do it this way
so we may not really want to do that
long term
uh but
there we go that's what i was expecting
right like when i push this in like that
it should just
get stuck right and it should not be
allowed to move at all
because it's supposed to be confined to
moving to a vector that it literally is
not allowed to move
anywhere right it's like a zero vector
of motion so
i wanted to make sure that was working
first before i interpreted what was
going on and
now it is so that's good that's what i
want
good okay so now what we want to do
is actually produce this unembed vector
that we are constraining to move by and
we just saw that it does kind of
constrain the motion in the sense that
if i make sure that this is zero now
you can't you you get physically stuck
when you're embedded and
you're not allowed to move anywhere
which is what i wanted to verify should
happen
and so now what i want to do is actually
produce the vector that i
will allow you to move along
um and so what you can see here is you
can see that this collides at p
um it's doing this intersection it's
taking the result occupied
what i want to do is be able to produce
something here
that represents the direction one would
expect to have to go
in order to to exit the
collision this particular collision
right
and this will be a summation in that it
will be like a sum of
of push directions right
and whether i want to like how those
should get normalized and such
uh that's a good question we'll have to
think about that
in a little more detail later for now we
just want to produce something
so we have uh rectangles and we know
that they intersect
if we've gotten into this part of the
routine we have two
overlapping rectangles in space
we have the one that came from
the thing that is moving and we have the
thing
the one that came from the obstacle and
what we want to know is
what direction would we probably push
uh these things in in order to get
us out of
of our current position right
so
with spheres this is significantly
simpler because you always know that the
push is in the direction
[Music]
of the point right it's from the center
to the point is always the shortest way
out
and the problem with rectangles is
that's
not true uh because
it was cube it's sort of true uh because
they're all equally
have equal dimensions so you can think
of it as a sphere and it's probably
roughly correct most of the time
but when you have something in an
arbitrary rectangle you have to remember
like one
of the three dimensions could be much
larger than the others
so if you look at the vector from the
center
it may have like a massively
overweighted
component that doesn't actually tell you
what you wanted to know
which is what the simplest way to get
out of there would be
um and so that's a little bit
harder
so i suspect what we want to do here
[Music]
is just say how far
in x y and z would i have to move
to get to the edges
right you're always closer to one edge
than the other
how far in x y and z would i have to
move
and that is going to be the vector now
the
nasty part about that is just that
it's sort of a if statement festival
right it's like there's two there's a
minimum
and a maximum and you have to go like
whichever one is greater
right whether i take the negative motion
because
there's two right there's two bounding
planes
to any kind of rectangular prism and you
got a point
and you want the point you want to know
how far it is to the closest
side and so i'm trying to think
but i can't i'm not really thinking of a
good way
this is actually not that hard right you
could just do a
test to produce the mask and then you
just keep
you just do a select on the two so
what is it booba oh
come up with your save hi
how you doing
what are you doing what are you doing
what's going on
do you want a brushing do you want to do
brushing times let's do brushing times
we're just working on the collision
detector
it's coming along pretty good we're just
working on
what we want our strategy to be for when
the gameplay code creates
interpenetrating objects
there you go
coat health is very important isn't that
right
oh we gotta trim your back your back
nails my goodness they're getting way
too sharp
all right um i got to finish this
code here is that cool
i just want to finish we've only got it
it's not much longer in the stream i
just wanted to just finish just this one
piece code
just with a sketch of something just to
see how it works bubba
okay how's that how's that sound
does that sound okay does that sound
good
you can type it for me if you want
i know you like to type on the keyboard
you definitely have some interesting
code
that you've put in in the past i've
experienced some very interesting cat
code
new new algorithms that mostly include
repeating a single letter for a long
time
oftentimes the space bar is involved
all right is that okay can i put you on
the floor now
can i put you on the floor you can go
around
yeah okay come on
go on go on bubba
all right
okay then um so yeah like what i mostly
just want to figure out here is like
what this directional
uh thing would be here and and really
so like you know let's just do this for
now
it's not great but this is what i'm
gonna do
so um
i'm just gonna take an average count uh
the number of times we occupy here we're
gonna
uh increase the the average count
uh and then i'm just gonna do like an if
average count
uh result dot repulsion times equals one
over
average count
right so uh i'm just going to go in here
and
track this repulsion value
by summing up some like unembed
direction here like we were doing before
the unembed direction
is just going to be like the center
uh of like the minkowski some maybe of
these two
uh colliders so um or i could just
you know actually for now we could do it
even simpler just because we're pretty
much out of time
so what i could do is just say like okay
let's just take the two collision
volumes
and subtract their centers right um
so you know the test rects
uh and the mover rect um so we want the
we want to say
that so if we were moving into it we
want to basically move towards
us and away from from them so we want to
go like okay we want to move towards the
mover
rect away from the test rect is probably
what we're looking for
this is not good uh we probably don't
want this to be the
the permanent thing at all but then at
least we've got
something we can start with right so
that's that's the basic
uh thing that we'll use so going into
next weekend we can
start to work with that right um and so
that looked a little odd although it
kind of works
notice how it pops it right up on top
there if it was high
and it keeps it out if it was in so that
actually
does exactly what it you would think it
would do actually
right um if it was up high we'll push it
up higher to get over the top of that
thing um because there's nowhere it can
go
right um
you can't you can't push in
so i mean even just that really stupid
piece of code worked
if we put a ceiling on here then it
would just work
it looks like so we may just luck out
and not have to do anything fancy
we may just end up with something really
stupid it's fine right
and the only thing we need to do here is
make sure we have a um
an actual cap on the ceiling so that you
can't
go arbitrarily high and go over
walls right and that's just adding a
collider
at the top of the room right there
that's nothing
that's really simple um so i think
that's good
uh and i'm happy with that for today
um that looks great yeah it just pops
right up over the wall
to avoid getting embedded um
so yeah in pretty good shape
yeah no real complaints so far
looks pretty good
uh and mainly the controller for the
glove kind of sucks right now so
that is something we'll have to work on
for sure although it kind of feels fun
to play with so maybe it doesn't suck
that bad
um so you know we want to like uh
we want to work on that and also i think
we want it like i said to be a sphere
all right uh that's a pretty reasonable
place to stop for today anyone have any
questions about collision detection
i can take a look at them and while we
are doing that
i wanted to show off something i just
received in the mail
check it out so
this guy i don't know that seems to be
like really
aggressively not wanting to autofocus
there it goes
so this guy um
is a uc one from grim audio
and they sent it to me uh because
i guess they decided they they asked for
permission
about a year ago to use some handmade
hero
code stuff uh in their i guess the
driver
uh for the the like the interface for
the driver or i don't know if maybe it
was the interface for the
this this has a little uh screen on it i
don't actually know
um but i was like sure uh can can you
send us one when you
when you ship it uh and they graciously
said yes
and um so it's a pretty cool
box i i have literally not read the
manual yet but
it has like a crap ton of audio on the
back
um so it's basically like a ton of
inputs and outputs
and i guess the idea behind it is uh
that it's it's like a little like
virtual kind of like
routing sort of thing like in other
words you can
plug in a bunch of inputs and outputs
and then use this thing
to control like where things go right
um and uh
and honestly like having had a lot of
problems with the stupid stereo mix crap
in windows i'm kind of wondering if i
can like once i go read how it actually
works
uh and stuff i'm wondering if maybe it's
something i could actually use
on the show uh to get a more stable
scenario like a more stable like input
output scenario
for the um for the machine
right um so you know
uh we've had a lot of problems with that
in the past
we might we might want to try um
but you know that's about it
js christ brought up a question um
what about tracking a previous location
and always moving back towards where the
entity came from um
yeah that doesn't really work
particularly well uh and the reason that
that doesn't work particularly well
is because all the entities are moving
and so there's no
particular reason to suspect that the
place the entity came from
is any better than anywhere else
right so what you really want is
something that is go
like so if we wanted to do this full
uh all the way right what we would
probably do
is say okay let's just start searching
in a radius
and see where the closest place we could
put this as unembedded is
right that's probably the best thing um
then if we want to go a stage above that
you can have your room regions
coded by reachability
and only pick a location that has the
same reachability
as the last place the player was right
and you can do all that stuff in our
case
it's probably not going to be very
important
um to do any of that stuff you know this
isn't the witness
or something where i cared a lot about
trying to make sure
that the player's experience was rock
solid and it was supposed to be that way
for game design reasons and all this
other stuff
this is a very chaotic room based
hopping game with
crazy crap happening and so i don't
care that much about those same sorts of
things
right so don't think i would bother with
reachability analysis
it just doesn't seem like it was a good
use of time
what was the name of the audio box it's
called a grim
audio uc1
so it it is um
let us open up microsoft's amazing
browser
grimm you see one
um so it is this
and uh you can see like
it's got like a bunch of output and
input options
right uh and
because i don't know very much about it
i really like i said don't know uh if
it's an appropriate thing for
anything that we happen to do with the
stream
but we obviously could
use a nice like mixing and routing
thing for uh
any number of reasons is because of like
all the trouble i've had with like
getting audio to both go to headphones
and to um
the other computer and all this other
sorts of stuff right
um and so i don't really know
like
i i don't really know uh we have to play
with it and find out
the reason i have one is because they
use the hand of samantha hero code
that's it
uh but it and so i was just like um
thought it was cool but also it may end
up being something i can actually use
because it happens to be something that
is in a space that we have trouble with
right
so it may actually be something that
ends up being useful plus knowing the
people who worked on it means that if
there's problems with the drivers or
something i actually have someone to
talk to which is different than most
things i use right
it could be like hey i'm having trouble
getting this to work or
it seems to be blue screening in this
case or something right it's like
sometimes it's nice to have friends who
work on a
device use because if you have a problem
someone might actually listen to you
which is different than
you know the normal situation
someone who started the series a few
days ago and wants to make a game of his
own how do i manage to catch up with the
current stage
um i don't really think you need to
right um i would just say
you know handmade here is a good thing
to watch to see the parts that you
think that you need to see for working
on whatever you're working on
but you can safely ignore the episodes
that aren't about those things
right um and if you go to
um the episode guide here
um
i don't this is such a weird episode i
don't know i don't do this
it's a very strange program um i don't
didn't make it
uh so it kind of is its own thing
it's it's just full nuts uh
there we go
um you can usually do stuff like search
for things in here
that you need to find like if you need
to know how to do sse or something or
you know cindy or something you can
look it up in here um
but yeah i don't know it's so basically
all
all the episode guide really needs to be
good
is some work on styles right like you
never
want like you see how small that text is
you never ever want your text to be a
fixed size
text should always be related to the
the rem size of the page so that it
grows as the page grows and such
you know um so
so it doesn't make a lot of sense the
way that it's set up at the moment
um but like the actual content is very
good
uh so you know you click on something it
goes right to that something and then
you get that so all of this
you know where it is in the video right
and so it's pretty good
and you can play part of that um through
it and whatever
and it keeps the stuff synced so like on
the side of a few things yeah i need
first of all the color
which stylistic like layout wise it
doesn't really work
it's a pretty pretty busted starting box
but content-wise it does
and like i said i don't really do it so
i can't i'm sorry a box really say much
about it other than like that's what it
is
i don't have time to go mess with this
stuff
so um but the content in it is very good
right
uh
i recently discovered your stream i
learned a lot from the in-depth videos
on how computer
actually works in front of a level like
the c tutorial and the blackboard videos
i'm really excited about circle galaxy
do you have any information about when
it will launch and what kind of material
will cover um
i don't really um i mean it will launch
as soon as possible but there's just a
tremendous amount of work involved in it
um and it's a very complex product to
try and ship so
uh you know i promised
that i'll put out an early access
version before it's really ready
so i will be shipping it you know
prematurely because
people really want to get their hands on
it so there will be a
sort of quiet early release that will be
available to people
if you signed up for the mailing list on
starcodegalaxy.com
you'll get notified when that's
available so there will be
that thing um and i
i you know i'm trying to get it out as
soon as possible like literally as soon
as i feel like everything is stable
enough and there's enough content in it
to release we will but there's it's a
very complicated project
that was done in a very small amount of
time
compared to how much stuff is in there
it included building two studio setups
at my house
a complete new design for an educational
system
a complete deployment of that in
javascript so it will run
on the web um
[Music]
all the videos the code base like
basically three complete game code bases
like it's a tremendously large thing
that is very intricate and complicated
and uh i've had to do a tremendous
amount of work to
to bring it to fruition and so i
i other than the fact that i'm trying as
hard as i can to get something out
early i cannot really promise anything
else
can you tease just how awesome sauce the
scg
player will be um
i mean no i don't know
i guess what i would say about the seg
player is you can look at it in one
of two ways one way is you can
think of it as it is completely
revolutionary and completely changes
everything you know
about how you would make course
materials
another way would be actually it's just
the obvious thing you would do
if you weren't youtube right
if if youtube if anyone at youtube cared
at all
about what watching things should be
like when there's a computer
this is just what you would get right so
i mean you can either do the like
paul graham an obvious thing is a
revolutionary technology nonsense puff
piece about it if you want or you can
just be like
oh cool somebody who actually cared
made a thing for playing back videos for
instructional purposes
and we got all of the things that you
would think you would do
art actually got done right
um so so you know it's
it's there there's a fair number of
things in there i guess that maybe
people wouldn't think of
because they haven't gone and tried um
right so so there's a bunch of things
that probably will be surprising
but when you see them i think you will
mostly think oh right that's how it
should be
i don't think you will think like whoa
that's weird or whoa that's
so far out there i think like oh right
of course we should have done that
right um
[Music]
so so hopefully the things i think
there's a lot of really
smart stuff in there but i think it's
all stuff that in hindsight
after you see it it will seem very
natural be like of course we should have
done that right
which is usually i think
[Music]
you know the kind of idea i like
um
have you implemented some kind of
friction effect
for the player walks or runs along the
voxel boxes
uh well there's no so in this game
things hop
so there's no real friction so i'm not
i'm not sure
there's only two types of objects in the
system ones are hoppers which just hop
around and the others are
gliding so they don't really do friction
they just
they're just allowed to go anywhere
they're allowed to go so we don't really
have a use case for friction in this
particular
game did you make the final products for
each module first and then build the
course around each for each module
yes
i mean to a first approximation i guess
that's not entirely true but that's
mostly
true yes can you explain again how the
unembedded vector is calculated
yes so right now it's not calculated in
any particularly smart way
so right now all we do is say look if
two things are colliding
we just take the centers of each of
their bounding boxes
and we assume that the thing that will
get you unembedded
is is the opposite motion of that right
so if if two things you take their two
centers
and you you use the vector that would
push
back towards the person who's moving
right
so you have one person moving and one
person who's stationary
for purposes of this algorithm right the
person who's moving
we basically push you back towards that
person along the line
of the two bounding box centers right
and if there's more than one thing
collides with we just average them
so it's not a very good it's not it's
not nothing it's not good
right it's not particularly good
computation but it's fine
for our purposes already seem to work
okay so we may not want to belabor the
point until we actually have some
examples of it failing
to do what we want
any idea on the approximate price
historical switch uh yes so
i haven't announced any final pricing
yet but the the estimate was it would be
like 50 bucks
per you know per
um module right
so the yeah the well 200 is for
so there's there's people who wanted to
do like a buy
everything so 200
it was the price point that was floated
for like you get ev
all the modules right
so so the the idea was that you can buy
um you know the modules are fairly
uh substantial and you only buy as many
as you wanted to take
right um and those would be 50 bucks per
right so that was kind of the general
idea
and the reason for that pricing was like
it's basically like the price of a game
right so it was meant to be kept around
what people generally were used to
paying
for non-educational stuff
just to keep it more in line with with
standard pricing
so the 200 thing was like if you bought
like
basically like a an umbrella package
right something that had all the modules
in it
um so that was more of a like special
you know like like a kickstarter tier
kind of a thing it's like oh the 200 one
has like all the stuff
and maybe some bonus content or early
access to everything
um so you know if you buy the 200 one
you get stuff early before it's actually
bundled into a module that kind of thing
my friend started working as a c plus
programmer and he showed me the code
base
he has to work with and it was a jungle
of classes templates
std colon colon it was very slow to
compile
is this a common thing in industry to
have this kind of code base i guess that
is why software is a bad quality
um pretty much yes so um
bad programming practices such as using
the std library which is a terrible
library
no one should ever use it for anything
um it's bad across the board it's bad at
everything
there are no good parts of std um
uh it's just bad
most of c plus is bad so classes and
templates templates are okay
in light usage sometimes but they're
pretty bad in general just as a design
classes are always bad assuming that
you're actually talking about things
that were induced with classes
structs and classes have no real actual
difference between them
it's only if you start using things like
virtual private those sorts of things
also all bad
right um but that's the typical way that
large code bases these days are
programmed and the reason for that is
not because
they make large program large code bases
better they actually make large code
bases worse
like the compiled time like you said but
rather that
the prevailing dogma is that these
things are good so if you have a large
code base that means you have a large
number of programmers which means the
majority of them
will be subscribing to that dogma and
checking in garbage
like that so you just it's kind of
unavoidable
because any large code base will
by default reflect the current day's
dogma
whether that dogma is good or bad it is
also then oddly enough for flexibly used
as a way to justify it it's like well
you know big code bases are written this
way so it must it must be about scaling
it's like no
that's that's dogma scaling it's too
hard to hire enough programmers who
don't believe the current zeitgeist
to do anything different what you're
seeing is is a political effect
not a a a programming effect but you
know
again that's just
is svg your full-time occupation now it
is yes nowadays i've basically had to
convert doing it full of time because i
really need to get it done
and out so i can move on um so
you know do you think putting completed
start code galaxy on a resume will be
valuable
um gosh uh
that probably will depend entirely on
how well it manages
to reach sort of a wider audience
so i really don't know
would it be easy to show some of the
industry who sticks to those beliefs
that cutting off
most of the siblings bs is beneficial um
no it's not easy and the reason why it's
not easy
is because as far as i can tell people
don't hold those beliefs rationally they
hold them
irrationally right so nobody who uses
std
has ever done any tests to determine
whether std was a good thing
they never tested compile time they
never tested performance
they never tested scalability they never
tested anything
right they just used it because it was
standard
um so it's very hard to convince them to
not do it
because they didn't base their decision
to use it on any actual
science to begin with so what are you
going to do
right so some people who just did that
non-thinkingly and then when you say hey
we should think about this maybe they're
like oh yeah we should
those people will probably be reachable
pretty easily but everyone else
is just going on dogma anyway so what
are you gonna say they're not gonna be
like oh
suddenly i'm suddenly interested in
actually evaluating this thing because
they weren't
they wouldn't have used it if they were
right
i mean another way to say that would be
if you ask most people
why they use
a lot of these practices they don't have
a
not like a science-based answer for you
like they don't have in answers that
like we evaluated these things and here
were some metrics we used
compile time performance executable size
bug count none of that stuff so
if you don't fundamentally have a
science-based answer
as to why you did do something it's
pretty hard to imagine
how you would convince someone
scientifically
to stop doing that thing because that's
obviously not how their brain works
like they obviously aren't making
decisions based on metrics
so what are you going to show them right
um what i think you would have to do is
just change the zeitgeist like you have
to change the dogma
first because they're the kinds of
people who will just go along with
whatever the industry dogma is
so you'd probably have a much better
likelihood of succeeding
by changing the dogma over time
rather than trying to change particular
people who are
dogma followers to stop them from
following dogma
right i mean maybe you could but then
what you're really doing is just making
them follow your dogma
but you haven't really fixed the
situation that well necessarily
still because it's they're still just
doing a dogmatic thing
right they're not actually evaluating
so i don't know like i i don't know that
there's that much resolution i think
this sort of thing just happens the way
it happens
right
i used some temples in my siblings code
to avoid large amounts of code
duplication by struggle with compile
times
could you recommend any material on meta
programming c plus plus do you think is
good
no no i mean this is why i say like c
plus plus just just sucks
it's a crap language um the reason i
don't use templates is not because i
don't want
meta programming it's because it's just
a bad it's a bad language for meta
programming
so you're just kind of screwed like like
there's a lot of meta programming stuff
you would want to do templates are very
bad at it
first of all they make it unnecessarily
difficult to do what you want to do
and then second the compile times are
terrible
yeah often times the error messages are
also terrible
do you used to use standard lips and
then switch to the hamburger style uh
yeah
so i kind of like bounced over or
like boomerang through it so i used to
program basically this way
i did some programming with sleepless
plus for a while so like inheritance
hierarchies
and templates and crap and then i like
actually evaluated all of them
uh at a project at rad i was like okay
we're gonna try like
seeing how the code comes out by like
using and not using these various things
and what i determined that basically
like the only things that i thought c
plus plus had added that were useful
were operator overloading for math
operations which i do think is a good
idea
it makes the code much more legible and
can be compiled relatively cleanly
um and the other thing was declare
anywhere
which c now also has
but that's it so inheritance not good uh
i wouldn't recommend it templates have
some benefits but the
costs outweigh the benefits so also not
good on the whole
um the newer things that see so like
lambdas
um or like uh
you know auto were not around at the
time
so something like auto is probably fine
would be my guess
um because it doesn't really do anything
it's just a
simpler shorthand for not having to type
in a type
when the type would obviously be known
so i would have a hard time believing
auto isn't fine to use but
it wasn't in the set of things i tested
at that time because it didn't exist yet
smart pointers are garbage there's no
need for them
for sure
declare anywhere is just the fact that
so in the original versions of c
all of the variables for the function
had to be declared at the top of the
scope
and you could make a new scope and
declare functions at the top of the
scope
but you could never declare like you
couldn't do like
int a equals five a times equals two
into b equals four because there was an
expression
in between two declarations that was
illegal all the declarations had to come
at the top
right um and that's just kind of
annoying like there's really no good
explanation for why you would need that
it doesn't really do much for you maybe
there's some arguments about
it enforces good programmer you know
discipline or something but like i don't
tend to like arguments like that
like i don't tend to like arguments that
are like the reason we do this is
because it results in a good programming
practice like i'll decide what the good
programming practices are thank you
what i want from the language is the
ability for me to
take programming practices that i think
are good and do them i don't want you to
decide that because i'm pretty sure you
don't know better than i do
what the good programming proc practices
are for my project
right um
so basically like you know
would you recommend rust over c plus
plus i mean i haven't really used rust
probably not rust seems like a pretty
bad language to me i don't understand
why people think it's good
oh well i kind of maybe understand why
why people think it's good i think those
thoughts are misguided but
um so no i mean
it's six and one half dozen of the other
though like if you look at russ versus c
plus plus like they're both i think
languages that aren't designed very well
but they probably if we really want to
start nitpicking
there's probably like a similar number
of things done poorly versus done well
so i doubt you know i also wouldn't tell
you to definitely use c bus plus over
rust or something
i think they're both lousy languages
um so i'm not gonna i'm not gonna get in
an argument about which one is better
because i
a don't care and b don't know that you
could make
a particularly coherent argument either
way
given that handmade hero is running for
quite a while doesn't it seem unfeasible
for solo indie des to go with a custom
engine especially since you're more
experienced
um i mean i don't know like probably
not at all i mean handmade hero is
not even completed in a single year of
programming yet
right we haven't even spent a year on
this engine yet
if you add up the hours even including
the explanation time
right we haven't even gotten to a
full-time year of programming yet
so and we have a crap ton of stuff in
the engine
um so so we haven't even gotten to a
year yet
well i don't even know what we're at um
but it's probably not a full year
if you actually tried to count the hours
right you assume you program like 40
hours a week
30 hours a week something like that um
right so
i mean i should also say like uh kind of
separately like one thing that i
definitely think
like perspective wise is i i literally
don't care
either right um so one way to look at it
is like like i don't care
what people want to do or don't want to
do um
meaning like someone who wants to do
solo indie development
they should they should do whatever they
want right i don't care at all uh
you know i could i could vaguely try to
you know
analyze your choices for you um
[Music]
and and you know i don't know but but i
don't care like to me programming is
about the fact that i like programming
it's not about it's not about business
you know um i'm not a business person
i'm not here to tell you how to maximize
your returns or something
right so asking me like what you should
use for an engine
is really not that useful so at this
point i tend to just tell people like i
literally don't care like it's not
really my thing
i don't care at all about what you use
um if i had to guess i would say you
probably want to use the unreal engine
or game maker um
[Music]
from what i've seen yeah i probably say
that's what you would do
if you aren't going to roll your own i'd
use one of those
wouldn't probably use unity i think
unity is probably
headed for a i would say unity
is not long for this world like if you
look at their company's financials
they're a public company publicly traded
company now their financials aren't good
they don't make money on selling tools
to game developers they make money on
ads
on advertising and such so i i just i
mean i think putting
yeah like i would bail from unity as
soon as you possibly can
that that'd be my like vague looking at
reading the tarot
you know cards reading the tea leaves
i would say bail from unity as soon as
you can and build a pipeline based on
something else that something else
doesn't have to be your own
right like it doesn't have to be your
code base it could be the unreal engine
which i think will be very stable they
make a crap ton of money they make like
infinite money
um they're not going anywhere and their
entire
revenue stream is basically built off of
game
game stuff right
um so so maybe unreal engine it's also
in a lot of
high-end stuff so that's fine so i might
think about that
you could think about just just a
smaller scoped tool so you know if you
get away with something like game maker
a lot of people have a lot of
positioning to say about that
a lot of games i play in game maker seem
to run pretty well unlike unity unity
games
oftentimes unless they're done by by
people who really know what they're
doing who clean up a lot of unity
garbage
they often play play really crappy
they're either slow
buggy messy they're like you know um
game maker doesn't feel that way game
maker feels pretty solid a lot of times
i play gamer it feels pretty solid
right um so
i would say look at game maker look at
unreal i think those
would be potentially reasonable things
to base you know your
your engines off of whatever you're
doing
i like i think at this point i was
strongly advised against unity
i don't see that going positively in the
long run
um i don't have a enough insight into
some of the new things like there's the
godot engine people have been working on
that
there's like other engines that that
were like
uh i don't even remember what they all
are but there's like other engines out
there
um i just don't have any insight into
but that's your decision and i don't
care
um you know use whatever you want that's
just my basic uh thing
and i can't really tell you what's the
right decision for you
i like programming so i'm probably never
gonna ship something ever
that's not on something that i wrote
whether it's a game or otherwise
it's just not what i do and i don't care
i'd rather fail to ship a game on my own
engine than succeed in shipping on
someone else's
because i don't prioritize that
right um i don't
enjoy using engines so
i would if i was gonna do that i would
just go do something
that made money just purely to make
money
right um i'd i'd go do a web startup or
something
and just try to rake in the cash if i
was going to do that i wouldn't
say how what's the most economically
feasible way to make this
game because to me that just doesn't
interest me i i don't care
about that at all um and so that's
really not something i can
i can make much um
of a of a recommendation on so
so yeah so my only recommendations is
what i just said um
and that's based solely on just looking
at what i what i would anticipate
unity's future to be and i just don't
see there being one for games
i don't see that being likely right um
but i do see i do think you will have
options
um game maker and unreal seem like solid
options for the future to me
um the problems with unreal engine are
that it's like this massively
over complicated sprawling mess right
um so you know you want to make this
game that's
pretty simple because you're an indie
dev and here comes this gigantic code
base that people use for shipping
gigantic
aaa titles right um
so you know i can appreciate that that's
why i always try to say like you know
like some stuff like game maker
it seems pretty solid if you just want
to work on a game you don't want to
think about coding you don't want to
think about engines and stuff
um i would say
like if you if you can get away with
like a 2d
like you're doing a 2d platformer kind
of a thing is in your wheelhouse you
know
take a look at game maker because it
just seems like it's the kind of thing
that's easy to get running quickly and
it produces a pretty quality product at
the end of the day
reasonably in my opinion unreal engine
is
obviously just massive and sprawling and
is probably more
technical expertise and you want to
really take on as an indie dev
but you know if you're trying to do a 3d
thing i don't know what other option i
really don't think it's solid to base
uh your future on a unity based engine i
just i think it's a huge mistake these
days i really think it's a huge mistake
if you keep your unreal game to just
stuff achievable and blueprint it seems
pretty accessible if you want to do c
plus plus code then it's very nuts yeah
that could be true um
like like if you're just trying to make
like a skin on a first-person shooter
like you know kind of all that stuff's
like already in there right
um and so so i could easily see like
there being certain tranches of games
where it's like okay unreal engine is
pretty easy for us to use we just kind
of like
we just kind of run the pre-built
executables we don't really program
anything in c
we use blueprint to just just do some
light like game logic on top
and that's the game you know or it's
like a walking simulator it's like fire
watch or something
right it seems like you could just do
that right because there's no game in
the game it's just we walk around
environments
and we trigger some sound effects and
that's the game like
you probably nowadays could get away
with like no programming basically like
just some graphs and blueprint i would
imagine would get you where you need to
go
so again like like some things to think
about are like
like what are the actual technical
requirements for this game
and can we get away with not really
doing anything you know
might be true there's plenty of games
that are that way
um so again really don't know uh
and and don't care like i really don't
care
what people do i'm only interested in
people who want to learn to program
engine code and i want to show them how
to do it
i don't care about people who don't want
to make engine code
they should go not make engine code
right and i'm definitely not interested
in trying to convince people
um to do something else like they should
do whatever they want
you know
all right
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for the episode of handmade heroes
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow the series at
home
you can always print the game on
handmadehero.org and it comes with
source code so you can follow along with
it
um we got better results today than i
was expecting
so i guess i don't even really know next
week if we
will keep working on the collision
sector that might actually be sufficient
for
pretty much most of our development that
seemed pretty solid
collision section wise um so
next weekend we might stop working on
that uh the only thing we
might do is introduce a spatial
partition so that the collision sector
will scale better right now it's it's
literally checking all the entities in
the active set
all of them every time it does that
collision check which is way too many
entities
computers are crazy fast it's insane
that it runs real time like it does
especially when you open up a web page
the thing can barely run um
what can i say uh so so that probably
should get handled we probably should
put a space partition just to to keep
that under control i think we
don't want to have this thing where we
started adding a bunch of entities to
the world and then
the collision detector becomes a
bottleneck so we should just put a space
partition to keep it
like nice and 01 style uh cost
um and then so i think that's probably
what i'll do next weekend and then we'll
move on to just gameplay
glove programming and fighting uh to try
and try and make some enemies that are
fun
to engage with with the glove um
which is the reason we built the clutch
inductor in the first place so we'll try
to do that
and come up with how we want that to
work we'll work on that
and uh uh so next week's space partition
weekend after that
uh doing some stuff with like collision
response
what happens when you hit somebody with
a glove how do we want the glove control
to work uh do we want like enemies to be
like pushed by the glove and things like
that
so now that we have a collision detector
what do we actually do with the
information we get back to the picture
besides just keeping things from going
into other things what do we actually
want the results
of those collisions to be in a game play
logic sense is what we'll do after that
so that's the robot going forward uh
hope to be back here for that
un until then have fun program everyone
and i'll see y'all on the internet
um and and so on so take it easy
everybody