alright hello everyone and welcome to
hand made here on the show we code a
complete game live on stream we are in
the middle of working out how to do
lighting we kind of came to a nice place
on last stream where we had finished
sort of updating our code to track
incident light and incident lighting
direction and we actually didn't have a
chance to debug it at all
so this stream what we're gonna do is
start taking a look at that lighting
solution and you know working through
trying to verify that we've actually
produced something that it's working and
it doesn't have obvious bugs in it now
one of the problems with doing anything
like this is that unlike code that has
well-defined inputs and outputs lighting
code is a lot more squirrelly than that
this is why for example if you've ever
seen the Cornell box for example which
is it's this famous sort of rendering
there have been attempts at various
times to try and produce what are called
ground truth images where we take a
photograph of something in the real
world and you can kind of see know if we
actually I can get the actual photograph
on here presumably we can I don't know
if it's if it's here somewhere
see
so this is not the original but people
have done actual photographs of a real
box that really looks like this but
that's very simple to construct you know
one red wall one green wall and sent
some white walls with two cubes in it
well two bright rectangular prisms in it
and then when you render you see if you
can produce something that looks similar
to that and you can kind of tell whether
whether or not your lighting solution is
making sense or not and whether or not
you're close to how light should be
transported so obviously you know there
are sort of approaches you can try to
take that at least are sort of about
figuring out whether you have bugs by
comparing to some kind of known output
but even then it's a pretty rough
scenario now why is this it's because
lighting has so many things involved in
it and they're so difficult to
individually analyze in any real way
that it's very difficult to know whether
you've got mistakes in the program and
also whether or not you're using
algorithms that sufficiently describe
the behavior of the light that you're
interested in capturing this is made
even more difficult in scenarios like we
have in handmade hero where we know that
we're not going to be able to capture
realistic lighting because we're trying
to solve this in real time and we simply
don't have the ability to produce a
fully accurate solution so what we're
looking for as well as an approximate
solution so our situation is
particularly difficult because we really
don't have much to go on to know whether
our code is working or not and so we
have to sort of take you the approach of
looking at various pieces and seeing
whether they produce sane results and
just going from there there is no right
right answer we can easily compare it to
because you know one of the problem with
with a hack that you're using to try and
get something to run in real time that
doesn't run in real time is that you
also now no longer have some even
of what the actual correct output should
be the correct output for a hack is
something that looks ok right I mean
that's sort of the definition of it is
that you run it and the lighting looks
Pleasant right like it looks good enough
that you're willing to make it be what
the game uses for its lighting that's
about all you can say about it
right and so that's kind of the issue
that we face when debugging this and
again there are so many different
aspects of it involved that it's just a
really difficult problem for example
we've got voxel acceleration structure
that we use to do the the lighting per
pixel we've got the actual purpose of
lighting computation we have the
lighting transport that's happening on
the CPU we have the final gather that's
happening on the CPU we have the
extraction process that turns the scene
into lighting elements and all of those
things can be buggy and more importantly
in addition to them being buggy all of
those things could also have algorithmic
shortcomings that are important to
address like some places where we have
cut corners may in fact be places where
corners cannot be cut or may be places
where the way we cut the corners is
simply not good enough and we need to
figure out some other option some other
way of producing an approximate result
that's more accurate or doesn't have
certain artifacts and so we just have a
lot in the mix and that is why do buggin
this kind of code is difficult and more
importantly broadening the discussion
outside of just debugging it's why in a
broader sense developing this kind of
code is hard there isn't some clean
specification that we can look at and
say well the code is correct when it
meets this exact set of outputs in like
a unit testing sense or something right
there is no well to find output all we
really know is that we want something
that looks pleasant and makes the game
feel nice when you're playing it and so
that's what our job is and it's and it's
not a particularly pleasant one but that
is what we must do if we want some nice
real-time lighting in the game and so
that is what we're going to do
I'm on day four eleven here so you want
to start with day 410 source code if you
are following along at home I'm gonna
open up visual studio which I did after
yesterday remember to register or
whatever it asked me to do there so it
is good to go I also changed the font
size which people were requesting so
they could see it better again this is a
new machine we installed just a few
weeks ago so it kind of had to be reset
up like the old one so if we take a look
at what's going on if I run the program
you can kind of see that we've got our
sort of unlit world here and if I hit f1
it will do one lighting computation on
the CPU side where it which is where
we're debugging it at the moment
and we can kind of take a look and see
what were what we're getting for
lighting results here right and even
though this was the first time we really
ran all the code that we typed in one of
the interesting things about it is it's
really not that bad it's got some issues
to it that are difficult to explain away
and so I think we do have some problems
with the shadowing the reason I say that
is because you can see there it's really
kind of a tough tough situation you can
see how light is propagating beyond the
blockers here this is fairly bright out
here and really that should be dark
because here's the light source and it
can't really get over there right but of
course the thing that is also a little
bit difficult and it's important to
remember here is that that we are not
computing lighting on this actual scene
we are computing lighting on the
synthetic blockers that we got and so I
think when you know and those little
synthetic reflectors were kind of
weirdly shaped right and and we may need
to kind of work on getting those things
to be more accurate descriptions of the
scene if we want the lighting to be okay
so what I want to start by doing is I'd
like to switch
back to a mode where we can visualize
the actual lighting elements themselves
because I think we need to do that in
order to start assessing whether or not
the shadowing is working correctly and
other things like that so as we start to
construct test cases I think it's gonna
be important to be looking at the actual
geometry we're doing rather than the
geometry of the game which is it not the
Jean tree we're using for actual
lighting now maybe we should be using
the geometry of the game for actual
lighting that's sort of a separate issue
but you know that's that's sort of
neither here nor there so anyway when we
output our lighting in here we've kind
of got this output text or debug stuff
and output lighting quads output letting
verts what I might want to do is
actually run one of these instead so
when we do output lighting I believe
that is I don't even think that's
getting called at the moment so if I
were to run output lighting here
I believe what it's currently set to do
in the textures mode is it's actually
set to output the voxels so if we take
the world and run the lighting solution
then what we're actually going to get
here is just the location of the voxels
in the voxel grid and we're gonna we're
gonna show one cube well they're not
really cubes but we're gonna show one
voxel element at the center of the voxel
in every case where there was some
lighting element in that voxel and you
can see that that looks roughly correct
so I'm not really concerned about that
that's part of the algorithm seems fine
we have issues to address in terms of
how we're sampling around them the
voxels and how big the voxels should be
and stuff like that but for the moment
that's really not the concern so I want
to switch to trying to output the
reflectors here and what I'm gonna do
there is when we run
this code I want to look at these actual
pieces that we've created which are the
things we're actually running the
lighting solution on now you have to
recall that we're we're not even really
drawing these in the quite the way that
they would be drawn these would actually
be discs so where these are just sort of
like little quads that's what I render
attempts to draw we just drew quads that
are roughly approximating where the disc
would be but the lighting solution is
happening entirely on these yeah it's
happening entirely on these reflectors
now I'm already seeing something
particularly odd here which is that if
we take a look at what we're seeing from
these we actually don't see any light
out in the areas where we were seeing
light before now there's a little bit
right that leaked out in here but not a
whole lot right most of it the light was
actually correctly shadowed even though
we really haven't built geometry that's
particularly correct so you know we
probably need to spam more reflectors in
a lot of these places in order to really
make this work right but even so even
accounting for that you can kind of see
that it did it wasn't that bad in terms
of how it actually worked here with
these reflectors right
so just looking at this that starts to
raise some questions to me as to why if
I actually go in here and tell it not to
do any of this stuff right so if I tell
it not to do any of that stuff why we're
getting all of this light out here right
and that suggests to me again if I just
like update the code here that suggests
to me that the reflection pass is
actually not producing as bad a results
as it we would be led to believe from
that and then it appears like it's
mostly the final gather pass that's
producing that bleed through lighting
now the question is why is that and I
think there's a couple of reasons that
could be now one is that the that path
is operating improperly like one
possibility is certainly that the final
gather is just wrong okay I mean
certainly option and if we take a look
at it here here's the gather final
lighting so one possibility is that's
just wrong right it just it is not
working properly and it's allowing light
to be transferred in situations where
light should not be transferred
certainly possible however I'm not sure
that that's the most likely explanation
it could also be that there's another
explanation and that explanation is that
the reason the final gather is able to
gather light past the shadowing is
because it is casting more Rays and it's
able right it's casting twice the number
of rays so it's able to generate enough
rays to see through the holes right in
in the geometry now I will admit
that doesn't seem like a very plausible
explanation why does it not seem like a
very plausible - well because if I run
this right and I look here you know some
of it seems a little bit plausible the
fact that these are red lights here have
gotten through does suggest that the Ray
probing is able to sort of get through
the geometry even in the other one right
so you know I I do think that lends some
credence to it but when I turn that off
when we look at the final result here
the the thing that kind of makes me a
little suspicious is that it doesn't
really get that dim back here either
right it's pretty bright now I guess I
could believe that that was enough
dimmer I mean this is fairly bright
white over here and this is blue which
is suggesting that it's coming from more
of a bounce sort of a thing I don't know
but it's definitely the case that I you
know I'm just a little suspicious pish
so I'm gonna go ahead and take a look at
this a little more carefully and we're
gonna start to run through this code and
maybe construct some testing like we can
maybe construct some situations to see
what's happening more explicitly so that
we can verify that this is working
better so I'm it's just to try to keep
my mental process out loud here so
people can hear what I'm going through
and how I'm analyzing the problem the
first thing that's a little that I just
kind of want to get that I wanted to
test is I immediately thought in my head
this is a bit concerning to me the the
way we're doing the raycast
so what I looked as I was looking going
like okay I saw what was happening in
that scene and I was like I'm not sure
that these blockers are actually
blocking rays that are going from behind
them right and if you take a look at
what
running here I'm sorry that into
position that there we go why are you
guys have to wait for the camera to get
into place what did I do
how did I break it I haven't even done
anything yet
you just go grab this here real quick
all right
there we go uh so if we take a look at
what's going on here I was like well
when these things are looking through
here I wonder if they're properly like
of what if they're properly hitting the
backsides of things and I remembered
that we decided that we didn't want to
have things that were one sided anymore
that's our e to side anymore
so things that are two-sided like you
know treating a card as if it as if it
hit from both sides we're not doing that
anymore so actually these things are the
only parts that you can hit so if I
switch it back to the reflector output
here right we've got all these sort of
cards in here and if I look for example
if these the only things that they can
that will prevent them bringing the
light source is this row and this row
well this top part too but that's not
really in the way of the light source
right so it's really just these and I
guess these interior ones would also
count if you happen to hit them so
looking from someone here right it would
be pretty easy to shoot through and hit
this light source because none of these
these aren't really blocking you that
much right there's this giant hole in
here so I feel like we do kind of have a
little bit of a problem there where we
don't really our our model is not
sufficient to really capture the
lighting that we're interested in right
we need some way of making this more
robust and that may mean having a ray
cast that's more accurate right
and that that could be a bit tricky but
I feel like we may want to do that so
here's some things I'm thinking of
so first off we know we have a bunch we
know we have essentially two different
things we're trying to recast against
one of them is like a cube right one of
them is is you know a right rectangular
prism and that's what most of the sort
of ground is made out of so you know if
I if I switch back to not showing the
lighting here so I could just set show
lighting on and off in fact do I do I
have a thing set a way to toggle that
like an f2 or something
like if I do this I'm just curious what
happens if I hit f1 again I already
dirty addressed this okay alright so I
actually can switch between this all I
want all right
that makes it nice so you know if we
take a look at what the actual world is
made out of there's a lot of these sort
of cube elements right and if I switch
back here I see that I've generated
these cube elements into all these
little reflectors it it begs the
question like for the purposes of Ray
casting shouldn't I just be able to use
the actual actual elements that would
line up perfectly with this right and so
it seems like part of the problem is
that look we want to do you know
transmission here and we have some
things which are arbitrarily shaped
those are our sprites which can have any
kind of shape really because whatever
the shape of the the bitmap is that's
what they're gonna do right but we also
have a bunch of structure geometry
that's kind of cube like right and so
picking a disk is not a particularly
good choice for the ray casting because
we can't fit disks to cubes and cover
them correctly right disks fit circular
things cubes are not circular
so it might be a better idea to switch
to a reflection element whose shape is
going to line up with the cube like a
flat plate is probably a much better
choice and we do have at least at the
moment we also have the luxury of not
even needing that flat plate to be
arbitrarily oriented right the flat
plate is also kind of in a situation
where it could be axis aligned right
none of our pubes ever break access
alignment in the game that may not be
true forever we may end up with some
rotating stuff at some point right
so we may not want to bake that
assumption in too hard but it is an
option right at least everything that we
were considering building so far has
that property to it right so what we'd
like to do is go ahead and maybe do that
first like that seems like maybe the
saner thing to do first is create
something that can do that intersection
test and maybe then from there we can
start to debug this a little bit more
because at the moment I'm just thinking
well you know I can start to construct
some cases here and maybe start to debug
the lighting code but really it seems
like a lot of the problem for the most
part is just that like even if the
lighting solution were correct our
geometry is so wrong that it just
doesn't seem like it's gonna that
doesn't seem like it's gonna ever
produce an acceptable lighting solution
with the way it's broken up right so
let's suppose that we wanted to do
better intersection testing in this case
right I'm gonna need Milton for this cuz
I want to draw it out and today's day
4:11
so I don't know what this is but let's
just say this is a rectangle we could
also use a square all right so what we
want to do here is say let's suppose we
have a rectangle somewhere and we're ray
casting against it what we want to do is
say where does the where does the Ray
intersect the rectangle if it intersects
the rectangle and these are kind of easy
questions to ask in series but harder to
ask together right so if we just look at
this question it's like oh well I don't
know how do I know if it did this or
that or whatever right and miss the
rectangle so let's break the problem
down from the fairly complex case of
Desiree hit a rectangle to something
easier to deal with so let's take some
assumptions first to make this a little
bit simpler so first for any rectangle
we can't assume that it looked like this
right we can assume that the rectangle
had a width and a height that we specify
we can assume that's aligned with the x
and y axes now why can we assume that
well we can assume that because any ray
and any sort of origin and direction of
array could be rotated into the space of
the rectangle right so to begin our
analysis we could assume that that were
true right we could assume that we'd
already put it into a space where we had
X and y and this were expressed and you
know this was Z and this were expressed
completely relative to the rectangles
own reference frame right now we may not
want to actually do that transform
explicitly because we may want to try
and bake it down to the simplest set of
equations this is Ray casting it's
expensive we want to make it as cheap as
possible cause lots of rays are cast so
I mean I usually want to do that but
just for purposes of our thinking
process we could assume that was the
case right so we already know how to
take the intersection of a ray with a
plane right so ray versus plane this
we've already done because that's what
we had to do in our existing ray cast if
I remember collect correctly right I
mean we wrote this ray cast here and you
can see us doing exactly this you can
see us taking the time at which the ray
hits the plane of the circle right
so if you don't remember this go back to
it but you can see right here this is us
computing for for a conical you know for
a disc this is us computing we're on the
the plane of the disk we hit so if we
already have this answer right then we
effectively know we're in here the ray
hits so in order to test whether or not
we hit a rectangle instead of a cone
instead of a disk it's not that
difficult right if it was already
oriented properly all we do was take the
distance in X and the distance sorry the
distance in X and the distance in Y and
we would see whether it exceeded half
the width in either direction and half
the height in either direction if it
exceeded one of those it was outside if
it didn't exceed either of them then
it's inside right so much like in the
disk case we just checked what the
distance was from the center right
because that right since this is how you
would do a circle we can just see what
the distance is we know we're inside for
a rectangle all we need to do is take an
axial distance right but of course we
have a problem since we don't actually
know what our x and y axes since we
don't actually know that our x and y
axes are aligned in this way in fact we
know effectively that they're not
aligned in this way we can't do that
simple check right we can't just say is
it you know what's the X distance what's
the Y distance because we didn't first
do this transform what we're actually
gonna have is just some rectangle
floating in space and a point on we know
it's on the plane so how do we then do
this measurement well like I said we
could transform the whole problem we
could compute a transform that
transforms the Ray into the point of
thing and then do a Pablo plow right way
too much work we don't need to do all
that right the Ray intersects
test already placed us down there we
know we're on the plane in order to
define this rectangle in the first place
we would need an X and y-axis right I
mean that's that's how we would define
the rectangle so if our rectangle
elements just store their x and y axes
themselves then the inner product will
give us exactly what we want that sort
of does the local transform to put just
the point in the plane into the space of
the rectangle so if we know we have a
unit axis in either direction here right
so if we know we take a unit axis in
either of these directions and we took
the inner product with it then we would
know that we got exactly what we
expected right we would know that we got
a we would know that we got the x
coordinate right now we can do something
potentially a little weirder here and so
let me kind of give you a little
background on this so think about what
we're gonna have to do here right and
let me explain the process explicitly
for anyone who's a little hazy on
exactly what's going on we've done this
many times on handmade here but not
everyone watches every episode obviously
there's a lot of it so I'll just try to
explain it briefly if we have a unit
axis right so basically if we have an
x-axis and a y-axis if we know that the
length of these axes is both equal to 1
right so we know that these are 1 long
then the inner product of the axis with
some point whatever the point is right
so if I take the point and the inner
product with say this x axis I know that
I'm going to get the length of the point
vector like right the length of the x
axis times the cosine of the angle
between them right that angle right
there right I know this is what I'm
going to get
well if we know that this is unit length
then we know that that term equals one
okay and if we know the length of this
right then we know that we're well in
fact Burgas we know the length of this
we know that what we'll end up with is
the length of P times the cosine of
theta now the cosine of theta is
explicitly this leg of the triangle
right right cosine of theta is the thing
that if multiplied by this length will
give us this length that's that's just
triangles that's just right triangles
right if I've got an angle here and I
have a hypotenuse we know that this is
hypothesis this side is hypotenuse
cosine theta we know that this side is
hypotenuse sine theta that's just right
triangles right that's Pythagoras and
and everybody else so if we know that
that's true that means that this right
here this P transpose X is the length of
B cosine theta which is exactly the
measurement of P along the x axis we've
done this many times on hand made here
right this should be familiar to
everybody so if we had unit axes in both
directions we know that we could just do
P transpose X P transpose Y right and
this would give us exactly what we
wanted up here it would give us the x
and y coordinates in the space of the
rectangle which we could then compare to
the width and height right so if we
wanted to what we could store is x axis
and width Y axis and height right and
then we would just do this and see
whether it falls between is greater than
negative 1/2 the width and less than the
width less than half the width you know
in between the two right so it's it's
this negative width is less than or
equal to P transpose X is less than or
equal to width and these need to both be
over to right because we're going half
the width one side half throat the other
side and P transpose Y
right I know what happened there to my
why uh so anyway this is what we're
talking about okay so hopefully that
makes sense to everybody now this tells
us whether we're inside the rectangle
but it involves a bunch of comparisons
right so it might be more interesting if
we didn't have to have these extra
variables lying around and could just do
something a little bit more
straightforward right okay well you can
see that this is an equation itself
right and if we multiply each of these
parts of this inequality by the same
value if it's a positive value we don't
change the truth of it right so we could
multiply each of these by like two for
example and it would still be the same
equation it would just have a two in
each of the terms but it's still true so
if we wanted to we could go ahead and
take this requirement and multiply it by
two over the width right if we wanted to
right we could say multiply this by two
over the width multiply this by two over
the width multiply this by two over the
width right and what would happen is we
would get negative 1 less than or equal
to 2 over the width times P transpose X
less than equal to 1 right so now our
comparison is with a constant and it's
the same constant on either side right
rather than the variable on either side
it's the same thing it's just between
negative 1 and 1 so the question is
should we just do this well we just
store 2 over the width and we multiplied
by P transpose X and that sounds good
right well remember we know that this
equation here the reason we ended up
with this was because we had lengths of
length of X cosine theta and length of X
dropped out of the equation because its
length was 1 leaving us with only length
of P cosine X which we know is the
x-coordinate we were looking for right
the x-coordinate of the point
what if since we don't actually want
that what we actually want is the two
over width multiplied version of the
coordinate to do our comparison what if
we just stored the x-axis pre x 2 over
the width then this term drops out and
we're just left with the dot product of
our special axis we'll call that X prime
maybe you know if X prime equals two
over width times X right we would just
be left with this so now we can do one
inner product and just test you know
inner product absolute value test for
less than one that's it right and that's
pretty cheap
so if we chose to do this which I think
we should choose to do as you can tell
by my sort of explaining it on the
blackboard if we chose to do this then
we could have lots of little rectangular
elements they could be oriented any way
they want and we only really pay the
cost of storing two extra axes and doing
two extra inner products twigs doing
extra products and one comparison now we
also but we also save a length squared
so in some sense this is almost a wash
the rectangle version is probably almost
as cheap as the circular version the
difference is just the storage is a
little more expensive now we can
optimize the storage more if we really
wanted to so if it comes down to a
storage issue we have options since we
know we have to store the normal to the
surface right because that's what gives
us that's what allows us to do all our
reflection computations in the first
place
and it tells it defines what plane it's
in so it's how we do our beginning of
array cast as well we obviously could
just store the x-axis just the x axis
and then cross-product the x axis with
the to get the y axis cross mount the x
axis with the z axis to get the y axis
I'm not gonna do that because I don't
think the extra storage is gonna be that
big of a deal and that way we don't have
to spend a lot of time doing extra cross
products and then have a coefficient
that tells you how long the y axis would
be after you did that buh-buh-buh a lot
right so I think all we want to do is
store our premultiplied x and y axes and
then I think we're pretty much done
right we just do two over the width
times the x axis two over the Heights
time the y axis and we're done I'm gonna
start out not doing that
the reason I'm gonna start out not doing
that is because we want to store our
debug we want be able to draw the debug
shapes that we're using so we're gonna
want to not have to invert those at
first but just so you can see we have a
very clear path to a very easy way
mathematically speaking of testing this
and so when the time comes to sort of
optimize this down it's not gonna be a
huge disaster it's pretty straight
forward any way you slice it okay so
let's
I'm moving to that scheme first thing
I'm gonna do is I'm gonna change our
extraction process so what I want to do
here is go into render group and we kind
of have these extract reflectors from
quads extract reflectors from verts and
what I want to do here is I want to try
and figure out a way of making these
reflectors just I'm gonna change
fundamentally the way we're doing this
so even before we change two rectangles
no you know what let me do in the
opposite order let's remove our extract
from verts entirely we're just not gonna
do this anymore
we're gonna do extract from quads and
the first thing I will do is I'll make
it so that we extract exact quads so
when we render the scene with the
lighting it will line up exactly with
all the quads right because now we'll be
able to do that they don't have to be
discs right so if we did that that's
we're gonna do first and then what I'll
do is the next step will be dicing those
up into small enough ones that they that
were satisfied with them with how with
how granular the lighting solution would
be I think that's a good idea okay
so if we take a look at this when we
call our extraction function here I'm
gonna use quads and I'm gonna go ahead
and and get that working I don't even
know if that we haven't called that in a
long time I don't even know if it works
with disks it does okay so there those
are our disks there and here's the
lighting solution that comes from that
and so that looks okay right nothing
particularly bizarre there those disks
do look roughly correct but as you can
see their disks so they don't even
remotely fit the geometry even if we
dice them they would they would not be
particularly good and have lots of holes
so let's go up now and fix that output
I'll go ahead and put it over here let's
go ahead and fix that extraction now to
use exact quads all right so if we
wanted to do that let me go ahead and
take the letting elements here so if we
wanted to do that what we're really
going to look at here is we've got a
normal and we've got our vector right
that our vector is the radius so what we
want to do is change this to width and a
height and expand this to have an x-axis
and a y-axis right and like I said
before that width and the height is not
necessary and neither is the y-axis
really all we need is a multiplier that
would tell us what to do to create a dot
proximal y-axis from the normal in the
x-axis so really we're only adding if we
if we want to be minimal having a normal
plus of radius is for floats and we're
basically going from those four floats
to having a normal a x-axis and a
coefficient so we're really only adding
three floats because we're going from
four floats to seven floats right so
we're not even quite doubling the size
of it and again we've got a lot of other
stuff we're storing here potentially so
we're not doubling the size of the
structure by any stretch of the
imagination we're only doubling the size
of the sort of I don't know if you want
to call it a local geometry storage so
it's not that bad
you're regardless and even in this more
piggy format here
we're not geez I should put on my pick
hat so even in the piggy format that
we're using now again we've got kind of
a lot of buffer sort of stuff we have to
do here so I'm not even 100% certain
that this is a something to even think
about it also what you know most of
stuff as I just try to point out things
that when we get further down the line
you know what our options are and
whether
should be nervous or not about about
what's going on so okay so let's suppose
we want to extract this quad directly
well all right what we're gonna have to
do here is say we have these vertices
and the vertices tell us what the the
quad is shaped like we need to assume
that the quad is is roughly is not
particularly skewed because right now
we're sort of we don't really want to
have to deal with skewed quadrilaterals
even though we may want to support them
in the future and could support them
potentially by doing a little bit more
math when we're doing our testing we
don't really want to necessarily think
about that yet and make sure we handle
that so we're just gonna only do this as
if we're handling right angle quads
right but it's not too much more work to
handle skewed ones either so it's not
it's really just making sure you think
it through properly so we can't even
handle this when we want to do like
squash and stretch we could we could
handle those exactly if you really
wanted to as well anyway so when we get
these vertices out you can see us
computing them here and we already
compute these spans right so we compute
the length of 0 to 1 which would give us
one of our axes there from vertex
herbivore x1 and we also do span 0 to 3
and that gives us the other one right so
these two together if we assume the coop
the quad is wound which we know that we
always try to do so if we assume this
wound counterclockwise right then we can
assume without any loss of generality
that 0 1 and we don't care about 2 &amp; 3
here right we can assume that picking
the y-axis as 0 2 3 and the x-axis is 0
to 1 would be a totally reasonable thing
to do right so in this case when we
compute these spans we could then say
immediately that the x-axis was going to
be span 1 0
and the y-axis was going to be span
three zero now these have a link to them
now the length is the entirety of the
distance right and we don't actually
want that as the length of the as the
width and we don't want the axis to have
that baked in we want to store these two
separately right because we're sort of
doing the fully blown out Pig format
first not the more compact baked the
multiplication into the length of the
axis to simplify the equations version
right that's an optimization and while
we're debugging things we don't want to
over optimize it even though we know we
probably want to optimize it in the
future it's not really pretty mature
optimization in the sense of you might
not want to optimize it's like we pretty
much w1 optimize it but it's premature
up times in the fact that it will make
our debugging harder if we pre bacon
these things because those are just more
things that can go wrong so rather we
would rather get it working with the
clear easy to understand formula first
and then bacon all the you know
craziness and that way we can just tell
whether we break it when we do the
optimization that's a lot easier way to
approach the debugging than trying to do
it all at once so pretty much for
optimization in this case still correct
term for what we are trying to avoid but
it's a different kind of people to
premature optimization then then certain
other cases right sometimes premature
authorization means you shouldn't even
optimize it that's it at all in this
case you probably should but not right
now all right
so coming through here we've got our
x-axis y-axis we know what the length of
these needs to be it needs to be one so
if we were to take the length of the
x-axis and the length of the y-axis we
would get our width and height right so
we would know that our element width is
going to be the length of the x-axis and
our element height is going to be equal
to length of the y-axis what we don't
have yet is the normalized versions of
these x and y axes now I'm gonna go
ahead and say I'm just going to use
normalizer 0 here
because I can
but when optimizing make sure we
actually just used the length station
but you know it's a little bit redundant
because since we already computed the
length year we could just divide by the
length here I'm not doing that because
we'd have to check to see if zero and
blah blah blah so you know when we
actually want to streamline this routine
that's something we'll want to do so now
we need to know where the location of
this thing is and this is gonna be
really pretty straightforward we don't
have an element R anymore that's what we
deleted but we do have an easy ability
to compute this now what we want to do
is just say well we've got our x-axis
and we've got our y-axis if we just go
half way along each we will be at the
center of this thing so we're pretty
much done at that point right so that's
really all there is to it for the
extraction that plucks out the x axis
the y axis and gives us the centroid as
well so that's all good so really all we
need to do now is anytime we were using
this we now need to do it the way that
we said before so we now need to use
this new encoding to do rendering of
quads when we're trying to draw these in
a debug setting and we need to use the
fact that it's a quad those axes in the
width and so on we need to use those for
testing when we test the Ray
intersection well here's the Ray
intersection and you can see that this
disc squared cone crap right this stuff
is now irrelevant right we don't care
about any of this anymore
this stuff is all not on the table so we
have this Ray P that is the position of
the when the Ray hits the plane sort of
the Ray in plane might be the weight
right way to to look at it or where the
Ray intersects the plane so what we want
to do here is exactly the equation that
I talked about up in here
we want to do this but like I said we
didn't bake it in yet so we're really
gonna be doing this one down here right
we're gonna be doing this style negative
half less than or equal to the value
less than go to half right that's what
we want to do so the first thing I'm
going to do is I'm gonna compute those
half a values and one thing you know you
could look at to simplify this equation
is you could just multiply everything by
two right so really we could just say if
twice this value is between H and H
right so what I'm going to do here is
just say you know X check equals
something and Y check equals something
and those will be the values we'll test
and what we'll do is we'll multiply them
by two so that we don't have to divide
the other stuff by two right so we know
this is an inner product and we know
this is an inner product the question is
what is the inner product well the
position of the Ray needs to be relative
to the point where testing against it is
right you can see here that we do the
relative source P and it's basically
wherever the like the Ray origin is and
we have the source position here I can't
say why we quite did it that way instead
of the other way around
because I guess you because you wouldn't
have the negative in here so that is
just kind of weird like why did we I'm
not sure why we freeze it this way right
like I would have preferred this be
flipped which we could easily do if you
take the rel source P if you were to
negate this this just wouldn't eat a
negative now right so like it's just
wasteful unless I'm missing something
that that is the preferable way to put
it so you basically put the Ray origin
in the space of the plane and then this
inner product here doesn't have to have
a negative because it's just the
relative origin right why am i on the
caps lock I got a ton by I hate caps
lock so the relative origin there yeah
we just compute that's what the D value
would be we then take the negative D
value over the source end and that tells
us where we're actually hitting this
thing right and yeah I think that's
pretty much all we need yeah and so then
we just take the the T ray that gives us
the rapey there that is already relative
again so we don't that Ray position
[Music]
yeah this this looks a little this looks
a little Squinkie to me I want to make
sure this is all correct that rate
position normally you would have to take
the rate you know if you actually wanted
the full rate position right you would
have to do that right
and I guess we just made the
optimization of taking that out because
you were then going to subtract it away
anyway right you're going to want the
origin to be relative to the source P so
I think that's okay but I want to do
this one more time I'm just not
comfortable with it quite like that so I
want to do this one more time expand it
out entirely I guess is what I would say
all right so if we take the rate
position and we say that it's ray origin
plus T ray x ray D which is the equation
for the Ray it starts at this location
it goes this far along this direction if
I then say you know and again like I
said I don't want to do this if I then
want to know what my x and y parameters
are then what those are going to be is
those are going to be the source
position right whatever that source
position is that's the center of my
rectangle I want to take the Ray
position itself and I want to figure out
where that is relative to the source
position right and I want to take the
inner product of that with the x axis
that I've got for the y axis that I got
and then I want to do a X check it's
greater than or equal to negative width
and X check is less than or equal to
weight right
and we could use an absolute value here
if we want to as well probably right so
that's what we want to do we want to
take a look at where the rate position
is relative to the the center of this
rectangle and we want to dot product
that take the inner product with each of
our axes and then take a look at whether
or not the result then falls within the
boundaries that we specified right now
in order to do that I have to do ray p-
source P right which means that I'm
taking whatever this equation was here
and I'm subtracting source P away from
it and you can see that ray origin -
source P right in other words this is
that and what you can see is we've
already got that ready to go so we want
to put that in here and honestly I don't
know that maybe we did it right before
but that seems right to me and it didn't
look like the equations were quite right
before I don't maybe we had a bug in
here I'm not sure maybe it's because it
was a cone we were doing something
slightly differently there I don't know
but this looks like the correct version
for this right
to me anyway because I do think you want
that rail you really do need that rail
origin there and I think that's
important so I don't know we may have
had a bug in there I'm not sure but
hopefully we don't have a bug now but
we'll debug that in a little bit we now
have to deal with the fact that when we
actually output this stuff right you can
see we need to do something with it
right so when we output our lighting
quads for example I don't know what
output lighting verts does
output lighting verts is irrelevant now
so that's just shouldn't even be in
there that was when we were lighting
directly from those so output lighting
quads is the only thing that we will
still would still be supporting so we do
output letting quads we go through
drawing each of these elements and I
don't really think we have any other
options here like this stuff just has to
kind of be done this way right and so
what we have to do is we have to make
reconstruct our quad here to draw it so
when we produce our X and our Y here
what we actually want to do is this
stuff is no longer relevant like we
don't have to synthetically produce an X
into y axis anymore because we actually
have them and so these can all kind of
go away what we really want to say is
just well it's just the element x axis
and the element y axis and since we're
going to expand out by those we want to
multiply by the width and height right
and again those need to be halved and
the reason for that is because again
we're storing the width in height but
we're going out in both directions as
them so we need to make sure that we
account for that all right so let's take
a look so here's our result and we seem
to be oh right this is the equation this
this produces a diamond shape which is
not what we want so what we really want
to do here is is you know a plus X plus
y we want to go both right so we want to
start in fact I would probably start it
at minus minus so I'd say we want to go
negative x negative Y right then we want
to go across X but stayed on the bottom
Y then we want to go across sexing up
right and then we want to come back on
the top and that would produce our are
winding they're assuming that we're
still winding counterclockwise I never
know with this way we did the quads
Eggman but okay so if we take a look at
what we've produced here what we can see
is like I'm pretty happy with that
actually that looks exactly right I mean
pretty much everything here is what I
would expect it to look like yeah I mean
that's all that's all pretty much
correct right and if we take a look at
our lighting solution now actually it's
it's considerably better there's still
some stuff that doesn't make a whole lot
of sense I'm not sure where the light is
coming from back here so I do wonder if
we've got some bugs in there
but we do we seem to have a lot better
lighting solution than we had originally
just in terms of again that sort of not
having the light leaking now the only
thing that's odd though here is that
we're not or I shouldn't say odd is the
wrong term probably the only thing
that's that's not really representative
at this point is we don't have enough
yet so this is still too few quads
really for what we want this is this
doesn't break you know here are the
actual lighting elements each one of
these lighting elements can only compute
one color value and that's obviously not
sufficient like we want to break each of
these big cubes up you know into a lot
more lighting elements like tinier
lighting elements you know what I mean
where we compute the lighting and it's
kind of a little bit tricky we're
probably going to need to do something
fairly smart here to figure out how to
break them up because we also don't
probably want to spend a lot of time
with elements that are like not gonna
contribute to the lighting like
underneath here or whatever right like
the bottom ones so you know we may want
to just not put bottom elements in much
like bottom elements things that are
pointing downward like wouldn't get
subdivided at all but things that are
pointing up or get subdividing quite a
bit right cuz it's just in terms of what
you can and can't see you know so yeah
so the first thing I'd like to do is
just subdivide these guys a little bit
and so you know the easiest way to do
that is when we do this extract
reflectors bit we have to start thinking
about this a little bit more carefully
so when we have this element count right
and we say that it's just going to be
equal to the quad count what we want to
do is is also do an assertion here
probably the element count is less than
like how many we have because it's a
fixed array at the moment right I don't
think we allocate space for it
what just happened
hold on second yes so you can see here
we got an only count but it's a fixed
size array at the moment right we don't
allocate space why would I know it just
happened we got a there was a weird like
hang there oh no in fact I guess it
wasn't a hanging it was just I was
looking at the screen and wasn't
rotating it alright so what we want to
do now is take a look at this and start
subdividing these guys so that we can
have a better lighting solution now in
order to tell how things are subdivided
I'm gonna need some way of actually
seeing what's going on which is easier
said than done in this case so what I'm
gonna do is shrink them just a tiny bit
when we output them only so in here when
I multiply by 0.5 right I'm gonna
actually do something here where I do
half the width minus a little bit and
half the height minus a little bit so
what hopefully that will do again only
when I'm drawing so we're still
computing with full width ones but
hopefully what this will do right is
we'll be able to see like a gap
everywhere right so you can kind of see
like these gaps now in in the geometry
maybe you need a slightly bigger gap and
once I've got that gap in the geometry I
can see now where all the lighting
surfaces actually are and I can kind of
go like alright well if I subdivided
this I would into like four I would see
lines down the middle and it would be
clear you know that it had actually
worked whereas before if I subdivided
all I could really see was the lighting
solution getting having more resolution
but you know that's not super clear so
that's the only thing I want to do there
so let's say for example right now let's
just say that we were going to dice them
up a bit by
applying by for how many elements there
were right and if we want to do that
then what we do is say well okay we know
that we know that after we sort of
constructed this right just gonna grab
this out here what we could do is just
create sort of a tiled set of elements
in place right so if I want to right in
here I could just say all right for each
of these that we were outputting before
maybe I output significantly more of
them right I don't know that we need to
keep storing original vertices either at
this point or original bitmap let me
just hold on one second let me just see
if I can get rid of that
right
so if I just was to get rid of that now
since we don't really care about the
original bitmap or the original vertices
because we don't reopen it does anyone
care
yeah so I think we can just do commands
wait bitmap since it's the only we just
we only do the white bitmap here and the
yeah and this we don't need anymore at
all right so I guess the only thing we
need to store is the UVs if we were
gonna still use UV but we're not right
because these things don't have any
textures on them so we can get rid of
that too I think we're good I think we
just get rid of all that stuff because
we don't use that anymore the lighting
is computed per pixel so we don't need
to have a mode where we send that any of
that down so I think we're just good to
go like there we go I don't know why
sometimes the framerate is very very is
is like locked at 60 Hertz and other
times it's not and I have no idea what
the difference is that makes me pretty
worried oh you know what it's just how
soon did we are cuz the per pixel cost
is still pretty high and I'm optimised I
think it's mostly what's going on there
yeah okay that makes sense when we get
here we've just got enough stuff that's
actually rendering right what we're down
here it's very little yeah that's fine
all right so let's see when we do our
output letting quads now everything is
nice and clean there and so we should be
fine to like subdivide our lighting
elements now into something a little bit
more fancy so if we wanted to we could
do something where we do a little bit
more like this so here we would do sort
of subdivision along the X and the y of
one of these things the element X and Y
axis is going to be the same let me go
ahead and grab this this thing out here
because el-amin is not going to be
elements plus quad and X any more
elements is just going to be whatever it
is and we're going to output a bunch of
them right
so yeah if we just say that we're gonna
do two by two then we know that X sub
count times y sub count times the quad
count is how many of these things we're
going to have this is a fixed
subdivision and then all we have to do
is actually do the subdivision here and
in order to do that we need to introduce
some notion of how we're gonna subdivide
the width and height and how we're going
to move between each of these now all of
this stuff will say the same right the
emission values are the same the normal
is the same the color value is all the
same because these are all the same
surface so the only and the x and y axis
is also the same right so literally all
this stuff is the same the only thing
that changes is we now have a subdivided
with tonight right
and that's pretty obvious what that is
right the width is just going to be
divided by the subdivision count and so
is the height right so all we have to do
to compute those to just go well we're
gonna divide these by however many
subdivisions there are and that's how
many each of them is going to be and so
the elements themselves are just going
to only be that you know wider high so
then the only other really thing we need
to do is put it in the right place in
order to put it put in the right place
we need to start at the base vertex and
rather than going out by half we need to
go out by half of the sub width right
I
in fact that was wrong before that
should have been half width times x-axis
in half height times y-axis so
everything should have been in a
slightly wrong place but it wasn't Oh No
okay so it would have been because we
hadn't done this part yet we had still
left the X and y axis equal to these and
it was only the element X and y-axis
that were different so that was okay
right we're fine so Europe e 1/2 the sub
width times the x axis and 1/2 a sub
height times the y axis that would put
us at the position of the first one but
we know we've got multiple ones to do
here right so we actually want to take
and when we're multiplying by the sub
with it's actually 0.5 we're actually
also going to take our X sub and add it
so it'll be like one point five two
point five as we move through our
various sub divisions in x and y so it's
going to look like this right and now I
think we have something that should
produce roughly the right results of
course there might be bugs in it in
which case it won't but hey that looks
about right so you can see that
everything got subdivided into smaller
sections right in theory we can change
that number to anything that we want of
course we have to have enough room to
store it and it makes our process slower
at like the lighting computation gets
slower and slower right
and yeah so eventually going to hit this
assertion where we don't have room to
store it and so we can make our a little
bit more lighting elements if we wanted
to
are these all controlled by the same
so really this is the value that should
be controlling all these right the light
data with that's how many of these
reflectors we're gonna have if that
makes sense so if we go in here and we
set this to be that presumably nobody
complains yeah so if we want to make
more here you know maybe we allow these
to be bigger I don't know but that would
allow us more subdivisions and of course
it takes longer to compute the lighting
result but again the lighting result
gets better at that point so here you
can see like a much more subdivided
version of of the solution and you know
this is is probably something we could
now debug fairly reasonably well right
it seems to me like it sort of still got
bugs in it I would say but I think those
bugs are now not gonna be related to the
fact that the geometry doesn't fit
properly or that it's not sampled
densely enough it seems pretty good to
me so I feel like we should now be able
to move on to actually making sure that
things aren't too buggy um what it looks
like here to me it's it's kind of a hard
to say obviously but what it looks like
here to me is maybe either we've got
some bugs in the raycasting so that
stuff's getting through that shouldn't
get through that's entirely possible but
the other thing that may be happening
here is we are not properly attenuating
our transfer function so that we're
getting when you do get an indirect
bounce the indirect bounce is too
powerful right that's another thing that
seems plausible
so so I'm not sure we've got a long ways
to go obviously but at least now we've
got stable geometry that that you know
makes makes reasonable sense right
and so again mainly what I'm concerned
about there is like I don't really know
why those are getting lighting involved
in them so that's a bit weird and you
know we've got a lot of we we don't even
have our interpolation story kind of
straightened out yet either so we just
we've got a long ways to go but we're
definitely getting closer to having
something that's sane but we still have
a long ways to go all right so I think
trying to think if there's anything else
I want to do before moving on I don't
know if we should maybe go to the Q&amp;A
now because I think the next thing we're
gonna want to do is it's gonna be pretty
involved so maybe I'll maybe I'll just
go to the Q&amp;A now then because I think
that's that's pretty much it for right
now let me see if I could still launch
it can I still launch the Q&amp;A
so I can launch it from the hero side of
things that can't launch it from the
twitch side maybe I'm not sure was it
sure all right
right and k'nuckles yes I am doing No
Shave November and although the the my
hair got kind of messed up by the pig
hat
so we have no questions that will make
it simple
for word rendering or deferred rendering
at the moment we are using forward
rendering we can potentially use some
deferred rendering a little later on it
depends how we wanted it depends on how
we choose to do the lighting exactly it
kind of remains to be seen moving to
deferred rendering is something you can
only really do once you're sure of how
you're exactly going to render
everything in the pipeline so it's a
little premature to say
with the subdivision of the rectangles
be something that you would do in a
tessellation shader if you were using
OpenGL so I think it's gonna depend on
who is making that decision and where
and I don't really know so we may find
that we can make determinations about
how to tessellate things for lighting
based solely on the input geometry but
we may not we may find that there's
actually a lot of hinting involved in
that or game specific knowledge in which
case you know we may send down some kind
of a diced version ourselves I'm not
sure certainly the way we're doing it
right now where we're just arbitrarily
dicing them up obviously that could be
done in the tessellation shader
are you going to be implementing shadow
maps I don't know that's a good question
I don't think so
only because I don't know that we're
doing much in the way of like really
direct lighting like that we're kind of
just going for like a washy kind of
lighting and I I just don't know if
shadow maps are gonna be relevant so
really I mostly just want sort of a
gentle global illumination bounce look
and I'm not sure whether shadow Maps is
really gonna be useful I'm not sure
question anymore hand made ray episodes
yeah at some point we'll probably do
some more handmade ray work and then to
remember when someone took your ray
tracer a few steps further on Twitter
what do you do to move to this picture
from the one you stopped at I think they
just changed the parameters I don't
think they actually did any thing
further they just kind of made a nice
scene with it
is my keyboard any good well I mean I'm
not sure ting about any good I love my
keyboard but keyboards are a very
personal thing
everybody likes different stuff you know
some people are like I want the old IBM
spring keyboards and they go for cherry
MX blue or something even more violent
than that some people like a stream Li
light touch keyboard I personally prefer
these these are razor this is a razor
keyboard
I think it's they have their own kind of
switches they're called orange I think
razor orange switches I believe are the
ones that are in here and I like those
switches that's just--that's I like the
feel of those switches I don't think
there's a right answer to keyboards you
know I think it's just whatever you like
to type on so you know I'm I certainly
can't recommend a particular keyboard to
someone because you know what they want
in a feel is not necessarily what I want
and so it doesn't you know translate but
if you like this kind of feel then it's
you know it's great keyboard if you
don't
baba says so as far as now if I would
want to plan a real time rendering
system there should have been some
differences or for now the light bounces
can also be used in that situation well
yes so what we've got now I think we
could do in real time if we move to the
GPU or even just optimize on the CPU but
it's kind of N squared e right now and
what we'll probably do when we move to
real time is use when you're looking
further away you use more aggregated
elements probably so you know the
problem would be one more step involved
there in making the rate trace faster so
you Bob wah is there a specific reason
to recalculate 1.0 over 255 rather than
store it as a value or does the compiler
optimize it away yeah compiler will
optimize a float divide that's a
constant it will produce the divided
constant as far as I know
through 25 I'm a new see a student with
limited free time to recommend watching
your series from the beginning or would
time be better spent working on a new
project in using your videos to learn
something as needed um I couldn't really
tell you it kind of depends on what
you're looking to do I guess what I
would say is the series is designed
specifically to be something that shows
the process of making a game not
something that's designed to be a random
access thing so you know maybe you can
use it as random access certainly there
are some things that are explained in it
that way like there's certain episodes
where we have just an entire black/white
episode just like devoted to me
discussing you know camera transforms or
something and that probably works fine
for that but mostly that's not what the
series is for most of this series is
just for you to see how game programming
works in general and how a game
programmer approaches working on various
parts of the problem because that's what
I thought was really necessary meaning
you know I think any individual thing
you need to know about game development
you should be able to find an article or
on it somewhere right or a lecture on it
somewhere so that's less interesting
it's more about seeing how you go
through the actual day-to-day work of
like putting things together and
approaching problems is really what the
series is more for so you know I you can
you can kind of take that as my general
overview on it and what you find useful
about the series is kind of depends on
you and and what you end up wanting to
do
I was wondering what sort of data
structures or algorithms you would
recommend to learn to get a wider grasp
on programming uh I mean that's kind of
a that that question is kind of a little
ambiguous right like what do you mean by
wider grasp on programming and what do
you mean by data structures and
algorithms right data structures and
algorithms could mean a very narrow
thing which is like ways of storing
traditional data so you know things like
a heap and a disjoint set forest right a
directed acyclic graph you know those
are data structures and algorithms
traditional things like how do I sort
something right and so I don't know if
that's if you mean that or do you mean
more like wider like kind of pie in the
sky things like a rapidly exploring
random tree or the metropolis algorithm
or you know the simplex method LZ
compression so I'm not sure but in
general I would say that I don't think
there's a specific set of those perhaps
regardless of what you want probably the
right answer is always it's almost never
a bad idea to pick some new sort of area
and go read up on lots of things in that
area that people have done and try
implementing some of them yourselves
yourself it's always good and it doesn't
really matter which ones you're doing
because either you're gonna find
something new and interesting that you
find useful or you're gonna be surprised
and find that everything is crap and if
you find that everything is crap then
that just gives you a good reason to
study that problem further and see if
you can figure out how to do something
good right so you know I've had both
experiences and I found them both to be
good like there's times when I've
learned things I like oh that's really
cool and that I've learned how to
approach a problem that I didn't know
how to approach before by reading what
other people have done in an area and
just studying the various approaches
that they had done and then I've also
had the opposite where I went and
expected something to be solved I read a
bunch about it turned out it totally
wasn't solved and then I ended up going
and solving it myself and coming up with
something new right and both are great
both are great practice both are
rewarding and interesting
in my previous question I was wrong I
wanted I wanted to ask if we want to
physically based rendering uh okay um no
I don't think so
physically based rendering is a little
bit too much I think to attempt with
this and also since we don't have any
real surface descriptions in our art is
gonna be kind of cartoony I don't think
that we want to go to physically based
in that sense because it's probably just
a waste of time
however that said as I kind of mentioned
we started the lighting keeping
physically-based rules in mind is always
kind of good on lighting so I feel like
you kind of want to know in general like
for this particular thing like you know
cosine attenuation and that sort of
stuff
you kind of want to know roughly what's
going on you know the Frenette or
whatever other sorts of things you want
to be aware of them because sometimes
they're important for your lighting look
and you don't want to just have no idea
like you don't want to be completely ad
hoc right I mean even the way we're
doing shadowing is is right you know
like in a sense it's the way you would
do physically based rendering you would
sample the lighting with multiple rays
or something like this you know you want
to you want to have some grounding in
the actual way light works usually
usually not always toasty stomp which
physics engine if any will you implement
we don't really do much physics other
than the basic movement stuff so we're
pretty much done with physics like we
won't be doing much else in physics are
you planning to have any procedural
generation your levels later we actually
have procedural generations and our
levels already it's just not designed to
generate any gameplay stuff because we
haven't gotten there yet but all of the
stuff in Hammond here was a little
generator thing already that just
generates some random stuff for us to
hop around in you once said you want to
use Vulcan on handmade here oh is that
still on the table or you're sticking
with um gel we're be sticking with
OpenGL I've Vulcan ended up being a real
pooper of an API so I have no interest
in showing it k'nuckles asked what are
things you've solved yourself I did a
lecture that kind of talked about some
of them in a limited sense that you can
watch actually if you want to
so this lecture why it listed the same
lecture twice I'm not sure I guess it's
one is in a list and one isn't that's
Google has trouble searching its own
stuff I guess
but this lecture right here is one that
talks about both situations really ones
where I did something in ones where I
learned something so it's kind of both
of those things I just talked about so
that's a good one
yeah Kaneko's I was actually surprised
that you asked that in fact because I
was almost sure you had already seen
that video so I was I'm like you should
already know some so I guess I would say
how could you sir jalapenos but haha
yeah I didn't have any anything in mind
just where to go after having learned
the basics of coding like the stuff you
mentioned but also where to start to
slowly understand I think the more
complex algorithms like there's probably
a hundred ways to sort something trees
etcetera but to get the basic
understanding where should I start um if
you want the basic understanding
I would actually start with the
algorithms book probably you know I can
show you the one that I learned out of I
can't say it's fantastic but just to
give you a big idea of what we're
talking about you know it's gonna be one
of those ones it's hard to find right
oh that's not it that's not it sir
that's it so this is the one that I
learned out of but I mean I don't know
right like I couldn't tell you whether
it's particularly good relative to other
ones because I only read this one and
it's good enough I didn't find any huge
problem with it so it seems like a
pretty good one to use but there's
probably better ones right and people
may be on the stream could recommend
better ones but you know it's got
everything in there that's the basics
you know you've got your crazy stuff
like median finding and the Ackermann
function and junk like this but then
you've also got all your simple stuff
your heaps you know your binary tree
whatever so that's the one you're
reading right now all right well what's
the problem in you've already you've
already got something that teaches you
the algorithms
so much a shortcut ah all right well I
mean it I don't mean to to be skeptical
here but this book is really pretty
brief like I don't know that there's
much of a shortcut like I mean most of
these algorithms are defining like five
pages or something how much of a
shortcut are you looking for I mean I
this book being incredibly concise you
know we it would barely dwell on an
algorithm for hardly any time at all are
you finding it somehow to be lengthy
viii made you once mentioned a numerical
book oh yeah those are the foremen act
in books those aren't for data
structures and algorithms those are for
people in shouldn't working with
floating-point arithmetic specifically
so those those are not algorithms the
algorithm he doesn't cover anything
relating to data structures and
algorithms what he covers is how to look
at equations and solve them in and break
down the operations of the equations
you're trying to solve instead of
solving them in the obvious way which
can produce numerically unstable results
solve them in non-obvious ways that
produce much more stable results and are
oftentimes faster as well but you know
at the very least not any more expensive
to do right so
and he's and there's there's more than
one on here
real computing made real yeah is also
there
I don't know that he's done any other
ones I can't remember but right
and Stan pancakes I don't know if I
agree with thing just read commute
I think Knuth is definitely more
advanced like if you're looking for just
the basics I think you want something
more like that rivals book
Knuth is definitely like when you're
looking to be real serious on it because
he takes a lot of detours he goes
through a lot of other stuff he
discusses a lot of points that are not
necessarily important just for the basic
understanding of algorithms you know and
so while like Knuth is probably
something that yeah most people should
be familiar you know familiarize
themselves with and know about so they
know when to read it it's definitely not
Oh Sammy says he was kidding okay good
because it's definitely not the kind of
thing that a beginner should be
presented with as their only option some
people who are you know particularly
good at reading programming because
there's there's different ways that you
know you get into programming right some
people are good at reading books by
parents of you'll aren't you know
whatever if you're really good about
reading books on programming then you
know Knuth may be a great place to start
it's tons of material it's it's exciting
like there's so much there you know and
it's the seminal part of the history of
computing maybe it's a good bet but if
you kind of don't really know what
you're doing you know and you're just
like I'd like to get some basic
instruction and how algorithms work and
stuff it's just it's not I don't think
the right choice you know
yeah
and koneko you know what i might
recommend in in in all seriousness like
i'm not this is not even a joke
recommendation at all is if you've got
internet access where you are that comes
for example through a wireless router go
into the wireless router and like see if
it's got the like parental lock settings
or i don't even know what they're called
these days that let you just turn the
router off for specific hours and then
just from 9:00 in the morning to 5:00 at
night just turn up have it like block
all access the internet i find that's a
fantastic way to like learn and get
stuff done because it forces you to
program the old way where you just had
nothing to go on and you have to just
like program and there's no thing to
look at there's nothing to read and
nothing is in coming and there's no
messages or anything you're just
concentrating it's the way i still work
my deb machine is not connected to the
internet so I still program for two to
four hours at a time with no
distractions and honestly I don't know
any other way to do it I really just
don't think people get very much done
these days compared to what they used to
get done and it shows you know and I
think it's because there's just too much
crap like you know programming is an
intense mental exercise and if you're
sitting around like looking at Facebook
or something I you're just not gonna do
very well and so I feel like you can set
yourself up for success by just getting
rid of it the nice part about the
Internet
is this trivial to turn it off it's got
to come in from somewhere and if you
just disable whatever devices is coming
in from that's it
and yet like I said if you do have
multiple people who depend on the
internet that live in the same places
you you can usually still get around
that because most routers have like
parental controls that will lock out
specific machines you know so you can
even go in there and just program you
know take your machine give it a defined
lease like put the MAC address for your
machine into the router and say this MAC
address always gets IP address blah and
then lock that IP address down to not
have internet access between those hours
right and that's it better yet have one
of your flatmates do it and have them
change the internet password on the
router so now you can't get the internet
no matter what you do you can't even
turn it back on right problem solved and
I can't recommend it enough if you do it
for a few weeks and you find that you
just can't do it
then you know that's fine that probably
means you're not a super you're not
someone who really loves programming all
that much which by the way is not a
problem most people I think who work in
programming these days don't love
programming anyway but if you do give it
a couple of weeks you may find that you
just actually really enjoy it
and you don't miss it because actually
like most of these things like Twitter
just mostly what they do is remind you
that people are awful you know and your
computer isn't awful it's especially not
awful it's not connect to the internet
because Microsoft can't update its
stupid operating system and you can't
get viruses and you can't do anything
else when you're not connected to the
Internet right so a computer that is not
connect to the Internet is actually
quite a bit better than a computer that
is and is actually quite rewarding it
doesn't change from day to day it's the
same
so yeah I would get basically say that
like you know a good part of the joy of
programming is being with a computer
that is not connected to anything else
and just having fun working with it and
so at first if you're really used to
like programming with like Facebook up
all the time or whatever the hell else
then yeah it's gonna be a little you're
gonna have to like detox or whatever but
after that detox if you were somebody
who would actually really enjoy
programming I think you will find that
you really just don't miss it
I mean
and serial Quiller we say if you have
enough space and budget having a
separate room and dust machine for
dwelling but you never use for anything
else totally agree and that is exactly
what I have set up at this office like
this machine that I'm on the stream from
right now is connected the internet and
it's not my work machine it's in the
back room my machine out there that I
actually program on for a living not
connect to the internet it's not even
plugged into it it never goes on the
internet it's on a separate local
network that only connects machines that
aren't on the network right and and
again that's that's not for security I
mean that obviously is a good practice I
suppose for security but we don't do
anything security sensitive here so it's
not for security it's just because I
find that's the only way to be
productive is to not have those things
and I find that I enjoy it much better
right
and k'nuckles also remember I said that
plugged into the internet it is plugged
into plugged into the local network and
I do have a server so I actually do use
source code control so I know you were
joking but I I'm still using source code
control actually I just it's on a local
server not on the Internet
yeah it is senior it's a new version of
see mirror see mirror too but it is
still source code control right I mean
Sumeria is the source code control
program it's still see mirror yeah it's
Samira - which is like a complete
rewrite there's no there's no shared
code in it it's see mirror - and it's
it's baller if you don't mind me saying
yeah I mean I wouldn't want to use get
because I have very specific preferences
for source code control but I guess what
I would say is get is still fine even in
that scenario right meaning like if you
like get or are at least okay with it
you can still run get on a local network
just fine right
so whatever and that's true of most
source code control like you know pretty
much whatever source code control you're
using it probably has a local network
version right we're gonna share SEMA or
two at some point probably not I maybe
eventually there's one more sort of like
switch will probably do it Molly rocket
in the future assuming we stay in
business long enough that's Morse has a
more sort of constantly running server
based thing to it and at that point
maybe I'd really see me or two I'm not
sure but no I'm not planning on
releasing senior to that's kind of an
internal thing only at the moment
and paid source code control episodes
yes the well the source code control
that my rocket is handmade it's true I
still have one more upgrade to do to it
the only thing it doesn't do now is its
own storage I wanted to get it to the
place where it does its own storage
right now it still uses the operating
system storage which I don't love Kevin
so you never access MSDN the OpenGL
documentation or other degradation your
work machine so I do access the OpenGL
documentation all the time on my work
machine I just have all the specs
downloaded and in a directory MSDN
I pretty much don't access because I
know it so well and I've programmed it
so many times that I pretty much just
use the windows headers now so yeah but
if I am working on something where I
need to do research I will write down
the things I need to research and
research them later so for example if I
need to know how to do something that I
think I'm gonna have to read through a
bunch of MSDN stuff I'll write it down
and I'll do it at night
I never plug the machine in to get it
I'll just go to like my laptop or
something and do it there
I would like to program without being
connected to the Internet but how do you
do it without Stack Overflow or other
references just breaking that reliance
just come from practicing experience so
what I would say is you don't really
have to break that reliance entirely it
depends on the circumstance so if you've
noticed on stream you'll see when I
search for things and when I don't write
the time that I search for things is
typically when I have to use someone
else's stuff and it's not working right
so I'm trying to call some things and
windows and they're not working or I'm
trying to call some things in OpenGL and
they're not working right and there I
want to try and see if someone already
knows why this thing isn't working so
that's still okay because you will find
that there are things that are broken
that there's really no way you could
have guessed and you have to ask around
or talk to driver people about it or
whatever and you know the Internet's
good for that so you're not trying to
break that that you just again write
that down when you're doing it move on
to whatever the next thing is on your
to-do list and then that night send out
the mail and do the googling or whatever
else you need to do right reliance on
Stack Overflow or something like that
for basic programming is bad that's
definitely true
the reason it's bad is because Stack
Overflow is highly variable right
sometimes on Stack Overflow the answer
is correct
is wrong and the problem with relying on
it is you don't yet know which is right
and which is wrong so I would highly
recommend getting developing a
discipline of exploration that does not
involve assuming that Stack Overflow has
an answer on it you should for any
programming thing that's about actual
programming you should try to figure out
ways that you can pull from diverse
resources do your own testing read up on
it separately right and come up with a
good methodology for becoming a
programmer who knows
that stuff without having to rely on
stock exchange right that's pretty
crucial and some of that happens online
some of that happens offline like I said
the point of having an isolated machine
are not using the internet when you're
programming is not because you should
never read about what other people have
done you should the point is to segment
that reading from the programming so
that you still spend time trying to
solve problems yourself you still spend
time analyzing problems yourself you
still send time developing without that
constant reading and looking at other
people's stuff but you still then want
to supplement that at night with reading
about what other people have done so
again you know it's not about staying
isolated all the time it's about making
sure you're not always connected alright
I think I'm going to shut things down
okay thank you everyone for joining me
for another episode of hand made here
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow on
the series at home you can always peer
to the game on handmade hero org and it
comes with all the source code so you
can play around with it and conduct your
own experiments if you want to ask
questions we have a forum site if you
want support the video series you have a
patreon page if you want to find out
where we're live we're on the schedule
bot and if you want to catch up on old
episodes we have a episode guide that is
it for today I will be back next week
when we will start debugging our
lighting code now that we have it
properly subdivided into geometry we
should be able to start seeing whether
we can get some good results and
figuring out what we're gonna have to do
to make sure our lighting looks cool and
is useful all right that's about it for
today hope see you back here next week
until then have fun programming and I'll
see everyone on the Internet
take it easy everybody