hello everyone welcome to handmade Hiro
sure we could a complete game live on
stream before we get started today I
wanted to point out the fact that
tickets are now on sale for handmade
Seattle don't ask me why there's nothing
let me do that there we go
at handmade - Seattle dot-com this is
not our conference I don't really run
any conferences anymore but it's it's a
conference run by abner who you may know
from he's the person who originally
organized the handmade Network website
and obviously it's taking place in
Seattle so if that's a place that you
can either get to or live in tickets
just went on sale there $40 for a
limited time and the the tickets button
looks like you just click on it and put
it in here if you want to get tickets
obviously there's a bunch of information
on here about what the conference has at
it
Abner's been adding stuff so go take a
look see if that's something you're
interested in and yeah and save yourself
some money if you want to go because the
ticket prices I guess will go up after
the early bird discount expires all
right today we are just gonna do a
little bit of ok wait I have to correct
something it says I'm surprised a case
like hunter I haven't played Chrono
Trigger someone has to fix this I
haven't played it I haven't played it I
I need to play it it's a game
historically that I should be familiar
with but I haven't played Chrono Trigger
alright sorry chat the chat still
talking about come on sugar from the pre
stream I didn't even bring up Chrono
Trigger Roman brought up Chrono Trigger
and then now people are at saying
they're surprised like I'm here but I
don't even know - Connor I've never
played Chrono Trigger
I do like a good JRPG though I quite
enjoyed Final Fantasy 10 for example not
that that has much to do with Chrono
Trigger but you know point being I also
love Wild Arms 5 weld Arms 5 probably my
favorite JRPG that game is awesome all
right moving on yesterday we finished
going through our code base using the
new memory analysis that we added so
that we could clean up anything that
looked like it was wrong that's the
first time we've been able to really
like view how our memories being
allocated and you know there are some
things I spotted I just want to take a
look at so we've got all that working
now and the only thing that I wanted to
do today and so that next weekend we can
start on some entity system stuff that
we'd want to do that sort of motivated
having this this memory view available
what I want to do is finish up that
memory view so that it provides a more
reasonable display of the memory because
right now it's sort of just hacked in
there and it doesn't really display the
memory the way I would like and so you
know since we did all this work I want
to make the display good so if we look
at this part of it this part of the
memory display seems pretty nice there's
a couple things I think I would like to
change that we might add today but we
added some pretty nice stuff in here
first of all you can toggle whether or
not you see debug allocations and you
can also toggle whether or not you have
call site analysis in there so this
would basically tell you like okay what
are the why can't I and when actually my
head was in the way I couldn't interact
with my own application um so the with
the call site attribution on it's really
nice you can actually see for any given
memory arena you know exactly who is
taking up all of the memory so basically
you know you look at one of these things
and you say oh you know in in my game
mode I've got you know sixty seven
blocks allocated and there's the 1077
total allocations where are they all
coming from right and we can see them
all here at
that's really important because that
allows us to go target anybody who seems
like they're allocating more than they
should be or doing something that we
didn't expect if we see somebody in here
who has allocations attributed to them
and we're like why is that allocating so
much right this is a nice view for that
and it's pretty easy plus we can always
just turn it back to this where it just
gives us a quick heads up so we can see
like our percentage usage and stuff like
that now if we go over to arenas this is
the part that's broken right now yes we
display all of our memory layouts and
you can hover over everything to see
what's what's what but the problem is
it's not correctly sized so what we do
is every block of memory that gets
allocated the sub allocations are
correctly sized but the blocks
themselves are just always 1/4 of the
window width long this leads to bad
visual information it leads to the fact
that for example this which according to
the byte read out there in the hover is
around 3 megabytes worth of data that
takes up the same visual space as this
which is about 1.7 or 1.5 I guess
megabytes of data and we don't want that
we want 3 megabytes to clearly be like
twice as large as one and a half
megabytes that should just you know
that's just common sense because
otherwise even though we cognitively
know that that's not what's going on
here when we look at this your intuition
just always assumes that if something's
you know twice as big as something else
it takes twice as much space or if
something's the same size it takes the
same space that's what if thinking and
so it's gonna constantly sort of screw
with our intuition about who's using
memory and why and so what we want to do
is go in and fix that that's what we
want to do today and while we're in
there like I said I want to add one
thing to this and that is that right now
we do not currently track peak memory
usage by anybody I'd like to probably
add that it's not very hard for us to
track a peak memory usage for an arena
and so I would like some way of tracking
peak mem and then we can display
in here select blocks Alex and and this
right here for example we could have
like peak versus you know we could do
this printout twice
you know once for peak once for not you
know current and the reason for that is
that if you look at like something like
the frame temporary area you know you
look at this and you're like wow the
frame temporary only takes two megabytes
of memory right well we don't actually
know how much memory the frame temporary
takes because we don't know like people
can use temporary memory and then get
rid of it right so if you come into
routine and you allocated you know fifty
megabytes of temporary stuff did a bunch
of crap in there and then you know ended
the temporary before the end of the
frame this will still read two megabytes
and we don't know about that fifty that
got used for just inside the frame right
so I do feel like I you know we want
something in here that just also has a
peak meter just to let us know like hey
this thing is two megabytes of sustained
but it Peaks out to a certain amount at
various times right that's just a good
piece of information to have in addition
so I'd like that as well to add in here
and that's not very hard to add but the
main thing we want to deal with like I
said is this right here and so that's
the first thing I'm going to start with
today is just let's get this thing
displaying in a way that's not totally
wrong from the standpoint of layout
alright I so if I pop back to for coder
and I take a look at that particular
routine the one that's actually doing
that that's the interval the memory
interval drawing routine right this
routine and if you see how we wrote this
routine I started to say where we're
gonna need this happening in the last
stream we're gonna need something that
can take a memory range and draw it into
position so what I want to do is be able
to generate calls to this draw memory
range and I want to pass like a starting
address
and a one pass last address with a color
and then I want this thing to draw them
and I want it to basically just fill up
the space proportional to how many bytes
were being used so the first thing I
want to do there is effectively keep a
running total of the amount of address
space that we use up and so you know I'm
gonna call this at address and it's not
really an address per se it's sort of
like a virtualized address because we're
stacking all these together and we don't
care about how the address space is
actually laid out in terms of page
mapping that's the OSS problem and not
only is the OS problem but we don't care
it doesn't matter how our memory is like
organized in physical memory really as
long as it's there there's not a lot of
differences now there are cases where
aliasing for things like the TLB lookups
and all these sorts of things can have
effects on chip so I don't want to be
taken out of context to say that it
doesn't matter how your memory is mapped
ever obviously there's certain cases
where you do care about that but
generally speaking especially when
you're talking about at the page level
it's certainly not something that we're
concerned about here so when we come
into the debug arena this is how we're
currently drawing for example our blocks
and so what I want to do is I want to
make this at address kind of move along
properly as we draw the stuff that we're
working at and so I think maybe I would
call this block address more
specifically and so in here what we
would do is we'd say like block end
address and maybe this is blocked like
start address and so the block end
address here is going to be whatever the
block start address was and then what
we're gonna do is add however much
memory is actually used in this
particular block allocation and so we
have the size allocated there oops and
so this will tell us specifically what
what we need to know for you know where
the block starts and ends
that means that when we go to draw this
it's a pretty easy thing to do once we
implement this draw memory range I can
just call this with those two addresses
and know that the block will get placed
where it should be placed right so I'm
gonna get this out of here for now I
don't want this right what I want to do
instead is just called raw memory range
and I'm gonna call this with the profile
rect we were given and then just these
addresses so we have the block start
address and the block and address and
I'm going to trust
oh and also of course the block color
that we decide based on whether it's
suppressed or not I'm just gonna trust
that draw a memory range we'll figure
out how to draw the correct number of
bars in the correct place to occupy that
space and we'll talk about that part
later so then what I want to do is we go
in here and draw the sub allocations out
of this same thing I don't really want
to talk about any of this stuff anymore
I'm not going to talk about sub regions
inside this blocks rectangle we're just
gonna talk about absolute addresses and
we're gonna let drum memory rains figure
that out so we're replacing this
effectively with this what I want to do
is grab these and I'm just gonna put
these up into this routine up here in
case any of its stuff that I want to use
later because this is the thing that
will actually be drawing those
rectangles but what I do want to do is
say this part right here draw memory
range it's you know I want this tooltip
to still work and so is in rectangles
not gonna cut it
if draw memory range might draw multiple
rectangles right I can't get a single
rectangle back that tells me this is
specifically where the mouse would have
to be there's gonna be multiple
rectangles and I need to know whether
the mouse was over any of those
rectangles so what I really want to do
is just say draw memory range should
itself tell me did you draw any
rectangles that contain the mouse and if
you do oops
then I need to know then I can print out
my tooltip so this is a rectangle also
kind of moves up in here as something
that we're going to do per rectangle
that we draw in order to return the
right information so at the
and here you can see me updating where
we were in the block we don't need any
of that anymore
we don't even need to keep a block index
that kind of goes away and furthermore
the block Y also goes away right we
don't need any of this stuff all of this
stuff is and even the block dim all of
that stuff the only thing we really need
to keep track of is the allocation index
and the reason we need to do that is
because we're trying to cycle colors so
that no two blocks that are next to each
other use the same color that makes it
easier for us to see where they are and
what they're doing
right now there is something we may want
to do with that later as well that we
could talk about and that has to do with
the grids so there there are some things
we may want to like imma put to doing
here
and really what I'm seeing with that
comment is you know when we look at this
map I don't know how valuable it is to
just have this rainbow of colors there
right because it's really not adding any
information it's just letting me know
that there's different allocations but
since I'm gonna put a border on
everything mmm I can kind of see that
already so what we may want to do here
is try to have our debug color table be
indexed by which grid like which line of
code actually cause this allocation to
happen and that one when we look at it
we can visually see based on the color
if there's like a lot of you know this
particular green we know that there's a
lot of that particular line of code
doing stuff and so I think we want to
change to doing that but there's a
little bit of work involved in that and
so I would like to there's a little bit
of work involved in doing that well I
should say because we could you know
just use the hash on like the pointer to
the grid or something but in order to do
it well what we really want is something
that sort of uses the grids and only
assigns colors to things that are
actually showing up on the map and so on
so you know we we need to do a better
job if we want to actually make that
work well okay so now we've got
ourselves down to the point where we
just need to fill in what this drum Emme
range is and then we can go work on the
drum memory range function and in theory
when when we get that working the whole
thing just works right so if you look in
here we've got drum memory range we know
that a lock each one of these
allocations right this debug arena
allocation each one of these tells us
both the offset and the size that's
allocated you know what I'm saying
and so if instead of using any kind of
sub allocate sub region of the rectangle
we just use the block start address and
produce based on this where the
addresses are they're covered by this
allocation we can just called ROM memory
range the same way we called it before
and have it properly draw the region and
if we then use this color that we have
here
I'm gonna call that a la couleur
actually we should be fine so if I have
an Alex start address here what's that
gonna be well obviously it will be the
blocks start address plus whatever the
offset is inside that block which I have
right that's where this would start and
then similarly the end address is just
gonna be the start address plus however
big it is right so pretty simple all I
had to do is compute those two things
and now I can call the same function
since I'm calling the same function for
both that leaves me in the nice position
of just having implement one function
called dram memory range which figures
out we're inside the profile rect we
have to fail in order to show that
region and there's a couple different
cases that we have to sort of handle all
right so some times or something like
this these routines can be kind of
complicated so some ways it helps to
enumerate the cases that we need to
actually handle and effectively what we
know is we've got a memory range that's
going to occupy some portion of our
memory rectangle right the total memory
display and what we know is that that
size could be anything so it could
occupy multiple rows so the first thing
we know is that we're going to have to
fill at least a rectangle in one row but
we may have to fill multiple rows so we
know that we have a start with a for I
loop that loops over all of the rows
that have to be filled and then on each
row we know we have three possible cases
that we could handle right one is that
we have a rectangle that starts at the
very start of the row because a previous
row overflowed right so we started on
the previous row and now we're still
filling in this row so we start at 0 and
fill you know up to a particular point
we know we might fill the entire row or
we might start somewhere and go to the
end of the row right and then finally we
have wherever
and we may just have a little trunk you
know even if we're not in there suppose
there's a fourth case which is just some
part where we neither hit the end or the
beginning of the thing we're filling
right so there's really four cases start
at the beginning go somewhere start at
the beginning go to the end start
somewhere go to the end and start
somewhere and in somewhere on that row
right okay so what we need to do is
figure out how to produce those cases
properly right we need to figure out how
to make this rectangle thing draw that
right and furthermore we know that since
we're gonna be drawing these rectangles
sequentially it's not really very hard
for us to see how this is going to work
if we have the rectangle that we're
filling if we force them to pass us the
mouse P that's currently active then and
let me just grab that here and pass it
there and there
I can trivially you know without doing
any extra work I can trivially change
this to include the boolean result that
I wanted where I just say anytime we
draw a rectangle if we're in it we set
the return value to true and then you
know we're effectively testing all the
rectangles for hit detection off we go
right so what we want to do now is say
all right while we're looping over these
rows we you know we need two things we
need to figure out what the row min and
Max is and then we need to figure out
how much of each row we actually contain
let's start with this which is figuring
out where we are well we now need to
define some basic piece of information
which is like how much space one row on
our display should take up right so we
need like a value that's like bytes per
row right and so something has to be
bytes per row if we assume that we're
allocating you know a gigabyte of memory
in a typical PC that's not very much for
a typical PC game but
say that you know handmade hero doesn't
have you know Red Dead Redemption art
budget so it shouldn't have quite so
much stuff um if we're using a gigabyte
of memory or something just just to
store art assets and the world and
whatever uh then the question is well
how much space you know can we afford
for drawing each you know each one of
our rows of it's like 20 pixels or
something you know how much space could
we actually afford to use there and in
fact you know let's actually compute
this out if we have you know maybe let's
say 800 pixels to work with or something
like that
and we divide that by 20 that basically
says well there's 40 of these rows right
there's 40 rows that we could show there
so if we wanted to say that there was a
gigabytes worth of stuff right and we
wanted sorry that's a divide there and
we wanted to draw a gigabytes worth of
data how many megabytes per row would we
need to do that and it looks like
somewhere around you know maybe like a
32 megabytes per row would be a good
number for handling that much
information right and that's actually a
lot more than we were doing before so I
believe before it was more like we were
drawing something like 4 megabytes per
row and so I do wonder if maybe that's a
little too aggressive but again this
number is one we can chart tune and zoom
we can have like a zoom that we would do
to you know allow you to see it more
specifically to if you wanted to right
so let's figure out how you know look
let's let's just pick a number here that
seems reasonable maybe we'll say that
will go with kind of the current one
which was 4 megabytes per row knowing
that maybe that's a little bit low and
we'll do more later so megabytes for
that produces the right byte number of
bytes ro 4 megabytes here and what that
means is now for a starting address it's
pretty trivial for us to figure out what
row it's on we just say like well
divided by the
four row right and the one past last
address we could divide that by bytes
for row as well right okay now I feel
like probably we would want to say also
in here if starting address is not equal
to ending right because otherwise we
don't want to draw anything and
similarly we don't really want to go to
one past the last address we want to go
to just before one pass last third the
last address right okay all right so
this will loop over all of the rows
correctly putting the you know so giving
us an opportunity to step through them
and at each one of these we want to
figure out how big this rectangle should
be now we know based on the row index
alone we should be able to figure out
the Y value right so we can start by
saying that this rectangle right the
rectangle has a min Y of something and
it has a max Y of something
well the max Y is the thing that will
solve for probably and the min Y would
be because we want stack from the top
down the min Y will just be whatever the
max Y is minus our row height and in
this case our row height is gonna
probably be 20 right that's what we were
using before I want to say so anyway so
let's call that row height and that's
gonna be 20 we're gonna subtract that
here and in order to figure out where we
are we just need to take the row index
itself and multiply it by that row
height now I suppose there's really no
particular reason I can't do this all in
64 this isn't a particularly time
critical routine so I suppose I can just
do this and be done with it all right so
now we have the ability to fill our rows
properly but we don't really know what
columns right we don't know the x
extents of this thing on any particular
row and so what we want to do
now is figure out we've got a starting
address we've got an ending address do
those starting at any addresses map into
this row or not right and so one thing
we could say is all right let's start
with the min X at the profile rep deck
oh by the way I need to add that in here
so the profile rect needs to we need to
start at the top of the profile rect and
then we subtract our row index minus our
row height right as we go so let's
suppose I start with my rectangle oops
change the wrong variable then I we
start with rect min X and rect max X set
so that they map exactly to the extents
of the prototype profile rect if this
entire row is occupied by us so our
allocation spans you know multiple rows
in its filling an entire row that would
just be correct so the question is when
isn't it correct well we've got two
cases that are pretty clear here
actually if the row index equals the min
row index then we know we're starting
somewhere in this row so we should set
this to actually be somewhere inside the
row not at the very start and similarly
in here right where we've got the
profile rect max X set to the I'm sorry
the rectangle we're filling set to the
max profile uh we have the same thing if
and I don't know why that expand that
there we go
if we're on the max row then we know we
end somewhere in here rather than going
all the way to the end right so now all
we have to do is figure out well if
that's the case where do we start and
end like how far along right well we in
addition to computing where we are by
using the row index times the row height
we can also compute the row starting
address right we can take the number of
bytes that occur in any given row and
multiply it by the road
on and in so doing we can come up with
the total number of bytes that it took
to get to the start of this row at that
point the two values we were passed in
the starting address and one past the
last address can be mapped relative to
the row so here I can say oh the
starting address - the row starting
address right / the bytes per row tells
me how far along this rectangle I went
right so if I lurked that T value right
this is effectively a T value if I just
lurked that so I went from profile
wrecked min X to profile wrecked max X
right
I would get how far I have to go across
now what you'll notice is really doing
this operation I could have because I
know that if I just set it to zero right
I'm gonna get all the way to the min X
so I actually don't need to do this I
could just always compute this lerp
right and so this becomes a little bit
more concise I could just say look use
this in the case where you sort of see
it here go in the case where you know
that you're on the min row just use zero
if not use the actual computation of the
ratio and then do the lerp right and the
same thing could be true for our our max
X right we could just say and we could
call groups we could call this T min and
T max as well so same exact idea here
check to see if we're on the max row
index and then we say if we are on the
max row index we want to go all the way
to the end otherwise I want to do the
one past last address - the row starting
address divided by the bytes per row
and then I want to go ahead and alert
that out in the exact same way okay so
hopefully that makes some sense and
again all I'm doing is just figuring out
where that spans are now that we've got
interact we can fill it and we can test
to see if we're in it and that should
basically be it right what's the problem
here a lot color it always a v4 though
okay uh so now we have to debug this
thing obviously not off to a good start
and sure exactly what yeah not quite
sure exactly what I guess that's
everything stacked on top of it so all
right but again this is really all we
have to do to finish this up okay so I
believe or I hope anyway that we're
passing this information correctly oh
you know what no we're not so we have to
start by fixing this our block start
address has to be equal to our block end
address at the end of this right we need
to move forward every time we draw a
block we need to advance so that the
next block starts on the end of it so
that's obviously that was wrong but I
think we also have other issues so let
me just fix that first and then we can
work on the other part of it as well all
right so it looks like we're still
computing a little bit of a wrong sort
of span fill here so let's go try to fix
that as well so first things first let's
make sure these are sort of looking
correct they look pretty reasonable to
me right we compute that start address
as zero we then compute the end address
by just seeing how big the block is we
put all these inside the block so I
think that should you know do it roughly
that looks pretty good to me so I just
want to make sure this stuff looks okay
so looking at when this gets passed in
computing the min and Max row here I
mean that seems reasonable right
[Music]
so you know honestly I don't see the bug
right away if you look at the min/max
why that seems to be right but there's
some weirdness here already like I'm not
sure why it skips stuff there but it's
not totally wrong either so I don't
quite get it I also don't know where
that seam is coming from so we got some
really weird stuff happening here that
makes it look like we do have issues
well alright let me but let's let's
focus more on just the basic parts here
so we know that these things are only
supposed to be 64 K long so the question
is why are they showing up if so why are
they showing up as like filling till the
end of the row because it looks like
maybe the min row max row is sort of at
least somewhat correct but this
computation looks incorrect oh it's
because these are backwards that's why
what I wanted to say but for some reason
wasn't saying I don't know why this is
um yeah much better so what we wanted to
say was if it is on the Munroe then we
do map it in otherwise we just assume it
started from the very beginning and the
same was true of the ending if it was on
the end we map it in so those were just
set to the opposite way round of what I
actually wanted but that seems like yeah
just a simple typo mistake let's see if
that helps there we go
all right so now if we sort of look
through here we can see all these folks
they're taking up 64 all them taking up
so just forget so they're the same size
we can now see this is that three
megabytes you can now really see how
long it is same here right there's a big
allocation and you can sort of see that
difference in there it gets you the gap
then here's the huge allocation for
handmade asset right it's using like
this huge amount of memory there for for
the asset storage so this is great right
this is a way better memory map than we
had before because now you can really
see the difference in terms of who is
taking up how much memory now you can
see the problem you have where we're
gonna have to be able to scroll this or
size it differently I think what I'm
gonna choose to do is just make them a
little bit smaller because I want to be
able to see them all at once
I don't really want to have to scroll I
want to be able to see this memory map a
little bit cleaner so I'm wondering if
maybe what I could do is just change the
row height to ten maybe and see if maybe
that's a reasonable way to do this I
don't know what happened there
there we go and so with a row height of
10 it's a little bit easier to see you
can you can get everything into one view
which is nice it is a little bit small
but that's okay you know for the most
part and so yeah like I mean that's a
pretty good memory view I mean I think
that tells us like everything we need to
know you know I'm saying it's pretty
clear who's doing what and why this
asset storage I think is almost that's
probably used the most exclusive for
audio which we're not actually doing
we're not actually using it for much
audio at the moment but it's there but
that's what we want to see so looking at
this I'm actually pretty happy with this
it's this part too that I want to
minimize as much as I can though
obviously and the reason for that is
assets are what take all your memory in
the optimal case because you just have
tons of our tons of sound tons of music
you want to just use as much memory as
you can for buffering that stuff up so
you don't have to hit the discs or have
loading screens or that sort of stuff
and so these parts of beam what's going
on what's going on Molly okay baby
for some reason Molly's sitting here
next to me I don't know what yes you
might want to play I can't play right
now
sorry baby anyway
so this is exactly what we want to see
but this is not so much what I want to
see and the reason for that is not
because this is too much memory to take
up it's fine actually it's pretty small
compared to this but again it's too big
given the fact that we haven't built out
our world yet we have a fairly minimal
number of entities in there right now
and so we can expect this to get like
ten times larger or something probably
and if you think of what that's gonna do
to our memory profile it's kind of a
disaster
it's gonna start to like bloat out a lot
right and so we've got we've got issues
there that's going to be a pro
so here's another thing I want to do I
think I can also help you everybody say
let's maybe we up it to eight megabytes
per row again that helps us kind of
visualize an amount of memory a little
bit easier because we have you know a
lot of allocations and stuff alright so
there's our memory map and it's pretty I
think that's pretty reasonable I wonder
if I can make it maybe just a little
bigger though cuz it's still a little
bit hard to to see in terms of row the
rows are a little bit small for my taste
okay so I think that's pretty good all
right
okay so all this looks pretty good now I
feel really happy about that I feel like
that lets us see the memory map really
cleanly I've got the size in here we
don't have a per frame thing going on we
main really not needed i may get rid of
that I'm not sure that I care but I was
gonna add something sort of like the
profile so like this right you know we
had that thing for who was taking the
time and why so that you know would have
been something interesting but we just
don't have a hugely fluctuating memory
like we don't really have that so I
don't know that we care about that too
much but you know who knows so anyway I
think that's all good and in here I
think the only other thing that I want
to do is maybe try again try to color
these entries by attribution instead of
just randomly by allocation index that
seems you know potentially more useful
so that's the only other thing that kind
of strikes me as something that maybe we
would want to do because all of these
are come from the same place so we kind
of want to see those all as one color
that seems like it would be a more
useful thing to do right and the problem
there is just I don't we don't probably
have enough colors based on the number
of allocation call sites we actually
have you know if I look at this and I
look at the number of call sites 1 2 3 4
5 6 7 8
9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 about
so you know let's say there's 30 to call
sites in there something like that how
big is our debug color table yeah I mean
our debug color table needs to be like
twice as big as it is right now and you
know that's a nice thing to have so it
would be cool to do something like that
and maybe we could like what if we just
took all this and sort of made one we're
like let's try to do that cuz then we
could actually see that memory map in a
much nicer way and I kind of want that
to happen so looking in here I write
like what if we just started putting in
some like 0.25 as well and so you know
like maybe this is like all the zeros
become 2.5 so they're just writer
versions of the same colors I don't know
we could also make all the ones be point
7 5 s instead I don't know if that's
good I really don't know I I kind of
feel like one thing so here's the thing
that would be a great hand made dot H
file if anyone out there is listening it
would be pretty awesome to do a thing
where you had a file that was just this
it was literally just this array and it
was like a hundred or like 64 colors
that had been tried to be balanced to be
the most different like the easiest to
differentiate so you try to solve for
like a certain number of colors that
will be differentiable like right a
little solver that just goes through and
like tries to like place colors almost
like blue noise in color space we should
do that sometime
and then just have it's like debug color
day
it's a 64 line file right there just has
the colors and that's it right don't
even put this so people just do this you
know what I mean that way they can be
whatever struct name they want that
would just be a cool file I think all
right so this is a bigger debug color
table now
and so I'm hoping that now what I could
do is when I draw these memory ranges
when we come through and pass the color
values so the block colors I don't care
about because those are not the
interesting part what I care about here
is this a lot color what I need to do is
have this a lock index the color index
basically get assigned to a particular
allocation based on the grid in question
so based on the like line of code that
that thing is coming from right and so I
think what I want to do is track these
things more specifically and allow them
to get indexed in some other way so for
example uh bear with me for a second
here if you look at how I was doing this
before right remember this call site
thing basically what I was doing there
is I was tracking the call sites
dynamically you know I'm saying so going
through the memory system you know these
things don't know it's just this it has
no idea what that grid was right well
what if I did something more like this
so we track the call sites here
and we duplicate them right at the time
where we actually look at them you know
I'm saying and that way we can assign
each one in index you know you know so
that way we just always could use the
call site data for doing things like a
color lookup and furthermore like in
here where we do like the push struct
right we wouldn't have to hatch this
anymore we could just use a direct
lookup into that memory so for example
instead of having to do a hash right
here like with this call site hash thing
that's actually a thing we could move
out to here and this wouldn't have to be
a call site hash instead this could be
call site stats and it would push a flat
array on that's just the size that it
needs to be so taking a look at the
debug state there would just be a veil
of very variable like a counter it would
just be debugger in a call site count
right and then you would just know that
these would be indexed makes sense so I
think that's kind of cool because then
we don't have to worry about the hash
anymore we'll do that
sort of as part of the process to begin
with and so then here where we are
actually making these hash things happen
we don't actually have to do that
anymore at all right we'll do that out
of line when we accumulate the
statistics and we want to allocate them
onto this you know do that under the
site we can just straight up look at the
call site directly in the call site
stats so here we just say like okay the
call site stats for this a lock call
slice index we just directly use that
array index to accumulate the statistic
then when we come through to the place
we're actually printing it out we no
longer have to loop over the call site
hash sighs instead we just loop over the
individual call sites specifically so
yeah basically this so that feels way
better to me anyway so that like
improves this as well so yeah I think
all of that's just much better right
so yeah the call site stats now probably
want to be a different name right
this probably wants to be that just so
we're clear that this is has nothing to
do with it oh and actually the well look
we don't even really need that anymore
now think about it because this doesn't
really need any of those things does it
oh well it still needs this
because it does need to check to see
whether that particular arena whether
it's in that particular arena
[Music]
so yeah I guess I still do knew that I
don't need that so yeah that works just
fine but the problem is now this thing
does need to know that particular piece
of information where we've got the grid
and the allocated part what I would
really like is to just be able to get
that from the index itself so let's make
that happen because I think that's just
better so let's just make this be a
debug statistic because that's what I
want so I want to be able to just say
look here's the debug statistics I'm
gonna push an array of those on there
when I come through here we're just
gonna go ahead and increment the stats
and then what I want to do here is I
want to print out the stats one by one
but I only want to print them out for
this arena and that's the tough part
right so we know that we can get the
statistics pretty easily like this but
the problem is how do we do this test
right we need to be able to look that up
separately and by the way this is all
this
so we need some way of getting the site
here so we can look at which arena the
call site belongs to in this case and we
need some so we need like debug arena
call site you know I'm saying so there
there is one other thing there I suppose
we're gonna not care about that so we
need some way of getting like get call
site from index right we need to do this
and I think what I'm gonna do is just
cheese out on that and make that be like
a cheese call where it just loops over
it just loops over the hash table or
something and grabs it I don't know
I'm trying to think if there's something
else I want to do here and I'm not sure
I guess we could just use this as an
array since we know it's fairly small so
in here we're gonna say if the debug
state you know if the index is less than
the debug say State Arena call site cap
then we would say debug state like
marina call sites so we can like access
them off of that index I guess again I'm
really not sure how I feel about that
maybe kind of unnecessary but I feel
like we kind of need it so I feel like
that's pretty good to go and I don't
know that there's anything else
particularly weird that has to happen
there so really I just need to actually
build that hash table when we're when
were actually collating the arena
information in the first place I need to
build that and then I would have those
indices assigned properly but I think
that's the only other thing that's
missing now from allowing this to work
right and yeah and I think that's all
good so if I come up here and just grab
the part of the code that we were using
before so you know inside here when
we're doing our collation we
these calls here which is where is it
this so in here what I want to do is
have a way of you know processing this
this bit of information here so I need
to handle these call sites right so
these probably have this and they
probably have this like so and for each
one of these allocations since I'm only
processing allocations that actually
happen here and there's not that many
call sites I almost say we just linearly
search the call sites instead of having
a hash table it it just feels I don't
know like the amount of time we would
waste maintaining the hash table I think
we would it would just be better to
linearly scan you know I'm saying
because we just don't have that many
allocation points that's my guess anyway
so in here what I would do is say debug
arena call site get call site wrong and
what you would do is you would pass the
glid and the debug arena and the debug
state here and then we would just look
to see is it in there so I would just
linearly scan first the site index I'd
say you know debug State Arena call site
count site index
have the result pointer here if we don't
find one we'll make a new one and off we
go right so we know that this is the
part where we make a new one we know
what that looks like it looks something
like this right and we know that we have
to like make space for it we don't need
the hashing anymore because I'm just not
going to do that and so really we just
need this part so as we loop over the
sites here what we would want to do is
here's the debugger and a call site that
we're testing we would do the arena call
sites plus the site index that's the one
we're testing if it matches what we're
looking for then we found it and we're
done otherwise we would have to create
one if we air it out of there and so the
only thing we've got left to do is
figure out how we're gonna store these
in a linear array I would say let's just
make space for one because we know we
have fairly minimal number of allocation
points I would say let's just keep it
simple right so let's see yeah not sure
how many we want to do but again since
I'm doing a linear scan I think we want
to put an assertion in here and
basically say look if you blow out the
number that we've got I need an
assertion because I probably have to
then I probably do have to change it to
the hash table at that point right so
debug actually arena call site counts
and then we need debug arena call site
call sites should I can just do like
this and let's just say we don't want
more than 64 of those so if not result
we need to assert the debug state arena
call site count and you know
I guess I don't know for sure that we're
not going to blow that out because we're
not seeing a bunch of those allocation
points so again it may be that we do
actually have to add you know it may be
that we do actually have to add that in
there
I don't know and and do a real hash
table
we'll just see we'll play it play it
bye-bye I played by profile and see what
actually happens all right so let's see
here's the call sites we need the arena
the grid and the index we don't need
next time hash at the moment and we
don't need to push so I'm just gonna say
let's let's assert the fist thing fits
and once I start that I'm going to take
the index and say that the index for
this particular one is is you know
whichever one we would pop you know push
on next and then the results pointer is
just that one we would then set all its
parameters up which is just these and we
don't have the hash at the moment and
then we would we'd fall out of there
right so now I gotta go fix all of my
compile errors and then we should be
good to go I want to stop this so let's
take a look the call site pointer for
this rina allocation probably should
just be a call site index actually
so we can just do that
all right so here where we've got our a
lock right the grid for the allocation
yeah so this stuff doesn't actually
exist in here we have to get the call
site in question which is fine so all we
do there is we say like debug state
arena call site site equals you know get
call site debug State just so we can get
the call site for the a lock and then I
would just say look there's the kwid and
off we go
so that just wants to be you know a
function that's really simple arena
location and all that's gonna do is say
do the same thing but passing index
so assuming that you're doing something
you actually can legally do meaning
you're passing one that actually exists
just so we know if we screwed anything
up you get it back and then this is a
convenience call that just says alright
if you pass me an allocation I'll go
ahead and do you wrap that for you and
off we go
so those should make it easy for us to
work with these and then modify how
we're storing them if we want to call
sites I think is what that's actually
called ok so let's see what we've got
here so call site now right is not
because it's the index that we actually
care about
so in here where we do debug Arina
allocate we don't want to set a grid
anymore what we actually want to do is
say that the call site index equals get
call site from and then we would pass
that grid in here so we know what the
arena is we know what the grid is and
that should give us back the information
that we wanted we can make this return
in u-32 as well so here we could just
return the result index every time
and then finally here where it's looking
at that call site what we actually
wanted was the index anyway so we can
just use that directly now without
actually dereferencing anybody and I
think we're now good to go right
barring bugs that I almost certainly
inadvertently put in there
we've now reorganized it so that it
works by tracking call sites through the
entire pipeline
I got a switch to a debug build to debug
this because I don't really want to deal
with the bad debug information that the
optimising compiler spits out so let's
go ahead and do that
and now let's figure out what we screwed
up right okay so we've got too many call
sites first of all of course I don't
actually know that could be because this
is wrong as well so it's hard to say
right off the bat but let's take a look
so here's that grid here's the debug
arena
so there is something a little bit there
is something a little bit bad about this
that I kind of forgot about and that is
that we probably do need to make the
grids do a string compare in this
particular case and the reason for that
is because the the grid pointers won't
be stable across reloads this wasn't a
problem previously because they were not
actually yeah they they were not
actually being stored permanently they
were being computed every time we wanted
to print them out so that's less good
right all right anyway
so really this needs to be that which is
not what I would have wanted but oh well
so in here I'm gonna just up this limit
till it works just to see where we're at
and then we will maybe put in that hash
table back in because it looks like it
might be something that we actually do
want if there's really that many of
these things and I guess there are
because now it works okay so there
that's how many we we have in there I
suppose so if I go ahead and change this
202 here let's go ahead and take a look
at those allocations again and see where
we're at in terms of actually tracking
them and whether I screwed anything up
there so if we look at the memory and we
take a look at those call sites like
here's us tracking those call sites
properly so actually I guess I am glad
we did this though
because looking at that what you can see
is that now that we track these always I
can start to keep peak allocation
numbers for these things because you can
see all of these places that allocated
stuff and then and then D allocated it
so that current outlays is set to zero
right so I am kind of glad we did that
it wasn't unnecessary I guess so now if
we look through here hopefully I can now
figure out a way to make this thing
produce stable colors right so looking
at this I'm doing something stupid right
now I'm just not sure what because if
you look at all of these you can see
that the call site index is actually the
same as far as I can tell but I'm
getting different indices and that's not
supposed to happen so either I messed up
the call site indexing somehow I guess
but I don't know
or I'm like picking out the Alek index
wrong oh we never we never used it so
never mind there we go
so now we're using the call site index
specifically across all call sites to
try to color code this and again it's
not perfect because we don't probably
have enough colors to actually fill
everything in but now we can see it's
still it's still quite a bit better
right now you can see that all of these
are taken up by the same piece of code
and that's just a lot easier to
understand right because now you know
that all of these are the handmade world
you know allocator they're okay so I
think the last thing I want to do I
don't know how much time I've got I've
got probably what 45 minutes let's say
let's let's say 45 minutes so I would
like to add in maybe some peak timing
and also we probably need to make this
thing scroll right because I can't I
can't like see the rest of it so we
probably want and we also probably get
rid of this because we're not really
going to use it right
so yeah that that seems like the right
thing to do I don't know yeah that seems
like the right thing to do the other
thing we might want to do is actually
compute all this information
[Music]
we might want to actually compute all
this information in a shared format
between the two routines because look
when you hover over this it might be
nice to get that percentage like hey
this is the like usage of this thing and
by the way here's the percentage that
that you know equates to right so that
feels like probably a good thing
yeah all right so I pretty much finished
what I wanted to do today so I think
we're just down now - you know I guess
just gravy and then because I don't
really want to start into something
totally new Hey look at that now you can
see the debug usage pretty cleanly -
right we don't track what's actually
happening in there because we can't if
we did it would overflow itself but at
least we can see like cleanly who's
using what right and that's pretty nice
so yeah let's just go ahead and go in
there and clean this stuff up I also am
wondering like can we just not like
can't we just there's got to be a way to
change how we're doing the you know I
don't want to have to click on the
profile to like open it up so surely
there's a way to make those things be
expanded by default like you know like I
don't know it's been a long time and
this part of the system is the crappiest
so you know maybe not but I'm just
curious to know if there's a way to
force that to be expanded by default
instead of you know instead of not so if
I take a look at the debug interface
stuff here
in fact I I think there was sort of a
expanded always kind of see these in
here so you can see like when you do
toggle expansion you've got this like
view collapsible expanded always right
[Music]
and that's from an interaction so if I
just take a look at the handmade debug
stuff here where we actually create
these when we get back one of these
groups like we're doing create variable
wink and so that has a debug element in
it which which I assume
I was gonna say there should be some way
to look at like what the ID of that is
right or maybe not I get a crate debug
view for San that actually works
so I guess the way this works is it just
says hey we hash something we hash the
dev ID of whatever the thing is that
you're clicking on right and so the
question is how do you get a dev ID from
from one of these things right like
there isn't one in here and you know you
there there does need to be one of those
and so looking at when I actually create
these I'm guessing that like these
groups see these groups have to get
placed somewhere too right
like they have to be put at the top
and I'm just not sure where that's
getting done so this draw tree here
I guess that is really the thing that we
just want to always be expanded
really
and so if we have that surely there's
some way we can force that to expand
debug ID from link so I think that's all
we really needed probably so as a as it
is like I said this system just did not
work out very well I feel like we can
clean it up tremendously now if we
really wanted to since we now know what
we actually want it can just be
simplified but I each one of these
things can be asked for as individual
trees right since we know what the tree
is here that we're actually using which
is to say although even that that's a
little bit weird now I think about it
because that tree isn't really there
either right such a stupid system when
we're drawing that tree it's like an
ignored tree I like a nonsense tree
right so even that I don't quite
understand how that should be working
yeah that's really weird when does this
first
you
yeah so I think that's just kind of
garbage it's using like this debug tree
which is a ignored like non thing and
it's so it's remembering but only based
on that which is just kind of luck that
that works at all I think so like you
know when this thing I assume wraps the
tree handle in there yeah it does so
this is just ridiculous
I mean really if you wanted this to work
properly which I suppose we do for the
time being anyway in here like you would
want to put like a you know a HUD tree
or something like this right and then
when you drew this thing you because you
need a stable pointer there so this
thing should look like that you know
what I mean and that way if you wanted
to you could do the you could you could
do like a toggle on that now where when
you do the debug in it you could do like
a expand and you just say this one here
and for that tree you want it to be set
into two to be expanded right when it's
when it's being used as the HUD tree
yeah I'm saying so really yeah really
stupid but that's the idea and so given
those we just need some way of setting
that expand always to be
this part here right that so I think
what we want is something that looks
like this and we'd passed the debug
state and the Deaf ID it would do this
and set it to whatever we asked it to do
I guess doesn't need to return anything
at all
so we just need to do the one call that
says like get an actual you know get was
it called something for link get ID for
link at dev ID for link I don't know
something like that that so you just
need to call this thing
and you have to pass that in fact it's
this so I I guess that's it again really
crappy but that's that's what we're
dealing with so now that we've got those
I think that would be expanded by
default right and oops memory group and
that way we don't have to manually drop
them down for no reason because we don't
ever really want to you know if I pushed
that F key I wanted to see it right
although not I say that they don't do
that so why not that should set the
expansion state right on the HUD tree
get a crate debug view for debug state
oh well I also don't know if this needs
to be done a little bit later I suppose
I don't think that should really be the
pro I don't think that should be the
problem though so I'm gonna have to go
look at why it's not looking them up in
the same place once again yeah
because okay so when we set those it's
on the HUD tree and it's profile group
in memory group right which are the
things were actually displaying we're
setting those to be expanded
that looks correct
so I think that should be right um but
of course it's not you let's just see
what happens here so we actually need to
start at the debug end you can see here
we do a draught recall and we passed the
HUD tree with that with what you know
with one of those so since we're passing
the HUD tree and that link pointer
what's the problem we come in here with
the same variable group right and we
call draw tree link on it
so here's draw tree link we have that
again this right here is should be one
of these like it should be like memory
group right so then we say like well can
it have children if it can then we're
gonna do some stuff here if it can't
then we're just gonna draw it so we know
it asked to have children cause
otherwise we wouldn't see any of those
pieces when we do drop it down so we
asked for the debug ID from link which
I'm arguing to give us the same thing we
had before will then call get our create
debug view for which will be this and
here's the view and then you know we'll
check to see whether it's expanded
always and if it is we should draw the
children right so what I don't quite
understand
is how this didn't do exactly what I
wanted because it should have and we
should have gotten into here so I guess
I got to step into that and find out so
let's see
I'm gonna go set a breakpoint I'm gonna
set the breakpoint on let's see here on
this draw call well actually now on that
drug Hall yeah
and then I want to do it on these so I
come in here and we're gonna call set
expand so we produce a debug ID for one
of these guys and I want to see what it
actually ends up being so there we go
let's see we set the tree and we set the
link I can now copy these I think yeah
thank you to George that there we go so
this is what we're setting our ID to we
then go get a create debug view we hash
this thing there's nothing in that hash
slot so we make a new one we record the
ID we say that we don't know what type
it is
and then we well interestingly the fact
that we don't know what type it is
seems less good because shouldn't we set
it to a particular type
that may be part of the problem so when
we got this view here how did it know
that it was you know let me think
yeah like how does it know we can look
at this as a collapsible in the first
place and does that have to get sorted
out by anybody I'm gonna take a look at
that so whoever looks at this thing just
curious
I mean it should be set to that right
but of course the fact that nobody uses
that means that the fact that we're not
setting it shouldn't matter so I don't
really know what to make of that
so let's see we set both of these we set
to expand it always and that's fine it's
run to that where we actually draw this
thing so inside here this should
actually not do anything because there
is no group right so we actually need to
do that then when we run this thing I
will now switch to one of the views that
we actually expect to draw there so now
we're gonna go into this draw tree link
so when we come through here and produce
this draw ID and then I'm gonna get try
to get one of these I should find it
right so the fact that I don't find it
pretty pretty much tells me what I need
to know right it's the fact that this
IDs IDs didn't match the one that I said
the beginning doesn't match the one that
I'm setting now but I don't know why
right so if I look at this I'm doing a
debug ID from link and I'm passing this
tree pointer and this link pointer but
those should have matched because you
know the the tree and the group came
from here and it was this which should
be the same although I guess we'll have
to check and then it should have been
this which also should have been the
same right all right so one more time
let's just see why the ID doesn't match
stepping into here here's what the ID
looks like
just right here copy that copy that
so this is what our ID should look like
and now let's go see why it doesn't look
like that I if I now run to this is the
profile so is that the first one I did
the first one right so I need to make
sure that I'm looking at the correct one
so let me just see
yeah profile group so when we come in
here now I'm going to build that UID
again so here that is
so that is the same so that the tree is
the same it's the link that's not right
so the thing I expanded somehow wasn't
the same thing and of course how that's
possible I have absolutely no idea you
can see here that we're setting that
link to debug state profile group and
I'm setting the link based on that so
when we actually switch to dev mode
profiling like here
how would that not produce the correct
results now I suppose I may have to look
to make sure that that doesn't get
changed somewhere
and I'll be honest I'm not sure what
could possibly be happening here because
we it just gets used
you know like I don't really know let me
look at that debug UI HUD function there
not that one
so what do we do on set hood
you
oh man Wow
yeah this just sucks so for whatever
reason we create a dummy group that sits
in there but then we just replace it
later with a different one why we create
the group I do not know like what the
point is of that just seems dumb but hey
that's what we do that means what you
actually want is this which is to say
when you create a HUD group we just
assume that you want it to be expanded
happy birthday and so that gets expanded
right here right another way to do that
would just be to say hey the default
parent group that thing that comes in
there right and then this said expand
function you know I don't know where
this should go but somewhere at the top
here probably lots of people would call
this thing
let's something like that oh actually I
guess it has to be
get a crate debug view for alright so I
think that was extremely roundabout way
to do this but hey we did it and so now
I think we should be good to go as as
torturous as that was should probably do
a marathon weekend sometime or we just
clean all this code out we now know
exactly what we want and we could do
such a much better job so now at least
these are open by default right which is
what I wanted because there's really no
reason not to I feel like these should
also be longer by default sort of a
separate issue
alright so let's maybe now go in and
when we look at this stuff right I maybe
want to go ahead and get rid of this
frames because we're not going to use it
and then for call sites so again looking
at this I think what I might want to do
there is set something up where we look
at Peaks for those and so maybe we take
a look at some of that stuff so let's
look at let's look at tracking those
Peaks and then also maybe we can have a
thing that sort of says in addition to
those buttons maybe we'd have a thing
where we allow you to pick a couple
modes like don't show me anything that's
not persistently allocated you know and
stuff like that so let's go into the
call sites and try to figure out how to
get the Alex to happen there or at the
Alec tracking to happen so we can track
peak memory usage and we can also
probably do that per you know that might
be the easiest way to start is just do
it per arena and then we'll add it for
the call sites later so let's start with
with that inside handmade debug when I'm
tracking memory each one of these arenas
I'm gonna say that maybe we just have a
peak memory like Kerr total Alec and
total Alec something like that and so
whenever we allocate a block of memory
so so when we have blocks allocated or
freed we will adjust
that that peak number so probably like
[Music]
trying to think I won't do this so when
we do an arena block allocate we would
say that the arena cur total a lock is
gonna be whatever the block allocation
size is it will go up by that much and
if the peak total a lock is less than
that we'll remember that as the
high-water mark for the arena and then
when a block is d allocated so like in
this case what we would want to do is
say whenever we remove the block we
subtract off like how however big that
free block was we take that back away
from the arena's total allocation out
way so that should allow us to just
track the total usage over time the
maximum that any arena ever hit even if
it doesn't end a frame there we'd still
be able to see it and so then when we
draw those allocation numbers in so it's
I when we do top mem lists for example
in addition to the basic statistics we
can have that piece of information so
you know the peak here's the regular and
then we also maybe have a peak so we do
a percent for um B for peak as well
so that's arena geek total a lock / f 64
megabytes and then here what I'll do is
I'll just say like or I need to put like
you know her and then something like
that and that way now I should be able
to see the peak for every arena in
addition to the amount that it's
actually sort of using at that time and
it's you know set a breakpoint there
probably an old one that got moved down
uh so then oh I forgot the MB so I can
push these a little further so yeah
that's exactly what I wanted to see hold
on a second let me push those over a
little bit
I think that's it so this is exactly
what I want to see for asset storage and
game mode it's exactly as what we would
expect the current amount that's used
and the peak amount are the same and of
course the reason for that is because
those are persistent storage systems so
you don't expect them to fluctuate much
during a frame they're just allocated
and that's it
but then on frame temporary this is
exactly what I wanted to see you can see
that it ends the frame with only two
megabytes used but there's actually a
really large amount of memory getting
used in there that happens as a
transient sort of occurrence inside the
frame so that helped us understand that
on certain frames we use a lot of memory
in there perhaps every frame that's a
lot more than the amount that we're
using just as a stationary storage
across the frame boundary so what I'd
like to do is then just you know
continue to expand on this when we come
in here you can see that we don't have
Peaks for call sites but there's no
reason why we couldn't have Peaks for
call sites I don't think so
let's see if we can go ahead and put in
peak tracking for call site data as well
so that when we print this out we'll be
able to get that number in here too
right okay so if we're gonna do that we
would need this percent for UMB to get
to happen down here as well right and so
we would need this and when we print out
this value right here we need to know
like alright like what's going on so we
need like peak turtle Alec we need that
to be on each individual call site and
so if I go out to where we're tracking
the call sites we you know we know what
we need we need this right and off we go
the we could track the Curt total Alec
as well
I suppose there's really not a reason
not to
and then we wouldn't have to do the call
site looping well they can do that later
but anyway this peak total a lock here
on the call site if we wanted to track
that the same way that we were tracking
it per arena we need to do the exact
same thing we did before accepts a
little bit harder because on every
single allocation we actually need to
take whatever the call site was like
this and we need to Inc that right so we
need to do a thing where we have like
debug arena I'll say site equals get
call site debug state call site index
and then we need to do like site just do
that down here site peek total a lock
plus equals whatever the allocated size
was right and so in addition to that we
also need up in here where we whenever
we like remove one of the one of like
the links we need to process that and so
I believe that always goes through debug
move to free list and so in here where
we do this we're now regretfully and I
suppose it's you know it's fine we have
to loop over each of these
and remove it now actually this isn't
quite right I think we actually need to
do it more like this oops
because we need to also process the last
one right so I can't stop before doing
the last one so for each a lock I would
need to say take the call site in
question for this particular a lock and
remove the size that this a lock
represented you know I'm saying so as
long as everyone always moves
allocations to the free list which I
think they always do that should take
care of it for us so on truncation you
can see it doing it here and on block
free you can see it doing it here so I
think that would track the peaks for us
right so if I go in here and look here's
the peak tracking it does look pretty
reliable right now of course we end up
with our scrolling problem I need to be
able to scroll this list I can't
actually see it here and there's another
thing that we probably would want to do
if you look at how this is laid out we
probably want to come up with a printout
0 megabytes not a helpful number right
if it's too small to list in megabytes
list it in kilobytes if it's too small
to list in kilobytes listed in bytes
right so that's another thing we can do
here so we need two things we probably
want to be able to scroll this thing up
and down and the other thing that I
probably want to do is I want to be able
to and I don't I assume we want that
here too right like it would be nice to
be able to scroll that up and down so I
think both of these probably want that
right I mean that's that's seems pretty
straight
or so we should probably have that but
anyway it looks like the peak tracking
is working here at least somewhat and
you know it's it's a little bit hard to
say because we don't have something to
compare it to to know if that's actually
true but you know yeah maybe so I'm
gonna do two things I'm gonna add the
scrolling and I'm gonna add the ability
to print the instead of like you know mb
or whatever I want some way of printing
that out better and so you know I feel
like this is a place where maybe I can
lean a little bit I don't know maybe I
can't lean a little bit on the fact that
we have our own print out here I'm just
kind of thinking like when we look at
these values and you know I've got all
this stuff you know could I just add my
own percent format specifier so like
instead of you here I could just do B
and have that work right
[Music]
or maybe percent m4 memory I don't know
I'm a little confused about the read VAR
argh unsigned integer part of things the
reason I'm a little confused about that
is does that read 64 bits or 32 bits so
it just uses the length specifier here
but I could say that mem was always
supposed to be 64 is probably I don't
know if that's what we want or not but
don't look at me I just work here so I'm
guessing I want to do something yeah you
know vaguely like this so if you pass
one of these things it's like a memory
sized thing you know I'm saying and so
we'd say like alright this is actually a
6m instead of a 4ub and we're just
assuming that you add the little like
stuff to the end to say what the heck it
was and so when we do this conversion we
would just say like alright convert you
know use 64 to ASCII I passed the value
and we do our little dance and then I'm
gonna into the the temp test part of
things I'm gonna stick some extra stuff
and so what I want to do here is just
figure out like you know my suffix is
just gonna be like B with a space I
guess four bytes right but then what I
want to do is like keep doing some tests
here so like if value is greater than
1024 then my suffix goes up to be like
KB or something and my value I divided
by 1024 write something like this in
fact we probably want to do it well I
don't know what I want to do
don't quote me on that um right and then
we would do the same thing again
probably like if the value is greater
than 1024 I guess you know what I could
do is do this a little bit more stable I
could say like if the value is greater
than like a megabyte
you know if the value is greater than a
gigabyte what that and then each of
these things just does like whatever the
thing is that you do you know what I'm
saying to you and so I could just say if
it's greater than a gigabyte then the
suffix is going to be gigabyte and the
value is going to be you know equal to
the value plus gigabytes 1 minus 1
divided by gigabytes right so we round
up and we just say like that's how many
gigabytes it is now you might argue we
should like put in a fractional thing
here and you're not wrong but we're also
not going to because we're out of time
and so then if I go look at you 64 to
ASCII 1 too many of those
if I go look at you 64 ascii you can see
this out care thing
so the out care thing I just now need to
add that you know those sort of that
suffix on to the end like so and I think
that's it so I think that should now
print out the values we're talking about
here see here having some kind of an
issue with the VA arglist
what's wrong with that
shouldn't that work
not sure I see what the problem is here
but obviously something is the problem
we're using this right I mean this is
what other people are using so this code
right here expands to like if length
equals 8va
argh-argh lists you 64 that's what that
expanded to right hold on one second
please make sure there's nothing else
weird going on here it's ummm like not
defined or something oh okay yeah I
guess it isn't in this code so what's up
with that is not to find it handmade
platform or something looks like it's
just really confused about what's going
on there
so this looks like the problem because
I'm assuming yeah and handmade shared
handmade shared is like not actually
well no this is handmade types so ummm
should be totally valid right I don't
get it what's the problem
so all that stuff works fine there's a
um I'm right here
did I just like there's a missing : that
was a really bad error message Wow how
about just missing : after case alright
um so let's see if this helps at all I
don't know if it if it does or if it
doesn't or if it well that is not 556
gigabytes case anyone was wondering
about that
let's try that one more time so we look
at whether the value is bigger than
gigabytes fix on there let me take a
look at that what we're we're calling
that
ah so these were cast to you 32s
and they should not have been oops and
we need to actually pass them as UMMS so
that'sthat's some that actually needs to
be converted to a um M right in fact
both this one doesn't because it already
is but they need to be passed as um M so
that so I'm just gonna make sure that
they are and the same would be true here
again we don't need to do this anymore
so I believe if we just make that a 6m
and that's 6m now we should get those
printing out properly and again this is
just a way to make it so that it's a
little bit easier for us to figure out
what the heck values we're dealing with
we don't have to like always like trying
to oh is that bites is that this is that
you know something else all right so
these look right this looks a little
suspicious although I guess we just do
greater than equal to it might actually
be true
they might have just allocated one 1k
block in fact they probably did this
makes it a little bit easier to see
what's happening right now some of these
things that were just zero before you
gets you like oh there's a 4k that takes
up 4 KS worth of allocations instead of
zero right and here you can see oh there
was a 32 byte allocation there for
something right so it's a little bit
better than it was but it's still not
quite as good as I would like let's just
try one more thing in there and say that
this is greater than or equal to instead
of greater than that's probably more
sane but that seems good and now we'll
go ahead and go to QA
yeah
and that looks better okay let's QA
do you think that having a way to
visualize the memory as an image could
be useful how would you implement that I
don't know what you mean like how would
that be different than this do you mean
like you want to draw like the values
that are in there or something
do you mean like like the contents of
memory and as far as whether I that'd be
useful I mean it might help you see
things like runs of zeros and stuff or
something but yeah I don't I don't know
what you would really do with that yeah
I don't know but if you wanted to
implement it I mean honestly it's pretty
straightforward you would just and it's
you know how you would necessarily make
sure that the speed is what you want I
don't know but you know you would just
say to OpenGL here's the arena start
address and here's how long it is it's a
texture and it would download it to the
card right I mean that's it it's memory
so you just draw it and I mean you would
probably want to draw it as mono so
you'd probably tell it it was a mono
texture because you don't unless you
want red green and blue to mean
something you just draw it as a mono
texture and then you either just be fine
with greyscale or you'd use a lookup
table to map like zero to a specific
color and then one through 255 to some
other color so you could see the
difference between zeros
maybe zeros ones as lying
or something like that right short of
that I'm not sure what you would do
because if you wanted to do something
fancier you'd have to have like PDB
information basically because you need
to know like okay where in memory are
things and is this afloat you know
should I draw it as a float instead of a
byte or something right but I honestly
don't know what a value you would get
from that
[Music]
brian says admitted admittedly i have
not been watching all the streams review
of the code but if this tracks memory
and the transient memory could reset
itself throughout the frame is what is
tracked only what is left at the end of
the frame and if you have collected peak
information is it the reason there any
of your static because you're not doing
anything new or different between frames
um so no let me just clarify something
we are tracking the memory usage just
flat flat out period so we the peak
value is the value that was hit inside
the frame and that's why for example the
frame temporary arena has a 46 megabyte
peak but only 3 megabytes is actually
allocated right as for why it doesn't
change well we wouldn't really expect it
to change that much if the game is doing
something fairly stable because remember
we are a pretty reliable game in terms
of memory usage we don't do the thing
that like most engines do we're just
everyone allocates everything all the
time everywhere and is completely lazy
about it so that's what one reason why
we're so stable but there's another
reason that we're stable and that is
that there are some things we're not
tracking and that is if an arena itself
comes into existence and goes out of
existence during a processing of a frame
we wouldn't see that right and so there
may be some there may be some arena's
getting created and destroyed in the
middle of a frame and that we wouldn't
track so just keep that in mind
are you playing to add more features to
this I don't think so except maybe the
scrolling started watching you a while
back is the earlier episodes irrelevant
worth it or should I start somewhere
more up-to-date well everything I do is
programming that's involved in game
development so it depends what you're
trying to learn I would usually
recommend that people watch you know use
the episode guide right like go to well
go to handy hero org and click watch if
you go down here there's like a previous
episode thing and you know look for
stuff you want do you want to know about
like scaling or do you want to know
about Fourier transform do you want to
know about GL and then when you find
something you want like click on it
right and and watch it that's why we
have this episode guide it's there to
allow you to watch the thing as you want
and not watch the things you don't want
but I wouldn't say that later things are
better than earlier things in any
particular way it's more like whether
the topic happens interest you are gonna
add an edit box to filter reduce the
visible lines for memory I don't know
probably not let's see thanks for the
image scaling explanation the pre stream
could you explain about zoom towards the
mouse position
well zooming towards the mouse position
doesn't really have anything to do with
image scaling that's just saying that
when you're going to display you know
anything there's a transform that you're
applying to it and that transform moves
and scales it whenever you apply a scale
the scale will always be about the
origin of your coordinate system when I
multiply something by 3 it gets three
times further from the origin period
there is no other thing you can do so if
you want to scale an image and make it
appear to scale about some other point
then what
you're really talking about doing is in
addition to scaling the size of the
image which really doesn't mean anything
about its location you must also offset
the location you're drawing the image
such that it correctly centers it around
some point you're trying to scale around
right so the way to think about it is to
say in addition to seeing the size of my
image by three I need to take the
location I'm drawing the image take the
mouse pointer and say well wherever the
image is relative to the mouse pointer I
need to scale that offset by three and
add that to the location I'm drawing the
image right because that difference now
needs to you know move the the transform
transform the image by that that amount
right I'm not explaining this very well
because it's kinda something we should
really do on the whiteboard but I think
I explained this stuff when we were
talking about transform centers before
so maybe something like this you know we
probably talked about this just the
concept that you know you've got two
things you've got an offset that you're
drawing things at and you've got a scale
and those things are interrelated when I
change the scale I need to change the
offset to make sure that I now take the
scale thing and put it where it needs to
be so you're scaling two things the size
and the offset right and scaling the
offset is going to have to account for
where you want the thing to be centered
another way to do it would be to say
write out the equation that says where a
particular point on the bitmap is when I
started my frame I want to know that my
before I started zooming I want to know
that where the mouse pointer is well the
mouse pointer right is at the Mouse
pointers location - the offset that I'm
drawing the bitmap at right that Delta
is how I get from the place I'm drawing
the bitmap to the mouse cursor right so
if I want the bitmap to now be drawn in
the same location relative to the mouse
cursor after I scale it I need to take
the I need to make the offset of the
bitmap be my current mouse location plus
the offset I was using from the previous
frame right divided by its scale and
then multiplied by the new scahill right
I need because I'm trying to like build
off of where it was before so there's a
lot of ways you could think about it I
feel like we've covered all this stuff
before if you really can't figure it out
we can do it some some time when I have
more time we could do a whiteboard
session or black board session in our
case where we show exactly what I'm
talking about but I feel like we covered
transform centers several times in the
past
the tiny part of the profiler you had so
you could click on a section and zoom
into that section to see more details
about a section do you see value for
that here
not really and the reason is because
with memory it's usually not so
important it's pretty obvious what's
going on most of the time whereas if
timing sometimes it's not right so I
guess what I would say is I got all the
information I pretty much needed from
from the view we've got you know I mean
just that
that tells me pretty much everything I
need to know you know I really don't
know it's I know what that is comprised
of it's not that complicated right and
so I could see in a system that was
sloppier about memory needing more ways
to like zoom in and gather stuff but
because we're pretty clean you know it
just it seems pretty straight for out
think we need to spend any more time
visually visualizing that stuff in the
thread tutorial you used a port to a
function I knew you want to keep it C
style but wasn't that cleaner to just
use a method inside of struct you'd
remove every pointer equals func so a
couple different things one is that
you'd have to define what you mean by
cleaner right I because what does it
mean for something to be quote-unquote
cleaner in this particular case if we go
look at the thing you're talking about
so you're talking about where we had I
don't know we call that work I think
yeah
so in here we had a thing where we said
look we have a thing that we put a Q in
here and what we want to do is we want
to say there's a callback we use where
we're going to say what we want to do
and then we have a thing where we have a
pointer some block of data that it's
going to do that on right and so what
you were saying is why isn't it a method
and the question is you know is is it
cleaner without a definition of cleaner
obviously I can't answer the question
but what I can show you is why I just
think stuff like that's a total waste of
time if you imagine and I don't know let
me find some like place that I can use
sort of as a scratch place to put this
in here if you imagine the two different
ways to do it here's the one that I did
and when you want to use this you
basically say you know whatever the
function is like Q work something like
this my work right I write one of these
things and then I say employment here
right when I want to add the work later
I say like add work to Q and I say the
my work pointer and I say what the data
is right and it adds one of these so
from the users perspective they do this
right and from my perspective that's
exactly what I wanted to do now if you
did it the other way you would end up
doing this
the C++ way is to say well we've got a
class and that's really just another
word for struck there's no difference
between those two things and so there's
the platform work you entry the platform
work queue entry has this thing in it
and I guess you know I don't know maybe
there's a void star data in here
something like that right as well so in
here we're gonna say well we're just
gonna call this function on the thing
right and this thing has to be virtual
now right because it's not virtual I
can't change it to be something else but
I don't have to do this anymore because
when I call the function it will get the
this pointer and so that you know
doesn't have to happen so that's fine
but you know off we go
and similarly this probably has to have
that in it or something right so it
would look like this I don't know how to
get for coder to not do that but either
way so it's gonna look something like
this right and then when I want to
actually do this thing here now what I
have to do is say well oh and I should
add the one thing that we have to do
here is whatever this data is I would
have to cast right to be fair so
something like that
right so here's the C++ way I make one
of these and now I have to derive from
that so I'm gonna say like all right
I've got the my data that's gonna be
inherited from one of these things it's
gonna have one of this thing one of
these in it right and then I'm gonna
have my index down in here right and
then I'm going to take this thing and
I'm going to implement it in here and I
do like that and you know maybe it looks
something like this makes sense and so
these are the two I assume if I'm
representing correctly what you're
asking
you're sort of asking why didn't I do
this version instead of doing this
version oh and then when I do add work
to queue I can't do this anymore so what
I have to do is instead something like
this right
makes sense so why prefer one of these
to the other and let me also put users
perspective in here and you can kind of
see the difference between the two so
here's my one and here's the the other
one right I and you know is there a good
reason to prefer one or the other
etc etc well the first thing that you'll
notice about these two is the function
and the data have to be defined together
right so let's suppose that the thing
that I'm trying to do work on is already
defined in my system somewhere
somebody's using it right it's a real
thing let's say just for sake of an
argument that the thing is one of these
I want to do some processing on an HHA
asset right so what would I do in both
systems in my system you literally do
this call it changes not at all instead
of my data you just pass one of these so
I would just say HSA asset data you know
the data that's it it just works in fact
let me write that out separately so we
can see so in my version I've got an HSA
asset pointer you know existing asset
and here I do ad work to queue my work
existing asset done I didn't have to do
anything if I come to the C++ version
it's like okay now how do I do this well
I can't go add a virtual function
pointer to this thing because it's
something that's stored in a file like I
can't add a virtual function table
pointer to it and be a complete disaster
right so what I have to do to implement
this thing that took one line of code
for me
in my version I now have to do this
ridiculous garbage make a new thing
called MyData - it also derives from
public you work entry it also has to
define this function thing again like I
do every time and now I have to put the
planer in here then I can do ad work to
queue right actually I have to do this I
think about it so you know you tell me
do you want to write these two lines of
code actually it's not even that's the
that's the input to the function so
actually do you want to write that line
of code or do you want to write that
every time right now let's make it even
more fun I want to operate on this piece
of data still but I want to do something
different well in mind it's another one
line of code I just pass a different
function right
oh but in the C++ version not so much I
get to duplicate this entire set of
things again and create my data three
for having some other function here that
does something different right and in
case you're wondering this is why C++
code bases are like billions of lines of
code and do nothing right is because
it's just a typing festival over and
over and over and over and over and over
and over again right and so then you
know for reasons I couldn't fathom the
way they try to attack these problems
rather than just recognizing that you
just want to do this
it should just you should just try and
make it nice and concise to do that are
there a few improvements we could make
is they add like all these additional
ridiculous things like lambdas and
standard coal and coal and garbage to
try and make this which just doesn't
work less onerous right and they'll be
like okay well maybe we template eyes
the work class on like what the function
is and then we wrap the function and
then thing and you're just like it
already worked the thing before like we
already worked why are you adding all
this stuff and best-case scenario you
end up in C++ seventeen getting back to
something that's almost this good but
usually not it is like all this other
standard library garbage with like all
these templates getting expanded
secretly and you're just like why did
you do that why would you do that you'd
massively overcomplicated your language
your code and the work the compiler
asked to do to produce something
reasonable when you just have the answer
to begin with it was right it's right
there so I just write the thing that
actually does what the CPU does and that
usually is the best way C++ is about
arbitrary syntactic garbage that doesn't
do anything and then constantly trying
to fight your way back to normal right
[Music]
and it's just ridiculous don't go here
and then try to rap your way back to
here just do this thing to begin with
and you're fine right I don't know it's
nuts people just don't know how to
program
the hunter says what about CEO Cisneros
in that case like I said why what do you
need them for like my version just works
you're just adding unnecessary language
features that complicate the work the
compiler has to do in order to get back
to the same freakin thing which is just
call a function pointer that's all you
needed it's one line of code right
and so like C++ is just it's an orgy of
features that the best case scenarios
that get you back to the thing you just
would have done in C and usually they
don't usually don't even get back there
when you actually go like look at what
the compiler generated it struggled so
hard to produce something reasonably but
like there's cruft in your code now
because it couldn't quite figure out how
to optimize everything out that was all
the C nonsense that C++ nonsense that
they added in there right so
so off you go
let's see Amir's I meant game memory dot
platform at entry equals win32 add entry
and game memory platform complete all
work oh well that's because I I keep a
boundary so that anything that calls the
platform layer calls your pointer that's
just a separation of the platform layer
it's just a preference I like to keep
that stuff separate it that way but you
don't have to do that I mean if you
don't want to they don't change so you
could Hardwell them in there it makes a
lot easier to do stuff like switching
things out under the hood but you know
and it like the plot the hot code
reloading we that part needs to have
those function pointers work so you
can't really make the member functions
because we call the wrong thing right
but yeah if you don't care about hot co2
reloading and you don't care about
having the platform layer B and the game
B swappable like that then you don't
need those pointers my nephew started
the computer science a year ago and when
I saw the educational materials they are
not good and professors mostly teach toy
examples I think there's a problem with
computer science education do you know
it can be improved
maybe the production programmers should
teach the program courses yeah I
actually said what I thought that was a
problem yesterday and really it's just
that programming is like a trade
discipline you know and universities are
not where you go to learn trades you
know you wouldn't go to university to
learn to be a blacksmith I think it's
the example I gave you study under a
blacksmith and the same is true of
programming you don't go to university
to learn how to program you study under
programmers who actually know what
they're doing
unfortunately that's not how we have
produced our system and it's true for a
lot of things nowadays universities are
like the worst place to learn how to do
something in my eye
because they're mostly filled with
people who don't know how to do things
in production right they they're filled
with people who study things and that's
different you know the notion that you
go to university to study literature
makes sense to me the notion that you go
to university to learn how to be a
writer makes no sense to me it's never
been that way and shouldn't be that way
University is for study not for craft
but we've combined those two now and it
makes no sense because most professors
in most disciplines aren't experts at
crafting so if you look at the world's
best programmers none of them are
professors I would say so we've gotten
ourselves into this really bad system
where instead of computer science
professors being people who study
computer science and you publish things
about computer science and if you want
to know how to do those sorts of
activities like sort of academic study
you go study under them instead we have
this weird notion that if you're going
to be a production programmer you go
there but why those are two different
disciplines you know studying Turing's
you know construction of a machine and
is that the right way to think about
compute computing and is church's thesis
still you know the correct way to talk
about whether or not we can compute
things and those are important things to
study and they're abstract concepts that
people need to be working on but is that
the are the people who are most
knowledgeable and most well-versed in
thinking about those problems the people
that you want to learn how to make a
renderer absolutely not right they're
totally separate disciplines that can
inform each other but that are not
related in terms of what you do on a day
to day basis right and so I don't know
why we got ourselves in this situation
both in computing and everywhere else
it's
it's just it's a huge epidemic in the
u.s. people going to university as
something they have to do to get a job
but those four years could have been way
better spent studying with someone in a
practical setting and they would have
been way better at their job when they
got out right and so we lost this notion
that university is just for academics
and that training is a different thing
how do you fix it good luck right that's
a social engineering problem way outside
of my area expertise and I can't help
you right
we'll take the last couple here with
their also begin issuing seal sauce if
you wanted to have it being a cue and
some other thing perhaps would you need
to inherit from two or more things it
depends how you want to implement it
usually I think C++ programmers if I had
to like you know put on their hat for a
second would not generally these days
say inherit from two or more things they
would say put a pointer in one of them
to point to the other thing you know but
yeah you'd have to ask a C++ programmer
and these days again they'd give you
some ridiculous answer with all kinds of
weird like standard function wrapping
lambda nonsense that you know would just
be yet another super complicated way to
call a function pointer date p00
is the C++ way a lot of Hoops coming
just to avoid the cast from the void
start of a datatype that you need to do
in the C function pointer method did the
C was a committee reason that it's more
type safe you know the C posis Committee
doesn't really reason about things I'm
sure they had some pedantic nonsense
that they think is a way you're supposed
to think about things and not wanting to
cast a pointer it may have been one of
them but you know who knows all right
I'm gonna wrap it up
okay thanks everyone for joining me
through most of the handmade here it's
been pleasure cooking with you as always
if you would like to follow along the
series at home you always can pre-order
the game on handmade here org and it
comes to the source code so you can
follow along with it in the privacy of
your very own editor that's it for this
week I'll be back here next week when we
may add scrolling to the memory window
or we may just be lazy and not do that
right now and move on to the entity
stuff that I wanted to work on we'll see
that'll be my call until then have fun
programming I'll see everyone on the
Internet
take it as everybody