and welcome to handmade hero sure we
code a complete game
live on stream we are going to do some
collision detection work today
um we're kind of exploring some options
uh that we could use with
uh sort of like
the same sort of stuff i did on the
witness only like trying to do a simpler
version
so still trying to approach it from the
standpoint
of something that we would consider
fairly stable
oops
so something that we're not going to
have a lot of concerns about um
which is usually the problem with
collision detection
and response code is that you end up in
situations where your game has all these
bugs in it
you see this all the time with unity and
unreal games
there's just so many bugs with objects
getting stuck
in things all the time or falling out of
the world
or doing all this other stuff so
the goal here um would be
to try to move towards a system that
doesn't have
very many of those problems so that's
what we're looking at doing
and given the limited you know on
handmade here everything is
very compressed you know normally if i
think about i'm going to make a
collision detector from scratch
i think about spending several months of
careful work
on something like that uh and we don't
get to do that on handmade here
obviously it's
you just gotta do some um fairly
straightforward stuff
so you know we don't have the luxury of
doing something extremely fancy
but um we can still try to do the best
we can
right
all right
so looking at the way that we're doing
this currently there's a couple things
uh that now if we want to start moving
this towards towards done
i think we should do uh
at the start right you can see i've got
this move entity locally thing and we
were subdividing this motion here
and i don't know that that's something
we actually want to do uh
yet so i was thinking about this
kind of just randomly in the back of my
head and i think we probably want to now
start just doing voxel by voxel stepping
um because there's really not much
reason of doing this two-pass thing we
were doing we might as well just start
in the voxelor in
and just move ourselves forward along
that voxel seems like a pretty
straightforward thing to do
so i think i might kind of change this
to doing
that right so when we do
this movement we'll just sort of do it
one voxel at a time
the way that i might uh do that first
is we just won't move multiple voxels
we'll only move
one um and
we'll we'll see what that looks like and
then we'll figure out whether we want
two routines
one routine that calls another routine
to move voxel by voxel or whether it's
all in kind of a loop we'll see i don't
know
but anyway um so the first thing i want
to do is take this
move entity locally thing here um and
and this from p2p
uh i just i'm gonna say look uh we're
not gonna do
so we're not gonna do any of this stuff
right uh we'll leave the motion
displacement size
in there and that'll basically be our
voxel size
so our voxel bounds are actually
before we were building a voxel
dynamically around the character
and because i want to move this to like
i said we're going to try and push
towards getting this stable now so it's
very solid and doesn't break and doesn't
have people getting stuck and that sort
of thing
so what i'd like to do is i'd like to
say okay
we're going to now say that in order for
our
so that our collision text will be more
stable we're going to always use the
same
voxel pattern so we're not
going to build voxels based on where you
are
we're going to categorize you into a
voxel
by saying the voxel's always the same
shape it's just
which cell you're in is what changes we
don't shift the voxel to align with
where you are
this was this shifts the voxel to a line
where you are um and we don't want to do
that
so instead what we'd like to do
um and i don't know what we've got for
math functions i never
remember what sorts of stuff we've
implemented on handmade hero
but basically if we have a floor
so you can see here we have a way to
floor
stuff and
you know it's it's not great um
you know i don't actually want it to
floor to an integer
um so this is less good
uh i i really would rather be doing this
probably so i might
say let's pretend that we have
that though so i might say like okay so
there's a floor
um function here and and it's going to
be like f32 to f32
and it's it's literally just this right
um
so i'm not sure how what the easiest way
to extract this is but i guess maybe
maybe we still just do it this way right
that's probably the most straightforward
way for the compiler to know what the
heck is going on
we don't ever want this to come out of
the cmd registers
so like it's not like it needs like this
is all just stupid syntactic
uh sugar that the compiler needs right
um so
i feel like
we need to tell it that we're just
extracting the float here but i don't
know i never remember
what these are right
i never remember what the heck the
actual name is
for that thing um
what's my syntax error here
just the quotes all right so let's see
uh we've got the convert we've got the
floor
we've got the set zero so it's probably
just the extra one there
so there we go um
so in order to do a floor
that's going to get us down to the
closest integer
boundary um
and so what i want to be able to do is
just
use that to re-center us around where
the
voxel is right and so the problem that
we have
if we do this floor is that it's not
going to be
at the right scale so
i want it to be based on the motion
displacement size
so i first want to uh
to sort of compress this space into
something where the integers are
along these boundaries right
so we want to do something that's sort
of like
you know uh vauxhall min corner
right we know that the from p
is where we are right that's where the
thing
starts and we know that if we floored
that
like so we would get um
the integer base so if we're at 4.5
or 4.7 or 4.3
we'll get four so if we wanted our
voxels to be
one unit long this would just be it
it would be like this right
where we just say hey um
let's just you know
uh build a voxel from the floored
version and
out so this would work if this were one
but the problem we have is it's not one
so before we do
the flooring we need to first compress
our space
into the shape where integers lie on the
boundary
right so in order to do that
i need to expand which is the opposite
like if i multiplied
by this right i would do the opposite
if i multiplied by this i would take and
i would
make it so that the integers were even
less correct
right but if i divide by
this then i am compressing that space
into the shape
uh that is and in this case it's an
expansion
right because this uh is 0.1
so by dividing i'm expanding it by 10
right which makes the integers fall on
the 0.1
lines so if i
do effectively the divide
versus multiply right if we do it like
this
um that will allow us
to produce a aligned version
of that you know uh
one one that is locked down to
the closest 0.1 right
and this is really just um we can even
you know we can treat this as a modulus
so another way
uh we don't have i guess a mod
function maybe um but that's another way
of doing
this like um
yeah so you know there's multiple ways
you can do it but there you go
so we floor it first we
um expand it back out
and off we go now in this particular
case
we want to do this for everything in the
vector
so we'd like to have a floor function
for the vector right because when we
compile this it should complain
because this is not actually
um mapped across vectors and you know
we're in c plus plus you know one of the
world's worst languages
so it it really doesn't know how to do
stuff like that and you have to get into
template disgusting land uh if you want
to try and do things like
automatically map floor over you know a
range of things
and so on so unlike a functional
programming language where this kind of
thing
is just kind of handled properly for you
most of the time
that's not you know where where we live
in sea land
uh so what i'd like to do is here i'll
just where i've got my sort of utility
functions of this form i'm just going to
go ahead and add that in there
so i'm just going to make a floor and
again this doesn't actually do anything
oh that's right i forgot we don't use
that
keyword here i changed to using function
one of the nice things
is if you change internal to function
then
the same parser can read where your
functions are in c
plus and in javascript
because javascript requires you to have
function in front of stuff so then
simple meta programming scanners will
find
either one your javascript front end
code or your cbs plus code
if you use function as a as a pound
defined for that but
anyway um so if we just say look
let's floor uh
the values in our vector
like so
um and off we go uh now this will know
like okay floor all of these
uh and we should have something that
knocks us down to the closest
uh one and then we can
expand it by that same amount here
and when we look um
at the remainder of the code it now
becomes a lot simpler
uh for us because we only have to test
the corners
for one like we don't have to do uh
we only have to test one voxel right
um we don't have to
worry about iterating over like a large
space or anything
so vox dim here right we now know
that the this will always be two
um we're just going to have like the min
and the max of each one
and we also know that the um
size of the cell is is
this uh here right
so we can just pre-define this as
and it's basically a constant it doesn't
change
uh so we don't need to compute it or
anything
uh and so we now have the cell
dimensions
uh the voxel dimension which is always
the same we have the
occupied uh corner codes
and that's it all right and
uh yeah so like if we look
um i don't know that we care about this
particularly much anymore but we might
um but you know there's a couple of
different ways
that we can look at this thing uh
we can make it significantly more
efficient than this
uh to say the least but
but i'm gonna kind of leave this in
place for now but we'll see what happens
anyway uh we'll start with the min
corner
um we'll expand that by the cell
dimension
that allows us to do this test is the
same as it was
uh and that gives us basically what the
occupied
um count is this is still correct
right um it basically tells us exactly
which one we want oh
that's no good um it basically tells us
uh whether or not there's any so one of
the things we can see very quickly here
is if the cell that we're on
is there anything in this cell um
that is there anything in the cell that
we can
actually consider a legal position or
not
and so when this any open comes back and
says
there's nowhere in the cell to be placed
that's like
a thing that the external so again we
don't know how we're this is going to
play out but at the moment
also you know what that goes away um
we don't know how this is going to play
out but basically what we need here is
to
that would be a clue to the external
part of this solver right
um to
to say you need to take some
action to get this object out of
whatever it's stuck in
and again to me this is again crucial to
build into the system because
we even if we assume that we do our job
correctly here
and our collision detector will never
place
two objects into a configuration where
they're stuck
the gameplay code might like we don't
want to have to
ensure that the gameplay code is smart
enough
to avoid that scenario we want the
gameplay code
to just be able to do whatever it does
and if things happen to get stuck in
each other
what we really want is we want this
collision detector to be so suave
that it will just try to figure out how
to get them unstuck
right so rather than trying to write the
whole game
thinking that we need to make sure
nothing ever sticks
what we're trying to do is make the
collision detector automatically unstick
things that get stuck in each other
right
and that's just part of making the thing
as robust as we can to eliminate the
as many possible ways that we can screw
the player we don't want to screw up the
player's
playthrough that's the worst possible
thing that technology can do in a game
engine
so we want to try to have it do the
opposite we want it to always be
trying to get the game into a playable
state
we don't want there to be failure states
where oh something got stuck
because the gameplay code did something
and now the game is ruined like we don't
want that right
so um
also inline we don't really inline
doesn't really exist anymore
so we've just been slowly replacing it
with internal like all these can be
inline
um it can be internal really i should
just change it to function
um because that's what i use these days
i i just put this in front of everything
it's just static is really what it is
inline doesn't really work anymore
compilers just ignore it
so it's kind of pointless i think
sometimes maybe gcc uses it a little bit
most compilers just ignore it
so yeah you know
it doesn't really matter anyway uh
so if we look here
at this any open um if
if the any open thing is like we can't
we can't find anything then i think we
just punt
so i think here we'll we say if any open
and otherwise
we just leave we don't try to do
anything
right um and so one thing we might do
also is not move uh the player also so
so what i kind of want here
is like a move result um
and there's like a uh found
like we found a place to put it and
here's the place
um so what i'd like to do is switch to
that kind of strategy
so the entity um itself we really aren't
using the entity
itself in any capacity other than we
need to look at like its collision
volumes
but we're not writing to it so
all we do is we say okay
we've got a move result we want to
produce
we start by assuming that it fails if we
actually get into the any open then
we're going to actually succeed
so we say yes we found a place and then
the question is
what is the place right so like what is
the actual
uh location that we're going to put the
player
in and so this is the part that we
actually have to think about
and we are probably going to return some
other stuff as well
all right so this gets kind of
complicated
uh now we have to start thinking about
this voxel in
in three different ways number one is
the
is the easy one which is can we place
the entity in this voxel at all are
there any legal corners
uh period right
and that's the way that we already did
like literally there's
many ways we can do that and we'll
probably change which way we use over
time here as we refine the routine but
certainly this way works if the occupied
count
is conclusive if if every corner
if all eight of the corners are occupied
um then we know that we cannot
place the entity in this cell it's
it's colliding so this part here is
saying all right if
if we could have placed it then it is
possible so that's the first way
we're reporting um information about the
voxel
right or about the collision that's
thing one
thing two uh is we need to figure out
if we were to place the player uh i keep
saying player but if we were to place
the entity because
this moves things that aren't the player
so i don't know why i keep saying that
if we are to place the entity in this
cell
where right so where would
it be placed and the problem that we're
going to have
right is if you look at
the if you look at the way we're doing
this
you can see like we do a get closest
point
in box for example and you can see like
we say
uh so you know if we produced the cell
and we said
we wanted to get the closest point to
um to the target point this would give
us that right
so you might assume well well use that
the reason that we can't exactly use
that
is
so i feel kind of stupid
because if i'm not mistaken
all you would have to do is start at the
start location
from p get the closest
point to the target point inside the
cell
and then just repeatedly bisect that
until you found a place you could stand
and that gives you actually the exact
answer
the reason that i feel really stupid is
because i feel like that would have just
worked in the witness solver
and would have saved like half the run
time of that solver
if i'd thought of that
then now granted
all of the stuff i did on the witness
was completely new
and so i was figuring all of that stuff
out and
that always is the case when you first
figure stuff out you don't have the
mental model for it
so you're not likely to make
realizations i don't blame myself for
that because the witness stuff was all
very new very difficult
and was surprising that it all came out
the way it did
so no you know what i think i think
that it's okay that it wouldn't have
worked on the witness one because the
witness one requires that the
person is standing on the ground
and that makes a big difference because
that means you have to move
along a manifold and you don't know what
the manifold is
because this is for floating objects
that's why this would
work it doesn't need to know it doesn't
need to move along a manifold
so i maybe give myself
i maybe give myself credit for that
so
so i wonder about the witnesses why does
the player not move on a nav mesh then
you wouldn't have needed the brute force
testing thing
um well so
there's a couple reasons for that one is
that
you still need the way to build the nav
mesh so the witness does have a nav mesh
for like the ipad version
and it uses my solver to build the nav
mesh
so you could think of the thing as
building the nav mesh but the reason
that
it doesn't use a nav mesh for the
movement
uh is is just literally be for accuracy
and efficiency
right if you build a nav mesh now you
have a
either a very coarse nav mesh that feels
crappy
right which is what you have in like
unity or something and that's why nobody
uses it for
movement they still use the collision
detector for movement
um or you
uh you have a nav mesh that's super
super detailed
and it's huge and creates a resource
loading problem
and it puts stress on the streamer and
all this sort of stuff right
so the beauty of the witness one is it
works in 100 real time it
it doesn't have to make a super coarse
version of anything
it can let you feel exact movement
um you know it's just better and there's
no
baking it's instant it's always live
for the people who are editing and
working on the game
so it's just better because the witness
one
can do either if you want a navmesh you
can just take the output of it and
there's your nav mesh
um you can reduce the density of it as
much as you
think you want to right um
or you just don't bother and you just
let it run on the exact geometry and it
works
right um so it's kind of just a superset
of nav mesh it's just like the better
version of navmesh if you want navmesh
you have it
if you know you can't or don't want to
do pre-computation pass or you want
things to be more detailed
or you have tons of dynamic things maybe
that's the other thing in the witness
there's lots of stuff that moves around
elevators platforms all this stuff
that makes nav meshes kind of difficult
because
what do you do at the boundaries between
those meshes
you need a solution for that that's
rigorous right
so nav meshes really aren't a solution
to anything to be completely honest
uh you kind of still need an answer for
how do you build the nav mesh what do
you do with all of your dynamic stuff
blah blah blah and so the witness thing
is just the superset solution it's like
look this just works
right and if you want the features of a
navmesh you can get them if you don't
want to deal with all the drawbacks of
nah meshes you just don't have to
you can just not do that and in the
witness we did both
so in the witness for click to move you
want a pathfinder so there's like a
rough thing that that's that
right me and john blair are on the same
team
spiritually we're not on the same team
physically all right
i wonder if what i just said actually
works which is
kind of nuts if it does so
um
i don't know
i don't know but it kind of feels like
it would
so uh i guess what i'm what i'm trying
to say is like suppose that you pulled
this
piece of junk out which is the part that
we want
after we're done making sure that this
routine works well
it's the part that we'll replace with
the spatial partition
because this this is the core cost
of this routine and this ain't gonna fly
right so
this will be a local lookup that just
gathers the things that are right next
to you for testing
um and so we want this to be isolated
probably for other reasons anyway but
assuming that we just do a thing that's
like uh
can place or collides
at p or i don't know what um
assuming that we have this and we put
pass in
the stuff that we need for uh
determining whether you can stand
somewhere right so you basically say
like
you know here's the thing this will be
you know a space partition thing it's at
some point or something or this will
just have the face participation
who cares the entity goes in here uh
the p that we're trying to test goes in
there and we literally just go
and say all right this is the
rectangular testing we would iterate
over the spatial partition
we see whether or not we're supposed to
have a collision here
we do that test uh and then we produce
the result here
so you know we would do a thing that's
like results
equals false it does not collide here
the result equals true
it does collide and that is the loop
so in here we would say uh rather than
all this stuff we just do
this part just this test
and we call out to collides at p
and we say sim region and the
test speed now i knew maybe why did we
do that
right well now i can call that
uh in a refinement loop right
um
what who who is biddle it's not like
mike biddlecombe is it
no way really
you serious
no you don't need a code word well great
to see you
how's it going i think the last time i
saw you was at handmade con
uh 20 20 20
19 would have been the one
uh
that was the last one that was like in
person right
how's it going
what are you up to
you in canada now
in the great the great northern expanse
or are you back in the states
mike biddlecon ladies and gentlemen he
is uh a
person i work with a long time ago he is
from canada
and but he was working in the states at
the time
and then he went back in vancouver yeah
vancouver is a really nice nice place
um anyway thanks for stopping by mike
to see you um
so the the thing that mike biddlecombe
was amused to
to see me realize um
is
if we are moving in 3d it means that
fundamentally we don't have to move
across any particular manifold like
we're just moving this thing across
just across space so once we
know if we test the sides of the cell
and we just make that be our criteria
for are you allowed to
move in this cell we can then place the
person
uh the entity anywhere in the cell right
because we know we know that the rule
for
could you be in this cell is are any of
the eight
uh sides of the cell vacant or not right
so then we can just do hey if we know
that we can
place a person in this cell let's just
root find to find out where
right now there is one case that this
won't handle correctly
that we'll have to think about and
that's if the place that you're in
if you're already in
actually it would it'd probably handle
that too
so if you're already in then you just
look for the out position
this might actually be really awesome um
so here's what happens you now have the
cell
the cell doesn't this is stupid we don't
really need this
there's because there's only one cell
right i mean we we stopped
you've got a min and max corner so like
the cell is just
is just that
right because we're only doing one
now uh so
in here we we go into
the uh the routine we check to see
whether it's legal to place
anyone in this cell at all uh we can now
just
root find to see whether we can uh
whether they're where in the cell we can
place that's closest to where you were
trying to go
and my i don't know
i can talk a little bit about why i want
to do that two-level thing because you
might be like well why not just do that
root find in general
and there are reasons i don't want to do
the root find as the definitive thing
because
i'll talk a little bit more about why i
think we want
two different rules for how that would
work
is is all i'll say about that for now
okay so let's suppose that we
then go ahead and and want to do this
test so if we
do a uh
[Music]
a collides at p test to see about
where we're standing so the from the
from position
like where we are right
um if we look at at whether or not
that's in or out
so a starting state
is this so where we are standing
we know the starting state in the future
we can probably elide this so uh
so we probably know which one that is
because the last thing told us but for
now we'll just recheck it
so we look and we say are we colliding
and then we then binary search for a
place
where that's going to be uh
where we satisfy the other criteria
right
um and the only thing
that i the only thing that
i think we probably want to add is some
awareness
of the state of the voxel sides
so if all of the voxel sides
i
i'm not sure how i want to use that
information in this part so i don't know
yet
but point being um
in this case we know what our starting
state is and i want to do
um a refinement here uh
so there's just gonna be you know a few
steps
of refinement and i don't know how many
i want this is basically a tolerance
that can be like
cranked uh and
so what we can do is as we do our
refinement
uh we will bisect
the difference between our from p
and our 2p to get like a place where we
think
we can stand so the like
uh you know this would be like the
the test the t-test right
is gonna start at 0.5 let's say
so then to compute the test point
we're going to do a
linear interpolation
we still need this
so here's the the like local target p
like i mean i guess this is like the the
place we're trying to get to inside the
cell we can't leave the cell
um so we're going to say all right the
local
uh 2p oh and there's so
there's one more thing about this too so
there's even
one more thing which is uh
do the refinement step only at the end
right so another aspect of this is
actually
this probably doesn't have to happen we
probably
can just do this at the end so the
refinement step
only happens in the final voxel cell
right
so to me i think um
it probably looks more like this where
we only
do we we first do the voxel to figure
out which voxel you're in and we let you
move through there
and then here we just say oh okay
at the end of all this
uh then we take and we do you know
we assume that you pass in um
the voxel that you're talking about so
this is the cell
uh we assume that you're gonna have the
stuff that you needed
uh which obviously you know you need you
need this stuff
so at the end after everything's done
when you are you have figured out what
voxel cell you have you have
determined that the player uh or the
entity i should say
will end up in then you call refined
voxel placement only on the final cell
and then what you do is you take that
target location you see where in the
cell
that would map to the closest point
and then you refine towards that to
place the entity
as close as possible to the correct
position
how do you like that that's a good
spelling there
doesn't matter um
okay so what we want to do
is we are trying to find
i guess
i'll show you why we need this um in a
second
but assuming that we started out in a
position
where we weren't right so so we could
just say like you know
a starting state equals you know it's
not colliding or whatever
right um but assuming that we started
out
colliding the reason that i need to know
that
is because if you think about the binary
search process that's about to happen
what we're doing is we're saying all
right there's a test point we're going
to start in the middle
we're going to take the local 2p right
and we're going to linear blend
do we not have a linear blend
okay it's called lerp for some reason
um so if we take a look uh we can call
lerp to uh use the t
value to say where from
you know the the starting location
to the local target right
we we take a half step
and then on each time we say
for that test p um
does it collide doesn't it collide you
know
oops
so we check to see whether it collides
if it does collide um
let's pretend that we are not going to
use this yet we're pretending that we
always start
safe so we start uncolliding if it does
collide it means we've gone too far
right we've we've stepped into the
colliding zone
so we need to step back if if we
don't collide it means we could
potentially go further so we need to
step forward
so what we want to do is say like oh
okay you know our t-test
um is going to have a step to it
uh that step is going to start out at
whatever the half is
and each time we're going to shrink it
by half right
so the t-test is going to take and
we're going to um uh
we're going to add or subtract
one of those two things um
and i don't
i i think we probably want to do this
uh
so i think we probably want to do
something like uh
we want to take t-test
and we want to say that like t-test
equals
t equals like um t-test
plus collides um or you know
you could do this like uh we make the
two steps here
so there's a t forward uh t
backward right
um or maybe like t collides
t uh safe or something
i don't know i and these are just
t-test like if we collide it's like
t-test
minus t-step and if it's it's not it's
it's plus t-step
right so if we collide we come back if
it's
safe we go forward and so you can see
now why i want this starting
state because if i know that we're in
collision begin with it's the opposite
so i need to do a thing where at that
point i say like oh
um if the starting state
actually was colliding then the t
step is the negative right we
flip it around so that when we add
we're actually subtracting and we
subtract we actually add
so we assume that the starting state is
clean in most cases
it means that t step will be positive in
most cases
which means that when we look and we say
we collided right
we want to step back so it's a minus
right
okay so that also means this is
branchless
which doesn't matter because there's a
ton of branches in the probably in the
collision detection part of things but
we can optimize that we can do whatever
we want
we've got lots of options um anyway so
if it collides we will t
collide if it doesn't we will t safe
right um those are the options that we
had and
this will root find us to the best
position to place
uh this thing like the result right
and so at the end we sort of have our
last
best position um that we didn't collide
so we can save right
like we can say that we have um
a result p it's going to be equal to
where we started
each time here that there is a safe
place
to put this so if we say like
you know if um
we didn't collide then the result p
equals the test p right um and so again
we can also phrase that this way
just in case we want to try and be
squinky about it
um if you know if it doesn't collide
uh or we can still say if it collides
we take whatever the previous result was
if um
if not then we take the new one right
all right so this is the iterative
refinement step so
again just to everyone i realize close
detection is very difficult
i realize all this stuff is really
complicated
so i apologize for that uh
but you know
what can you do let me explain briefly
what's going on
one more time for folks uh because like
i said it's complicated
so you know i've got it in my head and
i'm working it out and
i'm trying to explain it as i go but i
realize that like i'm seeing pictures
that you're not seeing
in my head right uh and so that's why we
go to the light board sometimes i don't
really want to do that right now but
if we do refine voxel placement what
we're basically saying is we've
determined that we can place the player
in this cell and
the reason for these uh two
um the reason for these two things oh
and we need we also need obviously to
make this loop actually work
uh we need to half it each time
anyway um so we do refine voxel
placement
we come in here what we're saying is
it's legal to be placed in the cell
so we've determined that we can place
the entity in this cell
that means that that cell is traversable
and so we're not gonna worry about mike
about where in the cell you place the
entities as being
legal or illegal right we're saying you
can place the entity anywhere in this
cell
because the rules of how you move things
allowed that to occur
so now all we're doing is trying to get
a ballpark figure
for where in the cell it probably should
be we don't care
if we overshoot or undershoot like if
there really was something
that you could have walked you know you
could have moved around
in the cell or if you allows you to
tunnel through
something that's fine because we're
actually handling the legality of that
at one layer up we're basically saying
look the voxel pattern is what
determines
where you can place stuff right
um if that makes sense right
uh so that's how we're gonna do that
that placement there and again that's
because
one of the things that i really think is
important for
collision detection work in games is
accuracy is not at all what you want
what you want is that things always can
get out of being stuck
so you pretty much don't ever want to be
thinking about things like oh
at a very small scale i need to find
exactly where this can move and i need
to prevent it from going through other
things
you're just setting yourself up for
everything getting stuck what you want
is
coarsely can the thing be roughly in
this area
if it can place it reasonably
and allow yourself a lot of freedom to
place it anywhere there because you
you need to give the collision detection
response
part of the code as much opportunity to
get things
unstuck as you can
so focusing on accuracy of
whether or not two things could have
moved past each other
or could have done this or that is never
really a good idea
in my opinion you want to focus instead
on
options giving the collision detection a
lot of
options to put things
somewhere that works so that's mostly
the
the way in which we're approaching this
this routine is just for iterative
refinement it's to place something in a
more plausible location to the viewer's
eye
is the way to think of it it does not we
don't want it to control
whether you could do something right
it's just to try and give the most
plausibly visually pleasant result so
that root find is there for that
and that alone we don't know what we
want this to be
um you could if you want it to be
accurate to floating point precision you
could do that right
and now you're out of precision your
floating point numbers can't
really do any more than 24 bisections
i don't know that we'll need that many
i'm going to leave it at a low number
for now we might crank it up higher
once this is not once this has a spatial
partition so it's fast
right but right now this is going to be
dog slow because each one of these calls
is going to have to loop over all the
entities right so we know it will be
unbearably slow to start with so i'm not
going to crank this up or try to find
what this number should be right now
we're going to
do the space partition before we play
with that all right
so refined voxel placement
um
we now know that we can just call that
at the end
um and so we know that the end of this
routine
here is just going to look uh like this
so the refined voxel placement part of
this
here is going to have
all the stuff it needs um
we assume we're sort of setting a target
now
for this by the time it gets into this
routine it should have all of these
things
the cell in which we would like to place
the entity
the region uh which we know because
that's already
you know just a given the entity we're
placing obviously also known
and then if the 2p is always going to
stay the same
that's where we want this thing to end
up so that's
a separate issue we don't have to touch
the from p
may have translated it may have
moved from cell to cell
as we go right um so that part is also
uh sort of a little bit uh different and
i'm not sure how we want to handle it
one way would be to map it into the cell
at the beginning as well
so it just teleports to there another
way
is it gets convected along in like the
center
of the voxel faces as we go and we
assume you had to come around
that way
that's arguably the more accurate thing
i just don't know if it would ever make
an
a practical difference so it might just
be a lot of bookkeeping that's happening
for no reason
right
and that's a really hard judgment call
so i suspect
what i'll do to start with is i'll just
say look
the first pass of this thing is going to
be
uh
is we're gonna map in that and you know
what the heck with it
like let's do that both sides so the 2
the 2p here we won't do a local it'll
just be assumed
right so we'll just say like note
uh it is expected that from p
to p have already been mapped
into the cell right so
so we're just not going to do that part
that part has to have already happened
so in here we have um
both of these now will map the from and
the two and we'll pass both of those in
and
that's just how we'll start and this
one is probably just right like that is
probably how the routine should work
this one might not be so so
right
so hair studios i i study cinematography
for rendering reasons
so when it came time i said i'm gonna
upgrade the actual look of the webcam
i was like uh let me
light this as if it was gonna be a pro
grade
thing and uh i
uh don't want to give away too many
secrets but let me just say that that
i guarantee you that nobody else in the
world
did lighting the way i did it
it is a a uh a technique i have never
seen
mentioned anywhere i was very proud of
it uh
when i came up with it because i was
like
that is really good uh
and um and it worked
very well i was i was i was uh
inappropriately proud of of my lighting
um my idea for lighting and i think i'm
glad you liked it because i thought it
came out really good
all right um so
yeah refined voxel placement
um
move entity locally so yeah i guess now
we just need to do the pathfind part
this part's fine this now just goes away
right so we're not going to do
any of this
that goes away and so what we're gonna
do here
is uh you know th
this is the most sensitive um part
of the um
this is the this is the most time
like
continuous stuff is usually better in
when you're writing
it you just do float computations and it
works right
the discrete part is always the part
where things get
hairy because it's bookkeeping and so
what we need here
is we need to start inside of oxycel
we need to figure out which direction
in voxel cells to move
and the really uh annoying
thing is we need to figure out a way
to
we need to figure out a way to figure
out when to terminate
right so
i mean maybe the answer is you terminate
when the closest point
would be uh
i mean you so i think you're going to
want to do something where you basically
say look we look to see
what corners are open we allow movement
to this
neighboring cells that have those open
corners
and the problem is just knowing
knowing when to stop looking at cells
i mean i think what you would do i guess
is you say
look i i move towards the cell that is
the closest one to the target point
on each step and i stop when
there are no cells i can move to
that would be closer than the cell that
i'm in and then i refine
yeah my glasses broke i talked about the
beginning of the stream my glasses
broke and
i only need correction in one eye so i
just kept the one
and i ordered new glasses and i'm like
now i'm a monocle
i'm a i'm the super villain i always
wanted to be
but now i gotta wait
for new glasses to come um
and get delivered right
i'll do a stream at some point i'll try
to put up a video
separately that like talks about how i
did the lighting
um i should probably do that um
i should put up a video that's like you
know
that's like you all youtube and it's
like
how to make the perfect lighting for 50
or whatever right
and it's got like me like on
like on the like as a little thing on it
it just says fifty dollar lighting
or whatever fifty dollar perfect
lighting no way or would it write or
you know like that stupid crap um
that uh
[Music]
that that is that is like uh what we
need and then there can be like real
cinematographer
reacts to casey's crazy lighting setup
or whatever
right like and then someone else makes
money off the video and we all make
money off of reacting to each other's
stupid idea
right um
so you know
i agree there needs to be arrows in the
thumbnail
for sure
get cinema quality lighting with this
one weird trick
all right uh so in the move entity call
um i think what i wanna do right is say
okay so this thing
like i said i don't know what these
routines are gonna look like but it's
sort of starting to fall into place
now right we kind of know that
this is what it is that looks right
it doesn't really need to be a separate
routine it could be moving but it's it's
well enough you know it's fine it's well
enough like
constrained um and contained
there that that we can leave that way
this is now probably just
actually the routine so i don't think
we're actually going to want to call
quote unquote this or any of that stuff
so i think
we're probably going to want to just do
it right in here
so i'm going to weld these routines back
together again like we had actually
pulled that out and i'm going to stop
doing that
and i think we're now going to do the
setup in here
so the cell dim is always the same
right uh that's the size of our voxel
and and off it goes
and then i'm going to have a for loop
here right
that's just going to loop until it can't
move to a closer cell
so we'll have some metric maybe from the
center of the cell
to the target destination or something
and this is kind of the part that's a
little bit tricky it's like
we may the reason this is why i didn't
immediately weld this routine
in we may want to call this routine to
get better answers by
doing the refinement on more than one
cell because if two cells
are within a a certain we don't know how
close we can do
um in each one oh yes the tip
professional cinematographers do not
want you to know that is
yes that is it
right
um all right so
if we assume that we are
uh
if we assume that we're going to take
this uh
and and loop through and move really the
only problem is is making that judgment
call like i said because everything else
now i think just sort of
happens um so we kind of have this idea
of a um like
of a walk point like we're walking
through this vauxhall
and i i don't know what this is for
um this is just stupid now uh
that is true that's a true that to do is
is not a joke
um so that's there uh but we're gonna go
ahead and start with the walk p
thing and we're gonna say all right we
have a walk p that's the point that
we're testing
um and maybe maybe
uh that gets like re-centered in a way
so you know maybe that just walks from
cell to cell in fact
in fact uh that's probably what we'd do
so we start this way um
and say yeah like
we're going to start the voxelmen corner
voxel max corner thing and the
walk p would be like
there and we're just going to move that
by cell amounts
right so depending on which direction we
want to
move this thing you know it's going to
be
something where we just take steps in
that direction
right so it's going to be like walk p
you know um dot x plus equals you know
sign uh
times cell dim
x right like it's gonna be this kind of
thing
where we're just stepping through uh
and and the cell itself like this
this thing is just gonna be like offset
um
in the exact same way right so we almost
don't need the walk p
right we're just that's just a way of
getting center so so this
you know could be in here or whatever so
at some point we then say like okay
like displacement or or like next
you know step or whatever is just going
to be
a thing that we offset the cell by
uh you know so we we step each time
and the step itself is just
determined by which direction we're
going to go so we do like one of these
you know what i'm saying we'd step
in one of these directions
does that make sense
no uh malicevixie what do you mean
the divide outside the floor
um oh yes man you guys are catching good
stuff for me today thank you
it's been a my brain's pretty slow today
i think because i was up too late last
night playing satisfactory
on stream um
but yeah yeah as i said you want the
divide then the floor
then the multiply is the goal
right um okay
so we can build the cell this
uh is wrecked min dim actually so you
know what this stuff
can just we can do this that way we
don't even have to do the offset part we
just say voxel min corner
plus equals step that's just better
right
um and furthermore we can actually just
ignore the step part now
and do what i wanted to do originally
because if we just have a vector we can
just do
something where we're going to be
stepping the min corner and then we just
each time we build the cell
by just stepping out by the dimension
right
so uh
i think we're narrowing in so here
we have the whole like occupied
um unoccupied sort of thing
um i don't think we want uh
any of this now it's all just not there
um we may want to continue drawing
uh the outlines though
uh so that part may want to be there um
but yeah so then let's see
what else we've got uh okay so we have
our for loop
uh we've got yeah that's all just kind
of garbage
um the cell
here we do want to exit with it um so we
can i suppose recreate it here by just
saying okay the cell
uh you know we we produce it by doing
the
min corner add the same way uh
from p and 2p in this case
this is just the entity's position this
is just the target
so i think that's just
this here
it's just that right it's just the delta
p so
so two we didn't actually record this
anywhere
um but we kind of just want to make that
a thing
that's where we were trying to get to
you know
um and so i think that's everything
for the sketch of the routine and now we
just need the actual way of knowing
how we step through the voxel and that's
like i said the tricky part
so in here we would then say okay for
and you can also see where we can save a
lot of time here because we can also
keep a bunch of our occupied stuff
right
if that makes sense oh uh yeah the
returns to me it doesn't complain about
the return statements till you
actually get a compiling program that's
just one of the things visual studio
does
it like doesn't get to that stage of
compilation or something so it would
have said hey you gotta
it would have erred the reason it wasn't
airing is visual studio just doesn't
do that until you get the program
linking
like basically to the stage of linking
uh so okay um
let's go ahead and
i and figure out how we're going to do
this part because this is by far the
hardest
part i think so
we figure out whether the thing is
occupied
right we
we know that if there's nothing open
um so so i i think we're probably gonna
have to do
something like this right
um so there's gonna be like a best cell
thing um and and honestly that's
probably this to start with so we assume
when we start that the best cell is just
the one you started in
and so if everything just fails you just
end up back
in that cell right
and that's it um and we'll have to work
on what happens
in that case also uh because remember we
have to handle
the case where we're trying to get out
of something um as well as the case
where we're trying to get in
like or to avoid getting into something
so uh this is probably now going to just
be like yeah whatever
the interior part of the routine tells
us is the best place
that's what we actually need to work
with right
so inside here what we're going to be
doing is trying to find that best place
and so uh when we look
at whether the thing is has any state
occupied
i think we probably need the same sort
of idea
here remember i said i have the to-do up
at the top it's like this can probably
be passed in
the reason i said that is because i was
pretty sure that we would
need to do the check up here and so we
would
be keeping a running check of whether
the from position
um is actually in or out right
so let's call the from p
here
uh let's actually call that
from p to make it a little clearer
uh i just feel like that's maybe a
little bit better
um
so you can see what's going on but we're
going to have that
that uh start location
and i want to know uh
whether we're colliding whether we're
whether we're talking about getting
something
unstuck or preventing something from
something from getting stuck
on its way to wherever the target is
right
so if we assume here that we've got a
start collide rate of
uh collides at p
so in here we say yeah
like hey man
uh we inside or outside
uh at the the start of this and this is
going to mirror sort of
what we were doing here so in exactly
the same way that we basically
flip the refinement in the same way that
we flip the refinement
in this version we're going to do the
opposite thing
we're going to flip the
the rule about where we can go
so what we want is
from now on like in here
um
what i'm trying to say is like that one
test are we inside or outside
when like are we colliding or not at the
start of the move
effectively acts as like a giant knot
right it's it's a it's gonna flip
what we consider the place we can move
to or not move to
so if we assume um that we started
colliding
we're going to want to allow you to move
out of any cell that you
we want to allow you to move through a
cell that's completely colliding
so when we look and we see any open
normally if any open is false if there's
no where to place the player in this
cell or the entity in the cell
that means we can't consider that cell
but
the opposite will be true
uh for any condition where we were
colliding to begin with
then we want to move we need to be able
to tunnel through things
to get ourselves out of stuck into
something valid
right um if that makes sense uh
so yeah you know what i'm saying
tired in here
alright um so again
the hardest part of the chain by far now
coming up for sure
this is going to be the tricky part
let's start with the easy
case which is um well this is the easy
case
neither i'm easy let's start with just
handling
one of the cases so although i know that
i'm probably going to want
to use that as a switch to change what
happens
in the selection path here we're just
going to assume
that this for now is always
false so you're starting from a legal
position
and we don't have to handle the case
where you're trying to get out of a
place
so at that point if you always assume
temporarily we assume that we only move
you
to cells that are going to be closer
and that the only thing let's just
assume
let's assume that we don't do let's
let's assume that we
don't ever care what the refinement
will actually be able to do which is is
possibly dicey that's why i say we may
need to call that routine
to check a couple different cells to see
which one would be the best
that can be like an upgrade version of
this routine
but at first let's just assume that each
cell
just has a uh when we do get closest
point in box
right that the points
we evaluate are just the closest point
on the box and we never
move you to a cell that is less close
right so if we look at what happens
there's for any point that we're looking
at the vauxhall
there's
we never want to move you further away
from the point right so there's only
going to be three
uh well let's say four
cells you could move to um i mean we
really could say one two three
four
so we could really say that there's
seven
cells you could move to right
and so i'm kind of thinking look as we
check
to see whether you can move um
[Music]
whether uh you've got the option to go
to
different cells like maybe we just loop
through those
here and then consider those cells
the best possible next cell just based
on whichever one
contains the uh
yeah i'm sorry i just don't know i just
don't know what the best way to write
this is
i'm going to have to experiment a little
because like another way to say it would
be like
maybe you just want to look at the the
look at the corner codes and
move as many court as many
of the axes you could move towards the
destination
if the corner codes would allow that
move then you do that move
you know so you move along x along y
along z
if if those are available you just do
that
so let's just let's just not over
complicate it then
um let's just let's just see
so uh i'm gonna then say look
uh let's let's say we look at what
these codes are and and we had a thing
we sort of did this before so we're
doing
kind of a slightly similar thing um
but we want to know like can we move
in x or not can we move in y
or not can we move in z or not right we
just want to kind of know
um which directions
we would be allowed to move in
and i guess we kind of also want to know
if we can move diagonally
and we could
you know and i don't know like if we
want to allow
direct diagonal movements it seems like
you probably do you would just say
if the corner is open right like like
you do
um
so like if
if you can move through the corner
uh
you would look literally just at the
corner and then
for moving in the uh
but for moving along just the cardinal
directions
you would look to see uh whether the
um
uh you would look to see whether or not
anything on that side was
so this is like a corner move right
um
that is a uh
move in z so you're basically saying
like is there any way i could get out of
this cell
in the z direction of the target right
um and you would do the same for each
hopefully this makes some sense
so um quarter move
z move y move x move
and you know that you're only ever going
in one of those directions like you're
never going to go
away from the target point um
because presumably whoever asked you to
move in that direction
doesn't want you to move in the opposite
direction right
like that's never something the gameplay
code wanted to happen
right um so
that's the idea uh and this
would allow us to test each of these
potential moves
right so
we can then actually do that like we can
test each of these
and see uh whether they are better or
worse
and then we just accept the cell that
would
give you the chance of getting closest
and we don't actually check first
we don't actually see how close you
could really get
inside that cell you know what i'm
saying
and so then we just accept that move if
none of these moves would produce a
better result
so if we get down here
um and we say there's nothing
that would put us closer right
that's the criteria for breaking so
there's like if you know a move exists
then great we do it if not then we stop
you know what i'm saying um at that
point like
occupied count
maybe just doesn't matter
at that point
so maybe i just don't care about that
um that's a good question and i don't
know
so we'll see i'm not gonna promise
anything
that may come back right um and the
answer here hopefully is yes because
this is asking the question of can we
implement the thing
we are literally trying to type in right
now so hopefully the answer is yes
because the answer is no we're going to
be very sad because it means we can't do
what we're doing
but you know uh and so
let's put this down here because this is
really just
a little uh variable that now doesn't
even have to be
a pound define um
so that can just kind of hang out there
and we'll decide what to do with it
later
so that's all good and now we just have
to write the code that actually checks
for the movement
if we look here at this stuff this is
sort of
yeah like what the step would be um
so i don't know how we want to do this
but it's probably something like
this
um
so
[Music]
let me just call this direction
right
so if we end up with a movement um
and and we could even just do like if
dur x
order y or z right
um so if we end up being able to move
this is not a
great way to do this but if we end up
being able to move
then we move if we can't then
we can't right
so we've got
something that looks sort of like this
or whatever and and really
i want to say that this is really just
this
so the same thing that we'd be setting
here i mean we probably just don't want
to do this but like
right
um it's just a sign it's just the same
thing we would use we're using to make
that variable it's kind of annoying
right but whatever
um so in each of these cases
it would be like this sort of thing
right so the
the moves if they're allowed are these
moves
and like i said to me
the problem that we now have here is we
need
a thing that actually tests to see which
of these moves
is actually better right in each of
these cases
we want to actually try to
produce a better cell for the next time
around
so um
we probably just want a function that
kind of wraps this
up for us
and in fact maybe we would just
do
maybe we would do a thing for now
because this is like i said it's kind of
hard
this routine so let's just kind of break
it down and make it as simple as we can
let's do a thing where we say okay we've
got the um
we we've got the min
corner is here uh
and the best
distance squared is in there
and then we just have a function we can
call
uh that will update this thing
uh and furthermore maybe that has the
moved in it so that way this thing
doesn't have to do something nuts like
that
so
that is sort of what i'm talking about
each one of these would be
like update best and it would be
um
that sort of thing so we just say
hey update the best the besties
here uh and each one of these
just passes in the like vector that i
was gonna try and use
to update the thing and then we just
kind of
jam all the stuff into the best function
and this allows us to like write this
code that you know
we probably need to do a better job on
at some point because this is just a lot
of stuff happening in a you know
a thing we need to probably be somewhat
fast
but that is more or less what we need
right
um we then don't need this so we can
probably make
these look that way
uh which means this can just pass dirt
directly
and this can pass der by component
which looks a little better um and then
here we just need the sign
so you know this is just the sign for
zero
um
yeah so this is just i think the sine or
zero of
[Music]
the delta so the direction you're going
or trying to go the sine or zero of that
uh
which i guess we don't really have
here
so we don't really quite have that so um
so i'm not sure exactly what we're going
to do here
we're gonna think about that
separately
i guess i don't care
i guess we just probably don't care
um
because we're just testing
these voxels for being closer if they're
closer they're closer we don't care
about the fact that if one of the we
don't care about the optimization that
one of those steps might not need to be
tested because it's
movement portion the movement vector was
zero
so i think maybe we can just skip that
probably and be fine but there's other
things we want to do here which is we
need the
we need the thing for this so we need
the side
part of it um
so we need like the side part as well
um and that's just like you know
this
actual testing uh and since we're gonna
do that i suppose
we can just go ahead and compute both of
these so we can just say
uh yeah like
let's use delta p
is the thing we actually need so maybe
we just do der
and side and we just go like look
if der dot x is less than zero
[Music]
i'm sorry if delta p to x less than zero
then der dot x
equals um
negative one side dot x equals zero
right um and the else clause
is
the opposite
um so you know we can do that
and if we wrote that out maybe more
concisely
uh it would look like this so
uh negative 1 0 sorry negative 1 1.
something like this and then this one
just looks like
the exact same thing
um again just random
i'm not sure what the easiest way to put
in that information is there's a lot of
ways we could encode that
but basically that's what we need we
need to know what direction we're going
and we need to know where to look up in
the uh
voxel occupancy for testing right
so then when this happens we would call
update best with that best thing
uh and here would be the update best
part
we need um the voxel move
here uh we need like this to probably be
initialized
to f32 max right
so when we actually start this nonsense
we would say well the voxel move that
we're going to try
um
the best distance squared is
maybe this is just distance squared is
f32 max
and everything else um
we need to fill in here so we're going
to need we're going to need the 2p
like where we're trying to get to the
min corner
and the cell dim right and these are not
actually going to
cop they'll just be kind of filled in
because hopefully this would all be like
inlined away
but again we're not really trying to
make this fast yet
so one step at a time
all right so in here we have
a voxel min corner
we have i mean actually i guess we can
just have
a cell
well no we don't need that um
so i think that's what we need the
distance squared thing
is is just going to be distance squared
there
um
[Music]
the following we're just doing a version
of into real oh
all right the question mark
operator and c is so unsatisfying
sometimes
all right
all right um so
in update best we know we need
um a direction
we know that uh we need to set all this
stuff up for it which i
think it now would have so
what it would do is it would go okay
suppose we made the test cell and the
test cell
is going to be a rectum dim of the move
[Music]
um
the movement corner plus the offset so
that the new min corner
um or the test min corner is
the current min corner plus the
direction
times the dimension of the cell
so that's where we would move the test
cell therefore is that min
corner plus the dimension
and then we would say uh new
or test p
is the get closest point in box
so if we said inside that cell we're
testing what's the closest point
to where we're trying to go and then the
test dist squared
is going to be the uh distance squared
of
the place we're trying to get to versus
the closest that we actually got so
the vector from where we could get to to
where we'd like to go that's the test
distance squared
we then just accept it provisionally so
if the distance
that we had before is not as good
then we accept it
right now the problem is we need to
accept the min
corner we need the basement corner for
the other people who are moving
so this has to be aurigman corner
and best min corner right because these
are
two different things um
so we actually need best min corner
because we don't want to up we don't
want to check off of that we want to
keep the best mid corner moving while
the rigman corner stays where it is
um so i think it looks like that and
then in
here we have to set these so
the best min corner we don't really have
to set but we might as well
um and then this goes ahead and does the
updates eventually it says okay if we
got one
it just takes the new move if we didn't
get one
then we just assume we can't keep going
um so we stop right
um
yeah so anyway oh and here's that return
remember i was saying like once you
actually get a linking program see there
it's complaining because we didn't
return
result right so
um so anyway that is my argument for
roughly how this routine would work uh
it's probably not very good yet but
hey for one day's work that seems
okay right like it's okay
um so now we have to start probably like
stepping through this thing
and cleaning up our bugs and whatever
else
uh has to happen there um but that's the
idea
right so uh
what we want to do is we want to
set a breakpoint in
here uh and we want to step through this
thing and we want to see like what the
heck is going on
right
[Music]
um
yeah um so you know like we're doing
this
right and we we loop through here and we
see
you know i don't know what what this
looks like but let's take a look
so this direction is one negative one
one right
so oh we must be compiled in
release mode that's not gonna go well
seems like that happened an awful lot of
times
it should have only happened eight times
but
maybe it may have unrolled this loop
so let me uh i want to step into this
so i can watch what happens and clean up
stuff
uh as we go
so here we go um so let's take a look
like here's from p and 2p uh
it's a very slight motion um
slight motion in y uh
we're going from two uh
this looks right right that's negative
one
um and voxel min
corner um
[Music]
looks
correct because we're on point ones
you know point one is stupid uh
before i go any further i i think i
wanna
not do that um you know you don't pick a
decimal
on a binary machine it's just dumb
right um
so so maybe we say like something that's
an actual
a close two power you know what i'm
saying
um so that it can be represented
properly
uh so that way it's the closest point
like 2 5 or whatever
um and now you can see like how much
nicer these numbers are right they're
exact
because we picked a power of two instead
of a thing that
oops i don't know what i just did like
cleared that number or something
um so so that's just probably better
right
um so
all right uh so we pick a min corner
that
looks correct to me um
yeah i mean that's that's the correct
min
coroner uh
so i think we're good right
um we look to see
we're we're trying to go one negative
one
one right we look to see whether those
are not occupied
i guess they're not um
i mean we can see it looks like nobody
there's no
this is free movement right so you're
just allowed to go
wherever you want so we're saying that
you can move
diagonally right
and you don't actually want to in this
case
you only want to move in y so this isn't
a good move but it's
allowed right so we then say
well all right if this is the move
um
we take and we make a test min
corner that is
the original mid corner it should be
point
two in each direction it is right that's
exactly
what it should be for the diagonal move
you create a test cell uh you get a test
p
out of that um and
the the 2p i don't know we can't really
do the subtract
i'm gonna so just to make debugging
easier myself before i
finish this uh i i'm gonna do
like a delta p here
uh just so i can look inspect
what the difference is between the two
points
that it's looking at uh without me
having to go do that math in the
debugger myself
so i'm literally just replacing what was
on the interior here with a variable
that i can inspect
um just hey because debuggers still
really aren't what you'd like them to be
so you have to like manually
a lot of times move your code around to
you know
make it easier for you to watch what's
happening so
if i go ahead and step in to update best
now
i can look and see what that delta p is
um and what you can see here is the
separation
is uh
is a little nonsensical
yes
i'm not sure about this i want to verify
that this is right
so the test
cell
in this case
you're trying to get here
i just realized what this is doing
okay uh what i said was totally false
you don't want to start this with f32
max you need to start this with
whatever the closest thing you've ever
seen
was right
um and you
need to keep that through the entire
time
probably right
so you're probably going to do something
like this where you say the best
distance squared
is actually like the distance from the
best point
on this cell you know what i'm saying
uh so we say
you know
the distance squared is the distance
from the get closest point
in box to the 2p
right it's it's actually like from where
you are right now
so the starting cell
um that you just
initialize into
you probably need um
[Music]
that as your
test because you don't want to move out
of the best
cell that you had right
um so i think
let me just double check here i think
that's what we actually want so
let me just see if this now prevents a
move
what is happening did that not recompile
or something
why am i not stepping through actual
locations in the code
that's freaky
what the heck is do what is that doing
very nervous right now
that does not look like a sane debug
step
um where am i at on four coder these
days i i mean not for coder um
remedy bg
what version
so three five is the latest version and
we are not anywhere near that
um so that may be a mistake um
hold please
uh
oh please while i download this from hio
which as we know from
apple's lawyers in the epic trial
is just i mean
it's so risque the itch dot io store
oh my goodness
what even happens at the itch dot io
store think of the children
being corrupted at the the horrible
itch.io store that apple is so
valiantly and courageously protecting us
from um
you know without people like apple to
to prevent you from getting stuff on
your computer that you were trying to
get i just don't know where we would be
you know i mean
thank god they don't leave decisions up
to the people who bought the computer
i mean that would be
can you imagine allowing the person who
bought the computer to decide what to
install on the computer i don't even
know
that's just ridiculous
totally unacceptable and i'm just
thankful that we have
people like apple to tell us what we're
allowed to run because without that
i would just be i mean it's a big scary
world out there
and i just don't know what i would do
you know i mean i just don't know
i would probably just i would just be a
career criminal
by now if apple hadn't
protected me from the horrors of the
things on itch.io
like a debugger that i bought that i use
i mean it's just
it's unspeakable really
so thank you apple for all your
tireless hard work making sure that
i don't ever get to make a decision
about what happens
on a computer that was is great
it was really something the world needed
was more centralized control over
decision making that's that's the thing
that everyone says is great
um
that's that's that's what people say you
know it's what people have said
throughout history if we just
had a central authority that could tell
us what to do
and apple is helping to bring you that
world right you know
so it's good it's great
really really pleased great company
apple
fantastic you know
okay let's see if we can um
get better stepping here um i know that
like there was all these weird things
happening with visual studios like pdbs
and stuff
so we may just have needed nope it's
just busted i so i don't know what's
going on there
maybe x13 pixels can tell us sometime
um i have no idea why it is not able to
step over those lines properly
um but at least now it's not picking
those moves which is what i wanted to
make sure of
um but we kind of need to actually still
see what the heck is going on
um because you know i i
i still want to go step through this
routine um
and look for bugs and such
right um
[Music]
so so let me let me
before i go any further let me run this
in o2 and see what happened
right
yeah i have ordered new glasses i hope
they come
sometime soon but i'm not going to hold
my breath on that
so you can see this is still in a bit of
a in a bit of a bad state
um so we're not quite out of the woods
yet we still got a pretty janky
set of bugs in here uh but okay
so let's see if we can't step through
and
clean this up
no i didn't i didn't buy the uh
the glasses from apple
um you know i i don't do too much
politics on stream but
i will simply tell you that like the
arguments that people use for things
are really interesting because you can
tell that they're never
argument that they're that they just
want
they just like apple and want that to be
okay they're not arguing about it
because they actually thought through
all of the consequences or analogies to
what they're saying
they just like an apple product or an
apple operating system and they just
want that to be okay so they
say something that they think
is making an argument but it actually
isn't making an argument
right because a lot of people are like
well as long as you know up front
what it is it's okay or it's a private
company they should do what they want
all things
and you would never accept any of those
arguments
for anything else you know
if somebody honestly said to you
like you know looked you in the eye and
said
we don't need public accommodation law
consumer protection law lemon laws
disclosure laws
we don't need any of those things
because
as long as a company just says
here is what we do up front right
and some big long list of things that
everyone would agreed
was horrible you pick everything
you want that's horrible right every
last little thing
uh you know discriminatory like like
like we set which races are allowed to
be by the computer
we say whether men or women can buy the
computer exclusively
we d if it's completely broken when it
gets delivered to you
tough tough we're not going to refund it
right
laws are there because a
transaction should only occur
under circumstances where the person
gives you the money
and you give them back a thing that is
then theirs
and we have spent so many
decades cleaning up all
the authoritarian crap that
companies or governments or everyone
else
tried to do using all those same excuses
it's just a private party it's they
should you knew
what it was at a time it's like no we
don't want
private parties doing these things
being able to purchase things and then
you own them
is something we fought for not allowing
a company to discriminate
to censor to decide what you can do
to take back something you bought those
are things that were in the law
and people just forget this
somehow in their mind none of those
things existed
the world just started and companies
were these beautiful
benefactors that that never
discriminated against anybody
that never shipped defective products
and didn't give you refunds
that never treated their workers
horribly that never did any of these
things
so if we just why are you getting so
upset about this why are you so why do
you want to tell this private company
what to do
have you read a book like i don't know
what to tell you
companies are horrible that's
you want things like capitalism
to have markets where consumers can make
choices so that we can allocate
resources properly
that's it we don't want corporations
competing over
controlling their users that's
absolutely ridiculous read a freaking
book
if you think that's a good idea it's
it's nuts
so none of those arguments to me hold
any water at all
it's obvious that you need strong
consumer protection
strong uh like
things that say that a consumer is a
person who presents their money
and receives the product and that is the
end of it and the company
gets no say in who that consumer can be
or what that consumer can do with the
product after they purchase it
that is up to the citizen and their
government
alone and as a corporation what you get
to do
is hand me the freaking thing i bought
yet competition is not what you think it
is competition is a way of allocating
resources
right and once those resources get
allocated
you end up with lock-in so competition
doesn't solve mistreatment if it did you
wouldn't need any of these other laws
if competition worked the way that
you're saying it does
you wouldn't need any of these other
laws you wouldn't need
anti-discrimination laws
you wouldn't need you wouldn't need
title seven right
you wouldn't need consumer protection
laws you wouldn't need
courts at all you you would
it would just be competition nobody
believes that's true
nobody people just say it because they
want
people like apple to be okay they just
like apple
competition all it does is at the outset
it allocates resources somewhere that is
all it does
it can't do anything else it does not
fix social problems
period right
once you have resources allocated you
can't really change it very effectively
competition doesn't do that
it's why you have anti-monopoly law it's
how i have all this stuff
i i don't know what to tell you like did
you if you've never heard of att like
have you never heard
of like what trusts were have you never
heard of railroads i don't know what to
tell you
i love capitalism i think it's a great
way to allocate resources it only works
when you have already created the
circumstances under which you want that
competition to occur optimally
you simply cannot trust it to solve any
other problems for you
it's not what it does right
it's not what it does
all right let's do one more step through
so this test is pretty obvious that just
does all eight corners
i don't think there's much because that
just got wholesale imported from the
other thing
no matter what that returns this should
always terminate
this loop should always terminate fairly
so we shouldn't have to care about this
we should just assume that whatever this
returns it returns we never have to
think about it again
right and then if there's bugs in this
that's a separate thing that we would
debug
so it's this part here that we actually
care about and it's the update best
termination
criteria that's the problem here
right this probably doesn't work right
or something
so we need to make sure that this um
correctly always terminates you know it
can't ever get into a loop
where we're like constantly go where
we're keep trying
new and new cells we need to terminate
after a few simple steps
right um so let's go ahead
and see
what we're doing here so we look at bess
we look at best and we see that we have
a distance squared of zero which means
that
uh this doesn't need to happen right
um so this one's just gonna exit out
immediately and we don't care
uh so what we wanna do is get to a one
of these that doesn't work
near as well right so we want one yeah
like that where there actually is a
distance so this means we're trying to
move from this cell to
another cell right um
if this makes sense uh and uh
we just want to go ahead and uh someone
said i love capitalism when it works for
me screw other people yeah
yes like that seems to be what people
say
right they just they don't seem to want
to
they don't seem to want to engage with
the fact that all these laws were made
for a reason
you had to make these laws because
competition
didn't produce
a fair marketplace
for humans for citizens
in the worst possible ways in horrific
ways right and somehow they just
throw that out the window because they
like apple or something
it's not just apple it's other people
they argue this for
it's it's not okay right i am not a
person who wants to throw out capitalism
i think it does a great job
of optimization right
but it has to be coupled with
restrictions
on what can be optimized because if you
just
let capitalism optimize it will optimize
on everything
including screwing the customer
right because as soon as a corporation
can start to screw a customer because
like they don't have
enough other options or the the cost of
the barrier to entry to that market
grows too high
it will just straight up optimize
screwing the customer all the way down
to zero
right and so
history shows this unequivocally like
there is no argument that that is what
happens
at all from anybody even people who are
extremely pro-capitalism which i am
right i think it's a great resource
allocation strategy
there are no examples that i know of in
history
of allocation strategies that beat it
but you can't just expect it to solve
all problems it just optimizes
that's all it does if you don't set up
your optimization problem first
it will optimize all sorts of things
that are horrible
and that's exactly what you're seeing
that's exactly what apple does and
facebook right now
that's what you're seeing you're just
seeing them optimize variables
that humans really shouldn't optimize
and you just need some laws you need
some laws that say nope we're not going
to do that
you're not going to collect information
from customers you're not gonna get to
decide
what software runs on what hardware we
don't want that to be optimized
because we are going to let the citizens
decide
what they do with what they purchase and
be free
from your intrusion right
in my mind that is a very very valid
argument
and you can have arguments against it
but one of them is not it's a private
company or capitalism
always work like those are not real
arguments because it's so trivial to
point to all the ways that that's not
true
and you obviously disagree with that
because if you really thought that was
true
you would argue for repealing all of
this stuff you'd argue for appealing
title vii
you'd argue for repealing um all public
accommodation
sections in all state laws you'd argue
for repealing
all workplace protection safety because
if it was just competition
that solved these problems you wouldn't
need any of those things right
so if you want to make that argument
that we repeal all of that stuff
make it but if you
aren't willing to say that all of those
laws need to be repealed then your
argument doesn't make sense so you need
a different one
you need a different argument for why
you think it's okay for corporations to
do these things
that they are a corporation is not a
valid reason because there are so many
examples of when you wouldn't
have accepted that argument so you need
a different one
you need to explain why this thing
specifically benefits the public good
more than it hurts you need an actual
carefully described argument for why
having a consumer not own a device they
buy
is better than having them actually own
it right
why why you think that allowing a
corporation to control
a customer's decisions after their
purchase
is a positive social human development
that you support
so that's what you gotta do right
yeah the handmade political podcast
no one's gonna go on that podcast
that'd be a lonely podcast with me just
complaining about stuff that seems so
obvious that i don't even know why i'm
explaining it because it's like i don't
understand
i don't even understand how people get
to the other conclusions other than
simply
this is what we wanted like i i i can't
even wrap my head around people who
argue for apple's behavior
like the only thing it sounds like to me
is i just like apple products that's all
i hear
because i don't ever actually hear an
argument
all of the things that they say make no
sense if you
wanted a infantile storefront
you could just get one like nothing's
stopping you
like like on windows if you want you can
just choose to only install games from
steam
nobody stops you from doing that if you
think that valve is doing a better job
of that
you never have to go to itch.io
right
i i don't know if your argument is like
well grandma
and she doesn't know it's like okay are
you actually saying that the world
should be governed
in a in a way that is uh
entirely determined on whether you think
your grandmother can handle it
like i i what i mean in that case we
wouldn't have
cars right cause you know that grandma's
gonna get in an accident that's why we
took away her license i just
it's so weirdly it's like an attic
filled with like cobwebs in the part of
the brain that was supposed to come up
with an
actual argument right
um anyway uh so this is the part of the
code
going back to here that i don't really
know and it's hard for me to step
through because it's doing like this
weird thing
i'm not sure if what's happening there
is we're stepping over these
because they're not triggering and let
me just see if that's the case so that
we at least know what we're looking at
because the debugger is doing a weird
thing there
and and i just don't know why it's doing
that right
um
oh well first of all these are backwards
that should not have caused a problem
though so that's a little scary
um so we're still buggy but
we forgot the knot forgot the not
i can't even blame that on the politics
because i wrote this before
um the apple garbage
um so i think uh
in here we've done the occupied we do
the not occupied for all these
this is this is still buggy though
because it should have still always
terminated
so it's still not it's not right
you know um we must still have a bug in
how this works
uh separately from that
um oh and it steps right now though
it steps right now so we can actually
see it um
okay so it picks up the bests if you can
do it it's picking up the best this
one's a distance squared of zero anyway
um so we don't have to care uh
about that and we want to look at one
uh that actually has a distance squared
like that one so that's good
uh when we produce the distance squared
you know let's go down here
uh when you produce this squared we can
look and see uh
how we do so we look here and we say
okay are we gonna update the best
min corner um based on on
a diagonal move let's see like let's
just try to think it through and see
what we would expect like like is this
is this thing we we think should be
happening
or not right so here's the place we're
trying to get to
we're trying to get to this 2p here um
and
we're starting off at this min corner
so you can see that like the min corner
that
we're trying to get to and the place
that we are now are like
we're totally in the right location
except for the y so what we want to do
really
is just move backwards in y we just want
to go negative y
right um so let's take a look at what
happens
when we update best you can see that
that would have got closer which may be
true because it's a diagonal move
what we want to do here is that probably
won't trigger
this should trigger hopefully and it did
so
that's hopefully the one we pick and it
is so now we
accept this new min corner the best min
corner here
which is a one y move right
um
[Music]
although it's not
oh yes it is i'm sorry we're moving from
oregon corner yes
so that should just move uh hopefully
along that
voxel now um and
and that's it right hopefully
it will just go until it gets
close enough to count
and we'll see if it terminates
[Laughter]
okay
when we move that out of the loop kinda
gotta reset the move condition right
yeah uh we could just check to see if
the
minimum distance decreased um
that might be better uh
but i think we're good now that was
probably the only problem
um the routine probably still has tons
of bugs in it we'll look at them
next week uh let's see what the status
is
if we run it now um hey look it's
running
um you can see that it's weirdly
it's moving in the direction it should
but it's only moving like
one voxel step like that was weird
it's like not do we not return the right
oh
it's because we're never setting this so
when we leave this routine um best
needs to create that best cell so
so this thing here um
so so like
this is probably not exactly the way you
would want to do this
but it would be like you know
that we weren't actually using the
result from that
uh and we we want to right so let's
let's see what happens there
so there's our like collision detector
maybe
collision detecting we don't really know
so it looks like that's able to
penetrate into the wall
in a weird way so we're not out of the
woods yet
um i think we're in good shape but we're
not out of the woods yet
right we're getting there but but not
yet
um
so i'm gonna leave it there and we'll go
uh we'll we'll go ahead and um
and uh pick it up next time
oh the j the the stream title is always
a joke
i just randomly said it
oh hey x13 yeah it
oddly enough changed when i set when i
switched to the not
so it must have been something that
visual studios pdb was outputting
right like because when i changed when
the code changed
it stopped happening so it's it's some
kind of weird pdb
thing probably because of a multi-line
the multi-line or
statement it was in debug mode
it was a debug pdb and it was when you
do it without the not
and and i don't know what was going on
there
uh right
so can you explain how that .125 thing
works
um sure so
when you uh are using floating point
numbers
floating point numbers are
basically just if if you
think about how you represent
decimals like regular
numbers that we think of as humans if
you think about how they're represented
in binary
you have bits that represent powers of
two right
so when you're trying to represent a
number that's not fractional
it's a little bit easier because you're
just thinking
oh i've got the digits if i want to
write something like
9 right
then i just say well that's going to be
like a 1
plus an 8 so i set the 1
bit and i set the 8 bit and now i've got
9 right
when you're looking at fractional values
that is not
how it actually works the way that
fractional values work is
each one of the uh
bits divides by that power of two
right so if you set the bit
for divide by half
you get 0.5 if you set the bit for
dividing
again you know next place down you would
get you know 0.25 or whatever right
so you can and this is not quite true
because this is not fixed point
there's also there's an exponent so what
you're actually doing is locating around
one of those
it's a little bit hard to explain but
the without a diagram and going into
floating point numbers more
but you're finding the power of two that
divides to as close as where you
are and then right you're putting
in some mantissa on top of that right
so no matter what you do when you're
talking about dividing by powers of two
you can never divide uh by like
you can never divide you can never get
an exact
fraction if that fraction could not have
been expressed
by dividing by powers of 2. you see what
i'm saying
right so if you want to have something
that has
a divide by a power of
5 in there which is what
point 1 would be
you're never going to get it because no
combination
of divides by powers of 2 it will ever
get you a power of 5
right one over five cannot be
represented
by any combination of one over
you know two to the something times two
to something times you know whatever
kinds of things
right you know what i'm saying so
if you are setting up something like a
grid step
you can get your numbers to be exact by
setting that grid's distance to be
a power of two divide right
um so the reason i picked 0.125 was i
wanted the numbers to not have all these
trailing
uh fractional parts because if i pick
like a decimal number they're going to
because it's the computer just trying to
represent it as close as possible and
it's getting
really close like don't get me wrong
but it's not exact whereas if i just
pick a power of something that's a
straight up
easy divide by a power of two of some
kind
then that's just trivial for it to be
exact it just sets the exponent to that
and
that's it right and you've got it
doesn't matter how many bits of
precision in the mantissa there are it
just
works right um
that's that's really it uh
um there's also like a standard
reference for this stuff
um
that's the one but let's use a oops
i'm getting binge here
so here you go um this is like the sort
of standard reference
right for this sort of stuff um
which you can peruse
oh and mike biddlecombe was saying that
that bruce dawson has some posts on this
um i have not read that but uh
presumably uh mike can post the link
to him it looks like someone else posted
a floating point guide link as well
how much of a difference can this minute
computation really make in real time
are you talking about the .125 versus
point one thing
is that is that what you're asking about
i'm not not sure what you're asking
is that what you're asking about
um so uh i
just in case it wasn't clear oh well i
guess which it wasn't
i didn't change those because i was
afraid
that the math would work poorly
although maybe you get some benefit from
that as well but
i did it so i could read the numbers
easier
right so what happens is
when you when you look
in the debugger and you're trying to
read numbers if i set this thing right
to point one you know
and i i'm going through the debugger and
i'm trying to read it
then the debugger is just pulling values
out of the stack
and showing them to me it doesn't know
where they came from
or if they should be rounded or anything
like that it doesn't know what i'm
writing
right so it's just going to show me the
value
the floating point value and i'm going
to see
all of this crap right
that's all you're gonna see is that kind
of thing
and the reason is because it was trying
there to say 0.7
but you can't represent 0.7
so the actual floating point value is
not 0.7
and if the debugger rounded it to 0.7
you'd be pretty mad because it's lying
to you
you're like that's not what's in i know
0.7 is not
in that floating point number because
you can't make 0.7 in a floating point
number
right so it's
it's all i was doing was just
making it easier on us because i know
we're going to debug this next
i mean i wanna debug a little bit today
and then i know that's what i'm gonna be
doing is reading through that and being
like carefully like analyzing what's
going on i just
if i set it to an easy divide power two
all i'm doing is buying myself a little
uh convenience because now when we look
um at the values well if it actually
that not actually compile there we go
there we go now uh when we look at the
values
what you can see is that well and this
is a bad example because the 2p
i shouldn't have picked this the 2p is
the thing that comes in from the engine
which can be anywhere
um this is actually the part i was
talking about
i should reshow it to you because i had
the wrong thing open sorry about that
so at point one
uh we look at what the corner is that it
finds which is the thing that it's you
know
aligning to and you can see you get all
these like point two
point two point two right kind of things
in there
um and as i go through it right when i
step
through i get weird twelve point two
nine nine nine nine nine
right and so all i was doing the only
thing i was trying to do is say look
let's just always use a step size that
happens to be exactly representable and
float
for legibility
that's it no no point to it
whatsoever so now look at they're all
nice
and clean right that was it
um i don't expect the math to come out
particularly much better
or something although that can happen
depending on what you're doing
right um so
[Music]
how long have you worked on this project
i don't know how to add it up
so we only 100 of the programming
happens on
on stream and we only program a few
hours a week
on the stream but
uh probably at least a thousand a
thousand hours
maybe uh if you put that into work terms
like how long i've been working on the
project so
like uh where's the speed crunch thingy
so i don't really know but maybe it's
something like a thousand hours
so if you worked you know i don't know
programming hours a week and the other
10 hours you were in
really bad meetings where people said
stupid stuff to you
it's about 30 weeks let's say
so we were working on it you know
oops
about two-thirds of the year if it was
real work
um so figure two-thirds of a year worth
of work
has gone into this if you count
how depending how you count it on-stream
programming is
harder than off-stream programming so
you know
new to this thank you for saying that it
looks like a render
um i i was i was proud of the lighting
i'm not gonna lie
i was proud of getting the lighting set
up i went many years without ever having
any lighting
and i was like we're gonna fix this
yeah we we need at one of these streams
we gotta just have a meeting
just you know we'll we'll get some of
you
y'all on the chat will
[Music]
like use a discord room to get like 10
people
in the thing and the only rule will be
that for the entire time
nobody can say anything provocative
interesting or useful
like everyone just has to like say stuff
like
how are we going to factor in the
user experience to this piece of code or
like like just you just have to say like
vague
unproductive unprovocative comments
for like an hour and make sure that
nothing is
is achieved and then we can call that
like our official handmade meeting
uh
is i o auto rare revs i don't know how
to pronounce that
um it's just mirrored
bulmanator totally
totally galactus
it's galactus pain
ezio auditora
something like that all right
uh yeah i agree dynamically should be
said
scale scale we should spend a lot of
time worrying about if it's going to
scale
you know we should just say stuff about
is this going to scale i think this will
scale it will scale better
if we something
you know we've got to be scared scales
got to be in there
dynamic and scale very important
maybe we can just dynamically scale
everything will be
very dynamic and very scalable and very
dynamically scalable
i think
oh ezio auditore is the main character
from assassin's creed
ii okay
all right
i think i'm pretty happy with how that
collision routine is coming i'm
i'm pretty comfortable that to say that
like maybe next weekend i think we'll be
able to to clean it up
and have something sort of working um
but who knows that could be a lie we'll
see
all right uh thanks everyone for joining
me for an episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always um if you do want to follow along
with the series at home and maybe you
want to go see if you can make sure that
routine works before i get to it
you can always pre-order the game on
handmadeer.org and it comes with a
source code
so you can play around with it if you
want to and
yeah that collision detection routine i
think is is in pretty good shape
it just needs it needs to be gone
through with a fine-tooth comb
so uh when we get to that i think we'll
be happy
and then we can do some battle code
which we don't really know what we're
gonna do
that's game design decision stuff which
is not really what i do
but we'll make some decisions um
love galactus uh we'll push this out a
couple years
so until next week have fun program
everyone and i'll see you on the
internet take it easy everybody
you