all right hello everyone I know this is
a weird back rub to be started backdrop
time starting the stream on but it's
because we had a pretty stream question
that was about C runtime libraries so
there's a little bit more busy you know
what I'll just here we go I'll just get
it back to normal this is what you would
normally see right there you go hello
everyone and welcome to handmade hero
it's show a recode a complete game live
on twitch no engines no libraries and I
think you know I was describing this to
some folks on Twitter and they seem to
really like the description of the game
that it is a game about limbless
children and demons which is bound to be
the feel-good hit of the summer which
ever summer we decide to release it in I
don't know why they particularly liked
that description but you know who
doesn't love them as children and demons
I mean that is a good that is good
wholesome family entertainment right
there I don't think anyone would ever
disagree anyway that said we finished up
some general purpose allocation stuff
last week it took a lot less time than I
thought it was going to take even to
just do the rudimentary one and doing an
optimized one really has to wait until
we put a lot more pressure on the asset
system and can even see you know where
or if it falls down so we were kind of
like alright I guess that was it for the
general purpose allocator it just kind
of happened and and that was it so what
I wanted to do is move on probably to
the next thing on our list really and
that you know is going to be debug code
I think it's the most logical thing to
do we're getting towards the point in
our engine dev here where we want to
start locking things down cleaning them
up and you know just doing sort of a
general thoroughness pass we've got some
bugs and things that we know we have to
fix later you know things that are not
at the level of quality that we want
them to be that we made note of and so
what we want to do is kind of move
towards a place where we can be happy
with the basic engine layer that we have
put in place so that we can move on to
working on the game and being confident
that all the services that we made will
be reliable and we won't have to
constantly be debugging them or fussing
with them
and will only have to actually do new
engine work driven by gameplay things
that we want rather than it being some
kind of a maintenance headache for us
right and so what I thought we do today
is probably start down the road towards
fonts because in order to do much in the
way of debug code you know we kind of
need to be able to display text on the
screen because we're gonna want to print
out you know values and and just you
know a sort of things that we're gonna
we're gonna want displayed are gonna
require some kind of font work so I
thought that's what we do today so I'll
talk a little bit about fonts and on the
blackboard and then we'll do some code
today is day 162 so if you'd like to
follow along at home and you are someone
who has pre-ordered the game on handmade
hero org you want to unpack day 161 s
source code so that you will be at the
same state I am and that way you can
follow along with the code exactly as I
am opening it up as we speak so yeah so
I believe like I said I don't think we
left anything dangling really other than
saying that we probably should optimize
the general-purpose allocator once we
have some workloads but that's a little
bit further down the line so I'm gonna
go ahead and just double check that
everything was was fine and that I'm
pretty sure that it was so yeah like if
I go here we're still all totally
correct nothing nothing sorry happening
we don't have assets we cashing in there
yet so we have we still have blinking
when things for a slow but that's about
it
and the pre caching is really just
something that's more about us
eventually deciding how those calls are
going to get issued because the ax asset
system actually already supports it as
well so I think everything's pretty good
there and so I think what I'd like to do
is start to figure out how we can do
some better debug overlaying write some
stuff that we can put on the screen now
to kind of give us a little bit more
ability to have insight into what our
code is doing a lot of times people ask
on the stream in the QA they'll say
stuff like how do you feel about
test-driven development
and just one of the things that's often
true about Game Code is that the hard
things to debug are often not really
super possible to tackle with
test-driven development test room driven
development really only tackles the easy
problems in game development ones that
really just don't super need to be
worried about all that much because they
won't be accounting for the majority of
your dev time on in a lot of cases and
so what is actually more important in
game development than test-driven
development usually is like
visualization oriented development how
you know however you might say that
which is to say that as your game kind
of goes through more and more
get-getting goes up in levels of
complexity simply looking at the end
results is oftentimes not sufficient to
know whether things are really working
or not because there can be a lot of
bugs lurking in the code that are very
complicated and it would be difficult to
ever diagnosed with a test or with or
simply by inspection or simply by
looking at the end results and so what
we tend to do a lot of times is we tend
to write visualizations like HUDs
overlays and stuff that try to show us a
lot of heartbeat information to see what
the game is actually doing so that we
can use our intuitions and the technical
patterns look like they might be wrong
so that we can investigate further and
get some of those harder more subtle
bugs that are very difficult to find any
other way and so that is one of the main
reasons we're going to need fonts this
game I don't know that the game itself
will be all that heavy in terms of
printing text out but I think for our
visualization we will want it in sooner
rather than later and so I'd like to
talk a little bit about how fonts work
in general and then how we can implement
fonts in our game so here we go here's
day 162 and we'll say fonts but
sometimes I like to call it
fonts with a c e at the end I don't know
why I feel like that's just kind of fun
to say fonts it sounds the same
but it looks kind of interesting and
cooler so anyway day 162 fonts what are
we talking about when we talk about
fonts what is incorporated in a font
system right
I'll start from the very basics for
people who don't know any type odd Rafi
or any anything and we'll kind of work
our way up to so that where no matter
where you are on the spectrum of knowing
about fonts we will we will bring you up
to speed okay so obviously we kind of
all know just no matter who you are if
you've ever worked on computer you have
a passing familiarity that a font is
something that kind of describes the way
text looks on the screen right and
you've probably seen you know files
TTF files which are like true type font
files right which are the ones that we
see on windows a lot but there's also
like Adobe type one in fact I don't know
if you saw recently Microsoft had a
really bad hack involving Adobe type 1
fonts where people could root your
machine by including Adobe type 1 fonts
on the web right and you know there's
been other types there's meta font is
another kind which was an old thing in
late a crate
there's a number of different types of
fonts out there thought sort of file
formats right and what these are is
these are ways of describing what the
actual characters in fonts are supposed
to look like and they're usually
described in terms of outlines so
typically for example like in a true
type font file for example or Adobe type
1 font file typically what you're doing
is you're doing something if you've ever
seen like Adobe Illustrator or something
you're typically doing something like
that
so a typical font file might include
something you know like some vertices to
describe like the letter T right
they might describe something that looks
like this right where you were kind of
saying okay we have some coordinates of
some vertices and we have some curves in
this case not really curves but lines
that go between the vertices and the way
that we're gonna describe the shape of
the T is to say that we're basically
talking about a filled area that exists
within these points just like you would
again in Adobe Illustrator and similarly
you know if for a curved shape right
then what you're gonna have is you're
gonna have something where you have
points and those points are going to
have like Bezier curve handles or
something like this which we've talked a
bit a little bit about
I also have a video online about
interpolation for Bezier curves which
isn't that really something we need to
go over at the moment we'll probably go
over it a little bit later in handmade
hero but point being there like those
things you see in drawing packages where
you specify you know two points and and
then two points that are sort of off of
those points and you kind of get these
little handles right and then it draws
like a curve based on the points and the
handles and like as you move the handle
around the shape of the curve changes
right you might get something that
looked like that but again it's the
exact same concept as the lines it's
just saying here's a filled shape you
know and we're gonna fill it in okay so
that's the first part that's the first
part of what's happening in a font file
right is it's basically describing some
filled shape that is from you know for
all intents and purposes
resolution-independent meaning there's
not really an ocean of pixels here
necessarily there is a little bit of a
thing called hinting which I'll briefly
mention but we don't really care about
it so much but for the most part we're
not really talking about pixels here
we're just talking about an abstract
shape and that abstract shape could be
scaled as big or as little as you want
it and it would still be able to be
infinitely precise because again it's
not talking about individual pixels it's
talking about just that shape so just
like in Adobe Illustrator versus Adobe
Photoshop you know in Adobe Illustrator
you can you know make the shapes and you
can scale them any size in Photoshop you
paint on the pixels and then that's you
know if you resize it it gets blurrier
or heart you know right it's the same
deal right so we're talking about
continuous shapes not pixels and the
reason behind that is because people
want to be able to ship one font file
that allows them to use that font at any
scale right you want to be able to ship
you know Times New Roman and be able to
say I want it 20 points 30 points
whatever right and it gets bigger or
smaller just like you do you know in any
package that you use so that's the first
thing that they do is try to describe a
relatively resolution-independent
outline shape for the font that would
allow a program that wanted to fill it
in to fill it in now
the second thing that those that these
do is they describe a mapping from some
character set encoding to these outline
shapes right and what do I mean by
character set encoding okay what does
that mean what I mean by character set
encoding is that in the English language
right or in Chinese or something right
we all know what we're talking about
when we say like the letter T right or
the symbol for meat or something right I
think it's got like a little it's like
something that looks like this right or
whatever and I'm trying to give an
example in Chinese balance speak Chinese
so it's hard for me but anyway there are
these glyphs right and so the font file
can describe this glyph it can describe
T it can describe the symbol for meat
right or whatever but how do you know
what symbol is describing right how do
you know we can't just give it you know
some arbitrary number like okay this is
you know glyph 17 in the file well how
do I know when I wanted to actually show
the symbol for me how do I know that was
glyph 17 right and so the answer that
you know we've come up with and could
the computing world is to have these
character set and codings and one of
them you're very familiar with if you've
watched a made here from the very very
beginning in fact I think it was maybe
in the intro to see print out now maybe
I don't even know if we did it in ham it
here oh it might have been even the pre
the test thing where I did a little bit
of C stuff but basically there's ASCII /
ANSI encoding for four characters
there's basically a character set
encoding that allows you to do you know
most like Roman derived languages in a
standard way where we basically just
defined what all the characters are
right we basically said okay you know if
you're reading Spanish or English or
French or something we have mapped sort
of in a definitive way that everyone has
agreed to use we have mapped all of the
characters to some symbols so we just
know that oh is 79 right like that's
just what we know so inside
file we could say something like we are
using an ASCII encoding so when we tell
you that this glyph corresponds right to
you know
index 80 or something we know that
that's going to be I guess I'm sorry
that's P right we know that that's P so
in the case I gave of T we would know
that we would put 84 as a numerical tag
on this T we'd say 84 is the T right and
so the choice of character set encoding
is very important because it defines
what characters you even can encode now
for example the symbol for meat in
Chinese has no encoding in ASCII you
can't encode it so if you were to pick a
font description that only allowed you
to use ASCII you would not actually be
able to include that character in your
font it just wouldn't happen because
you'd have no way of even telling
someone what it was now what you could
do instead is say okay you know what I
didn't really need this weird block
shape that's like number 2 23 and
extended ASCII so I just said like okay
that's gonna be the meet symbol and just
in my game I know to use that right you
could do that another thing you could do
is thing you use the thing called code
pages which are like ways of switching
out ASCII for a different set encoding
that would only work in for like say
Chinese or something
but again you haven't really solved the
problem and with only 256 glyphs which
is all you're gonna get out of ASCII
anyway you're not going to be able to do
something like Chinese which has gonna
have at least 3000 symbols even in a
basic situation and up to 30 to 40,000
symbols in the case of one that was
supposed to encompass the entire you
know archival you know ancient set where
you were going back through all you know
all the symbols that have ever been used
in Chinese lettering right so what we've
done recently is we've moved to a thing
called Unicode as the more standard
thing right this is kind of the older
school approach this is like the newer
school approach right and what Unicode
is is Unicode is a way of encoding
drastically more characters it goes up
to 16 bits in the naive implementation
like with Windows a thing called utf-16
and then it goes in utf-8 which is
a different encoding of Unicode it
actually can go above 16 bits can
actually do more and so look as we know
on animate Hiro 65536 right we know that
16 bits would give you 65,000 symbols
that's quite a few symbols that's
awesome
but utf-8 allows even more cuz it's
basically a variable length encoding
where it's still 8-bit characters just
like ASCII is but you can kind of double
up the characters and say that like a
particular character can say oh there's
another character coming after me that
combines with me to produce the actual
value and so you can kind of like chain
them to be as long as you want at that
point so you can get up to 24 bit of the
baptists pace which is you know 60
million glyphs right so so basically
Unicode is is the way that we sort of
broke in through that the ASCII table
that was just you know one byte per
character that which was insufficient so
now what Unicode is you know it kind of
has a good and a bad to it if you will
the good thing about Unicode is that
every character has a unique identifier
well it's not quite what I mean to say
but all glyphs have sort of found their
home in Unicode right so it doesn't
matter what random language you want to
do even if it's one that like isn't even
spoken anymore right
somebody somewhere hopefully has
allocated some set of the Unicode
mapping and said here is where those
symbols go right and what that means is
a single thought could literally if it
wanted to describe all of the symbols
that all humans have ever used to ever
write anything down like period right
and that's pretty cool but the problem
with that is that you're stuck with that
in giant encoding right so you can't
just use a table that 65k entries long
or or more like like 16 million entries
long that'd be a crazy huge table to use
in your game of fonts most of which
would be 0 because your game isn't
translated into Sanskrit right your game
isn't translated into all of these
archival languages potentially right
your game just
isn't gonna use all those you don't have
the font for it anyway
you're never gonna slay them so usually
what ends up having to happen and the
thing that's a little bit nastier about
Unicode is typically you have to sort of
treat Unicode as a as an intermediary
mapping because your lookups cannot be
dense anymore so typically what ends up
happening is you've got some kind of a
translation process that you go through
so you know if you wanted to use Unicode
it's typically going through some kind
of a mapping to finally get you into a
dense table of what does my font
actually have in it and that would be
dense right so I have a table of just
you know this font has 500 glyphs in it
right and Unicode is this gigantic you
know 24-bit address space or something
right it's not actually 24-bit I don't
think but you know somewhere up there
over 16 bits of address space you know I
go through a mapping that's a some way
of crunching this down to actually get
it to figure out where in this dense
table of actual font glyphs I'm actually
trying to look for the font that I want
so it's just like you'd be aware of like
Unicode just kind of has this nasty
property of because it's supposed to be
a universal encoding that can describe
any glyph it's actually not very good
for describing the glyphs that you have
so typically what you end up doing if
you want to support arbitrary languages
in a system is yes you accept Unicode as
your encoding but then whenever you get
one and you want to actually start
working with it to display something on
the screen you go through some kind of
mapping that will put you into the right
place in your table of glyphs you
actually right
okay so back to our font files so what
the font file ends up being at the end
of the day is typically something like a
Unicode oh and by the way I didn't
actually say it they are called these
the sort of entries into the Unicode
table they are called code points so
when you hear someone say a Unicode code
point they are referring to that
numerical slot that has been reserved
for this glyph slot sixty-three thousand
four hundred and fifty two or right
which corresponds to whatever glyph
that's like a Unicode code point that's
typically what that phrase is used to
describe right yeah so anyway so that's
typically what ends up being in
something like a font file is it will be
something like here is an outline of a
tea here is the Unicode code point right
that describes which glyph I'm talking
about so now the code knows okay that's
an English letter T okay I get it right
or that's the Chinese symbol for meat
right I get it so now there's it's
basically like a you know a way of
bridging that gap of I've just got a
bunch of outlines in this file I need
some way of telling you what do they
actually mean to a human who spoke this
language what do they mean and that's
what it tells you right so the code
point is almost all the information we
need almost all right we've got a glyph
we've got the code point but it's not
quite enough yet to actually constitute
a useful font and the reason is because
we don't actually know how to start
assembling multiple characters together
into words so let me tell you a little
bit about basic typography here I'm not
going to harp on it because your
handmade Hiro is not about text so we
don't have to be expert typographers to
do the implementation of the font system
in handmade here right if you were doing
a game that was all about fonts you
would want to be an expert typographer
certainly but I'll give you a little bit
of the basics so in typography right
there's basically everything is about
sort of the solids and the empty spaces
and the solids of the
the shapes they make and how they like
interrelate they spend a tremendous
amount of time thinking all of this
through and they have a bunch of
properties about fonts that they think
about so for example you might take the
letter G and if you wanted to talk about
that shape there's a number of things
that you could talk about you could talk
about the fact that for example the G
unlike the H in a standard font you
might say that the G has a descender in
typography speak which is this bit that
comes below sort of the line here and
then you might say that the H had like
an ascender which is something that kind
of comes up above this right there's
ways that they describe these things but
this line right here is often referred
to as a base line right and so one of
the things that is described oftentimes
in a font file is what is that base line
and what are the characters represented
at write how does the character glyph
get positioned relative to the base line
might be a piece of information that's
necessary in the font file right
similarly something like what is the
maximum descender height right like of
all of the characters in this font
what's the one that goes down the
farthest of all of the ascenders what's
the one that goes up the highest and
again these are things to allow you to
know when you're gonna go use this font
what is its general span vertically and
what is the actual region that it
actually typically uses right what is
another one would be what's the line
height meaning what did the photographer
created a spot envisioned being the
spacing between lines in a normal
scenario like you know if I was gonna
put the next character down here where
would it be right so you start to have
some information like that but most
important of all and unfortunately a lot
of fonts just don't even do this very
well but ideally speaking your font file
has a thing called kerning kerning
information and what kerning is is
kerning is a way of understanding how to
adjust the positioning of letters
rasaan Tilly based on which pair of
letters you're talking about okay and so
to understand the difference between
these things you first have to sort of
think of the difference between mono and
proportional right fonts which you've
probably seen before right a mono or
mono spaced might be the more
appropriate term right mono spaced font
a mono spaced font is the old-school
kind that was on typewriters and
terminals when they did not have the
level of sophistication necessary to
advance the right position by a variable
number number of pixels or space on the
typed page or whatever right and so what
happened was a font just had to have an
equal amount of space so if I had a G
and I had an i they both had to take up
the exact same amount of space width
wise which looks pretty dumb because
there's this giant gap on either side of
the eye right because if you were to
make it the size that you would normally
want to make the eye the G would like
sort of overflow it right so you kind of
had to adjust it to make it some kind of
uncomfortable size that was too big for
some letters and too small for others
but you know it kind of was like the
best you could do right and so as you
typed away it would just move by that
amount and you would end up with
something like the word Gil
would look something like that right
where the spacing was consistent between
each of the center points and it would
look really stupid because the way that
font ographers who laid it out in LED
would have done it would be like that
which looks a lot more natural and is
easier to use and also helps articulate
the difference between spaces in between
letters which are not what you want to
focus on when you're reading and space
in between words which is what you do
because it helps you tell right words or
recognize kind of as a chunk and so you
want them to group together cleanly and
not have the person be confused about
what is a space and what is the word
right that's not a good thing from a
typography standpoint okay so once we
have the sophistication to do so
proportional fonts were definitely a
preferred thing to do because they were
certainly better than mono space sponsor
for readability and so systems wanted to
support that
so they could produce better-looking
output that was more on par with with
what typographers were able to do you
know because they had refined that in
sort of the the printing press style
right they were making characters that
were different sizes already and so what
we want to do is we wanted to you know
in computing we wanted we want to be
able to do that same sort of stuff and
so what we can do is we can say okay
now whenever we draw a glyph when we
draw the next lift we'll just sort of
have some understanding of how far to go
but if you think about it it's actually
a pretty tricky problem because the
actual distance you might want to go is
not necessarily constant depending on
the letter right a naive proportional
font implementation just says okay for
every letter there's a certain distance
I will advance right and that's fine in
general and it solves our guild problem
to some degree right but what it doesn't
solve and you know and what's a what
sort of a I guess a level above that
right is the concept that depending on
which two letters you were putting
back-to-back you might choose a
different amount of space and to give
you sort of a example of of how that
works right suppose I was to take the
letter G and the letter J right and I
was going to put those two characters
next to each other well I would probably
want to space them so that there's like
a reasonable amount of space here which
would leave kind of more space there
right so when I'm thinking about how
close this J should be to something I
have to consider that right it's gonna
be a little bit different there now on
the other hand if I had an eye right and
a J those can go most closer to those
could go much closer together because
the J descender can easily overlap the
eye right the same thing would be true
in the forward direction that was kind
of a backwards looking kerning example
the same will be true in a different
example if I have an F right and I'm
going to follow it by an H right I guess
I drew my F kind of poorly if I have an
F like that right and I'm going to
follow it by an H that goes all the way
up right like so I would probably have
to space these so that you know it looks
something like that which leaves a fair
bit of space here but you know it's
the closeness there right again on the
other hand if it was an eye
I could probably snuggle that eye in
right next to it in fact this is so
common there's even a thing called a
ligature which we don't really have to
cover in handmade here oh but there's a
thing called a ligature which is
actually when the photographer creates a
unified glyph designed to represent F
and I together because it's so common in
often times they'll do it it looks like
that it's like a combination of an FN
and I right so yeah but point being the
distance between letters can be highly
dependent on the pair of letters not
just the letter that came first and
advancing by a certain fixed amount and
so that's where kerning comes in which
is the idea of modifying the inter
characters facing to account for that
pairwise difference and so what you end
up having is you have another lookup
table in this font file or shouldn't say
a lookup table because it's just encoded
information encoding in the font file
right which would be something like a
simple example would be something like
this it would say you know a character a
character B or I should use something
else character one in character to I
don't know what to say character I can't
use any because any glyph is gonna be
something could be in there character a
character B and then a kerning value so
it would say like okay if there's a G
and a J that are back to back I want you
to do you know the spacing is five if
it's instead an eye and a J or
back-to-back I want the spacing to be
less it's gonna be a 1 whatever and
oftentimes the way that kerning is
represented for encoding reasons is that
typically it's actually not the total
amount of spacing that's really not what
they tend to encode kerning typically
refers to the Delta between the normal
spacing and this pair spacing so
typically what will happen is you'll say
okay there's a normal spacing there's a
normal advancement right for a G so in
the table where the fonts are encoded we
say G advances ten units right that's
what G advances and the kerning for --gj
would say okay you were gonna advance
ten now subtract like five from it so
you actually just do five so instead of
encoding the five it encodes a negative
five which is the Delta from the G's
spacing to the you know right
that's just how that goes right the idea
behind that I believe is to save space
right because if I just encode one
remember this is an N squared thing
right this is N squared because if I was
to encode the kerning for every single
thought pair I would basically have you
know a times like however many there are
like if there's n glyphs I would have n
times n entries in this table and so I
think what they do is they like the
reason they don't just describe to
spacing entirely by an N by n times n
table is because I think they were
trying to say well it'd be more
efficient to say let's just describe a
default spacing that goes after every
character and then we'll just put an
entry in the table for when we aren't
going to modify that and then I think
that's why it ended up being kerning
ended up kind of being by default
defined as this thing that adjusts a
default spacing right hmm so that's not
good
so yeah so that's how much time we got
left all right so we got about 20
minutes left so 20 minutes left we got
25 minutes left so that's what a thot
file is right a font file and a font in
general you might say is something that
declares all of these guys right it
declares all these glyphs it declares
some fundamental things that we might
have like what are often called metrics
of the font font metrics which are
basically saying you know look where's
the baseline descenders ascenders you
know some some set of numbers that gives
me a little bit of an idea about how the
font is laid out and then typically also
a kerning table which allows me to sort
of know how I might want to adjust the
spacing of these fonts to make them look
the way the photographer intended
unfortunately a lot of times these
tables are awful
the photographer does a really lousy job
and that is annoys me to no end but what
are you gonna do and then finally the
thing that font files have oftentimes is
they have something called hinting as
well we don't really probably care very
much about hinting but what hinting is
is if you're trying to make fonts
that appear very very tiny then there
are some things that you don't really
want to do so for example if you're
talking about a font that was going to
become rasterized on a very very small
scale so let's make a very little grid
here that we're gonna rasterize right 0
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 I'm gonna make a little
8x8 guy here 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 okay so you
know if I was gonna raster as a font on
here one of the things that can easily
happen is if you're dealing with a
proportional font again it's resolution
independent he doesn't know what's going
on so we take something like that
example I gave you where you have the T
and what we end up with is some really
bad scenario where the T the way the T
lines up in our grid will look like this
okay well okay maybe not exactly like
that try that
okay now what you can see here is that
our tea is only one pixel thick but
because of the way that it happened to
line up on the grid it is now a half
pixel thick in this row and a half pixel
thick in this road now if we were to
render that even with anti-alias
rendering what we would get is a very
wide gray tee right because it's like
half way in all over the place right and
that's not what you want for readability
what you want is this thing to snap to
the actual pixels and you wanted to draw
the tee like this because that would
have been what was actually most the
most legible right oops I should not
quite do that I didn't mean to do that
right you want to draw the tee like this
or did I mean to do that one two three
one two yes okay sorry like that so yeah
that is what you would prefer to do and
so what hinting was was a way of
describing the fact that you wanted to
do this to certain letters like stems
and stuff to try and line them up with
pixels so that you wouldn't get that
kind of effect it's not really relevant
anymore on super high res displays so
you know Retina display or whatever
craziness when the pixel count gets high
enough you're always dealing with
multiple enough pixels that doesn't
matter but when you're talking about you
know an eight by eight font or something
like this it starts to matter
so there you go so that's typically
what's found in a font file and our job
now is we want to build something that
will allow us to take these font files
right take fonts and be able to use them
in handmade here on we have a number of
ways that we could do that right and so
we kind of want to think about what are
the ways that we could do that what's
gonna be most efficient for us and I'll
kind of propose how I think we should
probably tackle it because again
handmade hero doesn't have a lot of need
for fonts it's not a font centric game
so yet
probably do something with fonts that's
relatively easy and and is fast to
render like doesn't you know isn't gonna
be some kind of concern for us where
we're spending all of our time thinking
about how our fonts are working right
okay so option one is we could actually
load you know TTF files or something
right we could actually rasterize the
fonts directly okay and what would that
look like
right well what that would look like is
we'd have we'd have two options for that
one would be if we if we were in a
relatively sane way of doing it right is
we would load in the the font lifts
right so they've got that T we would
load in the font glyphs we would turn
these into triangles using a thing where
this is typically a process called
tessellation which we haven't talked
about because we don't really need to
use it on in our game at all but we
would turn these into triangles right
and then we would actually have like an
outline version of that font right that
we could then use to render things now
of course there's a problem there's a
caveat there which is if we were to do
that just once and just use the fonts in
this format we would have a problem when
we went to do like our s's which is that
we'd have to pick some discretization of
the s like we'd have to pick some degree
of fidelity when we turned it into
triangles and then if we zoomed in too
much on the s we would be able to see
that this part was a line and not a
curve like it was supposed to be right
so that's one thing we could do but of
course we could always fix that by
tessellating dynamically at runtime and
saying okay maybe we've read a really
fast test later and we then say okay how
big did you want the S will tessellate
it more or less depending on how large
it is blah blah right so we could load
TTFN and tessellate that's one option
two is we could load TTFN and implicitly
rasterize again not something we really
have covered too much on hammering here
but we actually implemented it already
we actually did one and when did we do
that right well if you remember when we
did our trying
I mean our quad fill remember how we did
that what we did is we said our quad was
a series of edges right it was a series
of directed edges and what we said was a
pixel we like figured out a bounding box
for our our quad and we said a pixel in
here is going to be filled by the quad
if it is included inside all the edges
right that was what we said you remember
this right well we could go right the
same kind of that's called implicit
rasterization it's basically you have
some function you can evaluate implicit
I've talked about implicit explicit a
little bit implicit is f of X Y some
function that we put in X Y it tells us
like you know some value out that's like
for example whether it's included right
where as explicit is like something
where I feed in some parameter and I get
out the XY of it so like if you know you
could imagine like drawing a line you
feed in successive values of T and you
get points along the line right so
implicit rasterization is when we're
talking about being able to step through
pixels and say is this in the shape or
isn't it right i and and and how do I
fill it right so we could do that for
our fonts we could do that by saying
we've got these Bezier curves right
whatever they are for RS and we're
actually going to do an implicit
rasterize that says for any point we can
ask the question is it inside or outside
of these curves we could do that you
definitely do that with what's called a
line test where you look to see how many
times you have crossed over shapes that
are in your set right and if you've only
crossed over you know going in one
direction if you've only crossed over
one line it means that you're inside
right whereas if you've only if you've
crossed over two lines you're outside
right and it actually it's odd versus
even right because you could do if you
did something here it's like I could go
in out in out right so it's basically
like if I've crossed over an odd number
of times I'm inside the shape if I
crossed over an even number times I
outside of it right we could write that
and the benefit of that is that that
just works at any resolution right no
matter how you scale or shrinkers warper
do whatever you want to the s we would
always have a perfectly smooth curve
going around the s right so that's
another one but I don't really think we
need any of these right
these are overkill these are drastically
over killed they're overkill for 99.999%
of all games right because most games
just don't have that kind of an
unpredictable heavy reliance on font
shapes most games know their target
resolution or there abouts or a couple
of them most games know how big the
thoughts will generally be appearing on
screen so most of the time making a
system that is capable of doing this
much work with the fonts just simply
isn't that important and you're wasting
your time if you go hog-wild on it it's
time you could have spent doing some
other feature in the game right and so
typically you go with option three which
is pre rasterized fonts right and the
nice part about pre race response is
basically pre rasterizing fonts turns
fonts into something that you or your
game can already handle right we already
know we can bit blit bitmaps to the
screen we even know we can transform and
scale them right we've done that with
our hero sprites and the sprites for the
background and all the other stuff right
we've built good systems for doing that
and so the nice for your Astros fonts
right is pre rasterize fonts turns fonts
into a problem that we already solved
and way that that works is if you're
trying to do press rest fonts what we
say is let's build right bitmaps that
capture the font add a certain
resolution we'll say ok for handmade
hero here's our target resolution right
we want 1920 by 1080 or something right
and we want our foster show up roughly
the size so you know we want them to be
you know 40 pixels high so let's just
rasterize the thought out at 40 pixels
high we'll save the results of that
rasterize
into a set of bitmaps or a single bitmap
where they're like packed together
whatever right and then we want to
actually draw these we will simply put
them back on the screen right we will
simply blip from the bitmap just like
we've lit from everything else
very straightforward right nothing
nothing crazy happening okay so that's a
lot easier and a lot more
straightforward and it also has a nice
aspect of no matter how complex the the
thing is that pre rasterizes the fonts
it doesn't matter because it's not
happening at runtime right here we would
have had to start thinking like Oh
what's the performance considerations of
this and you know is it gonna start
impacting my frame rate if you know
whatever like because there's complexity
here here we know that it's just going
through the standard bitmap letting pass
so I pretty much know exactly everything
I need to know about it and no matter
how complicated the glyph is it doesn't
change it's just however big it appears
on screen is how much it costs that's it
right it's just like any other bitmap
there's no magic to it and so we can
rasterize any font we want that way no
matter how crazy it is and that's fine
so how would we how do we do this right
how do we do pre rasterize fonts
well you typically what you do is you
start with a bitmap and you start
packing glyphs into it so you might say
like okay I start and I put the letter A
in here right and then I go the next one
and I put the letter B in here right and
I end up with a bitmap it's got all my
letters in it right Dada Dada right I
just pack all the fonts into a bitmap
that's just I know I can load that
bitmap and draw my thoughts right in an
anime hero we don't really pack things
in a bitmaps much so we could also just
store these separately as separate
assets in our asset file if we wanted to
that could just be separate right
doesn't matter however you want to do it
somehow we get all the actual character
images and we rasterize them into actual
bitmaps right now what do we store in
the bitmap well we don't really need any
color information because the font
probably will be colored on the fly when
we actually
we'll probably want to be able to change
the color of the fossil just be white
right so really this is gonna be can be
a monochrome bitmap as well right it can
just be an 8-bit value that tells me how
much coverage there was right it can
just be like an 8-bit value that's like
the the anti aliased white version of
this font like grayscale would probably
be fine
now you know you could do color if you
were doing some thought that was fancier
and had like you know some kind of color
you know maybe your artist makes the
custom for you or something that could
be too but most the time fonts aren't
color so you know you can just store an
8-bit version that's basically just the
anti-aliasing of the font that's all it
is okay so you need that you need some
way of storing all the glyphs you then
need a bunch of tables right first of
all we need the code points right we
need to know where you know like okay we
need to basically have a mapping that
says all right the letter A right
whatever that is right so we need the
letter A maps to like this location
right so there's like a rectangle or a
bitmap ID or something that says where
is the glyph for the letter e how do I
get the glyph for the letter A right
I need that then I need some positioning
information right for the letter A where
does that go
right because remember you might have a
letter in here that's like lowercase a
right it's much smaller than large a and
so I can't just use the size of the
bitmap to tell me where the things go I
I need to know okay you've shrunk it
down to the minimal you know box that
first for storage space how do I then
position that relative to like the
baseline right like we were talking
about the fonts how do i position that
right so we need some positioning
information and then finally we need the
kerning table right we need a way of
knowing for any two characters how far
should I advance between them okay so we
need to store a bunch of information
with our font that can allow us to get
all of that information back when we
load the thing in right so what we're
gonna want to do tomorrow since we're
about out of time for
we have a little bit more I think we
start about 10 minutes late but this is
a good point to wrap up anyway so what
we want to do tomorrow is start figuring
out a way to pre rasterize our fonts
like into our asset pack file for
example in a way that includes all of
this information and includes the you
know sort of the the the font the font
glyphs as well right and so that way so
we'll kind of you know expand we did I
think we did a pretty good job in our
asset system you know of sort of for
lack of a better term making it
extensible so adding in another type of
asset that was a that was a font if we
had to would not actually be very
difficult right and so if we find that
we would rather make a very specific way
of handling that we could do that but
the other thing that we could do
amusingly enough is we could just make
it so that the thoughts I think we
probably could even do something where
the fonts just use the tag matching
system still to like get the code point
out that way which would be kind of
amusing but anyway point being that is
basically it for fonts and so that is
the majority of what we have to do
tomorrow right is just we have to figure
out how we are going to start building
one of those font things such that such
that we can start using it in the game
and it's it's a bunch of Drudge rook
really it's not gonna be particularly
exciting it's like what I've told you so
far is it's basically what you need to
know to do it it's just I'm gonna have
to now show you sort of the the annoying
part of like interfacing with Windows to
get your fonts or you know some other
scheme by which you could generate the
fonts that you that you need you could
also use like the SDB TrueType library
for example to generate them so i'll
show you how to do it using windows and
you could also you know symmetrically
use some other operating system to
extract the fonts out of it but you
could alternatively use you know open
open type or stb font i mean SD be true
but true type which is you know what a
sean barie
it's libraries that's a it's got a it's
a great little true type font system
that really small amount of code that's
easy to use so that's another way you
can do it too so that's about it I will
go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A now so if
anyone has questions about fonts I'd
like to ask now would be the time tt PJM
aren't there licensing concerns with
fonts well it depends which method you
are picking so if you are if you are
doing one of these methods you may and
it's kind of a legal gray area depending
on exactly how you implement it so
honestly I I guess I don't really know
and and I don't even know if anyone
really knows with these you would
probably have to license the the font
file the font that you like like so with
with either of these methods you would
probably have to license the font to use
like in your game right so if you wanted
to use a bigger font you'd have to go
get a license for that font even if you
didn't ship the TTF so even if you don't
ship the TTF you would probably if you
literally did one of these methods
there's actually other ways you could do
it here that that might actually not
require that the amusing thing with this
method is you never need a license for
this method this method is always free
if you are in the u.s. if you are in
Europe that might not be true because
there are other places have different
copyright laws but the way the copyright
works in the u.s. is fonts cannot be
copyrighted so the only reason the other
methods are do require a license is
because the other methods are
technically software it was ruled in
in a famous Supreme Court ruling that
Technic might have been enough with
Supreme Court ruling I take that back it
might have been a district court ruling
I don't quite remember but basically
there was a ruling that said that
because the the TTFN or a fought file
was basically instructions to a computer
on how to generate the font at any
resolution that it was copyrightable as
software now the font is still not
copyrightable which means if you were to
load it up on the screen and trace it to
make your own new outline version that
would be legal and you could ship that
version with no license but if you
actually used their TTFN even if you
translated it into another one
automatically it would still presumably
violate the copyright because you are
translating the program directly at that
point not the resulting thought shape
which is not copyrightable on the other
hand if you are to rasterize the fonts
you have only you are only left with the
bitmap the actual image of the font and
at that point as far as anyone knows
there is no way to sue you for copyright
infringement because thoughts can't be
copyright it is not a computer program
it's just an image and the image of a
font is not copyrightable so in the US
no there i do not believe there are any
licensing issues with that if you wanted
to be safe rather than sorry you know
you could always license fonts they're
not super expensive but no this method
you down if you want to dynamically
create the fonts on the fly on the other
hand you absolutely do need to license
it even if you are in the u.s. because
that is is copyrighted
will you support Unicode in hand-made
here oh yeah I think we probably will
could we not pre rasterize our fonts
whenever the resolution has changed at
run time basically you could but I
typically don't like to do that because
if you do that then you are basically
shipping an extra set of complexity in
the game right like you're you know I
don't really want to ship a font
rasterizer in the game if I don't have
to write because just one more thing
that could go wrong and so I like to
just treat them as regular art assets if
I can if I can't that I can't we'd be
writing something using the font before
you code the actual font reading etc
well yes and no to generate the font
files no we won't because we just need
to get the data in there but to to just
determine the font API yes we'll write
some stuff that's like how do we want to
actually try to print things and then
we'll make that work
well classic bitmap fonts remain
relevant in the coming years or will we
just start flat out with vector fonts
for evermore I don't really feel like
bitmap fonts are super relevant except
in a retro
I feel like vector fonts are pretty much
the thing and it's just you know you
tend to rasterize them down to bitmaps
but I don't think you're you hand author
I don't think the idea of hand authoring
a bitmap font is really all that
relevant except for retro style like
retro style looks but there will be
retro style looking games for a long
time I would imagine right possibly
forever so that it won't go away
entirely but yeah it's not really that
relevant most of the time are you doing
quantum mechanics no because I don't
know any contra mechanics did you ever
try making a font yourself uh yeah I
actually did make it thought myself when
I was little it was a bitmap font though
there's not a it was not an iPhone will
you have unique fonts made for the game
possibly I'm not sure it depends a few
ancient is interested in that she might
be if you have multiple font families
and we're pre rasterizing them can you
stuff them into one file well I mean in
our asset system yes in other asset
systems who knows it depends whether the
asset system supports it right can I
come live with you and you tutor me no
we do not have a spare bedroom how are
combining Unicode characters that some
languages have handled oh so that's not
something we super need to probably
worry about in handmade hero but yeah so
I don't think I've ever actually
implemented this in fact I know that I
have not but in the Unicode spec right
there's two kind of ways of talking
about fonts
I've been talking about glyphs right one
way is to say I have Unicode code point
you know 87 or something whatever it is
right I guess 80 or something right and
it maps to the letter P or something
right and so when you see that you kind
of just know like I'm outputting P and
that's like what we'll be dealing with
on handmade here oh but I know there's
other things in Unicode which which the
Utica which were the combining glyphs
and that's when the glyphs don't
actually form separate pieces right so
instead of just thinking about like oh
it's a P and then it's an i and that
it's an L and an L right you know
instead of thinking about that it's
actually more like imagine with an eye
shape you were to have the eye broken
into two pieces the lower part and the
upper part right and this one was one
code point and this one was another and
when the engines sees this one followed
by this one it's supposed to know that
this one you know is placed up on top of
there or whatever right I have never
even looked at that part of the spec I
have no idea how what they actually what
it demands of you meaning I don't know
like if you actually have to do anything
special if you can just roll it into the
kerning table or what right because you
know it's a combination based thing so
it's possible that like you could do
something fancy there or it's possible
that no you really have to look at it
and go okay it's this code and when I
see this code I know I have to check the
next code to see if that code is this
because if it is it means something
different you know it could be way more
complicated right so I've never looked
at at that encoding and I have no idea
how that stuff works right
nay sir 88 I became a much happier
person once I started writing fonts on
the fly all the time all the time so you
mean you you actually just rasterize the
fonts like literally right when you're
about to draw a giving glyph you
rasterize it at that time or do you just
mean well I guess I'm not sure what you
mean
a bit off-topic what makes code
publishable you said you wouldn't
publish the current win32 platform layer
exactly why not I don't usually use the
term publish because I don't know what
that means exactly but ship is what I
would have probably said maybe I did say
publish though what I mean by that is
the win32 layer right now is just not
like it doesn't support all of the code
paths that you would actually need for a
robust experience on win32 right it
doesn't go through the 3d hardware layer
which means that the framerate won't be
right it doesn't have vsync because it
doesn't go through that as well which
would be which is bad it doesn't you
know probably handle like app activate
correctly like what it's in the
background so that there's like a bunch
of things you want to do to your win32
platform layer to make it like shippable
quality and so when we go you know to
final the game will go back to the win32
platform layer and go what are all the
things you want do to make this more
robust right and we and you know that
would also include like testing it right
on a bunch of people's machines so that
we could have a better idea that it was
actually you know more usable will you
be writing your own pre rasterizer from
scratch or using a third-party tool we
will actually be able to do this
entirely with Windows so that's pretty
easy in which episode will you implement
unicode skin tone emoji modifiers well
obviously that's the most important
thing to do
I mean if we don't have the ability to
have every possible skin color in our in
our emoji then you know can we really
call it a unified world and the answer
is also you know and so in order to
preach you know the proper amount of of
sort of unified world global happiness
we should obviously have all the skin
tones including ones that don't even
exist yet how much time do you spend
preparing for each dream none if you
were to have a lute history or storyline
history
you mentioned forty pixels if you wanted
to allow users to adjust this UI would
you still do pre rasterize at what point
would be the threshold for including a
proper non rasterized version I think
it's basically a judgment call like if
you want to do pre rasterized fonts you
just have to have some idea that you can
meaningfully cover the various usage
scenarios that you want to cover with
those pre rasterized fonts right and so
including a non rasterize version is
just some judgement call you make when
you're like in order to get the quality
that we want and the variety of sizes
that we want we need to switch to you
know a rasterized version knee below the
the or Larian method you use for the
particle systems move stuffs from high
density to low density cells could the
or Larian method be used the other way
eg to make something that has gravity
and pulls low density stuff towards
itself also I wonder if we're Larry and
simulation could be used for AI systems
maybe having different characters being
attracted to or repelled by crowds so
first I will say that the or Larian
method the term or Larian refers
strictly to like I was saying that
discretization on a fixed grid on a
regular grid whereas Lagrangian referred
to discretization into free-floating
points right
and and so the important thing to
remember there and we didn't go into it
in detail because we were just kind of
like I said that was a 2-day sort of
excursion into that stuff but the
important thing to remember is that
actually if you want to go further down
the simulation route boil Aryan is just
it's just about the discretization what
system of equations you choose to solve
on that system can be any physical
system right so we didn't get to that
stage because we didn't you know we
didn't spend two weeks doing real Aryan
methods or whatever but actually what
you do is not the hack that I did on the
stream where I just like picked some
arbitrary numbers and shoved them in
there right what you actually do is
write a set of physics equations that
are designed to govern the system that
you are trying to create then you
actually discretize those equations onto
the grid and you write a solver that
actually does a solving step all in the
grid which we never got to because
there's a bunch of stuff you can do is
it like I like hack or Larry I'm like
what I did where you don't have to do
all that stuff and you can still get you
results but the real method the full
method is actually much more powerful so
we can do stuff like simulating
gelatinous liquids that go here together
and do all and have surface tension you
know you could do real fluid dynamics on
an oil Arian grid just fine right and so
can you do gravity absolutely you could
do anything you want just the degree to
which it's appropriate to pet and how
how fine the grid has to be to capture
what you want all that stuff is kind of
like part of continuum dynamics if
you're interested in this reading about
this more continuum dynamics is is what
that was what I was talking about and
you know you could
oh is this a bit oh this is oh it's
Michael Kass yeah skip that I thought it
was gonna be Berra for somebody and I'd
say take a look but you know if you look
at continuum dynamics methods it's a
gigantic field
I don't know if there's good
would there be there's probably a
SIGGRAPH course notes like on it which
which might be good maybe not I don't
know I suppose the thing on the forums
up I could try to find some good
references it I you know I I think
pseudonym 73 might have already posted
some good ones but they're it's a whole
field and there's the ton of stuff in
there it's it's I mean there's you could
spend your whole life and people do
doing nothing but that kind of
stimulation work so it's very rich and
anything that you want to do you can do
it's just a question of how much it
costs to do it right cast of five isn't
abusive text in a game the bad game
design idea well I'm not a game designer
so I don't really I can't really answer
that but what I would say is I suspect
that like everything else the amount of
text in a game design is dependent on
whether that design is about text or not
right if your game is not about reading
things then yeah it's probably a bad
game design but if your game is about
reading things well will you use correct
typography terminology for the game or
will you be carefree about it probably
carefree typography terminology there's
not really a huge reason to be super
accurate about it I don't know that that
you're gain all that much from that you
know you could always go read a
typographer there's not that much
terminology actually in there
rob robbie by adding more and more
layers of complexity to the engine do
you start to measure and optimize those
parts just when the FPS is low enough or
when you you or when you usually start
with that position yeah so there's two
things the optimization is really not
the only one it's definitely a big one
in games so that's true but there's
really two reasons for the debug view
stuff
one is optimization but the other one is
bugs it would be really easy to should
have a game like handmade here with lots
of bugs in it that no one would ever
know about and you might say you don't
care but actually it leads to a worse
play experience and and those are kinds
of bugs you're like oh the AI decided to
do something stupid because we had a bug
in it and then like that monster isn't
as fun as it should have been right a
lot of stuff like that you will never
know because there's no way design unit
test for it there's no way to inspect
the code and figure it out ahead of time
it's just it's too complex and so the
way that you need to tackle those is by
having visualization that allows you to
see what the code is doing in an
intuitive way on the screen all the time
such you can always be aware of what's
happening and notice when problems are
occurring and I would suspect that even
right now there are bugs in our in our
code that we just don't know about that
when we implement more Vista we will
just see like ah there was an obvious
bug like we just saw it right and it
won't be as many right now because like
I said we haven't done sort of the
things that are more temporal like AI
and stuff that that work over time and
for to have that but like in our
threading there's probably like a bug in
our threading that when we visualize our
threads we'll just be like oh yeah right
you know so there's there's probably
just bugs in there and there's a lot of
bugs that went because games are things
that happen over time there's usually a
lot of bugs that simply cannot be tested
away and and that is why visualization
is so important because it's it's one of
the ways of really improving the quality
of the game and so you know it's it's
almost visualizing it's almost less
about optimization and and almost more
about about robustness real
what do you think is the hardest
challenge for you in programming these
days really it's the I mean it's it's
the poor quality stuff honestly you know
between between how bad Windows has
gotten and how bad developer Studios
gotten and like you know the fact that
Emacs is so slow and like it's just all
the tools are garbage that's that that's
the biggest challenge for me because
it's like I don't know you know I could
go try to rewrite all those and some
degree like I am starting to try and do
some rewrite some major portions of what
we use at Mali but you know it's a bit
of a struggle and it's always everyday
it sucks nowadays because every day when
you go in and do programming you always
just feel like you're like so alone
right because you're like you know that
nobody who works on visual studio at any
idea what they were doing and like you
know that nobody who like ship the
versions wouldn't attend any idea what
they're doing right you're like they had
they didn't care about me they weren't
trying to make my experience better like
they were trying to figure out to put
ads in it or how to make it good for you
know a Java programmer at IBM or
whatever right and and it's really it's
really frustrating and so you know John
blow I guess who I don't know if he's
still here on the stream but he and I
talked about this a long time ago and I
think I was actually I tapped out
earlier than he did I sent him a a long
time ago where I was like I think I got
to start working on an operating system
or something because I'm just I've had
it like I can't take it anymore and he's
like I don't know if that's such a
productive thing to do you know and like
there's so many things we could do you
know is that really a good idea but
about a year later he tapped out to and
he was just like yeah probably like it's
all gone to crap and we got to start
doing something about it right and
you'll notice he's actively doing
something about it right now like he's
trying to make a new programming
language is he's like we gotta fix this
stuff like it's obvious that nobody else
is gonna so like somebody somebody who
actually cares has to go do it right and
personally I think that's really awesome
because you know it gives me a certain
measure of hope every day to know that
someone like John is working on a new
language because it means there's a
chance that when I sit down to program
in five years it won't be about how
awful C++ is and how nobody who works on
that language has any idea how to
program which is how I feel
nowadays right I know it sounds harsh
but that's how I feel I literally feel
like the tools I use all day we're
written by people have no idea how to
program like they're so far behind the
curve on like how to program and it's
like the operating system the text
editor the compiler the debugger they
all just feel awful you know and and
they didn't used to feel that way they
used to feel pretty cutting edge when I
used to program on the Amiga I was in
awe of how good the text editor was and
like it was crazy to me that they were
able to even do that stuff in like you
know 20 56k right and nowadays you can't
even get a text editor to update in real
time you know on a freaking Jeep you
know dual SLI Titan or something right
forget it because it's just so slow it
doesn't even have to do with the
graphics they just they're running
c-sharp in the background or doing it
right and so that's a real challenge
like it really does make me miserable
like I really upsets me at like some
core level and so a lot of my hope for
the future is just about like maybe if
enough of us are this miserable about it
someday we'll change and to a large
extent that was a huge motivating factor
behind handmade hero was that I felt
like if I just kind of did some
programming that maybe was like here's
how I like to approach programming
problems and I and I would like more
people to start thinking about
programming down at a lower level and
and caring about like more holistically
what the code is doing that that might
inspire people to do projects that would
start to you know change that that
culture right and turn it around to make
it more like it used to be when the
tools I used were good and honestly like
I've been really encouraged by what's
happened because there actually is more
than one person right now who
specifically after watching handmade
hero went and started like a text editor
or something right and like someone
started to paint Pro
recently too right and like that's just
so encouraging because I I feel like
it's not that hard to actually replace
some of these things yes it's a year or
two of work but it's not 20 years of
work it just takes some people to
actually care about the quality of the
end product that's all it really takes
right and so in some sense like it
really it really has been pretty awesome
to see that start to happen because if I
can have any small effect on encouraging
people to do that it it would make a
non-trivial difference even just
selfishly in my life to some day boot up
an editor by someone and it's like this
editor actually works right like that
will be so great and so you know I feel
like there's a chance that's gonna turn
around and and I didn't feel that way
probably like a year ago so in some
sense like yeah
jomblo says the worst part is you say
stuff about these tools being terrible
and nobody seems to understand they are
terrible everyone is like what do you
mean yeah and and I mean it's true right
it's hard to articulate sometimes it's
hard to articulate it because if you
haven't been there if you haven't used a
really fast text editor then you don't
know that yours is slow right it's like
if you've only ever eaten you know you
know if you've eaten the fillet of fish
sandwich McDonald's right it's pretty
hard to tell someone that like no really
like sushi is pretty amazing like it
there's some really great stuff out
there right and you know that's just
that's just how it is you can't it's
it's hard to convince people somethings
terrible until you put something in
front of them that's ten times better
and they're like oh right well there you
go it's like probably no one thought
Windows seee phones were terrible until
someone handed them an iPhone and they
swiped on it we're like oh my god it's
magic right but that's just because you
know if you haven't experienced you
don't know I mean right now the things
I'm complaining about and the world I'm
envisioning that could have them fixed
is also very limited like some in 50
years in the future maybe we'll all be
living in some weird VR reality where
like we just think thoughts and the code
materializes right so I even don't
really know how bad the tools that I
would think are good actually are bad
compared to right you know I so I mean I
think that's why we have to start
building some good tools to show people
like hey by the way visual studio is a
piece of junk like here's actually what
it would be like if your debugger was
good you know
if you considered signed distance fields
for text rendering you can't render text
with signed distance fields unless you
use you actually need a more complicated
encoding so the reason is because signed
distance fields are always rounded right
and so you can't do things like hard
edges so in order to use signed distance
fields for text rendering unless you all
want all of your fonts to look like
blobs you have to you have to be
multiple signed distance field per
region of your font so you need
basically like a hybrid encoding that's
like multiple distance fields per region
like a Voronoi region with distance
fields which is pretty expensive it's
pretty spensive so it's not a it's not a
great choice unless you really know that
you need it because it is it is very
expensive and you have to kind of weigh
it against other options
don't you think you're not being
completely fair to the other crowd who
are not going to lower level for example
I love and care about lower level stuff
but to pay my bills I have to be able to
output an application within tenth of
the time it would take me if I do it
everything at lower level I have no
choice but rely on W F and C sharp well
you know I don't really think it's a
question of fairness is the problem it's
a question of quality like basically
what I'm saying is I am not satisfied
with the quality of tools I have now I
don't really care why that was that way
right like like if someone couldn't do
it because they weren't given enough
time to do it that's a perfectly valid
excuse but it doesn't help me right no I
mean if there was an excuse for why
Visual Studio sucks doesn't make Visual
Studio not suck right that's the problem
and so since I know it is possible to do
a better visual studio what we need is
people to actually say I'm gonna
dedicate the time to actually making the
good version of this thing right and so
I really don't think it's a question of
being fair or unfair right people should
do whatever they have to do to earn a
living I guess right you know I mean as
long as it's ethical hopefully so that's
not really the thing it's not like
saying that you know someone's a bad
person but it is saying that I'm not
getting what I need from this industry
right this industry is doing a poor job
actually delivering what I need to to
work with right and so it doesn't really
matter if it's fair or not something
needs to be improved and hopefully there
are some people who could figure out how
to make a business out of that and start
shipping development tools that actually
were good
it's not enough to see a good tool once
to understand that modern tools are bad
I feel like you also need to be a pretty
good programmer which is far from where
most of us are now if you are mediocre
programmer you won't feel it do you
agree I don't think so
I think maybe for modest improvements to
something like Visual Studio maybe
that's true like fixing how long it
takes to step in video studio to make it
instant maybe other people wouldn't feel
that as much because they don't know the
value of being able to let quickly to
bug your code or something I don't know
but like let's say you had a debugger
that actually visualized all your stuff
for you really well where you were just
like oh yeah I set a breakpoint there
show me all the structures and
completely you know instantly diagrams
them in points and like here's the where
you are and here's where these pointers
pointed to and I'll buy right like
imagine DVD written by someone who knew
what they were doing so like it actually
like visualized it really cleanly and as
you stepped it like updated
automatically and showed you all the
stuff and like oh you have vector three
so it plotted them in 3d and you could
spin it around like anybody I don't care
who they were or how novice they were
when they saw that they'd be like why am
I using this complete piece of garbage
like why don't I use that thing it'd be
so much easier to debug my code right
anyone could see that so I think if we
actually built tools that did what we
are capable of making them do today
right if you spent if somebody spent the
same amount of time making a good
debugger as Google spends trying to
target their ads it would be so
breathtakingly further along right then
what we have today with something like
Visual Studio that I don't think anybody
would not immediately see the difference
instantly right but that's just not
where we focus our time right
would you take a job in the Mafia if
they gave you a perfect version of Emax
and visual studio well I am Italian
which mafia were you referring to if
you're talking about Sicilian they might
I mean they do except non Sicilians I
suppose to a certain extent all right I
think we have ended the stream so I am
going to close it down here we go
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for another episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to follow along with
the series at home you can always
pre-order the game on handmade here at
organic comes with the source code so if
you want to play around with it and
you've learned by doing which is a very
good way to do it
you can go ahead and do that on this
website we also have a patreon page to
while support the video serious we also
have a forum site if you want to ask
questions or view anti depa soed guide
or see ports to Mac and Linux at the
community of done and finally we have a
tweet bot that tweets of schedule so if
you're trying to catch us live that's
the place to go it will tell you when we
will be live that's about it for today
tomorrow is an unusual time it is going
to be at 8 o'clock which and and
actually also I believe Jonathan Blow
will be streaming a language development
update earlier in the day so 6:30 I
think is the time for that so you want
it you'll want to check out a naysayer
88 at 6:30 for sure and and then after
that handmade hero will be streaming at
8 so it so it is a night packed with
programming streaming for your viewing
enjoyment ladies and gentlemen so hope
see you back here tomorrow for that 8
p.m. Pacific Daylight Time right here on
Twitch so until then have fun coding and
yeah I'll see you guys on the Internet
take it easy everyone