hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero the shore we could a complete game
live on stream we are almost at the
point I realized and I should so I've
kind of sighted today I should probably
finish this up we've reached the point
where we could rebuild all of our source
input files using entirely just the game
engine meaning you run the game and it
could rebuild its entire like run time
pack information I we can do that now
for both our art assets and our sound
assets the only thing we can't do it for
right now is fonts and so what I was
thinking is what we should probably do
today is try to put font building into
the game as well again we already have
the code for it it's just in an external
utility and then we would be completely
ready to just say look we can now just
ship a directory full of unn like full
of source assets that are completely
unprocessed and then we can run the game
and the game will just pack them all up
for you one time and then you can just
go forever right and so I think that
would probably be the best thing to do I
think it would be the best thing to do
because then we can ship a definitive
version as something on the like on the
sundial page or whatever for people who
appear to the game and try to build at
home we could finally produce something
that's like really easy for them to get
started if they haven't been following
the series at all it's just like look
you download this directory structure
and then you just get whatever the
latest source code is you run it and
it'll build all the hhas for you
automatically you don't have to download
anything
beyond that right and then you're good
to go from then on so that seems to me
like a good way to go I don't know but
that's my that's my current thinking and
so I think that's how we would probably
want to do it one of the nasty things
about that is we do use win32 to build
our fonts because that's where the fonts
come from like right now we load
them out of win32 and so you know we
have an ST B font path in there too but
we tried to do things without libraries
on handmade Hira so we were calling the
operations directly for that stuff and
so doing those fonts this way I don't
know it seems like a reasonable way to
go I'm not sure but there's another
thing that we could do and so this part
is something that I'm you know I don't
know whether it's the right call or not
it's hard to say but another thing that
I was thinking we could do is in order
to maintain sort of more of a
cross-platform feel of things another
option we could consider is if we took
the fonts and we actually bake them into
pngs
that we then load then when we
distribute the pngs
then we would by default have the fonts
working on all platforms so in other
words you wouldn't extract fonts out of
the OS or anywhere else when you
actually run the game you would just
have pngs that are loaded through the
normal PNG path right and baked into the
ehh A's so I don't really know what the
right tack is to take there it's tough
to say the reason that the that the PNG
baking path is a little bit trickier is
because that path actually requires us
to do a little bit of footwork because
we would need inside the hht file we
would need to store all of the
additional information that the font has
by default so we would need to basically
have a thing in there that says look
you're gonna load this PNG but man
there's all these other pieces of
information that go with it like here's
the kerning between all the different
character pairs or whatever right so the
nice part about getting it from you know
sort of a thought building process is
all of that stuff is stored in the font
file directly and it becomes pretty
easy to just make that work right but
the nice part about going the P&amp;G route
is then we can just create art assets
that we upload that's like here's a
bitmap that is the fonts or whatever
right and you know we can adjust in the
hht file we can say like here's how we
would adjust each individual you know
kerning pair or stuff like that and you
know it's easy enough for us to add data
to those hht files but I just don't know
if that's yeah I mean I really I wish I
had a better I wish I had a better
suggestion for what the right answer is
here I don't have a good feeling for it
so what I'd like to do today is explore
that because I want to basically figure
out what we should be doing here and get
a path towards actually doing it if we
load up handmade here oh so I'm just
gonna load it up here and I'm gonna go
to the file formats and just take a look
at the font like what are we actually
storing in here you know for those
currently just so we have some idea of
what's happening so if you look in here
when we've got the main HHA font
structure what you can see is that we
store pretty basic information this
would be really trivial to encode in our
tag files right because the ascender
height the descender height and the
external letting those are just you know
trivial values that we can just put into
a tag I mean a knot tag a block in the H
of T file right here's the font here's
the ascender height descender height
external lighting right so super simple
and then if you look at what else is in
there you can see we have an N squared
table that you just look up in to see
how far you should advance for any
character pair right and again that's
something we can store pretty easily we
can just have you list all the pairs and
we assume that there's no that there's
just like a default for anything in the
table that isn't what you won you
manually specify and then anyone you do
specify that's what that that's what
that pair again
right so similarly the one past highest
code point is just something that says
look here's how many of the Unicode
characters were actually going to
represent in here and so if somebody
does want to like do some localization
work on the game or something like this
so that eventually we would we would
have you know like let's say we want to
look at Japanese localized version of
the game so we need a bunch of extra
code points in there that say here's you
know code point this code point that
that tells us you know which which ones
we have right and you know not all of
them have to actually be filled right so
we can have zeros in there four code
points that we didn't store any you know
any actual bitmap for so that's fine too
and I think well so looking at this - it
looks like we actually compress it - so
we don't even have to do that it looks
like the way this is stored as it tells
you what Unicode code point goes with
which bitmap in a big old list right and
then one past highest code point just
tells you look when you expand this out
into a lookup table this is how big the
table would have to be right so that all
seems really good right and I think
we're storing these well I think that's
just fine we don't need to do anything
else
fancy there so really the question is
just how do we get the data in beyond
just this HHA font and like I said it
seems really easy here to just put it in
hhd and just have that work right so I
think what we would want to do is say
okay how are we gonna get all of these
bitmaps in there you know do we export
them all as separate PN G's is that just
ridiculous or is that fine I mean I
don't know that might be totally fine
you know what's an extra hundred PM g's
in there I guess and then you just load
them all in at process time you pack
them in the HHA and off you go
right
and that would obviously be the simplest
way to go because then like you just you
have one per and there's really not
anything else you need to do right
I don't know I really don't know the
thing that would be annoying is that if
an artist actually one of the entities
so if an artist is making them I mean
maybe the answer is an artist never does
make them you know like an artist
doesn't make fonts as PNG s an artist
like uses a font package or something
and then the font package just gets
exported into pngs and the h HT like
block that specifies all of the kerning
and stuff right I mean who knows I
really couldn't tell you so I mean I
guess what I'll say is let's try that I
guess because I don't really have a
better idea and I guess you know maybe
we could try that and so what I'm
suggesting here is you know let's say we
wanted to make this stuff work the way
that I sort of just described so inside
sources maybe we've got a thing that's
like you know like instrumentation or
you know developer or something and in
here you know we would have anything
that's a resource that only the
developers would care about right and so
in there we would have like a fonts
directory and the fonts directory would
just have like all of the bitmaps that
were being used for that purpose right
for font purpose and then the hht file
would just be something that's you know
in in the tags section here we would
have like a developer dot hht it would
list all of the stuff that's necessary
for packing up that font and off we
would go that's what I'm proposing
Yeah right I don't have I don't have
anything more concrete to say so let's
suppose we were gonna do that and so if
we looked at you know what we've got for
code here in the handmade code directory
we've got the ela guess it's already
loaded that we've got the test a set
builder and the test a set builder is
what we've been pulling the code out of
right that that goes into handmade
heroes asset import layer and so what
I'm suggesting is maybe we just take
this code that we have for test asset
builder and we know we've already sort
of shelled it but maybe we just make a
thing that's called like font or like HH
font right and instead of it doing
something like here where it says hey
there's this font I want you to pack
right like right here you can see this
thing doing like a font loading nonsense
thing right I and it it like says which
characters are supposed to be used and
that kind of thing so if we just took
this and then we bring that into a
routine that basically you know writes
out these things as as bitmaps in a
directory and as one hht that just has
like all of the definition of the font
in it you know is that is that
sufficient right does that work for us
so that's what I'm thinking I don't have
any better ideas but I think that's just
I guess what we should try at this point
to see if we can do anything reasonable
and you can see here where we're sort of
defining the two fonts that we loaded we
could try to generate the output for
those two fonts and then that would be
we would expect our font utility to
basically load those fonts dump all
those bitmaps in the hht out and then we
can you know harvest them and put them
into the sources directories and go from
there right so that's like the best idea
I have it's not a great idea but I don't
see much in the way of other clean ways
to do this or reasonable ways to do this
the only other thing to think of that we
would want to do maybe is like pack them
into P and G's in some weird way or
something else I don't know but that
just adds yet more complexity to our
code path that I'm not really sure that
we want it and yeah I mean in the in
theory I guess we could just expand the
total number like so right now we we
allow grids to be a certain size we
could allow grids to be larger so we
could make you know the sort of the grid
system probably do what we needed to do
where you know the grids maybe can be up
to like 64 by 64 or something like this
and then you could store like all your
fonts just in one bitmap that was packed
again I just I don't know
I really just don't have
I really just I mean I wish I had a more
coherent idea about how this should work
but it just don't this is one of those
places where you know there is no simple
answer to how you would do fonts and the
reason for that is pretty simple it's
it's the core reason why most asset
processing systems are lousy and why
it's just a hard problem in general and
that's because when you're dealing with
a very simple art asset like a bitmap
that doesn't really have anything to do
with anything like for example our title
screen bitmap is just a lone bitmap that
sits there it's pretty easy in your code
to just say alright we just load a
bitmap and we put it on the screen right
and there's just not a lot of complexity
there so there's not a lot of complexity
in the asset path where the complexity
comes is when assets have complex
interrelations and structures inside
themselves with data that depends on
those structures and fonts are a great
example of that not only do they have
the notion that there's like one sort of
asset which is a font that itself
contains many assets which are glyph
bitmaps but there's also data that
happens among and between these assets
themselves so the kerning table is a way
of saying that between two of these
assets here's a value that I need the
program to know right and so as you get
into more complex interrelationships
between things that's where the
complexity in asset processing comes and
it gets more and more complicated as you
go you can even see like every year at
the GDC there's like asset pipeline
talks how are there still asset pipeline
talks right it's because these are very
hard problems they're problems people
underestimate and they caused huge
headaches for studios because you end up
having huge amounts of data with huge
amounts of assets and huge amounts of
inter relation between these assets and
fonts are the place where we will see it
the most because they're the assets that
have the most structure for what we are
actually doing in our game which is a
very limited version of the kind of
pipeline we would have to employ if we
were gonna do you know Red Dead
Redemption right where you you know you
talk about taking these things to the
enth degree so I don't really know I'm
just gonna start with the simplest case
and I'm gonna try my best to work out
from there and make something reasonable
that's just you know I think that's the
best I can do in this case so I'm just
gonna try that and we'll see if we can
you know more easily if we can
relatively straight you know we can do a
relatively straightforward load of these
tags into something that works okay so
the first thing that I'm gonna do is I'm
just gonna create a new file I'm gonna
create like an H H font which is just a
gonna be a command-line utility exactly
like this one I'm literally gonna copy
the whole thing in here and then I'm
just gonna clip out most of it right so
I'm gonna start by just getting rid of
almost everything that there is in here
and then we're just gonna go from there
so we know that we don't have to load
sounds so that can go we probably don't
even need read entire file because we
won't be loading any files we're asking
the operating system to load them for us
I think so I'm just gonna cut all of
that out we don't need to load BMPs so
really we're just talking about this
right you can see us doing a create font
a add resource month this is us asking
the operating system to you know get
fonts for us right so this is our font
code that does its you know does it's a
little dance
we've got the font stuff all through
here with the DC and the glyph
processing and all that stuff I don't
know what oh this part was for the STB
path right which we're not doing that
was just one day I showed how to use
that path we don't care about that so we
can get rid of that so it's pretty much
just this we can then get rid of all
this stuff because this was our sound
stuff and we obviously already
that copied into our game the way that
we wanted it as well we don't need any
of this asset type stuff or any of this
stuff because again we're not really
going to have to do any of that
I'm gonna save ad font asset not because
we actually need it but because I just
wanted to see you know what we were
getting for these values we'll want to
persist the that idea forward so we want
to keep though like how we were getting
it out of the loaded font stuff there
and where those were getting recorded
and crap like that so we'll we'll look
at that in a second but otherwise we
don't really need this stuff we don't
need the ability to write hhas that's
not necessary so really all we were
looking at here is just the thing that
does the font part of this so in here we
will we will need this part so you know
when we do the font loading that we
don't need any of this and then we're
back down to just the stuff where we
actually do the font style stuff alright
just keep that in there for now so
here's where we do the font creation
stuff the hero here we did that and the
non hero and the sounds all that stuff
was just old code we don't care about so
let's go ahead and grab that out of here
and then what we can do is say let's
just focus on this stuff now it looks
like the way this was going is yeah so
you know like the right HHA part that
was this so you know this part here it
just kind of comes down in here this
part here was the initialization side of
things
and so you know that's probably this
this part will probably come down here
temporarily there we go
we're gonna move that probably out to
some kind of a well I guess we're gonna
call the thing ourselves probably from
like the command line or something
so this ad font asset here this part
looks like it kind of needs you to
already have loaded the font maybe I
don't know but I'm gonna put that right
here for now and then we're just gonna
take a quick look here what's happening
we've kind of got our okay so we don't
really care about any of this like I
don't care about freeing the font
because this thing doesn't need to ever
do that yeah so we really don't care
about freeing the memory or any of this
stuff because we're just gonna do one
font and leave and if you want to do
multiple fonts you can just call it
multiple times so I think all this is
fine I don't know if there's any let's
see that all seems fine finalized font
kerning feel like that can just be done
[Music]
maybe in here directly which is fine so
we get rid of that stuff again I'm just
trying to make this as simple as
possible and then hopefully we can
collapse a lot of this down initialize
font DC I'm not really sure where that
is happening at the moment probably in
here somewhere where is that happening
so it looks like that's just something
that happens as a matter of course and
only has to occur once so that I think
is something we could just do inside the
routine again directly so if I just that
can just start out that way and then
what's going on here so this load font
is just that yeah it's just the way we
get the font out of here so that this
also is something that could be done
directly so we really I think only have
one function the function is load glyph
bitmap I think that's it
I think everything else is all just one
big long glob of do this then do that
that doesn't really need to be done more
than once right so I think this should
all be fine and we can probably weld
this all together and be done with it so
if I get rid of this code and put in
here the loading code right there then I
think we're ready to make this thing you
know do its do its thing we can kind of
go from here so I'm gonna save this
information just as knowledge of what we
were using for fonts cuz I don't
remember what it was that we did at the
time so that we can actually call it
with that from like the command line or
something and see if we can reproduce
the same data that we had before for
example but for now what I want to do is
say look what we know we need is we know
we know we need a TTF file name we know
we need a font name and we know we need
a like a value that says how how
they you know how how what the point
size of that font should be so we know
that we need these things and we need to
get all of them so we kind of just want
to say look if the arg count isn't for
this thing ain't gonna work so we should
just say look if you don't give us that
we are going to give you an error and
we're going to tell you that the way to
run this thing is to say you know
TTF file name fontname point size right
so that will allow it to print out the
usage for people who don't know what
they're doing or for me when I forget
what the you know what the actual values
are and then if we assume that we
actually got that then what we're gonna
do is say well the first one was the
TTFN the second one was the font and
then we'll ask for the point size like
this or something right and that'll be
you know that'll be sufficient for our
purposes once we get those things then
what we want to do is inside this call
here we're gonna call the right fonts
call with this information so we would
do or you know maybe it's called extract
font that's sort of more what we're
doing here so here's the file name
here's the font name here's the point
size and then extract font is the new
name of this thing so if I then sort of
get this stuff out of the way then we've
got you know we're sort of ready to go
here we're gonna need Windows so we can
we can pre say you know since we're
extracting it here we're gonna need like
you know obviously standard IO dot H
but we're also gonna need like Windows H
right because we're extracting these
things from Windows so that's you know
we've got to get that from somewhere and
we'll have to include you know I I guess
what's it what is it platform or is it
types handmade types so it looks like
handmade types is what we would want to
for all of our types cuz I want like all
of my normal stuff in here right and and
we don't really know yet exactly whether
we're gonna use we probably won't be
dumping bitmaps we'll probably try to
write out a PNG just because that's what
our game load path is built around so
rather than add a BMP loader which
admittedly would be trivial we might as
well just like dump an uncompressed PNG
since you can do that it probably
wouldn't be very hard to just write one
of those directly so we would probably
do that looking at this code now let's
just try and make this make sense for a
load glyph bitmap and we'll see what's
happening there so we need a glyph index
so we need some idea of like what glyph
index it's going to be that seems like
that might actually be somewhat tricky
[Music]
I'm not sure if we maybe want to pass
that in so we've got this thing called
Global font bits that we must have
allocated somewhere here oops
that's not what I wanted
so it looks like that what's happening
is that gets created in the this call
here right so inside here we're actually
using this device context and we can
have our font bits pointer as well so
why don't actually know where that is
where is our global font bits there it
is
so that was just a void star so here's
our font bits we would create that here
and then we are selecting these things
in there the bitmap and the color all
that looks fine right so this sets up
our windows you know this sets up what
we need to do for windows it basically
looks like that
right so let's just call this like set
up our windows rendering rendering
buffer I guess
and so font bits becomes the place where
these things would actually be loaded we
then are gonna malloc a loaded font I'm
gonna ignore that for now and we'll
figure out what we want to do with that
later we have the font file name here so
we're gonna you know we know what that
is looks like this this is apparently
not the point size this is the pixel
height so I guess I want to say here
that's actually pixel height that's good
cuz I don't really care about point size
as a dumb name anyway so that's a little
bit clearer what's happening there so
let's see if we pass in the pixel height
then this will do what we want it to do
still right so this basically this loads
the font right
and I suppose in here because this is a
command-line utility we probably want to
issue an error message if for some
reason we cannot acquire the font as we
expect now I don't really know the best
way because since this is a font mapping
kind of thing there's a lot of issues
that happen here and I don't know what
all the marks I don't usually work with
the windows font system so for example I
don't know if you told it to load a font
that was already loaded I don't know
what this would tell you right so if we
said like load this Arial TTFN it's like
I already have that loaded I don't know
if this was return of zero and so I'm
not sure if checking that is the right
thing to do and furthermore this like if
this thing can't add it because it was
already added I'm assuming this would
then load that existing font so I don't
think there's like I don't know if
there's any way in Windows to say I'm
trying to render this specific TTF file
load it and render it I don't you know
because when Windows in their
infinitesimal wisdom doesn't have that
functionality in their API I don't think
so I'm not sure how we want to do this
it may be the case that we just have to
use create font a and assume for our
purposes that when we're doing this
whatever comes back from here is the
thing that will check for error it's not
perfect but I'm guessing that's the best
thing to do so if we get in back no
right
then we should stop and so we'll just
print out the TTF file name and the font
name here and call it a day so that's
all I'm gonna do there when we get down
to here we want to just select this font
I'm not sure what this text metric bit
is here that that was coming from where
is that other code here so who actually
loaded like who set up that text metric
oh I see
we're actually requesting it so I should
be able to have that let me let me grab
that out of here so I should be able to
actually fetch that here and then be
good to go so this will select it in
there this will get the metrics for it
so that we're good to go the rest of
this stuff now I'm gonna just say
alright let's you know oops
do a min code point max code point these
can just be done this way I like this
always good so once we get here one past
one past max font code point to be
honest I assume we selected that because
that's the highest Unicode code point we
ever would want to look for so I guess
what I would say there is I just say I
don't know that early needs to be a
pound of fine that could just be you 32
uh
so I might just say this and and do that
right that seems reasonable to me and
we'll just leave it like that
so glyph index from code point then
becomes a local like so and we allocate
however big we wanted that to be and we
clear it right and again just because
we're now just doing this entirely local
into one like flat simple routine that
extracts the fonts we don't really need
to store these things in any kind of
external structure we can just keep them
all you know where they should go now
HHA font glyph we don't really need and
so I think we may want to just sort of I
mean we could keep it there for now but
we don't really need to call it that so
I don't know how I feel about this at
the immediate moment I'm gonna leave it
in like I said the present time but I
you know this probably isn't something
that I would keep named this way I would
probably just call it font cliff or
something right because we do need to
remember this information but we don't
need to write it out into an HHA we're
just gonna dump a text file and so yeah
you get the idea alright so I think
that's reasonable
[Music]
that all seems fine so the glyphs would
go here that's all fine and that all
seems fine the max glyph count it's fine
the horizontal advance is fine all this
is fine oops so that's going to be
something that we want to copy what's
happening here clearing that seems fine
to all this seems reasonable
yeah all right so the glyph count as it
turns out we want to start at one we
want the the initial stuff to be cleared
it looks like then we're sort of going
to start filling out the basic asset
data at the moment again we really don't
need to write any of this out this way
this will all be tracked automatically
so mostly all we need to do here is
remember what these are these can this
could really be done anywhere because we
can get it directly on the test
semester's if we want to but for right
now I'm just gonna say let's let's do it
like this so that we can access it
easily as we go forward so that's all
fine we don't care about this we don't
care about this we don't care about that
so really what we need to know here so
this part I'm really not sure how we
want to proceed I guess what we probably
want to do is just provide some
information about what kind of thought
extraction you are doing so for now we
only have
American English right in the future
let's say you want to localize so you
want to do a character set from a single
font that has a bunch of European
language support as well so maybe you've
got you know cedilha and stuff for you
know see with cedilha
or you want to do an umlaut or something
like this right so these are basically
collections of code points that you want
to extract and so we kind of need
something that says what those should be
we basically need an array of like here
or all the code points we expect to have
and so that's sort of a separate thing
that I'm gonna pull out and figure out
how to feed in here so that there's like
an additional command line parameter
that's like which font set did you want
does that make sense and that way then
later like I said you know someone wants
to do a Korean localized version or
Japanese localized version or someone's
trying to add support for Farsi or
whatever else there's gonna be all these
extra Unicode code points that you need
and you might not want like if you're
gonna be doing like a Farsi version that
may come from a font that doesn't have
any you know Roman letters in it because
the Roman letters are going to be coming
from a different font if you're using
them so you only care about this font
for Farsi or you only care about this
font for you know Mandarin and so
assuming that you have it broken down
like that we need a way for the font
utility to basically take like a key
word that says which types of glyphs are
we trying to extract here and so that
over time if we want to we can add more
of those as we choose to add like
language support so that's what I want
to do here I want to add another thing
here there's gonna be a lot of arguments
this thing so there's gonna be pixel
height there's gonna be like care set
right
and we're just gonna have to go through
here and have some set of like names for
these things so we're gonna need like a
thing that's you know something like
this let's say so it would have like a
name like what do you want this care set
to be called and then it would have a
function right so there'd be some kind
of a callback here
that's like what's the care set in
question so it would be like yeah care
set creator name and the name is the
function in this case something gets
called here that we don't know what it
is but we'll fill it out later and then
we have a you know a pipe def here where
we say this is a care set creator
callback right or function something
like that so that's all we need then we
can have this have you know whatever the
function is that you call and so when we
go through here what we can do is print
out all of those so we can make a little
you know a little thing here where we
say oops there we go
so I don't know what this is maybe this
is just like basic English right so this
is like I just our test like basic
English or basic test
I don't even yeah maybe it's just test
right so we don't even it like it's got
the kanji owl in there it's not basic
English it's got some other stuff in
there so we're just we're not even
pretending that it's a real character
set it's not something that really maps
to anything that you particularly need
um I'll just do static here although
what do we have what do we have there
global global variable so we've got a
care set creator here that's gonna be
all of our care sets looks like that and
maybe just global yeah that's what is
and each of these is gonna have a name
[Music]
and a pointer right so I guess I'll just
call this test test and these can then
be looped over and print it out so I can
do like care set index is less than
array account care sets don't ask me why
this isn't this way because it should be
that seems good and then you know we'll
just loop over these and we print out
what they actually were so we would say
there's maybe I'm feeling really
generous and so each of these things
where we've got these care sets we would
say care set index dot name and I'll
even throw in for you
because I'm just that nice a guy
description so that you know you don't
have to guess what kinds of characters
are involved there maybe it just says
right so this way we can have a sort of
a way of doing a rudimentary sort of
extends extension service so that anyone
who wants to like add new care sets just
defines a new karasek creator and will
make this code in here pretty easy to do
and that way it's you know it's trivial
to make that an actual you know you know
you want to add a new language you just
kind of add a new care set crater and
you know takes ten seconds and off
you're off and running because the code
inside handmade hero doesn't care at all
about how you address those fonts so you
know if you want to be creative and hey
we're gonna specialize vertical printed
traditional Japanese right-to-left
reading you know go nuts right and this
would let you extract you could put in
like what the character ranges are that
you want and you know just go from there
and I think the code in the game would
then just support it just fine
so if we do that then what we need is in
here we need some way of actually
calling one of those functions so what I
want to do is introduce a boolean that's
like you know print usage or something
and so what I'd rather do is have this
immediate and and maybe actually I do it
the other way around now I'm thinking
about it maybe I do it like this like
that and that way we could do by default
print out the usage if everything goes
like perfectly then great but otherwise
we're going to print this out
and so in here what we do is we'll loop
over these again and I'll just grab this
out and say look we're gonna try and
match the string so we're gonna do a
string comp
on this to see if the care sets care set
index and maybe I'll actually pull this
out like so
we'll just look and see does this
particular character set match the name
that was given on the command line right
so that's that
so I'll test that if I find one then
we're in good shape and we'll call it
and we can say that we found the care
set and everyone's happy so maybe do it
this way so I'll just remember which one
it is here this should probably be
called test actually this should be
called peleset care set creator just to
be supposed about what's going on there
so we'll test each of these if we find
one then we remember which one it was
so then later what we could say is look
did we find a karasek creator because i
don't know also the care set name should
come in here it's as args 4 and the care
set name in this case will be matched
when it matches if it matches we get
that if we see that we'll try to extract
otherwise we won't and we'll say you
know error could not match character set
or unrecognized character set
and we'll say look man I don't know what
you're talking about
right so that's will allow us to have
sort of a easy system for just extending
which character sets you can extract
using this utility because the utility
doesn't care and the game doesn't care
so we might as well have a good way to
do that and so really then all we need
to do is call that function so in here
we would say the karasek creator that
you talked about we'll call it before we
try to extract the font
that'll make sure that we can actually
you know and I mean we can even just
pass in the karasek creator to be honest
I suppose that would work too but either
way so we'll do whatever we have to do
here to make sure that works and then
we'll come through and extract the fonts
given whatever that character set ends
up being we'll figure out what that
looks like in a second and that'll
determine what this looks like right so
coming through here what do we want to
do now in extract ok so you can see in
here let's get back to where we were at
we sort of malloc some memory for
processing here we went through and
started doing our thing this stuff we
don't care about at all because someone
else is gonna add that stuff right so we
don't care about any of that we don't
care about this we also don't care about
that because that's actually already
happening right here no one's touching
the Weisse context so that's just
redundant in here where we get the
kerning pairs out that all looks fine I
don't see anything special happening
there to you it seems fine to me we run
through the kerning pairs so so this one
pass mass font code point bit there
right we're just going to make sure that
those get sort of clipped
that all looks fine and we're filling
out the horizontal advance table so that
all looks looks totally fine I don't see
anything weird happening there when we
come through here
this is just our way of writing out all
of our glyphs we're not going to do it
that way anymore right because we're
gonna actually have to put these into a
hht tag file that we dump out the
horizontal advanced part of things here
so the horizontal advanced slicing thing
that's just again not going to matter
because that's something that we're
gonna export into text so we don't have
to deal with that at all
so that all seems fine I must have
missed when I was copying the code out
the part where we actually try to export
one of these is it this it's not
so how do we actually end up calling
load with bitmap yeah I'm saying to you
huh
so you're telling me we never call load
glyph bitmap what am I missing
oops
that seems weird would you not agree
with that like shouldn't someone be
calling load glyph bitmap at some point
here was there was there not oh that's
good I'm in the wrong file there we go
so if we look at what's going on here
these got added as bitmaps and we just
called them with this that's literally
all we did so that's pretty boring and
like exactly what we'd expect so there
there wasn't anything I mean it's good
news I guess
there isn't anything we have to do
besides basically this you know for
every font in the system there right we
would have to do that so I think that's
it and that data is going to be coming
from the like whatever our care set
creator
however we specify how that dumps out
what those code points are that's the
part that we have to do there right so
we'll want to make that work in some
reasonable way let's see so
part so one thing I'm a little hazy on
here is we we allocate space for the max
glyph count but like we should know how
many glyphs were doing because we should
be able to just say like this is how
many glyphs there are so I don't know
why the max glyph count nonsense
is happening so I think what I would
prefer is I think the the code for care
set creator should spit out here's how
many characters we expect because it
knows how many it wants mapped so I feel
like max lifts count is just dumb and
doesn't need to happen at all right I
just I just don't see the point of that
to me that there's there's no point
because if we looking here at how that's
actually used right it's just used to
specula allocate you know if it's just
there for no real reason so so I I don't
I don't see the point so I think what
I'd rather do is say look there's a
glyph count and that's something we're
actually going to be supplied with so
like this is how many glyphs and here's
the array of what their code points are
that should just be supplied so you know
something like this so you basically say
here's many glyphs there are here's what
the code points are for each individual
glyph so glyph index you know this right
glyph index from code point has to be
allocated like really wide because it's
trying to map a glyph I'm sorry it's
trying to matter code point back to a
glyph but the glyph count which is our
compacted array that
we just know so there's no point in
putting a 5,000 glyph limit on it when
we can just say here's how many we
wanted and be done so everything else in
here should be able to just go from the
glyph count directly so this right that
should be sufficient and then all the
rest of this stuff can work exactly as
it was this doesn't matter that is good
because we do need this to be you know
zeroed out or however you want to say
that but everything else here should
just work off the back lift count
directly so all this stuff seems fine
[Music]
again no max lift count necessary the
glyph count is exactly what it should be
there and so all that stuff should just
work then we should be able to literally
write this routine directly to now where
we can just say look here's the glyph
index we wanted we don't need to write
out zero because we know that that's not
an actual valid glyph index we'll go
from one to the glyph count in here
we'll say the glyph oops
with code point we know that it's
whatever the glyph index is in that
array gives us what we want this I don't
know what we're gonna do with right now
so we'll deal with that in a second but
looking at what this routine actually
needs to take we should be able to
simplify it a little bit now right so
the glyph index shouldn't be necessary I
don't think in fact why is that even
being asked for
so that's the reason it's doing that is
just for the horizontal advance table
which we could probably do on the
outside so you can see what's happening
there it's taking whatever the character
advance amount was there and it's kind
of like stuffing that in to the
horizontal advance table again that all
just seems pretty easy so I think we can
probably move that actually to the
outside so the return value of this
could just include that and we can
return we could we can move this to the
outside right like all of this stuff
just needs that care advance so at least
I think that's true so meaning in here
there's a notion of a kerning change
which comes out of here and it happens
if the other glyph index is not zero
right so that's on that first one then
everything else takes that care advance
and puts that in there so if those two
things were just something that came out
of the load glyph bitmap you know
operation then this is something we can
just do right in here you know what I'm
saying so we just need those values to
kind of pop out from that and I mean in
fact they can just they don't need to be
here anymore right so I think we just
need to translate this into something
that stores more than just a loaded
bitmap it actually just gives us all of
the glyph information that we need and
then on the outside we can just process
it that way right the max font with max
font height stuff what are we doing
there so that's just the biggest
character we can handle right again to
me that sort of seems like it should be
maybe more based on the pixel height
probably like you know if you told us
that the biggest pixel high
was blah we would say I mean you know
and the other question I have is can we
just get that from Windows do the text
metrics tell us anything like that so we
wouldn't have to guess or have limits
where we could we could we just ask it
what's the biggest thing that's ever
gonna happen in terms of an actual glyph
size because you you probably should
know that right
so just me where's the search bar there
it is so here's that get text metrics
function and here's what it returns so
you know looking at it here that is
probably what we would need to know like
you know for though for the width right
and we can even like double it or
something right we could we could put in
a safety factor there too if we think
this might be reported a little bit
Squinkie we could try to pad it out as
well but that gives us something to work
with
right and then the height value again if
we took the height value and padded it
that should also probably tell us so I
don't really know what those values will
correspond to I don't know how good they
would be what's what's overhang
so we may want to include that overhang
as well just to be safe so I'm gonna try
basing it off these things I'm gonna say
look let's try and get the text metrics
out of this thing and then we'll worry
about the you know the and then we'll
worry about allocating everything so if
I did this where I create the compatible
DC first and then we sort of do this
part of the process right so in here I'm
going to say create the device context
and try to load it reverse the order in
which we do these things so create a
compatible DC try to load the font into
it come down into this routine here
where we're ready to start doing stuff
with our fonts and this this field here
now maybe we can get rid of these so
that we don't have to like guess about
what's gonna happen in terms of how big
we would need things to be to properly
support it so to do that I would just
say all right you know select the font
right there get the text metrics out of
it and now we can use those to create
those two values
okay so then in here we'll pass those in
as the sizes and these can come directly
out of the tech symmetric now so the
text metric itself we can do you know TM
height and TM max care with I think we
want to add that overhang but I don't
know
and then we probably want a padding
factor I'm I don't know but I'm just
gonna I'm just gonna double it because I
have no idea how inaccurate mm windows
might be with this so I'm gonna just do
some like ridiculous nonsense here
so since there's not a lot of penalty
for us to just allocate a bigger buffer
than we need I feel like it's pretty
safe for us to do something ridiculous
here right in fact you know whatever
right so I don't think there's any harm
in doing that we can see later if it's
actually necessary and if we care but
you know that at least gives us some
padding and we can kind of move on from
there so if we Alec actually do that
then we can like I like that with here's
the thing called cheese point so as we
kind of move on here what you can see is
we've got some some garbage we're doing
here you can see our pre step X so
actually I'm right to pad this because
we actually leave a bunch of room don't
we it appears so you know that's
probably a good thing so you can see us
sort of bounding this stuff here so
we're gonna need these values when we
come into the program so that it knows
you know what the actual boundaries are
it's supposed to be keeping itself
aligned to which shouldn't be hard
looking at the rest of this stuff yeah I
don't I don't see anything else too
weird going on there um so maybe what
I'll do in our types file do we have V
to use in here I think we do yeah we do
so what I might say is like maybe the
way we'll do this is will actually say
that there's a V to u called max cliff
dimension you know and that's going to
be this nonsense here
and then these can just be passed that
way and then so when they come in to not
that when we come into here when we do
loaded fonts to our font code point
right then what we can do in here is say
look let's start passing things like
what's the max glyph dimension
that'll be passed in here I don't know
what order these things are going but
let's say that there's that there so now
everything that was doing max font with
so or an max font height like that what
we could do is say you know max glyph
Jim X x max with Tim Y right
and that seems fine same here nowhere
else these are used so yeah that mmm
looks like we're just kind of monkeying
around here that's the height right yeah
[Music]
whoa that was weird my second screen
here that's the capture machine just
blanked is the stream still alive looks
like it's still alive I don't see any
dropped frames reporting
so good alright um okay so max fought
with again it's just just this so I
think these can all just be done this
way and that should just do it so we can
pass that in pretty trivially the glyph
index and the code point can both be
passed in here if for some reason we
need it but I don't actually think we do
so so this isn't a non-issue now this
also doesn't have to happen because
that's always the case and so I think
this stuff can now just run straight
through all of this is fine there's
nothing weird going on there
this device context will just pass in
like so I don't know does this stuff so
does this sex the set text color call I
don't know that anyone ever actually
sets it to anything else so I would
assume that that's also something that
doesn't actually have to yeah so that
could actually just be done here where
we set the background and the text color
as a separate permanent things they
don't have to really be done here
apparently this doesn't have to happen
either I guess we tried that at one
point and didn't really need it so it
looks like we're just doing that let's
see here so these are actually I don't
know why these are set to like these
numbers I assume that this should
actually be set to this and this should
be set to
or rather I assume
famous last words maybe I just broke the
entire thing you know I don't know but
off we go
so this stuff and that's just we're just
reading out of the font bits there so we
would need to have that passed in for us
but that's pretty straightforward too so
that seems fine
bitmap bytes per pixel I'm pretty sure
that's just always for like did we
actually support anything else besides
that
I like this that's good stuff
so bitmap bytes for pic per pixel I
don't I don't have any idea where that
if some is gonna what for her to find it
for me
yes so that's just that's just always
four so I'm gonna put that in there I
don't I don't know what we were really
playing out there it's not like that
code would probably really work if we
weren't doing that like we don't really
support you know arbitrary bytes per
pixel for bitmaps or anything like that
so that's kind of a one of those things
that's maybe not not really quite true
so I'm not sure why that that looks like
that because I mean like even just look
up at this code here you know we're
we're just assuming that there's four
bytes four pixels so that's you know we
didn't really write code that's you know
supposed to be flexible in that way so I
really don't know what the point is of
that so if we look in here we've got the
stuff where we want to actually create
the bitmap in question this that's what
this is doing you know this is like
packing these texels so we we malloc
this as the thing that we're gonna
return but again I we don't actually
have to do that because I think what
we're gonna want to do is write it out
right here so I think we probably want
to do instead is something more like
this where we have like something like
this
and so in here this way we can write
this out in into a file when we're ready
and otherwise not really bother anybody
so I think that's all fine that's fine
we're gonna need these helper functions
this is basically just something we're
using to do our premultiplied alpha that
all seems fine and then this is us
computing the align percentage so that's
some pretty Squinkie stuff there but you
know that's this just somewhere to store
it and this is out height the TM descent
is something that we would need to pass
in here so you know I guess we'll pass
that in I don't know what bound height
is I guess that's something that we
found in here right like that's what we
found in terms of like the total area of
the thing that we looked through so
we're just like flipping things around
and doing whatever nonsense there this
actually also I don't know that that can
ever actually be float right because
it's it's gonna be a yeah it's gonna be
a regular value so really you know it's
more like that this whole thing gets
converted after being computed and then
we can go from there so all that stuff
seems fine this seems fine too
[Music]
I think that's basically it so really
all we need to do here is actually you
know this has to do it to do of right
out of PNG right we need something that
can can put this to disk but that's
really all we need to do and then we can
delete the memory that we were using to
house it if we were less Squinkie we
could actually just write it out
directly and that might be a more
reasonable thing to do but for now I'm
just gonna use the code path as it was
rather than you know fuss with it so I
think that's what we're looking at we
don't really have a loaded bitmap per se
so what we want here and we don't need
that what we want here is like a
something that we can return the results
in so like this would be like a glyph
result or something and so we want to
return one of these and we want to
return the stuff that we would actually
need on the outside to like write this
thing into a text file properly you know
we could also just write it out
ourselves but that just doesn't seem
necessary so you know let's say we got
the align percentage here that needs to
be stored and we've got what was some of
the other stuff here we needed kerning
change and care advance
so we want to record these and send them
back to whoever's listening so once we
come in here what we want to do in fact
I guess I don't even really need to
define it there I can put it down here
probably and say all right so the things
that are happening is that that and that
so this yeah I guess maybe I do want it
this way now let's give it away all
right so this will just be actually
calling a v2 now and doing its thing and
then this will assign it so up here
we'll just say and you know I mean we
don't really have to do it that way we
could do it some other way think the
default is always this so I'll continue
defaulting to that for now but I think
that's what we want now I would like to
start trying to build this we won't have
time today because we only got a you
know maybe 15 minutes 20 minutes left to
get all of this working properly but I
would like to go ahead and make this
actually get called these I don't know
why these are getting built at the
moment so we don't need them to be so I
think
yeah I think all this is fine except
instead of test a set builder cpp here
we just want to build HH font and
that'll let us just builds yep the
simple command-line utility I don't know
so I guess if you don't put subsystem
windows in there then it will just do
console automatically that's probably
the rule so we should that should
produce a command line executable I
would think we'll cross that bridge when
we come to it
so let me go ahead and go through get
rid of some of the errors here I'm just
gonna go ahead and well so I don't know
if we want these do we want these to be
s 32s do we actually use negative values
for them I don't think we should but I
guess if we're stepping s 32s here we
would have to so let's think about that
so the min would be this and the max
would be zero I think that's how that
would work and then all of these would
be you 32s because we can't we're never
going to be you can't step outside the
bitmap right I don't think so all of
these should be u-32 a bowl I think but
that's again famous last words
but yeah I mean this looks like it's
written that way already right because
if this this would fetch outside the the
legal area if you were fitting it-
members so that's just not you know
that's not something that was
contemplated about to it anyway now
let's see what else we got here that's
that so these we need to get from
somewhere else see here what's the
problem
TM descent that's true we don't have
that and we need to know it so in here
we would have to pass damn descents
we're gonna have to load those in there
what is the problem here Oh cuz we
aren't including the math library yet
that's fine so this needs to be just
device context it would have been here -
but we're not compiling that code pace
or code path rather so these can these
this can't be negative can they hope the
camp I'm not sure what would happen if
they were but hopefully they can't be
one thing we could do here is if we
don't know we could add overhang to both
because we don't know whether that
overhang is for vertical or horizontal
they didn't specify I don't think maybe
they did but I didn't see it
all right so then we've got basically
just this code to get trapper and then
and then we're good to go all right so
you know we're pretty close here there's
not that much to do to just get it
working to up to the point where we're
running font extraction and actually
pulling all the glyphs out and the
information we need we're just not
actually writing them anywhere which is
fine I think that would be a good place
to get to
and then next weekend we can focus on
writing them out and reading them back
in during asset update and then I think
we're I think that leaves us at a point
where we can just do full rebuilds
anytime we want no no weirdness so if I
were to include the math side of things
I think that's what happens here I don't
remember how to get those functions yeah
so if I include the math side of things
basically we get all of the stuff up
there will work now and we're really
just down to this side of things and so
you know for each of these we want to
call the load lift bitmap routine so
let's actually try to call that properly
so here's here's what happened there
you know maybe we do this and we say
okay there's the device context the font
bits we need the code point so that's
this right that's the code point we're
talking about the max left in we already
have the TM descent is again coming from
those text metrics so that's something
we can just pull out here because we
know that the bitmap nonsense like needs
to to fuss with that when it's doing its
extraction so assuming that that call is
fine then we need to loop over the other
glyphs that we have which is this and
fill out the horizontal advance table by
looking at the
if index were on and for every entry in
the table for our glyph we need to add
this information that comes back and it
needs to depend on you know what's
what's happening here why this looks
like this I don't know I guess that's
saying if this font is following itself
so that's what's happening here it's
saying like if this font is following
itself here's what you have to do is
that right oh no I see what it's saying
it's saying the other side's advance for
me has to be adjusted by whatever the
kerning change is yeah this stuff is
nuts I've never liked the way kerning
was reported in Windows and yeah and I
still don't
so this just tells me how I need to
update this these both come out of the
glyph which should make it pretty
trivial right it's just that and so I
think that's basically it
does font bits actually need to be au8
can it just be a void here so that gets
us down to almost completed all we have
to do now is we good all we have to do
now is actually decide how our font like
this code that says what font is
happening where we need that to to now
like have a more specific like we need a
definition of how that works you can see
here that we want to do a glyph count in
a glyph code point so we need like this
right and so what we need to do here is
have some way of saying hey care set
creator like you need to return to us
whatever that piece of information is
right so like you need to tell us how
many of these things there are right so
maybe what we could do is we could say
something like the glyph count is set
here right so you know well but that
makes it harder for people to use so
maybe we won't do that
maybe we will try to make a little
utility that lets you do this more
easily so let's try that first so let's
say we were gonna do this this obviously
is nonsense and doesn't matter so what
we tried to do here is said okay add
this character range add these specific
characters right so what we're kind of
doing here is saying something like
because like imagine this was the thing
that looked like this
or like that
so imagine me we're doing something more
like that and then here we would just
say okay include code-point include or
include maybe we make this really easy
so we just say okay include you know
this include from here to here include
these you know something like this right
so we want to be able to say like
include these ranges or these
punctuation x' or this specific
character and blah blah blah so if we
want to do something like that then what
we want to be able to do is we want to
be able to first count how many there
are and then we want to be able to like
set a thing that says what they all
would be right
I also think maybe I don't need to have
any maximums in this at all because if
you look at the one past max font code
point that could just be passed in as
the actual maximum code point that you
asked for right so we don't really need
to have a hard-coded maximum because
whatever they like the furthest one you
asked for was that's the end of it so I
think what I'm going to do is I'm going
to say all right let's say we have a
like code point code point mass I don't
know so there's something like okay
there's a glyph count there's a like
code point for glyph or you know code
point from glyph map and there's then
there's like a max code point or one
passed last code point so like this
would let you know everything that you
needed to when you get this you don't
have to guess anymore so you don't have
to have any hard-coded maximums right so
in here we would say all right
give us the code point mask and the code
point mask will tell us all the other
things that we needed to know so instead
of getting passed in a glyph count and a
one pass max amount code point like this
stuff right these will just get
extracted out of here
so the end I guess we also needed the
what was it like code point for our
glyph code points like that so this
would tell us everything that we needed
to know and that's what we will try to
make work as far as as far as like a
convenient way to make that happen from
our from our character range generators
and I think one really easy way to do
this is we could cheese out like super
Squinkie we could do some super squeaky
cheese on this where we basically said
all right look you pass in a mask you
know I'm saying I and so this thing gets
a mask and it just does this right and
what we do is we say inside the include
and include range right and include just
like this
maybe again this is just for making it
convenient so that people you know can
just have these not people they can just
use them tribulation have to make like a
raise and pass like a rate counts or
nonsense like this again it's just
working around C++ being a garbage
language so in here you know I want to
do my include stuff and we can even sort
of do the super crappy version here
where we call down to this other
function as well right so I think what
we would want to do is just make this
work in a way that based on whether the
mask is initialized or not you either
just record the maximum or you actually
build the array and so you know I a lot
of purple flashes today so if we were to
proceed here we just do like B index
index is less than a red count II plus
plus index so for each of these we would
just say okay if the mask code point
from glyph is set then we are quit
poking into the mask so we're gonna say
the code point from glyph of E e index
equals well this code point from glyph
so we actually need it to be that
right so we're saying all right the the
glyph count will advance and we'll store
which one we're going to store in there
if instead the code point from glyph is
not set then really all we had to do was
increment the glyph count and I guess
that happens either way so we could just
leave that on the outside
in fact I guess these both can happen
either way so we might just say look the
code point is that store it and then say
if the one past max code point is
actually less than or equal to the code
point then you need to set it right
so that's we'll do both functions which
means now if we want this thing to work
in this nice simple way where anyone who
wants to do a care set can literally
just define this garbage right here and
have it work then all we would have to
do is call it twice so the first time we
call it we say oh we've got a code point
mask and the code point mask is nothing
so go ahead and fill that out now we
won't have a code point that has the
maximum Xand stuff in it properly so
what we can then do is say all right or
it you know and this could be our
counter mask so we could literally just
call it and remember that we can then
say okay here's the actual mask that
we're going to use please fill that out
oops and all we're going to do is right
before then the actual array that's in
there that we you know that we want to
to fill out all we're gonna do is we're
gonna malloc vat array right so all
we're doing is saying take whatever the
counter mass says the glyph count was
and go from there now we don't want the
person to have to include zero
so in order to make this work we
actually want to always reserve space
like this
which is not you know maybe the nicest
thing in the world to have to do but
it's fine right so I think that's fine
and then when we actually call this it
will fill it out because now there is an
actual pointer there and so it'll know
what it should actually extract right so
I think that should be fine let's see if
we've got this down here that is total
garbage
[Music]
all right so that built and so now we've
got our utility done but not you know
debugged at least I think so is that not
that should have built an X
so it's our built I guess our build
directory isn't in the bin so let's take
care of that too while we're at it
oops sue if I come through here and I'm
assuming that HHA it's there yes so we
just want one of these right but we want
this for the font file so we want like h
h font bat and we want that to look like
this so that we can call it from
anywhere there we go so now if I do this
yeah it should say like hey this is the
usage and here are the Kara set values
that you can actually supply in theory I
can actually call this something and it
will you know presumably roll over and
die or something but we can't actually
make it run so if I wanted to will and
will like to bug it and stuff next time
but if we take a quick look here let me
say I pass like one of these things I
should print out - what we're like what
we're looking at here so maybe like a
little bit of status would be nice why I
did that how did that compile I must
have accidentally deleted it with a
errant keystroke there so when we're
doing this I might go ahead and do just
a printf that says hey like here's what
I'm trying to extract right like
extracting font you know blob and it'll
say like you know this mini glyphs code
points
right
something like that I don't know this is
really crappy way to print that out
I don't really super care what it says I
just wanted to put these in here and
then you know when we're done we're done
I don't know why that says true that's
supposed to say false
so yeah in theory you know this will do
something resembling something we need
to pass the font name there which is
what name yeah so if I call this with
some actual like one of these that we
had here so if I just like pass all of
that yeah that looks fine and that's
what's still error because it should not
have a care set so if I pass it a care
set yeah okay so we got a debug --it and
who knows what's going on there
I mean maybe we should do a little of
that right now because we started a
little bit late so maybe I should you
know at least UNCHR ashes
but other than that we're probably done
for the day so if I go into the bill
directory and make an actual startup for
this here is the command line that in
theory does something let's put those in
there working directory doesn't really
matter at the moment so let's go ahead
and save that into our build directory I
think that's in having into our debug
directory as ehh font dot r DB g and
that way they could switch between these
really quickly right you know what we're
devoting whether it's the font thing or
whatever so just show me I just want
this to show me where I crashed so it
looks like we're crashing inside some
kind of a malloc they're not sure why I
can't
so recent I can't get source here is
that so I can step in just fine I guess
it just doesn't know where I am
let me compile in debug mode and we'll
just take a look and see if it can give
us a better better handle all right okay
so let's see where we're at here what is
the value of mask sorry what is the
value of mask here
she's
all right
so we're in here that seems fine let's
take a look here at TTF file name oh
that's just garbage it's weird that that
didn't give me an error but oh well oh
no it's not no it's not that's actually
fine
so is it this this printf that's giving
us the the issue yeah so what's the
problem there is there something weird
about what we're printing extracting
font % s % u % u so what's the font name
that seems fine
what's the glyph count seems fine what's
the one pass the max code point hmm so
what's the what's the issue there we're
seriously having a crash in there what
am I missing
we're hitting some kind of a breakpoint
there like it doesn't like something but
I'm not sure what it is I must just be
tired
hmm
so I suppose one thing that could be
happening there is if we were doing
something stupid like when we actually
do this initialization of course the
other thing I forgot is we didn't clear
this we expect this to be cleared that
has nothing to do that because we're not
getting to that point but this
definitely wants to happen there so that
you know we get that nice and cleared so
I'm not sure yeah like if we were over
writing something maybe where this was
concerning us we kind of threw that in
there pretty hastily the way that this
actually works when it's writing in
there it's just running into the glyph
count plus plus oh that pretty much
everything you need to know right there
I was supposed to delete that plus plus
when we added this and I didn't
so that should probably solve our
problem yeah it does so that was boring
and stupid so I think we're good to go
now
looks like we're fine so I think we can
go ahead and go to QA yeah
so that does a glyph extraction and off
it goes I will say that the number of
glyphs listed there doesn't really make
any sense so I feel like I must have
screwed something up
[Music]
yes if you're not checking to make sure
that we don't include glyphs that are
zero so that's actually fine
we can also mmm so we might also want to
make sure we don't include code points
that already exists so we could have I
suppose gonna look up there but I'm not
really gonna worry about that so much
that could be someone else's problem but
I think we want this there we go a
hundred glyphs is more of what I would
have expected to see like meeting the
ASCII care set plus some of those kanji
that seems good all right so I think
we're good to go and next weekend we can
just merge that in how come I can't how
come I can't make in sohbat listen to me
on the main twitch channel how come
you'll only listen to me if I do it in
the in the handmade network one so I
don't know what to make of that but are
you going to implement the PNG writer
yeah well I think we probably will we'll
just do it uncompressed cuz it's really
not I shouldn't be unless I'm forgetting
something it shouldn't be really any
harder to implement a PNG writer that's
uncompressed then it's just basically
you'll be similar to a bitmap right if
we wanted to do a compressor then you've
got a bunch of work you have to do but
we don't have to do that for any
particular reason
you
yes the windows API does use Hungarian
notation that's why it's called
Hungarian notation right isn't isn't it
Charleston money's like being having
been Hungarian that is the reason why it
is called Hungarian notation
yeah
and he you know was Hungarian and so
there you go right Reese Erlich we had a
yellow for coulda flashed a do we know
about that color flash already I don't
really know what's up with for coders
renderer but this one I don't I guess
this version mmm I think this version
has the green flash code in it but maybe
it doesn't I don't know I don't know
what's up with four coders rendering
stuff I don't know what where those come
from I've never really looked at it
do you think you still improve a lot as
a programmer as post when you first
started I'd be curious to know if there
are specific things you work on to keep
improving um so I guess what I would say
is I feel like there's a like very
there's I feel like there's a really
long I feel like there's a massive
amount of improvement I could do in
terms of my programming ability 99% of
which is not possible in C++ or C C++
right so basically like I feel like I
probably am now about as good as I can
get in this language which is crap so
that's not saying much if that makes
sense
for general programming purposes right
so I feel like I could get really way
further down the line towards being good
at programming if I had a better
language and so you know I think that
just involves making a language or
waiting for someone to make a language
that's any good but basically like so if
I wanted to improve as a programmer
without getting a new language I think
mostly what you have to focus on because
there's plenty of ways I could become a
better programmer without getting a new
language but they don't really involve
coding they involve external knowledge
so like I could learn a lot of different
math things I don't know plenty of
there's always math you don't know right
and so I could go learn that and that
would improve my programming ability in
in the areas where that math is
applicable tremendously but like
improving just the actual act of
day-to-day coding all the things I could
do right now that I'm not doing in terms
of like making the code quo
better they all require a different
language that's just and people claim
that there's other better things you can
do in C++ like here's this new way to
program this thing they're all I don't
agree with any of them I think they're
all just garbage ideas there are clearly
way better ways we could be programming
we do not have the languages to support
them that's what I would say I think
John for what it's worth is potentially
enabling us to start pushing on that
stuff by having really like hardcore
meta programming pre phases in JI
because if you think about like what we
need to do language wise is we need more
people to be able to do experiments with
more language constructs and the way to
do that is not to make some stupid
language decisions at a meeting every
year like C++ does and then force
everyone to use it like that doesn't do
anything that's a waste of everyone's
time the way you need to do things to
find new language constructs that
actually work and produce good quality
code is you need a lot of people
experimenting to find what those things
are right and so I think that that's a
pretty good start and so I think that
that having maybe something like ji
where people can work on their own meta
programming stuff and when we find good
ones they can be kind of like pointed to
and say here's a language feature that
seems like it really creates some really
nice code with not very much effort on
the part of the programmer or whatever
that's more what we need and a lot less
of this like let's get a bunch of people
who think it's actually worth their time
to go to a committee meeting where
everyone will argue about stuff and
nothing gets done and then we adopt some
really crappy standard which is
basically how C++ involves I mean that's
just it's obviously doesn't work like
you can see the past 30 years can tell
you that
that doesn't work so I think there are
way better ways to do it and I'm hoping
that maybe J I will open up one of those
is it hard to write a level editor no
it's not that hard there are more things
you have to worry about but we already
had to worry about some of those like
you know and handmade hero if you run it
[Music]
so you know you're you know if you run
handmade hero I should probably do the
full build here so you know if you just
wrote just a game engine you could
probably avoid writing the stuff but
since we actually have some of that
support in here you know some of the
harder stuff to do like the picking and
stuff we actually already implemented so
you know
some of this stuff where I can like
select individual things by clicking on
them with the mouse like that that's the
sort of thing that you need to add that
you wouldn't have had to add otherwise I
don't actually know if that's something
that is all that hard but having to
unprotect the mouse and that sort of
stuff as an example but there's not a
whole lot more to it than that we showed
how to do like little ad hoc you eyes
here
we didn't go overboard with it so
they're kind of crappy but you know
making a better one is not a huge effort
it's just spending some time polishing
these things so you know I mean really
with this and this you should be able to
more or less make a level editor in hand
in here without a whole lot of effort
right we have block picking in there but
we're not doing that anymore I think
because we shunted the path that renders
the blocks into a different thing that
no longer calls the picking code but I
think that's not hard to add that so you
could have I think you could have done
that was working before
[Music]
um alright so there's a lot of stuff in
here probably not gonna get to all of
these what do you mean by a better
language I just mean a language that
provides more ability for the programmer
to quickly specify what it is they
intended to have the CPU do right
you know I it's hard to go into too much
more detail than that without designing
a whole language and saying like look
here's the better language but that's
the point
language design is inherently a
compression problem the output is known
right we can sit there and go here's the
optimal assembly language code for
pretty much anything like we know how to
do that right we can get a bunch of
expert assembly language programmers in
here and we can say this is the output
that we wanted right if we absolutely
took every little thing and did it 100%
correctly the goal of a programming
language is figure out the lowest amount
of text that you need to enter to get
that thing to be generated right
not only is nobody working on that
problem nobody even frames it is that
problem which is terrible but we haven't
really made any progress in that
direction since see that I know of
so I can't even point to a thing that
we've done since C that actually gets
you closer to that goal right
most of what I see languages do is they
trade the ability to create good code
meaning like efficient CPU output and
what they do is they say in how about
you accept the code getting crappier in
order for you to do less work to specify
it but I am not really that interested
in that like that seems like just being
really defeatist when you start off with
it right and so you know I just that's
what I mean by better language we have
really gotten very far C++ is absolutely
terrible with that you know I would
throw the entire thing away if I were
starting I would I would scrap 100% of
what C++ added to C and you know you'd
start at C and go forward from there I
really like your programming style
returning a struct from a function I've
been using it a lot is it true that it
was not possible to turn a struct from a
function at the early days of C I'm not
really an expert in the early days of C
but what I can tell you is that you know
if you think about what the compiler was
originally sort of set up to do
you could easily have imagined the
initial C compilers as just saying a
return value is like something that's
left in a register right I don't know if
that's how it was implanted originally
but that's a pretty good guess at how it
probably was and so if that was the way
that it was done originally then you
could see why strux would not really
have been returnable because there's
more instructive impe in one register
and so the entire compiler just wouldn't
work so my assumption is that at some
point they expanded the notion of the
binary interface like you know the ABI
to say hey if the return value of a
function doesn't fit in a register like
here's the rules for how we will return
it right and then that just got added
and then from then on you could so I
don't really know when that happened I
don't remember anything like that but
that's probably you know probably what
happened would be Mike if I had to like
randomly work backwards from knowing how
things typically happen in during
development my guess would be the first
compiler for C probably were all about
register Returns and it wasn't probably
until sometime later that someone said
it would be nice if we could return
anything we wanted and then they made a
way to do that
using the stack right if you're making a
game with a lot of on-screen text what
text rendering technique would you think
you'd go for I mean again if that's
really not super relevant on-screen text
is not the thing that makes text
interesting or not I mean it's not I
should say whether or not there's a lot
of text on screen doesn't really have
anything to do with how you would render
it it's more about the nature of that
text right it's exactly the same as
asking the question you've got a lot of
grass in the game how would you render
it and you need to answer a bunch of
questions before you know what the most
efficient way is does the grass need to
move around does it need to move in a
way that isn't really possible to be
baked down to a procedural function do
different parts of grass like as their
level of detail do i zoom in and out on
it right all of that stuff is important
to answer because all of those would
affect if you were trying to say look I
want to really optimize my text
rendering it's more about all of these
other things and not about how much of
it you have obviously if you don't have
very much of it you don't have to care
at all because you probably whatever you
do will be fine but if you do have a lot
of it then you have to answer a lot of
other questions am I going to zoom all
the way in until the top of a tee is
taking up the entire screen am I going
to zoom all the way out so that there
are billions and billions of words on
the screen at once that are all just
like a pixel wide like you know like
what are what are your actual
requirements and then you can start
talking about what actually has to
happen but until then it's kind of a
meaningless question because there's
just tons of different ways you could
and imagined to do it how do you
visualize your logic so easily sometimes
I'll write a complicated function it
will take me potentially hours to debug
or fully understand but it never seems
to be a problem for you I guess I would
say there's two sites that what are two
answers that one is probably just
experienced as part of it
I mean having programmed since I was
seven years old right like at some point
you just build up neurological pathways
that make it easier for you to do stuff
it's just the same it's like you know
how does somebody you know dribble a
basketball or whatever it's like well
after you've done it enough times you
can just sort of do it and that gives
you a pretty good you know leg up on
someone who's only been programming five
years or even ten years you know
programming thirty plus years is more
than that right and that's all so some
of its just practice that just
eventually you know you get better the
other side of it is there are conscious
things I'm doing that help I have a lot
of like sort of rules that I follow
you'll notice the way I structure my
routines tends to look very regular I
tend to not have a lot of return points
I tend to declare things right when I
actually have a value for them I tend to
do my if handling as nested blocks where
the else's are the errors right and
those things are just ways that I help
myself
eliminate the need to remember what I
did because if there's only one way that
you tend to do something you don't have
to remember which one you did you can
just assume that you did it right and
that the bonus of that cannot really be
overstated
when I was programming on the witness
which is a code base it does everything
differently than the way I do it
I had like way more bugs per day because
anytime I would interface with the
external code I would like make silent
assumptions in my head that I didn't
even know I was making about how one
would do something and those things were
just not the same it wasn't that they
were worse they were just different
right and so the assumptions I made
about how some other piece of code would
have handled something are wrong and
then I had to debug that right and so
those silent assumptions that you make
when you create a policy are important
it's important to understand that that
gives you a bonus and so if you can
create an environment where you and any
other programmers that you're working
with can all agree on some basic ground
rules of how to do things
doesn't matter what those ground rules
or if they're any good just even having
some does allow people to be more
efficient right se5a one says I keep
running into problems that I cannot
figure out but if I drop it and come
back to it a later date I can sometimes
figure out what's going wrong within ten
minutes any suggestions on how to
improve my problem-solving in this
regard
hmm I think I would probably have to see
the kinds of problems you're working on
and what you're missing right I'll start
with the obvious statement which is that
for a sufficiently hard problem what you
described is just what happens so it
doesn't matter how good of a programming
you are or how much you've experienced
you have if you're fighting a very hard
problem sometimes going away for a while
and coming back to it is the only way
that your brain can really grapple with
it because either you've become too
enmeshed in a set of assumptions that
need time to fade or there's too much
newness there and your brain hasn't had
the background time necessary to really
chew through it and condense it down
into operable like neuron pathways and
when you give it that time and then come
back to it they light back up in a much
more simplified way than when it was all
new and now you can make forward
progress right and so one thing to
remember is it's not necessarily a sign
you're doing something wrong if you're
fighting that you may just be at the
limits of human intelligence at that
point and that's just the way it goes I
don't think there are programmers who
are so awesome
that they never have what you're
describing happen right certainly I have
this I know good programmers out there
who have this happen I don't know of
good programmers that are so awesome
that they don't have that happen I just
maybe there are some ount know who they
are who they would be as for if these
problems are actually relatively simple
to an experienced programmer who would
have just come in and gotten the ten
minute
sir just fine and don't really need to
sleep on it or spend weeks or months
ruminating again I think that just comes
from a certain level of experience and
having worked through enough problems
that you start to have sort of generic
problem-solving structures in your head
that generally work for the simpler
problems right and you just haven't
built up enough of those yet but you
will if you keep working at it right
your brain will continue to learn
shortcuts to problem-solving that allow
it to attack problems more quickly and
eventually there'll be less and less of
those problems that take you a
significant amount of of dead time to
approach I don't necessarily have a lot
of ways of saying well you know here's
how you get better at that more quickly
but what I would say is just keep doing
it is probably the only real requirement
right keep forcing yourself to solve
problems that you find difficult and
they should start to get easier over
time as your brain builds up that extra
circuitry if you just don't if you just
say ask too hard and stop that's
probably the only real way that you will
not you know improve over time and get
and get quicker would be my guess what
font do you recommend for a native
desktop app a font that looks pleasant
to the eyes of a hard time finding one
thanks to your help
I don't know Roboto is pretty good from
the Google you can get that from the
Google free font set might be an Apache
or an open font I don't know what it is
Roboto is pretty good droid sans I think
was pretty good
yeah I don't I don't really remember
which ones I'm sorry I don't know but I
agree it's hard to find what's the
hardest program problem you found
yourself dealing with
[Music]
I don't really know how to answer that
question sorry Jeffrey use Waldron's
would you recommend it for C code is
there a decent Windows alternative
I haven't myself used it I do think
those types of utilities tend to be good
I guess I would say does LLVM address
sanitizer work on windows probably I
think it does that might be something to
look at I'm not sure if it does or not
though um one of the things you can do
is like what we didn't hand made here
where you can force allocations to go
through a thing that lines them up at
the ends of buffers that's something you
can do with just your own code right and
we did that handmade here oh and that's
one way to find those buffer overruns
that I think works pretty well and it's
pretty easy to implement just make your
own always call your own memory
allocator and then thunk it through to
whatever you were using in normal code
but when you want to run in protected
code you can make it so that it randomly
picks under or overflow protection and
aligns it with a buffer with a mem with
an unmapped page right next to it so
it'll fault and we did that on handmade
heroes so that's you can go look at how
we did that that's one way to provide
some some extra protection there if
you're on a platform that you don't have
an automated utility to do it for you
it's not that hard to make your own for
that what language environment do you
recommend for introducing young kids to
programming um I don't really know you
know like maybe like something like
JavaScript or something would be a good
start and the reason I say that is is
yet it's kind of a crapped language but
you know so was basic and that's what a
lot of us from the old days learned on
you know basics of crap language but
you're just trying to get your feet wet
so you know if the reason I'd say
JavaScript is it has a lot of the same
it has a lot of the same aspects of
basic from the old days which is that
you it's on everything so you know you
just if you have your kid knows how to
use a web browser you can just teach
them how to hit f12 and start looking at
the code right which is exactly the way
like old basic used to be like on an
apple to write use feel just like hit a
key and it would just dump you into a
basic shell right
and the other thing is you can just
tweak the existing stuff and see the
results on the webpage right and so I
feel like that barrier to entry being
basically zero is probably the right
place to start it doesn't have datatype
so they don't have to understand what
that means they can just like do simple
stuff like putting the file name of a
picture right so I would say javascript
is a good thing to start with and you
know don't try to start kids off with a
good quote unquote language because
you're not trying to teach them like
good programming habits or something
like that you're just trying to get them
to understand like what code even is
right and then once they can sort of get
the hang of like the JavaScript stuff
then I'd say try to move them over into
something a little bit more real right
where they could start thinking about
types and and something that has a
memory like C would be good but I
wouldn't start them there because it's
just it's too much right it's if they
won't have enough mental traction and I
think they just get discouraged if you
try to teach them see right off the bat
I think they just get too discouraged
that's just bestest my my thinking I
don't know I'm a la I don't teach kids
how to program so I don't really know
you should probably ask someone who's
tried you know there's people who try to
work on like early you know how do we
teach you know 10 year-olds to code or
something and and see like what they've
found is the most useful ways of getting
kids to start and stick with it and I'm
not sure
but like most people I know from my
generation probably started with basic
at least a little bit right and it's not
like you did it for long you know so I'm
not saying program JavaScript for like
seven years right but just a couple
months of you get learning how to
program at all or what programming even
is I think you want something really
basic and really really like trivial to
just see what happens when you tweak
things do you think learning to program
a C is a bad idea
yeah I kind of do I think C is maybe a
good second language to learn because
you should learn memory management and
you should be able to look at like
direct azzam output from what you do as
like the next thing you learn but but as
a first language it's just it's too much
I mean you could do it but I just I
don't think it makes a lot of sense you
know I'm saying how often do you work on
random sub products that aren't work
related
I don't really sometimes I do like meow
hash I tried to break off as a separate
thing but again that's I needed that
like I needed to hash or what I was
doing so yeah I wasn't like just sitting
around going oh I'm gonna make a hash
function just because I can and I don't
actually need it for anything
so most time I have a reason like I make
the thing cuz I needed it you know
all right um go ahead and close down
okay thank you everyone for joining me
for those two the hand made hero it's
Ana pleasure coding with you as always
if you would like to follow along with
the series you can always pre-order the
game from handmade here at out or gonna
come to the source code so you can
follow along online you can also always
click on the handmade hero head if you
want to get the rest of the my rocket
sites if you want to find out what I'm
working on these days it's all up here
check it out I will be back next week
when we will get the font stuff probably
hopefully yeah you know obviously
speaking I think next weekend we could
finish that up at which point I think
that means we are sort of code complete
on being able to just rebuild all of our
assets from a directory flow stuff that
anyone can now edit who wants to so you
can basically build a completely own
version of all of our art assets replace
them with your own do whatever you want
add as many new ones as you want and so
that's a good place to be I'm pretty
happy with that and we've so so we're
rapidly closing in on that there'll be a
nice milestone so maybe we'll hit that
next weekend hopefully we will hope see
you back here for that till then have
fun programming everyone and I'll see
you all on the Internet take you use
everybody