hello everyone and welcome back to
handmade here or the show Rico to
complete game live on stream we have
been gone for two weeks because I
accidentally broke the microphone that's
there's not really a lot more complexity
to it than that but I ordered a new one
and it even comes with the little little
bag of replacement parts and everything
just like the old one did so yeah so we
should be good to go now but of course
that means it's been two weeks without
us working on this problem so the
problem that we had when we were last
looking at our code base is still there
no one has magically come and fixed it
for us which is very unfortunate and you
know what are you gonna do I wish we had
some little magical code fairy who would
come and sprinkle little code dust on
our code and then we came back it's like
oh hey it already solved all the
problems for us what do you know but
unfortunately we have to be our own code
fairy and we have to bring our own code
dust and do our own code sprinkling so I
guess we'd better start sprinkling I'm
going to grab my keyboard so today is
day 303 and where we left off we were
trying to figure out exactly what we
were going to do with sprite sorting and
I had just sort of finished determining
that you could not really do anything
with a uniform sort that you would at
least need to do something more
complicated than a uniform sort and we
sort of started to sketch out what it
might look like if we did a full graph
sort I'm not sure we actually need a
full graph sort certainly on the forums
while I was away people had sort of
posted various suggestions and there's a
couple different ways we can go with it
it's unclear which way is the right way
one thing I do think is true though from
what I can you know from sort of my gut
instinct is one thing that I don't think
is a good idea Izzy buffering and the
reason I don't think Izzy buffering is a
good idea is because I think we're going
to have very semantic sorts of stuff
that we need to do such as keep the head
of the hero on in front of the body of
the hero even though it should
technically be behind it or other stuff
like this and I feel like if I go with a
z-buffer approach I'm constantly going
to have to fight the z-buffer to make
these things happen and I don't know
that I really want to do that so my hope
is we can do a solution that isn't
z-buffer because I feel like that's
going to be a little bit touchy and it's
twiki as all the rest of these things
are I feel like they'll be less twiki
than trying to fight with the z-buffer
that's my feeling on it anyway and Z
buffer is great when you have real 3d
stuff it's not so good when you have to
do stuff you got to kind of come up with
you know sort of lots of little fake
faker ease fake tricks to try and make
it to the z-buffer ends up doing what
you want to do and doesn't do things you
don't want it to do which is hard when
you don't have real 3d stuff that you're
trying to actual shapes that you know
make the z-buffer work correctly so what
we have and we'll have to see where we
left this here let's see here handmade
food what we have in our renderer and I
don't know where I left it I probably
left it in the sort routine no you know
what I should probably load the project
file if I'm going to work on more than
one thing or not I I forgot that's some
something that I have to do I have to
upgrade to the new for kodir I'm a few
versions behind on this machine there's
been a lot of bug fixes anyway so i
believe it was in the sorting code where
I left it down at the bottom here yeah
you can kind of see that I started to
sort of talk about putting the sprite
graph a situation here so one thing that
a quarter Tron from the chat had
suggested he had played around with it
himself on it you know doing his own
sort of research on it he was suggesting
that we do a sort of an inter leave
where we sort all of the Z sprites
because we know that those can be sorted
correctly and then we sort all of the Y
sprites because we know that those can
be sorted correctly and then we merge
those together and I haven't really
thought through why that would solve
problems or not there are some reasons I
can think of why it might solve problems
but I haven't really necessarily
convinced myself that it would be
correct necessarily i also don't know
people were suggesting potentially that
we could do sort of a poor man's BSP by
using an insertion sort obviously an
insertion sort is a little bit different
than the kind of sort that we're using
here where you know you compare items
against each other and you really only
do that comparison at very specific
times and insertion sort works more like
a tree where you always sort of test the
you know going down a binary tree you
test each individual thing and try to
find the place where it slots in and
because you're doing that every time you
end up sort of essentially buildings you
know what would end up being sort of a
binary space partitioning type of tree
for the data that's coming in and so we
might be able to leverage that in order
to get the sort working more properly
now one of the things I think might be
kind of problematic about that obviously
is how we would keep that balanced
properly because I don't know that it
that it works for you really you know I
you know you end up in an N squared
scenario if you don't have some way of
balancing that tree
so that would be you know something that
we would have to take into account if we
were going to go that route now
obviously it's very easy to do the
solution the quarter tron was suggesting
but the thing that I just don't know is
I'm not sure whether that solution is a
solves the problems that we have or not
and just to make it a little clearer I
can pop over to the current Milton
dashboard over here where where is that
that's in w Milton I have not updated to
the latest Milton yet I got to sit here
I have to do that sometime soon anyway
what day is today
so what this solution essentially looks
like was you know okay we know that we
have sprites that are sort of lying flat
on the ground right and we don't know
what hot tight they're at right they can
be different heights but we know that
they always point along the z-axis and
we called those RZ sprites right and
then we had other kinds which were
upright you know they were facing you
know along the y-axis and I guess if
we're facing sort of more this whale
I'll draw them more like this right
there sort of facing towards us and
those are our Y sprites now what we know
is that if we only had these rights
right if that's all we had then
obviously we would we don't handle the
case of interpenetrating sprites right
so the sprites cannot be on top they
cannot intersect each other so what that
means is pretty much no matter what
happens the Z sprites could be sorted in
z I believe right because if you ever
have a case where there's you know
sprites that are like in this sort of
configuration I don't think there's any
way because the Z is is a constant thing
I don't think there's any way unless
this is on top of this that you would
ever want to see this first so I believe
if all you had ever was these rights you
could sort them exclusively by Z I don't
know that you need to sort them by Y at
all I have to think about that but I'm
pretty sure you don't because even for
things that are right behind each other
as soon as one of them gets above the
other one and thus should be potentially
seen in front of one of one of them it
is actually higher in space as well so
they wouldn't even really overlap if
that makes sense so kind of hard to say
but it seems like you could sort these
by Z and you can certainly sort these by
Y and that would definitely work because
there's never a
case we're moving a why sprite in Z ever
changes its sorting relative to another
why sprite right because these are just
in planes and so either you're in front
of or behind another one and that will
determine your draw order so we can
obviously produce the correct order of
the Y sprites then we can also correct
the produce the correct order of the Z
sprites because these two things
independently work okay so then the only
question is once we have y and z sprites
in sorted order how do we know when we
need to draw a one from either of the
two things right because that means I
can have you know a list here of of Z
sprites and then a list of why sprites
that are sorted and I know that each of
these should sort in a particular order
in each of these which are disregarded
and then I need to just know oh when do
I start you know I start rendering like
some of these these rights when do I
render one of the Y sprites right and
then once I start writing wife spreads
when do I order is East friend again so
I need a way of picking what list I pick
from what that makes sense and so you
know the the theory anyway behind
quarter tron solution here was that if
you use a scheme similar to the scheme
we were concocting before it will
actually work for sorting in the case
where you have done the sorts correctly
for the two kinds that can be sorted
first and then only use it as the merge
right so you only use it as the final
merge step you basically perform two
independent merge sorts of things you
know you can sort with a real criteria
and then you only use the sort of fakie
like hand-wavy criteria to merge those
two lists together
well uh I like this idea I think it's
got some panache to it so I am inclined
to say we should give it a shot I think
it's kind of clever I and if it worked
it would mean that you could still use
any kind of sort that you wanted to sort
the y and z sprites and then the like
you you would probably have to use a
merge sort I think for the the final
pass but like for example if you felt
like you wanted to use a radix sort for
example on the two separate pieces you
could because now there would be an
absolute single criteria for sorting
those two lists so it opens up more
possibilities for you as well which is
just kind of interesting from an
algorithmic standpoint don't know how
important that is to us but it's just
kind of cool and so I like this
algorithm I think it's kind of neat and
so I kind of want to see what happens if
we give it a try so let's see what that
would look like and also don't forget
one thing that I have to do before we
you know call this whole situation done
even if it turns out this sword is a
good sort the other thing that I haven't
really done yet is we have to ping pong
sort of back over to the render side of
things because remember I sort of hacked
in the notion of the extents of these
sprites right I I did not really do a
correct boundary sort of case for these
sprites and so you know we're not
passing extents that are necessarily
correct which could give us some
erroneous results certainly all right uh
so let's take a look here let us take a
look what I would like to do is you know
we've got sort of this this existing
merge sort here right and I think we
have another merge sort here where we've
got this sort of sort entry version
right so what I need to do is I need to
do something first where I'm going to
get
these things in two separate buckets
right look I need to sort my my wise and
my Z's so I think I could probably do
that by some sort of like my you know
when I do my merge sort I do a first
pass that puts these things into two
separate buckets which can then be
sorted right because I know whether
something zazzy sprite or not in fact
you can kind of see how we were testing
that before and maybe if this turns out
to be too much of a pain we can start to
keep Y in Z sprites in separate buckets
went at creation time if we need to so
you know but at the moment I don't want
to like go making all kinds of systemic
trouble for us upstream when we don't
really know whether this is the thing we
want to do so it's going to be better
probably to put something in here that
could do it first and then if we find
that we want to optimize that away we
can be a little bit more aggressive a
little bit further down the line alright
so let's see so here's a merge sort that
merged sorts two things using the sort
of this criteria the is in front of
criteria so if we keep that criteria
then that means that really all we need
to do is sort of have we do the pre pass
and then we kind of have like we kind of
have little merge sort 0 that work on
sort of as if they were doing this sort
of a sort right and I'm trying to think
if there's some way we can just use I
don't think there's really anything I
can do to use this
to use this code really because this
code is is trying to work on a single
sort key and while I could do that in
you know in the case where where I
didn't have to have this extra data
riding around with it i think i have to
clone this routine for the most part
because there's no really other way to
make sure that I don't that I thought
I'd track all the sprite bound
information that we kind of need it
unfortunately so anyway here we go with
our with our situation here I'm going to
go ahead and put this in and i'm going
to call this let's see we'll call this
merge sort and i guess on sprite bound
i'm going to just call this guy a merge
sort by for now and we'll see i might be
able to condense this code down a little
bit more in the future but for the
moment i'm just going to kind of write
it out longhand so if i want to merge
sort by why i want to make sure that my
sprite bounds my minimum Y is actually
the Y that's closest to me so I want to
make sure that if entry a these things
are drawing from back to front so entry
a it needs to be behind entry be if that
makes sense so if entry A's y min is
like less than entry B's why min then we
would need to swap because if entry a
has a why that's closer to us that entry
be then it needs to draw second so we
would do a swap right and similarly here
where we're kind of doing our
partitioning same thing applies in this
case we have a situation where we need
to know who we're going to take first
and so we want whoever has the greater
Wyman because whoever has the greater
Wyman is the one who needs to be drawn
first
alright so that's how we would do a sort
for the Wyman's and we can do the same
thing on the sort for the disease as
well I'm going to I'm going to clip this
out here for a second this doesn't oops
this is extraneous older code we were
playing with so here's like our merge
sort and why and the exact same thing
would work for merge sort in X right but
for the time being well occur the other
thing I have to do is I do want this guy
this merge sort to work with the sprite
bounds I guess in that case maybe this
wood is murder huh start with one that
already works for this right bound so
yeah and I the other thing I could do if
I want to hear is I could say this in
front of sort key why is this guy still
doing sort key
oh because we still just call it sorki
all right that's not so in this case you
know we've got we've got is in front of
sort key what I want to do here is just
I could still say is in front of why I
can still do it like that if I wanted to
and so that we can basically keep this
same routine and that would be our merge
sort why and we'd also have a merge sort
x I'm sorry Maurice or Z and you can
kind of see it's it's a little annoying
right because it's like it's exactly the
same thing and I'm not sure we'll have
to think about whether we condense this
at all obviously if you're at
empathizing sort of person you could
condense it on a template of course
you'd still that still does generate
duplicate code so it doesn't ending
actually condensing it in the actual
output but it would make it more concise
to read but there might be other ways we
could get this to convince in actuality
and I don't know whether that's the case
yet or not but either way if we do have
a merge sort ynm word sort Z then all we
need is a way of doing that sort the is
in front of part we need a way to do
that for these two criteria so we need a
boops y and z and when we have is in
front of a and B that's a is in front of
B a is in front of be if a has a Zemon
that is less than the Zeeman of B that's
all right Wyman
all right that would mean that a is in
front of NY and the same is true for Z
only the sense is reversed right because
Z comes up at us on the screen so
essentially we're going to have a swap
here and we don't have a Zemon we only
have a zmax so we're going to be looking
at something like this where we say like
okay the result is if the zmax is
greater than the other person's emacs
then it's in front of so that now we
would have our two different merge sorts
that we need right and those will do the
sorts of the two separate buffers and
then we would have to have one merge
sort that merges all of them together
right now in the case where we have all
of them together we still sort of have
the same kind of a merge sort scenario
that we had before except i think we
don't have to really do the special
cases anymore meaning i think we can
just sort of do this the do the two
buffers and then do the merge of the two
buffers so I'm pretty sure that if we go
ahead and say merge sort here I should
be able to do a thing where we can yet
where we can make where we can make this
work so what I need to do first is I
need to partition this buffer into two
pieces right one of which is going to be
all of the Z sprites and one of which is
going to be all of the y sprites right
so unlike the previous merge sorts that
we did where we partition the buffer in
to tap into like two halves because what
we're trying to do is just sort
homogeneous things here we've got a
heterogeneous grouping of things so I
first need to pull out like all of the Y
sprites and all of the Z sprites and
sort them separately then I can do my
merge so I think what I would do here is
I would say since we have a temp
directory that we know attempt record
that's good a temp buffer that we know
can hold as much as we have in our main
buffer obviously I could move all of say
the Z sprites in the
and then I could move all of the wyse
rights so that they were compacted in
the original buffer or something like
that right so let's try to write a
routine which does that which produces
in sprite bounced our first spray
bounced our temp let's just move all of
them over into one and then you know
deal with the other okay and again like
I said this is not going to be the most
efficient thing here because probably if
it turns out that we really care about
how this is performing at the end of the
day we would probably want to do
something where we just keep these guys
separate to begin with and then merge
them later rather than handing the
render a buffer with all of them in it
and having it have to disentangle them
since it's pretty easy for us to know at
the output time which ones which ok so
here we go i know that i'm going to do
basically the same loop right i'm going
to loop over everything in the buffer
and here's my first my whatever you want
to call it my first right i know that my
first bright index that's the one that
i'm on and i know that i could say you
know if was a Z sprite or is east right
I know that I could say well if this is
as East right that I want to move it to
the temp directory right so I want to be
able to say like temp temptin or I guess
z count plus plus equals me all right
and I'm just kind of sketching out what
this would look like now what would
happen is as I start to move things out
to here and let me just draw this for
you really quickly so you can kind of
see what I'm what I'm doing I've got
this this buffer and inside here are
like all different kinds of things so
there's a Z sprite there's a Z sprite
there's another Z sprite maybe this was
actually two reefs rights back to back
or something like this and I want to
move the Z sprites out into this
empty buffer well coming through here
anytime I see a Z sprite copying it out
to here is not particularly hard
certainly right but what I do have to do
then is remember that this is now a hole
in the buffer right so what I need to do
in for the simplest possible case which
might not be the most vision but for
simplest is the next time I find right
a-z sprite that I start a why sprite I
need to copy it up to here so I
basically to compact these values does
that make sense so I sort of need two
concepts here I need a sort sprite bound
or i guess i should say i need a why
count and a Z count and then we've got
like the index that we're actually on
and so what I would do here is I would
go okay I've got my sorts right bound
that's like this one whatever this one
is and that's going to be the first
buffer plus the index that's what I'm
looking at and so then what I want to do
is say well if it's a Z sprite then I
want to move it to my temp at my my temp
buffer and increment the Z count right
and that leaves a hole wherever I am on
the other hand if it's not if it's a
wife right then I want to compact it
into the most earliest possible unused
space in this buffer which of course is
just whatever the Y count is and then
increment that now this may copy it onto
itself if we haven't seen any holes yet
it will copy it onto itself but that's
okay we don't care we could early out
that if we want to but who cares again
the time for optimizing this is not now
because we don't even know if this is
something we want to use we'd rather do
is go for something that works correctly
first and then worry about optimizing it
later if we verify that it is actually a
valid approach to the problem so at this
point when i exit here I now have my
first buffer and
my temp buffer my first buffer has all
of the Y sprites in it and my temp
buffer has all of the Z sprites in it
right and so what I can do now is I can
move again this is not very efficient
but you know ideally we just have more
attempt member lying around like we just
have min best probably what we should do
but just because hey we're writing some
of this code I'm going to even put it to
in here dude Casey this is really just
for funsies we should probably just pass
in more 10 memory what I can do now is I
can copy that sort of the the Y sprites
onto the end of the sea sprites or the
sea sprites onto the end of the Y
sprites one of the other and that way I
still have a regular tempura sitting
around if I needed one but wait no I'm
an idiot you don't even need to do that
now that i think about it because what
do we know therefore has to be true if
what i just did is I separate it out
this into some number of lies rights and
some number of Z sprites what I know is
the unused portion of the Y sprite
buffer is exactly the right size to be
the temp buffer for the Z sort and the
unused portion of the Z sprite buffer is
the exact right size to use for the temp
of the y sort right because this has to
be this size these were both the same
size to begin with so however many i
stuffed in here that's how many i didn't
have at the end of this one right
because it was full before so what
whatever i pulled out that empty space
is the same size as the number i pulled
out so now i should be able to call
merge sort with cleverly crafted
pointers it so that it doesn't actually
ever have to move anything around again
in this first merge phase right so now I
can call my other merges right here's a
right which are basically just the
standard now these are the standard
merge sort that we actually had same one
we had before so I've got my why count
it's going to be first and instead of
passing temp I'm just passed 10th plus Z
count so I'm going to have that end of
the temp buffer that it's going to use
there and then for the merge sort in why
I'll do it I'll pass it the Z count
which is how many are in that temp
buffer and then we'll use the the first
plus y count that end of the first
buffer as the temp buffer there so now i
have my Z's in my wise in place sorted
because remember we kind of did the
inefficient thing where we did the sort
where it copies it back here right which
honestly you know what we could get rid
of that now we don't need to do that
copy anymore well you know I don't only
on the last one see this merge sort
recursive right so i can't really I I'll
leave it in for now that's too bad we
could go get rid of it right you
probably should but anyway so after I
merge sort these I've got first attempt
are pointing to my why am I Z sprites
respectively right and so now i need to
to write the thing that will merge them
together and in order to merge them
together the problem is this part ii I
don't know if we can be as clever as we
were with the other part we just kind of
use those ones because this I believe
assumes it can look at two things and
have space to write them all
contiguously after the fact right and I
don't know how we would really do that
it doesn't seem pretty right so I feel
like this is a place where we're going
to need to do more of a copy here now
what's hilarious about this is if we
could just tell this thing
Oh actually this is a copy isn't it so
if this is a copy that means that the
other buffer still has all the stuff in
it so that means technically even though
we told it to sort in here an exact copy
of the sort of thing is actually also
sitting in here so we don't need to copy
it back because this just did okay now
the only question I have there is what
happens in this case so that won't be
true in these ones exactly so you know
we we would have to make sure that for
the Z count let's say so everything
should end up in the first in buffer
first so let's say in the Z sorting one
what we would have to do is say well
okay you know I in the case where we
have quote-unquote no work to do we
would still need to copy it to the temp
buffer right like we'd still need to to
do a copy to the temp buffer even though
we don't really need to if we were just
returning the value right and the same
is true here so we know we've got entry
a and entry be first and first plus one
we need to do like you know just first
zero
you know technically obviously we don't
actually need to do that because we
could the other thing we could hear do
here is at the merge sort stage where we
do merge sort Z and merge sort why at
this point we know that the y-buffer is
when we want what we can do is we could
say if you know the Z count is less than
three or less than equal to 2 then we
know that we have to do that copy back
because it will not have done the copy
back for us any other case will run
through here and it will do that it will
have left the two buffers the same so in
this case we've got a merge sort on z we
know that we're doing wait why do I have
these backwards should look like that
right we should do a merge sort why on
the number of threats we have in Y right
and then we say okay we're doing that in
our first because that's where we put
all of the Y sprites I should also
probably do a thing here how do we tell
if it's as if right we just do if
they're equal right
so we want to say okay if this sort key
this key so if it's Wyman is not equal
to its wimax then it's a Z spray yeah so
I want to merge sort in using y criteria
however many y sprites I have there in
the first buffer and they are 10 plus Z
count that's how many the I'm sorry 10
plus the account is where the temporary
area is in the other buffer that's not
being used similarly we want to merge
sort by why the f sorry merge sort by Z
the temp buffer and we want to pass the
unused region of the first buffer for
that now in the case where the Z count
is less than two then that buffer that
first why count needs to have you know
the temp stuff added into it right so we
kind of need to do this sort of a thing
here I guess we could almost do it this
way so if Z count equals one
we copy one and if it's too we copy to
anything else and it would have just
worked so i think that's all we need to
make sure that our buffer is is correct
right and then we know that what we've
got is we sort of have this notion of
our two sprites sets we know we have
well and I guess we could use this same
sort of looking thing here we've got in
half one in half you have zero and in
half one what we have here is first and
first plus y count those are our two
like things were coming from and then
the end is in half one the end of this
buffer is in half 1 plus Z cap oh but
that that's not even really necessary I
guess really this is the part we wanted
this doesn't happen ok so we know in
total how many we had right and we know
we're reading from half 0 or half 10
looks like I didn't need those ok it's
just that part of don't need all right
uh okay so I'm looking at the temp
buffer and I'm saying that's what we're
going to have to use your Oh although I
can get rid of this to write this not
really necessary ping pong thing that I
can get rid of now because I can just if
I want to instead of using first buffer
I can just use the temp buffer right so
instead I could say oh ok
after I do my mergesort why and my
mergesort see instead of using first as
the primary buffer to pull from let's
just use temp so in half 0 will be just
the the temp this will be 10 plus Z
count and then yet then we need to just
reverse the sense of this yeah
okay so now we can just pull out of the
temp buffer and right into the first but
for originally so we get rid of that
extra copy at the end because it's just
sloppy not too I mean it's not like an
optimization really it's just we have to
go one direction or the other we might
as well pick the one that doesn't have
an extra copy it's no skin off our back
so we started temp and temp plus Z count
we know we have to end at at the total
count number right and then when we're
reading from these things I feel like
these why I don't even know why these
are different here in half 0 probably
because I type it earlier so there we go
all right so then we come through and we
say well if read half 0 has bottomed out
we always read from half 1 if read half
one has bottomed out we always read for
two otherwise we do the test and we pick
from whichever one gets the is in front
of comes back right now what's a little
bit weird to me is yeah okay we pass
them in the opposite order so that that
looks right okay so i think i think
that's basically it the only thing that
we really have to be aware of here is
that really first of all this is first
post count we're ready to the first
buffer we don't to do this merge
comparison can be simpler now since we
know which sprite is a Z sprite and
which is a why sprites right
so yeah dude ok so our merge sorts right
since their recursive they need to call
the respective version of themselves so
the merge for Z it needs to call the
merge sort Z and the merge sort y needs
to call the merge sort why for obvious
reasons there we go and so now we've
technically implemented this but hey
that was a lot of gyrations there we
probably need to let go through this
code a little bit more carefully and and
and well I think that's the end the
sentence actually we probably need to go
through this code more carefully because
we probably made some mistakes in there
for example there you go so this is our
little check at the end here and I'm not
sure guess I wanted to just kind of see
what it did first before we were going
to assert on this let me sit here
so let's see first of all for anywhere
close we are sort of anywhere close
actually
so that's definitely better than what we
had before that much is clear but it's
still not we still got a ways to go
certainly all right
okay so let's start playing around with
this a little bit more careful here what
is this is in front of so I guess that
one the only slight issue here is that I
don't really know I guess this is
something we can use to always check I'm
not really sure but anyway yeah that is
neither here nor there i would like to
go through this a little more carefully
carefully first before i start to figure
out whether or not we have bugs in the
actual comparison stuff which obviously
we have to have at least one or the
sword or this idea just doesn't work as
a sort but i think it probably is way
premature to determine that anyway so
we've got about 50 minutes left so i'm
going to dive in here and see if i can
determine
well how well this is working so first
of all let's let's start by jumping on
in here okay so what we're doing here at
the very outset is we're taking a look
to see whether we have Z sprites and
we're for y sprites and we're sorting
them in here you can see a bunch of
people are going into Z and Y and so on
right and so let's take a look at what
this looks like after we're done so Z
count why account and that's probably
what we would expect right because every
floor tile is as East right whereas the
only things that are Y sprites right now
are actually occupied tiles like a tree
or the hero or something like that so we
would expect there to be dramatically
more Z's frights than y sprites and that
is what we saw so that seems okay right
that seems like a reasonable thing if I
take a look at well you actually you
know what I should do there's really no
reason not to just verify right so let's
go through from 0 to Y count and assert
that the sprite is the kind of sprite we
think it should be and I should probably
also put up here and Izzy spread
function I suppose I could do great sort
what was the what was the thing that we
were passing around before sort sprite
bound sprite bound just write that
okay so yeah so this way we could say
like okay if it's as East right I'm
going to start down here that in both
cases we have nosey sprites in the Y and
all these sprites in the Z right okay so
this way hopefully that gives me a
little bit of protection there to verify
that they all got sorted into the two
buffers correctly so that seems good
right so now I could also do a thing
that's like verify buffer I could do
this
and what I could do here is say well
okay you know you'll give me a buffer
and then this will say I want to assert
that is Z sprite of this buffer of
everything in this buffer equals the Z
sprite value you pass me in so if you
want to verify the girls these sprites
you'd pass in true if you wanted to
better either why sprites you pass in
false right so then that way this could
just be verified buffer why count first
false and this could be verified buffer
Z count temp crew right so that would
verify those buffers for us after the
merge sort we could verify again so
after we do this Hocus focus right here
we could say oh yeah after we grab these
out let's make sure that in half 0 18
half one or what we think they are right
so in f0 is supposed to be all disease
rights sorted right so that should be a
Z count and this should be why account
it should look like that
uh so yeah right so that look right
hopefully so let's Rivera Phi that as
well and so now we can at least verify
our to sort of primary that coming out
of here we at least didn't do any of our
sort of magic shuffling wrong like
everything's in the right place
according to these these verifications
right and you can kind of see what you
know all this is doing right is it just
comes through here and just issues a ton
of assertions all right there's nothing
to it so anyway we've got these
verifications in here so at the end of
this we know that we're at least sorting
fair fair sorted things and then we
would come through here and we would say
we need to merge these guys together now
my suspicion is that since we now are
working with these sort of sorted these
planar assorted striations at this point
what we would probably want to do is
make sure that we just always sort the
well I feel like we still kind of have a
little bit of an issue here with the is
with the with emerging so I feel like
we're going to need I feel like we're
going to need a little bit of a better
merge to make this go correctly because
right work we're kind of like working
our way up in planes of Z and forward
and why so we're kind of like you know
doing this process and in order to know
which sheet to pick next I feel like
figuring out whether the two things
overlap isn't necessarily going to be
what we need if that makes sense so I
think I need to think this part through
a little bit more I don't know exactly
what what what Steve did I don't know
what what quarter Tron did
but well he might be on the chat I don't
even know is the other chat I haven't
been watching squirt ran out there
anyone know anyway so point being we've
got a situation right where we now are
basically moving you know if we look at
this from the side sort of so the camera
is like looking down here what we're
essentially saying now is we're moving a
plane this way and this way and every
time we get to somebody a new we get to
a new plane we have to decide is this
new plane the one we should be drawing
next or as this plane the one we should
be drawing next right and so it seems
like I I don't know it seems to me like
that's a hard decision to make I look I
wonder if there really is going to be a
way for us to make that decision in a
way that like if we if we could make
that decision properly I guess the thing
that is a little weird in my mind is
like if we could make that isn't
properly why couldn't we have just
sorted by a single criteria so it does
seem like a little wonky like it does
seem like I'm not sure that this will
actually work but
no hard to say so anyway let me take a
quick look at what our current thing is
here so we have both Z sprites so we
never we never have this both Z sprite
condition right that's never going to
happen now or at least it shouldn't ever
happen now if that makes sense although
I guess it happens in the sense that the
built that the not build sprite graph
this thing here the sort entries when it
goes to verify its going to call the is
in front of so you know that will happen
but so we have the both Z sprites thing
and that's never going to happen in our
actual testing so in the cases that
we're talking about now that's always
going to be false and then we're going
to do the a includes be and the B
includes a bit and in this case like I
said so we're never going to be able to
have to Z sprites so the Y min Y max we
could for example ensure that we always
pass a Z sprite in a particular order
here if we wanted to write but anyway so
when we figure out whether we need to
sort by Z we were previously saying if
they're both these sprites or there's
some overlap so I guess that was saying
like essentially if RZ overlapped the
why of whatever this thing you know even
if it was a wise right if the sea sprite
sort of was was overlap it's it in why
then we would still sort by Z otherwise
we would sort by Y right and so let's
see what this is saying here so that's
saying we'll sort by Z we will look at
the Z Max's and we'll move them
otherwise we'll go by the Wyman's and
that is how we were doing it right here
we were doing zmax I suppose the other
thing we should do for verify buffer now
to think about it let's verify that
they're sorted correctly so we could
also do something like this let's assert
that buffer index sort key oops let's
assert that buffer mix- one sort key I
guess set please its way around right so
the one we're on let's assert that it's
supposed to be in front of the one that
came before it that way we'll also
verify the sort order of our of our
staging buffers right okay so something
got messed up before we get to the
magical part of the merge I mess
something up and you can kind of see how
I was approaching this problem right
there's just so much data flying around
that rather than try to inspect a lot of
it at the debugger at the head end I
just decided to write some code that
would do some testing right on that and
this is why I a lot of times I it
doesn't happen so often thank God but in
the past everyone was saying what do you
think of test-driven development and I
you know think I said a bunch stuff
about like well you know you always have
to make a decision about whether it's
gonna save you time or cost you time
while this isn't technically test-driven
development you'll notice i am adding
sort of more complicated tests here and
the reason for that is i'm doing exactly
that trade-off right i'm looking and
saying i think i can save myself some
time here by writing tests in code
because i think though
code tests will find the bugs faster
than I can find the bugs without the
tests right and that's kind of like a
thing where I'm always making that sort
of trade off in my head where any time I
have a piece of code I'm trying to bug
I'm always thinking would it be more
value but I've tests here is that going
to be the shorter way to go most the
time the answer is no and games but
sometimes the answer is definitely yes
in this case I think it was going to be
easier to do it this way now I don't
know if we actually found a bugger if I
just wrote the test wrong right so we
first have to actually get the test
working that's another reason testing
driven development it's always a little
bit costly but still so let's take a
look at at what's going on in here so
let's take a look at the first time
through this loop and just make sure
things are generally kosher so here we
go here is with index 20 you know what
that should be greater than 0
so here we go with this test and you can
see that we're at least passing
occasionally so it's not like the test
itself is complete nonsense but here we
have failed so let's take a look at what
we returned here this may be the case of
two things that are identical and so in
that case we would also have to do the
same test
alright so in this case we have two
sprites who both have an equivalent Z
value so you know I guess in this case I
wonder if we do want to still use in the
case where we've got equivalency values
if we want to sort them we may still
want to do that sort so I guess now I
think about it maybe yeah maybe I should
be doing the same sort in all cases
right so maybe I shouldn't actually I
shouldn't actually have done it this way
like maybe I should leave the old way of
doing it where we still do is in front
of in both cases right yeah seems like a
fair thing so instead of doing a so that
way we get that extra sorting of Z
sprites where they'll sort by Y if
there's these happen to be equivalent
that seems pretty reasonable so let's
see mergesort we want to call this
what do I want to call this because here
we sort of call you know we call this
merge sort but this is really like I
call this a separated sort and the other
one the merge sort because the other
ones the one that's actually doing a
merge sort and then I'll try saying okay
what if we just get rid of this and keep
doing it the other way around so here's
our merge sort it uses gives in front of
in both cases right and then we don't
have this anymore
alright so what do we have here let's
see where so now like you notice we
passed now that we're doing that kind of
sorting where we're actually still
keeping our Y's and Z's correct there so
our is in front of failed here on
somebody let's see what it said so in
this case we have somebody who is who is
closer to us in Z coming second which
seems correct but lower in why but it's
a Z sprite I guess only one of them is a
wise is only it only one of them is as
East right that doesn't I'll be honest
that does that's a little confusing
wouldn't I'm not sure I can immediately
tell why entry be wouldn't be in front
of because it's also higher I feel like
that wouldn't matter I want to see what
the visual results of this are at the
moment
alright
getting a lot of flashing there so
that's not great well I don't want to go
too far over time so I'll put that back
in for now and we will go to the QA and
then we'll take a look at this tomorrow
and we can also ask quarter Tron if we
did a faithful if that was a faithful
implantation of what he had tried to do
because I don't actually know Oh in so
bodies here
it would be great if it's about had a
question for the Q&amp;A I always loved his
questions or her questions its questions
is in savate gendered or as in savate
like a asexual
stay thirsty 90 I'm gonna skip that
question for a minute since it's not
related Rome says I'm trying to make
take a different approach using the
projected sprites on the screen to sort
and using the min/max y-values up as the
depth sorting key you are trying to take
a different approach so does that mean
you have not taken that approach yet or
whether you have not gotten that
approach working it or does that mean
you have gotten networking yet because I
was going to ask how did it work but
maybe you don't know how it works yet
working on it yeah well keep us posted
mass quarter Tron what he thinks of our
current implementation of whether that's
a fair weather that's similar to what he
tried or not
I feel like since no one's asked a
question I'll take the question of what
is a full stack developer a full stack
developer is what people just used to
call a programmer it's somebody who like
knows how to program but nowadays
there's kind of like this secondary
aspect of programming which is like
there's some people who kind of just
know how to like write JavaScript or
something but they don't really know
very much about how like computer
actually works or something like that so
they can't necessarily go work on like
if there's this you know some kind of
underlying database technology that you
have the source code to they wouldn't be
able to necessarily go like modify some
of it right or even know if it was
working right or not right because all
they know is like the issue a sequel
query and something comes back and they
don't really have an idea how it's like
magic like you know they wouldn't know
necessarily what was going on under
there and so I think typically what
people mean when they say full stack
developer is really what I would have
just called a programmer somebody who I
could tell to go do something that has
to do with programming and do it as
opposed just been like I don't know man
I only write the like web page or
whatever and so I think that's kind of a
newer thing and faithfully because well
nowadays are so much stuff that gets
done in software development you end up
having tons and tons and tons of work
for people who maybe aren't really
programmers in the full like you know
know all the ways in which you know all
the things that you might expect a
typical programmer to know then yeah and
I guess in theory it could go the other
way to like if somehow you're somebody
who does know how to write a sequel
server but doesn't know how to write
JavaScript or something you also
wouldn't be a full stack developer
because if for some reason you're like I
I couldn't go figure out how to write
the JavaScript for a web page then well
that's not the full stack right that's
not the full end-to-end part programming
that happens
poo shoes won't sorting fail because the
lower Z sometimes needs to be drawn on
top of a higher Z if as wise Freight
overlaps them see reference image
that is very good point poo shoes
yeah I like that that diagram is pretty
good that he posted maybe I'll draw that
into the stream here so who shoes drew
so it's basically a B C here's the side
view a b c and so from the camera in
this case right we've got
something that looks like this we're
here is a and here is C and here's B and
this should be behind right this is the
furthest miss back this is in the middle
and this is in front but this has a
lower Z value than this so it does seem
like yeah it does seem like this
approach wouldn't necessarily work
because we don't know it does seem like
it comes back to the same problem as
before right which is that we still need
to do the cycle we still need the cycle
so we'll ask fortiter on about it and
see if he maybe had something clever
there but I think you may be right which
still leaves us at the graph side of
things which is fine that's what we were
going to do before but it would be nice
if we didn't have to
maybe low at the start you mentioned
insertion sort and potentially
automatically getting a binary tree
representation of the sprites what
happened to that idea assuming i roughly
understood correctly what you've done so
that one and we could try writing that
one tomorrow too assuming that there
isn't something we miss in this one and
that this is in fact not a not a viable
algorithm the way that one works is is
by saying well let's suppose that we are
taking something like this and we go
okay you know we've got B &amp; B becomes
the top of our tree or something we get
a and we see that a is behind be so it
goes on this side right and then we've
got C and C is in front of B so it goes
on this side and then if another guy
wants to slide in here right we would go
well he's on this side of B which side
of C is he on while he's behind see so
he's you know this is D or whatever so
he's here whatever so the insertion sort
does lots of comparisons based on those
splitting planes as you go down and the
problem with this approach I think is
that I don't think in the end I feel
like it's going to just degenerate to
the same problem as this one which is
that unless you actually split things up
in some way when you're not sure what
should happen between any two things
you'll end up in the same problem we
ended up with here so I'm suspecting
that the graph approaches the only one
we can really do if that makes sense
how do you transform the sprites from
world to screen coordinates we do that I
mean we just do that with a standard or
very basic orthogonal projection
it'sit's doesn't really do much all
right I think that's it for today so
right we've got a we've got a few more
things we've tried here I think we may
still like I said it still kind of looks
to me like we're gonna have to do the
graph sort which is not a big deal you
know will write it we'll see how it goes
i don't think it's going to be a huge
deal at the end of the day yeah sprite
sorting is complicated what can you do
it's the kind of thing where you've got
a very semantic problem and semantic
problems are always kind of at a little
bit nasty right but anyway like I said
not a huge deal we'll keep playing
around with it and eventually we'll get
something that we're happy with all
right thank you everyone for joining me
for an episode of handmade hero special
coating with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home you can
always pro2 the game on handmade hero or
it comes to the source codes you can
follow along at home we also have a
forum site if you want to ask questions
a patreon page if you want support the
video series a schedule bot the tweets
to schedule at you if you want to catch
us live and an episode guide if you
would like to catch up on old episodes
that's about it for today I will be back
tomorrow livre 5 p.m. pacific daylight
time tomorrow until then I hope you guys
have fun programming and i will see you
on the Internet take it easy to everyone