hello everyone welcome to handmade here
I'll show Rico to complete game live on
stream today well we got 2 things to do
when we got some debugging to do and
then we've got to start playing around
with our system and figure out our big
goal next is to figure out how we want
to work these tags into our system we
just I'm pretty sure that we don't
really need to keep doing what we're
doing the tags because we just have a
simplified process now based on what we
actually got as art assets we can make
things simpler on ourselves we don't so
you need to we could decide to keep it
the way it is but I just think we're
gonna pay performance penalties for the
tags away they are now or have to do a
bunch of work to accelerate it when
really now that we kind of know what our
tag layouts gonna have to be it might be
something we can just kind of fork oh
but yeah before we go that we got some
bugs to work out and some some missing
things that we got to kind of fill in
from the last time when we got the PNG
exporter importer thing working and
that's really what I want to focus on
today now I realized after we ended the
stream last week I don't remember I was
doing I think it would might've been the
next day when I was just hanging around
or something I remembered I think I
thought of why we had a problem with the
thing we were doing we just had finished
rain we didn't have a chance to look
into it at all so it's probably
something simple but anyway I thought I
thought in my head I was like oh you
know it's probably because we're having
an off by one problem because that weird
requirement that you skip the first
asset in in any case right so when we're
actually filing things away we have to
be careful to honor the fact that we
leave slots open right and I just don't
remember if that's what we were doing
but that would cause us a problem so
anyway if you remember correctly and
I'll go ahead and try to refresh your
memory here for the folks who didn't
catch last week's stream or people who
forgotten where we were since last week
if we take a look at the handmade data
directory we've got sort of a set of
things here where these are the these
are the h @ JS that we already had right
we had intro art
test 1 test 2 and test 3 ehh ehh and
then what happened was when we run the
game and if I run the game now nothing
will happen because there isn't one
there if I run the game what we get is a
check at startup to see whether or not
there's a specifically named file and if
that specifically named files there it
will use it as a place to write
dynamically imported art assets that
come from PNG s in the art directory so
what I need to do if I want to trigger
the updater right is I have to actually
have that in there and you can see that
code up in here where we actually load
in the hhas you can see here that if
there's a test to see if the thing is
called local then it assumes that that
was something you can use for writing
now what we did is we made a little
program called HHA edit that will add
two in the future to make more stuff as
we want to be able to work with HHA
files for example we can just say create
oops local HHA and when it makes one of
those it just sticks in a blank one that
doesn't have anything in it yet so now
what happens is when I run now it can
process a PNG import and it does it
processed one of the hand files which
was just this little thing it was just a
test to see if it worked
and we found already that we had one bug
which is that we don't reverse the RGB
channels so that's something to keep in
mind there right so we've got some work
to do there that's really simple though
the more concerning part and the thing
that was the bug that I actually want to
focus on right now was just that once we
exit what we've done is when that gets
loaded in we actually update that HHA
file so if I go back and look at the HSA
file you can see that it imported all
the hand bitmaps it's actually got
report of them all not just that one
that we were looking for it imported all
the hand bitmaps and stored them in that
local HHA and now what we'd like to see
is if I run this again we'd like to see
it show up again but what we see instead
is that we get a an incorrect asset load
occurring right
I should set it to debug build so we can
inspect these values a little bit better
it looks like assets is undefined for
reasons I'm not entirely sure why that
would be but oh I see because the local
function of course it is anyway
that's right local variable anyway we
get a load error here and so our first
order of business is to actually step
through and debug that HHA header
updating code because obviously we've
got some problems because our restart
doesn't work properly so our import
works ok as far as importing into memory
is concerned but our import in terms of
updating the actual backing store is not
correct so that's the first bug I want
to address then we'll address the RGB
flip problem and then finally once we're
done with that then we're pretty much
progressing into the tag into land of
tags and yeah that's just how that's
gonna go ok so let's take a look here I
just want to refresh my memory about the
code and see whether or not the problem
I was saying about leaving a slot open I
just wanted to see whether or not that
was actually true whether we were
looking at that correctly or not so the
way that this works remember is we ask
for an asset index here if we don't have
one so we come through and if we're
updating an asset that we already know
about one that we've already placed
somewhere and we're like this PNG we
placed its asset here or something like
that then what we end up with here is a
new asset index allocation right so we
try to allocate a new asset index to
place that asset into our asset store
somewhere and so when we do that the
reserve asset call what this is going to
do is I think it just gives us an asset
in the global space right let me just
make sure that's true yeah so that gives
us an asset in the global space and
that's all it does so it doesn't
actually put that asset into the asset
storage of a particular HHA file
the first time we really deal with that
is here so you can see here we have
right modifications to HHA that's this
is the first place that we act start to
deal with assets so we come through here
and we look at asset counts you can see
us taking a look at we get we saw the
tags that each one uses and we look at
how many assets were expecting to have
in this particular HHA file right just
the one that we're looking at here so
when we sum that up we get a particular
number you'll notice we start that at
zero and we never add the additional one
to it right you see what the problem is
there so when we actually start writing
out asset indices here we're not
skipping that first one and we really
have to I believe we need to do that
because the way the loader works so in
terms of the asset count we really want
to do it that way so that we know how
many of those we actually have there and
and then when we actually put these in
we can put in zeros now I don't know if
asset types are a size perhaps can be I
don't I don't know how that one works I
don't think that one has a null entry in
it so in some sense we I don't know how
we want to do this if we want to do it
like that sum it up and then do an asset
count you know
like this so I'm not sure how exactly we
want to do that but you know if you take
a look at how this would work we have to
do the same thing that we were doing for
like when we do our desk type we grab
this one when we do our asset like we're
doing here in this desta right we
actually want to do plus one right so
this actually has to look like that if
that makes sense and off we go so I
again I'm not really sure exactly how we
want that to work do you think but I
believe that's that's you know more
correct than the thing that we were
doing before I don't love the way that
those things kind of move around but you
know what do you do
and we also should take here in these
push arrays where we're zeroing these
these are actually cleared automatically
by push array if I'm not mistaken so I
don't believe this zeroing actually has
to happen here I'm not sure why that's
still there get rid of it but anyway I
think that's the more correct updating
so if I go ahead and delete that local
hij and then create a new one so that we
can see if the import process goes a
little bit smoother this time
now when we write out that file in
theory anyway let me just make sure the
import still work properly now at least
it leaves that extra hole and we could
go test again and see now what are our
errors are here oh and we double check
here where we set this
oh so this asset type count also so this
is wrong here like I said it's a little
squirrely the way these work I wish they
were a little cleaner I think maybe the
best way to do it would be to just act
I'm trying to think of what the right
way to do it here's I think maybe we
want you know asset type count to just
be a different thing I guess
something like this but I just don't
like having those two there because I
like I say that was another mistake and
it just kind of piles up so anyway if we
have the asset type count and we use
that a little bit more specifically so
we say that the asset types are used as
a type count the asset array size uses
the asset count now the asset count can
have more in it there so that we could
say asset type count here and then these
are still all correct as they are but
this one again would be asset type count
and then when we go through here the
tagging X and file in the asset news
file both can start at one so they skip
their first entry right and and off we
go we chain through here we write out
the different ones that we expect to see
we could add some assertions in here we
don't have any right now and that's
probably a bad thing it it would make
more sense to have some assertions in
here like for example we should probably
assert that the number of each thing
that we wrote is the number that we
thought we were going to write so we
should say something like yeah like tag
index in file should be equal to the tag
count right and asset index in file
should be equal to the asset count and
then the the desk type just gets Inc
updated by movement I believe let me see
here is it just me or Oh or is it just
me or we not updating that at all so
that's what that would be another bug
right just type which is this fellow
right here
death type has to be advanced and I'm
not seeing that happen right so actually
this should also care like that right so
we want to assert that desk type equals
asset types plus asset type count and I
think that's just a little bit more
secure now so now like at least if we
don't if we say we're
right out a certain number and then we
don't write out that number then I will
assert early on so that we don't waste
our time thinking that it's going to be
okay
and hopefully that'll help us so let's
now take a look at where we crash out
here same place so I'm gonna switch to
debug build now and now I want to look
at what we're actually so I least now
have some sort of some opinion or idea
here that we're probably going to have
the right number of things written all
so this uses the high watermark right
yes that looks like um so once we yeah
so so at this point I'm pretty sure that
we've wrote the right number of things
out so now what I want to do is set the
bill to debug and watch that import and
I just like to see what's going on there
and one thing I could do is well so if I
go through and set this to debug like so
just to get that going what I can do
here is if we look at what these other
hhas are I can do something like this
like make a debug directory move the
local HHA into the debug directory so
it's the only one in there and then when
I could do is I can set the execution
directory here to actually point
directly to that directory well I guess
it's not quite that simple I have to
actually make also a data inside there
but that's okay so what I could do here
let's do it this way so we have our data
directory let's make a debug directory
here so here's our actual data here's
our debug right and inside here I'll
just make a different one of these with
that local hij in it
right so that way now I can if I want to
set this to be
debug and will only load just that one
right so now looking at when we step
through here we can actually figure out
what's going on much more quickly
because we'll only have to look at the
bad file we weren't the waste our time
stepping through the good files that we
already know work um so what we should
see here is we should see only one file
loaded so that's what I'm gonna check
for first right and that file should be
that the file in question should be the
local one right there it is so you can
see here we've got the information for
this file that we're about to load in
here it is it says it's got 13 tags 12
asset types 13 assets that's the correct
number the number we expect to see those
look reasonable those are arrays placed
up above the data limit the magic value
I assume is correct
let's take a look six six six one six
eight six eight I don't actually know if
that's correct but let's find out it's
not what I wanted hij F yep I so that
all looks reasonable everything's fine
there so the asset type of race eyes
computation and stuff should be right
this this should all be fine let's take
a look at that asset type array yeah
it's right there
yeah type ID twenty-first acid index 1-1
past is this just a pointer to a single
one of these I assume so we should be
able to look at all 12 like this I'm
guessing so it just basically says hey
there's a bunch of type ID 20s so these
are wrong
so that's bug number one from our
debugging
we should see there be space there
should be one there right so when we
update the HHA here where is that here
it is no this is not where it is I lied
I just lied where is my update it's not
here it's not there it is right
modification stage which I gotta
remember that name so when we write this
out you can see here this was supposed
to have a plus one in it and didn't so
it was saying there were no assets in
the asset range so that's obviously
wrong and that was probably the majority
of our problem too because what that
means is when it comes through here it's
never gonna find any right it's just
it's not gonna get any it's gonna think
it has none of those things to add so
you know that's yeah oops so if I go
back now and see let me make a new one
of these files hsj to create local HHA
by the way in case you don't already
know if you hit f8 on the Windows
command line it will recall the most
recent command that started with what
you've typed so if you type like a
beginning of a command and then f8 you
get the command that matches that thing
right the Windows command line is pretty
crappy
but at least it has a couple of little
shortcuts in there and that one's kind
of useful so anyway if I create one of
those and now I set us back and said
instead of using that debug directory if
I go ahead and set us back to handmade
this should run the import again and
this time when we run the import
hopefully now it will set that stuff up
properly and we should be okay now we're
still running in debug mode so we're
gonna be much lower frame rate rise
that's fine and so if I close that down
and now run it again we can see we
should have a different occurrence here
now we didn't crash we loaded but it's
worth noting that we don't really still
know we we don't know if we worked
correctly now you may say well I see the
little like mini sprite thing there it
doesn't that mean we're correctly it
doesn't actually the reason that we
don't know if that means that we worked
correctly is specifically because when
we run the game again because we haven't
saved out this is the other thing that I
said we were gonna have to do because we
haven't saved out the metadata for the
stuff that we imported we therefore
don't actually know whether or not a PNG
has already been loaded so what ends up
happening is we can't tell if that could
have just been the re-imported sprite so
to run a real test before we've done you
see it doubled the size because it just
imported everything again so in order to
run a test before we write out the
metadata we actually can run the test
first by creating one of the local HHA
files run the import once here it is
running right when it's done we verify
that we have the thing we do we close
now we can do is move local HHA to test
you know for dot HHA or something like
this or import test dot ehh ehh now it's
not marked as important so that means
there's
no import destination which means that
it won't run an import so now we can run
it again and we can check to see what
we've got and so now we see is mmm you
know we did actually get an import but
it's a different hand from the previous
kind that we imported right is that mean
we did it wrong no probably not
because remember we tagged all of those
hands exactly the same way so what that
means is it's free to pick any one it
wants and we probably just changed the
order in which they appeared because of
the way we imported them so still seems
like we're all good we'll have to double
check to make sure a little later but
again our tag system doesn't
differentiate between two things that
exactly the same tags it's free to pick
either when it wants and that's probably
just what it did here right so it looks
good looks like we're in good shape uh
and so if and if I restore us back to
the standard optimize bills we should be
in a situation where we will run at full
speed as well I at least I would assume
yeah and there we go
so from there really what we want to do
now is write out that metadata and I
think we probably want to I don't know
I'm thinking that I probably I'm
thinking that I probably want to sort of
do these two things together right like
writing out the metadata and figuring
out what to do with our tags a little
better than we have been I think those
two things are maybe related and one of
the things that I kind of want to
emphasize is that now
we have the we wrote a little utility
that HHA edit utility and one of the
things that I think is really
interesting about that utility is now if
we want to we should be able to make a
we should be able to edit right like we
should be able to make a way that use
that utility to update import or change
HHA files so if we want to we can
upgrade our HHA file format and we don't
have to really worry about backwards
compatibility because we could just
build a thing into that
HHA edit that just takes old versions
and updates them to new versions right
so we have a lot of options there and we
could choose to use them if we want to
now we don't have to but we could choose
to and so if we find ourselves a little
bit cramped when we're making these
changes we can go that route because we
now have the ability to do so similarly
if we wanted to that HHA edit utility
like that's probably where we'll go
ahead and put something like a merge so
you could say HHA edit - merge and then
type a bunch of files in and have it
combine all of those files into one file
and so stuff like that again makes it
easier for us to work with these files
it allows us to do things that we might
want to do come ship time like binding
all of Rho J's together instead of
shipping multiple h8 J's right so anyway
I think that's all good and I'm pretty
pretty happy about that so I think now
that that we're there I think now is the
time to start thinking about how we want
to address the tag situation now the
reason that I want to address the track
situation a little bit more carefully
than we have been doing it in the past
I'll go ahead and delete this now we
don't need that we could use that trick
again later the reason that I want to
kind of take a look at this is because
if I go in here and look at the art
directory
hmm what we're doing now is we sort of
have this notion of house right sheets
come in and those sprite sheets have a
fixed shape that the artist is telling
us they're going to use that means we
don't really need to store individual
tags for these assets we only need to
store tags for this sheet and what I
mean about that is like if you look at
the character template here I'll go
ahead and load it in if we look here at
what one of these templates looks like
all of the characters will have the same
template right so all we really need to
know what kind of an asset something is
underneath that is just its index right
it's 0 through 64 or you know X comma Y
depending on how you want to think about
it but it's really just a simple 6 bit
value that tells you where you were in
this grid and so anything in the system
that wants to look up something like
this knows that all it needs to do is
feed that 6 bit value into here and it
doesn't need to do matching it can look
it up directly it's my point
so we now sort of have we now sort of
have guidance about how that would go
and we may just want to take advantage
of it
similarly if we look at how these things
are laid out we know some type
information like we know that we've got
like blocks which were sort of things
you could use you know to to build sort
of places in the world so we'll probably
have a ton of those we have characters
probably have less of those but you know
maybe we'll have more who knows a lot of
characters like moms
their characters technically right so
maybe we will have a lot of those and I
think about it
hands items and you know obstacles etc
we know we have these different things
those themselves would be essentially
the main line types right like are you
talking about a character or cover hand
item obstacle or just like a something
else like a other basically right so
again I don't really know how we want to
do this but let me lay out some things I
was sort of thinking about in a little
bit more broadly in terms of changing
the line about where things are actually
specified so if for example in code we
want to talk about things more
specifically what we could do is always
talk about things in terms of we could
always talk about things in terms of
hard ideas that allow you to look up art
assets directly and we could still
retain some of the tag matching stuff
that we wanted by moving the tag
matching to be something that you just
used to get an ID if you don't know
which ID you actually want right and so
the tags could therefore be something
that's more defined in code or
extraneous to the art files themselves
it's just a thought and again I don't
really know it's really hard for me to
guess how the right way to do these and
that's just because I haven't done many
things like this specific thing if I'd
done like lots of games is art tagging
systems for lack of a better term I
would probably have a pretty strong
opinion about how this stuff has to go
because I would have seen a lot of
examples of what works and what doesn't
work
but that's just not a part of a pipeline
I've ever really done much with so it's
very much sort of a wait-and-see kind of
thing with me the whole time I've never
really been like it needs to be this way
because again same thing needs to be a
certain way or having a very specific
app in
about it should be done this way really
only comes from experience it doesn't
come from just like smarts and thinking
about something because you usually
can't guess all of the things that
you're going to hit and that's just
generally true like that's why I also on
handmade hero sometimes I do stuff and
I'm just like look trust me he we do it
exactly this way and here are some
reasons why that's cuz I've done that
kind of code so many times that I'm like
believe me this is always the way that
works out best for these reasons or
something other parts of code that I
don't have much experience with are
usually ones where I'm like I don't know
we'll have to see and that is how that
goes right everyone has some explore
experience in some places than in others
and so it's important to know this is
something that that you also want to
become familiar with yourself and for
your programmer time you don't want to
be too dogmatic
or sure about how you're programming
something that you haven't had enough
experience with right you want to be
open to new ideas and new thought
processes in lines where you're not sure
of of really solid reasons why things
were kind of particular way because if
you close yourself off too early along a
line that you don't have enough
experience with and you haven't tried
enough things then you may be missing
the best ways to do it right and so I've
never I don't know if I've ever said
that explicitly but that's why you'll
often hear me say things in two
different ways sometimes I'm telling you
that here are all the reasons why you
should do something this way otherwise
I'm like we want to wait and see that's
usually why it's like I have a good most
of the time internal barometer for I
know how this should go because I'm
pretty sure it will ship this way and be
good versus I haven't had enough
experience with this thing to say for
sure let's try some things right and I
think on any given project you want to
know that you want to have that
barometer because assuming you want to
continually get better at how you're
coding things you want to be aware of
the places where more experimentation
could be
to you and educate you as to how to do
something in the future right so that's
just something to think about so
long-winded way of saying I don't have a
super strong opinion about how this
should go the tag system was okay
I just think that looking at the asses
we're getting back it doesn't seem like
it's gonna do very much for us right
because the practical situation is just
that the artist thinks about making a
specific thing this particular orphan
that particular monster that's how they
think about them and so at the first
line of import it seems like you just
want to reflect that fact right let's
import all the things the artist made
and name them specifically what they
named them then on top of that we could
add tag matching if we have some times
where the game just wants to say look I
don't know what I want here I just want
something that lives like blah right now
the reason not to do it entirely that
way is that if people want to add more
stuff to the game then they want to be
able to add an asset that maybe fills in
a niche that you didn't have before and
in talking about this maybe it might be
helpful to sort of draw a diagram about
what I mean here so let's go ahead here
on day 465
Artspace it sounds like some you
toidy gallery and like you know
Manhattan or something anyway art space
so let's suppose we wanted to do
something where the generator generates
monsters and it gives those monsters to
parameters let's say because that'll be
easy for us to draw here that's the only
reason I'm saying to let's say that it
has HP so like the number of hit points
that this thing could take maybe certain
particularly armored monsters take eight
hit points to kill and certain other
monsters that are not particularly well
armored can be killed in one kit for
whatever definition of hit is in this
game again not only to hand meat here
I'm talking about in the abstract
obviously it applies handmade hero
because we will have stuff like hit
points but I'm not trying to say saying
straight hammer here I'm just trying to
say this in the abstract so we have a
generator that's going to generate
something for the number of hit points
and then it will also generate something
for the attack power right so we'll also
say something like well or or let's say
speed speed speed so yeah one is a
particularly slow right and this is
particularly weak
whereas this particularly armored and
this is particularly fast right so we've
got something here slow that's a one and
a fast is it eight as well so let's just
say we've got those two parameters so
any particular monster in our system now
can be described by a tuple two values
its HP and its speed and that's just our
thing right again not specific here this
is not how we're going to do it which is
an example of something that might come
up during when we're creating a
generator if every monster is defined by
an HP in a speed tuple then we need to
now pick the body of the monster from a
set of monster bodies that are available
and I guess what I'm trying to say is we
probably won't have 64 different monster
bodies just for this one purpose right
because remember when we actually go
further down this road there will be
more than just the HP in the speed
there'll be the HP the speed what type
of AI it's running you know like is it
skittish or aggressive is it holding a
bunch of coins doesn't have this is that
that right so there's a number of things
that we're going to be specifying here
it will get worse and worse in that
respect so what I want to emphasize is
that like 64 even if that might be a
reasonable number of monsters to have
well it quickly becomes intractable even
if you had one more and we're probably
not going to want to spend all 64 of our
character sprite monster designs on just
this one grid but looking back at it
let's suppose we go well okay so maybe
monsters in this area are one way in
this area or one way and this area one
way in whatever so maybe we have one
monster body here's a b c d e f g h i so
we actually use like nine bodies right
to represent 64 different possible
discrete combinations of HP and speed
and what we do is we look to see where
in this graph you fall and that's how we
figure out which body you are so
anywhere in between like one and two on
speed and one and two on HP will fall
into the a category and we'll pick body
shape hey anything that was like eight
eight will be body shape i and you know
various places in between what I was
sort of suggesting is that if an artist
wanted to come along and place one of
these things into location that was not
previously specified so let's say they
want to create a new area here where
they create body shape J that's
specifically for things that are sort of
like six three right like they're three
speed six armor and that will take a
bunch of things that used to fall either
in CDE or B and it will now make them
body shape J and that's just a way of
clarifying to the player to provide a
little bit more specific
to the body shape to represent the
underlying statistics to them visually
more directly right so let's suppose we
want to do that well if we want to do
that purely with art assets then that
kind of suggests that right the tagging
wants to be in the HHA itself because
you don't want to have to modify the
code you just want to import a new file
in there right but the reason that I
don't find that a particularly
compelling argument at the moment is
more specifically because look the
artist can't set that anyway the artist
is not in a position to specifying those
things because the artist doesn't have
the ability to really put any of that
information into this file it's a PNG it
doesn't have a way in Photoshop to
cleanly edit those things because the
artist would have to learn some like way
of marking up code in a text file or
something so what that suggests to me
again is just that we probably want that
data to be a side band it's something
that gets specified you know if we have
to put it in a separate text file fine
but maybe that's how we do that we don't
do it by pushing all that stuff into the
PNG so what I'm kind of arguing for
there is just the ability to say let's
have all of our art assets come in with
hard-coded well not hard coded but
integer based IDs and then if you want
to associate those IDs in some way with
picking then we'll do that right so
that's one one sort of way we can talk
about how that might go now again
another problem that we would have with
that is it doesn't necessarily merge as
well so as I'm sort of talking about it
I may be talking myself out of it a
little bit what I basically mean to say
is let's suppose that two people on two
separate machines decide to modify here
and main hero by adding a new one of
these things if they just mark them up
by tags they merge properly if they mark
them up using some kind of fixed ID then
you
to worry about well how does that ID get
set right
so it kind of suggests for me that we
really do want to maintain the tag
system almost exactly the way it is now
and the only modification we really want
to make is that maybe those tags are
only relevant for picking things at the
higher level but even that maybe that's
not the right thing I mean in some sense
I I guess you maybe just use
hierarchical tags
I mean it sort of seems like maybe as
much as I thought that we would want to
do something different it seems like
maybe all we really need to do is just
split our tag system into two stage tag
lookup the first tag lookup looks up
what kind of a sprite sheet you're
talking about the second tag looks up
inside the sprite sheet what actual what
actual glyph you wanted
I mean I guess that just it I guess I
don't see any reason not to do it so so
I I think if I'm not mistaken I think
the tag stuff just is probably still the
best way to go and maybe we just want
them to be hierarchical a little bit so
we want it we kind of want to split the
tag search up a little bit but that may
be the only real thing we need to do
there just to make it more efficient and
a little more logical than what it is
but it seems like that always merges
properly and that's a nice boat
especially for a community style project
like handmade hero where kind of the
point is for people to go in and modify
it and mess with it seems like something
that would allow people to share pngs
or hhas rather is pretty valuable
[Music]
so I feel like I'm gonna go with that so
I guess what I would say is the only
real thing that I might want to add now
is I feel like the problem with our HHA
files is there's nothing in the HHA file
at the moment that helps you understand
where the data from that HHA came from
and because it's basically just a
runtime format it's the kind of format
that I would use if I was shipping
gained myself and again since this is
not exactly that kind of a project it's
not the same as the kind that I would
ship myself it makes me think that we
want some annotation in there so I think
really all I want to do after all that
consideration I really don't think I
want to modify it that much it seems
like we made actually some pretty good
decisions even though we didn't have a
lot of information and go on I think
we're in pretty good shape I think
mainly what I would want to do is
looking at the file formats here I think
what I would want to add is when we're
discussing these I think I kind of want
to change the asset types array I just
want to get rid of it and have the
assets themselves store what type they
were and again the reason for that is
because now we're talking about more of
a we're talking about more of a editable
file format here and because we merge
assets together anyway we now know very
specifically that those assets are going
to be loaded into different slots anyway
so we don't care about keeping them
contiguous very much at all in the way
that we perhaps used to and so it seems
like it's it's just would be easier for
these to just be arrays of assets and so
what I would want to do is have the
array of assets and then also have some
markup for the assets so for example
something that stores the PNG file that
these assets came from so that when
someone is looking at an HHA file that
maybe they've received
maybe they got an HHA file from somebody
else and they're trying to figure out
what's in it just a little bit of markup
ability there so that they can gain a
little bit of insight into what it is
they're actually looking at so for
example let's let's just let's just go
down that road let's just let's just go
down that road specifically and see
where it leads us and I think that
that's a little bit more it's feeling a
bit better to me
what's going on there so let's suppose
at this HHA header file here let's
suppose that what happens is this
version gets incremented from HD version
0 to H J 1 and what it does we now
expect that the asset information is
going to be completely different than it
was before and so in addition you know
to the asset types like the asset types
used to be there it's going to not be
there anymore it'll just be assets and a
JJ asset some cells now get larger right
so the HHA asset will have in it maybe
in addition to its tag indices it'll
also have some markup information or the
other thing we could do is change this
to be an asset markup thing which is the
thing that would tell us about what that
asset was so you know it it's was asset
types before later it's it's different
than that so you know let's suppose that
you know it used to be this maybe it
becomes something like this
I think yeah we use Deus 54 for file
offsets right so there's some annotation
in there and maybe that annotation is
just like a glob of text you can put in
there like stuff in a description or you
know whatever else you wanted so there's
basically like information that you can
use to understand what it is that you're
actually seeing that seems pretty good
to me and so you know if we change the
version we'd get rid of this and we just
have the markup from now on right that
seems pretty good
I don't see a lot of downsides to that
but we would recount of rearrange things
a little so let me see what's in here
these are ways of removing assets yeah
I'm coming up these primacy number
things this tries to remove so this was
sort of saying hey look if you created a
grid for these eight days you could then
say oh I want to override a particular
asset that part we haven't really
figured out much about and it's probably
worth saying whether we would want to do
that now or not so when you load in an
HHA one thing we don't have the ability
to do right now is have HHS say that
other HHA stuff should not be used so
for example let's suppose that you want
to replace the version of the hero with
a different version of the hero by
putting an HJ file in there it does seem
to me like hey there's no way to really
do it because the tags if the tags match
it can just use either one of those and
so there's no way to specifically say
which one that you would actually prefer
right
so I'm guessing but I but I guess what
we could do there is we don't really
need that because if you look at the way
that our tags work you could just have a
primacy tag right you could just do this
we could just add one every time you
want to replace one to the whatever it
is that you were trying to replace right
so the tag primacy value is just a thing
that we then match on we always take the
highest one right I think that just
works so we really don't need we really
don't need this at all I don't think and
that's nice because that gets us out of
the business of ever trying to identify
HHA files at all which we don't I don't
think we really want to do like we don't
want to have to try and identify them so
anyway let's just go ahead and kind of
move move forward with this so what do
you do here is we're going to take a
little bit of tact that I often will do
I'm gonna go ahead and call this HHA
header one and then I'm going to go
ahead and make another one called HHA
header two right and this is just an
updated version and so I'm gonna pull
these out like so and here's the
secondary version of the file and so
what I was kind of suggesting as well
all right so we've got tags and then
we've got assets right and we'll leave
those two in there and maybe we'll
change the assets truck to have
that information but will also have an
annotation here right so in addition to
the tags array and the assets array will
now have annotations array I'm gonna
move the annotations array down like so
because it's kind of an extraneous thing
and I think because we're sort of
playing around with this a little bit
more and doing a little bit more with it
I think I might actually make this
header file a little bit more extensible
slightly just because we don't know what
we're gonna need I'm gonna go ahead and
say this so now we've kind of got a
block in fact I guess we'll do 12 so
we'll make this an even number here and
then I'll go ahead and put in another
set of reserved here for other race
stuff like that so in here we got those
three arrays there I'm gonna go ahead
and say that this reserved 64 is gonna
be what 1 plus I guess if I want maybe 8
more of that I want 8 total or something
like that then I would do 5 right so
these just leave us some zeros we can
play with if we want to add things
without change that or just if optional
additions so that's something we could
play with later if we want to and so the
annotation count here is always going to
be the same as the asset count that's
just the rule and then we would have an
HHA annotation and anafi would go now
since the assets now need a type ID I
think every where we actually see one of
these HHA assets we would need to
specify what its type was so we would
have to have a secondary version of an
HHA asset and you know
I mean I could still put the type in
there I suppose I'm just not sure how I
want to do that
hmm
so there's a couple of things about that
so I'm kind of torn here the other thing
that I'm not entirely sure about again
is for the tags stuff I guess I'm
wondering whether we actually need type
IDs on our assets at all
so the asset ID is just a quick way of
saying that you're looking for something
specific a body piece instead of a head
piece right but another way to do that
would have just been to have tags for
those things that you then match against
preferentially and so I'm wondering if
that's really we should just go all in
on the tag system and just the one thing
we should do to change it is actually
remove the concept that there is a type
ID for an asset at all right
and that kind of seems like a good idea
the one aspect of types that I think so
the only thing that I'm sort of thinking
about in my head it's related to that is
the fact that that's also what we were
doing to say which kind of acid it was
at all so whether it was a sound or a
bitmap or a font right so it seems like
we still want like asset sprite asset
font asset font glyph assets sound is
still something we want because you
don't ever want to match those external
to each other now maybe you just I mean
it's just weird to think that that would
be a tag - it seems like a waste of time
but maybe it's better to have that be a
tag as well that way everything just
goes through the tag system and you're
kind of done right and when you load
things then you can use those tags to
sort of partition things in a way that
that you want
I'm tempted I will tell you I am tempted
so it's just kind of generic right and
that way you only have one thing and
when you pull in the assets you parse
them out by those things so you know in
here you've got tagged primacy and
you've got tagged datatype right and
then you'd say like oh okay you know
we've got a thing that's like something
like this and then in here you would
just say like okay there's you know
what's the like that and so you'd set
those just in the tags and so the tags
is it's always tags right
everything is always tags and and the
the degree to which we want those things
separate it out we do at parse time not
in the file you know
I think I like that much time I got here
got like an hour so if I if I let myself
go long there so I don't know I want to
play around with it because like I said
I really just don't know but it seems
kind of like the right thing to do so
I'm gonna go ahead and say handmade file
formats v1 dot H and this is just a way
I like to keep the files a little bit
neater
by removing things that get kind of like
deprecated from a file format as it
evolves over time so if I wanted to keep
these around right I can say asset type
ID this is an asset type ID from v1 that
we don't use anymore but we might want
to keep around if we're trying to learn
no old file or something like that
similar we've got like an HS a header v1
you know that's what that used to look
like right we've got this
and so then these things are the v2
versions and similarly you know the HSA
asset if it does have it if it did have
a type we would duplicate it as well but
said I think I'm just not gonna do that
so you know we're left with just this is
what we're looking at and yeah I mean
that's that's basically it so then when
you've got these excuse me when you've
got these sort of two different file
formats defined like I do it the
currently what I can do is I can go now
to our agency edit and I can include the
old file format right as well as the new
one in here and so now what I can do if
I include the new file format in here is
I can make something that for example
duplicates a file format a file and
updates the header or something like
that right something that you know can
something that can upgrade file formats
and change you know a v1 file into a v2
file or something like that right which
is what I want to be able to do so for
example if I have a thing in here that
allows me to read one of these in right
so I'm like okay you know we've got an
HHA read here
and maybe I've got something like this
if I want to go ahead and and look at
what would be in here right I know that
I've got like an HSA tag with the tags
an HSA asset okay assets and now we'd
have hij annotations with the
annotations right so I know that these
are the things that I would want to have
in my loaded HHA when I would load it in
and so I could have a thing here that
was like okay yeah here's the read HHA
and here's the like right HHA and so you
know could read and write we could read
and write HHA so for example if I wanted
to do something like this we don't
really have a good command parser here
I'm not going to really deal with that
right now
what I can do here is just the same
basic thing that we did before so we
take a look here and we say all right if
we're going to like do a rewrite or
something like that then what we can do
is have like a source file name and a
desk file name loaded that way we can
load in the desk file suppose what I
could do here too is like well I might
do it this way maybe like that
so yeah we got the source file and desk
file there so what I'm going to do is
say ok for the destination file and the
source file I'm going to open those two
up so I'm gonna open this one up our B
and a my on this one up with WB and I
guess what I want to do is actually have
a and exists here so you know we kind of
did that I want to make a thing that
actually does that
so you can give it a filename and it'll
tell you if that file exists or not
so what we'll do is we'll say file star
test and we'll do an F open for read
just to see if exist there there is
there an actual in the C runtime library
it's so limiting but C runtime library
file exists is there a way we can test
that that's not what we want we want
stat is basically what we want but
that's not really the C runtime why only
since I have underscores in front of
them is that something they do now
because like F stat is not a C runtime
function right I mean that's POSIX I
think unless they added it
I don't think they did hmm because the
problem with F opening something for
Reid is if somebody already has it open
in exclusive access mode then your it'll
fail but that it's it is there right so
what you want to know is just does this
file exist you know and I really I
always just write this in in the actual
platform layer where it's it's almost
always there's a function that will
literally tell you exactly this
information to get file info and
unfortunately I'd really don't know that
there is a particular way it looks like
standard file system colon colon exists
is maybe one of those like this it
doesn't look like I'm not seeing
anything from a standard library
reference here
just take a quick look I don't
understand why these are all underscored
I guess that underscore ones are just
the UNIX ones or something like ones
that aren't technically in the C runtime
library just weird that most of them be
underscored I'm saying
yeah I don't really see you know I feel
so we'll just keep doing this way but
it's not great
you know normally you'd do this with an
operating system call if it's actually
good if you cared so oh well so we'll go
ahead and say that is how we know that
the file exists if we can open it and
we'll go from there so we can also say
now down here where we do file or it
exists for our create one we can just do
it early if file exists I'll name in
this case we want it to not exist right
so here we just go okay if it doesn't
exist go and do this otherwise it
already exists and it's bad and that's
fine here we can basically say you know
if file exists source file source file
name and file exists just file name and
we want to not that one then we go ahead
and do our shenanigans so here we can
say so something like that just to let
the person know that they can't
overwrite a file with it or whatever
something like this so that's a little
bit clearer just what's going on there
so if we get into a situation where we
can't actually where we can actually do
it we load one for reading and one for
writing and then off we go
I won't be specific with the error
message here I don't know if you're
allowed to f close I don't think you are
actually so this is a good example of
kind of something stupid so this is the
way you would want to write that code
right so you because you don't really
want to have lots of different error
handling paths so you want to be able to
open both source and destination files
[Music]
which I guess is not nothing there we go
so if we couldn't open the source then
we Perenara so you couldn't with the
desks we open a versus assuming we could
open either of those we you know we
close them alright so now what we want
to do is we want like this path to do
like read HHA and this path to do right
HHA so you know read from this right to
that and in this case we'll have one of
these loaded hhas that comes back so you
know off we go
you know I'm not going to do that we'll
do this either way so that is you know
how that routine would work pretty
straightforward right
that doesn't want to be there at all
all right um so yeah in this case we
want to make a v2 header right and I'll
see what go let's call it B - yeah and
technically since we don't really we
don't need to label our most recent
version we can just call it an HH a
header right and then we'll get that
here and I guess technically that was a
v-0 and now this is a v1 so maybe this
should actually be called v-0 to line up
with the actual version number that's in
the file so I think I'll actually call
it that let me go ahead and rename that
file as well to a different file name so
it should instead of being v1 it should
be v-0 so now we can do is yeah this guy
will work properly it will write a file
of a particular version this will
rewrite one that we get let me make sure
we can compile this now something useful
there we go so now we've got the ability
to you know use this to rewrite a file
if we implement these functions before I
do that I want to add one more thing
here which is I just want like a
something like this or info let's say
and what info I want info to just give
me like information about the file that
I provide right
and so this one I suppose doesn't need
to check for existence because it's not
overriding anything so we can just do it
this way so we load in you know the file
name we would want to open it for
reading like so
and then what we do is we just say like
okay give me back the loaded HHA for
this thing and then inside here what I
want I would want to do is print out the
info from it so I think what I would
want to do here is inside the loaded HHA
I think I might want to store some of
the stuff that's in there for example I
could sort of the magic value and the
version number and I'd want like the tag
counts and that stuff I need that anyway
right so I need that stuff here and yes
so I think if the aunt again if the
annotations the annotations wouldn't
look like this right so it's the source
file name like that
it's just a bunch of text here and these
want to be kind of strings right so
probably want something like this
problem is that doesn't stack very well
so you know I might actually just go
ahead and say looks like this something
like this and I suppose in here we could
need to stick an author in there maybe
it would be something so you kind of
know where it came from and the
annotations I think that's reasonable we
could add another array if we wanted
other kinds of annotations that I don't
think we needed expandability
necessarily in there so that would give
us what we wanted there and we could
have the version the source version in
here which is like which version it came
from and that would let us know I could
also say that annotations 0 gives us
some basic information about the file
I don't really know we want to do that
because then when you merge two of them
I'm not sure how you would resolve that
so probably not but that's yeah so if I
go ahead and implement the load HHA bit
here then what I could do is I can the
very least take a look at what's in the
header so if I do a header an HS a
header V 0 I can go ahead and do a read
of that I suppose what I can do is I can
actually look at this as two different
header versions here and just peek at
the initial values right
so what I could do is say alright let's
take a you three to four the magic value
and a you thirty-two for the version I'm
gonna go ahead and and f read those in
here right maybe I even do it this way
so I say look load in here from the
source file and then maybe we have
errors here so this will tell us what's
actually in the file when we do this F
raid and we can compare that here so if
I D pair 0 equals H I J magic value
and in here we can look at ID pair one
and see if it's HHA if it's zero this
tells us the versions and off we would
go right so here we've got a load read
HHA be zero and here we've got to read
HH a v1 so I think that supports both of
those to be honest I'm not sure we
really want to do it that way I might
want to do it this way we call it that I
think that's probably just better I did
do that so that it sets it up here just
seems smarter
don't know if I've got a way to allocate
why if the ability to use memory here I
don't think I do so what I want to do
here I guess is just a malloc so we can
have one of those and I want to be able
to zero it as well we want like a the
basic arena stuff there so again it
would be nice if we have that we don't
at the moment let's see here I guess we
can play with that in a minute so if I
just return a 0 add one of those from
then I should be able to actually run
this okay
this passes the results in here like so
happen okay so load HHA and then fire
not found
it's supposed to be read HHA and when we
dump the info now we should it's not
what I wanted when we dump the info now
we should be able to take and dump stuff
like the magic value or the version from
the loaded HHA so in here we can dump
the source version we know the magic
value was the magic value I guess
although now that I think about it we
could just save whatever the magic value
actually was and and put that in there I
suppose now that I think about it so we
could just say something like this
so that those are actually known yeah
that seems reasonable so if we do an
info dump
we rode one of these in we could then
actually printf here suppose this really
wants to be that it wants to be printed
as characters because that's at least
nominally how the magic value supposed
to go I guess so we know it's for long
and we know it's the magic value here
right so in theory that's all we really
need there I thought it was read HHA
isn't it create you know what an H HD is
that's new I thought we had version your
source version sorry and so that gives
us I think everything we need to get
started playing with this so if I do HHA
edit now oh I should put in description
of that there
so now if I do info and I print one of
these out then I should be a look and
just see you know these various files
that we have our version zero and that's
really all I wanted to do with that so
you could then see that one was first a
zero or one was whatever so if I was to
create one now so like let's say I
created one of the you know dummy HHA or
something right then if I do an info on
that's I'm hoping that that would give
me a version one right so now we have
two different versions of the file here
don't really want that one anymore but
that's the idea right so then for
loading we just need to write a little
loader and a little saver and then we
can have R to R then we could have not
only a way to dump the information if we
wanted to look at it a little more
carefully but we'd also have a way of
updating files that were with a previous
version right so let's take a look at
how we would do that so let's suppose
that what we want to do was read an HHA
what I want to do here too is F seek to
the beginning so I would like the source
file in this case to come back to the
beginning one of the problems that we're
gonna have here and I don't know how to
get around this little exactly is I
don't know if FC CAC chily supports
64-bit I hope it does I think we looked
it does now support that mmm well I'm
not sure what long int actually now
refers to I guess we'll find out
but anyway so hopefully we could still
do 64-bit seeks on this I don't know if
we actually can if we can't this is
gonna be unfortunate
I luckily for us we don't currently have
any files that are over 4 gigabytes but
since we're storing our bitmaps
currently uncompressed we easily could
so well but anyway inside here where
we've got our read HHA version 1 version
2 I'm gonna go ahead and FC cuss back
pretty sure that's how that works
set it back to the beginning so in here
we can load in the new information so
here we'd have an HH a header v-0
I'm sorry 0 v-0 whatever it is header we
do an f-18 of that and I guess one of
the things it's a little bit Squinkie
here
I suppose we need to keep the data store
somewhere so it probably would need like
that and so we kind of we really just
want to read the entire file probably in
fact that probably is the easier way to
do this I think we have that in our test
PNG
so if we want to we can do that here and
maybe that can just be a an operation
that also returns the size I don't know
to what extent we care about that but if
we did this we would now have the
ability to just read the entire thing in
the memory like so so if we just read
the entire file in like that then that's
the data store so that's the entirety of
that file we don't actually want to do
the F open here so we could just do it
with a handle like so I and do this
right so if for example we do to read we
do the read entire file on that then
what we would do here is just say result
datastore or equals read entire file
source file and then this stuff doesn't
actually need to do that F read it can
just try here to get the information out
so the only question is do we care about
crash prevention here like if we didn't
read anything in and I don't really
think we do for any particular reason
can't think of why we would but so if we
actually said look look this is a this
is a you 32
same with this then what we can do is
just test these and I think that's all
we really need to do there in order to
make the read happen let me just double
check that that actually worked I think
that should have been an arrow all of
these
all right so looking through here I
should be able to now do the same thing
that's doing before and it should give
me those back which does and so now I
know that I can do an HH a header v-0
here and I can look at the data store so
what that allows me to do is now I want
to start making this translation here I
want to make an H I J edit dot H file
because I would like to move this up
there right because just to keep it so I
can view those two at the same time we
go so looking at that we can see that
what we need to load is a tag count the
asset and the asset count is worth of
stuff from these two things and that
shouldn't be too hard for us to do if
we're loading in a v-0 file we have to
do the sort of up the what so we're
looking for it we have to do the we have
to do the version upgrade the the we
have to change it from v-0 to v1 I don't
know what you want to call that update
of the data format and if we're reading
v1 than we don't right so if we want to
read HHA v-0 then once we get the data
store out of there what we could see is
in I mean we know exactly we're going to
do this right we're gonna say the HHA
tag count equals something and then the
HHA tags is going to be a malik of that
right
so this is just going to be an
allocation of those things the same is
true of the assets array and the
annotations array so we're gonna go
through and figure out what the tag
count is and what the asset count is
oops alright so we know we want to do
assets and we know we want to do
annotations and we want the same number
of both of these so there's a notation
for every asset and the data store has
already been done for us - that part is
not something we actually have to do and
then what we have to do is just a loop
over the assets and process them into
these and off we go
so the important thing to remember here
is that when we go to actually do the
tags we're gonna have additional tags
for every asset specifically if we want
to do what I was suggesting about having
the tags themselves now specify all the
information then the data type tag is
gonna be added to every asset so it's
actually inside the tag count it's
actually gonna be the tag Cal plus the
asset count because for every asset we
need to add a data type tag right we
also know that we've got an additional
sort of like blank that's left in there
the zero tag it doesn't get loaded which
is super annoying is it cause me all
those problems so I'm not sure we really
want to do that but you know I don't I
don't know how to make it necessarily
any cleaner than it is because if you
didn't add it then that also means that
when you go to translate where all of
your things are you've gotten off by one
there because now every
when it's saying I use asset twelve but
they really mean they use asset thirteen
and they're just not talking about the
zero right and all these things like
this I'm sorry
they say they used s at twelve but
they're really talking about asset
eleven in the file because there is no
asset zero so you push you're off by one
errors to one place or the other and I'm
not sure we pick the best one but I
don't know that there's one that doesn't
have any of these problems because if
you want your zero to be an on tag you
got to do something about it anyway so
taking a look at these that's how this
would look and the only difference here
is that if this asset count includes the
null asset that asset obviously it's not
gonna get a datatype so it would be a
minus one there so that's what that
looks like and now we just have to kind
of look at what we actually are gonna
have tags wise so looking at the tags
just trying to think it through here
what we probably want to do is say well
if we're looking at a v1 file I'm sorry
to v-0 file we know that the tag count
is specified directly the asset type
count we don't care about in the asset
count is also correct so we can just I
think load these directly we should be
able to say like okay the header tag
count is the tag count the header asset
count is the asset count I think that's
just correct I don't think there's
anything else weird that we would have
to do there when we load out the v-0
header it should just work then what we
have to do is we've got to go through
and go read by asset types because
that's how these files were structured
so we're gonna have to use those and
unpack the assets into the asset array
that way now the annotations for our
purpose is going to have to be filled in
with default annotations in this case
and that's okay we can do that what we
need to do there to say okay there's the
default annotation of some kind and that
default annotation should probably have
just like a D validations one that
we didn't have any annotation so we have
to tag it with one now and so what that
would be is something like looking at
this annotation where we've got these
various strings in here what we need to
do is is do something that will write an
annotation out to the file and give us
back its result so we would probably
want something like a right annotation
here and it would take the source file
base name that's gonna be whatever the
source file name was here and again that
we probably should know what that is we
should probably have a way of specifying
that is something like that we'll take a
look at that a second we have an asset
name the asset name is not known so it'd
probably be something like just an
unknown fill in there the asset
description would be none or would be
like imported by read a chat jv0 right
and the author would just be HHA edit
that eggsy
and so maybe abs dispense friends just
friends for the parentheses parentheses
so like normally what we'll do is we'll
have a way of putting some annotations
in there for new files so that will kind
of have something that carries along
with the data as it goes forward but for
the moment like all of our old files if
you ever imported a v-0 file using this
utility it just marks it as like we
don't know where this came from like
it's who knows really imported it from
another file and the file didn't have
annotation data so as far as we know
they came from the ether and that's what
we're trying to tell you right so what
we'll do here when we load all these
things is literally every single
annotation in question will get this
stamped on it so every single asset will
just get the same
annotation stamped on it period and off
you go
right so the assets themselves on the
other hand those will be the same we
didn't update that file at all
so each asset index that we load in in
this case is going to be exactly the
same as the asset that we had and the
only thing that we're probably gonna now
think about what we will have to update
though is the tag array so it's not
exactly true the first tag index
one-pass let last tag index is going to
have to get modified so we probably want
to do think here where we do just ask
that and we create dest asset from here
like so so we'll copy that in but then
we need to do a first tag index one past
list tag index this kind of has to be
updated right the annotation doesn't
have to be updated because the
annotation always just gets set the same
way no matter which asset index we're
actually on so that part's fairly
straightforward and won't eat anything
and so this is going to end up being a
double indexed year this is going to
index first over I shouldn't say index
this is going to iterate over each of
the the okay asset type arrays and for
each asset type array we'll go through
all the assets refer to that type array
and that way they'll know what type idea
is again that's the thing that's we've
removed so it's just gonna use that
first to sort of place some information
back into the file that we can use later
now what I don't actually know how we
want to do exactly again is what the
tags will actually be for these things
that we're looking at here like head
Cape torso grass Tufts tone rocks or
tree shadow font and font cliff that
sort of stuff I don't know exactly how
we want to specify the
asset types out separately there are a
few ways we could do it one way is we
could just define an asset type V one of
these zero thing and we just copy them
over directly and figure these assets or
assets that are going to go away
eventually one way or the other and so
either you're looking either you set
that to you know a new version or you
use the old version I'm not sure like I
said how I really want to do that we
should probably think about it a little
bit more carefully and maybe we won't
touch that part of it till next time
we'll have to think about it a little
bit but for now let's proceed with the
straightforward translation of the asset
types arrays so in here what I want to
do is loop over asset type index and for
every asset type index here that should
be in the asset types array I think
that's a thing that's actually in here
oops I met header
so it's this for a man I'm actually
looking for yeah
and so for each of those I want to look
at the source asset types of asset type
index and that'll give me an HSA asset
type v-0 right from there I want to do a
loop over the source asset index I and
that's not the same as the asset index
right in this case or I should say this
is the you know asset type asset index
however you want to look at it that no
actually it is a source it is a source
asset index because it's stored in the
asset type absolutely right its first
asset index it's actually correct right
so it's like that's the thing
one-pass last asset index plus source
right so that's actually gonna loop give
us the that's going to give us the
source F asset index that we're talking
about like so and so for each one of
those we will just put it into place
with the best asset index this way
so that seems pretty straightforward
that allows us to unpack these the way
that we want to so the really the only
thing we have to do is modify the tag
array there in order to make this work
properly we should also zero out so we
should take the HHA annotation and the
HHA asset and also the HHA tag and we
should set this so the HHA assets zero
should be the null asset the HHA tags
zero should be the null tag and the HHA
annotations zero should be the notation
and by the way a reason I'm doing it
that way is because technically you can
do this now I think you can but not all
compilers support that like for example
Visual Studio even I want to say maybe
even 2013 to this word it 2012
definitely didn't support it so in the
interest of supporting compilers a
little bit further back I still write it
this way even though modern wise you
wouldn't have to do that right you could
just use open closed bracket right on it
which is much more convenient but not
actually supported everywhere quite yet
so maybe in five years you can just
forget about that but not quite yet
anyway so the tag count here needs to
actually use the asset count from the
source asset count that makes sense so
this is actually header asset count we
go and so source file name this is
interesting so source file name in this
case I think I want to pack that into
the HHA like I'd like to put that here
probably
and this kind of argues that what I
really probably will need to do is
actually make it so that the file is
loaded inside here it sort of resisted
doing that a little bit but it looks
like that would be better anyway because
if the error checking happened in there
maybe that's just cleaner because then
you don't the check in the air twice you
know to check it once here and and once
here so I could just make it so that
this actually works outside seems okay
to me it's just this right so in here I
would just say like okay if you want to
load one of these you try to like so and
get an error here if you can't so if we
did it that way then this right here
becomes source file and source file name
oops
source file name is the actual thing
that you would be passing in and the
loaded HHA in this case is the result
right so the other thing I might do is I
might actually just let this continue to
work this way so maybe you always get
one back but maybe it doesn't have
anything in it right so I don't know I
don't know I feel about that yeah I mean
I think I might want to do that that way
so maybe what I'll do here is put a
valid flag in here and so you know only
once you've actually vetted in does it
consider it to be valid
and otherwise it doesn't otherwise it's
considered to have been a failed read
and that way in here we could say well
alright if the loaded HHA is not valid
that we're not gonna write it you know
I'm saying and that maybe seems a little
bit saner so I'll come through here and
just say all right that's you know and
this is if not file exists just filename
blah blah blah blah
and again like just that felt a little
bit better to me I don't have a strong
reason why it just felt a little better
guess that can go right here and off you
go
so that seems fair and then these get a
little simpler right these we can just
make they don't have to look like this
at all anymore just like this
and that is nicer I mean I think that's
just easier like it's nicer for people
who are trying to make things with this
utility so that does seem like it
probably that was an improvement and
well this one I guess I don't know what
I want to do with quite yet probably I
want a thing that just creates a null
header and will change over to using
that later but for now this seems fine
so we okay here
I think that's all good and so here we
would you know write the file at this
point once we get it
so here's us reading it in you know and
and there is us writing it out so now if
we go to start compiling and we see the
right annotation here that's something
that we haven't actually implemented yet
we'll get to that in a second see what
else we've got
source s at types and source assets we
haven't read from the file yet well we
read them for values to haven't pointed
to them yet so we want to do that so for
example in here right we want to do and
I guess actually we could just do it
right here
hh8 asset source assets that's just
going to be HHA asset cast of the
datastore plus what the datastore says
the assets array location is the same is
true for the types
and thus a mysterious the tags so that
just basically gives us all of our
source like all the stuff we want to
read from oops that's supposed to be
zero because that's not around anymore
so at that point we just need to do our
tag rewriting and is there anything else
we did not do yet file exists needs to
move up in the world so and that's it so
so I think now that's supposed to be
annotations yeah so I think that's all
good at the moment but again so what we
need to do here also is when we go to
actually write annotations so what we're
gonna need is we're gonna need the
ability to we're gonna need the ability
to talk about data that's not in the
data store the current as it currently
exists right so like we have to be able
to copy we have to be able to copy data
that's in the data store or forward and
that's a little harder like that part's
gonna be a little bit trickier right
because the data stuff that's in the
data store varies depending on how it
works this way I think so the data
offsets there but we don't have the size
right
the size is implied by whatever the type
is so it's a little more work for us we
have to look to see which kind which
type this was and then we have to move
it over and that to me also that kind of
suggests again that maybe we want to
actually just include something that
lets us
ah we just want to include that
information directly right so we want to
have like an actual we don't want to
have to jump in here and figure out what
the actual size of the thing was to copy
every time we might want to just write
it you know I'm not sure like I couldn't
say for sure like maybe it's better to
just always actually compute it they're
pretty easy to compute least for these
two and HHA fonts a little harder it's
two arrays but you know these are much
more direct so it's it's hard to say
which one of those you would want to do
whether it's worth it to actually have a
size field for something that you
wouldn't have to do but when you go
through here you do you would have to
know like you have to know which type it
is to move it because you need to know
how big the data is that you're moving
so so yeah so wiring all this stuff up
at that point should be fairly
straightforward though the only weird
thing here again is that the annotations
because the annotations are missing I
think I might want to basically have
those be unpacked so I feel like I might
want to do this as loaded HHA annotation
I might want to just have that so that
this is actually done this way
trying to think if there's a smarter way
to do this there might well be so we
might want to do it this way where we
just say look these things are you know
just stuff that you having a loaded sea
version and you know other things may
want to be that way eventually as well
hard to say but let's just claim that
that's the case
so I mean here when I go to create that
array I had actually do this and then
what I can do is say well the default
annotation is actually this and then off
we go
right
there we go
so now we're down to just the tagging
and again that's yeah that's sort of the
thing that we don't really know how you
want to do so I may stop there and pick
that up next week other than that we
have the things loaded so if for example
I undid those two lines that we should
have our H shape we can also continue
having the other things compiled if we
want to buy inside the asset inside
handmade ith where we include the asset
the file format so that's in that's
right here right after that's included
we can if we want to use a pound to find
to change things back so for example in
the in file formats V 0 here we can
shuffle these around so like for example
if we just include handmade file formats
B 0 this is a temporary thing if we
include that we can define HHA header to
be HHA header v 0 and we can define HHA
asset type to be HHA asset type 0 and
that will like use
acet type ID step type by the zero so
that would solve our problem there right
and the only thing I guess that I have
to do here is in file formats this part
here you know if we decide to go this
route so that allows us to keep
compiling and keep running properly even
though we kind of have a split version
now so in theory this should still work
I assume although that turns out to not
Y be the case which asset file are we
looking at here
did I not have keep everything the same
shape let me just double-check what I've
got in here we've got header asset type
and ID those all should have been the
same and you didn't mess with the tags
we have annotations but they should not
be in the file so all this stuff should
be fine and and the header should be
fine too yeah and we don't have any hhas
that aren't the old h @ JS right so
everybody's fine there yes so we should
be able to just to leave this compiling
which is the only thing I was actually
going to try and do we should be able to
make it so that we can use the old
versions by just pound to finding the
new versions to be the old versions and
that way everyone in the asset system
still uses those older versions right so
they'd still use all of this stuff but
it didn't look like that worked properly
so I want to take a quick look and see
why because we should be able to still
compile with the old asset loading right
and that should in theory be the case so
let's take a look
take a look at the file here has version
zero which is what we would expect
there's not much else going on there
quite yet we just look at the handle
there's no errors yet
it's got all the stuff set that we
expect to have set so that's good too
it's got the asset types hmm no so this
is wrong so it isn't using the it's it's
using the wrong size for that fellow oh
this is outside of the pragma which is
not good you know what I should just put
this in here because these have to be
inside the pragma well I guess what I
could do is I'll just put the fragment
both places right we yeah it's supposed
to know it has to know specifically how
things are aligned there right it can't
leave gaps and it can't do other stuff
like that so these have to be inside the
pragma where we define everything we
also need to this version I need to
redefine the version number which I
guess I forgot to do that as well so
inside here we need to do a pound to
find HHA version zero so we'll just on
define it and define it I knew okay so
let's try that one more time so there we
go
so now we're just loading correctly so
I'm gonna leave it like that and then
next weekend what we'll do is we'll pick
up where we left off on here so we'll
just make a thing that allows us to
import our old files and change the file
format over you know add annotations in
so that we can then from now on when we
import stuff we can keep those
annotations we should probably put in to
the file as well what the ANA
tation what the source location was so
you know what the other thing we should
do is in here we should get rid of this
thing the asset indices thing what we
should do instead is well we can get rid
of it we should put in the that source
information into the annotations here so
basically this annotation would also
have a sprite sheet X sprite sheet Y so
it like tells you where it was in the
source file know if there's anything
else we want there but I was padded out
so that it's even sighs yeah and I guess
you know if we wanted to we could store
the file date even in there too I
suppose
I mean while we're at it right if you
just put everything in there so maybe
that is what we should do just do that
so maybe yeah maybe we'll do that stuff
and that way we can have all those
annotations in there they can always be
stripped out when you stripped it when
you ship the game if you needed the
space that's why I put them in a
separate array because they're not
actually necessary for anything but I
feel like again since this is a game
that you want to encourage people to
play around with leaving the annotations
in is how we will probably end up
shipping it but I put them in a place
where you could strip them out because
that's probably what you would want to
do when you actually ship to the game
normally you wouldn't want to waste a
bunch of space with metadata that you
didn't actually use when you're running
it alright let's go to the Q&amp;A here
so instead of tags why not relegate the
logic of picking a range of or ran a
bunch of specific assets to the part
that pulls assets in eg when making a
new entity or what have you have a way
to specify hey pick one of from these
specific assets here by path name or
some other identifier obviously comes
with its own issues might not be what
you want and all but is it I be retained
um so we got two problems one is first
of all well I should say first of all
before I say anything else that is sort
of what I was suggesting right meaning
you would have ways of segregating tags
out into two sets one set that's when
you create an entity you use to pick
from the tags that way and then another
one that's inside there when you're
actually using that entity that helps
you pick stuff like facing direction and
things like that right so I was counting
in that but there's some problems so the
first problem is if for hot loading if
you want to be able to support like
loading this new PNG that maybe the PNG
specifies a new set of information that
would change the thing you would have
picked in the entity creation thing that
entity won't change on the screen but it
should have right so picking every frame
is not a particularly good idea from
efficiency but we may have to at least
have a way to make sure that that does
happen look we want to we want to be
able to reap ich when we know that our
our assets have updated right so we need
to kind of have a way at least of
repacking to support heart hot loading
but yes beyond that it would be okay to
pick at least part of the tags first
other tags like facing direction those
vary over frames so they can't be
handled in the same way
we will not be getting scripting
we're going to use type def for the
enums no what do you mean type def for
the enums I'm not sure what you mean by
that exactly we're just using enums as
items also is an unnamed Union inside a
struct legal in terms of an CC I don't
think so
unnamed unions and unnamed strux inside
so unnamed unions and unnamed strux
in general nested inside each other I
don't think is supported by ANSI C or
ANSI C++ but I could be wrong about that
it's far too useful not to use and
should be part of the spec like for sure
since all the compilers we care about
support it we use it whether or not it's
in a spec samar though I couldn't tell
you
we'll hhe contain hashes check sums for
regional input files this might allow a
nice way to only update the changed
assets even if file timestamps are off I
didn't really want to implement a
checksum but we could
so there's our offsets there's our
Dayton checksum 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 don't
ask me why I padded those up to 8 I just
did if the entity holds a reference into
a table that looks up the asset and that
would work with hot loading no it would
not because it's the selection that's
the problem right so for example let's
suppose we go back to that diagram
remember remember this so we go back to
that diagram if you had a table of
indirection all it would do was allow
you to replace a with something else but
it wouldn't allow you to subdivide a
into new quadrants that each meant
something different right so that's what
I was talking about also what I meant
was go away with the specific code side
to find tags and leave picking down to
reference specifically by path or asset
name that's based on the source asset
file um I don't really want anything to
be based on the source asset file at the
moment though I implemented animations
as the base intertext and where every
animation frame is tagged with a number
between 0 and tau and as the t-value
loop goes up it says hey go to the next
sprite but not for this a good idea you
seen any problems with this and/or how
to do 2d animations normally know which
sprite to grab no I don't see any
problem with that the only thing I would
mention is that the efficiency of the
query may be kind of in question
so I would say always keep your tags
sprites sorted in a way that's easy to
look them up by that T value to
accelerate the fact that that's such a
common case so that's really the thing
that I would think you would need to
know but no it's it's a totally
reasonable way to do it because that's
sort of what you do normally with T
lookups a lot of times animations have
fixed frame rates at which point you
don't need to store the T you can just
look it up as an array right so you may
want to look into hey am I always
storing is the T always going up by a
fixed amount anyway and if so then just
store them and have a more compact
format for storing those kinds of tag
sets but yeah I mean it's not no it's
not the craziest thing I've ever heard
mmm any more on topics questions any
more on to other questions not looking
likely all right
miss clothes down here actually did we
but I made those changes we should make
sure we still build yeah all right
close this down no close that okay thank
you for joining us for the episode of
hand made here oh it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you want to
follow us series at home you can always
peer to the game on handmade hero org
and it comes to the source code so that
you can play around fit yourself we also
have a whole bunch of website stuff
there if you are interested in exploring
a little more we've got a watch page
that where you can do really good like
lookups to old episodes or have a thing
that tells you when the streams going to
be live and all kinds of stuff so check
that out so it's a really easy way to
watch the series whether it's new
episodes or old episodes we have an FAQ
for a frequently asked questions I've
seen those or anyone's watching the
series by now priority knows those but I
also have a handmade fund contribution
page where you can help support things
like the handmade network and the
annotated episode guide to handmade hero
that community people do that we try to
help pay them for and of course you can
always click on the handmade hero head
if you want to go to other our other
Molly Rocket websites like the game that
I work on during the day or upcoming
comic book or Anna nice blogs that sort
of stuff hmmm that's about it for today
I'll be back here next week don't forget
to check that watch page for the
schedule it'll be updated pretty soon
with when the next handmade hero
broadcast dates are until then have fun
programming everyone and I'll see you on
the Internet
take use everybody