hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete-game live on
stream we are going to do some debugging
today we basically made the entirety of
our font utility which is just designed
to extract a font from you know a true
type font or something that exists out
in the world already and this is
supposed to take that font and extract
certain of you know specific lifts from
it that we specified and produce PNG
files that can then be fed into our art
package I'm son our packets are art
pipeline exactly as if they had just
been created by an artist while at the
same time producing an hht file that's
got all the data like the horizontal
advance table and the number of glyphs
and the name of the font and stuff like
that so that we can kind of automate the
process so that no one has to manually
do all that work just to get a font into
the game it's the last thing we really
don't have in our asset pipeline we are
currently we have streaming sounds
streaming sprites and this is the one
thing we don't have a way to build
automatically through the game pipeline
we we had done a long time ago when we
first and when fonts something that
packed HH a's directly we don't really
want to do that anymore we want just a
single art build that has everything
with no command-line utility required
and we're pretty close to that so this
is really the only thing we've got left
I'm gonna go ahead and get started on
that process we pretty much made like I
said the entire utility the only thing
that we didn't do is figure out how to
write a PNG file out because we've never
done that before we sketched the
beginnings of that but we didn't quite
get it working and so what we need to do
now is get that actual PNG export
process into place and so our goal here
is to take this utility you can see here
this is the HH font utility take this
utility and work on this one part just
at the very top it's it's just a simple
function called
PNG and what we want to do there is get
it writing out the actual PNG data so
that when we read the PNG jada on the
other side we get the bitmaps for the
font now we already checked this code to
make sure it worked properly what we did
is we wrote out a bitmap version and we
knew that that worked properly so we
know that the pixels value here and the
width and the height are correct so we
know that we aren't dealing with like
corrupted data coming in and that was an
important step because since we have no
idea what we're doing here with writing
out this PNG we're just making it up as
we go along looking at the spec and
looking at our reader and trying to
match the two we don't want to start in
a situation where we don't even know if
what we're writing out is correct so we
definitely wanted to do that step and we
did that step but now we have to figure
out about the rest of this stuff to
figure out like how we're gonna actually
like what we're writing out incorrectly
such that our code doesn't work on the
other side for reading it and then we
have some extra work to do even on top
of that which is to say that our code
that reads PNG s doesn't bother to check
things like the CRC or whatever we
therefore we should be able to get our
reader working first because it doesn't
require the data checks to line up once
we want to take the extra step of having
these things be loadable by some
third-party art tool like that will
require us actually making something
that does do correct crcs there's two
CRC's mark Martin's reminded us during
the pre stream that there is an adler 32
crc stuck at the end of the z lib stream
as well we haven't done that either and
so that needs to be stuck in there I
don't know I don't think our reader does
our reader do that I don't think our
reader ever looks at that yeah so our
reader doesn't care about that so we we
should be I think as I'm misremembering
some
the thing we should be able to get our
reader working first just by
concentrating on exactly getting the
stuff that we care about which we should
be pretty close to we should get that
done and then from there we should be
able to add add back all the stuff that
we would need for a real to be a correct
PNG not just one that only supports our
one reader right because I would like to
go the full pull there okay so the first
thing I wanted to do today is just
remind ourselves what PNG filter
reconstruct does so if we look at PNG
filter reconstruct and I just come in
here and look at it I just want to make
sure that there's nothing weird that
happens during this process you know it
it doesn't look like it
I'm not sure what prior row advance was
supposed to be oh it looks like oh I see
that was just something for us for when
we're doing this more advanced filtering
things so you know I mean writing out
zero case it looks like it's just copied
directly let's take a look at what
happens in the PNG filter here right
before then our sorry right after then
when we write things out what do we
actually say so we say pixel op invert
and swap our so what is pixel our invert
do it just flips the thing upside down
and swap are just swaps these two so
thankfully when writing out the bitmaps
we're not really touching the values
much at all right there's really nothing
particularly weird going on there so it
looks like this stuff should be fine
what I do want to do really quickly is
just make sure test PNG is still working
because for all we know it might not be
so I'd like to take a PNG that actually
we know is good and make sure that it
can export that because I don't want to
assume that we're writing in something
incorrectly based on test PNG until we
verify that SVG is still working because
we haven't run it in forever and who
knows maybe we changed something and
broke it we don't it's not really
utility it was just for us developing
our PNG reader it's not something we
actually consider important so we don't
maintain it or test it at all it's just
a throwaway routine so we should double
check it just to make sure we didn't
break it because we would never have
known right so let's go into our sources
directory and let's take a look at the
intro cutscene I'm gonna go in here and
take a look at the art directory and
we'll just take one of these at random
right so I don't know here's shot 1 6 so
let's take Santa Claus so let's do shot
4 to PNG and what I'm gonna do is I'm
just gonna say that W build oops that
didn't work W build test PNG and it will
tell me what to do so file ok so I just
need to actually put the file
in here for the PNG which is this and
then I'm gonna do shot for two color dot
BMP and shot for two alpha dot BMP and
let's see what happens
so no errors uh looks like everything
loaded okay if I go back to the temp
directory and look looks about right
that's that's what I would expect to see
so everything seems fine there
no nothing particularly unusual so it
looks like test PNG is in fact working
so then again let's go ahead and get the
font dumping procedure kind of into
something that we can call repeatedly so
if I go into the handmade directory I'm
sorry into the temp directory and into
the font directory here's all the stuff
we've got you can see all of the pngs
that we're dumping here and these PM
geez are you know not working properly
which is what we would expect because
let me know that the code is broken so
let's make a thing that dumps and then
runs this so one of the things that we
would expect maybe is like the oh one
one for PNG well I don't know let me or
I don't know which one of these we
should do I guess let's try this one I
don't know what's a t9 what's what's the
what's what's decimal 89 in the ASCII
table decimal 89 would be the Y
character of sure that seems fine so
let's suppose we want the Y character
[Music]
that's the liberation mono dump so if we
wanted to make this work we would say HH
Vaughn oops 8h want the TTF file name in
this case
put that in here from here here we go so
this is the TTFN we want to extract
that's the name of the font that's the
size we then have to supply the care set
which in our case is test we have to
supply the desk hht which we don't
really care what that is but we can call
it test out hhd right now and then the
desk PNG directory which is temp font
that will produce the entirety of the
font and extract all the font bitmaps
and all that stuff we then want to run
our extractor so that's build test PNG
we want to pass one of those in so oops
not that so for example one of these and
we know that we want 0 0 8 9th up PNG
and then we will do W we're already in
the temp font directory so I don't know
why I specified all that extra stuff but
anyway out out RGB BMP out alpha dot BMP
so running those two things in series
like I did there well it should run both
of them and you can see it doing that so
it looks like we forgot after the
extracting we forgot for the font a
carriage return yeah we did all right so
if I now run this I should get both of
these things happening there you go so
it first extracts the font and then of
course I use this to like run two things
on the batch line on the same line two
programs then it does the extraction and
you can see it talking about it here so
it says all right there's the width
height bit depth color depth compression
method filter method interlaced method
then it says okay here's the I dot I
don't know what the 749 is but then it
says okay let's examine the see the
patters
here they are let's decompress looks
like we supported it let's write up both
of these bitmaps and then we're good
right
and so then we can come over here Oh
suddenly it's working we haven't changed
anything what happened all right so I
guess we have gotten to the point where
it's sort of working we just haven't
quite gotten it all the way there for
other people's utilities I guess who
would have known all right
so that looks like what we want the only
thing that we don't have there is the
upside-down nough some it we have to
decide what we're doing with that
so we're flipping that the image is
getting flipped there right and so when
we export that PNG we may need to do an
inversion because the PNG you know we've
got something that's like top-down or
something right but the PNG wants it
bottom-up or however that's working so
we may have to do a flip in place but
that's looks like that's about all we
would need to do to get that working
because otherwise it looks like we've
got the correct stuff in there so if
that's the case then well and there's a
couple other things we need to know
about as well let's let's just double
check something while we're still in the
mood to do so so if we look at when we
load the PNG here right we've got the
PNG comes out we get those final pixels
out you can see here we're not doing any
like gamma correction or any of that
stuff so there's no there's no like
premultiplied alpha or anything in here
I don't think so if we go into the code
inside the art the asset system where
oops sorry look the importer that's
going to actually grab an image out and
use it so you know if we look at what's
happening in say extract image
you can see here that we're doing a
bunch of work to do the promote like but
when we load the PNG right we're doing
our own unpack convert srgb to linear
multiply convert it back to srgb in PAC
that means we expect these to be gana
corrected but not alpha pre multiplied
and so what we want to do is make sure
that our HH font extractor is not pre
multiplying the alpha because that's
going to get done at another time so if
you look in here in libs a bitmap what
you can see is we are doing that work
right you see that happening there so
it's effectively doing a pre multiply of
that alpha but all we really wanted to
do was just write out the Texel as two
two five two two five two two five and
then write out the alpha as gray if
that's all we actually wanted it to do
makes sense so we don't really want the
srgb linear conversion or the
multiplication or any of that stuff so
this piece of code really just wants to
look like that so that it's always going
to just produce the exact Texel since we
know that the gray level here we don't
actually need to do any of this because
the gray level is the gray level right
and I don't think there's any need to to
adulterate it because it's just whatever
the linear linear degree level actually
is what we can do is just say okay
instead of doing any of this stuff right
we can just actually pack this directly
so we can say okay take the pixel do the
end with oxf F to find out what the gray
level is right like so and then when I
write this out what I really want is I
just want effectively the same routine
here that what we'll do not routine but
the same thing that was happening here
where we pack the gray up in the Alpha
Channel so you know this right
but the rest of it should just be white
right because we don't we want the Alpha
be controlling here we don't want to
actually do anything else with it so
that just packed pure white in and then
the alpha value and that's it that's the
end of it because again this is
effectively a monochrome bitmap so
that's what we actually want to write
out so I'm gonna write that now and make
sure that we can get a reasonable image
out of back so what that should produce
when I run this now is a solid bitmap
from the RGB which is just white because
there is no data contained in it at all
right and then the Alpha should be the Y
shape and it should be properly alpha no
srgb shifting happening here or pre
multiplication or anything and that that
does look like what that did so now I
think although we need to do a flip and
we could do that here I suppose if we
just invert these two now looking at
that it looks like we're already doing
that so do you see how destro is going
backwards and source row although
actually wait they're both going
backwards okay what why all right I'll
be honest I I don't understand why
they're both going backwards that I'm
not gonna ask but let's suppose that we
wanted this to not be flipped anymore we
would do that so that now the destro is
starting at the top going down sister at
the bottom going up right and so if I I
don't know why I closed that directory
if I look at it now we should get the Y
in the correct orientation and it is
although I'm a little weirded out by the
shape I don't understand why we've got
like empty area down here and also I
thought so that looks like it's off by
one I feel like it it should have been
yeah so I think this is Capote you can
see it doing it too it's supposed to
skip one line because it's supposed to
leave one pixel of padding all the way
around the font that was because we want
our textures to be padded with a with a
blank row for sampling purposes right so
really we do want one row of pad there
so that is the actual code that we
should do because that leaves the row of
padding and now that instead of two on
the bottom and none on the top they'll
be one on the topic two on the bottom
right so that's good there and you can
kind of see now we've got that nice one
pixel border which is what we wanted all
right so we're now effectively done with
the like part we actually need so we
could ship this now if all we cared
about was that the code for extracting
the font can be read by our extractor
right if that makes sense
so we want to do that but when we
actually do this here I want to be able
like you know these ones that are output
by our bitmap rotini routine for example
are compliant with off-the-shelf tools
so if I read it in right I can edit the
bitmap for any of the BMP SV out right
out but these are not like these pngs
although we could read them nobody else
can read them because we don't comply
with respect to a complete enough state
where they could actually read them so
instead if we try to get one of our PNG
s we get toasted right so what we want
to do first is we want you know before
we go any further down that road is we
want to actually get our PNG writer
working correctly so that it doesn't
have this problem anymore
I would also say that perhaps one thing
we could do here is loft the PNG writer
out up into the PNG reader because why
not you know here's our PNG reader parse
PNG why not
just have this be shared that way if we
want to write a PNG out from our game we
can do that too
so let's stuff that in here like so and
then up here where we've got that parse
PNG code right this endian swap can now
get moved back into here because it's
only used in this code and then the
parse PNG header there can be
accompanied by a write PNG that just has
that code in it right
all right now oh I take it back nope I
don't want to do that so this is a
little bit Squinkie because it needs
some way to write stuff out and so that
does seem less good I suppose what I
could do here is just have a stream that
allows me to write it out that doesn't
seem terrible
yeah I mean looking at this you can see
like we just have a pen chunk and so
that would probably just work right
so we could do that so maybe what we'll
do here is instead of write PNG taking
an output file name here what we do is
say look give me a stream and we'll just
write it to the stream you know I'm
saying so here we would just say all
right here's the stream same thing we
did before then we don't do this code
right we don't want to do that instead
what we do is just output these chunks
so in here everywhere that we were doing
an F right we can just have an out chunk
or like something like that right so
like just a and out data right something
like this and this exact code here you
know all it would do is say like you
know the what's what's the what's the
count and the memory that you want me to
write and then I have a stream here that
I'm actually writing it from you know
I'm saying and so that would just
involve allocating something from the
from the allocator right so from this
memory arena here that would just that
would just require us pushing a block so
there'd be like a push size call here
mr. dacks would be called data so the
desk memory pointer there would be where
we would write it to we would write
count size and then that do you have a
push copy call we do so if we actually
want to do this we could just do a push
copy and that just takes the count and
the data pushes it on here and gives us
back the result so there's a void start
that would come in that would be
returned as whatever the out data was so
yeah if we want to do that that's pretty
simple here's the result we push a copy
of the thing that you push in you know
that you put in here and then we append
that chunk now we may want to do this a
little bit differently I'll show you in
a second but that's this call right here
that just gives the back a stream trunk
we don't
actually care about the chunk oh and in
fact yeah yeah in fact that does
everything for us so this is really just
hey here's the desk there's this the
count and and there's the results right
so this is like really concise it's it's
just that oops I guess you can't do that
though because push copies to things so
yeah there we go
and so if we want to do that that all
works exactly we would expect we can
also do a thing where if we wanted to we
could do this slightly differently right
we could say that there's a void data
equals zero here so that if you don't
pass an actual thing to copy we will
just reserve the size if that makes
sense
I don't know if I actually want to do
that I might want to do this instead
right so maybe you would do something
like this and then you would just do a
push size call and not pass any data
right so that way you can reserve some
some space like something like that and
maybe this is out copy that should give
us what we need and then instead of an F
right we can just call that so now from
now on we would just do that I also feel
like maybe one thing we would want to do
there is pound to fine
oops
it's pound to fine and out struct that
basically says okay if we want to write
a type out or something like that we
could just say look pass us the stream
whatever stream you want to write and
then pass us the the instance of this
thing whatever it actually is and then
we'll just write that out maybe out
struct copy I don't know I'm not quite
sure exactly what that should be called
but then what it would do is it would
call out copy
on the pointer to whatever that thing
was and using the size of whatever that
thing is and the stream that you supply
you know I'm saying that seems like a
possibility another thing would be just
a regular out struct with a type and so
that would just be out size and that
would be stream size of type and that
would give you back a pointer to that
thing like so this would as well
actually so I think that's probably
useful and we'll see so that gives me
all of the tools I need and this that
means we can actually write this a lot
cleaner now than we were in fact I kind
of like that so for the PNG signature we
would probably leave it roughly the way
it is so we'd say like out struct copy
you know what I mean
although actually I think this just
wants out copy so this would be you know
there's our stream this is the size and
there is the pointer right but the rest
of these would be would save a copy kind
of nicely there if we just did it like
this so we say out struct PNG I header
and that writes to the stream that
amount of space so that we can then just
go like this make sense yeah
so there you go uh so we can just do I
think everything that way and make that
a little bit cleaner so these would just
be like okay you know doing well
actually these we write multiple times
it looks like so if we want to do that
again still really easy we just do an
out struck copy yeah so we can't do it
this way I don't know which one we like
better but here's another example so
then we would just say alright we want
to do an out struct so here's the stream
there is destruct right again it makes
that look at not a lot nicer so we're
like put out the header right the eye
header part then put out the footer the
footer in this case yeah again we've
kind of want to actually have some way
of getting the CRC properly which I
think there's actually some interesting
ways we could do that
all right so I'm not sure exactly how I
feel about that
and I almost kind of want a thing that
just outputs the headers and footers for
me a little bit differently but I don't
know we'll see so that's how that would
look right and then as we kind of go
down here again same same difference so
I think I probably want to leave this
roughly the way it is yeah just just
looking at that so I don't know you know
maybe this was a bad idea maybe we want
to leave it essentially unchanged so
maybe the better way to do it just
having looked at it it's like yeah not
great so maybe we want to do it so it is
exactly this way and it's just we just
replaced these without struct copy and
again it still is nicer because it's
just that but I think we do want to
leave it roughly that way that code
looks a little bit easier to deal with
right and so then again in here where
we're doing the F writes it's just f cap
struck copy and then we're just passing
those and oops I need a key this like
delete until the next enclosure that
should be that oops
okay so this is an out struct copy as
well so is this oops
and I think this right here is wanting
to do well so this is an out struct copy
but this is actually just a regular out
data right that's just like a regular
out copy yeah that's this and that's
trying to do something this big at that
location right so I think that should
give us everything we need and now we
just have to do type undeclared
identifier oh yes that doesn't exist so
now we just need to take a look at that
you know this code here and say how do
we actually write a file from that you
know what I mean
because it's gonna produce a stream but
we don't actually have any way to
actually use that stream right like we
don't actually know how to how to
actually produce it write a file from it
but now we can call right PNG anywhere
we want and it produces basically a
stream that just has all of the blocks
ready to go so if we take a look back in
our test PNG you can see in you know in
there we sort of have the the way that
there are test PNG program was doing
memory right so you can see when it
actually creates the platform shim here
that's how those allocators were working
as they were calling through this
you know platform API global so we
should be able to do literally that
exact same thing inside our HH font
utility and again it kind of looks like
someday we want just a common thing that
everybody can share because this code is
exactly the same right so if I take this
code and and just stick it here like
that is exactly what we want which kind
of tells us that that code should
probably be shared right between these
utilities so now if I actually run this
the dump screen to CRT side of things
that is what we would actually call and
so out here where we do you know this is
the place where we actually do our
writing of this stuff in the after load
bitmap we actually call that to write it
out and so right here where we do write
PNG what we want to do is take we want a
stream here to exist and actually do
that that writing write we want to make
that we want to make that work so in
order to do that what we would do is
just say alright I think let me see here
[Music]
I think we just need to include the same
stuff that we're including here so we
want this exact thing I believe yeah and
so now we basically have the ability to
do all the same stuff we were doing
before so we can you know make a memory
arena and and use it and all that
nonsense and we can then you know write
the PNG to a temporary buffer and then
dump it to the CRT so the actual call
here where we do dump stream to CRT if
we go down to where we were doing write
PNG the right PNG calls now to calls
right its first we write the PNG to a
stream so we've got something here
that's gonna create that this is gonna
be like the PNG stream and then we would
just say like oh yeah you know the PNG
stream gets written out to the PNG out
dry out name that actually has to be
opened right we have to do an actual
like you know test to see whether we can
open it here and produce a file so this
is the PNG out file we would say F open
we'd say can we actually get it if we
can't then we would print an error just
so they know that the font extraction
failed or at least partially failed
and that is right
PNG name right binary so that is what
gives us the file that we can write to
and that we will dump to here in right
PNG we just need the stream that stream
I believe there are easy ways to do it
you can see it right here so we can say
on-demand memory stream which is just
something that's gonna like allocate
whatever it needs to get the job done
and we don't need an air stream for that
at the moment anyway because we don't
actually have one we could produce an
air stream here eventually if we wanted
to so really all we need to do is create
the memory arena the memory rina in this
case I think can just be nothing we
don't have any requirements for it so we
can just do this and then when we're
done is it clear I don't remember you
can just free the memory so I think
that's all we actually needed to do this
is an address of here other than that I
think we're good to go right yeah so
that should give us the ability now to
share that code so that anyone who wants
to write a PNG in the game can also do
it which i think is good like I I want
that to be something we can do
eventually I'm going to delete all this
now and see if we can get the writing
working again yeah there we go
right because we got to make sure that
this code works properly
so let's debug that and get that working
now with writing the PNG this way and
then when we're done with that we will
start on the process of make oh that's
weird
I wasn't expecting there to be a bunch
of files there so let's make sure we get
that working and then we'll go ahead and
finish up the like CRC's and making sure
that the stream is nice and works with
all of the stuff that other you know not
our reader but other readers
industry-standard readers expect to have
in the stream so that we're more spec
compliant alright so I guess I want to
run actually HH font and I want to make
sure that we have this stuff in here
because I don't know if we do yeah we
don't so we need two things here we need
W temp font test h HT and then W temp
font right and I must save that so that
we not to do it next time
so if I run it we should crash the PNG
writer what just happened I guess that's
not what will happen let's try the exact
command line that we have that was
broken because apparently it's sensitive
to what specifically we were writing I
guess
why am I not crashing oh okay it's test
P&amp;G that's crashing it's just because
our file is busted okay well that's fine
we still can do the same thing but just
figure out why our writer is not it's
not working properly okay that's fine
yeah all right
so let's go back in here and let's let's
take a look at what happened okay so if
I take a take a look at the stream stuff
here so that's this code we're creating
a temporary arena by the way is is X 13
pixels with us today probably not I
noticed there's a bug in in two to one
that when you like when you run to
cursor it switches your focus to the
disassembly window which makes stepping
happen in the disassembly window by
default even if what you started to run
on was this window from what I can tell
so like Here I am in this window I run
it because this assembly like wasn't
open because the disassembly window like
closes which by the way I don't know why
there's I don't know why there's why the
windows go away in this mode I feel like
they should stay but you know what I
mean so it shouldn't switch to this
because then you console have to click
back here for no reason that's the sort
of minor issue anyway um so we create an
on-demand stream we call right PNG and
so we start by doing all this stuff
and we are gonna copy these things into
the yeah we're just putting these things
into into chunks right so there's the
count is 8 and the data is you know the
PNG header I believe I don't know if we
can actually look at what the pantry
header says here but you know something
like this
probably just a signature we can't read
yeah there it is Angie sure um so we're
gonna write that out and so what's
happening here is we get their result
out of this thing which we you know in
theory copied dumpty to push copy into
the memory for the stream and then we're
gonna do an append Schenck so that's
just going to put that chunk onto the
end right so in theory it should it
should just produce a nice chunks truck
that's got exactly this stuff in it and
that looks right you know I mean so in
theory this should just do exactly what
we expect but once we get here it should
just do a struct copy I don't know how
big these actually are eight does seem
about right and the data we can't
inspect at the moment well I guess I
guess I can so that's the IEEE header
chunk right and these lengths and types
are obviously garbage stuff too because
I mean they're in the wrong Indian
although I had her wait a minute
shouldn't that have been reversed
yeah um I guess it would start on the
low and go high side I I thought that
would have been reversed uh let me just
double-check let me see something here
here we go
I just want to look and see what happens
here okay so it does start out reading
reversed because that packs it in
reversed and then this switches it to
forward order okay so that just that all
seems good
right and this in theory is just pushing
on all of it what happened there well
there's nothing in here
all right so I mean that all seems
pretty reasonable we're gonna do a write
binary to the PNG out name assuming that
it works we come in here we loop through
the chunks we say what they are we dump
them all to the destination and that
seems fine like what's the problem
yeah I don't get it
so that seems fine but obviously I
screwed something up let's take a look
at what test P&amp;G actually fails on if I
step in what happened why can't I step
in tessa P&amp;G interesting that looks like
in another bug look at it creates a new
breakpoint every time I click on that
let me make sure that I didn't mess
something up in my state whether the
bugger here there we go alright so
stepping in to test P&amp;G I'm not sure why
we can't seem to step to the first start
there but let's go ahead and see what
happens when we try to load this thing
here's the parser it's going to consume
one of these PNG headers we're gonna
take a look what's in the header
that doesn't seem right
is that right
so why is that parenthesis no I'm not
sure what that's actually showing me
so something is up it's like there's
something at the front of the yeah so I
want to say that by default our
temporary nough is probably doing
padding of stuff is that gonna be a
no-no well that shouldn't be a problem
for us because we actually use the
blocks the way that they should be used
so what's going on there why are we
getting extra garbage at the front of
our of our PNG there folks what's what's
the deal there anyone know so if I look
here at this I'm writing the PNG
signature
and somehow it's like the wrong size
what am I missing
I must do this in something I mean it
looks like we're just taking the memory
from the stream allocating a chunk
adding it to the list of things to write
that's that's really it and I don't see
anything particularly weird going on
there also if I actually run this song's
test PNG why am I not seeing the
printout do you know I'm saying so
what the heck oh alright well there's
your problem for some reason this this
was a difference okay I'm not gonna talk
about that we're just come to him that
never happened so for some reason that
was I guess only four things that wanted
to annotate we wanted to just dump the
data so we want really that we want like
a different function which is just takes
a data stream and puts it to a file so
that would have worked first time I
think had we actually made the thing
that actually converts a stream properly
that's pretty funny
alright so I think now in theory oops I
gotta run me a full version yeah I think
now we'll we're back in business right
okay so now that we've got that moved in
there what I would like to do I you know
what I'd also like to go ahead and take
test PNG we had a run of this I think
right did we hmm
there it is uh so if I run test PNG oops
that's we're not in the right directory
for that so what's that
W handmade sources intro cutscene art
there we go uh the thing that I wanted
to mention is if we look at this piece
of data here we can actually now see the
Z the headers are eight zero zero zero
zero the way we write them and they're
eight seven 2603 the way they're written
by somebody else and so that should also
be something that we can now look up in
the spec and figure out whether we
should be setting those things the same
so let's start with that here we go so
if we take a look at these these are the
things that we were looking at right and
here's that specification for the stuff
that we should be seeing here's like
some of the flag stuff and the adla 32
checksum as well so on so forth
so if we look in here we see compression
method eight is the deflate compression
that's what we thought
compression method and compression info
right so base two logarithm the LCM
Windus of the LZ centers and window size
minus eight values of C info above seven
are not allowed scene fits not defined
specially for CM not equal to 8 so that
we can start decoding all of this stuff
the preset dictionary the F level which
is a compression level and then the
check bits for the cmf and flag when
fetuses besides sure is multiple
thirty-one okay so this is basically
another checksum there's just a lot of
check sums in here why they didn't just
put a checksum on the actual file I
don't know they must have thought
there'd be like weird like streaming
partial checking cases or something like
this I'm not sure so if F said I
should print it immediately after the
flag bytes so we don't want a preset
dictionary identifier at all so I think
we want F Nick to be set to zero looking
at this you can see that they also set
it to zero so that should be fine
f level there's nothing
I think zero is fine there too because
we didn't do anything
that's just advisory right it's just for
recompression so we should set zero
because if anyone looked at these they
should know oh yeah it's not compressed
well because we're not right we're not
compressing it well so F nicked an F
level can remain zero I argue
okay typing is hard sometimes so I think
we can leave those values as they are
right and so when we look at these
values here eight and all zeros so is
there anything we actually need to set
and I'm assuming that F check is the one
thing we would need to set so the
compression in fo the lz77 window size
minus eight the base two logarithm
thereof so since we never enter an LZ
I'm hoping that that doesn't matter so
I'm hoping we can leave that as zero as
well so I really think the only thing we
really need is f truck and so what that
says is CM FM f LG which is this right I
assume these are bytes
yes so these are two the two bytes and I
believe they're these two right so cm f
and f LG here so I think this stupid
checksum which i think is stupid is a
4-bit value of five bit value zero to
four so I think that means zero one two
three and four or five bytes I think it
says when viewed as a 16-bit unsigned
integer stored in most significant byte
order which is the opposite of what we
would be storing it as right cmf times
256 plus flag has to be what like why
would they what is the point of that in
what world would we need this specific
thing to be checksum here there must
have been an explanation I guess but I
don't know so what we need here is the
additional flags value is zero right and
the CM F value
the cmf value is just 8 right
so I think the f check check value in
this case is just going to be 8 times
256 and then we need it to be a multiple
of 31 so I think we're talking about
this
we have a mod
yes
so I think we're just talking about the
fact that this is a 2 right now and
needs to be a zero meaning it has to be
a multiple 31 so 2048 mod 31 we need to
change the value of cmf which is is it
the bottom bit where is this yeah it's
the bottom bits so we just need to add
we need to make this equal 31 so we need
to add 31 minus 2 right I think I think
I'm not talking crazy here
so we need to add 29 to it am I am i
right
like I guess so I think the F check
value is supposed to be 29 I don't know
man
so I guess they just thought that was a
way
I don't know man that is some nonsense
right there but I guess they've really
wanted the ability to check some just an
interior portion of the thing I don't
understand why there's so many check
sums in this thing like I don't
understand why you don't just have one I
guess they wanted to like you know I
don't I don't know they must have had a
reason
does Ely people weren't stupid so they
probably have a good argument for why in
that day and age that was the thing you
would want to do but I I don't know what
it is so anyway that checks some should
in theory solve the first problem if I'm
interpreting that correctly which I may
not be which is to say that now the that
ID app header should validate which
previously would not have done we now
need to start working on our CRC's right
and we also need to put the Adler 3 to
block in there so the CRC check in this
case I don't even know what it's
supposed to be so we're gonna need some
information about that like what the CRC
block that's in the PNG I believe
because that's just a PNG footer for
everything right
so here is a sample implementation it
says so we you know this is the code
that we are supposed to use
so I mean I guess this is fine
[Music]
I would imagine this probably a much
faster way of doing this nowadays than
what they're suggesting here but I guess
I don't know that we care about that -
particularly much so this is the code
they're saying it's a 256 byte lookup
table which you initialize once and here
is the initialization for it I am
assuming we don't actually have a CRC
table implementation at the moment do we
yeah I think so and then to actually use
it what we do is we look up into the
table we use that value that comes out
of the table and XOR in the input so
this is basically like munge what we've
got currently and then XR in the input
and then when we're done we do one final
XOR versus sort of a mask here I'm not
sure what exactly the point of this is
per se but that's just the finish the
finisher
all right I mean if that's what we got
to do that's what we got to do so here
we go so inside the PNG stuff here
I guess I'll dump this garbage in and
the CRC table itself I feel like we
could just run this generator and then
dump it like I don't know that we
actually need to generate this every
time that seems like a waste of time
because it's only 256 bytes long so it
should just probably be baked into the
executable and leave it at that so what
I might say is let's go ahead and leave
this if zeroed out temporarily like so
and then this makes your a/c table let's
just actually do that in a slightly
different way let's put this part in
here and forget that part there let's
call this stuff and let's dump this to a
file right so let's do this file or
let's just let's just do this so let's
write to standard out all of these
values for the CRC table each one of
them is just unsigned long so we should
be able to do you know something like
this I and just stream the data out that
way and what I could do is if we do it
like 16 at a time you know I could do
something like this
so we go through and well I can do that
so we can go through this whole CRC
table and every 16 or so same way I was
doing the other one so every 16 I'll
I'll put in a carriage turn there
something like that
just to make it a little easier for us
to cut and paste it but other than that
I think that's all we really need right
so let me go ahead and plop this into HH
fonts just right at the bottom like so
and then I'm just gonna run this right
so I'm just gonna run this and make this
thing just just write itself out so
here's a CRC table X that they claim
yeah I know it's unreachable code thank
you
powers are the worst okay so let's go
ahead and run this now oops
it's coffee equals zero okay so maybe 16
is a little bit aggressive maybe we want
more like 8 and there's a nice table if
I go ahead and lock that up into here
then what we can say is like alright
they want CRC table so here's our global
your a/c table and there it is right and
that way we don't really have to worry
about it in you know maybe maybe I'm
even feeling like super Squinkie
so maybe I'm just gonna go ahead and put
it in here and say you know maybe we
want the full the full monty there so it
should just pat out the value so they
line up right so in theory that's the
CRC table hopefully who knows so we'll
put that out there so now we've got the
CRC table and we don't have to include
all this nonsense code in our inner
application right
it's just baked in so then if we go
ahead and do update CRC here now we just
need versions of these things and that
seems a lot easier for us to do because
now we can just figure out what we're
supposed to CRC and go from there now
there's a couple different ways that we
can do this and I'm you know we'll think
about exactly how we want to do it but
I've got
my views so the first thing I would say
is well you know looking at how we're
gonna want to call this it's probably a
good idea also if we want to just make
this work right away look we don't need
this anymore right so the this entirety
of this code is just looking up into
here right so now we can actually call
the reference routines exactly the way
that they were written I just don't
think I'd probably want to do that
because I think we're we're gonna find
out in a second that we want this welded
in in a different way but you know there
it is so that's the that's what they're
claiming they want the CRC to be which
is fine with me I don't really care what
they want their CRC to be I just didn't
really want to have delayed defer
function called nonsense to create a
table if it the table is so short that I
could just make it in the app right so
when we actually come through here to
write the PNG what are we actually gonna
want to do you know I'm saying so like
how are we gonna actually produce this
so if I look at what's going on there's
a couple of different places that this
happens and you know it kind of looks
like least to me the way that we might
want to do this is say okay so there's
gonna be a range of blocks here and we
probably want to just have the CRC
operate on a bunch of blocks right and
so rather than doing this what I
probably want to do is something more
like this
like this maybe what do you think of
that too crappy so basically what I'm
saying is we we mark where we want the
CRC to stop right and then we just say
like okay you know the chunk footer CRC
is and we ask for it in big endian form
directly so that we don't have to like
reverse it every time so we just say
like hey there's a start CRC in an NSERC
every time and that's just like what we
do right and then we can just write one
routine that does it all and we don't
have to keep doing it every time maybe I
don't know I also don't know what the
heck we're supposed to do on the I end
chunk because I guess you just returned
the CRC of nothing
like I don't know so this one's a
mystery to me like I don't know what the
CRC of the end chunks supposed to be is
it supposed to be just a CRC of no input
or is it just supposed to be zero or you
know what I don't know
so I guess so I don't really know and I
guess what maybe what we'll say here is
like okay look if I pass you nothing
you're supposed to do whatever the PNG
spec says to do with no data I don't
know but anyway that seems to me like
the same esteem because then we can just
use the use the fact that we were doing
our stream out stuff into temp buffers
to allow us to compute the CRC across it
cross it really easily without doing too
much work so then you know if we look at
the CRC code here right I can I could
just make that code do something
sensible so if we have what is that CRC
it's it's a you 32 yeah so if I then
take the CRC garbage that we're supposed
to be doing here and I actually use this
code for it
then what I would need to do is so in
here you could see like what would
happen is it would just do nothing like
the Len it would do an update CRC of
zero if we didn't have any data I guess
right so I think what I want to do in n
big CRC is it will take a stream chunk
that's like the start chunk and it'll
take a stream and the stream itself
I well I guess it doesn't really need
the stream itself does it because it
just runs till the end of the other
chunks so actually that's probably fine
so I think actually maybe we don't
really need that so we'll just take a
chunk and run to the end right so it's
just going to do like wile start chunk
do stuff right so I think that's it
and then this code we don't really need
so this is the part that returns at the
end so I think we need to do this the
start of the value has to be this I
guess and then the interior of the
routine has to be this again just
reading the code so I think they
initialize with this value the X are out
with this value at the end as the
finalization of the hash it's not really
a hash at the CRC but you know whatever
so when we then loop what we need to do
is this across the length of the thing
right
so this is what we're trying to do here
what I don't actually know is is there
any I don't think there's any Indian
this this is operating on a bite by bite
basis and the table is just using you
lungs that were created on the same
processor that it was written on so in
theory we should be okay right there
think there shouldn't be any problem
here with with nd in this I don't think
so my assumption here is we should be
able to just say okay going through this
we just take the result value here and
we do this garbage right the rest of it
is just taking whatever the buff pointer
is and this n value right which guess
will do this way seems okay and so all
we need to do here is just loop over the
chunks so stream chunk chunk equals star
chunk chunk isvalid chunk equals chunk
next that gives me a loop over all the
chunks reached chunk we just say here's
the contents of this thing and here's
the side it's
right and I think that just does what we
want and honestly this doesn't really
need to be this way let's do it like
that right so I think that pretty
closely mimics what they asked us to do
is this account yeah so I think that
works and then all we really need is
when we're out putting these things we
would need to know where the stream was
so what I think I might actually do is
mark these I don't know how I want to
mark these I guess is what I'm saying
if we look at out struct copy there's
there's some issues here with how we
might do this but if you look at like
out struct copy or out copy I guess I
should say it actually returns the data
and so what we really kind of need is a
different way to mark this I guess what
I'm saying is like maybe it needs to be
that you know I'm saying you know it's
like that I don't know that that's great
but seems like the only way to really
make sense of this I would say
that's all I got so I don't know if
that's actually computing it correctly
as per the spec we're gonna have to go
read it a little bit more carefully but
at least in theory now that should be
writing out things that have check sums
in them or the CRC check sums in them
but we don't actually have the adler 32
checksum yet all right so if we open one
of these with now that Adler 32
checksum is still busted so we probably
are still gonna get an error right so
we're probably we're getting closer
maybe you can see that we're actually
we're actually getting like the windows
reader now does work right well we can't
quite see it in there I guess but you
can see it in here can I donno if you
can see it's actually showing the glyph
so we're getting closer to being able to
use other stuff here because they're so
like that PNG read it so we're getting a
little closer but we're still not quite
there and we know we need that adler 32
thing which I have no idea what that is
so we've got to go look up what that
actually is find somebody who talks
about whoops what that means
all right so Adler 32 is what this is a
trypsin failure to uncompressed data and
excluding a dictionary data computed
according to Adler through your
algorithm is out of the 32 extension and
improvement of the fletcher algorithm is
composed of two check sums accumulated
for bite s1 is the sum of all bites and
s2 the sum of all s1 values both sums
are done modular 6 5 5 2 1 s1 is
initialized to 1 s 2 2 0 the other
tricks was stored as s 2 x 6 5 5 3 6
plus s1 in most significant byte first
network order okay
and that is of what
of the uncompressed data okay so we
first want when we write this out this
data has to be addler 32 compressed or
marked the uncompressed data is the this
data here only so it would be this
right hoof
so in here the Adler three to check some
of the data is going to be basically
saying hey take everything from starting
right after the end line chunk all of
that data because the uncompressed
version of the data is that right
I assume but I don't know so meaning it
should include the nofilter bytes I
assume because that's what we fed into
the thing right so because that's like
external to the Zeeland part of this
that's happening in the PNG side so I'm
assuming we want all of that to happen
and so now we've got to do this Adler 32
nonsense which is sort of vaguely
specified right there so if we were to
do that we now have the trunks coming in
and by the way if we wanted to do this
in a in a Squinkie er way like a way
where we're trying to allow a few more
things to happen you know maybe possibly
sort of a little bit kind of we could
also do this right because that'll allow
you to pass it an end chunk or one pass
last chunk
you know I'm saying and so you just
normally it's set to zero and then
that'll terminate at that point but if
you wanted to stop on some chunk that
was before the last chunk just because
you felt like it you could so that's
nice so let's read the spec so it says
here it's a it's two sums s1 is the sum
of all bytes and s2 is the sum of all s1
values modulo six five five 21 right so
we've got s1 and s2 initialized thus
modulo six five five two one
so we always take s1 plus equals the
byte whatever that is right we then do I
guess really we do this right then s2 is
this and then it's stored as s 2 times 6
5 5 3 6 which is just to say the high
order but that's just shifted it up
right in most significant byte first
order so it's Indian swapped version of
this so at that point what I'm not sure
about is how we want to deal with these
I assume that these are Indian swapped
so I assume that this happens here is
that true I don't know
I don't know if the CRC's endian swapped
or not so I don't know what happens
there I have no idea
[Music]
I'll put to doing this is definitely
Indian swap they said that right in the
finis back so we'll got it we'll go
check us back and see it says at plus s1
I assume yeah so in theory this is the
thing that they asked for and excuse me
in theory that's this back right
whoops that Indian swap is in place sooo
that's that's that and now I guess we
are attempting to comply with the spec
fully oh but we broke something maybe
when we included that Adler 32 checksum
we broke something
so I'm not sure what we broke because we
shouldn't have had anything strange
there right but I guess we did so we
broke something there I'm just not sure
what that's the only thing we changed
right in the output stream
I think scoops so no we broke something
else here it looks like
or did we let's delete this whole thing
and just take a look so it looks like
we're still doing it right here with
liberation mono let's delete all that
and put the Adler thirty-two back in
that crashes our existing code
so it doesn't look like that actually
affected anyone elses reader though
just ours and off we go
so I guess I'm just not sure what did we
how did we break our P&amp;V reader that's
what I'm wondering so when this when
this does the decoding it should stop on
be final equals zero that that so that
shouldn't have really changed anything
right
oh I know no no I do know what the
problem is so in here right
that chunk header length needs to
include the size of the Adler checksum
that we added that's what has to happen
there right in order to make that work
right there we go
all right so I don't know how close we
are to being compliant unfortunately now
I don't know how to get something that
would we need a PNG reader like this
here tells us that it failed but it
doesn't say what actually was the
problem so it would be nice if we had
something that would now try to read it
and print out errors for us that said
like this here's your bug right cuz I
have no idea what those bugs would be
right I have no idea
PNG writer test suite
[Music]
PNG validator I'm bright like this seems
good in the house source code even Oh
SourceForge SourceForge is a bit
dangerous
[Music]
the fact that it has an amiga directory
makes me like it already so we can say
that about it I'm gonna go in here and
say that will make a directory for it
and then what we can do is just yeah I
mean I don't know hope that we can build
something like this to validate to
validate it for us right
is there also oops I don't really want
to print anything
just looking at this
here's the make file
so maybe I'll start with this
[Music]
and we'll see what we can do because I
would like something that can tell me
how the you know what's broken so I know
what to start looking at alright so if
we go in here and look at PNG check I
want to be able to build it so I guess
we'll just start by seeing if it builds
it all that seems easy
so PNG check actually has looks pretty
much good to go so if I try running it
on one of our exports perfect so it says
that there's a CRC error and and it's so
so we know our CRC code is wrong in the
IEEE header chunk right so there's a
couple different things we might want to
do for but first of likes okay so that's
perfect this is exactly what I hoped so
now I should be able to work through the
code and get everything lining up
properly so the first thing I need to
know is when we're doing our CRC's we
don't currently know whether we're doing
them over the right information right so
the first thing we should do is try to
figure that out if I go into the PNG
spec I should be able to get some
information about that so when we
actually look in the the CRC it says the
CRC feels our calculator using standard
seriously methods with pre and post
conditioning as a find by this I so the
CRC polynomial is that it is initialized
to all ones which we did the data from
each choice process from the least
significant bit the most significant bit
that is baked to the table
after all the data bytes of prostitution
is inverted it's one compliment is taken
this value is transmitted most
significant byte first so that means
this to do is fine right it is swapped
practical guy zero if that's a pre
calculated table and here's the table
and that's the table we use so hopefully
we didn't do anything stupid here but I
think that should have worked right
yeah so I think we're following that as
well as we probably could so now I just
want to know okay so for the chunk
footer what's actually supposed to be in
there where's the where's some
discussion of this let's just look at
the first time
a four byte crc cafe on the preceeding
bytes in the chunk including the chunk
type field and chunk data fields but not
the length right the crc can be used to
check for corruption of the data the CRC
is always present okay so I think that
is implying that if we go back and look
at what we were writing there what it's
seeing is the ID at like so for example
when we write to add it out it's
actually the chunk header that we want
there and we just want to skip the
length field but we want this other
field right so the chunk header is
actually the header that we wanted to be
looking at in the first place
and so in most of these cases we
actually want to do this
and in all these cases we could bake
that into the n big CRC or we can
actually have an offset so in here we
want to skip the length field so I'm
gonna say like there's like a skip count
or something that you do on the first
one right and that'll let us compute
that more conveniently there so the
chunk footer CRC in all these cases
there's one more here it's going to be
there and this will look like that so I
think that's more what we're looking at
here if I'm not mistaken so yeah once we
do that that means our end our end big
CRC has like a you know like a skip end
value right and it would basically look
like this so the first time through
we're gonna skip however many we should
skip there and then we'll stop right I
think that works I I could put like it
to do here that's like actually here we
go
because we don't support this right uh
so I think that would work
you know I claim that it would but I
don't actually know so let's try it so
if I now run this thing again like so
what the hey how did we what did I do
that should not have changed anything
should it that should have literally not
changed anything because we didn't touch
the we didn't touch anything at all in
terms of what's getting output here
right like that that doesn't really make
any sense because all we did was change
the range where the crc was actually
operating but we didn't actually write
anything different I didn't think and
that's even weirder cuz now it's saying
that it's a compliant PNG according to
PNG check
and it's compliant according to as
well so I'm not sure exactly what the
problem is with test VR and PNG doesn't
seem to be crashing here
liberation mono 89 let's just make sure
it's it is crashing right yeah it's
definitely crashing so this command line
crashes test B and G so I should be able
to run it oops under remedy shouldn't I
oops I guess remedy doesn't remember the
command line there oh it's just can't
find the file that's all whoops there we
go
so I think we're roughly good now that
looks like it's doing fonts properly so
I think we're now in the clear and we
can go to the QA but that's what I want
to do today and so I just went a little
accidentally go long because we started
late technically I have 20 minutes of
programming left I think but we'll go
ahead and go to the Q&amp;A anyway there it
is I was hoping that would work I
actually typed it into John's chat
because the naysayer window was open so
I accidentally spammed his history with
: QA
with with estimation part QA alright
what I actually meant to say on my
channel was Q&amp;A so now we should be good
to go here and yeah and I think our P&amp;G
reader is also in good shape I mean
reader and writer are in good shape now
so now we should have full font
compliance and so next weekend we can
basically just do a here is the final
art pass thing that rebuild our entire
games asset packs from source ters and
post those to the send owl and then the
neighborhood everyone can be up to date
somebody took my name said I thought
there should be an error because the
type was an D and swapped before CRC was
calculated but apparently that is how it
works yeah I mean I think I guess the
way that it's supposed to happen is it's
a CRC of the flat data right so it's
supposed to go in MSB order I guess
hi Casey I think it would enjoy a
revision demo Perry is that demo party
revision demo party there are plenty of
people yelling Amiga frequently and some
of the Amiga demos interests are very
very good yes I bet I would enjoy that
what do you think are other fields to
look into to get hired as the systems
for our other than the game industry so
here's one thing I will say and this is
just something that I was told recently
it may be completely wrong although I
don't have much reason to believe that
it's wrong because it wasn't coming from
an unreliable source it was coming from
a reliable source so supposedly
according to my friends Google that all
have figured out that game programmers
are better than their programmers and
now are hiring them at very high salary
levels which apparently is creating
problems for game companies because they
can't really compete with web money
right so from what I've heard if you
actually are a good game programmer now
if you just go apply for a job somewhere
at one of these ridiculously wealthy web
firms they pay you really really
ridiculous salaries the numbers I heard
were shockingly high put to you that way
like like several orders of magnitude
higher than if you look up what the
highest salaries are on Glassdoor for
google those were the numbers that I
heard I don't know if it's true but
that's what I was told and it's
problematic for game companies in the
area apparently retaining top people who
just want some money
[Music]
what do you think are other fields to
look into to get hired assistant program
is chemistry what does the align point
for font stand for the officer I reckon
yeah yeah so the align point for fonts
was just instead of a instead of
recording like where relative to the
base line the font is as a separate
thing we already had the align point so
we just used that so the align point
adjusts from baseline to use any
standard software development process
while creating this game I don't really
think standard software development
processes are good so no depending on
what you mean by that maybe there are
some we use like we do check we'd like
save the version of our source code
every day and stuff like that so we use
some things that might be considered
standard software development practices
I missed it during the stream could you
show it an hhe font file looks like yeah
it's really straightforward so far we
may change this when we go right the
reader for font hht data we made want
something else so we can change that you
know this really trivial for us to
change so this may not be what we
actually want but it's just what I
initially did oops temp fun but so if we
do we have less on here more so if we
look back one of these files what you
can see is it's just a listing of the
bitmaps and their align points for the
font plus the horizontal advance table
which is the N squared table of advanced
levels that may not be what we actually
want when we go to read it and we might
want something else
so we may want and we probably want a
glyph count in there for example at the
very least but you know we just want to
make sure we could print something so I
wouldn't I would take this with a grain
of salt we we probably want to when we
go right the reader next next weekend to
put the foss together we'll probably
have a stronger opinion of what we want
and we'll go back and change the HH font
to output exactly what the reader wants
but this was just to make sure we could
output what we know we know we'll need
all this data the question is just how
do you want it formatted right
Lucid frost our sampling profiler is
always strictly worse than adding
counting points directly to the binary I
have trouble wrapping my head around the
accuracy quality of sampling I mean I
guess what I would say is they're
probably always the you know the likely
true statement is they're always worse
than a expert optimizer adding it like
doing instrumentation to their code but
they might not always be worse than
someone who doesn't necessarily really
know what they're doing adding stuff to
their code right
you know me an inexperienced optimizer
it may go in and add instrumentation to
their binary that that fundamentally
changes the behavior of the binary in
some kind of bad way that causes the
profiling to not be useful that can
definitely happen whereas a sampling
based profiler is always the same
badness no matter what you're doing so
it's yeah I mean I guess I don't really
know how to quantify those two things
but I wouldn't necessarily say that it's
always strictly worse because saying
it's strictly worse assumes a certain
level of competence and quality done to
with how you're doing the
instrumentation and so like there's
plenty of things on handmade hero where
if we insert too many count blocks we
could easily slow things down in the bad
way and a sampling based ploof profile
might be better right than doing that so
so I think it's worth understanding that
there's it's not like instrumentation is
free and so you can easily have an
instrumentation case that's bad and so I
wouldn't I would encourage you not to
really think of them as one is always
good and one is always bad I would I
would think of them as sometimes one is
a good idea and sometimes another is a
good idea and so probably the right way
to think of it is
running a sampling profiler is a good
idea to try and tell you roughly where
your hot spots might be and then maybe
instrumentation is a good way of then
going and trying to attack those hot
spots directly and getting really
accurate data about just those hot spots
does that maybe help think about those
things a little bit
how does a sampling profiler work do
they need to pause every thread or can
they take a snapshot somehow and then
figure out where the program was so I'll
be honest I'm not sure what the current
state of sampling ProFlowers actually is
[Music]
you know I guess I don't really know you
know the old-school way is you would
halt the executable you look at what the
IP was of every thread and you record
that location right but they may have
faster ways of doing that now because
like let me I'll just I'll just give you
I'll just give you an example so if all
you're trying to do is sample the
instruction pointer it's entirely
possible for the x64 chip and I've never
looked to give you a fast way to just
grab the IP out of all the cores just
without stopping anything right I mean
that's an easy thing to imagine a chip
giving you for a low-level way of doing
a sampling profiler so imagine a way of
strobing the chip and just say give me
all your performance counters are IP
plus the performance counters that are
currently active just give them to me
right now but don't stop anything just
export it from the core right like treat
it like a standard right so all you're
doing is using up a right you know using
a cache line push right my assumption
would be that that's actually what's
going on now that's my assumption so I I
don't think they have to do the old way
of doing things where it's like you know
actually halt everybody
I would assume you don't have to aim her
but I don't know I mean I guess we could
take a wild leap wait it wait
this is not
I want the I want the full thing
[Music]
so let's see what we've got here
so I'm not sure I'll be able to find
this fast enough a definitive answer so
I've never looked for it before
I mean here's all the event counters and
these are just automatic you can just
enable these and you get events
but that doesn't really answer the
question
so I'm not sure I'm gonna have to ask
about that or I read this more carefully
I don't know if there's any way to read
out IPS at a fixed interval or just read
out ip's period without halting I don't
know
I don't know
yeah I would I'm gonna have to ask about
that
so what does this thing do
Prosser event-based sampling
this sure sounds like it right
so the PEVs facility has been enhanced
where it so tell me about this peds
what's PABs
yeah I mean this sure sounds like this
does what you want right
it sounds like you can just basically
say look here's the counter that I want
you to use and when that counter hits a
specific value dump or record that
includes the location of the IP does
that I mean that looks pretty
that looks like this does that
yeah
so I don't know because I've literally
never looked at this section before but
that sure that sure does seem like the
processor has at least some support for
not having to do an entire break of the
entire executable to cat to get that
information it looks to me like you can
have records written out at the
processor level based on performance
counter triggers that you are looking
for so my assumption would be that a
modern perform a modern sampling based
profiler like V tune is doing that and
not actually stopping anything in any
broader sense than this interrupt that
would be my guess
how many are there game developers who
actually care about fronts observation
isn't most game to have just simple
things for example maybe yeah okay so
just to be clear I'm talking about like
game programmers who actually know how
to program games like like the whole
game right so like engine programmers
not people who just write scripts in
unity or something those those people
are obviously not valuable because
anyone can do that the whole point of
unity is that anyone can do it so yeah
those people are not valuable except in
the extent that they make good games but
people who I've talked about people who
do like serious engine work right and
this was just what I was told from
people who had been trying to do game
company staffing they said that they
were having trouble because there's it's
not really feasible to pay people the
same salaries that Google was paying
them which were like you know even
though the game engine programmer
salaries are quite good right um they
are apparently much more worth it to go
optimize their data center or something
and they'll pay you four times what
you're making it a game company or
something which is kind of absurd if
that's true but that's apparently the
case and it makes sense right I mean
people who can make game engines can
make anything it's one of the hardest
things there is
and diffserv it was much higher than
$300,000 a year
so anyway I'm gonna go ahead and wrap it
up
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for an episode of hand made here it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
the series at home you can always go to
handmade here at work and pre-order the
game it comes with a source code so you
can follow along at home I think we
basically did what we wanted to do so we
can now take basic font files from any
font that we want and dump it out into
as if it were made as a series of PNG s
ready to be imported into the game using
the standard pipeline which gets us out
of the business of dealing with fonts
pretty much at all and let's just treat
them as just standard art assets and so
we can kind of ship a source assets to
people who are trying to build the game
at home and just have one directory full
of PNG s and then you just use that but
the source code and you're done well and
we have files so that seems good and
that's where I wanted to be at and now
we are so next weekend we can focus on
getting like a finalized asset pipeline
and be like here we go
basically we're done and then from then
on out we really just have to think
about things like how we want tag files
and obstacles and stuff to come in
because we still have like inside the
complete art pipeline we still have lots
of flexibility with how we want mark
things up and so we should probably then
start trying adding a bunch of stuff
like ground cover furniture different
outfits hats whatever like we should
just go through and try to implement a
bunch of random stuff like that and use
that as a way to fine-tune how art gets
imported and marked up and that will I
think then get us to a part where we can
sort of definitively say this is a good
art our pipeline now for handmade hero
we can be happy with it
and check that pretty major feature off
of our list that's about it I'll be back
here next week I believe I have to check
my schedule but I'm assuming I haven't
posted the schedule next week but I
should I should be here back next week
to start on that until then have fun
programming everyone and I'll see you on
the Internet
take it easy everybody