hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream it is another lighting
weekend here last week weekend we sort
of got everything working that the basic
like infrastructure for doing some kind
of lighting paths we still don't know
exactly how we will end up doing it we
have kind of a couple things that we're
working on right now for possible ways
that the lighting will play out but
regardless of what that way is obviously
we needed sort of this infrastructure
where we could take renderings from the
game feed them through a lighting system
and have ways of iterating on what was
in that lighting system to produce
lighting right now all we're doing is
very very simple blurring of the
lighting we're not actually bouncing it
around like we would like to so we
haven't actually gotten to implementing
the lighting transport part of things so
that's one thing you have to do the
other thing we have to do is we don't
yet pick up the results of the lighting
and feed them into the game the game
proper so what I'd like to do today is
just finish that part up so that we have
a complete lighting pipeline operating
where we can take the lighting come you
know it can come into the game sorry
come into the lighting system bounce
around produce a lighting solution that
we want to use and come back out into
the render that's there in order to to
produce whatever the final lighting is
right so that's what we want to do here
and so I'd like to kind of play around
with that a little bit today just kind
of get a fake version of that working
meaning the lighting transport will
still be fake but the rest of the
pipeline will be effectively real now
there's a little bit of an issue with
this which is to say that right now in
the lighting system were only computing
lighting on like one layer if you will
right
like there's four def peels that we
produce in the game and we only produce
the light currently on one I'm a top
level of the lighting of the of appeal
and the thing that we probably want to
move to in the future is we probably
want to have a way of using the lighting
information from all of the deaf fields
in order to produce lighting that can
bounce around behind objects this is one
of the big drawbacks of screen space
solutions to a lot of lighting problems
that you see is that you can only
compute screen space flooding solutions
for geometry that's at the front but if
like we have you are computing depth
peels for some other reason and we are
computing deaf fields because we need to
do blending in an order independent way
we want to do blend composition well
since we have all of that information it
means that we can do light transport
between four layers of geometry in the
scene not just the front layer so
eventually we also want to move towards
that as well as moving towards real
light transport we want to sort of move
towards something that takes those
flexing to account potentially so we
have that opportunity and we just don't
know whether or not we're going to be
able to take advantage of it in any
particular way but an example of how to
take advantage of that and we talked
about this when we first started
planning the system would just need to
say look why don't we just process the
lighting on four layers at once where we
just know that we've got essentially an
iteration over four textures for each
depth and we just do the lighting
calculation four times every time right
so anything that we were going to do
where we would accept light from one
texel in the past we accept it now from
four texels where each Texel is a
different one of the depth fields and
there's a different light source so
that's an example of how we would go
about using this in
Meishan more concretely and effectively
what we're doing there is we're
effectively saying let's use of you know
we're effectively doing sort of voxel
cone tracing or one of those other voxel
ization based lighting schemes because
effectively what a depth peel is is it's
a sparse voxel ization in Z right it's a
dense fossilization in x and y in the
sense that we cover the whole screen
projected outward but it's a sparse
vocalization in Z because you only are
taking samples where you kit the
geometry so it's very efficient in that
sense compared to a non identical or a
voxel that has to be regular subdivided
so even something like an octree in Z we
are much would be much better than that
because in Z we are literally only
concerned with the actual places where
the geometry exists and that's much
better than a box elevation in terms of
efficiency of elements right so that's
the sort of stuff that we have to think
of going forwards and so I I don't think
there's much left to say about it we
just have to sort of do the elbow grease
of getting all this stuff ironed out
which I'll go do now one further thing I
wanted to mention is that I don't know
whether multi grid lighting is going to
work out or whether we're going to have
to sample the lighting in a less up/down
sort of fashion and if it turns out that
we do have to sample the lighting
differently than that then one thing
that we're going to have to do is we're
going to have to be able to sample from
multiple resolutions of our textures at
the same time and in order to do that
one of the things that we would have to
do in order to make it efficient in the
shader is to switch to using actual MIT
Maps instead of separate textures so one
thing we might also want to look at
today if we have time is seeing if we
can get our current system to just work
with instead of one texture per myth
level for every one of the lighting
textures we want to store having just
one texture and having it actually have
myth maps I would like to move to that
regardless like either way it would be
nice to move to something like that
eventually I just don't know how
effective that's going to be on
something where we've got a rectangular
bitmap like the screen I don't know to
what extent cards will be happy with
about trying to move map that and so
that's really the the only real question
assuming that that works okay that's
probably preferable because what that
allows us to do is once you have things
in a myth map of a texture the bonus
there because it might sound like well
why does it matter the bonus there is
that inside a shader you can sample from
any texture log level that you want so
any mipmap in a given texture you can
sample directly from one of those using
a particular texture sample call that
specifies the myth map level so rather
than having the card compute the
mid-back level based on the unv
gradients or whatever else it wants to
do or things like this we can sample
from specific versions of the LOD you
know specific version of the texture
specific levels and the reason is that's
so important is that would allow us to
do things like if we want to sample
lighting and we know we want to sample
far away lighting at a high you know
miss being a very very coarse mid level
and we want to sample nearby lighting at
a very dense very low level myth right
one that's course I'm sorry one that's
fine detail we can do that in the shader
very adaptively
whereas if we have to specify different
texture handles for all those things
then we're ending up binding lots and
lots and lots of textures and we will
soon probably floods the thirty-two
texture limit that some cards impose
trying to do that so it's really just a
question of putting something there's no
difference between the two in terms of
functionality it's just a question of
going with what the card is more set up
to do
so that we don't run into limitations or
introduce artificial slowdown that's not
really necessary because the card is set
up to sample for MIPS it's not set up to
sample from hundreds of textures that's
just how some cards work that's just one
of the ways in which they're optimized
and you have to sort of play into that
optimization when you can all right so
I'm going to open up the state of the
code right now today is day 397 so day
396 is source code is what you want to
start with let's see oppress not want to
open at all there we go so let's go
ahead and run the app as it is at the
moment and if you remember at the end of
last weekend what we were doing is we
made it so that we could render lights
to the lighting system as part of the as
part of the main game render and so what
we did is you can see here we've got the
hero sort of hopping around in the main
game render and you can see how the
lighting itself we sort of took it from
that render path you can see how the
lighting itself now incorporates sort of
the hero sprite which is what we sort of
did to hack that in since right now our
game doesn't but the game code doesn't
know about lights and didn't ever try to
put in lights in the world so we just
made one up that's where the hero is and
you can see that basically what it does
is it assumes that everything within a
certain sphere around the hero is a
light source so that's what it's doing
right now and what you can see if we go
through the process you can see that
we've got sort of a set of blurred
versions of that right on the way up and
down and we also have several of these
right so that's the that hero one is the
only one we are capturing right now from
the game itself and the other parts
which are you know things like the the
normal surface normal stuff like that
we're not capturing it and so that's you
know we want to kind of
finish up that process of capturing
everything into the lighting system
correctly and then we want to go and get
it out of the lighting system but that's
really all we're talking about right now
like that's all we really are trying to
do so let's go ahead we're going to need
one shader for this and that shader is
just going to be the shader that takes
all of the lighting information from a
set of def peel data bit bases one peel
and moves it over to the lighting system
and like I said right now we're just
concerning ourselves at the top peel but
in the future I think we're going to
want to try and make that system a
little bit better so one step at a time
since we don't want to over complicate
our lighting pipeline just yet with the
multiple death seals as a reason that we
don't want to do that is because we
don't want to do a bunch of work on
something that we don't know whether
it's the right solution yet so once we
get our light transport working in a way
that we think is reasonable for this
game then that's the time to bring the
the peels into it because now we know
what we're doing we can minimize the
amount of work we need to do to extend
it to death peels rather than trying to
deal with depth peels the whole way
through when we don't even really know
how we're going to be bouncing our light
around in the first place we've got a I
think there was a problem someone was
saying well actually I guess I should
open up the github I think somebody was
saying that we accidentally had a typo
in one of our things here minor copy and
paste there it's a 18:44 they said oops
wrong file yes this is just supposed to
be down there we go it just so happens
that won't do anything particularly
different but it is useful to have that
there now one thing we could also decide
to do right we can see if you wanted to
prevent typos like that we could
introduce a little struct with a
constructor and a destructor here
that automatically does the shutdown on
the same thing that you did the startup
on right I don't know how important that
is to do here but it's just when you
have a bug like that it's worth taking a
second and asking yourself should I
introduce a system here that eliminates
that kind of bug how worried it worried
am I about having that right and so yet
you can imagine that that's one thing
that you might want to take a look at
right so anyway moving on from there
because I don't think I'm going to do
that here all right so what we want to
do now is we want to take a look at this
compute light transport situation you
can see here that we've got OpenGL begin
screen fill stuff happening here right
we do this what we did to hack in this
process is we right before we were going
to go and execute the first lighting
blend path we grab the texture from the
depth peel resolve buffer instead so
what this does is this makes it so that
we're just cheap you know cheetah Li
grabbing the color handle the emit color
buffer from the DEF peel resolve buffer
which is not what we actually want to do
so we want to stop doing this and what
you can see is if I stop doing that we
get back to just the the fake lighting
that we had in there and so what we want
to do is replace that fake lighting with
real lighting right and so
[Applause]
what we want to do here is start this
with a way to import the results from
our death feel into our initial lighting
phase what that means is we're going to
want to do one of these same exact
things right where we're running to the
destination right all frame buffer
however we want to do in this case is we
want to write to the very first buffer
so the thing that here you can see our
source light buffer index rate and our
desk light supper index what we're doing
is we're starting writing to buffer one
and we're reading out of buffer zero and
the only person who ever seeded buffer
zero is the fake feed lighting well in
order to move past the fake seed
lighting what we want to do is seed
buffer zero now right
we want to see buffer zero with the
lighting data that actually came out of
the renderer so here in the open trail
vegan screen fill in screen fill thing
what I want to do is write to that first
buffer in order to write to that first
buffer I then need to bind textures to
draw from that are not going to come
from a lighting buffer instead that
they're going to come from is they're
going to come from the DEF peel buffers
and so what you can see here is we've
got these depth field buffers they use
this OpenGL frame buffer here and they
have this series of color buffers the
color buffers themselves are announced
by these three enums here and so what I
want to do is I want to read from those
now what you can see is this there's a
myth
there's NPL their surface reflect right
and what we want to do is we want to
read from those three and then we're
going to write out to the buffers we're
going to translate those three into you
know into the result all right
so looking at this what that means is
I'm going to need some kind of a way to
access the source and in this case if
the we know what it is right it's always
going to be the depth TL resolved buffer
and we're just going to use buffer zero
so in the future we may do better than
that but at the moment we are not we're
just going to leave it like this so what
I want to do here is say okay I've got
an open GL frame buffer that's the
source it's the depth field resolve
buffer and I'm going to bind the
textures out of that now there aren't
four textures because remember this is a
different format than the lighting it's
just with a renderer boot forth and so
what I want to grab there is I want to
grab oh well not actually true I take
that back we do actually have one
because we also want to read from the
Deaf handle so there are actually four
they're just not the same for that they
were before so let's go ahead and put
the deaf handle first and then let's do
the color handles next so it would look
something like this
and so what we would find is the depth
handle and then the surface reflects the
admit the NPL now I'm going to go ahead
and use the enum in case we reorder them
I want this shader to just know that it
can get those in this order so there's
those enums and so this should be able
to compile now with no errors because
again I'm not calling any shader code
yet now I got to renumber these here to
make sure they go in the right order
let's make sure that happens there we go
zero one two three and here we have our
binding so now what we need to do is
basically this program process which we
don't have let's go ahead and put that
in there so we're going to want to do it
a use program again and we're going to
need a program for this so this is going
to be like a depth field to delighting
something like that
[Applause]
and then I want to do a use program end
so inside here I need to do an actual
draw at some point so there we are
and all this is again is just a
full-screen fill with a particular
program method all right so now all we
need to do we're pretty much set up for
doing the importing all we need to do
now is actually get this data into a
program right so we need to create some
kind of new programs here it's kind of
like the depth peel resolve I guess so
I'll start with that as the code we'll
use the stuff peel composite here let's
go ahead and do that
and let's see here let's go down here so
what I'm going to do is we'll call this
oops at the wrong place one put it below
the multiplet above the multi light up
is probably the best place for it there
we go so we'll call this function
compile appeal to lighting and I guess I
don't know that we have the srgb stuff
in here much at all so this is probably
not important what we do want to do at
some point is fix our version numbers to
probably be 330 at some point because if
we're going to basically be requiring
opengl 3.3 there's no sense in not
having all of our shaders b33 compliant
there's no bonus to be had by making
them old if we're saying that basically
we have to have open gel 3.3 to run
right if we're saying we're going to be
having that that complicated of a
lighting that complicated of a renderer
so I don't think we need any of this
just yet
[Applause]
but it does occur to me that the number
of times we've sort of been doing this
format string bit here I wonder if that
should be systemized in someplace where
we actually just build one of those to
begin with there's a little bit of
fussiness there because you know we've
got sort of the things that want to be
set in a particular piece of code in
common but what we could do is sort of
have a percent s at the beginning that's
just the default preamble or we could
even make it so that there's a thing
that gets passed in before that so that
defines to get here or just kind of
shared and that makes a lot of sense to
me so we probably should look at doing
that a little bit in the future and I'm
not going to bother right now if right
in the middle of something but that's
something that seems like we're doing so
anyway inside the vertex code here we
don't have a vertex color and we we
could use a UV but I don't think we
really want to I think we want to do a
direct right in this case it's hard to
say whether we should use a UV or not
it's just whether or not this sort of
stuff is going to be able to be down
sampled in any real way without a custom
shader I don't know so it kind of feels
to me like it probably wants to be
copied directly so I suspect that it's
kind of not going to want to do the UV
stuff pretty much at all so I think it's
just going to be something that straight
across that's the position and doesn't
do anything else for the vertex shader
and then in the fragment code we're
going to have a number of samplers so in
this case we're going to have a depth
sampler we're going to have a surface
RGB right let's uh let's name these the
right things so surface reflect sampler
we're going to have an emit sampler and
we're going to have an NPL sampler but
we don't take in any of this stuff and
then we do have out but the outs for the
blend unit color are actually going to
be complex now because we are writing to
a front back surface MP
so we do want that to be uniform and
correct so here is that writing we'll go
ahead and put that at the bottom like so
and we'll delete all of what happens
here because none of it is correct now
in this case we don't really want to
sample from a UV anymore and let me go
ahead and get these out actually that's
not quite true so it's going to be more
like this it's going to be more like we
have a depth from an R we have a surface
reflect we have a emit and we have the
NPL now from there obviously we get a
emit RGB which is from here we have an
emit spread which is from here this is
the encoding we agreed on this is our NX
and actually I should cause I could just
do this here's our n right i well know
you know what we need to do math on this
sort of in a in a more unpacking
kannaway so let's do it this way we have
our LP zero and our NP one right so
those are our lighting parameters which
we're not going to use yet so real we
can sort of leave those to the side for
the moment we have the emit in the NPL
both getting sampled the service
reflecting the depth and then we you
know previously I should also have
surface
select RGB and that'll just be server
select at RGB and I don't think we need
the coverage at the moment because we
don't do anything with it but there is
the coverage if we want it to just be
complete in declaring our variables so
this is really what we're looking at
here in terms of what we're sampling and
then what we have to do is we have to
compile at some point these values and
some of them are going to be pretty easy
and some of them are going to be more
difficult to produce so we'll have to
work on that right all right
so taking a look at what we've got here
what we want to do is say these texture
samples we want to just sample the
textures directly so we don't want to
use the UV so what we're going to be
doing here is more akin to the texture
sample from the device program where we
do where is it
this one right here where we do a
textile fetch so all of these ones in
the in the in the lighting transfer here
for example what we want to do is make
sure that these are actually sampling
directly from a texture so they're going
to look more like this right and so what
we want to do is we want to have an eye
Veck - which is the place to sample from
for the textile fetch so we'll just do a
fetch XY or something like that we'll
build this once and then we'll use
textile fetch everywhere else so for
example here
we've got depth equals Texas Texas
sampler and we're going to be sampling
from it level zero and then we just need
to patch that XY in here in order to let
it know where we're fetching from and so
the same thing is going to be true in
all of these so in order to get the
service reflect we're doing the service
reflect sampler we're going to do it
from the fetch XY and then we're going
to do zero and maybe the correct things
get calls there was the text Lex Y again
just propagate this change down do it
for everybody and finally we get the NPL
as well so now we've got all the data
that came out of the original render we
need some way of computing the various
quantities we actually need now for
enzyme it and vacuumed it actually turns
out are quite easy week we have the emit
RGB and we have the spread so what we
need to figure out is how the spread is
going to be encoded I think probably the
easiest way to encode it is just to say
that it's going to range from at zero it
will go entirely out the back at point
five it goes out the front and the back
and it one it goes out just the front
maybe it's hard to say there is is this
really a good way to encode both of them
I don't think into the range here
although there are some things you could
do you could partition the range as well
you could say that there's you know from
0 to 0.3 is back emission only 0.3 to
0.6 is front emission only in point 6 to
is front and back omission right so
there's a lot of different ways that we
can encode that but what I'd rather do
for the moment is not going to talk down
in that until we actually know what we
might want to do with it so just say
like use this to feedback in meters so
what I'm going to do instead is just say
that we don't do any back omission yet
so we just start out with only front
omission in the front omission is
whatever the omission was written to be
for the NP remember the encoding of this
the depth is actually the Z coordinate
so the thing that comes out of our depth
sampler here is going to be what we need
to put in there although we probably
want to you know we might want to
translate it into something that's more
that gives more information about where
in the world it is but you know I don't
know that we really need to worry about
that quite yet either
because we haven't gotten to the point
yet where we really are talking about
that particular piece of information how
it should be scaled or stored but when
we produce that NP right we know that
the depth is going to go in the final
part there and we know that the NX and
the NY are going to go in the first part
like this right now the NX and NY are
actual floating-point values here
they're not floating point values when
they come in here and so what we need to
do here is we need to bias these back to
where they're encoded zero to one at the
moment so what we need to do is actually
sort of blow these values out into
something that actually represents the
range of a real normal is that make
sense but I think that's what you're
looking at here is most that's most of
it that's mostly what we're talking
about I don't think there's really a
whole lot else to it so we really just
want to get this working the way that
you see it here and that should be
sufficient
so as you can see we've got a bunch of
texture samplers we got a query here but
that's really it so we've got a depth
sampler we've got a surface reflect
sampler although you know there's
another thing we could do here if we
wanted to
I suspect we could just start because
we're now we're using the layout
location syntax because we are requiring
three three we could actually use that
for the samplers as well at which point
I believe we wouldn't have to do any of
this nonsense anymore
so for example I think you can just
avoid any of this I think you can just
say that sort of thing right where if
you want to just specify once you've got
once you move up to this level open gel
you don't actually have to bind any of
these things that way at all right that
stuff just goes away and you don't have
to query anything anymore which is
really nice right it's just a much it's
a far superior system and before I
thought we were going to do anything
interesting with shaders I was like well
I don't want to go down that road
because that we will require a higher
open level bokken shell but since we're
doing nutso stuff in our shaders now
which is always the way writes to
seductive there's really no reason not
to do it this way right so I think we
could also do it that way and if we did
it that way then when you did OpenGL
create program and got the program back
the only thing you would need is the
program which is kind of nice you don't
need to store anything else and then all
this garbage goes away because you only
have OpenGL program common and OpenGL
program common can just be handled the
same for everybody right so that's just
nice right
so we could try to get that vet working
this way you know sure why not
so if we were going to do that then what
we do is when we do compiled depth feel
to lighting what we do here is we just
say OpenGL program common and take that
result and so that's that's really it
all right so let's move along here oops
I did I accidentally I did actually
believe that I bad so now we just need
to actually call that compilation phase
so let's go ahead and do that we need a
place to store it so I'll throw that in
here OpenGL program common this would be
desk peel lighting and then what we can
do is we can and one of the things so
maybe I'll show this today too
if we can get that location syntax
working nicely the other thing we can do
is is simplify a lot of this code as
well which would be really nice for a
number of reasons because a lot of stuff
we have been doing is because we didn't
have the option of doing sort of
something nicer with the commonality
stuff so we could actually we could
actually do something pretty interesting
here in a second as well so let's do a
desk appeal to lighting here with a free
program and then we'll do compiled just
appeal to lighting so
oops don't need common cuz there is no
such thing and then off we go
right so essentially what that's going
to do if it works properly is we
wouldn't have to ever say anything other
than texture zero one two three we
wouldn't have to query the location of
those or anything else and the reason
for that is just because now that we've
specified the location in here that
location syntax will say that zero one
two three is where you get these from
and like I said I believe you can do
that but don't quote me on that because
I maybe have that syntax wrong so let's
see if we can get that working now
surface reflects sample that is a typo
supposed to be surface reflect sampler
what else we got that 160 is the
conversion where is that happening yeah
[Applause]
all right let's see if that's any better
okay uh not great all right I admit that
this is not looking fabulous if we if
we're honest with ourselves right
there's not the look we were looking for
so let's so one thing I don't know is
whether this syntax is good all right
here let's take a quick look at the GLSL
specification just to see what we are
supposed to be able to do here and how
we're supposed to be able to announce
where these samplers go so that we don't
have to do that finding anymore let's
take a look
this is 1.5 let me see here
[Applause]
so I'm not sure if there is one of these
I just want
here we go I just want to know how
layout qualifiers will work with
samplers
[Music]
so let's see
none of this is particularly relevant to
us
let's see if they say anything in here
they don't
so I want lips
here we go I'm surface of the location
the GL comes to where an object is sort
of these binding points okay so the only
question is core in version 4.5 that's
not useful so we may not be able to do
that right because this is this is for
which we don't require anywhere else so
it looks like we will not be able to use
that right that's too bad
like I said opengl 4.5 is actually
pretty good the open jill's before that
not so good and so I never am really I'm
always a little unsure as to what I can
use on handmade hero that falls within
that line we probably should have just
said let's use opengl 4.5 and then use
the software renderer if you don't have
it or something like that that probably
would have been the smart thing to do
but oh well so anyway that does mean
that we need to continue down continue
doing what we were doing before which is
to make these things all 100% explicit
which is fine we could try to make
program common roll this up and maybe I
will try to do that because that there's
ways we could make this work right so in
OpenGL program comp common for example
what I could do is if has a CGI u ik
here which is just like samplers and
then what you could do is have a thing
that says well how many of them are
there and we know that we can't have
more than let's say 16 in any of our
current things because we definitely
don't get up anywhere above that so if
we just said well there's a sampler
account and there's some number of
samplers then when you do open jill
program common you would just set that
sample account and it would
automatically just query them in
kind of of uniform way right and and
then that way when during shutdown or
whatever you would during vine time
rather you wouldn't have to write a
separate binder for each of these you
could always just use the same binding
because it would just loop through the
samplers and bind them in order right so
we could try something like that if we
did something like that then we could
get rid of the sampler bindings and the
way we would do this I guess is when we
do the create program common you would
just do where's that let's see
pile here it is so when you do OpenGL
create program and it's going through
all the results like it does here what
you would probably do here is you just
pass the texture handles the texture
names as like a series of extras or
something like this or maybe you just do
this right so after you do OpenGL create
program that process would then do
something like result sampler count
equals zero and then you could do by our
OpenGL or just combine samplers or I
guess link samplers maybe is the right
way to do it and then you could just say
well let's suppose that I have an OpenGL
program common and then let's just say I
have samplers
[Applause]
and they'll do it like that we could do
it in even an easier way and let's do it
this way since it's kind of nutso but
let's just do it this way since this is
only done I basically when you start up
the render and isn't something that
speed intensive at all what I could do
is just say like look you can just call
this function and just pass them at the
end of the function then what we'll do
is we'll say all right let's make an
array of sampler names that just has all
these in it and then what we'll do is
we'll go okay well loop over those and
what we'll do is every time we get one
this isn't snow we will bind that
sampler on the end of the list of
samplers now the way we need to do that
here you can if they can see is we need
to do we get unit loops get uniform
location we need to do something like
this
so what we're going to do is we're going
to get this the sampler ID back
bypassing the name there like so and
when we get the fans're ID back what we
want to do is we want to see if it was
valid as well right because if it's not
valid then we don't want to bother
binding it probably well maybe we do
because maybe you want holes in the list
so hard to say so what we'll do is just
say if you gave us the name will store
the value so then we do is we say all
right the sampler count will store that
into the program itself right so this
basically just builds up a list there
and what we can do too is we can always
assert that the sampler count that we've
got is less than how far out you know
much room we have to store it so we know
we don't actually overflow by you know
creating too small a room or something
so there's our sampler linking and so
what that means is now you know every
one of these things we wanted to could
use that sampler linking let's go ahead
and skip this part of the process for
now so for example let's just go ahead
and and if you're this out for the
moment
[Applause]
here we go one star - Minnie I've
already got the array bracket on there
so I don't mean that there we go uh and
it's a frog handle frog handle let's
split handle man all right and so this
should just be what we had running
before right and it is so let's go ahead
and get all the rest of those of our
samplers of our programs working through
this way of getting the samplers so that
we don't have to worry about that
anymore right so what that would mean is
when we do use program begin we no
longer have to do any of these texture
sampler depth sampler nonsenses right
that stuff goes away and what we can do
is just say all right here these are all
unnecessary at this point right yeah I
think these are all unnecessary so like
this goes away this goes away all of
these go away
[Music]
basically everything that was a sampler
goes away so all of these go away right
and we're just left with things that
actually are data going into the program
everything else is at that point gone
yeah so now and we can get rid of them
here as well right so in device program
the samplers go away they're San Frisco
Bay here the samplers go away here here
[Music]
there we go
and now I should be able to kind of just
clean this up via errors so what we do
now is we say OpenGL link samplers
we pass the program that we're dealing
with here which is this one and then we
have just the list of names so it's not
as good as that location binding syntax
would have been but it's definitely
better than having to do this every time
I so you know that's the that's a nice
nicety and maybe you know I'll we'll see
other people are more well-versed in
opengl 3.0 x than i am
it may still be that there is a way to
do what we wanted to do so we'll wait
for people to to chime in about that
later
we may be able to get rid of the this
part as well but even if we can't again
this ends up not being so bad because at
least now it will be handled in a
relative
and you'll have to pardon the pun
uniform fashion so we won't have to keep
writing the code every time all we have
to do is just say what the names are and
that's it so let's put that down here
and then the rest of these come up there
we go and a couple more times for good
measure
[Applause]
nothing there so it's just these OpenGL
link samplers this is the new one here
they are and two more to go last one all
right
[Applause]
so I think now we've got all of that
stuff worked out oops
oh I removed string names there there we
go
but now all that should be fine and what
we want to do now is just say when we go
to do because I'm assuming that if we
ran it we wouldn't get anything or we
get something weird which is true what
we want to do now is when we do youth
program begin the common begin has to
loop through and set these right so when
we come through here and we set up like
the arrays for example we then have to
come through and do the same thing for
our samplers so we just have to do
sampler index equals zero sampler index
is less than the program sampler count
and then each one of these there's going
to be a GL uniform one eye that will be
whatever the program samplers value is
here goes to just put the new miracle
sampler index I think that's all we need
and it looks like we're back to normal
now let's check the game render as well
by turning off that sort of debug
lighting render
that's pretty awesome
that's like the depth value is what
we're seeing now is that that's the
result
I assume of the mistake I just of the
port I just made is we get to view the
depth buffer I didn't expect that but
it's pretty darn cool
either that or it's just some fogging or
something anyway let's go ahead and fix
that that house really cool I'm a stand
of viewing the death buffer so let's go
ahead and and just clean that up there
see if we can fix that although I really
do like it so it's unfortunately we have
to fix it but what we want to do here is
just figure out where that what was
going wrong there so in here we've got
are we still in our Z bias program are
we still doing things reasonably let me
just take a look so we're writing out
the surface reflectance to blending at
zero when we resolve we're going to be
resolving that so the surface
reflectance should be should be the
right color should be the correct color
there so I'm not sure why we're getting
that issue
let me just verify that texture sampler
and depth sensor go in this order
because I don't actually know what order
they do go in when do we actually use
the Z bias just see right here so
texture one is the depth handle so that
should be there yeah so I'm not sure
what's going on with that and the
texture sampler should be correct one
now I don't know maybe I don't feel like
I should have to do an if on the death
feel though I feel like it should work
to have the set either way because there
isn't going to be a second sampler
[Applause]
either way
so I'm not sure where that's coming from
[Applause]
hmm I am Not sure so here's what I'm
going to start with just because I'm not
sure who is at fault so in order to
pinpoint where the error crept in I'm
going to just start by switching what
I'm writing out so I want to see whether
I'm failing to fetch a texture here so
in the blend unit color I'm just going
to write instead of writing out surface
reflect I'm going to write out a bogus
value which is just all red and the
mouth of one so I should just see a red
screen right and I don't so basically
that tells me that at least if this it
function is wrong it's not wrong in the
sense that that it's the sole course of
the cause of the problem for example
right so something is going wrong a step
further so like in the compositing phase
or something like this so let's take a
look at this one in a little more detail
here so let's see what happens if if
from here where I'm going to write this
out let's see if the blend unit color
RGB let's see if I stuff that with a red
what do I get
all right so now I get full red so it
looks like somehow my peel sampler is
sampling things oddly I guess I'm not
sure because if these peel samplers were
sampling properly from the depth peel oh
well you know what no it could be the
resolve as well so the resolve happens
in between there
so this where we have color and pl depth
this could be the problem as well so
let's see what order these are in I
think they're actually I think that's
what's happening I think these are in
the wrong order I think that's supposed
to actually be like that yeah alright so
now we're back to normal
everyone's happy and smiling and that's
just great
okay so now my I guess my question is
where we've got that location syntax
happening I wonder if we can remove
things like you know like these values
by specifying where is the they go as
well because if we could then we could
get rid of a lot of these entirely now
as it is we can get rid of quite a few
of them which is nice but I'm wondering
if we could get rid of them all so for
example I can start getting rid of these
a little bit by saying that the peel
composite program is now just an OpenGL
program common so that goes away the
final stretch program same thing and the
multigrid light up so again I'm just
taking some time to simplify this down
so let's go ahead and do that so we
really don't need that or that or that
[Applause]
so again that becomes much simpler which
is really nice
same thing here actually I can say that
[Applause]
and painting it okay and so now when
we're doing these fries anything that
was previously calling common that
doesn't need to call common there we go
very nice uh and I think we're still
fine yeah uh so the question I have
there again is can we go even further
with that right can we also get rid of
sort of the the unnecessary especially
on some of these other these ones here
were like you know there's hardly
anything getting specified at all you
know that that would be the sort of
thing that it would be nice to remove
because they're just you know they're
creating cruft that's sitting around for
no reason so the question is would
location binding work for these and of
course I don't know let's take just one
example which is the result multisample
program and see what we can do so in
that case where we've got the resolved
multi sample program where we do layout
location equals zero on this for the out
you know is it possible for us to do a
layout location zero on that for example
right could I just say that the sample
count is going to go at location zero so
when I set uniform zero that's where
it's going to be and like I said I don't
know if that would work but that's what
I would like to try and so in here where
we do sample count equals get uniform
location sample K I'm going to leave
everything the same it's going to step
through and see what the result is
that's all I really want to do there and
what's that and that is then compiled
result another sample so if we come down
here and take a look
at location zero so now let's see
whether I can force it to some arbitrary
location that is not that and I can't
so it looks like that is not something
that actually works in this case anyway
which is a bummer but that's just the
way it goes sometimes however I suppose
I guess I'm not sure like if that's not
what that means like why why is it even
allowing me to make that specification
if that isn't what it's going to do is
that's just like what's the deal or is
it because do I need to specify maybe I
maybe I'm a victim of not specifying the
right shader version here like suppose I
specified version 3:30 and said location
equals 8 then what happens
still not so the uniform location seems
unaffected by the specification of where
it's supposed to be like that looks like
a meaningless thing to specify for all
intents and purposes right like I see no
there does not appear to be any there's
not appear to be any consequence to that
value unless I'm misunderstanding the
idea here right which is unfortunate but
it looks that way anyway all right well
will we'll address that a little later
we don't need to get bogged down in
OpenGL specifics because this again this
is just toying with OpenGL has nothing
to do with anything about graphics
really it's just that the stupid things
you have to do to get graphics API to do
the code you want them to do right like
it's annoying but it's just how it goes
so let's put that aside for now and go
back to what we were doing which is more
what I want to focus on anyway
which is now if I want to call our def
peel import stuff here let's try and get
that working so I'm going to switch back
on the lighting drawing I don't care
about this right now
all right so happily this does appear to
have imported the lighting values at
least somewhat right which is what we
wanted and this is what is this value
here this is surface reflectance which
is correct right that's exactly what we
want to see for surface reflectance here
and here is surface normal which also is
looking pretty good right so we have
plenty of data rendered out now you can
see how like the surface normals kind of
like averaged out which is kind of funny
let's see how the surface the other
values averaged out there there's the
surface reflectance and averaging
and it seems like our averaging process
is kind of busted which i think means
we're going to have to be more careful
about that
relatively soon but you can see for
example like if we just look at the
surface reflectance here there's really
no way that you should have such a
discrepancy based on movement
so our averaging down you know isn't
great at the moment right it's not and I
think a lot of that again has to do with
the uneven sampling so we probably want
to fix that at some point and try to get
something that's going to be a more
reliable down sample because that will
make our lighting be really inconsistent
and that's one thing that we're going to
have to work on for sure okay but
either/or we are able to do our little
sphere light here and we are down
sampling it properly so now we've kind
of got that part of the lighting that in
you know kind of impasse working
correctly and so what we want to do now
is we want to basically do some work
with actually bouncing that light around
and the way that we were going to do
that at which we haven't played with yet
right is we have the import phase which
is really just responsible of converting
values from the def field system over
into something the lighting wants to use
which is basically an unpack right it's
taking some relatively concise
information that's packed into 8-bit
values and it's blowing it out into big
32-bit values for the iteration process
we have the upward phase which is doing
our sort of down sampling it's not very
good right now like I said that down
sampling creates some artifacts so I
think we're going to have some problems
there and we're going to have to beef up
what this upward phase does assuming any
of this lighting stuff works the way it
does once we sort of get it into a more
real sense but then we've got the
downward phase the tower phase is really
the thing that was supposed to do some
of the lighting calculations and right
now isn't doing any lighting
calculations at all
all right so what we need to do is make
this downward lighting phase actually do
some lighting transport because that is
the problem with the current thing that
we're doing which is why it's not
actually producing any lighting is
because we're not actually ever running
the transport equation right all we did
was get the sort of procedural trappings
in place to get the data we needed for
lighting and to have a process we could
use for lighting but now we have to
actually put in some lighting equations
because without those equations we're
not really using the computational
framework to produce anything valuable
that looks anything like lighting would
look so that's what we want to get
started on right here so taking a look
at what we are doing we can get rid of
this if one it well I guess we'll leave
it there for now you probably want to
have some switches we can turn on and
off dynamically as well at some point
that would probably a good idea but
let's go ahead and pop over to the
actual code for the compute down
lighting so we can kind of see here this
is the code multi like down and so the
way that you can see this working is we
already did the lighting we already did
the lighting query so you can see here
we set ourselves up to sample all of the
information that we wanted and we sort
of had you know sampled things nearby
and the texture and all that other sort
of stuff but we don't actually do
anything now with the result right we
don't actually like we've got this
transfer light call and what you can see
is the only thing that transfer light
does is it just averages the light
together right which is like completely
you know non lighting does nothing to do
with how life should actually be
behaving so presumably what we would
like to do here is we would like to do
something that actually transfers the
light based on some kind of lighting
equation of how much light there should
be flowing from one place to another
now the
again the issue here we got to start to
think about like how we really want to
do this for real and what I was talking
about before in terms of the see here
Milton hello there we go so if you think
about what's supposed to happen here
like I was saying there's one point it's
sort of straightforward way to do it and
that's a little more costly and
difficult and then there's one way to do
it that that was sort of the multigrid
thing that I think is kind of a
harebrained scheme but we might have to
just jettison because I don't know if
it's even semi plausible but if you
imagine
looking at sort of a subdivided space
here where this is the entire lighting
information grid let's say at the
highest resolution so we know stuff like
oh there is a bright light right here
like we have that information encoded in
the bitmap at a very high resolution but
you know what we can't do is for every
pixel on the screen we can't step
through every other pixel in the
lighting buffer right we can't step
through 1920 by 1080 light informations
and calculate whether or not we can see
that particular light right because in
order to do that we would have to step
through all of the stuff and see whether
we could see it or not and furthermore
even if we didn't do that we still just
have way too many to do right so it's
not feasible whose is a feasible thing
for us to do at all so if we actually
imagine looking at a lighting sample and
we want to do something like figure out
whether or not we can see particular
life then what you can imagine us doing
is sort of a multi resolution query
where we did something like okay let's
take each of these four large regions
let's say and we'll say that the one
large region we're in maybe will treat
more specially but say for example this
large region here let's just assume that
that large region is only going to give
one sample so everything in here has
been averaged together same thing with
here same thing with here right and then
we're just going to compute the lighting
to each of these large regions rather
than to like every little individual
thing inside the region right that's
kind of the idea that we're going for
here and in order to do that I think
what we want to write what we would want
to say is well okay we know that we can
see each of these regions
if nothing
in the way in our smaller region right
so what we would want to do is take
sub-samples like here here and here
of how much sort of blockage there would
be how much shadowing there would be of
stuff that comes through it's kind of
what we want to say right so you can
imagine this multi-resolution process
where we want to be able to do that
basic operation and you know the multi
grid dreamed here that I cannot accept
many times as a harebrained scheme so I
don't honestly believe it's ever going
to work but the harebrained scheme is
that we could come up with one kernel
that you can apply at each step of the
multi grid that would just propagate
approximate results of this process down
so that you only ever did one of these
so for example let's suppose that the
thing that you're like the thing that we
want to do
looks something like this right so we're
taking a sample here and actually since
it's multigrid let's say there's there's
well now I guess we'll do two lower ones
let me let me draw this a little bit
better
so let's suppose we want to compute the
lighting here and let's suppose you want
to compute it from the entire
neighboring region right so we know that
there is going to be 8 texture samples
right that we would have to take to find
out what the data is in these regions
around then internal to us right this
would give us how the incoming lighting
flows in if there is no shadowing but we
know we probably want some shadowing
otherwise the lighting solution is not
going to be very interesting and so in
order to do that what we would have to
do is say well let's subdivide ourselves
right and let's do the same thing again
and what we want to do is say well ok
let's see how much of a shadowing there
would be if we were trying to look at
these things so looking at 3 looking at
0 looking at it 1 looking on a 2 4 etc
how much shadowing is there in our local
Mora slightly more local area how much
shadowing is there to be able to see
these things that are further away right
and so you would end up taking 16
samples for every one resolution here
that you wanted to do and then you would
use those values to sort of figure out
how much lighting contribution you
should add in the region you're
currently operating on and so you know
that this actually sounds like plausible
like vaguely plausible but that's the
primary operation we'd have to do on the
down sample and when we did that down
sample we would then add that lighting
result whatever we got from each of
these 8 computations right each of those
8 computations would tell us how much
light to
add to the result we're standing on
right the result that we're actually
computing about so yeah that's really
all there is to it so the one thing that
we don't currently store and I feel like
we kind of do need to store it as much
as I hate to have extra textures I think
we probably would is that one of the
problems we have right now is we're
always assuming that things are at the
Centers of their grid cells and the only
thing that we check check is the height
but we probably don't really want to do
that right we probably want to bias we
probably want to say that a cell
contains a point and the point is the
location that's the averaged amount of
the lighting that's coming out of it
right or the average location of the
occluders in that area right so we kind
of have two things you know like like I
say that as we sort of develop this
we've got to kind of think about what we
really want to store and how we can make
something that's going to be useful in
that way right
but anyway so let's suppose that we
let's suppose that we have that so we
all went to this by at least one one
additional thing that we don't have
right now which is just the position
because right now we do have the depth
but we don't have the position we can
assume that the position is in the
center of the cell for now but that's
not a very good approximation because it
may be that like there's a very big wall
here that's really what we want to talk
about so it gets it gets kind of
difficult to think about how those sorts
of things should should be happening
right and furthermore it strikes me that
like again it seems almost like it order
if we really do want to try to push this
multi light thing and see if it really
does a multi grid light thing and see if
it really does where
it also strikes me that we may have to
store two separate things but we may
have to store like the light and the
occluder differently or E or maybe store
them on the up pass and the down path
differently I don't know but that part
is just a little tricky and I don't know
if there's I don't really know what the
way around it is well I'm getting ahead
of myself so anyway if we just assume we
just start with what we have right now
that's basically the computation sort of
thing that we would need to do right we
would need to be able to do this sort of
light transfer now whether or not we
need the diagonals I assume we need the
diagonals because otherwise you kind of
get this weird your lighting will have
very heavy sort of axial components so
I'm not sure you can really ignore the
stuff that's coming from you know your
your sort of diagonal neighbors but who
knows so right now all we're sampling is
the cross and I think we may have to
sample sort of the diagonal as well and
so right now we also aren't doing any
shadowing so we don't sample the sub
cross on the next level down either to
figure out what kind of shadowing we're
going to be doing there so again a
little bit confusing and a little bit
complicated but that's sort of the sort
of where we're at right so what you can
see here is we have a front omission and
back omission that we're going to
compute because we're pointing a
particular direction and we collect
light on our back end the front front
and back row services because we are a
sprite card thing normally we'd only
have front because well because all of
our game is like these little cards
it seems sensible to treat both sides
since everything's infinitely thin
so taking a look at the transfer
lighting question here you can see that
we do a transfer light and we say here's
our you know our reception parameters
right r.fp ref and ref C and here's our
emitter parameters so without doing any
further work we can do the light
transport here in some way to something
other than just a straight average based
on our normal and things like that so we
can't actually do something there the
thing we can't do is the shadowing
because in order to shadow and we have
to be able to sample what's what would
be in between us now maybe we can just
have the transfer light equation sample
something that's in between the two
positions and try to do something smart
about that that that is something we
could add we're like that's where that
sampling here is the for right now I'll
just try doing just some basic transfer
so because this is so approximate I'm
not going to start with anything that's
even trying to approximate real lighting
transfer instead what I'm going to do is
just see how much these two things can
see each other right so since we want to
do this transfer light what I want to do
is say okay if I've got two surfaces and
I want to know how much light they're
going to bounce to each other at the
very least something I'm going to have
to do is how much are they facing each
other right the cosine of the angle
between them is going to be important
here because if for example I'm talking
about two surfaces that are pointing
away from each other then no light is
transferred so I have to do some kind of
computation there so the first thing I
want to do is figure that out so I'm
going to introduce a facing term here
and all that's going to be is that's
just going to be the inner product of
the light normal and the reflection
normal now the the product of those two
we we want to condition the result of
that because the condition of the result
that doesn't come out in a way we can
use for multiplication very well why
doesn't it well it doesn't because if
you think about two services that are
pointing the same direction here's my
reflector here's my light
if I have these two services I want to
say well how much like to answer between
them the answer we know here is none
right the answer is zero light is
transfer between them but the dot
product of these two right to take the
to get the cosine the angle between them
but dot produce two will produce one
because they're pointing the same
direction so what we want to do is do
sort of conditioning of this value if
they were pointing the way we want them
to point their value would actually be
negative one right because they're
pointing in opposite directions so what
we really want to do is we want to
negate this result right and I don't
remember sorry I know we just patented a
bunch of pound vines here here we go so
we have inner we have clamped zero one
okay good so basically what I want to do
is say all right let's take the negative
of this and clamp it like so and so what
that gives me is a value from zero to
one that just says how lined up these
two light sources are right and I can
use that to now attenuate that result
right I can use that to attenuate any
lighting transfer that's going to happen
between them so now we also get into the
how far away they are because these are
diffused surfaces not specular at the
moment although we may want to do some
work with that obviously in the future
what we want to do is take the light
emission and we want to scale it by that
distance as well use the inverse square
law there so the distance between these
two lights light P minus recipe we
really want that to be squared so you
know this is a length squared
computation
that's going to be modulated as well so
as that distance goes I want to be 1
over the length squared there as they
get further apart I want that to divide
out right so if the distance squared if
the distance squared where 0 if that
should never actually happen so I think
I can avoid that case because we're
always testing cells that are um there
shouldn't be any way to actually have
them become zero
I'll have to see if that's true but that
shouldn't happen so we know that we also
have sort of the fall-off term which is
going to be 1 over that distance squared
now somehow I don't I never did define
some of these it looks like so you know
length and the length squared of vectors
so the length squared of a vector is I
was used to dot product of of itself I
think there's a built in for length here
I don't know if there's a built in for
length squared I'll check but like I
said it's just a dot product anyway yeah
so there you go length is there's no
length squared so we just dot a vector
with itself that'll give us the length
squared so that's all we really need so
if we want the length squared of this
vector here that's what we'll get and I
think that's all we really need to know
so computing the lighting here if we
want to start by making something a
little more sensible than what we want
to do is do something like okay there's
the facing times the distance squared
times the color times the emission right
so then we've got something that takes
into account the angular aspect of it
we've got something that takes into
account the fall-off distance aspect of
it
and off we go problem with this although
that's all well and good is right now we
are not actually reconstructing the
position in any way that makes any sense
so we have to be able to take fragment
coordinates and translate them into
positions and right now we don't have
any way of actually doing that so that's
going to be a whole situation kind of a
whole whole what's the word I'm looking
for
that's going to be a whole valley wick
it's in and of itself am I losing that
term correctly spelled it wrong
I guess I kind of used it right you know
it's not I wasn't a fabulous teachers
and not one of my finer vocabulary
moments certainly if we're being honest
about it but it's all right baileywick
baileywick baileywick so baileywick I
pronounce it very old I pronounce it
late Middle English which is not good
so baileywick that's going to be a whole
nother baileywick so yeah so we can put
that transfer letting in there like so
but what we're going to find is it's
going to blow up immediately because the
length squared term that I said could
never be 0 will actually be 0 a lot of
the time because we're artificially
making all of our positions be exactly
the same which is not good at all right
that is the opposite of what we want and
so we need to have some way of making
this result here make more sense right
so we can start by using the UVs but
that's not going to be at all correct
and so we need to create a better some
better work there right all right so
let's start by oh dear I don't know why
sometimes we get a very low frame rate
and I never really know why I think it's
like we're pushing this graphics card a
little bit beyond what it can really
handle and our undamped spring here is
not particularly happy about that so I
wonder what it is just literally that or
that just the fact that we were like is
literally just the fact that we're doing
some more operations here enough to
really slow things down it seems odd
that it would be really that painful for
the card like is that actually the case
[Applause]
so it's not like it's just that slow at
the moment for reasons that are not
immediately clear to me I granted this
graphic card is extremely old so it
could be any number of reasons but we
don't have a lot of ways to profile it
at the moment let me go ahead and put
that in here what I can do is like in
six sort of the under damped springiness
I suppose of the body head dichotomy
there to prevent it from from causing
this problem that we're getting there
but that's not going to help us keep a
reasonable frame rate that we can
actually use for for testing it's the
only problem we can reduce the
resolution to something very low like so
all right and that definitely looks
better
all right so that's good enough for now
I'll just leave live with running at a
low resolution for this particular
problem for this particular situation
all right so again so this brings us
back to against the the sort of place
we're at in terms of lighting transfer
at this point right we need to now start
having our lights be brighter than one
as well because as you can see when we
get out to here you know the lights are
so dim at this point as well because
we're sort of we haven't encoded them in
any sort of way that makes a sense in
terms of the visible area so we probably
have to take a look at that in a second
as well but let's just take a look at
what our other values are for now so our
lighting reflect color seems pretty
reasonable you know I don't think we're
going to have a lot of problems with
that going forward right that seems
pretty much fine to me the team and
let's go ahead and take a look at our
normals again you have a normal seem to
be pretty sane as well right
so I think we've got those two in a
place where they're not going to cause
us too much trouble so it's really just
the lighting transport part that we
should be able to focus on getting
something out of at the head end so the
first thing that I want to know is can
we get a white and actual light in here
instead of just straight-up red and I
don't remember why we ended up with
straight up red was that just because we
had placed a bright red light for no
reason into the compiled lead bias
program what was using light pee
yeah so I'm going to go ahead and change
this to a white light at first I want to
see how it interacts with the reflection
color because something is weird at the
moment and we have to that's the first
thing I wanted to bug so if you think
about what's happening here this is the
actual result of the of the light
transport it doesn't make a lot of sense
because if you look at what's happening
to it we should be seeing some of those
colors start to come through at some
point now it makes sense that the part
we can see directly so the part that's
not going to have any bounce it makes
sense that that would be bright white
because again what we're seeing there is
just clipping off the end potentially
now we could do some some work there to
make sure that we do sort of our tone
mapping at the end would swing that we
do have to do but we should be able to
start seeing some bounce of light soon
that hat takes into account actual
colors and stuff like that but we're not
seeing any of that so we're kind of just
like not correctly doing anything at the
moment and I'd like to know why so again
one thing that I do want to do is crank
the power of that light up a little bit
so when we are transferring the light
over so when we do Jess peel the
lighting I want to scale up that surface
emission so the emit RGB here for
example I'd like to take the maximum
light power and that max light power is
just some arbitrary value that's how
strong we want the strongest light to be
relative to the 0 to 1 range which is
just reflected light right and so if we
do that we now have like this light is
very very bright so when it kind of gets
blended up yet you can see it should
always tend to dominate anything that it
blends with right very powerfully which
it sort of is which is good but what I
don't understand is like if this is the
top level version
how come we never get we never see
almost any light bleeding at all right
so we never see any light transfer
happening and why is that right so I've
got some issues in here to address so
let's start with the individual terms
and again all these variables are kind
of bogus so it's kind of hard to start
with it's sometimes hard when you're
just trying to start up because you
don't have everything worked out yet you
hard it's hard to know what's actually
incorrect but what I can do here is I
can say well what if we turn off some of
these terms so suppose I turned off the
fall-off and the only thing that we use
for the facing direction right what
would that do and what you can sort of
see here is not much right so the
fall-off term doesn't seem to
necessarily be a huge culprit there what
happens if I turn off the facing term as
well right again nothing so it's almost
like our lighting transfer is never
transferring anything at oh that's good
that's a nice typo try that one more
time so that would explain it there we
go
okay so that's more what I would expect
to see so now let's try turning on the
facing direction so now we're going to
only transfer based on facing directions
match matching up so you can see that's
not really working right so face facing
Direction not working so we got to fix
that and let's see how fall-off looks so
far which is again going to be kind of
really bogus at this point but all right
so fall off term not a problem that's
not knocking things off however it does
seem to be boosting the light power
which is not what I would have expected
because it should strictly diminish so I
guess what that means is our distance
squared is
yeah so our distance squared it's
supposed to be coming out from the light
so really what we want there is be you
know more like this sort of thing right
we never want it to increase the power
of the light if it drops below a certain
amount so we always want it to sort of
diminish the light as it goes outwards
right so if we're trying to diminish the
light as it goes that word again
the if the the fall-off rate here is
going to be also based upon what our
units are in this sense because that
value will get bigger faster depending
on the depending on the unit scale right
so this computation has to be made
correct at some point but we can again
hack in whatever we want here if we want
more distance attenuation we can hack in
something to you know to give us more
distance attenuation as we go right so
if we want to play with that value right
we can play with that value so there's
some more distance attenuation right
and if we look at what's happening to
these you can kind of see how that light
is spreading out and where where and
when it's sort of spreading itself out
right so now let's figure out why our
facing direction isn't working at all so
we have the light normal and the
reflected normal maybe those are wrong
would be thing number one the other
thing is we do the inner product when we
negate it are we sure that's right I
believe it is because again the light
normal and reflected normal the maximum
transfer should be happened when they're
pointing opposite which is when it'll be
negative one and we want to clamp that
between zero and one because if it's
negative after we do the reversal that
means they're pointing away from each
other we don't want to use that so when
I turn this on and we use the facing
term what you can see here is it
immediately kills all of the transfer
so with that suggests to me is we must
have a problem with how we're packing
our normals in and/or unpacking them I
don't know but something's not going
grow and right so when we do we
construct normal you can see here what
we do is we Square Root basically just
the the two terms that we have to make
sure that the result sums to one and we
stuff that into the normal that we're
using right the we got the MPX the MP Y
and then the Z so that should in theory
compute reasonable normals I don't know
why it wouldn't so the question is are
we sampling them correctly are we
getting them wrong some other way and I
don't know so when we're doing the light
samples for the left right up down here
and we're getting you know these these
parent samples what does that look like
well here's our front and back admission
here's our our texture sample for the NP
value and we construct the normal from
that NP value I look sane I don't
I don't see what the problem would be
there
yeah I really don't see it and I can
understand a lot of things are pointing
upward so I could see why there would be
less transfer when that happened but it
shouldn't be none right you should it
should attenuate but not completely
eliminate I would think and that's not
at all what I'm seeing so I feel like
that is still a little bit busted and
we're not really getting good UV values
out now what's weird about that are
sorry good normalize that what's worried
about that is this does look promising
like that looks like a thing which I
haven't sat down and tried to figure if
it's exactly right
but it does look roughly like a
plausible normal map right and so the
weird thing is if we're sampling from
that we should end up with some
reasonable normal so what's going wrong
I don't know
because the the you know the X&amp;Y is of
the position are definitely rum so if
there's one that's going to be more
incorrect it should actually that one's
the normals actually should be right
we're not hacking the normals at all
right now the normals are 100% passed
through the pipeline and so it's and
we're viewing them too and they look
reasonable so I'm not sure why we're not
getting something plausible out of there
now we are sampling from parent NP tech
and our NP tech and I suppose I don't
know if maybe one of those is coming in
wrong we wouldn't know if it was so I
suppose we could just double check here
to make sure that like all the samplers
are set up properly
but it sure looks like they are here and
if I do look at when we actually do this
setup let me just just verify that if I
open up a second window into this
program here this file rather I can I
get some confirmation that we're
specifying these buffers correctly so
zero is the front one is the back to is
MP ten yep three is the surface color
and four is the NP Tech as well again
all looks pretty reasonable there that's
that's what we would expect to see so
let's do this let's write the
reconstructed normal into the channel
we're not using which is here so let's
just see if we're clearing the
reconstructed normal correctly so here's
that buffer here's us querying the
reconstructed normal so this is you know
a X Y Z of the normal itself and and we
can sort of see whether this makes any
sense um
personally this isn't really packed in
any kind of same way because now we've
got like negative values Q's here we've
got negative and positive values into
your floating-point values and how those
are going to get mapped to a display is
kind of like well you know what I have
no idea what it's what it's going to do
with the floating point of a negative
value but at the very least what we can
see here is it's not ludicrous right
it's at least plausible now looking at
the the individual values themselves
there are some things here which again
don't seem to make a lot of sense so
maybe there are some problems here that
are bad so for example I'm seeing gray
where things should be pointing upwards
and once we've converted our normals
into actual real floating point XY and Z
then we shouldn't see gray for pointing
upwards what we should see for pointing
upwards is zero zero one correct which
should be blue and that's not what I'm
seeing here right so I feel like I
should be seeing blue where I'm seeing
gray similarly like something like the
hero where it's bringing in negative Y I
suppose that makes sense because that
would be blue and red would be set and
green would not would be negative and
not visible so that seems fair so it
really just feels like it feels like the
Z value is kind of wrong everything else
feels like it might be correct but the Z
value does feel kind of wrong
potentially
hmm
so let's see why does the V value feel
wrong well let's suppose that I was to
blast a Z value so let's just let's just
overwrite it with 0 and verify that I'm
seeing that correctly right so there's
no blue that's right that's what we
would expect but you can see why I'm
having trouble with this looking at this
screen I'm seeing things that are facing
upward are are somehow showing red and
green components they shouldn't be right
things that are facing upwards should be
showing 0 0 1 and they're not so again
I've got a problem somewhere in the pipe
here I don't know what it is but it's
definitely there and that's that the
bottom level that I was looking at there
and so that bottom level that bottom
level should in theory be the result of
the copy right as well so that's just
kind of troubling so I don't know what's
going on there let's take a look at how
we're writing out those values when we
do the def peeled of lighting make sure
there's there right so
the index in the end wire straight up
scales of the incoming value which is
just the X and the y right and then the
X and the y of the normal
we're just scaling them into the
negative one to one range right which is
what they should be no that's not true
I lied I lied so it should be negative
one plus two times the value so that
that was just a typo there all right
let's see if that gives me anything
better in this case much better much
much better that's what I want to see
okay so let's stop blasting the Z now
and sink to figure it out what was
happening there where's my transfer
light down there it is let's go back to
showing the right thing and now can I
see do I have there we go so that's what
I wanted to see that's exactly what it
should look like so now I have more
confidence that my normals are at least
you know plausible now like that looks
much better
good okay um
so now what we need to know is when we
do this sort of light transfer bouncing
around this my question is when we do
the transfer light why are we noting
anything when we use the facing
Direction term because even if it was
fairly low we should still get see
something right and so I don't know why
we're not seeing anything we can stop
writing out the normals here now because
I know that they are not the problem
what I could do is take a look at the
light normal so for example I could look
to see what we're getting in left ah ten
which is just the leftward light sample
and now I can just see what is that so
there's a leftward light sample and
again the leftward lights normal that
looks fine right that that does look
like what I would expect it to look like
so again I'm just not sure why I can't
get any transference at all it makes
sense why there's not a lot of
transference because again we're sort of
at this in this way where we have our
sprites are mostly facing upwards so
it's hard to get some transfer going
there because of that difference but
what we could do to there as well is we
could say we could take for example the
the level geometry and maybe bias it a
little so that we would see some so that
we've have bigger walls nearby right so
that's one thing we could do but again I
just feel like it's a little weird that
nothing is coming through still it just
doesn't seem quite right
and so since those normals are all
relatively valid I guess what I'd like
to do is let's take a look at the inner
product as just something we can write
out ourselves
so suppose we were to take the negative
inner product
[Applause]
I won't even clamp it yet let's take the
negative inner product and just just
write that out so what what is the
actual negative inner product of the
screen what don't you like about that
you don't like that that's just a
regular value okay that's fair
I want to replicate that out is that
something I can do like this for example
okay so here's that product and it
barely has any any result anywhere right
which which ain't great let's take a
look at the non negative version so
there's the non negative version so here
is we're basically looking at when you
just take the there were the two normals
next to each other and you dot them
together what do you get
so again in some sense I can see why
that would be the case because when you
have a bunch of normals like pointing
all upward they're not going to transfer
a light like it all right but at the
same time when you have like this part
here in that part here they should and I
guess that's where I was getting some of
that though
[Applause]
I'm supposed to be in the QA right now
aren't I but I mean I'm getting so
little of it it can it really be that
little I guess it could be I mean it's
not out of the question
I mean one of the things that is true is
that lighting transfer doesn't happen
much along the ground right like ground
to ground letting transfer if there's no
Hills it doesn't happen so it is kind of
true that I'm sort of setting myself up
for failure and that I'm expecting light
to transfer between two things where no
light should actually transfer let's go
to the QA we'll pick the SEC up tomorrow
but I don't want to use up all the time
that might be used for QA there we go
we've got a little bit of Q&amp;A in there
because yeah that does seem like it
could be plausibly true so I should have
- yeah I should have to think that
through a little bit further so we'll
see where we end up deciding tomorrow
midlow because some of our lighting code
end up being used by the audio system to
figure out where and how obstructed
reflected sound sources are probably not
because since it's on the GPU it says
it's on the GPU I don't really know that
there's going to be there's really not
going to be any way to like get back get
that back right I we'd have to like
round-trip it so I don't think it's
probably something we would want to do
that way you probably want to
sympathetic and run on the CPU
Lord of six try one - clamp uh well what
what are you suggesting that would do it
why would we do one - clamp
so you know what we want to do is have
it so that as these things turns towards
each other right
so as these things turn toward each
other we want the value to go up to one
and so that is the if this is a this is
B that is a transpose B negated right
that's the negative of that so if you
are going to clamp that value and it's
going to run between zero and one for
how close they are together inverting
the range is going to make it so that
this is the highest lightest rank
letting transfer right it's going to be
the perpendicular that's the highest and
that just doesn't that's not what we're
trying to accomplish here right like
that's not going to help us get towards
a functioning lighting system because it
like we know that it's definitely not
the case that perpendicular surfaces
transfer the most light is that's not
the case that make sense
ss gardener should you add a fake
ceiling for lighting or a non fake
ceiling based on the floor above the
current one yes I do think we should but
the problem is how to do it because the
ninth part of that's a death peel render
is it does give us like all the floors
but it doesn't give us the one above the
lumber on that's completely invisible so
it's like
not in tolerated a stream but will you
perhaps use something like a pipeline
state object for finding resources no we
probably won't do anything like that
basically we're pretty much done with
any sort of fussing with the pipeline
management I think at the moment like
it's pretty much probably will look the
way that it looks right now
and yeah my assumption is just that yeah
like so we'll have to see but in order
for to do the lighting transport there
we may have the problem of how do we how
do we get some values in that are multi
level so we can't have like a feeling
like we were saying
all right folks
I think we are done for today but we'll
pick this back up again tomorrow
all right Thank You overdriven episode
of handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding the few as always if you would
like to follow along with series at home
you can always peer out of the game on
handmade hero or it comes with source
code so you can follow along with it and
do your own experimentation maybe you
can come up with some good light
transport stuff we also have a forum
site where you can go to class questions
a page rampage transport the video
series a schedule bot that tweets the
schedule so you know we're in real life
you want to catch us live and episode
guide for catching up on old series
that's it for today I'll be back
tomorrow to play route the lighting a
bit see if we can get some reasonable
light transport stuff happening and yeah
and that's about it until then have fun
programming LC I've run on the Internet
take me as everybody