hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here of the show we code a complete game
live on stream this is well you know
I'll be honest I don't really completely
remember what it is that we're supposed
to be doing on this stream
I really don't it was Wednesday we had
brains working we were hopping around we
made the thing in the in the post Jim
does somebody asked where you could swap
your head with something else that was
nearby and that was kind of funny
so to be completely honest with you I
really don't remember what we should be
working on right now what I will say is
that there's plenty of things I can
think of that we should be working on
right now so rather than try to give a
pre bit preamble on the stream that's
like here's what we're gonna do today I
don't know so I must open the cup based
code base and see what it is that we're
going to work on I suspect that the most
profitable thing to work on would be to
start doing some work in the brain code
stuff maybe make some monsters or things
like that we had talked about maybe
making a little snake thing like walks
around or who knows and so that might be
an interesting one as well so let's go
ahead and get started on that because
that's you know that's that's some stuff
and things like that and whatever so
that's good so I think we'll probably do
that playing with the brains and the
movement mode stuff to try and get those
into a good more mature area today is
day 2 91 so if you would like to follow
along at home you can unpack day 2 90s
source code into a directory and that is
what I am starting with at this very
moment in the real world in life in the
world so let's go ahead and see where we
are gonna put a for coder here and build
I gotta I remember to update the floor
coat of this machine there is a new
build there's a build that's newer than
the one that I'm using here and I got a
switch to it okay so yeah what we've got
at this point is is we have the hero is
the only person who's really going
through real movement code at the moment
and nobody else actually is and so I
guess one thing that I could do just
right off the bat is we could make the
monster right it was just a little torso
sitting there we could make the monster
start moving around I don't know where
he would move around to
we uh but you know that's okay it
doesn't matter we you know what we'll
just have them move around for some
reason mm probably shouldn't eat cheesy
poof's on the stream so there's probably
is too much crunching but they're so
darn delicious you know all right
anyway so let's see here what have we
got to work with I'm gonna go into the
brain code and I suppose if we look at
what's going on here really all that's
happening for example in here is like
I've got a thing that says like oh yeah
if there's a traversable and i'm planted
you know like let's hop around I feel
like we could do something where you
know how it wouldn't take very long
oh you know what I think this is what we
were doing - it looks like we start with
the figure I was gonna say we'll do
Monstar but we don't even have to master
but I guess you know either way let's
get both of those working familiar in
Monstar because it looks like we started
on that I was gonna say us I wonder if
we can just go ahead and actually move
the Daman star around by just saying
like okay you know if you're a monster
and I guess the monster you know doesn't
really have a body or anything
I'm sorry doesn't really have a head or
anything he just has a body then I guess
what I could do is say let's take the
Monstar and grab out the parts for the
Monstar and there we go and the Monstar
only has a body I could say you know if
the body is valid because I guess I
don't want to do anything if it's not at
all at the moment since there's nothing
else then I'm gonna say get the closest
traversable to wherever I am maybe like
plus some random
Delta right for now will actually do a
real Delta then will randomize it later
so we'll just say like oh yeah look look
you know one to the right of wherever
you are or something so find the thing
that's closest in that over that
direction if the movement mode is
planted then we'll go ahead and a second
we move this down here then we'll go
ahead and set this stuff up for doing
the hop right we'll do a transactional
occupy and and that's it I don't know
what that's gonna do to be completely
honest with you but that seems fine oh
I've got to have somewhere to put it I
suppose that traversable has to be
stored so let's go ahead and grab that
there we go okay
so a couple things we need to do here
first of all I need to actually assign
the Monstar to something although
actually wait let's that shouldn't have
crashed should it have well it didn't
actually crash I guess oh no it did get
some space reversible updating render
worlds came from and occupying what did
I do here Oh cuz right
he isn't starting on an actual occupying
so this is the same thing as before we
need to actually start initializing our
entities properly so we do that in the
in the player you can actually see that
happening right we get this occupying
equal standing on the sort of thing and
we need to do something for that in in
the case of the Monstar right and I
don't know I guess we do make a Monstar
brain I didn't realize we did make a
monster brain I guess we just did it for
completeness Oh cuz we wanted to swap
with them that's why
and we only allowed swapping with things
that had brains you know I just said I
wasn't gonna another cheesy poof and I
totally I totally did all right so
anyway point being we need some way of
saying
that this is where the dude stands right
so I put that standing on in there like
so and it looks like I can if you create
one of these things I guess I could
theoretically make it so that it knows
where it is in that case - I don't know
that I want to do that yet so I'm gonna
hold off on that for a second because
what we need to do when we move into the
code for like creating worlds is we'll
probably clean up the notion of how
we're like saying where things are
placed so I don't know that I really
want to think about that all too hard
right now so I'm just gonna say we're
gonna have standing on gets initialized
when you create a monster and so I just
have to make sure that we actually do
that sorry occupying so when we create
the monster we need some notion of where
the monster is actually going to be
placed and when we create stuff we
should actually be able to like we
should be able to remember when we
create a monster but we'd probably want
to do that in a you know we want to do
these things in a way that's a little
bit more conducive to how we would
actually be doing them so for example
when we are creating rooms and stuff we
have the information at that point when
we do like add standard room we have the
information at that point but we're not
actually returning it right so what I
would like to do is something that that
works sort of maybe in this context
where inside the standard room maybe
every time we make a standard room in
fact we could just make them so when I
do like add monster and add familiar or
whatever right I could come in here and
just say you know what let's bring those
out here and when we're creating these
things we can also say oh yeah if this
is the time when we want to make one of
these guys will when we create the
entity we can use that entity and and do
the placement on it right I don't think
I don't know if we want to do yeah so I
guess what we want to do here is just
have a couple of these right I'd also
say something like this oops
so maybe like if it's negative -
negative - I'm gonna I'm gonna not add
the familiar just yet so we'll say like
hey if we're here and you know what this
is not an else I guess now I think about
it cuz it's gonna stand on that thing so
it's actually an if here I could do
something like this where I say like
okay let's remember what entity we're
actually going to be doing on here and
we'll make one of these traversable x'
so when we need to do add Monstar and we
got this standing on here we can make
that actually refer to an entity
properly right so when we create this
entity we should be able to say like
okay you know standing on in this case
the entity and I don't know what this is
going to expect this is a traversable
reference so I guess this is going to be
have to expect an entity packed I'm not
sure what will happen there
let's take a look so inside the entity
code itself we have a traversable
reference it has an entity reference so
I could just set the entity reference
index right so this is standing on
entity index equals and the ID and and
then we would have standing on entity
oops standing on index equals zero right
which it already would be so I think
this is really all we need and then when
we add the monster we can just say like
standing on is that thing I think got to
make that a dot now when we add this
thing I guess we've got a world P and
when we add monster I feel like we would
just pass the world P through so I'm
just gonna do that right and then if I
look at that monster and again like I
said this is stuff that will clean up a
bunch more later so it won't be as weird
once we kind of have more of a handle on
it so okay there's add mon-star and when
we add it here I guess we'd have to put
it above this code because it's getting
called from there and familiar would
have to be the same okay standard room
all right
in it points do-do-do-do-do-do hit
points that would go right about there
shadow alpha we're gonna have to get rid
of eventually but I guess now's not the
time that's when we do our render pass
let's put that up here and then add
piece that stuff should be sort of that
should actually really probably be in
the entity code but you know all right
okay so let's see if that works I'm not
sure if it actually we'll see what's
going on here I'm gonna double so before
I even start with that and we do the
Monstar stuff I want to actually go into
that brain code and and nuke it and just
see if I can get that thing initialized
properly first so that we know like
where the dude is standing all right so
there's Monstar and you can see that it
doesn't appear to be initialized
correctly because what you'll notice is
the square underneath him is not lit
blue and if it was an inch less
correctly it would have been so we need
to figure out why that's not happening
on Pac and so let's do that now and like
I said we still have we got you know and
at some point we're gonna stress this I
just don't want to quite a dress it now
when we're actually creating worlds we
need to sort of have some idea of how
things get created impact the initial
time and we want to keep that as close
as possible to how we pack things
runtime because you don't want a lot of
variability there but it's just
something we haven't thought through yet
so we don't really you know I I don't
really want to jump into it if I don't
have to right now I'd rather have it
wait for a little while
all right so if this is the add Monstar
code you can see that we're setting the
standing on here but I'm just I'm
assuming that when we call an entity
we're ending up in a situation where for
some reason it's not backpacking that
properly and right because we're setting
the index and in theory if an index is
set we should be having that that
work so let me take a look at what
happens inside world of CBP when we do a
pack of the entity right we recall is
deleted if there's a sim region if there
isn't so we set the value to zero if
there's no sim region that looks like
the error I think probably what we want
to do is leave the index the same right
what we would want to do instead is say
if simha region you know and get hash
from ID otherwise leave it leave it what
it is I think that's the more correct
interpretation there okay so that was
the problem and you can see now that
that's properly occupying a square so I
believe we can now go back to the way
the brain code was working and and test
this out see if this holds any water
here off we go so there we go
okay and that do it we'll just hop right
off into the middle of nowhere remember
we are not doing
we nullified the collision volume so
there's nothing to stop them from from
hopping hopping along so that's exactly
what we wanted and that's great
now not a very interesting Monstar it's
true but you know that's okay we're not
really trying to make a particular
interesting model star at this point
inside the code in an handmade world
mode I would like there to be a X
entropy I would like there to be a
random series that's like game entropy
that I can draw from
I don't know that we really need those
two things to be separate but for now
I'm going to say that we're going to
keep them separate so when we initialize
effects entropy we're also going to
initialize game entropy and the other
thing too is I feel like when we do the
series here we do random series here I
think we want that to be the game
entropy that that's coming from so we're
gonna want to do something like this is
actually you know I guess we could just
do serious but say random serious
serious equals world mode game entropy
like so okay and so now what's I have a
source of entropy there what I can do is
I can make this be a sort of random
thing where we just say hey whatever the
world mode is that game entropy I'm
gonna make it so that we can hop in any
direction that we want and oops that's
not what I wanted I wanted to random
bilateral right just kind of get that so
that that Delta is is meaningful now
when we update brains I don't know that
we passed the world node it looks like
we don't I don't know what we do with
the game State I guess we get the
controller's from that but I would like
that world mode here to be passed I
don't know what it's actually called
what is that called game world mode I
know why it's called game world mode
should be completely honest with you or
why we don't know what that is it's game
world mode not defined when we have
handmade brain CPP what are you talking
about it's right there dude
when does this get an itch what what
what are you saying
handmade NH world mode world mode is
their brain dot H is here but that's ok
because this is brain dot CPP so world
mode is right there
brain dot CPP is here how is it not been
defined yet does someone want explain
that to me
somebody's gonna have to swing that to
me I can tell you that hmm let's see
here did we include this somewhere we
should not have let's find out Sousa 9
who is actually I guess that doesn't
really help me now I really wish the
compiler would just tell me who included
what but of course that that's not on
the table alright so inside world mood
when I'm calling acute brain I should
have a game world mood world mode and I
do I'm gonna pass it here an ox figure
out why I can't actually use that like
what's the deal yeah so it thinks that's
an undefined type so somehow my world
load H is not actually taking effect
right it's just not even happening and
it I thought that it was right here and
it is right there's my world mode H and
so that should be included right here
before handmade brain dot CPP so I
literally have no idea why that wouldn't
be included so let's find out is
handmade world mode getting included
before hand
yes it is so I must just be missing
something game world mode brain dot CPP
is a game mode world and I'm just like
reading it backwards ha amazing why do
we call the file world's mode if it's
called mode world do we have an
explanation for that anyone anyone I
mean that just does not make a lot of
sense to me you know I'm saying
III do not understand why we would have
done that it's just kind of dumb but oh
well what are you gonna do who knows I'm
just gonna kick back on you some cheesy
poof's really do you like the best plan
those let be someone else's problem you
know Sam
your lies can't be bothered anyway um so
yeah this is now like I said starting to
work basically the way that I want it to
work which is to say that you know now
inside a brain we can just say oh we
want you to hop from here to here and
then the the underlying code just takes
care of making sure that that happens
and so that's fine at this point it
should also be the case that since
that's occupying a square we should not
have any more problems with you know
basically with it running in running
into it essentially we should not be
allowed to move where it can move in
theory and it should not be able to move
where where we are either because you
know because we did two transactional
Square stuff and that does appear to be
true right
that's kind of fast look too fast
all right um okay so there's a monster
doing whatever that is supposed to be I
have no idea it's like a mom start with
its head cut off which is basically
exactly what it is I suppose and so yeah
I would say that just for the not
because there's any reason that we have
to do this right now for any particular
purpose but I think when we add room we
should also like not add like we should
not put those point those ground points
down in places where they can't actually
be or we should make sure that trees
occupy them right and I think probably
what we want to do is just have trees
occupy them so we probably want to do
something like you know again not really
I don't want to go too far down this
route but I just feel like we might as
well not like have it be totally broken
for right now when we add a standard
room I'm just gonna say like you know
just do something stupid like okay you
know a standard room when you add the
standard room there's gonna be this
thing that's like okay you know how many
things are there in the standard room
there's gonna be like a traversable
reference for the standard room that's
like you know ground and there's you
know however many there are so there's
what 17 across and I guess well I guess
we'd probably want to access it in what
looks like a good what looks right to us
which is of course the wrong way round
thanks to sees the way they do their
array stuff but we'll say seventeen by
nine and then we'll just in here say
okay when we make this reversible
reference we'll bank the traversable
reference and just say that the standard
room that we're creating is going to
have
all of its points specified here hereby
so we'll say like alright the offset why
it's offset X plus 8 and the offset y
plus 4 we'll set that standing on and
that way we can have this thing be like
oh yeah I wanted to do an ad Monstar you
know what I could also do I could do
this and again this is not good
I mean this is not what we should do
eventually but I just for now I feel
like we might as well just hack it in so
that we can play with it and not have to
care so I could just say let go okay you
know room P I want it at you know I
don't know that 3/4 or something and
it's just the same thing here room
around or something like that
oops
and so inside here we could do this at
the end now
and we should still get our little
monster are freaking out right and then
when I go down and do ad standard room
down here I could do it now where I say
like okay you know the room gets added
here and then the Monstar
it gets added at this location right
what that would allow me to do later is
when I'm actually calling ad on anything
else like when I do ad wall for example
what I can do is I can actually go in
there and take the actual points and
have the the the trees or the walls or
whatever we're making occupy those
squares now you may ask and it's a fair
question why wouldn't I just not create
a traversable there rather than creating
a traversable and sticking something on
it and the answer is we may want
destructible walls we may want to be
able to move trees by like burning them
or moving them or digging them up or who
knows what so I think we want to create
traversable everywhere you could ever
conceivably stand and then just put
stuff on them and the only place we
wouldn't create diverse those are places
you can never go like in the middle of a
mountain or something an undeveloped and
I think we would just always say yeah
you can stand here if you can move the
stuff that's in the way so if I was
gonna do that when I do an ad wall I
want to do the ad wall a little bit
differently now and in fact this AB
style X stuff is not super necessary
anymore to a certain extent this for
loop could actually be over the things
that are in the room structure so I
could do like a ray count
room p0r for the Y and then you know a
ray count room P for the X and then
instead of these abs is I could switch
these two just using you know what this
has got to go right now we don't have
stairs I could switch these two just
using the p-value so I just say like oh
okay probably the rest of this stuff
still works all right
but the AB style stuff can come out ad
wall and stuff can be like this and then
the p-value can just be world you know
what is it world position he can just be
room P tile X Y right so then we just
have to make ad well do the same work
the same way we were doing before where
we pass in a world position instead of
passing in like weird stuff like this
and and then we just get rid of that
right so now in theory I think we'd have
the same thing we had before hopefully
and we do so that's good and so then all
I need to do is now say well when we
have the wall will also pass like we
were doing before the traversal
reference that the wall is standing on
and then of course since the wall is
standing on it it's a simple matter of
just saying oh here the entities occupy
you know occupation is there then all we
have to do is say like this that we pull
out the traversal reference
so now in theory those trees will occupy
those squares and I believe that no one
will be able to hop there and as you can
see it already seems to have worked
nicely
in that the the Monstar is now confined
to that location now you'll note that we
still have a little bit of work to do
which is to say you can kind of see that
I'm able to pass through anything we're
yet it's occupying that but I can pass
to something beyond it and the reason
for that is we don't currently have any
notion of how far you could hop so we
can just make you hop straight straight
over anything I could stretch
arbitrarily far and hop now I don't know
what we want to do about that right I
don't know what the maximum hop distance
should be or anything like that
I suspect we should just set it to be
some hop value that is whatever the
diamond is that you can hop inside of
but I don't actually know if that's
correct
like for example should there be a
collision point here that I can't you
know that my head hits is that a thing
that should happen I don't know right we
have that capability and certainly I can
turn that on
in fact it's trivial we already had it
right in fact where is it here so if I
turn the collision on for one of these
one of these dudes here where I just say
like oh yeah we'll still have the hero
and have a collision on it right then
when I run through here I've got a
collision box and so I can't right I
can't go any further you know and is
that the right solution I don't know
because there's like there's two ways
that we can choose to approach that
problem I'm not sure about that yet I
have a feeling that I shouldn't bother
with that like I have a feeling that
what we should probably do is make
collision not be for anything other than
actually reacting to things
like when things hit each other or
whatever that's my guess but I don't
know who knows all right um so I guess
one way to think about that would be
that well the head is actually a floatie
is actually a floaty thing right um you
know what that reminds me I wanted to go
in and see why we get sticking now like
we get a lot of sticking you can see
that the head sticks in a nasty way and
I assume that's because when we when we
we had monkey with the controller code I
think ID or rather when we composite
bill that code I think I didn't really
go through and finish making all this
stuff work correctly together so I would
like to see what's going on there so
let's take a look so the parts we have
here are like inside the brain here oh
one thing we do is we say all right if
it's analog you know what I was thinking
- I don't think we need to check for
deletion and the reason for that is that
brains run up front so I think we can
avoid doing that famous last words
so anyway when we get out the control
stuff here you can see us doing this
setting the uptick on hero DDP stuff and
then we come through and this is just
was the weird like swap code we tried
nothing and particularly important then
we do this stuff here where we you know
what I don't know why we've got change
volume and all that stuff on here
is d sword being used right now yet is a
little bit so I'm gonna leave D sword in
there but I mean get rid of this change
line calls we then have this ad I don't
know that we want that anymore that's
not super necessary although I don't
really know why oh we deleted it because
also because we now have that spacebar
was like for swapping stuff right so
let's get rid of that we've got our
recenter timer that is clamping that's
the does the countdown clamping and
where does the recenter timer actually
get used the recenter timer gets used up
here so ya know what that should be
doing reset your timer equals recenter
and then recenter timer counts down the
center timer gets used here i guess and
i think we don't want to decrement it on
the same time it's used so it's probably
something like that it's probably a
little bit better
alright so i don't know that get closest
traversable for the head i don't know
why we're doing that check that doesn't
seem to be all that relevant that get
closest traversable that seems to be
more well i don't know we'll see
anyway we get the closest p for that we
check to see what their whether or the
timer is up or not and if the timer is
not up then we're going to do well
timer is up then we're gonna do this
stuff right square DDPs less than 0.1
then we take the DDP we'll see if we'd
do a spring on the head in that along
that axis whatever the axis is and no
push is determined if the Khan hero's
DDP right is is less than 0.1 so if
you're not pushing in any direction then
no push is active so if there's no push
before the timer is up in this
particular direction doesn't have
anything happening on it then off you go
right so it seems like what's happening
here is I don't feel like no push is
working properly so how is that working
if yeah I think what I really should do
probably honestly is not speculate about
this I would rather just do a debug out
here so I'm just gonna say like hey why
don't you tell me debug boolean don't we
have a debug bool something like that
there it is I'm gonna say that I just
want to see these things so I can see
when no push is getting set and all that
sort of jazz so let's take a look so
there's timer is up and there's no push
so as you can see timer is up appears to
be working pretty well right and
honestly
so there's I mean there's the case
happening the bad case happening timer
is up was true which is correct
but no push is false so we should not be
clamping anything while no push is false
oh well we would if the DDP if that
particular element was less than zero
once so what I should probably also do
is do a debug value of DDP - so I can
look at that as well so there it is and
you know so it's negative one that
should easily prevent us from applying
this stuff here and you know what I can
I can make this a little bit more
explicit as well I could do something
like you know like this
so this will record whether we tried to
recenter and then I can just say like oh
why don't you tell me each of these so I
can see if you are or aren't doing it
right so yeah I mean it looks pretty
obviously like we are not recenter in it
it's Reese entering the two that it
should be and it's not resetting the one
that it shouldn't be so why is my dude
slowing down and does it have to do with
the head movement spec junk again which
was the culprit last time we had an
unusual error like this so should
probably go in there and take a look at
that but yeah in fact I probably should
do that right now when we do DDP we
initialize its Khan hero then we put it
into here right I guess I could also see
what the heads actual code does in the
world mode let's take a look so that
stuff doesn't get doesn't get messed
with anywhere right it's it's strictly
half getting called in here and so let's
see what happens inside move entity so
we say if unit max accel vector is true
then we do that that's sort of unifying
I'm going to say we don't ever want that
because we we are doing that ourselves
right and in there
we don't modify the DDP otherwise but we
do modify it by the speed right and that
seems fine speed and drag should still
be allowed to take effect that shouldn't
be a problem okay
let's take a look now that's interesting
so this is basically saying that an
entity somehow got going so fast that it
was in danger of violating the total
speed how did that happen
Wow the DDP with 72 per second although
it's got drag on it so I'm not sure that
that necessarily matters right let me
take a look here and just to be clear
also I mean we do clear DDP right that's
how that works
so DDP comes in should come in at zero
and we should never have anything other
than zero so when we set it here it
should always be set to something pretty
reasonable
similarly when we're calling it here if
the Kon hero
DDP how was that acceleration ever
plausible
I guess the spring itself would have had
to have created that result right
and furthermore I don't really know
about any effect why do we want any of
these things we really don't want it to
modify anything in that in that code
right I guess we do want some drag
that's kind of fun
all right so essentially we're
multiplying whatever our acceleration is
by 30 and we're adding a certain amount
of drag I don't think that's a good idea
because this already has the drag in it
right and so I think what we would
rather do all of this stuff really wants
to be considered together right so I
think having that sim region movement
code be a thing is just kind of dumb and
I think maybe since this has caused so
many problems I'm just gonna get rid of
it I don't think it's good anymore
right so I'm gonna get rid of that and
I'm going to say that move speck is just
not a thing right and so we'll handle
that outside if we want that if that's
something that we want and and we'll
we'll deal with dragon those sorts of
things in in sort of a different way so
take a look at this here
drag is the only thing in there
so let's see come out of this and I'm
gonna put this here for the moment
but we're probably gonna move this in a
second in fact I probably leave this now
so this is the well I don't know are we
gonna move it or we're gonna leave it so
this should be the only place with
errors now right except for the movement
code I don't know why this is jumping to
the wrong place okay so this movement
spec can go away and furthermore that
means entities don't have to have a
movements back
and I'm gonna get through all of that
out goodbye for you as well
okay so now the state that we should be
in is the hopper should still be able to
hop around right and but I can't move
the head because at the moment now we're
not actually applying the the DDP so now
let's go in here
to the part where we are actually doing
that and let's restore some of that code
so in here we'd say like okay we've got
you know we we figure out what's going
on here in terms of what the in terms of
what we think should be happening this
is again not this is so you can sort of
see why I don't didn't like the way that
was coupled before because what's
happening here is we have two things
going on there's how much you wanted to
move right there's the attempted move by
the player that's the thing that should
actually be subject to the unit max
acceleration right but then we've got
the Reis entering force and the Reis
entering force should have nothing to do
with that right there a centering force
is not something that the player is
using to move that's pulling the player
back and so so what we want here I think
is we want to say okay there's the con
hero DDP and the con hero DDP is the
thing that's actually going to get that
that sort of truncation so when we come
through here we're gonna say all right
let's apply that max acceleration right
here so we'll just say like you know
assuming that it's it's greater than one
will will undo it right that makes sense
is there a DDP regular no this will just
become DDP right so we create the DDP we
make sure that it's now unit length so
that you don't go faster on a diagonal
then you do like left and right you know
that that's all we're really trying to
do there and then we
can go ahead and do the recenter encode
they're a century code could do whatever
it wants so it's allowed to exceed that
maximum because it's going to be pulling
you back towards a location you should
be at so we're not going to touch that
we're not going to ma x a movement speed
here rather we're going to multiply by a
movement speed up here I think right so
what we would do is say like GDP x
equals movement speed right and movement
speed plus 30 so now we properly create
a directional vector we multiply that
direction of vector by your movement
speed to get the requested amount we
adjust that acceleration by forces that
are attempting to do other things to you
and similarly drag this this is the drag
right here already factored in right and
so what we would want to do here is
probably say the drag is always gonna be
factored in a little so if you're not
putting that drag in click this drag in
right you know I'm saying so and you can
see now why I want this out here is
because I feel like for gameplay tuning
purposes especially on the player but
possibly on everything we're gonna want
to create these very organic kind of
weird not particularly mathematically
rigorous played with till it felt right
kinds of things and so you know you want
to make sure that that is what you can
do and you're not forced to do something
that's not the proper amount the proper
format I should say all right so finally
we'll assign that DDP get all this we do
probably want to look into an OD at some
point for the drag coefficients but
we'll leave that for now and then in
here so this is going to be DDP
EEE is just going to be equal to the
negative drag times the DP alright uh
moving along alright so now that that's
cleaned up a little bit I can get back
to the debugging that I was doing before
mr. AMD card does not want it down with
the textures all right there we go
all right so let's see where was I
so DDP is equal to Clio DDP we then take
the length of it and assuming that's
greater than 1 we normalize it out to 1
we multiply it by the movement speed and
then we we apply the drag wait is that
correct one second
is that too much drag drag used to be
eight and it's on the DP so I feel like
that should be okay but if I actually
look at what's going on there I can't
move the head at all when that's on so
what am I missing
somehow that's still that's applying too
much drag and I don't know oh well No
I don't feel like that should be
creating as impossible and move it's
such an impediment to movement as it is
but maybe I'm wrong about that maybe I'm
not thinking about that correctly if we
reduce the drag force considerably can I
remove it oh yeah
I just realized a few things first of
all these DD Peas
if it's new push I want to add this
force in not equals it so there we go
there's that there we go
and now we seem to have also fixed the
bug so that is good as well
all right so I think that was most of
what I want to do there we have a couple
minutes left like three minutes left so
I could go back and get the familiar
head float we could start working on
that as well let me pull out some of
these debug code here we don't really
need it at the moment
and we'll just leave that like this all
right so in the familiar code first of
all we have to create one which we set
ourselves up to do but did not actually
do so in here would be like okay you
know add a familiar and the familiar
would be you know at room P for three
rounds or three and I'll compile that
and then we just have to make a familiar
take the p value it like it was before
position and now this sort is is going
to be important it's probably not
obvious as to why at first but this kind
of brings up a sort of another point
which is we're gonna have to just decide
at some point how we want to deal with
floating objects in terms of occupying
squares right
so we'll see how that goes so there's
the familiar
it's occupying that square so my body
cannot go in there we still don't have
it inside it again like what I what we
want to do with the head precisely but
that'll come a little bit later but now
we want it to this the familiar head to
be able to move as well and in order to
do that I think you know we're gonna
have to have a notion here first of all
you know we should probably do what I
said before which is the enemy flags
with like collides and movable and
deleted in that stuff
I think movable I was suggesting this no
longer necessary and I think that's
probably true so I'm gonna go ahead and
say that that moveable is not necessary
I think collides also I don't really
know how necessary that is anymore
either
but we'll leave it in for now because
we'll have to think about how we want
that to be handled I guess so let let's
just continue remove these and that
should do that right yeah I mean in some
sense we should just be able to say like
if the DDP if it's requested a move
we'll move it for now right otherwise we
won't try and move it so yeah getting a
little closer and tomorrow I guess we'll
get up tomorrow but Monday we'll get the
familiar going ok time for Q&amp;A
if you have questions go ahead put them
in to the chat box
Gaston 5-yr the textures not Dowling
probably sense well if you remember a
few episodes back I may be 40 40 or 50
episodes back when we did texture down
those we tried doing multi-threaded
texture downloads which were supposedly
supposed to work but they don't work
reliably and so eventually we have to go
back and stop doing that because it just
doesn't work it usually works on this
particular machine but it does not work
let me put it this way
it sometimes fails on this machine but
it fails even more frequently on other
machines so it's definitely not an okay
thing to be doing so we won't we won't
be doing that in the we won't be doing
any multi coated texture downloads in
the final game so why did this isn't to
make the game grid-based that's a design
decision so not really a topic for the
stream there were sirens earlier it's
man and tree back at it again we are not
really that close to man in tree here so
it's you know it's it's unlikely however
maybe he's in a different tree this time
in which case it could be closer to her
I suppose
skull crack
do you think even after getting a
four-year degree in M I s do I know what
M is is ally I know what M is is can you
tell me what M is is long brilliant I
guess technically if the gameplay is
centered around tiles and facing
direction you wouldn't necessarily need
collision detection so we definitely
need the collision detection to remain
in and the reason for that is we do need
to know when people hit each other with
projectiles and other things like that
so and like I said the head moves freely
so basically the game system does not
can't be tile based right it's only the
movement of the body pieces that is tile
based but the rest still has to operate
continuously so you know we can't get
rid of collision detection it's got to
stay in we just may never use it for
movement right but we will use it for
other things any other programming
questions
to terrace what are the 18 threads that
run with the game uh so I don't know if
we set a max thread count right now but
I can well I could tell you a couple
things first of all you don't really
need to ever ask assuming that you're
running if you in order to see those
threads you presumably would know you
would be running on you must be running
it on your machine and seeing it so if
you have it it's pretty easy to just say
like okay let me see what threads are
being used right so here's all our
threads and as you can see there's
really only two threads that do anything
and then the rest of the threads are
just there for background asset loading
so I can have some of them do some stuff
and you could see you saw them do
something there right I don't know if we
could find that usage again but there it
is and you can see that that's just like
asking the disk to please get us some
some art assets so there's two
background loading threads and there's
oh you know what I lied this is not two
threads this is showing you one thread
and then usage inside the thread so this
is actually just three threads to work
the thread that does all the game stuff
and the to loading threads right but
that's only if you're not running with
the software rasterizer
so if you decide not to use opengl and
you use the thing where we render
everything then you'll get a lot more so
if I then allow it to start if I unpause
right you can see that what actually
happens is there's a bunch of work being
done on the separate threads and this is
just their rendering right and that red
breeze going to be bit slow because this
is a compiled of debug probe right now
and it actually is significantly faster
and release so you generally don't want
to turn the software render on if you're
not gonna compile in debug mode but you
can see that these are the threads that
are that we're actually using so here we
still got one main game thread which
also does render work
in the render its which is right here
but then we also we did six threads of
rendering because this is a machine that
has like a bunch of cores right and then
there's still those two background
loading threads so that's our actual
threads in addition to those threads
there's usually Windows creates a bunch
of crap threads for you unfortunately
and there's really not much you can do
about that that's just like the way life
is and you can see those threads in here
if I do break all you can see those
threads in here here's our threads right
and our main thread but then it just
creates all this other garbage right and
a lot of it's like here's the sound
playing thread right and the this is
these are multi medias and sound like
the sound threads
here's another sound thread another
sound thread now why you need that many
threads to play sound I don't know cuz
ring the fact that we only open one
output channel for sound but you know
somebody thought that was a good idea
and then in here you know we're in the
kernel I don't know what these are doing
I suspect they have some kind of
something to do with some service but
you know without further information we
could try to load symbols from the
symbol Server Microsoft symbol server
and I don't know if it'll do that there
was a way to automatically do that but I
don't know and then we could have a
little bit more idea what's going on
this one right here is the AMD driver
thread right you can see it's an api's
driver so that's a thread for their
driver but that's that's life in Windows
so basically we asked for these threads
so that we could actually use all the
cores of the machine or at least a
significant number of the cores but we
leave some unused so that Open
Broadcasting System has some to use for
streaming so we don't actually open as
many as we would normally if you were
just running the game by itself but then
you know windows kind of spans us with a
ton of threads
does that answer the question what is
going to replace the Graham's flat
system just different types and seamless
textures well I worked at how the game
actually is supposed to look and it is
not it does not want seamless it's it's
got a specific visual design and the
ground slats are just not appropriate
that make sense
pokey why don't you program any UNIX
based OS we've answered that question a
bunch of times but since there's no
other questions I'll just answer it
again
this is why I'm obviously a game
programmer so in order to make a living
you you need to program on operating
systems where people actually buy games
and there you go so less than 1% of all
games are played on Linux so it's really
not it's really not feasible to be you
know primarily concern yourself with
Linux because you know you're not really
um you're not really I don't want to
eating your own dog food but I mean you
want to be the most familiar with the
platform that the gamers are actually
using you don't want to like you know be
super familiar with with Linux and have
no idea how Windows works and then you
know you ship on Windows and you have
all these bugs and you can't fix them
and people are complaining about your
game constantly on Steam and all these
seem forums and all that stuff right so
you know if you're pretty game you've
got a program on Windows first and
foremost there's a there's a bunch of
other reasons not to use Linux
separately and those have to do with the
low quality of tools for game
development on that platform and I
realize that's a very difficult thing
sometimes for people to grapple with
because they maybe are used to web
programming where a lot of the tools are
better on Linux than they are on Windows
right and so if you're used to
administering web servers or stuff like
that you may be like well it's way
easier to program online
and windows or something but the
opposites true like most game tools are
on Windows most things work better on
Windows for pro game programming because
it's the primary platform that games are
programmed on and so you take a big hit
going to Linux as well specifically with
respect to debugging GPU stuff which you
know a web server cares not at all about
GPUs but a game cares a great deal and
that's a problem I would prefer that
that was not the case I don't really
like have being so having to be so
closely coupled to Windows and so I feel
like it's not good that what I'm saying
is true but you have to respect the fact
that it is right you just have to
respect the fact that that is the truth
of the situation and so you know it's
not great it's not what I would like I
would like I would love it a 50% of
games were sold on Linux or something
that would be fantastic but that's just
not the reality of it so eventually you
know maybe we can hope that someday it's
not it's not the same as it is now but
that's that is the situation
I'm destroyed why wouldn't
multi-threading work all that well
complications limitations what does that
mean why wouldn't multi-threading work
all that well multi-threading does work
well it works well for us I'm not sure
what you mean
Casta five how did you manage to make
things work in Windows when you started
your career given that MSDN at least now
is negligible or unreliable or both well
I guess what I would say is two things
one is that Microsoft used to have a
saner API set right like Microsoft is so
far off the rails API wise now that it's
yeah if you came to it now you'd be like
I have no idea what's going on just like
oh we required Windows RT compliant
thread pool base thing that has to be
written in C sure and you're just like I
have no idea what's going on yeah it's
it's a nightmare now that's just they're
off the rails they're never coming back
what can you do when I first started
window spring that wasn't true there was
just the win32 api it's not a great API
but it's sane right it's like you can
its tractable its small enough that you
could learn it was not this giant
splatter of garbage that's just smeared
all over the walls like some kind of you
know lunatic asylum
where they're trying to like you know
keep the poop from from sticking to the
padded cell or whatever right like it is
now so it was much more sane and the
other thing was MSDN was a lot more
accurate and well-maintained at that
time as well it came on a like CD or
whatever you could put in your computer
and read and it wasn't bad you know it
was pretty kept pretty up to date and
like I said there just weren't that many
API so you could learn them so I
wouldn't say that I did anything special
to be able to learn this stuff I would
say that I just was in an environment
and at a time when it was tractable to
learn how to program Windows and
thankfully you can still program it the
way that I learned even today you don't
have to use all their new crappy crap
unfortunately
that may not be true forever you know
one of the horror of horrific things is
you know Windows or Microsoft seems to
be doing their best to try and kill off
Windows as a viable gaming platform by
doing ridiculous stuff like requiring
you to use weird api's or tying stuff to
the Windows Store or god knows what you
know maybe they'll succeed and the way
that we're programming Windows on him a
hero will go away at some point I just
really hope not because it's at least
tractable and you can ship a reasonable
product on it whereas the new stuff they
ship is completely unusable as far as
I'm concerned I'm just right you said
something about the multi thing to be
funky Oh what I was saying is that
downloading textures in OpenGL from a
different thread than the thread you're
rendering on that's the thing it's not
multi-threading in general
multi-threading in general is fine it's
OpenGL context having to OpenGL context
and using them in a multi-threaded way
just doesn't seem to work reliably it's
not a big deal it's it's not something
that's gonna affect us hugely in any way
really it's that's all
do you have positive or negative
thoughts when it comes to learning and
using Python for building applications I
don't really have any thoughts at all I
don't use Python so
and the middle you said dynasty and came
on to cities technically MSDN came on a
lot of CDs I guess used to get like this
big stack I don't remember how many of
them were the documentation a lot of
them were like the checked build of
Windows or whatever if they had debug
built in and stuff like that I don't
remember how many were actually the the
the CDs right we're actually the docs so
all right all good ticket for us which
purveyors do you use regularly just C
and C++ that's it
all right
alright thanks for joining me for
another episode of hand made here oh
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to follow along at
home of course you can pre-order the
game on and made here org and it comes
with a source code if you want to play
around with it in the comfort of your
own computing environment we have a
forum site you can go to if you want to
ask questions we have a patreon page you
can go to if you want support the video
series we have a schedule bot who will
tweak the schedule at you if you want to
know when the series gonna be live and
we have an episode guide for catching a
fun past episodes if you want to see
when we wrote the software renderer or
when we did the debug system or whatever
you can go over there and check it out
that's about it I will be back here next
week check the schedule bot four times
if you are interested in that until then
have fun programming this weekend and I
will see you guys on the Internet take
it easy everyone