okay hello everyone and welcome handmade
hero show recode a complete game live on
stream we are just debugging the stuff
we wrote yesterday which is Huffman
decoder well it's two things actually
it's a Huffman it's the thing that
builds Huffman tables based on the PNG
specs statement of how Huffman table
should be built and then it's a Huffman
decoder for those Huffman tables I of
course don't know anything about the PNG
spec so I am literally flying blind here
just reading the spec but I did want to
try to do it that way once first just so
we could have one on stream where we go
from the spec the only other time I
think we ever did any file reading it
was a BMP and I had read BMP files
before also they're very simple they
don't have that much of a spec so we
never did a whole lot in terms of trying
to get a spec working so I thought I'd
at least try for a little while before
looking at someone else's PNG reading
code to see how far I could get just
from the spec the spec is not great I
will say it doesn't really talk about
things I would like it to talk about in
a number of places and again that's
really mostly because P&amp;G just refers to
the deflate spec and the deflate spec
kind of doesn't really say everything
that I would want it to say about like
Indian this and stuff like that but
they're not awful I've read some pretty
bad specs in the past ones where I think
you might say you have no hope of
actually using the spec to decode the
thing and I've had to really just kind
of black box it and do a lot of like
poking and prodding so this is not that
kind of spec this is still a decent spec
it's just not you know a great one we're
you know where anybody can just show up
and write it you kind of need a little
bit of finesse on this one so I'm not
really looking forward to this debugging
process cause I do think it'll be a
little bit laborious but it's certainly
better than a lot of specs out there so
you know consider this a
middle-of-the-road kind of an experience
this is definitely you can get a lot
worse than what we're about to do all
right so
if you remember where we left off we
just left off trying to figure out how
we would sort of go about knowing
whether we have this right at all and so
if we come back to sort of the beginning
here and just walk a little bit through
the code I kind of want to explain how
we're sort of approaching this here now
we read an AI bat header out of the PNG
that well actually I should say we read
all the AI datte headers out of the PNG
and we don't really do anything with
them we just chain them together into
sort of a linked list that we can then
traverse when we wish to read them later
now the reason that I did that is
because I wasn't super sure that all
writers would follow the thing that was
in the spec the thing that's in the spec
specifically states that I that chunks
have to come one right after another
that's exactly the kind of thing that I
don't expect all writers to follow
because writers do all kinds of crazy
stuff so I just figured it's easy enough
for us to just remember where these are
and then traverse through them later
that way if someone does hand as a PNG
where the IDA chunks aren't contiguous
we can handle it plus since we already
know that there's this gunk in between
them we know we would have had to do
work to chain them together anyway so
it's pretty straightforward to just go
ahead and build the linked list then
walk back through them since we read the
whole file as a chunk anyway it's not
like we're issuing extra reads Plus this
isn't going to be a fast PNG reader
either way because we're doing bit at a
time reading here which is not
particularly efficient so just in
general this is I think fine it's a more
flexible way to do it and we're not
going for a world record here or even a
medium record so anyway when we get here
to look at the INA chunks what we are
looking at is some basic startup
information and the way that we're
consuming bits outside of the Huffman I
think is correct the reason I say that
is because this part looks sensible to
us we are getting a reasonable B final
in a reasonable B type when we read in
the first and then second third bits to
build those two values so I think our
assumption and also the spec said they
that we are looking at LS be like least
significant bit at a time bit
consumption is correct for everything
outside the Huffman codes and so when we
look through this part I feel like that
probably worked okay I do say probably
worked okay because I don't really know
but I think there's a chance that this
part is working correctly and then we
don't need to look at it too much after
that
so what we can see here when we get down
to the B type 2 which is what I expected
to see
turns out we will need to do this one
probably because as as Martins pointed
out yesterday although I misread the
spec on PNG when it when I thought they
were saying that deflate would only ever
use B type 2 I think they are actually
saying that they can use B type 2 or B
type 1 I think I think Martin's was
absolutely right about that when we went
back and looked at the section 10 one of
the spec it did seem to say that so for
right now though we're only looking at B
type twos we don't have any data it's in
B type one so we just want to get B type
two working B type one should in theory
be basically the same it's just instead
of doing these reads we would proceed
our Huffman tables with stuff that we
already know like basically hard-coded
data from the spec that we just put in
right so that's not going to be a huge
deal to support B type one after we get
B type two working it should be
relatively straightforward but getting B
type two working is going to be it's
gonna be a grind so in here what I'm so
what I'm trying to get at on the bit
consumption thing is I believe these
values are sensible then like I think
this you know 29 29 14 is not a
unreasonable set of values to get these
are basically the huffman table set up
values that were like they're just
counts of stuff that we're supposed to
get I think those are reasonable which
again is just I think we're seeing the
bit reading happening okay here but I
don't know one of
that one of the really bad parts about
compressed data so this is sort of just
a philosophical point is that compressed
data the better the compression scheme
the less possibility there is for
clearly erroneous output if you imagine
something that's an image compressor
right it's producing an output stream
and that output stream when you process
it is supposed to produce images right
well any possible way you can have
nonsensical data in that output stream
that does not lead to a correct image is
effectively wasted information inside
that bit stream right so the better and
better a compressor gets the more likely
you are to always see something that
could be reasonable in the bit stream
because all things that could show up in
the bit stream will be reasonable right
so you usually end up in this situation
where once you get into things like when
I'm only reading five bits at a time
it's pretty hard to get a ridiculous
value I can't get four billion coming
out of a five bit read/write because if
I got five billion four billion coming
out of a five bit read something really
bad has happened but if we'd actually
read an entire u-32 from the data stream
in a fattie non compressed format and we
saw four billion that's a real good
clear indicator that we screwed up the
parsing further upstream and we know
where to start looking for our error
right so one of the big problems with
compressed data and it's not a problem
in the sense that somehow they're bad
it's just for development purposes when
you're writing the decoder for a
compressed stream knowing when you
screwed up gets much harder because you
don't actually know whether a value is
reasonable or not because most of them
will look reasonable even if they aren't
that's just what happens when you can
only read values from 0 to 32 they're
all probably reasonable right so that's
sort of what goes on there right ok
so if we keep going forwards down down
through this process again no real way
to know whether our h.glenn team
got set up correctly but it looks again
like something that could plausibly have
happened right you know is it is it
ironclad proof that this got read
correctly absolutely not
is it obviously wrong no right so I feel
like this h.glenn table could be okay
all right
so we know that these H this part of the
the huffman table built here where we
have eight bits worth of possible
Huffman code right that we know because
basically every symbol that we read
could be encoded in up to eight bits
that was just the determination from
looking at what these values could come
out to be if that makes sense
basically the the HDL end table here
that we build our codes for seven here
is sort of on the high end you can't
have like a nine or ten bit value in
these code lengths and the way that we
know that is because when we actually
read these bits in we're only reading in
three bits for the length so even if the
all the bits are set we can never really
get to eight bits of code length now why
didn't they just add one to it so we can
get to eight bits of code length the
reason is because they do need zero
because they specifically said in the
spec that the h.glenn table will contain
zeros in the places where things aren't
used so we know that we're zero to seven
number of bits so that means that in
here eight bits of Huffman is more than
enough to do it
in fact now I think about it seven bits
of Huffman is really more than enough to
do it we don't actually need the eight
so that's actually not necessary this is
this doesn't affect our behavior in the
code at all because let me go ahead and
switch over to one that's not have my
head in the way
we can set this number to really
anything and it just makes our table
bigger but we don't actually need 8 bits
because if the longest code sequence we
could see is 7 bits long then I think we
don't ever really need the 8 there so I
think technically and let me just double
check that that's true I think
technically we'd be fine through the
compute half Minh there we would never
hit an assertion at 7 because these only
reading 3 bits and we can never have a
code length of of 8 so anyway we then
have the the compute - stuff which I'm
gonna go ahead and step into here I
don't know why I can't set a break on
that line we're not compiling in release
mode are we we're into we're in debug
mode I do not know why I cannot why
didn't it let me set a breakpoint
I don't know why I wouldn't let me set a
break down that line just Visual Studio
fantasticness I guess anyway if we step
into the compute huffman this is the
part that we wrote yesterday again just
flying blind from the spec I just trying
to suss out what it was telling us in
sear we've got this code length
histogram and all our first loop does is
count the values that we're gonna
actually count how many times we see
each individual code length so when we
get through here as you can see we now
have a histogram that tells us
everything that we saw so you know we've
got three zeros three five threes three
fives four sevens and obviously nothing
up here because the it can't ever hit
eight or above in this particular
Huffman again because it's only a three
bit read so here we initialize that the
zero away to zero and the reason for
that is that we're specifically saying
we're never allocating any codes to
encode things that don't show up so we
clear that one out and we set our next
unused code we then go through here and
what we do here is we each step of the
way sort of assign the Huffman bits to
let me show that there it is a sign the
starting value to each of the huffman
counts so for example four code lengths
count three those are gonna start at
zero and then fours are gonna start at
10 5s gonna start at 28 and what that's
doing is it's just leaving space for
however many of the Huffman's we we saw
right when we say we've seen X number of
threes we need to leave that many
Huffman codes available that many bit
patterns basically available before we
start assigning ones to fours 5 6 and so
on right and again this is us just
following the spec this is basically
what the spec told us to do now we don't
know if we did it right but you know
this wasn't my doing that's just how
they wanted to assign Huffman code so
that's how we're doing it right somebody
was saying we had a less than bug in
here I'm sorry I don't remember ink
valve is saying it may be your I
promised I would look at it but I can't
remember who said it so let me just look
back here it is yeah it was available I
think there is a type typo in the code
you copied from the standard you have a
less than instead of a less than or
equal to we didn't really copy any code
from the standard but we translated code
from the standard in a sense so I'm
assuming this is the part we're talking
about cuz I'm not sure what other part
we copied maybe it's the part later
further down he's talking about cuz I
don't know that there is a less than
here we have some less dense that are
search related but that's probably not
what he meant
so maybe he means the code a little
further out I'm not sure that's that's
yeah I don't know anyway let me finish
going through this code server is on the
same page and then we'll go to the next
one so this part is the part we really
just don't know this is the part where I
kind of just was like I'm not sure what
they mean here so we're kind of just in
like trial and error mode so what they
said was that when you take a code
from the huffman table what you need to
do is the huffman bits unlike all the
rest of the bits are going to come in
with their most significant byte at the
bottom right now I don't know what they
meant by that because there's two ways
that I could believe you to mean that
right
one thing you could have meant was that
you just are writing Huffman codes this
way which means that this routine
already takes that into account and is
assigning codes the way you wanted them
assigned for the way they were read in
right because nothing here says I mean a
Huffman code doesn't have a notion of
most significant that I can like I don't
I'm not a compression guy I don't know
that a Huffman code has anything other
than just first bit right like there's
the bit that comes in first and that bit
tells you whether you keep going on the
Huffman or not sometimes not sometimes
you read two bits in right it depends
how many but those first n bits tell you
whether to like output a symbol or keep
going then the next n bits tell you to
output a symbol or keep going right most
significant I don't know what they meant
by that because there's not a
significant to its part maybe you think
the most significant one is the one that
gets decided on first that would that's
my guess right but I don't know because
that's not really explained so I don't
know so looking through here let's see
if they say it explicitly because it's
been a while since we read this and
let's read it with that in mind because
this was where we've gotten to so given
this rule we can define the Huffman code
for an alphabet just by giving the bit
lengths of the codes for each symbol of
the alphabet in order so that's what
we're processing this is sufficient to
determine the actual codes in our
example the code is completely defined
by the sequence of bit lengths to 133
the following algorithm generates the
codes as integers intended to be read
from most to least significant bit so
oh so I'm assuming that that means is
this is producing the integers the most
significant bit is that comes out of
this is the one that will come first in
the bitstream
that's how I'm interpreting that the
code links are initially in tree land
the codes are produced in tree code
right yes
consider the alphabet abcdefg with bit
length 3 3 3 3 3 to 4 4 your step 1 we
have this I'm just a barman effort right
ok this code okay so I'm assuming that
they're writing this with the most
significant bit here and the Leeson it
again fit here and what they're saying
is this will come first in the bitstream
and then this and then this and then
this right that's what I'm assuming okay
and then on top of that where I'm coming
from with the bit most significantly
significant was the other part in the
deflate spec which was up here somewhere
trust me it was here here we go
that said everything's LSB right up to
the Huffman codes which are sir
suddenly MSB right so the Huffman codes
get read differently from everybody else
that's how I took that to be to be
specifying right okay so I given that
fact our task now the first thing I want
to do you cigaratte whether I actually
constructed the table properly when we
read that part and decided we had to
invert this thing here because this was
sort of as we were working through that
I you know I just said okay let's do a
simple thing in here to reverse the bits
as a test right so as we go through our
entries this will this base index here
that we'll construct I believe the entry
into the Huffman table as if the bits
were read LSB first now why they didn't
write them LSB first I don't know right
it seems to me like if everything else
was LSB why wouldn't you leave the
Huffman says LSB there's must be a
reason for that somewhere I don't know
what it is maybe that's because of my
naivete with compression right I'm not a
compression person so it might just be
that there's like a really good reason
for it and I just don't know what that
reason is maybe it's because if you're
consuming it literally a bit at a time
no I don't know why cuz it seems to me
like the right way to do it is just
right your Huffman generator so that the
least significant bit is the one you
start with it just seems to me like
they've done it backwards like just have
everything LSB and just make your
Huffman's LSB but I yeah I don't know I
maybe I'm just missing the special sauce
there so anyway when I come through here
I've got the base index and I'm gonna
generate the index off of the base index
by flipping the bits around it's not
gonna do anything for zero because
there's a bits are the same at zero
either way there's no such thing as a
most significant at least leave me a bit
when none of the bits are set
so it don't matter but we flip it around
completely and we tested that code and
actually made sure it worked and then
we're just gonna enter our thing into
the huffman table reversed that way when
we see the bits come in we don't
actually have to figure out how to msb
them our table just already flipped
right so again that might be a stupid
way to do this that's just what I did so
that's how this code works and we can
sort of see it working as well if we
just look here the hex though in fact
we've already got it right here so if
you look at the the flipping of these
right you can see that this one because
there's only seven bits per Huffman code
you can see here that the flip doesn't
do anything for those right whereas the
flip four here does it reverses around
that center line right so there's the
flip and yesterday it was flipping the
whole thing that's because I had set the
bit count to eight for some reason now
it's only seven that again shouldn't
affect our reading of the bit stream at
all because the seven or the 8 is just
how many bits we start with so we just
need to flip relative to that when we
look at it because remember we're going
to be seeing the bits coming in the
wrong order so we need to flip them
around so that when we actually look at
them we get the right answers there now
my assumption and I could be very wrong
about this but my assumption is that we
can't actually do just this so what I
because since we don't know how long the
Huffman code is to begin with I'm not
sure we can just flip it like that
without changing the way our bits
streamer actually streams in the bits so
I'm concerned that what we actually have
to do is flip our bit stream around and
read them in that order or have some
other fancy trick there so that's where
we left off yesterday and what I want to
do today now is actually work out on the
blackboard how this has to work whether
I can just flip and put it in the table
or whether I need something fancier than
that so what I want to do is work
through an example basically
to see whether or not the this actually
can be done without changing without
changing the reader into an MSB reader
if that makes sense right okay so
so what we want to look at now is let's
suppose that we have something like the
Huffman codes that we're looking at now
what I want to know is is this table
reverse if I reverse the table entries
is that sufficient or does that produce
wrong results after the first Huffman
code because I confident will produce
the correct results for the first
Huffman code
I don't know that'll produce correct
results for every code thereafter
because the shift be shifting in
behavior may be wrong so that's what I'm
trying to validate here so what we
fundamentally have is we have a buffer
that seven bits long right and that
buffer of seven bits long has been read
in LSB form right so as we read in bits
we read them in and stack them up so we
read in bits that go like this sort of a
thing right and we're looking at the
bottom seven bits of it so we know that
the bit stream was 1 0 1 1 0 1 0 ba ba
blah right we're looking at 1 2 3 4 5 6
7 bits so we're basically just gonna
look at this piece of it and we're gonna
look that up into our Huffman table
right now what we know for example is
let's say that we had two different
Huffman codes that we cared about and
I'm just these are not listen we don't
care that they're Huffman codes right
that doesn't even matter
forget Huffman we just want to look at
bit patterns right so we know that we
had one bit pattern that we cared about
right and it was 1 0 and that coded for
something a right and then we had
another bit pattern let's say that was 1
1 0 and that coded for B so if we were
reading these in most significant byte
format when we look at this and this and
I'll I'll just throw the last one into
that's another 1 0 right what we should
see is this is 1 0 right 1 0 so that's
an a we see 1 1 0 1 1 0 so that's a B
and there's another 1 0 so that's an A
right
just forget enough min that's just what
we thought we should see and
we see it right so now the question is
does the table generation produce the
same result if we just reverse the table
lookup right because what we want is the
thing that literally read it that way
from LSB to MSB and read it in the
opposite order over here
right so it basically said okay pretend
this whole thing was flipped around and
start reading from the most significant
byte down right again I think that's
what the spec was saying to do do not
take this as me saying this is what the
PMG does I have no idea I think that's
what the spec told us to do right so
what's gonna happen I look through the
table I'm gonna look up this seven bit
value right here first of all right and
what I'm gonna find because we reverse
the whole thing right is that our our
table in everywhere where the top bits
are ones up sorry where the bottom bits
are 0 1 because we produced this 0 1
Huffman code right when we were coding
the a well actually that's not true
let me rephrase that let me follow this
through exactly because this may be part
of the problem right so when we pack in
this code ah ah I think I see the
problem I think I already see the
problem glad we did this
when I pack in this code it's said most
significant byte first that means if
it's 1 0 that's the most significant
byte then it comes this then everything
else should have come after that right
meaning it's 1 0 and then anything else
those are least significant bits right
after here after this MSB which is at
the top of this then we flip it around
and put it into the table I didn't
remember to do that what I did when I
put in the bit reverse
right where is that here it is when I
put in the bit reverse I'm still
quitting the arbitrary part at the top
but remember it's supposed to be the
other way round right
so actually the the LSB part is supposed
to be this part here but I put that in
the MSB before flipping so that I think
is wrong that's that is incorrect so
that that is I think that is our problem
well it's a problem anyway so let's fix
that immediately because that is
definitely wrong again unless I'm
completely misunderstanding what's
supposed to happen which is entirely
like okay
so we know how many arbitrary bits there
are so we're gonna or in this entry
index which is the arbitrary bits part
and what we're gonna do is we're gonna
shift up the code part the arbitrary
bits amount right so we're gonna stack
that oops running so we're gonna snack
that part at the top right before we do
we're gonna put the like actual code at
the top so the most employed goes first
then the entry index is the part that's
in the least significant parts then then
we're gonna flip it around so they're
all backwards
right and then off we go does that make
sense
so that's what we're doing there now
since the entry index is arbitrary
really the only thing we'd have to flip
it is really the code and then we could
have packed it that way if but we're
just gonna do it this way so it's all
consistent right so now if we look at
what happens here when we start packing
a particular value which we'll do here
let's just look at it when we start
packing a particular value like this has
16 entries right what we should see is
the high bits should remain the same
right the entire time and only the low
bits vary and that's exactly what's
happening that's the opposite of what we
did last time so again I I think I
messed that up when we threw that in
there that was wrong so alright so
that's it well actually you know what's
interesting
so you notice it worked this time we
never we did not get past this before
right we got an assertion that we hit a
symbol we shouldn't have seen not one of
these one of the huffman decodes so
actually that was a huge bug that we
just fixed so that's great so hey yay
for working that on the blackboard that
told us exactly where we went wrong and
look we actually decompressed the exact
right number of things that's a great
sign that means it looks like we fixed
part of our Huffman decode there okay so
what I don't know now is is this we
don't really know if the rest of our
stuff here has made any sense and this
stuff I think this is all I don't think
we finished this so this all needs to
get I think this all needs to get yeah I
don't think any of this stuff is right
yet that exits after the first block
there right yeah so I don't really think
all of this I don't I don't really know
that any of this was correct i we sort
of put this in here and we need we need
to go back and look at that so so we'll
deal with that a second so at the moment
we do have some reason to believe that
we may be decompressing this properly at
least in a limited sense because now we
are able to complete and we get the
exact number of entries we think we
should get which is a good sign which
allows us to produce our Huffman tables
for the literal distances which we can
then use to decompress the rest of the
stream I just don't know yeah I don't
even remember what the rest of stuff is
I don't even know why we're why are we
exiting here I I guess that was just cuz
we didn't want to keep going I guess I
don't know so let me take that away
because we should be able to now work on
this back part of the routine to see how
we're doing there and that should be
able to allow us to once we get it
working run till the end of the
consuming the right number of bits so
let's get rid of that and see where we
blow up just I'm just curious now
because we should be able to start
working on that okay so you can see here
we've got a there we go you can see here
we've got a bug notice here encoded Len
of of 12,000 there so if we go back up
to there we go if we go back up to here
it looks like this is not quite right so
somehow we did oh well you know what
that might be though the second time
through the loop so let's actually
verify that that's true you see first
yeah so you can see the first time
through the loop we're good the second
time so this code is probably wrong it's
probably not consuming yeah I mean I
don't this just this just doesn't look
done to me so let's just go finish this
part first before we go any further
because I think this is just missing
stuff all right so our goal now is to
get this part to work properly if we
assume this part works properly which we
don't know yet see if we can get this
working properly because if we can't get
this to work properly then that means we
can go through all of the blocks and
actually decompress potentially the
right amount of data which would be a
nice first step towards getting the PNG
working so I'm going to go ahead and
pong back over to the spec here and read
that section so I believe that section
comes from here you can see what this
says here it says read the block header
from the input stream that's what we did
up above if it's store with no
compression we do the basic copy that
was this right I believe and this
this we didn't doesn't look like we
actually did the copy though right
so that copy Len bytes of data to the
output yeah so this right here wants to
actually you know retire this much data
so what we want to do is we want to
start outputting now we didn't write
anything for outputting but we want to
here at the very least we just want to
consume that size so this flush is a
byte this is the thing that basically
says hey let's get rid of any data
that's still in the bit stream from the
Huffman we're gonna read aligned now
this doesn't really need to be consumed
bits this should probably be consumed
size right and it should consume a u16
in fact we've got a consume for this
exactly exactly this right we've got a
thing it can just do consume that so
this will get us our 2u sixteens
that are the Loney and then now what I
don't know is I don't know whether these
lens need to be byte swapped it seems
like that's the Botes operandi here that
the they coming in the wrong order for a
little onion don't quote me on that
but if you look at what has to happen
here whenever we were reading values
that could take on a larger than a byte
value we had to do an Indian swap so I
assume that those values will be Indian
swapped I don't know I'm gonna put an
Indian swap in there for now
I can try to determine that from the
spec but I'm not sure if it's set in the
spec or not if we do do an Indian swap
here it just looks like this
right so if we load a a it's kind can I
do this yeah um I don't actually know if
that works it does uh so we can use the
intrinsics there or we can use the the
non intrinsic version usually this gets
compiled to one of those anyway let me
just double check that it will that way
we can do it in a platformer nonspecific
way and still get the get the thing to
produce the correct value there we go so
I'm gonna go ahead and just take a look
at that code just real quick
so if we run to here I'm just gonna go
to the disassembly I just want to see if
Oh got to actually do it actually right
this does it in place so if I look at
the code for Indian swap Len here I'm
gonna
I'm gonna look to see whether or not I
actually got a an Indian swap so you can
see here when I call in to that code and
I guess I should be more specific here
so yeah
so in here they call up to Indian swap
now this is not the optimizing compiler
so I'm guessing actually and of course
we don't actually hit this case so why
should probably do is set us - OH - so
it'll compile it in there and I can see
I just want to see if it produces the
bite swap I don't know so it's optimize
that out completely so I'm gonna have to
do something here to copy it so what I
could do is I could just say well when -
- and I could actually do the copy the
copy out right so there's the decompress
pixels I'll just copy the the input that
we get here maybe I'll call this test so
I'll actually do the copy the source
that we need is gonna be however big
this Len told us to be I don't have any
idea what that will look like because we
don't actually hit this part of the code
but if I actually grab lens worth of
data then I should be able to you know
just copy it out like that
okay again that code is never hit so we
can't actually see it but we can look at
what if this assembly is and just see
whether it actually did the byte swap
the way I wanted to right so look in
here looks like no so let me make sure I
- I let me make sure I get that code
right so that it does you can see it
actually doing that anime or there
alright so if I shift it up eight I mean
I feel like that should have done it in
a you 16 if I shift it up eight it will
leave the bottoms a zero zero right and
oh I thought I wrote it wrong I forgot
to shift the other one down so if I
shift that one up eight it should leave
zeros in the bottom if I shift the other
one down eight it'll leave zeros in the
top or them together that should be the
swap the compiler should be smart enough
to see that and I just want to know if
it is that's all I'm doing
let's see so actually it did a it did
our rotate which that's also correct so
that's that's fine I don't think we have
to care which one it does as long as it
does it and it did so I think that's
fine all right so anyway yeah don't
really know what's supposed to happen
here don't know if these are supposed to
be Indian soft or not but we're gonna
assume that they are I'm gonna put two
do in there just so we know that it's
not code that I thought was right it's
just something that I tried
so I don't know but that's what we think
so I'll go back to our debug build now
and take a look at the next part of the
code right okay so we did that now and
now we've got this section we don't
handle the non dynamic Huffman code case
so we're gonna have to do that later by
just putting in the tables manually so
we're down to here now okay so let's
take a look at that okay so when we get
to the part where actually decoding
let's actually follow the spec here and
see what they say to do they stated to
code a literal length value from the
input stream that's exactly what we did
here we're using the literal the lit Len
Huffman I mean to code one of those
right if the value is less than 256 then
we copy it to the output stream
so whatever the thing was we just it
gets outputted what the actual byte
right so basically lit Len as a you ate
just truncated directly down right just
so you know this right we're literally
just writing that to the output stream I
guess right that's what it seems to say
so that's just anything that comes in as
a byte goes out as a byte right anything
that's greater than a byte that we
actually start to use here right so
otherwise if the value equals the end of
the block which is 256
then break from the loop right so that's
this here because that's if it's exactly
equal to 56 otherwise if it's greater
than 256 we do some stuff right we
decode the distance from the input
stream that's this here then we move
backwards distance bytes in the output
stream now this is wrong even though it
doesn't say it here this step is more
complicated I think is the key right so
we just literally translate this code
that it's not right
so let's just get rid of this here this
requires us to do some work so if I come
over here to here here here so this part
here I think indicates that there's a
lot more that goes on in the length part
that we haven't written yet so this was
the pseudocode the pseudocode omitted
like all this stuff I think I think
that's what happened so if we look in
here what you can see is that like if we
have a number between 257 and 264 uh
then you're gonna do that length
directly right it's it's gonna be like
254 it's gonna be this the number minus
254 to get the length but if the number
has more right you can see it keep going
here if the number is higher than that
then you get into things where you need
to read more bits from the code stream
to determine how far you should should
jump right so yeah so anyway that is
what is this
length backward distance Paris where the
length is drawn from 353 to 258 and the
distance is drawn from 1 to 32 768 the
literal in length outfits are merged
into a single alphabet where values 0 to
5 represent literal bytes the value 262
takes on a block and to 0 represents
length codes postures of the false right
so I believe the next thing we need to
do is in addition to the Huffman des
code here we need two Huffman to code
the distance like we did and then we
need to do the extra bit stuff now what
I don't know is where those bit reeds
come so there's two ways we could
interpret this one is you do both
Huffman's first then read extra bits the
other one is Huffman extra bits Huffman
extra bits and I don't know which one it
is I don't know if the spec even
mentioned it but we'll look so we'll see
if the spec says so reading this closely
the litter Lonavala blah blah blah blah
blah the value to d6 indicates and a
block and values to d7 to 85 represent
length codes possibly drugs actually
bits following the symbol code as
follows so the fact that says positive
conjunction to bits
makes me think it comes right after I'm
not sure there should be a trivial
machine is restore with the most living
a bit first
of course cuz why wouldn't we switch it
again right fantastic as the machine is
just or at the most immune but first
eg bits 1 1 1 0 represents a value 14
not sure how that example clarifies
anything
you wrote it in display form of course
that represents 14 what else could it
possibly represent you neglected to say
which order those bits came in all right
whatever anyway so yeah reading through
this we know we need to grab an extra
bit
two or three four or five right who
knows how they came up with this I guess
it was just weakened right I guess there
was just weak and compression people
loved weakened so I'm assuming they just
tweaked it and this is what ended up
being the best thing I don't know
so anyway when we actually look here
this looks like the same table just for
distance codes so I think we just do
those two and off we go
I like that I think that's all we're
doing here so the main thing that I
don't understand is just looking here
it's like okay so we've got to invert
the bits so that's great
so I also I'm trying to think through is
there a fast way to invert the bits it
probably is it's probably like you know
oh if I if I subtract and then and and
then add or something
I get the inverted value like there's
probably a good binary trick to invert
the bits of a value and we're gonna want
to know that here because if we have to
like read in MSB based bits all of a
sudden I don't really and and this is
not during table generation this is
actually during decompression I don't
want to be sitting there doing actual
bit inversion that's just totally stupid
so we're gonna have to go think about
whether we can do a quick binary trick
to flip the order of our bits
I'm sure there's like Oh X or then
subtract then like there's gonna be
something my bet that will do that I
just have to think through what it is
more like do with search for a quick
binary bit inversion and find something
from 1962 that's like we found this
thing alright so let's try to make this
stuff work so I'm not sure what the best
way to do this would be but I think the
best way to do it is to just use a table
because we know that there's only 257 to
285 are their values so I'm just gonna
like I'm just gonna use like the table
entry thing we have here I think that's
the easiest thing to do
so actually we can use the PNG Huffman
entry if we want to
so think we can look up into the table
and it could tell us the value to
subtract from the base to get the
starting length number and then the
number of extra bits to read in to add
to that value and then we can just go
from there now again I the bit flipping
thing is going to be annoying but that's
just the way it goes sometimes my dude
so anyway inside parse P&amp;G we can have
some entries here so this is going to be
a distance value as is a length value so
this is the length extra so this is
going to be 2 57 58 59 60 61 62 63 64
right and it's going to be 0 bits extra
so I'm just going to do these like this
and you know I you know this can be
pulled out we'll just put it out here so
here's a global and we'll just make a
table it's not pretty but it'll work
alright so actually since we have one
that goes from zero to nine I could save
myself some typing by doing that so I
believe 285 is just 258
so essentially yeah what we would want
to do here is yeah just Inc encode the
subtraction value and then the the bits
used so the subtraction value for 257 is
we want it to start at 3 so it's 254
like you'd say key value and we'd
subtract 254 from it and we read zero
more bits in right and that goes up to
265 is the next time we change so at 265
we're assuming it's 11 so it looks like
we still always oh so do we always
subtract 254 from the value
that doesn't make a lot of sense does it
ah so it goes up one each time okay so
265 we would still do right this is
gonna be nuts to get right okay so at
265 - 254 is 11 which is what we want
but now we get one bit of extra data
right so now 266 we would not be
subtracting 254 any more from the value
right instead what we're subtracting
from the value is something that gives
us 13 right so what we actually want
there is 266 we want to know what value
we would subtract from 2006 to get 13
right
so we want to 6 6-2 53 which produces
the 13 value so that goes down by one in
order to account for the fact that you
read one more bit right so it doesn't
need to do that so the next one will go
down again right because since we've got
one extra bit there we now know that 266
should produce I'm sorry that's the one
we're on so we know 267 should produce
15 right so if we assume that 267 should
produce 15 then we want to go down 1
again right so every time we read that
one we're doing that one bit read we
know we kind of go down one more value
to account for the extra bit that was
specified right this is super weird
alright so now at 269 we start reading
two extra bits right oops she sees 9 we
read two extra bits we do that four
times 273 is 3
whoops so 277 is 421 is 5 and 285 just
produces 258 apparently that's just the
maximum value why that doesn't include
extra bits I don't know it just doesn't
so again TWiki compressors are TWiki
so 285 is supposed to produced 258 so -
85 - 258 is 27 so I guess we just take
the value right and subtract 27 and that
produces it and we read no extra bits
right so that one's kind of a little bit
of an anomaly there so I believe 269 -
249 is what we want to produce 20 right
so to produce and that's what we should
start at right oh no it starts at 19
oh right because it still does one bit
now we start subtracting more bit more
numbers
okay so 250 minus 269 is 19 that's what
we want
270 is supposed to produce 23 so that's
247 right so that's all good
and then we've got 271 has to produce 27
its 244 so yet that just goes down by 3
each time because hey we're reading 2
bits so that makes sense so keep reading
2 bits so that should be 241 and this
one again even though this is a 3 it's
the 2 bits here that count so we
subtract by we go down by 3 again on
this one alone right now let's just make
sure that lines up to 273 238 it's 35
that's what we expect right so now we're
up to 274 so this is going to be going
down by 7 probably so I'm assuming it
would be 231 not let's just see if
that's right so that produces 43 so
that's the right value yep so we just
keep going down by sevens each time so
that's going to be what 224 leave down
by 7 again so that's going to be 2 1 7
down by 7 again and I get to 10 so 277
minus 210 and that's 67
and that's right so now we're gonna
start going down by 15s because we're
reading for a bit at a time right so
going down by 15s this should be 195 if
I'm not mistaken this would be 180 this
would be 165 and the last one here be
150 so 281 minus 150 is 131 and that's
exactly right now we're going by thirty
ones right the last set and the thirty
ones are gonna be uh let's see so
starting here so it would be what 120
minus one is 119 right going down by
thirty again is gonna be what
eighty-nine so minus one is 88 going
down by thirty again is gonna be 58
minus 57 and then we're at the end of
those so let's see 24 minus 57 227 and
that's right
alright so we've built our magical
length table here which means we can now
use it to do our decode and then I don't
know how we're supposed to produce the
right value out of that for the bit
reversal we know how many extra bits to
consume and we know that we need to do
the reversal so let's think about what
that reversal actually means so when we
read this in let's just let's just see
if we can work it out at a small bit
level and see what we can get the bit
pattern figure it out I probably knew
how to do this at one point and I've
just forgotten because it seems like the
kind of thing you would do back in the
bit to Italy error alright so I if we
have a 0 or a 1 we know that that just
works right because you don't need to
flip the order of the bits in something
that only had
one bit on the other hand if we instead
have the bits in the opposite order so
we've got 0 1 I'm sorry 0 0 0 1 1 0 1 1
right and what we want to produce here
from these is 0 0 1 0 0 1 1 1 right how
are we gonna do it right how would I get
that so if you look at what happens
numerically to these just to see if that
helps us at all it's 0 1 2 3 and what we
want to produce on the other side of
that when we read it in instead is 0 2 1
right which is a pretty weird thing to
look at so who knows so this is the
transfer bit for information for 2
values not sure how we do it for 3
values
here's how it would look so that's 0 0 0
0 0 1 0 1 0 0 1 1 1 0 0 1 0 1 1 1 0 1 1
1 right and we want all of these to go
to 0 0 0 1 0 0 0 1 0 1 1 0 0 0 1 1 0 1 0
1 1 1 1 1 right looking at the numbers
that's 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 here it is 0 for
that's so weird so 0 for 2
what's that 6 4 5 that becomes 3 &amp; 7
right so 0 for 2 6 4 5 3 oh wait no
that's not a 4th that's a 1 and why said
it's going too fast zero four two six
one five three seven of course right all
right so
hmm
so what is for - the value in this case
or three - device so 3 - the value in
this case works for the inner - right
because 3 minus 2 is 1 and 3 minus 1 is
2 but for the 0 &amp; 3 it doesn't work
because the 0 becomes the 3 and the 3
becomes the 0 and we didn't want that
right
[Music]
if we did something like nodding the
value then it works for the zero and the
three because they get restored properly
but it doesn't work for the interior
because now they've inverted themselves
I believe right so for example if I take
knotted this will become a zero so 3
minus 0 equals 3 is correct for that
knotted this becomes 1 3 minus 1 equals
2 but it was supposed to become a 1
right I mean obviously I could put this
in a table that would get me out of a
jam but there's got to be something
right
yeah
so I don't know I'll search to see if
there's a good thing I can't think of
anything but those that some I'd have to
stay out for a while all right let's see
here Stanford computer graphics lab huh
there's a lot of a lot of this here
so it is pretty it's a pretty
complicated one so here's the one that's
the sort of not good way the lookup
table we don't care about because we
don't really want to do that
sixty-four multiply and modulus division
so reverse the bite so they use okay so
yeah these are one of those like
carefully constructed numbers ones we
would not have come up with that on
stream
[Music]
the last two steps cancer pursue the
rescue mrs. bytes so that's pretty nice
a non divided version you just multiply
and and you can even do it without 64
Wow 2001 that's pretty late so it looks
like there's nothing you can do other
than the constructed well-constructed
mathematical ops there's no actual
straight bit twiddle you can do you've
got to use and multiply which is cool
[Music]
but I guess that also does beg the
question so how big is the biggest one
I'm gonna have to read big so table wise
I might have to read up to 13 bits right
so I don't know a 13 bit table so it's
really 2 to the 14 right because it's 2
to the 13 for the size of table times
two bytes which is the size it's a good
so you sixteen right if it's reversed so
I don't know a 16 K table I'm gonna have
to go ahead and say I think we probably
can just I think we probably just do the
table to be honest so let's let's take
this guy here and actually make this be
a a thing
why did they do this I do not understand
the rationale for having the bits come
in in the wrong order if the entire spec
that been written that way I would
understand but it specifically brings in
LS B's normally for all the other values
it's real weird I don't get it I hope
they had a reason I just don't know what
the reason is so here we are you pass in
the bit count and it'll do the reverse
of that drop down here so we'll do a
reverse bits you pass in the thing you
want to reverse and how many bits there
are and it'll do its thing
I that's just the same value right yeah
okay so I think that does it
I hope so what happens if the value is
odd so I think you're still okay
are you still okay so if the values odd
does it hit the middle bit properly so
let's suppose your slip flippin seven
bits then 7/2 yeah because you go up you
do the middle one and it just it just
writes it onto itself so both of these
things produce the same result all right
so if we have our little reverse bits
here then we have to do our table build
and we know that the table goes up to
thirteen so well we can we know that we
have to do everything from 0 to 13 so
it's a 14 entry table might be a better
way to say it so
I shouldn't have said 14th retable I
should say it's one shift up 13 is how
many entries are on the table so when we
come in here we have to initialize so we
can go our index equals zero our index
is less than or a count first bits plus
plus our index now if we wanted to here
we could even make this table even
bigger and just do it when we build our
other table as well I don't think we
need to do that so I'm just gonna do
just reverse fits our index here what I
want to do here is just say like okay
the are whatever the reverse version is
here I'm just going to reverse the value
and wait no this is way worse because I
have to do it for each of these sizes
too cuz can you can you do can you still
you can't use the table of bit reversion
unless you know which size of these
you're using - oh that's awful alright
I'm gonna I'm gonna do the procedural
way then
because I think that would that would
just be oh no you know okay no no
so we can't still do it the problem is
we have to do a shift afterwards right
so if we have a thirteen bit table and
we want to look up the reversed value we
can still look up the reverse value but
we have to shift down the result by the
difference in the number of bits that
we're talking about right so if we're
only want three bits reversed we can
still look up those three bits in the
thirteen bit table but then they're
gonna flip to the high side and so we
need to shift them down by thirty minus
three right to get rid of the ten bits
that we don't actually care about to see
which ones we do care about so that's
actually not as bad as I thought it was
when I just said it it's still okay I
guess that's how I would put it right so
I think that's all right okay so we
still need to get one more table here
this is for dis extra this is the same
exact thing as the other one but now
we've got this nonsense here right so
it's exact same thing it's just it's
kind of got its own little yeah it's
it's got a very small number of values
and a very large number of extra bits is
basically what it what it boils down to
and what I think we want to do here is
rather than do the number that you would
subtract I think what we want to do here
it looks like
it looks like here we'd want to do the
number you add so it's like the starting
number right okay so here if we get code
0 the distance is 1 and there are no
extra bits and that is code 0
actually that was a mistake like that
butterfingers so you can only have 29
values it looks like so I guess they
just don't allow the huffman table to
have any more than 29 symbols in it
that's just how they did it
so there's only 29 symbols in the
huffman table which is fine if that's
what we're dealing with here so we know
we've got zero zero zero bytes I guess
I'll just do these one at a time so the
distance is two for the code length of
one the distance is three and four so
this is just the starting distance and
then you read this many bits and you add
it in right and of course there are no
bits to read this time so then we have
two ones the distances are five and
seven looks like so you start with the
five or the seven you add the one in
there two twos mm-hmm so that's nine and
thirteen starting points two threes 17
and five oops
two fours thirty three and forty nine
sixty five and ninety seven two sixes
and that's 129 and 103 two sevens well
it's two rates two nines - tends to 11s
to 12 to 13 so yeah then from there we
just go so 193 we have 257 385 513 769
1025 1537 2049 3073 4097 6145 81 90 312
289 16 385
and twenty four or five seven seven okay
so we now have our two tables that will
sort of decrypt for us what we need to
know to read the extra bits and we have
a way to reverse the bits as well I will
not use this table yet
I'll just call River it's manual but
reverse manual because we know that
works or at least we think that works uh
and then we'll get the table working
because I think we don't want to sit
there reversing the bits manual like
that that sounds nuts
okay so looking through here we've got
all that read stuff happening it's all
fine
let me put us over here so let's go
ahead and read from those two tables and
do what they say because that's the next
step so in the case where we're not
outputting a literal so this is the
literal I don't know why I put out there
probably should have done this I guess
so
when we get the little n that's over 256
then we need to do is actually decode
the value using the table so the little
N minus 256 is actually a table index
so this is our lenta index here and
that's gonna tell us the rest of the
information after we actually look it up
right so we have a Huffman entry here
which is the line' tab entry that's
going to be the PNG length extra table
looked up by that value that will give
us two things one it will give us the
extra bits that we need to actually
consume
so if the lent Abbe wouldn't I call that
value it's used so if there's a bit used
we actually do some stuff otherwise we
don't so we'll look at that in a second
here so we start off with the length the
length is assumed to be whatever the Len
tab index was actually it's whatever the
literal length was - whatever the symbol
value here was right now that I think
about it since I already had the line'
tab - 36 here I probably could simplify
that table to just be the AB value if we
had wanted to do it that way which
probably would have been smarter but
well it doesn't matter anyway so anyway
we come in here we get the the ya I
don't know why I didn't do that it seems
weird for that I didn't do that I'm not
sure why I didn't do that let me let me
read
because when we look this up here I
don't know why I didn't just set this to
be the value that you start with I made
like my life harder for no reason right
because here it's just 257 the length is
three right so this should have just
been that I don't know why it wasn't so
it's just 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 13 15 17
19 okay three twenty seven thirty one
thirty five forty three one nine six
seven eight three nine one 1530 163 195
227 258 alright so let's try it again
so when we go ahead and create the
length now all we need to do is just
start with the length table symbol and
then if there's more bits we just add
whatever the consumed its value is
however many told us
what was it bits used yeah
however Romania told us to do there and
whatever comes back we need to reverse
right so that's how many bits that's the
one to reverse it's like this so reverse
bits takes what's the value in the bit
count I think that's all good and then
we add that so that's how we decode that
symbol
yeah
so then when we get the distance value
back the distance value is actually the
distance table index right because it
doesn't actually tell us anything other
than what to look up because we're about
to grab a bunch more bits from the
stream so then what we want to do is
look up the PNG Huffman entry for that
the PNG Huffman entry for that is gonna
be whatever the distaff index is here's
the disk table then what we're gonna say
is all right the distance itself which
again is backwards so it's actually
negative but we don't care because we're
real subtract later so the disk table
symbol is what we start with and then
this is exactly the same we could
actually make our utility function first
if you wanted to because this is gonna
do exactly the same thing so it's gonna
take a look and see do we need any extra
bits if we do need extra bits then we're
gonna consume those bits and we're going
to reverse them then we're going to add
them into the distance to produce our
final distance value then when we're all
done with that now we actually go
through and copy out so we need a source
value here our source value is going to
be wherever we're at in our destination
stream minus the distance that we're
traveling backwards right and then we
want to do a count down so we take our
length and we just copy the values in
and I should note here that I don't
really know if it's subtract distance or
if its distance plus one I assume that
it's just the distance here because the
distance starts at one so I assume that
it's just a negative distance so I start
where I'm at I go back and then I copy
right now what I can do here just a try
and again put in more assertions to
catch like when we're interpreting the
code stream wrong
what I can do is I can say if the
distance would have moved me back like
if the source is now less than where I
started right so you know the the
decompressed pixels here then I I
screwed up
right I've obviously got the thing wrong
so if we got if I can just assert that
source is greater than equal to you can
press pixels right because the distance
value if it moves us back before the end
of the pixel the start of the pixels
unless it was a malformed stream which
again we know it's not we like we know
we did something wrong in our decoding
so that's just a another way to help
catch the error right
max reverse bits count is 13 so that's
the way all of these soups are gonna be
reversed okay um so I have no idea what
that's gonna do but hey we did our best
so let's see where we're at and we can
debug the rest of it next weekend
because we're out of time so the literal
length that we got the first thing here
was 1 which is a literal of 1 that
sounds wrong so I'm assuming we did
something wrong I don't know why you
would output a bite of one as the first
thing doesn't really make any sense then
we get a little n of 255 which is
actually what we would have expected
because that's what we put in the data
stream so I don't know where that one
that one seems wrong the other values
seemed right then we got a 263 so a 263
is going to tell us something about our
length here starts at 10 there's no
extra bits used so it's a rep of 10 in
theory let's see what our distance said
our distance value is 3
wait what ah I know that's the wrong
table I'm like it shouldn't be three it
should have been one so that table I
typed the wrong table there let's try
that one more time alright so this time
we should see that come back as a one
now and it does so now we're starting to
copy from there we're gonna copy some
values from that into the stream so you
know it's working but I'm not sure we're
really actually getting sensible values
we'll have to go inspect what the pixels
are and see we also don't know what
transforms were applied because there's
obviously filters that get applied to
things so we'll see so okay so that's
the deflate stuff I we don't so the this
is not necessarily a decompressed this
this is not necessarily to be compressed
pixels because there's the filter stuff
that gets applied and I haven't looked
at that yet so when we look at the ID at
here let's actually just quick read in
preparation for next week what what do
we actually expect to see maybe that one
means filter mode one or something so
maybe that isn't wrong you know who
knows so let's take a look at that yet I
don't indicate begin with image scan
lines represent starting the image
layout the layout and total size let's
run our turbo field I had her focus the
originator economy I had her chunk note
the filter meant to 0 implies gonna be
pending a filter type bite to eat scan
line hooray so that one probably was
correct
it's probably the filter type and we're
good to go and off we go compress the
filter data so okay so image layout
we've got two color pixels pieces ruin I
right I just flip typewriters I the
beginning of every scan line this little
bike is knocking sir brother you miss
data but is included in the data stream
sent to the compression step okay
so actually actually-- the first bite of
every scanline is a filter bite which
means that if we were doing decompressed
pixels here we're actually gonna do
decompress pixels plus one which gives
us a place to store that that filter by
right although it's not actually a plus
one
[Music]
it's because it's not it doesn't need a
whole u-32 so yeah I don't want a
special case that I mean I guess what I
could do is try to retire a scanline at
a time but you could compress right
through that so I don't think that's a
particularly good idea why wouldn't you
put all the filter bytes in one row by
themselves right I mean come on all
right
it's fine
so I'm just gonna say like hey the
allocate pixels call is smart enough to
do that
so we'll add like this thing now so
there's just one of those per scanline
and it doesn't get multiplied by the
thing all right so that decompresses
some stuff and it's whatever that's just
okay I don't know I'm not a compressive
compression person so maybe I shouldn't
call it dumb but that seems real dumb I
don't know why you wouldn't store all
the filter types together because why
would those compress along with the scan
lines like the coherency is gonna be in
the filter bytes not the pixels that go
with the filter by it's right unless you
think all the scan lines are gonna be
full duped but even if they were you'd
still could just do that rep twice and
you're not gonna save very much so that
seems real dumb all right so let's see
where we're at here so it looks like
we're getting
how far does dest
so the test there's only 26 away but
it's getting like a distance value of
107 so that's obviously wrong right so
we get some we got some badness
happening already
so this stuff's probably wrong we'll go
ahead and start work on this next
weekend I'll go to QA now but we meet a
lot of progress I think like we're
actually decoding stuff now I think
we're pretty close so I don't think
they'll be that much more
ratchet freak little in my history let's
my you you are right sir you are very
right
[Music]
thank you for that that I mean I
probably would have taken a while to
catch that as we walked through as we
started to bugging it the next time
that's that's real good so presumably
we'll get a different thing here
although I don't know we maybe look at
the same thing what happened to so this
was the source was did it just read too
far was the length value huge so we
should I mean I got a step through it to
see what actually went wrong here
at scale but once this works do you
think it could be sim deed no it's a
highly dependent it's like reading
individual bits all the time so I mean
you could maybe do something with like
this part to copy bigger chunks or
something but it'll also be clear if you
write little n greater than equal to 257
yeah I guess that's true we could do
this so it's easier to see I mean
suppose for that matter you call us to
do that so it's clearer that this is a
byte output I don't know how how that
seems maybe maybe that's six and one
half dozen on the other
when you're making a PNG reader I assume
you want game textures to be in PNG
format no we that is not true for my
projects I create uncompressed image
data and then archive them all with the
sum compressor is my approach a bad one
I asked because I know we we are not
using pngs for a game format this is
because we just wanted to have a quick
way to get Photoshop exports into the
game and Photoshop has a bunch of quick
PNG export stuff that are like it's
hard-coded into it you can't change it
to do use BMPs or something that's
easier to read so no I don't care about
P and G's of storage format at all it's
a dumb format I would never store a game
asset in a PNG it's just to read in
Photoshop should reverse fit stable be
you 16 and not you 32 it could be I mean
it doesn't really matter I guess it's
probably better to be to be smaller so
I'm sure
so in that case where we do reverse bits
there I should just cast it down so that
should still do the same stuff right
no--but reversals needed see deflate
select three one one first two bullet
points Shawn this is cheating because
you've already written a PNG compressor
you're not supposed to be helping I feel
like
well yeah sure we we you're talking
about these two I mean we read that but
it did it not say
[Music]
I mean it says it right there right Sean
is that just wrong
it says the extra bit should be
interpreted as a machine integer store
with the most significant bit first so
that seemed to completely contradict
that other bullet point
[Music]
by the way the lesser utorrent you at
the beginning is in the loop in the
Huffman decode function the one with bit
index
okay so Val bus let me look at which one
you're talking about so you say the
Huffman decode function this function
but there is no loop in this function so
you must mean some other function
the one with bit index this one
i I don't know which more time I talk
about this one
oh and be type-0 yeah I don't know if I
really soon
yes you're right I don't know where app
came from I guess that's the outer one I
should probably make it clear which one
is which here and I could even move this
into its own function where it can't
access that we haven't really gotten to
this one yet so this one may be really
borked as well like I have no idea if
that's right at all
the extra bits after being unpacked to
describe and 3-1-1 should be TripIt so
you so you're saying it you really don't
you think that that was just poor poor
choice of wording on their parts that
make it sound like you have to reverse
them but but really this doesn't have to
happen like this is not clear the case
which would make a lot more sense right
cuz I don't understand why they would
want you to have to do that reversal so
I mean I could believe that but I don't
know
I have to look and see why we're not
able to do stuff here but
so those actually all seem pretty
reasonable so far how many times do we
go through this so we go quite some time
before it gets whatever the bad value is
like do we ever reach the end of the
block no so we don't quite get the it to
the end of a block though so we're sort
of okay but not quite right
Elvis yes that loop so I really don't
know what you're talking about then I
don't understand how that loop could
ever do anything other than the way that
it was written if that makes sense
so this assigns values to everything in
the next unused code array right the
reason they use less than or equal to in
the spec is because they didn't do the
whole array they did however many bits
you told it to use right but I'm not
doing that I just did the whole I just
do the whole array just period right so
I'm not skipping the last element if I
what if I did less than or equal to it
would overwrite the end of this array
and right into whatever was next on the
stack which we definitely don't want to
do makes sense
yeah so so this like in the spec this
would have been written like this where
is the max bit Oh like this right but
we're not bothering we're just it always
does this these are both they just do 15
they both just do 15 right
so anyway I'll go ahead and stop now it
looks like there's no more questions
anyway so yeah I don't really know one
way or the other whether those things
are supposed to be reversed or not we'll
have to take a look but we're getting
closer here seems pretty pretty close
it's just there's some I'm sure there's
some nagging little hard to find bits
that we're gonna have to sort of turn
through but it seems seems reasonable we
also have to validate our tables you
know I could have entered some stuff in
the tables wrong which also would would
throw us off so there's a lot of sources
here that could be wrong and you know
we'll have to figure out as we go
we'll have to figure out probably now
that we can see actual data coming
through we'll have to look and see where
we start to go wrong since we're using a
PNG whose contents we know that should
make it easier for us to figure out like
where we start to go off the rails by
looking to see what the data is that you
know see whether we get that you know we
expect if that makes sense all right so
that sounds good I'm gonna go ahead and
shut down thank you everyone for joining
me for their son handmade here oh it's
been a pleasure coated with you as
always if you want to follow along at
home you can always peer to the game on
hand me here org it comes with a source
code so you can do your own experiments
if you want to try and get the PNG
reader working before next week you
could give it a shot but I will be here
next week next weekend to do exactly
that so hope to see everyone here for
that until then have fun programming and
I'll see you burn on the Internet
taking these or everybody