hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete game
live on stream we left off at a rather
enticing location yesterday or I should
say last weekend it's yesterday in
stream time but it's last weekend in the
real-time world we now have some pretty
some pretty great ray-tracing times
compared to what we used to have and
actually much better quality results - I
don't know although I'll tell you right
now that is not what I want to see I
don't remember exactly where we left off
what we were doing lighting testing I
think we turned off the actual casting
and took a time and took a time sample
at the end of last stream so we're gonna
have to turn the Ray caster back on
first before we do that I believe we
just turned the cost metric to zero when
we're actually doing that test so at the
top of grid ray cast we usually set cost
metric to zero - this line right here
but if we turn it back on it's in really
good shape the speed is quite good and
the quality is actually better than the
old one so as far as the raycast I think
we're getting pretty close to done but
there's a couple things I think we can
do that would improve the speed of it
dramatically now one of the things that
we have to look at now is we were taking
some timings in just the standalone like
let's take a look at how fast this
routine can run profile part of things
and what you can see here is that if we
start looking at like how long the
bookends take which is to say without
actually doing any ray tracing just
doing like setup work and then the
cooldown work like basically the the two
things that have to happen on either
side of the ray tracing which is at
startup we have to do some some builds
right we have to get some spatial
structures ready for our grid walk and
then on exit we have to do a bunch of
stuff there's two basic phases one phase
is we have to write out the actual color
data to like summit basically summit
into the into the textures that we're
going to download to the GPU and then
the other thing we have to do is we have
to blur the spec map into the diffuse
map so those two processes are you know
taking a lot of time right now
you can see that what we've got it down
to five point one seconds for our stress
test that's down from seven point four
and we know that even if we weren't
retracing at all it's two point five
right so only half our time is now
currently spent in the ray tracer so
what that means is that really we want
to look at this number as if this number
is really itself - the 2.5 so it's
really like and this is a this is
rounded up it's 2.6 so really this
number is more like 2.5 that's what
that's what we're actually looking at
for the time if they're actual ray
tracing takes and then the other stuff
so stuff that supports the ray tracer
and building the maps at the end that's
the other half of the time now that's
both good and bad a it means that our
ray tracer is getting very fast because
now it's starting to be actually not
even the hotspot it's starting to drop
below the 50% line
so good on us for that but it also means
that well we're gonna have to start
going and looking at the other pieces of
the code and optimizing them but that's
okay because we we knew sort of we had
to do that and also you know this is how
optimization works the faster you make
one part and the more you focus on one
part the slower everything else gets by
comparison because that thing keeps
getting faster any other things stay the
same speed so we did an optimized
compute irradiance and we know that that
really dropped the time dramatically and
we know that that's the case because
whoa wow I haven't seen for Koda crash
in a very long time and all I was doing
was looking if I wonder what's going on
here OOP my it must be bad Ram this is
an ancient version of for coder that I'm
using I just never have any time anymore
oh he's so busy with everything that I
don't ever have any time to actually
update my for coder but one of these
days I will update the stream for coder
to something I was gonna switch to ryan
flurries custom layer and just backdoor
it might changes into it that way there
was like a public repository of it it's
been long overdue but you know well just
dedicated a stream or two to doing that
anyway what I was trying to say was if
you take a look at what all this entails
basically in that remaining 2.5 seconds
that we know is being taken up by the
actual meat of the raytracer we haven't
taken a sample yet to see how fast it
would be if the grid ray tracer were
running but the fastest possible
irradiance computations so if we were
for example to take compute voxel or
irradiance at and try to reduce the
total runtime of it to something even
less like we did optimization of it as
you can see here to sort of simplify
things a bit but the question is like
can we can we take a sample that sort of
gets rid of some of this and also like
we don't know very much about this we
haven't looked at get hoc tehy drill
offset at all but if you take a look at
how this is working here it's entirely
possible that this would flow much more
cleanly if this were done in float is
what SSE as well right because you can
see there's actually two fairly large
parts to this there's the get octahedral
offset part and then there's the
octahedral from unit vector part so it's
actually it's actually got to do both of
these things and both of these things
could be they could be being done very
stupidly by the compiler right so we
probably need to take this and make this
more sane as well because we want this
whole routine to flow as smoothly as
possible and especially when you start
seeing things like sine of an absolute
value it's always possible that those
things are not implemented very cleanly
when the compiler has to look at them
and figure out that what's being done
can be I mean like so especially when
you see this like that's just not you
know you probably never want that right
now we don't really know like maybe the
compiler is doing some things smart
there so we could look at the
disassembly and see but based on what we
saw before if I had to guess right now
before we look at the disassembly I
would say you know we're probably in a
lot of trouble there because FM's f is
like maybe going to be done with an and
but maybe it's not I mean I don't know I
don't know what it's going to produce in
fact let's just find out so if I go
ahead and
take a look at this I don't know if it
welds the voxel irradiance sampler
directly into this routine it should but
I don't know if it does actually
it's alright compute radiance at so it
doesn't because here we are and you can
see us calling from here and what I want
to do in here is I just want to take a
look mainly at this and maybe now would
be a good time to sort of get this over
on the other side here because we maybe
just want to be able to see it about
larger and at the moment I'm not really
looking particularly hard at the state
it like I'm not trying to debug this
assembly code so I don't really need a
watch window right now mostly all I'm
looking at here and you know what why do
I still have code bytes on we don't
really need code bytes at the moment
just makes a little harder to read you
know here's here's here's a random
remedy request I always throw these out
on stream i feel bad for george cuz i'm
just like you know it would be cool if
unicorns could fly but like if you look
at this it's pretty hard to read because
it's kind of just unformatted right and
it would be kind of cool if this could
be tabulated a little bit like you know
if there was another one of these
checkboxes that was like aligned columns
or something and you could see the
assembly language code so these would
all like all of the params would like
all of the the arguments would line up
here so like you know movies move SD
would have the x mm 0 b in the same
places like the mauve even though
they're different lengths mnemonics
right something like that would probably
be pretty cool and you know I don't know
there's probably just a couple simple
things you could do to make that
to make that kind of readable another
example would be like suppose you color
highlighted these some house so
everywhere that xmm one was used it was
a specific color or you could just click
on it anyways and if you whatever you
clicked on that one at least would
highlight so you could could see like oh
you know this is moving in X M M one and
I'm kind of wondering like where that's
used so it would then highlight the next
place that X mm ohms use it you know
happens to be here but if it was like
lower down it might take you a little
while to find that right when you're
just blind reading some assembly from
the compiler if it's your own code you
usually don't need this but when you're
looking at the code that the compiler
generates which is most often what
you're looking at because you know it's
pretty rare these days to really write
routines in assembly you're not gonna
have a whole lot of them so a lot of
times when you're looking at the
assembly language you're looking at semi
language that wasn't yours and so it's
kind of it would be kind of cool to have
a little bit more in here you know it
doesn't have to be nuts because this is
not a reverse engineering tool you know
you see those tools that are like
designed for reverse engineering and
then there's like all these crazy things
like aw let me mark up what this one is
and let me replace this use of X in one
with an actual name so I can see it you
know that stuff it would just be a waste
of your time because nobody who's just
casually inspecting compiler code like
you would in a debugger like this is
gonna use any of those features so they
just be wasted but just a slightly
better view of it here would be cool
because that would allow you to read it
a little bit more easily
so just features that allow you to read
the code a little bit more easily not
really reverse engineer it but just read
it seemed like they would be worth it I
don't know just throwing that out there
so anyway if we take a look at this code
here you know I'll be honest I don't
even think I know that instruction
that's probably sort of embarrassing for
me to say but I honestly just don't even
remember if I've ever used that so let's
find out because yeah I do not know what
that is
it's a single scalar some kind but I
just I have no idea what that does let's
see so it is a pretty simple instruction
it support zero only and it's a one
throughput one you up so it's only on
port zero and it's one cycle long seems
pretty straightforward I don't know if
the intrinsics guide will have that in
it we can look because I may have to
look in the architecture manual but I
assume this is probably in here
oh so that's just the compare that's
just the compare
so interestingly like what's the ah okay
oh wow okay so I feel kind of dumb I
never knew this I guess it's because
when I write SSE code I pretty much
always am running it wide so I've
actually never encountered this
instruction which I know is kind of
crazy yeah I feel like that was worth
doing because you know it's just kind of
dumb that I didn't know that this is
kind of the nature of modern programming
when you have so much stuff to do you
don't have a chance to really get as
into it as you would like so normally I
always use the comp instructions and
what you can see here is they have a
special one just for if you're only
doing a single scalar and what it looks
like it does is it actually does the
comparison of just the low order float
and it puts it right into the it puts it
right into the flags
I assume this says you know this says
return to boolean result but that's
because they're talking about the
intrinsic but there is no such thing as
return the result right I mean this is
an instruction so it does something with
result and if you're talking about
something that doesn't take register as
a destination because it doesn't here
you can see that the only other register
is would be this one and so if it's just
doing one boolean result that's going
into the flags so that means you can do
this and then do a jump I didn't know
that because I always do wide when I'm
writing Cindy because the whole point of
running Cindy is really doing wide I
never really think about what the
instruction patterns are gonna be for
single float but of course single float
happens all the time
any time you're compiling code that's
just typed the word float so this right
here is presumably an instruction that
they're basically saying look we're
going to compare these two probably
because it's like this
where did it go octahedral from you here
we go
probably because of this like again it's
hard to see exactly what's doing here
because I haven't followed through the
code and it's really not marked up here
it also it's hard to tell where it came
from but if you take a look at what's
going on here it's probably doing like
this test or something and trying to
jump around it right
that's the charitable one that's the
charitable interpretation the fact that
I see multiple ones of these makes me a
little nervous it could be that those
are there for a reason and the fact that
there's only two so what's the second
one though there's not really gonna be
an if in here right folks
so is it back in here
so I'm I'm not I'm not super comfortable
with that I don't really know what
that's doing right so that's that's a
little bit scary because I can't really
work out I'd have to start stepping
through this and really pay attention to
what it's doing but I don't really
understand why we should be seeing two
of those because if it was doing a
branch I'm not sure what the other one
was we're not really doing any other
branches in here right you could kind of
see like there isn't there really isn't
anything else where anyone should be
doing any kind of branch all the rest of
these as far as I know are just straight
line code so that's a little disquieting
and again that that just makes me
nervous because I don't know why the
compiler would think that it needed to
do two tests like that because there
really aren't two things to test so
let's just double check let's see what's
going on there I'm gonna go to floor
here but you know this is a
straight-line piece of code right it's
not a test Hadamard product v2 floor
those are all obviously you know not
gonna do branches unless the compiler
did something really crazy ah so
octahedron oh no no never mind sorry I
just jump to the wrong function so
looking at this you know the absolute
value here there's three of them so I
would have expected to see three of
these if it was somehow interpreting
that as a branch but it doesn't you know
that does oh there they are one two
three I just missed the third one so you
can see three distinct calls to that I'm
not sure where the actual
other branch would be at that point
meaning the branch that that does VZ
less than zero
I'm not sure where that is right so I
don't know if the compiler did something
smarter there or if I'm just missing one
of these so there's three
so I'm not seeing so I'm not seeing much
else so I don't know why I'm not seeing
four of them I mean one reason might be
so here's the thought like it could be
that the reason that I'm not seeing four
of them is because this test is the same
as that test so what it may have done is
just welded those two pieces of code
together here I'm saying in other words
when you saw absolute value if absolute
value was being done stupidly which may
well have been I don't know
vac you know it could be saying like
okay let's do a test on this to see if
it was less than zero you know I really
don't know so I think what I would
prefer to do here is just make this not
as stupid so if we take a look at what's
going on with absolute value I'm pretty
sure we've already done this right and
you can see here that this is how you
would prefer to do absolute value so you
you basically just say look we know the
sign bit is the highest bit of each lane
so if we just load in you know into the
register a thing with the high bit set
and everything else clear then we should
just be able to mask off that part right
now if you take a look at how this is
written I don't know that this is
particularly smart I suppose it depends
exactly how the compiler wants to
generate this it probably will just put
this and load it I mean I don't really
know but let's suppose you were actually
going to generate it for real you know
this is probably not the fastest way you
would want to do this so for example if
you wanted to you could just get rid of
this
and make this an and not right because
we're nodding this and there really was
no reason that we had to not it because
there's an instruction that knots it for
you so if the compiler actually thought
that it needed to do that specifically
you know not so good and in fact you
know we could just say all right look
let's take let's see what's gonna happen
on the compiler we're using here if I go
to God bolts and yeah well we don't need
a privacy policy because streaming this
you can't know that but but it's true so
if we take a look at the compiler here
and MSV sees compiler is kind of bad at
SSE style optimization so it's probably
gonna be the worst case it's probably
gonna be worse than clang would be my
guess but if I go ahead and grab this
here and we just go ahead and paste that
and we don't really need an inline here
and we don't really need our weird kind
of like boilerplate stuff there that
we're using so I'm just gonna go ahead
and and get rid of that so if we write
this code straight line I'm pretty sure
that it requires me to include and trim
dot H before it can do anything but
otherwise it should be fine
and let me just see this larger let me
see what else we've got floats and PS
get problems F 32 right I'm gonna get
that one better you 32
and done
right should be nope okay so we take a
look at the assembly language that's
coming out of this now which hopefully
we should be able to get you can see
that we've we've got the absolute value
routine here's what it looks like oh and
while we're at it you know what else we
should probably do is is let's do the
other one too so this is what we were
doing before right so hopefully we can
take a look at what these two routines
do right I'll I'll label them one and
two so we can see because I'm just
curious like what we were getting before
with this absolute values all right so
if you take a look at what these
compiled to here it's not going to be
very instructive because these are non
it looks like we still have something
going on I can't no no that's right
I just don't know what that with this
little I don't know what that little
orange checkmark means no if that's a
bad boy I was gonna say is we don't
really have the compiler options in here
for optimization and so we don't really
know what it's going to do when it's
asked to produce you know code that's
more usable so if I just grab like a
bunch of stuff here so at least the
thing knows like you know we don't need
exceptions we do want inlining we don't
need float consistency right so if I
just get rid of some of these ones that
we don't care about and just focus on
some of the optimization ones like this
here's what this will produce right so
supposedly that's doing the right thing
right you can see here that and it's
doing with the load so it's not
generating the value right for reasons
that I could not tell you yeah I don't
know feel like and looking at these here
I just don't even know why like for some
reason it thinks that it needs to do
this this load even though here it knows
it can do it I guess because it's just
happens to be F abs I guess I don't know
but it looking at what it's doing here
for some reason this D word pointer load
it's doing it as a memory operand which
is the correct thing to do here and it's
not doing it here it's doing a move
aligned and then an and now it's a move
aligned so the compiler even knows that
this thing could be a memory operand
because it is aligned so it you know cuz
unaligned memory operands fault on non
vivre non the prefix instructions so
I'll be honest they don't really
understand why it generated this code
that seems just like bad code gen maybe
there is a reason for it I don't know
but you know off you go cuz a move
followed by an and in that way it just
doesn't make any sense
like I just don't know I I don't know
what the point of that is
oh never mind no no I do see so for some
reason I see what's going on it didn't
do it because it thinks it needs to load
out of our CX the address of this which
is completely nonsensical because this
is just I mean that's that's just a
register like that should just be in a
register when this routine is called
right I mean that should just be an X mm
whatever the first pass registers I
don't even remember which one it is but
that should just be in the register so
so I I have no idea why it why it would
do that maybe it's cuz it can't see the
call sites I don't know so anyway these
all look really good and what I'm not
sure about is so where are all these ifs
coming from in my code is it like a
compiler version thing or or like are we
just getting unlucky like because I mean
I can go write this code it's not a big
deal but I'm just not sure I understand
why the compiler is outputting all of
these fish statements I don't know where
they're coming from right I'm just I
just don't understand because we're
getting a bunch of them we only asked
for one if statement but we're getting
three right and so I really just don't
know why so unfortunately this is not
particularly helpful and I guess you
know I can't really figure out where
that's coming from
I'm gonna just go ahead and try then
because I don't know what else to do if
I just you know if we look we say okay
we're going to come here we're gonna
look down here we see all these compare
instructions and all these jumps jump
jump jump jump right let's just see what
happens if we replace the absolute value
with our other code for absolute value
right so if I take a look in here and I
say let's just you know go ahead and and
and do you know this this same pattern
here but let's do it in here in fact we
could even just call this version of the
function I'm not sure that that makes a
lot of sense but either way
so suppose we do this and we say all
right we're going to do the exact same
thing only now instead of doing the NPS
with something that got passed in we're
actually going to have to do an mm
convert here like so and what we're
gonna do is we're going to and with a
with a set 1 of this thing right and
also since this is not wide these can be
set 1 SS is I don't remember if that's
the intrinsic though it may be that you
just do an mm conferred yeah I think you
just do a convert s sf32 no convert f/32
SS convert a the naming scheme it's just
the convert I just need to convert my
float in here and and you know it's
always an adventure of me trying to
remember the crazy names naming scheme
okay so it's not you don't switch the
f32 in the SS I guess which doesn't make
any sense to me but okay
unless it's unless it is a set oh you
know what would help here just give me
the vanilla stuff no so it is mms it's
it's oh nevermind what am I talking
about it is that so I don't know all
right so if we just set these so we're
just basically going to do a set s s
instead of a set one because we don't we
only need to set the bottom we don't
need to set them all and then I'm going
to load just this one value here so I
think that should be fine and now I just
want to see because again this is AK
same thing we load the mask we put you
know we put the mask into the next
member edge astir we and it so we get
rid of the bit and then we convert we do
convert s sf32 to get the result out
right so if I actually go back and now
look at the assembly language for that
and just say look are we still seeing
all these calm I you know all these
jumps and you can see there's actually
no jumps now at least I don't see any
wait what's this though I've got like a
call in there now what's the call to
is the call to this so now it's doing a
call it stopped welding it in there and
there's still those comparisons alright
so that was worse I'm so stumped right
now where are those comparisons coming
from so then at that F ABS F was fine
that was not causing any problems so I
guess that's can just remain and in fact
it seemed to be able to do a better job
when it was there probably just because
it's left code and it knows that's an
intrinsic for itself
I guess cuz the call is now gone right
so I don't know I'm gonna start welding
this in because I have no idea what it's
doing right so let's start by putting
this piece of code directly into the
lighting right because I just again I
have no idea what it's doing so since I
just don't know I feel like I need to
start inspecting this very carefully so
this here is T right and the diffuse
that lists in this case is going to be
I'm sorry the öktem coefficient that's
going to be coming from the diffuse
atlas here right like that and this R
that we've got the R is going to be what
we pass in here right so that's the you
know it's the sample n right
so take a look at that um and if you
take a look at what's going on here we
also don't really need this to be packed
anymore because we're loading these out
anyway so we can just you know look at
them like that right so that's pretty
straightforward and I think that you
know that wouldn't change the behavior
of this thing at all right
that's so we're not really doing
anything weird here all we're doing is
saying okay wait no this is what that is
what we're running so I don't need that
yeah so that's just the same you know
there's nothing there's there's nothing
different about that it's just the same
thing as we were running before but now
we've welded it in now that should not
really change anything I don't think
because it was already being welded in
by the compiler but every time you
change the code it helps to look because
at this point right we have no idea what
the compiler is doing we really don't
know why it's making these decisions
that's what I'm trying to figure out so
I just want to test every change I make
just to see and make sure that I'm still
getting these spurious comparison here
and there is an actual there is one
compare right so it makes sense that
there'd be one of these if the compiler
just did it directly I just don't
understand where there's three right
okay so we've we've now put that
octahedral from unit vector call in
directly and these now should all be
pretty straightforward you this is just
three multiplies these are just some
calls to floor there's really just a lot
in there
you know I'm saying I got a re-up mighty
yeah um so yeah I don't really know
what's going on but again I'm just gonna
continue down this path until I find out
so I'm gonna go grab octahedral from
unit vector and I'm gonna paste that in
directly as well so now instead of the
UV getting computed by a call I'm going
to ask it to convert compute to the UV
directly and so if this now is going to
be UV like so then I can say okay well R
is the thing that's going to get used in
here so previously where we were doing
like vxv whatever that's all going to be
ours that are you know because there
isn't a V anymore and I think that's it
right UV UV UV UV and so that's now the
code welded together so now there's no
jumps that were there's no calls that
were asking the compiler to do so now
we've told it to inline everything now
presumably because it was already in
lining everything again we should still
end up with roughly the same code so I
don't expect to see oh crap it's been
staring me in the face the entire time
that's where it's coming from
it's this
that's what it that's what it is right
duh
so here was one test and here were the
other two there and there I don't know I
mean I don't know why I didn't see that
but just didn't so these functions here
these sign of functions I think that's
really all we needed to look at I
probably didn't need to go through all
that but hey so these are pretty
straightforward right
you know I don't know why the compiler
wouldn't understand that but I think
it's just because maybe it's a little
too subtle for it to suss out you know I
don't blame it but it's pretty
straightforward for us to just do the
same thing we did with absolute value
right so if we want to take a look at
what's going on here in the sign of all
we're trying to do is return one or
negative one right and we just want it
to match the sign of the input so what
we can do is we could say look if we
just load up a mask here for this thing
like so and we assume that the value
that's coming in here is the sign that
we we wanted and we know that we want
one to be returned and we just want to
flip the sign one way or the other
that's pretty straightforward because if
we take whatever the value if we take
just that bit from the value and then we
use one as the other value we can just
blend the two together by taking just
the one bit from the input value and the
rest of the bits from the value one and
merging those together will just give us
the answer so we'd never need to do a
test here there's there's no reason why
we would
ever have to do a test here right so if
we take a look at what's happening
because we're an SSC blah blah blah like
four point whatever we should be able to
just grab a blend and basically say look
here's the blend that we're going to do
and what you can do here is you can see
how this is working if the mask is set
it grabs from from B so if it's one it's
gonna grab from this one if it's zero
it's gonna grab from the original right
so we don't have to use a negation here
and this is why I say like really for
more optimal code like I feel like if we
look at the absolute value code I feel
like the easier thing is just to load
the the non nodded value you know I mean
it doesn't really matter but like you
can see like sign bit from you see how
this is doing this right like so it's
just better if you do this and and not
is a little confusing because I don't
remember who gets knotted so I find it's
best to always check so you see it's a
that gets knotted that's the opposite of
my intuition usually and so you know
since we want the mask to be knotted the
mask would have to come first so this
will just automatically not the mask
that way everyone's loading the same
value so it can just store just one
value which is the high bit right um and
you can always just load that same value
so that seems good right so when we load
this up you know we're really just doing
this sign bit from here and we could
even have just a thing that does that
automatically probably but it doesn't
matter so I'm going to do a blend V here
and load that up again I'm gonna do a
blend V here and since this is wide I
don't think there's an SS version right
meaning there's not that so it's gonna
do this wide whether we like it or not
and that's fine because we're only gonna
use the bottom anyway so whatever so
anyway we've got our mask
and we know we know that it's if it's
zero somewhere it's gonna take the lower
part so we want our 1.0 to be what we're
taking most of and then just wear that
high bit is set we want our value to be
there right and that's it that is the
entire sign of operation that'll just
merge those two together right and so I
think now if we look we should be
getting rid of all of the jumps except
for this one here and we'll take a look
at how we could get rid of that jump as
well in a second here because we don't
need that one either so we might as well
just especially because it's not
necessarily very predictable I mean it
might be but it you know I don't
actually know so there's that one
compare that's this line and here's the
J and B which this J and B is for the
Comus because you can see the flags are
not touched I don't think anyone here
she's doing the compare leaving the
flags SS jumping down here right so I
think and now you can see our these are
our two blends that's where those
comesss used to be so I think we're good
right I think we're all good so I
believe we've still got everything nice
and and and happy here all of our
transmittance seems so we're working
okay at some point we probably need to
find some better ways to test this but
you know so we could just see where the
light scatters to for now is pretty good
all right so given all that we might as
well just finish what we're doing
because that inspection kind of led down
a little bit of a optimization path
there we might as well finish off by
just getting rid of these jumps right so
if we would like to we can see here that
you know we're doing these absolute
value sums here those should all be
straightforward in the UV estrogen sinus
all of this stuff can just be done this
is the only part that we don't know how
to do yet and so all we really need to
do is is use another blend right so we
know that this would be the condition
this our Z less than zero
really this you can see these two
computations they just compute temporary
about variables right so since these
just compute temporary variables really
this is the only thing that's happening
in here right like we can just compile
this code and it's exactly the same
because computing these two temporary
variables doesn't do anything unless you
then assign the mating so this is really
the only part we need and so if we want
to we can just do like a basic
conditional assignment here and just say
hey yeah like UV x equals like you know
mask assign something like this
where we just say all right we just need
a mask here and you know we'll produce
that mask somehow right this is what we
need to do now it doesn't really make a
lot of sense for us to do this in calls
because like all of this should really
be done in f/32 X's soon anyway because
we would want all this to kind of
dovetail into our other paths here right
so I mean you know I'm not gonna
overthink this I'm just gonna say okay
look let's make an f32 for X here
that's our Z mask and that's just gonna
be equal to the that our Z value so it's
just like look whatever the our Z value
is if it's less than do we have a zero
if 32x yeah so basically if our Z is
less than zero then what we want to do
is we want to use that to do our our
blend I don't know yeah we've got so
it's just this it's just select so from
there I can just say all right
our UVs are gonna be selected from that
and then we don't really have a good way
of pulling these out yet and again I
don't really know that we want to but
you know so temporarily I might just
kind of pull them out just to make sure
things work okay but then we can we can
move on so if we just do a select here
would look like this right so it is just
that masks assign
right and then again the only problem
we're gonna have now oops sorry
the only problem that we're gonna have
now is this stuff is not all in f/32 X's
right so like all of these things are
not actually f32 X's and we kind of want
them to be that right okay so so if you
take a look at how these are getting
extracted here
Martin's part pointed out something that
was really smart and it just was me kind
of being a space cadet so generally
speaking extract is just not a very good
idea right if you were actually trying
to extract an integer value into a
general purpose register then that's
what you would want to do but we don't
actually want to do that here in a lot
of cases we just still want a float so
really what we want to be doing is just
this always so we always want extract
zero but we just want to shut down and
put the value X looking for into the low
float of the packed version right
because there is no x87 code happening
here right so we're never trying to
transit something out of the SSE
registers out of the xmm registers and
put them in to the sorry we're never
trying to transit them out and then put
them into somewhere else like we're not
moving them out of the register store
we're this is strictly compiler dressing
to say hey you know we need to move this
down to the to the first Lane just
because we know you always generate
everything in the first Lane I'll deal
you just say where it was but there is
no way for the tell the compiler that
like so anytime we down shift from SSE
wide to compiler floats it's too dumb to
know like that we might just want to
leave it in one lane and there's some
reasons why at least in the old days
I don't know if it's still true but
there are some reasons why you might not
want to do that anyway the reason is
because at least on the older chips if
you you'll notice that these are it's
not purely set-dressing even at the
lower level so if you look at like a
mole PS right you can see that it's
generating an actual mole PS assembly
mnemonic and instruction SS is generally
something different right so it's not
actually purely set dressing you might
say well what the heck like why is there
a mole SS I mean it's the whole the
register is for wide and it takes one
you know cycle to do it so what's the
are sorry for cycles to do it what's the
deal and the answer is at least in older
chips I know it could save power like it
would actually somehow down throttle if
all the code was SS code I think I think
right
whereas PS code has to do the full for
wide and I think it requires more power
I think do not quote me on that but I
seem to recall something like that so
you know if you just take a look at
what's going on there it's pretty clear
that that there could be at least on
certain platforms and I don't know if
it's always true but there could be
reasons why you do want that to always
be in that first Lane right for power
reasons so if we take a look at these
extracts if this extract code here we
kind of don't want to do this so I'm
just gonna I'm gonna leave this here and
say change to convert SS I don't quite
want to do it yet but that's you know
that's what we're gonna do I'm gonna do
an extract here just because again I
just want to take this one step at a
time but eventually what we want to do
is kind of collapse all this code down
because we can actually do some of it
- right like so you know there's no any
reason not to just finish off this
routine right there's no reason not to
do that all right so if I go ahead and
do an extract zero here now we've done
all this you know in the SSE registers
and then transited back quote-unquote
out but you know really it would just be
staying in lane zero anyway and so I
think now we should have that entire
section of the routine just running with
no branch right so you know now if we
take a look we shouldn't see any more
jumps in here it should just be one big
straight piece of code right that just
goes straight on down and you know that
that is exactly what it looks like to me
right no no branchy branch right nope no
branch opposed um but again like yet is
this particularly smart you know not
really because you can kind of see here
that we've got some pretty
straightforward stuff happening with UV
there's a little bit of a Swizzle going
on here so it's it's not like 100% the
same everywhere but it's pretty close
right so yeah so yeah if we take a look
at what actually needs to happen here it
seems like we could probably get some
free speed up there as well just because
you know what we're doing here doesn't
really what we're doing here you know we
can just get a few free multiplies in or
whatever like because some of its just
kind of wide without again without
really thinking their routine much like
without really overthinking much if you
look at everything we're doing
I think it's literally all just for the
txt Y computation like there isn't
anything else that's happening here so
all were really
doing at that point is saying well we
and you know we can also get rid of this
code now we don't need this so that'll
make it a little easier on us to read as
well there we go okay so now if we take
a look at this routine we should be able
to just sort of say well okay where is
this stuff actually getting used so if
you look at T X into y like who cares
right look what are those what are those
doing in and when so let's take a look
at where they actually get used and what
you can see here is really it's just
part of the text little pointer thing
you can see it here at the T X T y
stride there and what you can see is
when we actually do this DX e Y you can
see the stride Z Delta X Y bit here
looking at looking at the strides it
looks like we could probably just add
another term in here right and then this
would just this would just take care of
it right
where does X Y this what's it right here
no it wouldn't I take that back because
this is this is specific to this
nonsense here
so the base offset which got computed
here so the term would really yeah it
would go in here sorry
so min XYZ time start XYZ you could just
put a term in here that had these two in
it and then it would just get handled
when you did the extraction here it
would extract out those additional terms
as well right so we probably can
slipstream that like really cleanly to
so that top part of the code can be
simplified quite a bit I think of course
a lot of this code could probably
simplified as well yeah but that's sort
of a separate issue yeah all right so
anyway if I take a look at that
let's just see what happens if we start
bulking this up a little bit but keeping
these things together seems pretty
reasonable because it looks to me like
they kind of always end up doing the
same thing anyway right so those txt Y
values we can really just flood those
out as an f32 for X that just has the X
and the y in it together and that seems
like pretty straightforward right at
least it seems like that to me so again
we're gonna be sloppy with the loading
we're just not going to be very careful
with how things get loaded here because
I don't know that I really want to start
doing any data reorganization and or
padding stuff or whatever because they
don't know that we really care about
that I don't know how much performance
that would really get us so I'm just
trying to get the stupidity out right
that's that's really it I'm not trying
to go for like the the fastest possible
routine or anything just try to get the
stupidity out that's it so if we take a
look at what's going on in here you can
see that we're doing like a divide x and
our XY and and there's the one norm here
right so this this summation there's
there's not a lot we can do there
because we're sort of doing a summation
and
you know the horizontal ads are slow
really slow on these chips and not good
and they take the permute port if I
remember correctly so it's just it's bad
so we probably don't really want to get
too fancy with this part would be my
assumption so we may just want to do
like the basic thing that's crappy first
and then you know we'll if we really
want to someday come and make this
routine dramatically better we can try
that as well but at the moment probably
just don't want to go there so for now I
think I might just do something like
this and just call it a day right so now
we have our UV in here and we would need
one shuffle in order to make this line
work out because now we've got like a
thing that's like an O X Y right and
that's gonna be this line of code but
unfortunately as you can see like this
one is right but this one is the other
way round
no I'm sayin so we need the X we need
the two bottom pieces to to shuffle
around and so I don't know we can do
maybe this and there's really no point
to the second half of that because we're
just shuffling the bottom two PS values
are around in there and that's fine but
it it always shuffles two vectors at the
same time so there I don't know yeah
there's there's really no point to it
except that we could use a shuffle
I hesitate to even bother to bring this
up but so we could use a PFT here PFT
would be better right and the reason
that PFT would be better is because dust
destroy the destination register if you
think about how like this function works
if you look at chef PS you destroy
whichever the register is that you are
passing in here and you can't just pass
the thing you want to shuffle here and
the other one here because it's lane
locked so flipping the two bottom pieces
wouldn't be possible because I believe
the two bottom pieces come from the
destination right I think
oh no never mind no no no so it's okay
because you could get you mom
no no you can't so see the destination
here well you know it doesn't even say
which one's the destination so I don't
know we'd have to go this doesn't say so
I'm not sure how to look for that this
doesn't say but assuming that a is the
destination which I don't know if it is
if if a is the destination you can't do
it if B is the destination again right
so I'm again because we're not trying to
be super smart here
you know whatevs but it's definitely the
case that you know if we were being
saucy salamanders about this then the
shuffle stuff you know really should
just have a big to do want that's like
some places where we shuffle Forex
probably should be using a chef tea
instead of a chef yes because they don't
destroyed the destination right so it's
just something to be aware of you know
again you know I don't want you to have
to over always overthink stuff like that
because you know it's not always
important but it's worth noting like
when you're at if you're actually up
against it at some point right and
you're really trying to optimize some
code there are because SSE is like an
absolutely terrible instruction set like
it's just absolutely horrid that
horribleness means that being a shrewd
optimizer actually does make a
difference because all these like crazy
tricks and knowledge about all the
specific
hisses of each instruction do actually
end up making a difference you know
that's not the case on really
well-designed instruction sets you know
the better the instruction set usually
that's not true
so I just thought I'd point out that
that's another kind of one of those
little weird things where it's like look
if you're actually trying if you really
are targeting sse4 you know not AVX
because that has the prefix instructions
at which point you know it's unclear how
much it matters a slight difference
maybe but you know who cares so if you
don't have any prefix instructions and
you know you're really actually trying
to get it to go as fast as possible
there are all these little gotchas in
there and you want to be aware of them
because if you really need the
performance there's a bunch of stuff you
can think about right so you know just
want to point it out so that's all so if
we go ahead and do this code as as
written then you know the the sine of
function needs to get ported to F 32x
obviously which we can do and then we
can get rid of that and just take a look
at where the XY is used if you take a
look at how this piece of code is now
functioning you can see that it's
exactly the same so we can just stop
doing the extraction and just let it be
exact
I'm sorry let it be wide and these are
now don't need to be lofted and the
result doesn't need to be extracted
right so now it's just again it just
keeps getting a little bit simpler this
now doesn't have to be done as a v2 at
all this can just be the one vector
right it's one plus the UV and now the
UV is correct so then we get down to
here where we've got this particular
coefficient it needs to be loaded what
are you complaining about
here o 0.5 F needs to actually be looted
you know what that's probably not gonna
get used again so never mind
okay so again yes sign of not a thing
that we actually have but we could have
it pretty easily so if you take a look
at sign of this is the one we want we
already wrote it wide so if I just go
over to for example where we had
absolute value which we also wrote wide
and sign but from an inverse sign but
from and blah blah blah blah blah blah
blah blah blah all we should have to do
here is say look we already wrote this
wide so let's just start actually doing
that as well this whole nonsense
situation can just stay exactly the same
and this piece here can just do what it
was going to do instead of doing all of
those conversions and stuff it can just
actually do this just the actual
instruction right so we still need to
set PS here and the value now though is
already wide so that will just work and
I think that's mostly all we need
that's a set one PS and off we go okay
so this now has to be fully wide so
that's just a vector of ones instead of
one the Hadamard product here where
we've got the öktem coefficient times a
UV that's just going to be a straight
multiply because the Hadamard product is
just a wide multiply when this becomes
wide so really this is the only thing
that we needed that we don't have right
and I don't know if we have a loader for
v2 s we probably don't so I'm just going
to assume that it looks something like
that and then it can multiply the UV
this here where it has to load 1.5 s in
both places again is just going to be
probably a vector of 1.5 s nothing
particularly fancy there so it'd be
something like this and you know these
other lands can just be 0 for now right
so that will produce this I value and to
produce our txt Y values at that point
we just need to floor it so at that
point we're really talking about this if
you take a look at how this is working
it's producing actual integers I don't
know to what extent we actually want
those to be integers so to be completely
honest with you we may want to leave
them as as not that at all
because if you look at what happens
through here we just extract these at
the end but everyone else is just just
actually f/32 is the tollway
so I don't think there's any reason to
actually force a conversion there I'm
not sure that it would actually do
anything for us we're not working with
particular large values here so it
shouldn't matter
I don't think and so this txy here I
think we can just do a floor on I and
call it a day so at that point this is
really just a set one I don't know why I
did that it's really just just this so
anyway at that point I've got the the
two uses of 2x and 2y here
which again now I think I just want to
fold that into the base offset because I
don't see any reason why I wouldn't this
is just a horizontal ad right so I think
what we can do is in here we'll just say
all right so the base offsets just gonna
get the TX y value added in and you can
see here that the y part needs to be
multiplied by the row stride you know
I'm saying
so in here there's like a thing you know
that looks something like this where we
boost the X and the y that's backwards
though so it's that right because the y
is multiplied by the diffuse terrorist
right there so I think that's the only
place the base offset is used so I think
that that just works right and and and I
don't know I don't know that there's
anything else we would need to do there
so yeah that's some code I probably
screwed it up but but that's the actual
code in question what is happening here
all right
so apparently I I did screw it up right
and you can tell that because we're
loading out of bounds here so this this
somehow do you know was was very unhappy
and did you know didn't like anything
about its life and so it decided that it
just couldn't go on anymore somewhere
around here and this is probably not the
actual instruction that faulted because
you know these are broadcast
instructions and you can see that that
is not what's happening here this is
actually a move unaligned so it's you
know it's going to be one of these and
so this base X Y Z value here is
probably just wrong right
because that's the thing we changed so
if we just take a look and you know we
we nerf it right oops so now in theory
when we run this we should end up in a
situation where now it's it's wrong but
it should be okay cool it shouldn't ever
fetch out of balance right because it's
always ever it's just loading one value
now forever right it's never actually
doing offset so we know that the offset
is wrong here
this line looks pretty innocuous I mean
I could be very wrong about that but
since all this thing was doing before
the only thing that it had to do at all
was just multiply the row stride by the
Y which should have done and multiply
the X by just one write it what didn't
change so I don't think there should be
anything weird about that like I don't
think that line should be wrong famous
last words so I think we're mostly
looking at this code up here for
whatever the bug is like whatever's
wrong with it right
okay so yeah
yes so that looks pretty straightforward
to be completely honest with you so I'm
not sure where exactly that's going
strange that's a little confusing
because there's not very much in there I
suppose I should double-check the sign
of as well because then that is
technically part of the stuff we wrote
taking a look at this here we're doing a
blend v where the mask is doing value P
and that I mean that looks right to me
no same thing weird there so that seems
fine so I may just have to do step
through this to see if there's something
weird going on here the shuffle Forex
could also be be busted let me just see
what those are I'm fine to do looks
pretty reasonable though right I mean
there's nothing nothing particularly
weird there so I made just step through
this real quick to see if I see anything
weird going on and again I don't I can I
can sort of refer back to this code here
and just see if there's anything that I
that I see that's jumping out at me so
if you take a look at the öktem
coefficient here which is what this is
loading into the diffuse atlas
it's supposed to do that times the UV
you know which we're assuming we've
computed and that's what it does it's
going to offset it by 1.5 1.5 on both
which is what this will do
and then it wants to floor that value
which again is what this will do so you
know again not very complicated here
looking at the UV computation it's going
to be 0.5 times 1 plus the UV again
pretty simple like I don't see a lot of
weirdness there so this part just
doesn't look that complicated and maybe
I'm overlooking something right like
maybe I'm like forehead slapping there a
little bit but so it looks more like
this part would be the problem of course
that doesn't really make any sense
because it seems like that part was
already working fine so I don't know but
you know this little part here could
have been wrong or something so let's
just let's just take a look carefully
through it and just bet and see what we
can do so yeah so taking a look at the
octahedral from unit vector part of
things so if we come through this
routine here you can see the absolute
value here is just you know the sum of
these values and we just didn't you know
we didn't do anything
yeah I mean we didn't really do anything
that so that's just sums those up and in
all the four lanes we'll all have the
same value there right because these are
all f/32 Forex replicates we compute the
UV then by doing one which is just you
know one by doing one over the one norm
which is the sum we just did so that
should just be a div PS right I'm gonna
thank okay guess I don't have that in
here no area so that's just gonna be a
div which is what we would expect and
then we're going to multiply it by the
RX the r dot y value and we're zeroing
out the other lanes right so again
pretty straightforward I don't see like
how I don't know how we screwed that up
but maybe we did we then have the Oh X Y
here and the Oh X Y value is like then
it's like the thing that we might use
you know so we're only going to use it
in places where the V is less than zero
but so we want to compute the X Y the X
Y is going to be the sine of x + y which
is what we have or of the UV x + y which
is what we have here times 1 minus the
absolute value of y in X so that's where
this shuffle comes in it's just trying
to reverse the order of those two values
and we can verify that that you know
does or doesn't work because who knows
but it seems like that's fine again I
don't I don't see a lot of places where
that can go wrong we then compute the
mask here and the mask is just is Z less
than zero right
and if Z is less than zero then we want
to select out lanes of X Y in that
particular case whereas otherwise we
just want to leave it untouched and then
we flow into the other route
right so again I don't know I don't
quite see where the problem comes in
because all that seemed pretty good
right so I'm kind of tempted here
because I don't know I'm kind of tempted
to just call the original code and then
look at the to value and see you know am
I really am I actually getting
differences in these values or was
something else happening here right so
right about here where we do the floor I
should be able to say like hey can we
just let's just do a spot check please
giving the octahedral offset here for
this particular direction right and and
that's all I wanted to do there like I
just want it to tell me like hey run the
original code path and let me see like
what these values are because they
should be basically exact all the time
because we're even flooring at the end
so although maybe there could be
occasional places where it's very
slightly different but because and then
when it gets to the floor it changes
which way it floors
most of the time these should actually
be exact exact I don't really want to
struggle to read these values out so I'm
just going to give it an OD here so here
we are actually probably put this on the
next line there so let's actually do
this and so now all I want to do is say
look we've got T X Y and we've got check
and I want to see both these this is the
place where I almost need like George to
remind me how the heck this thing works
because I don't remember
ah
that's weird I mean it shouldn't matter
because it's gonna get handled later but
so that's because of this right so we do
have things happening in the other two
lanes is that gonna cause a problem
later cuz those are the right values but
is that gonna cause a problem
it shouldn't right cuz here's a multiply
that should knock out the other those
two lanes you know there's a zero zero
that's supposed to that should knock
those out so why would that that
shouldn't cause a problem should it ah
well that's wrong so yeah this is just
wrong okay well good to know right
so the question is where is this going
wrong and I have no idea because it
looked pretty good to me so we're gonna
have to go through and and see where
this is going wrong roughly since I do
have the luxury of doing so imma do this
expansion one more time because why not
so here I'm get octahedral offset I'm
gonna grab this and in here I'm actually
going to put oops I'm actually gonna put
this in like this where I can just say
alright do this computation mmm excuse
me
where I've got the direction here and I
just want to go ahead and and run this
code with the original set of things so
I can have the intermediate values so
all I'm gonna do is just change these
two different names that I can expect in
the watch window like so so that as we
come through here
that's all we need right
okay so this is just going to produce
all of the intermediate values and then
what I want to do here is probably
something like this almost this is not a
very good way to do this that's okay
actually honestly we just can just do
that okay so I think we're good now and
again there's no point to any of this
other than simply that we are trying to
compare intermediate values so we can
see where this went wrong so in theory I
should force a fault here hopefully
whenever these are incorrect so like
that and so now when we look at these
values we should be able to see that
they're wrong right so these these are
the input values there and txy check is
is for ramp and so now i should just be
able to look at the other values to
figure out where in the chain we're
going wrong because we're just trying to
reproduce a piece of code we already had
so it seems like a waste of time for me
to try to hunt a bug myself when I could
just run the two pieces of code in
parallel and see which one where they
diverge right so since I have the luxury
of doing that I'm going to so let's
first look at the check UV so the check
UV values are these and in fact we can
just look at like the X and the y here
like so so those are the check UV x and
y values that we're producing those are
right after we do this this plus bit
here right so after we do get octahedral
from unit vector which is like this bit
here then we do this it's this line
right it's 0.5 1 plus the UV so we just
want to see what this is so if we take a
look at so those are wrong yeah I mean
that ain't that ain't no good so we've
got something wrong happening up here
you know which means I think since we
were doing this it feels like this is
probably must be wrong somehow right
like this this piece of code is is
probably busted this Oh X Y so that
means we got to paste this in and just
take a look and verify that but that
that's presumably what's wrong so let's
take a look so if we grab the octahedral
from unit vector part of this and we
just shove that in here like so this
should all be fine so if we just do
these as ours like so we were calling
this check UV right so this is actually
going to be called check UV check UV
check UV check UV h IQ v check UV a
check UV look at that
and this is our and here then this
should be fine right and the problem
that we're going to have here is this
gets destroyed a little bit so we
probably just want to be able to look at
these two values separately so we might
want to do like make this an interim UV
that we that we check differently so for
example if we did this now we can look
at with the original value of a UV + o
XY was and then what the final value is
so that we know like whether the select
is working or something right because
otherwise that value gets destroyed and
it's pretty hard for us to know what the
heck is going on in here so if we want
to do the same change to this routine
right all we really need to do is make
sure that these are computed outside for
starters like so and then we just need
to make a new version of this that that
does both right so we would have like
this here would be called check iuv
right
so that we have both of those and then
this piece of code here would produce a
secondary values and then we would have
Chucky V equals check I UV and then this
would assign the o XY based on whether
it thought it needed to or not right so
I believe that's all we need yeah and
now if we run this hopefully again we
can just look up and see what what our
divergence pattern looks like so for
starters let's look at check one norm I
don't think this is wrong but you know
we might since we now have them you
might as well verify everything what the
heck
oh dude where did our absolute value go
so okay when I just said I don't think
this is wrong that was totally wrong
where'd our absolute value go what the
hey
that was stupid that was really dumb
okay so now we're reproducing the valium
so it was just we just forgot the
absolute value happy birthday all right
so now we should be good to go I think
and so now we just have straight line
sampling there and we can also take a
look at how fast that is because it's
pretty easy for us to do so how are we
doing on we don't really know how our
timings are it's really very difficult
to take them because at this point this
number is dropping quite a bit and so
we're getting down to the play point
where like debug collation and all this
stuff like if you look at how long these
things are taking this is now like half
of our frame time right probably need to
fix our debug system someday but and so
like if you look you know you could look
at this and it looks like oh that's
really high number it's this is heavily
multi-threaded so this number is like x
many right so the actual frame time it's
taking is actually quite a bit less than
this it's gonna be that divided by four
right so this number is more like the
same as that frame display number right
and you can you can see that happening
in here
oh sorry t-bo collation no no no not
debug collision so just the frame
display just that right so waiting on
the frame to actually happen is roughly
the same amount of time as we're
actually spending in here right and then
of course we've got all this code as
well which you know probably is taking
too long but that's sort of a separate
issue so anyway like you know we're
getting into good shape here because as
this shrinks down were we're pretty much
taking the lighting out of the
the Pat are sorry the ray tracing out of
the part where it's it's the slow part
of our of our system right so if I go
and run I'm just curious here so if I do
it builds I don't know why I'm in the
code directory that's not what I meant
to do I mean to go to debug and do build
a trace like prof. like so I'm just
curious if that affected our runtime
positively or negatively because I'm not
sure what it will do right you know we
made some changes we don't know what the
effects of the changes are so it's just
curious I just wanted it's not at all
what I was trying to do this is the
horror of using two different editors
one at one in at work and one hunt
stream life is horrible
all right so in the lining system here
if I look at this timings you can see
here's the optimized version here and
and that's a city like slower right so
we're at a point where we're we're
pushing this piece of code unless I'm
wrong about that we're pushing this
piece of code in a certain direction and
that direction may not be good right
meaning because we haven't welded this
into the surrounding code there's just a
lot of cruft going on in here and we
kind of need to make sure that we're
actually going to do it correctly now
also visual studio is really crap the
compiler for us to see code so it's not
going to do us any favors but we do want
to make sure that we can do some of this
stuff smart right so we've got some
issues in here because that's running
more slowly than it should be right
because if we just left it the way it
was it in theory would have been better
now granted I can't really say why
doesn't make a lot of sense but I would
like to look real quick to see let's say
here in the release build I would like
to look to see what it is generating now
for
that code
I mean it looks pretty clean so I'm not
really sure why that would have gotten
slower that's that's a bit of a that's a
bit of a mystery to me to be completely
honest so I'm I'm not entirely sure but
we definitely have some stuff we've got
to do and you know so I'm just gonna
push a little forward on cleaning up
this code and we'll go from there
so convert s 32 seems fine just looking
at what we're doing here
so I mean really like this stuff is it's
not good and I might just go ahead and
fix that really quickly here while we're
at it because I've got these two dues in
here right so what I actually want here
is I want this these all to call extract
zero right so that these are all gonna
do exactly the same thing but so all I
need to do here is just do a shuffle for
X right we're if we're doing extract one
we just put one everywhere like so so
this is this is what I actually want to
be doing so for each one of these you
know it just looks like this and what we
could do is call that a convert f/32 so
to mirror this the other thing we could
do is say all right convert f/32 VI
right and it's just this
right I think um so then what we could
do is anywhere that we were doing
extract you can just do a convert f/32
and it'll just pull out the value for
you right so if we go to like you know
here this is this is convert F 32 0
convert F 32 1 convert F 32 - what are
we complaining about here that and then
the rest of the places where this was
happening same thing so this is like
converted F 32 0 convert F 32 1 convert
F 32 - blah blah blah blah blah convert
F 32 so you're am converted F 32 oh wait
no no not correct these are all zeros
okay
and that pull that one of each these
this is just pulling out the zero so
that'd be like this
[Music]
and to a certain extent if you're always
purling out zero you wouldn't need the
shuffle right so I don't know if the
compar smart enough to remove the
shuffle so we may need to convert F 30
to zero as like a special case you know
I mean I don't know so that's kind of a
separate issue too let's take a look so
all right off we go
so that shouldn't change the runtime and
I'll think I guess we'll find out but
that should be basically the same yeah
so it looks like that was back down to
what we expected is that just variance
that's happening so we're not slower
we're basically the same speed okay so
it looks like there's actually a fair
bit of variance in there actually I
shouldn't have jumped to conclusions
okay so if anything we're actually
probably a little faster because it
looks like it more consistently gets
down lower there so okay whatever so I
was that's below kind of our our noise
floor for this particular test we don't
have a way of really looking at that so
you know we've seen values that are at
least this low so just be advised that's
where we're sort of at now at our best
um so what I kind of wanted to do then
is just say well what what would happen
if we just said where we do the compute
irradiance so like here where we do this
compute voxel irradiance at you know
what if we just what if we just went in
there and and did just that right like
what if we just welded this directly in
there so it just Falls straight through
and this stuff can just be
factor Dow and similarly like this stuff
that comes in here can just stay in the
registers and doesn't have to do
anything right
so I don't know what will happen there
but I'm just gonna try it real quick to
see what happens so if we were to grab
like this entire load of crap here and
you can see that reflect color foo which
was already it's already in exactly the
right format in fact let's just we can
start with that I suppose you can see
here that this is about to load this
thing up exactly the way that it already
actually is right and the only thing I'm
not sure about is when we do the tile
loads we've got to get rid of the zero
lane I'm sorry the three lane if we want
to make sure that's zero but if I look
it shouldn't matter because it never
actually gets used right so we nerf that
value anyway so the lanes not actually
there so in theory this right here can
just return this value right so in
theory we can say all right this this is
let me just real quick so if we pull
this out here and the ABB raycast which
calls this somewhere like right here
right so if this thing needs this to be
to be this way we can just have the the
wide light sample come back here and
this this routine which is now super
slow compared to our new routine can do
the old way so we can keep both of those
running just fine but now what we'll do
is we'll just for the other case we'll
we'll just return it as an effort you've
why it's that we're not doing like
extractions and then just just to weld
them back together right it doesn't make
any sense
so this here we'll just do an f32 for X
this was just saying reflect color foo
it's already exactly what it needs to be
so we're just going to
say look here's their flecked level
right that's what comes back and we're
gonna get rid of of that so now we've
just got the emission level in the
transmission level that happened
automatically and then the reflect level
it just gets melted in there and off we
go so I think that should just work fine
that should produce exactly the same
results it's just again getting rid of
some of the cruft of backing into this
slowly from where we were to you know
slowly optimizing each part now you can
start to weld those parts together and
you know I mean that's like way more
efficient now right and again part of
that's just because the visual studio
compiler sucks at optimizing as a C code
so we're not really optimizing this much
all we're really doing is getting cruft
moving cruft out of it and moving that
craft out of its just helping the
compiler do an okay job right but we
haven't done anything like all this has
just been kind of just nothing right
this is all stuff like a Pilar in theory
could do if it was really fancy and so
all we're doing is just like
hand-holding the compiler right and and
getting it to the point where it's like
oh okay right I see what you were doing
there right so that's fine and you know
maybe this routine can be done a little
bit better I don't know but if we take a
look at what happens on the outside you
can see that we're just doing the max
here with this reflect level this whole
thing right can just be could just be
dropped in here now so I don't know if
we want to do that or not
like this may just be stupid so I don't
know but if I was to just say all right
you know dump this whole thing right so
now reflect level is this and we're just
going to optimize this disaster in place
here so here's this whole giant nonsense
Factory
and we know that the diffuser at lists
code should just just work because it's
named the same thing so these things
don't have to happen probe be single and
probe n single are two different things
now so we kind of need to call our probe
n single and these two things like
occlusion D in probe P single or don't
get used until down here right so
there's the sample P so I'll just name
it that to make it easier on us and then
occlusion D isn't even used as it is it
no it must be it's the thing that does
the occlusion end is what it's called
okay so we're just going to start here
which is doing literally nothing and
where's our one and 0 here one
and zero there we go okay so again
nothing fancy happening here nothing
even interesting just welding those
things together and so there's now the
final routine and go ahead and run it I
don't really expect it to do anything
here particularly much but you can see
like this number just continues to go
down and really again there's there's
nothing magic about it it's just helping
the compiler see what the heck is going
on and so again if we take a look at
where we actually are on this welding
those together more directly you know
all we did was that we're now starting
to get down towards like we're rapidly
descending into where there's very
little time spent in the Ray tracer at
all right because we know that this is a
floor like basically 2.6 is the fastest
we could be if we did nothing we do no
computations were at 2.6 right do any
more t action here oh yeah there's a
little bit left there's a little bit of
T left
okay so you know just looking at the
grid ray caster at that point and saying
you know should this be welded or not I
think for at least for MSV sees sake we
probably should and then you can take a
look and these things are already in
lanes so some of this may just be able
to persist and some of it may not so
let's take a look at probe piece single
for example because we don't really know
what some of this stuff even does so
because we haven't looked at that part
of the routine today even at all so
let's take a look at where that code
actually does anything so that's going
to be in the sample P part of the code
right which is it's just this here right
and so the question is is there anything
fancy we could do there to prep probe P
single in a faster way I don't see a lot
going on there but you know obviously
this could be streamlined a bit I should
think
so looking at probe sample P this is
just done completely wide right and if
you look at what's going on there it's
only doing it just to do this just to do
this right so if we wanted to actually
we could just add this and have it be in
the right place to begin with right also
what the crap is going on here so here's
what I'll say I don't know that I want
to do it now so let's maybe wait till
tomorrow to do this so let's go to QA
now but I'm just gonna say look now we
can streamline this code pretty
significantly because we can make this
stuff just line up with what it actually
needs to be on the way out and save a
bunch of shuffling right take some
pressure off of port five which i think
is the only port on sky like that can do
anything
shuffle related so let's just say like
because now I think now that we know
that we're just look we're just gonna
leave these in X Y Z's we're not trying
to do this multiple at a time so it's
we're only gonna get a 3x speed-up ever
on this stuff we're not gonna get 4x and
so just that's the way it is we gave up
on that because we don't really want to
do the match nations that might be
necessary to get that happened so we're
not gonna do that but we want to just
get this flowing smoothly with that
three wideness because there's a lot of
opportunities for us to advantage of
that so we're just gonna do that right
and it won't be the world's most optimal
ray caster but it's pretty darn good and
it's getting faster and faster and
faster so I'm pretty happy with it right
so I think that's all we really need
there and and so let's just go to a
brief Q&amp;A and then tomorrow we'll just
pick them up right back where we are and
you know
sorry to be off-topic I finished all the
five days in the intro to see and it was
awesome but there's a huge gap between
the intro and the main course that I'm
not able to fully understand what's your
suggestion I'm new to programming
started reading Kane I recently um I
don't have a suggestion at the immediate
moment the only way I can say is I do
have a C course coming up so I'm trying
to address this there's going to be a C
course coming up you can put your name
in the star code galaxy to sign up for
when it's ready and that's a complete
course basically it will take you from
knowing nothing so like it would it the
idea is it takes you from any number of
points so knowing no coding knowing
coding but not C knowing C but not
low-level or knowing low-level and from
any of those points takes you to
complete game implementation so it
should do what you need unfortunately
it's not quite ready yet I'm trying to
get it out soon it's just I always I
just have so much stuff to do it's hard
for me to always yeah there's too much
stuff to do in the world unfortunately
and so you know and not very many people
are ever doing any of it so that's just
where we're at
but yeah the intro to see stuff was just
a thing that I was that I tried for
tests streaming to see how things would
go but then it turned out tons of people
use it because there's so little good
intro to see stuff so I've been asked
for the past five years of handmade hero
all the time like how do I learn this
base stuff and I'm like I don't know
because the learning materials are all
terrible so I'm trying to rectify that
so hopefully eventually star code Galaxy
star code galaxy com4 if you missed it
star code galaxy comm if you just go to
our code galaxy comm and sign up there
that'll be well I'll send it out and and
then folks can can have an option we
haven't announced like pricing or
available in this of it but it you know
I think it'll be around 50 bucks so
it'll be pretty cheap and it'll come
with everything so that's that's the
current plan I don't know what the
actual release plan will be but it
shouldn't be it's not gonna be one of
these like ten thousand dollar coding
bootcamp nonsense things it'll it'll be
it'll be very affordable
well good all right well I guess if
people have questions that they haven't
thought of are posted here they can
always ask them tomorrow because we'll
be picking up right here where we are
leaving off so I will go ahead and close
it down thank you everyone for join me
for in the episode a handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to follow series at
home you can always prepare to the
source code period of the game rather it
comes with a source code so you can
follow along at home that's on handmade
hero org I'll be back here tomorrow to
do the rest of that routine just get
that slip streamed and and nice and
clean so we you know there's not all
these weird extraneous shuffles I hope
see you back here for that till then
have fun programming everyone and I'll
see you on the Internet ticking
everybody