hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here of sure we could a complete game
live on stream today we're gonna do a
longer stream than normal so I might
actually do two days it's actually I
might break even though you know days
the wrong term for handmade hero since
it doesn't really equate to anything
that's day related but two sessions so
I'm gonna go ahead and start doing some
of the texture stuff that we want to do
and I want to try and do that basically
in one big in one big sort of changeover
but that's going to be a lot of work to
do there and so we're gonna see if we
can get it done in two two long streams
maybe we can maybe we can't it's
anyone's guess but that's what we're
gonna try so this is gonna be day 4 77
I'll probably break when this is done
and then restart adieu a day for 78 so
we'll probably do two separate streams
separately labelled streams I'm gonna go
ahead and get started here for those of
you who aren't familiar with what we've
been working on right now who maybe
haven't been following for the past few
weeks we did an out we basically pulled
a render out into its own completely
reusable piece that doesn't actually
require you to be running handmade hero
at all and if you take a look here we
actually now have this pretty cool thing
called win32 renderer test and when I
run win32 render a test you can see is
we've got an entire hand made hero style
scene that you can run completely
separately now there's a couple things
that we want to do here and to finish
off our renderer section and I want to
try and do that all today so the first
thing that we want to do is just fix our
API for calling primitives now I'm gonna
talk about that in a second but we're
gonna dovetail that with fixing the
renderer so let me just show you real
quickly where we're at on this and then
I'll talk about that so what you can see
here is if we open up our win32 render
test example program this is an example
of how i'm on win
you could load and use our render very
easily this little demarcation on the
file all of this stuff is just some
windows code that for opening like a
window right and loading a bitmap so
it's just a little bit of simple code
that you need to start up your windows
application has nothing to do with the
renderer all the stuff for the renderer
is basically right here here is our
function that is called threaded at the
moment you don't have to call it
threaded but you can so you call in here
and you can see everything that you do
this is not related to the render it's
just a call to initialize a some
statistics keeping here is a texture
cube that's part of the renderer you say
hey I want a texture queue here is the
render initialization part of the
renderer
this init test scene is just our demo
scene so that again is not part of
render this is not technically part of
the renderer but it is part of the
utility coax render you can just say I
want a standard camera that's like
viewing a scene and then we have some
variables we set up inside the run loop
we just ask windows what the size of
things is and then we use a utility
function in the renderer to fit a 16 by
9 aspect ratio to it you don't have to
like here like right here you can just
use recommend max if you'd rather so we
actually support either aspect ratio
fitting your window or not depending on
how your game wants to run we then do
some camera parameter updating again
this is totally up to the application as
I leave you at the render it's just
however the app wall separates camera we
then do our render calls process the
texture queue begin the frame we want
vsync to be off if possible although
it's not really possible in windowed
mode on Windows 10 so it doesn't it
won't actually do that but we're
requesting it in case it can we then
begin one group of render calls we say
where we want to view that view the
scene from we push a scene on we end the
render group we end the frame and that's
it very very simple to use this render
now really simple understand here's our
quick simple scene this is the only
other place we call the renderer here
here here here and here and that's to
put elements onto that like that's
basically to put our primitives into the
render buffer so they can be rendered
right and so what we want to do today is
we want to do a combined update first we
want to update these functions to be
more in line with a finished API one
that's been thought through a little bit
and tuned because all the rest of our
API is now kind of have and we have a
pretty nice API now so all of that wants
to be all of that that looks nice
all of this wants to be as nice and it's
probably ok as it is to a certain extent
but it's not quite there yet
for starters for example we want to
support rotation and you'll notice we
don't have a rotation sprite primitive
in there now so you see how these things
collapse into 2d that's purely how we're
asking them to do like we're that's what
we're requesting right now and obviously
we don't want that so we want a
primitive that supports rotation because
it's easy enough for us to do so we'd
like to be able to support stuff like
that we'd also like these to be maybe a
little more straightforward they're kind
of complicated right now into terms of
how they're used and maybe there's ways
we could make that a little bit more
sane but then the other really big thing
we want to do is we want these textures
to be things that are faster than they
are right now
so the way that we do our textures right
now is very slow it's really the slow
part of our render in terms of
structural aspects these textures are
created as separate textures and in
order to make those textures work
quickly we would have to count on the
card supporting bind list textures which
not all cards do certainly most modern
cards do a card that came from today
would almost certainly support behind
those textures I guess I can't speak for
like phone chips and stuff because
there's a lot of those out there and out
and or that much about them but I mean
for thick you know basic gaming cards
like you would see even integrated
graphics I believe will typically
support by on those textures now but as
of say four years ago it wasn't
necessarily true so there's probably a
lot of cards out there that just don't
so in order to make
work better I think what we want to use
as textures rays I've said that before
texture rays are almost ubiquitous at
this point it's pretty hard to go back
to find a card that wouldn't support
texture arrays so being able to turn
these into something that's a texture
array based thing that would probably be
really good for us and so that's kind of
where we want to go with that and that's
a big change to our API I probably said
that wrong that's a big change to our
renderer it doesn't really change the
API too much other than getting rid of
one thing that I really wanted to get
rid of which is this part right here
when you load into the texture queue
that aspect there of having to do this
feed-forward thing this feedback word
thing I wanted to fix and we'll see that
mm-hmm we can fix that a little bit
later
but basically what I want to do here is
I want to start looking at that texture
array stuff and see what we can do about
that and I feel like there'll be a bunch
of things we can do there so that's
really what we're looking at cleaning up
those api's and as we do that moving to
a texture array system and that will
both increase our performance
dramatically in the best case and clear
the way for us being able to do
performance optimizations but it also
will just make the API easier to use so
all of that stuff I kind of want do in
one big push that's our big push we're
gonna start today maybe we'll finish it
maybe we won't but that's that's what
we're doing and that's really the last
thing on the renderer before I would
consider the renderer pretty good there
is a thing before saying it's finished
and that's the lighting but we don't
need to finish the lighting anytime soon
we've got some basic lighting in there
we can improve that over time as we get
our scenes together in the game will
ping pong back to the renderer to sort
of make those lighting improvements and
get something that we're happy with with
lighting so that part is kind of a
separate push at some point it's not
something we're going to do now and it's
not something that we need to have
before we consider the renderer finished
I mean for the purposes of this this
pass
okay um so the first thing I want to do
is let's just start with something
really simple okay and we'll let this
drive sort of our meander through the
codebase here and trying to make things
work a little bit better like I said so
at the moment what you can see is when
we've got these calls here so one of our
calls is push right push right as you
can see it passes an x-axis and a y-axis
and one of the things that happens here
when we're doing this is that because
we're just using global x and y-axes
when we when we pass these through you
can kind of see how these sprites
collapse now why do they collapse
okay what's what's happening there and
again this has nothing to do with the
renderer cuz the renderer just thinks
about quads and so if you're just
thinking about quads it's impossible to
get this problem to be the renderers
fault because the renderer is just
rendering the quads you tell it to
render you know that's all it's doing so
that back-end is not the problem the
problem is right here in the push sprite
call it's how we're constructing that
quad so if we pop over to Milton for a
second and just do a little diagram so
folks can be on the same page about
what's going on here why are there two
why are there two separate cursors I
don't know what's going on there but I
suspect it's not Milton's fault that
looks like a Windows thing all right
well anyway here's day 477 this is going
to be camera matched quads
and so what you can see when we run this
is there's a number of issues that we
want to address in terms of how you
specify these sort of upright quads
right and you can see here that we sort
of have a notion you pass in a thing
here that says what you want in terms of
whether something's upright or not and
then what we do is if something is not
upright then we assume that you're
giving us the actual axis for it if
something is upright then we do this
kind of like upright standing sort of
separate thing that we do to make it
look like a sprite card and just to
underscore the difference between those
two things what you can see here if I
take the tree and I change that true to
a false so that it's not thinking it's
upright right now then what happens is
when I run it you can see that the trees
are kind of flat lying on the ground and
furthermore you can see the z-fighting
happening there that z-fighting is
happening because those two planes are
completely coincident so the z values of
the tree and the z values of the the
grass are completely equal theoretically
but because of the weight it er aters
work there they're going to oscillate in
discrete space to be slightly different
and that's where you get that Z fighting
from right anyplace where that's not
happening you don't get the Z fighting
okay so that's what happens if we take
out that part of the thing where we go
from the you know we've got the sort of
two different ways if that can be called
there with the true and the false so the
first thing that I'd like to do is I'd
like to separate these two things out
because I don't think we wanted one call
for both of these things I think I would
rather have two calls because they're
really two different things I think I
would like to have a push you know this
is effectively a push quad or a push you
know I don't I don't really know how to
say it right but a push to D push to D
plate
call right it's a it's a thing that's
gonna do not this right so something
that here you pass in and you just say
hey if you want to create one of these
sprites we create one of these I don't
know what that brown P is okay so that's
just how we decided to position it we
decided to raise this up off the ground
so the ground P part is is not
particularly relevant you know this
would probably turn into something else
like maybe this is a a center peak all
and so if you want to push a sprite
where you just said what the x-axis
y-axis is and so on
then you know maybe it looks like this
and maybe this is you know if I push a
sprite on and I just want to say what
the x axis and y axis are and you just
used those axes then it looks like this
right and that to me would be clearer
it's just a little bit nicer if we do it
that way the menu vmax UV thing again
also I don't know how necessary that
really is in this case because again
that doesn't really potentially need to
be there we could just assume that's 0 &amp;
1 in fact maybe I will do that for now
where we maybe we move that in like this
that's because the color is something
that you'll probably always want to
specify or often often want to specify
but the the min and Max UV you're
probably not necessarily that so we can
have a lot of default parameters here
because a lot of these things wouldn't
have to be known and so that way when we
do this yeah these can just go away and
if you want to specify a color you can
and so you know if you imagined us
wanting to push one of these on here we
could just say alright that's a push
bright and that pushes a flat sprite
into with the world P that pushes right
on with the world position in the and
it's just the world axes and whatever
you specify are the axis that it
actually uses right and furthermore we
can we can make that a little bit more
general there let me go ahead and where
the words are
what's going on here no none of this
okay
so in here where we do our push right
don't ask me why I didn't just use the
one that was over here what you can see
here too is the x-axis and whacks come
in as as two-dimensional and I don't
really want that either
so the way that these work right where
they're being pushed off they're just
assumed they're just assuming certain
things about how they work and I don't
really want to do that either so what
I'm going to do here is say that these
are going to be used directly and so
this is if you just want a 2d sprite and
you know probably most of the time
you're going to specify that axis as
well so I feel like these I must want to
be probably up here like this because
those are the more likely things to be
specified and these are gonna be VIII's
so this is a thing that literally takes
a construction a direct construction
from you and it goes from there don't
ask me why do that there we go
okay let's pop back here these are just
scales on this
- something like that
and we could just make it so that you
actually pass these in scaled but I'm
just gonna say for now let's not do that
because maybe we need them for other
things we'll see now the Z bias doesn't
come into play here because no one has
specified one but I think we want to
specify one and so the Z bias is also
something that kind of as the sprite
goes up you might want to it to have
specified the problem is we don't really
know what should have the Z bias and
what shouldn't so I feel like in this
case this has to be for non Z bias
rendering I just don't see any way to
really get around that because we would
need to have I mean I guess you could
pass in what effectively worm in UV and
max UV kinds of things and then it would
you could use those as Z biases but I
think this is basically for non si bias
rendering so this is if you're just
pushing sprites down in general and you
don't want to do anything fancy with
them
that's this call right and I think
that's roughly what we would want we
don't have much cost for that we're
mostly doing sprite cards in this so I'm
gonna call this thing like a push up
right and it's just gonna always do this
oops and this is gonna have a little bit
more two teeth to it now right
so when we call this function what's
going on with this view I uh sir so
that's actually set to a different thing
looks like we edited that here that's
our current tuning so let's keep that
there we go and so I'm gonna go ahead
and and make this look look a little bit
like its own separate thing and so these
folks here now are going to call this
push up right call they're not going to
call the push sprite call anymore
they're gonna call the push up right
call
get that going and then we're going to
tune that and I'll switch the trees back
to that too in a second here once we
actually decide what the function code
looks like so now you can see we've got
those the grass going through there the
Krampus head also is but we aren't
looking at the Krampus head in that
particular view right now so that's fine
now what I'd like to do is take a look
at how we're doing that upright call and
think about how we actually want this to
work so to start with we look at what
the calls are here's the like base P
that's on the ground that we're doing
here's the size that we want to be
here's the min UV and Max UV again those
I think could come in here and really be
more like default because for us they're
always going to be these parameters I
think for other people maybe they
wouldn't be if they're trying to pick
sprites out of a texture Atlas or
something like that that they're using
they might want that to be the case I
don't know but you know that's that's
their choice and we can make that be
something that they deal with later
right okay so let's go ahead and and run
this now so there's again the the grass
just being the way that it was which is
what I'm expecting I'm not expecting to
see any change here so here we can start
thinking about what we want this to
actually look like now
so in addition to the x-axis and y-axis
when we're working on this stuff here
what this also needs to be able to
function properly is it needs to know
what you expect the z-axis to be
because right now it doesn't know
and it also well I guess that's not true
so we need a number of things really
what we need here is to know what the
camera looks like right we kind of need
to know like what's the camera
parameters for this scene so that we can
face this sprite card towards it right
so let's go over to Milton and sort of
explain how that works so what we're
doing right now and you can kind of see
this you can kind of see this with the
way this is working is we want to talk
about a 2d sprite but we want to talk
about it in a 3d world so we typically
have something like here is a you know a
cube or something that we've drawn and
we want to place the sprite on this cube
and we want to construct a sprite card
that stands upright from the cube okay
and we're doing that right now by a
particular geometric construction that
you can see here okay and if we skip
this part just temporarily and then I'll
come back to it explain what it does for
those of you don't remember or never saw
that part all we do is we take how big
you wanted this right to be we multiply
the input X and y-axis by those and we
assume that the Z coordinate for it was
nothing right so we assume that we're
going to use the X and y axis as like
three dimensional vectors that just have
the first part in there okay and then we
imagine right
placing the points of the quad by
starting at the ground position which is
here going negative 0.5 along the x axis
which is going to be this way right so
we're going here half the width in the
in the negative x-direction okay we
imagine the min X min Y to be there we
then
the y-axis for the min x max y right and
what does that do
well the y-axis remember this is Z Z is
up so Y is like going out back that way
so this is going like over here and
placing it here often the in the back I
should maybe I could even do it this way
let's say Y is that way and X is this
way right lying down so it's going there
then we're adding the x axis for our max
X min Y so it's going over here to do
that and then it's adding that Y axis
again right to produce the Max version
so if we did nothing at all this sprite
would be lying down flat like that for
the X and y axis but what we do instead
is we actually take the 1 those those x
and y axis that we had so again if we
assume that the world X and Y axis look
like this then what we were producing is
something that looks like that if we
take these axes and look at what's
happening to them in this sort of
upright code this thing that does the
magic snip right what you can see is we
produce a second set of x and y axes and
those set of x and y axes actually use
the y axis as the z okay so we take the
x axis and we reinterpret it as if it's
y was going up instead of out and we do
the same for the y axis so what that
does is it creates two sets of axes
these are the original ones and here's
the new ones so right this part is still
the same but this part has changed ok
then we blend between those two okay now
let's keep going here because we
actually have actually that's not true
sorry we blend between those and this
modified one here so we have to kind of
talk about this one first - right ok so
in the render group we also have the
game transform
x and y-axes right and what that is is
that if you remember let's just jump
back to the this right here is the
camera transform it's got the X and y
axis of the camera transform right and
so what you can see us doing here is
using the cameras x and y axes and what
we're doing is we're blending between
that what the transform would be for the
camera and what the transform would be
for a purely upright sprite okay now
what that means is this is one set of
axes the ones that are just world X&amp;Y
and then the other one is for camera x
and y in order to draw what that is I'm
gonna have to give a little example in
terms of the camera so let's say the
cameras looking this way right I those
axes are gonna look something like this
right and one pointing straight up at us
but the world ones are going to look
more like this right because the world
ones are aligned to the world grid so
what we're doing is we're effectively
blending some measure of the where these
things would be in absolute sense versus
where these things would be in a camera
sense right we're blending between those
two things to produce the final
transform now what would it look like if
we just used the full on-camera
transform right I'm gonna set the T
parameter here to a variable so we can
see the difference pretty easily
so here I've compiled I'm going to
compile this and run it with the
standard T this is this is that and what
I'm going to do is first I'm going to
show here is if we just use the world
axes and if we just use the world axes
what you can see is that these things
are locked to their
world alignment so as we rotate the
camera they're not following the camera
at all they're just purely cards in the
world right there purely 2d cards fins
sticking up in the world if I set this
to 1.0 then now what we get is things
that purely follow the camera right so
here you can see that we are all the way
the grass is always pointing directly
toward us right and so that's that 1.0
version the one that's always facing the
camera that's really the one that we
want to have so that our rotation works
but remember there's a reason we didn't
use it directly it's because we want a
little bit of that parallax right and we
want a little bit of that attenuation
right so this that was happening before
to our sprites that was the tuning we
were wanting the camera by using a
little bit of the world axes in addition
to the camera axis got that for us right
this kind of thing when we're looking
here we get this kind of Bend now why
didn't it do that well it did that
because remember we were just all we
were thinking about was the case where
the camera x-axis is always the same so
the camera x-axis and the world access
are the same so the only change is the
y-axis whether it was actually pointing
and in this case it was the Z it we've
changed it to the Z right because here
this transform change it to be in the z
axis so I should really say z axis right
so we're talking about a case where the
z axis points either straight up in
world space or lies down somewhat based
on how the camera is pointed right so
that was really what we were doing is
adjusting that fold over we were sort of
from the side we were saying okay we've
got one access that looks like this and
one access looks like this this is the
camera one this is the one that comes
from
render group and this is the world one
right this is the one that's just zero
zero one always okay
and we were blending between those to
get sort of a hybrid amount of lay down
for our sprites okay and so the problem
that we have is that we still want to
produce this lying down effect but we
don't want to produce any rotational we
want the x axis to always be the cameras
x axis so the problem that we have is
the fact that this is wrong
the the way the x axis is going is wrong
we want this x axis to always be our x
axis and we want the y axis to be the
only thing that's changing right
hopefully that makes some sense now what
we could do is we could say all right
well that's pretty easy right
that just means this is always zero
right I'd like done right problem solved
so now we get the laydown effect and and
the but we also get the facing the
camera bit right although as I'm looking
at it doesn't look like we do why not oh
sorry wrong one we always want the
cameras
and so that would give us the correct
sort of lie down effect where we want a
hybrid in terms of the the lying down I
should put the trees back in so that we
can see it because we're using grass
which is kind of small let me let me go
ahead and put the trees correct here so
that they can continue to do that so I'm
gonna do a push up right here and let me
just make sure this is correct
I think that'll just work and so what
you can see here is now the trees are
rotating to face us which is what we
expect to have happen when we move the
camera but the trees also should are
doing a little bit of the tilt that they
should be doing right and that's what we
want to see happening now unfortunately
it's a little hard to see in this case
so I do think we want to maybe try to
construct a test that will let us know
to what extent we're doing that
correctly because we may still be doing
it slightly incorrectly and I want to
figure out a way to make sure that we're
not like it's hard to really see whether
those trees are tilting up as much as
they should be
and I don't know let me let's let's
maybe see how they look when they pan I
guess the other thing you could do is
just draw some more like an upright just
rectangle kind of a thing and see how
that looks
what just happened
looks like our panning is busted
oh that's not supposed to be a plus
equals that's just supposed to be in
equals so here where we've got the
camera offset and we're setting that
here the only problem is that will
overwrite the drop shift so I feel like
we didn't have a good way to really set
that up this kind of needs to be an
additional offset kind of a thing so I'm
not sure what to do about that how we
want to do that I feel like almost the
dropship needs to be something specified
separately so let's just do that you can
do an offset and a shift and so here
what I could do is say all right the
result offset equals zero zero zero and
the result shift equals
that where we actually have the shipped
in there and then when we use the offset
we'll just add them together that way
this can just cold set that and it will
always still have the correct one I want
to switch I want here this camera
panning I want to start with panning
because I think that's gonna make it
easier for me to see so rather than have
to wait for it to do its rotation I want
to see the panning as we go and just see
if it if it feels like it's doing its
shifting properly it's kind of hard to
say
um I really don't think I'm gonna be
able to tell so I think I'm gonna have
to draw like some just like something
that's a card okay I got I got a I'm
gonna have to draw something that's like
more rectangular so that I can see so
I'm gonna replace the tree with a wall
texture for now so I can see if it's
actually getting a curve to it because I
want to be able to debug that function
and I feel like I won't be able to yeah
so that's not getting a curve to it and
so my question is why because I feel
like it oh because I didn't set the T
value back to 0.25 which is what yeah
there we go so now I can see very
clearly you know that getting that that
sort of tilt to the side and then if I
look at the rotation version here let me
just set that to false and then when we
look at the rotation it should still
face the camera but this is still not
going to be quite right and we'll talk
about why in a second so now you can see
that the cards are clearly facing the
camera and they clearly have the sort of
slanted vertical lines that we expect
them to have and so that's you know
that's exactly what we want so why am I
suggesting that that's not sufficient
and that we have a little bit more work
to do well the reason I think we have a
little bit more work to do is because
this assumes that the x axis and y axes
are 1 and 0 right
now if we weren't going to use those so
if I try to twist my tree around
we'll just get complete nonsense right
so here's an example of what happens let
me go ahead over to the renderer test
and ask it to output a tree that has
some kind of a rotation to it so you
know we'll say alright our tree color
it's gonna remain white but now I'm
gonna specify two axes like this right
but what I want to do is I want to
rotate the tree a little bit right so I
want to like make the tree be sort of
skewed over right and furthermore we
don't we allow actual skewing and stuff
so these don't even have to be unit axes
so let's suppose that I just said all
right the x-axis if from now on is going
to be 0.5 F 0.5 s it's actually the
diagonal going off to the side and then
the y-axis would be negative 0.5 F 0.5 F
so it's the kind of so now like we're
kind of making a diamond shape well not
a diamond shape but you know like a 45
degree rotation and some scaling in
there right as well so there's our
there's our scaled folks and what I hope
you can see I don't know if you can
quite see it entirely but what I hope
you can see is now we're getting some
wrong results right do you see how
they're kind of twisting like it's a
little subtle but you can see the size
is changing and they're collapsing a
little right and that's because right
you can really see it now right
hopefully you can kind of see how it's
it's collapsing that that's because we
just made assumptions about what the
axes were we're not supposed to be doing
that the x and y axis that we get passed
in are supposed to be sort of what you
want your X&amp;Y axis of the sprite to be
in the camera plane in the view space
right so you're supposed to be able to
pass whatever you want in there and all
we're supposed to do is make sure that
it lies down a little bit to get some of
that perspective foreshortening but
otherwise it should always be in that
plane and we're definitely not doing
that right now so what we need to do is
we need to make a construction here that
does that more correctly
okay so if we take a look at what's
going on in this construction what we
can see is that really these this axis
here we really want to construct this
other set of glenn beck's so we know
that these always face the camera right
these are constructed purely from the
camera so we know that these two axes
are just always correct as far as the
camera axis are concerned right that's
what they always mean but if you look at
what is happening here
what you can see is that like sorry if
you look at what's happening here you
can see that these two axes are always
constructed with built-in assumptions
about what is the x and y axes it should
be you know the x axis in this case is
always constructed as if it was the
world x axis and it doesn't think about
any rotation that might have been with
the camera
what we know is that we always want the
x axis to be following the camera so we
still want this x axis to be a
construction based on on the cameras x
axis but furthermore this y axis right
so this right here is a way of
shortcutting that weight which we kind
of did but this right here is assuming
that the y axis is also in that same way
always going to be aligned with the
world z axis right and that's not
necessarily going to be true so what we
would rather do is have a way of
constructing first of all taking the
camera version of this into account we
would like to take into account with the
camera
what would a slightly lied down version
of this thing look like so that's all
we're trying to do is do that slight lie
down right and so what I think we want
to do is fundamentally change the
we're constructing these things in the
first place rather than using these axes
that are passed in at all I think what
we want to do is construct our basis
first that is a slightly lied down basis
and then do the construction directly so
I think this is what I'm gonna argue
when we actually go to construct the
x-axis y-axis thing for our sprite this
is actually how we want to do it so this
is like our hybrid x-axis right oops
so we imagine that we've created some
kind of hybrid axes here right and these
hybrid axes are going to be the slightly
lied down space so it's just the camera
axes what lying down a little bit right
and then the reason that I want to do it
this way is then that takes these passed
in axes out of this out of the
construction entirely because again we
don't care what they are
we want the user to be able to specify
those anyway they wish to spin their
spray it around or turn it upside down
or stretch it out along the x-axis Pinal
on the y-axis all of those crazy or skew
it they want to do whatever they want to
do so let's just apply that at the very
end and then what we'll do is we'll just
tune this one part right here to take
into account the line slight lying down
that we actually want ok so that's what
I'd like to do so this can go away did
we eliminate that correctly in this case
too right we did yeah that just is the
size part there so that's good that can
stay so what we want to do is create our
axes here where we basically make
through whatever
that we're going to do and let's figure
out what it is that we want to do here
we want to figure out what these are and
I'm gonna say ahead of time that the
x-axis right like I said all the x-axis
always wants to spin with the camera
because this thing should always be
facing the camera the only thing we want
to do is lie down a bit so it's only the
y-axis that will ever get a lerp to
begin with so what that lets me know is
that our x axis we know what it is right
our x axis is just the x axis from the
camera I guess I can leave this in here
oops I guess I can leave this in here
but our x axis is always this and so
what we're really talking about here is
how we're gonna get the y axis because
our x axis is just known I'm having a
bad cut-and-paste day right so when we
construct whatever we're going to
construct we know that our x axis that
we're going to use is always just the
cameras x axis because no matter how we
look at this thing we never want it to
do anything about the rotation around
right so that's always aligned with the
screen what we do want to do is take the
y axis which is the upward one that runs
along the upward direction of screen and
lie that back into the screen a little
bit so the question is if we want to
lurk these things together and I don't
know that we want to lurk them we may
just want to rotate it into the screen a
little bit so I'm not sure which one we
want to do but let's suppose we stick
with the looping how would we create an
axis that's more lied down right like
what would that look like exactly so
that's the question right I and so let's
talk about some simple ways we could do
this first of all we know where is the
the basic we know what the basic camera
access would be right
we know that this
is what it would be if we weren't going
to change it so if we were just gonna
make it so that the camera it was a
perfectly spaced perfectly camera facing
sprite card we know that it would just
be game xform that why because that's
just that's just exactly what the
screens y-axis is and then if we think
about what we might want to do to make
this axis lie back down to the screen
what we could imagine is well okay what
if we just actually did exactly that we
said look we know that the z-axis right
well the z-axis points back at us so if
we were to subtract some amount of
z-axis from this thing it would push
this axis back into the screen right and
just to show you what's happening there
so for example if here is our camera
here's the screen so we know that our
y-axis this is our camera Y right so
this is the one from the game transform
so if this is our camera Y we know that
this is our camera Z because the Z
always points back towards the camera so
if we were to subtract some amount of
the z axis right that would push this
back into the screen some distance and
then if we wanted to ensure that this
thing was normal we could normalize it
to shrink it back down to a unit axis we
could also not normalize it the choice
is up to us right but what I'm gonna do
first is I'm going to normalize it so
I'm gonna say let's try that first and
let's use those as our as our basis
right so let's start there and we have
to debug that a little bit but let's
start with that as the construction
we're going to try and what you can see
right now is we're getting that that
facing which we want where they are
turning to face us and we'll turn them
up right later to make sure we're also
getting that slant it's really hard to
read the slant on something that in fact
is already
you know rotated but you can also see
now we're not getting that collapse that
we were getting before so you can see
how that's an improvement there right
like that's that's looking right now
let's tilt them back straight up so
let's take out the part of this was that
was passing different axes and let's
make sure we're still getting a pleasing
amount of perspective in there and we'll
see how that goes right and I'm not sure
about that let's switch to panning I
should make a key that lets me switch to
panning because I feel like we're doing
it enough that it's a pain in the butt
to have to change it every time oops
what oh what am I doing here I want to
render tests but I'm not getting it oh
because it's right here that's why
[Applause]
so you know now that I think of it
though we are never quite going to get
the slanted look we're looking for but
the way I'm doing this because that
y-axis is still that y-axis really needs
to tilt more towards the world z-axis in
order for it to be more upright so I
kind of know that that lie-down is I
kind of thought it through wrong that
lie down although we made a good
function for doing the lie down that was
quite nice that's not really what we
needed there so it's more like we just
want to shift it towards the world's
z-axis I guess which would look like
that right so I'm just there blending it
towards the world z-axis and you can see
now we're getting a little bit more of
that I don't know that I'm getting
enough of that and also I suppose this
has to be normalized right as well I
want to make it a normal in that
direction and we'll see what the t-value
should be I'm not sure what it should be
yet we'll take a look I'm gonna probably
increase it a little more than that
let's see what happens if we blend
halfway between those two
so I feel like that's getting a
reasonable amount of that in there
let me just check to make sure our
construction is sound I'm gonna try
cranking it all the way so it's just
using the world z-axis to make sure that
we just end up with flat cards
that looks about right to me
yeah I think that's correct
so the question is to what extent is
that good or bad right look I don't know
how and I think that might be sort of an
artistic tuning issues so I kind of feel
like maybe this T parameter would want
to be controlled by the artist you know
what I'm saying or the programmer in an
aesthetic sense meaning I don't think we
want to prescribe that you know I feel
like that's something we're gonna want a
tune that's my assumption so if we
switch back to the trees here because I
think that's probably what we want again
very simple but I think it's correct I
think it's a reasonable way to
parameterize it oops
no no I did that it's not what I wanted
to do although I do want to test that
let's actually test that real quick make
sure we don't get any collapsing here I
don't think we should but
seems okay
they always seem to retain a reasonable
amount of their you know their surface
area um so if we go back and switch to
the tree texture here here's what it
looks like with the tree is currently
and you know I don't know again to what
extent that T value should really be
tuned you know when we're looking at it
rotation never looks particularly good
with sprite cards anyway so I don't know
that we care too much about this but you
know it's the kind of thing that we
should at least support so let's suppose
we set that to okay didn't mean to do
that let's suppose we set that T value
to 0.5 so here's one that has like sort
of a bit of the attenuation and a bit of
the camera in it like half in half and I
feel like that's a good that looks like
a pretty good happy medium between the
two but like I said maybe we'll sort of
specify that blending parameter as a
call to the function so that people who
are doing this you know to the extent
that they're that they want to tune this
they can sort of play with that T
parameter and get the things out of it I
also think that we probably want that
the Z bias to be parameterised on that
same t meaning that if this sprite card
was directly up and down you would not
want to apply an easy bias because the Z
sorting is actually 100% correct at that
point so I think what we want to do here
is say look when we lurk this thing we
also kind of are luring the Z bias right
and so the Z bias is going to be based
on this T value it will go up to you
know it will
it will get to that amount at the point
where you use the least amount of
blending so because this T value is sort
of the other way round trying to think
of how I want to say this so you know
the T value is going to go from one of
these things to the other and if we
freeze the T value such that it goes
from the like world Z which is this to
the lerp Z which is that if we phrase it
that way then I feel like we'll end up
in a situation where we get the this
parameter being more natural for the Z
bias as well because now the Z bias
increases as you go towards the camera Y
axis which is what we want now this
value although you know one thing that
that's worth mentioning is the degree to
which those axes are need biasing in
them is probably also kind of different
so I feel like this parameter might have
to be tuned as well although we could
possibly solve for it based on the
difference between the y axis in the
camera and the z axis in the world so
this you know parameter here could
really be based on the difference
between those two things
and that seems actually kind of
reasonable to me so if we assume that we
have a world up Vector here I kind of
want to say that this value here is like
the inner product of the world up Vector
and the you know and the camera up
Vector wait what just happened there how
did we end up with wait what
how did we end up with the lerp around
that somebody tell me what's happening
here that's an error right yeah okay I'm
having a bad cut-and-paste day I've said
it once I'll say it again um all right
so if we go from the world up Vector
where we would not need any bias to the
game X forums Y right then if we imagine
this is the camera up we can sort of
make this a little clearer what we're
doing here we're we're just blending two
up vectors together to get a different
up vector so assuming that we blend
these two together now we get a
situation where we sort of where we know
we could produce a measure of the need
for bias by looking at how those two
vectors relate right and so if they're
pretty close together we wouldn't need
much bias at all because the blend isn't
going to change the z-buffering
but if they are then we do if they're
quite different so I you know
I'm not sure about that we should
probably put to do in there - like tune
that value more as necessary but like
that seems like a pretty reasonable
approach to me and I don't know whether
it should be the inner product or not or
if it should be more of a distance
measure between the two vectors because
one of them falls off with the cosine
and one of them falls off without it
right you could you could linear as I
call so inverse cosine or you know
approximately inverse cosine that and so
it's hard to say like which which that
should really be at the end of the day
okay but I'm reasonably happy with that
and yeah I think that's probably okay
all right
okay so if we if we just want to leave
it like that which I think we do then
the only real thing we need in here is
the ability to specify a T value right
so what I want to do here is say look
that T value can be adjusted so if you
want to specify the T value for the
flattening this is the thing that
controls like t camera up and we'll set
it to 0.5 and we'll use that everywhere
right and that's the blending that ends
up getting done perspe right if you'd
like so different sprites can like lie
down to different amounts if you need
them to and off you go
I think that's pretty much everything
that all looks good to me so a couple of
things that happen here that are worth
noting so one is I feel like the render
group should have the world up Vector in
it so you know in case we ever want to
change that I just want to see like you
know in here we don't reference the
z-axis anywhere it looks like so I think
this is the only place we're talking
about world up so I think what we might
want to do is say look when you specify
one of these render groups you can
specify what that world up vector is
maybe it's in the render transform it's
hard to say whether it should be or not
I'm think it maybe would just be
something that'd be set in here you know
so maybe there's like a world up the
vector that's set in here and everyone
uses it and then when you do a you know
begin
when you do begin render group we'll
just set it and the only reason for that
is in case we want to be able to support
in the future changing the world up for
other people so it doesn't have to be
the z axis this would give them a
convenient place to do that
that doesn't so the rest of this stuff
doesn't break so then you would just use
like okay here's the world up Vector
right and then when you actually do a
begin render group we would just set it
inside here as part of the settings and
then we would never change it and most
people probably wouldn't because they'd
be following our conventions if they're
using our renderer but if they wanted to
do that they could and that seems worth
doing so I think that's basically it for
those calls I don't know what else we
would need here so let's think about
these calls a little bit we passed the
texture we passed the ground position in
the size and then pop optional a color
so I think that works pretty well I
don't really see any reason to complain
so my next question is well cubes right
they are cubes are going to be
potentially a different story so when
we're sending cubes down the question is
how are those specified and it looks
like they're just Center and out center
and radius and then we have a color at
the moment they also have an emissions
value which seems fine as far as storing
lighting is concerned
and I think that'll just be something
we'll address a little later on so I
think maybe the cubes are fine the only
question I have is so this thing right
here where we have these sort of like
texture coordinates for everything I
feel like that's something we want to
have as a like a fully programmable
thing so people are going to want to
pack you know control the texturing of
these cubes a little bit more than that
including us like not just not just
other people but us so I feel like we
want a structure that's like struct cube
texture layout or something like that
and you know you if you imagine taking
these things and putting them in here
just so we can specify what all these
texture coordinates should be
so if we look at the cube texture layout
we kind of need like a full fully like
articulated set of UV coordinates for
this thing and these have to kind of be
programmable in you know in a in a way
that fully says there's six phases to a
cube top bottom and then for around the
ring and we probably want all of those
right so when we go to talk about the
mid here mid mid mid mid we probably
want to have those actually be like mid
zero mid one mid two and so on right and
I guess I'm not sure how we want to talk
about those like you know maybe plus X
plus y negative x negative Y so maybe
it's like hey this is 0 this is 1 this
is 2 and this is 3 so you know the thing
goes
like that I guess now I don't think I
can actually do that quite yet because I
think these are actually dependent on
the way we do boxes so I think because
of the way we're doing lighting at the
moment which I you know we might change
in the future to make it
I hope our lighting gets better
obviously I think I'm just gonna leave
them in that order but you know that's
the order that they're going in now in
terms of the texture coordinates so you
could imagine each of these here now as
being something specified separately and
then what I'm gonna do is just say okay
let's suppose that we then create sort
of a cube texture layout thing here
that's like the default cube and the
default cube is looks like this right so
you start by saying what the bottom ones
are
you they then say what the the mid ones
are and this is just an array a four of
these because right now we're not
actually going to use different
coordinates okay
and then finally the top and then what
we can do is say you pass one of these
one of these cube texture layouts into
the function for when you want to
specify what the cube texture layout
actually is so you know
maybe I'll call the TV like that
so you'll see cube UV layout you'll pass
in one of these by default it can be the
default cube right but you can also pass
in your own cubes and then in here when
we look it up we'll just read out what
these values are so the UV layout will
come out of here and it it does seem so
if we ever changed to using instance
stuff we could also instance this
because it's going to be repeated pretty
often
probably
[Music]
just thinking that through it's like it
you could pretty easily use a lookup
table for this so I'll just say because
really this is gonna be self similar a
lot so a lot of cubes are going to have
similar UV layouts so sending down all
of this stuff as individual things
doesn't make a lot of sense in terms of
optimality like if we're just trying to
think about how you would make an
optimal renderer and so I don't know
that I ever want to go down that kind of
route like handmade Hiro is not gonna
have an optimal sort of you know
Hardware renderer because it's not
really supposed to be something where we
spend all of our time doing micro
optimizations on the renderer because
you can spend an eternity doing such
things and the problem is that you know
because hardware support is what it is
you end up in situations where you have
like 50 different paths in your renderer
depending on what sorts of things the
hardware you're on supports and I don't
know that that's a particularly useful
thing for us to be doing right um but
it's worth putting the traduz in because
at the end of handmade hero what i would
like to do is sort of have a list of
like hey folks you know if you're
looking for programming exercises to do
here are the sorts of things you could
do like add a path to handmade gyro
that's optimized for geometry shaders
right and then you have a bunch of sort
of notes in the code that are there to
let you know here's a place you could
improve the performance of this thing
and here's a way to try it right and I
think that'll be good for people so even
though I don't necessarily plan to do
some of those things I feel like they
are useful in the sense that
they could be good for people to you
know know where the where they can make
those contributions or higher and then
how right alright so let's let's go here
is cube UV layout that should do it
so here we're pushing the the cube on
here we're specifying all the parameters
here so if we want do that we would have
to do the default cube none of this
stuff is necessary like the emission
value will default to that anyway so I
feel like we can just get rid of that
and that would solve that problem let's
see here emission light store this is
default cube matching set default cube
UV just to make it a little bit clearer
this should be alright and so that just
lets us change the you've ease of the
cube a bit as necessary and so you know
we can construct different sorts of
layouts for the cube UVs
if we want to at that point and you know
maybe we do want to write as you can
imagine us sort of making walls out of
these things we might want to use the
different parts of that texture to kind
of slide around and make different ones
so just to underscore how that works and
to make sure that change we add it
actually does work you could imagine us
doing like in here all we know is like
that something is element wall let's say
right that's the only piece of
information that we actually have but
let's suppose we have like element you
know wall start an element wall and and
these are just like different types of
little wall pieces it's not going to be
correct because we're not really gonna
do anything with that but I'm just I
just want to show what that would look
like so if you imagine us taking that
default cube layout here and just
placing it into our own system what we
can do is say alright when we're gonna
draw one of these cubes there's a couple
different cube layouts we could use and
maybe they're just parameterised on this
so you know we just make them line up
with this thing or something right
I don't know we don't really have to do
that we could actually do it just fine
so we'll do like wall UV is this and
we'll start you V is something else so
in order to do the will start you V
these values would shift over so what
you can see here on the midline is it's
basically just using zero two zero two
point five so the wall start I believe
is just it's just this right it's just a
thing that that shifts it over by 0.25
and that's literally it
there's nothing else that has to happen
we're just shifting those texture
coordinates over to pick out the next
panel in the packed wall and that that's
right it's nothing special and wall End
is exactly the same as well the top and
bottom are don't change cuz those don't
change it all right but the same would
be true here right we're just sliding it
over to pick the last one and that's all
we're doing and if we wanted to get
creative you could see also generating
use of the macker pretty easily because
as you can see they're exactly the same
values the only difference between them
is what you specify as the x-coordinate
in the mid so anyway so that's well
start in wall and you've ease so now if
I built this you know no one would care
because it doesn't matter to the code at
all currently but let's suppose we made
it matter to the code so let's suppose
when we do place rectangular wall and
then what we do is in here we say you
know here's the thing that that place is
what it is if the Y so the Y doesn't
place end pieces but the X does so let's
just say if the X I'm gonna I'm gonna do
a little test here to say look the seen
element
LM type equals element wall
and then a place to tell them type in
here and then I'm just gonna do a thing
that says look if the x-axis is at its
min right now then the LM type equals
element wall start and if the x equals
max X then the LM type equals filament
wall end right and so that just gives us
the ability to set those now when we set
those again we're not actually using
those UVs anywhere so what we do have to
do is when we actually test these here
we just kind of need to say like look
this can loft out we need to be able to
pass different stuff in here so we need
to be able to say like okay this is
going to be the default cube although
actually we made one for these it's just
wall you'd be right but what we can do
here is dispatch on this thing and say
like look if it's a wall start or a wall
ends we can do something different here
well start UV well and UV and now we're
drawing potentially three different
types like I said these aren't going to
line up at all because that's this is
not how you would actually do this but
it should just let us see like you write
that we're getting one of these in each
case right and that's all I was trying
to do so just to get that basic you know
sort of starting and look in place and
as you can see they go the wrong
direction depending on which kind of
thing you were doing because we didn't
actually do you need to figure out which
face you're talking about as you go
around it so it's gonna be right from
from facing forwards it'll always be
right but from all the other directions
it'll be wrong right because of just the
fact that we didn't set those up so
that's all that is and we could also go
ahead and change this one now to
actually use the mid wall version so in
here like when we do this regular wall
UV this one actually
wants to be 0.5 to 0.75 because that's
the one for an actual wall run as
opposed to a wall end so we can do that
as well and now we know that that's
working correctly unless I'm missing
something that's not a very complete
test but it's good enough one for now we
can count on the person calling the
renderer to be able to texture their
cubes however they want to texture their
cubes which is what we wanted and so now
like yeah and if you look at it sort of
you can see it from a if you had all
these be the same height they would kind
of line up right no so that's Z Rand we
actually want that Z to not be so
another thing we probably should do
there just to test it is this Z value
should should really not do what it's
doing here so when we do this push cube
I'm gonna move this over well you know
I'm gonna do I'm gonna do it this way
I'm gonna say it's going to be equal to
zero point zero if it's a wall
so if that's any of these and I could
just make it is well function but I
don't really care enough in this this is
just the test code and that just will
line all the walls up so they're like an
equal height right and so you can kind
of see how that all kind of comes
together similarly I don't really want
the wall colors to vary so this are I
don't really want to have happen either
so one way to do this actually I suppose
would be to do it like this and then say
okay you can set these to their normal
things but you know z equals 0 and R
equals 1 in the case where this thing is
a wall because I don't want you to be
you know doing all kinds of funny
business and then you can see kind of
making that segmented wall but that it
lines up now you know
so that's that's all I'm talking about
and I think that's basically it that's
that's really all there is to that
that's all I wanted to do and so now we
kind of have a more complete test of
that and that's all good
so camera is panning it was true I'd
like to take a little look at the
panning version but then I think we're
pretty much done here
maybe I'll even go the extra mile who
knows and and push those up a little bit
so that they I'm just gonna a little
bump here
so that is I think pretty much concludes
our work with the renderer in that sense
and I think we want to move on to the
texture situation and I guess we could
also let take a little bit of a quick
benchmark just a really brief kind of
like just just a quick temperature test
to see how slow we are with the texture
changes and maybe we can go in and sort
of nerf the lighting computation in the
pixel shader as well just to see if we
can't get an idea of what our look of
how expensive our texture changes are so
that we know if we've done a good job
getting rid of them you know I'm saying
so I feel like this is good
I'm just gonna let it run through its
paces here and make sure nothing
untoward is happening I think we're good
to go
[Music]
so I feel like that's just that's all
good so what I'd like to do now is I'd
like to go ahead and test some of the
texture change stuff a little bit so we
have a way to stress it out already and
the way we can stress this out is just
by when we push our simple scene on we
had a way of doing a lot of grass cover
right it's this thing um so if I just
dump a ton of sprites in there we get a
lot slower and there you go you can see
how slow we get in this case and I'm
sure we can slow us down even more
you know just just push an arbitrary
number on there until you get slow
enough and what I'd like to do is find
out how much time we're spending in
different parts of the pipeline here to
just just to know who's at fault because
I would like to get us into a position
where texture changes are the expensive
part before we optimize our texture
changes you know just to make sure that
we can actually you know see what we're
actually doing so let's let's try
I know it's always sort of I know it's
always an exercise and frustration to
try to use any kind of anything that has
to do the GPU is always bad they're just
they're horrible they're not built like
CPUs they don't have proper debugging
they don't have proper profiling and
it's awful we know this but let's just
see if we can get some measure of that
going and hopefully maybe I don't know
we'll be able to do something where we
can at least say look here is how much
those texture changes are costing us and
you know they're bad I don't know if we
can make that happen
you know it's speculation on my part
that's ever even gonna happen on an
Nvidia part because Nvidia parts are
good at texture changes
so it's hard to say whether this would
really be the case or not I don't know
so we're gonna try this may not help but
we do need to do that stuff for texture
changes anyway why am I not able to oh
this is the the new product right right
okay um so I need to basically make one
of these things I'm gonna make I'm I am
gonna make this inside a handmade msec
proj and I'm just gonna make the win32
renderer test thing be what we're doing
I'm just gonna call it that because I
don't know what else to call it
I'm gonna pick the executable from the
build directory here
and as far as the working directory is
concerned I don't remember what we set
the working directory this thing to so
I'm just gonna look so we're I want to
make sure we always run it the exact
same way so it's in there so we're gonna
tell it to run it in there and that
should be it actually so hopefully we
can make this run what I don't know that
I really care about this
I guess I don't know if this needs to
access the network externally because it
should only need to use loopback so I'll
just try not allowing it through the
firewall first and we'll see if that
actually poses a problem
so it seems like it doesn't need that so
I'm just gonna skip that I assume that's
just for remote cap there
so what I can't say though is you know
I'm just I'm just testing to make sure
insights working it seems like it maybe
is working and it's taking a long time
caps the frame but that's probably just
because there's a lot of dispatches in
there so what I assume is that we're
really not seeing the texture change hit
that much at the moment because if I
looked at the you know if you look at
the little graph that was on the on the
overlay and the HUD it was showing that
the texture part was very was was
getting overstressed right or it looks
looked that way so I'm not sure that
we're really going to find that our
current problem is texture changes and
we've got some things that we probably
need to fix like the fact that we're
relying on multi sampling everywhere
instead of only in one pass and a bunch
of stuff like that so there's a number
of things that we probably want to do
and we will see what we could do about
those later I don't really know what
it's doing right now
but here's here's my guess because we
issue so many draw calls I'm guessing
that it's like doing a replay and doing
a screen capture of like every dispatch
so we're gonna end up with like 8
billion little tiny screen grabs of like
one piece of grass drawing you know I'm
saying so ironically although I'm not
sure that the actual dispatches are the
problem at the moment in our actual code
well they probably are the problem in
our capturing for whatever that's worth
so one thing we can also do is because
we draw so many grasses at once we could
also do a thing where we just check to
see whether the grasses are the same
grass and draw them in a batch as a test
right as just a way of seeing whether or
not this is the case this looks like we
could be here forever I'm not
anticipating this is ever gonna finish
in our lifetime so that's fine like I
said working with GPUs is terrible it
always is it's the worst part of the job
so yeah not sure what to do about that
I'm gonna go ahead and close this stuff
because it's not working and I'm gonna
go ahead and investigate this a little
bit differently like I said you can
never really GPUs are awful yeah kind of
wish they never happen um so let's go
ahead and pop over to the renderer and
what I want to do is I want to just look
at where we're doing those dispatches
and I'm gonna fake some coding here too
to aggregate batches before we actually
do the work of aggregating backs patches
just so we can see what the difference
is right that that's all I really want
to do so let's start with some of that
right
and and we can go from there
where's our where's our stuff here
whereas our Ryszard we're sort dirt is
like where's our dispatch so this is
where we dispatch everything and I just
want to see so when we do our drawing
here you can kind of see when we do what
we end up doing is we draw one triangle
strip and then we have to restart right
and the reason that we have to restart
our triangle strip is just because there
is no way to just send quads down like
for some unknown reason they got rid of
quads as a drawing method and I don't
know why because they are very efficient
for drawing sprites and I guess their
thinking was just well use a geometry
shader and and output them that way I
don't know but the problem that we will
have is that by calling GL draw rays
there's really no way for us to draw
multiple quads without doing more fancy
footwork here now what we can do is we
can sort of start to construct something
that would allow us to draw draw these
quads in a way that that doesn't occur
incur much of a penalty and that would
be by actually having an index buffer
that tracks as we sink the quads that
sort of tracks that and what I what I
want to know because I don't actually
know is whether primitive restart index
actually exists at the moment in terms
of like let me see here
so primitive restart is not an envy only
thing so I'm guessing I may be like have
the wrong name for it
hmm so I'm not sure how to search for
that because it was part of core and I'm
just not sure when it went in but quite
a few cards have it right
so I feel like it's a fairly highly
supported feature but I'm just not sure
I don't know about how much coverage
there is for a primitive restart but
basically what you can do is if you and
and you know now I think about it I
guess it doesn't really matter I mean
it's gonna save us only one index but
what you can do is if you want to do
something like send down quads you can
use a tri strip to send down four quads
four vertices that form the quad and
then a restart element that says okay
I'm gonna draw I want you to restart the
Tri strip right so we could do that but
in order to do that we have to switch to
having an index buffer in addition to a
vertex buffer and once we do that we can
just send down quads as six indices one
two three one two three and be done
anyway so we can probably just switch to
that and be fine with it
I'm interested to try that so what I
would like to do here is instead of GL
draw Ray's um Jill duck what's the dock
it's like open Jill dock it's like a
someone docks tachi oh that's and I'm
like it's it's got a good searchable 1su
GL draw arrays if you look at how it's
called it just assumes that you're going
to point to a array of vertices somehow
and those vertices are going to be
interpreted in order and what we'd like
to switch to is being able to send down
vertices and then indexes into that
vertex array and so if you look at how
this is is patched here what we'd like
is a call that allows us specify an
index buffer and sip don't know why that
did that okay there we go
and so I believe this is the
of the index buffer line I never
remember yeah so if we want to we can
call draw elements and pass an index
buffer as well and so when we call this
GL draw arrays we can instead call GL
draw elements and pass an index buffer
down so if we wanted to for example we
could do that right here where what we
could say is look instead of that call
let's use this call and then when we do
mode count type indices same basic idea
we want triangle strip actually no let's
do GL triangles instead write the number
of indices were going to send down now
because this count here like the number
of elements to be rendered before we're
doing four vertices we're gonna do six
indices now okay we're gonna see what
kind of indices were sending down let's
send down unsigned shorts more efficient
int is good it is probably what we want
for right now because we don't want to
have to break things up into bunches now
let's break them up into bunches anyway
so let's do short let's let's get our
short shirt on and then we want to pass
them down okay so what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna draw by index I'm gonna create
some indices here and what I'm gonna do
is just create the indices that would
take four elements in Tri strip order
and I'm going to use those as indices to
draw actual triangles myself okay so a
tri strip is 0 1 2 3 that's how it's
constructed to draw quad 0 1 2 3 so what
we want to do is if we know we're
getting 0 1 2 3 down the pipe I'm just
gonna draw two triangles right well I
should actually drawn this way so I'm
going to draw 0 2 1
then I'm gonna draw one two three okay
to counterclockwise wound triangles out
of the that buffer and again exactly
what I just said zero to 1 and the other
trials to be one two three all right
and so we're we've done literally
nothing useful here at all other than
transform you note switch between
alright and we didn't even work why do
we not work that seems pretty
straightforward doesn't it triangles we
want six what is the problem here zero
to one I did have that right yeah what's
the try support it's not downward is it
it's not that is it
I honestly don't remember what order
they go in and I look it up
no it's ABCD I have that right it's
exactly as I drew it one two three four
don't ask me why they're drawn winding
clockwise because that is not oh because
all right they set them that way for
some reason
oh wait so this is only if it's
clockwise though so are they so it is
the upside-down way I don't know look I
someone show me what the actual order is
where is it done just just show me this
back why am I even looking at this I
don't care what anyone posts on the web
show me this back
here we go 1 2 3 4 5 here is the winding
1 to 3 3 to 4 so they actually put the
triangle out in clockwise order thick is
that true
they kind of dumbfounded right now
I don't know what to make of that
anyway either way this is sort of
irrelevant here but I don't know that
that's actually a problem if I disabled
GL coalface I'm just curious what
happens because we shouldn't we didn't
see anything
so that suggests that it's not just our
winding order that's wrong right
something else is wrong here I just
don't know what it is so I don't think
that's actually the problem the winding
order is a separate issue so I'm not
sure why our draw elements call is
erroneous here
I did say unsigned short and I specified
on the sign shorts I did say I wanted
six
oh it's how many elements though not how
many vertices
where's our draw on this call
what's the count in this case
this couldn't get starts tickets of
Jennifers by successfully transferring
elements for count vertices right so now
I specified the right thing six vertices
so I'm not sure why we're getting I'm
not sure why we're getting hosed there
because these two paths should be the
same now so if we are specifying these
like so versus like so
I'm not sure why it doesn't like our
index version maybe I need to use a
different call but open Jill's always a
little weird like that but feel like it
should be fine
because these all are basically the same
thing right
hmm all right so what's what did I screw
up here I'm curious
I suppose I don't know where we set the
oh this is the problem sorry about that
I forgot the hole we aren't setting the
array pointers there we just transfer
down the buffer so these all need to be
offset by vertex index here in this case
so in that case I am gonna go ahead and
make this an int temporarily but we'll
be able to fix that a little bit later I
think okay sorry that took so long
all right so now as you can see we've
got our our winding was in fact
backwards I do not understand why
they're wound that way too
to begin with but that's okay
I'm fine with that we're gonna still
have we have front face clockwise yet
okay so don't ask me why that's the case
but it's fine that it is we can just
reverse our winding and no one cares so
if I do 0 1 2 and then 1 3 2 instead
that'll reverse the winding and we'll
draw our quads in the order that we
expect and that's fine so now we are
drawing with indices here and if we want
to we can now go ahead and say well and
and you know what I think we're trying
to do for a break here so what I
probably should do is it's go to a brief
Q&amp;A before moving on and on the next
thing what we'll do is we'll switch over
to using a giant index buffer for
everything and then we'll move to a
texture array as well
let's go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A here
Martin says primitive restart indexes in
GL course since version 3.1 so we
probably could do it I thought you had
to bind a GL element array buffer to do
indexing is this not true if no buffer
is bound yes so my recollection and
again GL is kind of a crazy mass at this
point of lots of legacy features but one
of the next things about those legacy
features a lot of them still work so
when you're just kind of starting out if
you don't want to bind an array buffer
depending on whether you asked for a
core compatibility context I assume but
maybe not I don't know you can just call
draw elements with a pointer and that
draws it sucks the indices out of your
memory at that point so you don't need
to bind one now you probably want to
bind one and we're going to want to bind
one I believe but I don't think you have
to
using indicee seems to take a lot more
memory if the vertex a that contains
texture coordinates normals etc how do
you know when it's a good idea to render
by indices sorry I'm not sure that
statement sounds backwards to me using
indices doesn't take more or less memory
regardless of those things that you're
talking about
can you rephrase that question perhaps
or be more specific because so using
indices just takes however many bytes
and index takes you know in our case
it'll probably have taking two bytes per
index and so for every triangle you're
gonna have six indices two or five if
we've used primitive it restart so
you're talking about a six times two or
12 bytes per quad right so if you think
about what would happen if we didn't use
indices well if we want to draw a big
batch it would actually be way worse
than that because for every triangle we
have to send down three vertex 3 sets of
vertex data so we'd have to send down 6
whole vertices which are massive right
so indices actually save you a lot of
memory it's the other way around if that
makes sense
I want to regarding involve us
appreciating question if that's all
right
why were the next steps of investigation
into the message box call not working to
try to do it with an indirect call then
next to do it on another thread what was
the line of thinking so the line of
thinking was just I wanted to know if it
was the thread in particular that was
causing the problem like the which
thread he was calling it on in the state
that it was in
so what I wanted to do was move it off
that thread and there's another thing I
want to do if it still doesn't work
which is having passed zero for the
window handle on a separate thread and
I'm just like reducing the number of
possible problems sequentially to figure
out which one is causing the problem
what is your opinion on texture race
versus texture Atlas is why do you
choose to texture race so texture
atlases and texture arrays have
different trade-offs the reason I chose
texture arrays is because they I don't
want to say mipmap properly cuz that's a
kind of a bold statement they map better
than texture Atlas is so texture atlases
have a particularly nasty problem well
couple nasty problems one is that you
can't tile your textures so if you want
a repeating texture you can't do it with
an atlas because there's no way to
specify off atlas coordinates that would
wrap around into the chunk you're
actually using so there's that
limitation and the other limitation is
the fetching outside the Atlas will
actually cause you like fetching to the
side of your fetching outside of the
region of the Atlas you want will
actually pick up other pixel data rather
than nothing so you can't use clamp to
edge and with it with a texture Atlas
what happens is as you mipmap the
texture atlas those textures that are
next to each other
blur together and create a error in mid
mapping so you end up having to leave
tons of space in your texture atlas and
you waste a ton of space that way so
it's six of one half dozen of the other
because the strength of texture atlas is
is that you can place things arbitrarily
close together right like you can you
don't have to make everything be a
square right
but the downside is well you sort of
also can't because when you mipmap it
you'll get incorrect results if you
don't leave lots of empty space there so
it's hard to kind of it's hard to kind
of think that through I guess but that's
that's the you have to make a trade-off
you have to figure out which one you
want to use there and I think texture
arrays are kind of better in that case
does the window size have anything to do
the tuning of the T value in the
renderer no it shouldn't the T value in
the render has nothing to do with the
window size the window size is just how
big the thing appears on the user screen
but that the T value is strictly about
the ratio of the height in camera space
which is irrelevant at which in which
the screen size is not relevant
texture areas require all textures to be
the same size and have the same number
of MIT Maps though yes but that's fine
for our purposes
isn't that a significant limitation it's
I mean it's a limitation but it allows
you to do a lot of things you can't do
right like you can wrap your textures
and tie all the textures and you can get
clamped to zero properly in all cases
yeah whereas like you say atlases
require a bunch of pixel shader
instructions if you want to do a bunch
of that stuff so you know you will be
slower right because now you've got all
these operations happening inside the
texture atlas and you pay for those
they're not free
what are we going to mipmap and Hanuman
here will everything now we will
probably generate MIT maps for
everything
how long has Fall Break gonna be I don't
know just a couple weeks oh good
somebody rewrote the dependency Walker
for Windows 10 yeah I'm down with that
let's see
so let's go ahead and get this thing see
how it does
a PE view is that a thing that views
executables or something
oh that's a command-line utility maybe
can't say that's looking particularly
good at the moment
well that works better
do you know if texture sampling is
implemented in hardware well yeah of
course it's implemented in hardware what
do you mean
jus-just or i/o do you mean like is the
texture coordinates computed in hardware
maybe that part I guess I don't know
currently that's a good questions test
your sampling is almost certainly
implemented in hardware because it has
to be very fast but I don't know about
the UV coordinate editing that's a good
question
well here's what I would say though the
even if you implemented it yourself you
could implement it faster with the
texture array than you could with an
Atlas though right because an atlas has
to do a lot of crazy checking it can't
rely on the power of two mipmap stuff or
any of those things so it's gonna do
like real divides and I don't think I
don't think it matters where it's
implemented in hardware or not in that
sense how this is are just going to be
slower period right I mean cuz it's just
a harder it's more math to do an atlas
than it is to do a texture right text
array is just simpler its power of two
dimensionally and so all the standard
tricks apply like you don't have to do
any complex stuff like you would with an
atlas right
I've read the sequel ass this is just
about paradigms what sets apart the
functions you have made to construct
struck certain ways like get standard
camera from the methodology around
constructors in C++ that I presume you
dislike or are they actually similar um
so I guess it depends what you mean let
me let me pull up an example or the
example that you're talking about just
so we're clear so I assume you're
talking about this get standard camera
here so I'll start with the most the
simplest and most basic thing that I
think is terrible about C++ right so
let's look at how this would happen in
C++ with a constructor so this is a
constructor and it would look like this
right so this is what it would look like
if you were in C++ uh so first things
first I don't know if the user wants to
waste their time initializing this
object or not right I have no idea
there's a number of ways they might want
to initialize it so in the usage code
they might want to say some number of
things
these are all things I might want to say
right I might want to say give me
whatever the default is
give me zero give me uninitialized right
here's the C version and I could even
say default camera right so here's the C
version of this thing here's the
imaginary one that I wanted to write and
you can see they're actually fairly
close right where does it fall down well
mostly in this line and the reason that
it falls down is because C isn't smart
enough to overload on this right so I
can't I can't do that exactly because
it's not something I'm allowed to do in
that way so you know you're stuck with
that which is which is slightly less
good but it's almost the same so now if
we wanted to do this with constructors
how would we do it well now I end up in
a situation where I pretty much have to
make a totally separate set of typing
just to make that happen right I can't
do anything even close to this once I
have constructors because instructors
constructors are all implicitly named
the same thing as the class and use
there's no way to differentiate between
them
right like I have the this is now the
only thing I can do period I can't even
get the other ones at all right so what
I would need to do now is say well okay
I mean I suppose technically speaking I
can do this one still probably I don't
really remember Cassie plus plus
evolved a bit since a lot actually since
the last time I ever programmed in it
seriously I don't remember it wouldn't
have let you do this then but it
probably lets you do this now because we
haven't like unless we blocked which a
lot of people do but if we brought
blocked an operator equals down here or
something I think it would let us do
this because I think this is just an
assignment constructor at that point so
either that's gonna call this path which
we have not disallowed and so which will
be created correctly for us or it's
gonna call the operator equals I think
it's gonna call that one the copy
constructor by normal C++ rules so we
haven't disallowed that so that one will
work this one there is no zero zeros not
on the table so the question I'm sorry
there is no uninitialized so I can't
just not initialize it yet so the
question becomes well how would I do
that
right like how would I make an
uninitialized version and the answer is
now I have to make some monkey business
here that I I don't know I mean like
this I guess
so it's like okay
you know that's the uninitialized one I
guess the other thing I could do is use
a policemen operator to well that
doesn't really work in this case so like
I don't know I don't even know if this
actually works but this one I don't know
how to get this one to work at all I
don't know how to say I just I'm gonna
initialize this later right but let's
say that this did work right even if
this or not that it worked let's say
that this was acceptable to you this is
not acceptable to me as a syntax but
let's say that it was or that you went
out of your way to now do
like okay you know uninitialized or okay
let's say I do something less terrible
and I don't know right now the question
is well now I can't even make that
happen directly to this thing either
right I now have to do like well okay
let's create a new one of these and copy
construct it over or something right
which is what I'm doing here but it also
makes it hard for me to do the other way
round where if I didn't want to spent if
I didn't want to rely on that I could
have done this right um and that's nice
to have that flexibility here I would
now have to use a really ugly placement
new syntax which is like I don't even
remember what it is you know I'm talking
about there right it's it's horrible
place intact
it's this garbage here so
[Music]
here it is
so now you have to do this absolute
garbage right we're in order to get the
constructor called I have to do this so
I have to do new address of camera right
to get that to happen and then this is
the type here right so it's camera and
then that's my camera I mean I guess I
can just not do that right which is nuts
I mean I don't even know like so you can
see why this I just
there's no it's not like you can't do
the things it's just they did a terrible
job with that right I mean it's just
it's really dumb I mean if you even
thought about it for half a second what
you'd realize is there's just multiple
phases to the things that you do
destructs you declare their layout you
provide ways in which they can be
initialized you state when and where you
want them to be initialized right and
those things should just be exposed to
the to the programmer none of those
things were done here right you know if
that the half decent way to do this
would have been like you know like this
right and then you would have just done
like oh alright you know here's the
things that you can do for that or if
you didn't like that you could just do
it like this and like every would
wouldn't immediately know what that was
and you could have all of the options
that you wanted and furthermore if you
wanted to change it later you could just
call it right you just be like hey this
camera here
I want to reinitialize this camera so
it's like what's the what's the actual
camera that you're gonna do oh I'm gonna
do you know that and so I don't know
what you want the syntax to be here to
differentiate this from something that
returns the thing so maybe you could
just use your scope operator or the dot
if you wanted right or something here
you know or you could do that if you
wanted I don't care what you want the
syntax to be whatever you know whatever
you want in that case some way of
defining another one would be that I
suppose but just something halfway
decent would allow you to do this
another way to do it would just be to
say look it's actually we don't care
these could like define them that way
and let them actually be those functions
and just say that the definition of a
constructor is something inside the
class that returns that thing right and
then this just it does that it's like oh
I wanted one of those then you can also
do this if you wanted right all of these
things would be better the one lady is
so boneheaded it just I don't even know
it's like it's like the worst possible
thing so I just don't use it cuz it's
just stupid the syntax is bad it forces
you to do weird things to like try and
to do even the basic stuff like it's
just obvious
so there's an API principle that I
introduced called granularity right the
idea is that if you have a series of
operations you never make a feature of
your language or your API be that those
things are removed and you have to call
them at a coarser level so if allocation
and initialization are two things that
happen to objects you never say that
those two things happen together what
you do is you provide a way to do one
and you divide the way do the other and
those are both good you make them good
first then you provide a nice way of
doing them both at the same time for
when that is appropriate right and you
make all of those things good you never
start at the high level and say oh crap
sometimes now people don't want to do
them together we don't really like that
so we'll make this weird placement new
thing to sort of get around the facts
but it's kind of janky and weird or
whatever right and blah blah blah
you always build up from the steps that
you would do if you were doing it all
manually you always make those perfect
and then you condense condense condense
up higher and higher and higher until
you get to the you know the highest
level version of your API but they don't
do that in C++ C++ always goes the other
way around somebody has some idea about
how you should program you should
program with constructors and
destructors later on someone's like hey
man I don't want to initialize and
allocate this thing at the same time I
want to do those separately and they're
like oh okay
here's this jakie new syntax we did to
fix that problem and you're like oh well
but I want multiple ways of initializing
it and they're like oh huh well here's
this really janky way to fix that right
and they end up with this thing that is
like all these different patches on top
of patches to try and restore what the
basic functions that you already had
were that you lost when going to their
new higher-level feature right that's
just dumb
Martin said I was second Dutton excuse
independence Agra which it won't show
anything okay so it can't browse that
Matt that that's fine I mean I don't
care I don't need to browse dotnet
dependencies back to the message box pre
few man sir removing the filtering of
message oh X 738 made the window appear
huh all right so I guess ox7 38 actually
does need to be there even though it was
pretty bad and slowed us down are you
testing the renderer with the PNG asset
do you think the render would have
better performance with bitmap because
the decoding of that is easier than the
PNG one
oh no no so just to be clear the
performance of the render has nothing to
do with P&amp;G verse bitmap those are
loaded once and then used in memory
decompressed so there's no difference
between the asset whether it's loaded
from PNG or bitmap l : if it says I'm
not sure if it doesn't camera equals
brackets and C++ call the constructor I
don't know probably they did that
because it's bad right but but I don't
know what they did
cheaper cope says also placement new
returns a new object in terms of C
syphilis objects lifetimes so you
technically need to access it through
the pointer return so it's discussing
yeah I mean you probably don't actually
have to impractical what'd have to be
right dark he popped II do you think you
could submit a constructor like that cos
committee I don't know and I don't care
I mean getting off of C++ is a major
priority for me and so you know I I will
not be programming c++ five years from
now either I'll be on my own thing like
our internal stuff at Molly rocket will
grow to the point where we're only using
that or I'll be on ji but there is no
way I'm using C++ you know five years
from now I simply won't let it happen so
I don't care what the Super's loss
committee does they're hard to work with
they've been making bad decisions for
thirty years I don't there's an it's a
it's like rearranging the the chairs and
the Titanic right like they say I mean
it's working with the seagull stuff
committee would probably be more like
rearranging like the ice in the martini
or at my opponent padeen rearranging the
ice and the lemonade on that of someone
who's holding a glass of lemonade on a
deck chair on the Titanic like you're
not even going to move the chairs you're
gonna be able to get like an ice cube
moved around right so yeah
also I'd like to say some meta thing
about that so so one of the things also
that this is a meta thing that I find
kind of annoying so a lot of times
people all this this submit something
the C++ committee thing I use a similar
statement to one that I find equally
sort of misguided which is a lot of
times if you're using something like
commercial product like Visual Studio
and I'm like this thing sucks because of
X they're like well you know you should
have reported that or something and I
think that's kind of just fundamentally
annoying to me at a basic level and the
reason for that is because I don't want
to pay you to be m2 and then be your QA
department like I don't want to pay you
and be your designer the point of paying
for something is that you did the work
and you deliver me something good if I
have to design it for you or I have to
find the bugs for you then that's me
doing the work that you should have done
and nowadays what companies do is they
offload all of the work on to their
customers I have to report the bugs and
I have to do the profiling and point out
why it's slow and I have to argue with
you about why SQL shouldn't be installed
when the thing gets installed or
whatever right and that's fundamentally
annoying like I have a full-time job I
have two jobs really right arguably
possibly three I don't have time to fix
C++ I don't have time to fix Visual
Studio I need some competent people to
do something for once right so like C++
is an open standard so I don't sue
or blame them for being bad because
they're not really getting paid in a
sense but in another sense they are
because most of the people who do this
stuff are actually working at big
companies who do make money on this
stuff right so who knows but it's hard
to blame see what's plus too much
because you know it was what it was it's
not like Java where it was a company's
project or something but something like
Visual Studio is a commercial product
and I pay for it right I actually used
the professional vision version of that
you know what Molly I don't want to be
responsible for figuring out how to make
your product not be bad like that was
kind of supposed to be what I was paying
for and so this kind of notion that
nowadays it's all the community's
problem and it's never the company who
was supposed to just deliver something
good to begin with he's really annoying
and I feel like when you ship something
you should reverse that mentality the
mentality should be we are gonna figure
out how to actually deliver a high
quality thing and it's not up to our
customers to do that work for us and I
feel like that kind of used to be
because you couldn't patch very often
you shipped physical floppies you were
kind of forced to do a better job
nowadays forget it you know it's just
sad anyway it's time for lunch so or
break anyway so I'm gonna go ahead and
do that we'll be back here let's say 15
minutes or so maybe 20 and we'll do the
the sort of the foray into seeing seeing
how to speed up our rendering and
texture changes