hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could cleat game live on
stream we are at the immediate moment
about start doing some handmade hero
programming but I just wanted to mention
for people who watched yesterday's
attempt to build tensorflow we left it
running so it could just run because we
know that tensorflow takes hours to
build and it did but it eventually
finished and if you run it again now
which is I just did I it does complete
so I mean I don't know that we really
built tensorflow perfectly but it sort
of works so now if we build it we tried
doing a rebuild it took 48 seconds to
not do anything but tell us it was built
and now if you do it hot
it only takes 4 seconds to not build
anything which by the way is the time it
takes to completely build a fade hero
from start to finish but hey it works so
now we have a tensorflow build and so at
some point I think we might play around
with that I think a fun thing to do
would be to go take one of their
Colonels and show how if you just
rewrite it in C it's probably like 20
lines of code and compiles in you know
instantaneously because it was so
hilarious how bad the tensorflow build
was I mean and you know I've never seen
it build that bad before in my life
I mean sure there are builds that are
worse than that somewhere but it's it's
amazing to me that that you know it's
amazing to me that that trillion dollar
companies I mean it just goes to show
you that what we do with programming is
I would say it's largely just mostly
about honor I guess to program well
because it's pretty clear that you can
have no idea what you're doing and still
have actually into our company right and
tensorflow is the proof of that there
just isn't competition out there right
so mostly your success as a company is
about things that have nothing to do
with programming because if it was about
programming there's no way this would
ever fly all right so let's go ahead and
get started on regular handmade hero
[Music]
where we left off before is we were sort
of at the point where we're like look if
we want to do some some reasonable you
know lighting we're trying to play
around that and seeing what we could do
to get it to work and it's just that's a
very big investment right and we played
around with some things we weren't
really able to do anything particularly
simple that would allow us to get
reasonable lighting going on so we have
a fairly complex set of things in there
now
but they're not really quite what they
need to be you can see that our
interpolation works pretty well and if
we just have you know a basic single
light source and stuff surprisingly we
get really good results out of that but
you know that we don't have a really
solid plan for how we extend past that
and there's just a lot of work that has
to be done in order to get there so I
don't know exactly how we want to go
forwards with this we have really two
things that we could do because we do
have at least now a sense of how the
lighting actually is working and if you
look at how it works right now where I'm
hopping around with this little sort of
circular light source in the system now
we could just kind of tune that out and
say that's what we're gonna work with
for lighting for now is a few little
circular light sources and then come
back to lighting kind of at the end of
things and try to tweak that and get
that more proper when we're we're a
little bit further down right by the way
is this is this work so it's worth
noting that I don't think we get sound
from this machine at the moment which I
suppose is into problem but I should
make sure that works the streaming
machine because at some point when we're
doing work on that sort of stuff we
should probably should probably make
sure we can place sounds from this
machine onto the stream because right
now like that's playing a little sound
effect but it's not coming out on the
audio for the stream so that's a little
bit a little bit busted so I guess what
I would say is I think maybe what I'll
do
and again I'm not 100% sure what I want
to do here but I think maybe what I'll
do is just
spend a few weeks going over the
lighting with a fine-tooth comb putting
in what I think should roughly be you
know the lighting for a reasonable
working solution just because I would
like to do that and then we'll just take
whatever is at the end of that and we'll
say that's gonna be our lighting for all
the development process and we're not
going to go any further with it right
and then when we're done with that I
will just we'll move on and we'll finish
the game that way and if we want to you
at the end we can come back and you know
rathole on lighting for as long as we
want if we want to keep improving the
quality of it because again lighting is
just a really is one of the most
complicated things you can possibly do
in graphics is any kind of realistic
lighting or even just propagation any
kind of secondary bounce lighting and so
I would like to you know limit the
amount of time we spend on that and
there's other stuff that we have to work
on anyway we want to finish some of the
entities stuff and we want to finish
like we want to make sure we're grabbing
regions appropriately like right now
we're sort of not you can see the look
that's not getting the stuff that's down
there we should be picking that up and
it's not being picked up until we move a
little bit forward right so there's some
things like with bounding where the
lights are calculated and which things
are pulled into the active set that we
do want to like get a little bit more
tightened up for development as well
because we'd like this to be you know
it's pretty close to just being fully
presentable as a game right in terms of
like the presentation quality's up there
and if we just finished up some of these
things and we have a fully presentable
game that we wouldn't really have to
worry about the presentation quality up
until we basically are finished right
all right so like looking over the
lighting we had a couple different
aspects of it that needed to really get
addressed so one of the main things that
we're not doing right now that we kind
of need to do is we don't have really
any concept of what the lighting values
actually are so that was an issue that
we're gonna have to address and then we
also have the problem of we don't so
when we're actually doing the lighting
computations we don't really have a
what's going on there either because
when we're actually sampling the
lighting points we don't actually have
anything we don't actually have any way
of getting that to work properly at the
moment it's it's buggy and weird so we
have to kind of like get the raycasting
stuff working properly as well what we
did verify at least to a first
approximation is that our rate caster is
working properly at least we did some
rudimentary debugging of that so that it
looks at least appears that our rate
cast properly can tell when there's
interference and when there's not and so
on right so that seemed to be working
and so I think we can more or less
assume that that is correct right and so
you know we think this parts working
okay and we think that the the red cast
is working okay but we don't the light
summation is not really and the light
persistence from frame to frame like
that sort of stuff isn't really working
and so we need to kind of get those into
a rudimentary state of working so that
we can at least know that that system is
is okay and go from there right okay so
what we need to do now is switch over to
the other well so I guess there's two
things we can do now one thing is we
could leave it the way it is at the
moment
so right now you know we are doing a
single light that you can kind of see
here is moving around the player what we
could do and maybe what we should do is
we could figure out how we want this to
work in terms of what the lighting
values actually refer to so right now we
just have arbitrary floats in there that
are just saying like okay at some point
we're gonna map zero to one to a
lighting value but we never really had
any idea of what that means right so we
don't actually have any correspondence
to the real world of what the lighting
values actually are and furthermore we
don't have any exposure function so like
at the
and we don't actually try to map these
light values to into any kind of a space
that makes sense right we don't have the
idea that there's values that go into
lighting that eventually get resolved in
some way right so one of the things that
we probably want to do is get that
working properly so that we can at least
visualize these things well and the
other thing that I'd like to do there is
have a way of visualizing them in some
way that we can use that that doesn't
that allows us to see the lighting
without any that allows us to see the
lighting without any weirdness like so
that we can actually like see maybe like
blue is no light green is like in the
sweet spot of like relatively what we
would expect letting to be and then you
know red is like the breasts bright as
the Sun or some you know what I mean
like something that would allow us to
really have a better handle on what's
going on there
all right so let's go ahead and try to
go further down all of these lines in
order to get us warmed up I'm gonna say
let's do something we've been made do
for a very long time which is let's just
make the render or hot reloadable so
that we can anytime we want change
anything in the renderer and it'll just
automatically rerun so if we go into
win32 hand-made dot cpp what you can see
here is that when we're doing stuff we
actually have the ability to load
multiple dll's here and we know that
because we load a dll for the game and a
dll for the renderer right so if we take
a look at the DLLs for the game for
example you can see this stuff happening
here so you can see looking for a
handmade dll there right and it does
this sort of like looking for a lock
file and and figuring out what it should
do with that to determine when it should
reload the game but then there's also
like a renderer and that renderer I
don't actually remember exactly how we
link that in but I think maybe it's just
hardly
in at the moment I guess I could be
wrong about that yeah so as you can see
here like we we kind of hard link in a
render earth there right so so these are
all like bringing that like the renderer
code in here and I don't know if we ever
actually load it as a DLL we might let's
let's take a look I don't remember if we
actually did that part or not let's see
did you do P sound
no it doesn't look like it it doesn't
look like it so if you go over here to
the build directory and we look at what
we've got you can see us building the
the handmade open gelled yellow oh you
know what yes we do we just load it
somewhere else forgot about that so I
believe what happens is this right here
right so this stuff right here right so
here's the the call that we actually
make into the renderer to get it started
right so I believe what happens is the
renderer loading there is just do this
the renderer loading there is just
calling get proc address to initialize
the renderer so it's like actually right
here it's this that actually does it and
you can see that it says like okay I'm
gonna load the DLL through here and then
I'm going to initialize it right so I
think all we really want to do here is
say ok let's move this stuff off into
let's like make a common system for
having our dll's be reloaded so that
this one can also get reloaded any time
that it changes so if we look at like
handmade if the win32 handmade code what
we could do is pull out the code that
actually does that reloading so that we
can use it for other things and if you
look at what's going on here you can see
we have this win through to game code
thing and it's got the game code DLL the
file time of the DLL so we know when it
changed it has the functions that are
used by that so that it can be called
into and then it has an is valid
right which basically says like did we
actually were we actually able to load
one of these things and what you can
sorta see here is like this is actually
pretty generic like the only difference
between this and this is which of these
functions are there like which things
you actually call into so in you know if
we wanted to we could sort of pull this
out into something that you know made
maybe a little bit more sense we could
pull this out and these would all say
the same and only these callbacks here
would change right so if we wanted to
you could imagine we had something like
win32 loaded code or something or win32
you know i don't know what we want to
call it win32 something win32 code stuff
win32
[Music]
mm I don't know I'm gonna call it when
three or two loaded code so we're gonna
call it and at you know immediately we
could say well we know that that this
right would be there we go we know that
this would be everything that we need to
do the hot reloading part of this and
this is the only part that really
changes right and what we could do is we
could make even this part do roughly
what we want it to do because we could
consider these particular things here
where we have like these these callback
pieces we could sort of try to make
those be a little bit more generic right
so for example you can you can imagine
if we just did something I don't know
like say this we could just say look
this thing's gonna load some functions
and it has some pointers here and then
we're just gonna say which ones they are
for anyone who actually loads it so we
could do something like that right where
we would use it in this way and then you
would just point whatever this table is
here you would point it at this and use
it in your own way right and the other
way we could do this is just make this
thing be utility and that utility just
sits at the top of anyone who wants to
actually do this right and so you know
maybe this is a better way to go about
it I don't know but here's just I'll
sketch it out so let's suppose we have
this as win through two loaded code here
and we just say look this is the loaded
part of this and then the other part
lives down here and so then later if we
want to we can make another one of these
which is like win32 renderer code and we
just say look there's a loaded on top of
that and this part here right
gets the
the load call right you know I'm saying
and so I guess what what this would look
like is this part that's at the top you
know you're responsible for calling an
update function on it anytime you want
it to check and then you load what you
want to load out of it any time you get
to a point where anything you know and
you think you would need to write so
that would be relatively straightforward
to do and you know you could imagine
doing it even kind of more ridiculous
than that and there's a couple of
different things we could do here that
would kind of be interesting to so if
you think about this part of the code
right one of the things that we did that
maybe wasn't the smartest thing is we
could also just say what if there's only
like one thing that actually that you do
here which is sort of a like initialize
I could imagine doing this so that
there's really just one thing so there's
just like something like this in fact
that seems like probably the right thing
to do I'm gonna go ahead and say this so
bear with me for a second so let's
suppose we had a thing that's basically
like a win32 loaded code entry point and
yeah yeah yeah yeah I think this might
be the right thing to do so bear with me
here and I'm just gonna sketch out what
I think this might look like so let's
suppose we just made a thing that's like
a loaded code entry point right and what
this thing is going to do is it's going
to have some kind of a be 32x return
right and that's going to say whether or
not it was able to
consider itself valid so that's where
that will go and when you do this thing
what you get past what you pass in is
some kind of a like you know code table
right or a function table and it's gonna
fill that out for you and it gets past
the module to load from so whatever the
you know the out external code did it's
gonna get that passed in right and you
know we may never even need to actually
store this this may actually just be
done in line but anyway point being this
is what it would look like and then we
would have win32 loaded code entry point
so what we would basically do is say all
right you're gonna call one of these and
so really what there is is there's a
win32 so this win32 game code thing here
for example right it's really just going
to have a function table in it and so it
could be win32 you know function table
or whatever
32 game function table
right and then the same thing would kind
of be true here right so you would end
up with a function table that you know
in 32 render function table right that
seems better to me because then these
all look exactly the same for all
intents and purposes and so we could
probably just get rid of them and we can
just have the loaded code thing be the
only thing that we actually need right
and so I think I'm gonna try sketching
out how that works and doing it this way
I think that would be better right and
it also gives us the opportunity to
perhaps make all of our code be hot
reloadable even the platform code
because at that point we could sort of
extend it forward so I'm gonna play
around with this a little bit and I'm
gonna see what happens if we go down
this route so the first thing I'm going
to do is say what if I get rid of this
so I have a function table and a loaded
code thing and I know these two things
work together right and what is just
working through the compile errors I'm
gonna sort of massage the code that it's
in there currently to see how I want
this to work out right and so if you
look at this win32 load game code stuff
right where it's going to load in the
the dll here what I'm basically saying
is all right I want that function table
to to get initialized and well you know
you know I'm thinking this can even be
automated one step further than that
[Music]
yeah okay so let me go even one step
further than that so we probably don't
even need to do this manually right so
what you can probably do here if you
want to is this can actually also
probably just be a table and since these
are just function pointers that go in
order we can probably just literally say
like all right there's gonna be we can
probably just pass this with it and it
would automatically update the function
table for us because everything's just
gonna be a series of get prog-rock
address calls right so we can actually
just do that honestly that probably just
works right all right
so let me just go ahead and do that
again here's where metaprogramming would
be nice because you wouldn't have to
type this twice but you know C++ they
don't know what they're doing over there
all right so here we go
in this win32 load game code here where
it returns a game code all I'm going to
really change that to be is something
where we have where we pass it the
loaded code thing that we want to use so
like here we would say all right here's
your loaded and then this function table
here is just going to be like you pass
it what you wanted to do with with these
three things and we can bundle those
together like win32 function table
definition or something like that and we
just say like here's the functions that
we're gonna write here's the function
count and here's the function names
write something like this so you would
say all right here's the loaded code
that we're working with and you know I
guess I could even expand it a little
bit further and say well or we could
even put this in there right
right so I guess in that sense we could
just say okay you know what let's make
the loaded code structure just do that
for us
even better so you can pass one of these
right here's the loaded code thing we're
going to use and it's not going to do
that anymore
and we're gonna do this so then we say
alright win32 load game code let's go
ahead and load this up and the way we're
gonna do that is that all of this stuff
that normally happens here right is
actually going to just fill it out into
this loaded function so in here we do
get file attributes and we have the lock
file name get the standard all that
stuff will be the same but now we're
gonna do it in here right I'm also gonna
have this not include any reference to
game code exactly right so you can see
here these are the actual names of this
I guess so I guess we actually want to
do these
okay like so and so here we're just
gonna say alright we want to load these
things we're gonna load them off of the
dll like so right and you can see this
starting to collapse down so now we'll
have those names over here we're sort of
saying that the is valid is actually
gonna be something that either all of
them work or they don't so you know this
shouldn't say either the callbacks and
we'll just say like the callbacks can be
zero you must check before calling or
check thee is valid boolean in your two
little code okay so now we're okay I
don't know what that's about
exactly but I guess we're just doing
some kind of checking there anyway so
here's some a bunch of nonsense and
we're doing some reloading here I guess
that's about whether or not we want to
we don't want to pile up too many files
I guess or something anyway so we're
gonna load the DLL in and then instead
of doing each of these manually what
we're gonna do is we're gonna loop over
the the function index right because now
we know we've got this isn't actually
called result I suppose it's called
loaded also this temp DLL number
shouldn't really be in the state should
it it should be in the loaded I would
think so I'm also gonna do this I think
that makes more sense yeah
and that's just looking for a bunch of
different versions of the same name
because we don't know which random
version it output right if I remember
correctly it was because win 30 is
because Visual Studio is terrible and
locks the PDB so you can't actually we
had to make it so that it output
different ones I think oh well and also
there's another reason for it it's
because we wanted to keep the old DLL
loaded yeah so basically I guess it's
not Visual Studio it's actually just
Windows cousin Linux you would just have
an inode for that so it wouldn't matter
right yeah okay so anyway we'll probably
want this because this temp T a little
number thing is gonna have to be
something that we manage more carefully
and we'll probably do that per DLL so
put that in there then we'll have loaded
like so and the temp to ulil name is
there which is what we want and then we
go through however many of these there
are so however many functions that are
going to be and each one of them gets
loaded so we're gonna look this is this
right here actually is a pointer to a
pointer so for each of these we're gonna
say alright whatever the length one of
these things is right we're gonna do the
get proc address on it and we're gonna
pass the name of the function we're
trying to load and that's gonna load it
right and for each one of those we'll
also know we'll just say like alright
the is valid flag is going to start off
equaling true but if any of these don't
work
oops right
go if any of these don't work so if we
do a get proc address on one of these
and it doesn't work so it'd basically be
this right then we know that the oops
and that's not result as I guess it's
this then we know that it's actually not
valid anymore
and the game should just be like at now
not gonna work right so I think that's
all we really need to do and what we
wanted to do here I guess is clear this
so I guess what we want to do is have
another one of these loops over here
which basically says and and I guess we
don't really need to do a loop because
we have a zero rake all right so we can
actually do is just say look if if it
wasn't valid so like if this was not you
know if that wasn't in the works that
wasn't in the mix then we can just say
clear out this this table so if we if we
failed
if either we couldn't load the thing or
whatever then just set them to zero so
the game kind of stops at that point and
there's an error and maybe we want to
display an error here I don't know hard
to say
anyway so that would do all of our
loading for us right and this will load
anything now so we can prep these for
arbitrary sets of code and it will just
produce what we want right and we don't
have to do anything else so the only
thing we had to load there or change
there I guess is in the state we got
this temp DLL number thing and that's
now because we might load many dll's and
maybe multiple of those dll's actually
would need to know things like which one
of them they were loading just like the
other one did so we probably need that
to be you know per DLL so we're gonna
have to leave it like that and boobs
and so that will load everything for us
and now we just have to change the other
code to use this more effectively so now
if we look down here and we've got
unload game code which is the complement
of this right really all we need to do
there is say hey actually we want to
make this work with anything so what we
would do is just say if you pass us
whatever the loaded thing is here we're
going to go ahead and tell you that it's
unloaded so we're gonna do this we're
not gonna free it because we don't do
that anymore we just let those things
pile up we're gonna say that it's not
valid anymore and then we're gonna do
this right and we could if we wanted to
and I don't know that we do but we could
say that like hey if we have a load and
unload maybe what we'll do is just say
this here item right it's a thought okay
so now here's the people who actually
use this stuff and if we take a look
here we've got this win32 loaded code
that we might want to do for like the
game code for example and what we'd want
to do now is just say win32 load code
right and we'd pass exactly the same
things that we were passing before all
of this garbage right and now we just
need to pass like this thing to have it
initialize and we need to have specified
this to be something that actually has
some state right so we want to actually
say okay the function count is going to
be equal to however like this is our
functions right so the function count is
going to be equal to however many
functions we actually have in our table
we know we want an actual
game code thing that's like this right
this has the functions in it so we're
just gonna say alright point the
functions at this game structure right
cuz that's what that's gonna be
so fill that thing out for us and then
you know get the names going in there
now when we load the code it should just
run right we shouldn't have any problem
with that right it should just be able
to load it using that information and
then yeah so in here where we do the
compare file time to see whether the
executable needs to be reloaded also not
sure what this is about or why it's
turned off oh I guess this will restart
the entire thing but we don't do that
anymore you can see us doing a win32
load here here's an unload and a load
and so we would want to do those again
right and so a couple things about that
if you now start to look at what's going
on you can see that those are passed
frequently and they don't change right
so what we probably want to do here is
actually weld those in so let's go just
do that really quickly too so here at
win32 load code the other thing that I'm
not sure about is what is that state
variable actually used for because we
don't use the state variable anywhere
here so I don't actually know what with
to to build XZ path name what is that
what does it actually use the state for
so like all of this stuff should
probably be just in the loaded code
thing right so I think this is actually
not what we want anymore
right I think like we want to just weld
this together because yeah all of this
stuff all of this stuff is kind of a
little bit wrong yeah so I think that
stuff can just be put into the loaded
code thing so I think that's what we
actually want so let's also do that so
if I say that this is actually this and
in here we say we're gonna do that right
so there's our function now and then
instead of passing the state here we're
gonna pass win32 loaded code like so
exci file name state XE file name one
all this garbage right I think let me
just double check you look at what
that's actually holding there it is
well okay so you know what
the only thing I would say is actually
the no okay that's just the path so we
don't actually that will be the same for
everything so never mind we can leave it
like this this won't change per loaded
that's just the path that's just the
path so we're good
alright so it's really only these things
that we would need to actually weld in
there because it's just redundant right
so what we'd rather do is this that
right so um that when we do a load we
don't have to pass anything new right so
hmm excuse me
so in the loaded code thing we can just
say alright in here we just have two
pointers one is the full path and one is
the lock full path and then when we do a
load code on here we don't have to pass
these anymore right because we know that
they actually are just pointing to
something inside the struct itself so we
can say all right this is the full path
and this is the
right okay keep going this right here
just needs to look at the game code this
here needs to look at the DLLs right
time but you can see that this now this
whole procedure here needs this part now
needs to be something you can just call
to make your stuff do what it needs to
do so we want this to be kind of
encapsulated into a little unit that we
can just use if you look at how we have
to sort of stride this out we want it in
two pieces because some people need to
call it in two stages
so like we want to grab this and this
and kind of have them be separate pieces
right so what we want to do is do a
thing like
let's say this something like that let's
say so I did that so you know something
where we say look let's check for a
change and a return this and that's just
this right here so this part where we're
like let's check for a code change check
for code change is just this code right
and it's gonna take one of these win32
loaded code things and it needs to know
the full path to the DLL so this part
right here right it needs to figure out
what the last right time is for that
thing and that it needs to compare those
two right so whatever the new DLL all
right time is and the old one right and
the only thing that I'm not super clear
on here is I guess so are we basically
saying that thing just updates in place
I don't really know also this should
probably be that right so anyway this is
what we're gonna do here and that'll
encapsulate this part into something we
can reuse for everybody so that and then
like we need something here where we can
take this part which is the unload and
the tree try set of things so this needs
to be like this needs to be updated in
here so I don't know what we're gonna
call this but like reload
like so and that'll do this reload it'll
do the try thing it'll say like as long
as this thing is not valid we're gonna
try again we're gonna try a bunch of
times to get it to load and see if we
can right
and then we're gonna you know we're
gonna sleep on that so if we grab these
out now and we make this thing the oops
and we make this thing be the loading
off the came code I guess this also has
to do that then if I just drop these
down back where we were doing went
through to low code we should be good to
go like that right
I think seems plausible anyway so let's
go ahead and try to make that work this
right here the only thing I'm a little
confused about is this should take the
deal of less right time now that's fine
it should just work all right fix that
the state here when it does went through
the codes that's gonna need this for
sure
so just pass that down all right so this
is win32 check for code change this has
been through to reload code and now I
think is that it is that everything I
just accidentally deleted we got one
more thing full so this needs to be past
the state there is that is it address of
state what is that I don't know what
that is whereas went through to load
code where'd it go yes just state all
right so let's just finish up the
compile errors and then let's see if it
works at all and from there if it does
work we can from there if it does work
we can then move to the next step which
is putting more things through that path
which is what we want to ideally put
everything through that path I guess all
right so here's the win32 load code what
is it saying assignment within
conditional expression okay yeah I I
know I did that on purpose but all right
thank you mister compiler
so I guess we'll do this if 'function
then assign it else we're screwed right
reload code has to return a value no it
doesn't like false incorrect but I think
we're good now alright so all I really
want to do now is just start putting
more things in that system and I mean
hey we at least know it worked once so
if I want it to to verify that this
works in handmade here I need to do
something right so what I would need to
do here is figure out something that can
make a change to that would immediately
update itself I assume in the world mode
for example one thing I could do is
change the debug light so because that
would be obvious so if we go in here and
you can see like we've got this maybe
what I'll do is I'll make the debug
light much higher up and verify that it
actually changes what the lighting is
yep and then I'll go down here and
change it back so now it'll move it down
again and all right so we know that that
code reloading is working because I just
changed code on the fly and it worked
just fine
and so now the thing is like alright can
we get that to happen in the renderer as
well right and also if we wanted to now
we could we could make it push more
things in there so
you know one thing we might want to do
is make it so that actually there's just
a win32 we can make it so there's just a
win32 thing in general that reloads
itself
so that all of the platform code is also
hot reloadable I mean I don't know that
we care because we probably like most of
the stuff doesn't run every frame so I'm
not sure that there's much used to it
because most of the stuff is like
startup stuff and that you can't hot
reload because it's already happened
right so that may not make a sense but
at least the renderer we definitely want
to do that for so I'm gonna go ahead and
take a look at what that would entail so
in here if we said you know that this
part looks to the win32 in it default
renderer right so that's coming from the
renderer DLL and if I want to I nope no
bad so if I want to I should be able to
go to the renderer code here and redo
how this is happening right so you can
see this
I mean really this is just the case of
just not calling this code right I mean
we can leave this code in here if we
want to but I mean I mean really I think
that's most is so you know there's a
global called
you know went through to render function
names and it's just that right and it
knows that it's only got one of these
things so you know that would just work
so in the case where we want to do our
own system now for this which we do I
should be able to do exactly the same
thing that I did with the other one so
this nonsense here right so I should be
able to say alright if we want the
renderer to do this as well then back
where it actually loads that up and we
kind of need to say what that file name
would be here as well so I guess we
again I don't know the reason that this
code exists here at all is just so that
people can not have to write that
themselves out in their own thing and I
don't know that I really want to keep
doing that so what I might say is maybe
this goes away right maybe this goes
away and what we do here is say that
this this stuff here actually moves into
the renderer test right so the renderer
test itself is going to need to do this
part of the code like in here where it
loads the thing which
is who knows where right here I guess
yeah so in here where it lives the thing
we would just say yes so you have to do
that yourself now so if you want this
stuff that's on you
right and so that code just goes in here
I don't know why this would be separate
like I don't know why so let me just
yeah
so that doesn't matter at all
so this part right here can just be
welded together it just looks like that
and that right this goes away and our
renderer test should still work just
fine now cuz it's just calling the same
code it was calling yep
so this code should be fine and now we
just need in our other side of things we
can just use this to create our own you
know function table here right
so inside win32 handmade it's we're
gonna do our own version so that we can
hot load it instead of using the
currently existing thing so we're gonna
have a win32 renderer function table and
in fact we could even put that in here
and do this right okay so now we can
just yeah so now we can just call the
exact same calls are calling before and
and just point them at the renderer and
that should be the end of it now they'll
be a little more work involved because
the renderer is not hot loadable at the
moment because i don't think it knows
like we have to put into thing that
knows that when you're going to reload
it you have to call the function in it
that's like shut down the GL stuff and
then restart it later right because it
has to recompile all its shaders and all
that garbage right so we're gonna have
to have a thing that tells it to like
redo stuff but other than that
we should be okay so so we will have a
little bit more work to do but that's
okay we've got some time left in the
stream so it should be pretty reasonable
right I'll forego don't by the way yeah
I know we can turn off the assign within
conditional expression but we don't want
to right we already turn off lots of
them but that one I think is not a
particularly good idea right so here's
the the warnings we thought were a good
idea to turn off and that one we wanted
to keep it okay so moving along let's go
ahead and actually call this in win32
hand-made here
and so that dll again maybe we want that
name to be standardized I'm not sure we
do so I may not do that what I may do is
say all right we've got a compilation
thing here we probably need to do the
same stuff as like we probably need to
do literally this and so we have like
oops we probably want to do the handmade
renderer test needs to have that and
what we probably want to do here is say
all right this is the like OpenGL lock
or whatever and
and I think that's what we're looking at
here now the bummer here is that means
that our build up bat probably gets a
little more complicated because again we
got a workaround Windows right and so if
you look at how we build the game you
can see here it's like hey it's gonna do
all this nonsense right like waiting for
this lock and once the lock is done it's
gonna delete it right and maybe you know
since these things get built together
baby what we could do here is actually
reorganize this a little bit and say
alright if the testbed went down here
and the renderer is here let's move that
inside the lock and then we only have to
have one lock right so if I said like
okay here are the renderers so it here
we do like waiting for PDP lock or we
echo to the lock right and then we
rebuild the renderers and the game right
something like that I guess makes sense
so we do compile here of the renderer
using the same technique and in here we
look and you can see like we've got
handmade and then that found random
thing there right and the pound random
on the PDB
hmm
so wait a minute when we do this compile
[Music]
I'm a little confused because that
random number don't remember I got to
watch my own video to remember what we
actually what kind of nonsense we did
here we're only specifying a random one
for the PDB but not for the DOL so I
guess that's because we move the DOL
ourselves yeah
so that's because we move the DLL
ourselves okay so I guess what that
means is that as long as the renderer
just has an arbitrary nonsense PDB we
actually don't have to rename it which
is kind of nice and if we put it inside
this lock then we don't need to locks
either right so basically all we have to
do here I think is just put this right
there right and say that all right so
win32 handmade open jail random PDB and
that should be fine
all of this should just work I think
that way the lock filename doesn't
actually need to be different so instead
of this we don't that can just be
instead of game code lock we can just
have this be like called lock full path
or code lock right and it can just get
used for everything now we can't choose
to have more locks later if we need to
buy multiple t plexi mat right but for
now we don't actually have to do that we
can just use one lock and everybody can
share the same lock right so that seems
good so let's make that happen
and let's make this happen right so
first we're going to start by loading
the renderer in a different way so the
way we're going to do that is just say
ok instead of this code here when we do
a win32 load code we're gonna have this
called renderer code here right and this
is going to be like render a code full
path and this right here is going to be
like win32 renderer function table names
and the actual functions themselves I
guess like we've only got one right oops
and so then when we actually load this
that's supposed to be that we should be
able to just do like hey we loaded this
renderer code and so now we can actually
just call like renderer load renderer
and I think that's it
so we've got a few compile errors here
oh and that's winter so this is renderer
like functions or something
looks like we also need to pass the
window DC they're handmade code win32
render attest no such file or directory
right can't do a pop tea on that yeah
there we go
all right so win32 load renderer needing
the DC is the only weird thing there and
you can see what was happening with that
here we do init default renderer gonna
pass the window we just called gut we
just called get DC on it so I guess it's
just that great um oops
oh no accidentally deleted RC time okay
alright so I think that's all good and
it works so now the question is can we
get it to reload right
and so we're gonna have to change the
structure a little bit of it because in
terms of what we actually call in the
renderer you can see that we've got so
if I jump to that platform render or
structure you can see that there's like
functions in here that you call and we
don't really want those to work this way
anymore right because what we're gonna
do is when we call load we then want to
be able to call like begin frame and end
frame every frame and when we reload we
don't want to call load again right so
when we're just changing things that
happen for frame we don't want that to
actually change things right so we need
to kind of work out how this is going to
happen without there being any weird
problems like that
so because we can't we can't
reinitialize all of opengl I mean
I mean I guess we could the so I mean
the problem right is that we have a
bunch of texture state and so I guess
there's two ways we could do this one is
we could just make it so that the render
just gets strobed and it goes off it
goes the other way I guess we could do
it is just have a call into the asset
system that's like clear everything
right and then we do just reload the
entire renderer so like we shut down
open jail and reload open jail
completely I mean the upside to that is
you know that it's complete but I don't
think I want to do that and the reason
is because if you think about what we'd
actually be using this for so if you
think about what we'd actually be using
the reloading for for it's gonna be like
changing shaders and stuff right and so
we don't want to pay the cost of
resubmitting all of our textures and all
that stuff just to change something in a
shader so we probably want to make that
roundtrip as fast as possible so my
guess is we don't really want to do that
so what we probably want to do is say
that like renderer begin frame and end
frame which are the functions we
actually call here we probably just want
to migrate those out so the platform
renderer would these right would
actually move out to here like that and
then these would actually be things you
actually get proc address so they they
exist external right so begin frame and
end frame actually get exported
so this stuff here right actually gets
exported
and so I assume congeal loader in it or
I don't know yeah
so in here like where it's doing all its
whatever the heck it's doing right so
like in here for these win32 up until
begin frame and win32 opengl and frame
so these callbacks like that are
happening in here would actually just be
called begin frame and end frame and you
would look them up directly right
so I think that's what we would do and
this would go away we would say in here
that there's like begin frame and end
frame and you know maybe these are since
they're the win32 versions maybe they
look like this that I guess is what we
would go with so then if that's actually
happening then we do need one of the
thing which is inside the build up bat
when we say we're gonna build this
renderer we need to say that we're
exporting these right so we can just say
that we've got like you know win32 begin
frame and win32 and frame and off we go
all right so that's all well and good
and happy and dancey and everyone's you
know doing their thing but what we need
to do now is make it so that the
external code that's actually using
these knows to call them not in the
render itself so it can't use that it's
got to use renderer functions right so
let's make sure that happens
but other than that I think now it
should work by having all of those
things loaded so in here we're like
actually it's renderer functions
actually its renderer functions
actually it's Frankenstein's monster and
so on so in this code which is just the
render test code again this part here
wants to now do a little bit more stuff
right and maybe this just gets welded in
and we just have these pieces of code
like right in here so with the win32 in
it default renderer thing that's
happening
we would want to just go like this and
right so we just want this to to load
these up and hopefully that works right
now this goes away I think because
that's going to happen here
and I just want to make sure this
compiles okay mmm
limits is gotta be passed by address now
and this is just going to be like
okay so I also probably want to make
sure this actually works at all so let's
see and I think that's fine it's just
right it's we don't have any lighting
here but you can see that it's still
there we should probably add some
lighting to our render or test or at
least turn it off but so that seems fine
right
all good and then what we want to do is
[Music]
get this one working with reload because
now everything is calling through for
separate functions so you can load and
then also do begin in frame so that
means we could reload and it would in
fact switch which begin and end frame
calls were being used so if we were to
do that we would want to do that
I presume kind of after the end of a
frame or before at the beginning of a
frame one or the other so I'm assuming
what we want to do here is say all right
let's also see hmm where does that
where are we actually updating that down
here here it is so like here after we do
this stuff I'm assuming we would just
after we reload the executable
we'd also reload the renderer if we
wanted to like maybe right there so
right after we end the frame we'd do
something right so maybe we'd say like
if win32 check for code change then
win32 reload code you know what I'm
saying just that and I don't really know
I don't really know what I want to do
after that the settings get like munched
I just need there to be like a strobe
that says hey it got reloaded so you're
gonna have to reinitialize yourself and
there's like a settings there's this
thing right and it's gonna do a diff on
these so we just need like a force
reload kind of thing and I suspect that
probably we could just clear the game
render settings like this one and then
it would just all look new so maybe
that's the easiest thing to do
I don't know but that's that's the next
part so let's just see if this works at
all right now and and then we'll kind of
try to massage things into place so if I
just change something that I know will
will create
issue or whatever right so like if we
run this thing now and you know the game
is doing its thing and I go into the
renderer here and I say oops that's not
the renderer I go into the renderer and
I just say actually I guess I want this
I want the open jail not you know
agnostic code and I say like oh yeah
like you know what let's just let's just
change like the clear color or something
so that like when we do a GL clear here
like we're gonna clear to some other
thing right and this is going to be a
disaster right in theory I think so I
guess I'm not sure I can't see this cuz
my heads behind it so I guess I'm gonna
have to do this which is not what I
would prefer oh you know what I could
put it here that'll work
my head's in the way so where did we
crash we crashed at address zero Oh
so actually I didn't need to do that so
that just means we hit a call into
something that didn't actually exist
I guess meaning the reload didn't work
right I guess I should check these here
to prevent that but that does mean that
something broke because it should have
gotten addresses for those things so so
we did screw something up with the
reload that doesn't screw up when you're
actually just loading it like normally
right so let's go ahead and make that
happen so here you know we we sort of
have an issue we're like you know if if
we can't load the renderer we would need
a fatal error right so
so let me go ahead and issue like a
fatal error because if we can't load the
renderer then we can't even display an
error message right so we would have to
rely on the operating system to put up
like a dialog box on our behalf because
that's the only thing we could possibly
do right so I don't know where the error
message thing is here but that's not the
one I'm thinking of talking about the
platform err win32 error message so yeah
[Music]
I'm just gonna say I'm unable to load a
renderer here and that's actually winter
code and then inside the begin frame
thing for rendering we'd also have to do
the same thing
I mean I guess part of the problem here
though is frame probably gets used
elsewhere look where is frame used yeah
so I mean one of the problems is like I
guess I'm not sure to what extent we can
really run without a renderer you know
what I mean
like more or less this part here
probably just has to say like okay
I assume all this stuff
so like you know the global pause things
a little weird cuz like you know I guess
I don't actually know so limit well
let's do it this way let's actually just
look for where that thing is used so
it's in here
and it's in here and I guess I don't
know if freemen can frame and deal with
the fact like maybe frame end has to
deal with that fact that it doesn't
actually get one of of the render
commands right yeah so I guess what I
would say is like probably we just need
to do this
I mean I really don't know if that's
sufficient
it's really not great I mean this should
probably be rewritten a little bit to
support like not doing these things
right so you know debug start and debug
and
so I guess I can do this so I guess we
can do it like that so this part here is
the only part that this really depends
on and it's a little bit iffy right so
you know we can't initialize the debug
state memory if we don't know like what
the the actual size is there which is
kind of busted so if you look at the
render dim the relationship of rendered
in here it's it's it's because it needs
to place these things and that's just
kind of stupid like the that's just we
shouldn't have done that and I also
don't know that we even really need to
do it anymore you know what I mean
so I don't know like I feel like that's
just stuff that should be removed a lot
of this stuff should get cleaned up at
some point but you know it's debug code
so we don't spend a lot of time on it
after it's sort of in there and working
it's like hard to usually make excuses
to go make it not be bad but in terms of
these right so yeah it's like rendered
in width and we're going half of that
backwards so that's two like the left
corner right or whatever and so these I
don't know like in terms of placing them
I feel like they just want to get placed
repeatedly right so you know who knows
what this gets set to here but basically
like if we got rid of this these would
be the only things that actually like
didn't work right and so I think what we
want to do is just do like
just stop doing any of that
look I don't I don't think any of this
is good or necessary I don't even know
if we're using this anymore but I think
we do want like this to go away right so
we shouldn't have that and that way in
here we can just say look we'll do the
debug start and end only if we actually
have the ability to draw stuff and that
way we can always continue to the debug
collation even when we don't have a
renderer right just for hardening
purposes and so now like we just have to
what's the what's the problem here
should probably compile and debug mode
so I can see what's going on so now we
just have to like actually suss this out
a little bit more but yeah so we
definitely only want the is valid part
of the renderer code here we definitely
only want to call these things in those
circumstances and that needs to be there
but then we have to go figure out why we
why it was becoming invalid in the first
place because it shouldn't have and so
we need to go figure out what's going on
there okay so in theory I mean I would
think if we just like recompile now it
should break right because just the act
of updating the renderer breaks and you
can see yeah we definitely did and
unfortunately like I can't get a call
stack back here so I can't actually see
where I actually am so where I'm
actually jumping into zero I don't know
because since the IP was set to zero I'm
not actually sure I might be able to
still look at it somehow and try to find
out where it is but what I might do is
just step in to the code at that point
and see where we actually go wrong so
what I might do is say all right let's
go to the code that actually does the
reload
because we're assuming that this is the
problem and let's just see if it is
right so here's me recompiling and like
we should get a breakpoint here at some
point
Oh hmm not sure why it didn't let me set
a breakpoint there all right so we may
have to compile in debug mode I guess
this doesn't know I guess where that is
all right so here's compiling a debug
and so in debug mode hopefully we can
get a breakpoint on that particular
thing so I'm gonna go ahead and rebuild
and so we've stopped here at win32
reload code which is where I expected it
to stop and I'm just going to step into
it here so you can see the load code
attempt and it thinks it succeeded right
so so it thinks that it actually did
load the code so let's see what it that
was bad
I didn't mean to do that well I can
still look at what I wanted to look at
so if we look at renderer code here then
the function table that's actually here
I suppose I should check it this way
does actually have code for each of
these but so I guess the problem happens
further down the line so let's see where
the problem actually happens if I step
through the code here for example does
it happen in begin frame now just keep
running down does it happen
in end frame maybe then I mean the next
time we call the renderer isn't for
awhile right so presumably none of this
fails because it doesn't involve the
renderer how about this nope
so then we get down to the end frame
call right and so it's in there so it's
actually it's actually in the opengl end
frame call stop that
so why would that be and I can just step
through that now and find out I guess
but the question is why would we be
jumping to zero in here like what are we
jumping to is there something that we
pass here that we jump to fit like are
we calling any actual programs inside
here cuz it doesn't are we where would
we be doing that I'm gonna have to just
step in there because I don't I don't
know where we would be jumping to a
function pointer in here unless it's
just the Open GL function table itself
but what that should just remain like we
like that should just be mapped into our
address space and should not have
changed right I mean it's that wrong I
don't know so I guess we'll find out I'm
gonna go ahead and run again I will
force it to reload so here's me
reloading and oh and I guess I got rid
of the breakpoint that was on the other
function there
uh wait a minute
that breakpoint is still there how come
I didn't hit so why isn't it letting me
set that breakpoint I don't understand
why it's being so finicky about this
breakpoint like why can't I just set
this breakpoint it doesn't like that
breakpoint again hmm can I set it here
so it just can't set a breakpoint now
it's like I don't know man
I wonder why remedy cannot set a
breakpoint is this something to do with
the currently loaded state of it or is
it just that the build itself makes it
difficult for it to know how to set a
breakpoint there or something
so it just can't figure out how to set a
breakpoint there and we don't really
know why but it really doesn't like it
so it's like this file it's just like
look I don't know where breakpoints go
anymore apparently I need to update my
remedy to the new version so I wonder if
I'm actually just hitting a bug and
that's just a bug that's occurring I'm
not sure that's that's one I couldn't
tell you yeah so I don't know something
about the PDB and the eggsy being not a
sink there I guess well it's good enough
for now let's go ahead and keep going so
now that we break here I'm gonna go drop
over to the OpenGL side of things and
I'm gonna look at the part where we
actually go to the end frame just so I
can see like who is jumping to zero like
I don't know exactly who that would be
and so I'm gonna try to just like run
over to that hmm so no it doesn't it did
not get there somehow
apparently let's try this one more time
hopefully we still have the breakpoint
no all right so I think like we're not
super able to actually set these
breakpoints here because for whatever
reason when we actually do the rebuild
it looks like this rebuild throws remedy
for a loop like the fact that we have
the other dll that we're loading also
has the random in it unless there's a
bug in the way that I'm doing this like
unless this this build step is is
somehow busted which I don't know it
could be
IIIi don't really know
hmm so yeah we don't know who is doing
that and we don't have any way of
actually stepping into it I guess we
could just use a different to pucker
temporarily is thing one I could also
try to instrument it so you know what I
could do is I could just say well okay
so well and you know what I could do
this so we believe that that works a
fresh recompile without remedy running
at the time and then we could run to
that point and then just step which we
do know works and I'll just step up
until the actual breakage point right so
there's the reload right and now I'm
assuming that like I can't really can i
oh so I can sort of run to a new break
point so does this actually work
yes so here we go into and win through
to end frame here and that's going to
call open gel and frame which I guess we
don't know maybe that doesn't work I
mean where is that let's see
that's not a very good total texture
memory number now is it and that's
completely invalid so this is not off to
a good start if we're honest about it so
I guess one thing we would say is we got
some bugs we can fix right now even
without looking for the rest of this
since I'm in here now I'm going to do a
little bit more of the looking there but
that's just total garbage so yeah we can
take a look at that a little later all
right so let's take a look at where
we're gonna call here so you can see
that the call is jumping to a specific
address so that's not going to jump zero
on us but we do call some pointers
immediately after that right so I guess
we'll see what happens here so let's see
where this goes
say where the heck are we so in that
first call they're out to wherever this
is calling out to which this is unable
to actually tell us where that is in the
source code that's actually where we
fault out so let's take a closer look at
that and that we have to do fresh builds
here apparently right
let's render here I'm gonna pay
attention to a couple new things here
now just because I know there's some
errors in there
so one of the things I would like to see
is this is the renderer here is this
okay so what's going on with this how is
the platform pointers zero I guess that
must just be because it doesn't actually
ever need to set that I also don't know
what's up with total texture memory
being zero do we not track that anymore
cuz I thought we were and no I guess
we're not so why are we not checking
that anymore
I guess we don't track it anymore
because since we use texture arrays we
never count whether or not we use them
or something all right I should put it
to do in there all right so I guess that
platform stuff is as expected and in
fact we have a comment right here that
says like we don't use it so it's
literally there just for like other
people who want to write renderers to
stick stuff in there which probably
makes sense because like if you're gonna
use like direct3d or something or
whatever you probably want to stick a
handle in there that's like here's the
direct3d handle or whatever right so it
makes sense all right so when we reload
this code some something weird is
happening and we're not sure what that
is the what
that is the what right there what is
that about
that is just nonsense that's probably
why we were messing up remedy as well
all right so let's fix that because we
basically copied code in there or I
shouldn't say we copied it we moved code
in there and then didn't make it
actually generic right so this is
getting the original DLL name right but
that name is not it's only that name
means we're gonna copy this file
potentially on top of an existing DLL
that we need to change right so this
needs to be a unique name and it can't
just be arbitrary right and you know I
don't know how exactly we want to deal
with that but if you look at the fact
like we're putting the temporary DLL
name into here right we just need some
way of this thing having a different
name depending on which one of the files
is actually loading right and we could
just pass in morning for that but
probably the easiest thing to do would
be to say like when we do the win32
build XE path file name so
so in here if we pass one of these
unique numbers to it it's gonna do one
of these things right and probably what
we want to do there is just have some
way that that can also handle like sort
of some additional uni King right so
I guess what I would say is maybe we
have a thing in here that's like yeah
you know what I'm just gonna do it so
I'm just gonna have this thing actually
be stated in there so if I go to the
win32 loaded code thing I'm just gonna
say like hey let's have a like that
right and so we're just going to
actually specify this so when we now go
to set the DLL full path and stuff like
that like this I'm just gonna actually
put it and because I was like well you
know what I wanted to be named right so
we'll say that there's the render
attempt dll and then down in the code
version of the game code version rather
we'll set that one so that we can see
what they actually are hopefully this
will also fix our remedy problem because
now remedy because we were like swapping
out the files underneath remedy with
wrong files so I think it was correct to
complain cuz it's probably like I don't
know what's going on here man you know
you're you're pulling a fast one and and
I don't want to deal with it which is
totally fair all right so let's try that
one more time
so here's okay this is a debug build so
let's slow
and now I'm gonna go ahead and rebuild
no dice hmm that's unfortunate
so my what did I do
I thought I fixed I thought I fixed the
problem I totally didn't all right so
let's check it a little more carefully
doo doo doo doo doo
all right
rebuilding should break right here
here's the reload so this will just
clear that out here's the load that all
makes sense let's take a look at what
this actually builds here
sorry so that's not actually good it I
mean it's not horrible but we actually
needed that to put a number in there
because we would rather it actually make
the unique number I mean it doesn't have
to that's still fine but it's not the
best right so we should probably
initialize those to non zero but it's
fine
so if we look at this it's like saying
look we're gonna copy this dll to this
DLL right and off it goes and then we're
gonna up that number so the next time we
reload it's gonna be different right
so it wasn't able to copy that it was
able to copy that for whatever reason oh
because it's already loading this one I
guess that's why so really this thing
should increment either way right that
is actually forcing it to do one failed
copy file for no reason so I may fix
that just while we're in here cuz I
would never remember to do it again
because it's kind of an arbitrary
failure so basically what we would say
is look every time we do this we're
gonna Inc the DLL number right and we
probably just want it to wrap so what we
probably want to do here is say look
when we get to the end of this we would
just wrap around to 0 and this part
should probably not do it that way right
so what should probably do is like say
look if temp T a little number equals
loaded tempt you all right zero right
and in fact we could actually just say
like do it that way right so up here
then we would say actually attempt index
equals zero attempt index is lesson yeah
we're gonna try this that many times and
then in here we're just gonna like roll
this number over as many times as we
want to right all right so that now
should be a little bit more sensible now
let's take a look at what fails we're
gonna do went through to reload code now
there's the unload here's the reload
we're gonna try to copy it to here that
should succeed and it does now we're
gonna try to load it right
now it's loaded and now yeah we still
don't really know why that was having
such a hard time and I and I don't know
why I would like to see whether I was
causing that remedy buglet can we now
step to this okay and all that stuff
yeah we can so here we are an open Jill
end frame and so inside geo bind buffer
we actually get
oh and wow it's so it's it's actually at
the shield behind buffer call okay all
right let's say I believe that
did this fix our remedy issue by the way
no hmm all right so did I still screw
something up would be I guess the other
question I have like because I'm that
remedy issues weirding me out it could
just be remedy passive bug but it could
be that I'm like screwing up the PD B's
and the code and stuff right so I'm a
little nervous about that because I
don't actually know and let me look
so here's like some of those temp deals
right that you can see and maybe if I
delete those and we'll just watch which
ones are created because I'd also like
to just know you know what's happened
there right so if I wanted to here right
and just run the game I'm just curious
like what it produces here so it
probably presumably did these right I
mean there they are right and then when
I do the we and they are different like
you know it didn't like copy one over
the other or anything like that and then
when I rebuild which I'll do now I'm
gonna do a derp and yet produce these
two and again they seem like they're
properly sized if I look at the source
field you mean if I look at the source
dll's they do seem to be reasonable
right so I guess I'm not clear so
there's two things here that I want to
know and I don't really know you know
what I should do though should get a new
dota hero forget where that is
I don't know which one I want to go with
sand assassins not bad an over Lancer is
probably pretty good pretty good ones
here
all right anyway so assuming that that
copies working properly so I have two
things that are bugging me the first one
is I don't know why remedies getting
confused about the games breakpoints and
it's especially weird because the win32
dll that that is getting rebuilt though
it's that didn't get overwritten right
so I don't know what it's weirded out
about there like that should have just
still been working right there's nothing
I don't see I don't see why cause like
at the very least I should be able to
set break points here in the win32 code
because that's not even one of the
things that's getting replaced so that's
really weird and I think that must be a
bug in remedy I don't know if George is
still on if he thinks it would or
wouldn't be he would know better than I
but I don't know why that's happening
but then the second thing is like why
are we jumping to an unknown function
there and that question is a little bit
weird and I wonder to what extent like
is it because we can't reload something
that calls opengl because doing that
reloading mm-hmm changes some kind of a
state that I mean I don't even really
know why that would be the case but
let's at least try to verify what's
going on there so if I run
and now I rebuild right
I can still set a breakpoint now which
is weird I don't know what determines
that part of it it's kind of strange but
if I now jump to the end frame call and
step in here go to OpenGL and frame so I
believe it was a bind buffer call right
it was this I want to say probably and I
don't know maybe it's this maybe all
we're seeing here in fact now that I
think about it maybe the problem is that
we we maybe have a global that we don't
reinitialize or something like that in
which case we're gonna have to go take
care of that but other if that's the
case and that's pretty easy but either
way so here's the OpenGL call or
function it's looking for a vertex
buffer which should be here somewhere
but for some reason can't find it
there it is so it's just passing one two
GL bind buffer ah but it's not yeah yeah
all right so this is way easy this was
just me forgetting how this worked this
is a trivial book so the problem here is
just here's we've got a bunch of
functions right and GL bind buffer
despite looking like a pretty innocuous
call actually is technically not in
OpenGL one so that's the actual problem
is we just haven't reloaded our GL
function table right that was local to
the DLL and you know it didn't get
reloaded that's all so in terms of
what's happening when we load all of our
extension nonsense right like this stuff
we don't have to
surely care about but the part where we
actually load like all of this crap
right that stuff actually still has to
occur you know I'm saying to you and I
guess what I would say is I know it's
kind of annoying but I'm just maybe
gonna go ahead and say let's just put
those into the OpenGL state itself
I mean I think that's what I'm going
with right so let's say that instead of
what we were doing before we just wanted
to go in here and say that you know this
open jail thing keeps track of all of
our stuff and we're just gonna say that
all of the functions go in there like
sorry man that's just where they go
right so all of this garbage
right would have to go in there and hey
you have to call them anyway right so
we're just gonna say look we expect them
to be defined and you're gonna have to
call them or something right and we can
use this old system for that probably
just fine right so in here we just say
like Open GL function like this and
maybe it just looks like that and then
all of these will be in there and we're
just going to make that work right so
like in here we would put those we're
gonna have to fix the the swap interval
one will have to be handled specially
because I think that's kind of a little
saucy err
exercice was i can't just replace that
because no sense of typing it multiple
times so if we do that then what I can
do is just say like alright let's move
the rest of these into that like so this
is a little bit boring but at least now
these will be a little more uniform
and no comeback so then here's all our
gigantic disaster of 8 billion open
shell functions that need to get in here
and so we need all of those and now what
we do is we just say all right when we
were loading those before now we're
going to load them into the actual open
jail struct so that they'll persist okay
and the problem we're going to have here
I guess is that we need these to be
defined ahead of time I suppose and I'm
not sure where that actually gets done
who includes this thing I don't actually
know
somebody does so it's it's actually
right there and oh so this is actually
all fine so really all we have to do is
just change these names to actually
conform to the naming convention we have
now so it should be as simple as just
doing this right
I guess that don't know what some of the
capitalizations are on these in OpenGL
but I'll look here so that's I guess
that but but most of these I wouldn't
know right so she'll buy and frame
buffer gen frame buffers frame buffer
texture 2d check frame buffer status
blip frame buffer attach shader compile
shader program create shader I don't
know why that is why does it think
that's a keyword
that doesn't bode well probably means
we've got an air coming down type use
program jet program info log kind of
amazing that modern day we still have
this issue none of this stuff ever gets
fixed like why am i doing any of this
right like why isn't there just a way to
call OpenGL who knows um well I sort of
dunno logistically why meaning I know
the corporate politics involved in Y but
that's not really an excuse now is it
listen that's an explanation of why but
it's not a good reason why
all right um so now I guess we should be
able to make all of this stuff work
through the open gel layer more directly
so when we call stuff we would pass the
OpenGL pointer around and people would
just call through that which I think
should be relatively straightforward but
I guess we'll find out if it's not but
basically it would just involve you
doing this right you know I'm saying to
you and then you know anytime somebody
has to call something they got to do it
through here I'm gonna not do that one
just yet because I actually don't know
how that would work I mean I guess we'll
find out I'm not sure if this will
create a problem to do it this I'm not
sure about these she'll get string eye
things but oops
see
yeah
so mostly this just would involve sort
of weaving open jaelyn through here but
other than that the code stays the same
and we could have done this the other
way by just calling it again but I feel
like this is a little bit nicer because
then at least we can also see I like the
idea of making it visible like what
we're actually storing and calling off
of dynamic pointers versus things that
are welded into the system that feels a
little nicer to me because I just like
it better represents what's actually
going on so it's not trying to hide like
that fact and you can see just when you
read the code you're like okay those are
like all that that's all the stuff
that's actually coming from dynamic
quick calls into the driver that are not
necessarily you know even in Windows I
assume both of those need the thing
and this would probably be happening for
everybody makes a program alright so
this is all pretty boring
msyn interesting here really that has to
get threaded that and almost done
actually alright so
now we've got to go make it so that the
loader is working off of these because
it's still thinking it's letting you
know Global's which it ain't so this
codes specifically right and one of the
nice things about it is we now unified
all these so all of these actually don't
have to go this way anymore
all of these can actually be done this
way now right which is nice so this
stuff we can actually just kind of grab
these guys and stick them in here right
and oops so that should be nice
and there we go so now everyone hoops so
now everyone can load that way and we
can change this to just say well we know
that it's exactly the same thing it's
just off of OpenGL pointer now right and
so that basically takes care of all of
our loading so that loads everything for
us now which is nice and and better
anyway so then these right here are also
the same oops it's just they're inside
the conditional so I thought this open
she'll get info needed to take the open
shell pointer now right yeah so this
should have been doing that is there
another one somewhere yeah that is
totally not true and so what we should
be able to do now is take that code that
was previously doing it this way and
make this work that way too
right so there's no reason not to just
do these through the same path and and
now everything is like actually much
nicer to deal with because it all goes
through the same macro and everything's
relatively uniform so I think the only
thing we have that's really not good
is this because we will swap interval I
don't know where that gets called
exactly we can look and see so you can
see like our vsync would break here in
that case and so what I think I'm I
might do is if we look here and we say
platform OpenGL set sync or whatever
maybe we would just do like maybe we
would just do platform OpenGL set sync
we'll do the call itself right so like
the place where we were gonna do it
[Music]
wouldn't be in here where's the win32
areas where did you go here so what we
might do is like this because this one's
special so we might do is we'd say hey
like if we don't have one right then try
to get it and then you know off we go
that way what we could do is say the
place where we took that out of which is
here you can just say look
[Music]
we'll initialize two trying to do it and
but anytime that we find that we don't
have the function we'll try to get it
again so if anyone calls us it'll try to
look it up again in like a new renderer
and think that would be sufficient not
sure all right so here's the whole thing
again let's see if it works
running with us updating the OpenGL
table in a structure now so we can just
have that around and then let me rebuild
and see what we get now when we hit this
code path right just to see what happens
so let me run it and see what we have
what happens crash wise so it looks like
we're fine right so now it looks like it
is reloading the renderer so that's good
let's try it in a release mode and see
where that's at
so here's running and I'm gonna go in
there and change the clear color thing
again and I guess like we should now be
able to change whatever we want in the
renderer code and it should actually
just work and then the only thing we
have to do which I'll save for next
weekend is just putting it a thing that
strobes it so it recompiles the shaders
and stuff but otherwise I think that's
it
so what would be something I could use
to test it might be like so let's do
this I'm gonna put in a half with call
here yep
and then I'm gonna rerun that not sure
why that takes so long but I guess
that's just the reloading time I'm not
sure I have to work on that reload time
probably it's a compile time right it
unloads the code and that's trying to
reload the new code but the compiler
hasn't finished outputting it yet all
right okay we'll do a quick quick Q&amp;A
but that's really all we wanted to get
accomplished there and so now we can
reload our render code our whole
renderer
which is nice
a lighting question but it also has
application meteorology do you know of
any algorithms to compute shadow or no
shadow for all future February seconds
or are we simply stuck with the
Punxsutawney Phil algorithm the current
but rather limited state of the art so I
don't think that has anything to do with
it though because it's in like I mean I
guess I don't know but doesn't it have
to do more with whether it's cloudy or
not or which direction the groundhog
faces or anything like I mean is it does
it really have anything to do with the
position of the Sun I don't know
Knox gobo says sorry I missed it what
did you use tensorflow for oh nothing I
was just wanted to see how bad it was to
build the answer is very bad but we did
get it to build so wasn't as bad as we
were fearing because we were fearing
maybe we wouldn't get to build at all
well bus is not faster to load a shader
from a file and change them on the fly
when the files modified yeah it would be
faster sure but then of course you also
can't change any other things right so
you can't change like what actual steps
you do in the renderer so we would like
to be able to change everything
Kronus org says that we should lewd
procs by wittle proc address and if it
fails then load library OpenGL 32 DLL
and get proc address in which situations
is it relevant or did I miss something
so I guess I've never really experienced
a situation where I had to open OpenGL
32 DLL myself and then call get proc
address but I'm sure there probably is
something but I couldn't say would you
recommend the OpenGL struct function
table for versioned si libs can you be
more specific about what you mean by
versioned si libs
if you wanted able to stereoscopic 3d
are there OpenGL functions difficulty
for that or would you have to do
everything manually so the answer is yes
and yes there are specific opengl
functions for stereoscopic 3d they are
antiquated and you wouldn't want to use
them what you actually need to do if you
want to do stereoscopic 3d nowadays is
actually also quite complicated because
usually you're talking if you're talking
about stereoscopic 3d you're usually not
talking about rendering two images that
are just slightly offset left and right
that while you could do that for
rendering maybe like if you're trying to
make a hologram or something maybe that
would work but if you're actually trying
to do like virtual reality then you
actually need to apply lens distortions
because the lenses in the headsets of VR
systems don't project planar things to
your eyes they project sort of a warped
a spherically warped image onto your eye
and you need to know the distortion
parameters of that image so you really
can't
you really have to basically have lens
data and you'll note that all VR
headsets now report lens data and that's
why you have to render using that lens
data so you need to know the lens data
and then you need to implement shaders
that actually like produce images from
the correct stereoscopic separation but
then that also will produce Warped
images right
you mentioned there being no standard
way to interface with graphics and the
Pollack's behind it do you see acidic
reason what console manufacturers
couldn't push hardware vendors for
standardization and have that standard
bleed out into general computing sure
again like politically speaking what is
their motivation to do that console
manufacturers 100% always never for any
reason want anyone to be able to use
their stuff right the whole point of a
console is they lock it down completely
and don't let anyone access it except
people that they allow so the last thing
they're gonna do is define a standard
and let everyone else use it so that
people who can write games that run
really well on a Playstation 5 can also
now write games that run really well on
all this other hardware that's the clone
of it right so that's just not I don't
see that as being politically plausible
as a thing that would happen right
viii page says if it matters I once
implemented a network in C++ from
tensorflow and it was faster
single-threaded by an order of magnitude
compared to the 28 core multi-threaded
tensorflow implementation yet that's I
would like to do that as well I would
love to do that test as well if you
happen to have it lying around email it
to me we can take a look at it sometime
he's the same OpenGL context being used
after render reload yes
so OpenGL context are not tied to a DLL
they're tied to a thread so as long as
you set your OpenGL context up and make
it current to a particular thread even
if you reload completely all of the code
that that thread is executing the
context is still there right so the only
reason we had to reload all the pointers
was just because look those pointers
were in the dll's data space so when the
DLL got reloaded it got a fresh set of
Global's and they were uninitialized
right so we could have chosen to just
reload those in but I chose to just put
them in the struck that sticks around
for APS the requirement of being
downloads compatible and introducing
breaking changes is only allowed in a
second api struct
[Music]
I mean I guess what I would say is I
don't really understand the question
exactly or really what we're trying to
accomplish if I had a specific thing in
front of me that you were asking about I
could probably tell you the answer but
I'm just not sure what the question is
if if what you're asking generally
speaking is can I use a structure of
function pointers to something that
changes so that there's code that's
gonna use this structure and later on
I'm gonna update the structure with more
to add more stuff or change things you
know can I still use it and the answer
is of course you can actually all you do
is make the structure longer and put
changed versions down at the bottom and
rename anything in the upper part to be
like deprecated or whatever right and
then it just works that's it
and you conversion it as many times as
you want and it will just work anyone
who is calling it in the old school like
in the older version just gets the first
n of the pointers right and so the only
thing you actually need to make sure
that you do is if it's a feed-forward
system meaning if you are pass instead
of if if it returns you the table then
it just works if you have to pass the
table in and it fills it out you just
need to send the size or a four or a
version number and it can figure out the
size from that but that's it
[Music]
tomorrow's my first day work at a
triple-a company how do i jump into a
huge codebase ue4 that i know very
little of i am a little bit intimidated
also by the object-oriented nasaan so
there's a couple things i would say so
the first one is that you have to
remember that nobody knows how it works
anyway so one of the things about you
know modern c++ and large operating Co
bases is even the people who wrote them
have no idea how they work and you could
tell that like you know people who wrote
LLVM screw it up all the time and have
no idea what the hell's going on in
there right and the same is true of Yui
for right so nobody knows actually
what's going on in giant code bases like
that and so it's not like a bunch of
people are running around with perfect
knowledge of everything that's happening
in these code bases and it's just you
who doesn't know it's like no no none of
these people know it's too big and very
obfuscated so a lot of times even things
they think are happening are wrong and
they have to end up debugging something
and going oh crap yeah I forgot about
the fact that the abstruse template
repository factory doesn't produce
things in the same memory space as the
reef functor er and so I had to like go
in and add an adapter class to make sure
that it gets you know and off to the
races so the second thing I would say is
remember that all of this modern
programming garbage still compiles down
to assembly language at the end of the
day it can't do anything at all that
isn't just see right there is C++ has
literally no features in it right
there's nothing in C++ that can SCP you
can do so all of the ridiculous
fanciness is at the end of the day just
going to produce basically C code and so
all you have to do is start remembering
what all this ridiculous garbage
actually translates into in terms of
actual code functions and then it
becomes much easier because you're like
oh yeah here's 17 levels of templates
and 15 nested class hierarchies but you
know what
it all boils down to a frickin table
call where I just look up in the table
and call a function because that's what
a CPU does right nothing
CPU doesn't do can show up in one of
these code bases because it runs on the
CPU and there's no objects in a CPU and
there's no templates in a CPU none of
this stuff exists right so the key thing
to focus on is just yeah it's a giant
crap load of meaningless text that
someone typed into a computer but at the
end of the day it actually turns into
CPU instructions so just focus on
learning what this crap ton of code
actually boils down to which will be
quite small at the end of the day and
slowly over time you like oh okay all
right I get it
I had to spend like three days stepping
through thousands and thousands of
source lines but now I get it this huge
pile of templates just creates a four I
loop right and it sounds like I'm you
know making a joke but I'm not that you
will see that you will see something
where ten thousand lines of code
generated one four I loop that does
something relatively straightforward
right and that's just what you want to
remember because that's what's actually
happening it's one of the reasons that I
think it's ridiculous that people say to
not teach C or assembly language anymore
because it's ridiculous because what
you're actually teaching them when you
teach some C++ or Python or any other
things is you're teaching them nonsense
you made up right and maybe some of that
nonsense is useful sometimes but it has
nothing to do with a program right it
doesn't have anything to do with a
computer does it's all nonsense it's all
just stuff you made up because you
thought it was better to type in this
set of words than another set of words
but it's not programming programming is
only things that a CPU can do because
you because it can't do anything else
that's the definition right
and so it's so crucial to remember that
no matter what arbitrary pile of garbage
like Swift or Python or tensorflow or
anything else someone dumps in your lap
at the end of the day it's just assembly
language at the end of it so if you can
just focus on what does this huge pile
of garbage that a lousy programmer wrote
who doesn't know what they're doing what
Loup did they actually create at the end
of it because that's all it can do and
once you can find out what that's doing
then you can kind of reverse back
through their disgusting garbage pile to
figure out what you actually need to
change to make the loop do the thing you
wanted to do now it would be great if
those people had ever like gone to a mic
act in lecture and realize that if they
just wrote the stupid loop to begin with
they would have saved three months of
work and anyone could read it but they
didn't so here we are
have I heard of ipfs no I don't know
what that answer is it
Internet Protocol file system or
something
[Music]
it's very important that I don't spend
much time looking at large C++ code
bases because interplanet art taro
probably interplanetary interplanetary
file system it's a decentralized file
system which is hash based mapping on
the nodes of the network for file lookup
does that work though so why would that
fix anything though
I guess I'd have to go look so I'll say
one thing about that and maybe they have
an idea about what they're doing that
would be relevant here but my first
thought on that is like well ok so let's
suppose that what you decided to do was
we're just gonna take every piece of
content at some kind of like block like
at some kind of blocking level so we're
like I don't know based like a file per
file traditional file or something I
mean who knows what it's gonna be but
like we decided to take all the data and
we block it up into chunks and we're
saying we're gonna like identify these
chunks by the hash of the content of the
chunk and that way anytime someone says
like you need this thing you can just
say ok here's the chunk that I need it
or whatever right and so you know that's
the kind of thing that someone who
hasn't thought about the problem very
long probably thinks about I guess or
maybe the answer is someone who knows
way more about than I do figures out
some reasons why that would actually
work but like in my head I'm like well
that doesn't work at all because the
entire point of modern you know network
traffic security is that you can't have
anyone know what it is you were asking
for right
so for example if you take a an HTTP
request then sure that transfer makes
perfect
if everyone was communicating via HTTP
then you would say well rather than
communicating by HTTP within the URL why
don't you just communicate by this new
thing like
ipfs and we just say here is the hash
that I was looking for and anyone can
respond right anyone who's got it will
just hand it back to me but that's not
how the world works now the world
everything works by HTTP which means
that you can never have anybody besides
the person who owns the thing actually
know what you were asking for right so I
guess I don't understand what that means
like asking who has the file that
digested this hash you can never do that
because if you ask that question you've
already broken your security model so
what's their solution to that how do I
ask for a thing without anyone knowing
what the thing is by hash see you I'm
going with
and you know I'm I can go read about it
but that'd be what I want to know right
like how do they solve that problem and
maybe they've totally solved that in
which case that's cool right because it
seems like that'd be useful maybe I
don't know I could I could bring it up
here someone posted a link I PFS
oh no no
so I mean yet like again maybe this is
just high level but this is just exactly
what I just said and no that doesn't
work right I mean I mean it doesn't work
because basically everyone in this
network now knows what everyone's doing
so it's like hey yeah you know that you
know porn you were watching
well now everybody in the entire network
knows what it was because everyone saw
you asking for that hash and they know
what that hash is right I mean it
doesn't work even for basic stuff let
alone once we start talking about asking
for actual like things that's you know
important right I mean I guess you could
argue that people don't care because
they know that you're watching the porn
anyway right but I'm just saying there's
no way that works like this doesn't work
so maybe there's more to it than this is
like the thing for you know this is how
ipfs works for dummies right they're
just trying to explain it so maybe it
actually has something smarter than that
but if this is literally what they're
doing it doesn't work so no not a
solution right
take a look at the white paper where's
the white paper
here is
[Music]
let's see do
I mean yeah again I just I don't I don't
see it right I mean it says right here
you're sending everybody everything
you're doing right so like literally
everything you browse everyone in the
network knows your entire web history
right I mean that's this right I mean
not everybody because it you know
different people see different parts of
it right but anyone who's pretty
aggressive could probably find out quite
a bit
and I mean again there's not even a
section in here that talks about that
like you would want this should have a
thing that's like security and it
doesn't which is not great right so I'm
pretty sure this just isn't useful like
it's probably fine for BitTorrent like
if all you're doing is trying to trade
like pirated movies or whatever then hey
like you're only on there if you're
breaking the law anyway so who cares if
people find out about it because that's
all it's used for so all they need to do
is already using it at all well you're
probably stealing something right but if
the idea is we would try to use this as
a backbone for the internet it no like
it that does not work this is not
tractable and I don't see anything in
here that suggests that they've solved
the problem unless I'm missing it right
like am I missing something
yeah exactly so so ginger bill I think I
think they are not trying to solve this
problem which is why I say when people
are asking me if this is useful in
trying to rebuild the Internet like no
it's not this is like a very specific
thing for solving a very specific
problem it doesn't help fix the Internet
at all like it helps make a better
BitTorrent probably but BitTorrent is
not the backbone of the internet for a
very good reason because it can't be
right
[Music]
I think no single node in the network
has to a higher percent of a file so you
can only request an incomplete fragment
which will make it harder for the node
hosting to guess what it is
I mean why because all you have to do is
figure out roughly you know let me put
it this way
first of all no that's obviously not
true
because if you can watch your porn video
at some point you've got a hundred
percent of it right if you could watch
the whole thing if you wanted to steal
your pirate copy of Avengers 17 you know
everything explodes or whatever then you
had to get the whole thing so now you
know all of the chunks that were in
there and anytime anyone asks you for
one you know that's what they're looking
for so done right it's so simple like I
could make a node that did that tomorrow
just looking at this thing it's it's not
even it's not like some super elite
hacks or a job it's just that's it if
you can watch something you can get the
whole thing if you can get the whole
thing you know everyone else who's
asking for any of it at that point I
mean at least in your general vicinity
like anyone who ever sends you a packet
and anyone who wanted to police this
sort of thing has a pretty easy time
they just flood this system with
thousands of servers that they rent on
AWS and they collect every single thing
that everyone asked for from them right
so I'm pretty sure this just isn't
relevant this is just like hey let's
make a better BitTorrent which totally
worth doing has nothing to do with
fixing the internet like will not really
have any effect on it right
I mean hey maybe can replace Dropbox
which would be great because Dropbox is
stupid right
but like no not helpful on the Internet
scale
in translation internationalization
honest jr some good resource to explain
how the internet works you said that it
could not be used as a back with your
permission to Y so again I was trying to
explain the reason why the reason why is
just because when you have machines
talking to each other and you start to
use them in a peer-to-peer fashion so
you know when I need to get so right now
when I go to ask for something so if I
want to get a video from Netflix right I
send a web request to Netflix now
everyone on the network who happens to
be in between right who's passing those
packets along to Netflix eventually
which i think is actually Amazon but
that's a separate second thing can see
one and only one thing and that is the
IP address of the machine I was asking
right because everything else about the
request is encrypted via HTTPS so they
don't even know what resource I was
asking for so as long as I'm asking for
the resource from a site that has
sufficiently many resources no one knows
what I'm actually looking at right so
you don't know whether I'm watching a
super sweet awesome film like Ernest
goes to jail or whether I'm watching
like you know scenes from a marriage by
Ingmar Bergman right so I can lie to you
and tell you I only watch sophisticated
movies and that the thing that I'm
streaming you know is extremely
sophisticated and relevant to film
history right like I only watch
Nosferatu and I watch it 24 hours a day
but actually it turns out that the
entire time I was just you know watching
cartoons right and you have no I am
annoyed the only thing you know that I
was talking to a Netflix server and you
may not even know that if you can't
quite figure out what the Netflix
servers are but you probably can because
you can just keep asking where Netflix
is and it'll keep sending you IP
addresses and you could probably cover
like most of what they are
um so the problem with the thing that we
are pointing out there is that thing and
people that prevent this before vint
cerf proposed long ago he said what if
we just looked up data by hash the
problem with it is that once you convert
data into hashes as their names now the
way you ask for something and when you
ask you can ask multiple people people
just around you and say hey did you
happen to ever get this part of this
file because I need it right this
massively improved distribution because
it means anyone can answer any question
now because if anyone ever got part of
the Saturday morning cartoon from
Netflix they know that I'm looking for
that now when I ask them they can just
send it right back and we never have to
ask Netflix for it that's nice
but the problem is now everyone knows
what I'm asking for it's not just
between me and Netflix now it's me and
everybody else who I happen to ask right
so basically all of the like problems
that you get with privacy get greatly
exacerbated in a hash based system
because now all of the peer-to-peer it's
not really a hash space it's just a
peer-to-peer nature of it right the fact
that I can ask anyone and those people
who have parks the file could just give
it to me improves the like reliability
and speed of the content delivery but it
completely obliterates any privacy that
you had
all right I'm gonna close it down thank
you everyone for joining me for the new
set of handmade hero spit-up pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow us areas at home you can
always peer to the game on handmade hero
org and it comes with a source code so
you can follow along with it
I also am working on a few courses that
are going to go up here that you can buy
later but they're not quite up yet I'll
have some more information about that a
little bit later on maybe next month but
I'm hoping that there'll also be some
good course material that you can get on
here so stay tuned for that it should be
coming a little bit later on all right
that's it for today I'll be back here
next week I believe when we will go
ahead and start working on the lighting
using the rendering reloading we just
did and we should that should allow us
to have a little bit faster turnaround
times there which would be nice alright
that's it for today have fun program
everyone and I'll see you on the
Internet take it easy everybody