okay welcome everyone to yet another
tantalizing episode of handmade hero the
show we could complete game live on
stream I have to tell you that
immediately after this dream ended on
friday everyone wrote in to say that
there was a typo in the code and so well
we're not going to get a chance to watch
me find the typo because basically you
know it was it was a total spoiler alert
situation I now I know that there's a
typo in the code I don't have to go
doing any debugging to find it so we're
going to start off the episode today
just magically knowing that there's a
bug because literally everyone saw it I
suppose that's one of the bonuses of
doing programming on stream is yes your
mental energy is diverted because you're
talking all the time but you get this
special bonus of everyone's looking at
your code is your typing in so if there
is an obvious mistake it's highly
unlikely that it's going to go unnoticed
by two thousand eyes or I don't know how
many people let's I don't know how many
people actually watched that episode
already yeah so when you get that many
eyes on it I suppose you you've got a
pretty big pretty big bonus there
alright so let's get started because
really all we were going to do today
anyways debug it so we've got one bug we
know we can fix and then we can start
taking a look at other bugs and if we
run out of bugs to fix in the short term
then obviously we have to move on to
getting rid of the N squared part of our
algorithm because that's going to cause
us problems for you know obvious reasons
anyway uh let's go ahead and open up
here we are on day 3 07 so if you want
follow along at home you want to impact
day 306 is source code that's the source
code state that we're starting with you
can see let me just before I actually go
show you what the typo is that people
had reported which I you know it was
sloppy of me to leave let's see where
we're at here okay so it's a little bit
hard to see here you can see there's a
little bit of the rectangle problem but
I
the the problems a little bit more
noticeable if I actually turn on let me
just go back to the to the state that
things were in before i started
simplifying it down to look for the bug
just so you can kind of get a feel for
how bad the bug was or how bad the the
sort was doing before we do any of these
these bug fixes so you can count like a
baseline if you will so all right so in
at standard room we kind of removed all
of the room tiles right we sort of it's
zero it out this else clause so if I go
ahead and didn't put that back in that
will certainly add a ton of stuff back
into the to the game so here is you know
here's one rooms worth and you can
already see that the room is sorted
wrong so I'm going behind these things
and and again we don't actually know in
some cases how wrong the sword is
because we're not feeding it exactly
correct values yet so there are some
cases with that but you can tell that
you know it's already it's pretty bad
right the trees are wrong in blah blah
blah blah right so even with just one
room nevermind a room stacked on top of
it you can see a lot of problems okay so
what was the typo well the typo was just
that when we were in the render group
code and I switched things from wrecked
min max I forgot to switch the push
wrecked recommend max right and you
don't know if you remember back to the
time when we did this but we were I had
done it with referee max I was like oh
we have a recommend in we should use
that and I changed one of them but I
didn't change the other one so we still
have a recommend dim here i recommend
max where we should have had a recommend
dim and so obviously that makes the
rectangle completely nonsensical so in
fact presumably that made most of them
have no area as well they would be
inverted because probably the basis B
would be further away on the screen then
the scale dim which is going to be down
to the corner because it's a small you
know it's going to be a small number so
if you set that as the max it's going to
be probably a rectangle that has
negative area which is not going to
intersect anything ever and hence not
participate in the sort probably or
maybe he does weird things i'm not sure
we haven't really looked at what the
ramifications of that would have been
right okay so here is the version of the
code running with out the typo and it
looks to me like you know certainly
there are some improvements here you
know obviously these pieces are sorting
properly the the steps are sorting
properly but there's still some
weirdness to it that I don't necessarily
know if I completely would understand
immediately and I don't know and and
would indicate to me that maybe there's
a little bit of bugging us there and
other parts which which maybe don't so
let's take those one at a time so the
first thing that I'll point out is you
know the the heroes sorting incorrectly
it doesn't really bother me because we
haven't really done much work yet to do
how that's going to work and furthermore
I don't anticipate that actually working
the way that it's working now with the
janky Z values how we've got it I
actually figure now that we have a
topological sort we will just add things
it's like the heroes head is on top of
the heroes cape the heroes cape is on
top of the torso and we'll just let it
always sort properly since we now have
the ability to mandate sort orders for
things without having to touch Z values
or anything else so I think we'll want
to build that into our system somehow
however so that's one thing I've so I'm
not worried about that yet it's not
super concerning to me and we've got the
the rest of these things here look kind
of okay but you can see that as I when I
hop up on these we get some sort of
oddness happening there I don't know
that I care about that either because
that's the way those are being rendered
right now is there rectangles that are
self intersecting they're in the same Z
plane and self intersecting that's not a
case I necessarily care about handling
at all anyway because that really
shouldn't be happening I don't want that
to be occurring in the actual game
anyway so that's also not a problem but
what does concern me is over here if you
take a look at the left side of the
screen you can see that the trees
although everywhere else the trees
appear to be sorting prop
really you can see that the trees on the
left side of the screen do not appear to
be sorting properly to me anyway right
looking at those yeah you know the the
trees all these trees at the top I guess
I don't have a mouse cursor at the
moment why don't I have a mouse cursor
did we are we not in handmade oh right
because we turned off the the debug
stuff let's turn that back on we don't
actually know what that's going to do do
we go build handmade internal is off at
the moment let's turn it back on and
when we did begin render group we
decided that that needed to change to
have the what's that thing called the
well can't remember we decided to change
that yes so that it would take the the
height of the screen rather than having
that come down in the perspective
transform or the orthographic transform
so basically this these two parameters
here they just hopped up to you know the
they just hopped up to the call where we
create the render group so that's pretty
easy change otherwise looks like we got
no problems re-enabling that so let's
take a look at what that what's
happening there okay so there we go we
can see that this is still incorrect
right like that should I believe those
are Z sprites or should be Z sprites I
guess we can verify that they actually
are coming through as these rights but
you can see that they're not sorting
properly even though I believe those
should have a very high Z value right
like those should be things with Z
values that are always going to compare
on top because they should be extremely
large Z values I think so i'm not sure
what's going on there either and you can
also see furthermore that when that
turns on you can see that i get proper
sorting for all the things that it
overlaps so it almost implies to me that
like these three
these are not actually sorting against
each other right okay uh so what all
that what all that sort of adds up to
for me is I would like to augment our
ability to see how the sort is behaving
so really although the it was nice to
have people catch the typos I think the
sort of path i'm going to go down this
week for getting the sort stable and
doing what we wanted to do is really
going to be the same as if i hadn't been
told about that typo so if we still have
the typo had to find it i'm going to do
exactly the same thing and what that is
is try to add some sort of visualization
to the system such that i can see a what
the screen space bounds of various
sprites are because right now I have no
idea right like right now I'm looking at
this screen I have no idea what the
bounds are for those trees they could be
completely wrong you know I'm saying if
they could be just completely erroneous
and I suspect that what we'll find is
they are and remember part of that's
because we're not sending down the
correct we don't actually try to look at
the scaling of things or you know
necessarily if if the ex and waxes are
different or blah blah blah right so I
think what we want to do here is go okay
let's make something that operates in
the renderer that can draw what the
bounds are of our sprite so you can see
and then maybe also if we're lucky we
could add something to that system that
such that when it is drawing those
boundaries it's also going to be able to
show us what the groups are that were
sorted together so for example all of
these trees going up the left-hand side
of the screen should form a coherent
sort group right because the one at the
bottom needs to know that it's in front
of the one that's right above it and so
on and so forth though I can point with
my mouth burning it so like this tree
needs to be sorted against this one
which means tutorial
blah blah blah blah blah all the way up
right so all of those guys have to form
a coherent sort group in order to be
sorted properly if there's a break in
that chain if for some reason it doesn't
think that those sprites are in the same
sort group we have a bug we'll never
know that we have that bug other than
seeing incorrect sort the results will
never know that that's a type of bug we
have if we don't have some way of seeing
what the sort groups are right we
wouldn't know whether that's you know a
part of the bug or whether it's some
other thing that's happening in the
system that has nothing to do with
producing what the sort groups actually
are right so that's where I would like
to go with it so the first thing I'm
going to do is I'm gonna start by
turning off some of the entity
highlighting because we've got a little
bit too much of that going on right now
and so I want to eliminate some of that
and I think we can also eliminate some
of the gratuitous wrecked outline stuff
that's happening at the moment because
you know it doesn't really need to some
of it does not really need to be there
like so for example I would like to
where are we were in World mode right
here default flat transfer so all of
those are fine I'm going to go into
entity I think that probably most of
them are in here yeah so I'm going to
take the volume highlighting out so that
we don't highlight any collision volumes
at the moment and i'm also going to take
out the wrecked outline for the
traversable I don't I don't actually
know that that one ever needs to be
there anymore that one might be one that
we can just kill entirely but that way
we'll have a lot less stuff on the
screen that looks like rectangular
pieces right so now we can sort of hop
around and it's all fine you also notice
the speed has increased quite a bit and
of course the reason for that is the
less of those you have the less sort
groups they sort of form probably and
the less n squared sorting stuff has to
happen blah blah blah blah blah I mean
who knows though that's pure speculation
so anyway if we look at the situation as
as it stands now what I should be able
to do and you know what's actually
what's kind of interesting about that is
if you look at what happened
removing those made these sort properly
somehow which is kind of odd uh not sure
what to make of that exactly hmmmm I say
that seems a bit odd because i'm not
sure why that would have had all that
much of a impact on things like if you
look at how that goes and and what
happens if i move my selection cursor
down that's very odd so merely the act
of adding a few z sprites in that are
kind of stratified there immediately
caused a problem where the sort order
was determined differently than it would
have been if there's only one flat sea
sprite because there's obviously always
a flat sea sprite spanning there so I'm
kind of that's that's very strange I'm
not sure why that's happening I might
want to gather a little more data here I
might want to add a room on top just to
see what happens with those sprites and
and we'll get rid of it in a second but
I want to take a quick look at at what's
happening there so that's going to be ad
standard room oops that's going to be ad
standard room and I'm just going to say
okay let's you know let's push one more
room on top there and see what we see so
yes so that well you know you can see
that that sort is just wrong let me kind
of move up here so you can see that like
some of them are on top and some of them
are below so I feel like we've still got
some pretty so some pretty fundamental
problems happening on there so that's
good that means I don't necessarily have
to have anything all that much like the
those little bars in there but although
I could put them back in if I want to
spin that bug all right
I'm going to start by going into the
renderer and I guess I'll do this in the
OpenGL render since that's the one we
use most of the time now so what's going
to happen here inside this renderer is I
gotta need some way of rendering what
the sort groups were and what the sprite
bounds were and that sort of stuff now
thankfully the sprite bounds are ordered
in the same way that like we can index
into the the sprite bounds using the
same indices that we index into
everything else I believe at least i'm
pretty sure although now that I think
about it I guess we don't really even
need to do that now that i think about
it really all i have to do is just add a
pass here after i draw all these things
do another pass where i draw all of the
sprite bounds right because i have the
list of sprite bouncing i can draw them
there's no real impediment to me doing
so so what i could do is say all right
here's the thing that lets me get that
array started right and then i can just
loop through these as I go
so I'm just going to say for each of the
bounds here we go i'm going to say sort
sprite bound and equals countries plus
bound index and maybe i'll call that
pounds for each of these bounds I have
information about what is in the bound
right so if i go to render h you can see
that I've got this sort sprite bound
I've got a bunch of information about
the edges here these sprite edges tell
me you know who's in front and who's
behind of each one and all these other
sorts of things and those are indices
into the sprite bound array so i think i
could draw a fair bit of information
certainly and I could also have in here
where we've got the visited and sort of
drawn thing I could add another thing
that's like sprite a debug box or
something and I could use that to do if
i want to a sort of a similarly
recursive bounds drawing sort of thing
where I I sort of show look paths among
different connected groups if that makes
sense so yeah I think I should be able
to do this relatively straightforward I
think all I really have to do here is
say well all right let's go ahead and do
like draw bounds recursive on this and
I'll pass the bound and I probably
should call this something so I can tell
what the open that it's an open jail
call right so I do open Joseph I say
here's the bound and I probably i don't
know this
because of the way we were doing it
before I'm just kind of thinking maybe
the easiest way to do it is to pass that
bound index as well so if I come up to
here to draw bounds recursive I'm
guessing that the other thing that I'm
going to want to do and i'll just
quickly put these in here so here's
sorts right down and this is bound index
so when i call this function i can then
quickly check in here if the bound flags
and sprite debug box it's the zac same
kind of depth-first traversal we were
doing before i can do that and then i
can say well as soon as I check one of
the bounds I'm going to or in the debug
box lag so I know I won't ever draw this
guy again I can then loop through just
as I was looping through before all of
the sprite edges so i can say like ok
for each of the edges coming off of this
is it next with the next edge of same
front for each of the edges coming off
of this node i'm going to walk backwards
to that node so i can just say like ok
opengl draw bounds recursive bounds and
edge i'm going to go with behind because
that's the order we walk in from front
to behind and now I've got a thing that
will crawl those now what I'd like to do
here is I would like to draw a couple
different things first of all I'd like
to draw the screen area because
obviously the screen area is the thing
that lets me see kind of what we
specified as the bounds for a particular
sprite and then I'd also like to draw
perhaps an edge between like a line but
to connect the diff centers maybe of
those boxes I also feel like I would do
myself a favor of visualization wise if
I go ahead and say hey draw all the
connected groups in the same color so
I'm going to do a thing here where I
also
say you know v4 color right now I feel
like we had a thing in debug where we
had a color table right here's that
debug color table and I feel like maybe
the debug color table is something we
want to just kind of have as a systemic
thing so other people can use it as well
and so you know if I I'm not sure where
to put that exactly but you know let's
just say that everyone gets a copy of
the debug color table if you ever want
to use it it's there don't worry about
it it's all fine right so let's say we
pass in a color here then I've got some
options for how I want to draw these
things i want to draw some lines here so
i think what we'll do is say this is all
going to be done with lines and then i
can just do one big start and end block
for each individual recursive call so
here's how I'm planning to make that
work right I'm going to go through each
bound and for each bad i'm going to
start with a different color right and
obviously i don't really know what's
going to happen with these colors as
they loop we don't have necessarily
enough colors to ensure that every group
is a separate color unfortunately so
there's really not much I can do about
that we'll have to let the line
connectors sort of clue us in as to that
as much as possible but what I don't
want to do here is I don't want to
create a new group for every bound index
because a lot of those boundaries are
already going to have been used so what
I think I'm going to do is I'm going to
do an early check and hopefully this
makes sense to you as I'm saying it if
the bound flags and oops if the bound
flags are not set for that guides that
reminds me i missed it here we go if the
battle flags are not set then we're
going to actually do the call and the
reason I care about that is i'm going to
start the GL i'm going to start up the
GL stuff for
the drawing and set the color only on
ones where I know that I'm going to draw
it that way we don't use up colors in
the color table unnecessarily and
possibly get fewer actual distinct color
regions than we should simply because we
you know are cycling it based on the
bound index which is not actually
representative of when we're actually
drawing a new group so what I want to do
here is say like group index equals zero
inside here will increment the group
index and then I will use the debug
color table by taking group index
instead right there we go I think I can
do this right so this will be a get us a
neat color out of the debug table you
know every time we need a new group go
ahead and start a group of lines call
the recursive bounce drawing and then
end the and then end the you know the
set uh sorts right bound is an
undeclared identifier is that so
what how is that the case so these I
thought these guys were operating on
these in this I guess were what I'm I'm
confused so you're telling me handmade
OpenGL doesn't include sort sprite bound
it's not true you seem to think it is
alright well I'll take your word for it
and you're right you are correct sir
let's see here so it looks like the
problem is we kind of have a sort order
problem there because loaded bitmap is
going to be in the wrong place for that
ah yes so maybe something more like that
there we go I hate this aspect of C++ it
is so annoying okay function does not
take two arguments that's true got to
pass that color through although
actually now I think about it we don't
have to pass color at all do we because
if we just if it's just set in OpenGL
and we're all just drawing lines then
everything's fine I get certain trees
identifiers not found that probably just
needs to be forward declared get sword
entries bloop bloop and by the way these
are done right these are not ten memory
size isn't being used anymore all right
let's see we need to pass directly the
the float pointer there so there we go
surpassing that colored open shell that
we're drawing bunch Alliance now this
shouldn't do anything yet because we
haven't actually issued those line
directives so we should just see what we
normally see which is good enough that
no surprise there but now we want to
start actually drawing those lines and
you already remember how to draw in
OpenGL right when you start a primitive
type like triangles right then we set we
just set what our vertex pointers are
going to be now when we draw these lines
we're going to have a problem with
texturing because presumably texturing
will still be on because I think that's
our default state is to have texturing
usually stay on there's texture 2d so
what we need to do when we come down
here we're going to have to disable
texturing because we don't want our
to pick up any texture that may have
been set so we need to make sure that
that's okay all right so then when we do
our open gel rendering here all we have
to do is retire some actual vertices to
draw a line now there's a couple
different kinds of lines that we want to
draw here right one is we want to draw
like a line from us to our sort
neighbors right so I guess I'll just
call this neighbor or something and
that's just going to be bound plus this
behind edge and I guess you know what
else I could cusp of us behind so if I
have two of these things and i want to
draw a line to the one that I'm you know
that's behind me what I can do there is
I know what the screen space bounds of
these things actually are already that's
going to be specified in here and what
that entails right here is just getting
the center I guess of that or I assume i
want to draw the center just getting the
center of both of those and then drawing
between them so I just have to know like
what is my Center and I can do that I
think by just saying get center because
I believe we already implemented that
function if not we can go do it on
rectangles so there's the screen area
and then I need to do the behind Center
which is the you know one for the one
we're drawing too same exact thing so
now I've got two points that i can draw
between so if i want to draw a line
after I do the recursive part I'll do it
ah not sure when I should do it really I
guess I want to do it well they're all
the same color so I guess it doesn't
matter because they're all just going to
fill pixels so it doesn't really matter
when I do it but I guess I just want to
now say okay let's retire two vertices
one on either side of the one for each
of them right so I've got the center and
then I've got the the center of the one
that I'm the one that's in front and
then the ones that's behind then after
that's done I can also draw a rectangle
right where we say we've got the screen
area and we've got the min and Max of
that so what I could do here is say like
a you know what's my men my I don't know
screen min something like this sin smin
uh so i could say okay give me the min
of this and give me the max of this and
then I just need to draw you know the
the vertices of the rectangle around and
I think we have open Jill rectangle and
then we could do another one here that's
like you know something like line
vertices or something like this opengl
line vertices and really that's just
saying this this exact same sort of
thing only instead of doing the
triangles for a solid rectangle i'm just
going to use i'm just going to go around
the perimeter right so i'm going to
start with the min and i'm going to draw
from the min to the max in x and i'm
going to go you know counterclockwise
around then that's one line then i need
to start their right and then draw up to
the max so i'm going up the side of it
then i need to start there and go back
along X but staying up at Y and then I
need to start there and go down the side
and that's all of the vertices in that
rectangle right one you know four lines
one for each side of it so there I can
just say like okay you know output the
vertices for this line I before this
rectangle and we're good so hopefully
oops and that's a found screen area
so hopefully that's good it looks like
get min is not in their mid corner don't
ask me why we thought we needed corner
in there but I guess we did and so now
hopefully we'll see something there we
go and you know some of that looks kind
of right and and a lot of it just
doesn't look right at all right and so
already we can tell there's there's bad
news happening here right like there's
some people whose screen areas is you
know is just garbage or something
because some of it like if you look at
the here the region of the hero it looks
really pretty good right it looks
relatively correct and of course there's
some issues there because we're not
scaling things right but you can see the
lines are connecting it to the things
that it's over and that all feels kind
of right but then we've got these
problems of these other rectangles where
everything sorting us and I'm not sure
how right that is now part of it might
be right because it might be looking at
a solid filled rectangle like let's say
the clear screen you know what I'm
saying if all of those are just going
back to the clear screen then that's not
really a problem and now I think about
that's probably what that is I'm going
to take the clear screen out for a
second and see if that's the case
okay so that's good that's you know
that's a that's pleasant so now we know
that really that's just the clear and
it's the clear that's sort of making
everything end up forming into one giant
group right so that's that's that's a
happy thing okay and that's looking
pretty good in terms of detection there
you know that's that's looking
relatively sane and I don't really want
the clear to be doing what it's doing I
you know I don't know that that's a
particularly useful thing for us to be
worrying about is having this giant
thing that would unify because if you
think about what happens is if we leave
the clear in there it means that
everyone will always be part of one
single giant group you know it's in it's
it's just a given because there's one
thing that covers the entire screen
everyone's going to get sorted as part
of that group and there's no need for
that to happen because we know that the
clear happens at the outset anyway right
so the clear doesn't really need to be
in the sort in the same way as
everything else does and I the only real
question I have about that is what's the
right way to slipstream that into the
process right because you know at we
could do the the most straightforward
thing which is to just have the clear be
something that's get you know you just
set what the clear color is and then it
happens automatically the and I don't
know maybe that's a maybe that's a good
idea
the reason that I hesitate to use that
as a solution even though it it's you
know it's relatively reasonable the
reason that I hesitate to do that is
simply because we don't really know how
the pipeline is going to expand we may
have to clear like other surfaces and
stuff like that but I guess what we
could do is just say that we're never
gonna really be clearing a hammy heroes
not the type of gamer we're going to be
clearing stuff that has content in it
ever we're only clearing on start so I
guess it would be fine for us to just
say well when that day comes we're going
to have to have another thing where we
say we want to render target and we want
to render target we get it we just say
what the clear color is so I suspect we
could just say Without Really much loss
of generality or really anything that
just the clear is something we'll manage
separately and typically there really
isn't any reason to clear anyway so it's
not even something that that really
needs to be in here we could just bake
it in to the program in general so yeah
you know what we could say something
like in handmade OpenGL you know if it's
handmade internal we clear or or better
yet I think maybe in here what we would
do is say well GL clear color and we
could get our hideous pink on
we could do that and then just leave the
clears off and you know do we want to
maybe reenable them in the future I
don't know but we could just say all
right you know that's how it goes
because pretty soon we're going to be
putting in real ground tiles and then we
want to see anywhere that for some
reason we're not drawing you know what I
mean
although really I think we said we might
want to do fogging with that as well so
I don't know we'll have to cross that
bridge when we come to it I'm not sure
how we're going to want to draw some of
that stuff so we may have to have
control over the clear color and you
know that's fine if we do all right so
yeah what I could do there is just say
I'm trying to think of what the easiest
way to do that would be I guess you know
what we could do is say well all right
let's say that in the platform system
here let's say that in addition to what
we were sort of passing through let's
see let's see where are we where are we
not the platform api I just want the
game writer commands I'm just going to
say like all right so let's say that in
here in addition to this stuff we're
also going to have a clear color and so
that way it can look in OpenGL it can
say oh well the clear color is just
going to be whatever they said it was
right and then we can just say yeah you
know what and the render entry type
clear is not going to be a thing we're
going to get rid of that and when we do
our clear here we're going to pick up
whatever was skin was in those commands
so you know we can decide what we want
to do with it later just fine but then
when we actually go to issue a clear
command instead of pushing something on
here we'll get rid of that instead of
pushing something on when we try to do
that instead we'll just set the commands
right so when we do our store color here
instead we'll just make that be a thing
where we don't have to do any of this it
would also gets out of the business of
storing that screen area I want to keep
that screen area in there for other
reasons i think so i'm not going to back
that out but you know we could now if we
wanted to so the clear oops
absent-minded typing so the clear now
does what i wanted to do now we've got
to get rid of these and what I'll say
here is I'll just elevate this draw a
rectangle call up to where we were doing
the clear in the previous case right and
then when we you know I'll just grab
whatever that commands clear color is
here and let that happen and then i will
delete that from the software renderer
so it will still be compliant as well
all right initializing conversion from
something to something else u32 to real
32 that's true so in this case we need
to do render command struct so in here
we
clear the clear if you will so after the
push buffer Maximus buffer size in the
push buffer base where we're going to do
the element count and the sword entry
size in here we just need something
that's going to initialize the clear
color to you know black or who knows
what okay so let's see what happens now
if we get a setting of the clear color
we do so that's all that feature is now
restored and now we're sorting the way
that I had hoped we would sort in actual
local groups and yeah that's really all
there is to that yeah so it would be
nice to perhaps to have things that sort
of exists outside of the sort thing will
sort of get into that I guess in a
little bit but let's try turning on some
more rooms now and turning off let's
first turn off the debug and see where
we're at in terms of sort behavior now
that we've got that single sort because
I suspect that was creating a lot more
cycles and things that are difficult to
break and so you know we were probably
getting worse performance out of the
sort than we thought we were going to so
anyway let's go ahead and switch back
out of here and we can also have a thing
that's like if you know show sort groups
or something like this and I guess well
you know what we do have this whole
ridiculous thing so we could do a global
variable b32 global show sort groups and
then you know I'll be honest with you I
don't even remember how that system
works at all but we should be able to do
something where we can just put that if
in here and then that can get enabled I
think oh you know what except it's in
the platform layer how does the platform
layer deal with that I don't remember
little pause
here we go so here's the platform
controls and we have like these two so I
want another one which is you know
global show sort groups and then I can
just put it up here so in theory of
course I have to actually recompile it
but in theory I guess that would let me
toggle them on and off except that's
still wrong but it does work so that's
good
okay uh all right so we're starting to
get there and if we turn it off we can
see that the sort a now appears to be
working at least more correctly right if
not correctly but we have this problem
here and also we don't know what happens
if we add like that's not much of a test
really if we go in here and add the sort
of much more heinous cases here of
having more than one room on top of each
other we you know we get a better idea
of just how far we are from having all
of our sort dreams fulfilled let me go
ahead and hop up here so you know it's
not bad but you can see it's not really
correct
you know there's still a bunch of
problems there so I suspect that we will
probably have to do some looking now at
our sort criteria and then we will also
have to look at the sort cycles so so I
think what I'd like to do now is take a
look and see if we can't draw an
indicator that lets us know when we have
cycle problems right now I'm going to
flip back to Milton for a second here on
the blackboard to just remind you of
what this is because I talked about them
but then we haven't actually dealt with
them yet because this is another problem
there's essentially two sources well 3i
guess sources of error I might as well
write these out while I'm on the
blackboard there are three sources of
error for our sort
okay so what are our sort error sources
well one is just bugs right one is
everything that we talked about and said
and did is correct theoretically but we
made a mistake in the implementation
right like the typo that we fix the
beginning of the stream for example okay
so that's one source of error another
source of error is like bad comparison
because remember we're using an ad hoc
sorting criteria that we kind of made up
about why sprites and Z sprites and how
we sort the two of them together and we
haven't really ever determined that
that's actually a comparison that's
going to work for everything that we
needed to work for and so we may have
cases where actually the problem has
nothing to do with the fact that we've
got a bug it's because the comparison is
operating exactly correctly and the
algorithm is operating correctly but the
comparison is just fundamentally
theoretically unsound and we know that
we could construct cases for that
because we're inherently doing a sort of
hand wavy kind of sort since we're in 2d
and we're representing full 3d objects
with complex sort of interrelations with
just two d cards and those cards can't
capture the real relationship between
these objects that are actually supposed
to be volumes right so we've got that
and then the final one is a you know
graph cycle resolution and by resolution
I mean the act of resolving like resolve
the cycle not resolution like how many
pixels something is right and so what I
mean by graph cycle resolution is we
know that we can end up with things with
a topological sort like this that was
sort of in the diagram shape that I drew
up above it can be much more complicated
certainly but the most simple kind of a
cycle right is I've got a few elements
and they point in a ring and what that
means is
there is no way to actually correctly
sort these objects there's no the sort
criteria doesn't yield a single ordering
it could be that we have some of those
that if we that that the comparison
although that obviously part of that is
that means the comparison isn't great
right because we've created a thing
where it can't really tell us what order
to draw things and that's obviously not
great but it could be that if we had a
more intelligent way of breaking the
cycle then the comparison would still be
okay so it might be that for example
we're choosing to break the cycle here
and draw ABC but really what we should
have done is done is rogue cycle here
right and drawn BCA and perhaps I should
draw it a little differently instead of
breaking the cycle here we should have
broken the cycle here right so bc a
rather than ABC and so who knows that's
again another place we could potentially
fix the problem of bad sorting again
because there is probably no uber
solution out there for us since we are
inherently doing a intractable problem
under specified problem whatever you
want to call it we don't have the real
3d objects so we can't do them and with
a z-buffer or something like this
alright so that's the possible sources
of problems and so what I might want to
do and we've got about five minutes left
here so what I would like to do is maybe
just go in real quickly and see if I
can't in the next five minutes add
something that will draw graph cycles
for us so it'll let us know if we have a
graph cycle somewhere that'll you know
become clear and so the way I can could
do that is I could say well I if we go
over to where we're doing our sorting
let's take a look at how this algorithm
works at the moment so what you can see
when we walk the sprite graph is that
what we're doing is every time
we walk on a node we set a sprite
visited flag that lets us know that we
shouldn't ever come back through here
look we've already used it now this is
really handy but what it means is we
don't actually know whether if we were
to traverse through this group whether
we would hit ourselves again right all
we know is that somebody touched this at
some point but it could have been
another traversal so what we need to do
here is we need to have a way of knowing
that we hit it on our traversal meaning
we started somewhere we went down a path
and we got back to part of our own path
again and if we see that then we know we
have a cycle so how can I do that well
I've got two ways without really even
modifying this algorithm pretty much at
all I can pretty much keep the exact
same code just change a little bit
there's two ways I can do that and let
me show you what each of them are
because they're both extremely simple to
do one way is to use a generation tag
now you saw this already we use it for
asset tracking where we essentially have
a number and that number increments and
we can use that number to see what pass
through an algorithm something was done
on so right now we have a flag we have a
boolean right one bit that means that we
have one bit we can set and if we only
have one bit that we can set that means
we can detect a cycle only in the grand
scheme of things we can only say as I am
typing a cycle we can just say whether
we visit it ever but if instead we set a
bunch of flags 20 we are we I sorry we
set a generation tag 20 at startup and
then every time through we set a that
tag to if it was 0 we know we can
process it we set that
bag to be equal to our generation our
time through the algorithm right so for
on past three or whatever or past four
we set it to that tag then we would know
when we look at the tag we not only know
whether we visited but we know if we
visit it on this time because we visited
this time its value will be equal to our
value make sense the other way we can do
it is with an erasable tag so we have a
bit that says we have visited this thing
we need that bit to be permanent right
because if it's not permanent then the
next time someone comes through here
they're going to reach reverse parts of
the graph that were already traversed
and that's not what we want we want them
to just tie back into it right and say
oh I know that that whole sort already
happened so just tie in here and be done
with it right but what that means is we
can never tell whether it was us who was
traversing this or somebody else because
the flag could have been from some
previous pass will preach some previous
walk that started on some other sprite
not us and that doesn't necessarily
indicate a cycle so what we could do
instead is have another bit and say this
bit we're going to set as we walk and if
we ever hit something with this bit we
know that we cycled on the way back will
erase it since I already have a bit
field I'm just going to use that so I'm
just going to call this sprite cycle
check and then I'm also going to do
something where we just do a sprite
cycle
so what we'll do is we'll use the cycle
check flag to see whether we've gone a
cycle and we'll use the sprite cycle
flag to you know well you know what I
was thinking I guess we don't even need
two of them I guess we could just use
one probably well we're out of time so
let me just quickly throw this in there
and then we'll worry about how we want
to deal with it later so when we step
into this flag here we would we would
always do an or in to put the cycle flag
in when we Traverse and then when we
come out of it after we force the edges
we would just set it uh we would just
get rid of it right so we'd say set
whoops where are you sprite cycle there
we go we would just say I want to and
with not this right cycle right so
though where is it that's the not what
I'm looking for there we go sorry brain
fart I'm like where is it you know it's
been a bad day when you don't until
where the tilde key is so anyway so on
the way in will set it on the way out we
will clear it and what that means is
that when we get to a particular node
right before we do anything else we can
do a check to say if the sprites let
this right cycle flag is set then we
know we have a cycle because it'll get
cleared on the way out of a non cycle
one and so we know that that's the case
so now what we need to do is have some
way of telling that we've hit a cycle
and we already have this nice handy
graph lock thing so we can just have a
thing that says are we in a cycle or not
right so what I'm going to do is
essentially poison any group that has a
cycle with that cycle flag
and the way that I'm going to do that is
say okay we're going to start with the
walk every time we start the walk we're
going to say that we did not hit a cycle
and then every time through here we're
just going to say okay the walks hit
cycle equals the walk kit cycle or you
know the flags get set so essentially we
come in here and we say we know that
walk hit cycle will be set to true if
we've hit a cycle and so I'm just gonna
say and presumably that's a you know
when we're calling down that wouldn't
necessarily be relevant anyway but
either way we're then going to make sure
that that propagates to everybody else
so that we know that this is a group
that cycle so we're going to say okay if
we hit a cycle or we're in a cycle we
are going to keep that flag through we
are in the cycle flag regardless and the
question is when we come back out do we
clear it so I'm just going to say if we
haven't hit a cycle will clear the flag
on our on our exit right and that should
leave us with groups that have cycles
set if there was a cycle in them so we
can see it does that make sense and
that's really it and so then if we want
to draw those and I'll turn this on by
default all we have to do is look for
that flag and set the colors accordingly
so what I'm going to do is probably do
something a little more drastic when we
do open Jill draw bounds recursive here
probably what I'm going to do is say
before we call that let's actually just
make it so that we will only draw sets
that have that so we'll just put another
thing in here that says oh by the way if
the flag and cycle isn't such don't draw
it so just only show me people who hit a
cycle somewhere so now in theory and of
course there could be both the lower in
that
in theory I would see cycles if we had
them right they would draw the outlines
and I don't see any right now which
means either but we don't have any
cycles or my algorithm doesn't work
right so there we go seeing whether or
not the algorithm works in debugging it
will be tomorrow's job because we're out
of time but there you go all right so if
you have questions I may have answers
okay for those of you who did not see in
sohbats amazing quote I highly recommend
checking it out
anyone anyone
having is that a question or a statement
that looks a lot like a statement
how do you decide when a problem is
complex enough to need visualization
well the answer to that is usually you
can tell that you're just having that I
suppose without some sense of intuition
for it built up with experience it's a
little bit difficult so I don't want to
suggest that it's easy it's it's
probably not but the general sense of it
is pretty much any bug that you have or
problem that you have in your head
you've got some attack skills that you
use to go after that bug right and
typically what happens is you think
about what the sorts of problems could
be and you think about what you would
need to do to see if those problems
existed right and so for example I'll
take a very simple example that should
hopefully be easy to relate to for
example you might have some math code
and that math code might be doing
something where certain values in the
computation should be readily in
spectabile and easy to figure out if
they're wrong right we've seen that on
hammer here a bunch there's not a lot of
need for visualization in that case
because stepping through the code in the
debugger is likely to yield the problem
there's not a lot of bookkeeping and
it's just one pass through some math and
you can see what's happening fairly
easily right however other types of code
have a lot to do with big pointer
restructure II things right or
relationships between very like lots of
different objects this sort of stuff and
when I mean obvious i might mean like
physical objects like in the game world
not objects like structures or something
in those cases when you think about what
the information is you need to verify
it's very hard to verify by hand for
example if you were writing a binary
tree
and you're wondering why your binary
tree code has bugs in it well a binary
tree might be 300 elements of things
it's hard to see what your algorithm is
doing all you see is a bunch of pointers
and you have to like on a piece of paper
like write down what the pointers were
and figure out who was pointing to who
and okay did was that rotation was
supposed to move this thing over here I
did it did it right and so when you
start to get a lot of interrelated
things happening over multiple functions
that tends to be the the kind of thing
where you need to do some sort of
visualization work otherwise it's just
going to take too long to find the bugs
all right a programming questions let's
see is the build graph still n squared
yeah we have not touched that so if you
look in here inside sword entries you
will see that we have the builds right
graph and walk sprite graph code the
walks right graph code is 0 n i believe
it's it's roughly 2 m I think cost wise
and then the build graph code is still n
squared right because you can send you
can see it I mean there's no index a
there's no den Dex be so you know it's a
little less than two it's a little less
than N squared obviously because it's
you it's got this like the n times n
plus 1 over 2 or whatever it's the it's
the because we don't have to consider
the previous nodes it's not really fully
N squared but it's still proportional to
N squared so still 0 n squared even
though it's doing less than N squared
actual things it's still doing a number
proportional to N squared
if that makes sense
any other programming questions
programming question
I said programming questions questions
that I have nothing to do with
programming or for the pre stream you
guys know that you know that's true
all right I don't see our programming
question so I'm gonna wrap it up wrap it
up thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade here it's my
pleasure coding with you as always I
think we made some good progress on the
sort today and so yeah I think maybe
we'll have a good week you know
hopefully we'll be able to i think it's
going to be hard work getting because
anything like this it's kind of a
nebulous algorithm that's hand wavy like
2d sprites sorting it's definitely gonna
be the sort of thing where we sort of
thing where we have to grind a little
but you know i'm optimistic about it and
once it's done it's done so that's good
too so they made some good progress and
we'll continue on that this week here is
what i will say if you want to follow
along with the source code at home you
can always pro2 the game on hammer here
or it comes with a source code there's a
forum site you can go to if you want to
ask questions you have a patreon page
you want support our videos series we
have a schedule but if you want to catch
us live and an episode guide if you want
to catch up on past episodes that is it
for today I will see you guys tomorrow 8
p.m. pacific daylight time until then
have fun programming and i'll see you
guys on the internet take it easy
everyone