hello everyone and welcome to another
episode of handmade hero the show recode
a complete game live on stream on Twitch
no engines no libraries just us and
basically we're doing it old-school
we're kicking it old school we're doing
it the way that you used to do it when
you sat down in front of a computer and
you're like it's just me and we're going
to make this computer do something
awesome right that is what we do here
and we're in sort of the middle of you
know a sort of a a big shift I guess I
would say and I guess I want I want to
sing yesterday i was expecting today to
kind of be more in the middle of it as
well but yesterday we kind of just typed
in all the stuff we had to do and then
we ran it and it kind of almost worked
perfectly i think there were a couple
things that weren't quite working right
and so we kind of lucked out you know
some days you just you luck out right
and so today really i think mostly we're
just doing a little tune-up in there and
so we made me coming to the end and the
thing that we were working on was moving
over to a unified asset file so before
we were loading bitmaps and wav files
off disc just randomly like you might do
and what i want to do is consolidate
those so you could ship these little
asset packs which were basically a
bundle of an arbitrary number of assets
in the game and that would include their
metadata like when they should be used
and that sort of stuff and then the game
would just look at all of the asset
files that were in you know the sort of
startup directory for the game and it
would merge all those together and that
would be the assets for that the game
would run with right and so that's what
we did and yesterday we showed how to
sort of change over to making we had our
file API is used to just read a whole
file of time we changed over to make it
so she could read little pieces of the
file and so that's all done now and so
we're gonna do is hop back in there
because there was a couple things I
think with our the way asset membrane
was lining up and there's a couple
things I think there's a couple little
bugs in there so even though we kind of
it kind of worked the first time we try
to I think it's not quite working and so
we got to go in there and now do you
know we're a time to even really step
through it much of the de bugger so
today we're going to do is go back in
there just kind of clean it out all out
make sure we've got everything working
we want and then we can just move on to
our second testing of it which is I'd
like to test having more than one asset
file so we'll go and we'll have you know
our we have a little thing that does a
test right writes out a asset file as a
test and so what we could do is we could
make that thing right out to separate
asset files and you know make sure that
the game can merge those two asset files
together properly without making a
mistake right and so that be that's sort
of the next logical thing on the horizon
because we need to make sure that that's
actually working we wrote the code but
we don't know if it works till we
actually run it so today is day 1 53 on
hand made hiro de 152 is the source code
if you pre-ordered the game on handmade
here org day 152 is the source code that
you would want to unzip into your source
code directory if you wanted to be at
the exact place in the code base that
I'm at when I start running right now
right so I'm going to go ahead and load
it up here here we go and mukuro dot cpp
i'm gonna do my little compile just get
things started and where we left off I
you know like i said look to me like it
wasn't quite right because i ran the
game right and it sounded like mm-hmm oh
that's unusual well okay so maybe not
maybe we've got a better oh wait no that
was we knew that was there that was
there less time to write yeah that was
sort of the indication that something
was wrong but it's not actually a crash
right thing that was actually just a
cert that was like hey wait a minute yes
it counts wrong but when we ran it yet
something seemed to work correctly like
sound you know it's streaming the sound
and playing the sounds correctly
yeah what and all of them what seemed to
be there you know what and then we kind
of have this weird thing though like
where are the shadows right I don't see
the shadows and so I think you know my
my guests before we didn't have a chance
to really live you look at it but my
guess is that what's happening is when
we loaded the asset files we forget to
account for the fact that asset 0 is the
null asset so we actually I think are
loading the the shadow into the 0 slot
which means that everything else still
works correctly but when it when you go
I want a shadow it goes okay here's the
shadow handle it gives you back a SAT
handle 0 and you're like oh everybody
knows that's the null asset so it
doesn't return anything right so I'm
assuming that that's what's happening
with our shadow and that's why we're in
this situation where our shadows
disappeared but every literally every
last thing other than that seems to be
loading properly and identified properly
right like that's the head that's a
tourist oh that's the legs there's the
other head there's the other tour so
there's all the ground patches there's
the trees like every other bitmap seem
to come in and identify itself properly
and so it's just a question of like okay
you know what's what's going on right so
that's my guess just having sort of when
we when we first ran it yesterday that's
what i was thinking in my head oh we
must have missed that but i'm going to
use that as an excuse to to kind of just
take a quick look again at when we do
test asset builder what i want to do
here is I want to kind of take a look
and see when we did our asset file
creation you know I don't really
remember I don't remember what we did
with zero I don't remember if we even
really looked at that in the code and so
what I wanted to do is just kinda take a
quick look through it here and see what
was supposed to happen in the asset file
right and so what it looks like here
right if you see it looks like it sets
the asset count to one which means it's
going to leave space the zero asset the
zero the asset index zero will actually
be no there won't be anything in there
and what I'm thinking you know in my
head I don't think that's a very good
idea I don't think it's a very good idea
for the asset bundler to leave slot 0
open and the reason I don't think that
that's a good idea is because i feel
like the asset bundler doesn't need to
leave those slot well you know as I'm
seeing that I kind of take and maybe I'm
even taking it back because if things
inside the asset file had to refer to
had to have a null pointer as well they
would need to do that so maybe you know
what maybe that should stay and so what
that means is that the first asset in
that file is going to be the null asset
it's going to be a garbage entity you
know garbage asset that should never be
loaded and so what we need to do in the
handmade asset thing is we need to make
sure that we're correctly expecting that
right that we're doing the right thing
there and actually you know being aware
of the fact that that that zero with
entity is not in there and so on so if
you look at what we're doing here if you
look at what we're doing here I think we
can kind of see what the problem I think
we can kind of see what the problem is
right so the asset count in the file
first of all it let's talk about these
problems one time so first of all we
have this assertion and the assertions
saying the number of assets we actually
processed out of the asset file was one
less we when we looked at it it's one
less than the asset count we were
actually expecting right and we can sort
of see exactly why that would be we
don't even you really need to
investigate further we already know
exact whether it would be and the reason
is because here's the asset count that
we that we count up at the beginning
when we look at our HHA files and we
only have one of them and that asset
count here is going to be 1 plus the
number of actual assets in the file
because it's going to be that 0 slot
right so if there are 50 assets in the
game it's going to report 51 okay then
what happens down here when we actually
load them out we only load out the
assets that are actually invalid type
asset types right because we're picking
and we're basically doing that asset
merge and the asset merge never loads
the null asset type it never loads
things with that aren't in an asset type
of right and that first asset is in the
last it's not in an asset type of right
so we're only going to load 50 assets
total out of the file even if
were 51 with Anna lacet that mill assets
never going to get touched right and so
that is the first thing that we would
have to fix the first thing we have to
sit fix is when we increment the asset
count we're going to have to subtract
one from the asset count in the file
right and we're going to have to that's
not to do that's a note the first slot
in every HHA is a null asset preserve
right so we don't count it as something
we will need space for right so that's
time and that way so I think we would
have seen let's say we have three HHH
files is our number at the end would've
been off by three instead of off by one
because we left by 14 for every file
that we have okay and similarly up here
we kind of have the opposite problem
here we're starting out at asset zero
but the problem is we actually want to
be starting off at asset one because we
want to leave that null spot open right
so we want to make sure that we have
exactly one null rather than one Mel per
file which is what we were doing before
right so we want to subtract one from
the s I got here and started at one here
because that's what gives us the actual
layout we want one no total no matter
how many files there are okay so that's
thing one thing two is when we actually
start loading the assets right when we
actually start loading the assets we
have the problem of the asset count
starts at zero but really we need to
reserve that for the metal asset right
so what we need to do is we need to
first make a null asset right so we want
to basically make a null asset here
where we're going to take a look I
suppose we should actually just generate
one where we do a zero struck we're just
going to say you know what that first
asset right that if we're going to
assets asset plus the asset count right
we want to take that asset and we want
to zero that out right we want to take
whatever that is and we want to clear it
so that if anyone actually ever looks at
it it's just a bunch of zeros
really ever should look at it but just
so we know this is 20 it's just blank in
there right and then we increment the
asset count by one right to make sure so
we want to do no Casey reserve one null
empty at that's all right what no asset
at the beginning and I think that will
now align things properly compared to
what we were doing for and hey what do
you know the shadows are back and we
don't get that assertion so now I think
we're in a little bit better shape to
proceed because like I said I think you
know what I saw it I thought come up I
was like I kind of kind of think I know
roughly what's going on there and and
that was clearly a problem right so now
that we've got that what I'd like to do
is like I said I'd like to move on to
testing to make sure because you know
right now the code appears to be working
but we're only loading one HHA file so
for all we know this asset merging might
totally fall apart and break as soon as
you actually have two files because all
of the all of the merging that's going
to happen is really basic right now
because it's all loaded basically
exactly you know it's loaded essentially
the exact same way as it was before and
so some things about whoop that's I was
a little sometimes I put my palm
accidentally on the little like part of
the the wacom tablet scrolls and it goes
nuts right gotta maybe I should disable
that I think I probably could disable
that pretty easily but anyway so I feel
like we have the exact same thing here
with tags potentially since we want to
reserve a null tag right I think we want
to do something like that and since we
were reserving in they'll tag in the
file as well I think the same is good
thing is going to be true here right so
we want them like the first asset and
tagged slot is a null so we don't count
it assuming we need space for it so I
think we want to do exactly the same
things here all is that again all
exactly the same stuff and so that that
way when we do the tag base the tag base
starts at one right instead of starting
at zero and is based from there up and
then similarly when we come in here
right and we do our tag count I want to
do reserve one ml tag at the beginning I
10 struct be that particular tag right
and then I want to increment that tat
count by one and then well you know what
that's actually not how the tag count
works i forgot the tag count i think is
actually already handled up here right
so that's this this part is never
actually used right yeah so really i
just want to do that i just want to
clear that initial tag right and that's
fine so we're do it here and the tag
base has already be set up for us we
don't have to worry about that so there
we go and I think that's all relatively
good that all seems pretty good we can
now get rid of this guy this code is the
old file test code that we had we can
get rid of that and now you know we've
got sort of our file stuff looks pretty
good so let's go ahead and test that
with the tags and make sure that the
tags are still being aligned properly
oops not at all apparently what did I do
wrong there still got the asset tag
count right it's got the tag base right
we're still incrementing it we do
correctly account for that in the asset
yes we do so that's all good but HJ
asset tag 0 we are zeroing that struct
which should be fine right and then we
read them all into the tag base so I
don't know why that would be broken
you know what I do know why that would
be broken now that i think about it so
what I realized here is this is actually
a little bit wrong right because the
number of tags is the tag count minus
one right and here we're actually using
the tag count regular so what we really
need to do is you know we need to skip
the first tag right which would require
us to do something like this right we
want to load one less tag right and we
want to read like this is the thing
that's reading it in it's reading it
into the correct place right but we need
to skip the first tag here where we do
file header tags right so where it's
telling us to do it we need to skip
forward one tag to skip the null tag
right so we're going to skip the first
nut tag since the snow then what's going
to happen down here is when we're
rebasing the tag right that tag base
again the tag base is not quite correct
because the null tag is sort of a
different tag than the other tags right
the null tag is getting collapse down so
what we really have to do is say if the
asset HHA first tag index right if that
equals 0 then what we would want to do
is just make sure that everyone actually
equals 0 right that everything is mapped
to the no tag right on the other hand if
it's not equal to 0 then what we want to
do is move it up by the tag base but
again we would move it up by the tag
base minus 1 right because we would want
to move it up we would want to move it
up to its location but minus that you
know it's 0 tag and so again this
complexity comes from the fact that we
we don't want to duplicate the fact that
there are many no tags when we do that
shift up right yeah so that's a little
janky oops that's left tag index so
that's a little janky but i'm not sure
like i have to think about it but i'm
not sure there's a lot of ways to unjam
by that because but it by its very
nature we're kind of merging these
arrays so there's going to be some
finicky kind of like handling of the
edges of that just by you know by its
very nature right and so I feel like on
the whole that's probably fine I'm not
too worried about the fact that it's a
little finicky again it only really
happens at load time and it's something
that's not too hard to verify and test
should we need to really like take a
more you know a careful look at it at
some point so that looks pretty good I'm
going to go ahead and pop over to test
asset builder here and I'm going to try
and figure out a good way that we can
make something that splits this into two
HHA files so that we can actually test
to see whether it's working at all right
and so what you can see here is we've
got this code that writes out the file
and so what I'm going to do is I'm going
to try and pull I'm going to try and
extract that part out so that I can do
it more than once all right so all I'm
going to do here right is I'm just going
to go ahead and you know extract that in
the in the most direct way you know
exactly how you would think again kind
of doing this is that compression
oriented programming that I'm talking
about here's something I have that I
want to do I want to do it twice so I'm
literally just pulling it out just at
that time and making the thing that I
can call twice right and I'm not doing
anything more fancy than that it's
really really really really basic right
so this is a little right HHA and so
then what I'm going to do is I'm going
to you know make something like this
where you pass it in a file name and
then I'm going to replace oops I'm going
to replace that hard coded file name
with one in here that it can pass so you
kind of say okay you know now would be a
good time to write the HHA i want you to
write it to this file right so we're
going to have to pass in the assets
because it's going to need something to
write so it's going to need you know
this pointer here so there we go and
then we'll see what compositors we have
okay we don't have any so that that's
how we would write out an asset as a
function call and once I've got that now
I can feel free to write more than one
HHA right i can write more than one so
what i'm going to do is
I'm going to break these up into two
separate you know sort of blocks very
arbitrarily so i'm going to have one
here where I'm going to say right here
oh right and then i'm going to have one
here that's like right nan hero right
and those are literally they're not
going take any parameters or anything
they're just going to be functions that
do that thing ok and so here we go i'm
just going to cut out this code will be
the same in both of them basically just
a little startup bit here right and then
this code will actually be unique and so
i'm going to go ahead and grab the stuff
that's not the hero right there's the
non hero i'm going to put that in there
and you know I feel like the sounds are
also not the hero right so so those
maybe would go in there in fact you know
what let's just even let's let's get
nuts let's get crazy here people just
absolutely ludicrous because I remember
someone one time I don't remember the
circumstances but I know we could go or
a couple days ago something somebody
asks could you put all the sounds in one
asset file right and so let's just do it
they wanted to see it let's do it right
so there's all the sounds now and the
music will all come from a different
asset file okay and so there we go and
so now I've got these all of these files
separate they're all going to do their
own their own little dance here right
and again just total test code really
nothing nothing all that much to it now
you know even even as I say it though
you know I mean why not go a little bit
further it wouldn't take much to do it
just something like initialize it takes
a game assets right something like this
if I want to I can pull out this code
we've seen it a couple times maybe it'd
make my life a little bit easier I don't
really know but but there is something I
can do if i want to write and now i can
just say initialize assets like so right
and that's you know pretty
straightforward so maybe i'll do that
and that way i know that this code is
always kind of getting initialized same
wage
I'm which is you know again not really
not really a big deal in this particular
case but can't hurt so let's go up in
here and make this be test three right
this is going to be test two and this is
going to be test one and then I'll do
those files i'll do right here oh you
know right nan hero right sounds
something like this and then i'll go
ahead and compile those now if I take a
look so if i go to the handmade right
data directory and i'm not sure do we
have any global variables as well I
don't know if we do I don't think we did
I don't think so so really we want we
thought that's it in terms of making it
happen multiple times I don't think we
need to do anything else so if I go in
here and I look I got that test out HHA
I'm going to delete that right I'm going
to make get rid of that and then I'm
going to go ahead and just run this code
right so I'm going to go ahead and run
the test asset builder I'm going to let
it do whatever it's going to do and
there you can kind of see the output of
it it's got test1 test2 and test3 now we
have no idea if that did what we wanted
right we have no idea but what we can do
is we can kind of go look now and see if
we can load those files successfully and
then we can see whether we can merge
them successfully the first thing I'm
going to do is I'm not even really going
to do the first test what I'm gonna do
instead is I'm going to just try loading
just one of them right and so now what
we should see we hope right if we've
done this correctly is we should see the
things that are in that file show up but
not any of the other things right so our
asset system will just find that it can
actually load any of those other things
it'll only be able to load the ones from
the first file right and so what are the
things in the first file if we take a
look at what's in there right we've got
the hero that the Cape the head the cape
and the torso of the hero in all four
directions so what I expect to see is
the hero and the familiar the torso the
Monstars those will all show up their
shadows won't the environment won't show
up and
that's what I'm expecting to see right
and that's exactly what I saw so that's
good so that the file writing is still
working properly again we can test each
individual file that way here's testudo
HHA we'll go ahead and load that and so
okay we've got some kind of a problem
here not sure exactly what it is but it
looks like looks like the asset count is
somehow wrong like there's more assets
in the file then a cap then it counted
total right am i right yeah alright so
that's on test2 and test3 same thing so
it looks like only on test one HHA which
is the first one written which is rather
suspicious right in fact I just how
suspicious is it right I just to see
just how suspicious it is we could also
do this right and if I run the test a
set builder again so that it's written
them out in a different order now let's
see if test2 is still the problem or if
test2 has magically been fixed by our
order reversal Hey look at that so
that's very suspicious and says to me
that we've got something that we didn't
quite initialize properly right because
the order shouldn't matter if the file
is going to be wrong it should be wrong
but obviously I didn't quite extract
that code quite correctly so I'm going
to go figure out why not right so let's
take a look in the assets what have we
got we've got the tag count wrench like
Matt got the asset type count not
initialized so there you go very simple
and by the way I've said this a couple
times before
I've said many times before one thing I
like to do in a lot of my production
code is if there's no reason not to do
it I will always initialize everything
20 always and the reason is because
uninitialized variables are very common
in programming and they're very easy
mistake to make in this particular case
right it doesn't look particularly
harmful actually that's zero there it
doesn't look particularly harmful or
anything right it seems kind of harmless
i found that error you know right away
or whatever and it's not that big a deal
right but other times it can be much
more subtle right other times those
uninitialized variable bugs can you know
can come back to haunt you and so rather
than relying on having to actually
manually slice things and remember that
you actually made meal initialized all
your stuff right I i actually vastly
prefer if there's if you don't have to
worry about the speed implications of it
in fig no case i highly recommend clear
to 0 because clear 20 solves all those
problems and is pretty cheap you know
it's it's pretty darn cheap so i do a
lot of that in fact at work my version
of the arena stuff that we do in here
where we do push array and all those
sorts of things i actually pass flags to
these things and one of the flags is
clear 20 and I pass it often so I just
like when I push new memory I just it
gets cleared to zero right because
that's a really easy way to avoid having
those kind of bugs in cases where you
don't care about the extra time spent on
that right so let's go ahead and run
that again let's see if my hypothesis
was correct it looks like it was let's
go ahead and try to load a third file
now as well so i'll switch back here go
test 30 was the dying not do it
correctly I thought I did did I not
initialize the tip the output type
properly what happened
I initialized everything that's all we
got right do we have anything else do I
count on one of these let's see asset
count is one asset type count am I right
about the asset type count or as asset
type count also need to be set to 10
that's interesting asset type count uh
so actually that wasn't really a bug I
take it back although we should probably
initialize that because it's kind of bad
not to i would suspect it turns out
that's actually not relevant okay so the
real bug is not clearing the asset types
array probably i would suspect right
this value was irrelevant it just wasn't
wasn't relevant at all so what we
probably want to do is something more
like this where we say okay there is
asset count number of asset types right
that's just how many there are and what
we want to do is clear out those HHA
asset types so they're set to 0 0 for
every asset type that we don't touch
right so we actually need to initialize
this entire array which again it's not
really a huge deal but it's something
where you know we probably should do it
again this we're using the C runtime
library and our external tools so test
as I builder doesn't get built in so you
know I'm fine with glowing them sitting
here just kind of like we're fine using
the printf and all that sort of stuff in
here so we can go ahead and do that it's
this asset types situation right and the
size of that is going to just be the
size you know of the of the whole array
right I want the whole thing cleared to
zero
right and I've got a pound include I
don't know where that's that I assume
it's a memory H I don't really remember
yeah so let's try that one more time
write that out and run it there we go so
now we're we've taken care of our
uninitialized portion for the test asset
builder again we don't really care about
that code it's a relevant code it's just
for testing but you know we have to make
it work well enough to actually do our
tests right so it's worth debugging it
feel least to the point where we can use
it not worth worrying about it much mark
to that so now let's see about merging
again before we implement this win32
side of things let's do a cheese version
where we just force it to do exactly
what we want to do in this case and so
what I'm going to go ahead and do there
is say all right the file name right I'm
just going to do a simple thing where I
say if the file index equals 0 then the
file name equals one thing right
something like this else if right else
if something like that or invalid HHA
something like this right so if the
autumn is 0 will load the first one if
it's one will the second one if it's to
below the third one and now we'll load
all three and now we can go you know
debug our emerging code which you know
like I said we have not had a chance to
test yet so this will be our way of
debugging that code right so at first
blush it appears that everything just
kind of works so maybe the emerging code
doesn't have any bugs in it or none that
that are sort of evinced by this but I
don't really know oh dear that does not
look good in our load sound call oh my
well okay so we've definitely do have
some kind of bug in our loading code and
it's in the sound stuff because you can
see what
happened here somebody got back an ID
that's wildly invalid so our asset file
thought that there was a valid you know
a valid ID out in the middle of nowhere
right I mean there's no we don't have
anywhere near that number of assets so
that can't possibly be a valid ID it's
happening inside the prefetch sound code
so in here that info where we have that
info next idea to play you can see that
that's just garbage right it's just
totally and completely wrong since we
know that was the music basically we
know that we're either setting or
adjusting those assets incorrectly so
let's think about that you know what
that's a good point so when we merge the
assets in we are not updating that thing
one but thing too is that's so far out
of bounds I'm not sure that that we I
mean I wonder if we were even setting
that quote I think probably we weren't
so when we create create one of these
assets right I wonder if we weren't when
we create a sound asset if we weren't
initializing that properly or not so in
here it looks like we are right it looks
like H sound next idea to play value
that looks like we are initializing the
sound properly and if we go look down
here when we're actually adding it in
when I look at this I kind of feels like
that should have been correct so I'm not
sure where that really bogus number is
coming from so we're gonna have to do a
little more forensics on that but one
thing that I did want to point out is
when we load our asset files that is
actually something that's going to be a
little bit difficult for us right
because next ID to play for this for the
sounds right that value we don't know
how to remap that value right
oh and now I think about it that's
probably exactly what's happening even
so if you think about it this is this is
actually probably exactly what's
happening and why we're getting the
bogus value so it is probably the exact
problem that i was just saying so here's
what happens right we rebased our tags
so we know that the tags are correct so
basically when we have you know multiple
files and each one of them so we have
these tag arrays when we merge these tag
arrays where this you know this used to
be tag 0 that used to be tag 0 that's
used to be tag 0 right and now they've
all got you know all the tags zeros not
to hear right this used to be tagged one
tag one tag one now tag one of this one
maps to hear tag one of this one maps to
like tag 17 you know tag one of this one
maps the tag 35 or whatever right now
that we're doing that remapping for the
tags we know that our assets all point
to the right tag so if some asset you
know if an asset here was pointing to
this particular part of the tag table
and then another asset here was pointing
to this part of this tag table right
they might both be pointing to tag to
this guy when it gets merged will still
be pointing to tag too but this guy
should be pointing to tag 18 now right
so we have to remap that and we're doing
it what we're not doing however is in
the assets what if an asset points to
another asset we really don't have any
of that except for one place which is
the next sound ID so what will happen
there is the first time we play a sound
that has one of those right that came
from a file which gotri you know when
the things got rearranged the first one
will be fine but its next pointer right
I mean to think about how this worked in
the file may be right they look like
this so I had you know sound 0 and it
pointed you know to sound one and it
pointed to sound too you know like so
those now have to be remapped so they
can kind of jump you know so they can be
correct because when we map these right
and this is you know if this
slot 0 slot 1 slot 2 or actually it
would be more selecting out let's say
this is slot 16 15 17 18 this pointer is
going to be 16 this pointer is going to
be 17 I should say this point will be 17
this one's going to be 16 or 18 right so
16 points in 17 17 verse 18 right when
we be mapped these they may get loaded
into some part of the asset array way
down here right and now this asset is
acid at 237 well if it's pointing to
asset 17 still it's going to point way
back to some totally different asset
that's not even a sound potentially
could be like a bitmap right or it could
be to some other totally different sound
right and we'd have no it'd be totally
wrong and so we need to remap those
pointers otherwise we'll load garbage
which is f what we saw where the next
idea to play with some garbage value
that was probably like the bitmap width
or something or the floating-point
alignment for the bitmap or something
right so that's just a garbage thing so
what we need to do when we load these in
is we need a way of translating where
the assets are trying to point to so
that we can make sure that they actually
exist in the right places right so yeah
so we know they're all inside the same
asset class right and we do know what
the base of the asset class actually is
so when we come in here and we say asset
count for type 1 passed last a SAT
master assassin is source type first
asset index is telling us sort of the
base of these guys right so if I were to
take whatever that you know that next
pointer actually was right and and do
the rebasing on it that would that would
do the trick the problem here is again
do we don't actually know what kind of
an asset it is right we don't know
whether it's sound or music at this
point and again I don't think that's
something that we ever actually stored
so knowing how to remap it is actually
kind of tricky
because in order to know whether to
remap it oh well you know what I take it
back we kind of do no we actually do
still no because what we do know is in
the asset type ID right where we've got
like asset tag as a type ID that stuff
in this in this we do know that
everything above a certain places sounds
right you know I'm saying to you so we
actually do have the ability to say
something like okay you know asset first
sound something like this right and then
we can do something like this I guess we
don't even care if there's empty stuff
in the tree we could even just do it
like that right and so we can do
something like this where we say okay
that it's bracketed so we actually know
where the sounds are and then we could
always determine whether something with
a sound just by doing a simple
inequality check right I could pretty
truly say is this a sound by just going
is it in between here and here and then
I still wouldn't have to store whether
the thing was a sound or not right so
what i could do is say oh all right you
know at the end of this I could say if
is sound and pass it they that that
asset index right so basically is is I'm
not the asset index the asset type right
so which one is its source index like so
right basically if this is a sound type
right if if this is a sound type then I
know I have to remap it so I know I have
to take HHA sound cut next ID to play
and that next ID to play has to be set
to be the correct value for the offset
so I know that its current value right
like so oops didn't that subtract in the
wrong direction right I know that's it's
offset from its base and now what I need
to do is say okay now i need to make it
the offset from our base wherever that's
going to be right because I know that
that's where it will load right so I
know that that all of the things in my
asset type are going to get loaded
together so I know that that you know I
can I can remap it that way now it's a
little cheesy because it means that you
couldn't have an asset in one class have
its next idea to play be an asset in
another class right that that would be a
limitation of this style of remapping
whereas I could do something more
ridiculous in fact maybe I'll do it more
ridiculous just so you can see instead
of doing the remapping sort of in that
tricky way maybe I'll just do something
like asset remapping table like that and
so what we would need to do now is make
an asset remapping table that remaps one
type of asset to the other and so as we
come through here right what i would do
is say okay there's you know going to be
one of these profile so as we go through
the file and we load out the individual
assets we have a remapping table that
tells us where they go right and I could
totally you know I can totally do that
although it's easy to write I'm just
thinking about it like man I'm
introducing this whole of the table
lookup thing that has to have i'm not
happy i'm not happy about this let me
just tell you i want to tell you from me
to you I'm not happy about it I don't
love it right I don't really like that
that aspect of it I don't like the fact
that the next idea to play is so janky
in terms of how it gets remapped and I'm
wondering whether we want to introduce
some kind of a shorthand that's going to
make a cleaner so for example if we
wanted next idea to play to be something
you know something a little bit more
special-purpose right so if it was just
for doing streaming music and looping
that's all it did we could do this a lot
more cleanly right and so since I don't
know of anything really that we're going
to do with it besides those things what
I'm kind of thinking is that I should
take a step back and say don't bother
introducing this whole remapping thing
when we don't have assets that really
need to reference other assets you know
wait till there's some real reason why
we want that feature and instead make
next idea to play be a little bit
different right just change the way that
that code works so that it doesn't have
to be remapped and that means we also
wouldn't have to do this right and that
seems better to me and so the way we
would do that right is we would go okay
inside the file format instead of
storing next idea to play we would do
something like you know enum HHA sound
sound operation is probably wrong but
sound chain something like this and we'd
have like HHA sound chain underscored
none we'd have underscore loop and we'd
have underscore advance right and that's
all we have and then this right here
would just be one of those where we said
okay this is going to be some value from
HHA sound chain and that value is going
to tell us what we should do and so
that's going to be like you know chain
so that when we do is we say okay by
default chain is going to be equal to
none so you know our sounds by default
will not we'll just play and stop and
then what we do here is when we actually
do these sounds we won't have to store
the last music value or anything like
that right all we have to do is say in
general if this is not the last sample
right so if first sample index is not
equal to total music I guess what I it's
a little bit tricky here because it's
going to be added to music chunks so I
guess what I'd do is I'd say all right
if
if first sample index plus 1 music chunk
is still less than right if it's still
less than it then I know it's going to
have to do its advanced thing so what
we're going to do is say this music
value sound chain is going to be equal
to advance right so go you know play the
next sound right and that's it that's
all we I think we would really have to
do it's this music and we just modify
the mixer to understand what that means
right so what it's going to do is it's
going to say okay if the info says that
the chain sound got chain oh wait we
have to do sound up chain it's just info
chain if the info says that we have to
chain this sound then what we'll do is
we'll just know that we increment we go
to the next one right so if it tells us
to advance we just always play the next
one so all of the music chunks exists
sequentially in the fat file right so we
just do prefetch sound whatever our
playing sound ID was right playing sound
ID we would just say you know what sound
Shane advanced or get next sound insane
in fact you know what we would do what
would really do is we'd actually just
just do exactly that we wouldn't even do
the if we would just do that we do
prepaid sound get mixed sound in chain
and we have that next ID to to play
would not be there we just say here's
the sound info for this thing in fact I
don't even know do we need the info for
anything else yeah we only kind of do it
there right so what we'd really do
probably even condensing this further is
next sound in chain we just ask it
what's the next sound insane for this
sound right and this will be you know
something that we put in the other thing
and then we will prefetch that the next
sound of chain
this will move over into our asset
system so this might be an inline to be
pretty simple so yeah we'll make a call
we'll make a call to the thing called
get next sounded Shane and that would
take probably the game assets as well
because it needs to do that query right
so it needs to take the assets so do get
next on a chain it'll prefetch that
sound and then later it's got next sound
and Shane down here and so what it can
do is when it comes down here and says
you know next I need to play it'll just
use next sounded chain right and it will
advance to that ok and so that's pretty
straightforward right and so the only
thing we think we really need to do now
is just fix no fix this guy here so he's
going to return a sound ID what it's
going to do is going to take a sound ID
in and it's going to say all right let's
get the sound info of that ID whatever
that ID is let's assume I guess we could
do is room that the result is going to
be nothing so that there is isn't it's a
there's no sound that follows it will go
ahead and ask if the ID we got past is
even valid right we go ahead and get the
sound ID out in fact I guess we don't
have to do that because we call get some
people just get the null one back if it
was null so that's actually probably
fine to get the science sound info we
then just do an if right on the info so
we say I guess we could even do a switch
where we say info chain and then we
handle our cases right we just handle
those cases that we had up here like so
so assuming it's none
nothing to do it's all good assuming
it's loop we're going to return the same
sound that we have and assuming its
advanced we're going to return the
result value equals ID dot value plus
one just move it one forward right and
we have an invalid code path here avail
a default case so I think that's what we
want because now we don't have to get in
the asset remapping business it's just
loads and works right and so let's debug
that make sure we don't have more
problems in there that I've created by
sort of what I've been doing let's take
a look oh dear oh right these are not
going to be set correctly because we
have to rerun the exporter since we've
changed the data definition there right
so let's go ahead and run it
nicely
all right one so that's better and now
that's you know we've sort of gotten
that problem out with the remapping and
we just don't have to worry about so I
think that's good i think that's where
we want to be i didn't like the
direction it was going without me to
remap the entities because i felt like
we would be doing a lot of bookkeeping
there for potentially not a lot of wind
so i would like to see more asset vile
referencing of assets between assets
before i would say that that's a good
way to go it seemed like just a lot of
work that didn't need to happen right so
I'm glad we got really bad that's much
better all right so I think that's
probably a good stopping point we only
have two minutes left in the stream
anyway so I'll go to the QA a little bit
early since I don't know that there's
anything that i really want to start on
right now because the next thing that
I'd like to do is to sort of you know
take a take a step back and just go and
go all right let's go ahead and actually
implement this stuff that actually gets
us the the fight all of the files of
this type in win32 right which is you
know again something that we're going to
have to go to have to write new you guys
haven't really seen me do any stuff like
that in win32 before and so I want kind
of want that to be handled properly so
all right that is it I will go ahead and
start the QA going if you have questions
about what we did on the stream please
prefix them with Q colon so I can see
them because I filter out the question
so that you know people who are trying
to talk about something else on the
stream can go ahead and do that and so
that I can see the questions that people
are asking and answer them so please put
a cue colon in front of it and then I
can check it out
you
duckbill Phil can we do advanced and
then loop sounds yeah I mean every sound
has that value set separately on it
right so you can do whatever you want
right there's no restrictions on on that
I mean you could you know if you were
just sitting down and going I don't have
any reason for it i'm just going to
start playing with this because i'm
interested right which by the way you
know is not something I super do that
much these days because I'm a production
programmer so I tend to focus on what's
going to be a valuable thing for me to
implement for this game right but when
you're first learning that's not such a
good mindset to have playing around with
things is good and valuable right
because it helps you learn and so you
could imagine doing some more things
here if you just wanted to sort of how
much functionality could we get out of
this thing and so one example is you
could change chain to be something a
little more specific you could change
chain to be like instead of a u32 you
could have it be to you six teens one
that's like a command like none loop in
advance and one that's a counter and so
if you set it to loop you could set the
loop counter to something and then in
the sound playing code it would count
how many times it played the sound with
the same ID right so every time it gets
hits down here and does invalid next on
a chain it would go if playing sound
equals next sound right if these two
things were already equal increment the
loop counter and check the info for this
sounds loop count and if I'm above that
loop count then advance right so you
could actually have inserted multiple
loops in and then advances so advanced
advanced loop loop advanced loop loop
loop advanta just with that one thing
you could make these pretty crazy series
of things you did right I just don't
know that there's any real what reason
you'd ever want that but you if you're
just kind of looking to program for fun
it's it's fine right if you're doing the
ID value plus equals one what you
eventually loop off the last sound asset
well the idea is that that would be a
bug in the asset build because if you
notice what I did here is I only set it
to advance if there are more to play if
it's the last one I set it to none so it
will end so the idea is you set advance
advance advance advance advance advance
end and so when it gets to the end it's
no longer going to keep trying but we
can let it run someone was actually
saying that we had a separate bug on the
forums that we haven't had a chance to
debug yet and so actually I can t do
this for another reason which is we
should have an actual different bug at
assertion they were saying they get if
you just let it run for a while although
actually you know what they said that
you had to that it repro if you did it
with the chipmunk version so so I think
if we do this version where plays fast
yeah so let's let that go because we
have another bug to catch as well
potentially not a question but Abner's
internet will be out for noches oh no
what happened to heaven or what happened
to his internet that's unfortunate I
didn't realize that's do that
can i watch when you first started
writing this game yes you can go to
handmade hero org and click on video
archive there it is so this is the
assertion and basically what it was as
you can see it's not the things don't
quite line up right it's just barely
under right and we kind of fixed these
so we still have a book i don't know if
i should debug it now because
technically this is the QA and I don't
know that I'm really supposed to be
doing it but it doesn't look like
there's really any questions that are on
topic so let me just take a quick look
at it so basically what we're looking at
here is our samples played is is getting
set to end sample position but n sample
position is actually not actually off
the end of the samples right it's a
little bit short right ends it ends just
a little bit short it's and so I wonder
what
so let's take a look here and sample
position yeah this does look kind of a
little float precision a
so we were going off of chunks to mix
and when we do our computation right we
said the total chunks to mix you know
versus the tungsten makes it the headend
was was 309 or whatever I don't know if
the actual number would have been
because it gets overwritten by other
things something probably clipped it
where we did the rounding right where we
said okay the number of chunks were
mating and sound you know we did sort of
our clipping and I'm guessing that if we
actually go do the math out for this
we're going to see that that's too
sloppy to actually guarantee that we're
always going to end at the correct
number we may be off by a little bit
right and it it's not going to actually
matter right like we can keep going and
it's fine but it's a little glitchy so I
think we might want to set it aside a
day to kind of go through and maybe
clean up how we're doing this whole
chunk counting thing to make sure that
we're you know doing it in the way
that's as robust as possible so that we
don't have because like trying to get
that stuff to always line up properly
seems error prone
right and this is going to be that this
is right and it's only going to really
happen on pitch shifted sounds but we're
gonna have plenty of pictures and sounds
that happen only when I dude volume or
is it so anyway though case in point
right you can see the sound ends
properly so we don't have that problem
but we still have plenty of bugs left in
our sound that we really should go back
and fix there's something with the when
we moved over to the asset fell stuff we
introduced a little glitch at the end as
well so we just have some stuff that we
need to we need to kind of go through
that sounded one more time it's not
quite as robust it needs to be and we
need to double check that we're writing
out the ends of our sounds properly as
well
sorry for not related to the stream but
what is the next thing you have planned
after assets I probably will will try to
tackle well either well we only have two
things to big things on the to-do list
at the moment before moving on to game
code which is like the we have the debug
code like debug annotation and being
able to draw debug stuff and you know
debug readouts hud's that sort of stuff
so debug code debug infrastructure it's
about time we did that we've got enough
complexity in the game now that it you
know would be helpful to have that
infrastructure and lighting so those are
those are the only really two big tech
features that we don't have and so once
those you know we got to go do to those
two and once we have those two in then
we can kind of do it some passes on
thick to kind of clean things out fix
some of the bus of things you know it's
kind of solidify stuff a bit and we'll
be you know we'll be pretty ready to
sign off on the engine in terms of like
this is ready to start prototyping the
game you know ready to start start
writing whatever we want for the actual
you know intro the game in the you know
how we're generating the maps and how
you're now the combat works and all that
sort of stuff how do you determine
whether to fix a bug or keep moving
forward so you know the ant the actual
answer that question is not exactly what
I show on the stream and the reason for
that is because I have two bucket this
into educational chunks the answer is
you fix the bug immediately always
always so when you are doing production
programming you fix the bug always
immediately right now and the only time
that you don't fix the bug is if a it's
in code that you are in the process of
deleting so there's no point in fixing
because if you're deleting the whole
thing or B you're in the process of
fixing a different bug so that you can't
really go to bug that bug right there is
no other circumstance where you don't
fix the bug immediately you
always fix the bug immediately so if you
find it you go fix it that's definitely
the rule and if you're not going to do
that you would better be pretty darn
sure that you're not going to use the
code that the bug is in that you're just
going to delete it right that's my
opinion so I don't really leave bugs
sitting at all I never move forward past
the book and so on the stream the reason
I have to do that sometimes is because I
need to try to bucket things into one
our educational pieces and I don't have
the luxury of always doing the thing
that would be the best programming
practice I try to as much as possible
show the best programming practice
because that's what the streams about
but I do have to do things we're like
okay you know normally I'd go take a
look at X now but I'm kind of going to
not necessarily do that because it'd be
really inconvenient to do so in terms of
where the streams lineup but yeah so the
sound code has a bug in it I'm sure and
so I would like to go spend a day
debugging that above day one of our
hours right debugging that but you know
I'm trying to teach you this thing and I
don't want everyone to forget what I'm
teaching you about the asset code when I
go do that code right so I kind of have
to make some concessions to the
educational nature of this project that
are not necessarily exactly how I would
have done it if you know if I were doing
it completely alone if I decide to go
for a PhD or something in the future
will you give me the blessing to write
about compression or ed program you
don't really need my blessing you know
compression oriented programming is the
thing I would like people to do and so
I'm happy to hear that people would be
writing about it I would like more
people to do it so
any other q Cullens or or not
looks like not all right but I'm going
to wind us down here I'm going to go
ahead and remove this one point nine but
I'm going to say well you know what I'll
do I'll do something more like this I'll
do do k see if you use the 1.9 version
there get it can clearly repro a bug in
the accuracy of the sample played caps
so yeah I have a feeling the problem is
that this really wants to be a ceiling
because we allow you to play over and so
I feel like we're act I feel like it's
really just our math is just wrong and
so I feel like when we if we go through
there and do a little more of a
fine-tooth comb approach we can fix that
in a much cleaner way all right okay uh
let's take a look let's take a look at
where we are at okay file save all right
thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
at home to the source code you always
can it's at handmade hero org you can
pre-order the game and it comes with a
source code the whole time so right from
you know the very first episode you can
download the source code and you can
play around with it and it's a good way
to learn if you're traveling program you
just want to play around expert with
some of the ideas that we're doing on
handmade hero you can you can do that we
also have a forum site you can go to
catch up on old episodes there's the
anti episode guide there there's a form
can ask questions there's ports to mac
and linux that the community has done so
if you're trying to follow along one of
those platforms in advance of us porting
to it you can check those out we have a
patreon page if you want to support the
video series that's the place to do it
and we also have a tweet bot the tweets
the schedule so if you're trying to
catch is live you can check the tweet
bot I will be speaking this thursday at
the intel buzz workshop in seattle so if
you do want to stop by and check
out and say hi that's where I'll be it's
a it's a low-cost event for the
community Intel basically you know I
think they the tickets are free for
people who register early and they're
only like 20 bucks or something for
people who register late so it's
actually you know it's kind of just
something they do for community outreach
it's pretty cool so check that out I
actually know what the web address is
but Intel buzz workshop right Seattle so
that's the old one of course they didn't
this one this is actually it seattle
until buzz work shut up Abby my app com
right so it's here and so this is this
is the actual thing I don't know if
they've actually fixed the speaker thing
yet to actually lift me know if they did
it's right there and so that's that's
where that's at thursday at the impact
hub which is this thing down downtown so
yeah i will tweet out some more details
about that a little bit later if you're
sit in it that's where i'll be this
thursday and definitely come say hi if
you have to check it out until then we
will be back here tomorrow 5 p.m.
pacific standard time as always right
here on twitch love to see you back here
when we will go through and yeah I guess
I I think I want it will make me save
the sound stuff for a little later like
I saying we'll probably go do the win32
code necessary to load the files so we
don't have to hard code it like we're
doing now so we came to kind of finish
that up and and call that nice and done
and then we'll be good to go we can you
know sort of look at look at some of the
other stuff so we'll be doing that
tomorrow hopes to you back here until
then have fun coding and i will see you
guys out there on the Internet at large
taggies everyone