hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show where we code a complete
game live on stream we are just sort of
cleaning out our bug list here because
we've got some issues that we had set up
where we were like we know we want to go
through and sort of fix a couple things
that we'd had that we'd left sitting for
a while and we did a bunch of that and
we're down to the very last few things
we did part of one of them yesterday
which is switching our OpenGL texture
downloading from asynchronous to
synchronous because drivers were not
apparently very happy and we actually I
heard from friends who done a bunch of
like porting work to various platform
stuff - who were saying yeah do not try
to do multi-threaded OpenGL it's a
disaster so I was like okay that's
totally fair so we are switching over
from multi thread to single thread open
gel texture transfers and so we did part
of the work for that yesterday and we're
gonna do the other part of it today and
then hopefully we'll have time to kind
of wrap it up and debug it as well and
then we'll have that off our list and
then we can move on to the final item we
have which is clang compatibility which
is then we'd be done with all of our
issue list well all the issue lists that
we can do right now the other ones like
make sure we have a guy in a tree or
stuff like that which is you know kind
of a Content request okay so the thing
that I wanted to talk about today I
thought would be a good time to show how
to do this that's just an educational
sort of concept that I thought would be
good that that we can use for the system
that we were about to implement
yesterday that we set up and we're like
okay we're gonna build son I should I
really just need to make a we do a
stream where we just go find what that
bug is because it's got to be something
we could figure out and I and the source
code is publicly available for this
program so it seems crazy not to take
advantage of that and fix it all right
so let's see here day 325
and I want to talk about ticket taking
and ticket taking is it's pretty cool
it's a multi-threading concept that
let's try and get that ok connected
that's really pretty simple once you
kind of see how it works it's really
basic but it's pretty handy and it's a
little bit better than the way that you
might do mutexes otherwise and so I
don't think we've done one on handmade
hero and I inside my codebase at Molly I
think I I might literally use them
exclusively like I don't even know if I
use anything other than ticket taking
there might be I don't really know but I
think I may be almost entirely ticket
taking in our code base so I'm not I
don't quote me on that but it's
certainly the bulk of the things for
ticket taking so I started to show how
to do them
so what what ticket say what is ticket
taking why do I care about it what why
are we talking about right now
well as you know if you've been
following the series when we originally
did some of our multi-threading work as
you know you obviously have this sort of
fundamental you sort of core problem
which is that when you have two or more
threads in the system working on things
that could happen at the same time you
have an inherent consensus problem where
there's states of things that you need
to be coherent right you can't just have
two threads randomly writing to the same
memory or reading from that memory and
expect good results because you don't
know the order in which they'll do
things and you could end up with
corrupted data and we sort of did or not
even said Krebs data but that invalid
states basically right and we talked
about this a bunch so I'd encourage you
to go maybe listen to the earlier ones
if that sounds very strange to you or
you're not sure what I'm talking about
but in general just to recap we could
take a very very simple concept such as
a linked list that we've done many times
singly linked lists and we've done many
many times on handmade here oh and if
you think about the operations that are
involved right if we think about a
linked list
let's say that I just make the very
simplest kind that I possibly could and
so I've got a link struct and inside
that links direct I just have a pointer
to the next thing right and then it
doesn't even matter what the data is in
it we don't care we just know there's
some data in it and an X pointer and so
all we have the very simplest thing that
we could possibly have we just have a
pointer right mm-hmm and that's all
there is to it right now you've seen me
write the code for adding and removing
things from a linked list many many many
many times and so you kind of know
exactly what the code for this type of
structure looks like when we need to
maintain it right if we want to add so
here is like where we would add a link
write the add code is extremely
straightforward right I'm gonna get you
know whatever my link is you know my new
link here is just gonna be equal to you
know something you know whatever it is I
a locate a new one or I grab one off a
free store or who knows doesn't matter
for the present thing so I have a new
one right and I'm gonna say that
whatever the existing first thing is is
going to become my next pointer right
and then the first thing is gonna be me
okay and so if you think about what that
happens
diagrammatically right is previously I
just had this first pointer and it's
pointing to something we don't know what
it could be null right it could be
nothing but it possibly is an existing
linked list with some number of chains
in it right and so then I come along and
I've got this new one that I've made and
so what I want to do first is make it
point to this one whatever is there and
then make first point to it right and I
have to do them in that order because if
I did them in the other order I wouldn't
I would lose this one right because I'm
using the value of first here so I can't
overwrite it prior right so it has to be
exactly this right in order to do it if
that makes sense
now I'll mention something else there
are there is another way you could think
about this which is if you want to be
sly mr. sly pants you can initialize new
next like like whatever the whatever
this value is new next equal to new like
I could I could be sly right I could do
new arrow next to that points to itself
and then do swap first and new next
right because then it like first goes
into here and new Nexus into there so
it's worth noting that actually if your
CPU had sort of an atomic swap operation
you can almost make well not almost you
can make this operation be entirely
atomic because all you have to do to add
something to the beginning of a linked
list is an atomic swap and you could do
it just pointing that out not so easy is
is to delete something from the list
right to remove something for the list
and I guess maybe I'll call it remove
because it's not really delete I suppose
so if we're going to remove something
from the list now what I've got to do is
say all right the first pointer whatever
that is is the thing is the link that
I'm going to get right so I've got an
old link that comes off here right and
then what I want to do is I want to set
first equal to whatever old next was
right but I can't just do that because
if I just did that I could possibly
crash because I don't know that there's
anything on the list ahead of time so
technically I have to do it if here
right I have to say if I actually got an
old thing then I could do it now you'll
notice there's a distinct difference
between these two things and let me
write that out a little clearer I was
not great I probably should have put the
space left space for the if but I have
to say if or
old right then we can do first equals
fold first I'm sorry next but right I
can't we know that I can't sort of
access that guy until I've actually
verified that he exists so there's a
sink difference in these two this one is
like essentially conditional free right
this is just moving some memory rounds
in a very predictable way either by
doing two writes like so or a swap right
depending how you want to structure it
this one on the other hand has to do a
read a test and then a right that's just
that's just the way it is okay so now
the question is what if we want these
things to be happening for more than one
thread at the same time right
what happens if I want to start having
this stuff be multi-threaded so people
are adding and removing things from one
of these singly linked lists let's say
without regard for the fact that other
people may be using the list at the same
time and I want to guarantee that I
always have a real linked list and I
don't end up losing a link somewhere or
getting into some situation where
somebody's pointer points in the middle
and nowhere or who knows what happens
right I want to maintain the integrity
of the list well you can immediately see
the problem with multi-threading these
if you just leave the code for add the
same as it was then the problem is it's
just two-step process right now like I
said before if you happen to have an
atomic swap right where I can I can
actually swap to me and I don't mean
swap a register in a memory location
right I mean swap two memory locations
atomically if you happen to have
something like that then you could do
this in one atomic operation and add can
be completely mutex lists it can just go
but if you don't have that you have two
steps and if you have two steps then you
have the problem of somebody can
intercede and once you have done this
one step here
they may come do their odd operation
while your thread may have gotten
swapped out or something
who knows what or is busy like waiting
for some piece of memory and now when
you do first equals new you've corrupted
the list because they added something to
beginning of the list then you overwrite
that they're the correct first pointer
with your first pointer or fitting
whatever they put in there right you're
if you've essentially their ad will
essentially disappear because you
prepared your new link pointing to the
head the previous head of the list they
came and added a new head and now you
over wrote the head pointer to your
pointer so you've totally they're new
they're their addition has just
disappeared right now same things true
have removed when I pull this off and
then start to test it well somebody in
here could have done another remove and
now we're both removing the same element
right or they could come in and remove
two or three elements and then I write
this back in there and that's wrong
because it's right so anytime you have a
couple steps in the instruction you're
at a point where you have two choices
you certainly can't leave the code as it
is so you can either do one of two
things one is you can try to create an
algorithm that's just about doing atomic
move or compare operations that will
work right and that's for if you want to
be mr. fancy-pants and I don't really
necessarily recommend doing a whole lot
of that and the other is you can do a
fast mutex right you could do something
that's very low cost but that basically
ensures that only one person does things
at a particular time right and so that's
what I prefer to do is have a very very
fast mutex o mutex that only takes a few
instructions in the case where it's
uncontained only you know a hundred
instructions or something 200
instructions whatever if it's if it is
contended so very very lightweight and
you can use them everywhere and they
don't really slow your code down right
that's what I want I don't want some big
heavyweight nasty mutex thing that has
state or any of these other things no
good right
well state that has operating system
state or anything like that
so I want something very very very
simple my threats are not gonna go to
sleep or anything like that
they're just gonna do quick checks and
then lock up for a couple cycles if
somebody else is in it and then proceed
that sort of stuff right so ticket
taking is a way that we can implement a
really good fast simple mutex for little
chunks of code that we just want to wrap
so that we know that when we're going to
access this particular piece of data we
just want to make sure that we're the
only person who do does this simple
atomic operation on it and then we can
proceed right so what is ticket taking
about well we know we have this concept
of atomic operations in the CPU and we
talked about these and we talked about
the meze protocol right which is the
thing inside the CPU cache which allows
different CPU cores and different
entirely different physical processors
in a multi multi processor masti not
just a multi-core machine to get the
state of memory straight between
themselves right and we know that we
have certain operations we can rely on
that will go through that meze protocol
to do the right thing and make sure that
we can do stuff like test and set a
particular value in one operation
without the possibility of another core
or processor coming in there and doing
something in between right and one of
the things that's really great and
Fabien pointed this out to me actually
it was in the middle of hand-made here
before he pointed out to me I think I
mentioned to it there's a really great
paper and I'll mention it again it's
called weight free synchronization
that's by this this fellow right here
Maurice Herlihy and this is probably one
of the best papers that there's been in
like the history of of stuff papers and
certainly in in the history of
multi-threading I don't think you could
get a better paper than this it's
insanely good and the important part of
this paper that the takeaway if you take
away nothing else
it's that atomic compare exchange is the
fundamental building block for all
consensus algorithms and the reason for
that is that Maurice Hurley he basically
proved in that paper that for the vast
majority of things you
I want to try to do concurrently it is
literally impossible to do them without
that operation like that is the
fundamental operation atomic increment
is not a fundamental operation nor is
decrement nor is swap it's only atomic
compare exchange that actually lets you
build everything and so at some level
you can kind of think of it as like well
the best you're gonna be able to do is
certain very specific other sorts of
things with the other atomic operations
but for anything real atomic comparing
exchange is where it's at right
but anyway details for the paper you can
go ahead and read them it talks about
consensus numbers and all sort of the
fundamental things and Maurice really he
invented all that as far as I can tell
like that paper is paper we vetted
always like hey guys guess what I
figured it all out we can we can stop
now and that was it so with our atomic
operations the one I'm gonna focus on
here is atomic compare exchange and
basically the one that I you know
there's various flavors that these sorts
of things could take but what I want to
talk about is Sicily the atomic
operation again we've done it before on
handmade hero but it's essentially
atomic operation that says you know if
you know I've got some pointer right so
if my my target here I'll guess I'll
call it the destination if the
destination equals an expected value
right set the destination equal to a new
value right and in either case I want
you to return to me what the old value
was right
and even that I don't really necessarily
need all I really need to know right is
was it going to say
I don't even remember what I was gonna
say Oh all I really need to know is
whether the assignment succeeded right
so that is a pretty big one right and
the other one that I wanted to mention
is the super simple one that we've also
done on handmade here which is just
atomic increment right an atomic
increment is just one that says all
right I just need you to add 1 to the
value of whatever is in this location I
don't care what the value was beforehand
I just need you to add something to it
but I need you to tell me what it was
before right and so that one's really
simple that one's basically just like
you know return star dest plus plus or
depending on the situation
plus plus star dest right kind of a
thing whether or not it returns you the
pre or post incremented value can differ
depending on you know the processors
implementation or the library that
you're using outside the compiler that
you're using to access that could choose
to do it different ways and so on as
well right so just keeping these in mind
these are the atomic building blocks
that we tend to work with and I think
that's pretty much everything I wanted
to say too
motivate this whole thing yeah all right
so let's talk about our ticket taking
scenario now so ticket taking is a very
very very simple thing we can do and it
actually doesn't really involve the the
well I guess you'll see it doesn't have
to involve sort of the more strenuous
consensus number things so if you look
at that Maurice Herlihy paper I'll kind
of make a brief mention back to it in
case you want to go read it but we'll go
a little bit forwards from there
regardless so anyway ticket taking let's
first talk about what we need to have
happen right so let's say that we have
our list you know add function here that
we were going to do right this the one
that I talked about beforehand right and
we know that this thing is not atomic we
know that it's not thread safe so when
we call this add we know that we've
going to have to do something to make
sure that anyone who's working with this
list has prevented everyone else from
doing anything at that time right so
that's just you know that's what we're
trying to do here and so we want to
basically put something around it like
we said we usually call these things
mutexes the phrase mutual exclusion
right we often call it something mutex
to say a we want to be mutually
exclusive when we access this thing we
don't want anyone else to access the
same time because we know the operation
we're doing on it fundamentally can't
happen at the same time as someone else
who might be using it right so if
effectively what we want to write is
something like you know begin you know
access or whatever end access and we
kind of want to wrap this thing in just
a little kind of wrapper that says we're
going to begin access here we're gonna
end access here and everything inside
here is going to have to happen in a way
that is ensure that nobody else can be
doing that any
to the list at the time when that
happens right so what we need from this
begin access and access what we need is
some way of saying make sure my thread
can do what it's going to do so wait
until my thread can do what it's going
to do also once I am ready to do what
I'm going to do make sure no other
thread can think it can do it and then
when I get down to end access its make
sure I can tell any other thread now you
can do it right so we need to sort of
wait till I can do something lock
everyone else out do the thing and then
unlock so everyone else can come back in
and that's the fundamental option you
know mutex operation right okay so
what's one way we could implement this
just looks a very very basic way to
implement this right well if I have my
atomic increment and for purposes of you
know of simplicity here I'm gonna call
this atomic add because that way we can
think of it as one thing like you know
if if I want to be able to do plus one
or minus one I can which is kind of
handy for talking about this in the
general case I don't actually need it
for the ticket taking necessarily but
yeah for describing it other ways you
might do something I might so let's say
we could talk about the more general
atomic add not just increment although I
don't think I'm actually needed for the
ticket ticking that's separate issue so
when when you look it's only this how
might we do something well you could
imagine we could do something where we
said well alright let's suppose we have
some volatile global int right and
remember I'm just gonna say again what
volatile means and for the love of God
people do not write in and send me any
of those awful volatile articles that
people sent in that we're just all wrong
trust me when I say what volatile means
I'm not lying to you
volatile just means the compiler cannot
assume that it knows what the value is
because it read it before and it is
important to use in multi-threaded
coding it is not
superfluous despite what you may have
read on really bad Stack Overflow posts
so anyway let's suppose we have a thing
here volatile in called mutex and we
have that as a global variable right
well you can imagine we could do
something where we could say alright
let's go ahead and do some sort of a
operation on that integer right where we
could say yeah if we were to you know if
atomic you know add on my mutex with one
write something well you know what I
might do not think about this to be
safer pretend I didn't say this let's
just do the let's just use this one
because it's much nicer so let's say I
do atomic exchange right compare
exchange we go of my mutex
and I want to do a atomic compare
exchange I want to compare it to zero
and I want to set it to one right and so
if I do that and I get back 0 which is
what I'm expecting it to be right then
I'm going to do my operation so I'm
going to do this this thing here
if I don't then I know that this mutex
was not set to zero right and so what I
can do is I can say well alright let's
just assume that I do this in a loop
forever and if I ever get to do my
operation I break okay so when I'm going
to break obviously I need to clear back
my mutex so I can add a bit of code in
here let me clear this out a little bit
just to make that a little cleaner to
read list add mutex equal zero
break and let's assume that this is
being done in a for loop right so now
take a look at what this is going to do
by default you know this mutex is equal
to zero I come in here I say all right
atomic compare exchange zero one
it's obviously equal to zero so I stick
a 1 in there I then do my list add I
then clear the mutex back to zero and I
break right off we go now since this
isn't an atomic right just to be safe
you probably want to write barrier in
here right you want to finish anything
that was gonna happen
you want to write barrier right here so
in between these two I probably want to
write barrier because as soon as I set
this to zero that means any other thread
could could start executing right to
start doing code to it so I probably
want to write barrier in there but
that's a little bit not part of what we
actually care about at this particular
point so ignore that temporarily all
right so now if another thread while we
were in here came through and did if
atomic compare exchange right what's it
going to do well that mutex is set to
one right so this will fail and so when
it fails right because it will return a
one it won't equal zero when it fails
it'll just skip this and loop and try
again so what will happen is the first
thread in will set it to one and do the
operation the rest of the threads will
just sit there trying to atomic compare
exchange over and over and over again
until they can now as long as list add
is only a few cycles long which it was
it was like what eight cycles something
I don't even
like hardly anything it's just memory to
however long it took to read those
things from memory so maybe it could be
up to 300 cycles or something if you had
to read the memory you're only in a
block for a very little bit of time if
you ever block it all but chances are
you won't block at all because you're
probably never going to hit at the same
time or very rarely so most of the time
it's free right it's just the cost of
this one operation and that would be an
effective mutex right we could just do
that and that would implement our linked
list no problem right but there is kind
of an annoying aspect to implementing
the mutex this way even though we could
and even though we know that atomic
compare exchange is a nice safe easy way
to do this and nice and clean and it's
good and you could write your whole
program with nothing but atomic compare
exchange and it'd be fine right this
would all be great and it's and whatever
but there is one downside and the
downside is there's no guarantee that
any particular thread who comes into
this process will actually get a turn
really right because unless the hardware
itself happens to enforce some kind of
specific attempt based something there's
nothing to say who gets to go when if
thread one comes through here and or
let's say thread a comes through here
right and a takes that mutex so a gets
into this routine now becomes and hits
this atomic fair exchange it fails right
so it goes into the loop and it's just
in a fail loop right when a comes out of
the mutex threads seen might be coming
in at just that time and thread C could
take the mutex right and B even though
it was there way before C is still gonna
fail and keep on looping and now thread
D comes in and takes the mutex and a
comes in again and takes the mutex and B
just keeps getting unlucky and never
happens to be executing at the right
time you know to actually get the mutex
right so you can kind of see how if this
were an expensive operation where people
actually probably are gonna have to wait
some time
we start to get into a kind of a
negative potential situation here which
is that we really don't know that we're
being even remotely fair to the people
who are trying to take these mutexes and
even though this isn't a hard real-time
scenario that we're in it kind of starts
to feel a little bit bad right it's like
well how long has bee been waiting at
this point and dee could probably stand
to wait a little bit so it really would
be better if we let me do its operation
that's you know that's gonna let the
system flow more smoothly if we tend to
process people in the order they came in
hopefully that makes some sense right so
now let's talk about ticket taking it's
a it's a way to solve exactly the same
problem but in a way that ensures that
the people who came in order get retired
in order right so basically same exact
process as the mutex but people who come
in the order abcdefg get retired in the
order a b c FG which just tends to be a
smarter way to make your systems flow it
reduces the possibility of bad churn
that can cause things to be highly
latent and in games we tend to not want
things to be highly latent that way
right so a ticket taking system works by
just adding just one more piece of state
that's it so now I have a volatile int
you know ticket served in a volatile int
ticket finished right and the way that
these work is every time someone goes to
try and take the mutex they are going to
instead of spin locking on a value
that's like either 0 or 1 based on
whether anyone's in there
they're instead just gonna first just
take a ticket like you would at a deli
counter where they've got one of those
little machines where you pull the
number out of right it's like what
number are you oh you're 83 right well
that ticket being system is exactly this
thing right here and this is the now
serving right that now serving thing or
whatever you want to be
it's not really but you get the idea
okay so how does this work well when I
go to actually take the the mutex right
when I want to start doing my operation
I first just do you know what's my
ticket number
well my ticket number is my atomic
increment on ticket served right so the
first thing I do is I take a ticket I
just increment that that ticket served
and now I know I've got a unique number
because everyone who comes through here
is going to do an atomic increment so no
two people will have the same ticket
number and the ticket numbers will be in
the order in which the threads hit this
line right or I should say the order in
which the threads were able to execute
this line so it's up to the meze
protocol to be fair at that point but
we've pushed it down to the meze
protocol level who is deciding what
order our threads go in at least right
we have not introduced any additional
term so we take a ticket and now all we
have to do is wait while our ticket is
not equal to ticket finished
and now technically we don't want to
wait exactly on ticket finish because we
have a start-up concern here this is the
semantics this is the idea but if you
think about what happens this starts at
zero this starts at zero so when we do
the atomic increment well let me know we
could as long as the atomic increment
returns the previous value right so it
will return zero for the first ticket
we're fine right so then we just do our
while loop we say let's wait until we
ticket finished is equal to the ticket
that we had right and then I do my
operation so whatever my ops go here
ops go here and then I do one more
atomic increment on ticket finished
right but that's it barely more
complicated than the other code right
barely barely barely more complicated
than the other code right it's got two
atomic operations instead of one but
those atomic operations are technically
even simpler they're just increment
there's no compare exchange right so
there we go hopefully that makes some
sense so basically all this does is it
justice alright let's just give out a
number to every thread it comes in here
and then we'll have every thread wait
until it's number is the number that's
currently supposed to happen very very
simple right really really clean you
know you just debug it once and then you
can use it everywhere and it's really
great right and it has this really nice
property unlike other kinds of mutexes
you might do where instead of it
randomly letting threads go depending on
some who knows what it's always based on
pretty much first-in first-out which is
just a better a better way to go all
right so hopefully that all made some
sense and you know like I said hopefully
that's that's enough of a brush up on
the multi-threading stuff that what I'm
about to do is not going to seem silly
and weird but let's try and get that
implemented down
in the codebase so I'm going to go ahead
and open up handmade code and I'm gonna
go ahead and say that we've got in our
handmade shared here where's my platform
I believe we have our ad or like we've
got our times there we go
so we've got our atomic ad you 64 here
and we don't really need a you 64 we you
know but I guess since that's what we've
got we can use it it might as well right
so we'll just that's what we'll do so
let's say I want to make one of these
things I'm gonna do exactly what I just
said like literally exactly what I just
said so here's a struct I'm gonna call
this a ticket mutex and what I want to
do here is I want to have a new 64 right
volatile cuz I've been putting the
master ticket and au 64 just will call
this serving right and that's all I need
to implement the ticket mutex I just
need these two here now one thing that
I've never been in 100% sure about
because I've never actually done the
timing is I always wonder whether these
should be padded so that they're on
separate cache lines does that make
sense
because since the meze protocol will do
sharing based on the cache lines I
always wonder if you if it's better to
have your tickets and your serves on
separate cache lines it'd be a really
hard thing to measure and you need some
code that was really hitting this Muta
commute X is hard so I don't actually
know you know I've never tried to
actually construct the thing to test it
but I've always just kind of wondered it
and I know if anyone's ever really done
that maybe they have and and someone
could send me a link but anyway ignoring
that so now we've got two things right
we've got one which is like you know
begin ticket mutex and we got another
one which is n2 ticket mutex right and
these are just going to do exactly
what I said we've got a ticket mutex
pointer that we want to use and what we
have to do here is we have to figure out
what our ticket is right so this is our
you know our number right and we can say
I guess this is probably better called
you tech since we have them hanging
inside it call ticket you tix ticket so
maybe that looks that looks better to me
so you can say I've got to get a ticket
out of here so I knew that I have this
atomic add you 64 right and hey that
returns the original value prior to
adding that's what we wanted and the
thing that we want to add is just one so
we could have used increment there isn't
an increment in here already so we don't
have to care we'll just use that so this
will add and give us back our actual
ticket move it to the next ticket number
we can then just say why don't you just
loop while our ticket number is not
equal to the serving number off we go
and that's it that's the entirety of the
beginning of the ticket mutex right when
we want to end the mutex we don't really
have anything else we have to do right
because there's no we don't even need to
know what our ticket was right because
we know that these things are fully
locked so all we have to do then is just
say hey whatever the serving was oops I
forgot an ampersand up there yeah
whatever the serving number was I just
want to go ahead and move that forward
right and that's it so at that point we
didn't have a ticket mutex that we can
use anywhere that we want to in order to
ensure that people who access a
particular primitive of some kind will
not do so concurrently so that any
threads that happen to be pounding on it
they'll always sort of go in order and
serialize just at that one point right
so that's pretty great now in order to
bug that we actually have to use it
obviously and so let's go ahead and do
that if we come to our asset processor
here I believe we had a place where we
were talking about this right we had
this add up thing going on here where we
had a texture app that we wanted to
and so what we wanted to do here is is
exactly sort of what I wrote we have to
have a like a texture op mutex somewhere
so we have to pass that texture op new
text in here and then we'll have to do
our end ticket mutex
with our texture op mutex right but then
when we're in here we can do whatever we
want and again although we want to
generally keep the amount of stuff we do
inside a mutex to be relatively small
since we have done in actual mutex we
can do any code that we wanted here so
it doesn't matter how intricate it is we
don't have to be smart about it or try
to figure out how to do a lock free list
where we're just doing things with moves
because if you look at how simple it is
to do the new text version and if you
can just keep the amount of code in
there to be relatively succinctness to
try and be lock free or whatever you
want to talk about there right so
typically speaking this is a pretty good
way to go especially because it's a lot
less error-prone as well right so anyway
if we're gonna do this operation here
what we need to know is where that's
actually going to get stored and so we
need some notion of a place where when
we're doing our loads where those things
can sort of be placed right because this
is sort of has to access a global it's a
separate thread right it has to be able
to access some kind of a global list or
something of this nature that can be
pulled from and operated on and other
things like this so I don't know exactly
how we should do that I'm not 100% sure
but do we it looks like we I don't I
don't really know how we want to manage
this I think we do have a place where we
get Global's of this nature inside
handmade CPP let me just double check I
thought there was one here somewhere
yeah we have like like debug global
memory and those sorts of things right
and so the way that these work is when
we first come into game update render
right there's this notion of one of
these things that gets sort of set and
we're gonna need something like this
because these are separate threads that
are doing this I'm well you know what I
guess we don't even need to
necessarily because these separate
threads do have data that flow with them
so as soon as we could just target
something with them and and that would
probably just work so maybe we will try
to do it that way yeah okay maybe I'll
try to do it that way but we will at the
very least need something stable like it
has to be something that sits around it
can't be something that gets some we
updated lots of times or anything like
that so we do need something that's
going to kind of have a return sort of
like a flow back kind of a feel to it
has to be persistent it can't be per
frame I guess so I'm saying because
these threads that are going to access
it operate across frame boundaries so
they can't it can't be something
specific like that all right so if we're
going to do something like this we have
game render commands right and we also
have I guess game memory gets passed in
and so what we could do is inside one of
these things like maybe game memory is
the best place for it probably let me
take a look
game here it is inside game memory we
can probably have a thing in here where
we point to whatever that that list is
right so we'd probably have something
like well
platform texture up cue something like
that I'm just guessing
and so platform work queue is not really
defined and this is something that I
would want to find so I'm gonna probably
put it here and what that would have is
just that texture up first maybe we want
texture up last as well and then we want
a texture up first free and I don't know
why I felt compelled to type that so
many times so we've got a first to last
in a first free and I think that's
probably all we would need right and so
this guy needs to have the pointer to
that it needs to know where that's going
to be and so when it does to begin and
end view text inside here it now needs
to be able to do the operation that it
was trying to do right and that
operation
I guess texture apps I think they've got
a next on them I'm pretty sure they do
anyway I could be wrong about that but
what we would need to do here is I guess
trying to think about how this guy would
actually handle the situation where he
had to wait it would be nice if he could
but I don't actually know
I don't actually know how he would go
about waiting
hmmm this parts gonna be a little tricky
and here's why
so when we do texture op ads the problem
that I was thinking of is I guess we we
don't really know how many we need right
that seemed would be the main problem I
would think here and to be honest I
guess I don't really know that we need
to chain these because we're gonna
process them all per frame anyway so
it's entirely possible that we wouldn't
really ever have to do them in any
particular way but anyway that's neither
here or there the point is the the
managing the the amount of them we have
is a little bit it's unclear exactly how
we do that right it's possible we could
just say well we only allow this many
per frame to be added and we just make
sure we allocate more than enough for
that to have happen but I'm just not
sure what happens in the case where we
find that there is an overflow should
there be an overflow no maybe we just
say there never can be an overflow it's
just a hard error and everything goes
haywire in that case but you know I'm it
would maybe be nice to have a better
idea of what we could do there but I'm
just not sure right I'm just not sure
what what the right solution is so I
have to think about that some more but
you know barring that right if we if we
are to say just like okay there's got to
be something on the free list that's
just a requirement and the game doesn't
work if you run out of memory if you run
out of queues here right if we say that
and I guess I could put that to do here
can we devise a soft failure case for
running out of ops what we do want to do
is say all right well when we add an up
here we've got the first three so we'll
say ok we'll take whatever is on the
first three
this is for adding I guess we'll do it
this way
maybe so this is the OP that we're gonna
add our desktop
I guess this can also be put here this
is the destination app and so what we
want to do is essentially do like you
know something like this where we copy
it on but first obviously we have to
advance the free list like so so that
pulls us off this copies our settings on
and then what we have to do is we have
to push it on to the list so then we've
got our queue last do like if queue last
you know few last equals Q last next
equals test will ensure the test equals
next you'll see really although I guess
anyone passing to us probably has
already done that in fact we could just
do this and if there isn't a last
pointer then it's just Q first equals Q
last test so that basically just allows
us to put those opps on there and it
puts them on there inside the mutex so
that we know that nobody else can do
that right and that's really mostly it I
guess
so inside this queue we then need our
mutex
right because our queue always has to be
able to like anyone using the queue has
to be able to do that and I guess I
don't know where shared gets included
here just shared not get included here
all right
so yeah we need the ticket mutex to be
visible to that code so you know we kind
of need we kind of need this guy to be
up above right we need these guys to be
a nice place maybe somewhere up here for
example yeah and yeah so at that point
really we're mostly down to just routing
we have our add up calls and the add up
calls will have to know where to get
that texture op Q so where's our work
happening that's it there it is
so our load asset work has to have a
pointer to this right it's got to be
something that it can access and it
looks like it's got it doesn't really
have anything else there that it could
to do tasks with memory I suppose is one
and you know another thing that we could
do like I just got to point this out
it's not something that we should
probably do here because it wouldn't
really make much sense based on the
frequency of things but I'll just gonna
mention it let's suppose we did a ton of
adds to this linked list just a ton
right like thousands per frame then we
would be hammering on these mutexes a
ton and that would be bad what we could
do instead is inside the task with
memory where we have one per thread we
could just build separate lists one per
thread and when the task gets retired
take them off then and put them on to
the main list as a chunk so it you only
take the mutex once do two rights you're
done right
and so you can see how like how you
would choose to structure this would
depend a lot on how often you were
expecting to do certain operations
anyway so yeah in this case we need a
texture op q here what did I call that
thing form texture up q and yeah that's
an address there and this guy needs to
know this so I believe inside game
assets we need to know where the texture
op Q is so let's see inside game assets
that would have to be known so in here
we've got platform texture out q and so
every time we're going to do one of
these we would have to know what's it
called assets just yeah so we've just
have assets texture up Q and off you go
now when we actually queue the work
obviously is another time that we're
going to have to map okay so that's the
only time so we in here when we do our
final state loaded we would have to do a
thing that's like hey the texture op
tube it's going to be in here alright so
last step of the plumbing might as well
do it because we're almost we're almost
done even though we're close to at a
time
so when we passed the the allocate game
assets thing let's just pass the texture
op q their form texture up to
and we'll just put it in here so
presumably this is something that will
get passed I think I said we would put
it inside the memory right and so when
we allocate those game assets we can
just do a game memory so now all the
plumbing is worked out and that's all
great but inside our win32 handmade we
would have to actually point it at
something which currently we don't I
don't remember how we did game memory
exactly but it looks like game memories
actually static and since game memory is
actually a static thing that doesn't get
reallocated I think we could also
probably if we want to
I think if we want to we could actually
make it just be included right I think
you could actually just do that and now
I think we would work just fine if it
wasn't for the fact that when we
actually go to run this right there's
not going to be anything in the free
list right free list is empty so it
should immediately yeah it should
immediately assert on the free list so
just because you know we're in the
middle of it if we were going to
populate that free list let's just say
that we went ahead and populated it with
a bunch of of memory here if I went and
said you know give me a give me a
virtual Alec of some kind here you know
something like this and I said like okay
yeah you know we we've got mmm one of
these texture app guys and maybe we say
like how many of those do we want I
don't know texture app count
we've got 1024 that's so many more than
we could ever possibly use right but
whatever
so we allocate an array of 1024 of these
right and we get that memory we then
just loop through these and we say
whichever one
we're on Jimmy
whichever one we're on we just want to
set its next pointer equal to whatever
the next one is oops so they're all just
changed to each other right
the last guy we know would want to not
set that so we just don't touch him
and then our game memory texture op q
all we need to do is set that first free
equal to the first guy right if we were
being mr. snarky pants snark bottoms on
this particular case we could even do
this because I mean why not
oops yeah I mean you only live once
right
and that would initialize our free list
with a giant set of these guys yeah all
right so that's the texture op list and
at that point I think we've actually
went everything except the fact that
nobody actually ever does anything with
the texture op list right which is not
exactly the best thing in the world to
say the least
so if we wanted to we could then
actually call our OpenGL manage textures
thing and actually have it download the
textures and then be done however we
also do want to be conscientious here
return the last one probably so I'd
probably say something like a texture op
star last equals zero and in here just
say like last equals op sort of a thing
something like that and so the reason I
want to do that of course I'll show you
in a second it's relatively
straightforward when you see it so if I
now want to go ahead and do my manage
textures I can do that
in win32 handmade we come down to the
place where that would probably happen
so right before we're gonna do like our
opengl stuff or something after that's
been filled up and maybe you know maybe
we do it right after we get out to you
know maybe that's a good time to do it
so we do like our debug frame end thing
and we we do our write right before
we're gonna unload the the game code or
whatever maybe I'm not sure where the
best place to do it is
yeah yeah I don't know maybe like right
here I'll just do it right here so right
here when we're about to do our open
Jill managed textures obviously I sort
of said before we have to be able to
make sure that we're always new texting
these things so I have to take my mutex
again just like I did before and at this
point I guess maybe you only live once
ness of it I guess I shouldn't have been
so Yolo because I don't really want to
type that again that's just a lot to
type so I suppose I should have actually
been more reserved and said yeah you
know what texture up hue maybe is a
thing yeah do it that way you almost
don't live once
okay so then we've just got texture op
cube or sorry platform texture op do op
q equals game memory q
okay so our texture app cube you Tex has
to get taken and released so that we can
actually do this operation because again
this is going to turn to that list you
can't have people sticking stuff on the
list in the middle of that we should at
the back we actually could if we wanted
to and we would have to know not to mess
with the stuff that's at the beginning
of the list if that makes sense but I'm
not even gonna do that anyway what I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna put this sort of
one down from it and show you what I'm
gonna do here I'm going to take the
mutex right I'm gonna say okay whatever
the first thing is I'm gonna take that
first texture off off and then I'm gonna
pretend the list doesn't have anything
in it anymore damn right so I'm just
gonna quick take the mutex get in pull
the whole list off essentially zero it
out and now I'm holding the whole list
and then untaken X now everyone can keep
adding back in there so we don't have to
they don't have to wait while I actually
go talk to OpenGL because I just pulled
the whole list off and off we go
right so that's fine no need to be
fancier than that right so then I can do
last texture app equals manage textures
past that first texture app that's gonna
run through it's gonna return me the
last one so then all I have to do is
just put all these guys back on the free
list right and to do that that's pretty
trivial right I just take the mutex
again remember everything we do in here
have some you text and like I said I
could do that in there if we wanted to
but taking a mutex is so cheap I just
feel like might as well get out of the
way and just in case they want to come
in there might do it if you really cared
you could test the timing see if it
mattered I doubt it would either way but
you know what do you do so anyway then I
just want to put these guys on the free
list right I want to make sure they can
go on the free list so then what I do is
I say well alright whatever my last
texture app was if I had a last texture
up if I didn't then I you know what I
could even do this if I don't have any
texture ops
then I don't need to put anything on the
free list obviously so really it can
look like this I suppose right put
assuming I got something right so
assuming I got something I have the
textures managed I begin the ticket
mutex and then I say okay whatever was
on the first the first felis before
that's gonna be the last
whatever my last texture up I found was
I'm going to point him at that part of
the first free list and then I'm gonna
set the first free list a point to to me
right and I think that should do it but
I've written a lot of code there without
really doing much so you know probably
won't work but that's the basic idea and
now we can go to the QA you might as
well run it to see where we've foul up
horribly oh hey look it almost worked
which is pretty hilarious so we solve
somebody to do I'm kind of surprised
that worked at all the first time but
that's fine so we can go to the Q&amp;A now
and then tomorrow we'll finish that up
the debugging and and that should do it
also I suppose while I'm waiting for any
Q colons I might as well just take a
look at these things but you'll manage
textures with data so we didn't do there
is one thing we didn't you do yet though
which is also the the asset State thing
and so I don't know if that's that may
be one that we have to deal with as well
because right when we once we add the
texture up we shouldn't really
technically be using the we shouldn't be
setting the asset to its final state
until until we actually do the app so do
you Mitsuki I've already said like a
thousand times I hate Vulcan so there's
never gonna be a handmade Vulcan
renderer not for me anyway easy side do
you need a safety ripe area before the
current ticket increment inside mutex
unlock no so one of the things that's
true pretty much across the board
is where my where's my ticket root
access so one thing that's true across
the board is that Atomics insert their
own barrier so basically one of the nice
things about ticket mutex as well is
that it actually naturally has its read
it's its barriers on either side because
these Atomics serve as the barriers so
that's kind of nice right and so so you
don't need them because of the Atomics
if you didn't have those Atomics then
you would have right but yeah
so at least as far as I know there's no
need to put any additional barriers but
that is the barrier and yeah the unlock
so this is like I said this is kind of
an interesting aspect of the ticket
mutex because you're issuing atomic at
the start and atomic at the end there
naturally various other types of mutexes
which is I think what you were sort of
assuming where you said oh you missed
the atomic at the end other sorts of me
taxes don't have an atomic at the end
right they may just do a regular set and
they don't need to do it atomically and
then you would need a barrier so yeah
do you use an sRGB frame buffer and/or
premultiplied alpha yes we use both of
those things we use both an sRGB frame
buffer and premultiplied alpha we use
that surgery frame buffers srgb textures
and premultiplied alpha everywhere well
not everywhere we do use non
premultiplied alpha for the secondary
frame buffer but everywhere else we use
premultiplied alpha so all sprites are
premultiplied alpha at the moment
but I'm not really sure I while I don't
like that aspect of it I'm not really
sure that's a problem oh you know what
also I might do while we're here is the
wiggle make currents thing here is it
just in it yeah so this stuff I want to
get rid of this stuff so there's no more
thread OpenGL RC any of that stuff
so this stuff should all yeah this
should all go away goodbye and all of
this stuff should go away so now we just
have the one open jail bar see and we
don't ever have anyone else do anything
with it which is what we were trying to
get to one thing that's really nice
about this is as far as I can tell
that's 100% reproducible which is great
so it means we should have a much easier
time debugging it you could imagine was
something multi-threaded like that we
could have had a situation where like it
it was highly variable
coordinating I can explain about the
secondary framer for not being
premultiplied what's the secondary frame
but for for the secondary frame buffer
is just to have a alpha composited upper
layer so I can actually show you it what
it's doing it'll make a little more
sense later on but for right now you can
sort of see if I go up these stairs do
you see how it alpha blends a new floor
in above me like that in order to make
that floor blend in seamlessly and not
have the sprites disappear individually
or be able to see through them or
anything like that that is that is what
that's were so that's that secondary
frame buffer and since that that is
rendered without I didn't want to go
have the renderer have to make it
produce a pre-rendered alpha secondary
frame buffer because there's no reason
to pre multiply the alpha since it's
never getting scaled we don't actually
need the alpha be pre multiplied so it
was just easier to leave it on pre
multiplied but everything else is pre
multiplied because it produces more
correct results it might be plenty to do
but since you are using C++ have you
used any azzam calls inside your code
you can't call Azzam from C++ in the end
the on Microsoft's compiler you can you
can in LLVM so if we were using LLVM we
could have we could have used as an
inline assembler but you can't in Visual
Studio why you can't in Visual Studio is
beyond me
it's like you know it used to support it
in the 32 and I think still does in the
32 bit compiler but then when they moved
to 64 a bit like I guess Microsoft had
gotten so far away from ever knowing how
a computer works anymore that they
didn't think it was important to be able
to put inline assembler into your code I
which is stunning to me I have no idea
how you can even be a programmer and not
think that inline assembler is important
if anything they should have massively
upgraded the inline assembler when they
went to 64 a bit and done stuff like
made it easier to you know
to never have to use like NASM or
something but they didn't do that so
barren vortex is there a reason you're
not using scope mutex guards that handle
unlocking whenever the guard goes out of
scope yeah because I don't I mean what's
the difference it's just whether or not
you put in curly braces right like so
for example again ticket mutex so you're
gonna put something around this right
and so if I do it this way that's what
it looks like and you can see it very
clearly if instead you use the scope
mutex guard then it looks like this
right so this is five lines of code this
is four so you've typed an extra line of
code this now can no longer like if I
wanted to do something with first
texture up here I couldn't write and hey
guess what that's exactly what I wanted
to do so scoped mutex guards are garbage
as far as I'm concerned like I don't
ever use them I don't think but they
just don't map to the actual way that
mutexes work at all in my opinion so I
don't really ever use them all those
kinds of scope things I think make more
sense even in the case where they're not
great like begin block end block pairs I
do use scope so for you see me you do
like time functions so I do sometimes
have those and temporary allocations I
sometimes do but mutex is just aren't
that kind of a thing that's just not the
way mutexes work typically you want a
mutex a little tiny thing and then use
the actual variables that you used in
there right and so begin end is the
right thing for mutexes especially
because it's not a mystery if you forgot
to unlock the mutex your code will just
hang immediately right so it's very
unlikely that if you ever ran the code
at all you would know the bug
immediately it's not like memory where
you might be worried about the fact that
you could leak it like you'd forget so
you want to make sure you do it when it
goes out of scope or something it's not
like that it's not a bug that you can
really have particularly easily so mutex
guard not so good
you
all right I think that's all the queue
so I'm gonna wrap it up oh don't no
don't do that all right
see I say
oh yeah so and why doesn't say is we
still obviously have to debug that so
we're gonna have to check it out
tomorrow
it's kind of weird I'm pretty surprised
at the way I guess I don't have a good
guess it looks like we ran out of
something right like for example if we
mismatched our include are our mutexes
there which I guess we didn't because we
only have two places where they happen
but maybe we ran out of stuff processing
somewhere or orphan something but you
can kind of see right like we only have
a few places where we do begin ticket
mutex we do begin then there and we do a
begin then here this is the definition
of them and here's the other one so
basically we don't have any mismatched
pairs so we're probably not hanging up
that way but we've got something that we
run out of right something stops and the
way you could tell it is all those
textures are loaded right but now we're
not getting any new textures like see if
I move the turn the guy around and it
tries to demand pages in they never load
so I think we got a pretty good idea of
what is happening here we just got to
figure out why we're draining out like
that and and so you know if it's not the
mutex maybe it's you know something with
the free list or something where we I
don't know we're not pulling from the
right place or we orphan saying so
hopefully we'll be able to check it out
tomorrow hopefully we'll be able to bug
that and then we can cross that guy off
the list too because then we're down to
just clean compatibility and I think we
can get that done before I gotta go
on vacation in quotes alright so anyway
that's about it for another episode of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
cooking with us always if you would like
to follow along series at home you can
always pre-order the game on handmade
hero org it comes the source code so you
can play around with it yourself we also
have forums site you can go to if you
want to ask questions a patreon page for
our support the video series a schedule
about if you want to know where we're
going to be live you can subscribe that
and it'll tweet at you and we've got a
guide if you would like to follow mmm
along with past episodes like you did
tonight that's about it I will see you
guys tomorrow for the last stream of the
week 8 p.m. Pacific Daylight Time until
then have fun programming everyone and
I'll see you guys on the Internet
take it easy