hello everyone
and welcome to handmade hero show recode
a complete game
live on stream before we get started
today i just want to take a minute to
thank our sponsor
uh the rust recovery foundation this is
a great organization
if you haven't heard of it they're a
they're just a collection of really
kind-hearted programmers
who work with with people out there who
are really into rust and have found out
in one way or another that there are
programmers out there in the world
not using rust and that can be really
hard psychologically on people
there are some people who never come
back from it and so this organization is
just a great
um it's just a great way to
help support those programmers and try
to
let them get readjusted and
re-integrated
into programming again after what can be
i mean it can be a
really big uh shock to the system and so
uh yeah check that out if you get a
chance uh the rest recovery foundation
they do great work and um they help
uh literally dozens of rust programmers
every day uh
sort of over overcome that really that
world crushing
realization that not everyone in the
world loves rust
um as much as they do so it can be very
hard and i just
you know if you if you have some empathy
for that kind of position
i highly recommend checking it out do
give generously
let's go ahead and get started today um
we
have i think uh more or less
finished what we wanted to do on the
collision detector
essentially what we wanted here was we
just wanted to to make something
adjust my monitor um that i would have
some some confidence that wouldn't crap
out on us i didn't want like a very
brittle uh collision detector i wanted
something that would be
fairly stable and so what i did is i
made something
that does sort of a voxelized sort of
collision system
uh with some fairly straightforward
rules about how you can move through the
space
and i think it's pretty good you know we
didn't try to do any formal proofs on it
or anything
not that anyone ever does that besides
me for their collision systems but
you know we could go that route if we
wanted to really get into it
but we don't really not for this game
but you know you can see here i've got
the glove on full collision so
we're just checking to see you know it
can't really go through things
if it does get stuck in things uh
because like that where i
push an a object that has to be moved
uh like the gameplay is moving an object
into an object that cannot itself be
moved
uh you can see it generally finds places
to put things if it does embed something
like here where it can't find a place to
put something and it has to embed it
uh like it does there um it is capable
of moving things out of embedding
so i think we're in pretty good shape as
far as collision is concerned
i don't have a lot of concerns about the
system right now
so what i'd like to do today is move
more into just the cleanup phase
for the collision detector uh the things
that i wanted to do
was add a spatial partition so you know
i'd like to have a thing
where we uh i i'd like to do something
where we can
not test all the entities every time
right we've got a kind of ridiculous
system right now that actually checks
all of the entities uh in the entire
world uh
and excuse me uh and that's really
not in the entire world in the entire
active set so the entire like
everything that's paged in here right uh
all of these entities are getting
checked for collisions
every time uh which is completely
ridiculous
if that makes sense um and so
we we more or less know that
we have to have a space partition at
some point it's already
much slower than it should be it just so
happens that computers are so
darn fast these days that the game still
appears to play in real time
um but that's only because computers are
so incredibly fast and we just haven't
dumped
enough entities in like if we doubled
the number of entities i think we could
get it to start slowing down
certainly um if you look i don't
remember what the profiler is here
if you look you can see like this is
starting to creep up
uh in time here and remember this
compute light propagation is
multi-threaded
so actually this percentage time uh
is is how many cycles it's taking it's
not really representative
however of just how expensive
um this is because this is only running
on one cpu
so it's taking that many uh i'm sorry
one core it's taking that many cycles um
without even being multi-threaded right
so it's an issue right uh it's an issue
and so as you dump more in there that n
squared will just keep rising it'll get
worse and worse so that's why you really
want a space partition because we don't
really want to see this uh
on our it should be mostly free like
collision detection here is not that
complicated if you just don't test too
many entities
so we we really just kind of want to
simplify that down
right we want to make sure that we don't
have that
creeping up there
all right so those are two things we
want to do to get us into good shape
here uh so what i'll probably
do before i do the spatial partition
is start by adding a spherical collision
type
uh so so that we can have spheres and
boxes the reason i want that
is just to make it a bit smoother so
like for example
uh this guy here right um
uh you can see like this this dude here
is
uh i feel like that
i i wonder if that should happen like
i don't know how these guys like work
exactly but i feel like they shouldn't
embed in the ground like that but maybe
they should i don't really know
um
we should take a look at that because i
don't feel like they should do that
unless i don't really remember how we
move them
to be completely honest with you so i
don't actually know if that's true
but we should probably look at that it
doesn't get stuck because it allows him
to move
but it's not really supposed to be doing
that right
so that's something we should probably
take a look at but what i was going to
say is any of these people who move
around
like this dude or the glove they should
be spheres
because we don't actually want them
getting stuck on corners
right we don't want them to have uh
like trying like that
right
i need a thing to like turn off
uh above layers of collision there
above layers of floors we don't want
them to get stuck
uh i guess that wasn't a stock well that
right we want them to be able to roll
off of corners and they're not going to
right now the thing that i was saying is
like this guy
isn't stuck there per se um
but it does seem like he's allowed to
interpenetrate maybe more than he should
be able to
this is a better okay that's a better
example so uh
to see how he's on that so i'd like
things to have a rounded appearance
a rounded collision volume so that they
roll off of things more cleanly and so
if you
have two flat faces and they hit each
other right
it's not going to be the the collision
normal
is not going to be such that it can move
cleanly around it
um it's just going to run in and stop
whereas if you have
a to me a sphere
it can always move sort of diagonally
around
and keep going which is kind of more
what we want right
so i'd like to have a sphere collision
volume and
uh allow both spheres and cubes and the
other thing is i just
i'm not confident that that i don't
understand what that embedding that
i don't understand what's actually going
on there um because i
i didn't think we allowed that it's a
little hard to tell
maybe it's not actually embedded but it
sort of looks like it is
right um it's slightly embedded
right um
and so i'm just i'm the main thing i'm
just concerned about is
why did that happen right um do we have
a bug
that makes it so that you get slightly
embedded like that and i don't really
know
right so i'd like to take a look at that
as well
uh just so i can have some understanding
of what's going on
uh but i'd also like to add the uh the
spheres in here
and we'll so we'll leave that guy as we
won't actually replace him with a sphere
i'm gonna replace the glove with the
sphere first and that's we'll do today
and then we'll take a look
uh at uh
and then we'll take a look at what's
going on with that
okay um so if i go to move entity
which is in here
then what you can see is essentially
this
routine where we look to see what
happens with a particular
collider um this routine
would need to understand the difference
so this routine we need to understand
the difference
between a sphere
and a rectangle right
so this
would need multiple routines it would
need
sphere versus sphere sphere versus
rectangle
and rectangle versus rectangle we
already have
one of them which is rectangle versus
rectangle
but we don't actually know
uh we don't actually have a way to set
one of these collision volumes
to be a sphere yet right so we need
a way of of putting that in there we
also
don't i mean one thing that's a little
annoying is we don't have a way of
rendering a sphere
uh our renderer just renders sprites
so it's a little bit difficult for us to
render
a sphere in the first place which is
unfortunate um
you know if this were a general purpose
renderer rendering a sphere is easy
uh in our case we just don't have you
know we've never built any rendering
capacity for things like spheres because
we don't really render
any 3d geometry other than just a cube
right um
so if we look at this it's going to be
something more
a little bit different so you know if
you take a look at how this goes
uh where we've got this replace the
spatial partition thing so this thing
where we're iterating over the entities
that's going to iterate over the
entities within a particular space
partition bucket or something like that
um and then what's gonna happen in here
when we do this
test is we're just gonna have three
different tests we can do
right so we're going to have
uh probably something that looks like
this
um
where we just check and we say
is this entity right um
something like that so like in here
where we do like
where we look to see what kind of
collision we're talking about we just
say like all right
um we are gonna have a um
a flag that tells us whether an entities
use a circle or rectangular collision
and what we'll then do is say all right
when we do a spheric collision
we loop over and we just need to do
uh a check either way
and then the same would be true for our
other branch here
and again this has to get replaced with
something better
at some point but that's fine so then in
here
what we need to do is we need to pick
two different things so if there's a
sphere collision flag we need to do the
test on
this one as well so in here we would do
uh oops
something like
that so we're going to say look we want
to know whether it's a sphere or not
right and the if we know that the task
entity is a sphere
uh then we'll just do a thing like look
if it's a sphere
and uh
if it's a sphere and a rectangle
intersects
sphere or
if it's not a sphere
and rectangles intersect right something
like this
makes sense um it's pretty
straightforward
so
[Music]
seems good and the same would be true in
the top one
it's just going to be just a little bit
different
but almost the exact same thing
so in here we would say look uh if this
thing
if the thing we're test against is a
sphere then its
spheres intersect otherwise
its rectangle intersects sphere
right um and in this case we have to
flip these
if the pardon 4 coder i don't know if
anyone's ever going to fix the
indentation in fork odor someone tell me
if they ever fix it so i can switch
to the new to a new version um it's been
broken
for like ever um
so yeah anyway you can see here uh
this is just reversed so you know we
have rectangle intersect sphere
uh in this case the mover is the
rectangle and the sphere
is the person who we're testing against
um and then in here the opposite's true
so if it's not a sphere
that means well we were the sphere right
so
move erect goes in the sphere slot
and off we go um that's really all we
need to do
uh to add the spherical collision but
uh we have the issue here
of
you know what i just thought of
something interesting i hadn't really
thought of before
hmm
oh boy
you know what we don't need to do this
i i kind of just realized that we don't
actually need to do this
so because we know
that we're always doing
we're always doing spheres or rectangles
right we
should actually be able to do this way
more efficiently
we should be able to do this without
actually doing any additional branches
right because what should happen
is we should be able to say
something like
if shapes collide like mover is sphere
and the move erect
and then test is fear and the test rect
right
and we should be able to compute the
answer
as to whether these two things collide i
think we can just
do it as one series of relatively
concise operations
and then we just use the booleans to
merge those together into the answer so
that we only ever actually do one branch
which is if they collided
right
right um
well it's not branchless uh someone
said that in the chat it's not
branchless because we still are doing a
branch here
we could make this branchless if we
wanted to
um but it's unclear that you want to
make this
branchless because this only happens
once in a great while it only happens
when two things collide
right um so the vast majority of the
time
if you're doing this you're probably not
going to collide right because most
things are not colliding
but if i had all those ifs in there for
the check it would have to do
branches it would have unpredicted
branches all the time
right because it would constantly be not
knowing whether the thing
is going to do this or that or this or
that or this or that right
so if shapes collide can be done
branchless
right and we let this
be the branch here that's just a better
structure for this loop
because that means that we don't branch
on things that are very
variable and we do branch on something
that actually matters
right so i'm not trying to be branchless
i'm just making a certain section have
no branches so that we don't have to
worry
right um
you know so we just want to
do something like a is sphere a wrecked
b sphere brecht
uh pretty straightforward
[Music]
if left's code is better isn't no code
at almost
best why are we even programming then
okay so let me just say one thing before
i go any further
it is my absolute firm 100
non-ironic non-sarcastic belief
that actually most people programming
today
if they just didn't program
we would have better software
because most programming that happens
today just makes things worse
as far as i can tell like it doesn't
actually make things better
so so actually
abc derek i i agree with your
what was probably a joke comment is
actually true
like the vast majority of programming
that happens today
the world would probably just be better
off if it didn't happen
you know so so yes
like another way to say it would be go
watch glenn glary glen gary glenn ross
and when al pacino says
um ch choose out
uh uh kevin spacey for making something
up
right uh and somebody i want to say
it's a is it jack lemmon who says if
you're gonna make something up
be sure it helps right um
that's that's i think where i'm at with
this
is like if you're going to type in code
make sure it's actually helping
you know what i'm saying like make sure
what you shipped was actually better
than what was there before it
and if it's not just delete it
i want to watch that movie again i i
tried to watch the other day it was it's
not available on anything though like
the
blue ray was like coming out um at some
point
i don't know if it's came out yet uh i
want to like watch a good version of
that movie
david mamet anyway
um it's it's a good play it's a it's a
good play
the movie is good too all right so
anyway
um in shapes collide uh we know we have
rectangles intersect
uh and we can do that with a wrecked and
b-rect right
and so in here like i said what i'm
doing is is very simple
um i'm just doing
uh a combination where the boolean
composite gives me the right result and
i'm just doing some extra math that i
don't need to do
but that way and i'm merging the results
together
right so what we would want to do is
something like this
if we were just writing the whole thing
out
but um
i don't actually i'm pretty sure
we don't actually need uh
to do most of this and this is the
reason that i rolled all these together
if you take a look at what happens with
a rectangle's intersect routine
wrong one
okay uh so if you take a look at what
happens with a rectangle's intersect
routine
it looks like this
right uh and maybe we'll do this
because that way it's exactly the same
as the other routine
[Music]
so this tells us whether the uh
the rects intersect
right i and the other thing
that we know
uh is we have this closest point in box
right so if you think about it
if you take a sphere
and you want to know if two spheres
in you know are intersecting
it's really simple to do because
if the two center points of the spheres
which we know if the two center points
of the spheres
are less than
the combined radius so radius of a
radius of b
if the two spheres get closer than that
some
then they're intersecting because
spheres are directionally independent
like
spheres are the same in all directions
and the only thing we have to say is
like well we're getting it input as a
rectangle
we're just going to not allow ellipses
right so we're just going to take the x
and treat that as the radius well half
the x is the radius
um and when people create these they
have to know
right so that's fine we could try to
support ellipsoids but
i mean it's a lot more uh work to
support an ellipsoid
uh yeah it's definitely a lot more work
to support an ellipsoid
we're gonna have to do like lagrange
multipliers and crap
i think
i'm i'm pretty sure there's no way to
support ellipsoidal collision without
like doing a lagrange multiplier like
freaking quadratic equation solve thing
we could do it like we could definitely
do it but it's going to be way harder so
because no one cares about that in this
game you would never do that
on purpose right um so
yeah i wouldn't bother but my point is
just
we know if two spheres intersect by just
looking at the difference of their
centers right
so we can do something like this like
center delta
right um and that's just going to be
like if we have a center a and a center
b
we could just say like okay
we know what those two values are and
then we subtract them
right this value here
uh we can take the length squared of
that and just see
so spheres if the spheres
intersect it would mean that the length
squared
of the center delta
uh that separation
is less than the
radius
and there's no point in doing a square
root here because
we can just compare the squares together
so we might as well right
so we can just say okay maybe
like max x or uh
get him a
right
um so these are pretty straightforward
uh this is just a
you know subtract and a multiply same
here this is uh
you know jimmy
really for collision if we want to
improve this and we might want to uh
what we'll want to do later if we
actually care about the speed of this
is we should probably store our
collision
as a center plus radius min max
for collision is is probably not the
best thing
uh because we want to be able to handle
rectangles and spheres
min max makes a ton of sense if all
you're doing is
just overlap testing like this because
you know
you can see that it's pretty
straightforward to do
but it doesn't make a lot of sense um if
you actually want spheres
so there's that anyway um
so if you take a look at this right if
you imagined
we have a sphere
then this
would give us the closest point on a
to the sphere of b if it was if a is a
box
this will give us the closest point on b
right
if b is a box to a again this is
one two
really just two uh times three so six
operations to find uh
this the closest point
on the box so producing the spheres
pretty straightforward producing the
uh closest points very straightforward
and so
like you know a wrecked uh
sphere a wrecked b sphere
and b rect a sphere
um are pretty if we assume that a is a
rectangle and b is a sphere it's
actually the exact same computation
here only with uh
oops only with a um
a different subtract on the inside right
so this is just like center b minus
closest a
so you can see that the actual amount of
work and we have like
i haven't even looked at what this
actually computes
it's entirely possible that now we could
fold these down into a lot more ops i'll
put a to do up here
but you can kind of see where i was
going with this
if you
can someone please tell me if the new
four coder fixes the indentation
i really really want that um
it's super annoying uh
anyway so we can probably fold down some
of these operations
uh quite simply as well
and we just have to analyze these we
don't have to do that right now because
we really don't care
but you can see why i wanted to build
these into one routine
there's so little computation here that
i feel like i can
not only share computations between
things
pretty easily because like especially if
we don't store the centers if we store
the centers you know concert but
these are things we're going to want for
all the different routines except for
box
so like folding all those down to a
simple set of things with no branches
i feel like we can get this down to a
very tight routine that just tells us
whether these collide
no matter what they are and then for our
results
we just and a bunch of stuff together
right
um so for the result it's just a bunch
of binary crap
so if like a is sphere
uh and b is sphere
uh and spheres that's a
that's a collide um and then all we do
is just have a bunch of these
right um i'm just gonna let four coder
indent this wrong
at this point uh there's nothing i can
do about it
it just it just wants to indent
everything wrong
um so a sphere b is fear in spheres if a
is sphere
uh and b is not a sphere
then we just look at uh aerect sphere
i'm sorry b rect a sphere
uh a is not a sphere
and b is a sphere
then we do a rect b sphere and finally
uh we just do if neither of these things
is a sphere
then we're done right so we just we just
smoosh
right we're just smoosh
um
and that's it um so
there you go
i think that's the entire routine um so
that allows us to do
shape collisions uh either way
and again the only reason to do this
is just to allow uh people to move
diagonally around corners
a box can't move diagonally around
corners right the the motion of a box
around a corner is strictly like a right
angle
so you know if it's going around a
corner it has to first go clear the
corner
laterally and then go past the corner
you know right
and so the the reason for spheres is
just because it allows you to say like
look if you hit
anywhere on the left half side if the
corners on the right side
then the sphere can glide around by
moving in a curve diagonally around
and that's what we want uh it to feel
more like we don't want you to have to
clear the entire corner and just kind of
roll
off the corner so the idea behind this
is just to provide a different
ways of having
the collision feel this is strictly for
feel
right that's what it is uh so that it
the game like makes itself
uh i guess now i'm done with this i can
actually line it properly and fork odor
won't hopefully
uh realign it for me so i think that's
it
um you know barring bugs and
borrowing bugs in here i think that does
everything we need so
from then on all we do is we just say
look shapes collide and here's our
sphere information
i don't actually think we need uh
anything else there's any flags
uh here we just need to add the one for
the sphere
and in theory this won't do anything
hopefully
it should just do its regular it's
regular thing
um what is the problem test entity
is not known oh there you go
um so in theory this should do nothing
because nobody should have spherical
collision
set uh so when we run it
um we should just have i mean it should
just do exactly what it did before
right everyone should collide as a
rectangle
and off we go if i change it to sphere
so when we do the glove which i don't
actually remember
um
where that is
where do we create the glove
is it in here
it's in world mode so it was this one i
guess yeah all right
right because you at cause you don't
create them at gen time you create them
when a player enters
the game because you can have multiple
players and stuff yeah
that makes sense not not dumb all right
so
glove right we create this thing um
you know the flags
um
where did it go
so the flags here uh we just want to ore
this in
so that it will you know know that it's
supposed to be a sphere
uh and the problem we're going to have
now like obviously we want to debug this
but also we don't know uh we can't see
it
is a problem right so we have no idea
whether that got set correctly we have
no way of seeing it it certainly doesn't
seem
like it did anything there so there's
that
but we don't even know if it's uh
we don't even know if it's correctly set
because we don't have any way to draw it
right like i said we don't draw
actual spheres there or anything like
that um and so when we look at this
thing we're just like
i don't know like maybe it's a sphere
maybe it's not
so at the very least uh that i'll do the
simplest thing i can
which is i will just draw a different
color for a spherical colliders
just so we know like roughly um
you know like blue will be for the
regular rectangle colliders and red will
be spheres or something
right so nothing particularly fancy um
but just in here right where we're
picking the color
uh i'll i'll do like a if entity flags
and when they flag sphere
we'll just change to being a different
color
and so you know um
that way i can just verify that you know
it is what i think it is
and then we can move on to debugging
from there so there you go
so at least now we can see like okay
that's supposed to be a sphere
we know roughly what like i can't draw
the sphere because you don't have a
sphere drawing and i don't really want
to add it
because it's never going to appear in
the game it would just be for debug
we know the sphere is the thing that
fits inside this
cube right the radius is is as long as
that
so you know we know what it's supposed
to do what it's supposed to look like
and so we should be able to just debug
it uh from there
i will say um it's hard to say exactly
what's going on there i mean that
the problem with that is yeah like like
it's gonna be hard to kind of know like
is that correct or isn't it right um
like like this is where we're probably
gonna need like
forget spheres we're gonna need like
pretty good diagramming to like figure
out the collision points and stuff like
that so you know
we'll see but point being at least we
know that that
is correct in terms of getting
the gloves set to a spherical collision
volume
uh so let's take a look at these
routines now and decide we want to do
testing lines uh going forwards so
uh with our collides at p here uh this
is all pretty straightforward and you
can see like mover is fair mover wreck
test is for a test rect
uh we're just passing in basically the
flag and
uh so we're just we're just looking at
the testosphere and mover a sphere
uh we're just looking at those two and
passing them
into shapes collide
and like i said shapes collide is pretty
straightforward so you can see that we
ore together collision stuff
and basically the first part of the
collision is just
these are the mask values so like if a
is sphere b is fear we're going to run
the sphere collection routine
we're going to run the sphere collision
detector
a not b then we do b rect a sphere
right not
a b we do a rect b sphere and if they're
neither of them spheres then we use the
rectangle
right now we assume the rectangle
part is correct because that's what we
were using uh we should probably look at
this more carefully to make sure that it
actually is correct but you know
that one is not really what we would
implicate right now
we assume that this is not implicated
because we know that we're never going
to use it
right because not both of these are not
going to be true so we're really talking
about these two cases
a sphere not b sphere uh not a sphere b
sphere
those are the two cases we don't know
which one we're looking at at the moment
um well i guess we kind of do because we
always pass the mover first
so in this case we know specifically uh
that we're going to be doing a sphere
not b sphere
so so this is the case that we'd
actually be looking at in this one right
here
um so b erect a sphere is what we would
be interested in
and you can kind of see here that we
look all right so what's the square
of the radius of a um
and you know i wouldn't have
a lot of concern that that would be
wrong it's a very simple computation
right it's just saying what's the x
dimension
uh and we're going to take half of that
because because the diameter would be
the dimension the diameter
are the same um so the radius is going
to be half that right so that seems
pretty straightforward
this here is just looking at how far you
have to go to reach the closest point so
we're saying the center of a
which is the um the center of the sphere
uh and the closest point on the
rectangle like how far apart are they
right um and again this
you know fairly straightforward so the
as a collision check that seems pretty
clean to me because all we're all are
asking
is if we took the closest point
that we could find uh
to the sphere's center
if that is more than the radius away
then we're obviously not colliding
because the sphere is only the radius
long so it would never reach the closest
point
if it's less than the closest point well
then it's obviously intersecting
right so it's a pretty simple algorithm
i chose there
so looking at this we don't use closest
a we do use closest b uh and closest b
says all right whatever the minimum
is uh well i guess we start starting the
inside
whatever the maximum is of the
minimum of the box so the min corner of
the box
and the center of the sphere right so
whichever one is less
sorry whichever one is greater uh and
the reason that we do that
is we basically basically say all right
the minimum corner of the box
and the center of the sphere we want to
take whichever one is higher because
we're basically trying to say like look
if the sphere
was um on the min side so if it was less
if it was
uh to the negative of
the box then we want to just pick the
minimum
corner right and we want to do that for
all of the dimensions independently
which this will do
and that produces a particular point
right um
and then we just take the minimum for of
the maximum
and that point which will do the same
thing for the other side
and that will produce the closest point
right
[Music]
so
excuse me um so i think that's all good
[Music]
um
and that all looks pretty solid so
really what i would
like to do here i mean
what i'd like to do here is do some
diagramming and again it's the hardest
thing in handmade hero because we really
haven't built out anything for it
um but what i'd like to be able to do
ideally is be able to move a little
circle around
a little sphere around and validate that
as i touch it to the
um as i touch it
to the box that they collide and as i
move it apart that they don't right i'd
like to be able to
to actually interactively do that um
that's what i would normally do um
maybe i just have to build that i don't
know it just it takes a while right
um but that's what i would like to see
here because i want to know
um i want to be able to like test
visually
because looking at it numerically
it's very hard to know if it's working
correctly um
um
i mean i suppose i could do like some
testing of this routine
non-visually you know i mean i could
write something that
calls it kind of in a for loop with the
sphere getting closer
and then while it's moving through it
would test it you know
um
it's just not as good you know visual
tests for collision
things are always better than than like
a unit test or something because
especially if they find a bug it's very
hard for you to like
intuit what the bug is if you don't have
a way to see it
you know um so that's the thing
uh
um so yeah you know that that's the
thing and it would be nice right
uh it would be nice if we could could do
it
um
so i guess what i'd say is i mean i have
a little bit of visualization already so
maybe i can
let me just see what i can do with what
we've got
uh and see if i can improve it to the
point where this
um would
work better i don't know
um
yeah so the other thing that's important
to look at here
is like this can be improved
really dramatically as well
the unembed direction we now have a lot
more information about it
so for example if two spheres are
colliding then the unembed direction is
just the difference
of their centers right which we we
already know
um so like
and the same would be true here so these
these
values for for rectangle stuff
we still aren't um
actually computing that separation
we could change this
uh to be doing it based off of centers
and then i do think we could compute it
much more straightforward
uh what that separation
[Music]
direction should actually be um
but for everything else so for for the
rest of these
we do know what it is right um
and it's slightly better than this so in
this case
this is true this is correct for spheres
because it's going to be the same
as this right it's the same value um
but for non-spheres this is an
improvement
because it looks for what the closest
point is
on the box and then uses the center
point of the sphere that's going to be
the
direction that you could move the sphere
out most quickly
so that's the that's the easiest way
to move out of there
and so this uh
this could be improved by just having it
be that
right um so that's another place where
that could be
done better um
uh and so you know we should probably do
that too
at some point
so yeah um something to think about
anyway um so yeah so looking at this
when we draw the collides at p uh
stuff you can kind of see like
when we
like when we look at this stuff you can
there's so many things we'd really like
to draw more
i i'm just really torn about what to do
here because it's
you know it's always a an issue on
handmade hero because it's like
i try to do stuff sort of like what you
do
if you were actually programming for
real
uh but the reality is we can't actually
really do that
because it would just take too long
because engine work takes a long time
and normally you have eight hours a day
to do it and you definitely don't have
eight hours a day to do it on the stream
um you know the amount of hours we've
spent on handmade heroes so far is like
so tiny compared to the amount of hours
you spend on making a game engine
you know that like we we haven't even
gotten it's been like i don't know five
years of handmade hero
but it's only added up to less than a
year's worth of
of actual work if you were to lay it out
on an actual work calendar so the
problem is i always have this problem of
like well you know the obviously the
right thing to do here is to make a
little
app so we can look at this so we can
just visualize it
properly and watch really carefully each
individual step because there's almost
certainly bugs in here
and we just don't know what they are and
there's no real way to
analyze it other than visually because
the only definition for the correct
answer
for motion like this is that it visually
does what we think it should
right um there's no like rigorous
mathematical definition
that we can apply to this motion stuff
right it's just like
it should generally allow things to move
in a way that makes sense right so
um
so i guess what i'm going to do because
i don't know
what else i should do here um is i guess
i'm just going to try to instrument this
i i really don't know what else to do
this
i think that's probably the most
straightforward thing i can do
uh is is actually try to instrument it
and uh
yeah like i really just don't know what
else
so the way that i'm gonna instrument it
is
is you know just
pretty straightforward like i'm just
gonna go like all right
um let's make a
a part here that's like if you know
collision instrument collision
or whatever so there's just going to be
like a giant chunk of code
comes in here and we just say okay
so if a is fear and b is fair uh
well and and more specifically i guess i
could just say
something like this right um
and i can draw the box in the sphere i
can draw the actual separation between
them
and look um again i kind of feel like we
should change this
rectangle definition the way that we're
doing this
uh because if you look at how it works
it wouldn't be
hard to just look at because the way
that we're doing the rest of these
is basically just looking at the
separation right we're just going like
look
how far away are these two things if
they're further away
than their size right
then they're not intersecting
right i mean it's not it's not rocket
science
this one is not this one is like a
direct overlap test
um but if you you know imagine
doing it differently
uh you could you could say something
like um
you know uh the center delta
x uh if if that
is um
um
if if that's if that's less than
then the dim like you know
so something like this so you basically
like look there's the radius
um everyone who was using the radius
before now uses like
just a part of the radius because for
spheres we're not going to consider
we're not ellipsoids but in this case
then we just say
look uh
and in fact we could do this
you know and so in that case we would
just say
okay we've got the total radius and then
we've got radius a and b
uh and so i think uh
it's this right
like if the separation of these things
in any particular axis
is less than the combined length in that
axis
then i'm sorry the command radius and
that axis
then you collide right
um and so if you look at that
it then looks the same as like these
right we've done them all now
in terms of some kind of a separation
uh between the two
and they just start smushing like closer
together
right you know what i'm saying
uh and i think we can do that
right i think we can do this and we just
get rid of this
and i think that would work right
let me just prove to myself that it sort
of does
but it's like if we're going to start
testing this routine i want to actually
[Music]
want to actually test it right so
i like moving this glove around crazy
like that
it's like the uh the um spring gets
because it's just a crappy spring thing
it doesn't have any intelligence in it
it gets super wound up and then it can
go super fast because we don't have any
uh caps on it right looks like that's
broken so no what did i do wrong here
oh duh just the wrong
sorry about that it has to be
touching and all it has to be
overlapping in all three i don't know
why
um yeah sorry sorry about that my bad
uh so yeah anyway point being um i'm
going to smush these down into a more
compact routine
and then i'm going to try to visualize
it as best i can
uh and we'll just go with that for now
because yeah making like an entire
like test thing which is what i would
like to do is probably not super
feasible
uh looks like that's still broken
somehow i feel like that's correct
though right like
the rectangles intersect if the center
delta is less than the radius
in each direction um
oh nope still still screwing up
these are signed
right um so we can do it that way
and you know that's fine um
but i think i probably wouldn't i think
what i'd probably do
is this
right um again because i'm just trying
to keep this
all looking roughly the same
because i want to smush it down
right i want to keep smoosh i want to
keep smooshing
as it were so rather than absolute value
i'm just going to square them which is
the same as absolute value for our
purposes
because it will ensure that they're
always positive and we're only doing
a comparison so if we square both sides
the comparison will still
hold um
right uh and it it will
get rid of the negatives
salty hello
oh who's the puss who's the ultimate
programming puss
do you want to enter some code do you
want to put some code in
yeah you do okay
okay
do you want to talk to the chat do you
want to read the chat
chad always likes it when you show up
well some of the chat does anyway the
cat people
hmm
big tummy kiss all right um
i don't know what the puss is up to at
the moment um
she may just be hanging out or she may
be mousing around i don't know
so we'll see what do you want to do puss
what are you up to do you wanna sit do
you wanna sit in my lap
do you wanna are you mousing around or
are you just hanging out i don't know
what you're doing
what are you doing what are you doing
hmm
what do you think you got
you got any opinions on it
okay all right
um
well while the puss is pussing around um
i'm gonna go
uh hop over here and just play with this
a little and see
if that fixed the uh the stupid thing i
did with the um
rectangles yeah looks like it's fine now
uh although it may not be colliding
properly let's double check
no it does looks good yep
um so now we're really close come on
come on
come on okay okay
that's a good puss um
so now we're really close uh in terms of
how these things are getting computed
right um
you can see that these are like getting
to be very sort of
similar sorts of computations which is
what i wanted
and i feel like there might be a way to
just kind of simplify this down more
as we go
we don't have to do it right now but i
wanted him to all look like that because
you can see that there's like a pattern
emerging right
where there's like you square both sides
of the thing and you do a less than
comparison
so that's always the same and the only
difference
right is whether you sum
the squares or whether you don't
right um it's mostly what's going on uh
and the the other side is basically
always the same
the only difference is whether you smush
x out to all of them or leave it the
same
so i don't know to what is okay the pus
is scrolling the mouse now
um what are you doing puss
are you trying to adjust the view what
are you doing
what are you doing
what are you doing what are you doing
huh what are you up to
what are you up to
what are you doing what are you doing
this is how i push program they program
facing away from the monitor
apparently how do you even know what the
code says if you're not facing the
monitor
how do you even know you don't do you
you're just winging it you're just
winging it
you're just winging it
all right um
so i don't think we need to go any
further with that uh
like i'm fine with leaving this uh long
form for now
but like i said i just kind of wanted to
get that into
a you know roughly roughly
identical uh comparisons
so that we could sort of see what's
going on um
so that it would you know uh
so it would be easy for us to see later
on like how this is going to smush down
further because
we can eliminate a lot of redundant
terms eventually compute
just a few things once the compiler
already hopefully will be able to do a
bunch of that for us because a lot of
these are the same
computation right but we can probably
help it out by
simplifying things down past where they
are whereas the
the other one that was in there for
rectangles looks nothing like any of
these
the other thing you can see is this uh
gets us ready like
we can just start storing this like all
of these computations should probably go
away
because we can just make center
um center radius
be the thing that we actually pass in
right so so
we can just make those be what we store
for collision volumes
because we don't really need rectangle
we min and max
isn't uh as as useful anymore now that
may not be entirely true because we have
to look and see how this
will go it may be that min and max
actually do still need to be there in
which case it doesn't matter as much
but we'll see okay so puss so we have an
answer
puss has sat on the mouse pad so
as long as we don't really want to use
the mouse particularly much we should be
fine
but that's what the puss has hath
decided we need we need a good
cat like right here
we need i need to buy a
like a cat um
friendly sort of tower you know like one
of those things
that would go like right here so that
the puss can
stay
aware of the entire situation
and oversee the programming um
the entire thing if she wants to and i
can still type
right um so anyway
okay uh so i don't really know
about that part because i haven't ever
tried a routine like this before
i probably uh
[Music]
the only time i program 3d much anymore
at all is on handmade hero i used to
program 3d all the time
and so i would have thought about things
like this a lot more nowadays i hardly
ever think about 3d
um i just don't do 3d programming much
anymore even that's all i did for like
many years
um so i haven't ever looked and said
okay now that we care about
reducing branches which we didn't use to
in the old days
um now that we care about reducing
branches can you make a single routine
that does
rectangle versus rectangle rectangle
versus fear and services fear
all in one with a very limited number of
ops my
uh suspicion is yes we can do it uh and
it's looking pretty good already
it's just not our priority um
at all so anyway uh
what i want to do is is find some ways
to draw this stuff
a little bit better here and so what i
might do is say well let's draw
um a couple things
if we can so let's just pretend that we
have
some kind of a diagramming system uh
and i'll just say like all right if a is
a sphere
then i'll do a like uh you know
uh we'll just put some diagramming stuff
in here right so if a is a sphere we're
gonna draw a sphere
uh and it'll be center a uh
radius a uh and we'll we'll do the same
thing
you know you know for this and
what we would do here probably is say
like
uh you know
some kind of garbage like this right
um
you know what i'm saying uh we you know
probably you could probably do this
these days i think
um couldn't couldn't do that
uh in the old days but nowadays most
compilers have this it was like only gcc
had that for a long time but but
you know almost everyone has it now you
know what i'm saying
um so if we assume we do something like
this where you just imagine this is
snuffalopic-oriented programming here
i'm just imagining that i magically had
a diagram system
what would i do right like what would
that diagram system
um have in it
like how would i use it right uh and it
would be something like this
where i would just say okay uh
here's me drawing
uh the various pieces if i have a sphere
um then what i want to do
now is say well even if i don't so now
what i want to do is
look at the uh separation between these
and i don't know like maybe i want to do
like maybe i want to do the testing here
and actually draw a different thing in
each case
uh i mean i could right
maybe i want to do this
so if we have two spheres we would draw
both spheres
um and
you know something like that we would
then do like diagram
uh like
the separation between them which would
be like
that uh
i don't know so so i i might
actually say
[Music]
something like this
and the line
that connects the two uh
i would want to do like
just so we can see i don't know
that we have anything else we're
computing here
because that that's basically it right
[Music]
um
so there's really not much to draw here
right
but but there you go
and so we need to do is uh
some kind of like a condition uh like
this
so we would just say look there's a
result that comes out here
um and we would say like uh
yeah the result is that they collided or
whatever right so it's a true
this is a true or a false so we want to
be able to see that
you know what i mean um so something
like that
and uh you know maybe maybe we would say
like collides and then the result would
say like yes or no
right so something like that so if i
imagine i had the system
it would look something like this and
then you know for the other ones here
i guess i would say uh
we've got the not case so
you know for those two
uh and those would just draw boxes
instead
um
i think we want this probably in all
cases
right
and so then the interesting cases are
here
so in this case where we've got two
different ones uh then we have to kind
of do
like okay
we've got a is a sphere and b is a box
or the other way around
right um
and then in here we would do
we need this stuff
so in this particular case we have a
diagram point we want to draw the
closest point on
a sorry the closest point for
a um
the closest point on a to b so
in this particular case if a is the
sphere
then it's the closest point on b that we
would draw
right um and so i guess i
i lied we don't actually want this this
is only in the sphere case
and then in these cases it's the other
way around so we would have the closest
point on b
to drawn to a right
so that's the actual separating we
probably don't need that
um and then the opposite would be true
in this one so we draw the closest point
on a
out to the sphere center which is b so
we can see
like where that would would go right
um
[Music]
so i think that's it um
i don't know that there's anything else
that we would need there right
so we'd basically just have a diagram
here
that does like a begin and an end and
it you know that would be it and we
would have
uh maybe diagram and i don't know
we probably want to have multiple ways
of doing results there
but anyway we'd have some way to like
dump these diagrams
uh out and off we would go
right so when we
are calling these we would call it uh
you know it would be called lots of
times so it gets called from in here at
this
uh collides at p thing uh for each
entity
and um
i i don't know
i i would guess we would probably want
something
like this in there so so
if you look at what happens in here
right we've got move entity
and there's like a bunch of different
phases that kind of happen here
right um and so in here this is like the
voxel
uh phase so when we're drawing those
diagrams for collides at p
uh that's going to be all of those
calls in there are going to be for
uh doing the voxel right
um and
you know we can
i don't i don't know how far we want to
go with this but we can do it
um you know
more specific than this but basically
we'd have the phase
would tell you like oh we're doing
collision voxel or we're doing
refinement
right um and that way when we step
through it with the diagramming
we would know which one we had and
that'd be it now then we would have a
handmade
you know diagram dot
this must be something that ryan put in
there because i don't yeah i bet that
was it
uh because i'm like i never do that okay
um
i don't care about that uh anyway so uh
we'd have a
handmade diagram here
um which would accept these commands
so you'd have you know
just whatever the heck i said we had we
have
so you put like names in there or crap
like that
uh you can draw spheres so they would
have like a center
and a radius
um and and we just assume that the name
is nothing
uh for now
and
then we got the box
and this result thing which
i guess i should probably make it
symmetric
um and that's it
right so if i go back to handmade.h
and uh you know
after we kind of get uh this crap in
there i'm assuming that you know it will
be sufficient
to put it like here in terms of include
order
and you know that's fine
and so then if we compile it i need to
actually have
handmade diagram.cpp here
even though nothing actually happens
uh yeah and so then i can make this
compile and leave it this way for next
time
to have these be implemented
right and
oh wait we do internal here i changed to
using
function instead of internal uh so that
way it's the same as javascript
i thought that was kind of handy because
i was like oh now
whatever parser you write to identify
functions
will work on my c code and my javascript
code how clever
right it's not that clever but
since i always put something before it i
was like oh why don't i put something
that actually
works the same as as some other language
and off you go
okay um these should have defaults
as well so if you don't care
you don't have to have those things
specified
all right and that's it for today i
guess next time we'll add some of that
and off we go
where is
shouldn't that have given an error
how did that
oh duh
maybe what i'll do here is
that
you know i don't know
i was like how did that compile it
compiled because
it was just zeroed out that's why so it
never actually got compiled
all right any questions
oh so 4coder 4.1.8
does fix indentation we have to
do that
we have to update
oh uh i can explain why i typed const so
one of the things i was doing for star
code galaxy
is i i
so i try as hard as i can to not
force people to turn off
a bunch of warnings on the compiler for
the beginner code
right and so i'm now used to
the stupid it
really aggravates me like deeply
but the default in c plus because the
people who design it are the worst
people in the world um
they default strings to constant
so if you want to accept a string
literal it has to be care
const star right
which is the dumbest dumbest
idea it is so stupid i cannot even begin
to describe
just how dumb it is
it is extraordinarily stupid
but that is how it is so
i reflexively now sometimes type c
constar
if i don't remember whether i'm in my
code base for the start code galaxy code
base because
that's the one place you are for it
forces you to use const you don't get a
choice
you would have to disable warnings to do
anything else
i mean unless you want to type this all
the time
right um
so yeah i mean what can i say c plus
horrible language designed by people
have no idea what they're doing i've
said it a million times i'll say it a
million more times
it's horrible that's just one example of
just how stupid it is
it's like guess what folks if i wanted
my string to be constant i'll tell you
you know i'm the programmer not you
if i wanted my string to be constant i
would tell you that it was constant
why is a new diagram system needed why
not just use the existing renderer um
so we will use the existing renderer uh
we're not gonna write a new renderer
the diagram uh stuff is just there
because this gets called like hundreds
of times a frame
so i can't like what you saw i mean it
already has a little bit of drawing in
there
right if i take a look at what's
going on you know um you can see it
drawing a bunch of stuff right uh
so you can see it drawing but
we don't really have any constructive
way to actually
look at that information it's just some
overlapping cubes and
me you know i can sort of tell like okay
so it sort of started there
and it like tried to get over there i
guess
but if i try to actually put like
imagine each one of these corners had
collision testing done on it
right so how the heck am i
ever going to actually look at this
information constructively
if i add anything more to it and so the
the diagramming stuff will not
use a different renderer all it's going
to do is i'm going to have a little
panel so i can step through
the diagram and show like one at a time
right
um so that's all i need i just need
something i can dump a bunch of like
line box directives into
and then it will only output some
restricted subset of that to the actual
renderer
so that i can actually look at them
that's all it's going to do we it
will call the existing renderer
off topic should the push array for
spatial grid leaves
in handmade lighting.cbp be aligned to
16 bytes
for move aps on 128 bit memory
operands i
don't remember but let me look
so you're talking about this one
right here um
so i guess my only question is
are you
so is the problem that you're seeing i
mean assuming you're seeing a problem is
it probably saying that the compiler is
generating a move aps
so my preferred solution to that
would actually just be to not have the
prof
compiler produce a move aps
because there's no reason to produce a
move aps
um but obviously if your compiler is
doing that
then then it is so
uh yeah you can certainly fix it by
passing the alignment
value here right so you know if you want
to you can do
you can do that um
this doesn't need to be cleared right
oh why do we clear it that way
here that's fine right
um so you should be able to do that and
there shouldn't be any problem with that
like it should just work
um but
you know ideally the compiler would not
think that was aligned because we never
told it it was a line so i'm not sure
why it thinks it's aligned in the first
place
um so
but i'm happy to i mean it's no skin off
our back
at all to align that so that's totally
fine
so like i'll just put a note like
so
um so like
that's totally fine um because
again aligning to 16 here doesn't cost
us anything it's basically
free it's not like aligning a structure
or something
where we're losing actual memory and
cash bandwidth by adding it
here this is a giant array like it's a
huge allocation
of crap all packed together so aligning
the base to 16 is fine
um my only question is is lighting
spatial grid leaf
uh i assume that's aligned already yeah
it is because four wide so i was like so
that's also has to be a line but i was
assuming it already was and it is
so that's totally fine
are we playing any cylinder or capsule
collisions uh no i don't think we need
those for anything
um those spheres should be sufficient
for our purposes
i don't think i ever said we would add
cylinders or capsules i was just
pointing out that those were things that
people used
but we don't have a use for those
should id dot value be checked to be not
null in
handmade asset um
i guess my question there is where
specifically um
where are you talking about um
which which part of it
load font
[Music]
okay
i'm assuming this is the appropriate
load font
what the heck is this oh asset builder
yeah we don't care about that
um
i mean i would say sure
i i don't know that we ever actually
use that so
uh you know um but in general we allow
that for other things
so you know there's no reason we can't
allow it here
uh you know most of our stuff does do
that
right um so we certainly could
right like
that'd be totally fine i don't think
anyone
does that so i don't know that it
actually matters whether you do that or
not
but if you just wanted to support it to
support it
uh
i mean there's no reason you can't
uh let's see where this is called
i mean the thing is like it's kind of
just redundant
because you look they're guarded the
font stuff is guarded already so i don't
know that you can actually ever
get that situation um
to occur
um
so how i don't know how you were ever
having that actually happen
but
uh but yeah anyway point being again
much like the alliance 16 when
it can't really hurt that function isn't
called super often or anything so
and the the check would almost always be
completely predictable anyway so it's
free
so there's no point in not checking it
right
first time catching your stream live
after finally catching up with every
handmade here i've said wow all right
that's dedication
really fun and enlightening fire along
so we're looking for sdg as well all
right awesome
for the upgrade to forecaster 1418 it
seems to break something with modal
bindings oh
um well that's unfortunate
i guess i can't upgrade then uh
all right i don't know what's going on
i just hope somebody fixes something
soon so somebody let me know
when we can re re-switch or whatever
could you explain the flood fill
algorithm as it was used in the
minesweeper game
i mean no because i actually don't
really know what you're talking about
what what kind of flood flock do you
just mean
talking about if you have a series of
cells
and you say fill all of the cells
connected to this cell
like that kind of thing
ah the fix for auto indentation is one
line you could apply it to your current
force okay maybe we can try and do that
then
any reason you only have the x y z
diagonal case in the voxel collision
system wouldn't you want
x y x z and y z diagonal motion as well
yeah i mean i guess i don't know
[Music]
um
you may be right
it's entirely possible uh
it's entirely possible that we should
just have a few more of these
right um
i mean it's also entirely possible that
we shouldn't do this one
i don't know right um
i'll put it to do in there
hard to say
does fan made here really not have a
straight line yeah i mean i
we've never done any sphere drawing at
all we did do
one time we did something different
which was we
were trying to distribute points
on a sphere and we drew the points so
like there was a thing that looked kind
of like a sphere but we've never drawn a
sphere in handmade hero we don't have
any spheres
this is the first time there's ever been
anything spherical
in handmade hero because everything's
either a flat plane or a box
right
uh so we've never had to draw a sphere
it's not hard to draw sphere
the reason that uh
it's kind of a pain in the butt to add
currently is that our renderer only
draws
cubes and planes it really only draws
planes
right so drawing a sphere is something
that's pretty easy if you have a general
purpose renderer but ours is literally
just a little sprite render that's all
it does
right um
so
um
couldn't just apply a circle to a camera
facing quad to fake a sphere uh we could
i mean
i'm not worried about it like i'll just
draw whatever i can just draw some like
a little cross or something like
we i don't care because we don't have to
actually draw a sphere so it's not a
problem
it's just yeah it's not something we
ever did
uh this algorithm and wiki flood fill
okay
i guess what do you want me to explain
uh i'm not entirely certain what you
want me to explain i mean this is a
pretty complete explanation right
how does it work
well i mean so
the the thing to think about here
is there's lots of different ways you
might implement flood filling but it's
pretty straightforward
to understand it right
which is just that every time you
have a particular star you can just
think of it as any connected graph so
anything
where you have like a cell here you can
imagine a connected graph is
each cell is connected to each of its
neighbors so every cell has four
connections to the top
bottom left and right you know what i
mean
any connected graph a flood fill is just
take the node that you are on
add each of the nodes that are
connected to that one to your thing to
consider
right fill the current one
and then move one down the stack right
that's it you just
keep going and that's a graph filling
algorithm and it fills graphs
no matter what the graph is doesn't
matter if pixels or otherwise right
that's it um so they're always they just
keep a stack
and they just say the first thing you
put on the stack is the starting point
you pop it off the stack consider it
find its neighbors add them to the stack
if they're connected
right and in this case connected means
empty
like you don't want to go into things
that are filled so the edge would just
be right and
that's it it's just it's just a simple
walk right
so i mean i can explain it in more
detail if there's something else that
you want to know but there's not much
else to it than that
you can see why like in here there's
talking about how like
a simple recursive algorithm doesn't
work very well the reason for that is
because there's so many pixels
if you're doing like a pixel fill that
you blow out the stack space
for your program if you are basically
using recursion
as your stack but
you know
so all right um but someday if if you
people really want to know more about
flood fill if you really like confused
about flood fill we can talk about it
more detail some other time
maybe during a pre-stream or whatever
but but there's really nothing to it
it's it's literally just
if you imagine you just have a graph any
graph
uh so if you want to flood fill pixels
or minesweeper your graph is just
each cell is a node and it's connected
to four other cells which are the the
nodes inside of it
and you just imagine the edge
connections
are just a
it's connected if the if the cell is
empty it's not connected
if it's if it's filled right
and then you just do a simple walk you
just say push all the neighbors on
and then go to the next one
what so cyberpunk 2077
what is the status of that game does
anyone know because it sort of came out
but it's not
doesn't really work you know
so so like did they have any kind of
like announcement
as to what happened with that game is it
gonna be like
updated or anything
because like like it it was it got taken
off of playstation
like it's gone so so it's not really out
in the sense that there's some stores
that still don't even allow it because
it was so
unfinished or whatever right so so i
don't know what to make of that
but
all right anyway thanks everyone for
joining me for this one handmade here
it's been pleasure coding with you as
always
if you would like to follow along with
the series at home you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero.org
and it comes with source code so you can
play around with it
i'll be here back here next week while
we'll put in some diagramming and we can
start doing some testing see if there's
bugs in the collision that we need to
fix
until then have fun programming everyone
and i'll see you on the internet
take it easy everybody
you