hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream we are well last weekend
we basically did what we wanted to do
which was pull out the renderer so that
it could be more easily used by other
products but also because it's kind of a
good excuse for us to clean up the
renderer now that we pretty much know
what it's doing and we really haven't
had a chance to do that in a long time
what I'd like to do this weekend is
continue down that path a little bit for
our own benefit not for other people's
benefit although it helps other people
to who might want to use the render
subsystem and just go through now our
API and make that cleaner and while
we're doing that I would also like to
address the problem of texture arrays
because right now we don't really have a
full profile of what's low and what's
not in our renderer because it hasn't
been a super high priority for us
so it's premature to say what we do and
don't need but the fact that we need to
do a texture change per quad because we
were coming from a software rendering
side of things that didn't care what
size bitmaps we were using really just
doesn't play well with a lot of hardware
we could make it run fast on this
particular Nvidia card that we have
because in-video allows using texture
pointers that can be set per primitive
very easily unfortunately that's not
always a realistic way to go if you want
to run on like Intel hardware I don't
know if they might still not have
support for that I'm not sure
so as much as it might be nice to stick
with arbitrarily sized bitmaps I'm not
sure how realistic that is for us in the
in the end and so we may want to do a
way of keeping all of the sprite based
rendering going down a particular path
that say only allows 512 by 512 bitmaps
and we pack everything into those that
size and then we can still have a path
that renders arbitrarily sized bitmap
for other reasons because obviously like
our debug windows stuff or the title
card or things like that those can be
because we can't afford a texture change
when there's only 10 textures on the
screen it's no big deal
right so it's really a throughput issue
it's saying look can we get the majority
like when we have a thousand two
thousand three thousand sprites on the
screen which you might want in handmade
hero if we just make all of those run
down a texture a path then we're in a
situation where we really won't have to
worry about that part of the performance
will be you have to worry about the
standard things like fill rate whatever
on the back end we won't have to worry
about just the act of getting those
quads down to the card efficiently
because you know right now that dispatch
overhead is going to be super annoying
right so anyway that's basically what we
need to do and so I'm just gonna go
ahead and get started on that I am going
to open up what we were working on and
just bring everyone back up to speed on
that oops let's go ahead and load
handmade dot proj and do a build so if
we go back to what we had running as of
last week if I go ahead and run this you
can kind of see that we made a simple
little spinning demo here that was hey
if you want and this is at running
completely outside of handmade here oh
so this is just a test to see does our
render engine do what we want and where
we left it was hey
you've got rotation in there we actually
don't currently have any calls you can
make that have that makes sprites always
face the screen right so you see how
when we rotate it around the sprites
kind of rotated with it and in handmade
here we don't rotate the screen so it's
unclear that we would ever care for this
ourselves but since the renderer
supports it just fine and it's literally
just the API call that isn't there I
thought we might want to address that
and similarly we've got a couple other
things we might want to address like
offsets within the system so these trees
these trees right now we're kind of
floaty right they're floating because
we're placing the base of the sprite but
really we would probably want to place a
alignment point inside the sprite and
again that's something that we can do
and it's just an API cleanup thing
because we actually have that in the
hand made hero side of things and so on
so just I'd like to look at some of
those things and just get a feel for
that I might also want to try slapping a
lot of sprites through here to see if we
can just use because now we have this
thing running as an external render test
it's pretty easy for us to profile this
we don't have the whole game to worry
about it's kind of this nice convenient
thing we can run tests on the renderer
so I can slam a ton of sprites in there
if I want to and then I can see to what
extent those sprites cause us problems
when do they become problems for speed
and is that does the problem come from
the dispatch overhead or does it come
from the filler 8 problem these are all
things we could get out of this test app
since we did the work to make it it
might be nice to have sort of that
nicety on top of it so let's just go
ahead and start down this path there's a
number of things that I've said there
all of which I think are worth doing so
let's take a look at them here's our
win32 render test this again is the test
code that we were working with right so
this is it here and what I would love
to do is again I'd like to work on the
API as well as the texture side of
things so the first thing that I'd like
to do is just now that we have it
working let's talk about what like what
the for lack of return let's talk about
what we actually want the API to look
like and what's actually bothering us in
here okay and so the first thing I'd
like to do is I'd like to break out this
so we've got this render test right like
we've got this win today to render test
right and that's an H and a CPP file one
thing I could do and in fact I could
actually break this out a little bit
more specifically what I could do for
example is we've got this code directory
here right we could make a directory
under code specifically for the renderer
and just put things in there that are
the renderer like we could do something
like that where we have that sort of
basis I don't really know if I want to
do that or not and the reason for that
is we kind of share some code right like
we want to have like some common things
that are shared in the render and so on
and you know you can see those things
explicitly in the win32 render test
itself right so this right here these
are the pieces that it uses and if I
open up render test dot H you can see
that handmade types is included as well
as the intrinsics the math and then the
actual renderer pieces right and so one
thing we could do is say alright let's
make a common and the common directory
has you know the it has the things in it
that everyone includes that's like sort
of everyone's who speaks handmade hero
uses these things so we can do that and
then we would move like handmade math
and handmade intrinsics in there so it's
basically like these are the things that
you need to use and then handmade render
the or the renderer directory would have
the two render things in it and that
would make it easier for people who want
to
that sort of stuff out to know what they
pull out and what they don't right I'm
just not sure how much value there is
there probably not a whole heck of a lot
so I might just stay away from that from
now and just we know what those things
are right we know what they are because
they're listed here so I think that's
probably sufficient right I mean I think
that's probably all we really need there
so I think what I'll do is I'm just
going to start down that I'm just gonna
start down the road of kind of like
cleaning up this API a little bit and
one thing I would like to do is inside
render test you can see that we've kind
of got some stuff here that's that's
it's defined that the renderer needs and
we kind of like stubbed it out right so
what I'd like to do is say well I
believe we had handmade shared is like
the thing that has all this stuff in it
right and Cindy also right
and so handmade shared is actually the
thing that has this stuff like all of
the pieces that we were using for it
are kind of all in there right and so
the problem is that pulls in a lot of
stuff that maybe we don't actually want
like we don't know that we necessarily
need the memory subsystem and maybe
that's a little bit onerous for people
right and that pulls in the platform
layer and that sort of thing so I do
wonder a bit like this for example like
I'm kind of curious maybe this should
not be there right like maybe that
should not be there handmade memory and
if handmade memory isn't there what
happens right I also let me go in here
and pull this out into the types section
because this is one of our core types
now so if we were to do that like what
would we actually need to put in there
and so you can see some of these things
here like we've got copy is one of the
things that we don't have because that
you know that is used in the in the
memory system right or that's defined in
the memory system I should say and so
I'm just kind of curious if I and and
I'm just you know again thinking out
loud here if I pull that out of the
shared system and I put that into a
standard location where it would
actually be set like let's say here what
do I actually need to worry about you
know and so moving along here you can
see like there's a couple issues that I
guess I would have but other than that
not too much right because on here I can
just include it and so we're talking
about a pretty limited set of things
[Music]
pretty limited set of things here let me
see here a temporary memory with so this
you know this can also do it here like
so um so in terms of keeping that out of
I guess can I put it underneath though I
actually need to put it underneath I
think yeah in terms of keeping that out
I think that's not such a big deal I'm
gonna make the the maximum and minimum
there I'm gonna try putting those in the
intrinsics for the moment like so see
where this is at
that should have like that should have
taken care of it we have to take a look
at this a little bit carefully I just
want to kind of disentangle these a
little bit that makes sense and it looks
like checksum of is again just something
that wants copy
I think copy can just be in shared
though that seems like something because
it's not necessarily about the memory
allocator it's hard to say like it's
hard to say what belongs where in this
in this sense right but let's just put
those in here and see what happens
there we go
so that's in hid yeah so in handmade
memory what we really want is shared to
come before memory there although I
don't know to what extent shared ever
uses anything memory related it doesn't
really look like it does so I think
basically if we just make this always
before then I think we're okay and again
the fact that you have to do any of this
is ridiculous this is just C nonsense
it's just dumb so anyway yeah so I want
that like this right yeah so we're good
yeah um sooo now I just want to think
about what we've got here for these
different for these different files and
whether I actually want them all and you
know how you know to what extent all
this stuff is actually necessary to be
broken up into multiple files or not so
we have like a handmade Cindy thing here
and the Cindy thing as you can see is
just the stuff we did for making it
easier to work with Cindy by using types
instead of having to actually use like
underscore mm underscore whatever every
time you want to actually do something
for those and so that's how we broke
that out so we've got math we've got
Cindy I don't think that actually needs
to be here necessarily cuz I don't think
we use it there so really I think we
only need it in in handmade right I
think that only really neat I think that
only really needs to be in handmade so
you know if we were to put that in here
I think that basically just takes care
of it right so I don't think The
Handmaid's I don't think that the stuff
needs to be included in the same way
like that it can just be pulled in as
necessary I guess well I meant um I
don't know if handmade random still
needs to be here could also test to see
if that's true it doesn't so actually
these might all go away so that's even
better cuz now we've got less of that
stuff in there the software renderer
does use some of the sim D stuff and
probably would like right because it's
Cindy based so I guess we would need
Cindy for the software render so where
that this right here
I guess that's the appropriate place for
it and then if we move it out we would
know right that they move together so
that seems pretty reasonable me I'm okay
with that and so now we're down to just
like the intrinsics are here because we
need those and then the math library is
here I don't actually know if the math
library again we can sort of continue to
back these out a little bit I don't know
to what extent the math libraries
actually used in this file
I assume the intrinsics are though so
like for example if I move this down to
the bottom I'm assuming it would tell us
what intrinsics were missing so well
only rotate left
I guess interesting so only the murmur
hash update is actually the only thing
that requires the transaction the shared
library that's interesting to say the
least but so math is actually not
required here either so yeah I mean I
guess what I would say is given that all
of that is true I'm gonna go ahead and
say let's get rid of those enforced
includes and let's just actually have
all of these in the places that they
need to be and then we can get rid of
them
as we wish right see here so test PNG
it's a edit and we can sort of maybe get
some of those to be less you know you
know we can start removing includes as
we go from different parts of the of the
system as as permitted right and again
that's just trying to make sure we're
not being overly like we're not like
pulling in too much stuff for no reason
so if I pop back over to wind through to
render test now which you can see here
so you've got the OpenGL render and the
basic renderer subsystem that we need
those all makes sense if I pop back over
here and look at what we're including
you can see what we're including here I
don't actually know if we want to get it
any lower than that because presumably
you want like the intrinsics there so I
think that's pretty much what we want
right and if I go through here and look
at what happens as I migrate these up I
should be able to start to see where
we're acquiring some of these other
calls so what I'd like to do is get to
the point where we're doing you know
something more like this and just to see
what's going on okay so here now we can
see like where some of these other
things like this memory is equal and
stuff right so now I just want to look
at where those are being done and why
and whether or not we should be
including like shared in here right
because it may be the case that what we
really should do is this and if we do
that instead of this right maybe that's
a more sane way to do things right and
I'm not sure
now string-length I'm not sure where we
are defining string-length currently
seems like it should be in there but I
don't know so it's actually in here cuz
this is because we needed it for the
debug stuff and I wonder if it's
possible that it could be
that could be put somewhere else right
like could we put that for example into
the type system here as a basic it would
be nice if it was more like in you know
somewhere else honestly but I it's so
basic it's like a lot of these other
things it's called from everywhere right
even the debug markup which has to be
included everywhere so for some reason
we're not getting gluant in here that's
probably just because I was over
aggressive when I pulled that out yeah
so that that's not gonna fly so I take
it back you can't quite get that absurd
but we can get close these can go then
if we were to do that and I think now
we're basically running things pretty
straightforward so this is what you need
and again the reason that I got rid of
those interior includes was just because
I want to make sure that people who look
at this now know this is all they
actually need right this is the entirety
of what they're actually using so that
way we don't have to over complicate
things when I asked the can we just use
the one from windows that H thing also
so I want to know if there's a bitmap
header in Windows that looks like this
so that we don't have to define it for
loading a bitmap seems like that would
be useful but I don't know I could just
leave it in there we'll see
alright let's go ahead and poke these
out here as well like so and so now
we're kind of left with just some
support functions here and then the
actual scene stuff so what I'd like to
do is I'd like to pull out the actual
scene stuff and the render loop here
like so and I'd like to go ahead and
make it clear like what those things are
so it's really easy to see what's going
on right so what I'm thinking here is
basically like you know I've got this I
got this function to place random
elements in the scene I've got this
thing to initialize a test scene the
thing that puts the scene on the render
loop that actually like renders the
scene right
and then I've got sort of these these
support functions down here have like
nothing to do with the API right they're
just like Windows stuff so what I was
thinking is we could just make it so
that like the one thing that it actually
needs to call which is load bitmap we
just place up here as a as a predefined
write and then what I can do is just say
hey everything below here is just
support functions
so this we can make a nice big like
thing here so everyone can see that this
stuff is just not important right and we
don't care about this this is just a
piece of test code so I think all of
this is fine and I don't see any
particular nonsense here oops let's just
make sure that looks that way
and then I think we're good to go
this I think we did want so I think
that's not an if zero anymore
[Music]
all right so win32 allocate memory we
also need let me go ahead and grab that
prototype out don't ask me why that's
not marked and let's do the same thing
here so this stuff is all like not
actually part of the thing
[Music]
so then we can just kind of distinguish
those things pretty easily right that
seems pretty good that gives us a pretty
nice-looking sample app right and so now
we can start to look at the sample up
and see what does and doesn't look good
so this for example just places some
random elements in the scene against it
that sample code let's make it easy for
people to read and say like adjacent or
region is clear and what I can do is say
like okay or or you know what we could
also count we could we could have it
return the count right count occupants
in 9 by 9 3 by 3 sorry and so what we
could do there is just say like okay
like you pass an X&amp;Y here and it will
return the occupant count
and so here we can just say look if
count occupants in three by three equals
zero and we place it now we can kind of
see what that does more clearly right so
both of these are now kind of
self-explanatory so you didn't have to
read that in there that way someone
coming to this code doesn't know it
works can really clearly see what we're
doing they have to understand these two
for loops first and that just gives them
a little a little bit of help there
right and we could expand on this a
little bit by just saying here's the
center x and y and that way these
actually collapse to just x and y which
makes again it a little easier for them
to read so they don't have to think too
much about it if that makes sense so now
they can sort of see what that looks
like and an off there you go so I yes
that's fairly nice and I guess I could
say in unoccupied I could say that right
I and off we go now one of the things
that we found that was a problem is when
we were doing these tests seeing dims
what we really want to do is see how
many we have so we kind of want to say
like that like the two of these
multiplied together is like the total
square count and what we want to do is
we want to fill it with like trees and
walls or whatever else we have
proportional to how many of these there
are so we want like these to be related
to the total square count like maybe
like we want a fifth of all the squares
or an eighth
of all the squares or something right to
be filled with whatever it is something
like that right so what I want to do now
is I want to say let's do that with
trees let's just say look like one in
every well we know we're placing them in
it they need eight three and one in the
middle so we know that like the maximum
we could place would be like a ninth
right and we don't want to be really
close to that so let's say we say one
fifteenth of the squares I'm just again
just making this up right so let's say
put a website didn't actually do that
right did I so if I just say that's how
many we'll try and that way now it won't
like be dependent on that side you can
pass other sizes and it should still
maybe pick a reasonable number of trees
right so that's just like how many trees
there are or whatever and let's do
another thing since walls are not
particular interesting right now instead
of placing the walls the way that they
were placed let's place the walls as
like like square things or or something
right um so like let's do this
b32 place rectangular wall I don't know
then X min Y max X max Y and then all
I'm going to do is say check to see if
all of that is empty and we can also do
a thing here where we say like is empty
testing scene X Y right and so what I
could do here is say
results equals this equals grass and
again not doing this is not because the
code is better it's just because this is
a sample app so I'm trying to make
things as clear as possible for the
person who dupes for the person who's
reading it so again in here what I can
do is just go through and test for
emptiness in all of these so basically I
can just say okay for you 32 x equals
min X X is less than or equal to min wah
maybe max X sorry plus plus X place
equals true we'll just assume that so
what I'll do here is say if and I can I
can also make this a part of the loop so
I can do here say if it's empty in both
places if for some reason either of them
are not empty right if I guess the way
to say it
either of the two X rows of wall I'm
just going to place like a rectangular
wall piece if either of them aren't
empty then we're just going to say that
you can't place the wall here right so I
want to should also pass the scene
like so and so what I want to do here
say all right the scene I want to know
that whatever X I'm on I want the min Y
and the max Y of that X to be empty oops
because right we're if I'm going to
place like a rectangular wall area then
I want to know that it's empty in the
two rows of X and then the two rows of Y
so if it's not them placed equals false
and the same would go here so if I do my
Y loop now like so then what I can do is
test min X against Y and max X against Y
right so then if placed then we actually
do the exact same thing but if you look
here this will over it will like place
too many things if that makes sense so
it's like we would be over placing one
of them so we can really do min Y plus
one and less than max Y right because we
don't actually need to go up to the ones
we already checked when we were checking
X so then we can just do the exact same
loops again like so and actually just
write them in here now there we could do
something fancier here if we wanted to
we could do the first loop checks in the
second loop places
I don't know how cheeky we want to get
with that really it's hard to say I mean
here's what that would look like
so if we just did it in one pass we just
say I mean in one set of loops we just
have two passes over the loop zero and
one right and so when we actually go
through the loop the first time through
we check if it's is empty and what we
would do here just say look if pass
equals zero do this else do this other
thing
right and in the case of the do this
other thing it's really just saying look
let me set the the thing here to a wall
and so this way when we go through the
first time we do all the placement stuff
and then here we just add the place and
that we don't really need to do it in
here now I guess technically um you know
we can just do this and so if we can
still be placing then we do if not we
don't and that will place a little
rectangular wall around so we can kind
of you know you can kind of see what's
up oops forgot we need to set both of
these there you go
and I think that should allow us to
place one of these um see what I can do
is place a rectangular wall here I don't
know where I want to place a rectangular
wall I just I'm totally just randomly
making this up so all I'm gonna do here
is just say hey let's go ahead and and
pick some like random set of these I
guess this will do and you know what I
could make this be a thing if I wanted
to to get a random like X&amp;Y right but
let's just say that walls are a maximum
of you know ten units wide so or I guess
in this case I should say nine units
wide
I mean heck we can put whatever padding
we want in there but I say Tim X equals
R and mod 8 y 8 and then here we just do
X Y X plus DMX
and that would be the nine wide version
uh
and then see what we get
I have no idea what we get I just
thought it would be nice to have actual
something like an actual structure of
some kind in there just to kind of give
it a little bit of fun right and so now
you can see that it place like these
little things in there that maybe like
that's a little too small like I don't
know if that's really what we want it's
probably not so I'm guessing that this
actually should this dimension thing
should be like some minimum so it's not
you know so now we've got our test scene
going and you know there's a few other
things here that I guess I would say
maybe would be useful to try just to get
more sprites in there we can also count
the number of sprites that we have which
might be nice just so we know our I
should say how many quads we're drawing
just we have a little bit of perspective
on that but the other thing I was gonna
say is we could try throwing a lot more
sprites in there to see what that
performance looks like
and and so yeah like you know let's
suppose and I'm just gonna say let's
grab let's let's go ahead and Lemongrab
here a hover file like this
and let's just grab one of these things
that we can slap down a lot of just to
see how that affects our performance
among other things right so like you
know if we just make a ton of these
things and place them down there or a
ton of these things you know what
happens or a ton of these like little
flower doodads right and so I'm just
curious what will happen there I'm gonna
maybe grab this one because it's kind of
weird-looking or maybe the grass ones
are better because there's like more
grass there I don't know so let's just
grab one of these so I'm going to go
ahead and Lemongrab this guy right here
so there we go I'm gonna save that off
as test cover grass discard changes and
now what I should be able to do here is
I should be able to really like slow us
down dramatically by just putting a ton
of those on there and I think this card
should be able to handle a lot but we've
got two things that could be slowing
down what is that we kind of have a
crappy pixel sake shader right now and
other stuff so you know I'm basically
what I want to do now is like make this
thing sort of roll over and die and then
once we have it dead we can look at
doing the sort of improvements that I
wanted to do right and maybe and like I
said maybe we'll do those started on
those tomorrow maybe right now I'll just
go go ahead and clean up some of the
push API stuff that I wanted to do and
tomorrow we'll start on the acceleration
of stuff but either way like you know
this is sort of where I want to go with
it what was this called again
okay so here's our cover texture which
will now be loaded in and now whenever
we're you know whenever we're actually
drawing it we can just push a ton of
those on if we wanted to now we kind of
don't really have any particular pattern
for it at the moment which is a little
bit of a problem
because we want to push a bunch of these
onto the surface of the thing so like if
in the case where it's not a wall and
not a tree right and we actually could
do it for the tree as well so actually
that's not true so we may want to do
that as well but if we want to here we
we quickly run into one problem where
the speed of the random number situation
may actually cause a problem for us we
so we probably don't want to call like
random odd we could call our random
potentially and because this is pretty
straightforward right so we could be
doing that and using that to generate
randoms so we'll have to be careful here
and see we could also just use those
standing random pattern and that might
be what I do so maybe we'll do that
we'll see in a second I don't want to
promise anything I'm not sure what we're
gonna do exactly but anyway so if we got
this ground P here and I've got this
tree texture that I was doing
I must switch it to a cover texture and
then I'm just going to render it as it
is at the moment and the rendering it as
it is is really just there because I
want to see what it looks like with them
just one per tile right and so there's
the you know grass kind of cropping up
there so now what I want to do is I want
to get this to be much smaller right I'm
on I want to shrink it down so it's
probably going to be something more like
this right it's not big it's a tiny tuft
of grass and yeah and
we go so there's a tiny tuft of grass
that's probably a little too tiny maybe
I got a little overzealous there let's
try making those about twice as big and
we'll go from there so there we go and
so now what I'd like to do is just spam
a bunch of those into place right so
when we're doing the push right here
what I want to do is have a way of
pushing a bunch of those sprites on and
so I'll just do a loop for the moment
and again I don't really know this loop
could be really slow so we'll see in a
second
well we'll double check that it's not
and we'll go from there so I'm gonna
push some number of these on and I'm
gonna make a random displacement that is
based on the radius so we know that the
radius is like 1/2 meter in either
direction
so I just want to make a displacement
here's the displacement it's gonna be
0.5 F times two random numbers
and the thing about this remember is
that these are themselves they're not
going to be signed right these are
strictly going to be positive so we need
to make sure that they are actually are
signed
so actually what we really want instead
of shrinking these down to 0.5 what I
really want to do is is offset them
right so what I want to do is subtract
0.5 from them so that they're 0 to 1 0
to 1 I want to subtract them so they're
negative 0.5 to 0.5 and then the
displacement I'll just add onto the
ground P and what I could do is I can
actually make this into like I can make
this into three dimensions right I just
saying look we don't want any Z
displacement I mean I could put a little
Z displacement in there but generally
speaking I don't really think I want it
particularly much right so oh sure why
that's taking so long
so hopefully that just meant we rolled
over and died I'm not sure though I
could mean that I did something horribly
wrong let me just make sure that this is
working well as we increase the numbers
here there we go okay so now hopefully
what happens is at some point when I am
getting up into some place where I break
now the problem is we may just end up
pushing too much stuff on the push
buffer at some point and we get like a
problem with that has nothing to do with
like we're just over writing the buffer
right like and I thought we had an
assertion in there for that but maybe it
doesn't trigger and this is a good time
to try that because it should report to
us in the case where it doesn't all
right so here's this thing here we're
operating and we've we've crossed the
line into badness I'm gonna find the
exact point where we do because I think
that might make a little bit easier for
me to troubleshoot but it looks like we
don't properly assert maybe or maybe we
just start throwing things out I guess
we just start throwing things that we
don't assert because it looks like the
game still runs correctly it just
doesn't push any more stuff on there so
yeah is that really what happens let's
find out
so all of these they do check the entry
so so shouldn't we be hitting this oh
but what about the current quads those
make batches of quads so those make
batches of quads which maybe don't
actually have the checking we check the
render buffer we don't mistake the
vertex buffer like noticeably absent
where did that check go did we really
not have one there that's kind of messed
up that we didn't do that I mean we
check stuff pretty thoroughly here
that's pretty bad to not have that I
mean no harm done I suppose but still
right because we explicitly have in the
platform well I guess it's out in the
renderer now we explicitly have a thing
that says how many there are for this
exact reason right in the render
commands right here this is there
specifically for that
right so we should have been saying you
know we should have been checking that
all along and I'm not sure why we
weren't maybe I'm missing something but
I feel like that should have that check
should have been in there because that's
messed up so I don't know maybe
something else well it didn't trigger so
maybe something else weird was happening
there that I'm not understanding right
but that's just kind of bizarre so we
didn't have a check for that I'm not
sure why maybe I missed maybe I'm
missing something and we actually do
check it some other way it looks like
here we've got prevention in there so
this could have been I guess if we
always call the current quads call odds
this could this I'm glad we're doing
this disagree this could be cleaned up
quite a bit so we always call get
current clots and nerf it here so I
guess this is also so this we actually
did protect ourselves against it this
assertion still should have been here we
were protected against it but we didn't
put an assertion which we really want
because we don't really want the game in
debug mode and that shouldn't be not
implemented it's an invalid code in
debug mode we want to know as soon as we
blow out the buffer size right we want
someone to tell us that so I'm glad we
put that in there that you know you
never want to silently I mean it's good
that we it's good that we handled a
failure case so that was good but it's
in debug mode you always want to fail
loudly so that the person doesn't like
just silently not know you could imagine
the bug being much more subtle than that
where some things just occasionally
didn't render and they never got the
assertion they didn't realize that they
were blowing out the size of some buffer
that they needed right so you've got to
have a loud failure in there if you
don't have a loud failure in there then
you can let more subtle books again bugs
like that where the whole screen where
it just stops drawing a huge section of
screen well those are easy but you don't
you can't guarantee right that it's
always going to be that straightforward
you know what I'm saying so I think
that's relatively important to keep in
mind um so yeah I think if we then just
say look give us a lot more vertices
please then we used to have and we're
just going to go ahead on and and render
to them what's going on here there's no
way we're using that many vertices come
on seriously I mean that's not possible
what did I do wrong we do set the max
vertex count somewhere right yeah it's
right there
I said are you sixteen or something no
so tell me what the situation is here
commands is undefined
are we compiling in release mode yes we
are
show me commands please
[Music]
okay if commands vertex count plus 4
times quad count is greater than max
vertex count oh it helps to put the
invalid code path marker on the actual
path that was invalid shockingly I know
you must be very surprised to hear that
but that actually is required so okay
sooo this is good it looks like it's
getting a little bit dicey err
potentially in terms of render speed
which is what I wanted I'm not sure why
we're not seeing here I guess we haven't
gotten yes you can see it's getting
slower um so I should be able to just
slow this down quite a bit here and what
I can do there are some tricks that I
can pull here too I can do some
additional work to make sure that we're
not actually causing the problem
ourselves in the push calls right so
let's say I Jack this up to something
really bad okay and I make this thing go
really slowly okay not quite slowly
enough I mean like really slowly like
like ultra slip
I mean technically we could probably go
slower than that but you know all right
that's fine right close enough so when
we are in this mode right and we're
going really slowly there's a couple
problems one is I don't actually know
whether the slowness is from the
renderer or from Mike this code right so
we don't know if like our push cube push
sprite calls are just too slow and
they're actually causing the problem
right but because we're just rendering
from those buffers that gives us an
excellent opportunity to do something
that allows us to see if that's true or
not so here's our global run rip what
you can see us going down here we create
a render command buffer here right we
preach a bunch of stuff onto it we
render it and then what you'll notice is
every frame through we generate a new
one of these now what we could do
instead is actually not clear that
buffer right because actually if you
look at that buffer all we really need
to do is save the settings from the
previous time through and just not
update them that's all we would need to
do and if we did that then we would
could run without actually calling push
scene right so so this right here
wouldn't actually need to happen so what
I could do is say all right let's see
how fast we are if we don't reach the
geometry so all I'm gonna do is I'm just
gonna I'm actually gonna let this whole
thing happen I think all I'm really
gonna do is take the virtus Rotex arrays
stuff and not do it like that's all I'm
gonna do so basically instead of push
simple scene on here I'm just not going
to do that
the only problem is I need to update the
camera transform so that's a little
harder
I don't think of easiest way to do this
so when I do push simple scene like what
I could do is maybe I could even do it
with an if zero right every night or an
if around this where if we've already
done it once we just save and restore
that version I think I can do that
so what I think I could do here is just
say yeah like that max vertex kind of
vertex kind of thing let's just save
like every time through here I'm gonna
go ahead and get whatever the last
vertex count actually is and then I'm
wondering if I can just do a thing where
I read out the simple oh well yeah I'm
still just not sure how to do this right
I guess what I could do just reach in
and change the thing I mean I could just
render the same scene without changing
it maybe we'll just do that so let's do
this
and I could reach in and try to find
that camera parameter too and change it
I suppose that would work too to a
certain extent um so here in the default
render command stuff right all I'm gonna
do is just pull this out so we'll
initialize the render commands and then
what I'll do is I'll just do an if here
to basically avoid doing this stuff in
the case where we aren't actually going
to update
so if updating we do this otherwise we
don't and we just use the render
commands from last time so that just
means this is updating equals true and
if I just run the game s is I mean the
test render as is that should give me
the same situation I had before slow you
know very kind of silly ridiculously
slow and then when we actually go
through to do the first time after we
update once we just won't update ever
again so we only call that path once and
then from then on we just render the
actual same scene right and so then what
we can see is we can find out how much
of our time is spent in the actual
render code as like the actual
dispatching to OpenGL as opposed to just
the code that builds up the scene
hopefully right and then from there we
can have an opinion about the difference
in speed between those two things which
is something that we want and I could
also reduce the number of frames we
averaged across so that it doesn't take
as long but you can see right here it
looks like it's taking 90 milliseconds
of frame roughly
and that's without doing any of the push
with without us doing anything so that's
strictly time spent in the render either
us pushing the information to OpenGL or
like the card actually rendering it so
you can see there it's pretty clear like
what's going on so you know around 90
milliseconds a frame if I then just go
ahead and let it update every time this
will give us a little bit of a clue as
to whether our actual push buffer calls
matter at all and just to see whether
there's much of a difference between
those two things or not I probably
shouldn't rotate the camera just to
compare apples to oranges because this
is yeah this isn't a fair test because
the fill rate goes down right here when
all these things are back facing so
we'll see so it's not really a fair
comparison and I should just leave the
camera where it is
so you know it's a little slower but not
I mean so we still would want to
optimize that push time it's not great
so we still have problems with the
computation the push time I and so we
can work on that but it's clearly not
the majority of the time so we really
need to fix that dispatch time which is
what we thought we would have to do and
so we should do it this seam should not
be hard to run we should be able to get
this running in 60 frames a second on a
modern card like this one so I'm pretty
sure that mostly what we need here is a
way to avoid is a way to avoid doing
those texture changes
okay I'm sue now that I've got that
under control I'm gonna remove this
temporarily here go back to what we were
doing I could put it back later but I'm
gonna leave it this way so I think
that's all I really want to do for today
on the that test side of things so I
feel like what I could do is just leave
this number leave the number of extra
sprites pushed on here leave that down
in like the low range and then we'll
crank it back up tomorrow when we want
to start working on the texture stuff so
just leave it like this and so now what
I want to do is just go look at the API
side of things a little bit more so
let's start with the basics
here's the render loop right and here's
the information that we want from OpenGL
and we can start documenting this a
little bit here we know that the window
is passed as the LP parameter because
that's what we're going to use so I want
to
target with that so here's just the
steps that we're going through right and
I don't know about the how we want to do
the last counter I'm guessing I don't
really think we want to quite do it that
way I think what I'd rather do is say
look the last counter is gonna be no and
then when we come through here and we
get the end counter I want to only do I
want to only do this update when we know
that we have an actual an actual valid
frame so what I'd like to do is say and
this present need to be 300 let's make
it 122 seconds so what I'd like to do
here is say look if last counter dot
quad part is not equal to zero then
we'll do all this stuff you know
otherwise we don't know how long the
frame took so we're just not going to do
anything like we're just going to render
that first frame that's like a do-over
right and we're not going to time it
so you know that's yeah I mean that's
pretty much all we're talking about
there see the frame variabilities it's
quite high and I don't really know why
that would be a nice thing to look into
at some point too like I don't know why
it's such a that's a pretty wide range
right and I don't know if that's because
we're sort of like issuing two and then
we got to wait for the grass right a
little bit in the issue another one and
I don't know if it if why it's not
leveling out as much it could be because
again of the of the of the vsync so you
know we could in the win32 open gel
layer we could look at the Swap interval
and inside here right when we set this
swap interval what we could do there is
provide a call for you to not do that so
what we could do is have in here a thing
that says like internal void win through
to set vsync and have a vsync enabled
where we say look if you want the vsync
enabled otherwise don't write and I
guess I wouldn't quite do it that way
I'd probably do it this way right if
these think is supposed to be enabled
it's 1 otherwise it's zero right and
then in here we could just for timing
purposes go ahead and turn that off so
we could say like set vsync falls and I
could also say like OpenGL
and so now it would allow tearing and it
will just run as fast as it can
them Theory won't wait for the V Blanc
but I mean we don't really know whether
it will or won't to a certain extent it
doesn't really look any different to me
and it looks like it's still waiting for
the V Blanc honestly I don't see the
tear so I don't know it could also be
because if it's for if Nvidia forces us
to do that I don't know if they do one
of the things that happens is inside the
Nvidia control panel each individual 3d
program right has overrides for it
specifically I don't know where that is
so here we go okay so if you look here
you can see that there's like a bunch of
settings and in here it says like use
the 3d application setting in theory
that means that they that it is going to
obey our call
I assume right but we don't know and if
I actually go to program settings I can
also see like for my particular one what
would necessarily be set
we don't have an override I don't think
like there shouldn't be an override for
our stuff because we create one and so I
don't think there's any reason why
vertical sync would be forced off so
given that I assume that this is as
vertical sinky as it's going to get and
I guess like I said I don't know but
that's just seems to be the case so
assuming that is the case we may just be
forced to vsync because we're running
through the compositor on Windows 10 and
hey we're in a window right like if we
actually put the full screen code in
there maybe we would see something else
happen but who knows
so yeah so I don't know where that
variability comes from that will be a
subject for future profiling to figure
out where that's actually coming from
because we don't know so anyway here we
go
right so we're just going to say hey
start it up there
and there we go so here's some simple
explanations of what's going on here so
if someone reads this example they can
see and so far it looks fine to me right
like I don't see any weirdness happening
here
this is what you would expect right and
you know this is a pretty simple API
right I say I want to initialize it I
say I want to set the vsync right and
then in here I can look and say well
okay I need to allocate memory
and here's that information here right
and these we can probably simplify a
little bit in the future for a number of
reasons one is that first of all we can
probably get rid of this notion of the
textured vertex vertex array and we can
probably convert like this all into one
thing I'm guessing and then the other
thing I think we could probably do is
make it so that the push buffer we may
actually be able to just not have a push
buffer at all because since we know that
we're just batches of quads based on the
textures we may just be able to just
have those batches right because we are
not we're not a general-purpose renderer
here we're a sprite renderer so we know
we only render quads so right we don't
really need a flexible push buffer so
you know a certain extent we may be able
to just get rid of that entirely it's
just not relevant and we can just pretty
much ignore it right and just say look
we've got batches of quads the quads are
completely homogeneous and like you just
go from there and the only thing it
needs to know is hey here's the pointer
to the quads and go to town so if we
just say that that's all it does then
it's a lot easier right and we probably
don't really need a push buffer per se
you just have a giant list of quads
segmented into two parts ones that are
all 512 by 512 textures and ones that
aren't or so
so we can probably play with that a
little bit and make it simpler we
certainly don't need this many pending
texture operations
so this is where we're going to put all
of those texture ups and since we have
to you know do that sort of texture
since those have to be cued up we just
want to let the person know that hey
like however many textures per frame you
want to download you kind of need to
have that queued up there I don't I'm
still don't really know if that's the
way we want the texture to to work it's
a little confusing as to whether that's
really appropriate or not but it doesn't
matter anyway so here's the then here's
the sort of scene stuff
and so this is the camera setup I don't
think so we may want to pull out our
stats here into something else so that
those are not in line like you'll see
there's like a lot of this cruft here
like this is cruft this is craft that's
craft and this is all cruft so you know
to a certain extent I think
I think we kind of want that to be meat
like down here you know
because it just seems like maybe it's
distracting it doesn't tell you anything
about the API it's strictly for
performance timing you know so I'm just
thinking out loud here like what if we
just pulled that out into a thing like
frame stats that would get rid of these
variables to start with right it would
get rid of this it would get rid of this
whole situation and then you can just
read through this it's a little cleaner
it's mostly what you want and then when
you come through here this this back
half this part here can actually be
handled that way as well so like all of
this stuff we could actually make be a
thing where you say like okay let's
update this in some sensible way like
not sure how we really want to do that
you know what they probably like this so
I think I want to do that so basically
in here you know we'll have a thing that
would handle those stats so this is like
every frame this is like and we'd have
an init version and so I think this is
kind of nice because then it gets the
stuff that you really don't need to
learn the API it's not really relevant
it gets it out of there which i think is
good because you're just trying to like
focus the person who's trying to learn
this is attention on what actually
matters in the API you know so here's
the frame stats that we need to start
out with these are all already correct
so really we're just this is the only
one that actually gets initialized to an
actual value right because all the rest
of these are just clear to zero which is
what we would want anyway and in fact we
don't really have to clear this to zero
we could just make this being an it on
zero thing but we need the periphery Qin
C so probably doesn't matter right
because this is gonna have to be figured
out here anyway right we're gonna have
to call this so it seems fine at that
point
and this doesn't really need to be
global
so ya don't know why that was in the
first place but it was I guess so anyway
in here when we do this we can just make
this pretty straightforward that should
do it
and so once we have that taken care of
we should be able to make this work off
of the stats so now if I do stats last
counter it's that so now what I can do
is say well all right we have to return
second Celeste will assume that the
second still apps is zero so no time has
elapsed at all and then what we'll do is
we always want to get the end counter
but we don't always want to compute the
seconds to elapsed value so sometimes we
want to come to me and specifically what
we want to do is we want to do it in
this case right and then what we want to
do down here is say that last counter
equals encounter so we want to get the
encounter and update that we only want
to do the processing in the case where
the last counter wasn't zero because the
first time through that it's gonna be
bogus values we want to avoid processing
those bogus values we can do the output
debug string and all that fanciness
every so often this is off of stats as
is that so all of this is fine oops and
that should do it right yeah
hmm yeah
all right so in order to get second
Celeste we need to do like that update
frame stats thing and we need to do our
frame stats here in terms of the frame
stats themselves we need to initialize
them here so we can do frame stats stats
and we can just do an init frame stats
like that and then I just need to make
those be known so here's the update
frame stats bit and here's the in frame
stats bit and there we go
let's just do that okay sue we've pulled
that out now so it's not gonna get in
the way of somebody who's trying to use
this let's just make sure it's still
working okay and we still actually get
we can see our seconds elapsed is
obviously working because we are
rotating at the right speed but then we
see the print out down there so that
just kind of again that just pulls it
out and gets rid of something that they
don't have or wouldn't want to look at
right so yeah like right here we can put
this up with the rest of the window
stuff
so that will you know just let people
know we're doing that think everything
else here is pretty self-explanatory
with the comments that are in there now
so finally what we want to do is say
we're setting up the camera
so
I'll put this
so just give them some idea of what's
going on here
so this should be sort of making sense
hopefully to people I don't know maybe I
should put this way this is just like so
I think we're good there now we get down
to this part here
and it's so there's a couple things I
think what I would like to do is we've
got this t camera shift here we're doing
an orbit we've got one here that we're
doing as well
and I'd like to do both of these so I
think what I might do is say hey every
time we do a shift back by tau that
means we've done one loop around I'm
gonna do like camera is orbiting those
false and I'm gonna do or I should say
like camera is panning maybe as false
and then I'm going to do like a if
camera is panning here and I'm gonna
make it so that we can do both of these
movements to test the camera and they'll
just happen serially so every time we do
this I'm gonna do like camera is panning
equals not cameras panning so they're
like every time we wrap on tau we will
get that change so we start out by like
rotating around just to see what that
looks like you know and and then once we
finish rotating around then we will do a
pan around and it should alternate
between those two that way you don't
have to flip a switch in the code to
have the camera do something other than
what it was already doing right and that
seems pretty reasonable to me let's come
along mr. Koh Deepu it's a nice speed
for rotating the camera but it's a
little slow if you're waiting to see
what happens when it finishes its entire
orbit
so that seems fine
I guess the only thing that's a little
annoying about that is that they're not
coincident but I don't really care about
that
so this tests both of those things
pretty well
and I've found that you can also see we
get some problems where these grasses
are too far forward there's a bunch of
weird stuff in there so we're probably
gonna have to make sure that this this
is a little too much like we need to
make sure that they actually stay sort
of semi contained for lack of a better
term you know so that they're sort of at
least nominally inside the the region
just for artifact avoiding purposes so
that's a little bit better you could
like to keep them like relatively
confined to the space that's all um okay
so we've got this startup pretty
well-documented now and then I'll say
so that's pretty good I think that's all
pretty self-explanatory and so now we
get down to this stuff here and I think
this is where we could start to make a
little bit of a difference here for the
casual user so if you look at what's
going on here either it's just a little
bit much right and some of these things
here like you could imagine us building
this into some kind of a system that
would handle things a little bit nicer
for you so if you look at what's
actually going on there's just a lot of
business here let me spread all of these
out and just in terms of seeing what's
going on so like our begin render group
and our depth peel and depth peel runner
group like well I don't know that we
really need the DEF peel stuff in the
end because I think we can auto depth I
think we can just auto def peel
everything and be fine with it
I think that the OpenGL I think that
like this stuff here is ok if you just
showed me this I'd be fine with it but
the camera transform like z-rotation get
standard cam person to ask it for each
outfit all of that stuff
feels a little overwhelming for people
who don't know like what all that was
doing and why it feels like maybe if you
don't care you wouldn't really want to
have to do this stuff right and so it
would be nice to kind of take a spin
through and figure out what how to maybe
package that stuff up a little better
I'm also curious as to the draw region
stuff we've got window with and window
height here and we're making it the draw
region out of that and then we're
passing opengl round of commands that I
want to make sure that all of this stuff
is necessary and does what it thinks
it's gonna do for beginning and render
group when when do what are we using
those things for exactly also I'm
curious what is the pixel height stuff
doing is that just there for the is that
oh is that for the cliprect
for the for defining the clipping region
it's not what that's there for I'm
assuming that's what that's there for
but I don't really know
[Music]
okay so it's there for two reasons it's
there for the clipping and it's for
unproductive so basically it's there
because the clipping yes so basically
the clipping the clipping we only use at
the moment for the debug system but the
the unprojected termina quare the camera
can see those are both useful so I feel
like we want to continue doing that
right that's pretty minimal
what does OpenGL render commands do with
the window width and window height
it's that just because it needs to clear
the whole region or what yes so that's
just because it needs to clear the whole
region and that's fine too
[Music]
hmmm I say so there's a couple things
that I'm thinking about here so I do
think we may in the renderer have over
complicated things a little bit in that
we didn't really bother
we didn't correctly so when we specify
things like clip Rex we're specifying
those in pixel coordinates but we don't
need to specify them in pixel
coordinates they can be specified in
just regular coordinate coordinates like
negative 1 to 1
or something in screen space and I do
wonder if we're not just making life
more complicated for everybody by doing
them in the space that we're doing them
because if you look at what happens in
here I suspect
yes so I mean we immediately take the
pixels XY and we just turn it in to
screen space coordinates anyway right
like that's that's what we do with it so
if you just didn't do that if instead
you just sent down negative one to one
as your spread then we wouldn't need to
pass this in and I'm guessing and I
could be wrong
yeah I mean nobody calls this in a non
debug sense except for inside the render
itself and the renderer itself went does
like get camera rectangle at Target
calls into here and it passes screen dim
so it's literally just passing its own
thing to divide right it's dumb so I
feel like that screen dim really doesn't
need to be there it's not so so I feel
like we've maybe made the renderer use
pixel coordinates for no reason and I
mean look we're just doing it it's
really just doing it for no reason so
that's an API screw-up and the reason
that's an ApS grew up is it's basically
you can now see it's leaking out the
pixel the actual number of pixels on the
screen are leaking out into code that
wouldn't have had to know them so code
here that's just rendering a scene
wouldn't ever have to know the number of
pixels on the screen and we're making
them know it and I don't care for it
that is non good so if I then look at
the OpenGL renderer where that actually
interprets the cliprect so you can see
here let me just make sure yeah there's
only one place so where this actually
interprets the cliprect so in this
interpretation of the clip rect instead
of doing it as raw coordinates that we
pass the GL scissor which this is the
only time we ever actually do that
instead of doing that what we could do
is just actually use the render height
here and multiply the number that we get
by the render height to get the clip
rect and that way everything would
always just work in terms of screen
normalized coordinates and that would be
that so I feel like that's what really
should happen I I feel like that's an
API cleanup we should do here so looking
at that if I actually go to handmade
instead so here I'm calling the actual
game right so like here's an example of
when cliprect
oh that reminds me one more thing
somebody asked why we were getting this
error we're placing the where we're
having this over something makes the
Alpha I'm sorry makes the depth feel
compositing network properly and I
realize I gave the wrong answer actually
I said it was because we run out of Def
peels that's not why it is these if I
remember correctly are actually outside
the depth peel pass so I believe that
what actually happens is since these are
rendered on to the top def peel which
isn't strictly correct I believe what
happens is they just erroneously fill
the alpha value of the DEF peel with a
new alpha value that's wrong I think
that's what's actually happening right
we could fix this and we probably should
right we could fix this composite it's
only for debug mode so it doesn't really
matter but it's worth noting um so what
I was going to say is here's something
that uses the clip Rex
and we also know something that uses the
unprojected like the lighting for
example so we should be able to see if
we can do this removal I don't think it
would be that hard the clip Rex will
break almost immediately if we do the
removal but I think we can get them back
so I think the only thing we really have
to worry about here is is
the the the debug display code so I'm
just gonna see what happens how hard
would it be to get rid of this right so
if I come through here and I'm in the
renderer and I just I just get rid of
the fact that it even knows the screen
dimensions at all I want to see how much
of a problem that that place is on me so
here's screen them I just it's gone
right and what I do need to do to back
that up is the rect the cliprect right
here and the render setup that needs to
be a floating point value it can't be an
eye anymore so it would need to be like
like a rect of that kind right so I'm
just gonna see what happens and we'll go
from there
so I mean here we get this flip ripped
out here's the clip rect and what I need
to do is I need to create a rectangle to
I from it basically like these need to
become u32 values so if what I'm saying
is that this clip rect itself is like a
negative 1 to 1
like specified clip rect so it's in like
screen normalized coordinates for
whatever that actually means for the
screen then like right here you know
we've already got stuff that does that
right we have the render within the
render height and the 0 the 0 to render
with 0 to render height version of the
viewport so what I should I believe in
theory do be able to do is just say okay
if I want to create min and Max values
out of this then I should be able to say
that the clip rect that I get each of
those coordinates can be transformed
like range transformed into a u32 right
if I go to the math thing and I look at
the lerp here right loop is sort of what
I want to do but it's 0 to 1 not
negative 1 to 1
right and so if I wanted to I could make
a lerp that actually worked as a
negative one to one or I could make one
of those and just that would be what I'd
want I don't know how useful this is but
I'm gonna say maybe we would do this
so s32 like by normal lerp this is an
incredibly special purpose function but
who knows maybe it's useful um
so if we have a by normal T and we're
going between two actual you 32-valve or
s 32 values in this case let's say right
then what I want to do is I want to
convert this T to a 0 to 1 T so this is
like a tea by normal and to get a team
normal it's pretty straightforward it's
just half the range and then I offset it
right because if this is negative 1 to 1
this will make it negative 0.5 to 0.5
and then I offset it by point 5 I get 0
to 1 which is exactly what I wanted then
I can create a float result like a
floating point result by doing the
standard lerp exactly as I would have
done it right so I can say all right
just lerp between these two values as
you would have done and then finally I
can create the results by doing the cast
like so I don't know if we have one that
can do that we'll find out so then what
I could do is say let's get each of
these each of these rounded values
together so here's my lerp of these and
I probably want to look at these values
because if I get them wrong
and we step into the butter I want to be
able to see him so I'm just gonna say
like let's do a by norm
appear to the render width and a by
normal to the render height like so so
then I know my clip min X and my clip
min Y and what I don't know is how big
the rectangle is I might just keep doing
it this way even though we could do the
length directly I'm not gonna I'm just
gonna leave it on a uniform path I think
that feels a little better to me so now
I can just do this and leave the
computation exactly the same okay
so now I just say all right get the clip
rect out figure out what it actually is
in screen coordinates and then when
you're done
pass that information to GL scissor so
we can have a little party right and
that's all we need to do there that's
the end of that so if I do that now when
we're actually setting that up in the
renderer
what is this complaining about P 2 min
max sorry these are actually
there we go I think that's all good all
right and so now what I need to do is I
actually need to make sure that we're
Act passing clip Rex in the normalized
screen space from now on instead of in
instead of in the space of the actual
pixels of the screen we stop doing this
we know that was wrong we fixed that so
that's can just go away now we've got
these sort of things that use that we're
using the screen dim before I want those
to be gone so what we're gonna do is the
clip space X&amp;Y here again that supposed
to just be a negative one to one value
so I think we can just I think we can
just use this directly like I think we
can now just say look forget that stuff
don't worry about it
let's do clip space X Y as the input so
it's already in that format so let's say
that this is clip space X Y and then
these are now responsible just passing
in that proper clip space value right so
they are negative one to one now okay so
now when we call get screen point you
can see here we're doing we're actually
doing this nonsense to produce a screen
point we're just gonna say that whenever
you call get screen point you're
actually gonna get stuff back not in
that space now that's kind of obviously
fine because the only people who call it
are people who get the clip rat and of
course the clip right path now it goes
the other way do I have any I have a
little so this actually all just
collapses down really well as it turns
out so when we do get screen point this
is literally undoing the thing that we
don't want it to do anyway right it's
it's undoing something that we
done I should say right we've wanted in
clip space that is literally undoing
clip space so just forget it don't undo
the clip space transform right so this
is get clips face point here and now
when we get the clip space stuff here
just don't round it right just make a
rectangle min max out of the min corner
and the max corner and everyone
hopefully at that point would be a happy
puppy right I think maybe who knows so
when we get the clip rect out of these
you know do those we're gonna get clip
space back and the clip space now is
what we want so that's a good thing and
I think then we can just move on from
there so we'll see how that goes going
forwards let's keep going here now
inside begin render group we don't need
the pixel width and height those can go
away and then in here where we're
setting up the clip rect where we do
recommend dim now we know that this
actually can just be a clip rect in this
space right
so for recommend dim I don't know if
we've got let me just see here I don't
know where recommend max calls are and
stuff like that or recommending so if we
look at where our recommend dim is here
it looks like we've only got an s 32
version for that particular one that's
not really gonna help us so we want to
do this so what we'd like to do here is
say look here's our you know what let's
do recommend max because that's way
clearer
right that's what we want so that's good
now when we have begin render group we
don't care about that we don't care
about this and now I think we're just i
think we're just working on debug state
right so now we just have to make sure
that our our clip Brett stuff actually
does something useful care we don't need
the width and height right
so we just need that clip rect stuff to
work let me go ahead and see where we
set the rectangle to I there that's
gonna be one of these now and we'll see
if we need anything else all right so
we've removed that part from the
renderer we don't know if this will work
or not anymore
you know it might it might not so you
can see where yeah we're not getting any
cookies there so we've got some issues
who knows what those issues are we'll
find out in a second
um so looking at most of what we did I
think we're okay right like you can see
like our regions are alright if we
actually go through playing the game
that if that all seems fine too so it
looks like the only thing we've really
got wrong here is I don't know if the
clip recs are wrong but maybe the the
clicking is wrong so we need to look at
the click part of things and just see
might be get screen point or I'm sorry I
don't remember what that thing was
called
there was like a get a clip space point
yeah so these I don't really remember
how the clicking stuff worked here let
me let's see in the debug system how are
we doing
how were we doing that stuff excuse me
like what are we even calling we call
unprojected saprykin project and
unprojected is no longer it needs this
to be done right so what we can do is
just provide one of those right here so
here's our inline v2 clip space from
screen space right this is it and then
that makes it so that you provide that
so here's your screen space X Y and then
you can provide the screen dim yourself
right so you can say you three two green
jim xq 32 screen Jim Y and then we can
just say screen dim equals v2 screen Jim
X Gen Y so this way you can do that and
really this is technically window space
I suppose or pixel space because it's
not really screen the screen is a thing
it's a hole monitor right it's it's not
accounting for those things so let's
make that a little more explicit there
just so it's clear and so we'll do
pixel pixel dim pixel Jim turn clip
space so then as long as the person who
wants to call on project we could say
Mouse pixel P equals this oh sorry I
should say mouse click P so we can call
clip space from pixel space there and we
just have to provide the width and
height width I think was getting passed
in here right it's getting passed in
here somewhere
I don't really know where well if we
called begin render group oh it would
have been in hmmm
the place where we calling begin render
group here so in debug start we have the
width and the height would do we save
those we do so they're right here so we
can actually grab those out and pass
those down right we could pass them as
float we're saving them as float which
so I guess maybe we'll just since this
is the only person who even needs this
let's go ahead and actually hmm just
take him as float I was taking him as I
was trying to be nice and take them as
that's non float but don't forget that
they're float now my friends and so what
we can do here is just go ahead and take
those as float
let them call that and now that should
work right
so now if I run it hopefully we'll get
clicking back on line there we go
and so now the other question is
clipping working and it is so that's
pretty great I'm really happy about that
that now that means that we just don't
have that extra annoyance right because
I that was bugging me and I like the
fact that now you just don't that's not
part of the situation
everything that happens in the render
group happens inside the under like that
normalized coordinate understanding
which is just better because why leak
pixels into something that doesn't need
them right it just it just makes it more
dependent yeah
this is like I said all comments are
always inaccurate alright
so that seems good to me and I think we
can end on that so I like I really like
getting that out of hair this is where
that should go not here
and then this is fine because this is
sort of telling us what we're gonna do
as far as camera fitting is concerned so
these sorts of things are fine and I
feel like that's where it belongs right
like camera setup stuff and this command
stuff that all I feel like belongs in
the outside this render group stuff
shouldn't see it you know so I think
we're getting better there all right I'm
gonna go to a Q&amp;A here
sure dish do you think you'll get back
to 60 frames a second in the debug build
or at least a usable framerate um I
don't know but I don't care I guess
particularly much like the actual frame
rate it runs in the debug build at the
moment is actually fine with me
so like like that's fine that's like
totally usable like I don't I don't mind
that at all any other on topic questions
I'm playing do you want the render API
to have a UI mode basically a polished
version of what the debug display is
using so no interaction with the
lighting system perhaps using screen
space coordinates or is that something
that will always be for debug and 2d
stuff will need to be handled by some
other means um I haven't thought about
it too much but I don't really want
there to be much UI at all in this game
if any
I would rather you're just playing so to
the extent that there's ever like a menu
it would I would want it to be like as
simple as possible so I don't think I
would want to have anything even
remotely as complicated as the debug
system at the moment so to pretty much
know like I think we would probably have
just a very simple thing that's coded
just for the one like if we need a menu
of some kind or something like that but
no I I don't think I would ever do that
for this project
it just isn't I don't really want there
to be a lot of UI on the screen ever
Oh for the other person who's using the
render engine um no because they already
know how to do 2d so I don't think they
need me to do that they can just go
ahead and extend the renderer however
they want for 2d stuff I don't think
there's really any issue right it's just
the 3d stuff they didn't want to have to
know how to do so if they end up using
this renderer code I'm not worried about
their 2d stuff because I think they can
just render that afterwards the however
they want and they don't need me for
that at all I don't think I mean they've
already shipped 2d games so like I'm
sure for UI they don't need me to do
anything
oh did I say mat slightly wrongly yes
you're right
should be in unoccupied
um okay so any other on topics doesn't
look like it on Twitter you said all
user interface design is an adaptive
compression problem what did you mean by
that well it's I I mean it's I thought
it was kind of self-explanatory I just
mean that you've got encoder and a
decoder right the encoder is the human
the decoder is the computer and what
you're trying to do is have the very
minimal amount of interaction to get the
result so the human is trying to encode
what they want to do the the computer is
trying to decode that into something so
you know the best user interface is the
one that has the least amount of stuff
the human has to tell you to tell the
computer to do it so what you're trying
to design when you design a user
interface is you're trying to design the
most efficient human encoding process
that the computer can still decode into
the right thing whatever that is whether
it's a touch file full of code or paint
package decoding something into a
drawing you know right it's it's that's
all it is and I say it's an adaptive
compression problem because there it
doesn't have to be static right the
computer can the user can tell the
computer things that it uses to adapt
what it's doing to decode like for
example if a user records a macro and
then does the macro invocation that's
sort of like a dictionary lookup into a
dictionary that got built on the fly
right it's like an LZ compression like
macros are LZ right I feel like this is
pretty self-explanatory but maybe I'm
wrong
let's see
going along with getting rid of
unnecessary params do the camera sov
aspect ratio near for clip play need to
be passed every frame or are you going
to move them out to one time setup call
actually all of those have to be passed
every frame except possibly the near and
far clip plains because the camera fov
is animatable and the aspect ratio
changes every time the user resizes the
window
I mean the aspect ratio doesn't but the
fit does I should say right this has to
be done again if that makes any sense
furthermore remember the other person
using this or whoever it is might want
to support multiple aspect ratios not
just sixteen by nine so actually this is
completely unavailable to even the
aspiration itself so only then your our
clip claims are really ones that don't
animate but one of my conside a
grammatical error around 620 is was it
okay
thank you I assume that's why you're
talking about
Nordic clear hey Casey how can I start
with C++ that might be when to ask the
chat why are you talking about like C or
C++ that might be one better for the
chat I don't really have a lot of good
advice on on beginner stuff for C or C++
language learning because I learned it
so long ago that I feel like there's
probably gotta be better resources now I
hope but I don't know
I like having grammar checking
um so we're looking good here I'm liking
this I feel like maybe we clean up the
camera stuff tomorrow this then this
part is looking pretty good
pick up the camera stuff at the
beginning tomorrow and then maybe this
stuff we clean up the push bright push
cube stuff right and then that leaves us
for next weekend
just texture rays you know I'm saying
marie-claire how do you manage your
dependencies in a c-plus fresh project
can you be more specific what do you
mean by manage your dependencies I mean
I guess the managed part I can infer but
just X define dependencies since
different there's a lot of different
things that someone could mean by
dependencies so so define specifically
what you mean by dependencies and I can
definitely answer the question zero
would you consider doing this sort of
overhaul and any other parts of the code
like your what you're doing dinner yeah
like I would definitely at some point
want to do passes to improve the quality
and design of things that we've
organically sort of worked out but we
haven't really had yet a situation where
we super need to do that and haven't
done it so at the moment like I don't
really have plans to do that to anything
in particular but it may come up right
so we may be like yeah let's we really
want to really make sure this thing is
good so let's go ahead and break that
into something pretty well nailed down
for the renderer I think it's eminently
worth it this was an excuse to do this
because someone might want to use it so
that's a good reason to do it now but I
wanted to do it anyway because we've
gone through so many sort of things
we've tried because we sort of set out
let's do OpenGL let's do lighting that
sort of stuff just in terms of visual
quality game I feel like it's worth
taking a minute to say hey let's let's
get this cleaned up let's get this into
a state we're like this is how the
renderer works and then we can go from
there so I think that's a good thing
nor declare libraries okay um so
generally speaking interna in terms of
using libraries in c++ i find that
libraries generally speaking are not
worth using so i don't use any for the
most part and now i'll break that down
so i find libraries tend to have
problems they oftentimes don't work the
way I want them to or don't play well
with my code they like to do things like
allocate memory when I don't tell them
to or create threads or do things that I
don't want so there are very few
libraries that I'm willing to use but
sometimes there are libraries that I
want to use and in the case where there
are libraries that I want to use here
are some of the things that I do number
one I usually try to keep libraries
isolated to pre-processing and I don't
put libraries into something that I ship
so for example in a game I do perhaps
want to use the Aguas audio compressor
to compress audio so what I will do is
snap a version of the odd Vorbis dll's
because dll's don't have to be rebuilt
and they don't have to be like
maintained really and then I will just
get proc address on the DLLs call them
to compress the audio and just use them
that way and then I just consider that
like part of the build that I use is
those dll's
right and I do that to keep their code
out of my code so it doesn't bring in a
bunch of stuff I don't want and make my
build process more complex right so
insofar as I can just snap a copy of the
source to something snap a build of the
DLLs keep put that aside and just use
the DLL from then on that's what I'll do
in terms of using actual source in an
actual runtime that I'm actually
shipping to other people I'm really
selective about that I'll only use code
that I can make work with my stuff so if
it if it requires using the C runtime
library for example I just won't use
that like I would never use a library
that required the C runtime library if I
can patch around the C runtime library
by providing my own look malloc and free
to it or something and my own like file
streaming then I'll you potentially use
that library and what I'll do there is
just copy the source code into my
project and build it in line with the
project I never under any circumstances
use anything like external build
management project management any of
that stuff
anything that might update things on its
own is totally unacceptable
like I consider it the build to be what
the build is I don't even remotely
approve of like the Left pad nonsense
where like you automatically get updated
packages from places or any of that
stuff that's like a totally unacceptable
there is no circumstance in which that
should ever be done I think it's like
massive source of really bad situations
the number of things that are bad about
that card development process are to
innumerable to mention but they have all
of their base code that is used by other
people and that other people are
building products to depend on should be
released very infrequently and tested
very well and that is the opposite of a
sort of you know guns in the air let's
just update everything all the time and
we don't even know how many products
were depending on and we're letting a
package manage do it right it's just
that just breeds like really unknowable
bad like software situations where
you're you don't know one who even
shipped this thing knows how it works
right
or even what version of whatever
software they're even using to ship it
right so that stuff is just really bad
and that's because I tend to prioritize
like reliability in a build and in
software over the latest newest fast
moving oh we just got some
new random thing in and we built it and
let's just assume it works and off we go
right like I don't I'm not okay with
that I don't really believe you should
treat your users like alpha testers all
the time just doesn't seem like a good
plan to me and it's frustrating I don't
like being treated that way as a user I
like preferred the days when developers
had to do testing because you know they
we're gonna ship you a disk and they
couldn't ship you an update to the disk
right I liked having that forced moment
where somebody actually did some Quality
Assurance and so so I'm just against
that in principle so that I can't really
tell you if you want to go that route
I'm against it I never do it how you
would do it if you were somebody who
wanted to you'd have to ask somebody
else you know
alright I'm gonna call it a day thank
you everyone for joining me for the
nerve sort of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as it always is
here's what I'll say if you want to do
some of your own API practice you can
always peer to the game on handmade hero
org and try going ahead of me and seeing
if you can do some API cleanup that
anticipates the kind of cleanup that I
might do and then we can compare notes
so head over to handy here and check
that out if you want to we also have
some other good stuff on there there's a
watch page you can use to check the
schedule and it also shows the live
stream whenever the stream is live so
that's a pretty easy way to do it it's
also got the episode guide on there so
if want to search episodes and play old
episodes it's really great that's on
there check it out we also have the fun
the handmade fund which you can
contribute to if you want to support the
people who are doing good work like that
episode guide or like the handmade
Network forums that some people use to
discuss the series all that stuff some
handmade here at odhh or check it out
we've also got if you're interested in
Mali rocket in general and what we're
doing during the day we're not streaming
handmade here you can always click on
the little handmade hero head it shows
you our other projects in the works and
also our personal blogs and our company
blog so you can jump around through all
those and see what's up
we also of course have mailing lists
that you could subscribe to any time
there's usually a little subscribe that
you could put in there for our
newsletter which comes out very
infrequently it's only when we've
actually got something interesting to
announce and it always comes with a nice
little drawing from Anna as well so if
there's that there's a bonus to it which
is pretty Pleasant anyway that's all for
today I'll be back here for tomorrow
we're not gonna try a little more
cleanup of the API and then I think we
should be in good shape to kind of call
it on API cleanup generally what I then
I'd like to move on to is that
performance just just going in there and
taking a look at the the performance and
I think that's mostly about texture
management which we don't do and we need
to do it so packing those things into a
nice array I think is most of our
problem and then from there we could
take a look at anything more subtle that
we might want
that's it for today hope see you back
here tomorrow until then have fun
programming I'll see everyone on the
Internet
take it easy everybody