hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here of the show where we code a
complete game live on stream no engine
no libraries it's just us here and right
now we are we're kind of a little bit of
a of a wind and we did a bunch of work
to both make our renderer operate in
Sindhi and to make the renderer operate
multi-threaded which turned out to be
actually incredibly beneficial because
our renderer now runs 1920 by 1080 at 60
frames a second which was so far in a
way above what I was planning on making
sure we hit I was thinking we would just
try to maybe do a quarter of that at 30
frames a second so I was we were 8 times
faster right now than I was thinking our
target would be and I don't know what to
make of that other than God gosh
machines are fast I guess is what I'd
say but we do have now a bunch of sort
of cleanup work that we have to do
because we kind of were like pushing
through the renderer and doing
explorations there to try and get things
going but now we kind of want to
solidify the render into something that
actually renders the the game reliably
in the way that we want it to and so
there's a couple things that have to
happen for that and we kind of want to
go through and sort those out so we're
gonna do that that is what we're going
to do now and if you would like to join
me as we do that at home today is day
1:30 which means you can unpack day 1:29
source code and you will if you start
with that you will start exactly where I
am
right now so let's go ahead and open
things up here ok and so where we left
off yesterday we had gotten to the point
where we you know we have these sort of
splatty
things happening right these little
these little splat patterns that we were
making our ground tiles in and I noticed
that we had some seams in them and so
what I wanted to do now that we've got
the the renderer kind of working the way
that we expected to and stuff I would
like to go in
investigate to see if we can figure out
if there's anything in particular
happening with these seams that should
concern us and there's a couple reasons
why that's gonna be a little bit of look
it's gonna take some work for for
starters we don't actually know where
the seams are coming from there could be
tons of places where those seams are
coming from we could have a bug in our
source art where it doesn't have
completely smooth alpha right we could
have a bug in our code that actually
blitz these tiles to the screen such
that they're not meeting up perfectly
which would mean that like actually we
would be seamless if they were put into
a different location we could have a
problem with the way that we're doing
our splats such that when we produce a
ground tile we're not correctly layering
in the other splats from the other tiles
there's just a ton of places where that
that you know that problem could be
occurring right and so it's like I said
very difficult for us to kind of start
to think about what is actually going on
there so what I'd like to do is start
doing some experiments so I can try to
get you know just to see kind of like
you know basically taking the thing and
shaking it a little and seeing if we can
hear anything rattle around inside so
that I can see whether there is
something in particular that I should be
looking for or if I need to really just
do a completely general walkthrough
right and so the first thing that I'm
going to do to try and take the source
art out of the equation is I would like
to play around a little with what
sourced art is actually being used so
that we can see and there's something
that's kind of unusual I would say about
the patterns that I'm seeing here and I
want to point it out to you just so you
can kind of be on a similar page right
and the thing that I find that's pretty
unusual about what I'm seeing is like
you know when I look and you can kind of
see here I wonder if we should maybe
zoom in on this in fact I think maybe we
should so that we can see it a little
bit more carefully let me go ahead and
and
to make a little smaller version of our
window here so in the renderer now we
should be able to zoom in essentially
for free right because since we pass a
focal length in when we do our
perspective transform right we can in
fact I'll go ahead and put those here we
have a focal length right and we also
have a distance above-ground right so if
we want to we can go ahead and change
that distance above-ground right so you
know here it is at nine or whatever but
if we wanted to move closer we could
change it to five right and so we have
the ability to just kind of now that our
renderer actually works and does all
kinds of fancy things we can do stuff
like that and it's no big deal and so
you know zooming in on this and looking
at it right I have to say that even just
just looking at it right now and kind of
eyeballing it I would say that it it
looks to me a lot like this it looks to
me a lot like this is just a little bit
too low right it looks like it's a UH or
I should say or this is too high right
it looks to me like if this were just
moved down a little bit you would not
have this problem I'm gonna go ahead and
zoom in even further just so we can
really see what's going on there but I
don't know if you can kind of see I feel
like this right here if this removed
down in this line were to continue right
that this would kind of be in the
correct place a little bit lower and so
you know I don't really know for sure I
can't say for sure but I'm just looking
at it it feels a little bit like that's
the case to me and so maybe that is the
first thing that I will do to try and
look for the problem is see whether
these things are lining up properly and
so in order to do that the first thing
that I'm going to try is when we
actually render these ground tiles I'm
going to see what happens if I start
moving them to separating them
a little bit further from where they
should be according to what would line
up and when I do that I want to see what
I'm looking for is I want to see whether
I see but a crack between them or not
because I should see a crack form
between them when I separate them but if
they continue to sort of separate and
draw into the gap that I know that the
way that I'm drawing them they're
actually being drawn too close together
and they're overlapping each other which
is not I want them to abut right and so
that would you know just that alone
would definitely cause a scene so let's
go ahead and and look at where we're
calling that right so here's our ground
chunk rendering and when we do the
ground chunk rendering we're pushing it
on here and we're calling ground side in
meters which looks like exactly what we
would have expected it to be so that
that seems pretty good when we do the
push bitmap call so it feels like it
should be roughly the right thing in
fact you know what I could do that's
even easier than that what I could do is
start to multiply this by a value to
shrink them down right so let me go
ahead and multiply that by something to
shrink them down okay so now what I'm
going to do is I'm going to back them up
until they just exactly touch and then
I'm going to see you know is that number
actually the right is that actually at
1.0 or is it a little bit past 1.0 right
if that makes sense
all right so at nine nine nine nine
there they go they've joined right so it
looks like we're actually we're drawing
them at the right size right there's no
they are they are exactly a budding
there doesn't appear to be anything
funky going on with that right far as I
can tell
that looks totally fine so I I don't
think we have any problem with our pixel
fill here although there is one thing
that we don't quite do yet with our
pixel fill that we probably do need to
do for to be absolutely perfect but in
terms of visible artifacts I don't think
that's actually causing any you can see
this guy this flat right here for
example also has that seam and again if
I if I change it so that we just
separate them even a baby bit you can
see that there's nothing there so so
it's not it's not a case of that right
so now the the next thing that we have
to think about right and and I'm I'm
hoping that this has something to do
with it because we kind of need to go
address this in general anyway and that
is that you remember inside the renderer
we did not actually figure out what we
were going to do with with the tiling in
here and so this is kind of and in fact
now that I think about it there's a
there's a couple things that we have to
talk about here and in fact one of them
would cause the seam one of them will
definitely cause the seam so now that I
think about it we would have had a scene
from this even if we didn't have a scene
from anything else so this is kind of
interesting and we'll have to talk about
that in a second but if you remember
here right we had this formalized
texture boundaries thing and we never
really did that and so you know if you
think about what happens here if we're
not exactly sampling the textures 100%
properly then obviously we're going to
have a problem with that and we need to
figure out what we're going to do to
address that because the bilinear you
know implies a lot of stuff here
so let me go to the blackboard and
explain what I was just realizing there
because I feel like that's that's going
to be crucial to us getting us into a
state where it is perfectly seen three
seam free so there's day 1:30 and what I
want to talk about here is I want to
talk about bilinear filtering and the
implications it has for rendering things
and tiles
okay so here's what we currently have
right we currently have some tiles and
let's say for the sake of argument right
that these tiles don't have a lot of
pixels in them now we made our tiles
much bigger than this our tiles or
something like 256 by 256 but let's say
they were actually just 6x6 which is
what I happen to draw here right and so
right up abutting next to this guy right
is gonna be another right there's
another dude in here okay and so here's
one ground chunk and here's the next
ground chunk now there's a couple things
if I want these to actually be when we
draw them on the screen if I want these
to actually be correct there's a couple
things that have to be true the first
thing is that I have to properly draw
two all the pixels which we just checked
and the second thing is that the the
color values that are chosen for the
pixels that happen to be like right
around here have to line up exactly at
the edge with the same colors that would
be chosen here so like the pixels chosen
here have to be the exact you know they
have to be exactly on the function right
if the if the if the if the color values
if let's say this was grayscale or
something right and the color value
curve kind of looked like this we have
to make sure that we are like producing
pixels that are right along the color
values right and that there isn't some
discontinuous step that would be
perceptible at this boundary right the
example would be suppose you know if you
think of this more as a function or
something like this that you could
visualize a little bit more easily in 1d
you know suppose that I were to draw a
sine wave of grayscale values right in
there so you know actually I guess it
would look more like this right so if we
were if we were to have white here and
black down here you know if I were to
draw this in and we were to take samples
at these you know we were drawing these
in here or whatever we would want to
make sure that as we redrew this on to
the screen that we didn't have some
discontinuous jump across this boundary
that was different from the jump it was
here right so when it's filling
and it's going like okay you know I was
here and then I was here right if the
next one is over here you're gonna see
that is wrong right or if it's like
right here or something
you're gonna see that's wrong because
the person's expecting it to look like
it was at a different place right
because they'll see that discontinuity
it's a little hard to understand I guess
but you know when you're talking about
looking at something like a seam you
know you can imagine things a little
more dramatic right if a line was
passing through these pixels like this
you couldn't then have the line kind of
pass through like that over here right
because you'd see that little jump no
matter how tiny it is you know unless it
was it's essentially well below a pixel
you have that problem right and so the
reason that I bring all this up is
because we actually have a problem here
that we are not addressing right the
problem is that we have a function that
we're actually using to reconstruct
smooth colors from a bitmap right it's
our bilinear filtering function right so
our whole thing does this by linear
filter function where it blends whenever
you ask for like a color here it blends
between these four colors to produce
what the color is right and so think
about what that does on the edge here
okay what that needs to do on the edge
here is as you start drawing out to this
edge this edge actually needs to produce
the halfway point between this pixel and
this pixel but the problem is this pixel
exists in a different bitmap right
because here is this is tile B and this
is tile a so how is the renderer ever
going to know what color to produce out
here right it can't possibly know
hopefully you can see why that's a
little bit of a problem right
so we have a pretty significant problem
that we would have to that we have to
resolve their we have to find a way that
we can fix this this problem you know we
have to find a way that we can do our
sampling in a way that doesn't have this
issue and so what I think I might
propose because I don't think I can't
think of a lot of reasons not to do it
what I might propose for this game is
that instead of our texture mapping
being based on texture mapping an entire
rectangle like this what I'm thinking is
what if we were to base it on on texture
mapping a rectangle that had one pixels
worth of stuff around it right so what
we would actually do is we actually have
you know this here is so instead of if
we had a six pixel bitmap we would
actually interpret it right as four
pixels by four pixels with a one pixel
border all the way around it okay does
that make sense and so this one pixel
border everywhere around it stores what
the color would be in the adjoining
thing so that when we then draw another
one next to it right we just make sure
that it has in that border pixel a copy
of what the other person's pixel would
have been so that the function is
reconstructed properly hopefully that
makes some sense
so that's what I would propose this also
works out kind of nicely actually
now that I think about it the reason it
works out kind of nicely is in order to
get proper anti-aliasing for our sprites
we want a one pixel border around all of
them that is filled with nothing so that
it always bilinear is out two to zero so
that way we're always fetching into the
texture we don't have any hard borders
so I feel like you know that's probably
something that we would want anyway I'm
just thinking I mean I'm percent
positive I think that's high so we want
anyway so I feel like what we'll
probably do is we'll just go with this
so that's something we definitely have
to fix so since it's something we
definitely have to fix I'm just going to
go ahead and fix it so yeah so first
thing I'm going to do to fix that is
think about how we're doing our UVs here
right what I want to do is make it so
our UVs are at that first pixel when
they're at 0 0 right and so what that
means is that when we actually sample
into a texture when we have our 0 0 it's
actually not going to be at it's not
gonna be at the bottom corner rectangle
quickly yeah so let's go in here and
take a look at that right so here we go
in here here's our textile fetch right
you can see our fetching and when we do
the fetching we're doing enough of our
fetch XXY right and so what we want to
do here is we want to do in fact our
width
m2 and our height ma m2 I think is
actually kind of correct
that's that's actually getting pretty
close correct but let's just let's just
finish so what we want to do here is say
okay well yes so we want to say is the
zero zero coordinate of this would be
like right here so this would be the
zero zero texture coordinate right and
this is like a non you know this is this
is a value that no one would ever be
allowed to actually sample from it's
strictly there because we will be
sampling kind of back from it or
whatever so the zero zero value is
actually gonna sample you know starting
starting from this guy now I got to
think about this a little bit let's
think about this a little carefully here
because we also have another thing which
we need to think about which is the
pixels themselves right so let's suppose
we're bleeding this and we're bleeding
it you know to an actual place where
it's it's completely aligned so we're
doing this and we want to draw you know
we want to draw from here so if we were
to pass in a fill like so right this
would be whatever this pixel coordinate
is right and this would be whatever this
pixel coordinate is at the center so
let's say that we're talking about the
center of a pixel right and so if
something's one two three wide it would
be that big and if it's four wide right
it would be out to here right
one two three four like so so I have to
think about that one two three four
yes so if we assume that we're using
again that that's sort of if we assume
that we're using that fill rule where
we're basically saying if you know if
your maximum is less than the pixel then
you wouldn't fill it right so something
that's four wide would just barely not
fill this guy so I think that's a
pretty traditional way of doing pixel
centers I am NOT mr. pixel center so
someone who's a graphics expert can
correct me if I'm wrong but so if we
were to draw it to that pixel then
drawing to that pixel I guess what I'm
saying is we'd want that to map to here
right and then when we specify this guy
here right
I would guess it would map to there all
right so let me see what that actually
gives us so if this is a right then
we're sampling right in the middle of a
which is what I think we would want to
do again we have to kind of back this
out into the actual calculation in a
minute but we would want to set up right
in the middle of a here we would want a
sample right in the middle of B see B C
and D and that's good and this would
actually start to sample the in-between
of these two as it goes that way right
so I think that is correct because that
is what would guarantee a stability to
do both blitz so what you can see here
is there's like a point five offset
between these two things in some sense
right meaning that we want a sample
right in the middle of a which in the
middle of a is actually this is actually
zero zero in the bitmap sense right so
if our texture coordinates are 0 0 here
that's actually negative 0.5 negative
0.5 in pin texels right because the text
will look up has to use integers if that
makes sense so we want the integer 0 0
to line up right here
essentially so I think that's roughly
correct with the pixel centers so I'm
going to try to make that work that way
and I believe we're already doing pixel
centers this way if I'm not mistaken
meaning that the pixels coordinate is
right at its center that's already sort
of the way we were
conceptualizing it but yeah III guess I
haven't been 100% thorough on that we do
need to do something for our fill rule
right now I think we would fill these
pixels and we probably don't want to do
that but that's a separate issue anyway
although I guess the Alpha there would
be zero anyway doesn't matter
point being so if we're gonna do this we
first need to figure out how to adjust
these texture coordinates right and so
at a what we want to produce if if we
were in this scenario right the reason I
say that we want to bias it is because
remember we're gonna do a bilinear blend
right so we have memory right we've got
our memory out here that actually has
the texture things in it a b c d e f
right and if we fetch from zero zero
we're gonna get a right and if we fetch
from you know 0.5 0.5 we're still gonna
get a right but we're gonna grab some of
B F and E right we're gonna go halfway
to them right and that's not what we
actually wanted what we actually want
now is we want zero zero to sort of to
to map to and in between we want zero
zero to be the in between of whatever
these negative pixels are these border
pixels and a right that's what zero zero
should be it should actually be a blend
and point 5.5 of a Texel which again we
don't know if this is a 4x4 then what's
0.5 of that it's going to be point zero
soaps 0.5 of a Texel in UV coordinates
is going to be 0.5 divided by 4 right so
0.1 something if that makes sense
so in UV coordinates right we need to do
that we need to do that bias right we
need to bias it by that half Texel
that's just something we have to do
okay so let's take a look at how we
might do that it's kind of fun to have
this guy so giant he's huge
alright so what I want to do here is I
want to say okay first of all we'll deal
with the scaling a little bit later
we'll talk about scaling a little bit
later but what we want to do here before
we do our fetch right when we compute
the UV coordinates we want to be able to
bias the UV coordinates in Texel space
in order to get them into this correct
position here right so we want to bias
them in texture space we want to bias
them I think by negative 0.5 negative
0.5 right from where they were but we
also want to account for the phantom row
of pixels that's going to be there right
that we're not mapping so we really want
to add 0.5 0.5 because you know we're
starting here and we want to to bias by
0.5 point 5 so we want to to basically
say like we want to bias by 1 and then
subtract 0.5 right of a Texel so after
we've already multiplied by the width to
put us into textile space I think that's
what we want to do right now I don't
know if we actually have that value
loaded it seems like a value that we
might keep loaded let's see here for you
know for other reasons but I don't
actually remember it doesn't look like
we have 1/2 here I do not do not see it
so I'm going to go ahead and introduce
one I'm just gonna introduce 1/2 right
and that's just 0.5 and so what I want
to do now when we compute our fetch
coordinates again I want to go ahead and
and compute those I want to go ahead and
compute those with a bias and so in here
we basically have an mm add PS right and
I'm gonna bias them right
see here like so so this is sea bias
texture coordinates by plus or by minus
one texels plus 0.5 texels to produce
proper alignment or sampling all right
so if we assume that we do that right
and so we assume that we're going to
step it properly so that that is aligned
there then the other question I have is
how far we want it to actually go and
again I think we're actually doing that
properly already by saying the width
minus 2 because whatever the width of
this texture actually is right we want
to take out two of the pixels basically
right we want we want to not count two
rows and two columns right so I think
with minus two is actually the proper
thing that we would want to have happen
there
yeah so that seems reasonable oh I don't
know no no I did that I did that wrong
I'm sorry I take it back
I take it back we are trying to put
ourselves into pixel space so this is
not it's it's the other it's the other
way around right so we are here right
and we have this phantom row of pixels
so we want zero zero to map to one one
right right - point five point five so
it's actually just adding maybe maybe I
did do it correctly
I've confused my own self let me say it
one more time so this is the way it goes
sometimes so here's our phantom pixel in
the texture map we want zero zero to map
to here right which is in pixel chord in
texels in the bitmap it's point five
point five so I feel like I I just I
guess I did it sort of properly by
accident bias the texture coordinates to
start on the boundary between the
zeroeth and first pixels guess I'll say
this 0 0 &amp; 1 1 pixel right and I think
that is what does that right yeah I
think that is what does that so that
seems right to me
alright I wrote the right code or well
it's probably very premature to say
that's right I wrote some code and and
it was you know not what I expected it
to be alright anyway so all that did was
introduced that little bit of bias there
and so that shouldn't really change
anything all that much but now we at
least have that phantom set of pixels
and and that again we can sort of try to
debug later with little structure to
make sure that it's actually working
and then in terms of how big this
actually is in terms of how big it
actually is like I said before I feel
like it's still correct in terms of the
width - and hide - - so I think that was
actually right so that's my assumption
can't say for sure whether it's correct
but I think that's basically what we
wanted to do in terms of textile centers
alright so going back to the the chunk
rendering now what this implies right is
that we need essentially an apron when
we do Phil Gramm chunk we need an apron
of pixels around the thing to make sure
that it's always got whatever the
neighboring pixel is and so really all
that is is when we set up this
orthographic render right we just need
to make sure that our size is actually 2
pixels less in terms or I should say 2
pixels more than it would actually
otherwise be right because we're gonna
grinder into this but we need to capture
essentially a different area into that
so this is what we are you know
ostensibly capturing right but what we
actually want to do in terms of this is
how much you want to capture but we want
an extra apron around it right so what
we really want to do is say well not
quite we actually want the width here
right to be as if you added two pixels
to it
right and knowing how much to pixels is
in terms of meters again we would have
to know what the pixels 2 meters is here
which happens to be what we're actually
computing if that makes sense because
right here we've got our meters 2 pixels
right our original value is this so this
is like original meters 2 pixels and so
what we would want to do
let me actually draw out the map a lot
of finicky math today all right so we've
got a thing here that we're drawing in
right and it's 256 by 256 but what we
want to do is make sure that the actual
region that that occupies in world space
so you know this this region maps to
some to some area of the ground right
that's going to be drawn at 255 254 by
254 right so we need to do is make sure
that actually this 254 by 254 region
right 254 by 254 the Tiffany for my 24
region is what actually has to map to
the the Tiffany 4 by 254 region actually
needs to be the full size and meters
right so we do our meters to pixels I
guess all we really have to do is say Oh
pretend that you had 2 less pixels here
right and figure out whatever that you
know take what whatever you thought you
were going to cover and cover 2 pixels
less than that right and I think that
will give us that that apron around the
edge right so I got actually we've run
it to see what that will actually do
since grand chunks don't get redone of
course now I don't remember where the
seam was let's go down to where the seam
was there it is and hey look the seam is
gone what do you know
that was surprisingly easy
a lot of finicky math there where you
have to kind of think it through but
then it ends up being to love that we
added point five in one place and we
subtracted two in another and suddenly
all the seams are gone ladies and
gentlemen you know that is something
that's so satisfying when you're
programming when you're just like okay I
thought it through I knew what was
supposed to happen I figured out a
problem and I corrected it and it
actually worked when you did it when you
when you thought it through right just
super satisfying so there we go
I it looks like we got rid of a fair bit
of the seeming I don't know if we've got
rid of all of it it's a little hard to
tell now because again some of that is
it's hard to say whether it's art or not
and that kind of looks like that's
probably art but it's really hard to say
so but the hard seams that I was seeing
before are now gone and so that's at
least a good thing and like so like
something like that right there I can't
quite tell if that's something that
would that is a reasonable or
unreasonable in terms of seeming so we I
think we might still have you know
something that maybe isn't necessarily
about the sampling boundary but that is
producing some harder seams than we
might want right just trying to look
around so if I turn off the red green
stuff here that we were using are kind
of like pink dye if you will
ahead and do this here we go
yeah so it looks pretty much like what
we would expect now now again in order
to make a good ground we're gonna want
to do something other than completely
random splatting so we certainly aren't
done with our ground generation by any
stretch of the imagination oh hey look
there's a little like area that didn't
get filled there speaking of other
reasons why you don't want to use pure
random so yeah so we got so we've got
work to do on a ground generation but
that's like more of a world generation
time thing so but it's definitely
looking a lot more seemed free we've
gotten rid of the systematic texture
same problem that we were having there
and so you can kind of see like that I'm
not sure if that's an art seam or not
right look I don't know exactly what
that looks like so that's a little bit
hard to tell what exactly the art has in
it and what it doesn't so that's that's
a little bit of an issue but yeah anyway
that's looking good and so I'm happy
that we got rid of our primary rendering
artifact there so yes so at the moment
though of course we have another problem
which is that our ground chunks also
aren't sorted so we're seeing the
background chunks right now sort of the
front ones which makes it pretty darn
trippy to look at right but but that's
just the way it goes so these guys
that's that's looking nice I'm liking
that a lot and now we've got our our
pixels and texels corresponding a little
bit more what I wanted them to
correspond s so it's and that also by
the way what I what I showed there is as
close as I remember it the OpenGL pixel
10 Texel standard so you know when we
render it on hardware it should look the
same pixel what pixel to pixel unless I
messed something up but that was that's
as I remember the closest I remembered
to it
so yeah I don't know how are you feeling
about this I don't even know what I
probably should be doing right now to be
completely honest with you because I'm
wondering at this point you know we're
zipping around here and we're generating
these ground chunks so nicely I mean if
that just this is so cool like this is
this is getting to be a real engine
people it's doing all sorts of fancy
things here anyway if I change to using
a very high off the ground camera what
is happening
oh right yes okay well that's what I
should be doing now now we know so right
so the thing that I need to do is
everybody for their queries actually
uses what this value is like the
distance you know above ground for the
queries for like getting the unprojected
get the camera rectangle at distance and
that stuff so that was why you couldn't
use that one for debugging and you have
to change if you want to use the debug
camera you have to use in the in the get
render entity basis you have to do this
right so that way it still reports the
camera to the game as if it wasn't that
right but there it goes
so yeah so that was a little bit of a
stupidity on my part but what are you
gonna do anyway so if we take a look at
what's going on here right you can kind
of see how cool this is already it's
just on-demand generating these guys
right and so you know one one thing that
we could plausibly think about doing now
and I don't know if this is the best
possible use of our of our time right
but we only got seven now I got 17
minutes left because we started 10
minutes late is we get that little kick
up right when we go to generate those
ground chunks now part of that is just
because we're massively over filling on
the ground chunks really we don't need
to do a hundred splats to generate a
ground chunk if we were doing a more
sane generation pattern we would need
far fewer so some of it you know we
could take care of that way but since we
just wrote that threading code it sort
of begs the question should we
potentially just have the chunk filling
happening on another thread right
because now we know that we've got you
know a thread system we could have it
just sit there and actually have some
other thread that's working on filling
those ground trunks and you know I don't
know that's that's certainly something
we could think about doing and it might
be fun because we've got that hiccup and
that hiccup is annoying right you don't
want that in the game and so you know
it's a question of how do we
to deal with it it's pretty cool how
this works I'm really enjoying this for
whatever reason I think it's just kind
of fun when you get into a nice
situation where you're like generating
things on demand because then it opens
up just a lot of possibilities for us
down the road with whatever we really
want to do in terms of how we draw the
ground we just have a lot of leeway
there now because since it's all
generated on demand we can do all sorts
of things and basically create a
completely unique ground texture
everywhere in the world that that has
whatever sorts of stuff we want in it
you know and it can use the underlying
geometry to do whatever kinds of
fanciness we want it to do so yeah maybe
it's really stupid idea but we could
certainly look at doing that where we
fill the ground chunk on a separate
thread I have to think about how we
would want to do that exactly there's a
couple different things and so you know
maybe it's a good idea to start doing
that because we'd have to think about it
in terms of queue work and how we would
want it to happen so maybe that is a
useful thing for us to do I'm not
entirely certain I guess the other thing
no I mean yeah you know just thinking
about that maybe it is just good because
we're gonna have to do it eventually
we're gonna have to deal with this sort
of thing eventually the other thing we
could do is start playing with the asset
loading I suppose that's the other
threading sort of thing we could do if
we were going to go down that route but
so if we look at how this thing is
working here where we've got the tiled
render group to output stuff uh what we
would have to start doing is
partitioning our threads into stuff
that's doing background work and stuff
that's doing foreground work right and
so you know what we probably want to do
like we already kind of set up to this
to have a foreground thread in a
background sorry a foreground crew in a
back
q right we have where is it where is our
Q here we go
so we have our Q's here and we have our
high priority Q you know we could have a
low priority Q right and we could just
say that you know there's stuff that
goes on the low priority Q will kind of
like happen maybe like only one thread
is dedicated to servicing the low
priority Q or something like this right
I don't really know but let's just say
like I said I don't know I don't even
know why I'm doing this right now I just
felt like maybe we should so we'll just
say like low Q and maybe this needs to
be hyper - Q right whipper - Q so here
we go we should probably get rid of this
at some point I don't even know why
that's there right so here we go we've
got high priority queue and we've got
low priority queue when we go through
and we create these things here I want
to I guess I probably want this to be
I'm just compression oriented
programming like I always say I
basically just want something that's
going to create one of these queues so
there's a platform work queue and I'm
gonna create it right and so make queue
or something
maybe I'll just pass it in say you know
went through to make queue right and all
that's gonna do is just this right it's
just gonna do this this stuff that we
were doing for the queue and it'll take
with it what the thread count should be
for that queue and
I'm trying to decide whether I want this
tool to steal threads or not well we'll
leave that for later
so anyway for right now we'll leave them
completely segregated and we'll see
whether we want to do it in a little bit
of a fancier fashion so primarily the
thing that I'm concerned about the
reason that I'm segregating these
because what we could do is we could
make it the other way we could do it is
make it so that basically the there's a
set of threads waiting and those threads
all just pull off of the high priority
queue if something's there or the low
priority queue if something's not on the
high party cue the problem with that is
that if we have things that take a long
time on the low priority queue they will
starve out the high priority queue
potentially and ruin our performance so
I am gonna keep them segregated for a
little bit and you know if we decide
that we want to change that we always
can't change that it's not a big deal
the platform code has I mean the the
game code doesn't really know what we're
doing down in here so we can feel free
to tweak it as we see fit right as
things go so here's the thread count is
gonna come from here now and we'll put
this in here so we'll have the thread
info what wait what is thread info even
do Oh
thread info thread info is just the
thing that we pass and what is in the
thread info nothing except the logical
thread index and a queue so I'm gonna
change that since the logical thread
index isn't even used at this point I'm
just gonna go ahead and say that this
platform work queue that is what
actually gets passed here so here's the
queue so we don't actually need any of
this anymore at least not for the moment
so that goes away entirely goodbye and
then we don't care about this at all so
now we have the thread count we don't
care about this that's not relevant at
all you don't care about any of this and
all we do here is instead of info we
just passed the cue pointer
and what is else is a cue have in it
that might need to be initialized I
think nothing they all initialize to
zero right yeah so they are all clear to
zero so that's all fine and dandy so we
make two cues here and then what we need
to do is we need to actually initialize
them right high priority queue low
priority queue and
we don't actually really need to clear
those to zero do we because we don't
actually you do we actually ever care no
we don't
so actually we could actually just do
this a little bit differently we could
do it this way where instead we just say
oh yeah you know the queue gets
initialized here like so just to all
zeros but not that giant entry list of
things because that way we don't just
spend a bunch of time clearing for no
reason so we can initialize those we
make the threads we kick off the threads
and now we've got a queue right and so
that should be fine let's go ahead and
compile that this has got to be an arrow
and that's got to take an address so
then what we could say is like oh yeah
okay so you know instead the high
priority queue is gonna be six threads
in the low pair to queue is gonna be two
threads or something like that right and
then when we run it off we go
seems fine right and everyone's happy
and so now we've got another cue that
can have some stuff in it the work can
be done and let's just go ahead and and
make that happen
so if we go in here now to handmade CPP
and I take a look at Phil ground chunk
right when we do a tiled render group to
output what we want to do is now instead
of passing the render queue we want to
do like the low priority queue right so
the trans State when that takes the
render queue it's going to take the low
priority queue as well Oh prairie queue
priority queue probably should just call
that the hyper
- I don't know why I called it the
render queue doesn't even make any sense
really it's not like you could couldn't
use it for something else
high priority queue low priority queue
um yeah so what that that i think i
think is really all we would need to do
to get things started but we will have
obviously well you know and i'm just
gonna do it and then I'll show you the
problem that we're gonna have which is
kind of I don't know what it'll actually
do I'm kind of interested to know but
anyway so we have a couple things we
have to do here first of all our render
targets have to be aligned that was one
of our requirements for them right and
so one of the things that we have to do
here is when we actually allocate these
ground chunks they're going to have to
be aligned right and so when we do our
our initial ground chunk creation right
in here when we do make empty bitmap
that's that's got to actually give us an
aligned bitmap right because everything
needs to be aligned to those two there
Cindy boundaries to the 16 byte
boundaries so in ground buffer bitmap I
have two in fact
why is that working I guess it just
happens to be now that I think about it
we had to do that before that has
nothing to do with the threading that's
just because the renderer is accelerated
right so that should have been already a
problem let's see what what does it make
empty bitmap doing when it allocates
this stuff it just does a push sighs
yeah it just it just goes ahead and does
a push sighs but it never actually
ensures that it's aligned right which is
kind of ridiculous so okay that's a
little odd
one has to admit that it's a little odd
right
are we admitting that has anyone else
admit I don't know if anyone's made that
I hope you're admitting it but I don't
know if you are so well what I would
like to do here is I would like this to
start passing alignment so I guess maybe
yeah I guess I guess we'll stick with
the thread thing but that's a pretty big
to-do item so I don't know how we want
to mark off this is a to-do item
normally I have a little pen and paper
here maybe I will just use a pen and
paper which I have here and start that
for handmade hero so let's see what
we've got here I'm gonna write down our
first official to-do item on the paper
which is push size alignment and ground
chunk allocation us but it's working
properly because I guess things just
happen to be 16 by the line so far and
we just didn't hit that which is odd
computers are complex sometimes things
just go your way and you look into
something that should have been broken
and just isn't but anyway so yeah what I
want to do now is I need to kick off
rendering on these guys right and so if
you remember the way that we could do
this before we have a way to push things
on a cue right we just do platform hat
entry like so and that just is one of
these guys it's one of these do tiled
render work things and so what I'm going
to do temporarily and this is not a
really a long-term solution here and it
actually does also suggest there's
probably one other thing we want to do
to our queue but we'll get to that later
is we've got a fill ground chunk well I
guess it's actually just fill ground
chunk see here yeah Ram chunk where is
Phil Gramm shucks Phil Gramm chunk there
we go so what we want to do here is we
want to make the stuff that happens
inside phil gramm chunk
we want that to be callable from the
work you write and so what we need to do
there all of this stuff is pretty much
wrote right for the most part
right it just doesn't begin temporary
memory for I guess for the render buffer
yeah then it just does arena allocation
and the arena allocation is just for
that render group right yeah so I think
really the primary thing that we would
need to do here is we just need to have
a way of kicking this off so that I
guess I won't try to do that we're not
gonna fit that all into two minutes I
mean maybe I could but I wouldn't be
able to talk at all during the entire
time because that actually gets into
also extending our temporary memory
stuff to be a little bit more a little
more flexible well yeah that's mostly
what we'd have to do in order to do the
top render work is we'd have to put that
in here so I'll go ahead and and just
comment this out and maybe we'll do that
we'll do that soon why did I paste that
that's not what I wanted to do there
what just happened wait a minute
oh right cuz that's calling the
low-priority kid that I did not actually
mean to do let's put that back on there
wait a minute how is this possible
you're telling me just because I happen
to mention that the thing is now it is
not a line it's actually complaining
about the alignment just now that can't
be true like I just said I only just
said oh wait this isn't aligned why was
that working before and now it actually
is not working how is that even how how
does that happen
I mean seriously people and you know
what's probably hilarious about that let
me see if I'm actually right
man that is hysterical okay this has
been a great hand made hero so did you
guys catch what happens there so like I
said we shouldn't have been able to
render the ground chunks with our
renderer because it should have been
unaligned but it just so happened that
it was on a 16 byte boundary anyway as I
was saying that I happen to be adding
the low priority queue the low priority
queue is on the transient state
structure which happens to be in the
same place right that's in the memory
arena the transient arena that happens
to be where we are allocating our ground
chunks from so by adding another eight
byte pointer that pushed it out of
alignment to 16 - right so we could just
add if we wanted to right we could add
one more 8 byte pad to the structure and
that would force all our ground chunks
into alignment so I guess now that I
think about it it's not that odd because
since all of our stuff is really gonna
be aligned to eight bytes probably since
we're compiling in 64-bit mode we had a
50-50 chance that our ground chokes
would be aligned right oh that's great
that's definitely where I'm ending it
and going the QA because that is
hilarious I love that that's so great
let's go to the Q and the a if you have
questions please put Q colon in front of
them so I will see them how are you
doing out there
what's going on
girl and uh boom good stream today
sometimes it goes really great yes
sometimes you luck out and sometimes you
don't right and that's programming and
the stream captures that right the
stream captures days when when you get
something to eat and it's cool and the
stream also captions days when you're
just staring something going what is
going on here so the ground chunks
rendered differently every time you go
upstairs and come back down no they
don't it's the same there based on their
coordinates in the world so they're
always exactly the same when you come
back to a region that's obviously what
we want because we want to look familiar
right because I mean we're just
splatting things in there really milling
that right now but what we're going to
do eventually is is be thoughtful about
how we compose that ground texture so
that it looks meaningful to the player
like whatever the region is that we're
on Abner coin break could you can you
address the recurring question the
stream isn't about making games I'm
tired of trying to explain what the
stream is about so the stream is about
making games it's about making games
from scratch there are lots of streams
that are about how to load up unity and
like drop some entities in but you know
I mean that's really not all that
difficult and so what this stream is
supposed to do is to teach like how
unity was built right because obviously
people need to be able to make game
engines otherwise we wouldn't have any
game engines like Unreal Engine or the
engine or the crisis engine or the
source engine or countless of the custom
engines that are out there for you know
specific games I don't know like
whatever Grand Theft Auto five uses the
Frostbite engine so this stream is about
the whole process and we will do the the
kinds of stuff later on where you know
once we're done with engine work we'll
do work on you know game stuff that
looks a lot more like just working on
you know what you might see if you were
using a store-bought engine but saying
that working making an actual game from
scratch isn't about making games is is
really strange because if you if there
weren't people who knew how to do all
the things that I'm talking about on the
stream here you would know nobody would
be able to make any games right I mean
all of this stuff is actually required
to make a game and the only reason that
you don't have to know it all is because
you can go license something that might
do some of it for you
but of course if you do that you also
put yourself at a pretty significant
disadvantage because everyone else
that's the exact same tool you do right
so you're never gonna be able to do
anything technologically to
differentiate yourself from another game
that also uses unity or that also uses
Unreal Engine 4 because guess what
that's all you got so it's important to
know these things I think in general a
few if you care a lot about game
development I think you should know
these things
because they're important right and they
they have a lot to bear on they have a
lot to do with the future of game
development right they have a lot to do
with who will make the engines of the
future who will make technological
advances nobody who doesn't know the
stuff that I'm teaching on handmade hero
is ever gonna make a significant engine
advancement right because anyone who can
do something beyond what we're currently
doing with things like unity and unreal
they all are gonna know all this stuff
right this is like you know handmade
hero is like the compulsories for an
engine developer you should be able to
do absolutely everything in here if
you're gonna be on an engine team right
and and I don't think that's a any kind
of extraordinary statement like I feel
like any good engine program I know if I
was like would you feel comfortable
making handmade here from scratch they
would be like certainly right you know
of course and so I feel like you know
are they gonna do it exactly the same
way I do know because every programmer
has a different style right but they
would be able to achieve the results how
long have you worked on this project a
hundred and thirty hours ish something
like that so so that's three so three
weeks of programming time if we were
working for 40 hour weeks it would be
three weeks so we're three week three
work weeks into the project roughly a
little more than that
how are you deciding what gets cute or
not on high versus low so the idea is
that anything that needs to be computed
this frame is a high priority item and
anything that could be computed sort of
in across a couple frames is going to be
low how are you going to implement
seamless tiles with what yangshin lee
creates so that is what we're doing here
we are taking artwork that she made and
we're splatting it in to create seamless
tiles
she made the splats now we haven't
actually done the work to create useful
things out of the splats we're just
randomly throwing them on there so
that's not particular useful but when
I'm saving how we would do more logical
creation of stuff underneath with the
splats until we get to world creation I
don't see any object-oriented patterns
are using object orientation no we are
not
I assume the yellow cyan magenta squares
are for debugging what do they represent
yes so we're in the camera zoomed out
mode here right and so if we if we
change to to actually viewing the game
right
you know this is what it would actually
look like and you can kind of see that
the yellow square is right around the
border if that makes sense
and so what the squares are for is when
we want to do some debugging work and we
take a look out here this yellow square
represents what the player will see on
the screen this cyan square represents
the simulation boundaries so we're
simulating everything in this region so
that things that are off-screen can
still like walk on screen and stuff and
the purple boundary is the region where
we consider things so that stuff in this
region as it moves outside might hit
something in here but these are not
actively simulated if that makes sense
so yeah so that's that's basically what
we're trying to do with those with those
regions and they'll come into play more
later when we're actually working on the
game game part of the game and not the
engine because you know again when
there's stuff like a eyes that have to
walk around or whatever it's important
to make sure that we can see that
they're properly being simulated out
here when they're not on screen
you always say we who is we well it's me
and everyone on the chat
looking for some looking for some on
topic questions you say three work weeks
but do you feel like you can maintain
this pace eight hours a day well okay
obviously yes because when I'm normally
programming I don't have to explain it
all what I'm doing it so like yeah maybe
it would be hard to program for eight
hours straight every day but the amount
of programming I do on the stream would
not take me an hour it would take me
like 15 minutes right a lot of the time
sometimes you know if I have to think
something if there's something I have to
think through then maybe that takes the
same amount of time because I'm going to
draw up like explaining it on the
blackboard is the same as me working it
on a piece of paper so that part math
I'll be okay but the vast majority of
things that I explain to things I
already know one could just type in and
so those I take a massive hit on the
stream so so I think I think it's
totally fair to say that it Maps
basically to work hours because normally
I'm Way faster at coding than what you
see on the stream because on the stream
I have to explain it and I can't
concentrate not because I have to talk
to so I'm also at a disadvantage in
terms of remembering where everything is
and I work full time to the day normally
so I'm also have to page in this code
since it's not the code that I normally
work out so yeah I think it's very fair
to say
it seems like the ground checks are only
getting generated when they would
actually be visible not before when you
get the ground check into low partic you
will empty ground be visible for one or
two frames while they're being generated
yeah so what I what we will want to do
once we have them generated is we'll
want to sort of see what our typical
event horizon is for generating ground
chunks and we'll want to cue them up a
little early which is pretty easy right
we just use a slightly bigger region
do you think at the end near end someone
like John blow would be interested in
making a game at the handmade hero
engine in a similar format to see how
the game design phase evolves the engine
I don't know you'd have to ask him
alright I think that's it for on-topic
questions am I correct about that I
think
anyone anyone No looks okay alright well
we will go ahead and wrap things up then
let's go ahead and save everything out
here there we go close alright thank you
for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along with code at home
you can always go to handmade here at
Oregon pre-order the game and it comes
with a source code so you can download
it every night after I'm done here I
upload it and then you can download it
and it's all good so if you want to play
around with it at home that's an easy
way to do it you can also go to the our
forums page if you have questions and
you can ask questions on the forum you
can also go to there's like an annotated
episode guide and there is a like a
ports page and a resources page there's
all kinds of stuff on there that you
might want to check out we also have a
patreon page if you want to support the
video series it's always much
appreciated and we have a tweet bot that
tweets the schedule at you if you're
trying to catch the series live you can
subscribe to the to the the Twitter feed
and it'll tell you whenever it's going
live so that's about yet we are off
tomorrow as I will not be here tomorrow
evening so we're off tomorrow but we
will be back here on Monday so I hope to
see you all then when we'll go ahead and
start playing with that low priority
queue and see if we can't get our grand
chunks to move off of the main thread so
we won't have those hiccups which would
be good all right thanks everyone and I
will see you tomorrow oh no I won't I
will see you Monday all right take it
easy everyone and have a good weekend I
suppose well I well since we're in
America see you tomorrow have a good
weekend and I'll see you on Monday