hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream yesterday we worked out
some information about sorting that we
think will help us sort of put well I
guess I should say it's our first
attempt at putting to bed our
long-standing sort of Z situation that
we wanted to clear up before we start
the regular game code and I don't really
know if we've completely solved the
problem or not but we came up with you
know sort of one plausible sorting
criteria that might work and there's two
things about it we don't know one is we
don't 100% know like I don't know that I
definitively proved that it's always
gonna be the correct sort for us I think
I you know was properly thinking through
the cases that we're likely to encounter
but you know maybe there are cases that
we are definitely going to encounter
with our sprites that I just didn't
think of right so that's one possibility
where we can't say for sure that we
really know that it works the other
possibility is is less about the sorting
criteria and more about the sort that
needs to be implied with a sorting
criteria I think it might be possible at
least have a feeling that it could be a
plausible case that we can produce a a
non topological result with our sorts
meaning the sort criteria that we picked
is not guaranteed to produce a total or
partial ordering that's consistent and
so running a regular sort routine on it
like merge sort may not actually be able
to properly resolve the sorting even
though our rule is sound it may turn out
violating that and it's pretty easy for
us to verify that fact so that's kind of
actually a something we might want to do
right because what we could easily do is
run an N squared algorithm after the
sort only in a special debugging
scenario that goes and compares every
sprite with every other sprite via our
sorting rule and alerts us if any of
them returned the
wrong sort order right so we do our sort
with our mergesort then we compare every
pair in the N squared way and go are any
of these sorts long in this list and if
they are then we know that we did in
fact hit that case where we produced a
non topological or a thing that cannot
whose orderings cannot be properly
solved by by a regular straightforward
sorting routine and if that's the case
then again that's not that's really not
a death a death knell for us at all that
just means that we would have to
escalate our solve from a regular sort
to something a little bit more graph
theoretic like the kind that Andrew
Russell talked about in the blog post
that I showed yesterday that he wrote
specifically for us which was very nice
of him about how he was trying to do
sorting on River City ransom underground
where he just decided that because of
the way that their sprites were there
was no choice but to use a semantic
understanding of what was in front of
what which leads to a clearly non
sortable set it's a it's a set that has
to be sorted as a graph and so we might
be in that category we don't know yet if
we are it's not the end of the world it
just means we'll do a graph sort and
that's totally fine but we certainly
don't want to do a graph sort if we
don't have to because a graph sort will
probably be slower than a straight
forward merge sort I don't know that
that's necessarily true because we
haven't really looked at it but you know
it's probably the case that we would
want to stick with being able to do a
more straightforward sort if we can so
that's just what we're doing so far and
then we'll see as we get a little
further into it whether it really
whether we hit either of those two cases
we should be able to see that once we
start testing it out in some real-world
scenarios does it do sorting the way
that we think it should or are we
running into problems where it's just
not producing the kind of source that we
think should be happening so let's go
ahead and open up here open up so one of
the things that's true is we got you
know we we wrote the sorts and they're
compiling but as you
see if we run the program it's not it's
not actually running the sort right now
so nobody calls the sort we wrote the
sort but it's not it's not actually
being called so it's still just running
the old thing which isn't what we wanted
all and is doing some old stuff as well
so today's objective really since the
sorts already done except for one thing
I think Steven well quarter Tron I think
on the on the on the chat he pointed out
something that is a mistake I forgot to
flip the the signs here when we did both
Z sprites what I wanted to do was say
you know if the wyman is not equal to
the the Y max I think well actually you
know what he was he was tweeting at me
that there was a problem here but I
don't know if that's true if they're
both Z Z sprites are ones that have a
bound so I don't know I think this is
actually correct if this is not equal to
that and this is not equal to that then
they're both Z sprites otherwise one of
them's Izzie's right and the other one
isn't right I'm pretty sure that's the
case but yeah I could be wrong about
that seems right to me anyway I'll let
you guys figure out whether it is or it
isn't in the chat and then we can always
go from there
what's going on how come I can't whoa
what's going on here my my keyboard is
messed up there we go all right so
here's our merge sort that does the
sorting that we actually wanted to have
done and what you can see here is it
takes this sort sprite bound in now
there are some things about this that
are kind of interesting and I don't
actually know how much we want to take
advantage of this but it's something to
think about here so in addition to the Y
min the y max the Z and the and the Z
max we've got this the index which is
the thing that we were going to be
drawing what occurred to me is that the
Z values we could insert fake planes
essentially that are there to be our
layer dividers and what we could do
potentially is
actually get sorting into layers for
free out of this I think because if you
think about what's gonna happen with
this sprite sorting we're gonna end up
sorting by Z as you know as a criteria
for for the sort in addition to
everything else and if we have a
situation where where we had something
with infinite Y bounds right then it
would always sort by Z so if we stuck in
a giant infinite plane essentially in
between each layer that would
automatically sort everything below it
or above it so intellect sort of two
groups and we would know as we retired
things we would get to those little
plane markers as we were retiring render
instructions right so that's just
something to think about and it kind of
seems like the sort of thing we might we
might care about if we go back up here
and take a look at the sort entry
information and then we look at the sort
sprite down what we want to do here is
sort entries we probably want to leave
because we were sorting other things
right we were using the sort for example
to display the top performance eaters on
our profile so we want to leave this
case in here right we want this to still
be active and so I'm not going to touch
that case but what I am going to do is
probably turn the whole renderer over
into using sprite bound sorting so that
now we can start to push things into it
that will actually use that information
and so the challenge here is not going
to be doing that because that's not
going to take very long and you'll think
it's really just a case of swapping them
out the problem is that we don't have a
lot of this information at the immediate
moment and so we're gonna have to do is
actually start going in and figuring out
where is that information going to come
from and obviously for our straight
up-and-down cards you know what do one
of the things that I think we luck out
on by if we can get away with this sort
criteria one of the things that you can
notice here is that well for our
straight up-and-down cards we don't
really think we need a lot of
information about the Y bounds so we can
just ignore the Y bounds entirely
and leave them as straight up and down
cards that's what the sort criteria
loves to do so hopefully the only things
we really need to mark up are these
ground these like flat tiles and those
we actually kind of do have an idea of
what their bounds are because since they
are ground tiles we know they take up
one ground tiles worth of space which
gives us what their actual Y extents
should be so hopefully if we're lucky
getting this information into the
renderer won't be particularly onerous
because we will be able to do some
fairly straightforward stuff here I hope
I don't really know but that's my help
all right
ok so let's get started on this see
where we get to so we've got our render
group and mainly what happens here is
when our render group pushes things on I
believe that you know first of all the
sort key information when we're doing an
entity basis P result stuff that's gonna
kind of that's gonna have to change a
little bit because now we don't sort of
care about the sort k anymore we really
just care about what the Z the max Z
value is and that's a value that's gonna
get transformed in probably I don't know
is it I guess that value doesn't really
have to get transformed all that much it
just has to get put relative to the
camera I think is the only thing that we
really care about there well actually
even that's not true because since
there's nothing but really we can just
use I think the Z value straight up so
we may be able to get away with not
really having to do anything with the
sort keys here at all I don't know if
that's true don't quote me on that but
if we're really lucky we may be able to
excise sort keys entirely from the empty
and the basis results that would be
really lucky let's not push push our
luck and say that it's going to be true
let's just say that would be great if it
happened in the meantime let's focus on
what's actually known here which is that
in our code before where we were sort of
doing this stuff where we're pushing in
these sort of sort key
entries what we're gonna do now is just
change that and I'll just go ahead and
look for that here where is our swear is
our sword entries I thought they were in
here but I guess they're not at the
moment at render group sort entries
looks like we don't talk about those as
many places as I thought we did but yeah
you can kind of see them happening here
so anyway here is where we actually push
our render element and everywhere that
we're talking about a sword entry in
here we really want to now talk about
one of these alternate kinds here that
we have the sort spray pound right and
so what I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna
take this piece of code here I'm gonna
say everywhere you were talking ass
sprayed entry let's talk about a sort
spray ban instead okay so now we've
essentially got the same thing we're
pushing sort sprite baths down from the
top but a little bit bigger there were
twice as big but that's it so it's not
too bit it's not too bad but it you know
obviously not great at time expands like
that's not fabulous but what I'm gonna
do so now that we have that information
there when we push this information when
we do a push render element we're gonna
actually need to push in what we think
the sprite bound actually should be and
so that's the real place where this gets
a little trickier right so here's our
sort sprite bound it's going to come in
here and that needs to get written into
the buffer for that future sorting so
instead of sort entry sort key equalling
sort key in this case and index equals
command well actually I guess yeah now
think about it we don't need to copy the
index part so I don't know what we want
to do here I don't know if we want these
guys to be well let's do it this way and
I don't know I don't really want I don't
love the fact that this is something
that's got an additional element to it
that doesn't actually need to be passed
in right because you can see that this
index here is going to get set
inside the push routine because it's the
thing that knows where the actual entry
is right and so that index is telling
you the offset into the push buffer
where the actual operation goes but if
we take a look at the sort key side of
things I was saying I wanted to make it
so that I could just pass in the entire
bundle and so the question is do we want
to pass in this
wimon WiMAX zmax thing as some kind of a
separate sort of value it and that would
look like this that would just be like
okay
sprite bound or something like this and
sprite bound would have you know these
three values in it and then this would
just have the sprite bound in it as a
separate thing right or something like
this that would be the value and and in
fact I guess we could say that that's
the sort key in some sense if that makes
sense right
so you know we do passing the sort key
we still set the sort key but now the
sort key is the sprite bound thing and
off we go now if that's the case then
that means in here like every time we
were sort of looking at these particular
things when we do sort sprite bound a
and sort sprint been B here what we're
really talking about now is well you
really don't need the indices so
actually when you're doing is in front
of you're talking about just passing
those two things separately and then
when we're doing those is in front ups
here we would just say like oh you know
what why don't you pass the sort key
instead and really also similarly this
could be made clearer to the optimizer
probably by just saying hey those are
objects you don't have to worry about
aliasing you don't have to worry about
writing to them now it should have been
able to figure that out itself but I
don't know sometimes I like to turn
things into pass by value just so the
optimizer knows what's going on here
I you know it just avoids any
possibility of confusion when it does
that substitution of the in line I
always get a little nervous about it
because I think it slows us down in
debug mode but you don't love but you
know that's just that's just the
realities oh people don't care about the
game industry when they make their
compiler alright so anyway all you need
to do is just pass the sort keys there
and there's one more call down here to
it right there's two cases where we care
there's the merge part and the part
where we're actually doing just two
entries so if I go ahead and pass the
sort key in both cases then I think I'm
good to go now obviously we've got a
problem in our outer code which is that
now that you know ostensibly we've
effectively
you know we've made it so that now all
we have to do is go out to the render
code and tell it to use the other sort
and we're good to go but obviously we
kind of have a problem here where now
all of the code that was previously
calling these guys and it was passing in
you know some notion of a sort key it's
always wrong right we now need to give
it more information about what these
values actually were supposed to be and
so when we do a push bitmap call if you
think about it we really now don't have
any idea what those values should
actually be and that makes things a
little tricky it means we kind of have
to go like alright I you know what kind
of bitmap was this and all that sort of
stuff
we have whether or not the thing is
upright set in the object transform so
that is something and we could probably
try to figure out something like what
the min and Max values of certain
elements are based on the sprite size
but yeah it's a little hard to say let's
think about this for one second so we I
mean in theory what we could do and I
don't know if this will work properly
but in theory what we could do is say
use that object transforms upright
versus not upright use that to determine
how to interpret the bounds of the
bitmap and then use those bounds as just
straight-up modifications on the values
I don't know if that's good enough like
I don't know if that's gonna work but
maybe that's what I'll try and for the
sort Emel to see what happens you know
sometimes you just cross your fingers
and and try something and then you let
what actually happens inform you as to
whether that was something that's
workable or not right okay so what I do
know is that would let's start with the
obvious stuff which is that now we've
got this this notion of the sort key is
is it's just done right because we don't
we know one thing we know for sure is we
can yank all the existing sort key stuff
straight out of here
because even if we need to do some other
computations this ain't it right so we
know that this all goes goes bye-bye
right
so that's gone and so we can eliminate
all that and let that guide us with now
how that's going so we're passing sort
of these pieces of sort key information
from the dim basis stuff we don't want
that anymore so when we actually get the
bit map dimension back the object
transform has that that where is that
guy there it is
we have that up right there and like I
said you know we even have it to do that
it's whether or not we want that to be
in the object transformer net and again
I don't know whether we want that I mean
I'm transferring that maybe it needs to
be in a different place maybe push
bitmap Misa take it as a parameter I
don't know but what we do know is we
need that value because one of the
things that we said that's crucial to
our soar criteria we could not get
around it when we thought about it there
did not seem to be a way to get around
it is we need to know whether something
is acts like a ground tile so it's
effectively flat or whether something
acts like an upright tile so it's
effectively vertical and in the case
where it's upright we know that we don't
need to set those Y accidents we just
need the Z max and so in the other case
we need the wide sense and the Z max is
just whatever the Z value actually was
for that sprite right okay so let's take
a look at that so when we go to do that
we know that we've got this sort of
sprite bound and the sprite bound is
gonna be set in one of two different
ways so one is sprite bound Y min sprite
bound Y max equals some value right
which is the Y value
now if the thing is a card and Y then
what we would know is that whatever its
actual Y value is just wherever it
actually is in Y and in 3d Y like where
it is in the three dimensional Y
coordinates of this thing that's our
sort just straight up right because we
know that it's only a card that's that's
that's vertical it can't ever have a
different Y value then than the one that
is its position it's always straight up
and down so we can take the offset plus
the auto transforms position right so we
can take the object transforms Y plus
the offsets Y and we know that that's
what it is
so that's really easy to set what's
what's hard to set and again this is if
it's upright so this is if the augur
transform if we're talking about an
upright sprite right what's harder is
that Z max value because the Z max value
is the highest point on the sprite so we
know obviously that we start out you
know here but we know that we're going
to go by a certain amount of scale that
height we're gonna actually expand out
the size of this thing right and so what
I'm thinking is that if we take if we
take a look at what happens and get bit
bapt in when we pass that height in
there you can sort of see what's
happening here we do a height x with the
right here we get that size and we're
taking the size and we end up blowing it
out to basically be centered around its
its center it's whatever its alignment
point is and then we sort of figure out
where the sprite is around there now
what you can see when this happens we
get the size and we get that alignment
what we kind of want to know at that
point is well we want to know this piece
of information right here sort of right
we want to know what the highest point
is gonna be if we were just sort of go
upwards by that amount with with sort of
this the y axis in this case is really
the z axis right because the sprite is
standing upright in z is kind of the
idea right and so I don't actually know
what I should do to get that out in the
most convenient possible way and the
fact that the sprite can be rotated
definitely doesn't help but what I think
I'm gonna do just to make things a
little simpler is for right now I think
I might just say let's take whatever the
height of the sprite should be and we'll
say you go half that up now what that
doesn't take into account is where the
alignment point is so it's not really
quite correct and I feel like that's
probably something we'll have to make a
little bit more accurate in the future
by going okay let's see now how are we
actually rotating the sprite perhaps or
where is the actual alignment point and
I could you know I could do something a
little bit fancier here obviously you
can see where the demint you know dim
sized and dim aligned come back
I guess anything about I you know I
could certainly take dim sighs and dim a
line and make those be a little bit more
accurate here maybe I should so if we
take the dim pxy and you take a look at
what happens here if the Y that comes
out of that is basically gonna be I
think the Y that we want well it's gonna
be the bottom corner depending on how
its rotated I say I think I'm gonna put
it to do in and I'm just gonna do the
easier thing first I'm gonna say to do
more accurate zmax calculations this
doesn't handle alignment rotation or
axis here scale because really what we
want to do is take the maximum of the
bounding box of the rotated entity which
again it's just a little there's a lot
of fussing so I think what I'll do first
is say well you know for people who are
not doing any of that fanciness then we
pretty much know that if you were
centered you would be something like
this so at most we'd be off by 0.5 of
that height so I'm just gonna let that
be a temporary temporary sort key and
we'll see how that goes
all right so in the other case we have
the exact opposite problem right in the
case where we have something lying flat
then what we have is we know that the
sprite pounds Emax we know it exactly
it's just this right because we know
that the sprite is constant in Z so we
know that it's Z max is just whatever
the Z value of this thing was cuz
flattened Z but what we don't know is
what are its extent in Y now we know
where those extents might start right
because we know that it sort of has a y
value that's you know centered around
this potentially or is related
to that but we don't know how much to
add to the Y min and the y max to
actually get it to sort of flow out to
that entire size so the question is here
how much do we want to do that by again
we could do exactly the same thing here
potentially but we're probably going to
have to be more accurate than this I
would suspect in the future
so again this probably won't give us
right results but we can start with it
and so here we just be saying well the
minimum Y would just be however for a
back light and and the y max would be
however far forward and height we would
go and for something that was simple and
not doing anything more complicated that
would probably be correct
I think but I think these are inaccurate
enough that I suspect we will not get
through the whole game with those
holding so after we sort of get things
working we'll probably have to go back
and go ah see it doesn't really work
here and it doesn't work because of
these sort criteria so now we kind of
got to go do the more real stuff all
right so that's our push bitmap call and
once we have spray found now we can just
pass right down to this and off we go
right now what we probably want to do
here a little August let me finish this
stuff off so yeah what is the object
transform it's offset P
yeah and in some sense here we can
probably also take advantage of just a
little bit of the commonality of the
code here and just say well okay so the
wyman zoe's that and the zmax is always
that effectively but then what happens
here is like oh yeah you just you add in
this in the case where you know that
you're you're an upright sprite and you
add these in in the case where you know
that you're a a flat you know lying down
sprite seems reasonable so all right so
moving along we've got a push rect
situation here that I think and I'm not
entirely certain but I think we can just
sort of use the exact same code would be
my suspicion so when we're like doing
something like push rect I think we
should be able to effectively use exact
same calculation I don't actually know
that that's true but that's my suspicion
and so now we've got the same situation
with clear if we want that to sort to
the bottom of the screen then what we
would need to do again is sort of use
that fake cleaner idea I think I was
doing before we could say we've got a
sprite bound and here's our sort key and
that sort key well sort key min Y min
equals real 32 minimum sort key Y max
feels real 32 maximum and then swore key
Z max equals real affinity to minimum
and that'll sort I think below
everything else that exists so that
would still satisfy the same criteria I
believe famous last words can but anyway
so now that we have that information
what we need to do is we need to do two
things first of all we need to find a
way to share this particular code right
here and so let's see if we can pull
that out into something where we can say
you know okay Spray pound get bound for
right if this was something that had to
be called as a separate thing
how might we do it well what do we need
we need two things we need the object
transforms offset P and the upright
right and then we need the height and
the offsets of three things so we need
the object transform comic the Spanish
Inquisition so we got the object
transform we also need the height we
also need the offset but I think with
all of those things in place then that's
pretty much all we need so then we can
just say like sprite band equals get BAM
floor and then we can just pass it the
object transform offset height oops not
so good and then we can compile and I
think we're good so now we've got our
sort key stuff I think under control
there and and should be able to just
like I said kind of copy that over to
the rectangle case when we do a push
vector so there we go
and now the only question is well what's
height well height is just the the Y
dimension I think that's all we really
need to do there and then we can pass
that as as the bound okay so now if we
run this we're gonna run into a world of
hurt I suspect very quickly like you can
see and the reason for that of course is
that our renderer doesn't know that we
changed the format of our sword keys so
we're gonna have to go tell the renderer
that that's well not okay so if we go
into the lunacy here forgot our sort
entries so here's our sword entries
command right and it's gonna pass that
sort memory game commands thing you can
see it sort of pulling this information
out here and you can see that when we
when we grab those sword entries out you
can see that it casts it to a sword
entry there and that's just because
whoever sorts the entries that's what
they wanted to do there yeah so what we
need to do is make sure all of these
people start using the correct
sort of the correct thing for sword
entries now what they did occurs to me
that we didn't do particularly well here
as you can see that we've got this sort
of notion that everyone can just cast
this value now that's not great because
now you know if you imagine that we have
this in 20 different places well I
wouldn't really have any way to make it
easy for me to know that that's what was
happening so when I do a cast like this
but I probably should do and you can
sort of see why hopefully this would
make some sense is I think probably what
we want is inside the the code that's
shared in the renderer that's doing that
sort in fact maybe I could put that in
sort that's TPP here what I could do is
say well alright let's let's make this a
more like standard operation so we know
that you know when we go to do our sorts
you're gonna call this routine and that
way if the sprite bound thing changes
then you know that it was supposed to be
different so we've got this sort of
concept that we're returning a sort
spray bound and we would say get sort
entries here and then it would do just
exactly this and again there's nothing
weird happening your other than the fact
that we're just kind of cleaning up that
notion that what you're returning is is
a particular type right that's all I'm
trying to do and so that would take the
commands so that would take the game
render commands and now you know we
would say like oh okay
let's go ahead and and get those sort
entries out and we just say the sort
sprite band in this case as opposed to
sort entries is going to be equal to get
sort entries for these commands off we
go and and so now that's all good and
you can see that that will cascade our
errors there but of course we've got our
OpenGL render as well and it's doing the
same thing so what we want to do here is
make sure that that it also uses the
same code path so here we go right just
making sure that happens there and now
everyone should have cascading errors
that help us correct it everything to
the right case what just happened there
okay there we go alright so that's fixed
now but we still have one more place
that isn't calling the right thing and
that's the thing that actually does the
sort you can see when we call sort
entries here it's still thinking of this
in terms of sort entries so what we want
to do again is if we have this this had
been doing the correct call in the first
place right
it would have immediately given us an
error and that's that's the only reason
I want to do that right so now that
anytime I change that since that is a
cold cast now it's gonna be better right
okay so now when we actually get here to
do our sorting obviously like this the
radix sort
not an option anymore so that's like
totally totally not okay so we're down
to just being able to merge sort these
guys right that's the only thing that
we're gonna be able to do so let's go
ahead and see if that's okay
what is the would don't remember what I
just said this sort even took so it
takes a sort sprite down star temp how
much space does temp have to have so 10
pass to have the whole size right so yes
so it's got to be effectively this size
again you can see the sort of cascading
stuff here why I think it might be nice
in case we want to make these sort of
changes now that I've seen them happen
once the sword entries here right are
also wrong because I believe I believe
we've got sort memory being allocated in
here
so needed memory size is yeah you can
see it doing like a size of sword entry
here so I feel like that's again the
sort of thing where we probably want we
probably want that to be clarified and I
guess you know inside the sort maybe
that I don't know where that should go
probably in here that makes sense and
then probably like we want something
here that's like get sort memory size or
get sort temp memory size and that way
inside the win32 code instead of it
doing this it can actually like ask and
and know right so it's gonna say like
okay here's the game render commands and
in that case it's gonna take the element
count and it's gonna multiply it by the
sort sprite bath and that really all I'm
trying to do here right it's nothing
particularly complicated I'm just trying
to make sure that these operations kind
of are all bound together in a
reasonably close way if that makes sense
so you can kind of see that like hey
everyone's got to do it the way that
they do it and if you change one you'll
know to change the rest of them it
that's really the only thing that I was
trying to accomplish there it's nothing
particularly fancy so in here we could
just say like okay get sort temp memory
size for these render commands and then
get rid of the rest of this stuff and
then in here when we do that gets sort
temp memory size will return that with
the needed sort memory size and then I
think we would be good to go all right
so when we call get sort entry
an OpenGL renderer okay so it looks like
that's not is that not in here for some
reason shouldn't that that would have to
because when it calls a sort I guess it
doesn't have to I don't know so maybe
these have to be in the actual sort code
I don't know let's find out short
entries sort memory what it calls the
merge sort sprite based so it's great
very good ok and handmade slow would
also need to do this so here is our Oh
so you know what this is actually the
exact test code we wanted to when I was
saying we want to test it more fully so
we can say like Oh make sure that is in
front of and speaking of is in front of
my head is in front of that if is in
front of is true for everybody in our
you know in our cases so it handmade
slow we can go ahead and do that that
test you know what I was you know what
I'm wondering did this really never so
I'm in it yeah I'm gonna test this cuz
that's actually happening in our debug
build I'm kind of surprised that that's
not causing from is it time to function
with it is it just with a yeah okay so
let's go ahead and run this and see
where we're at now
so what I'm going to do here is I want
to actually go step into this call so
I'm gonna go ahead and and see if I can
rerun this statement right so that I can
see what the actual sort comparison did
in the case where I've already kind of
got an error here so here's two sprites
and oh well they happen to be the same
actually
so for sorting two sprites that are the
same then I guess I guess the result
could come out either way right so that
doesn't really count so I guess we would
soups I guess we would say more like
okay if it's in front of then that's
fine if it's not in front of it then we
have to double check are they equal
so we'll just assert entry a sort key
you know why min equals entry a sort key
why max and this will then get us down
to only cases where there are actually
different sort keys and we can see so
you know assume that we'll just verify
that oops verify that these are all
completely equal to each other so Y min
Y max see Max and these are all B's all
right so now let's try and get that
assertion and and take a look at one
that's probably more likely to be
correct okay so if we take a look at
entry a and entry fee in this case they
should be actually different values now
and it looks like they are right so
there's e max values are different they
are both it looks like up right sprites
because they have exactly the same
values here right they they're both
they're both exactly and so if we take a
look at their Z max values
we see that this one is 1.25 and this
one is 0.75 so what we would expect to
see is this one should have been sorted
ahead of this one and I think that's
probably what we're not seeing here
right because entry a entry entry a is
being it's coming first and list right
and entry B is coming it's coming after
it now this doesn't actually do an N
squared check this only doesn't end
check there's probably not what we want
check anyway but it's good for our for
immediate checking purposes just to get
the basic bucks out other team so that's
fine anyway so entry a probably
shouldn't be right because if entry a
and entry be are compared then we should
find that the Z max value of entry be
should put it ahead so what's our actual
index here index is 70 so it does point
to a problem with the sorting because it
means that the first 70 entries were all
sorted properly and this is the only one
that's actually wrong so far out of how
many out of 2000 so um maybe you know
the other thing that we should do is
probably look at what is actually what
it's actually doing which is kind of a
separate issue here so let me let me
actually if this zeros that so I can
actually see what's going on
not great not great not great folks
don't love it it's a blank screen okay
so probably what we're gonna have to
start with is something simpler like I
don't know that I want to try and debug
2000 sprites stuffed into themselves
there
I suppose one thing I could do is start
with something that's in a set of
discrete layers like the like the
cutscenes that might work as well so we
should probably take a look at that
perhaps as our first order of business
because that would only have to ever
sort in Y I'm sorry in Z and we could
verify that that was working properly in
fact I think that's a good I think
that's a good idea so I think I'm gonna
do that I'm gonna do exactly that what I
don't remember is where I actually force
that to happen I think it is in here
somewhere so I should be able to do this
and now I should get
come back here I should get just the
cutscene starting let me make sure that
that's true
yeah okay so now let's start off with
this we should be able to sort of break
in here and see what's going on let's
double check that we kind of have this
sense of these correct so you know is in
front of just by its grammar a is in
front of B so we want to return it if a
is the closer one right so let's just
make sure that that's true if we say to
sort by Z then we want to know that AZ
max is greater than B Z max because a
would be in front that's true and Y
would be the opposite sense so that is
correct so now let's go down here and
make sure that this is in the correct
way too so we do our merge sort here we
say okay we've got our two entries we're
going to compare the first and second
entries in the list we're going to say
if the second entry was actually
supposed to be in front of the first
when we swap them that seems correct to
me right that seems like that's going to
go in the correct order so then we move
down here and we say all right we're
doing our sort of split merges our two
halves we're splitting and we're merge
sorting each of the halves then we have
to put the the halves back together so
we start through here and we say all
right if we're only reading the first
half then we output it if we're only
reading the second half then we output
it right but if we're reading both if
we're still reading from both what we
want to know is which one of the two it
should come first
so if read half zero should come first
and we put it in there if read half one
to come first then we put in in there
right and so that all looks pretty
reasonable to me everything there seems
fine then if we take a look at our is in
front of like I said that seems
reasonable as well I think all of that
looks pretty good in terms of checking
whether they're both z sprites both of
the sprites would be Z sprites if they
had Y bounds which is what would happen
here right they would both be Z sprites
if they both have a Wyman and ymax that
are not the same a includes B if if a is
min
and Max basically bound B which is what
it looks like here and the same is true
here and we know that we don't reject
why max because y-min and y-max would be
equal in the cases we care about because
both sprites would not be similar there
now I yeah I think that's about right I
suppose technically this might be wrong
in certain cases where I mean that wrong
but inconsistent in cases where the wise
were actually equal so it's possible
that we would want to expand this out
into something a little bit more
specific but that should all be fine for
our basic scenario of of sprites that
are strictly in Z and so what we should
be able to do is we should be able to
take our cutscene scenario and make a
pretty clear we should be able to get a
pretty clear understanding of what's
happening here so let's take a look so
when we come in and we're about to do
our merge sort we've got two entries
that doesn't sound like enough let's run
a little bit here there should be more
than two entries there we go so now
we've got 39 entries honestly that
sounds like too many but probably a lot
of those are debug I'm guessing so in
fact maybe what I'll do temporarily is
also turn off the debug so inside a
hand-made basically just for the moment
I may go ahead and say where we were
doing our debug out in fact I guess we
do we have a convenient way to turn
debug off on and off
so handmade internal would turn it off I
don't know if we really want him an
internal but you know what I guess for
right now let's go ahead and turn that
off so I'm gonna go into the build up
that file looks like we're down to the
five-minute warning
although I started a little bit late so
we actually probably are like 10 minutes
so if I come through here and say okay
let's take handmade internal off so that
I won't get that debug now I should be
in a situation oh looks like we are
missing a few of our our undef calls
basically so debug begin data block
needs to go away debug and datablock
used to go away at debug b32 needs to go
away and then what are these other guys
here debug game frame and void function
returning a value I really need to get a
version of work order that can do the
jump to error properly I have I got a
email Alain about that because I haven't
updated this one but the one I have the
most recent one I have still doesn't
actually jump to error the go to the
scrolling doesn't like quite work right
on the newer builds alright so let's go
ahead and take a look here debug game
frame end void function returning a
value all right so that just means get
rid of it
debug set event recording identifier now
found okay that's just again another
case of debug set event recording and
off we go so now we shouldn't be piling
anything on to the drawing that involved
right there's nothing else on the screen
now so we should just have a set of
layers and there we go there's the eight
layers we should just have a nice set of
layers it's like here's the things that
we should be sorting and this is the
simplest possible case we should be able
to make sure that nothing super stupid
is happening which may be something
super stupid is happening
so let's take a look so in this case you
can see we've actually got all of the Y
values are set directly to very specific
things I'm not sure why those are set
the way that they're set so I guess the
first thing I should figure out is why
are those being set as having those Y
mean wise either way either way if you
look at these it should be pretty
straight forward how these Z's would get
sorted right I mean that's pretty easy
to understand because they're all they
all have Z so they're both everything
Suman compares can go through the both
these price paths we're always going to
be comparing Y max Azim axis so the Z
maxes should be sorted totally correctly
and we should be getting the highest Z
max well that's that's a menial chain we
don't really spend any time on it so I'm
okay with that but hi this is a this is
not a front to back renderer right I
mean that's kind of obvious put this
check back in so if you come up here to
is in front of you can see that we
return is in front of correctly
unfortunately when we ask is in front of
we are then using that to move the
closer thing up in the list but a thing
that's in front of other things should
be drawn later in the list right
so actually we if if a is in front of B
then we would swap them right because we
yes so it's the other way round
from what we had it in all cases right
it's actually like that so there you go
all right so that's more what we were
trying to do there so now let's take a
look at where we're at okay so at least
now we know that our like fundamentals
are not completely messed up we are
still able to produce the correct sort
for a simple set of Z flat sprites so
that's good again and I just wanted
because this is relatively tough do you
think we're doing here I wanted to make
sure that we weren't totally messed up
in some other way so we know that that
appears to be working correctly so now
let's jump back to the game side of
things where stuff is going to get a
little more squirrely and we can start
to figure out where the rest of the bugs
are and also like I said we have to kind
of determine that this sort even it can
be done as a straightforward sort which
I don't actually know if it can or not
so that's you know sort of a separate
issue that we're gonna have to determine
as we go forwards all right so I'm going
to put back in
or jumping straight to the game without
the title sequence and now we can take a
look at what happens here okay so taking
a look at this what we can at least
determine so far and this is good a good
thing for us what we can at least
determine so far is we never fail our
check in an obvious linear sweep right
so that's good we also have a bunch of
interpenetrating objects here so that's
not great but yeah so the fact that we
have a bunch of independent
interpenetrating objects isn't fabulous
for testing the sort but that's
something we can start working on
tomorrow by actually put it giving it
some some more realist stuff by fixing
our sort of layer stuff we we sort of
did these two things together as part of
one one go okay so let's check just for
the sake of argument as well you know
let's say we didn't do that so let's say
temporarily that we went and went to
world mode and when we were outputting
our entities let's say that we we didn't
do our truncation stuff that we were
doing that flattens everything down into
the plain right I guess that's actually
I always make this mistake I keep
forgetting we moved it out to this its
own entity file so when that's happening
here right we've got this this notion
that we're sort of doing our relative
layer transform thing here and we don't
actually let's say we don't actually
want do that so we want to use the
correct Z here
so we'll just actually let it draw the
things in Zi the way that they we're
gonna draw the things in C just because
I kind of want to see what it does with
the sort in that case so let's see so it
looks like it in that case I feel like
it's wrong meaning we're not getting the
sort that I would have expected and the
reason I say that is because you can
kind of see that these things I believe
should be where's my I don't have a
mouse cursor I guess oh right because
handmade internal turns off the mouse
cursor I can turn that back on for the
moment
so I believe that all of these right
these sort of closer up ones I believe
I'm standing on the further back ones
and maybe I'm wrong about that and then
in which case I stand corrected but I
believe I'm standing on the further back
ones which means I should not be sorting
right and you can kind of see like even
you didn't see that that's definitely
the case right you can see as I'm sort
of doing this that those should should
not be sorting the way they're sorting
right I should be behind those and you
know there's a number of reasons why
that could be but those are what we'll
start to address tomorrow because we're
pretty much out of time today so we've
got everything running properly and
everything I think is sorting properly
by the rule but we now have to go see
are we feeding the rule properly because
you know we got those janky computations
in there for like zmax stuff and then
also we've got to start actually
outputting these in a little more
sensible of a fashion so I'm going to go
ahead and go to the QA and then we'll
we'll come back to this tomorrow to get
things sort of working a little bit more
more correctly I think
hello Andrew good to see you here thank
you very much for reading the blog post
I thought that was a really interesting
blog post even separate from handmade
hero because you know I'll be honest I
guess you know part of it's probably my
fault because since I don't work on 2d
games really I I have it like educated
myself about what people generally do in
terms of making sprites show up in the
correct order because it's that
inherently you know sort of it's it's an
inherently semantic problem of like we
you know this isn't real 3d it's it's 2d
plus you want to fake the depth how do
you do that right and so I really didn't
know much about how people have done it
and I imagine there are you know
different approaches that people have
taken in the past and so it was really
interesting just to read about that I
would I would be interested in reading
about how other people are doing it to
like I think that it would be kind of
cool to just now that I know it's not
it's not a completely trivial thing
right it's not just oh yeah you just
sort by Y and you're done or something I
feel like there's probably games out
there that have done interesting things
like like the stuff that you were doing
that I wouldn't have known about and so
I'm interested in that I feel like it
would be cool to find out how people are
doing their sorting so I really enjoyed
reading that blog post I thought that
was great and I really liked the
solution that you were using it seems
pretty cool and I'm looking forward to
playing the game too because I think I'm
played a double dragon like game in a
long long time
so you voucher the coordinates used for
the sort rules are world space right
with another approach be to sort the
screen space coordinates from the top of
the screen down so previously what we
were doing was sort of sorting the
previously what we're doing with sorting
the screen coordinates right and the
problem with that is that sorting the
screen coordinates doesn't give us
information about what to do
in the cases well I mean it's it's
pretty obvious why you can't sort the
suite screen coordinates right like
so the problem is you know you've got if
I've got it like if I'm gonna draw like
a 3d case here so suppose I've got this
sort of tile in the world like a
platform or something right and then
there's something on top of the platform
when you look at that top down you end
up with this right and you have no idea
if the ball was below this thing right
then it that you know in this case if I
was to label this a and this B in this
case B should be drawn first than a
second so it eclipses it in this case
the ops it's true but all you're gonna
see in screen space is that so you have
no idea right so at the very least you
would need sort of a screen space
augmented with Z so maybe when you're
talking about screen space you mean oh
well I I mean XY of screen space plus Z
screen space right so in that case you
have a similar problem and the similar
problem that you have there is well now
we start talking about like okay we've
got situations where you know you look
at something that's you know trying to
think of what the the good example would
be now you've got something that looks
like this
this is not a very good drawing I admit
that
all right so now you've got something
that looks something like this and
you're viewing it from here right so
what you end up seeing on the screen is
you end up seeing something that kind of
looks like this right depending on how
high up we're viewing it right and these
two things overlap well if now we're
sort of saying well whatever whoever had
the higher Y sort value or the lower Y
sort value draws first which we would
need to do to ensure that this guy drew
first then we have the problem that well
people who are standing on top of these
things or even you know in the case
where we're talking about like a screen
space rug right for example in fact that
may be the better case here like we have
sort of a a thing that is on top of four
different tiles and then we've got
somebody standing on that which is the
case we were kind of looking at before
so in this case we have this nasty case
of like okay when I actually go to look
at this thing I'm gonna see this sort of
thing happening here well when I look at
what's going on this may well be you
know so the person who's standing on top
of this rug may well be somewhere like
in here whereas all of these things may
be you know kind of behind it or
whatever or there might even be one of
them that's kind of sticking up like
over here right and when I start to try
and use this as just a sort by why
obviously isn't gonna work a sort by y&amp;z
now I have to figure out well which do I
use in these cases to sort of break the
tie right what were or rather which
which am I going to sort by and how
because I've got y&amp;z now and I don't
know necessarily which one of which to
use if i strictly sort by Y I'm gonna
get one answer if i strictly start by
Xion getting another answer
how do i break the tie right or how do I
know which one to use and as far as I
could tell from if you go back and watch
my very
long ramble through this as far as I can
tell the only way to really know which
way to break the tie was to have the
actual bounds in Y and use them so you
can't just have Y Z you need like y-min
and y-max and Z that was as far as I
could tell but you definitely can't just
use Y that's for sure
whether you can use y&amp;z with no Y bounds
I don't know but I couldn't quite figure
out a way to do it and again you can see
me work all the way through it Monday
and Wednesdays streams were all this so
you can go watch Mondays and Wednesdays
and see me work it out and as far as I
could tell you need this you definitely
can't sort screen space because screen
with no Z because there's that doesn't
give you even remotely enough
information
Andrew Russell Nets I have a question
about your development approach I don't
think I've ever seen you create a
separate program or environment to test
stuff you always seem to work within the
running game do you ever find this to be
noisy um so I guess what I would say is
it depends on the circumstance but I
usually find that the only times I want
to be completely outside of the game
environment is if I'm just doing a
purely theoretical algorithm thing and I
have a test bed already for that like I
used to do that I had a 3d thing called
math viz that I wrote that I used to use
for making for doing 3d algorithms when
I was working on granny at rad and I
don't know I don't think I've put up the
screenshots from that since I
yeah I don't know that I have those up
here the I had some screenshots of what
that looked like
and I could go find them
certainly
well point being me I should go grab
them on a thumb drive I could show you I
guess what I'd say is I find a lot of
times that slows me down a little bit
too much to do but it's definitely been
something that I have done in the past
and the way that I approach that is if I
think I'm going to be doing a lot of
work on a certain type of algorithm like
3d algorithms whatever what I do is I
make a little toolbox and a little
system for you know playing around with
stuff that I can use to you know sort of
prototype things and draw things really
easily and so I do do that sometimes and
you know what I thought about I wonder
if this machine has
darn oh my got kind of sight about there
because that that's where it would've
been I I guess this must have been this
machine probably got cleaned out at some
point but like it would have been in my
old rad game tools source tree and
unfortunately that's that's gone like it
doesn't it doesn't come with the granny
SDK it's just you know it's it's just
internal development stuff so I don't I
don't see it here and I guess I guess
all this stuff is just gone at this
point yeah so it must it must have
cleaned out this whole directory and
then but after having cleaned out the
whole directory it left all of the
directories there I guess
cuz like there nothing on there that I
don't I do not know
yeah I I don't know I mean it's like I
feel like I'm grasping defeat from the
jaws of victory here like this would
have been I could actually just run the
program because it would have been here
but I don't it does not appear to
actually exist in any capacity here yeah
so so much for that but yeah point being
there there was a programs called
Malthus and it you know
and just says i realized i telled i know
i have seen you do something along these
lines on witness wednesdays just that's
nice to meet you yeah I mean another
thing to remember about handmade hero is
you know as much I try as much as
possible to show how actual game
development works to the extent that's
like you know I don't prepare for it and
I don't try to think of the solution
ahead of time and then just type it out
right I try to actually like struggle
with things you know accurately and be
like okay you know I'm programming this
just sitting down and if I have to work
out something I'm gonna work it out on
the you know whatever uh as much as I
try to do that there's also just the
fact that some things I'm just not gonna
do look I'm not gonna spend you know I
think the curve fitting the original
curve fitting algorithm for granny I
mean I probably spend I don't know 200
hours working on that thing and so like
something of that magnitude would have
taken almost all the time that we've
spent on hammer here oh just the whole
thing just on one algorithm and so
showing how that actually works just
isn't super feasible right and so he
made hero isness you know necessarily
not gonna show me tackling us an ultra
hard problem because I don't think you
could like I don't think you could make
a show where you did that because what
you'd see is so impossible for you get
through and also there'd be no talking I
would have to be thinking the whole time
so it's like you know so I feel like I
try to make it a fairly accurate
representation of what programming is
like coming up with brand new algorithms
in hard researchy areas we don't do on
handmade hero and i don't think you can
do in the context of that so your
intuition that i don't seem to be doing
that as much as maybe you might think i
would is probably correct in the sense
that if i was working on some really
hard problems on handmade hero you would
have to see me doing something like that
and probably those would be very long
silent you know hundreds of hours of me
sort of like you know whatever and so i
think that's just kind of the nature of
what you can and can't do in a series
like this
I suspect that's part of it
yeah I'm sorry you know I don't know if
I've got let me let me see I might on
another machine have a copy of Malthus
still kicking
I'll go look and see if I do I probably
don't but give me one second
so let's see here success so this was
the program that I used for all of
graining development and and basically
the way it worked is it had like this
sort of primitive UI thing that I
written and and it's just a very simple
UI it's it's very similar to the kind of
approach we took in handmade Hiro but it
was before it was made a little bit
before I kind of got immediate mode UI
so it was a little bit like a half way
thing but you know it's got sort of
these like pretty simple sort of
draggable slider things that you can
throw in there to kind of edit things
quickly and then what you would do is it
had this concept that you could like
just drop in visualizations that you
wanted and I don't know how many there
were there probably 10 or 12 or whatever
and I just I just zero some out when I
didn't when I was done with them so
they're not all in here but you know you
could compile in a bunch at the same
time if you needed to and then you could
just basically click on them and when
you clicked on them you would switch to
that visualization you can see me sort
of doing it here and so it had a bunch
of tools in it like you could draw an
arrow from one place to another you
could draw like a move manipulator so
this is like a you know kind of like the
kind on the witness' right and you can
see here this was in fact some of you
may be familiar with that little thing
that thing I posted which is like here's
how you solve gjk really efficiently and
without all the really stupid math that
I think a lot of people do who don't
really know how the actual algorithm
works and this was the actual way that I
figured that out right so here is here
is the tetrahedral case and so you
imagine that the gjk has just taken a
step in this direction and it found this
as the maximal point and you can see
here that I'm highlighting the three
points that I believe make up the
correct
simplex for the next step which would be
the triangle ABC and you can see that
I've like labeled them the way that I
would have labeled them probably in the
algorithm as well and then what I would
do here right is you can see how I would
start to make sure that my code was
working is I can drag the values and
make sure that they actually switch at
the times that they should switch right
does that make sense hopefully that
makes some sense so you can see that I'm
like going like okay yeah that case is
pretty solid here well actually I guess
I got to see this up right case so there
you go right so I can see like okay so
it's on it's it's thinking that this
edge is the closest now and that seems
correct but as soon as I move this up
till it's or I guess I should say til I
move this up so that it's actually this
triangle highlight so I should be able
to see that you know whatever that kind
of thing
and that's how I can play around with
those and kind of see what's going on
now in this visualization I'm afraid I
can't probably much down because I don't
think I remember what the heck this
thing was I'll be I'll be honest with
you it's some kind of a culling thing
you can see it's must be a spatial
partition because it's kind of and there
were usually keys that did stuff right
and I don't know what those keys are in
this visualization so not much I can
really do with that one here's an AABB
so access aligned bounding box
visualization of some kind this looks
like me testing the this looks like I'm
testing the Minkowski sum of triangle
right like with a with an axis aligned
bounding box because that's what that
looks like right actually I should say
Minkowski difference probably right and
the reason I probably doing that is
because like this was clearly compiled
at a time when I was working on gjk and
so you know it's it's not surprising
that's like okay I've got my axis
aligned bounding box and now we're going
to talk about a case where I'm colliding
with something so I want the axis
aligned bounding box too you know
overlap the triangle or whatever you can
see that I've I've colored it purple
when I believe it to be enclosing the
origin and you can see here
so this is like a visualization in that
sense of the minkowski you know I don't
remember how I pan there we go so you
can see that this is a visualization of
the Minkowski difference in this case
it's taking the Minkowski subtraction
right of our Bukowski difference of the
triangle and the axial line bounding box
and then it's looking to say well does
the convex hull of this thing enclose
the origin week because we're humans can
see pretty clearly that it would right
if you took the comments all these
points but that's exactly what gjk
purports to do right and so you can
imagine why I was wanting to look at
that so there you go now similar like I
said you know these sliders were all on
some things you can see that in this
case we've got a what is that like a Y
plane there I guess so
you know I think if I tweak this yeah
you can see it kind of does some some
changes too like what the what the VIS
is showing so you could tweak those out
like maybe I don't want to see that you
know maybe I don't want the grid in
there or whatever and so you know those
were just ways of kind of tuning the VIS
and then if you take a look at these
things you can see that there's you know
whatever they were each of the the
visualizations itself you could sort of
throw in you know little things that
that would adjust what was going on I
don't know what pincushion length was
meant to do I can't imagine what that
was meant to do
pin cushion is that actually is that
changing anything obvious it might have
been something that I got rid of but I
don't see anything changing so I don't
know what that was meant to do for annoy
length doesn't look like doesn't
anything air so I don't know what those
are meant to do there at all these
points are just readouts of the
manipulators so if I was trying to bug
something you know I might want to see
that obviously and all that stuff I
think this supports the same stuff that
we support in right in in handmade hero
for drag-and-drop so you can do crap
like that I don't know that that's very
interesting though so yeah so when
culling I don't know what this one was
supposed to do I suspect so what I'm
guessing and I don't know for sure
but what I'm guessing is that what was
supposed to happen here was there's
probably supposed to be a data file that
this would have loaded and it would have
told us a bunch of stuff about this
right so we would have loaded something
in and it would have shown us like a you
know there would have been a mesh that
would have gone with it and so I suspect
the reason that that one isn't doing
anything is because of that so hopefully
that makes some sense so again you know
that's just like a simple test bed and I
would just always throw things into that
test bed I had like the curve fitting
stuff in there at one point I had yeah -
diva stuff in there I had a post based
information one in there just lots and
lots of stuff and that's where I would
always prototype things so hopefully
that answers hopefully that answers that
question a little more cleanly for you
in practice
all right I don't know what's oh and
here's the okay so now that my head has
disappeared because we're out of time as
well I realized this probably was also
showing an inset render probably that's
what that was doing yeah anyway yep
there you go so that was math vis and
like I said that was used for basically
all of the algorithms in granny at some
point we're probably you know if they
were non-trivial they were probably
prototyped in math days at some point so
yeah so that's it there we go I'm
probably gonna wrap up now but but
that's that's how that worked Andrew
whistled that was really awesome to see
thanks no problem again thanks for for
writing that blog post I really enjoyed
reading that and I think a lot of people
on him I hear were pretty sure to see
that as well so I think that was that
was a really great thing if you if you
have any more blog posts like that that
you happen to write up about interesting
2d stuff you're doing on on RC are you
that would be great I'd love to tweet
those out to everyone so that I could
check them out all righty
that's it is it for today let's it's
closing on up all right thanks everyone
for joining us for another episode of
hand made here also a pleasure coding
with us always we are almost you know
we're we're struggling along like with
the sorting I think we're getting a
little more under control but kind of
happy because as soon as we finish this
sort of Z stuff that kind of puts the
renderer to bed structurally in a way
that I'm pretty happy with because it
means we don't have to think about the Z
anymore which I wasn't liking we never
really got it in a place where I was
happy with it so I think this will
finally turn the crank for us to the
place where it's like okay now I'm where
I'm a little happier with the way that
we're processing the Z so we'll keep at
it we'll do it again tomorrow and then I
think next week we might you know if
we're lucky next week will be the the
week
we can finally finish up the sort of RZ
conceptualization if we're lucky you
never know until then if you want to
play around the source code at home
obviously you can always peer to the
game on hand me hear it or it comes to
the source code you don't play around
with it we also have a forum site you
can go to ask questions a patreon page
if you want support the video series a
schedule bot if you want to know when
we're live and a past episode guide if
you're trying to catch up on old stuff I
will be back here tomorrow same time I
think 5 p.m. it's 5 p.m. Pacific
Daylight Time for the last stream of the
week hope to see you there until then
have fun programming and I'll see you
guys on the Internet
take you use everyone