alright hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Heroes show recode a complete
game live on stream before I get started
today a pretty simple thing we got to do
today it's a little bit of busy work but
we're just replacing printf so that we
can have that without so that we're not
relying on the C runtime library for it
a couple things I wanted to mention one
is that I'm gonna tweet out soon about
it but the early registration for
handmade con will be ending soon I
believe we're getting the point where
the speaker list will probably start
getting finalized and so if you haven't
bought tickets to hammock on and you
know you want to go already definitely
make sure you grab those before the
price before the better price goes up I
know most people always say that the
ticket price is not really important
because I'm traveling to handmade con
always cost my other ticket price which
is what we work hard to do we try to
keep three prices as low as possible but
I mean you might as well save $20 if you
know you're going to if you don't know
whether you're going to go then don't
worry about it
you know hey it's only $20 i guess is
the dance the converse and you can wait
till closer to the event but just
thought I'd point that out that's one
thing and the second thing is I will be
speaking at this conference they asked
me to come and speak at it and generally
you know I try to support any speaking
any conference that seems to be run you
know ethically and for the benefit of
the public and this this you know they
asked me if I would give a talk here and
it definitely looked like the kind of
talk kind of comments that's really for
the benefit of the public and so I was I
was down with that I don't know very
much about it other than the fact that
they're a group that does basically
research paper review kinds of speeches
these are the speakers for speaking at
it but it's actually part of a bigger
very strange conference I have no idea
like this conference was purely
bizarre I had never heard of it but I
looked and I was like I it looked like
one of those like Kafka s things where
you're like what is is happening because
I looked at like the you know the the
names of the presentations and they're
just they're like kind of hilarious
right like things that are just I look
at them and I'm like it what is it's
it's all like stuff that I don't
understand how you would need a
presentation about they're so bizarre
but you know or they're just like kind
of often the kind of in crazy town about
like you know things that I don't even
know like but anyway point being the
conference is crazy I have no idea what
the deal is with it but it looks like
it's fairly sizeable and popular and I
guess all you really have to do is you
register for the whole thing I don't
even know point being if you happen to
be going to this thing and going to this
crazy conference this papers we love
conference is it's like a one-day thing
that happens before it and I will be
speaking at it so if you want to go to
that there is the bad information and I
just don't even know what this is I I
could not tell I have no idea it was
very strange
and so I just kind of closed it and was
like well all right so anyway but the
papers we love thing is kind of cool and
if you look to they have a papers we
love Twitter feed that's kind of cool
too if it's the sort of thing that
you're into but they basically you know
tweet out you know little presentations
that people do about various like you
know papers that have come out recently
and I guess the main thing that's
probably a little problematic for a game
person is they tend to not be super game
eccentric but it's kind of cool anyway
like just in terms of you know keeping
abreast of like what's going on research
wise is kind of fun it would be neat if
there was a game version of this
there is I don't know but it would be
kind of cool for someone to have a like
a feed where it's just like hey papers
that are sort of relevant you know to
games and you could just subscribe and
kind of see them as they come up anyway
that's it for the business if that makes
sense I'm gonna go ahead and get started
on the actual up or I could just launch
the intel architecture guide because you
know that's always good I'm gonna go
ahead and get started a 327 so go ahead
and used a 326 the source code when you
get a chance and I am going to go ahead
and go back to doing the printf if you
remember where we left off
we essentially implemented a little
scanner because we just started this at
the end of the stream last time but
basically we replaced printf with a call
to our own function and we did a little
scanner but but all it does is it
essentially just prints out what the
format codes would have been but it
doesn't actually do anything right so
all you see is just what the format
string is I mean minus the percent which
we stripped out so our goal is
essentially to go from just the format
strings to actually printing things up
and like I said that probably won't be
too hard for us to do in relatively
short order except for a floating-point
print out
floating point print out is
traditionally extremely extremely
extremely difficult if you don't believe
me just see the the trail of papers of
people trying to implement floating
point print out lucky for us and I
mention this on the previous stream I do
know that someone recently printed a
paper that actually supposedly has a
much cleaner and easier way to implement
floating point printout so hopefully we
can go lean on that and maybe it really
is much easier to do now but up until
that it was definitely the case that
that people struggled with it
you know if you
if you looked at what some of the
standard papers were before on how to
print out a floating-point number
they're pretty crazy let me see if I can
find one from the old days let's see
dragon for I think is the one that I was
thinking of let's see if we've got it
here but you can see I mean just even
looking at the code it's kind of crazy
but just in terms of how easy it is know
is that well the one I'm thinking of I
want the paper it's what I want
is this the one no this is the new one
the one that I actually want to use but
I thought there was kind of a I thought
there was kind of an older one here this
might be it
all right anyway not worth rattling on
point being if you want to spend some
time going down that particular rathole
yourself you can go look at for example
you could just open up that paper that's
the new paper that is the one that I
wanted to take a look at and go read
through its references and find the old
ways of printing them out and it's just
kind of crazy how you know convoluted it
was and how obtrusive a problem it
apparently was it's not a problem I've
ever looked at myself I don't know if
maybe people are making a mountain out
of a molehill or something but point
being lots of people have kind of
flailed at it and it didn't go well so
that is really the only part that
requires any special care is the
floating-point part everything else is
actually just kind of a bookkeeping and
since we don't have any concerns we're
not using user input values there
anything like that we don't even really
have security concerns in this case it's
a lot easier to we can be sloppy if we
want to be sloppy on this sort of thing
in it and it's not going to be a problem
for us so that's also kind of a a handy
sort of a bit there so I don't know
where I put this thing I'll admit that
but I think it was down here and okay so
it is so here's our function that we
wrote that's kind of set up for us to
start implementing our printf you can
see that it's format string list you
remember we talked about the arglist
part for variable length argument lists
because you know how that printf tends
to be implemented as a variable
arguments if you don't understand how
those work go back and watch the
previous stream because I explain how
that sort of stuff works so at this
point what we need to do is start
actually processing these percentages
and handling them properly so as you can
see what happens here we come through
and we've got our sort of our
destination output little utility that
we have here and we're looping over the
input and every time we see a percentage
sign right now we're just skipping it
but if we don't see a % then we're
actually outputting it so what we need
to do now is implement something
that actually does work on the % now I'm
gonna do something very simple first and
then we'll sort of expand it out because
we've actually got a lot of things we
have to handle if we want to sort of
have a predict that does the stuff that
we need to do because we have stuff like
0-2 and stuff like that like you know
wit specifiers and pad with zero and
those sorts of things so in order to
support those properly we have to do
some additional work besides just
looking at one character after the
percent and printing out the thing that
it's indicating but for example when we
get the % what I could do here is say
well okay if the thing that I'm looking
at now after the % is an S for example
let's just take a look at how we would
implement one ez
print app type okay so if it's an S then
I want to look at the s string value
basically and what I know that I can do
because we talked about this before is
once I have an Arg lift I can pull
things off of the Arg list
now if you remember I I kind of showed
you what those functions look like over
here I'm just gonna bring them up again
so you can look at them on doing this
well I don't want VA start but I want VA
arrgh
so if I go to the definition of that you
can see it's kind of circuitous Li to
find here but we can just drill down you
can see how it goes right it's just
looking up into the stack to find
whatever the argument is that I tell it
and I'm gonna pass it this T and the T
value is just the type that I think
should be on the stack at the current
location right and it's gonna pop that
guy basically it will not only pop it
off the stack but it's going to like
advance it's sort of idea the VA list is
sort of a pointer right to where on the
stack we're reading from it's gonna move
that forward or in you know forward or
backwards depending on how your compiler
decided to do it but it's going to move
it in the correct direction for
advancement I'll put it that way it's
going to move it
by the size of that type so if I tell it
I want to read a care star it's going to
go forwards by like eight bytes on a
64-bit architecture right and it's going
to give me back the value that's in that
location so that's what I need to do so
if I see an S then I know well okay I've
got an argh list and I need to read a
care star because I'm expecting the
argument to be a care star so this is
like the string pointer right and now
that I have that string pointer I'm of
course supposed to insert the string
into the destination at this location
right well that's pretty easy to do
because we already know and I suppose I
could also do that advancing there
that's pretty easy to do because we know
that we already have the ability to just
kind of stream things out right we've
got this out care thing oops that I can
use so for example what I could pretty
easily here just go you know okay for a
care star you know source equals string
or something like this star source you
know plus plus source and for every
character in the source I'm just gonna
go ahead and output it to the
destination right so that's you know a
pretty easy pretty straightforward
version of the S code and so if I run
the game well I'd actually have to have
the game running there we go so if I run
the game now and we go to something that
was s you know an S style thing oops I
should be able to get it so that we can
actually print one of those out of
course that should be one there and I'm
not getting it so did I forget something
if at one oh I did
all right
so let's see what we get here there we
go
so in this case we got a string there's
the string that we're looking for I feel
like this should work right I wonder if
we need we probably need to support and
up passing a null string here too don't
we how we doing on this chunk X there we
go
so to copy that in there and
well that looks fine but for some reason
when we get to here we're getting a
string out up right so yeah we haven't
sort of another problem here that we're
going to have to address which is that
since we're walking the stack we have to
pull out all the other things too so I
can't just pull out the esses unless I'm
only printing out s's if that makes
sense because if someone has a % D on
the stack there I have to pull that one
out or it won't work right because since
I'm reading the stack in order if I just
go look for a care star because I'm only
think I'm looking for a percentage s is
that's not gonna work so I at least have
to grab out the other kinds of values
like I said I want to start with just
one so I can show you it working so what
I'm gonna do instead of that is I'm just
gonna straight-up break in the case
where where it's not a percent s so that
way we're only dealing with things who
were there percent s as their first
value if that makes sense of course I
suppose we kind of still need some way
of seeing the rest of the string kinda
think of good way to show this because
then we won't see anything there I guess
I could do something like this parsing
percent it's true that way we'll skip
anything that's that comes that comes
after
okay so let's see hopefully I should be
able to find something that has a
percent test as its first thing well I
guess all of these guys do right so
there you can see our percent s working
as we had intended it to work so you
know we've got origin chunk and and all
that sort of stuff so that's all not
that's all fine but you can kind of see
that also we don't get any percent print
at s is printing out when we are
proceeding them by something that we
don't understand and of course the
reason that that happens is because like
I just said since we have to you know
the the very args function is pushing
all of those things from the end of the
function onto the stack in order and we
have to peel them off in order if we
don't then we'll just get garbage right
because if we didn't peel off 1% D so
someone pushed an integer on then they
pushed a string pointer on if we don't
peel the integer off first right in
advance by that much to get to the
string that get to the care estar we're
just gonna garbage because we're going
to read the integer as the care star or
as the first half of the care star right
so we do have to be able to do that to
make sure all of this work right okay so
let's just try to take these in order
now you can see here that our first one
is a percent o2 f ms % d e % d p % d d
right so in this format string you know
these guys would be easy the percent d %
d % e and the percent o2 f ms we can try
to just like parse it we won't print the
floating-point number yet because i said
that was the part that's hard that we'll
have to save for a subsequent time but
we can sort of still hack it like we
still could sort of print it out in sort
of a janky way right or even if we don't
print out we could still just peel you
know advance the pointer properly so
that we can still print out the rest of
things all right so I want to take a
quick look to see what the actual spec
is for printf format specifiers just
because i don't know if they have to
come in any particular order or what the
rules are I don't really
No so it looks like you can have flags
that come first and these are the flags
so a minus a plus a space a pound and a
zero and those are left justify instead
of right justify force a plus or minus
for prepending right space is to use
blank spaces versus zeros you know so
you can do spaces with zeros and a
number is let's see used with Oh X
substernal student than 0 different than
0 so I guess this one just does ok so we
don't really care about most of these we
probably care only really about plus and
that's it so we can just look for those
two I think that's the only things we
really need to support for plus and 0 in
the flags ok so let's start with that so
we do parsing % and we see that it's got
a percent here and so then what we want
to do is say all right and I can get rid
of this now because we're gonna actually
grab everything here we go
so what I want to do here is I want to
now grab sort of all of the other things
that I can grab so with specifiers all
that sort of things so first I could do
you know if at 0 equals whatever we got
here I guess it was plus if that's 0
equals it's the other one I wanted to do
0 so we kind of know some things here
which is force sign pad with zeros and
the zeros true what sign true so we can
just kind of peel this 2 guys off and
again I'm not doing anything
particularly interesting cure this is
just pretty ugly code really and I
suppose like
sort of do this with a star for these
guys because we're we're not sort of
doing a look ahead in this case we're
just you know doing the the very first
thing we're looking at so first we're
just gonna say alright handle the flags
and you know for good measure I suppose
what we could do is accept but ignore
other things as well so you know I mean
I could say whatever this is left
justify right and then I guess it's just
space and pound what is it if no sign is
going to written a blank space so and
finally we got pound all right so if I
write it like this right and I'm just
kind of putting this out here so you can
kind of see it what was this thing this
was like Oh annotate if not zero so the
problem with this is right like I can't
quite write it exactly this way because
if I write it like this that could only
come in this specific order which I
don't really want them to write so sort
of what I need instead is some way to
kind of just sit in a little loop and to
read each one you know individually
right so I kind of need to do a thing
where I'm more like you know
I don't know something like parsing
equals true while parsing switch start
at and in here I kind of need something
it's more like you know whatever I got I
got I'm gonna put this here so I can now
say 'la and I could even kind of
condense this up into something a little
cleaner maybe like that right so now
I've kind of got this way of treating it
like a little mini tiny parser and that
way they can go in whatever order they
want the user can doesn't have to worry
about which one they put first I don't
know if that's exactly the intention of
the authors of the spec I mean printf
snot the most well thought-through thing
anyway but you know at least this way I
think the idea is that you're supposed
to be able to put them in any order so
let's just support that and assume that
that's true so that seems reasonable to
me we you know we come through here and
we just kind of go like okay let's you
know keep reading flag specifiers as
many as we get we've got fourth sign
paths to of left justify positive sign
it's blank annotate if not zero and
that's about it right yeah so then here
as well so then we'll come through our
single groups are saying equals true
we'll do the same thing for whatever
comes after it so let's see
we're supposed to have a Flags field
then a width field and the width field
can be the minimum number of characters
right so that's a number or it can be a
star so it has to be one or the other or
nothing right so we can either get a
number a star or nothing
so now we want to handle the width so
that doesn't really involve a parsing
loop like that
that just involves reading as many
numbers if we have them as we can read
or a star so basically it's like hey if
star at equals zero at this point I'm
sorry if u equals star at this point
then we're going to do plus plus at and
we're going to say that we need to read
the width and so the width itself I
don't really know what happens here but
I guess we'll say with specified equals
false and then we kind of need a thing
that's like what the width is right and
we'll just put 0 for now so according to
the spec in this case if the if there
was a star as the width we need to read
the width out of the stream right so we
know how to do that right we just do V a
argh and we can say arglist and then we
just have to say well ok if star is the
thing you know if there's integer coming
out of here
then we need whatever the you know the
int is and I want to put that into the
width and then we know the width was
specified as a specific value right
otherwise we want to see if you know the
star at sign is
you know in between the the numeric
range so if it is then we've basically
got a number that we want to read so
then we want to say that the wisp
specified is true and at that point I
feel like we we have the notion in here
somewhere that we can read values right
we've got this s 32 from from Z kind of
thing so I should be able to just call
this now one thing that's kind of
annoying about this is it doesn't tell
us how far it read right so what we
could do is we could also say s3 2 from
Z we could say that this returns the
value and the new at right I could do
something like that and that seems
pretty compelling because then I can
make the old function s3 2 from Z where
you pass in the @ sign and then I could
do sort of like internal or something
like this like that that returns a more
complicated result and so there we had
would have result that value would be
the thing that's being tracked here and
when we get to the end the result new at
is going to be equal to whatever the at
was then we return that result so this
function can just do call the internal
one and just return the value so that's
all fine but then you know down here
where we actually care we can just say
like oh alright there was a value that
we wanted to read so let's get the width
by just saying s3 2 from Z width read s
32 from Z internal and I'll pass that at
sign and I'll say at
you know what else I could do I could
make this even simpler I could just do
don't even bother with that and just say
this takes a pointer to a pointer to an
apt right because then I could just do
like alright so do too so and this way
we just write it back into here and then
this guy just says well alright there's
an ignored value that you know it
basically creates a little pointer that
this guy will lock and then we're all
good right yeah so that seems reasonable
that simplifies things a little I don't
care about that anymore okay I guess we
don't have a B 32x in this code base
which is fine so now all I have to do is
say well read the width and read it from
this at so that'll advance it and then
we know the widths was specified right
so that just eats up whatever the
numbers were that came before it and
treats those as the width and then we
consider the width to have been
specified and then we're good to go
right so that seems pretty
straightforward now we have to deal with
the precision which is a dot and then a
number or a dot and then a star so it's
essentially the same code is this but
it's just it's if they're only if there
is a dot percieving right so essentially
what I want to do is say precision
specified false precision zero I guess
since these are technically s thirty
twos
I don't know what happens if you specify
a negative width but I guess we'll allow
it for now because I don't really know
maybe that's when we read the spec
because it says that integer so that's
signed so anyway when we come through
here we go ahead and do the exact same
code if there is a dot
so if star at equals dot then we need to
do the exact same code we have here like
so if it's star we read the precision
and if it's not then we parse it out of
the stream we could also since now we
know here if we see the dot I think it
has to be we could say this is a
malformed printf precision string or a
precision specifier just so the
programmer knows that they probably mess
something up because if we see the dot
we know that there's really only it's
only allowed to be a star or a number so
at that point we want to make sure we
handle that okay so now we've got
precision in there so finally I think
the only thing we need after that is the
actual specifiers and there they are
right there's a d uo x fe g a CSP and %
or whatever yeah so let's see what let's
just take these one at a time we'll just
do a switch start at and we'll do a to
these so case D or case I these are
apparently the same case according to
the listing there we've got a u we have
an O
X's we've got F can't say I know what
decimal floating point lowercase and
decimal floating point uppercase mean
but I guess that means if you're gonna
print out a man or kyun in or imp
whether you wanted it upper or lowercase
pretty impressive that they thought that
was necessary to specify but alright no
sense not dotting your T's Crossing your
eyes and so on so we've got e G G and
then we've got a and a hexadecimal
floating point hmm I didn't know that
that was in there I feel like that must
be new because I don't think that was
there originally s he
and percent and other what does that
thing call just of our unrecognized
format specifier so we've got one of
these already right and I guess no
matter what we do here when we read this
off we're going to increment forwards
right I guess the only case is if if it
was null right
so if start at is valid we'll advance by
it but if it was no we don't want to
read past the end of the string and
confuse people with a crash or something
like that but yeah in this case we just
go alright we've got a string that looks
like that so that one's done and then we
just have to implement all these other
guys here and like I said we don't
really have to implement them yet we
just have to make sure we're getting the
right argument type off first so that we
can take them one at a time from there
so this is just going to be write a an
integer that's what it's specified as
being so here's the value we're printing
in this case it's going to be an
unsigned integer in this case I don't
know what an unsigned octal actually is
but I assume that this is always going
to be a
I assume that these are always going to
be integers unless we have instructions
otherwise but I feel like we could have
instructions otherwise couldn't we like
shouldn't there be like an L specifier
or something like there's nothing here
that says that the thing is gonna be
long ah there it is
length we forgot one so where does that
come flying with precision length and
then specifier okay so one more
oops so one more we got to do here
HHH LLL jzt and L boy I feel like they
could have done a better job with this
but all right so it looks like
it looks like essentially the only thing
you can do with floats is to make a long
double which which I don't even support
so really we don't care about that at
all so L is out so it looks like we're
mostly looking at HHH l so I don't
really care about most of these so I
think we'll probably take the same
attack here I'll lead them all but I
don't think we're gonna actually do any
of them except for L which is if we want
to say like you know it's a long a
64-bit value or whatever right which I
guess is ll in this case can't quite
tell so would an unsigned long int be 32
bits or 64 bits by this nominal Eicher
right is that you know is that 64 is
that I don't know you gotta love that
nonsense
but anyway so if we want to handle the
length here really all we have to do is
just take a look and see if we can match
any of these things
so if star at equals we've got I guess
this one I'll do normal form because
these are doubles so if it's H followed
by another H or an L followed by another
L
those are double character sequences
everything else is single so all right
so we've got H's we got ELLs
we've got jzt jay-z and capital L and so
you know yeah in each of these cases
we're gonna advance I don't know which
one of these were going to handle in
actuality but yeah so at that point we
need to be able to read these often if
you look at what's happening here really
all of the you know we want to handle
these guys in groups because if we do
end up specifying widths these guys are
easy because they're all specific to
themselves but but these guys kind of
happen in groups so like we don't want
to have to deal with a separate type of
read code for all of this stuff right we
want to be able to just read off the
value using some kind of a with
specifier that we make right so yeah I
don't know what to do about that exactly
other than probably something like
excuse me with some nose blowing time
here and hey my hero I guess what I'll
do is just get kind of the largest
possible value I can and then we'll just
you know read their argh
you 64 or something like this I don't
know exactly we'll call it but what I
want to do here is just say like okay
somebody has to use the width specifier
at this point to figure out which one of
these we're going to do because actually
we might read a u8 you know or are you
16 or are you 32 or are you 34 when we
read one of these so I guess we'll say
Reaver are integer right and we don't
know which of those types of values we
actually want right we have no idea and
I guess we could even pick whether we're
doing signed or not so you could do
something like switch on blank and we'll
just have to do something like this and
you can see that's pretty ugly right
it's the kind of code that C doesn't
really make particularly easy to write
because it's still very procedural it's
still very clear how you would make this
concise but basically you suddenly have
to take like a leap in the template land
and things go really horribly wrong when
you go there so they just there isn't
really a whole lot you can do if you
value you know any sort of semblance of
working code in C to make things that
are you know cleaner than something like
this but that's roughly yet so we could
do something like okay past the length
and arglist and and off we go
right now the arglist in this case I
think we would want it to be a pointer
because we need it to advance
unfortunately yeah that kind of means
that we've got to do this little dance
here where I have to dereference it so
that
they're macro kanri reference it which
is kind of stupid but I believe that's
just what we're gonna have to do because
we want to use the artist and advance it
so that our parents gets it advanced
right so this is essentially what we're
looking at you know we've got we've got
a floating-point version and a non
floating-point version right and the
floating-point version really is when
we're gonna accept two things I suppose
because we don't really have a way to
read anything else if that makes sense
and also I suppose I probably did I
never do an F I've recently I don't
think I ever mentioned this but I've
recently been less enamored with R and
I've switched to F and the reason was
because it sounds too much like red when
you use them in like things that are
like packed value formats it's it tends
to get confused at the red channel I
find whereas F doesn't really get
confused with anything so I've kind of
kind of changed my feelings on that
anyway so now we can kind of do these
guys a little bit differently we could
say here like okay so there's a value
that for reading and it's read ver Arg
float or integer depending on which one
we want and we need to pass the length
thing to it thanks I don't know what
we'll call this I'm just going to call
it Lin so this will be you through to
when equals I guess the default Len is
just always for in well you know what
we've got to I guess we have integer Len
and float length because the default
float length is 8 and the default
integer length is 4 so yeah so then we
can just kind of go in through here and
say all right if I'm doing a float
like it would be in say this case I just
do a float length arglist
and I can grab that and so all these
guys can do that read and you know what
these this has to be an address as well
I think that's all of those so that will
get all of those guys out then we have
our integers far argh integer integer
length there we go
and I don't know what we're gonna have
to do about the sign extensions sort of
stuff there so we'll take a look at that
in a in a second because really so when
we do reading the integer and we get the
you 64 out we should be able to just
kind of cast it slightly to another one
so I could do you know unsigned integer
and then have another one that's just
like signed and it just does read word
unsigned integer
and we'll just pretend that that value
that we read was actually a sign value
because when we read it off the list
right it doesn't know what it is so it
just cast it to that and sticks it in
the value so when it comes out if it was
signed well the values still correct for
the signed value it just C thinks it's
the wrong thing so all we really have to
do is tell C hey by the way that value
was actually signed so you know just
chill out man and off you go so that
should be fine
so this should be signed integer and
this should be unsigned integer right
and then for the rest of these guys I
think they're all unsigned right I don't
think exes
I don't think exes or any of these guys
oh these are floats nevermind
this desert floats see is just a care I
think right so I don't is there anything
can do with C oh you can you can get a W
in T out of it so I guess we still have
to sort of maybe a little bit I don't
know whether this means I should still
read it or whether it's an error because
like there's nothing in the table here
so I'm not sure what they actually want
you to do there
and in either case it reads the same
size right like what's a W into T is
that actually bigger type death of a
type elderson maker so yeah so I don't
think that's so I don't know exactly
what we should be doing there to be
honest with you how much for we supposed
to read here so anyway keep on going
here I think I've got a little time left
anyway because I started about 10
minutes late anyway so we'll read that
value out there and then we've got the P
+ + % the % case we don't read anything
off the stream that's just the case
where we output like if someone was
actually just trying to output % right
straight up the P case is what a pointer
address so that's still gonna be the
same kind of a read I suspect although
that does that mean we always would read
a pointer size yeah it looks like it's
always a void star so basically that's
another one that always comes out the
same size no matter of what and then the
N is when we write the number of
characters written so far so basically
this is going to be a pointer to a
signed integer so you know this is
basically a destination like a tab best
or something this is if we want to know
how many reprinted I don't know that we
use that anywhere other either but we
might as well parse it properly we can
always choose not to support you know
any of these we don't feel like writing
but you know so in this case we grab it
in town I guess we should keep the int
value even though we're only supposed to
process of the C but let's go ahead and
start running it I don't know
disastrous this is going to be but we'll
see so let's take a look here where we
at
we've got a dot on here let me let's
step through this code at least once
because I don't even know what's going
on here okay so first we want to take a
look we've got a dot o 2f specifier so
that means there's no there's nothing in
here right which is good so we just skip
over the flags because there's no flags
we then have to handle the whip and
there's no whip either so we skip that
we got a precision so then we look to
see whether it's a star it's not a star
we look to see if it's a number oh there
we go we're missing that we're missing a
little plus we need to consume that plus
earned that dot rather so that's all
good yeah and in this case we still have
it to do here right which is to do
actually set different values here which
we're not doing ok all right so I think
let's see here
we're getting there
I'm recognized format specifier which is
what what was the string that we were
past present a 2.0 2f % %
I feel like that should have worked so
that is a bug that is not a malformed
specifier let's try that again
I want to nope that's not what I wanted
can you show me thank you I would like
to go ahead and I'm gonna kind of cheat
here a little bit because I wanted to
bug that one case what I'd like to do
here is just sort of fake it I'm going
to basically say that instead of every
time you you call format string I'm
actually just going to like pretend that
that's actually the string that that
that we were given right so I'm gonna
say like you know format string well you
know what I don't even have to do that
I'll just put this at the very start
so here's game update in render and I'm
just going to go ahead and put it right
here and so that's just takes a
floating-point number but that's that's
it so I should be able to just pass it a
one okay so let's go ahead and compile
that and now in theory the first time I
come through here should get should hit
that right I should get that case and I
do so let's see what I do I've got a I'm
gonna jump forwards to where we actually
hit the format specifier let's see what
we get here says the 0 we get pad with
zeros that does seem a good idea
we then don't get anything else and
that's what we would expect we come down
here we don't see a star for the width
but we should see it too so let's
advance that we did and the width is 2
that's what we want the width has an
average specified we look at the Pacific
fest flowers the precision specifier
says there's a dot there is a dot that
we advance forward we take a look it's
not a star it is however a number well
ok so actually it seems like we're
missing there should have been
recognition of the fact that there was a
leading 0 as a separate thing so I kind
of have to fix that as well but let me
just go see what the other problem is
here so it goes and grabs the F off of
here there it is and you know these guys
don't advance their letter at the moment
which they should now we it's unclear
whether we want to go through here and
advance every single one's letter or
whether we just want to have someone
who's not supposed to advance back up
but I don't even know if that's relevant
oh wait no we actually did we did do
didn't
no I guess in all cases we don't I
thought I did it like if at so I must
have accidentally deleted it because
they're gonna say we used to do it right
so after that I just want to say if
start you know plus plus that I
accidentally deleted that I guess okay
so let's try that one more time
and watch what happens in the and you
know what I want to fix that one of the
thing first so in this case what I
really want to say is if it's a star
okay it's a star that's all good but
then we should have had let's something
in here let's see
I feel like they'd it's not really
documented the dot zero part like it
doesn't really say anything about that
the dietary written is short of this
number the result is padded with leading
zeros so does that mean point zero two
is not really a valid form string and it
shouldn't huh all right I guess maybe my
point zero two is not even really should
it just be point two I don't know
all right well I guess I don't have to
fix that then back to the debugging so
let's take a look at what happens in
here first time through so we get down
to here and we're at the percent F thing
we advanced forward so now we come
through here what happens well we skip
the percent all of these oops that's not
what I wanted
okay we skip all of these because none
of them should be there so I'm just
gonna verify that they're actually skip
because maybe one of them isn't skipped
or something like this no that happens
we then do a switch we find the percent
and that's good and we advance so I
think now if it was just the fact that I
actually deleted the advance I think
that was the only problem so now I think
we're all good
and yeah this looks much better now okay
so I think we've essentially set
ourselves up for success now we just
have to do a couple printout routines
and those will be real easy to do
probably I think except for the floating
point one like I said but everything
else looks like it's in reasonable shape
so I'm going to go ahead and remove that
test code here since it's no longer
necessary and then I'm a growth QA Q and
a
not a lot of questions which makes sense
it's pretty straightforward duplicating
printf is just kind of busy work for the
most part
soy sauce the kid will you be doing a
sprint F it it is for at F that that is
printf that's what we just wrote I mean
that's printf right there right
is the github repo accessible to
pre-orders yes it is it's not really a
supported feature so no guarantees that
you know it'll work for you or whatever
but every pre-order does come with the
code because people wanted it come with
a code that allows them to authorize on
the github so it's not an official
feature of pre-ordering but it is
actually available to everyone who
pre-orders I just don't support it like
if you screw up in authorize the wrong
username you're on your own
like I'm not even gonna look at it so
it's not an officially supported part of
pre-ordering whereas if you like can't
download the source code for some reason
from the normal send owl supported thing
I go and find out why and help you
I'm following you're serious from
beginning and I'm writing my own game is
it okay to use in my win32 lair similar
code with same thought but mostly
written by myself actually what I've
said before is the platform layer stuff
like the win32 code and stuff you can
just use exactly the one that's in
hammer here if you want it's not in a
shippable state right now anyway like I
you know it will require a bunch of work
to finish off parts of it for shipping
but you can just use it so if you wrote
something solar to it you can also use
that but you can actually just use it I
pretty much already said that that part
can be used but even before the rest of
the source code is officially released
as public domain just because you know
the it's just some platform code I don't
mind if people want to work with it
early what do you think for DRM I'm
assuming that's a joke question I guess
I don't know you know it might not be a
joke question but if it's not a joke
question the answer is there's no DRM on
handmade here oh I hate DRM if it is a
joke question then the answer is like
obviously handmade hero will have to run
constantly connected to a server and as
soon as you if you don't connect to a
server with like strong authentication
and everything then it will just shut
off the game immediately
hey guys how come the handmade the hmd
bot doesn't mention the fact that this
keyboard was given to me by bib low and
fiery Drake this is actually a gift
keyboard it should say it should say in
the little thing who is responsible for
the keyboard and in so far I think
that's an excellent idea I think every
version of handmade hero should require
a yeah like a one of those like rotating
RSA key like USB plug things and if you
don't have that plug in your machine you
can't run the game at all
like that's just it forget it like you
can't even run it I mean that's like
bare minimum for sure
all right let's shut this down thank you
everyone for joining me from the episode
of handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with us always if you would like
to follow along at home you can always
peer to the game on hand made here at
Oregon it comes with the source code so
you can follow along each night on your
own and experiment if you would like to
we also have a forum site you can go to
ask questions a patreon page you can go
to if you want to support the video
series a schedule bot that'll tweet the
schedule at you if you want to catch the
series live and we also have an episode
guide maintains our very own mid lobe
that has wonderful annotated time
ordered notes on it so it's really easy
to catch up with past episodes and jump
around to the parts that you're
interested in that's about it for today
tomorrow will be the very last stream
for a while because I will be out of
town and I won't really have access to
anything I can use to stream in a
reliable way so we'll be a couple weeks
off hopefully everybody who wants to get
caught up will have time to get caught
up and I'll post the schedule when it
will resume once I know so yeah I hope
to see you back here tomorrow 8 p.m.
Pacific Daylight Time for the final
stream for a while before hiatus until
then have fun programming and I'll see
you guys on the Internet
take it easy everyone