hello everybody and welcome to handmade
hero we are uh trying to fix a problem
today that is the problem uh that you
can see we have we introduced some kind
of a bug at least i think we did uh when
we we really did some nice work with the
lighting um and it's it's very like
efficient now and does really uh pretty
pretty dramatic largely large number of
samples uh but we have this like light
brightness contamination problem i
suspect it's actually due to a bug and
not an algorithmic issue i think we
introduced some kind of a bug like where
we're sampling or filling something
wrong you can see when we don't have the
light contamination it looks great i
love the look of the lighting it's it's
fantastic um
but we get this weird light
contamination bug where uh you know
you can see the sort of weird effects
with the lights where they like over
bright
um and there's just something very
strange going on that
really to me doesn't look
logical like i'm guessing that it's that
it's an actual like
uh
you know whenever you have a lighting
system it could just be a bug i mean
sorry it could just be a um an
algorithmic bug meaning oh you're doing
this sampling slightly wrong or you're
you know you you've got some kind of a
math issue that's going to lead to
feedback or something like that it's
certainly possible that that's what's
going on um and you know maybe the
reason we're seeing it now is because
the lighting is running at such
a high rate that you know it quickly
contaminates whereas before it would
like very be very slow
or something like that
um totally plausible but i also think
it's very uh plausible that maybe we had
a bug
uh that just wasn't really uncovered by
the old system the old way the old
system work kind of masked the bug um or
something or
we introduced a new bug that actually is
is doing something fundamentally wrong
here um that leads to this result
so uh either way that's what we have to
track down and thankfully uh it's it is
somewhat detectable so in other words if
i go into the code here
we actually have some checks that we can
run um that we did before
i think they were in the lighting atlas
code here
where we can turn on this light atlas
assert and what that does is it slows
things down quite a bit by just running
over the atlas all the time
looking at these texels and running this
validate texel component uh call right
um and you can see that validate text
component call
uh in here it basically just
does whatever check we want whatever
we're looking for at the time
um and what you can see here is that
there's a
the way of producing a valid test
component here is we've got this range
negative hundred to a hundred
my guess is that you know now we should
really never have things that are below
zero uh i don't
see how you would actually get that uh
we could check
uh but you shouldn't really ever ever be
able to do that
um so if we set let's just see what
happens if we if we set it to a uh
guarantee that it's above zero i'm not
sure it might be that it occasionally is
slightly below uh but i'd like to see so
i'm going to turn on the light atlas
asserts here
and then we're going to see what happens
if we um if we run it do we ever get any
light values below zero uh because i
don't think we would right and the
reason for that is that lighting is
always summed
uh it's a sum you know it's a weighted
sum
and since none of the lights are we
don't have the concept of negative
lights there's we don't have in the game
right now anything that's like sucking
light out of a region
um so
because of that uh you would never
expect the number to be zero because we
never we would never even if we didn't
clamp it uh or anything else you would
never expect you'd be able to sum right
so uh if we check that we now know that
we can have like kind of a lower bound
there but we also know we could now
impose an upper bound which is to say
that our lighting system because it is a
summation of um
of samples we should never be able to
produce things that get higher than the
power of the light sources in a region
and my assumption is that we do because
that's how you would get this over
writing here i don't know what the level
whoa
that's really cool i don't know what the
level of over brightness is but i'm
hoping that this would
trigger of course it didn't i'm
wondering did i do this wrong
um
because you would think that would
trigger here the fact that it's not
triggering here
uh is a little suspicious maybe this was
not actually on
let's let's take a let's double check i
don't actually know
so here the validate test component call
will always return false so this way if
we want to we can say like okay look it
should stop right away
and it looks like it does so that's good
um i don't know why this
zero to 100
it seems odd that that wouldn't trigger
based on what we're seeing but i guess
i'm wrong i thought we tested this and
it did trigger so i'm a little bit
weirded out about what's happening here
um but i don't know i mean i guess we're
gonna find out
when we
when we go here uh also i suppose
there's a separate issue which is that
we are viewing the specular lighting
here i'm sorry the diffuse lighting here
um i guess we haven't really looked at
the specular lighting and so it could be
that there's something weird going on
there i'm not sure uh that's a that's a
tough question and i guess we'll have to
look at that a little bit more closely
as we go
all right so i guess the next question
is can we do some kind of a bounds check
here where we reduce this to something
that does trigger
is there a lighting bound that will
trigger
and i don't know
um if there isn't that's further
that's a further clue as to what's going
on because i don't i have no idea how
what we could be seeing could be
happening if the lighting values are
always
within range
this should surely trigger because i
think we actually have light values
right now that are greater than one so
again unless this code is just broken um
i would think
yeah
um
let me go ahead and switch this to debug
mode i'd like to see exactly where
that's uh i assumed the validate text
component
so don't think that would be called
there i i wanna see what that's doing
i'm not entirely sure
why it would stop there um
on a push like call it might have been
actually above that but we'll see
okay so we do have a validate text on
the push drift call that's just to
guarantee that no light that we push in
is brighter than the texel validation
right
so i'm i'm really weirded out now i mean
this is possibly good it might mean that
this bug will be more obvious than i was
thinking i was assuming this would take
a while to hunt down because i was
assuming it was going to be pretty weird
right but if we can't even find a light
texel value that's outside of this
fairly narrow range that might mean that
actually this is
a much more straightforward bug to find
and that we're not getting weird
exponential light leaking or anything
like that
so what's the brightest kind of light
that we're sending down here i don't
actually know it looks like we've got a
5-5-5 emission
um and that's in
some entity i assume we're just doing
like lights in the world
uh in our like
you know in our room generation or
whatever
i assume that we have uh
some kind of standard lighting here that
we do you can see here
uh we have
lighting that we're adding
i guess we iterate over these
with the light spacing you can see that
here
this was just some lights that we added
and you can see
there's some kind of a of a light
this is the code where we add it i
believe this is the size
of the light so quite large
um this is the light
uh amount itself
and
i guess i don't know how the emissions
works out exactly uh let me just double
check that i'm interpreting those values
correctly because i don't remember what
they all are
so add piece light is here you can see
it's like entity radius offset emission
color okay so no i take that back so
this isn't the size of the light i guess
the size of the light is the first one
so it's it's this
that actually is the emission so it
multiplies this lamp light color
uh and so that would make sense this is
a 10 emission light but each one of
these is like around 0.5 so we would
expect everything to be around a 5 power
light
right
makes sense
so i guess i'm not sure
uh exactly
what to make of this uh
because so the weird thing about this is
that i don't know
that kind of means that maybe this is
just an exposure problem
like that could mean that we because we
just don't have an exposure curve in
here like i wonder if we're just that
literally this isn't weird what we're
seeing
um
if that makes sense because if we went
into the validation layer and just said
look
you should roughly be i mean let's give
it a little bit of headroom for
numerical accuracy sake but you should
just always be
uh in line here
and then we
uh go in and we
nerf out anywhere that was adding so the
fir that ad piece light should should
assert right away uh so we go in here
and say okay let's let's knock those
down to a value that's legal that's
light legal right um in
in what we're looking at here
and uh and we then run again et cetera
et cetera like let's try to get to a
place and see do we actually have this
problem occur if all of the lights are
within bounds right um and i'm gonna go
ahead and assume that that's all fine
and switch to the
release build here
so here's our lighting running where
everything is basically kept within the
zero one range and hey guess what uh we
don't seem to have this bug right
um
so to me that sort of suggests that
actually maybe the bug is just that we
don't have any exposure there are some
light flickering artifacts that i'm not
sure what they're from
that looks kind of
uh
a little bit broken but it might just be
because the lighting region is a little
too small right um if you look at uh
where we're checking you can see like
okay the light
as i move here when the trees page in
that appears to be when that lighting
changes
uh so it may be that we just need a
slightly larger region than what we're
currently using
if that makes sense so we may need just
slightly bigger it looks like there's a
light that's too bright here i don't
know who is
adding that light
but so there is somebody still adding
lights that are too bright for them
again that's okay because i don't think
we actually want to fix this problem
that way i just wanted to verify that
that was the case
uh and and then we'll think about this a
little bit more okay
so if that's the case then i think i've
learned probably what i
probably what i need to learn here which
is that this is actually not necessarily
um
this is not necessarily actually light
contamination this is maybe just an
artifact of the way our algorithm
convects light
um
and i guess i'm not
really sure
so
here are some
kind of confusing aspects of this i'll
just go through them
so first of all why do the lights on our
system have fall off right because if if
you notice like we don't actually have
any light fall off coefficients or
anything like that the lights are just
the lights we never programmed in you
know you can see here
um
you can see here what appears to be
light fall off
uh but we didn't program any light fall
off so why did that happen
well the reason that happens is because
as you get further away it is simply
proportionally less likely that you will
hit the light source with the rays that
you cast so the inverse square law is
not actually in our computations it's in
our casting because we cast a fixed
number of rays out from every light
sample point so each of the light probes
cast a fixed number of rays the
percentage chance that any of those rays
will hit a particular light source goes
down with the inverse square of the
distance away from the light ergo the
lighting ends up with an inverse squared
falloff but we never wrote that in there
it's just an artifact sampling exactly
the same reason in real life that you
have inverse square it's because if you
emit photons the chance that any one of
those photons hits a particular
region of of uh space is
going to go down as you get uh further
away from the emitter of the photons
proportional the inverse square law
right so the inverse square law is
literally just there as a thing that you
uh that you get when you sample lighting
the way that lighting actually gets
sampled right
so
that's why we're getting this fall off
now the thing about the over brighting
is
we also when we throw out a light like
when we cast a ray
if the ray goes a certain distance and
doesn't hit anything it just samples the
lights in the from the probe in that
area
and it's possible that that algorithm
because that gather
that gather does not have the inverse
square law in it right
um
it may be that that
when you are in that state
first of all i guess let me let me do
this
suppose i just turned that off like
suppose we hack into our grid raycast
and the code for the grid raycast uh is
going to just be
if you don't hit something like if
you're going to bail on the grid raycast
because you ran out of walks cycles like
you you went too far or whatever uh like
this right
uh instead of doing a probe uh sample uh
p single or whatever we somehow turn
this off
right
so in the code like
uh in in here
we just don't
um
i mean another thing we could do is just
force it to go all the way so we just
say there's no such thing as grid walk
iteration
this this termination condition is just
not going to happen anymore i don't know
if that'll be sufficient because it
still will happen at the no at the edges
um but presumably that's okay
it might not be um but we'll see so
suppose we run it um
that way do we still get it we do so
that's a little weird because i'm not
sure why that would happen um
like i said the inverse square law
should still be in effect there
so i would think that you would still
get the fall off
unless i'm misunderstanding something um
i suppose there's a
a collusion
and a hit emission so i suppose we could
do something like a hit ref color gets
zeroed
like so suppose that inside here when we
terminate we set the hit ref color to
zero
i think that would do it
um but i'm not sure
okay so that at least
seems to confirm my suspicion
right
um
if we end up
going
if we were if we would have hit a
termination criteria here
um
i still see some weird like i don't know
what is going on there
right that seems a little weird right so
i think we got a little bit more
bugginess going on here but just in
terms of looking at what happens you can
now see that the contamination is no
longer actually occurring
i don't know what exactly is happening
there
like in that one particular case we can
get the contamination so something it
still feels wrong it still feels like
something
pretty busted is going on there
you know what i mean
but you can see if we just have if we
just don't allow you know if we don't
allow that sort of spread to occur so
somehow like
these rooms where we have the
you know i suppose it makes sense
because it's green
um these rooms where we sort of have
these the the green lights seem to be
the only place that this actual problem
comes from i guess which is a little
weird i'm not sure why
hey there's the puss
um
so this is interesting i wonder uh this
is kind of a separate issue
but
let me look at this a little bit more
closely
oh and also let's let's draw occluders
and like like base let's draw the
spatial partition
um there's like a draw spatial grid
debug draw spatial grid function here
um and like we'll get rid of cell bounds
we'll draw the uh actual pieces that are
in the spatial grid
uh
and
i'll turn on rendering of that just so
we can see like what's going on
uh with that
so you know as you can see there's one
of the interesting things about this is
there's no actual
um
pieces of geometry with me because we
turned them off like we don't push a
light on there or anything as far as i
can tell there's nothing going into the
lighting grid so my positioning in the
world should not really have an effect
on what's going on
the scrolling might like i said because
you know it new things come in which can
affect the lighting is a global solution
that's happening on basically everything
in this blue
square
so as the blue square slides around you
would expect the lighting solution to
change
to a certain extent
but it doesn't make a whole lot of sense
why it changed like that amount of
change
also another thing that's very strange
is it seems to only happen on quarters
like you notice like
wrong right
wrong right so when it scrolls one half
of the way
you know when it's done one click it's
wrong when it does another click it's
right you know what i'm saying
uh and so that feels really odd uh it
suggests that maybe there's like a bug
with the fact that you know uh the way
the system works if you look at the
spatial grid
um the spatial grid is actually aligned
uh to
the spatial grid actually has like four
four atlas cells
per grid square
uh there like there's more in each
grid square uh there's there's four grid
squares in one spatial atlas
the reason that we did that was because
uh we were
you know based on our metrics we found
that there just wasn't enough geometry
in one of those uh square like there
wasn't enough geometry in a single grid
square uh to justify actually walking
that many you know what i mean
so it turned out to just be more
efficient to have more of them in there
and you know maybe that was a mistake
i'm not entirely sure
it could be that it was
um
it could be that it was but either way
uh
the whether or not that decision was a
poor one
has fairly little to do with the fact
that it definitely seems to have an
effect
standing right there allows the light to
leak
standing right here doesn't and there's
no
real explanation for that that i can
think of
right
um
i guess
one thing i could imagine being true
is
if that has something to do with the
fact that
the
boundary is
possible to hit
in this case and not really possible to
hit in the other case
hmm
i say
the fact that those leaves are kind of
stuck as well is kind of weird to me
you know what i mean
like why
is that some kind of a nan sort of thing
or like why are those unable to clear
um i don't quite get that so presumably
if i clear them out this way and i go
back in now they would be right
um
but like that's very strange
hmm
i say
i mean
i literally have no idea how to explain
that pattern do you
so i think we need to figure out some
way to test this scenario more
astringently i i just like this is
bizarre
um
and i would say like it's gotta be a
legit bug meaning
i mean how could that be like a math
error right like how could that be like
oh we're just sampling poorly and we
should wait the samples different like
that's got to be a bug bug like oh hey
you're sampling outside the bounds or
the thing or like there's some like way
that like uninitialized value can get in
there
right
um
but i don't have a good strategy for it
at the moment
um let's start by drawing the octahedral
values since there's like looking at the
spatial grid didn't really tell us very
much we do know that something about
that stagger looks wrong meaning like as
we kind of
um
so you know there is the fact that when
light probes are inside a light region
we don't update their value
i wonder if that has something to do
with it we should probably look um
uh but here's our here's our actual
light probes and uh you can see
so this light this is a bug we have
right now that that we needed to fix at
some point we just haven't quite decided
how uh but it's actually removing light
from the system so i doubt it's involved
in this
uh which is that if a light probe is
inside a light source it erroneously
gets set to no light
you know what i'm saying
um
so there's that
uh but again that's
if anything helping us right now because
it's not providing
light contamination it's actually like
forcing those light samples to zero
i so you know
that's not really implicated in this
case
you can see there's some weird like you
can see the sort of
weird light changing here
and
you know the
i feel like that's a little bit of a
clue
so if you notice
when the light when there are not
when we would be going outside right
that's that's going outside the um
there is no wall
to stop
things getting hit here
when i hop forward now there is
when i hop back you can see that the
light changes to a green tone
but why
right there's no reason why the lighting
should become green at that point i
don't think
so the fact that not having a wall
makes the lighting green is kind of
confusing now maybe it's not because
these lights are sort of a little bit
green tinted
and i suppose maybe for the sake of our
current predicament where we're trying
to debug things
maybe i should see what happens if we
don't do randomized lamp lighting
so for example if instead of uh
randoms here we actually
force all lights to be pure gray right
like pure white
they don't shift the color at all
um does that still happen i don't know
let's find out
so it looks like the answer is no
uh so the green
is is
maybe because these lights were green
i'm not sure right but you can see that
that had to be the case because now it's
not now that everything so it really
just gets a little brighter as you go
and these lights get paged in which
again suggests that this wants to be
expanded a little bit it looks like
maybe these lighting bounds are a little
too conservative it should be larger the
region that we're lighting
and that's fine but that's sort of a
separate issue
from the actual bug bug with the light
contamination
so if we go uh now that there is no bias
there like the lights are all pure white
um or i should say pure gray i don't
know what you want to call it they're
they're color neutral
can we still get the bug where we get
the weird
green here i mean
uh weirdly the answer to that also
appears to kind of be no
um which is very confusing
because that
i don't know why that would be the case
does that mean that you just have to
exceed a certain power value before you
can get that bug or something like where
did the bug go right
where did the bug go
so assuming i set these lights to the
maximum value that they could have
picked when we did randomized so i'm
going to set them both to seven
so it's basically going to yeah it's
just a just a
more powerful light
shouldn't it
now
it should have the bug right i mean if
it doesn't have the bug i don't know
what's going on
yeah
although it still doesn't quite
contaminate there it goes
so
this is really confusing because that
almost suggests that somehow this is not
a bug
or not exactly a bug i don't know it
must be though because how is it
happening how does it leak only on the
quarters
let's think about that
something's up
so how are we leaking only on quarters
how's that possible
uh first of all can we delete some of
this code
uh like what do we use some of this
stuff for nothing right
we don't care about quadrant index
we ask for the cell center
for wherever it is that we are
do we care about the remainder
we do not so that can stop coming in
here
right
so remainder is now
not something we need
uh which is great again that's because
we now do the stepping auto uh
automatically gets solved we don't have
to use tables anymore
um
so yeah
is it that this computation is wrong and
we're sampling the wrong places somehow
um
hasn't i don't understand like i can't
think of a real reason why that would
change
the reason that that doesn't make a
whole lot of sense to me is because i
don't see
why it would make a difference
even if you stepped through the spatial
partition incorrectly i don't understand
why you would get that light leaking it
doesn't really make
it doesn't really make great sense
i guess if you suppose that the light
somehow you always exited with a value
that was producing some kind of an odd
clamp
then if you put a light always
if you imagine that there was a bug in
the light
tracing so that
you
when you hit this bug or that you often
times
because of this bug or whatever end up
clamping to let's say the maximum or
minimum bound of the lighting volume
then you could imagine getting the light
contamination because you have placed
when when a particular when a light
source
ends up
locked into that placement
at where because that's where you would
keep sampling
right
um
it's not a good
idea
what i'm saying but it's an idea it's
better than what we've had so far which
is not an idea
so just to be more concrete about what
i'm trying to say here is suppose that
we go
and we look at an area that's having uh
the light leaking versus the time when
it's not
so uh let's suppose i hop back here
like i'm not getting light leaking right
now right
uh and if i zoom out slightly to show
what the lighting volumes look like
you can see that the corners currently
don't have a light source in them
exactly right the
by the way anytime i say exactly did you
y'all ever watch the qualcomm keynote
the most amazing keynote like ever given
uh
where like
it has bishop desmond tutu and steve
ballmer and big bird and maroon 5
in the same keynote
and like steve balmer is like is like
disney's where's my water application
like that one has anyone seen this
anyone
has anyone seen the qualcomm keynote
that i'm talking about
are you serious
okay good i was hoping someone had seen
it because i'm like if no one's seen
that keynote it's the most important
keynote ever in the history of time
because it is so amazing and ridiculous
like it's it's hard to make it all the
way through because it's so cringy but
at the same time it's easy to make it
all the way through because it's so nuts
you're laughing the whole time
embarrassed but laughing the whole time
anyway the reason that came
to mind was because at the very end well
it's not the very end but almost at the
end of the keynote
um
the ceo guy i think it is
asks like one of his underlings right
it's like
hey were you born mobile and the guy
goes not exactly
and
it always just sticks in my head the way
he says that
it's like
not exactly
and so uh whenever i say exactly i i
sometimes get uh
uh yeah it's the one the the most insane
keynote ever qualcomm ces 2013 is
exactly the correct one yes no it
doesn't it does not the one where steve
ballmer says developers developers
developers that i don't think that was a
keynote was it that was a microsoft
company meeting i think maybe uh that he
said developers developers rubbers
um
but yet
uh
yeah
um of the things you have to watch like
obviously like everyone should should at
some point watch
the one where the all the microsoft guys
are dancing on stage like the bill gates
steve bomber dancing one is amazing
um
you should watch that for sure but the
qualcomm
keynote is
is an absolute masterpiece i have no
idea why they thought any of it would go
over well and it just keeps getting more
ridiculous
like why is big bird showing up in the
middle of this thing how is bishop
desmond tutu in the middle of this thing
like it's just it's so nuts and none of
it comes off well
and not only is big bird in it but a
qualcomm guy or somebody or maybe it was
somebody from sesame street's like you
know app division or something is also
like has a big bird
like
hat and wings on but not anything else
like it's so incredible like you have to
see you have to see that qualcomm one
it's so nuts
it's so nuts i cannot even tell you
um
so i highly recommend you watch the
qualcomm one if you can't handle really
embarrassing videos
then you probably won't be able to watch
it because it's incredibly cringy it's
incredibly cringy
none of the people on stage well i feel
bad there's like three people who were
clearly actors hired uh
they're like supposed to be this like
these born mobile they're like young
people you know 20 something or whatever
those people were probably actors that
were hired to do that role and they
probably were hating their life
for the entire time but happy to get a
paycheck i'm sure as any struggling
actor would be but oh my god i feel bad
for them because they're
like all they can do is is read the
freaking
script that they were handed that's
terrible right um
and so uh you know i do feel bad for
them but everyone else it's like why did
you do this like why did you why are you
doing this
it's so terrible
um
anyway
um i i uh yeah
i'm gonna go back to debugging this
lighting but but that is it's a true
cultural moment
anyway not exactly
uh this
these corners don't have
uh bright
things in them at the moment although
they kind of do like that's a light
oh but that's not a corner this is the
actual corner that's corner of a room
not the corner of the vlog
that's not a light that's not a light
there's there's no
in fact there's no lights anywhere on
these two edges there is a light on this
edge here here and here um
so i don't know if we then move forward
to the light leaking part which is now
um although it's not fully light leaking
yet
the corners do not have light sources
in them
so that's maybe not concerning i don't
know
here is an actual light leak scenario
um
and
i don't know what to make of that i
don't seem
i don't know my theory doesn't seem
super likely right i mean it doesn't
look like any it doesn't look like any
particular area
is having this problem i would say i
don't know where these people are
getting their lights from
i
i guess it must be that they're hitting
here and somehow picking up samples from
inside but it doesn't
seem like that should really be possible
because
these are full occluders
so you would expect it to look more like
this does
um and the fact that they are able to
get lighting is a little weird
although i guess it looks like it's
actually coming from over here maybe
you know what we probably need is like a
clearing button so that we can clear out
the light atlas and force it to
recompute
uh from scratch because uh although
every frame we recompute the lighting we
do it with the you know when it samples
the lighting it's got to sample it from
something and that something is whatever
the last frame's lighting state was
so we re-compute the movement of the
light every frame but we need some idea
of which lights hit what surfaces and so
the last frame's light probe data is
what we use for that which means that
there is one frame of feedback and we'd
like to clear that out right because in
a case where you have a feedback thing
like that
right
okay more clues
i just saw a clue
like how is that how is that happening
do you see these
watch this row
it's like there's some kind of a way
that you get into a state where people
who are not getting any light suddenly
get the light
right
how
and it's sudden like that that it's not
even it's not even like a slow
like there was it slow but there it's
instant
this is a real head scratcher
we need a plan for investigating this
and i
don't have one
part of the reason i don't have one is
probably because i don't do rendering
for a living
um you know i'm guessing here that if
like you were the kind of person who
does lighting research for nvidia you
would probably have a pretty good idea
of how you would go about debugging this
right
um
and
i'm guessing like
you know they would they'd be like oh
yeah you should probably put in some of
these checks and you know or draw this
you know i don't know something like
that
uh and we
don't know that but
um
but we need to figure it out because
otherwise we will never have our good
lighting that we basically have now
if we just didn't have this bug
so we have to figure it out
which means we have to figure out a way
to debug it
which means i have to think of a way
to structure the debugging to look for
it
so we have some clue
which is to say that when we see
something like the bug in an isolated
area so here
we do know where it's coming from
because the sightedness of the
the drawing
shows a siding
um
where we can see like that the
thing is coming from a particular
direction
right
right there
you can see that it sort of comes from
one
direction more than another right there
it's like
it was coming from
back
behind it
and instantly which makes no sense
i
don't get it
so
so let's suppose that we did not ever
allow any feedback i'm assuming that we
wouldn't
see like you can see here look it's all
telling you right like those little
things tell you which way the light
comes from the light like snuck out
around here came down this way and now
these are all getting light from that
direction
right
that's what's happening
um presumably because the ray that cast
goes all the way out to like here or
something or i guess it can hit the
ground right
and pick up samples from the ground
that just makes no sense what is
happening there
how does it go back to
what looks correct all of a sudden
is that because those values have like
wrapped or something
wait but they can't even do that because
we're checking for that
this is currently running the validator
which means no light is allowed to go
above 10 in the first place
hmm
[Music]
oh i should uh
because i'm now back at the code let me
explain this
uh i think someone was asking
correct me if i'm wrong i saw something
go by in the the chat someone was asking
like is it a bug that there's a y value
used in an x computation uh
and vice versa
so the answer is no
uh it's supposed to do that and the
reason it's supposed to do that is
because what's happening there is it's
using
um
it's it's the code for walking along the
grid is basically a bresenham like it's
a very simple uh
we wanted to have a very simple way of
of stepping through the grid
and so what we did is when we step
through the grid we just look at how far
off of the ray that we're casting each
possible
grid square would be that we could step
to and we step to the one that's like
the closest to the ray
and when you want to measure the
distance from something to a line
you measure along the perpendicular
which of course is
x you know one is x and one is y if you
want the perpendicular you flip them
right
um
so you know
yeah
um
you can also see here that this is where
the negative comes in you know probably
these should have both been a plus
uh because it is a little confusing like
when i just looked at it i was like why
isn't that negative
um
so like arguably like
[Music]
it's probably the case that in here we
probably should have done that is a plus
so if you know let me just change that i
think that just probably makes more
sense
so if we do stepping delta x here uh you
can see like it just it only gets used
in these two places this should probably
be a plus
and then when we compute it up here just
so that you can see
uh it probably should have been like
that
right
so you know
basically like instead of that being
negative here
what the heck
all right
what is happening there i don't know
uh anyway
the we change it to a plus down here so
they both get added and then up here
it's got a negative in front of it right
um and that's just because you know it
it's like
when i looked at it just now i was like
why isn't there a negative it's like oh
because we left a negative down the
bottom that which is you know
if you're looking at the code here when
you set it up it just probably makes
more sense that you would do that right
like it doesn't
you know
just seems a little more sane
uh yeah
that's all
yeah uh just slavic yes uh you had the
same thought i did and so that's why i
wanted to change this notation because
now it's much easier to see uh whereas
before when it was distributed down here
that just
i mean it's not like one's right and
one's wrong they both compute exactly
the same thing but it's just it's easier
to see that you did it right when it's
all in one place like that instead of
spread out right so
you know
um
unfortunately that has nothing to do
with our bug or maybe that's something
to other bug but we don't know um
what it would have to do
with our bug uh so we don't really know
we have no idea where this bug is coming
from and we don't really have a
particularly strong idea about how to
look for it
we do know that there's some kind of a
strange alignment issue so we have a
little bit of a clue which is that
somehow when we have the alignment off
me you know maybe there's a you know
here's one thought
maybe when we get the alignment
wrong there's some kind of like a when
we walk the grid we're walking it
incorrectly and we miss we'll we we can
like tunnel through some occluders that
we shouldn't be able to tunnel through
um
i don't know that i think that's a high
percentage chance but
it's something
we could think about
um
it'd be nice to get these
uh folks here to
uh to to maybe trigger again and maybe
we could use those as a case study
and go inspect uh how the casting is
working
so
you know um
you know part of the problem is that
that you can also see that like those
are not the first people contaminated
right
um
so it's like it has to spread around the
outside first
maybe
let's look more closely at the order in
which that contamination contaminates
like where does it actually come from
so it actually did start
right there
right
like it did legit legitimately start
right there
uh that's the first place that i saw
it get bright
um so i i guess i'd be interested to
know if we
i don't know which index that is
um
ah
yes
yes we now know the answer to the bug
and you know what
we probably should get out the owl of
shame for this one because i literally
freaking said this before
i don't know where that owl went let's
go find it
um
all right well uh
so
that was embarrassing because
uh as i was saying before the owl shane
paraded around
um
so i lit i literally said we would have
this problem i don't know we could go
back and check the tape to see how
strenuous i was about it but i literally
called this problem before
and then i forgot to actually go deal
with it right so we
you know maybe i can chalk this up to
streaming because a lot of times if you
only stream only so often a lot of times
i feel like a lot more on the ball when
i'm programming
you know in my normal job day-to-day
uh and a lot of times you forget stuff
where stuff gets messy for no reason and
code uh
when you
um
are streaming it should be cleaner and
it's not because you never have that
kind of clarity but
um
essentially what happens
is when we are casting we removed z
because now there is no actual the
spatial partition is
always the same in z right
but what we neglected to do and i
specifically said this
uh what we neglected to do is actually
stop the
looking through the spatial partition
when you exit the cell in z
so as a result if someone can leave
through the floor so anywhere there
isn't an an underneath tile right
um and and similarly you would get the
same on the edges right if somebody
casts just out that direction
and instead of leaving the green volume
they get out the bottom and go like
straight like far down or something
right although that seems like less of
an issue it probably is more just these
ones in here
um then you can easily have this problem
now there's a couple different ways we
can deal with this and i'm not exactly
sure which one we want to but i would
start by saying maybe the best solution
is actually not to fix this problem and
to always have
floors everywhere uh because
in theory that should be fine now we
probably want to put something in that
validates that never happens but you see
these like where we're missing those
floor tiles there i don't actually
remember why we have that problem i
think it has something to do with how we
fill in the world
um
[Music]
because remember we don't really have
much in the way i think we call it the
apron
we don't have much in the way of room
generation code our room generation code
is pretty crappy
uh it doesn't really do anything
interesting at the moment
um but you can kind of see how it
it uh works here right it iterates over
this stuff it looks for overlapping
entities
um
and i guess if it doesn't find any it
puts them in there why it doesn't have
any only on that side i couldn't tell
you
i suspect it's probably because when we
changed how things were aligned this
code is probably now wrong
um
like when it iterates over
things it's probably wrong
um
so like this uh get total volume thing
like this code i don't know we'd have to
look at
i'm not sure i care about it at the
immediate moment
but i would suspect that this is
probably the issue is that it's not
actually
add reduce to get total volume of tile
eps eps ets yeah i mean one of the
things that we should also do here is
collapse this to actually just using a
grid which you know currently we we
didn't really do that um
your people are going to send these an
owl of shame to microsoft like an actual
owl
it would have to be like the biggest owl
in their new campus that they're
building like there's microsoft is
building some new campus thing i don't
think it's done yet
um but they had like um
uh
this thing
this
right
this should just be a giant owl like
like instead of like whatever they're
thinking this is gonna be it should just
be a giant owl of shame in this thing
like just absolutely huge
you know something that's several times
taller than the actual tallest building
on the campus
right
um
they have the same block they do you're
right they obviously have the same
lighting bug
they haven't fixed it either
um
so you know like they've got
uh
plans here they've got big plans
but i think this should just be a giant
owl of shame that just like looks and
you know what would be even better
microsoft if you're watching this
put a giant alice shame in here but put
it on a rotating base
so that during the day like the the owl
of shame just rotates like a clockwork
owl around and casts its gaze of shame
upon each building like in turn
because like we know that
all the only thing that anyone's doing
in any of these buildings is shameful so
you might as well acknowledge that with
a giant owl of shame in the centaur
that's my feeling anyway
that's my recommendation for the
microsoft campus is a giant owl of shame
that looks at all the employees with a
very shame with a shaming gaze
okay uh so we have been shamed as well
today by the owl of shame
i
let he who hath no owl cast the first
shame um and we certainly
we certainly
uh have been shamed today
so i think the solution to this problem
should probably be like we could solve
it by
in here when we cast array figuring out
what the t value is that would exit the
s exit the grid in z
but my suspicion is that actually what
we should do is just make sure that
there always r bounds because
you want the lighting to work properly
and if and you shouldn't really be able
to exit the cage
out the bottom
i don't think
maybe you should
because i feel like you should just
always hit something and that something
is either like black a black tile if
it's a pit
um
i don't know it feels like you should
always hit something but maybe that's
not true
uh
i don't know
um
[Music]
so it's hard to say uh but but
you know there's two ways we can solve
it one is we could go in here and say
look uh there's going to be um
a a clamp
on z
that we probably i would say it would
get enforced maybe
maybe it would get enforced
in
the step where the if the t terminate
if the t terminate
times the ray would put us outside z
then we just
you know that doesn't count uh you know
it could be here
you know what i mean um
uh
i guess let's see what happens if we do
that
so in here if we make some
requirement that we're going to clamp
the t terminate to
a bounds that has to do with z
uh
that seems pretty straight forward
so
that would be like
that would that would be like having in
here an f32 z
or something
where we just keep a z that steps along
the ray
[Music]
and we break whenever we would have left
the cell
um
you know i really don't want to do this
let me explain why i don't want to do it
since i'm not probably making much sense
so i think we do want to just go fix the
room creator and call it a day
so let me explain why i don't want to do
this
so suppose that that is how i was to
solve this problem and the game does
take place in a 2d sort of environment
but it is somewhat 3d right like it
still has like we're kind of allowing
things to move in 3d and think in 3d
so my fear is that let's suppose that i
do fix this problem by just enforcing
you know when you look here you can see
the the bounds
uh are this green thing
if i did force it to stop when it hit
the bottom of the green thing well you
could still get pretty far outside your
square actually if you cast let's say
from here and maybe this wall didn't go
all the way down like who knows
even if it does before i hit that i
could easily get too far away right
um so i would still end up potentially
pulling light from sampling that i
really shouldn't you know what i mean so
i think we want to constrain it and
maybe the answer is the reason
for that is that this has to be way more
constrained like maybe this is far too
tall
and you're like look you should
constrain it the other way but i think
the smarter answer is just always build
closed geometry
so that you always hit something valid
like a valid thing because that's the
actual thing we want to have happen and
so it seems like having this like bogus
space around is probably not the right
solution
so my guess is that we really just want
to fix this code unfortunately this is
not the code we're often working on so i
would rather have not have done that
right now but i think there really isn't
any better solution
um
so you know yeah that's where we're at
so
when we do this overlapping entities
exist i'm assuming that's was failing
but i guess we don't really know
um
if we were to add something obvious we
probably could see if that were the case
uh by adding some other thing like
instead of
um
like here's just my suggestion like
suppose we went in here and said all
right if overlapping entities exist or
they don't will actually be something
else
so we say
um
here's the the predicate overlapping
entities exist will be in here
and rather than doing an if statement
we're always going to create uh this
ground cover thing where we place this
this random entity here
uh and
i don't know why we're adding collision
volumes uh to it i think probably for
lighting i would guess
so we're placing these collision volumes
in here
and then what we want to do is we want
to say we're always going to add one of
these
and
we're going to add one of these
like just floating in the air or
something when
this comes back
true
uh if that makes sense
so when we say like height equals random
between
five one whatever this whole thing make
relative get volume from from minzy
to be honest
why is that not
varying the height of this thing
that seems a bit weird
i guess because the it's only the
collision volume
that's kind of weird so you're telling
me the collision volume is randomized
but the placement this this is some
weird code i don't know what
oh we do do a ground p thing here
yeah i don't know anyway this quote is a
bit weird i don't feel like the the
ground is uneven but this would suggest
that it was
so i guess i'm not sure i completely
understand
before i do this
let me see what's up with that is that
really what's happening there
is ground uneven outside the
outside the generated rooms
i guess it is
that's that's definitely uneven okay
i guess i just didn't look at it very
closely all right so that is what
happens here that's fine
um what i wanted to do is say okay let's
suppose that the height is always
clamped to something like very
low or maybe the p value is dropped
quite a bit lower
so rather than this if statement we're
just going to say okay look
if
it's overlapped
then the ground p is just gonna have
like some
you know
large amount subtracted away from it
so that we can see
where
like we're getting overlap and where
we're not just so i can verify to myself
that's actually the problem um because i
don't know if it is or if it isn't right
uh so let's see
so
of course one issue is i probably should
turn lighting off for this because i
can't actually see outside with without
that um but you know what are you gonna
do
um
if i look
i can't even really see i mean i guess i
can see that i can't see through it so i
guess that does mean that there is
something
there
let's look in one of those gaps like
that was a gap right
all right
now i'm a little weirded out because it
doesn't feel like this ground p
actually
got
dropped though it looks like they're all
at the correct level
doesn't it sort of
oh that's just for the trees
that's just for the trees
my bad
uh let's do it for everything
but i think that answered my question
because you could see that it filled in
all the holes so
i think we're okay
um
all right so let's see here
these are all overlapped so they should
be low and i guess they are let's make
it let's make it more pronounced than
that
let's drop them way down low
that doesn't seem to have done anything
why why didn't that do anything
um
anybody
anyone
no
any any any suggestions
anything anyone
anyone um because that
that should say anytime you would have
overlapped something you should be
placed very low down
right
i mean
that should be extremely low
it should be like way sticking out the
bottom
and yet
nothing
is sticking out the bottom everything is
flat
how how is it possible i ask you
um
what am i missing
this is the p-value we're using
right
maybe let's take a look
because i i'm obviously doing something
stupid again this isn't the code we were
supposed to be working on so
i
kind of got to page it back in
um
let's go ahead and
check out this
function
here
so like we're calling it
i mean that
seems like a thing
right
i don't get it
so i guess one thing is that it's
centering
that's kind of weird
so the volume
get maxi center volume okay
so
that's a little weird well is it though
so the volume got created
if we look at what the two values are
it's like z10 to z11 more or less right
i mean
that's that's what we ended up getting
and
the volume
[Music]
i mean that
means that
the entity placement is at negative 12
and the volume is
i guess offset from that
i don't really understand how this code
works at all
i guess what this is saying this is
interesting
so what this is saying is that actually
this make relative call is assuming that
this is actually
this get volume from minzy
it's
this is not based off of the p-value
so really that doesn't adjust anything
it's just saying look this is going to
be
uh we want something that's going to be
relative to this p where we're placing
the thing
so that's wouldn't actually do what
we're trying to get it to do
uh
it'll just offset it so really i guess
what you would do is you'd do it here
yeah this code kind of sucks i mean
it's fine but
it's just that's just kind of just
unintuitive
one more pass over the room gen stuff
and i think we'll be more in business
which we'll want to do um
before we get much further but that
should work now
um
things should now be sticking out the
bottom when
they are overlapped right
i should think
uh i guess i don't know but let's find
out
i i'm hoping not i mean everything
shouldn't be overlapped anyway
um all right so the things that are
overlapped are now gone which i think is
what should have happened they're so far
down they won't even be in the spatial
query i don't think
so now we should be able to do them more
reasonably so we'll push them two units
down which i think will still be inside
the spatial partition to be pulled in
but
uh
so we can actually see
yeah you can kind of see them now of
course the lighting makes it difficult
but you see there
right
um
we should probably try to turn off
lighting or something just so we can see
but you know hopefully maybe we can
just look at it this way and see it here
so let's let's give it a shot i'm going
to hop out
to
the
outside here
um
like we overflowed our entity count
there
right this is this assertion is we don't
have
enough space to unpack an entity
which is kind of nuts
is that really possible
what if that's a bug
you wouldn't think so right
um because the max unpacked entity count
jimmy
um
i guess i don't know what we normally
set that to
max unpacked entity count is maxim
region entity count
that's a lot of entities is that really
the case i mean it could be i suppose
[Music]
i will temporarily up that limit but we
don't really want that to be that high
because it shouldn't have to be
all right
so if we now look we should see yeah so
you can see that those are exactly what
i assumed they were which is their down
right
um
so
yes i mean the problem is that we are
reporting those as overlapped when
they're not overlapped which is what i
thought right
so
with that in mind um
i guess the question here is
what do we do about that
because uh this code is obviously broken
so something about the way the
overlapping entities exist function
works uh
is broken
and
it's reporting that there is an entity
that overlaps the entity we're trying to
add even though there really isn't
which again wouldn't be a problem if we
had an actual grid but because this is
not really a grid the whole thing's in
3d and we're just pretending we have a
grid
uh
you know
hard to say
so
if we've got the total volume of the
tile
and we are subtracting epsilon from it
so it shrinks inward slightly
for some reason
we're still registering a hit there like
as if there is some
uh volume
that's colliding
and i'm not
really sure why
so let's take a look at these collision
volumes
um
it's pretty easy for us to add them and
i'm not sure
like where they all are right now
because we made some changes to that
stuff in this past where we're cleaning
stuff up
and so we may actually
want to just see where this stuff
actually is let me you know that's
actually an entity.cbp let me just turn
on drawing those
um
just so we can tell like what are the
collision volumes because we don't
actually know
uh so there they are
and if we hop out to where we were
having this bug
just we can look let's see what happens
right so in here
um
oh
well
aha
so i
see
what's happening there
it is that our room boundaries are wrong
uh well that was educational
i guess we can
deal with that really easily uh so where
we add the
when we do the room generator
we add bounds for the room
and
i guess i would say that that probably
shouldn't actually
that that probably should be avoided
when we check for like like
we should fix it
but we also should probably turn it off
um
so if we do get room volume
this is not offset by a third by a half
which it should be
um that's really it i think
in other words this should have
um that offset baked into it and it oops
and it doesn't
um
is about it
i'm not sure how we do this
in this
program
i assume offset
yeah so that will adjust the room to be
on the new grid alignment where things
are centered
um
and
you know you can now see them
uh in the right place
and presumably now if we looked we
wouldn't have that overlapping problem
but again we also probably just don't
want rooms to be participating in that
anyway because rooms are not solid they
don't prevent you from placing things
they're just a boundary that lets you
know where the room is right
um okay so let's see so now that's
and not still not right it's close
oh
duh
so i guess i forgot about the fact that
it's actually not
literally 0.5 it's the half of a tile
so let's take a look at the um
the part where we get the volume for a
tile
i think it's skip total volume or
whatever right
so it's really this
0.5 you know
mask grid tile dim that's the actual
code we want
um so this should be
like this
and the only question is what to do
about the z there
and i guess i'm not sure
uh but maybe now this is aligned more
properly let's hop out to a place where
we were looking at before and see if it
makes a difference it might not
might still be wrong but let's take a
look uh so now hopefully those are lined
up yet so those are now lined up exactly
on the corners
uh which is what we want so that's good
yeah
uh and hey we also have uh the
light appears to be arranged properly
now so that
we would presumably not get
that leaking let's see
if we do or don't the lights are all set
to max
brightness here
[Music]
so they they should create the situation
so we still have one there right
that's still definitely the weird like
leaking scenario
um oh and you know what uh we've only
solved half the problem so
you can still leak out the top
right so the collision volumes
um
are not like the ceilings
are not
in
place which is a little bit odd because
i
i mean that's that makes sense because
the apron doesn't create ceilings but we
created ceilings
in
uh rooms
actually
so it seems somewhat odd
does it not
why are we not seeing those in the
collision volumes
i thought we placed ceiling tiles and in
fact we saw them
when we looked
before
so
what's going on here are those not
collision volumes or
are they something else like i don't
recall how we added them but we
definitely had
yeah like
this
you know ad piece occluder so i guess
occluders are not the same
so do collision volumes get added as
occluders and so do occluder pieces
we're going to have to unify this stuff
you can you can tell that code is in
need of cleanup
now that we know how everything works
all that's kind of ridiculous
so there is a code called push occluder
but it seems like it only happens if you
have a piece type of occluder
although maybe push cube would also do
this
i'm not really sure
it doesn't look like it does
i mean it looks like the only place
that's called is from here but we don't
know if the like lighting box push
happens somewhere else as well i'm not
sure
but
we know that
i mean don't we
we know that we're
we know that we have occluders for the
walls so i guess the answer is the
aprons don't have light occluders or do
they
let's take a look at the actual apron
generator does that push any occluders
it pushes a cube but it doesn't push an
occluder
i guess the tree has an occluder
like it doesn't look like it right
so i'm kind of confused as to how we're
actually getting
light blocking from these things when
we're not actually pushing occluders
it's very
confusing because
these are else ifs
so you can't have a flag that sets
occluder otherwise
um
as far as i can see
the only thing that you can do is add
piece occluder right
and that happens where
so it happens when we're creating the
room tiles
which we expect there's the ceiling and
the floor
there's one for the tree
so we haven't by adding those back in we
haven't actually put any occluders in
that region so technically actually
there are still no occluders there
which means we wouldn't expect that to
stop the bug at all
uh
so there's that
which i guess it doesn't i mean we did
observe the bug so
i guess the answer is we should be able
to because we haven't actually changed
it because we haven't had any includers
yet we should be able to get this weird
bug to happen again too
yeah
like somehow
i don't quite remember exa there we go
uh there it was
okay
um so let's actually add the occluders
in now and we'll just rely on the fact
that eventually we're going to come
through and do a massive cleanup of the
regeneration code as well
so it's okay that it's janky for now
much like we're cleaning up the lighting
code now we will do a cleanup pass on
everything
um in good time
so i'll go ahead and
add in a
occluder to the apron generation because
like i was kind of under the mistaken
impression that that like cubes
automatically recluders they're not
apparently
um so we want to do add piece occluders
here
um that will be added for the this
entity
we don't really care much about trees
probably uh at this point because
they're kind of just there for set
dressing
um so we probably want to do actually
the way we were doing it in the generate
room code right uh so
i guess
just you know the the whole volume
um
whatever the ground tile volume
is i think is what we want
yeah i mean i i think it's literally
this
right
um
i could be wrong about that but
so we know we've got a ceiling occluder
uh and then we know we have like
this
other occluder here that's that's going
to presumably be just this vol
and we know we want the ceiling one as
well uh which
should just be
exactly the same code i think
the color part uh is like gonna be like
a moon color
so i don't know like
in a sense this almost should just be
like a light
it should be like moonlight
right um
i would think
and so actually this is probably just an
ambient light a low amount of ambient
light for the outside
would be my
guess
uh
so
like
um
this code
um so in the roomgen
we would actually do like a lighting add
here with an entity the radius
would be
this
um the offset would be this
i
think um
the
lighting amount would be very low
uh and the color would be like some kind
of moonlight color right so it'd be like
probably no red probably a little green
probably a little blue
you know something like that
uh
did i mess something up there
oh you're only allowed to have one
radius okay well maybe this has to be
more like this then
so put the radius in directly
and the offset indirectly
like that
um and then we have the emission and
color they come
in here
like
so
i guess
um
and so i don't know
like
you know again not not sure about this
but
uh
let's let's give it a a spin let's give
it a little let's give it a little go
we can turn off collision volumes
because they don't matter
as it turns out it's only occluders that
matter
so
we can turn that off
and not draw those
flip back to the game here there we go
and hop along
so
not
solved at all still having the same
problem
uh and the question is why let's take a
look at
um
those
actual spatial grid elements
debug draw
spatial grid
i'm gonna turn that back on turn off the
drawing of the
lighting series we don't really need
them
um and let's just take a look at what we
are drawing here so
you can see
out in in here it does look like we've
got
floors and ceilings on here pretty well
so let's take a look at if we can go
back to the yeah like right here
let's see if we can
look at the
uh
actual raycast
so that's the ray direction
it's only iterating through this one
piece
which is what you would expect
um
and it's hitting the ground so we solve
the problem i think
right
um
i mean that is
that is exactly preventing that cast and
i guess
you know
well no i mean
we saw this have the bug again right i
mean i i
quite sure i did
it's just not doing it right at this
immediate frame
um so like if i was to switch the ray
around
is there any
rhyme or reason
uh to that
i mean it seems pretty well cabined
right
so that seems pretty reasonable now of
course it can
convect the light around i mean it is
able to get sort of
right like to that
area okay
um it's a little bit hard to see
everything here because it's hard to see
where each grid piece is actually
um
let me see if i can
provoke the bug where these guys
actually light up again
for some reason i can't which maybe but
i thought i saw i thought i saw them do
that did i not
really see that
um
am i just am i totally wrong
you
so
that's
suggests we have a totally other problem
as well right
so here you can see array
that actually is able to get in between
like
oh because there's no ceiling
on the outdoors area
apparently
only on this part of the outdoors area
so is that true on the inside as well
you're not able to get are you are you
able to get outside
of here
as well
because hopefully you can't you know you
can't right like it's it seems pretty
well capped and it does stop there
um
right like it's hitting the wall which
is what we want
let's double check a few other
directions
of cast
from the same location just to see what
happens i guess
um
but
that scans out
pretty well
you know
so it it seems like it's picking pretty
reasonably there but there isn't any
ceiling over here and so that does seem
like a bug and that probably means that
the room generator needs to do that
because it's not currently adding
ceilings
in all cases right
um
and the ceilings are added pretty ad hoc
like we probably should add a lot fewer
ceilings uh just like one ceiling tile
that went over the whole thing would
probably be sufficient but at the moment
it's not doing that
and that's fine uh but if we look here
like you can see like the not spec
outdoors thing
uh is is totally not what we want so so
probably you would need
something
like in here
we would do a
if spec outdoors you do one thing
otherwise you do another right
so where we add that occluder piece
there
we would say
um
probably want to like
make this a little bit more
systemic and just say this is the thing
that gets added always right
but let's let's just do this for now and
see if this changes things
for us
um
[Music]
so that still seems really buggy to me
uh
like there's still something going on
with where if where if you happen to get
right on the edge there
like it's still not it's still able to
do some kind of a really like erroneous
cast for some reason
that i'm not sure like what's going on
right
like something is busted there where
it's able to hit
it's it's able to hit something in a way
that i don't understand like like as if
casting out from here produces a hit
that's like
somehow really illegitimate
or something
well hmm
so you know yeah so like i'm not really
sure what that is but there's still a
bug there for sure
um
and super peculiar
i wonder what would happen to so like
what happens if we don't add lights so
the only lights are just the ceiling
lights that's the only thing you can
possibly hit what actually happens in
that case
um
we have some kind of like ad standard
lighting right
so the standard lighting pattern thing
here if we just didn't do this
so so if we if zero both of these out
um
there won't be any of those lights
and the reason i'm doing this is i just
want to make sure i want to confirm the
fact that it's it's that you can hit
these lights somehow that's what's
happening
um
i don't know if that's true or not but i
just want to make sure
i'm assuming it's true
so i do feel like something's a little
off um
so we thought anyway
that we added in both cases
a
a roof light that was the same lighting
right
but in this case
there's no visible lighting
in this case there is
so why did this pick up
lighting from its ceiling tiles and this
did not
are those ceiling tiles did i add them
incorrectly right like something is
weird there
what
did i accidentally type that totally
wrong
oh wait no i didn't i put peace light in
there
ah
it is because these are in the wrong
order
the outdoors one is the one that's
supposed to get the light and the
indoors one is the one that's not
supposed to get the light
try that one more time
so it's definitely getting light now
which it wasn't before
so i think it's probably about about
right seems roughly right
i will say it's not as much light as it
probably should be getting
uh i mean uh in terms of like what we
actually want to provide here for light
but i think we still have a bug because
i don't think the light should be
spreading when we turn on the other
lights i will say this is an interesting
way of doing the lighting
um
we should just add ceiling tiles for
lighting like instead of the way the
standard lighting pattern works we
should just make this always add this
should just be the light
you know what i mean
um
that seems like way better and
i don't know uh
hard to say anyway
uh
so if you turn back on the
the standard lighting pattern here
the question remains as to why we're
getting the light leaking happening in
the way that it's happening
um
it doesn't make solid sense to me
let me i'm going to go ahead and turn
these off
because
now i mean we know they're there
and really now we're just gonna have to
look for like how the raycasting is is
doing the wrong thing because i don't
know
um i will say when we are not having the
bug it looks fantastic i love the
results
so that's good but we still have some
weird stuff happening here and we don't
know what it is
you can see we're going to have to
expand that apron a little bit because
you can see as those lights come out now
that the lighting up is very fast
uh it updates so quickly that you see
the error and we want to leave it fast
because we want to be able to move
lights around and stuff so we don't want
to slow it down if we don't have to
right
um so you know
but i mean man that looks awesome
i mean it's so good
it's just so good
uh so like yeah
definitely want to get these last few
bugs out of here because it looks so
good and then you get that and it's like
what is happening right
and we have no idea
we don't we don't we still don't even
after solving a few obvious problems we
still don't really know what's causing
that
and that is not a good place to be you
never want to not know what's causing a
problem right
um
okay
hmm
i say
uh
alpha lion mill uh it is it is the
it is the uh
code we wrote like like this is it's our
own engine um that's that's what we do
here on the stream
uh and that's why we have a bug uh
that's why we have a bug not some engine
team has a bug because we are the ones
who wrote it
uh i will say that
what is happening there
uh
that
might have something to do with it if
the apron
if the if the aprons aren't really
sealed
um
if the aprons aren't actually sealed
then we still could have a similar
leaking problem
you could blame younger that's true
that's true
i suppose technically we are using a
graphics engine made by
a previous version of ourselves
and it's their bug like we didn't
literally type in the bug today
right
so the bug is from several weeks ago
or possibly even
years ago because you know we only work
on this a few hours a month
on stream and so
you know
this bug could have been from a fairly
older version of a younger version of
ourselves right totally totally possible
and that we are simply not to blame why
are why are people blaming us for this
you know
um
it's it's not our fault
so i i do wonder uh i'm curious
does it have something to do with the
fact that the that
we don't always add a solid
like blocking region
hmm
yeah everything in the game is 2d art
except for
so like all of the art is 2d
but because we wanted to sort of have
like a pseudo 3d look the walls are made
of actual cubes
um but everything like you know like all
that stuff is 2d like that's a 2d
it's a 2d character right um as you can
see but what they're just
locked to the view so
they kind of appear like they're sort of
not 2d i mean they kind of still are
obviously 2d if you look at them right
um so everything's 2d except for just
the wall pieces
uh the walls are actual 3d
because there didn't really seem to be
any other way to do it
um
look i don't know
i don't know really how you would do if
we had an idea to do it we probably
would have done it because we were
trying the whole game's art is supposed
to be 2d
but unfortunately like
i just can't think of any way to really
do walls
in here that would be
[Music]
that would be actually
2d and not 3d so you know the walls are
3d because we couldn't think of any
other way to do them basically
all right so what is this bug like what
is the deal
i just have to figure out what chunky's
deal is
um i guess we don't actually know that
this is a bug
we just don't know like this might be
that that's just how much because
there's a lot of light in this area
maybe that is actually supposed to be
that bright
but it also could be above look we don't
really know we don't know that that's
hard to say
we do know that if we get
like
there
this is clearly some kind of a feedback
bug
because it doesn't make much sense
why standing here would produce that
result but standing here would produce
that result
i don't know like that feels probably
just wrong
i mean maybe it's not
but it kind of seems like it probably is
uh celery boy we are going to make a
game but it's only because i feel
obliged to do so uh i'm not really a
game designer so
you know
the
the idea is to make an engine for a game
but um
you know in order to know if the engine
works you kind of have to have a game so
we will put
game in the game
uh but it won't necessarily be very good
right like the game design might be very
bad
uh because that's not
you know i i don't actually know how to
do that part um
that there is a good stream for that
jonathan blow does streams and he's like
you know i mean in my opinion the best
game designer that there is like i've
never seen a designer as good as he is
so you can go watch his streams uh and
catch some game design from that when he
happens to be streaming that um but you
know i can't help you with that part
uh
all right so
obviously we've got that is the bug
it only happens in very few places now
but it's definitely there we can provoke
it fairly reliably
and i do wonder a little bit if it has
to do with when the lighting
gets into a place
where it can hit
a uncapped region
uh celebrate i agree that it could be
educational watch them and learn game
design but it's not going to be us right
uh because i'm not a game designer and
i'm not going to learn game design
just simply
putting game design into a game is not
sufficient to become a good game
designer right like you have to to work
a lot harder than that so this really
won't
have that really won't happen on the
stream
um but you know we will make uh
improvements to the engine like we're
going to clean up the engine we are
that's what we're doing right now is
we're cleaning up the lighting uh which
now i think looks fantastic i really
love it um but we've got some bugs you
can see like there's some weird right
like what's happening there
you know
um
although actually that's not actually no
i take it back that's not actually a bug
that's just because this apron is too
tightly bound
uh if this were further out like that's
because you're just seeing the wrapping
of the lighting atlas
so
uh never mind about that but
um
so i think it i think it may still be
just the z
it might be i don't know although that
wouldn't explain this would it
because there's no z
leaking there is there i don't think
there is
i don't think there is
i could be wrong
but like that still feels wrong and we
know there's no z leaking going on there
because you can see all around is
completely
black
uh well not black but low light
so i don't know do we think that's
logical or don't we
let's take a look at the cast i mean we
inspected them in this area they all
looked pretty reasonable though
is the thing
um
i don't know where there's a there's a
light cast right
um
and you know it's picking the floor
uh which is exactly what you would
expect it to pick
i mean it's
so
i guess one
one problem
that we have
uh can the rate oh let me answer that
question the first uh the part where can
the ray escape the door to nothing it
can but that's okay
so if the ray
goes outside of the lighting atlas
region
that shouldn't cause a problem now maybe
it does maybe we do have a bug
but that actually shouldn't cause a
problem
the thing that was causing us the
was that if the ray can cast in z
outside of the z bounds
and get further into the actual valid
part of the lighting atlas that was our
actual problem right so if it can you
know
so if it casts out this way we wouldn't
really expect any problems because all
of the light out here there's nothing
out here for it to sample it's the
lighting atlas is bounded by this cyan
there's no nothing to sample outside the
cyan you just get what's at the edge of
the thing which is fine you can totally
that's a totally fine place to sample
from what was happening before that was
illegal was basically like you'd be here
you'd cast a ray upwards and it wouldn't
hit anything so it would just keep
stepping and stepping and stepping and
stepping and it would pull light from
way the heck somewhere else right or
tunnel through a wall like it would just
keep casting and end up like sampling
from over here or something right
that was still inside the light atlas
and it was pulling light from some place
it shouldn't have been allowed to pull
it right
um
if that makes sense
so
what i'm thinking
as well though like as another thing
um sample from the wrap region it
doesn't sample from the wrapped region
uh just to be clear uh what that is is
just the renderer
so when it goes to render it just
like
you when we set these bounds you should
never be able to see the cyan boundary
that's just because we have them sized
wrong so we need to push that sizing out
a little bit and then we're good uh all
you're seeing here is just it happens to
if you use a debug camera and you view
outside where the atlas is it's just
gonna wrap right
um so that doesn't really matter
um
uh and felt craft i'm
inclined to agree with you what i was
about to say uh
at least i think agrees with you and let
me say it and you can tell me if it does
so
um
i also like don't know how that we saw
like how is that getting brighter in
there right that suggests to me that
we're still somehow able to escape that
area
sampling wise
right which
we shouldn't really be able to do let's
let's double check that but let me see
what it's going to say first what i was
going to say first is
when we do a sample
from the light atlas so if we hit a
light you are automatically getting the
inverse square law for that light
right
when we hit
a
non-lit region
so something that just has indirect
lighting and we sample from that
no matter where we sample we're gonna
get whatever that color is and we're not
inverse square lawn that
is that somehow wrong
i mean i don't think it is
at the moment that's
it's not a it's not allowed to do that
on grid walk
iteration out is it i mean it it
basically it sets the hit ref color to
nothing
i guess we should change the hit
emission to nothing as well
i think that
maybe we should do as well
let's just see i just want to make sure
that it's not something stupid
and like what's that
so we we have a bug on
on
every other boundary
right
because what would be causing that to
change
could it really be an accurate cast that
is causing that
i doubt it
i mean i could invent an explanation but
that seems wrong
doesn't it
like it seems like that should not have
happened so it seems like we still have
some kind of an error
does this happen with pure white pure
red lights i
it happens with
well currently the lights are pure white
aren't they oh no they're not
here's a pure white light
the ceiling tiles outside are not pure
white
though
and
you know we don't get the same kind of
bleed but the light isn't as bright
uh if we change it so that the light is
in order to i'd have to add a little
more energy to make it because they'd
have to be all sevens i could make them
all sixes
uh or 6.5 or something um
but
this will now be like a brighter white
light
um
i mean same same same
we wouldn't expect the channels to have
anything to do with it i mean you know
if we had some kind of a summation bug
if you make the lights dim enough then
you don't get this kind of overbrighting
problem but i'm not sure i guess i don't
really understand why
um
again still kind of just confused as to
what exactly the bug is you know if we
knew what it was we'd fix it right
um
[Music]
so it's weird there's like some boundary
where we go below the amount that will
do this contamination
for whatever reason
it looks like
like that's just not enough
somehow
you know we we don't know why
but that's just not enough to end up
leading to the feedback
that we see
i guess
right because the entire system is now
apparently stable and like i can't get
any of these rooms
to evince the bug
um
the heck is that
it's like some weird like noise that i
saw down below
so there is some kind of value
sensitivity here and i'm not sure
i know what it is it
might just be that
you know i no i i don't have a solid
explanation
because you would think that it would
either be stable or not stable and that
the total brightness wouldn't matter to
the stability
right
like
you should just see the same
thing and
it seems like we have some maybe we have
some kind of clamping happening
somewhere where if you're below a
certain threshold then it takes energy
out of the system in some way or
something
i don't know
the reason that the light in the bottom
left is brighter than the others
i think
um
is be well no you know what i'm not
gonna say i do not know
it does seem weird
it seems pretty weird i don't know if do
if the height or something is there
something else randomized about lights
i i don't see anything yet
so i would assume i could be wrong
i would assume that that is also a bug
meaning or related to the bug the fact
that that is brighter seems
wrong
because uh
simply being in a corner doesn't
obviously doesn't do it because like
that's also a corner
and that's not it
we could look at what the casting looks
like in that region
uh and see i don't know if there's any
particular thing that we can find out uh
from that unfortunately but let's check
so uh if we
just move our casting debug back one
and down one
that would be the place that we're
trying to pick up
right um it's right on the light source
like this this big white thing up here
is the giant light source that's sitting
uh in that area
you know
and uh
the cast looks
you know like what
what i would probably expect i don't
know what is the purple line supposed to
be
do we remember what that is i don't
remember what the purple line is
oh the purple line is like the face
the face normal of the octahedral map
it's like it's like where the the face
of the octahedral map is pointing
right
and i mean you can see them hitting it's
just hitting the light source there
so there's nothing particularly odd
about the casting that i can see
um
uh so i i don't know i'm not sure why
we're getting more of that like for
example i would assume you should you
would think
that that if there's a light in that
quarter now maybe there's not a light in
that corner
um actually let's take a look
there is i mean there's a light in that
corner
so the fact that there's a light in that
corner it's a little bit odd i'm not
sure why we don't see the same kind of a
brightness there
right
um
because again like you would expect this
is like the same kind of geometry
basically and the same
yeah now there are some i mean it's
possible that it has something to do
with the fact that
the
sampling sphere is like biased
possibly um
so
uh you know you're correct the light
sphere is larger
uh
it is larger than one tile i think
maybe the problem is that it's centered
wrong
like the light sphere is is a is like
further in on this side or something
like that
that would explain perhaps why it would
be brighter
in this corner than in other corners
um but i i don't know other than that i
can't think of a lot of reason we could
draw lights
uh pretty easily so if we just want to
know a little bit more about that that's
probably not particularly difficult we
could just say like all right show us
like where lights specifically lights
are
um
so so here's all the lights
i mean they look
totally
normal i don't see anything weird there
i guess i would say i don't
understand
though
why is it pushing it looks
like it's pushing down a different size
than the actual light is supposed to be
wouldn't you say
so here's the push light call you can
see it adding a radius here i is this
supposed to be is this off this might be
supposed to be like a half
like a one-half thing
yeah i mean because this is a rec center
dim not a rec center half dim
so i guess i don't know
i guess i don't know which one this is
supposed to be this says radius
and so this should probably be two times
that right and is that what we called it
everywhere
yeah we called it a radius so i think
that's fine
um i think this code is just wrong so
that's supposed to be two because this
is a radius
right
which means that actually
uh
it it's that
is where the lights actually are
um
so
you know
and i guess i would also say
uh
you know looking at how they're placed
there's it i i have no idea why you
would end up with more collection in
this corner
like i don't know why that light would
in theory be
more than any of these other ones i
doesn't make a whole lot of sense it
could obviously be luck
like we could be seeing like sampling
bias here
and we could try to
prevent that by doing some kind of else
oh what there was a to do in calc base p
for offset
let me take a look
um yeah it could be that it's picking up
light through the wall somehow
but i'm not sure
we didn't see any evidence of that
uh when we looked at the casting here
so
i don't know uh maybe we should have a
way to turn off lights like i click on
them and like
take them out of the solve so we could
see if it if which lights are affecting
which thing
um
that seems like that would be kind of
useful but
uh yeah but i don't know
so
let me look at the to-do that you're
talking about uh so you said calc bass
offset
calc bass p for offset
uh let me take a look at that
um that doesn't really matter that's
just how the lights are arranged
it's so that's actually fine
um
i don't think that matters
so one thing that we haven't considered
is is it possible that two lights are
getting added on top of each other in
that area
although that wouldn't affect anything
so i guess it doesn't matter
but
so uh yeah i'm not sure there's still
some definite weirdness
that we have to track down it's also
kind of odd that some rooms seem very
stable and some rooms seem unstable
and that part is
confusing
uh you would expect there to be a little
bit of instability everywhere
um if it was like a bug bug like a you
know if it was a fairly obvious thing we
did wrong
so it kind of has to be maybe slightly
more subtle
this part
like why
you can like that doesn't make any sense
why is that getting brighter
if anything it should get darker because
there's less lights right like these
lights are going to fall out of the
solution about here
why is it brighter there for a second
there's something wrong where we're able
to like
someh somehow we're adding like to the
wrong atlas or something weird is
happening
uh
so what's happening here is like we're
getting some residual brightness sort of
like in this region right and
so if we look at like this cast
here
hmm
[Music]
so
i mean in theory though that should be
fine because this is just gonna this
will clamp
to the light atlas
so your sample point
would would just be here i think
maybe i'm very wrong about that but it's
but the
but the light atlas sampling is clamped
in the actual sampler
um let's keep looking though
you
so you know yeah i mean i i don't think
that's a problem because it should just
clamp back to here i don't know why
that would really be causing us any
problems
um
also
that's going to be a
t terminate which in theory shouldn't
sample
like so
if we look at the lighting code in grid
raycast we don't actually
like not only would we not
think that that was a problem but we're
nuking those right because hit ref color
and hit emission if you
the this is the case that's being hit
there spatial grid node terminator
so when we hit that we're actually going
to produce
zero
right maybe that's wrong but let's take
a look at what happens if we set that
right
because we'd fall out of
this case
um
and i guess something hit would be
this is what happens in the case where
you get something hit
right
if you don't get something hit then you
do this
uh and so both of those things would be
fine we'd end up out here
um we would we've have it all
uh we would end up out here doing a
bunch of work and coming down eventually
this is all the sampling and all that
crap
and we would eventually say
that we were going to take
uh
the ray weight times the transmission
level
and the hit ref color
the transmission level is just a reflect
level versus the emission level
so like it seems like if as long as this
is zero
i mean we shouldn't have even had to set
both of them as long as hit ref color is
set to zero it should not be able to
accumulate anything
it's just it's just zero
so those are actually going to just be
zero
um
and i suppose one thing we could do here
is we could draw this with the color
that we actually found
um
as well
like we could put hit ref color as the
thing that we draw just to be sure
but
you know
this this just isn't going to contribute
so i just fundamentally do not know
where we're getting
any of this light from
um
like how are we getting
more light in this area
let's because we can let's take a look
uh while we're in this exact place where
we see this bug
let's look at the uh the
in the in the lighting code
uh let's look at the debug draw
octahedral values as well so if we turn
those on
where is it claiming that the light is
coming from
so it's claiming that the light is
coming from here
right
it's claiming that we're getting that
light by casting through the wall
and
so even though we can't actually find an
example of us casting through the wall
um
we are nonetheless
casting through the wall somehow
this one seems brightest so let's look
at that one
like
we need to like show me all the casts
in just this big
i don't know man i don't know how it's
like it's
claiming it's getting the light from
there but we actually can look at the
light values and we don't
seem to get the light from there maybe
is it possible that actually what's
happening
is that our sampler is messed up so it's
it's actually
maybe okay
maybe the problem is that our sampler is
actually sampling offset from where
we actually
hit
how about that for a
stupid idea
so in this like ridiculous code here
where we're taking the
um
you know
here's here's the total bounds like
we're offsetting it from there whatever
right
uh we do
our you know our sampling code this kind
of nonsense
is it possible that somehow this code
when it goes to get the atlas out of it
that that is wrong
so i guess the first question i would
have is why the heck is the spatial grid
involved in this computation
so
maybe this code is just wrong
did we just never realize
that
did we just never realize that we had
this code wrong when we switched to
these being
staggered because if you think about it
the spatial grid
that should not be involved anymore
because the spatial grid is not aligned
to the atlas at all it's a completely
different grid
right
and it's very possible that when we
wrote this code originally they were the
same
and because it's like super optimized
code like all of our stuff is gone like
things we would have normally done to
like assert or check
is very hard to do because simdee you
know one of the super crappy things
about the way you have to program
nowadays is when you actually go to
optimize something simdi-wise
you get screwed
everything becomes very hard to assert
and debug and all these other sorts of
things
but that could be
our well not exactly our problem but
like in that case
that we just saw
that could be the problem um hold on a
second let's take a look at this
so let's
reproduce that uh
that would make sense that so that would
totally
fit
with
why
um
it it it gets wrong as you stagger out
right as you go on half boundaries this
code is wrong
um because it's not using the correct
thing so i'm going to go ahead and say
that that's our problem it's not
probably our only problem but that is a
big part of the bug
yeah this is just wrong
so everything after this is probably
correct because everything else is done
relative to the atlas
like it should be
but this is totally wrong because this
is not the bounds of the atlas and this
is not the dimensions of the cell
right
okay
i i think i'm
definitely right about that
so
[Music]
taking a look at the lighting solution
the grid that we actually want is the
atlas grid
why do we just have something called
grid when we have two two grids is a
very good question
grid
what the heck is grid
maybe we picked the right grid there and
then and i'm totally wrong and that's
the case then oh well
uh we did not find
where is it
all right i lied so grid actually is
atlas grid
so we're okay there
um
or at least i think we are but we should
make sure
meanwhile i'm going to change this to
atlas grid so that i don't have this
confusion again
i'm
still kind of weirded out by this stuff
so i'm not sure i really believe it yet
i still think maybe this code is
slightly wrong
um
in fact
in fact i know it's slightly wrong
because look at how this is being done
yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah
this is definitely wrong
it's it's still wrong
so
if you look at how we're choosing where
we're going to sample you can see that
the corners of this thing are based on
like
like do we know that this grid how did
we actually position this grid exactly
let's okay
not exactly
so let's take a look
at
the
literal alignment of the yeah i mean
like so you can see this is just
we're confused
we have confusion baked into our system
this
thing
whatever the heck this is supposed to be
right
this
cyan region
so if we look at let's just work it
forwards and because i'm pretty sure now
i'm right i mean i'm right that
that there's something
uh
off-center about the way this is working
so if we look at what is actually
drawing the that code uh
it is the sign that cyan boundary
is
like the lighting bounds which i don't
remember who draws those
so we should double check it might be in
an update lighting actually uh
let me just see
yeah
so this is drawing
that's this code
there's the total bounds of the spatial
grid being drawn in green
uh and there's the hot voxel erect
being drawn in cyan
right
uh and that hot voxel wrecked
i don't know why that got offset
is the atlas grid total bounce
and so you can kind of immediately see
what we screwed up
right
supposedly
[Music]
our light samples are being taken from
like these points
right
but the actual location is like
when we sample we're sampling as if
they're here
right
so we're
totally we're like sampling in one place
where we're taking samples from
or casting rays from a location and
writing back a result for that
uh atlas point but then were sampling
from it as if it was in a totally other
place
right so this square
these samples are as if they were out
here which is totally not where we
actually took them from so the raycast
doesn't line up
where we are casting the rays is not
related to where we actually then
pretend those light values are
you you feel me dog
so that's that's the problem
like period
um
so we need to go
resolve that we need to go be very
meticulous and make sure that everybody
has their ducks in a row about
where the samples are taken versus where
the samples are written
right
so uh i vote for a quick break we've
been streaming for three and a half
hours uh let's do a quick break and
we're gonna come back and do that uh
because that is almost certainly
uh at the very least what's causing this
brightening and that weird remember i
said like that should not be flickering
like that that is almost certainly
what's happening there is as you move it
around the alignment of the grid versus
the samples is moving and so sometimes
you end up sampling on one side of a
wall and recording the results on the
other side of the wall right or things
like that
that's going to be why you're getting
that
that happening
i don't know if this has anything to do
with our light leak problem so i can't
promise it'll solve that but this is a
big problem so let's solve this first
and then we can
maybe go back to looking at the light
leak problem all right
break time
[Music]
oh
[Applause]
[Music]
um
foreign
[Music]
hmm
if you don't i mean what else do you
want me to do i don't know what you want
me to do for
a break
you want this instead
[Music]
i mean that's your other option right
now
cody oh yeah
you want
you want cody to do it
do you want do you want a uh do you want
a product placement for a um
uh
[Music]
um for a vpn
i didn't realize um
like someone said the will smith
approaching thing
uh i i didn't know
what the academy actually was i think
i was under the impression because like
he resigned from the academy right and
maybe they would have kicked him out you
know because of the incident or whatever
um
i think i thought the academy awards
were like a union award thing like you
know there's a street screen actors
guild
or like the writer's uh guild
association of america or writer's guild
of america or whatever it is wga
the sag and wga right
um
i think i thought that it was the the
award was like union like the union
was that like like union members voted
or some i think that's what i thought
like i thought like oh yeah the
screenplay like the wga members vote on
best screenplay or something that's what
i thought right
um
but actually
after this whole incident i looked it up
and it's like that's not what the
academy is the academy is literally just
like a separate organization for them to
like
gladhand each other
like if there's nothing it's not a real
thing like the academy awards the
academy of motion picture arts science
or whatever is is literally just a
completely separate organization for
giving themselves awards
i guess
it it it's not actually one of the
unions i i thought
i i
am so weirded out
by the academy
it's it's like it's literally just a
separate glad-handing organization
for for like giving themselves awards
um
like it's it sounds very much like the
game awards in that sense only only it's
somehow been legitimated
so so like i think we should start our
own organization like
here on handmade hero called the
handmade hero awards and and shockingly
all of the awards will go to handmade
hero
anyway i thought that was pretty funny i
didn't realize that
so like
saying you won best picture
means that all of the people who decided
they wanted to be part of an
organization that gives best picture
voted to give you best picture
it's so interestingly self-selecting
i don't know if we'd have we've never
had anyone slap anyone else on handmade
hero
but that's probably because it's just me
and i'm not probably going to slap
myself like oh like you know i don't
know
i mean really if we wanted to do
something like the game awards it from
what i've seen the game awards are like
just a giant advertisement like no one
cares about the awards they're just
there to advertise new games or whatever
so we could also go that route instead
where like handmade hero awards are
literally just me like pimping the
stream for an hour right it's just like
talking about exciting things we're
gonna do on the stream
later
so like even though it's an award show
which is supposed to be for things that
already happened instead mostly all we
talk about is things that are gonna
happen someday
well
speaking of things that are gonna happen
someday
let's make one of those things gonna
happen someday is us fixing this stupid
problem
okay
so
let's start with me being really
freaking confused about the sampling
so somehow when we sample
the rays from one of these places
i guess it's because we're calling get
cell center p
must be the reason for that
right
i mean i guess not really
that's just the spatial grid
so it's really actually the place
outside of this it's the
um
it's the part that's actually telling us
what location we want to cast from
so when we call it's actually when we
call
grid raycast
the
call site
this part here
uh that's doing the full cast that like
vox center p
uh
that that's actually what's creating
this this
situation right
ryan
i like that
yes
exactly
so
that cell center p
is total horse poop
and probably has been for a while
right
by the way i'm eating peanut butter
pretzels
from costco
basically costco
i need to get a costco sponsorship from
the stream
because a lot of things i eat on the
stream are from costco
but i'm not getting paid where's my
costco sponsorship money
that's what i want to know
like how come we don't have little
costco banner and stuff right
where's those sweet costco monies
i don't think i've ever seen a streamer
sponsored by costco so
probably not gonna make that work but
you know i'm just saying
yeah you should talk to mr costco
let's get mr costco on the phone
let's make that happen okay
so
this is just a giant horse poop pile
because we're casting out of the center
of a grid square but we don't write the
sample values back to the center of the
grid square we write them back to the
corner of the grid square so how what
sense does that make
right
not very much
not very much at all
so
i mean we can start
by asking the question of why does that
call even exist why would we ever get
the center
of an atlas grid
i mean i guess because we want that for
other reasons
but it's just garbage
like i don't i don't see the point of it
so
if i may
uh i think we need to start by uh doing
something like let's not do that and
let's just get them in corner
you know what i'm saying to you
uh let's go over here to the mr light
atlas sun
uh and let's figure out if uh there's a
reason why we're we're calling this oh
that's the wrong atlas um we are looking
actually for the spatial grid
so
in here like we want the cell bounds and
we want to use the minimum
uh of the cell bounds because that's
where we're actually writing that sample
right
so let's start by doing something like
this
uh
just to see
if we can slowly work our way
uh because now this will move all our
sample points to the wrong place and
then we'll offset the grid to being in
the correct place hopefully maybe i
don't know
um
so you know we'll kind of go as we go
so uh we have a second problem which is
that the thing that draws them is also
going to be calling that get center so
this box center p thing
i should also
we should just call this like
cast
from p because it's not
gonna be any particular boxes center
anymore
uh and then if we do draw
you know what's kind of funny i should
have just changed where we draw them and
then said it was correct right that's
that's like that's like the u.s
government solution to the problem
instead of actually solving the problem
just try to hide conceal or change the
numbers or redact the like pages to make
it seem like everything was fine and
then you don't actually solve the
problem that's what you should have done
but
you know silly me i went in here to try
to actually fix the problem
what am i thinking
anyway
in debug of the hedral values
this is this part here
um the center p that should go away
um
center p instead should be like cast
from p
and that should be the corner
of the cell
right
i assume
that's my story and i'm sticking to it
i don't care what you think
i'm
going with that
narrative
okay
so
uh
in theory now we're casting from those
locations i don't actually know that
that's true
uh i also don't know what the heck this
is i guess that's just the thing that
says that there was something there or
something
um but we need this to be rectmindim
uh if we're trying to do
actually no that's not true uh
so because we are trying to say like
this is a little rectangle centered
around the thing that's casting i guess
i don't know what the point of that
thing is um
we don't really need that but because we
can see where it is just fine so that
those little red
like those little red squares are not
particularly valuable to anybody i don't
think
but you know whatever
uh anyway now we can see what's actually
happening so this is the this is the
truth of the matter this is this is the
sad truth of it all right
um
and
the the reason for this is because again
like this voxel
you have to remember is
we can only interpolate between points
that we actually have
so
the
this cell it doesn't really count for
anything and we need to actually clamp
to just the
to the earlier values like we're kind of
like we have a one-off problem here
right
um where we want the number of
we want the actual thing to stop one
before
uh the final number because we have to
be able to sample from anywhere
everywhere in it uh now i should mention
that even now like we're gonna get some
pretty bad lighting artifacts because
like half the crap is like in the floor
and other things like that so you know
that's not good but we should already at
this point uh have gotten uh potentially
fixing the oh wow okay well
that's that is i don't know what that's
from but that's pretty good uh as you
can see we should be able to fix the
light leaking from the uh
from the one part that we had here but
man we've got other issues
that's fine uh like i said before you
know uh
we
want to fix this all the way
maybe this will help i didn't think this
was going to but maybe this will help us
solve our light leaking problem because
if we can make that happen
like
that pronounced
uh
hopefully that would help us solve it i
don't know though that may be wishful
thinking
you can also see some really strange
stuff
already
like how is all of this bright
when the black like
the the black sample spheres would say
that there's no light in that area right
so
anyway
um so pushing forwards we kind of have
to
finish getting all the rest of this
stuff working
i want to finish my pretzels first
though
so
at this point
uh our samples are definitely in the
wrong place they're now properly aligned
with the atlas sort of
but also not because we now sort of also
have to think about the fact that we
want
the actual bounds of the voxel
uh to
[Music]
to clamp out before the end of the voxel
right
and we're gonna have to look to see like
how we actually create some of these
things because like i said don't
remember it's been so long
since i wrote this code but you can see
on here where we're doing the like make
voxel grid and this sort of thing
we are
going to use when we're making these uh
these grid pieces
we're going to be using like information
about how many um
how many things we have inside the voxel
so
you can sort of see here how the spec
atlas
i mean they're fixed sizes right so the
spec atlas and the diffuse atlas are
both whatever this atlas cell count is
and you can see that when we create the
atlas grid we end up making
a voxel grid with
you know
the whatever the atlas cell count is
in it
my
thinking there
is that that really should have been
stepped back one
right
because
uh each grid square is
only in you can only interpolate within
the the cube
and you can't
you you
need to end
the size of the voxel is going to be one
less than the number of sample points in
the atlas
in each dimension
so if you know the x dimension of our
atlas has 10 samples in it
then the atlas grid should only have
nine cells because you need one at the
end in order to interpolate all the way
out to the outside
of
uh of the atlas right
so the voxel dimension for the spec
atlas like did we factor that in that's
i guess what i'm wondering
and i don't know uh because it's been so
long since we did it
so if we look at like make like
make
light atlas
um
where we have like the voxel dim
how do those things line up
and i'm not sure
i mean it like it looks to me like they
basically don't
yeah so i mean
i think
i think i'm just right about this i
don't know
i think essentially what you want here
is when you look at the atlas cell count
you have to subtract one from it when
you make the like corresponding spatial
grid that's just what happens
right
um
and i don't mean this spatial cell count
i mean literally the grid that
corresponds to the atlas
like this
is not correct
uh so at the very least the atlas grid
here i'm gonna say we need to start by
subtracting one
uh
in all three dimensions
when we determine how big this thing
actually is and the vox cell dim is fine
that is what it is we don't care about
that part at all i don't think
um
but at a bare minimum like we need this
thing to be exactly the bounds which now
you can see like at least it's starting
to line up the way that i wanted it to
right
so whenever we are clamping something
whenever we are going to like
sample and we clamp it clamps back down
into something that is the correct
spatial region now what the heck is
happening here i have no idea so that's
that's going to be a fun little treat
this is all just so freaking weird like
i have no idea i have no idea what that
is about so we're not going to pretend
that we know what that's about yet but
first like i said i want to solve one
problem at a time so the first thing we
want to do is figure out
okay if we assume that this is now
bounded properly then the next step is
to actually make sure that the bounds
line up with something that would work
so we want to shift the bounds
uh so that they are back in the center
of you know
they're back like roughly centered so
when we align this particular grid and
decide where it's actually going to be
uh we want the
the uh once we make this voxel grid with
you know the the cell dim and all that
stuff we want its base like wherever
it's actually placed
uh we want that to be offset
uh in a some particular way right
and so at the moment
um
[Music]
this setman corner nonsense
right uh that wants to be offset by one
half
uh the fundamental grid size right so
instead of atlas min corner here being
like uh this this offset here
we actually it looks like we sort of
already kept it at centers so this
actually wants to not happen
um the z might need to change high voice
um
so this
might need to occur or something like
that we'll see in a second uh but we
need to
uh remove that sort of offset on x and y
because that should actually be uh
centered now in theory
okay uh so
i think that's about
about right i can't quite tell
it's too high
um
definitely too high okay so so i lied uh
maybe
it it
oh um
[Music]
so so let's let's turn that off for one
second
uh and let's see where that is roughly
at okay
um
that seems pretty good but still
probably a little bit too low
so i'm going to say shift it up a little
bit
i don't know if half the fundamental
dimension is the right amount but it
might be
that looks better
so i think that's about right
yeah roughly
roughly
okay
uh so
the
overall size of the lighting is is it
correct is it not correct i'm not sure
how the alignment is overall
it looks like it's skewed a little bit
that way
but not in a way that would necessarily
concern us because it's two versus one
you're always gonna have a little bit of
that
um so that's probably fine so i would
say this looks about right on alignment
i'm gonna i'm gonna say that's roughly
correct
yeah you know within reason within
reason
um so i think those are now aligned
properly i don't know exactly how when
we send down our lighting values we send
them down so we may have to update that
a little bit so here when we do uh you
know push lighting render values
i don't really know what we send down
for our uh
for our actual textures here
doesn't look
looks like we just used the atlas grid
total bounds
uh which seems fine
that's the hot rocks voxel rick minimum
and the invot dim
uh
that seems fine
for sampling
probably
possibly
yeah i think that's about right
yeah
um
but of course we also sort of have
another problem here which is that
anything that is outside in z wants to
clamp back in z and i don't know if we
have anything like that in the shader so
we kind of need to
uh
first make sure that the shader itself
when it does this lookup the shader is
gonna have to do something about that
um
[Music]
right like
it's gotta actually
make sure that it keeps you bounded
inside the voxel which i don't know if
it actually does or even tries to do
uh
so that's a good question
um
what happens
what happens there
does anyone know
uh so
we should probably we never were able to
get a four coder that actually could
show these properly so we probably
should move these out into their
separate into separate files now because
it's just too hard to read them
um
i had hoped at some point that you know
you'd be able to just include your
shader code directly in your c code but
that
didn't happen
um so
you
know uh
i suppose i could fix it now i have
access to the four quarter source i
should probably just go fix this myself
uh because i can't imagine it's that
hard all it has to do is not change to a
string parser
um
and just leave itself doing regular
parsing and this would work
so
uh maybe we can fix that someday anyway
if we look in here
uh
we we're setting the vox minimum corner
and
uh the cell
dimension uh
what inv total dim means is that
okay so it's just the inverse of the
complete dimension of the voxel so that
seems fine
um
so at some point
we're gonna compute which
uh
cell we're looking into
and it looks like this is
you know the code that does that right
there's the sample lighting
uh and then up in here you kind of have
uh okay we're sampling from this voxel
offsetted by this
you know this cell
index versus you know offset by that
cell index
so that implies to me that we first in
here we must have computed
what our base
voxel lookup was
um and you can see it's got an 05 offset
there
so i think this has kind of been wrong
the entire time
basically we had lighting values that we
were offsetting by 0.5 which was kind of
correct in terms of their placement but
we were never casting from that location
right
um and i guess originally that was okay
because we had so many z samples that we
actually just left it in place and we
didn't need to shift it but now that we
only have two z samples they both have
to be inside which means that you
actually have to cast from where you
think you're casting from
so yeah this is kind of confusing
but i think this probably was slightly
wrong for quite some time in a way
uh but anyway
so when we come in here uh assuming that
now our voxel is always aligned we don't
really have to shift anything
because the placement of you in the
world should just be correct
right so so this
that should not be required
um when you do the floor value you'll
just get the correct corner and this
will give you the correct interpolant uh
and the only difference here is we want
this to be clamped right
so we don't want this to go too high or
too low
because you'll just end up sampling
weird places
in the texture so
that's easier said than done
in x and y because we don't actually
have a maximum x and y
here
i
like that is not in the actual
thing right
so if we look at the lighting sample
which is this
code here
um
when we do the uh vox i plus devoxx eye
that needs to get clamped
and i think that's basically it
i don't really remember how glsl works
at all
but i assume it's not that complicated
to clamp something
uh
so like for example we have like clamp
zero one here
uh we made some of these macros
uh
they're this garbage right here
so i assume that if i were to do a clamp
um i could just clamp
to zero and something else right like
if i said all right
the i value is actually a clamp
of this vox i plus dvox i nonsense
um and the minimum value is just 0 0 0
which i think you can do this way in
glsl
and this value is just like the maximum
like it's like the lighting
[Music]
uh
the maximum lighting
voxel dimension which is this thing and
hey look it's already a vector even so i
think that would just
fix it for us right
so in theory that should clamp things uh
uh
who knows
but like in theory that would clamp all
of our lookups now so that they aren't
fetching out into no man's land
um and
i i guess like i don't know but i think
that uh yeah i mean that's why it's not
black now like it was before
uh right
so okay
still a lot of weirdness though like wow
like what is happening right
so uh
but getting closer
so we've fixed the alignment i think in
the shader to now be clamping and in
theory i think it should be clamped to
the correct places what i should do now
i want to do like a little bit more
cleanup work first but what we'll do
pretty soon after is i'll seed this with
uh
known values so i'll just put like rgb
rgb rgb in it
not actually compute any lighting and
then verify that i'm sampling correctly
uh you know what i'm saying
in the actual shader because you know
now that we've made a fairly substantial
changes here it's going to be kind of
weird like we're definitely going to be
in a
position where we don't
um have like
you know uh
we don't we won't know where our stupid
bugs are right so we have to start to
feed some structured art through it to
like secure one system at a time
uh but before we do that i want to go
fix other problems with the spatial
alignment of the atlas
which is to say that when we are doing
our sampling in here now i want to make
sure that this makes some sense because
i don't know that this makes any sense
either
so in here where we're doing
our sampling now we know that we're
loading the atlas grid inverse cell
dimension and total bounds in here
which is
good that's what we want
um
but i don't know
about the rest of the code
so how's the rest of this stuff work
let's look
so
the voxel dimensions for the diffuse
atlas are loaded here
um the floor of the f chord and that
that all looks right so we're tracking
the minimum
we're
uh multiplying by the inverse dimension
so that tells us where we are
uh
in the grid
we
are
taking the stride
of the atlas and the dimension of the
atlas for sampling purposes which is
fine
we are
looking at the max sample location which
is also fine
we're clamping the b chord to the max
value
and the minimum value
that seems right
to
me um
i don't know that that seems right
that all seems like totally reasonable
so i could be very wrong about that
uh but that all seems like pretty
reasonable like it's just it's just
trilinear blend
i
it's
interesting that we say this because we
did kind of weld it in right
yeah so we don't actually need to do
yeah
uh anyway
so i don't see
any real weirdness there that all seems
like fairly sane
to me
mostly
um
now i don't actually know and i would
like to check that where we are
raycasting from makes any sense at the
immediate moment that i'm not sure about
but it shouldn't be too hard to figure
that out
um
why am i not
why is my raycast not moving look at
that it's like i'm not gonna move
what's up with that
why why am i like no you don't get you
can't move
that's bizarre isn't it
are those clamping to something
weird
um i don't see quite why but it's fine
so
[Music]
the atlas grid cell count is actually
wrong now because we fixed that part so
this can actually do
a debug pick from everywhere in it
but that shouldn't really have been the
problem because that's
yeah that
i don't know why that clamp would have
been not working in the other dimensions
but i guess it's not
yeah like why why is that busted
it's like no
you are not allowed to move
doesn't that seem kind of odd
like what's the deal with that
i mean one assumes that's the atlas
indexes clamping happening but maybe
it's not like if i get rid of the
clamping
is it still broken
okay that's just mysterious
so we've entered like full nonsense land
where we have no idea what's going on
obviously
so what's the problem here why is our
debug uh
why is this not allowed to edit
is there something we don't know
um that we're supposed to know
aha
yes there is
so this
has to actually work and it's not going
to now
so this was getting reset every time
which is
not good
um so what we want to do here is we want
to actually
pre-determine like we want to pre-make
that number
this right here
so we want to like v3 atlas
grid cell count
we want the atlas grid
you know to have been computed ahead of
time
and we want the atlas grid cell count to
be
checked here we want to say like
okay if the
atlas grid cell count is not equal to
what we have it set to then we will do
our little fancy dance
that was weird
to say the least
um
okay
so hopefully that resolves our problem
and it did
um i can put the clamp back in
now it looks like i already had so
that's fine
um
but now let's get back to the question
at hand which is okay so
what are we actually seeing here when we
do these raycasts because you know who
knows we don't really know let's take a
look at one of them to see what the heck
is happening because we don't have any
idea
so
uh
i don't actually see where this is
casting from oh it's right there
um that's not really that useful to me
let's try
like
there
maybe
um
yeah that
is
not
correct at all like
so we're casting in a totally not
correct location apparently
or something
it's just considering itself to have
always hit
right
let's look at the z one down
i mean those all seem fine i don't see
anything weird there
seems fine
now so we're definitely in a weird place
so we're offset somehow like that's not
hitting the ceiling
is it oh wait no it is no it is that's
the light source
so this one was also probably inside a
light source
ah
but you know why it was casting from
inside a light source
because full cast is probably using the
wrong location now as well
one assumes
so in here
i
[Music]
so that should have fixed it so i'm not
really sure
atlas to spatial grid index offset i
wonder if that's wrong
like i wonder if that initial grid index
is wrong
half atlas index
okay that makes sense
that on the other hand
i don't know if it does
so my first question would be can we
just not do this anymore
so does anyone else use this
because if not like it seems like pretty
with all of this work that we're doing
during raycasting it seems pretty
inexpensive to just say look get the
initial grid index by actually mapping
it into the voxel so i don't have to
care if these two things are aligned
right
in fact now i really just don't even
want them to have to be aligned because
there's no reason why they should have
to be aligned
and so i think we want to get rid of
that entirely like i think we want to
get rid of this concept
completely
we want to just map the thing into the
spatial grid just full on right so we
take whatever the light probe p is
and we just map that in
i
i don't actually know what the
code would be but
this i guess
and i assume we needed to be clamped as
well
i mean although it always
should be
so
that's actually if you could just assert
that it's inbounds actually
um
so i guess you would do something more
like
all right half atlas index is out of
here goodbye
um
uh
initial grid i
is get index 4p
[Music]
for whatever the spatial grid is
and whatever the light probe position is
figure it out
uh and then here in initial grid index
we're just making a flat index from
whatever that was
i'm going to assert that it's inbounds
because
who knows
maybe we screwed something up and it's
not
but it should always be because we only
cast from inside the spatial partition
we never cast from outside
um and so
a flat index from
is u32 so let's
cast that down
although i don't know why because it
doesn't have to be
a flat index anymore in that way it can
just be 32-bit so actually
switch all this to 32-bit it's now fine
because the only reason there are 16-bit
is because previously we had walk tables
we don't have walk doesn't work because
we optimize all that out
so
you know
that's all fine
okay so in theory now we should at least
be starting from the correct grid
location uh
you know although i guess you know
before i even look at anything i should
fix finish the rest of this though
uh so now we should be starting from the
correct grid location because we're
actually mapping it in here and we can
get rid of that half atlas
um
we don't really need atlas to spatial
grid index offset um
like it seems like we should be able to
just get rid of this
and it's used like out here in this
thing
but i don't think we care about that at
all
i mean we can still use that as the way
we do the alignment at the immediate
moment but um we don't need to store it
certainly
uh so we'll just leave that because it
needs to compute how it's aligned and
how it's aligned at the moment is
probably fine
um
but you know
we don't really care
okay
uh so we still have really weird casting
bugs so like we're not casting from the
correct locations still you can tell
uh pretty easily right
um so what's the deal with with the
what's the deal with grape nuts you know
what i'm saying
why is there no timer i don't know
you know why there's no timer we never
started it
we never started it
sorry about that
3 45.
sorry we never started it
we've only been programming for one
minute and 30 seconds
all right anyway uh
so
yeah
we are still messing this up uh so let's
continue down this this uh
situation and see if we can't find some
more bugs before we start stepping
through it more because like we made
some pretty big changes so let's just
see if we can make this a little more
sane
um
there's really not a lot
to talk about here
i mean we kind of know this is working
properly because we can look at the
bounds
so
the the placement of the bounds
seems still roughly correct
i mean it seems skewed very heavily
forward
for some reason that i don't
totally understand
so like maybe that's a little broken but
uh that
that's really we don't care too much
about
at the moment right so we'll deal with
that a little bit later when we actually
align these right now that shouldn't
matter at all like it shouldn't matter
how they're aligned
um
we you know we we should be able to fix
this uh no matter how they're aligned it
should work
okay
so when we've have it all
when we
create these
uh voxels we create the atlas spatial
one that all looks fine
the offset is just there for the count
which again i really don't think we care
about now
all that stuff had to be very careful
before because we needed the walk tables
lineup we don't care about that at all
anymore
so it should just be fine now
um
yeah so so i mean that all seems
reasonable to me i don't i don't know i
don't think we need to belabor that code
very much but let's go into full cast
and
uh take a look at what's going on in
there i also don't know like full cast
like i have no idea what the point of
full cast is anymore
um it seems like you would just probably
weld that into here because there's no
point to it
it's not really a thing anymore like
it's kind of dumb that these are
separated but you know
anyway
uh
so the grid raycast
path which is usually what we call uh
we're just passing down that initial
grid index which is just coming from
whatever the position is in the spatial
grid
that we get from the light probe p which
is
you know what we are working with so
hopefully
um that's all fine
ray origin is just the four wide version
of that we should probably unify these
names a little bit
um
you know maybe we call this
light probe p so that at least we don't
have yet another variable in there for
no apparent reason
and
yeah i mean
that just seems pretty straightforward
so i'm not sure why we've got such a
messed up solution happening based on
what i see but who knows let's keep
going
so in here we then say okay we're going
to take the spatial
dimensions of the spatial grid
uh that all seems fine
uh we're going to get the center point
and get the difference from that that
all seems fine i don't actually know
what cell dim is used for
in the four wide case
it's only used in a bunch of code that
got if zeroed out it looks like
so i might say like let's just lose this
this was like the old stepping code that
was non-present ham that was crappy why
i didn't use a president in the first
place i don't know it might have saved
us that nonsense of going down the walk
table route because it probably would
have been a lot faster
so that was kind of a mistake
um
but yeah you can see i'm just going to
remove this uh
why does it jump
what is happening there
there's some weird thing happening with
undo where it goes to some place that
had nothing to do with an undo like we
didn't undo anything there did we
i don't know very strange anyway
uh so if i delete this code then we
don't need the cell dim4 which you know
just trying to remove stuff here because
this is getting kind of like very
uh
there's a lot of
dead code in here so i just want to kind
of start cleaning it down to what we
actually now still use
um so
looking at this code we
do need the cell dimension because we're
using that for stepping for the
bresenham part of the code right we do
need the ray weight that's fine uh we
don't really care about total cast
initiated much anymore we could probably
clean up some of these statistics in the
future but that's not arming anyone so
it could stay
at the moment we are getting the cell
center uh that's of the spatial grid we
again don't really care uh the fact that
we have to get this at all is dumb like
so that's why there's two there because
we could have just we already knew what
it was
um before so that's kind of dumb but
anyway this gives us the difference
between where we are actually casting
from and the center of the spatial cell
that's all fine
um at least i can can't think of any
reason why it wouldn't be fine
um
and then all the stepping code again we
didn't change the spatial index rules or
any of that stuff so all that should
just be fine
um when we go to sample from the
atlas this again should also i think be
okay
but it doesn't again we're having some
kind of a weird issue here where
for some reason our actual like our
actual spatial grid stepping seems
somewhat off or something
um
i'm gonna turn off
debug drawing in its entirety here
uh so that all i see is just the cast
and it looks like we also have lights
being drawn but i guess that's
not really a problem
i'm okay with that
all right uh so
i guess one pretty odd thing
is
that
what i'm looking at now suggests that
the spatial partition is sort of oddly
aligned
to the grid
but you know that really shouldn't
matter but it's a bit odd
right
um
like the spatial partition is now like i
don't really want the spatial partition
to be aligned in that way against the
casting i want you to be like in one
cell or not because otherwise we're
going to have a lot of numerical
precision fiddliness i think
so i would like to do
a slight change there so
when we're actually talking about the
casting
um
and we look at like the alignment when
we do these uh i would want this to be
like a half off
so we took that out before for the
spatial grid i think i still want that
in there
um
so maybe like the vox seldim xy i'm just
going to offset it by half a cell
so that it lines up with the corners um
i don't know that's my story and i'm
sticking to it it's not a very good
story i admit that
um
okay so
here's us casting
um
from this location
and i just i'm gonna
look to see if these are sane at all
i don't know if they are
they seem pretty good
they seem they seem pretty good
oh man check out how long that cast
hey man that's light for you
those photons
uh okay
so
literally just the fact that we were on
the numerical edge was enough to cause
that much of a problem apparently
um also we're we're
our alignment is shifty which is very
weird so we got another problem in here
like you see how it's shifting so our
alignment is inconsistent as we move
through this through space which is
not good
um so we'll have to fix that
uh but
otherwise
much more stable now aren't we just
uh i kind of like that shifting effect
i don't want it in there because it's
wrong but i kind of like it it's kind of
cool looking
so for some reason our atlas slides are
sampling slides relative to the grid
why would that be
because again the spatial grid should
not it should not matter because the
atlas grid is actually the only thing
that matters there
um
[Music]
so i don't really understand how we're
getting a shift
on the atlas grid
[Music]
how could that be happening ladies and
gentlemen
boys and girls
actually probably everyone who watches
this show is probably not a boy or a
girl anymore they're probably a man or
woman but
men and women ladies and gentlemen there
you go
so
what would it be
what would it be that would cause the
voxel to shift
and it's in
it's like
it's actually in like the voxel wrecked
that gets sent down
[Music]
so it's like the atlas grid's min corner
got set to something else
like here
but how is that possible because it's
always locked
i guess is it because of the
camera offset part
um
that does seem wrong
so the camera offset is a rolling value
so how the heck
how the heck was this working
am i missing something
so this is the original origin
offset here
which includes the actual
value that we strip away
right
how the heck was this not causing
visible role
as we shifted
what the heck
i don't understand
does someone else understand
that is totally confusing
because right like when this comes in
and you send down here the
the
[Music]
p values right so you've got sim origin
p and origin p
so the sim origin is going to be locked
it doesn't roll it just jumps
but the origin p would roll
and
oh i see because we set it to a round
value
we actually round it ahead of time
okay
i see what you did there
so that offset is always going to be
like a fixed
amount that we've squared
and i suppose that's fine
um
so really this part here we could have
probably avoided
this is just adding back in this in a
sense
um
[Music]
so we probably could have just gotten
rid of that
it we could have just zeroed the dim
here out and then that wouldn't happen
that probably is how we should have done
that
but whatever um
so this is
now wrong because the number of cells is
not
the voxel dimension of the diffuse atlas
right it's actually
going to be
the
this cell count
so i'm not sure that actually is the
right number to use either uh but let me
think about what that is actually doing
because i don't actually know
so what that's actually doing is it's
uh
it's trying to produce how large this
particular thing should be
but isn't that just
i mean we already have a voxel for it so
wouldn't you be able to just get the
dimensions directly
that seems kind of busted
so i think this is just wrong
uh and i think what you actually want
here
is
the
actual app like the actual
uh atlas grids dimension
right
um i mean i don't even know why this
isn't
asked for
here
maybe we don't have
that concept but we should
like there should be a way to ask how
big this thing is
which is just the cell dim times the
cell count
and there's a total bounds so that
should be pretty trivial too right i
mean that that's actually the whole
thing
so
yeah
so let's just say what if we said that
this was actually the total bounds of
the voxel
so
that solution
atlas
grid
total bounds
let's start there and then let's try to
figure out because i still don't see
though that that's just cleaning up
something that shouldn't probably have
been happening the way it was happening
but what is going on with the sh
what the heck
we're just seeing so much weird stuff
happening
that i don't understand
like how are we getting that flicker
nobody knows
and that is just from this
that's just from setting the minimum
corner
can that really be true let's find out
yeah that's really weird
so the alignment here is really strange
and probably there's a little bit of a
deeper bug happening then as well
cause like just by changing the
alignment you can get very strange
things to happen
which don't make a whole lot of sense
right i mean
it just slowly creep along
um i would like to draw
some
more stuff here
uh
so let me draw the actual uh
octahedra values again so i can see are
they sliding their sampling location
or are
we somehow sliding the shaders sampling
location
because either one would be
could happen right
so it almost looks like it's just the
shading that's sliding
right because like the octahedral values
are locked in place they don't look like
they're sliding and they don't look like
they're changing either they just look
like they are what they are
if we zoom in
[Music]
on like that value you can see it
moving
right
but the actual values
the actual values clearly do something
different depending on where you are
[Music]
i say
we're getting close
but we're not getting quite
so where's the spatial grid at
like what's going on there
looks pretty solid
not exactly
um so even as the grid slides as is
represented by the cyan and magenta
coloring
i i don't
really see any evidence that like the
actual things are sliding
so i'm really weirded out by
[Music]
by the octahedral lighting values
because if they're not changing how the
heck
is the shader that far off we must be
setting
the value the alignment in the shader
must be totally busted like
when we set that value
it's setting it wrong or something
so that as we slide we are offset
like right
oh the scale is wrong
the scale is wrong the scale is wrong
it's wrong
that's what our problem is
the scale
is wrong isn't it
okay so why is the scale wrong
why is it wrong
somebody tell me why the scale is wrong
if someone else can tell me why the
skill is wrong then i don't have to
figure it out so that would be nice
but unfortunately you probably don't
know and that's fine i mean i'm the one
doing the stream it's my responsibility
at the end of the day not gonna blame
you
uh but okay so you can see the hot voxel
rect here is getting pulled out of the
atlas grid's total bounce which is what
we want
no it's not
so because we clamp in the shader
to the actual maximum value
that probably means that this needs to
be divided by actually the smaller value
i am going to argue
here is my argument you feel free to
disagree with it it's not
going to be very eloquent
i'm going to argue the following thing
when we
do
so so
[Music]
when we do our sampling
uh we do
the
the vox i plus devoxx i
right in
here so the way this works is we
are
off we're first subtracting
to to get the vox i value in the first
place
right
um
we are
first subtracting
the minimum corner
which is set
here
uh which we assume has to be correct
because there it's just one point in
space it so unless we were pulling that
somehow from
uh yeah i i don't know how that could be
wrong i mean maybe it is but i can't
think of how that could be wrong exactly
but
what we then do is we multiply by the
inverse total dimension
right
now why we do that in two steps i have
no freaking idea
like that should just be one value right
um
but because we are
because we're using light lookup voxel
dim
which doesn't have the minus one baked
into it
we're actually off by one in this
mapping
that's my story
uh and again i i don't know
why we set it up exactly this way that
seems
stupid
um
but that's just kind of
where we're at right now so i guess i
won't change it i don't know um the
light look look up voxel dim
value uh which is
which is for you
this
i think
in order to now line up yeah has to just
be you have to subtract one from it
because otherwise you're going to go
one further than you should when you're
talking about which cell you're in
i i will say that that's a little ad hoc
i should really work that out
directly but yeah
i mean it seems like i was right but i
was like a little bit hazy in my
thinking so i probably should have been
a little bit more careful but
um
okay so let's turn off all of our debug
stuff now and see what the lighting
actually looks like uh so we can figure
out how far away we are from this being
actually working properly
um
so
uh
well something like that
if you will
or if you want
um so here's the lighting
uh you know does it look stable maybe i
should turn off those bounds as well so
they're not shifting around you can see
like it's not big enough we should
probably make it you can see the edge of
the apron there which we want to fix
so we maybe should do that as well but
let's see how we're doing here do i see
any flickeriness
everything seems pretty stable except
for where we're clipping off the apron
um
i mean that looks pretty good
getting some z fighting on
that ground patch there but that's
probably just
somewhat inevitable we should pick those
we need to pick those values with blue
noise
so uh
looking backwards a little bit so you
can see the alignment here is not
fabulous
uh so maybe we should try to skew that a
little bit more i don't really remember
how that code was working
let's take a look
uh in here
says casey
um
to be completely honest i'm not sure why
the atlas
is shifted like that um
so i
like i would not be able to
tell you
why
the atlas appears to be biased in that
direction
like do not know
um so that seems bad i should have an
argument for why that is the case and
the fact that i don't is not good
what i would ask is if we enlarge it
does it continue to be biased in that
direction or is it like only one or two
off like how how bad is that
um
actual difference so like in here we've
got these like voxel settings
if we were to enlarge this voxel
somewhat so suppose that this was going
to be
i don't know uh 20 and 28 or something
like that
um
which maybe is a little bit too much of
an ask for the lighting system but i
don't know i just want to see what does
it look like right
i just want to see how it's aligned
so it's still like
sort of a little off but not that bad so
i don't know if that
is something i should expect or not i i
feel like that's a bit confusing
um i do feel like that's a little bit
confusing but you know all right uh so
if i go into world mode and i remove the
camera wrecked there uh it's weird that
these all drawn in like different places
should probably have like one
centralized place where we can turn
these things on and off
um
you know maybe that's another cleanup
thing we do at some point is just try to
like gather up the debug code into
something that makes more sense
um
you know
and all that but
um if we go down to push lighting values
so here's the two uh the hot voxel rect
although can you even see those anymore
it's really just the camera wreck that
you see
right so if we just turn off the camera
that should be it which is this right
here
all right so like if one were playing
the game
um
it would roughly be this of course we we
do have that uh debug cast still running
i could probably get rid of that
um
as well by just doing like
okay so if we were actually playing the
game
it seems pretty reasonable
like this would be fine
um we do want to make this lighting not
look so squarey and weird which is
pretty easy to do now actually
so we should probably do that but
very stable i would say
there's a little bit of lag up at the
front end because it's not lag but
hiccups when you page when things get
paged in and out
um but i think if we added a slight like
i'm not averse to having a frame or two
of lag in the lighting if it means
smoothing it out slightly
so we might not have to do wider regions
we maybe could get away with that
um
by just
having the um
uh
the t update value be something else
i
like you know it could be something more
like
every
[Music]
you know quarter
um so like four frames every four frames
it's you know more or less completely
blended
um
let me turn off that debug cast as well
debug pic
so
[Music]
zero
um yeah
meow
so if we meow along here and we pretend
we were playing the game you know how
grumpy would we be about this lighting
um
i mean i think it looks really good so i
think really or most of our problem is
that we place it we have our lights
placed in some kind of weird ways that
probably aren't very good
um
so maybe we fixed that part but overall
i'd say the lighting solution seems very
good now
right
um so
we also can make this much faster
because we've
we're still like validating the entire
atlas every frame
um and we have the grid raycast
debugging turned on
we could turn that off
because that's also a huge
issue
um
okay
uh so we actually we probably aren't
really that far off our frame rate
either uh which is kind of nuts i don't
know though we'll have to look and see
how bad we are
so we're a little bit not great uh in
because with that larger you know making
the lighting
being slightly larger in the lighting
region
is an issue
um for sure right
because there's just more there's more
of everything to deal with
so
having to go to a larger lighting region
is expensive
and i don't know
uh like we'll have to see to what extent
we can speed things up more
um i'd also be kind of curious now to
know what would happen if we just cast
white noise instead of
a pre-computed light directions
on the sphere because i don't know like
it would add some noise back in but it
might uh be nice i don't know
so we should try that as well but
i would say we're pretty good to go um
this still has asserts baked in
so like
it also like we got a lot of we we have
to go through and like
now pull out any code that's like old
code and stuff like that and also like
we do have handmade internal and slow on
so i assume if we turn those off we'd
actually get more speed as well um i
don't really know
looks like we have some things in our
diagram code that didn't get their own
what is that set origin
the heck is set origin
it's this
it's next to overlay
so it's
this apparently
uh
let's
get rid of that
render diagrams not found that's true
because that's probably inside here yeah
um so we would need something that just
stubs that out right
so
like this sort of thing
so this accesses global diagrams group
so the collision recorder why is any of
this stuff on at all
this should not be on in the
non-internal build right
that seems kind of busted
um
so that seems like something we probably
have to fix
because we don't actually have a way to
turn off the editor i guess which is
pretty broken
that should be on internal right like
that's not supposed to
a thing
um so you know i don't know like it's
probably not it's not 60 frames a second
for sure
but it might be around 30 and this is a
pretty old machine
so we might have to do a little more
work to make sure that we can actually
hit 60 with the lighting on
um and dropping the ray count down would
probably do it like in other words if we
wanted to
uh we could do only eight rays
instead
so
you know right now we're casting 16
um
per texel right we could drop that down
to eight see how bad that is
it might be pretty bad
uh but again if we switched to white
noise then we could
also be dynamic with how many of those
there were which might be nice
as a separate issue
um we could try it
just to see
if we go to hh sphere
uh if i remember correctly we could now
delete some of this stuff like the walk
table offset
and that sort of stuff right
um
so if we were to rebuild the light table
and have it cast fewer things
we could see if that would give us the
speed back that we need as well
um so if we do an hh sphere
uh
w build h8 sphere
uh if we said like
um
eight
and
then uh i don't remember what this is
called like handmade
sampling squares again
so we did eight and eight uh instead of
816 which i think is what we were doing
before
uh
why is that still generating directions
oh i guess we still do do that stepping
all right well whatever
um if we rebuild now
what happens
so that's with only eight rays per pixel
um
and again i don't actually know we
should probably have a way to do frame
rate counting outside of an internal
build
but it could be that actually now it's
just the diffuse build is what is too
expensive for us so like just processing
more of the texture map
right um
if that makes sense uh so you know
uh we'll see
can i revert this buffer
kill buffer
sampling spheres so yeah you can see
it's eight now right
um
so if i go to handmade internal
what is that complaining about world is
an undeclared identifier somehow i find
that very hard to believe
but okay
so i mean now we're easily hitting 30
there right um
so that's good
but it still might be the case
that
uh
it still might be the case that
you know i don't i don't know
how
expensive the
that sort of
blend is
but i would imagine it's pretty
expensive
so like if for example i took that blend
out
you know like
this
if this blend went away
what would happen
besides the fact that we don't get any
lighting but you know what i mean
so you know we're in here
we're running it around 30.
we dropped that out of there
no change
come on
that can't be possible can it
thought this thing was super slow did we
really speed it up that much
why are we so awesome
i guess would be the real question
all right
so then you're telling me that the cast
is all the time
apparently the cast is all the time
good to know
well
we've got issues we still have issues to
address
um
but
you know having issues to address is
is not as bad as where we started which
is with buggy lighting the lighting now
looks i would say excellent
um
i do think that
we have some issues with like look we
don't want these like weird pools of
light and we may want the shader to
interpolate a little differently
because there is a little bit of
squariness there that you're that you
get um so there's a couple things i
think that could look better
right um inside looks quite good
uh but outside not so much so i do think
like taking a look at that would be good
separately
also what the heck is happening there
can we talk about that what is that why
is that
cube like sized differently than
everybody else
or is that just because like there's
some random
randomness in this maybe it's just
because they're randomly picked and
one's kind of off to the side i don't
know i'm just gonna call that source art
bug for now
um
anyway
looks really good couple things i don't
love
uh
so this
looks not good like
i don't know exactly why we get such a
weird
i mean we i know partially that the
reason for this is because the interior
node here
is
like
can't cast because it's in the middle of
geometry so it's going to be blacked out
right
um so i do wonder if we might want to do
something else there
like
set this equal to halfway in between
these two
or something
like
smooth any atlas any casters things that
can't cast they just get set to like the
average of their surroundings or
something
um
not which will be less accurate but
perhaps more visually pleasing
you know what i mean
uh so i don't know why is the lighting
the lighting down here is just casting
from up above right because we turned
off z so it's actually pulling the light
from
the the surface to light down below so
we're about to pull out these lower
areas right that's going to happen
um
but yeah
uh i do wonder now what happens if we
add back in a moving light source so we
can kind of take a look at how messed up
that is we do have one bug like that
we'd have to sort of fix that's going to
cause a huge problem with that um
so
yeah there's there's an issue there but
let's suppose we go back to the ad
player thing and there used to be like
um
a light
happening in here or something
uh or or maybe i guess that wasn't
that's not true it was actually in
world mode it's it's this
i should look for those temporaries
that can stay
i can stay
[Music]
lovely
all right so if we put this debug back
light back in
we're going to hit a nasty bug that we
have to figure out how to solve which is
what happens when a a a light
is basically entirely eclipsing a uh
one of the nodes
right um and you can i think you can
kind of see what's happening there
uh with that sort of glow in and out
what's happening is that the well
instead of telling you one and i just
show you
so do you see how the light itself
occludes
uh
one of the main probes that would be
hitting it so you get a brief moment in
between when the super bright light
fills everything and then it immediately
gets pulled out
of the solution right
um
so
uh yeah in order to fix that we could
make the light be up higher but what we
probably want to do is figure out some
way to
accurately deal with that fact like that
when something has that behavior of
going in there it's also too freaking
bright
uh so we probably want to reduce the
brightness of it considerably but you
know
so if we put the light up a little
higher so that it's outside of the
um that it's
higher than the
thing
i'm not sure what i'm trying to say
if we oh that was that's the size of it
that's not going to help
uh so the debug light p
if we just make it be up a little more
so that it clears hopefully
uh
the light probes
where they are
and i don't know how high we'll have to
put it up for that to be true
there we go
um so now with with us moving a light
around the environment i'm going to turn
off
the
debug drawing there
and
oops
maybe i'll make that a little brighter
and i think you know when you see what's
happening here
uh i think you can maybe appreciate as
well why the white noise might be good
because you can sort of see how you
you see the sampling boundaries when you
have a bright light because
of the r of the fact that we're only
casting out through certain directions
you'll see that right and i can make it
a lot more pronounced by turning off the
uh
the standard lighting so if we just get
lighting out of the world and we're the
only light moving through then you can
really see where it falls down which is
why i wonder if white noise might be
now because we can do it if we should
maybe try it just see
um
[Music]
you know
but so do you see those kind of square
patterns that's just the sampling sphere
right and if we were casting at noise if
we used sampling that varied over boy
this looks so cool though holy cow this
lighting is awesome
um
that's so damn cool
we wouldn't have those weird checker
patterns we would have some noise
that varies over time
but given how this is working now that
might be okay i don't know
right
um this looks so damn cool though
right but you would even out some of
that checker pattern in exchange for
some
noise um
uh so there's a couple other things we
can do too now let's also look at some
other stuff we should probably make a
list of what we want to go through
there's so much stuff now that we've
kind of zeroed in on this and we've got
it mostly working there's so much stuff
we want to go iron out
we also turned off like our our
convection sampling so like that's
actually turned off right now
which i don't know what we want to do
about that i
like do we want to leave it off
i don't know
uh
is it buggy we it might be right um
so that's kind of a separate thing that
i'm not sure what to make about it okay
so so in here you can see the code
right here uh this code
um
so if we were to nerf this
right
uh now we would we would have it so that
um it it's actually sampling when it
runs out of
time right so when it
it will the light would potentially
propagate further you know what i'm
saying
i don't really see any difference though
i'm tempted to just add in some white
noise here i kind of just want to know
what it's going to look like
you know what i mean
i'm just i'm really psyched about how
well this came out
for fully dynamic lighting literally
completely dynamic with no
precomputation
no light maps and no gpu support
this is 100 on the cpu side this is
pretty darn good i think
um so i'm interested in in maybe adding
some noise there i don't know
so i mean this is the code
to generate the ray direction uh i don't
know how much like that will actually
cost us it might cost us a bit
because that's not particularly well
optimized so this may slow things down
too much i'm not actually sure
um
so i don't know
but
if we imagined not looking up into the
sample table anymore
so instead of this
right we just don't do that
and we say
ray d single equals this nonsense
right
um
i think that's all we would need
i i think that's all we would need
uh and the inv octim
i i assume is just over eight there so
so the octin x
yeah so it's it's just over eight there
so so basically like
this code is is the same code
uh let's just take a look
i don't know this this may be a very bad
idea
yeah i don't know where the heck this is
going to get entropy from i shouldn't
have removed it i removed it remember i
was like ah we don't need that anymore
we're just using a table
ah forget about it we'll deal with it
later as
dumb
but uh yeah what are you gonna do so
we'll have to add a more optimized
version of this in here anyway
but
i if we go to the lighting work and we
look and see how we would put entropy in
here we have the sample point entropy i
don't actually know
um if that
is
valid
uh
like i don't know if anyone's setting
that sample point entropy
so they sort of are
um
and so you know there's a thing
happening with the thing
so
maybe that's fine
uh
who knows
uh but all right so the poor poor
solution to this problem
um
i guess it's just random seed offset
this is not going to be good
to say the least
all right so maybe or maybe not that's
white noise injected in here this could
just be a complete disaster i don't know
if it'll actually work um
but
so you know that's the white noise
version
and you can see like you do get the
flickering-ness
as you go kind of further out right
um which you know i don't know how
likely we are to fix that
um
uh what i will say is we now have the
nice thing of like you can just set
lighting octahedral raised protection to
whatever the heck you want because it's
not reading out of a table anymore
so you just be like oh yeah we're doing
32 samples
now
right or whatever it's going to be too
slow to use but you know you can set it
to whatever you want
um if that makes sense oh
but not like that
uh you have to set it the same as your
sampling
inverse sampling because otherwise you
will just explode with light like you
have to have that value match the value
that you're using for
uh
i mean you get the idea
so if we want to do a ray count
here
uh
that is in the ray weight
um
and like i said i don't know this might
not be a good idea it might be that we
have to use predefined directions or
something
um but we'll see
so there's like a
slow version
and there's not very much flicker
it's pretty imperceptible
um you get some noise in the far out
places but man like that's pretty low
i'd probably be okay with that
uh and maybe you can do some denoising
on that right like over time
so it's pretty good
um at 16 it's you know it probably
significantly worse
but you can see the noise pretty bad at
16 right so i'm guessing somewhere
around 64 it becomes pretty good
in terms of noise level
yeah i mean at 64 you basically like
wouldn't really know
it's just we can't afford that many
samples right you see how slow it is
um we can also add some lag
so you know if we're only going at eight
uh or something like that
uh where you would see it
uh i wonder if
uh
where that sweet spot would be for um
the lag right so
you know we could
make it more laggy like 10 frames
and you know that's pretty good
i wish i knew more about sampling and
de-noising
like nothing right
um because i bet we could put some kind
of filtering in on this as well that
would make it so that you got more use
out of the samples we're taking like
right now we're probably not doing a
very good job
like figuring out how to weight those
samples or whatever
this looks pretty freaking cool
so yeah i think we could probably call
that done for a while like i don't know
that we really need to worry too much
about this
i mean that just looks so cool like
you'd play a game that looked like this
i don't even think you would mind but i
do think we can do better i just don't
know that we care at the immediate
moment right
um
so that seems fine i
would say that the entity gen code
that's putting in all these lights
i mean when you have more lights you
don't even notice only when you're in a
really dark area you can't even see
the flickering at this point
right
so
there's
too much light it looks like in
sometimes in these areas like
just too much because the convection now
happens so we do
like move light around a lot
um
so like
i'm still just enough light to push this
i think to push that region over the
edge
um
but yeah
we probably want an exposure curve
we don't have an exposure curve right
now we probably want that
uh so i think that's pretty good
um
i mean nice work
everyone think we
did a really nice job on this lighting
um
still has some rough edges but it's
pretty darn good and i
i'm not sure what we would want to do
exposure curve wise
uh
and you can kind of see we still have we
can still end up in these like over
brightening circles like that
uh where the light kind of propagates
out and is very bright
right
um
and i'm not sure that might still be a
bug
uh i assume that's from the fact that we
are carrying a very bright light right
now but it still could be a bug that
it's
a like
adding too much light the sampling that
does yeah i don't know exactly but there
still could be a bug in the sampling
that allows you to end up with more
light than you should so i think that is
probably also
something we want to look at
so i'm not
i don't really know
um
yeah the darker one will be what it
looks like uh whenever you're in a
region that has no lights
uh assuming that you're carrying like a
light around right
so
uh
you know like well let me finish what i
was doing here first but we can do an
example of what that would be like
um so you know like i don't know this
world generation code is such complete
garbage uh that you know
but uh
if we turned off lighting in like the
main room or something like that
um
all right
you know i mean i don't exactly know if
this will do what we want but i think it
will
so like if you imagined right
you're in an area where
you have like no light
uh then in that part of the game that's
exactly what it would look like and if
we pretended temporarily
so uh move entity is nerfed because
we're we have to remove z from that
um
i like that
don't care about that
you got to love that
how do you not love that
i i don't know
um
i
i i just don't know
uh so where is new p is refined voxel
placement so yeah if we did like
don't care about that
what i actually want to do here is
change this to just auto move the thing
so
[Music]
so it's more like
if we say that we don't care about that
then what we do is we say
uh we move it to where it's going and we
leave the function
um
so what i was gonna say is if you
imagine this was actually oh god
what have i done
okay
um
the diagram
and
has to be in there doesn't it so
uh you know
totally fair
although i guess i could have just put
the diagram and in there i don't know
why i didn't do that that's like a
smarter way to do this right
like that
um
yeah so that's
what
i put a diagram end in there didn't i oh
i forgot the return
there we go
so assuming that i bring the glove with
me like right um which is the other code
that we have to work on now sometime
soon um but if we imagined
uh that the glove was more like what the
glove actually is going to be uh in
when the game is actually
sort of nominally a game
um
you know the
the glove would have a light on it
because it's glowing magical glove or
something
and so
the glove itself
would
presumably have that um
so
something like
this
um
[Music]
i don't know
i i really just have no idea what i'm
typing in here so you'll have to forgive
me but it's gonna be like you know
um
i don't actually know
where ad piece is defined here
but i assume that like it is somewhere
predefined
yeah like that
um
okay too much light
obviously so we probably still have a
light bug there because in theory it
shouldn't be able to convect like that
and i do think that that probably has
something to do with the like
transmission rule like i i assume and
let's double check this i assume that
once you add the like that convection
rule that that's where you get that from
although i don't know
um so we'll have to take a look but yeah
if
we um
if we turn this back on does that still
happen
wow it does all right so i think we
still have a bug
for for how we're doing the sampling
such that
the light contaminant
thing works because i i don't think
that it should
um
and maybe i'm totally wrong about that
but i just don't think that should be
happening
but it's pretty clear that if you get
too much light in an area it's able to
sort of like
propagate somehow and that doesn't make
intuitive sense to me not saying it
definitely shouldn't happen
i'm just saying i don't understand why
it's happening so something seems up
you know what i mean
something's up
uh you can see that
like the light you can see we need to
fix that problem with the light going
over the area like like how is that
happening
all right someone needs to explain how
that's happening so we still have some
kind of bug there but we have no idea
what's causing it like as long as the as
long as the light is kind of
in one particular spot it's able to do
that
how is it possible nobody knows
so we still have one more bug to find i
mean we probably have more than that but
somehow it's able to feedback
and we don't really know how like we
don't know what's going on there we're
blind the the blacking out part we know
what that is it's just over it uh over
it it hovers over the light probe
right
um
so if we imagined uh
that's so weird what is happening we
have to figure that out i'm gonna be
very satisfied when we finally do but
it's like something about the fact that
the light
is able to just
even it's anywhere i stand as long as
it's stable
it feeds back
now why these other lights aren't
feeding back i don't know
right like why are the other lights not
feeding back
they're all stay in staying in one place
so i don't know why that would be
um
but something's up
right
uh anyway uh that in terms of that like
going across and blacking out things
that we know what that code is that code
the code that's causing that is just the
um
this bit here
and that's preventing you from
raycasting out from inside
you know from inside things basically
um
if we imagined just not doing this
that probably prevents the blacking out
but we need a better idea of what it
should be set to
um
so it's still like kind of an open issue
right uh
so i don't know
no
so you can see now we don't get the
blacking out right um but you still have
the problem of it doesn't pick up the
light so
it's still not
good right like it won't pick up the
light while it's over there so you get
like this progressive like dimming
behavior and that's not good right
um
so that's a little bit messed up and
also you know like we want to be able to
crank this to a higher value and not
have that light contamination so we got
to figure that out
what do you suppose it is
i think it must be a bug in how we're
sampling the way that we're producing
the light sample value is probably just
not
correct
like it's probably that we're missing a
term in there that's supposed to dampen
the contribution by some kind of thing
that's more correct that looks so cool
by the way
that you know
so what happens if we let you cast out
from inside things so suppose we just
didn't do this
i suppose one problem is now you have
light leaking through walls so that's
not good because the walls are allowed
to cast so that's probably bad
um right you can see
yeah there's no stopping it
um
so it does seem like i think that pretty
much tells us what we need to know like
our sampling
this code that samples that does the
blend produces values that are too high
somehow
like it's needs to take into account
um some
kind of
i mean i just don't like something's
wrong like because it shouldn't ever be
able to produce a value higher than what
it
the light value is but i guess it could
if the light value is that high then
that
is just slowly transmitting the light
so i guess that's harder to say
like
i suppose what i would say about that is
it's possible that's just sort of slowly
solving the problem correctly and
because we don't have an exposure curve
eventually you will get up to a higher
level of light
as the things bounce around and if you
don't have any actual occluders which is
what will happen when i did what i just
did there
maybe that's actually correct it doesn't
quite sound right
so i don't know about that
um
so yeah i'm not sure i should probably
wind down for today it's already like
five o'clock it's time to make some food
um
so yeah i guess we'll pick this up again
tomorrow i think we should add an
exposure curve
in there and we should probably set all
our lights so that they're just between
zero and one
so like one is the brightest light like
24 is the highest number
but i don't know
uh sandwich maker was suggesting
um
a simple exposure curve
yeah so kind of like a a soft knee
compressor basically right
um
send all code download stuck at 346.
that's not possible
did it break
i know i updated like 640 something just
the other day
it can't be 346 unless something very
weird is happening
or send out broke i mean there's a
reason we are going to replace sendal is
because it's so bad um so that's
possible
but i don't think it should be that far
back unless they broke something
um so yeah i guess i'm gonna stop for
today because we've done a lot of work
today and but we definitely
this
is very strange that light contamination
and
we're gonna have to figure out what's
going on there i don't understand it at
all
um
yes 646 sounds about right
so team r b like
well
i'm gonna i'm gonna end it here for
today uh we got a bunch of stuff to look
at next time
but it's looking pretty darn good i
would say
um
yeah 646 it's it's maybe a day or two
behind
uh but it's not it's not like six 346 or
whatever
uh but yeah i try to update it i might
because we should be desi 650 today i
think i'm gonna roll the counter on that
one so that uh it will be easier to
upload it was getting very hard to
upload because the package was too large
um so hopefully now it's easier uh send
out doesn't make it easy to actually
update the stupid thing but yeah the
github should always be up to date
and the send owl will be hopefully more
up to date now because it'll be easier
to upload it
than it was
but anyway
um so i think that's it
i'm going to call it there
and we will pick it back up next time
so thanks everyone for joining me
for this episode of handmade hero
i will see you all on the internet take
it easy everybody