hello everybody and welcome to handmade
hero uh show where we code a complete
game
live on stream uh you'll forgive me for
being a little silly uh right now um
someone sent me
a clip we were talking about
cryptocurrency
the pre-stream
and someone sent me a clip of john blow
crashing well he didn't crash it but he
was thinking about crashing garlic coin
and it was cracking me up i didn't even
know there was a garlic coin and neither
did john
um all right that was pretty good
no okay
um
well uh nothing we're gonna do today is
going to be as fun as crashing garlic
coin um
so
so uh
i don't know what to tell you um
we're we're just going to be i i believe
i wrote last times couple weeks ago
because
i didn't stream in a little bit well i
streamed some stuff but it wasn't
uh programming
i so i
we wanted to put in a collision detector
that was you know more reliable because
we're want to put in some combat code uh
into the game and basically what we're
doing here you can see the fist is
stopped in place right now um the reason
for that is we replaced the collision
sector uh the reason for replacing the
collision detector
was we wrote a little voxel one that did
incremental search uh just moving from
voxel to voxel as it determined that it
was okay for it to move there
and unfortunately like i just wasn't
it seemed pretty stable so like we
didn't really have uh problems with
things getting stuck
but
it it didn't roll off of corners the way
i'd wanted to so it was pretty easy to
like
walk and have it like stop at like a
corner
and so what i wanted to do is be like
smoother and kind of do roll off
and one of the things that we noticed
when we were looking at that kind of
thing where we had like that kind of
roll off effect
uh is the rolling doesn't really work
particularly well if you do incremental
voxel search because even though the
voxel search space that you probably
should consider has a valid path that
you would go to get to a place that's
closer to the place you're trying to get
to which indicates the clutch detector
should allow you to move there
it doesn't actually ever get to check
that voxel because we only check voxels
that would get you closer to where you
were when you actually move into them
and that does not allow you to move
through an intermediate voxel to get to
a closer voxel end so that doesn't come
up very often except in the case of
moving around corners so in order to get
it nice and slippery so that you get a
lot of nice slide in there
this is kind of the uh baby oil edition
of handmade hero uh you know it's kind
of like a jean-claude van damme sort of
greasing up for a 1980s action movie
sort of a thing we're going for here
where he will just slide right around
the corners
that is
that requires us to do
a more comprehensive voxel search now i
already wrote it if i remember correctly
so really what we're talking about today
is debugging and i guess finishing at
any part of the implementation
that we hadn't already uh
that we hadn't already implemented right
and so i
again don't really remember exactly
what we had left to do but hopefully
it's pretty obvious uh when we go
through it uh you can kind of see here
the way that we set up the code just
looking at it really
quickly uh you can kind of get a very
very very broad
uh idea about what's supposed to go on
here you can see that we make a voxel
grid
right and the voxel grid is based on if
you if you look here you can see
uh we take the two places that we're
trying to go so we're
you know
we have a location that the entity
starts at and we have a location that is
where the entity would end up if we did
not apply collision detection right
because we know those things trivially
if we just turn off the collision vector
then we know that you know we start out
at wherever we were on the last frame we
have a particular desired motion
direction we have an amount of time and
we have a velocity so it's trivial for
us to figure out where we would end up
so that basically gives us a line
segment right
so we know that line segment
effectively gives us
you know an approximate bounds on where
we should be looking we don't have to
look at the entire world to find out
what the best place to put this entity
is during collision section we know that
we're going somewhere around that line
segment you know we're there's not going
to be
any time where we want to pick something
too far away from that line segment so
if we merely turn that line segment into
a voxel region a localized small voxel
region that contains the line segment
then that will allow us to proceed with
the algorithm uh the algorithmic search
so that's exactly what we do we create a
maximum voxel dim which basically says
okay if you were moving at a very high
speed we're going to basically clamp
your velocity like we're never going to
let you move so fast that you you huge
swaths of the voxel and that is really
there just to ensure um sane behavior of
the game
we don't know for sure that the game
play code will be non-buggy or even that
we want to spend time making the
gameplay code non-buggy and you remember
me talking about this i talked about
this
specifically when talking about getting
stuck in things
one of the things that i said very
specifically is we don't want to require
that you never embed uh in inside
objects like have two objects intersect
because even though we could require
that the collision detector never
produced that invalid condition and we
could do that code in fact we kind of
did that code
that is insufficient because the
gameplay code you know might teleport
somebody or do something like that and
we don't want that code to have to be
bug free because gameplay code tends to
be sloppy it tends to be imaginative it
doesn't you don't really want your
gameplay code or in the case of where
you know in a proper game the
uh would be programmed by somebody else
right like i'd be doing this collision
detector but john blow would be doing
the gameplay code right
and
you don't want to have to tell john
to restrict all of the things he does to
oh you want to implement this gameplay
feature well slow down you've got to
know all this numerical analysis
relevant to the collision detector that
i now have to explain to you and you
have to get right every time or you will
break the game right
that is a horrible idea for game
development right first of all if you
don't have a programmer like john who's
an expert at actual regular programming
as well that's they're gonna have no
idea what you're talking about so that's
a problem but b even if you do happen to
have someone like john who could do the
numerical analysis stuff it's wasting
all their time so rather than trying out
imaginative features and progressing
forward at the game design at the
maximum speed that they can which is
what you need for them to uh can you
know maintain their creative momentum
right you've basically just thrown a
huge spanner wrench into the works by
making every last little thing they do
they have to think about whether or not
this can be made numerically robust and
blah blah right
so the same thing is true of movement
speed
we don't want this thing to ever have to
consider massive swaths of the of the
area because it might be too uh
computationally expensive or whatever
but we also don't want gameplay
designers to have to think about if they
accidentally wrote equations that make
things move way too quickly because
really it's free for us to just clamp
those maximum movement speeds before we
do anything inside this routine and then
it doesn't matter if they accidentally
do that right things will just move a
little slower if they do that then what
they would have done otherwise and it
was probably a bug that they did that
anyway you don't want things like flying
around the screen the player wouldn't
even be able to see them so if they
wanted to do that they probably
should have written a teleport so most
of the time if that happens it's a bug
in their computation like they were
trying to compute what the resulting
speed of something would be and they
totally screwed up and they just
produced a really arbitrary like high
number in this one case
we want that to be okay we want to just
solve that for them so that you know
they they can just ignore it so that's
part of what's going on here right we're
trying to we're trying to smooth that
out make sure all that uh is just easy
for the gameplay the designer to just
throw whatever they want in here and it
won't explode uh that's part of our job
when we write a collision detector
okay
so now
if we go through here
you can see the operation of it we build
a voxel that's the size that we expect
uh to want to search we clamp the size
of that voxel to a maximum
i don't know what that maximum is we set
it presumably somewhere voxel stack dim
is is i would assume set somewhere yeah
so it's set to 16. so there's a 16 by 16
by 16 maximum voxel size which is quite
large uh and we just aren't going to
allow because remember the game targets
like at least 30 frames a second but
usually 60 frames a second so in 60
frames a second the amount that any
entity should reasonably move is going
to be small because you know if it was
you know any larger you you wouldn't be
able to see it
move
boop
um so the max voxel dim is limited to a
16 by 16 by 16 uh and we just clamp it
right
so we just say look uh after we
uh produce this we've got a voxel size
we make a grid that's going to hold
information about this voxel uh we do
some diagramming stuff this guy's
this gets uh eliminated uh in release
builds so that doesn't really affect the
algorithm it's just for us to be able to
see it
uh we go through and we say all right
we're gonna start in whichever voxel the
uh entity was in when it first went
there
and we're gonna push that onto our voxel
stack as a starting cell
and then we're gonna do is we're just
gonna loop you know we're just gonna
keep looping and using this little voxel
stack now why is there a stack all of a
sudden because before there wasn't well
the stack is really the thing that
differentiates these two
parts of what we're doing
the voxel stack
is there to tell us
that we have or haven't
looked at a particular series of cells
it's like a flood fill algorithm we know
we start in a particular voxel cell we
know that we can move to any neighboring
voxel cell if there was no collision in
between them right so in other words if
if the corners of the voxel were
uh were not in colliding
if any corner really was non-colliding
that two cells share
we can go through them right
so what we do is we just
start with the cell we see which cells
could we move to we push them on the
stack
before we were just taking whichever one
was closest to where we were going and
that just wasn't enough of a search
because that's basically like an a-star
search without the backtracking right in
a-star search is you always try the
closest the we always try the grid
movement that would get you closer to
where you were going first
and then when if that doesn't pan out
you backtrack and try
the next closest right so an astar
search is basically just
i'm sorry to throw these terms out there
i know we haven't covered a star search
in handmade hero but it's a very simple
algorithm
basically there's you know uh
they're sort of the old school
full grid search which basically
requires visiting every node
uh in a graph to produce the
path
between two things and then a star is
just that exact same algorithm
um
[Music]
uh what's the
well you can tell i'm getting old
uh
that's really sad it's sad getting old
your memory just goes um so the the grid
algorithm
it's named after the person who's a
famous uh computer science person
and like their name just like poofed out
of my head right it's just like
uh
but the shortest path
for a series of you know in a graph
there's an algorithm for the shortest
path and you basically visit all of the
nodes in that graph
and uh you
produce the shortest path from the node
a particular node that's the node you're
starting at
and it actually produces the shortest
path to all nodes at the same time
right so it's basically just like if you
started from here here's the shortest
path to all
possible
places right
um
and
a star is literally just the same
algorithm but instead of having to visit
all the nodes
uh you sort the order in which you check
the nodes
so that you always produce the shortest
path as soon as you could
if it was on a like if if you have an
any accurate estimate
of the distance between
two nodes and you know two nodes in the
graph that aren't directly connected so
it's just a way of employing a metric to
increase the chance that you find the
path early now you can never find the
path earlier in the worst case because
the worst case is you just even for a
star right you just create a grid
uh or you create a graph in which
there's no shorter path other than the
one that you would try last because it
actually is always the furthest away
node that ends up getting to the place
you're going right it's like a it's like
a real like sort of
um
a real thwarting kind of thing and in
that kind of a graph just to give you
some examples what that kind of graph
looks like is if you imagined um you
know like a a
a real path like in the real world
where there was one really circuitous
path like in a garden all the way around
that kind of came in the back of the
place that you were trying to get to
and
the rest of it was just a wide open
field you could walk all the way through
in any direction you wanted to
up till the place you were actually
trying to get and that was completely
walled off except for that really long
path around right
and so you know the shortest path
algorithms that use heuristics they all
try like all the open field paths first
because they're like well that goes
directly there doesn't it and it never
quite does and then it's like oh that
one that makes you walk all the way
outside the garden and all the way
around and back in the other entrance it
turns out that's the shortest path
you try that one last and you're back to
the worst case of visiting basically
every node
in the graph so you know there's no free
lunch in those kind of graph uh
traversal algorithms but
something like a star finds the solution
faster so before what we were doing is
basically an a-star search without
actually um
having the back tracking so we were
doing the thing where we would just walk
straight across the field and try to get
into the place we're trying to get to
when we couldn't get in we wouldn't try
any other paths right so we'd never find
that path where you had to go a little
further away first
and then get uh go around
a proper a-star search does that and
that's sort of what we're adding here
now we probably won't bother doing the
a-star part of it the a-star part of it
uh is
well maybe we will i don't know
um
at the moment we're not sorting the
order in which we insert these things
into the graph
uh we may find that it doesn't matter
because we're remember considering a
very small number of voxels so i don't
know whether we'll actually want to
bother doing that or not but we might
because if you think about it a lot of
the movements are straightforward
movements a lot of the time the
collision detector
doesn't have to do anything at all
there's nothing in the way of the thing
being moved right um oh i just glanced
the chat dijkstra thank you god
it it's really sucks
that i can't remember names anymore
and yes uh zero i agree that dykstra's
algorithm was a very bad name
because
he's
a famous
cs uh
researcher who developed many algorithms
so
saying dijkstra's algorithm
you're really not saying anything you
have to say dijkstra's algorithm for
shortest paths or something like you
have to basically qualify it
because
if you didn't it'd be like which one of
dijkstra's algorithms right so you kind
of have to know the context when you say
dyches diagram but thank you for that
it's it's really frustrating um
what they say about memory going when
you get older is absolutely true
i would never forget something like
dijkstra's algorithm when i was 20.
uh and i forget things like that all the
time now so it's just like
brain
brain decay it's real
um
and i've heard john blows exactly the
same thing uh
maybe your memory doesn't go that bad if
you didn't have a good memory to begin
with i don't know
um but i think people like myself and
john have had pretty good memories when
we were younger we remember lots of
stuff and lots of papers and lots of
things like that and you could really
see when you go uh when you had a really
good memory and you never forgot stuff
like that where you could say like oh
this was a cs paper it was by these
people they're from this university
right like a bunch of facts they were
kind of all in there and then nowadays
they're just like
i'll read a paper and i'll forget even
what the paper was even about
uh you know um never mind like who wrote
it and where they were from
uh so it's just like you can tell your
brain is just you know your brain is
full as you get older the neurons
uh they're they're like old and crusty
and they don't want to move around
anymore
all right so uh
let's go ahead and and take a look at
what we actually wrote in here because
this all seems fine like that seems like
a reasonable set of things
uh for this system to be doing
so i don't think we need to really look
at that code yet i mean we're probably
gonna want to debug it and stuff but you
know that looks like it's doing the
right thing we push the initial cell
onto the voxel stack and you can see
then we're just going to loop until we
run out of things to look at so we're
basically just going to like search
through this voxel
uh and we're going to you know we're not
going to stop until we don't have
anything left to try
uh and we may need to so if you look at
the way this is written currently uh we
definitely would want to fix uh sort of
or add optimizations to it because this
will uh
visit all the voxels in the entire grid
in the case of no collision which we
probably don't want to do so at the very
least we would want to early out when we
find a voxel that contains like the
point we're moving to
because you know you can't get any
closer than that
um but we probably do also want to
eventually put a sort in here to
basically make this a proper a-star
because there's not a lot of reason not
to so we'll take a look at that a little
bit later
uh anyway we come in here and we say
let's get the current cell out so what
that does it says like whatever
is on the top of the stack that's where
we're searching from right now um and
then we go ahead and say all right what
is the actual extent of that cell so
that produces for us a little box right
that we're going to test we iterate over
the corners and you can see you know i
probably put a little to do in here
we probably want to just store um a bit
array that says which corners we've
tested uh because if you think about it
a lot of times any you know
every cell in the voxel array uh shares
corners with other cells in the vaxels
array so when we iterate over those
cells and test them we are really going
to be retesting
uh every cell will probably get tested
in a complete voxel visit uh all of the
exterior cells will be tested uh
i guess it depends which exterior you're
on so face exterior cells uh will be
tested four times
uh
the corner cells when we tested once
perimeter edge cells uh will be tested
twice
and interior cells will be in test will
be tested
um
eight times right
and so if you think about that's just a
tremendous amount of waste because
collides at p is not a cheap function
right it's going to be a fairly
expensive function it's not that
expensive once we have spatial partition
in here but it's still pretty expensive
so we probably want to store just a bit
at least that just says did we already
compute this cell or not so instead of
storing
like uh just one single thing which is
occupied or unoccupied
we would also store a third thing which
is you know third state which is
untested
and then we'll just look up
you know what's the state of this grid
cell if it's occupied or unoccupied we
move forward if it's um untested we test
it and re write the value
of whether it's occupied or unoccupied
right
so that'd be a pretty easy optimization
here too and we should probably do it uh
we go through and we just check to see
what collides uh and what doesn't
collide and we produce an in embedding
count while we're at it the reason for
the embedding count is to see whether
we're uh stuck at this time and i feel
like really that should probably only um
i i don't know um
what we want to do about that
sorry a bit stuffy
what is the time
photo lithography routine
if you tell me your name and dated my
brother
how did you guys get from photo
lithography machines
i mean from from dijkstra to
photolithography machines just because
they're dutch
dutch national pride
gotcha
well yeah i mean the dutch should be
pretty proud because right now literally
all the chips in the world all of them
that i know about
uh that are cutting edge are made on
dutch machines
right
like i don't think there's any
i don't think there are any
like
sub 10 10 nanometer chips being produced
on non-dutch machines
right
like like the dutch
are the only reason
uh i guess it's not the dutch because i
mean
they're a multinational corporation but
they're owned you know and were founded
in
or founded by dutch people
um
so yeah like there's
basically there's no
nobody else got
uh got the like
the process after 14 or 12 nanometer
um no one else really was able to do it
intel tried to do the 10 nanometer kind
of failed i mean there are some limited
10 nanometer chips they're producing but
they're not really very good
um and then
basically the seven five and three
nanometer nodes are all dutch everywhere
else
um
right
i mean am i wrong i i don't think anyone
else has managed to ship an actual
production node there are other people
with extreme uv
uh
like technology but it's not it has not
successfully done a commercial run if
i'm if i'm not mistaken so i'm pretty
sure the dutch are the only people
or a dutch company is the only company
who has successfully been able to ship
lithography machines at that scale no
one else
that are actually commercially viable uh
you know ibm or whatever you know that
they've got
crazy research machines that can do even
deeper than that and all that stuff
right so it's not like it's like some
kind of like world record of how uh you
know dense you can etch a transistor but
no one cares about that i mean that's
that's like you know just just research
stuff uh it does it only comes into play
later if you can actually commercialize
it because you know
nobody cares if you can put together a
very very tiny transistor
if you can't do it at scale and quickly
right it has to be efficient otherwise
it doesn't help you because they need to
produce millions
or tens of millions of chips not like
one chip you know a day or something
so
anyway
brief transgression yes if you are dutch
uh you are saving
mankind's
uh
semiconductor industry as we speak
all right
so the embed count part i i do think
we're probably gonna have to look out a
little bit more carefully
so
i suspect we'll have to track that
because i expect we'll want to know
things like
did we enter this cell
from a cell
that
where you were stuck so is this a stuck
search or an unstuck search i suspect
we'll want to take different actions
depending
but i'm not going to deal with that just
yet
because i want to think through the
regular activity first before we start
thinking through the activity uh in the
case of actually being
embedded and trying to get out of
embedded
uh so what we want to do here is we want
to now see like what is the actual
you can see like what is the actual
activity
um
it looks like we wrote this to try and
make it easier for us to
quickly search through
uh all of the places we were going to
search with our voxel search or
something
um
seems like all this is
right
uh we wanted to check
i guess at least six
we want to check at least six neighbors
um instead of eight neighbors or
something
i don't know
uh and so we just did a
a simple loop that presumably get
unrolled where it's just two
checks one this set of three and then
another that's a set of three right
you can see it happening here
um
and that's it uh this just tries to find
whichever one was closest
all right
so
i guess i'm not immediately sure
i guess i'm not immediately sure why
this did not move
at all
um
[Music]
it could be
uh
it could be something to do with this
push not
working right like we're pushing on
the wrong cells or something
it could have to do
with the way the push works like this is
in bounds is wrong
um
uh it could have to do
with
yeah i don't know there there aren't
that many ways that this would be
failing so i'll be interested to see
because it doesn't really look that
broken
um and so it's a little weird i also
don't know
uh one thing that's a bit odd
uh
is
that like when we run this thing
i'm not sure why i'm not seeing so like
when i hop on here right you can see
that it's doing the collision detector
because when i move my head collision
volume which at some point we should
really change the size of because it
should probably be a square but you know
whatever it doesn't really matter you
can see it runs a bunch of collision
checks when i do that so it's definitely
operational
um
[Music]
so that's not a concern but what you can
see here is like for example right here
uh
it it never really checks any more than
one grid and interestingly you can see
it it actually moves the glove
uh
somewhat correctly inside that um
right you can you can see it move inside
that cube i don't mean well maybe you
can't this is twitch
uh do you see there there's like a
little like uh placement you can see it
uh so it searches along the edge of the
voxel properly
but it doesn't seem to ever actually
create a larger voxel
right
so it does not seem to search
uh further than that
and so one thing i would like to do
uh in that case is
just start looking at this code here
because it seems like the voxel area
doesn't really get
labeled
uh
properly or something
one thing i can do here that i think
maybe i i possibly should do
is rather than only showing this uh
showing the voxel
rather than only showing like where i
search i should probably also show the
entire bounds of the voxel right
um so like erect min max
that has the voxel min corner in it and
the voxel max corner in it um
might be nice
uh
just to start with
and
we may want to do
i guess we may want to do a min dim
because we clamp
excuse me
we clamp it as well so what we might
want to do is say okay let's reproduce
the span from
uh the voxel dim here uh
yeah like
so basically like when we do the mo when
we do the uh cell dim voxel dim here
we're gonna make a
excuse me
um we're going to make a voxel grid when
we do make voxel grid if we look at what
that gives us there's a total bounds
right in there so i guess i i can just
not even bother
creating
a rectangle for this i can just draw the
one that's in the grid and that's better
because then i that's the one it's
actually using anyway so then there's no
risk that i screw it up right
um so supposing we draw like just a gray
um
we'll just draw a gray box there
so that i can see it right
um and now we can look and see like
what's the bounds
so you can see here that there's uh you
know at least
from the boundary that we're looking at
um i i don't necessarily know
i i couldn't say for sure
whether those bounds are correct based
on the movement yet because i guess the
other thing i didn't draw was the start
and end so i think i'll draw the start
and end as well
but what i can say is already it looks
buggy
uh the search anyway because if this is
the bounds we should have been able to
search through at least these other
um you know you can see that this whole
slice of the voxel here would have been
closer to the target uh that we're
moving towards so it already seems like
the search is a little bit broken um
but before we get into that i would like
to also draw a like diagram um
line basically
so i'd like to draw a line that we see
the from p and the frumpy and the 2p
uh i'd like to see the frumpy and the 2p
uh because that tells me whether or not
we got the right bounds based on the
input that we were given which is
important
um so i want to look here and take a
look at what the that uh stretch is so
if that's the frumpy
2p
right
um at least it seems like it
uh that seems really broken
right um
we know that our voxel dimension was
supposed to be like 16 16 16.
and here we are we're stretching this
thing out that far
uh and yet we only encompassed a two by
two by two voxel right so we obviously
screwed this up somehow
uh and we should fix it right
i might also just
make that gray as well
so let's debug this because obviously we
don't know what we're doing here
um
we take the voxel starting corner
and in fact i guess if i look here uh
don't really know
so that all looks fine because this is
just computing a starting cell
uh
which actually what do we do with this
starting cell
so this is ignored
entirely
so we we got some work to do here so the
cell dim we need
this
i
looks like we kind of didn't really do
what we were supposed to do here
we don't use it you can see initial cell
is actually coming from here now
um so really this should be moved up
here
and this uh starting cell should be
labeled with that so this is just old
code from before
and this uh should be removed because
that's a misleading diagram now i think
right um
to a certain extent
um
i think i think that's a misleading
diagram
so when we produce the voxel starting
corner
um
here and we use that to create
the
yeah like this is so weird
this is totally wrong like i don't know
what this is doing
because
we want the from p to be the thing that
we're going towards here
so
really corner b is not the cell
dimension times the direction
it's just from p isn't it
um i mean 2 2 p
furthermore
i guess i don't really even know why
we're doing it this way because
when we call
uh make voxel grid
we do the setman corner the setman
corner is just the floor
um
yeah uh
i i mean to me look
to me i feel like this is just this is
just broken
right uh
i i think we just want this
like these are the two
uh places we're going to
right
and
we just want to take the entire area of
these so we we want you know them to be
expanded because we floor this we've
already expanded into the
uh the downward direction
the voxel uh here we want to expand one
plus yeah you can see we're already
doing it um
so i think we want
this
i think
um
and you know i'm not sure but i i
believe
that's what we're actually looking for
here
so
yeah we want to do the initial cell it
well we don't even need to do the
initial cell because that's going to get
drawn in here anyway so i don't actually
even know that we need that right so i
think this is more what we're looking
for this is
and i i i we must have just kind of like
hacked that in there and not really
thought about didn't look correct right
um so now that looks much
more sane
right uh now work
you know if that's the motion we were ax
axed that's good asked
to produce
now we're like properly bounding that
region
right
because you can see now that we're
trying to hit the target
by enclosing the motion inside the voxel
area which is what we wanted
so now we can start the search uh
figuring out why our search isn't
working
and so let's take a look at that so we
know that the only criteria for entering
the search right is that the stack not
be empty so here's the stack
not empty part
and that just means the depth has to be
greater than zero now we know the depth
should not be zero uh when we enter the
routine
because
we have just done a push voxel stack
which should have
incremented the depth and you can see it
incrementing the depth here
we
we shouldn't be able to hit either of
these unless this is saying that we're
not in the bounds like that could happen
if we screwed up
the alignment of the voxel or something
like that
so if we
we could look at that
but the first thing i also want to know
is we look in here
uh we're never drawing the actual
uh
voxel we're on
and so i'd like to now put that code in
here to show the voxels as we test them
so when we come in here and we say uh
you know
let's draw this thing
you know maybe we'll do it like this
where i'm just going to set the color
based on
you know whether it was closer or not
so if it wasn't closer or if it was
uh we'll just like set these uh colors
and then we'll draw whatever the voxel
was that we actually tested because you
can see here we get
the cell that we're on here so it's free
for us to just pass that to the
diagrammer and say hey draw the cell
so this way i can see like what cells do
we test um and which cells you know you
know which are basically participating
in the solve
uh so if we look here you can see that
we test exactly one cell it does find a
placement um in it that says that it's
closer and then we test no further cells
so that gives us a pretty clear
indication of who
is not working
so inside this flip
routine
where we try zero uh and a one
we are never pushing this voxel stack
uh for whatever reason right
so our side computation here where we
figure out what direction we're going
right
[Music]
for whatever reason this code never
produces
any actual pushes
it would seem
right
uh because if it ever pushed anything on
we would loop around and at least draw
one more of these
so why doesn't that work what's wrong
with this code
um
and i can't say i see any
obvious wrong thing in here
um
i can't say i see anything obviously
wrong with this
so
i think i'm gonna have to step through
it and see it's probably something
stupid
uh but i'm just not seeing
what the stupid thing is
uh it could be that this is like never
firing
or always firing like it's always saying
it's occupied or something
um but that doesn't seem likely so i
don't know i i don't know
what's going on there so i'm just gonna
go ahead and uh turn it to a debug build
um and then i'm gonna set a breakpoint
inside move entity
uh so that we'll get a stop
whenever
[Music]
we try to move anything
so
um
excuse me
i'm now going to go ahead and look
just at that part
so i just want to watch it go through
this routine
um so that i can have some idea of
what's going on so here's occupied
um
oh
yeah duh
you guys probably all saw that right
before me
uh it's the wrong way around
it's it's supposed to be if it's not
occupied
right
um
we gotta update our four coder
my understanding was that at some point
that indent bug got fixed i also wanted
to try that new there's that new 10x
ide coder thing
um
that's being worked on which i love the
idea of like i love the fact that it's
just like a performance focused ide so
i'd like to test that out at some point
too
um maybe we'll do a subscribers only
stream at some point where we play
around with that
um
all right so now we should be pushing
these okay so i knew it was something
stupid and it was i just didn't
see it uh
off off the bat like i should have
um so now we're doing our search
and
uh i think
i think now that would probably be the
only bug we were seeing there so we now
have to look at other bugs uh find other
bugs
so you can see we can uh do like some
punching we're embedding into that wall
too far
uh and i'm not sure why so we probably
want to look at some of these things and
see it looks like there's some bugs in
that um that we want to get rid of
and again i think
so
my suspicion not knowing is that the
reason we can embed now
uh is because we are
allowing that
remember we just allow you to use
embedded cubes
uh and we don't want that anymore we
only want to allow embedded uh voxels if
you got there from an embedded voxel
we don't want you to start in unembedded
voxels and allow you to place yourself
in embedded voxels
um so we you know it's an issue uh so
what we wanna do now is work on these
bugs uh we wanna work on like that and
then we want to work on getting this
working because this is the whole reason
we added a more
um thorough search space here so like we
we may need to do some stuff for like
our corner roll
uh to
for example widen the voxel so that it
searches uh outside as well
uh like like a larger region for example
we might be able to fix the corner roll
off already by just adding inflating the
voxel size right
a little bit
from where it is so for example uh in in
this kind of thing here
we could do something where we say
uh the you know the optimal dim is like
two more than it was
and the min corner
um is like
you know
uh
the mid corner is like one seldom back
from where it should be
in fact i guess we don't really have to
to do that
right we could probably just subtract
the cell dim there
so that we're always searching like an
additional cell wide
uh
and and you know that might fix yeah it
does
um so i think that fixes the corner roll
off and so now i think the main thing we
have to change is just the embedding
problem and then also we have to fix
like the performance right because right
now it's absurdly expensive we're
checking all the entities in the world
for every corner of this glove
for every voxel square it's just it's
you know it's a testament to modern
computing that this runs as fast as it
does it's nuts that it's that fast uh
but hey
that's modern computing
uh so the embedding stuff is not gonna
fly uh so what we probably need to do
here is just say look it we start out
um
and we'll find out you know whether or
not we're embedded on the initial cell
um
so
we need something like
ah gosh i don't know
i'm not sure exactly how to freeze this
one
um
but it's probably like
you know i i probably want to do this
slightly differently
so this call here probably wants to be
something
uh that we do
as a function call
and we probably want to be able to do it
yeah in multiple places so
i think i'm going to do a couple things
here
the first i'm going to do is reduce the
i'm going to put in the thing
where we know whether we've tested a
particular voxel corner or not
um and then the other thing i'm going to
do
[Music]
is
i'm then going to like track the
embedding
so that the embedding is like known
like i think what i want to do is say
okay
once we have a an embedding type we
never allow you to move to a cell
uh
that
we we never allow you to move to a cell
is embedded if you have been embedded
right i'm sorry if you haven't been
embedded uh because this is the prop
this is the code that's the problem here
right so in other words if you turned
this off
my my argument is you will no longer
embed into walls that's my argument
you know we'll see maybe i'm i'm totally
wrong
about that
i guess i am totally wrong about that
hmm
all right so i guess i've got more
investigation to do here because this is
the thing that allows you to to uh that
i thought was the only reason you would
be allowed to embed so we have some
other problem here where we're allowing
embedding into things that probably we
shouldn't be allowing you to bet into
and i don't actually know where that's
coming from
it could be that this is getting checked
improperly somehow
that's certainly a possibility
meaning we're checking something we're
allowing you to move in a way that we
didn't actually check
that would be one
possibility so an example would be if we
checked a certain set of corners but
then allowed you to move in a direction
that did not inc that was uh using a
different set of corners right
so that would cause the problem it
doesn't really look like that
though
so
uh you know i'm not sure
why we would end up there for the
embedding part right you can see that
you know this would all be set you would
get this in bed count set if it was
going to uh here i so i don't
without clearing these i don't see how
you get into a voxel
that's closed
how does that happen
i do not know the answer
oh
well do i no i guess i don't
so there is one thing that happens here
which is that
if you ever did check
a square that was completely
embedded it will allow you to move
inside that square and maybe that's a
bug
but you shouldn't have ever considered
the square in the first place
so that part
seems a bit odd
um
but like for example
i can remove that from consideration by
adding this if statement so if for some
reason that were y
it was allowing that embedding to occur
uh
then now it won't i don't think that
should have been it though
so
i'm not expecting this to fix the
problem
but i feel like i should test it yeah so
you can clearly go straight on through
right
so what's going on there like how is it
able to walk through there i need to
like set up a good diagram here so i can
see what's going on because i'm not sure
the other weird thing is it does stop
the glove
so it it just weirdly like stops the
glove
inside
right
um i don't know if that means i've got
some kind of a like displacement error
here
um
but that's pretty strange right like i
don't know
i literally have no idea why that would
be the case because
we didn't change this collision function
possible that we're just checking the
wrong
places
seems odd though
um
so yeah i really
don't quite know
i i don't understand
oh yes i do wow yeah this code is
totally broken
so yeah this is busted here right
because
it's it's not vox
it's not voxel in corner right
um
it's cell dot min
right um so that that's also i don't
know how that ever worked
i
yeah that that doesn't really make any
sense
um
uh okay well yeah i mean that was an
easy bug to fix so
hey surprise surprise now we don't embed
anymore
um all right so we still have a ton of
work to do though i mean just because we
fixed that um
now there's at least no mystery there i
wonder if we can do roll off here but
yeah
yeah we can
um although that looks like someone got
stuck there
what happened there
so that doesn't make a lot of sense i'm
not sure why that's stuck
so we still have some additional
problems there like that doesn't look
that doesn't look like a problem at all
like it should seems like it should be
able to search
just fine
right
um
so that looks like it that looks like
there was a problem where it did put it
inside something maybe i don't know so
it's like we still have a couple
problems there i'm not not comfortable
with that because that should not have
happened even at this stage so we still
got some nastiness going on here i would
wager
um
okay
so
uh this
probably can come back in now so don't
think you should ever get to one where
you're embedded
uh unless you started out there
and uh
i think we should probably fix some
performance things now really quickly we
probably don't have to do the full
spatial partition part
um but yeah like we should probably
uh
we should probably at least try
to only test those voxels once so that
it's not so sluggish because like we're
testing so many corners at that point uh
that it could become pretty expensive
right
we could also decide to reduce the total
number from like maybe like 16 by 16 is
is way too much right you can see how
large of a region that is uh and maybe
that's just a bad idea but there's so
many things we can do performance wise
here that i'm not sure we need to really
worry about that because once we uh put
in yeah like look at that so you can see
that that get got stuck there i don't
know what's going on there i like that
there's a weird
sticking thing that happens in this
doorway that doesn't make a lot of sense
to me so we gotta take a look at what's
happening there um because that because
i don't know right
um
but otherwise the other parts of it seem
pretty good
so i think it's all fine uh
uh other than that one weirdness there
the rest looks fine so i guess we just
continued down this road and let's start
to try and clean up
uh
the rest of the stuff we've got here
that's kind of janky
um so the first thing that we could do
like i said is we could push this stuff
um
in a better order
the problem with that
the only problem with that is
i'd have to make sure i have to think
about it but i think because it's a push
stack i think that's okay we should be
able to just as long as we push things
in the order we want to try them
i think it should just work
so so i think
if we
if we change this here um
if we just change this to like
well no
i'm trying to think
so if we if we do what we have written
now might just try them in the right
order to begin with
so
uh the only thing we would need to do
here is we would need to early out if we
actually found the location we were
going right
so if the best distance squared
like drops to zero then we would just
exit right so like if best distance
squared
is uh zero
um
[Music]
or even like
yeah i mean i don't know exactly what we
want to do it maybe even something
higher than zero is okay but anything
close enough like that
um we could probably just stop at that
point right
um so if you can find the location that
you're going to you don't have to
continue to check places right
um
it also seems like we're kind of allowed
to get embedded in the hero a little bit
there so it's like again there's some
really weird stuff going on so i think
we've still got more bugs
that we need to work on but
you know we'll see
like so in that you can see an example
of kind of what's a little weird here
and this is why i'm saying i think
there's some
jankiness so like
if you look at what's happening there
right
um and in fact i think we have you know
we have better ways of looking at this
uh
i want to say we can do that
yeah
um so if you take a look at what's
happening here you can see why like i'm
pretty sure something's broken
and the reason for that is this is a
straight linear move
it doesn't really need to look at
any of these other cells
right it can just look at the ones as it
goes and then it gets to a place where
it's
basically as close as it can so
you know once you're outside it so here
now i could understand why it's not
because if you're trying to place it
outside
uh then it would get here and go oh well
i haven't reached zero just you know
difference in destination
um you know so i'll keep going or
something like that
uh but
you know even in that i could change the
the criteria to fix that but
if we look at the rest of these it's
like why are we testing all of these we
shouldn't ever have had to if we're
actually going in that stepping order
um
and so if you look at this it's like
well the problem here is that we don't
actually go towards sort of the most
like we push these three in really any
order
uh so we may always push like the
leftward moving one which we would
because it's side x is first
if it's a y move we push the x one first
that's going to go
in a direction we didn't actually need
it to go
and so the problem is we're then going
to search off of that search for the
whole time so we need a better way
of pushing these on there that pushes
the one that's going to be like closest
first
um
instead of the other way round you know
what i'm saying um so we probably want
to fix that as well and we'll take a
look at how to do that in a second
in the meantime what i'd like to do is
when we do this check i feel like this
could probably be done better as well
instead of looking at the best distance
squared perhaps the thing to do would be
to look at like
the distance from the actual cell
like
you know there's going to be an ending
cell
so get index for p
um in the voxel grid
it looks like this doesn't actually
clamp though
so we'd we probably want to clamp that
yeah i'm not sure i feel like that
anyway
um when we look at like the places that
we're going to end up so you know we did
the initial p here right
um and
we would have like a target cell eye
and like we would want to clamp this so
like we want to clamp this to
the voxel
you know what i mean
um and i don't know
like i don't actually see
a function for that
which we would want
so
yeah i mean
so i think i would want one in here
which is like
clamped to
boxeldem or something
where you pass in an index
and
it just clamps the index
i would like one of these
that
was s32 yeah so you can see here right
we should just be able to do
like
something like this
cell count
so here i can just clamp this thing
and know that it's inside
and i feel like we want that right so we
want to do a clamp to voxel dim
[Music]
when we're doing the simulation so we
can just do like clamp to voxel dim
right
on both of these
so
we don't really need to clamp the from p
because we know it was included but the
2p might be outside and we want to we
want to clamp that
right
so
uh
we do
and then we can check for equivalence
so basically like when we're in here
we should be able to say
all right
if
r equal
the target cell i and the best cell i
um we'll just say that that's good
enough for terminating the search
and maybe it is maybe it isn't maybe we
shouldn't really do that
um we'll have to look
uh and see
um but you know hopefully it is
uh and you can see like already even
just that it does produce
some reduced ones in ones where they
happen to push in the right order you
can see there are some there that only
do that don't do the whole thick uh
testing right
so so that's a start
it's not an end
um
so a couple of the things that problems
we have here i i don't know
i need to make sure that this is always
so flumpy now yeah
i need to make sure this is always
producing the same voxel regions
properly
which i think it should do
um
so i think that's a more correct way to
phrase that
so we we take and we produce the you
know the minimum sort of including area
there
uh but it's inflated by one
right
yeah
um so i mean like yeah like how does
that happen i have no idea right so
we've got some pretty serious bugs in
here
um
that we're gonna have to roll through
because i have no idea
so we then want to
[Music]
yeah so we've got the initial cell i
and the target cell i those are both
those are both fine
uh and we start in that initial cell
and that's also our best cell because
you know that's we assume that you don't
move if we don't find anything better
um
so yeah so now i don't really know
uh i don't know how we're producing
uh
how we're producing like those
embeddings
i really wish i could tell and again you
know it's a it's a problem of debugging
code where like we just don't have a lot
of time on handmade hero to produce
things that you know
would tell us much about what was going
on here right but you can see it allowed
it to put it all the way over there i've
no idea how that's possible it doesn't
even
it means we've got like just a severe
typo or something because the actual
activity of the algorithm should never
be able to produce anything like that
um
it should be basically impossible
so we know we've got a fairly severe
problem going on in here
we just don't know what it is
and
um
you know the thing that would really
help again is if there was some way i
could reproduce this and i suppose there
is in a sense
um
but again we just don't have like on the
witness i made really good tools for
this that was the only reason i was able
to get that system really nice and
good
um because what you need is you need the
ability to record and then single step
through
uh and we just don't have that um
you need to be able to see like what
just happened there
right so you can step through and see
each individual one and it's always
something stupid it's usually not hard
to fix
but without being able to step through
it's almost impossible to tell what the
heck is going on
uh in each individual thing now we do
have the ability to to single step
without recording but that's not really
going to help us here right
um
i mean maybe it will
um i'm not really sure
but i can try it
so if i turn on single stepping here
and i push into you can see it doesn't
really
produce much there
um
that's zoom
what the heck
i thought zoom was does rotate what's
going on here
how did that end up being rotate
so confused about the camera controls
right now i thought alt
was rotate
what did i do
so i've managed to completely forget
what our keys even are
oh weird okay
i see yeah told you you get old you
forget things um
anyway
uh so looking at this right uh from the
side here
and if i switch to
single step
like you can see there like like what
even happened
right
um
it's it's totally like incorrect
in many ways right so you can see that
like it picked this square
as the starting square as far as i can
tell
but the rule is that the voxel is
supposed to be one bigger than
right it's supposed to be one more on
the side of the starting square and
totally isn't
um
so this is just like completely wrong
and i have no idea why
um
i guess one reason why is this probably
shouldn't be a floor
it should probably be around
of course i don't know if we have that
so we actually
have it we just only have it if we round
to integer for no reason
so you know
we could
just have it
which we should
so there you go
now i don't really remember
to be honest i don't remember
for round ss
i don't remember what the actual
uh thing you pass is because it's like a
weird like mm round thing
uh that
you know the intel
uh
naming scheme for these things are is so
bad that it's like impossible to
remember
um and i don't even know if it's
documented in here
we may have to look it up somewhere else
no it is there we go
um so we want basically like this
rounding mode which is rounding to
nearest
um
i believe we just want that
for the way that we're producing the
cell
boundaries
right
um
so i guess there is there no round ss
it's right there
all right um so that's fine uh and i
guess we gotta pass the like
uh set zero
to this thing
uh as well
so i think that's all good
that would be our rounding function
um
yeah
that all seems good
uh so all we need then is we just need
to like actually export this value uh so
we would need a
yeah um
an mm convert
ss f32 to extract it out of the register
even though it doesn't come out of the
register because it's floating point
just stupid um it's fine
floats in c are now stored in the ssc
registers anyway so i don't know why
you know it's just a dumb
c is now more cumbersome than assembly
language like congratulations guys
it's way easier to program ssc in
assembly language than it is in c that's
how bad the c support is
so stupid
um
all right so you know in here we're
doing
uh
this this round function in both cases i
think that's what we want it's just to
round to whatever they are
uh i don't know what this is uh i cannot
convert from v3 to okay so there's just
uh like a floor
uh that distributes
two v threes
um
not that one
that one
uh so we probably just want one that we
can distribute
to v3s as well
all right
um
[Music]
so i think that should always produce
aligned voxels and i
i want to now see why we're not always
getting a larger voxel than where the
thing uh thinks it should be
but we're definitely not and it's really
strange that we're not so something's up
there
and i don't know what that something is
but i guess we'll see
okay
uh so you can see there at least now
we're starting off
in uh well even that's wrong
like those are not aligned
so what what is going on i think this is
just like
yeah
too many sparse days of working on code
like this doesn't really work like this
is something you do in eight hours you
don't do it in like you know
two hour chunks spread across seven
months or something
um anyway uh so if we take a look at
what this size is here and we say like
okay we're going to take the front p and
the 2p we're going to round them and
multiply them by that size the starting
and ending corners should then be like
they should be aligned to the voxel
though
right
um because you did the divide and then
you got an even number and then you
multiply the number out by the
displacement size
so
that should give you
i mean shouldn't that always produce an
aligned value i'm not sure
i get it
um but we'll see so we set a corner a
here this
wouldn't really be
[Music]
um
so i guess
yeah i mean i guess technically so the
way they think about this is
you need them to have been biased first
in order for a round to work that's the
only problem there
so maybe i'm kind of wrong about that
like you want them to be
yeah
you want them to
uh be expanded after that so i suppose
it is right
to do a floor like we were doing
um
then first figure out what order they go
in
right
um so whichever one is the minimum
you you put here
uh and you subtract one i suppose this
was our problem
is that this is supposed to be twice the
cell dim
right because
you floored so the minimum corner is in
the correct place so if you subtract one
cell dimension from it you now have
expanded the minimum size by one cell
which is what we were trying to do
the maximum size on the other hand
um you didn't
right because you floored it so if you
only add one you're just encompassing it
so if it's on the mac side you then need
to do
uh two times to get past that in order
to have the correct dimension
um so i guess that's okay
so that's really what i should have done
there
we didn't really need the round function
that was a bad way to think about it
but let me take a look and see now what
we've got because i still don't really
know
if we've got the right thing and this
code is just just terrible now i don't
know what i did but i really screwed it
up so it's in a horrible state
and we're going to have to clean it up
one by one but the first things first is
make sure the voxel size is correct
so i want to do at least that
at first right
and and i guess the thing is it's just
too slow even now to even really test
right so let's try something a little
bit uh simpler first i'm gonna reduce
this voxel uh
maximum to like be smaller
uh and i'm also gonna make sure that we
like when we draw the 2p and the from p
and all that stuff um
well it'll actually be okay because we
know that the the 2p can be outside of
it and that'll be clear
um
but let's just see here uh what happens
so uh if we now look at this voxel size
hopefully
i'm hoping we will see
that it is
aligned properly which is the only thing
i was trying to do here
so it should be such that now
you get the correct sizing i don't know
why we're seeing that extra because like
i said that two
the two that's in there should not
actually be
uh
a problem there i don't know what we're
seeing there
probably just the uh the fact that it
resets the
step every time
um
but yeah so like if you look
at the voxels
just trying to see if i can get um
any kind of an indication that we're
properly sizing them now
it at least looks a little bit better
right
but i'm not sure
i'm not seeing those cases where we're
like
um
you know incorrectly uh seeing one on
the edge right
but
so i mean what is happening there
i just
oh right
okay wow
so the other problem we have
is that we aren't
wow yeah this is this is actually harder
than this is this is surprisingly
difficult okay
so the other problem we have is that if
we clamp the size of the voxel we have
to make sure it still includes
the starting point
right
um
so i feel like we just need to do this
in a fundamentally different way like i
need to first clamp the distance vector
and then just do this directly like this
doesn't work
right
like like that's just not going to cut
it we can't clamp it there and if we
because if we do we risk moving the
voxel so that it doesn't even contain
the starting point
so i think what we have to actually do
instead is first clamp this
so that the 2p gets truncated earlier
right
um so basically we would say something
like
the starting corners computation can
remain the same but the ending corners
computation
has to be a thing that first does
a max on so we first have to convert
the delta p
right
itself using the same algorithm so the
delta p
would basically be you take you take the
delta
uh and you figure out
what its
displacement is
so
however big that is we convert it to a
motion displacement size movement right
um
we then clamp that
uh in fact i guess this is
more like this so we convert the delta p
itself to a voxel-based movement
we would then clamp
the
the this the size of this
right
um so we clamp it to within min or max
of that
that value i don't know
if we have a clamp function for v3 s's
because i don't know that we ever wrote
one of those
but either way
it doesn't really matter um
we can just say look the delta p clamp s
equals a clamp
uh between the max voxel dim
in either direction
so this clamps the motion so that the
motion can't be more than
whatever
you know the search space
can't be more than the maximum voxel in
either direction and then we just take
whatever that delta p clamp was
and we say like the ending corner
is actually now going to be computed by
from p plus the delta p clamp
right
um
i'm going to call this delta p i
uh and then that way i can compute delta
p clamp
oops
by taking this and multiplying it by the
motion displacement size
okay
um i suppose we don't even need to do
that though
now to think about it um
because really you're already gonna
you're just dividing by that
here
um so if instead we just took
uh
sorry
if instead we just took and added it
afterwards right
we don't have to bother multiplying it
um i suppose
so in other words we would and and
really
um
[Music]
i i guess we could do it slightly
differently and just say well you know
the motion displacement size uh if we
did multiply it out there then we
wouldn't even do any of this we'd just
say it's the voxel starting corner plus
the delta plea clamp
right
and then
yeah we just do
the computation we were doing before
and
this is just the voxel oops
this is just the voxel dim now
so maybe that's a little bit cleaner
right
um
and now we can maybe clean up the string
because that yeah that code was really
uh screwing us up there quite a bit
um so let me see while it's embedded
because right now the the glove starts
off embedded so it can't move if we
don't until we re-enable that embedding
code until the hero moves and we can
actually use that to our advantage here
so that i can look and see
you know do i feel like this is doing
roughly the correct thing
um
[Music]
and it does look pretty good now
that looks a lot better than it was
um probably still not great
but it's better right
um so that seems good
uh the embedding prop thing like not
having embedding support is a huge
problem and the speed is now terrible
which is exactly what you'd expect so
that's fine
um
but
uh
we at least now have the correct bounds
i also am noticing i'm not getting stuck
into things like we were before so i
wonder if actually the picking the voxel
bounds incorrectly
might have been the reason why we were
getting some of those embeddings that we
should not have had right um
so that's great uh no complaints there
and also now um
i don't actually know
uh
i want to say we could now put in a
thing that's like
this
or something
um
where we have like
what we did with the corner
something like that
uh and so what we could do here is now
try to pull out the code where we're
doing our uh
yeah uh so now we can do is try to pull
out the code where we're doing that
check uh so one thing we could do here
is just say
uh all right
instead of doing this um on the interior
we will uh just
you know we'll just populate this vector
using lookups
and
i don't know exactly how i want to do
that
long term
um but basically what i'm talking about
here
is something like this
um
we call a function
that's like get occupied 4
or something
it will perform
basically this
so we won't do that anymore it will do
that
it will also perform this
so that really this uh
this part here we'll just do like
we'll just check on the boolean
how it wants to do that when we go to
re-enable that code path so that will
also get handled up here the embed count
stuff or how that wants to
uh be handled who cares
um so this will happen out here in a
function that's like you know um
check
or
update corners or something right
um i don't know what i decided to call
it down here
this is probably a bad name get occupied
for let's like check corners or
something is probably a better name
right
um
so we'll call this thing like
check corners
and it will need
the voxel grid
i assume
we'll need the voxel stack
um
it really doesn't need very much right
mostly it just needs to produce these
values
um
and so now we could do is say well all
right let's take
uh in fact maybe we take all of these
and we just wrap them up in a in like a
little struct and that's what it does
so there's something that looks like
this
and we produced one of these from
uh anywhere
you know
uh in the system we can produce one of
these
so we then want to do this iterator
thing and it's the cell
that we care about in particular so
uh we need to be able to look up we need
to know like the absolute cell index
um so this piece of code here
uh probably wants to be like part of
this
like so
and
when you call this function you just
give it the
cell
index so it'll start out by getting the
cell bounds
uh it'll then iterate over the corners
of this voxel
testing each individual one of them
like this
and what we want to do now because this
is all fine
uh but we want like some of this stuff
like the field repulsion all that stuff
we now just want
this stuff
to
operate on codes that we pull out of the
stack
um so this right here the corner code
the embed dir
we want those
to basically
update themselves inside this routine so
we never call this function which is the
x really expensive part
if we've already called it so this just
it's just a simple way of speeding this
up by about 8x
before we actually do any real
optimization just getting rid of the
fact that you call you're doing the same
thing eight times for no reason
right
so if we go through here and we say
uh okay so the
uh
the corner i is gonna be the cell i plus
uh the vox it or i
um that's the lookup
uh let's do an assertion here
where we first just verify that you know
it's
um
not fetching out of bounds
so we'll just say or like
so maybe i can just call this because
that's really all we well i can't really
call that because it's it's going to be
one plus the cell count
so that's not really right
um
so actually is an array bounds would
work unfortunately that's we we've never
unified our gen v3 and our v3s so at
some point that might want to happen
because then this would work
so i don't know what we want to do there
i'm i'm going to like ignore that for a
second
uh and what i'm going to say is okay
uh i'm just going to do this manually
and assert that this stuff is correct
so i just i want to make sure that we're
never fetching outside of the array
i could also assert that like
um it's greater than or equal to zero
but i don't really know that that's a
case that probably won't happen uh this
one we could easily have an off by one
thing that we screw up so i feel like
that's a good one uh to check right
uh okay so
that's our corner
um so what i want to do now is set all
the values in here so the first thing we
need to do is set this one
uh which is just what we're actually
testing we then need to do our tests
and
to do the tests
we should probably just make sure okay
so
the voxel grid has that in it right so
stack
oops
grid dim
um
in order to do the tests we're going to
need the sim region and the entity
so those are the two things that we
didn't get
so let's grab those here
uh
and then we just yeah like
the unembed d is just a thing that yeah
we had down here that we set to zero
before we started right it's just a
summation
um so the unembed d can just be there
um and well i guess actually we can just
set it to zero here
uh so all we would need to do here is
say result unembed d
um equals you know clear
um
we can also say
yeah i i assume we just want to do this
so we'll just check to see if the count
is correct uh and if the count is
correct we'll clear it so that you can
move right so if it's embedded
uh we just clear it i assume
again i'm not really sure what we want
to do there so we'll we'll take a look
at that a little bit later
um
so
we now want to rewrite this part of the
routine
uh to do some
things that are a little bit different
right
we now want to rewrite this part of the
routine to
you know have a slightly different yeah
slightly different feel to it
uh
it looks like the collision field
part of this
is actually just the thing we actually
wanted so maybe i wrote this
uh
not quite right
you know instead of having two of these
maybe what we actually wanted
um
was
like a collision field well probably not
so i think what i'm going to do is i'm
just going to say we have a collision
field
and one way to produce it is to do this
the other way to produce it is to do
something else that we'll do in a second
but either way after we're done uh so
we're basically gonna have like um
an if here right
uh
where we produce the collision field in
one of two ways
um one way is we produce it the old way
by calling the actual collides at p and
the other way is we produce it by just
doing a lookup so we'll put the
repulsion uh and the occupied
uh
stuff
we'll pull those out
of
the corner code part
and we'll set the corner code part
as well
so if we look at you know the stack here
and we do the corner code
if we look up the corner codes here it
doesn't even matter how we really index
these because it whatever it is as long
as we're consistent
it's fine um maybe i'll say like the
corner code
is a pointer
to the corner code here
and we just look up the corner code
using
uh exactly what you would expect
so corner i z corner i
y corner i x
and we then say look if the corner code
equals zero we haven't tested it yet
um so test it uh and then set it to
something
uh and then otherwise pull the value out
of the corner code that we actually want
right
it may actually even be like slightly
simpler than that
uh
it could be that we just set the field
to what's in there either way so it
could be that we just do this
let's let's
maybe maybe we do this even a little bit
differently uh so maybe maybe we
actually just do this
and
this
um
okay so so field maybe goes away and
sits there right
so we check the corner code uh
and we just say if the corner code
equals zero uh then we go in here and we
set the corner code
equal to
like either two or one so one is now the
cleared value and two is the non-cleared
value
uh
we then come in here and we say
uh that the occupied value so the thing
we're using before
is just the corner code minus one
um and that just just converts it back
to a true referral value we couldn't use
the trend values here because we need
zero which is the cleared state uh to
indicate that we haven't tested yet
right
and then what we need is in the actual
uh
in the case where you're embedded we
need that repulsion vector
um so the repulsion vector would get set
in here as well
so like that uh
i don't even know what we called it
we called it
embedder
right
so in here we would look uh and grab
these out
and just say okay
that's the new embedder
and uh we're gonna store whatever the
the field you know kicked us back
at that point
should probably name them equivalently
so you know maybe maybe we should have
just done this
um repulsion
right repulsion
repulsion uh
oops
so
that way you can at least tell like what
are these things
they like line up right so occupied and
repulsion line up with occupied and
repulsion um and
you know it's clear like how that code
flows through instead of it being sort
of you know arbitrary and weird
because i was just kind of naming them
off the cuff
uh as we went
so
where is that
grid part of things
there we go
um
so in here i just change this to
repulsion now
uh and it should be good to go and so
when we uh look up all this stuff now
uh all we're gonna do is just say okay
you know and and maybe i should have the
repulsion
uh pointer here
um
snapped the same way
like so
uh and so we just say like okay uh the
the repulsion vector
we're going to sum
like so
and we're going to write to it here oops
repulsion
[Music]
uh
and then i think we've got roughly what
we want right
uh so now we just do this computation
uh of check corners
it produces all the stuff we need but in
theory it also caches the values
so that we don't have this problem
where we're computing everything over
and over and over and over and over and
over and over and over again
even though we already know the answer
which again is just a way of like
alleviating some of the stress before we
actually do the optimization of a
spatial partition which we desperately
need
um
so we'll go from there
the
stack needs an address uh
what else so now
um we have the problem of
we
need to actually use this corners part
now
um
when we do our lookups
so
that kind of thing
uh and in here i don't know if we want
to pull this out or not if we probably
don't have to so we can probably just do
it this way if four coder will let us
um
go
and that's all we should really need to
do
should probably just let it indent this
however it wants
since that's what it wants
all right
um
no
real
other things to do now i think uh so
we should be good
uh and
this has to actually return its result
but i think that's roughly what we want
and now it will cache those result codes
uh
correctly now we need to
make sure we actually set everything in
here those are the only two fields we
set those i think it's okay
um
[Music]
the embedded part we set at the bottom
so yeah i think it's all set now
um so we should probably step through
that uh but but it's basically the
correct thing now right
okay so see you can see why i asserted
this right we've got a problem here so
the corner i
is
exceeds its authority there
um
i'm not sure
what we want to do with that
um
or how that actually happened i should
probably uh go into debug to check that
but you can see here like where it it's
asking
for something that's clearly out of
bounds
uh
you know another way to write this that
probably was smarter was like this
right
it's a little bit easier to read
um
[Music]
oh the stretching
okay so
so i'm not sure
i
i'm not sure
why is this 2-2-2
shouldn't this be one one one
that's probably the bug
we were like over testing
the thing
[Music]
no i guess it is two two two because
it's
one one one would only test the zero
point so it means it has zero and one
um so so that's fine
and we should always so let's see let's
put in a different assertion here
um so let's assert
this one
on the outside that the cell that we
pass in
isn't incorrect
because we don't really know like it
could be that there's a bug in the
interior of the routine
uh but let's
but you know the presumable reason that
this fails is because someone passes a
bogus
value so let's take a look at that first
chris i don't actually know okay there
we go
um
so you can see it's as i expected which
is okay so our check corners routine is
fine
um it's not the thing causing the
problem the thing causing the problem is
that somebody here
is allowing a value to get pushed in
that is outside the bounds
of what's allowed now what's weird about
that is i thought
that the push voxel stack
um
would have prevented that from happening
so like
we're checking to see
if it's in is in bounds
right
uh
which is is looking at that cell count
um
so i guess the problem okay so the
problem we have
must then be that this process can
produce a one larger version
yeah and it can actually
that's actually true
so i suppose that this
i suppose that the problem here is that
this actually always has to be one less
than the voxel dam
right
because we're expanding
[Music]
uh
we expand that in fact it has to be two
less than the voxel dim
because we expand the voxel
here
um by one on either side
so
this has to be clamped
to
underneath that size
right
um otherwise it easily could do that i
would think um of course it's still
doing it which is weird yeah
um
so that has to be clamped for sure
and i guess i don't know now how that
would produce the bet so that was my
only hypothesis there so i guess we'll
have to investigate further because you
look at this
it's like okay quarter a b or min corner
you know we produce the thing we check
we do the span we round i suppose the
rounding
could also do that
uh so we probably have to eliminate the
rounding as well but that's probably
still not enough yeah you can see it
doesn't it does it like immediately
right so it's wrong immediately
which means we've got some like really
bad bug in here that i'm just not
thinking of what it exactly is um
hmm
uh so this should fault whenever we get
this problem okay so z what is the voxel
dim in fact let me run in debug mode so
we can just inspect these values
so
let's take a look at voxel dim
uh
and you can see there like a yeah i mean
so the voxel dim sac dim is eight
right and we're already at z8 so how did
this happen
let's
take a look at these values here so the
voxel starting corner
oops
um
[Music]
you know
seems like a voxel starting corner to me
uh
the delta p clamp
is what
um
i guess let me look at the delta p i
first
so kind of surprising
because based on that
all of those values are clean
like
they're properly clamped to below
a span of eight
so
kind of confused
um
all right so what's the voxel span
the voxel span is seven three eight so
it is wrong it's corner a
corner b
um
hmm
oh
wow
i'm stupid i'm looking at the dim so
this is actually totally allowed right
um so that's fine
that was not the case i cared about
uh
my bad there i i care about the case
where it's greater than eight in the
case of the dimension
uh not the case where it's less than
eight so so this is actually what we
wanted to look at
not the other one
so here we have an x of nine
uh so the delta p i here is negative six
uh and so the question is how did we get
that value
um
so
yeah so negative 0.125
um 0.625 if we add these together
we get .75
which is a span of
six
so i guess where this is coming from is
we add
one on the seldom side and two
on the other side for expansion
um
so i suppose the only real problem here
is is that the negative two
if you clamp to six you can still add
three
here and here in the worst case
so is it really just the case that this
just should be a negative three i mean i
guess i'm not sure but it seems like
that's actually the case
so i don't know maybe that was actually
the only problem
i'm still not super happy with this code
i feel like we need to have a better way
it's close it's closer than it was
but that voxel-bound code still is kind
of feels just sloppy right it doesn't
really feel right
um so i don't know
but let's give it a try now that with
that clamping in place just to see
um if we're still having that problem
but you can see why those asserts are so
valuable right like a lot of times i
know
where the risk is
but by inspecting the code you can't
necessarily tell when you're going to
hit the risk right so the really great
part about assertions is they allow you
to use your intuition about what's
probably going to fail
um to actually catch the failures before
they cause really serious problems right
um because you'll get assertions rather
than your code just like dying at some
point you don't know why
um
uh so yeah
um so
uh
you know actually it's looking better
now you can see we still got a corner
cut catch there
uh so we've got a bug you know we've
still got some bugs
um
but it is looking a little bit better uh
so you see like we've got some kind of
an embed bug right it got caught in that
corner
um
fortunately we now do corner rolling
properly in the case that we were trying
to solve
both sides which is good
so we're getting closer but i think
we're going to need another day of
debugging here to like clean this stuff
up and then we also need to put back in
the embed
code because the embed code is necessary
it's pretty easy for us to do now i
think
um
we just have to augment the stack to
have the embed code in it uh so that's
not that bad
right um
but so you know honestly we're getting
close uh the code's still just a little
ugly we gotta fix some of it um
and and we can definitely do that
uh but you know yeah it's still a little
bit off
um
but it's definitely feeling much nicer
now
you can see how nice and slippery that
is
um
and so so we just have we have a little
bit of a problem i think with with
how those bounds are picked
still is not perfect
we'll fix the embed stuff but we're
getting much better right
um
so that seems really good
the definitely positive improvements
there so you can see that stick right
like that's an actual bug um
where you can get in a position in the
corner where you can't escape
uh
and i
think that's just because of the we have
a bug that allows you get embedded and
then we don't have the unembedding
um so we definitely still have some bugs
in there like the unembedding code now
is not actually that
not not very difficult because we have
the ability to call check corners early
um
so like if you looked at how the embed
stuff worked you could say
um
you could do an initial check
i i'm gonna say this for next week uh
but you could do an initial check here
where you just do like you know
do initial check uh to see if we're
embedded
and use that
to
allow or disallow
stack um but i think probably what we'd
need
uh is in here
this would probably be need
this would probably be necessary
uh
to create it
as a are we embedded
flag that goes with the stack
right
all right we can do some brief cues and
a's here do i still have the ability to
type this
insobot is like a national treasure
i think we can all agree
insobot's question is fantastic
i've been real down i'm programming
lately have you ever had a phase where
you were just totally over computers uh
no
so
i will say that i hate
programming publicly now like i do not
like doing
uh
like like i would if i could rewind
and ha and know what the current state
of programming
and like the development community would
be today
i would never have done handmade hero
and i definitely would not have started
my own company
um
i would just go take a research and
development position somewhere where i
don't have to ever interact or have a
twitter profile or any of those things
right
um so development community absolutely
um the difference between
interacting with developers 30 years ago
and interacting with them today it is
there's no
i can't even describe to you how much
worse it is um
it's
it's indescribably worse
uh
so that part yeah but the programming
computers is awesome still even to to
this day
um
and to the extent that you
uh
to the extent that you don't want to do
it as a job i can totally understand
because a lot of jobs out there are
terrible because they involve exactly
all the things that i'm referring to
when i say interacting with
developers sucks
so
i could understand not wanting to do it
as a job but not wanting to do it at all
doesn't really make much sense to me
because uh
you know i mean you can buy a raspberry
pi for forty dollars
um
and like program your own os for it and
just go to town man like there's so many
opportunities today for so cheap i used
to cost like thousands of dollars to get
a computer
that was powerful enough to do things
like rendering or whatever right
um
and so so i really think it's important
to
mentally distinguish
between the parts of being a developer
that suck because the modern
because the modern ideology broadly
speaking
in development and probably pretty much
everywhere is terrible and isn't good
um
[Music]
and is icky and gross
distinguishing that
from whether the act of programming when
you take the humans out of it is good or
bad is important because to me
programming today actually is still
really good
uh
it's
the fact that you probably don't really
get an opportunity to do it
without
um
you know
all of the crap
uh the the terrible ideology at most
companies the terrible ideology of most
developers
the terrible ideology of colleges or
universities
um
all of that it's important to understand
that is a temporal anomaly it is a
symptom of things like a failing society
right
um
it is not a symptom of a failing
computer
the act of using the computer is still
pretty great
and you can even if you are in a
position to do so you can even bypass
the parts that really suck like the you
know windows operating system or
something
and even the windows operating system
isn't that bad to use if you unplug it
from the internet if you just install
windows once unplug the computer from
the internet and program on it it's
actually fine
right
uh and you've also got linux so you can
and linux is totally fine too if you do
a similar thing if you find one
machine whose hardware linux runs on and
you install it once and then forget
about ever updating it again or using a
package manager and just go program on
it and and enjoy yourself
again that takes all of that garbage out
of there right
um
so i think
you know
i think that those are really important
things to separate i think computers are
still a lot of fun to program and i
think there's still a lot of fun
to use
if you are using them in the same way
that you used to use them in 1986
right
the problem is if you start to associate
computing with all of the bad ideologies
that have now infected computing as of
you don't have to do that right um
if you can if you can't find a job
that allows you to not do that
then please still don't blame it on
computing just take a different job
right uh go find a different job to do
and do computing as your hobby right
and wait until
uh
you know the the
eventual reset or collapse of the
current uh
system
and
you know
maybe computing will be a job again some
some day but maybe it won't right so i
don't know go go
consider a different career path
that you'll be happy doing during the
day and you can still program on the
weekends that's what i would say
do you think it's safe to assume if a
cpu has avx-2 it has fma
oh no
it absolutely doesn't have fma
um
avx-2 cpus don't have fma
uh
as far as i know that if if avx2 cpus
have fma that's news to me
fma is an avx-512 extension as far as i
know
um
[Music]
i didn't think there was a fused
multiplier accumulate
um
in in avx2 uh other than for like 16-bit
integers there's like a 16-bit integer
f-mat or something
but but i don't think so
i could be wrong i mean
i i
very rarely do floating point work on
guaranteed avx ii com
parts because most time if i'm doing
floating point work it's for client code
and client code doesn't have avx2
usually you can usually only assume like
sse4
you know sometimes you don't even assume
that
uh depending on on it but
um if you look at the mad
listings here right so these are
multiply add instructions right um
you know uh which ones you have and
don't have so you can start to to check
things off so if you just want to say
um you were gonna limit yourself to the
things that were
uh prior to
uh avx 512 it's basically this list here
um you know maybe you could say uh some
of these but who knows right so if we're
just going to check yourself this you
can see this is what i was trying to say
when i said except if you count 16 bit
you can kind of see that there really
isn't any uh fused multiply add
uh available
in in pre avx 512 instruction sets
so so unless i misunderstood your
question
uh
to the best of my knowledge an avx-2
cpu
definitely doesn't have
a fused multiply accumulate you would
have to check the avx 512 support first
um
and if you check the avx 512 support
that
might indicate it but it also might not
so typically what you do is you don't
check any of these anyway if you want
fused multiply add
you just check directly for the fma flag
it has nothing to do with avx2 like avx2
just doesn't have multiply accumulate
um except for for 16 bit like i said
so
uh
and it's not even really like it's 16
it's not even really it it's not like a
terniary instruction
um it it's paired
right uh
it so it's a it's a very specific it's a
different it's for different stuff
right
uh does that does that make sense mine
mark 42 i i mean all i'm trying to say
here uh if you didn't already know is
that avx2 has nothing to do with with
fused multiply add
so so checking the av x2 support of a
processor just doesn't tell you anything
about whether it has fuse multiply add
they're they're completely independent
um
the avx2 support is just is just not
relevant to whether it has
uh fma it's the fma flags that tell you
if it has fma
right
uh and or or you can check avx 512 and
cross your fingers but my my
recollection is that avx 512 doesn't
have to have fma maybe it does but i
don't think it does
so i'm pretty sure that like
avx 512
can also exist without the fma part
don't quote me on that that might not be
true
um so so i don't know so i did i just
don't think the avx 2 part makes any
difference just check the fma
um
and you're good
no i'm pretty sure avx-2 cpus often
don't have fma
extensions uh
i could be wrong about that
but
uh
so i wanna say that like
so suppose that you took
like uh
suppose that you took the fma extension
here
um and we looked at at what it was
listed under
me
trying to think of how
we would know
uh
okay so
let's find out
so let's take one of these uh well
doubles you know maybe isn't the best
uh test so let's take the simplest one
we might want
which is the fmad
for floats right
uh and let's just take a look
at
what uops.info
thinks it has or doesn't have right uh
so we know this is an fma flag
um
and so you know
we can look and see
but
so i don't know you you could be right
uh you could be right because i'm
looking at it here
uh
and it looks like maybe you're right
yeah
um
because it seems to think that it
measured one
on like
older
parts
so you might be right
um
so it doesn't exist on ivy bridge
you can see
it not existing there
uh so i guess the question is does any
uh avx2
operation
exist on iv bridge
right
um so let's take a look uh if we
pick a avx2
op here so like
whatever
uh
are these really avx-2 only operations
i guess so so avx2 like okay like 64-bit
integer add apparently was avx2
um
so let's take a look
does iv bridge have
adq
right
um
[Music]
no
so you could be right
um because if even if they're separate
flags if in practice
as soon as they added avx2 they also
always added
fma
i'm not sure how to check in any way
other than this is the only problem so i
don't know that this is particularly
dispositive one way or the other like
this is a pretty crude way of looking
so i don't know that's intel signed um
we could also look at uh
you know
um
parts that came from amd
right
so there's it doing a vp adq
and what was that fma one
i wish i could list multiples of these
at the same time
how come i can't go back
you can't go back
apparently back buttons just are not a
thing
uh it is v f a
so i don't know
it could be
it could be that if you've guaranteed
avx-2 support no one ever shipped a part
that didn't have it um i mean we're
looking at it here and that seems yeah
likely
i don't know i i wouldn't recommend it
as i guess all i can say
if they're separate flags i wouldn't
recommend doing that um because i don't
know
it sounds scary
but
it could be
it could be i almost never have the
ability to ship things on avx-2 cpus
unless it's server code and server code
usually doesn't need floating point it's
usually only integer so i've literally
never had an occasion to use an fmad
um
in those circumstances
i
so
you know i i've never
i i just never have looked at that so i
really couldn't tell you uh from any
kind of experience
i just i would still be kind of nervous
about it but you know
um
the spot check on ups.info it seems like
if you've got avx2 they've got they've
got the fmat so
i don't know
you can see here that the fma
[Music]
extensions right they're all floating
point
so that you know like i said like
on a server you don't
you know
on a server you don't get that
uh
so
what's the time for fuse multiply add um
oh wow that's really good too
that's really cool uh it's cool to know
that if we ever get up to avx-2 support
on client machines
uh that you can have a four
four cycle latency because so normally
if you do
a multiply followed by an add it's it
would be five cycles so you actually
save a cycle in addition to having
a more accurate result
one of the reasons you usually do fused
multiply ads is because they're more
accurate
right you you if you do a multiply and
then an add you first have to like
round the intermediate results right
which loses precision and then you do
the add and then you round that result
which also loses precision right so
if you can combine those two operations
you
don't have to worry about
losing those bits in the middle
um so usually you do you do
fuse multiply ads because
uh they're more accurate
so i didn't know if it would be the same
cost like five
cycles
uh but just more accurate but it turns
out it's actually also faster so that's
great too
very nice
all right
um so like
i think we're done
um
are we done we're done right
i mean no one's objecting to us being
done so i think we're done
okay
thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero uh it
has been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
the series at home you can always go to
handmade hero.org and pre-order the game
it comes with the source code
um
the collision detector was feeling a
little dicey there with that
but then we kind of like straightened
out the bounce checking now it's feeling
pretty good actually so i think we might
be
almost done uh we have to put in a
spatial audition
uh and i think we probably still got
some bugs in there
so we're gonna have to go through it
with with a little bit more diligence
but
uh
that's looking pretty good and we're
getting the nice edge roll off now
um so i think when we kind of go through
it one more time maybe one more weekend
i think it'll be in pretty good shape
we'll then have to spend a weekend after
that and put the spatial partition in
for sure because otherwise it's just
always going to be too slow
uh so we need to make the
you know we need to do a uh some work
there and that'll that'll be like at
least another another day of coding
so we'll go ahead and do those things
but then i think we have a nice really
smooth feeling
collision system
and i suspect at that point
combat
will be implementable nicely
uh
not that i know how to implement it
because of course that's a game design
thing so not really my thing
um
but you know we'll put we'll put
something in there
for combat
you hit the thing and it takes away a
heart
that's that's
that'll be the combat system
um
so we'll put that in there and uh
you know
maybe we'll try to try to tweak it uh
we'll do what we can
uh so we'll see you back here next week
for that i updated the schedule so it's
up there now um
and i think we'll be on sundays for a
while now
uh because i have some recording stuff i
have to do on saturdays so
that'll be it uh so until then have fun
program everyone and i'll see you on the
internet
take it easy uh one thing i might do