okay hello everyone and welcome to
handmade here are the show recode a
complete game live on twitch no
library's no engine we got to do
everything ourselves and again the
reason why we do this is two reasons one
so that you can sort of have the
complete freedom to do whatever you want
on a game it's so that by the time
you're done with handmade hero you
pretty much know how absolutely
everything works and that's a pretty
powerful thing to be able to do to know
and to be able to do depending on the
circumstance but also it's it's honestly
it's a lot of fun we get to play with a
lot of stuff that you don't typically
get to do and we kind of try to bring
back that old-school feeling of being
able to sit down at a computer and sort
of start poking if the innards as much
as possible at least to the extent that
windows lets us which is not always as
much as we'd like but you know what are
you gonna do that's the that's the state
of the world these days I'm gonna go
ahead and get started here if you would
like to follow along at home we are on
day 99 so if you have free order of the
game you have X to the source code you
can go ahead and download day 98 source
code and unzip that into directory
you'll be exactly where I am right now
and where I am right now is actually
that's kind of an interesting breaking
point here where we kind of have to we
kind of got to do a bunch of work to to
sort of push forwards we wanted to add
lighting to the game and we did the work
to add normal maps to our pipeline but
what we have not done yet is actually
produced anything that the normal Maps
can sample from we essentially don't
have any kind of a light field and so we
need to do now is we need to figure out
a way that we're gonna be able to get a
light field of some kind and so that's
what we've got to tackle today now we
had to reboot the machine pre stream
because machine is old and it doesn't
really work so well but so I gotta go
ahead and get Visual Studio back into a
state where it's working here it seems
to be relatively good there so that's
fine
I gotta open up our blackboard which
hopefully is saved at the location where
we were last time let's see here
today's there it is okay so yeah let's
just real quick
I'm just gonna say what we kind of need
to do here in order to make forward
progress on our on our lighting so here
on day 99 really what we're looking for
so I gotta move this over here let's try
that again
so here's day 99 so what we have to do
now is we have to make some light fields
and what we want to do here is we
already sort of talked about this what
we were going to do we want to be able
to sample the lighting in the world so
that at any given point we can sort of
get some notion of what's going on
around us in terms of light and so
there's a couple different ways that we
talked about doing that two of which are
relatively straightforward for us to
implement which was the ones we'll try
to do today and one of which is still
kind of a little up in the air because
we're not sure exactly how we're going
to produce that field but what we need
to do is we need to produce three light
fields eventually we kind of talked
about these before we've got you know a
top a middle right and a bottom that we
wanted to produce and these are
basically three different bitmaps that
we want to be able to pull data from in
order to compute the lighting and the
way these work essentially is you can
imagine them all sort of stacked on top
of each other right like so and we're
sort of imagining again because we
really have to come up with
approximations and hacks for lighting in
2d because you know we don't really know
what the full description of the world
is so we can't do any kind of you know
fully real simulation and even in 3d you
can't do real simulation but you can do
closer approximation certainly what
we're kind of pretending is the middle
layer right so this guy here these are
our layers stacked up on top of each
other the middle layer is sort of where
things are in the world you might say
and so we're kind of thinking of this as
being the ground
and this is being the sky and so when we
sample you know when we when we sort of
are looking at lighting essentially what
we're saying is when we want to sort of
look cast out lighting around us to see
what kind of light is incident on a
surface we're sort of saying that all
right we're gonna produce a ground
bitmap that we'll use probably as the
ground as well right we want to produce
a ground bitmap and that we can probably
just use and sample our lighting out of
that right and then we could have a sky
bitmap which is some bitmap that just
represents what's up there in the sky as
well and we could sample from that and
those two would make our top and our
bottom light fields to sample from what
we were calling sort of environment maps
for now and then we've got a middle that
is really like the part that's gonna be
a little more tricky and what we want to
be able to do with the middle map is we
want to be able to sort of use some
amount of occlusion in here so that you
know as a light passes by let's say
there's a moving light source that's
passing by the place that we're sampling
we want to get that sort of passing by
effect so that the light kind of plays
across the surface of whatever we're
sampling and furthermore if there's
large objects like if there's something
big in between these two we want not
very much light to get past to see the
point that we're talking about so this
middle map is really going to be the one
where most of the trickery comes in the
top and the bottom maps are really gonna
be a lot easier they're mostly going to
be more about bookkeeping they're more
about making sure that our renderer can
first save a copy of whatever that base
layer ground is before it starts to
splat stuff on top of it because we need
to be able to sample from the unspotted
version right and that's really all
we're talking about here in terms of
producing these maps the sky map since
that's not something that you ever
direct directly see it's basically
something that is unseen by the player
but that's sort of what's above the
world can really be whatever we want but
we'll probably want to put stuff in
there you know it depends on exactly
what we want to do but you could imagine
if there's things like sort of
above the player like if they're in a
dungeon or something and light is coming
down through there we can stick light in
there so things that are below it up
here to have this extra light
Commandment and it sort of it suggests
what is up here if you will so that's
kind of just some something to think
about so what we need to do today before
we can make any more progress on our
normal mapping stuff which we've sort of
done most of the work for but we haven't
really gone and really finished it up
what we have to do today is now go and
produce some of these maps at least the
top and the bottom map and the middle
one I guess we can sort of leave out for
now but we need to at least produce the
top and the bottom map so that we can
have some semblance of a real you know a
test map to sample from just to see if
our normal map is working and to give us
some idea of what's going on there so we
don't really need to do anything
particularly special with those right
now we can literally make test patterns
in them and then see to it that the test
patterns actually are respected right so
let's go ahead and do that right let's
go ahead and and and start to get that
going because it's really gonna be a
bunch of wiring right so at the moment
we can sort of do that by saying we've
got these environment maps right where
are those guys handmade render group
we've got these environment maps here so
what we'll do is we'll start by creating
some space for those those environment
maps in here and then we'll sort of
progress and push them outwards as we
need to as we sort of like make the
renderer into more and more of a thing
so hmm
I'm just gonna go ahead and drop those I
think those probably should really just
be down here because they're things that
are fairly dynamic so I'm gonna put them
down here in fact I guess these are
really transient things so I guess I'll
put them with the ground buffers so
let's call these our ground or sky I
guess or I guess we could call them our
top or end top and bottom since we don't
really know that sky right it could be
some other thing
and in the middle so what I need to do
now is I need to just allocate some
space for these guys and I guess I don't
really need these to be pointers they
can just be that and then I'll make the
bitmaps in them now the question we have
here there is a kind of an open question
which is just how big should these maps
be and that's a good question right
because this is lighting we don't
necessarily need it to be at the same
resolution as we would do everything
else we could say that's going to be
sort of a sub sampling of that I'm not
sure yet so but that's just something to
think of as we don't really know what we
want these environment maps resolutions
really to be but so I'll just say you
know M map width and nmap height are
going to be things that we'll specify
for now outside and we'll just assume
that we have made these environment maps
to whatever the specification is here
okay so going into handmade CPP where we
actually initiate sort of our transient
stuff when we're when we're doing this
initialization we can also here do our M
top middle and bottom stuff and our M
width and height that sort of thing so
what I'm going to do is I'm going to say
that the trans state right that is going
to initialize the end map with and I'm
just gonna say that the end map width
and height are gonna be let's say five
twelve I'm just pulling these totally
randomly 512 by 256 that's just what
it's going to be you know why not and I
guess what I could do to make this a
little bit easier on us as I could just
make this an erase we could initialize
them in a loop and we'll just know you
know that 0 is top and 2 is bottom all
right once middle that's what those are
going to be set to and you know I think
about it Z going up makes a little more
sense doesn't it that's the way the rest
of our coordinate system works might as
well try to stay a little consistent
there so all right so let's go through
these in the list in a loop rather so
we've got our map index and our map
index is going to run from 0 to however
many of these we have right and then we
are going to take whichever environment
map we're on alright so here is our map
we take it out from the end Maps array
one at a time and we go ahead and
initialize all of the LOD s in there
right and remember what we said these
LEDs were going to be is they were going
to be successively blurrier versions of
the same map right so we start with you
know an LOD that's at the full
resolution of M map with MF height and
each time through we basically have that
size so that it gets smaller and smaller
so okay get rid of that so what we now
want to do is we want to do another loop
inside which is whichever LOD index this
is or LOD index this is and that's going
to go all the way to however many
elements are in that array the moment
we've said there are four and so what we
can do then is say that the map LOD at
that index is going to be one of those
make empty bitmap calls which we already
have which I believe is set up to to
allocate space for us so all we really
have to do is just give it that and it
will it will go ahead and push size on
to our transient arena to store that map
so what we can do there is say all right
let's go ahead and get that done we'll
pass the trans Arena right yeah that's
our transient Arena there we will pass
whatever the width and height is that we
want of this particular thing and then I
guess we might as well clear it to zero
though I guess I don't really know that
we need to do that it's probably to be
honest I guess we don't really need to
because we got to fill it with stuff so
anyway what we want to do is start out
because we want this to be successively
lower levels of detail what we want to
do is start out with that sort of width
and height that we are saying that the
highest level of detail should be and
then each time through
I'm just gonna go ahead and shift that
down by one so that we essentially get
half the size in each dimension which is
a you know a quarter of the size for the
bitmap right so that should produce for
us that sort of cascading level detail
where we have maps that are first you
know the full size then a quarter the
size that a quarter of that size like an
eighth
I'm sorry sixteenth and and so on right
so that should give us the maps then
when we're down here we have to have a
way to actually you know sort of pass
those maps which we've sort of been
passing nothing right so what we're
gonna do is we're gonna stop start
passing those maps really pretty
straightforward right we're just going
to pass the end maps as they come so
we've got the first end map like so
we've got the second oops that's not a
game state that's trans state so and
then that final one now I believe these
go these went in the other order right
but I'm going to look it up first in our
render group so the coordinate system
when we actually push one of those on it
takes the top and the middle and the
bottom like so and that's how we said
that those weren't coded so that's what
those are and if I compile that now I
can just go and clean up anything that
we had there oh of course the render
group that that's a environment map is
this not do we not pound include we
don't pound include any of the render
stuff here
I think that's probably a mistake so
honestly I think what I'd like to do is
go ahead and and pull that out here I'd
like that to be included up here ideally
but oh and of course loaded bitmap is
not there but that should also be moved
out looks like I made that a little bit
too high up as well here's where we're
actually putting this stuff like so but
loaded bitmap I'm gonna actually pull
that out into the render group as well
because that's something that probably
eventually wants to live in some sort of
rendering oriented context so what is
happening here okay so these are
winters and they really should not have
been pointers that was a mistake
so let's get rid of that and then we
should be able to compile and let's see
here sample environment map looks like
everything is kosher now of course these
maps just have garbage in them well
actually guess technically they have
just zero in them at the moment because
they're in the trainer Rita which would
have been cleared when it was initially
passed to us so we should really get
nothing in particular happening here
there should be no lighting contribution
from them which is fine that's totally
what we would have expected so now what
we want to do is we want to actually put
start putting something in there so that
we can start actually sampling from it
so what I would like to do first is I'd
like to actually request that we draw
these maps somewhere so that I can see
that they're actually you know doing
something right I want to actually I
want to be able to verify that these
maps are having something in them that
we think that they have in them right I
don't want to just start trying to
sample them blind so the first thing I'm
going to do is I'm going to in here
where we draw the you know do the
coordinate system call what I'd like to
do is I'd like to go ahead and add some
calls before we do that to draw what is
in at least the top level of the
environment map which I don't actually
know if there's anything else that we're
using at the moment a lot index may or
may not be doing in this so we are
actually using the roughness to
determine what laud index to use so I
guess the question is which roughness
level did we actually put in there when
we did make a sphere normal map
roughness makes P R normal
zero-zero so we're still sampling from
the we're always gonna be sampling from
that most from that topmost LOD right
you can see here that we've got
roughness times whatever that array
count is and we're rounding that so
that's base is going to give us you know
if we're passing zero that's which is
what we said the roughness was
everywhere
that's going to give us always that
top-level LOD so that should be fine so
when we've done this when we've when
we've gone to draw these I really just
need to draw that top level so that we
can take a look at what that looks like
and then at least know what we're
sampling from so I'm gonna go ahead and
take this coordinate system call here
and I'm just gonna make another one of
them like so where I'm going to say all
right ignore the environment Maps ignore
the tree normal map all that stuff let's
just draw somewhere in the world and I'm
not sure where we're gonna put it at the
moment let's just go ahead and draw
though those top-level maps so that's
the Tran State you know the end Maps
right I want to draw zero LOD zero like
so and I want to draw three of these
right I want to draw em from f1 and map
to I just want to draw the top level LOD
and maybe I don't know maybe I'll go
ahead and do this as well in a loop
because this may get a little more
complicated if we want to start drawing
all the LOD levels so let me just go
ahead and say that we're gonna do map
index we'll do it for each of the maps
so there we go and maps and now we
should have a way to draw all of that
now I need to put it somewhere so I
guess I will say let's see the x axis
and the y axis let's let's go ahead and
redefine those here I'm going to say
that the x axis and the y axis are going
to be scaled maybe you know let's let's
say that there's a map scale and the map
scale is going to be like
I don't know 50 it's gonna be 50 and
we'll just say that this is going to be
map scale zero Oh 50 is probably too
much or these are these drawing we're
still in screen spacer aren't we okay so
if we're in screen space that makes it
even easier really what I can do with
the x-axis y-axis stuff is I could
actually just stuff in there what the
the map actual with the actual size of
the LOD of the map is right so I could
just do loaded bitmap LOD equals map la
0 like so and then just say that we're
drawing that and what I can do here is
is make it so that we take out whatever
its width was and whatever its height
was and that's what what will actually
draw it as right so we don't really know
where to draw these yet so I guess I'll
just say map P or something like that
and that looks about right
so there we go map p x-axis y-axis color
LOD the color we don't really care about
that should always be full brightness we
don't want to affect it in any way and
so what I can do here is then say okay
map key plus equals y axis which will
move us down to the next one so we can
draw them and maybe I'll do you know
just a five pixel spacer or something in
here as well right something that can
kind of give us a little bit of a break
between them so we can tell so map key
that will start out I guess will start
out at the at the upper left corner or
the sorry the bottom left corner
assuming that we're we're actually doing
that that we're not doing the Y flip in
here are we yeah
see map LOD cannot convert yes that's
true yeah so let's take a look I
actually think it might still be in the
upper corner now I think about it just
because of the way that that's working
okay what oh oh right
it draws those yellow markers everywhere
so we actually see the yellow markers
for the things we drew I'm actually
gonna I want to draw just one of those
because I also want to know what our
coordinate system is here because we
still haven't finished any of the
renderer coordinate system stuff so all
right so yeah it is it is upper-left
still because these are all actually
screen coordinates that were passing in
so el-oued the end map 0 which is our
bottom map is the one that appears on
the top and then it goes down from there
we might have to scale these by half you
know we might have to do something like
this because otherwise they wouldn't all
fit so if I do that we could actually
probably get all three of them on the
screen you can see them there 1 2 3 and
obviously there's nothing in them right
now the Alpha value is is incorrect
everywhere it's it's going to be zero
everywhere so there's really nothing to
see but we're start to fill them in we
should start to see something so let's
say for starters
I guess every time every frame what we
would want to do is we'll start off by
clearing those guys and drawing some
stuff into them again stuff that we can
test for normal mapping so when we start
off with our rendering I guess what I'll
do is say well I guess I can even do
this down here since this is just test
code at the moment before we start
rendering any of this stuff what I want
to do is actually prepare those Maps so
the easiest thing I could do is I could
actually use the draw rectangle call
from the render group right
I can I can just point the draw
rectangle call at our one of our bitmaps
and I can fill it with a color so the
very first thing that could do is we
could fill say the bottom with red and
the top with blue and then if we do our
normal map lighting we should at least
be able to see red tinge and blue tinges
on the tops and bottoms of our stuff
right so I'm just going to start with
the simplest most simple thing there and
that is what that would be so the first
I'm going to do is I'm just going to
clear our bitmaps here all of the LOD s
I'm going to clear them all so that we
can you know start with that I'm sorry
not all the LED is just that top LED so
if I take the trans date if I take the
zeroth map zero flawed or look you know
I don't even know how you pronounce that
I usually say law and it just sounds so
clunky there doesn't it I don't know so
anyway either way though if we if we go
ahead and and and allow us to say LOD if
I take this guy and I go ahead and and
produce what's essentially a full clear
for him right and so that's just we
translate and map width Tran State and
the map height and you know I really
could just pass some really huge number
here too because it'll clip so that
would be fine as well but you know
whatever
so I'll clear the ground I guess I'll
clear it to pure red and I will clear
the middle to pure green which we're
probably not using at the moment or at
least I don't think we should be I think
we might have some code in there
actually that is using it at the moment
which might be a mistake we should
probably turn that off
for what we're doing at the moment but
anyway then we'll make the sky the sky
will be blue so it's let's see here - no
conversion that's true but I think we
can just use our eye to convert those
from Yuen's to reels and then we've got
to actually do just that should do fine
right we're just using the zero with one
here which all kind of denote even
though it doesn't actually need to
happen so there's our G and B clears and
hey look you can already see that it's
actually sampling from it we can see a
bug already which it looks like I
inverted the sense of the blend that's
happening here I don't know if you can
see that but you know you can see how
the blue properly is sort of feathering
out there I don't know if it's
feathering out entirely correctly but
it's like feathering out so you don't
see a super harsh line but with the red
you do see that really harsh line and
that's not at all what we want right
that's that's that's not good so what I
can do there is I can go in and fix that
which is good we've already kind of
found one thing that we did wrong so
that's in here right and if you see this
is this is the stuff that's actually
supposed to be what's what's a little
bit odd here even also to think about
this the way this is working this was
supposed to be our ground map but we're
actually getting it on top and this was
supposed to be our sky map and we're
actually getting on bottom so we also
have a sort of a flip in the sense of
who is doing what here which is another
thing that we should track down right
alright so we've got plenty of stuff to
work on here let's get started
and again this is exactly why I'm doing
it this way you can imagine that if we
had just actually done some lighting in
here it would have been much harder to
tell what's going wrong and so this is
we've we've done this once before when
we were doing bitmap loading structured
art is a very important way to debug
code because code especially rendering
code is often very complicated and it's
really easy both to have subtle bugs and
also to have hard bugs that are
difficult to debug even if they're not
subtle and structured art is a good way
to help you to guide you through that
process
because there's no sense trying to debug
a subtle situation when you could
instead first make it very pronounced
because then if you make it very
pronounced it's much easier to see
what's going wrong and that helps guide
the debugging process whereas if you
constantly are actually fighting with
always real data then it makes it so
much harder for you to actually see
where the problems are and see what's
going wrong because it's hard to look at
some arbitrary data and say yes that's
wrong yes that's right when we have
something so clear as just like bright
red or bright blue and we can see where
it's going we kind of know that there's
a problem and so the other thing we'll
probably do what I what I might suggest
we do very shortly here is actually just
fill this this with a white debug
texture or something as well so that
we're only looking at that sphere normal
map that we drew in there so that we
don't have to worry about the underlying
tree either but that's not really that
important right now it's not really
getting in our way too much so let's
take a look at this first of all we know
I guess the bottom map whatever the
bottom map that's coming in here I'm
gonna go ahead and say and just just do
this right I'm going to change it to top
so we're just sampling the top map so we
know that the top map is correctly
coming in as blue but we do know that
we're picking it incorrectly and so
we're taking a look at this normal dot y
and we're saying if that is less than
negative 0.5 meaning it's it's pointing
in the negative direction we're saying
that that's going to be bottom and so
what that must mean I feel like probably
suggests
that our normal map is actually sort of
pointing in the wrong direction it would
seem I'm not totally sure about that but
let's go ahead and check right make
spirit normal map so here we are and yet
so we're coming in here we've got our
height as our Y goes it starts off yeah
I mean you can already see that it's
wrong right we're starting with we make
our low Y values so that they encode
that way but our bitmaps is top down at
the moment right currently I believe are
especially the way we were specifying
our bitmaps was was top down right
because the pitch I'm assuming anyway
that that's the way we start with that
we're starting it we could always take a
look here yeah so that's that's a
mistake to be sure I guess we should
think about it a little bit how we want
our bitmaps to be structured do we want
them to be top down and bottom up
because really I think we probably want
our bitmaps to normally actually be
bottom up not
not top down and the reason I say that
is because most graphics API API is like
you know OpenGL and stuff they want the
bitmaps to be bottom up as well so it
seems like that's probably something we
would want to be using mmm I guess we'll
let that sit for a minute but I think
maybe that might be something that we
tackle sooner rather than later
because again while we're here in the
renderer I don't want to get too far
down the path of not having our
coordinate system straightened out and
so maybe what I'll say is maybe let's
let's think about pretty soon going
ahead and straightening up this
coordinate system stuff and so we kind
of did this it's true we just
straight-up did this even before our
architecture excavation was complete but
so we're doing lighting right now and
the other thing we do obviously we need
optimization in here but what we want to
do is straighten out all coordinate
systems coordinate systems that screen
world texture so that we have all of
those consolidated before we go any
further but all right we'll skip that
for now so we'll just allow those to be
wrong we'll have those be wrong for now
because we're not sampling them
incorrectly as it turns out we are
actually sampling them properly so
that's okay so with our sampling what
did we do wrong on our bottom map though
let's see here we have our TM map we are
saying that it's we're going to add one
to it that means that it ranges yes so
the problem here is that we're going the
wrong direction you can actually see
that that's what's happening because TM
maps going to range from negative one
all the way to negative 0.5 and the
problem here is that we're going to at
zero this is going to be zero but at
zero
should actually be one right so this is
actually inverted if you will from what
it should have been and we can probably
go ahead and multiply that through if we
want to simplify things I don't know
that we really care that much about it
but you can actually see in here right
we could have we could have simplified
this guy a little bit more right because
if we multiply the two through so let's
multiply the two through we would just
get that right and so if we do that we
end up with this right and so we can
then move this over here and subtract so
we'd end up with negative 1.0 minus two
times T nmap and yeah in theory that
what wait I can't be right did I do that
wrong I did that wrong what did I what
did I mess up it's a bad math day
obviously let's do that one more time
looked like I did it wrong to me maybe
it didn't look like I did it wrong to
you but we have this guy and he's going
the wrong direction so we've got it we
want to be able to subtract one from it
in fact I can verify first that that's
correct and you can kind of see now how
we get that tapering that we had wanted
to get there right so if I multiply a
negative two through like I saying I
should get that and negative two right
that should be what we're getting and so
that seems and that's still correct so
yeah I guess I actually was correct
there negative two that produces
negative one that looks like why does
that look totally wrong to me
TM map no I guess that's right that's
right because this is always negative
0.5 to negative one so it's always at
least going to add one so hey yeah math
is right even when you're wrong I don't
know if that's a good way to say that
but it's okay so that's fixed now and
we're doing our sampling so that's all
fine
and what we want to do now is probably
take a look at actually computing where
we're sampling from a little more
accurately because we're not really
doing that at the moment and I'm not
exactly sure what the best way to do to
produce a test texture for that is but
I'm guessing that really the best way
might be to put in some kind of a
checker board or something so that we
can you know we can see a pattern a very
clear pattern that we'll be able to
recognize so I'm going to go ahead and
and put that in here
so that we can actually so that we can
actually see something all right so if I
do this we've got I got my map index
that's going to go through each map and
then I'm going to try to do just a
checkerboard here I don't I don't really
know I'm gonna make this up as I go
along let's say we're gonna make a 16
pixel checkerboard oops that's not what
I meant to do so we're just gonna go
through whatever that LOD zwip is and
we're going to just go by by a you know
a checkered checker dim let's do checker
width and height actually oops
height so I'm just gonna go through both
of these and say alright I've got you
know the X and the y and I want to make
a checkerboard right and so I'm gonna go
through here and I'm gonna draw into the
LOD that we're on like so and I want to
draw from you know a min P to a max P
and you know the max piece is always
going to be the min P plus checker width
checker height right and
so max P min P and then in here we want
to be able to set the color essentially
and so what I want to do is I want to
say I wish draw a rectangle in fact I
could fix this right now in fact let's
just go ahead and do that let's fix this
compile that I'm gonna make draw
rectangle take a color value just like
everything else so like that right and
that way we can say that the red is
color are the green is color G the B
blue color B and the a this color a and
then I'll just force everyone else to
use that oops and let's see are you
definition for our color that'll be
color 32 now so and now all of these
draw rectangles oh they actually have
things going going pretty nicely for
them actually because they can just do
you know pass a color there I don't know
if we've written to v4 or not but we
will now looks like the Alpha value is
always same here so yeah and alright
keep going so we have not done two
before yet so there's our color this
this just simplifies this down because
we're already we've already got the
entry color so that's good
looks like this one rectangle was still
storing just an RG and a B is that
correct yeah so these guys should really
just be store in color now this weird
with v4 it up here people
all right there we go so these guys are
going to call entry color like so entry
bitmap well is if zeroed out so I don't
even know what that's doing all right
so color being passed here again that
should all just work theory and these
guys can now be much more simplistic
because they actually could just pass
straight through which is great that's
what we want so that way there's less
shuffling less less fussing and so 2v4
is just a thing that i usually define
math libraries so that you can quickly
get from one to the other really easily
right and they're they're just like you
know if I have a v4 I define two before
which takes a v3 which is like XYZ and
then it takes the W right it's really
really basic right and so the result the
result that X Y Z equals XYZ and it was
all tough W equals W and then it returns
it that's it and I usually just do one
of those for each dimension up and I
guess we only actually have two here
right so if you want to make a v3 it'd
be the same thing right you do something
like this and then it produces that by
by construction and that's it all right
so we're still drawing that there that's
good but now let's go back let's jump
back to our quote-unquote checkerboard
drawing routine so if I draw this guy
here now I can pass a color value to it
and what I want to do is I want to set
the color value equal to this particular
LOD is color right I mean this
particular maps color and what I'll do
there is I'll say all right there's a
map color per index here so we'll just
do map color equals right and we'll
define
three of these map colors so I'm gonna
do before well now we only need three
for the math color
so I'll define it the same way that we
were defining it before where we've got
it red green and blue like so and then
this color will just always be whatever
the map color is initially for the map
index but then once we once we see which
part of the checker we're on we'll
optionally turn it to black right all
right so the min P is also pretty simple
the min P is just the X and the y right
that we have so because this is already
going by the checker with no checker
height so the min pain the max B are
known the color is known so the only
thing that we have to do now is we have
to figure out where we are on the
checkerboard right we have to figure out
essentially which checker we're on I
think I'm gonna instead of doing that by
math in there I think I'm just going to
do it by a toggle so I think I'm to do
it with like checker on right and so
then what I'll say is you know checker
on it'll either be if the checkers on
will be the map color otherwise it will
be black like so and then I'm just going
to set checker on equal to not checker
on like so now in order to do that I
need to alternate on rows as well so
what I'll do there is do it row checker
on like so on and then do checker on
equals row checker on and then Road
checker on excuse me pills not write
checker on I think that should do it
let's see here LOD height sign downside
mismatch so the heights are intz right I
guess so let's take a look here and then
we need to specify what we want our
checker width and height to be and I
guess I'll just call those for now 16 by
16 although I guess our height is less
let's do 8
I agree with you it's getting out the
value in there I don't know what I'm
gonna do there we'll see what we're
gonna do
let's leave the 16 by 16 all right
so there is our checkerboard lovely
isn't it you can actually see our
bilinear filtering in action as well
because I don't know if you can see
there but right in there you've got like
when it's in between two samples it
actually produces the sort of a
different value right it produces an
in-between value so we've reduced our
checkerboard now what's interesting
about this is you'll notice we're not
getting any light anymore on this entire
thing which is particularly interesting
just because I guessing that means that
wherever we're sampling the tree the
tree is is essentially getting into a
situation where it's only picking up
some black texels
I'm guessing that's true and I suspect
that's probably because we haven't also
haven't done any of the stuff for
actually figure out where we should be
looking in the texture map so now be
good time for us to go in there and
actually start to make that happen what
I do want to do though just quickly
before hand is I also want to clear this
guy out because I'd rather just see like
just the normal map would be my
preference so what I want to do is
instead of using that tree I think what
I'm going to do instead is we've got
that tree normal thing here instead of
that I think I'm gonna just full-on make
a test thing which is like you know test
bitmap and test normal map right
I guess we'd call this the diffuse color
I don't know what we'll call it yet
because we're not sure exactly what it
Act what can what it actually would be
relative to our lighting equation but
we'll call this test a fuse and test
normal and then what we'll do is when we
make that tree normal map right right
here instead that's going to be a thing
which actually makes two here so we'll
we'll go ahead and take that test defuse
and say that we want to copy its width
and height and then we want our test
normal to be a sphere normal map with
zero roughness off of that that's the
test well but what we also want to do
here is say game state test diffuse
equals make empty bitmap and that's
gonna be however big we want this guy to
be so I don't know what that's gonna be
for now we'll say that's 256 by 256
maybe that seems reasonable maybe a
little bit large we'll see and then we
will have to fill it with something
again not particularly troublesome there
hmm
I can just do it draw a rectangle call
for that as well so I can do a draw
rectangle into this test diffuse I can
say that I want it to be from zero zero
to its width height all right like so
oops and then I can just say the color
is gonna be like a neutral gray just so
we can kind of see what what it all is
right so okay tree normal is not a
member of game state that's true test
diffuse test normal
and what oh right I always forget when I
change the size of something we don't
support that in the dynamic reload all
right so of course I probably should not
make it the same gray as our background
okay I admit that that may have been a
mistake
because then we can't tell if it's
drawing or not that yeah okay you know I
admit that that was that was that was an
oversight okay
it was definitely an oversight let's try
that again okay there we go so now we've
got that guy in there and now we should
be able to see if we're actually getting
lighting contribution in there when we
start to work with you know the the
actual bounce stuff okay so how much
time we got oh not very much five fifty
four well I guess we won't have time to
do what we want to do here which is
actually go through and worked out the
bounce math but we can do the bounce
math tomorrow that's fine let's just
take a look at what we were doing here
yes so we're not actually doing anything
in terms of figure out where the
sampling is so that's why we aren't
getting a leading contribution it's just
picking the upper corner of the map so
we need to do here as we actually need
to do the work to look up into the map
and see what is actually where you know
what is something and that's actually
figure out some actual value
now we could act we could do something
kind of cheesy right we could do
something where we use like the normal
for example to pick where we want to be
in the map right I mean you could
imagine something that did you know like
a starts with the width and then moves
by that you know moves by the width over
to picking the the normals x-coordinate
right or something like that I'm just
totally making this up but you know what
I mean right
you could imagine something that was
doing sort of a more straightforward
thing here this is not at all what we
want to do but it's something that will
at least pick stuff out of it oops
here we go and hey you can see that it's
sort of starting to get that reflection
in there it's we're not really there yet
because it's it's literally just sort of
using that as almost a deferred texture
lookup but at least we kind of know that
that what we're trying to do is sort of
working right so that's all good I don't
know if those are exactly but well no
those are probably fine bilinear samples
now to think about it so that's that's
probably fine too so yeah I mean it all
looks pretty good I think I just don't
want to get started on trying to
actually do the sampling properly here
because we probably just do not have the
time to actually do that so I'm guessing
that probably I should I should call it
quits and yeah and then we can you know
we could pick up a little bit later we
can pick up this this how we do the
actual math ferret where the sampling
should be tomorrow and we also kind of
got a thing cat keep in the back of our
heads that we got to do something with
them with the middle range the with the
green and I have no idea we're gonna do
with that so we gotta we gotta plan that
out a little bit that's gonna be a bunch
of work I think figuring out how that's
gonna slot in there all right so I guess
we can go ahead to a Q&amp;A the Q&amp;A now
like so on
all right let's do Q&amp;A please prefix
your questions with Q : so I can see
them and please try to keep the
questions on topic I tend to skip
off-topic questions I do off type of
questions on the pre stream so if you
want to ask off-topic questions you can
you just got to come back tomorrow 15
minutes for the stream starts looks
pretty calm though looking pretty calm
poo shoes in the move entity function
you have two variables that are never
used new player play an oboe player P
will you delete them for me will you
delete them for me well I don't know are
they doing anything that we might want
to use later old player P and new player
P yeah this is probably gonna get a
pretty big hatchet take it to it anyway
so if for some reason you really want
them to go away we could delete them yes
that's totally fine
with this scheme let you have a pool of
water reflect a starry sky well the
question is so what would determine that
would really be mostly what you're going
to do with the with the resolution of
these maps I mean yes obviously the
technique will let you do that
but we there's there's a bunch of things
you have to keep in mind in terms of
sampling and so if you think about
what's happening in here I can sort of
give you a little bit of preview of why
that might be a little bit rough just in
terms of of keeping things looking good
so the problem right is that you end up
with when you when you have something
that you're sampling like a reflection
like that right you know you've got
these sort of normals and you've got
bounces that are coming in like whatever
direction are we're looking from we're
bouncing back up and depending on the
normal we're sort of getting different
bounces that may or may not be coherent
into this you know texture map right and
what ends up happening is those bounces
are going to sample this texture map but
they're going to sample it sparsely so
there's no guarantee that you won't get
some really bad artifacting in there
because of the fact that you might be
sampling like very far apart like one
bounce here might sample there and then
the very next bounce may sample like all
the way back here and so you just don't
you don't get the kind of anisotropic
filtering that you might want for a
pretty starry sky reflected in a pool of
water right and so I don't necessarily
guarantee that we're gonna try and solve
that problem because what I'm looking
for here is more lighting and not
reflections and so it will probably do
is end up using fairly low resolution
maps so that you wouldn't really do
reflections the more be for more like
glossy or sort of lighting stuff and not
as much for reflections but I don't know
so that's really why I would say you you
have a bit of an issue there to be
honest with you I don't I'm not really
sure how people normally try to solve
that problem in 3d when they do
typically what they'll do is they'll
render the scene that they'll do
something very similar to what we're
doing they'll render the scene from the
perspective of the of the plane about
that it's bouncing and I just don't know
if they if they do anything fancy to try
and prevent the sampling from getting
ugly or whether it just does get ugly
I'm not sure maybe you turn on like
anisotropic filtering for those textures
to try and well know that an isotropic
filtering is really gonna help I guess
it would so I don't know I don't really
know how they try to fight this when
they're doing a reflection in 3d because
I think they would have the same problem
and I'm not sure how they try to correct
for it it may be that they just don't
and you get sparkly Ness I'm not sure
but that's the thing to watch out for
if you want to see the lighting distort
according to the spherical shape of the
normal map would that just be part of
fixing the math in the section where you
sample from the end map yeah that is
literally it like when we do that
tomorrow it should Bend and then that'll
be that
but until we do we're not actually doing
that so obviously it doesn't behave like
a reflection because we're not
calculating a reflection takes big
surprise right
what are their benefits to having three
top middle bottom and mass versus just
using one nmap for the whole thing uh so
I don't know how I would use one
environment map for the whole thing
because like I don't know how to get
spacial in this to that right like I
don't know how to get height involved
there if I don't make multiple maps if
that makes sense
so really that's most of it if I knew
how to get everything out of one map I
probably would but I can't think of
anything offhand so here's like I'll
just to give you a preview of sort of
what I've been thinking of what I've
been thinking of is there's a ground
right texture which we already made so
what we would do is we'd splat lights
into here right
basically so oh I'll say this the steps
here so here's our ground so for the
ground right you'd splat the ground
texture in there like we were doing
right so we're already doing that
because we want to draw that on the
screen we would then splat the shadows
for those things this for entities on
their right and we might even say take
the shadows and do those in a separate
bitmap so you might actually have ground
and shadows as two different bitmaps
right and then we take the middle map
which is where the lighting is right so
there's lights written into that middle
map right we take that and we draw that
into the ground map so we like add these
lights into the ground map right and
then we've got sort of a ground map that
has lighting in it that's also got the
shadowing in the ground texture then we
have a middle map that just has the
lighting right and then we have a top
map that has none of those things like
the top map just has some sky stuff or
whatever or like whatever is above us
right and then when I'm sampling to try
and get the 3d this out of it I feel
like that will give me sort of a gray
found plus lights down here your ground
plus light bounce basically down here
light in here just light and occlusion
and then you know sky up here which is
what I'm looking for I I don't know how
else to do that with just one
environment map with just one map like I
don't see how that would work
really hey that's basically it
I'm not sure I understand the point of
the bottom map will the ground be
contributing lighting to objects above
the ground yes I mean that's that's what
happens in real life too right like
bounce off the ground is like a big part
of what determines the look of things
that are sitting on the ground and so I
was just gonna see if we could get some
of that in there now once we actually
get all this working if we find that we
don't use one of these we'll just get
rid of it right because we can easily
just save computation by just getting
rid of it so my goal was first to put in
all three see how the effects come out
and anything that we find just isn't
useful we just nuke it and so we could
end up with just the middle map if
that's all we need but if it turns out
that the other ones do add a nice effect
we'll keep them
all righty any other lighting questions
looks like no
well you need a set of end maps for each
level in Z my thinking is yes and I was
thinking that basically what we do is
they would just kind of cascade in some
way right like I'm thinking that we
would basically like start with the
lowest level ground right and that's
gonna get rendered and that would be the
bottom end map and then we you know
after we have the sky map which is
essentially the ground map of the thing
above us sort of like inverted like so
we would take what the Alpha is of the
ground map that we would be using next
right you know if there's an alpha of
the ground which basically tells us
where it is we would use the Alpha map
of that composited with the middle map
of the layer above us would tell us
where the lighting like it's the inverse
alpha of that composited with the
lighting above us middle map lighting
above us would tell us where lights will
be shining down into us so you know
that's how in stacked things we would
get light lights that are moving above
us to be you know sort of shining down I
don't know if we want to go that crazy
but we could right and that just be part
of that process of peeling Z you know of
rendering the bottom first and then up
and up and up
any plans for doing over brightening on
the lights or even HDR um I'm not sure
so I mean basically like I don't think I
want to do HDR just because I'm not sure
how we would really get away with it in
software I mean we could I'm guessing
that the only thing that we'll really be
able to do in terms of over brightening
on the lights is using that middle
buffer possibly using that as like a
bloom kind of a filter or something like
that
but yeah I don't see us being able to
really do HDR in a software pipeline
just because I float16 I don't even know
yeah I mean I guess we could try this
yet now I can't honestly I really can't
think of any way that we would really be
able to do that you know maybe we try to
fit in a separate sort of blur buffer at
some point that that can get a little
bit of the bloom in there or something
like that but but I don't I don't really
see us being able to do much in the way
of of HDR in the software pipe
could you contain all lighting
information in a five byte bitmap 0:25
absorbance reflectance scale for RGB
alpha and scattering I want to try it
but I feel really hesitant because you
weren't against non 32-bit Alliance
trucks so I guess I I don't I mean I
it's it's probably fine I would I
wouldn't say that non 32-bit Alliance
trucks are necessarily a problem because
you're pulling this stuff in sort of as
pixel values anyway and so you could
probably get away with a five bitmap
format I don't know that you'd have too
much problem with that because even if
you did have a problem with that you
could just pack you know a couple of
them together and and sort of have less
of a problem with the was sort of the
unaligned nosov it but I guess what I'd
ask is where does the normal go in that
scheme right that seems like kind of a
kind of the issue
grumpy giant reduce excessive injustice
or to to lighting range gets good
results we could I mean yeah we could do
something where we say that there's you
know a zero to 255 actually Maps you
know 2 to double bright or something
like that I don't know I'll have to
think about it I will have to think
about it I'm not sure how I feel about
it do you plan on camera level lighting
effects such as stun grenade for lack of
a better example I don't know are you
talking about just taking the screen and
overlaying stuff on to it or brightening
it that's pretty easy for us to do
certainly I don't know how much of that
we really need to have in this
particular game but we could totally do
that it's not very hard
if you can do without alpha you could
possibly use RGB e or the e is the
exponent for all the channels uh I mean
it's just it complicates things a lot
through the pipeline if you want to do
HDR properly like if you do RGB for
example you're constantly having to deal
with how you load out and repack that E
which is a real pain now I mean it's
possible I don't know if it's plausible
but it's possible we could do something
with HDR I don't know I'm I would lean
towards not trying to put HDR in here
because I think we have enough stuff to
worry about I'm not sure that I really
want to try and do much with HDR but you
know I mean it's not really the case
that the renderer is completely locked
and difficult to change too much once
you do it I mean you know what's the
architectures in place a lot of times
you can make modifications to it so it's
not out of the question that we could do
it non HDR and then later on make it
more HDR right that's not not really out
of the question but I'm not sure we
could sort of keep an eye on that and
make sure that we don't do things that
will make it really difficult
is saturation hard to overlay no
saturation is actually pretty easy to
overlay if you want to in fact you can
kind of just just pull to the average
like I mean a pretty simple example
right is you know we could we could do a
pretty a pretty easy example of how that
works right so you know with our clear
here where's our clear render entry
clear so if we had something that was
like render entry saturation or
something right
you could imagine having a thing that's
like a saturation value work you can
just do a post pass and change whatever
the saturation ends up being of the
final thing that's not too hard to do it
would basically just be you know I'll
give you a quick sketch of what that
would be like so when we have our clear
we can do a saturation here where it
just passes whatever that saturation
level is I guess we'll just say the
value or the level I don't know what you
would call that level so we can push on
a saturation and set that level to level
and then you know in here when we
actually do whatever our math is which
is here we go we're pulling stuff out
when we grab one of those right render
entry saturation we can do a thing where
we just loop over the output target and
for every pixel that's in there change
its saturation right and so we could
just have a change saturation call which
takes the output target and you know
just takes that
level parameter and if I go to draw
rectangle like so if I take that out
actually don't want that exactly what
I'd rather have is draw a bitmap
probably okay here we go
so if I take draw bitmaps code and
change that to change saturation and I
just say okay I've got the buffer that
I'm changing and the saturation level
then what I could do is is force this
thing to loop over everything right so
just go ahead and do jestro this and
just have that loop over everything in
the buffer so both width and height full
width and height
it doesn't read any texels or anything
like that right but it does read in the
desc like so and really all that you
would do here is when you have this this
destination that comes in instead of of
actually doing any blending with the
text or anything that you can just sort
of desaturate it right and so one way to
desaturate it pretty easy way in fact I
guess what I should do is just double
check that I haven't ruined anything
here but so let's just go ahead and say
that result equals D for now yeah so if
I go in here here's what here's our
screen as it stands currently if I go in
here to handmade CPP and I add a
saturation in like so so we do right
before our render output I do saturation
render group zero point zero so that
would remove like well actually I guess
well yeah that should give us the same
screen we had right and so now if I come
in here and and actually make this do
something what you can imagine
you can imagine like the saturation is
sort of how far from gray something is
in some sense you might say and so you
know we could convert to the HSV color
space and convert back or whatever but
you know that might be a little
expensive although there's cheaper ways
of doing it now so we can look at all
those but I'll just show you a real
quick way to do something stupid which
is you know you can imagine your RG and
B values right you know we're sort of
imagining them between zero and one
right and they're kind of sticking like
this sort of thing right and what we
could say is well what if we just
average them together right so we did
like R plus G Plus B you know over three
or something right so we just took
whatever the average was and then we
represented these as deltas off of that
well then we could just multiply the
deltas by whatever our saturation amount
is and we'd go further or less away from
gray right and so it's pretty trivial to
hack in something like that again
without having to do a whole HSV
transformer although people have gotten
those down really cheap so we you know
if we really find that we want to do
this and we want to do it accurately we
could probably just do a real thing but
you know so I'm just gonna do that
average here is going to be one over
three right times the R plus the G plus
the B so this is just the average color
value and you can do better things for
grace to estimation here because there's
suck you know there's like your eyes
more response or the green and that sort
of stuff so you could do fancier stuff
here to get the grayscale value really
just you just want to plug in here
anything that produces a grayscale value
from the are the G and the B right and
so then you've got your your delta is
just going to be the are the G and the B
minus that average value right so it's
whatever you would have to do to get to
those color values from wherever you are
you know what I'm saying so once you
have that delta value then what you can
do is just reconstruct the new color
right and or I could just say right I
have a V for a result and that's just
going to be you know my average excuse
me that's just going to be my average
vector plus whatever that level is times
my Delta right so if it's 1.0 it adds it
all back in if it's zero it doesn't have
any back in right and then I want to
keep the Alpha value the same because
we're not we're not changing the you
know the the brightness the the sort of
opacity I should say of the thing I
forgot these are a lowercase now still
in my hand made hero like oh I gotta be
uppercase before so you know as you can
see now it's black and white right and
what we can do is we could drive that
off of an animated parameter so you can
see that it's actually you know doing
something we have that that gamestate
time thing in here angle is that getting
reset yeah angle is getting reset so I
guess I just want my game state time
here so I could just do game state time
0.5 F plus 0.5 times sign game state
time let's do that and in theory I guess
that's going to be able to slope times
Lisa will speed that up a little bit
yeah
so our framerate is awful at the moment
obviously so you know because we're
still super unoptimized and all that but
you can kind of see that we're you know
desaturating and and you know and on
desaturating how everyone put that but
again that's not really an accurate way
to do it
but that's basically what you would do
so what you want to do here if you want
to be a little bit better about that
right is you can just what you want to
do is do a fast HSV transform and then
you know and then do well you know I'm
not even sure that how much more
accurate that even is but if you did it
fast HSV transform and then did a fast
back that would that would basically be
what you would need right and so that's
that's just how that go so hopefully
that makes some sense
you
will like it reflective horizontally
from walls etc in this scheme so
potentially that's that's really the
part that's that's kind of what we're
talking about with that middle layer and
like I said we don't really know yet how
well we're gonna be able to do there but
that middle layer is what we'll be
trying to use to get some of that bounce
that local bounce so I don't know a lot
of this is just you know like I said I
don't know how well it's going to work
it might be awful it might be cool I
have no idea
lighting in 2d is always kind of just a
you know hmm he's always just a hack and
so it's how well you end up tuning your
hack to it works or not right and so
we'll we'll kind of see how much we
actually can get out of it now we can
over saturate it's true we can over
saturate I guess by cranking that value
so all right no more questions
seems like all right I'm gonna go ahead
and close down I guess I'll saturation
that we'll leave that in there just I
mean might as well but there we go okay
save the mischief
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for another episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
at home and you want to copy the source
code you can get that by pre-ordering
the game and you'll get an email that'll
give you a link that you can use to
download the source code every night
after I'm done I upload it so you can
check it out and just play around with
it and learn and you know it's a good
way to learn to sort of thinker with if
that makes sense we also have a patreon
page if you just want to support the
video series you can subscribe to that
it's always very appreciated we also
have a forums page that you can ask
questions on or look at an annotated
episode guide the communities put
together and also look at community
reports to Mac and Linux which can be
really helpful if you're trying to
follow along another platform and you're
not that familiar with that platform
people have done a lot of work a lot of
groundwork there's two and make that
easy for you there's also a tweet bot
which treats the schedule so if you want
to follow along with the live stream
that's the thing to check out and
speaking of that we will be back here 5
p.m. same time same place tomorrow right
here on Twitch 5:00 p.m. Pacific
Standard Time hope to see you all here
when we will do our correct equation for
bounce lighting which we really do need
to do because like you saw today we have
absolutely no curvature to our
reflection which is not good at all so
we'll be getting that fixed and then
we'll sort of be moving on to maybe
wills take a look at that fixing our
coordinate systems before we start
moving on to things like optimization
and of course trying to fill those light
fields with something more usable than
just red green and blue checkerboards so
thanks for joining us I hope to see you
tomorrow
and whether I do or don't please have a
fabulous Tuesday out there on the
Internet
take it easy everyone