start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade Hero the show recode
a complete game live on stream you know
yesterday I asked for some people to
post in the forums and we didn't get
very much post in the forums just ok cuz
maybe no one knows the answers to the
question I was asking but I will say
that even just on last night's dream I
don't know who it was who originally
posted the link to the MIT
OpenCourseWare video that i retweeted on
the on the on the tweet stream here this
if you if you go to the tweet bot i
retweeted it somewhere here this this
right here this guy i thought that was a
pretty good lecture i it was still a
little opaque in some parts but honestly
like it actually clarified a fair number
of things for me on the whole PNP thing
and why you often hear people either
saying wrong things or saying things
that sound conflicting and you're just
like wait a minute I don't understand
what are we actually saying here well
like I said before I don't want to go
into PNP kind of stuff too much because
I don't really know anything about it so
it doesn't make any sense for me to talk
about it on the stream but I do like
mentioning stuff like this just as sort
of a sides because I feel like it maybe
encourages people to go learn about
these things so I'm just gonna briefly
say what was on that video and hope that
maybe some of you out there will be
interested in it and you'll go take a
look at it because obviously you can
watch that video and it's MIT
OpenCourseWare so you could then go
watch a whole bunch of videos about this
and maybe get interested in some of the
theoretical CS stuff which is again not
something we cover on handmade hero and
not something I know but so here was the
interesting diagram that he drew in that
lecturer that I thought was pretty great
and I think I figured out based on the
way he was talking where one of my
biggest confusions about how people talk
about things like P and NP came in and
so I'll just briefly say what those were
again please don't take anything about
to say as instructive because I am NOT a
theoretical computer science person so I
don't know I'm merely telling you what
my impression was of this thing so he
drew a pretty cool diagram and it kind
of looked like this where he sort of
said like okay let's pretend that we
just have some notion of how difficult a
problem is and he said I didn't really
want to talk too much about that because
in order to get more specific you had to
start using terms that had very specific
definitions and this is just meant to
sort of a blanket picture so he didn't
want to say complexity or anything like
that but so he just said difficult like
the problems get harder as we go in this
direction so like the hardest problems
would be out here and the easiest
problems would be here and then he sort
of like started like dividing up this
line and what he did was he said like
okay let's go ahead and talk about where
things are in terms of like when we're
saying P or NP what do we mean when
we're talking about those things and he
drew something that looked basically
like this
he said that P was like from here to
here right and he's like you know NP is
from here to here and then he goes like
okay you know here is exp right which
was something that I think I mentioned
on the chat yesterday and then he was
like okay then here is like R so he drew
this little thing so already just having
this this simple diagram and remember I
I got confused on last dream although I
think I kind of had this Osmo sized
inner diffused into my brain for him
because I was kind of thinking about it
in a different way but remember NP is
non-deterministic polynomial time and we
could talk about that a bit later but
that's just like you know P is
definitely polynomial time we talked
about that yesterday and this is not to
respond all the time all right and these
we don't know what they are yet all
right so the first thing that
immediately was kind of clarifying for
me when you do this diagram was like oh
I get it the reason why you start to get
confused when you hear people talk about
stuff with P and NP even if you don't
even know what they mean is because NP
is always like thought of as
superset of P right so it's not like
this is P and this is NP right it's like
this is P and NP includes all of P in it
right and so somebody might say that
something was in NP even though it was
actually polynomial time and they're not
wrong
does that make sense so like already
that was kind of nice to see it drawn so
clearly we're like oh these the way that
computer scientists chose to break this
down they didn't make the sets exclusive
they made them like inclusive so it's
like polynomial time is some set of
algorithms non-deterministic polynomial
time is like a bigger set that includes
all of the original set right an exp and
R and keep keep going out from there so
like okay that's that's really nice like
that was pretty clarifying I thought
that was pretty good just to start with
okay the next thing that he said that
was really helpful I thought and he kind
of didn't say this in the clearest way
possible so I apologize maybe I
misunderstood him but it seemed he
seemed like after he said a bunch of
things that kind of like routed you know
zeroed in on this and I if this is
actually the way the computer science
fear theory people talk about it then
now I understand why a lot of things
they said weren't making sense before so
this would be pretty great too and that
is we mentioned np-hard in that it
always seems to be used weird or used
wrong and like I said on the previous
thing I was like I don't even know what
it means like I don't want to pretend to
know I don't know I'll probably just get
it wrong well this is sort of clarified
as well and the np-complete thing which
was also kind of annoying and when you
hear people say it and blah blah blah
and you never really know what any of
this stuff is well he clarified that too
which is pretty great what he basically
said after going through a bunch of
things was that hard means basically
greater than or equal to right and this
the equal to part was the part that
always confused me because I thought
when they said CS things they usually
meant greater than so I thought when
they would say something like np-hard
what that meant was that it was like
outside of NP like it was to this
of NP right it's empty hard meaning I
can't solve it using an NP algorithm
right that's what I thought they meant
but that's not what they mean when they
say NP hard they mean greater than or
equal to NP which I which never sunk in
for me so what that means is that like
right at this point where you transition
from NP to X they're actually saying
well it's either right at that point or
this this direction so it could still be
in NP but it's definitely not easier
than anything in mp it's not right
because these problems would you know if
we imagine that we started breaking up
NP problems into some finer
discretization of how hard they were
np-hard means that it's at the very end
of those problems but it might still be
there right so it's greater than or
equal to it might be right there or it
could be out here right but it might
still be there so greater than or equal
to that was like a big thing that was
like oh that's nice now I get it
when they say that it makes sense where
it lines up so that's pretty cool
second great thing from that lecture
okay third great thing is finally saying
what np-complete actually really means
at least as far as the the part that I
thought had always been kind of
confusing about it
np-complete doesn't actually mean that
something is in NP that's not what they
use that term to mean again a assuming
that I understood what he was saying in
this lecture correctly what they
actually mean by np-complete is that
they have proved both that it is in NP
right meaning that that the first part
of what you know the part that I would
have thought np-complete meant they have
proved that it is in NP so it's
somewhere in here right but they have
also proved it it is empty heart meaning
that it has np-complete means literally
this one point right here so np-complete
does not mean that something like if
something was in here if it was an
easier problem in the NP space for
whatever that means and I don't pretend
to know but if it was an easier problem
than the hardest problems at NP its not
MP complete its it may be in NP and it
may be not in P
not that we can prove that yet because
the whole thing about whether P equals
NP right these might be the same but
assuming they weren't the same it might
be not in P and it may be in NP but it
might still not be NP complete because
if it isn't NP hard if it's not the
hardest type of problem in NP then you
wouldn't call it NP complete right now
again we don't even know if that's
possible like we don't know if it's
possible for something to be in NP and
that B and P complete like like I don't
even know they didn't cover any of that
so you need a real computer science
theory guy to start talking about what
else what other possibilities there are
but I really liked that part was like oh
okay I think I get it now I mean to the
extent that a non theoretician is going
to get it I think I get it now what you
mean when you say NP complete you're
saying that it's right here it's as hard
as any other problem in NP and is in NP
so it's not out here right and that was
kind of solidifying okay so the other
things that I thought were good in here
is he talked about what's outside
because that came up on the chat I asked
about that I was like what is it called
you know what are the heart of things
are there heart of things do we know the
law and it turns out that we do know a
couple things
exp is exponential time right and I
talked about that
which was like two to the end or
whatever right exp is exponential time R
is finite time which just means it it
finishes like like I can be solved in in
eons perhaps but not an infinite amount
of time it doesn't take an infinite time
and he said we do have examples of
things that are in our but that are not
in any of these so like this space out
here right does have problems in it
and he said that there are problems
outside of our so this space out here
does so like the halting problem which
is just given a program can you tell
whether it will ever actually finish or
whether it will loop forever that
problem is you know out here apparently
again he just mentioned that kind of
offhand to the lecture and you know he
said they'd go into that later and
whatever but anyway so it did kind of
answer to these questions what he said
and this was sort of what we talked
about with the P equals NP thing you
know being a
question he just basically said well you
know we don't know if this region really
exists for all we know P and NP might be
the same so like this might move you
know all the way out to here someday and
we just have that and then he also
seemed to imply and I don't really know
again not being a CS theory person I was
like really okay I mean you know I cool
he seemed to imply the same was true for
NP + X he was saying that they didn't
it's ever at least it sounded like they
didn't even really know whether any of
this range was actually partitioning
ball it might be that P just goes all
the way out to R and then there's R so
there's just P n R it sounded like that
but maybe I misinterpreted we was saying
again that's not something I have any
idea about not a CS person so no idea
but anyway at least this stuff was
pretty much easier to understand in his
lecture than I've ever seen it presented
before so that was pretty great
it's a really easy lecture to watch it
doesn't require any fancy math or
anything and you know it he explains it
in very intuitive way most of most of
the things so I thought that was all
pretty cool and so I would highly
recommend if you think any of that's
interesting to go check out that lecture
it's an easy thing to watch it's fun
sometime you just put it on and check it
out and maybe you'll get interested in
some of this stuff like I said it's all
pretty interesting I've never really had
time to look into it that's why I don't
know any of it but that doesn't mean
it's not interesting to know so maybe
check it out give it something that
piques your interest what I will say did
not go so well cuz that went great I was
like awesome that clarifies so many
things maybe we can avoid making any
more Naumann clay sure mistakes on the
stream if I ever refer to this stuff
which I don't know what I will but if I
do that was really great I think it
would help me in the future just having
this mental picture it would help me
from making stupid mistakes when I'm
trying to you know refer to something
right but the thing that did not go so
well was traveling salesmen and so
traveling salesmen I still want if
somebody who's somebody who's a serious
CS person ever watches the stream and
wants to explain this a little bit
better I would love to hear it so one
thing that was clarified and this I mean
you know again I don't really think this
is all that relevant
you know at least explains to the
confusion if people said well the NP
part like obviously these MP things they
only deal with what's called decision
problems right and we didn't really talk
about that yesterday because again it's
it's more CS theory kind of stuff but a
decision problem is just something that
returns like true or false right it's
like bool function of something right
it's like that's what we're talking
about so the thing can return true or
false that's the only kinds of functions
that they talk about when they're trying
to talk about NP
you know why I don't pretend to know
that's CS theory stuff like I said so
don't know but that's what they were
talking about so when they're talking
about this class of NP problems they're
talking about things that can be phrased
like this so obviously traveling
salesmen the one I refer to when I
described it is find the shortest path
right it was like a graph theory thing
and we were saying oh there's these
points in the graph find the shortest
path through them right it was like you
know if I've got some network of things
here and basically I have a series of
nodes like so and I want to know I want
to visit all the nodes right and I want
to visit all the nodes and I want to
know the shortest route I could take
that would visit all the nodes at least
once right each node has to get hit
what's the shortest path that would do
that right and so what people were
saying as well the decision version of
this is we could we could turn that into
because because if I want do that I'd
have to return a path right
I can't phrase that as bool F because if
I want to find a shortest path will I
need to return the path right it's a
sequence it's like oh well start at node
1 and go to node 5 and then fort right
it has to return some some string of
digits and a string of digits is not a
boolean right
and so what they do to turn this into a
decision problem is they say well okay
in order to turn this into a decision
problem we'll just say is there a path
shorter than some length that I'm going
to give you so I'll say okay
is there a path that reaches all the
nodes that's shorter than length 15 now
that's true or false right definitely
true or false so now you can phrase it
in in terms of this but you won't
actually be able to you won't have the
problem that we talked about yesterday
of not being able to verify the path
because now you don't have to verify
that its shortest you just have to
verify that it's 15 or less and you can
do that by just walking the path right
because one of the things is in this
bool even though they're phrased this
way the answer is still expected to be
shown meaning you're still it's still
supposed to be able to show you this
inside so what you should be able to do
is walk the path add up the values and
end up with something less than 15 and
verify that you visit all the node once
obviously we could do that trivially so
we don't have to worry about the problem
I talked about yesterday of not having a
verifier that runs in polynomial time so
we could do that right and so what
people were claiming is well that means
that traveling the regular Traveling
Salesman problem could easily be
considered you know NP in terms of how
hard it is because all you have to do is
if you have if you had one of these that
told you whether it was you know you
could pass in is it less than 15 or
whatever right and it would tell you yes
or no then what you could do is you
could just call that with a binary
search on the you know the number right
you could just say oh is there one
that's less than 4000 no yeah okay
is there one that's less than 8000 right
and you could just keep picking numbers
and binary search till you found the the
thing and then that number and that path
would be the shortest path okay what I
don't understand about that though what
I don't understand about that activation
is why I say that I didn't feel like we
quite got an explanation about
travelling salesmen for the layman about
whether it actually would be considered
NP or not in the sense that again it's
not a certain problem so I can't really
be but how hard is it is it exponential
or not the reason that it's a little bit
that's a little assassin to me is
assuming that we've got a cost for each
of the
routes you know like this is five and
this is ten or whatever right the person
who constructs this graph could just
make sure that the weight of the the the
costs here you know if there's n nodes
right in this graph because this is what
we're talking about the the complexity
of this is you know oh two to the N
currently we don't or actually no it's
it's factorial I think right I think
that's what traveling salesman is I
don't remember but point being gets n
factorial point being if you have n
nodes right and what you're saying is
well if we proved P equal to NP then I
could give you a polynomial time
algorithm that would tell you whether
for a given size right whatever that is
whether or not there was a path then I
just binary search well that means
there's some polynomial time thing right
and then it's gonna be log you know n
times that polynomial time oh isn't that
in P well the thing that I have a
problem of is this n the N is not the
same in here right what it's gonna be
log in is the sum of the route lengths
right which is not part of the
definition of the original n the route
links are just freely settable so if I
wanted to be if I wanted to be mean what
I would do is I'd set the total route
links in fact I can just set every route
length because I'm being very mean I
could just set the but I could just set
the route links to be something that
adds up to two to the two to the N right
now just because you take log base two
of it you still end up with a running
time right you're taking log base two of
this value well now you still end up
with log base 2 of 2 to the 2 to the N
which hey is just two n times P which is
still exponential right so my feeling is
that in order to claim that we would
actually be able to solve the Traveling
Salesman time in polynomial time given
that P equalled NP if someone proved
this someone would have to explain to me
how that's actually going to work when
you can when you can feel free to it
seemingly confound that by just setting
the route lengths to be sufficiently
large that a binary search of them takes
to end time now maybe it's just well you
can be clever about how you binary
search like binary search the the actual
breakpoints of the things but then it
assumes that you know how you might
traverse the paths which should be 2 n
different possible ways and so I don't
know I am unconvinced Casey remains
unconvinced that if P equals NP then
real travelling salesman not the
decision problem but real traveling
salesman could be done in P time so that
doesn't mean I think that that's wrong
it just means because like I said not a
cs30 person so I have no business saying
wrong or not what I am saying is this
explanation didn't convince me this
explanation sounds like it's really just
a cop-out and I could still construct
problems that make it so you take to to
the end time because a real solution the
Traveling Salesman the wit in P time
would not care what the route lengths
are the route links are just numbers
that are input to it but this is very
dependent on those route lengths which
introduces a whole other problem and so
someone would have to say to me oh but
that problem is also solved when P hears
that solution right so I'd like to see
that before I'm willing to say okay so
Traveling Salesman still remains a
little bit of a nastiness there but at
least we got into why there was
confusion because people who are saying
it was an MP we're talking about the
decision problem they're definitely
right about that because that was
mentioned in the lecture so that's not a
question the question is more just
actual travelling salesmen what's the
deal there right so if you are a CS
person whoever ends up watching this
lecture and wants to do the handmade
hero community or at least me a favor
and post
that explanation is I would love to see
it just out of curiosity because hey I
guess nobody really thinks P will ever
be proven equal to MP anyway so it's
largely academic but so is CS theory
it's largely academic and it's it's
interesting what can I say all right so
hopefully that doesn't make you
aggravated hopefully that makes you
interested in going to watch that
lecture because I know I had a great
time watching it and I hope that other
people will too
thank you very much to ever post
originally it was it long boolean I
don't remember who posted it on the chat
please take credit where credit is due
for posting that initially someone
posted on the chat like yesterday and
and I washed it last night and it was
great all right so let's get back to to
our sorting situation here and the
practical part of this right like I said
all the CS theory stuff the reason I
don't know it is cuz it never really
comes up so I've never really been able
to justify going to study it but the
order notation part the simple part of
just figuring out what the scalability
is and algorithms I really do feel like
it comes up a lot
Tom Forsythe and I had exchanged on
Twitter yesterday actually where he was
saying he he was expecting me to rant
about how it wasn't useful I don't know
I think it is useful what can I say bye
I love to rant you know I love to rant I
love to complain about things or
notations not one of them I think it's a
great thing I'm glad that CS
theoreticians works that stuff out I
think about it all the time when I'm
doing stuff if I'm working something
like oh that's gonna be N squared like I
think I'm in my head and I'm glad that
you know that that sort of framework had
been put in place for me the other stuff
that I don't know the exp the R that's a
do I see how I'd ever use that not
really but you know at the same time
like I said it's all interesting so
that's good anyway and maybe someday it
will be big you know maybe if I knew it
really well I would be able to use it
you know you never know until you
actually know something really well it's
hard to say whether it's gonna be
practically useful because you don't
know it so that's usually the case with
math stuff when you learn it you're like
oh you know what maybe I could use that
maybe there's something I could do with
that so anyway back to sorting we talked
yesterday very briefly about the fact
that our bubble squirt was sort was N
squared and the reason that we were
saying that it was N squared was because
it takes n passes right
/ n things right we have the the
elements that we're trying to sort and
we have to do n passes over that right
so n passes times n things is M squared
that was very easy and we could see it
directly because actually I guess I
don't have my code up yet but when we
looked at the actual code in handmade
code handmade render grip when we have
our sort here see here there it is you
can actually just see it here is the
outer loop here's the inner loop if I
multiply the number of things here it's
count times and everything's here count
minus 1 I get count squared - count
which is obviously going to grow at the
order of count squared now just in case
that confuses people I know we said it a
couple times just want to make sure
everyone understands if I say something
like the running time of this thing is N
squared plus n why do we then say oh
it's just N squared
why do we say that where does the n go
well the reason is because I only care
about the worst case term because like I
said you know N squared looks like this
n looks like that as soon as I want to
only talk about what happens at the
limit of this thing well this dominates
I don't care how much this is that's so
minor at this point I don't care so this
Plus this is not really my concern right
I only care about this so when we do
order notation we're strictly talking
about hustling scales we could write
this if we wanted to be a little more
Civic nothing wrong with it but in
general we don't really care we don't
care about this that much because this
will dominate as we get out to those
those higher numbers and it just doesn't
matter that there's an extra n in there
because this is what's gonna kill you
right so again that's because we're
talking about scaling it's sort of like
when you you know in math you let when
you try to let things go to infinity you
only care about certain things cuz other
things disappear it's a little bit like
that you only care about the dominant
term when you're talking about scaling
and these other terms that just will
never be able to grow that fast it
doesn't matter even if they were you
know at higher constants or something
it's just not gonna matter right so you
can see in here that's what we had and
this bubble sort was gonna have to take
count passes over count minus 1 things
and that's just too slow
right again if we have a lot of items
now why isn't it a problem in our
current thing we don't have enough
enemies and that brings us to the first
thing that we should really point out
here and that is scaling only matters if
you actually scale right and so one of
the problems with order notation is that
it only really kicks in once you have a
lot of items right what it's designed to
do is to say what happens if we want to
do these things in bulk a huge number of
them it's very good at answering that
question it's not very good at telling
you what to do if you don't have very
many things and unfortunately very many
things can differ quite a bit depending
on the algorithm and why does it differ
well if you remember I talked a little
bit yesterday about constants what I
said was that well if I want to talk
about the order of something
execution-wise I say that there's some
constant right maybe I say there's C -
you know M squared plus C 1 and plus C 0
right and what I'm talking about here is
like the cost for doing the N squared
part of things right whatever that part
of the algorithm is is might be one
thing the cost for doing the linear part
might be another and then there might
just be some overhead
right some startup cost it doesn't
matter how many things I process I'm
always gonna pay it right you can
imagine this being a very kind of like
crude way of talking a little bit about
how much it costs to execute something
right and what you can see from this
sort of thing here is that these C's
will not matter at all
when I let and get very large right as n
gets very large right billions trillions
infinity when it gets very large only
the biggest term will count right only
the biggest term because it doesn't
matter what the C is unless the C is 0 n
squared will be so much larger than n by
the time we get out to those very large
numbers that even if the C one part
right was very very very even if the C
one part was very very big and
two part was very very small so that at
the beginning the N squared term even
though it's a larger term was getting
multiplied by very small coefficient
right eventually I'll get so that n
square is so big that no matter how tiny
this is it doesn't matter right so when
we talk about order notation we're sort
of what talking about what happens at
the limit as we scale this thing and
that's why we care about this part about
what this highest exponent is that's why
that's what we say N squared that's why
we say that about it right but since we
are not always at the limit when we're
talking about game programming and
practical programming things the C's
actually matter and so what happens is a
vote how many items are you sorting well
I don't know let's find out actually how
many items are we sorting you know it's
not infinity I'll give you a hint so
let's go ahead and break there on that
guy sort entries sort entries let's go
ahead and run there here's a typical
call to store instances probably
rendering our cutscene and count just
one okay great so that's that that's one
let's count
now let's see here also one can we ever
get more than 179 there we go
looks like 80 is somewhere around where
we're at let's try running the game this
is the cutscene let's see where that's
at County is a hundred count is 160 yeah
so what we're talking about curious it's
not that large right it's 160 that's the
number so what that means is that 160
well you know what's 160 squared all
right 25,000 anyone here think that a
computer has trouble processing 25,000
things No
so one of the problems that were faced
with very frequently when we're dealing
with actual practical usage
these things is we may be below the
point where the numbers are growing
large enough to start ignoring what the
seas are or even carrying what the seas
are so it may be for example one common
thing is that let's say we have
something that's N squared and something
that's n but the number of things we're
doing is so low that these values don't
actually come out to be very large right
so maybe our n squared is 25,000 right
so we have one thing that would do
something 160 times and one things that
would do it 25,000 times right those
would be the two algorithms this is
algorithm a this is algorithm B they
both do the same thing one so N squared
1 so n we know that this will do 160
this does turn in twenty twenty-five
thousand well how much slower would each
operation in B have to be in order for
it to be s slow as a well we already
know it's doing a hundred sixty things
so if it was a hundred and sixty times
slower that would be enough right well
what sort of thing is on the magnitude
of a hundred and sixty times slower a
cache miss right you will oftentimes
wait for hundreds of cycles on a cache
miss depending on the processor and so
if B was an extremely extremely cache
unfriendly thing to do let's say don't
know how but let's say it was and a was
extremely extremely cache friendly you
might see the kind of thing worse for a
lot of workloads a was actually somehow
faster and B was slower now if you crank
that number up to like 100 billion all
of a sudden there's no way you're ever
gonna want to do anything other than one
because a will take forever but if you
never do that all bets are off
right furthermore the other thing that
may happen and I'm gonna mention
quicksort here pretty soon because it's
relevant is that remember when we talk
about Oh N squared versus Oh n we are
talking about worst case right we talked
about this yesterday when we say
something's Oh M squared we don't mean
that it takes Oh N squared
time we mean that it might take oh in
squared time it could often only take oh
end time it could often take oh one time
we have no idea how much time it might
take
we just know it won't take more than N
squared running time right and so what
might very well happen is there might be
a great algorithm that's Oh N squared
but it almost always performs its work
actually in Oh n time and so as the case
with sorts for example we know that this
is quicksort right here we haven't
talked about it yet quicksort is an O n
squared algorithm right merge sort
the one that I talked about the other
day is actually o log n well and log n
right and we talked about what that
means right so it's log base two so it's
the it's two to the x equals n solve for
X right it's it's what 2 raised to what
power equals n so a very flattening
function no matter how big you make end
this comes out to be a pretty small
number because it's log base two right
it's the opposite of how nasty this is
it's like a very good thing it's it's
sort of reducing our number by a lot so
we have an O log N and log N and we have
an O n squared now quicksort actually
I'm telling you these two sorts this one
you've seen this one you haven't seen
yet quicksort is Oh N squared merge sort
is Oh n log n however the C runtime
library chose to implement this one this
is the default sort now why on earth
would they do that why would they make
the default sort the N squared when they
know full well there is a trivial I mean
I showed you how easy it was we did it
on the blackboard right a trivial sort
that would not have been that way and
the answer is because quicksort most of
the time actually doesn't go n squared
most of the time quick sorts actually Oh
n that's this expected running time is
not N squared and it turns out that it's
expected running time in practice when
measured is often times faster than
merge sort at least back in the day when
they were running on the kinds of
machines
that they were using for the C runtime
library when that was being developed
right so that's another thing that can
happen is you can get caught up thinking
about the worst case that the worst case
isn't actually the one that you ever hit
where you hit it very rarely and don't
care
for example now that's where the thing
tends to make me pretty nervous I don't
like knowing that there's some kind of
worse case hiding in my thing that might
make me explode but you know again it
depends on the app application it tends
on what you're doing if it's the case
that it means like one frame out of a
billion you hit a stutter maybe that's
fine because let's face it the graphics
driver an Adobe Acrobat and whatever
other garbage the user has running on
their machine the updater for
again the updater for flash might decide
to run right in the middle of your game
and that's tons of lag frames right
there maybe the fact that sometimes once
in a blue moon in this rare case you get
just the right input to guilt om squared
on some album that wasn't that way maybe
that's fine right but if it's something
that's absolutely time critical and you
know that you cannot afford something
like that maybe it's not such a good
decision and then maybe even though you
know that this will be faster most of
the time maybe you pick this because you
don't want to risk having that just
perfectly Allah the stars aligned and I
went M squared on my quicksort right so
that's another thing to be aware of is
that when you look at these order
notation things you need to be aware of
what they're telling you is the worst
thing that could happen they're not
necessarily telling you the average or
expected or anything else they're just
kind of saying hey ma'am
this is what what could happen in the
worst case alright so let's talk about
some other sorts here just kind of
briefly I'll talk about some of the ones
that we that have been mentioned and
I'll just briefly sort of say what they
are before we get around it know if
we'll have time today to really write
one where because I kind of decided it
was we need a more blackboard time bathe
because I kind of wanted to talk about
some of the stuff that I saw in that
that cool lecture yesterday all right so
anyway let's talk about some sorting
algorithms here and what they what they
do so you know that there was the bubble
sort we talked about that one already I
showed you
sort which is just we break the problem
down to pieces sort the pieces and then
merge the pieces together so we have
bubble sort
we have merge sort then we've got
quicksort which we haven't talked about
yet but this is the default one in the C
runtime library this is the one that's
in the CRT so if you actually go and you
look at the function Q sort kind of grab
it here you can see this one here this
one typically is implemented by
quicksort that's why it's called Q sort
now I don't actually know if it's
required to be quicksort it may be that
the spec allows you to implement
whatever you want I don't really know
I'm not a spec slower kind of a person
but point being it's called Q sort
because that's what it traditionally was
so that's a common one because you know
you'd see that we've also have in this
list one that got mentioned a couple
times on the stream which is radix sort
and that's kind of a very special kind
of odd sort and I feel like these are
all the ones that got mentioned Oh
insertion sort
where's mentioned as well and this one I
don't ever I don't think I've ever done
really okay I think I have done a pseudo
insertion sort I think I have done a
pseudo insertion sort we'll talk about
that something that's sort of like an
insertion sort I don't think I've ever
really done a full insertion sort okay
so let's talk about these so bubble sort
we know what it was we said it's Owen
squared we've been over that a dozen
times now hopefully everyone understands
why and everyone understands how you
implement this right you just go through
all the items and you just swap any oops
did that come out I hope I didn't just
ruin my my plug there you double-check
that disaster disaster I did order some
longer cables for this so I'm opening
that
hoping that I won't have this problem
anymore once they finally arrive yeah
okay I'm still on that side so I'm sorry
back to what I was saying so yeah so
bubble sort we know what so n squared
you just go through all the elements and
you keep moving them up if they're
supposed to be up or down sir supposed
to be down and if you know
you do that end-times you know that even
if something was all the way at the end
it will be all the way at the top you
have to do em passes over n things
ergo it is N squared
now the merge sort we know that it's
basically the same thing in terms of at
the low level we have to do passes over
and items every time but we only have to
do log n of them so it's log n log n
right this is n passes over n items and
this is log and passes over n items
right okay so quicksort is actually kind
of a weird it's it's really a pretty
weird algorithm and the reason that I
say that quicksort is a pretty weird
algorithm is because to me it feels
almost like a randomized algorithm in
fact there are randomized quicksort but
it's not usually discussed in the terms
of a randomized algorithm because it's
often implemented I think even the CRT
implementation of it is not done
randomly it's not done it's it's not
done with any randomness in some sense
so how does quicksort work first I will
tell you that it's Oh N squared and I
don't know that we're going to try and
prove that here because some of these
things as we go through them radix sort
is probably easy an insertion sort is
probably easy but quicksort
I don't remember it may be kind of hard
to see why it's N squared unless you got
some CS skills but let's see
so quicksort is sort of a little bit
like the merge sort it's based on
breaking things up but unlike the merge
sort which does it kind of in a very
deterministic way which breaks it down
to like individual pairs and then merges
the pairs and up into bigger bigger
elements that goes it uses what's called
a partition and so I'm gonna go over
here and talk about that so it just does
a partition pass first right well my
handwriting just gets worse and worse it
does what's called a partition I blame
the tablets I feel like if I was
actually writing on chalkboard or
something I'd be fine anyway it is a
partition pass to basically break up
things into groups based on how they
relate to one particular value in the in
the
set of things so for example if I have a
bunch of stuff in here five nine four
three one two seven like so what a
quicksort will do is quicksort will say
all right I got to start sorting this
the first thing to do is pick what's
called a pivot which is one of the
elements although I guess technically it
wouldn't have to be one of the almost
it's just some number right so I'm going
to pick a pivot and I'm gonna break this
group up into two smaller groups based
on where they land relative to the pivot
right so maybe I say the pivot in this
case is three because that's just what I
happen to pick and so I break this up
into things that are less than three or
less than or equal to depend on when I
do it but let's just say less than three
so in this case we have one and two and
then I do things that are more than
three or equal to right because I need
to put the three itself in there
somewhere
and so then I would have like okay more
than equal to three it's like okay got
three four five what's seven nine right
so now what you immediately know right
is that these things always come before
these things so unlike in our merge sort
because remember our merge sort when we
broke it down to pieces we had no idea
what order the pieces came in that's why
we had to at every step we had to do a
merge we had to do a merge
every time figure out where things go
but after this partition we know that
the one and two come first and the three
four five seven nine they come after
right that makes sense so you've already
figured out part of your sort you and
you can do this in place right you could
imagine doing this in place where you
just kind of swap things out as
necessary right I could like I could
just go oh I got to do less than you
know and more than three I can imagine
kind doing in place or if I don't want
to it in place for whatever reason I can
do it with just two buffers of the same
size right and I just kind of write them
through I go okay what's less than three
just put them into their position then I
go what's more than three put those into
their position right and then I know
that I can
ping-pong back and forth between those
really easily and things just get more
and more sorted right and so all I have
to do to continue down my quick start
path you can kind of see where this is
going
I just keep applying that I pick a pivot
again I say the pivots too it's like oh
wait actually probably you wouldn't
actually do this you just go when you
get down to two items you just swap them
if they're not equal right so if they're
in the wrong order so probably don't
focus on this one but point being when
you still have more than two items you
just do the same thing again pick
another pivot
what's the pivot I baby I pick seven
this time right and so then I go okay I
pick seven for the pivot I need to do
more than seven less than seven right so
less than seven things are gonna be
three four five and the greater than
seven things are gonna be seven and nine
this is now done because I've you know
consorted this one needs to pick a pivot
again so I picked the pivot five maybe
and then I've got just five and three
four and hey now my whole thing sorted
right and so what you can kind of see
about this hopefully is you can see why
I say that there's like an expected
running time of om but a worst case of
Oh N squared right and the reason is
because how long this takes depends on
what you pick for the pivot right
because if I pick a pivot that splits
things fairly well then I will be able
to do this very quickly right I will not
have to go through very many passes at
all it's actually wait sorry did I say
expect it I win that's that's not right
that's bad I believe it would still be
an log n yeah I don't think it's
expected Oh ed that's that's that's
pretend I didn't say that I don't I
don't I don't see how it would be
expected Oh in it would probably still
be expected n log n yeah anyway but
worst case N squared point being the
reason is because if I pick this pivot
poorly I may end up still having to do n
steps right let's say every time I
picked the highest one so I pick nine
right and that means I'm still I if I do
this this way so I pick nine I end up
with one two three four five seven in
one group and then nine right okay I
pick again I pick wrong again I get
seven so I'm one two three four five and
then seven I pick wrong again I pick
five I got one two three four and five
right and essentially what you can see
is I'm gonna have to go through n steps
because I'm only removing one thing I'm
only sorting one element every time it's
just as bad as a bubble sort right so
the fact that this is expected to be
faster
the only reason it's suspected to be
faster is because you assumed it would
be very very very unlikely that no
matter how you chose to pick your pivot
that you can somehow manage to pick it
that poorly that often right what are
the chances that if you have a hundred
items you will pick wrong every single
time that's a one in 100 chance followed
by a one in 99 chance followed by one a
98 chance right you would have to go
through this incredibly unusual thing to
hit that that worst n-squared case so
most of the time you'll end up with a
pivot that splits it into 1/3 and 2/3
let's say right which is pretty good so
that is is quicksort and that is an
example the reason that I decided to
describe it here even though I don't
think I've ever written or cared about
quicksort myself the reason that that is
so the reason I chose to describe it I
wanted to give an example of an
algorithm that might be N squared but
might not be N squared when you run it
it's worst case as always N squared
because we do know exactly how to
produce that scenario you just make sure
you feed it the inputs in just the right
way so that it picks the wrong values
but the chance of that actually
happening practice incredibly incredibly
incredibly slim especially because as
you get more items the chances that you
can pick wrong that many times in a row
just keep going up and up and up right
so that's the deal with quicksort and
the thing with quicksort to remember is
again that pivot picking is the most
important thing
and so when you are writing quick sorts
basically there's you you might almost
say if you know something about how the
data might look when it comes in like
for example you know some really good
potential pivots or you know that it's
very evenly distributed the values are
like let's say for example that you knew
that your values had a certain range to
them and that they were pretty
distributed over that range that gives
you a really easy way to pick those
pivots you know that like the the dip
you know halfway between the min and the
max value if you knew what those were
would be a great pivot because you know
that things are evenly spread throughout
that range so you know that will split
them roughly in half right so if you
have a bunch of information about the
things that you're sorting and you find
that you're it's very important for you
to write a good sort quicksort might you
might be able to actually guarantee for
your data that it won't hit the N
squared case and then you know maybe
that's a really good album so again even
when we say that it's Oh n squared it
might not actually be om squared for you
because you may be able to use specific
knowledge that you know about the the
values that you're putting in there that
would make it so that you could avoid
ever hitting the N squared case right
and again that's also a good example of
like I was saying I was talking about
randomized algorithms before that's kind
of a good example of a randomized
algorithm in the sense that you could
imagine using randomness to ensure that
you wouldn't ever get highly correlated
things in this list right
like if for example what am i transect
so here's a perfect example it's already
in hand made here so let's say that the
way that this thing worked was it always
just picked the first value in the list
as the pivot that's just what it did
right well if we were to do that we
would pretty much be guaranteed N
squared running time for our cutscenes
in our sort B
we know that our our cutscenes put
things into the render queue in
precisely an ordered fashion the Z's
just go up linearly they go like one two
three four five six seven right the Z's
just go straight up so whatever you know
the the Louis II happens first the
highest C happens last or whatever we
know that that's always the case and so
it would be like the absolute worst case
for this thing but if instead what you
did when you started out is you randomly
permute it all the elements in the list
and then ran quicksort then you would
know that no matter what the algorithm
was outputting you would always end up
with sort of a jumbled version of it so
you could never hit such a reliable
worst case that might be coming out of
your algorithm so there are cases where
people use randomness to try and
decrease the likelihood that some highly
correlated algorithm on one end of the
pipeline isn't totally messing up your
sort on the on the back end now I don't
tend to really love to stuff like that
because in general I'm like well if you
have that information you should just
try to feed that information into your
sort like right another sort right but
again if your goal is to write a
general-purpose sort maybe you need to
do something like that okay
so let's talk about another sort here
let's talk about radix sort radix sort
is an O one sort not really people often
say say oh sorry
that's good oh one sort it's actually o
K n I don't know why I said brain is
going a little bit obviously it has to
visit all the items that's that's a
that's a non-issue but it's got an extra
kind of weird thing in here so let me
talk about this let me talk about this
for a minute because it's kind of it's
kind of like the Traveling Salesman
thing where I said you're introducing
this other thing radix sort introduces
another thing so how does the radix sort
work a radix sort basically says well
you know this is a computer and the
chances that I'm sorting on something
that is truly arbitrary right is
actually somewhat low now there's 20
times that we do sort on arbitrary
things you can imagine like a sequel
query that has to sort things there's
often complex stuff that's trying to
sort on or whatever
radix sort not gonna help you there but
a lot of times we're sorting on things
that are like you know it's a 32 bit int
right and we know that no matter what
value could dream up we're storing it in
a 32 bit int so it ain't never gonna be
bigger than for a billion right that's
just that's just the truth
so radix sort is about exploiting the
fact that even though we're talking
about very specific numbers that in our
imagination are arbitrary in practice in
the computer most of the time in stuff
that were computing with isn't really
arbitrary because it's got to fit in
something the CPU actually works with so
radix sort
does sorting based on a direct look at
the values that its story the sort key
that sorting and it assumes that they
are a fixed size and this K that's in
here is that size so a radix sort is
actually has two different sort of
things that affect its running time it's
the number of digits right or bits I
should say like the bit count right and
then there's the the I shouldn't say bit
count this is again if you if you want
to be a little more CSE it's really just
I'm gonna say digit count I guess
because the radix sort I think
conceptually is more about whatever you
consider digit to be and maybe you want
them to be binary or maybe you want that
to be you know a bit or whatever because
when you actually go to implement the
radix sort you could you could do it you
could choose to chunk those things up in
different ways right okay so the radix
sort has a dependency on the digits and
it has a dependency on the the number of
items so how many things that you're
going to sort and the way that it works
is basically by peeling and I think
we're out of time so maybe we'll yeah
we'll talk about how it works in detail
more tomorrow but it basically works by
peeling it says well I know that I've
only got 32 bits worth of possible
things and I write if I'm sorting the
set of all 32 bit integers even you know
if every single possible 13 sure was in
the set I know that I could basically
talk about 32 different
sort of categorizes if you will of where
things would fall in the final result
right conceptually speaking you could
just think of it as saying well I know
that I've got this 32-bit value and I
know that this bit here right is going
to be let me take the high bit first so
assuming that we're sorting high bit
first
I know that this bit here right anything
with this bit set is going to come after
so anything that that doesn't have this
bit set right so right off the bat I can
partition my my things into two halves
stuff that does have that bit set so
that doesn't have that bit set right
then I could do the exact same thing to
those partitions using the second bit
right and then partition those into
things that do and don't have that bit
set and don't do it don't have that bit
set right and if I just do that 32 times
if I just did that 32 times going down
it I would have my complete thing sorted
right because I can just do literally
just a binary split each time and then
by the time I get to the 32nd pass
everything's sorted and so that's why it
changes it into something that does not
actually require even in log n
operations there's no log n in here
right it's only K times n where K is the
number of those sort of like
discriminators that you're going to do
right and sort of the reason that I said
it it's not clear what this actually
means is because it's sort of up to the
implementer how they might want to break
things up right and so you might want to
break them up into bigger values than
just per bit because you know maybe it's
it's more efficient to to break things
into more than that number of buckets
now this does require space you can't do
these in place at least I don't know of
any way to do them in space I don't
study sorting so maybe there is but so
this requires extra space but you know
usually that's not such a big problem
and then finally we've got insertion
sort insertion sort and again we'll talk
about this one tomorrow
probably implement maybe we'll implement
this and this that seems like a pretty
good thing people seem to be very
excited about that
so maybe we'll implement these two and
of course we already have this one
I'm not going to implement this one
because I don't really care about it and
because it's not that useful but I'll
just briefly say I believe insertion
sort assuming that I remember that one
is Oh N squared and the reason is
because the way it works is it just says
well you know what I'll just take the
things here are my items right I'll just
take them and I'll make a thing that I'm
gonna put them in or whatever and I'll
say like okay I go with the first one
and I just stick it in the first slot
right so you know I got a and a goes
here I take the next one and I just go
should it go in the first you know what
is this relationship to a if it's less
than a I move a up one and I put myself
in its place if it's not then I just go
to the next one right in which case I
put B here so the reason this gets
slower is because as I go right I have
to move all of these things out of the
way and even if I didn't even if it's a
linked list or something I still have to
potentially visit all the items for
every insertion which is N squared again
right so even if I assume that I have
some easy way of I don't have to
actually copy everything out it's still
N squared because just looking at
everything I might have to do that n
times for every insertion right so
insertion sort not particularly
interesting but the reason that I said
sometimes I do a pseudo insertion sort
is because I do find this sort of a
thing very handy if I just want like top
n right
so let's say that I I don't care about
sorting I just want to know like I've
got a thousand items right and I want to
know what the highest four are right so
what are the highest four in this thing
well I might make a little thing that
just has four entries and I just do
exactly an insertion sort on it because
I know that that'll be really really
fast to just go through and go like okay
for each item I just do n pass through
and so then it becomes an O four times n
right or just Oh n algorithm just go
through all the items look at this
little side table that's got you know
four entries in it right and
like okay is this item greater than this
one is greater than this one is greater
than this one is greater than this one
right and when I find one that's greater
than I just move everything down right
and one falls off the end and I stick it
in and that's all really fast operations
because we're just talking about a few
bytes of memory that should just kind of
romp around in there right so that's a
place where I do use a certain start the
reason I called that into pseudo
insertion sort is because I never use it
to actually sort all the items I just
use it if I'm trying to find the top end
so yeah not really in the surcin sort
all right with that let's go to the QA I
think that wraps up pretty much
everything that I want to say about
order notation because again not my area
of expertise don't really have much to
add about it in general I think that's
all the information that we'll need for
handmade hero at all and tomorrow we'll
just implement the tooth those two sorts
there emerged in radix so you can
actually see how they work
all right q-and-a
you
snowy crystal Zee so why would you not
always do radix sort with a sort of just
whatever the size of the type is okay so
there's a lot of reasons for that let me
just let me just sort of give you let me
just sort of give you an example so okay
what did I say
I said that we can always do sort in n
log n time right we know that that's
what we can do and I believe it correct
me if I'm wrong see us guys on this but
I believe that this is actually proven
meaning this is the proven lower bound
I think somebody actually just
demonstrated flat-out math lies that
there will never be an O n sort it's not
possible it just does not exist so if
you're talking about general sorting
there is no way to actually do better
than this
but we know we always can because you
could use a merge sort for example and
you know that that will do that right I
think there are other ones I know if I
keep sword I said that there's there's
more than one there are multiple sort
algorithms that will always do that and
so the thing is well how many items are
you sorting right you know if you are
sorting in fact you could almost do this
math wise a radix sort I just said takes
K n time right where this is the number
of like bucket things that you're that
you're using for it that's like how am i
it's going to take well if we look at
these two here the question you could
ask would be when is this value worse
than this value and the answer is they
have both have the N so you're just
talking about comparing K right to log
in if log n is actually smaller than K
right if that's you know if that's
actually smaller then this is probably
not such a win right and this might be
the case because often times you know
let's say I'm sorting you know maybe I'm
sorting a million items or something
like this so let's make it easier on
ourselves and say that we're sorting you
know 60 64,000
right so we know that login is is like
sixteen or something right then you're
gonna say well you know if it's sixteen
then this K you know how many things
that we're gonna sort this K was like 32
is that such a good idea right but maybe
it's smaller than that maybe I'm doing
it in bigger buckets so maybe it's more
like four or five right something like
that right well that's fine right that's
totally fine but that only that will
only be true as long as the thing that
you're sorting on the sort key is very
small right it's gotta be something like
a 16-bit integer right 32-bit integer
it's got to be something like that if I
had a giant type like you were
suggesting let's say I had a type that
was like 256 bytes you know long well
now suddenly K is almost always gonna be
bigger than long it's gonna be much
bigger than log n right log n might be
something only like 16 or like 20 or
even 30 - if we were sorting four
billion items it would only be 32 right
whereas this K is now massive no matter
what you were doing with this is 2056
bytes long that means this K is it's
probably 256 it could be maybe maybe
it's 128 maybe it's even as low as 64 or
something maybe depending on how you
were bucketing these things and how much
remember you chose to use but man right
that's starting to get pretty brutal
it's actually you're doing twice the
amount of work four times you're going
to work a considerably more amount of
work on this sort right so that's the
first reason is because K and log in do
not always compare favorably a lot of
times they do and the K is better maybe
but a lot of times they don't and so
that's one thing right the other thing
is you it may be impossible right so it
may be like impossible to make the key
right and so if I'm gonna sort on things
it may be that I need to compute
something that happens between these two
things that is not representable as a as
a a quantity now I know that sounds a
little weird and you're like what are
you talking about
well let's say we were trying to sort
based on the the euclidean distance
between two things so I've got this is
the thing that I'm sorting I'm sorting
an entity right and my entity has a v3
in it that's the location where is that
thing right and so I want to sort these
entities and I want to sort them based
on how far away they are like from each
other or something like this right see
if this is I don't even know if this is
actually all that legal I could make it
into a total ordering by doing some
things but that would require me to talk
about this but okay so partial ordering
and total ordering this gets into some
sorting stuff I don't know if maybe
we'll talk about this if maybe we won't
but point being let's say that the thing
that I want to sort on was actually a
function and it was a function of the
two things so I'm gonna sort on
something that's like you know I I want
to know you know distance between entity
a and entity B right and that's gonna be
like a P minus B P right and it's gonna
be whatever that that length is right
and that's gonna be well I guess I'm not
sure exactly how I could make turn this
into a sort I have to turn this into
something sorty because the length is
always gonna be positive so I need
something I need to I need a way of
using you have to just trust me that
these things exist if I can't think of
it just give me a second I'll I'll think
of a better example cuz that won't give
me a that won't give me a value that I
can store it on
how about how about a string okay so
I've got an Indiana has a name the name
is arbitrarily long so it can be you
know I don't know 26 bytes we have no
idea right and now I tell you I want to
sort these entities by their names so
that they're in alphabetical order or
something like this now I'm like well
okay for the rest of all of these sorts
right for all the other sorts all they
have to do is compare two items which
means it does not matter how long those
strings are they just work and they'll
compare the two strings and off you go
radix sort needs the sort key to be a
fixed length which means that the only
way you could possibly turn it into a
radix sort is you'd first have to go
through every single entity and you'd
have to look at how long the name was
right and then you'd have to make your
sort key be that many bits
however you know many bytes that thing
is you'd have to make it be you know
however many bits Long's the longest
name was that's how big your sorc you'd
have to be and then you'd have to
actually do the radix sort on that giant
thing right and so that right there is a
good example of how it may not even be
all that feasible even to just set up
the radix sort because even to just know
how big the key is you would have to do
a pass over all the data just to find
that out right whereas all the rest of
the people they don't care at all about
that furthermore you could invent kind
of really strange things in here which
is let's suppose that our sort order
actually takes into account some kind of
cross string behavior that might happen
so for example maybe I say something
like oh I've got like Dave
Bauer or something right is one of my
strings and let Carl Worthington is one
of my entities right and and then
there's like let's say Big Tuna all
right so here are some strings with all
of the other sort functions it would be
free for me to introduce weird cross
strings that think crossed string things
that happen I could say something like
they appear in alphabetical order except
for if the name Carl is being compared
to the name Dave and if it is I want to
switch the order
so all Carl's always appear before all
Dave's but otherwise everything is in
alphabetical order right now I would
have to do a thing we're like I have to
pre-process if you even can I mean you
could come up with things that are
pretty crazy here that maybe I'm traffic
if you can always pre-process or not I'd
have to do some weird thing to like
pre-process the names to make sure that
the the bit value I end up using for the
sort key for the radix is always the
right thing in that case or other stuff
like that right whereas in the other
cases in the comparison function when I
do you know I write my comparison
function for the sort all I just do is
say like oh well if it's like a Dave you
know if it's a Dave in a car all you
know do this one branch else do this
other branch and it's free right I don't
have to think at all I have to do
anything it just works so I can throw
special case stuff I can throw variable
length stuff everything just works with
all the other sorts radix sorts none of
it works radix sorts all you have to do
all this work to turn things into
strings of bits first and then you can
do it right and so that's another reason
why you wouldn't want to use a radix
sort is because it's very difficult to
turn things into radix sorts if they
have complexity in them let's see here
where my on cues
any news on potential pet white guests
stream stay tuned on that did you
mention sort stability at all I did not
so sort stability that's pretty easy to
to talk about so I'll talk about that
so sort stability just means that if I
am going to take some input right and
the input looks like a b c a d e f or
something like this right
imagine i have this and i say want this
sorted well all of the sorts will always
give you back a a b c d e okay so every
single sort that we're going to use
would do this for you no problem but the
question is which order do the a's come
in let's suppose there was something not
in the sort key that's stored over here
right so i have for each one of these
elements i have some number associated
with them five nine two three one seven
eight right so the question is well for
all these other guys i don't care
because i know that they're going to
come out in what in there's only one
order they can come out in b c d e f
right so i know this is gonna be the the
b that had the nine in it this is gonna
be the C with the two this is gonna be
the D with the one this is gonna be the
e that at the seven that's gonna be the
F that have the eight right but what
order do the A's come out in well that
is what sort stability is if a sort is
considered stable what it means is that
the A's will come out in the same order
in which you put them in or at least in
a predictable order right maybe you
could argue that one that have them came
out backwards was still stable because
we know they always come up backwards
but point being stable generally means
they caught in the same order you put
them in so the a5 comes out first and
the a3 comes out second okay if a sort
is not stable
that means they they could come out in
any order we don't know maybe the a
comes three comes first maybe the five
comes first we are not guaranteeing
anything very very simple concept first
question probably have why would you
care and the answer why you care is
because sometimes you want to sort by
more than one thing sort of in waves
right so for example I might want to do
something you ever see this where you go
like oh you know somebody gave me this
thing right and it's like oh it's like
here's the name and here's the like date
and here's the like you know quantity of
tuna right and like this is in Windows
Explorer and so like then I've got all
these things where it's like oh here's
like in food text and that was made on
like July 9th you know and it has like
two tons of tuna in it right and bla bla
bla bla bla right well you might want to
go like sort these by name like give me
the the sort by name right and you're
like well it doesn't matter whatever
sort we do it'll sort by name it's fine
right but then we maybe we want to do
like sort by date I took out sort by
date and it's like okay we sort by date
and I notice like there's a couple
things here that have July 9th right
kind of weird right there's a couple
things to judge a night so I want to see
on July 9th what had the highest
quantity of tuna well if I've got a
stable sort right I can do stuff like
say oh well sort by the quantity of tuna
first and then sort by the date or sort
by the date and then the quantity of
tuna and know that it will leave my
original sort right items will come in
the same order that they used to come in
so for to answer the question that I
gave as an example if I sort first by
quantity of tuna I know that all of my
things go in descending order of tuna
then I could just go click on sort by
date and it would bring the July nights
all together and I would know that it
would always be descending because they
started out I had pre-sorted my list for
quantity of tuna I click on date and I
know it's stable so it will never
rearrange
these up to put the zero first when I do
my date sort right it will keep them the
same and so sometimes being able to like
sort by one thing and then start sort by
another thing and know that the first
sort will now take precedence anytime I
have equivalent values in my second sort
is kind of handy right so in this case
here it's like let's say this sort was
important I sorted this on something
else before and so this value and this
value I want to know the fact that this
one was the lesser of the two for some
other sort and then I run this sort I
want to preserve that order so I know
that I'm going to encounter these in
that proper order that I tried to
prepare over here I won't get that if
the source is not stable not a huge deal
to be honest with you I can't think of a
time I've ever cared about stable
sorting doesn't mean you don't care it
just means I don't usually care me below
what else if anything do you think we'll
need to sort besides the sprites I don't
know it's possible that there'll be one
or two other things it's possible that
the sprites will be the only thing
cuber Caleb could we possibly generate
hints the ground chunks in such a way
that you using radix sort would be more
optimal I'm pretty sure that actually a
radix sort
radix sort might well be optimal just in
general for what we're doing but it's
hard to say Cronos yes it is proven I'm
pretty sure I assume thing you're saying
that was response to was was the fact
that I was saying that o n log n is the
fastest that sorts will ever be meaning
that there is no such thing as a sort of
general data that can go below n log N
long billion is shellsort basically
bubblesort
with a variable span between values
being compared yes as far as I remember
my recollection of shellsort
which I believe is named after someone
named shel I don't know if that's true I
don't know why it's called a shellsort
I'll be completely honest with you I
don't I don't remember why it's called a
shellsort
it just is my understanding is shellsort
is exactly the same as bubblesort it's
just you compare sort of a different
span so you go like oh okay
you know here's my items and normally in
bubble sort I compare these two then I
compare these two that I compare these
two then I compare these two then I
compare these two they can read these do
right that's a bubble sort and I do that
until the list of sort of keep doing it
doing it doing it doing it doing it to
list the story of a shellsort says yeah
you know what let's not do that let's do
like first we'll do like this you know
do elements that are that far away from
each other or something right and then
maybe we'll do elements that are that
are less right and I feel like there's
like a whole family of shell sorts and
they're based on how you choose on which
passes which distances you know and the
idea is hey you could move if there's
things at the bottom that really should
be towards the top those first passes
like get them up there right and so I
feel like shell sorts are generally
about - basically they're the idea is
tune a bubble sort so that the kinds of
data that you're getting actually takes
very few of those passes to bubble up to
the right place and you can imagine that
working right if you know kind of how
your data might might come out you can
probably design some shell passes that
will have it take this with a grain of
salt because I don't remember that may
have a totally inaccurate explanation of
shellsort but that's what I remember it
being
mr. slick 10:15
is this cross-platform yet it depends
what you mean I as I said many times in
the stream I it will not be
cross-platform until we're done with it
because I won't be doing streams for
other platforms till we finish the game
on one platform but other people have
done ports so there's an SD L port of it
if you want to use the SD l port of it
so it's cross-platform in the sense that
other people have posted the code on the
on the get on the github that you get
when you pre-order the game or whatever
there's an SD L port up there that
people did and I don't I haven't looked
at it but I assume it's up to date I'm
not sure
dragon keno - with something like a
PivotTable be a sort problem or
something else altogether
is that more a sort amalgamation
summarization I'm sorry I don't really
know what a pivot table is I know
there's something in like s Excel or
something but I never used one elven off
topic which more do you like the fixed
function API of OpenGL or the
programmable one I've been using the
modern approach but reading examples for
the fixed pipeline they seem to be a lot
more intuitive easier understand the
flow of things I prefer the programmable
one but I wish that it had been better
designed at this point it's kind of all
smooshed together now because it went
through so many likes baby steps to get
to where it went it's kind of you know
snowy crystals so bio description is a
stable sort resource intensive since it
seems like it could be max N squared n
log n depending on sort type since you
have to run through the data twice no
so really all that matters like for
example I think I think you could do
like a stable merge sort right because
you're only reversing elements when you
have to and so like for example I feel
like you could do a stable merge sort
just fine and it's Oh n log n right
because all that matters in fact let's
let's double check I mean you know this
is this is known merge sort stable yeah
so most implementations views a stable
sort because you know when you're going
through the elements if the way that the
sort is set up makes it easy for you to
just copy the things in the order they
happened in the original thing when you
don't detect a switch then it's stable I
feel like bubble sort would also be
stable and it's only N squared right
let's see
Narad 91 wouldn't you stop teasing us
with the interactive fiction post and
get to the details what details are you
talking about in so far us will you
leave in some bugs for speedrunners to
break the game with up well
you don't leave in bugs or speedrunners
to break the game with you just you just
have bugs I mean what are the chances
that we're gonna make this whole game
and not have any bugs in it right like
you always have bugs and so we don't
need to leave them in we'll just we'll
just have they'll just be some and
they'll find them and then it will be
fun or funny to watch dragon Kino 2 with
a sort is this actually adjusting and
rewriting the data on the disk or would
it just be in using would just be
updating X's or pointers just once you
sort could you read start to finish or
is it pointer intensive read 10 records
jump read next five jump well it depends
what you're doing right in our case
we're just sorting in memory and you can
see right here all we do is just swap
the stuff in place but if you wanted to
you could do it in a different way you
could do it with a reference table and
in fact you could almost actually to be
honest we're already sort of doing it
with with a reference table right
because what we sort is not the actual
things we just sort the addresses of the
things so we sort by the sort key and we
remember what the addresses are and then
we just go grab those addresses so we're
already kind of using one level of
indirection to avoid having to copy
things around when we do our sort
new rad 91 says I mean how you actually
went about solving the problems it seems
so closed for weeks then cliffhanger so
I hate to disappoint you but we're not
going to talk about the solutions all
this all the Molly rocket code is
proprietary I've said this before but
I'll say it again like we don't post
that so like our engine will be
proprietary and it will not be discussed
how it works
so the posts on the current one are four
players mostly they're just talking
about why we thought there were problems
and which problems it is that we are
solving if that makes sense
and there will be then there'll be a
game announcement on there that that
talks about the game and and that sort
of stuff but we don't that's not a
programming blog and there's not going
to be any discussion of the programming
on there so I can save you the trouble
if you're expecting that there's there's
not going to be there's not going to be
any programming discussions on the Molly
rocket blog
snowy crystals
I read a post the other day that said
syntax coloring is bad for programming
practices and in enforces skimming
rather than understanding do you agree
or not I feel like that's a pretty
that's got to be a pretty data free I
mean that's just obviously a random
statement I mean how could anyone have
proven such a thing so that sounds kind
of arbitrary to me but I guess on the
other hand what I will say is I turn a
lot of it off like you can notice that I
generally don't syntax highlight very
much so I guess for my tastes I don't
tend to like that much of it but that
may just because I don't love the way
that syntax how others tend to highlight
things I don't know so I would say
probably depends on the person very
since no rad 91 now I know that I have
to buy a game to find out that's fine
thank you uh you won't have to buy the
game to find out the because the game
won't say how its programmed either and
on the blog we will talk about like what
the game does that's interesting and and
they'll be gameplay videos and stuff
like that so obviously like we'll talk
about which problems we feel like we
solved and how well we solved them if
that makes sense
but we just won't be talking about how
we solve them meaning the the actual
implementation will not be public
let's see any cues any other cues I
think we're done with Q&amp;A anyway so it's
probably good that there are no more
queues because that means we can wrap it
up all right it looks like that's about
it on the questions if that makes sense
so yeah let's go ahead and and wind down
thank you very much for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always we will be back to programming
tomorrow as I think we have now gotten
through everything that there is to say
from my perspective on our notation
because that's like I said all I know I
am NOT a CS person so you know as much
as I do about augmentation now which is
not very much but it's the amount that I
think you should know if you are someone
who does game programming because I feel
like you should be aware of of what the
complexity is of the algorithms that you
choose and so now that we're done with
that tomorrow we can implement some of
those sorts and yeah and then we will be
done with sorting because there really
isn't that much to it and it's not that
big of a deal
for games most of the time sorts are not
really that important and so really I
just wanted to go over it as an
introduction orientation because we talk
about it a lot and I mention order
notation on Hammad here so far sorting
is kind of a very classic one there's a
lot of literature on it so it's just a
good place to kind of sneak in a time
talking about hey there's a whole field
here and there's all these things to
know about if you care and so that's
what we did
so we'll implant to the marrow and
that'll be the end of our sorting we'll
move on to some other stuff that is it
for now if you would like to follow
along at home with the coding tomorrow
you can always pre-order the game it
comes the source code on handmade hero
org
you can also go to our forum site and
ask questions if you have follow-up
questions you can subscribe to our
patreon if you want to support the video
series and you can also look at our
tweet pot to find out when we are
broadcasting live and that of course is
known for tomorrow 5:00 p.m. Pacific
Standard Time I will be right back here
for the last few more the week the
Friday's game and then the tweet bots
will of course after that tell you when
we will be live next week that's it for
today thanks everyone for joining me and
I will catch you guys on the Internet
and hopefully tomorrow at 5 p.m. for our
sorting take it easy everyone