hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here the show recode a complete game
live on stream we are going to give this
a shot today we don't actually know how
long the internet will be up for
apparently there was some kind of a
significant outage in the area and I am
told although I don't know how accurate
it is that the internet is currently
running quote-unquote on batteries I
don't know what that actually means I'm
assuming it means some kind of a UPS or
some kind of like that large battery
backup system but I think it could kind
of go at any time
so we're gonna give this a shot if it if
the stream craps out in the middle don't
worry I am recording it locally and
that's what I post for the video on
demand so I will do the entire episode
one way or the other and it will go up
on YouTube it's just people watching at
home on Twitch right now may find
themselves without a stream if the
internet cuts out because obviously
there's nothing that's going to be able
to be streamed if there's no internet
but that does not mean the stream is
gone it will hopefully return just fine
let's go ahead and get started what we
need to be doing today is moving towards
a stable voxel implementation for our
lighting we've done a lot of the
groundwork and let me sort of give you a
refresher for those of you just joining
us as to where we are in the process of
implementing a fairly good lighting
solution in our game you can see the
little hero hopping around here and
there is a light source above the hero's
head and what's happening here is we're
just running a very simple test at the
moment that is picking the light source
closest to wherever the various sort of
parts of the of the scene are so for
example in here this would be like the
closest light source and you can see
there's a little white square there
that's showing the light and you can see
here that all of this stuff is getting
lit by that similarly like up here it's
getting lit by that and so on and then
what we're doing is there's some basic
ray casting that we tested but right now
it's sort of knocked up in any
particularly smart
and we don't have a lot of ways of
blending it incorrectly so actually the
quality of the solution you see here is
totally crap at the moment and that's
actually not because our interpolation
isn't good our interpolation was quite
good and in fact if we do casting
against just the single light source at
the hero head we get pretty good results
but what's happening here is that
boundaries between where the light
source would switch we get artifacts
because we just kind of overwrite
whatever was there before with whatever
is there now right and so we don't
really get any we don't really get any
coherence at those places where the
boundaries switch and furthermore we get
no frame to frame coherence either so we
don't get any smoothing or anything like
that and that's something that we also
have to address because once we go and
turn on the full secondary bounce
lighting as well it's actually infinite
bounce lighting we've gotten there that
we are sort of waiting to turn on that's
gonna need to be smoothed over time and
so for that we need to keep it as as
well so we have ourselves stuff to do
all of this good stuff and I think we're
kind of on the verge of having quite
good lighting coming we've done it
several tests over the past couple weeks
with very good results and so now we're
just trying to pull that together but
the main piece that we're missing right
now is a way of blending light fields
together
now what I mean by that and I I can
probably just go ahead and hook this up
I think we left this code path in there
so I can probably do a really quick
reversion to it to show you what I mean
but especially what we're doing is we're
doing a light field interpolation that's
interpolating the distance from the
light source effectively and the normal
to the light source that's sort of how
the the light field is being
interpolated and I don't know that
that's really the way that we want to do
it but what I can say about it is that
by using sort of negative light values
as we sort of discovered you could do
some really amazingly high-quality
interpolation much much better than I
ever really thought was possible in this
case we sort of stumbled upon it and I
said whom I wonder if we effectively use
distance fields we could do some good
interpolation here turns out that
intuition was quite right indeed and we
ended up in a situation
where it kind of is something that I
want to test a little bit more
aggressively so here we can see where
we've got this test cast from probes
here and there's you know test light
transfers a thing that's enabled right
now and you can see us here doing some
light transfer from from the voxel in
here I think we if zero this out at the
moment am I wrong about that that's the
end if and if so here's the transfer
version where's this coming from
normally not let's see yeah this is
coming from the cells of the standing
voxel yeah so basically if you look at
what's going on here where we where we
transfer these out we're currently just
getting them from our actual solution if
I was to turn that off and just get them
from some tests fears that we know the
exact answer what hopefully you can see
here is in our in our running app
assuming this passed the works what you
can see here is here's the light field
interpolation and as you can see it's
really remarkably good and you might be
wondering what I mean by remarkably good
but if you look at like what you're
seeing here in terms of like the edge on
the sphere and stuff like that if I you
were to look at this and say well okay
so what's the big deal like you know it
just looks like you're at our place and
lighting what you have to remember is
this is actually reconstructing the
lighting per pixel with nothing more
than a 32 by 32 by 32 voxel and this is
the level of detail we're getting I mean
look at that edge there right it looks
like you're actually computing the
lighting per pixel using the actual
lights and in fact it has no such data
right and just to underscore you know
how good that is because it's relevant
to today's work if I was to go into the
OpenGL code here and turn you know go to
the Z bias or daghestan fuzzy bias
program but when we actually create the
texture instead of using sort of linear
interpolation if I actually switch it
back to
nearest interpolations so you can see
for example here in our lighting this is
where we're studying these up you can
see the light is set to linear here if I
set this to nearest so you could just
see what it looks like without
reconstruction it's pre ridiculous what
it looks like when you don't reconstruct
these fields just to look at what kind
of data we're feeding into the lighting
solutions so if I turn off the linear
interpolation so you can see it looks
like without reconstruction here is the
actual data that's going in there right
that's what it actually has to work with
right and so look at that I mean that's
the resolution that we're storing the
lighting at and yet with the
reconstruction function that we chose to
use we were getting we get a perfect
edge right and so that's why I say that
that's kind of like a compelling
argument for using this kind of a light
field to reconstruct the lighting to the
extent that we can even though it's kind
of an ill-defined problem because I'm
just guessing and I don't know but much
like I was guessing in the first place
I'm just guessing that if we're getting
solutions that are this good from this
reconstruction if there's any way at all
we can produce this light field from the
full transport solution oh my god that
lighting would look so good
and yet it's incredibly cheap to produce
because we're only producing 32 by 32 by
32 samples in total nowhere near the
kind of density of information that it
appears like we're providing when you
actually look at the results and so that
to me again pretty compelling so that's
sort of where we're at in terms of what
we are trying to do so hopefully that
makes some sense to everyone I'm doing a
quick checker it seems like the internet
still up so so far so good
um all right so what we need to do now
I'll go ahead back to the light transfer
so what we need to do now is start to
figure out how
we're going to talk about these light
fields and how we're going to produce
the light field data that we're dumping
down to the system and like I said this
right here is just doing a light cast
from the closest light source and if we
go and look at how that people code
actually works
what you can see here is that when we're
in and lighting computation normally
what we'll be doing is calling this
compute light propagation call we're not
calling that right now because we're
trying to do tests so what we're calling
is this test cast from probes and what
test cast from probes does is tech cat
test cast from probes clears the voxel
to begin with and again that's something
that we actually never ever want to do
so our you know short term goal you can
think of it as coming up with a blending
solution that means we don't have to
clear our voxel anymore instead we could
just take the results of last Lane frame
and blend them with the results from
this frame and get something usable so
that's like thing one thing too is we
call get leaf lightly for P and what
that is is it does a spatial query into
a spatial hierarchy that we built
specifically for storing light sources
and that just tells you what are the
closest light sources to you right and
the reason that we need this is because
we're gonna be doing some biasing of our
sampling towards light sources this is
not that important right now but we just
wanted to test it because we're not
trying to really attack that part of the
sampling problem yet so that's kind of a
little bit for later but as you can see
like this right here is a pretty
important thing for us to use kind of
like going forward and what we may want
to do right now to make our testing a
little simpler you can see here that we
get the light for every place that we go
to cast we get the light source that's
closest to that thing and that is
probably something we don't want to be
doing right now we probably want to be
doing something more like this where
we're just gonna use just that one light
source that the player is hot the one
that where the player is hopping around
and it's above their head we just want
to use just that one light source
probably and that way we could debug a
little bit easier so here you can see me
hopping around with that debug light
source you can see me hopping around the
world and you can also see that the ray
caster when you put it into this mode
where there's only a single light source
and you can just see the results just
from that light
source you can see that our ray caster
is doing a pretty good job as well with
the data like as I hop here you can sort
of see it goes out into that room and so
on now again our storage and our casting
is very sparse and that's why you get
very blocky results as you can see it
kind of it's on that grid there right
and so that's why like at the moment you
know this is not a particularly
effective way of dealing with this light
field it has a number of problems one of
which is that we're just kind of writing
an off value in there so we don't have
the full interpolation that we need so
we need negative light values in there
and that's something that we have to
work on so that would make like areas
like this look a little bit better even
just in a single ray case but the other
part of it that's obviously a problem is
that fact that all we're doing is a
single binary like shadow on/off and of
course that will always even if we make
this look relatively clean and
relatively smooth in there it'll still
always have what I would call that
flashlight look it still looks like the
hero is just kind of emanating a light
source out from them
there's no bounce right normally if we
shone a light in here this would get
some light right and if we don't have
those secondary bounces then they'll you
won't ever really see any light in there
right and that is not particularly
useful because we want that richness so
in order to get those secondary light
bounces again we have the technology in
there to compute them we can call the
light propagation function and start to
transfer light around actually quite a
bit but before we can actually start
taking advantage that code path and
there's one thing we have to write in
there which is the voxel sampler for
that code path but before we can start
taking advantage of that code path we're
going to need some way of actually
blending light samples together because
in order to use the secondary bounces we
have to be able to sum some of these
this light information together right
okay so that's kind of where we're at
and as you can see even in this mode
right now if I was to pull back and move
a little bit forward you can see exactly
where we're getting good interpolation
look kind of right here and then places
like this where we're not getting
particularly good interpolation that's
because around here it's not really
saying much about what has to happen we
don't really get negative light values
in there so we just get this kind of
wobbly like bad interpolation pattern
you'll notice this is not a stair step
and this is again that's just because in
here we're just getting zeros rather
than negative light values which is kind
of what we need to have happen there and
so we need probably some way of filling
in that kind of information about the
light sampling so that's going to be a
challenge as well and so when we look
around in here we see that problem
immediately and then their problem we
knew is that blending now for blending
we can also imagine testing that because
what I can do is start to introduce some
lighting lag effectively this is
updating the lighting every frame and
what I might like to do is a first step
just to sort of get ourselves warmed up
and try to start working with these
light deals that we kind of just sort of
randomly invented and don't really know
what they do because we don't have a lot
of information about them yet what we
want to do here is maybe introduce a
little bit of light lag just to see if
we can get cross flame blending working
so what I might try to do is when we
sort of hop through here right what I'd
like to do is get it so that that that
there's just a delay it sort of slowly
fades from one to the other not because
there's any reason to want that slow
fade right now but more because I know
that I need to be able to blend these
things across frames in order to get
enough samples once we start to do the
more heavily sampled version so that's
why I like to start doing today just by
the end of the day if we're lucky maybe
we can get to the point where we get a
nice delay in there and all that is is
proving that we have a way of coherently
storing light over time as we sort of
drive the the simulation over a series
of frames all right so we need two
things first of all we need to stop
clearing our voxel right this is not
going to be helpful and so we're going
to need to we might want to do something
in there we might want to do
some kind of reduction because we're
like adding things into the box loves a
blend we may not want to forego this
loop entirely but this may want to be
like a multiplier or something where we
reduce the values that are in there by
some amount right but if I stop clearing
it then what you'll see is as I move
around the light that I add just kind of
stays where I'm putting it right so if I
leave an area it will still have that
light right you can see that there's
still all this light in here so for
example if I go in here right I've added
light to this area as I hop here that
area is now in shadow so it doesn't get
updated any more right and it doesn't
get updated until I hop out and the
voxel gets reset because it moves
somewhere right and so everywhere that I
touch where the light actually hits
something
I am updating but then any place where
it doesn't hit I'm not updating and
that's what you end up seeing there
right okay so now what we want to do is
start blending these over time using
some kind of a ratio I don't know what
exactly we want that ratio to be but if
you remember quickly we were already
doing something sort of like this before
you can see here we had some stuff like
from linear blend coefficient we derive
some stuff here right we've got a
comment about this I don't we
essentially say it's like all right look
the irradiance preservation is going to
be 59 sixtieths right why because we
want to take 60 frames to really like
change the legs significantly that's one
second of game time so we want kind of a
one-second laggy light source behavior
effectively and you know we might change
that something else over time just based
on what we're doing we don't know
anyway we come up with two values one is
herb blend you one is herb blend V ER
blend U is just whatever the value is
effectively that we're going to take the
existing voxel values that's we're going
to preserve the existing voxel values F
and then herb blend V is sort of the new
blend right that's that's what we are
adding in so we're going to add in 160th
effectively right and
keep 59 60th and again this is just an
arbitrary thing you know we could have
made this 30 over 60 you know who knows
we're gonna tune it however we want I
don't know why we've got T updated here
I'm not sure if that's even use anymore
that's probably old news yeah this is
just garbage at the moment that was used
in kind of an old code press so I might
place it down back in where that that T
where the remember that code actually
gets called in here yeah
there so we know we computed those
values and we're gonna use those values
to tune the blending but for right now
we need to do is actually have those
sort of start to control what the
Lighting's going to be so let's suppose
that we just did a very simple sort of a
very simple sort of use of those just to
get ourselves warmed up like I said what
I want to do is say curious that or
blend hue and here is the herb blend V I
want those to be available in general
across my functions so maybe what I'll
do is I'll just put those into the
lighting solution itself so if I go in
here to the lighting solution code you
know we'll just say look there's going
to be these sort of accumulation values
this is where they live
and then inside the solution here when
we're actually looking at those values
we set them up like this and now
everyone can access them such as people
in test cast four probes so then in test
guys from probes like it here I could do
something where I keep some amount of
the value that's in these cells of the
voxel for example by just saying look
whatever the color is of the light at
that point I would like it to decay a
certain amount the certain amount of
decay is going to be that ear blend you
right and then down here where I'm
actually putting the the casting values
in so when I actually when I actually
spam the voxel you can see that the
voxels Pham call right here
when we are in that spam voxel slice
call
what I could do is say all right well
when we actually place these values in
here instead of just placing the value
directly and I'm just gonna use a
summation instead so I'm going to use an
herb blend V for that and then that way
we get sort of a new value for for the
that color and I'm going to do that with
a normal as well and this is just
complete garbage what I'm doing here ok
so just want to make that clear and
we're gonna see a couple ways that it's
garbage right off the bat but it's very
very garbage and you'll sort of see why
as we as we go I'll try to cover all the
the reasons why as we sort of encounter
them but I'm gonna do it from both here
so we're gonna do both of these are
going to get multiplied by the ER blend
hue value which will reduce them and
then they're gonna get summed in their
right soaps here we need the letting
solution and so that's all I wanted you
to start and that's just a simple sort
of like lagging effect that we're gonna
put on there trying to see here if
there's any other thing I don't think so
that I need to worry about so I think
that should be fine but there's one more
there it is oops
what I do there there we go
sometimes theater gets a lot of
all right so what's basically going on
in here as you can see is we've
introduced some light lag but also what
we're getting is it looks like we're
over brightening this and I suspect the
reason for that well actually I guess
I'm not sure exactly why we're over
brightening so we should go take a look
at why that is I probably messed up some
term somewhere but you can see that the
lag that I introduced is in fact there
but it looks like we're adding more
often than we should be oh you know why
I dunno why and this is exactly the
thing that I was gonna say why the first
reason why this is garbage sober okay um
so what's happening here of course is
that when we do spam voxels slice it's
actually writing to an area that's nine
voxels around whatever the target is
what that means is that a lot of our
rights are gonna overlap and when those
values overlap they're going to sum to
greater than the total amount of light
that should have been introduced in that
area now that's totally fine when we
just have an equal sign because we're
just gonna overwrite whatever the old
light value is where the new light value
is so the fact did multiple people
trying to compete in that area doesn't
really affect you but as we're trying to
move forward to get more accurate more
interesting lighting we don't want that
we want to be able to sort of blend
light things together and we need to be
able to take lots of different light
information and blend it together in a
way that doesn't produce over brightman
so we can't just add everything together
right that's not going to cut it so what
we want to be able to do going forwards
right is we would like to be able to
sort of have our voxel information that
we're going to do for this frame and
then we're going to want to have the
voxel stuff that we have from last frame
and we want to be able to sum these two
together in some way that will normalize
them correctly so at the end we'll end
up with a summation that actually works
right that actually sums to the correct
sort of amount of contribution from the
last frame in amount accomplished is
this frame no matter how many incoming
samples we actually have at this
location the voxel
we don't want to care about that we want
to be able to produce the result
regardless right so what that means is
we're going to need some kind
a summation waiting value in here right
we're gonna need some way of saying look
this is how much total light got added
and we need to renormalize how many
total samples got added and we need to
renormalize based on that number of
samples to get us back to good now when
we look at what we've got here you can
see that we're keeping our large voxel
dim in here probably there's not going
to be a lot of ways to do this in place
we're probably going to need to have
sort of a buffer of the last frames
values and then a scratch buffer where
we're computing dis frames values right
so what we're probably going to need is
something like this where we have like
cells and new cells right something like
that and the reason for that again is
because it might not be possible for us
to really record the information in any
other real way right and similarly when
we do light voxels cell here as far as
new cells is concerned like this this is
probably not what we want to store
probably what we need to store is like a
light computation cell something like
this and what that's going to have to do
is record something else so for example
it will probably need a total weight
you've seen me do this before and then
like a light si accumulator
and a light and accumulator and again
these are probably not sufficient we're
probably going to need more than just
that information to record the light
arak accurately in this area so you're
gonna see me expand that a little bit
but the point is it needs this value as
well so this stuff that happens in the
box is cell by itself is probably not
sufficient and we probably want a
special type of storage just for our
scratch computation
something like this right so when we do
our light computation we're probably
going to want to have something like
that and we don't really know but maybe
we're gonna need something just more
expansive over time in general right now
if I look at where light box the cell is
actually used
we may get some insight as well let me
just go ahead and see here voxels so
yeah so what you can see here is because
this is really only used in our set up
what we could also choose to do if we'd
like to is just
loyalties in line right so we could have
a total weight in here and it lights the
accumulator and a light an accumulator
those could actually just be welded into
where the box of cell is stored again I
don't know how we want to set this up
it's premature to really think too hard
about it so I'm just going to put them
together like that
and then what we're going to do is work
with it here so rather than have this
thing doing this sort of blend here what
I want to do is set myself up to do the
accurate blend and so the first I'm
going to do is clear that total weight
and then also the accumulators so now
we've got something that cleared all of
our settings and now I can accumulate
into these and then when we get to the
very end
right so after we've cast everything
then what I can do is I can go through
and do just a nice stable interpolation
between the two of them in here and so
the way that would work is I would go
ahead and find out what the total weight
was to begin with right and get a safe
ratio out of it so I'll get a
normalization coefficient out of this by
saying don't ask me why there's a zero
there left over from the old code pack
so in here what I want to do is take a
safe ratio so I get the inverse of the
total weight again that's just a
standard one normalization you've seen
me do this a ton of times and what do I
do now is normalize the light see and
light and accumulators down so that they
are rationally normalized values
something that's based on the total
amount of weight that went into them
rather than having something to do with
just an arbitrary additive sum that we
don't have any idea how many people put
sums in there and we don't know you know
how to get it back to a value that's in
line with the actual amount of light
that came in so what I do here is take
the norm C and the norm the norm C for
the light C multiplied by the lights the
inline end and what you can see here is
when we're right there this is
probably not the best way to do this
because what we probably want to do is
do this after the fact right so since
we're already gonna do a loop down here
I might as well clear it right after I
use it like that right that's a lot
saner because what that'll do is make it
so that while we're already touch them
on they're hot in the cache right here
we're about to you know we we had to
load them in any way we can clear them
right they're probably mostly for free
right alright so that's all we need to
do for this but this just gives us the
actual light sea value right this is the
new light see and the new like n right
now we actually need to do the lerp
that's actually pretty easy that just is
the light and oops and the light C
values in question are just going to be
lerp of their previous selves with their
new selves right so this value here is
just going to be this and actually I
guess since we have coefficients let me
just do it that way so first we're gonna
do is use the air blend V or blend you
value rather that keeps you know 95
percent of the previous solution and
then we're gonna do is it justice here
probably although we can sort of do it
here instead I don't you know I don't
know exactly how this routines gonna
expand
normally I could roll this right into
this multiplied here but I'm not going
to do that just yet because I'm not sure
that's what I actually want to do going
forwards right so this is what we're
doing here so this is just another
linear blend basically right couldn't
let the moment that right there gives us
what we needed however we haven't
actually done anything with the I don't
know why that's complaining
what is the issue here oh that's because
it's hot code reloaded yeah we didn't
remap that time so anyway we'll be fine
when we run again the only thing I need
to do now is I need these where we're
actually recording the information so
where is our actual test cast here
spam boxercise here we go
where we actually write these in what we
need to do now is actually write these
in in some way that actually preserves
sort of that weighting information that
we needed so we're gonna sum the normal
and the C accumulators here for use
later and then we're gonna record the
total weight and since we don't have any
idea how important these samples are the
total weights always going to be one for
everybody right now all of the
information is going to be like equally
valuable basically right so now if we
run it we should get something that
correctly lags the light source but
doesn't get infinitely bright over time
in fact it should just converge back to
what we previously had and what you
could sort of see is that's exactly what
it does right so you see how there's
about a one-second lag there as it fills
in
so anyway that just shows that you know
we can blend these values together over
time and you know they're fine or
whatever but you know as we sort of
continue through here we sort of end up
with the problem that well this sort of
way of recording a light-filled really
only records like one light field so I'm
not really sure how this would work if
we were recording you know multiple
light fields right and trying to blend
multiple light fields together however
we can certainly try and find out right
because one of the things that I nurse
just now in the test cast from probes I
know looking up a different light source
per right but I could that restores us
sort of querying a different light
source per voxel cast and that looks
like this right and what you can see
here is well it does something right
it's not horrible but it does sort of
create some issues and some of the
issues it creates for example like I was
saying before is that because we don't
really know how to blend these types of
values together we get some weird
results like in here for example what
you're seeing I believe is the fact that
when I add in the negative light from
this person it kind of affects the light
that should probably have been coming
from this person although I don't
actually know that that's true it may
just be that the closest light source is
always from here
so these never get computing light
sources from here it's hard to say but
point being you know there's a lot of
stuff going on in there now which is not
really correct and so you know it's hard
to make any kind of judgment calls about
that interpolation at all really
but anyway but it does sort of work so
it proves that our voxel sort of does do
one of the things we needed to do
however the other problem that we have
with it right now is that the voxel
isn't stable so when we hop like between
those two for example right
you can see that some things get cleared
do you see that like that whole room got
cleared the reason for that is anytime
the voxel moves around the light values
just stay there we don't really do
anything to try and make the voxel copy
when we move where the world is relative
to the voxel so the other thing that I
want to try and get done today if we
have time which I think we probably will
right now yeah we've got we've got an
hour so that's easy um the other thing I
think we could do that should be
probably pretty easy is if we just go
ahead and try to copy the voxels so that
when the voxel moves relative to the or
when the world moves relative to the
voxel we copy the correct block of the
voxel out and clear the part that we
don't know about so it doesn't have like
residual lighting values sitting around
in there that are wrong okay wish I had
more almond milk
I didn't start with enough almond milk
that was a big mistake okay
so if we take a look at how this is
working our test cast should probably be
able to stay the same as it is the part
that has to change right now is really
the begin call I believe that's what you
can see curious when we do begin
lighting computation we do a bunch of
kind of sort of computations at the head
end of that and we figure out where
everything should go and so here you can
see us computing these values and then
we push some volume outlines on there
right and we get the lighting going and
what you can see is that if we look at
where this how this happens you can see
the lighting voxel are these two
boundaries here I believe and what those
are is I want to say that I don't really
know if this is true I'm kind of making
this up but I want to say that what we
do here is this is the lighting bounce
that's currently being computed so
basically this is the hot voxel it's 32
by 32 by 32 and we're actually doing
work on that box'll
um but this bigger one here is just what
we're storing so because it's pretty
free like memories cheap it's pretty
free for us to store a bunch of old uh
voxel values so that when we like hop
around we don't use them necessarily so
what we kind of want to do is store a
large voxel filled with all of the data
but we don't really want to actually
have to compute all that data so that's
what those two are and so what we really
want to be able to do now is say alright
look when we move where things are we
want to copy the block that was the hot
voxel before we want to copy that to
wherever it is now right and leave the
old stuff in place as much as possible
right so we're just kind of scrolling
we're like it's like screen scrolling
right it's old tile map scrolling but in
voxel space right so the first thing I
can do is I can sort of figure out like
well okay if this stuff is sort of
aligned to a certain extent right and
you can see that it is because in here
we do
well actually wait
oh no we don't so it looks like we never
finished the alignment code either
because you see that modulus operation
and stuff there
you
it seems like this stuff isn't quite
aligned properly either
it looks like we're not actually doing
the alignment so I think we do want to
do that part too so there's two things
we have to do what is we have to keep
the voxel aligned to the actual cells
you
so I think we're okay yeah I think it's
okay all right so if we take a look at
how this is actually working right let's
go ahead and do some some investigating
here but let's make sure that this stuff
is it's working okay so to start with
right we know that the simulation origin
effectively doing is saying well we're
going to set the size of the voxel here
that's that's presumably based on some
multiple like the voxel demand that
stuff when we initialize the lighting
that's going to be based on sort of the
the fundamental unit size right you can
see that here
and that fundamental unit size right is
guaranteed to be something that aligns
with the world units properly now my
assumption is that we are not aligned
right now because we just assume that
whatever the simulation center is that's
where we are but you can kind of see
here we don't actually know that that's
true
like all we're doing right now is saying
that like whatever the minimum corner of
the hop value is it's always a space
around the simulation center minus the
hot tip but we don't actually know that
the simulation center itself is a line
or do we maybe we do because if it's
aligned on fundamental units as well
then maybe we do kind of know that let's
find out so I'm going to set a
checkerboard lighting pattern and I just
want to see how we are aligned here and
whether it ever changes right whether it
ever flips around so that we're not
aligned we reach so that we're not
always aligned with the world the same
way and this should be really we've
tested this before it should be really
relatively easy to see um so if we use a
checkerboard pattern and I turn off the
in the OpenGL system here I I'm going to
go ahead and
just turn off the filtering so I can see
it a little easier there we go
so what you can see is that at the
moment right the checkerboard pattern is
aligned so that we're kind of running
down the middle that the checkerboard
lines are running down the middle of the
squares in X and they're aligned and Y
so middle X aligned and Y and then you
can see that when I moved right like
when I moved here to here it actually
changed so now it's in the middle of
both right so what that tells me is that
no we are not always aligned the same in
terms of world origin the world origin
itself actually is is sort of moving at
different fundamental units there like
potentially 0.5 so what I'd like to do
there is figure out some way of making
sure that we actually get that alignment
properly you can see here so we can
always be up to 0.5 off it looks like on
the world origin we're never anything
other than point 5 off but we definitely
can be 0.5 in either X or Y versus what
the what the input is right whoo that's
at least what it looks like to me
like that seems seems pretty
unmistakable so that's definitely I
think the case my assumption is that has
to do with how we're centering the
world's origin
my guess anyway all right so if a if I
go to the code for the lighting that's
actually doing that computation one
thing that I then want to do is I want
to say all right what's going on here
with that so as far as the world
position origin P is concerned what I
want to do I guess is take a look if
there's any sort of offset there the
fundamental unit if we go look at how
the world works here right I'm gonna
look at that fundamental unit let's see
just go search for where that's used so
what you can sort of see here right is
the fundamental unit is used to build
everything so everything kind of built
off of that one fundamental unit and you
can see it creating the world out of
them as well right and so the world
chunk dims are always a multiple of that
so what that means is that we should
always be aligned as far as the
fundamental unit is concerned in the
voxel but if there's ever a non integral
so basically like if we're ever have any
offset from there from begin letting
computation we've ever any offset we
need to account for that so basically
that means is that if I go into the
world position struct and we look
there's this offset parameter if that
offset is ever anything other than a
zero then we would be slid sort of
around from where the chunk boundaries
would be so what I assumed we would want
do to keep ourselves aligned to the
voxel properly would be to say first of
all we have to account for that offset
value so we need to start by taking the
offset and moving back to where we
should be and then
we can continue moving back to align the
the voxel completely with with that
fundamental unit so I think that would
keep the Vox aligned properly don't
quote me on that but that's what I think
and so now what we would see hopefully
and it does look like it's the case is
that checkerboard pattern should always
align itself perfectly to the actual
world sort of placement of tiles that we
had which again is arbitrarily like we
don't care just to be clear because I
know this might seem confusing there's a
lot in play here and it's all kind of in
my head I apologize sometimes I take
some things for granted but what you can
see going on here right is we don't
actually care at all about whether or
not what that that's what's going on
there we have multiple sorry to get
distracted there but do we have for some
reason multiple
of the same cube drawn in the same place
there somehow or is that a box of
sampling bug of some kind
you
so that could just be a box of sending
buckets right on the boundary that's
probably what's happening so with linear
interpolation you wouldn't see any of
that at all so we're good all right
anyway sorry I got struck it anyway so
if we look at this we don't care that
the voxel is aligned to the world
geometry that we don't care so we are
free to place these squares however we
want to and we're also free to change
our voxel resolution to be something
totally different than this
it could be twice as large or half as
large if we wanted to right what we want
though is we want whenever we move the
simulation center by a discontinuous
jump like that like that right we want
the voxel cells to be in the same place
as they were before so you don't want to
slide a portion of a voxel cell over so
this was just my way of making sure that
the voxel cells themselves always were
on a fixed grid even as we scroll around
the world arbitrarily and that's what's
going on now you can see as I move here
that the voxel doesn't actually remain
exactly the same right it changed there
you see I'm saying right to it to a
different location right and so I feel
like to a certain extent that sort of
underscores how that has sort of that
that different results it's working
there but anyway you get the idea so
with that in mind what I'd like to do is
say all right now that we've got that
taken care of let's see if we can go
ahead and copy these values now that I
know that they're at least aligned okay
so let's go ahead and switch back and
stop doing the checkerboard pattern
all right and what I'm going to do now
is I'm just going to switch to using the
transfer that we were using before and
I'm gonna try and get the copy working
so that it preserves those lighting
values across the jumps right now I've
left I haven't turned linear sampling
back on so we should still see like
tile-based stuff but I kind of want that
because it makes it easier for me to see
what's going on right and so that there
provides a very good test case that jump
where the voxel just clears there that's
what we want to stop happening because
there's no reason for it to clear just
because the simulation center changed we
should be able to preserve all of our
light values still just fine okay so how
would we know that that's happening well
the first way that we know that that's
happening is when we look at this
incoming value for the world position of
the origin P what we know there is if we
were to track that value then as the
world position moved around we would
know because we could compare it right
so what we could do is we could say in
the lighting solution let's just store
whatever the last one of those was so we
can say last origin P like so and here
we can say look did it change
so we can sort of have like a center
moved boolean value where we can just
say like R equal to if these two are not
equal and again we don't actually want
to make them exactly equivalent here
because we don't care actually about
this offset this minor offset so we
could choose to zero that out right
that's one thing that we could do and so
what we might want to do is something
like this
take the origin P that we have changed
the offset to zero and just remember
that part so if the center moved we
would say look if these two are not
equal any more than the center
definitely moved I don't know if we
actually have an R equal for them looks
like we do and then that last origin P
can now just be stored and that just
gives us a way now of knowing when do we
actually have to open looks like we
don't actually have one sorry I spoke
too soon
it looks like actually are in same chunk
is all we really needed so actually we
could just do this amusingly enough we
already had a thing that does exactly
this comparison so if these two are in
the same chunk then the center didn't
move right and so that's all we would
actually have to do and then what we
want to know again is just like what's
the difference between these two right
like how would they actually how would
we actually have to copy the voxel from
one to the other and so what we could do
here is say well okay let's just say if
the center moved then what we need to do
here is actually perform that copy so we
need sort of like a delta for how you
know what where the voxel how many
pieces the voxel should copy over
basically right and so in order to
figure that out what we need to do is
take the difference between these two
values and then use however many
fundamental units that actually is so
what we would do is say well the Origin
P right the what the new one that has in
it in the world position a chunk
difference here right so we kind of want
to figure out what that chunk difference
is so we have our chunk X and we want to
subtract that from the one that we know
and that gives us a like a deep chunk X
right and so in here what we could do is
just compute what these offset values
actually are and then we would know like
this is how far we actually had to go so
we did this we you know moved this far
in each of the dimensions but of course
that doesn't really tell us how many
voxel cells we moved that tells us how
many world chunks we need we moved and
we now need to also know what the world
chunk size is in terms of voxel values
and that's also something that we can
store so in other words inside our
letting solution here
we can also do is record maybe something
like this right and in fact this should
probably be this we didn't have v3 s is
implemented at the time we wrote the
chunk stuff so that's why they're not
stored as those to begin with we should
probably go back and change that oops so
what you can see here is we're just
saying look we've got a delta that's the
chunk Delta and here it is but now we
need to multiply that out so that we
have some idea of how many voxel cells
that is so this would be like voxel
cells per chunk right and that's a v3 s
because the voxel cell the chunks are
not the same they're not cubic right
they're actually rectangular so the
voxel cells per chunk multiplied out so
we've got our d chunk times our box
itself or chunk is how many voxel units
we moved during that frame so if I do
that now I've pretty much got the
information I need if I can provide that
voxel cells for trunk value which at the
moment I don't actually know what it is
are in the same chunk it doesn't seem to
be available that's probably just
because it's not exposed
let's see here we need our worlds out we
need our world to be passed in here and
we would need that anyway so when we do
begin lighting computation we would need
that because we also need to use that
world value because it's the only thing
in here that actually knows for example
what that fundamental value actually is
so if we look in into the world data
that chunk dim in meters is what's gonna
tell us that right so actually I suppose
we can do this map every frame it's not
expensive
I can probably not bother storing it in
the white solution even though it is
going to be constant what I could do
here is say look the voxel sells for
chunk this can just be a round where we
just do the divide so we could just say
alright we know that the world has a
chunk gem in meters that's how big a
chunk is we then want to divide by
however big these voxels supposedly are
so this is voxel dim right and this
would give us the information we
actually needed right that's pretty much
all there is to it I think that would
give us the correct value of so know
what that's still doing there
these have to be pointers and these is
flux cell Tim of vectorizing I need to
be accessed by their members that's
about it I think and so I don't know if
we have a Hadamard product for v3 s is
we probably don't it looks like we don't
how do our product where v3 s is is the
same as ahead of our product for VIII's
it's just an integer multiplied instead
so it's really not a big deal
all right so begin lining computation
now needs to have the world pass down
that's being used and that's not a big
deal we obviously have that data anytime
all right so let's go ahead and and see
if we can get this going and I want to
step through that code as well and I
want to look at what the values we
compute actually are so when we're doing
the copies here like from here to here
we're going to need to do the copy based
on that D chunk value and so that's
gonna you know assume that this
computation is correct I want to switch
to debug mode I want to look at the
values we computed to make sure they
look sane before I implement the actual
copy so I'm switching the o2 to an OD
which tells compiler obviously to debug
mode and then what I want to do is just
set a breakpoint right here so I know
that the center will move sometimes I'd
like to probably break like there and if
I'm right I should be able to hop what's
going on here why am I not getting
anything
there we go I should be able to hop
across the boundary like that and cause
a move and when I caused the move here
what I should be able to now do is look
at voxels ellsberg chunk which should
give me 17 9 and 3 which is exactly what
I did and I should be able to look at D
chunk which is how far we actually moved
and it should tell us how many chunks we
went any particular direction this
claims we went one chunk in Y I could
sort of believe that I don't really know
if that's true or not though because we
don't have a lot of information about
where the actual coordinate centers are
at the moment so could be true could be
false we may have to debug that looks
like a pretty straightforward
calculation now and then if we take a
look at D voxel here we're gonna we're
about to compute that unfortunately it
looks like it went off scope but
actually it looks like remedy preserved
it for us so it's 9 in this case right
so this is claiming that our solution
our coordinate center moved up by 9 but
that's all it did let me take a look at
the origin P here all right
oops here's the one we had before so
let's say we went from 0 0 0 to 0 1 0
supposedly as our coordinate center um
and I mean all right you know I could
believe that I don't necessarily know
what's wrong yet but we haven't really
done much to verify whether it is or
isn't all right so let's go ahead and
take a stab at the copy again we've got
some you know we have a fair bit of time
left I think I think we should be done
and about what 40 minutes something like
that so if I go in here and just go
ahead and and the stream does still see
me alive by the way those batteries must
be pretty good
when effort though they has thought that
up
yeah anyway so moving along if I go in
and actually take a stab at the copy in
the begin lighting computation call what
you can see here is that if the lighting
is enabled and we have a center movement
occur then what we're going to do is
we're going to try and copy the voxel
we're going to scroll the voxel by this
much right and in order to scroll the
voxel that much what that means is we're
trying to copy we need to copy each of
the sort of dimensions of the voxel in
that way right so if the voxels supposed
to go you know if we're moving to voxel
squares you know along X then we need to
copy the voxel tuvok so squares
backwards along X in order to keep it
aligned with where the world now appears
to be so if you imagine just doing this
like for one axis so let's suppose we
were going to do it for the y axis since
that's the one we currently have a test
for then what I would need to be able to
do is I would need to be able to say
alright I know that I'm going to have to
do a copy either forwards or either
forwards or backwards right so let me do
just a if statement here as this as a
simple way of doing it and say look if D
voxel dot y is less than zero and this
is not probably how we're going to do at
the end but I want to just walk through
it
doing the fully explicit way oops first
so if you take a look at what we're
gonna do here if we are going to walk
over so the Delta voxel movement was
negative meaning the player moved in
negative Y then we want to move the
voxel in positive Y right and I should
probably draw this out because I
realized that didn't really probably
make any sense what I just said
I'm going to try and make it clear I'm
sorry
all right so thinking about this purely
in one dimension at the moment although
I'll draw it this way because we're
talking about Y so if this is our one
dimension this is y and it's going this
way right then this way would be
negative this way would be positive if I
have my voxel and so I'm gonna go ahead
and put one down you know there it is I
if I have my voxel and what I'm saying
is okay
previously I know that the simulation
center right was like right here so this
is where the simulation center was that
value is last origin P right but now
when I look and we call this the you
know function again what I see is that
now I get this so this is now origin P
right this value so this is zero one two
three four this value is four five six
this value is six so when I subtract you
can see in the code here right origin -
last origin when I subtract these two I
subtract six from four and I get
positive - what does that mean it means
that the player well the origin the
camera origin right or the the sort of
simulation origin move forwards two
units like that that means that now it
this location is effectively this
location right and for me what I need to
do is I need to take this part of the
voxel and move it
so that it's actually here right so what
that means is everything that was in the
voxel every square like if this was a a
has to get moved there so every voxel
square needs to be moved to backwards
from where it was so you know voxel I
minus 2 has to be equal to voxel I right
or voxel I needs to be equal to oxal I
plus 2 right so this is the update step
that I need to be able to do and when
I'm doing it I have to be careful not to
over write values I'm actually going to
need so for example let's suppose that
I'm doing this particular copy if the
first thing that I did was I updated
this cell by popping this into here well
now I've lost the ability to correctly
update this cell because this cell was
supposed to be what was here but I've
already overwritten what was there with
what was here right so in addition to
making sure that I do this properly
these two things are not equivalent when
the source and destination are the same
right if I'm going to do this I had
better make sure that I pick the order
of I of iterating over I that doesn't
overwrite values that I haven't
previously moved that I haven't already
moved to their new locations right and
you can see which order that would work
in quite cleanly if it was a positive
move so I'm going negative right in
terms of you know things are going this
way I would want to walk the voxel this
way meaning I would want to set this
value first because it's grabbing from
like here then I took this value because
it's grabbing from here that's at this
time is grabbed from here right I always
want to walk in the same direction as
the movement of the center was not the
direction I'm moving the voxel because
they're actually moving the voxel if I
walked in that direction this way
then as I as I update these values this
value needs to be grabbing from here
there is nothing there nothing there
this value grabs from here this already
got overwritten right with whatever the
blank value was or whatever right so it
doesn't really work to go in the
opposite way alright so when we look at
the D voxel like I said we need to we
need to go in the I direction that
corresponds to that so when I do my for
I loop for the D Vassell why in this
case what I need to do here is I need to
make sure that I'm if it's less than
zero then I'm going backwards right so I
would say that the Y value for my voxel
in this case I just gonna start at the
maximum Y but Y value like so whereas if
I was going in the other direction I
would need to make sure that I would
start at zero and end at the light large
voxel like so so in this case you can
kind of see where we're at right these
are the copies that we need to do and
the actual copy we need to do is pretty
straightforward this D voxel value here
tells us how far we're copying so
actually when we look at what's going to
go on here
if you look at what we're going to write
in this particular piece of code if
we're going to copy two of the voxel
squares we've kind of got that here
right
here is what we would need to do for our
copy if we're copying in why and I guess
we can fill in this and its entirety and
since we're only copying and why I can
put in the other ones here as well okay
so if we do this where we're going to
run over all of them and then do a why
copy on each one and the why copy is
discriminated I can also put that in
here for now like I said we're going to
kind of have to make this a little more
flexible eventually but for right now we
can do it this way all right so doing
this copy in here we then need to figure
out okay so what does the copy update
actually look like and so if we're going
to assign this particular cell this is z
Y X so here we know we have to use this
form of the equation where we're doing
well I guess it doesn't really matter
which direction we choose to do it in it
will just depend on how we write this
particular code but if we're going to
update the voxel that we're stepping on
in order right then the one that we're
going to grab it from is the opposite
direction of whatever the the d box will
value was right so this is just going to
be d voxel Y right it's Y minus D box of
Y and what you can see about this
routine is that we can't actually
execute this routine if this value
excuse me would actually be out of
bounds right if it's out of bounds
there's nothing we can you know we we
can't really fetch outside our voxel
that would that would be very bad so
what we need to do instead here is we
need to think about well what could we
actually iterate over in this case that
would would actually work and what we
know is that if we're fetching Y minus
the d voxel Y we know he
that the Y value is less than zero right
so we know that this is going to be
effectively a plus right we're sort of
fetching whatever the you know that far
forward right so it'd be the plus two
case the bottom one there right that
means that this value has to be pre
offset so that it's got to be at least
as low as d voxel Y right
so in this case right would not be able
to fetch even if the value was zero
right
and if the value was you know one then
we want to take into account that we
have to be one less than that right and
so this routine here would do the voxel
copy exactly as we need it to do but
what do we do with the remaining cells
right and so what we would like to do
there because we also need some way of
like just clearing whatever's in there
right so what we'd like to do here is
instead of this we'd like to also be
able to talk about the area we're not
actually going to touch we know we will
touch basically everything from light
light large voxel dim minus 1 minus d
box of Y all the way down to zero but
depending on how large this is that
could be like none of the voxel if it's
large enough right so what we want to do
here is basically say look let's clear
everything else we know this is the
first value we'll touch right so let's
say we know what that is we know what
our max y bound is so then when we do
the copy here we'll just say all right
let's go from that max Y value which we
know we actually will use we'll go from
that plus one and we'll clear everything
else
so that would clear it out okay so now
we have the negative version of the
routine that we think would probably
work correctly I mean who knows right
and then we're going to need the same
thing to happen but in the other
direction so we're gonna have to have
one where we're grabbing from things
that are behind us as we go right and
for that to work we're going to need to
do something where we do the opposite
we're going to need to start with D
voxel Y because we know we're going to
subtract that much of it away right we
know it's positive now right and so in
this routine we're going to start at
zero and we're gonna go until we hit min
Y right and we're gonna start here at
zero
I'm sorry might start at min Y right
we're gonna go until we hit the end of
the voxel and we're going to go upward
subtracting away from backwards so here
we know we can just go until we hit min
Y like that and do our plus plus there
right okay so that's a sketch of the
routine it's probably a little bit buggy
because I it's hard to type it's hard to
do stuff like that while you're talking
if you ask me but that's what the copy
is supposed to do we'll see what it
actually does although that was a pretty
bizarre situation looks like that
routine is a little bit bus to Ferris
you can see but anyway that's that's the
basic idea so let's go ahead and step to
this and debug this right so the first
thing we want to do is make sure that
our x and z values are dealt with
appropriately and I think they probably
are right because all we're doing here
is going from 0 to light large voxel dim
in both cases and so presumably that
part of the routine couldn't really be
all that bad right
furthermore if we assumed that this was
going to do just another Y loop in here
I would think we wouldn't have any
problems so let's assume that that's
okay for now we could take a little
closer look at it if we think there's
something weird happening there later so
then we just have two cases here right
and we we
sort of talk through what each of them
is going to be let's make sure we kind
of know what's going on so let's say
that D voxel Y in this case is negative
2 right ah yeah so this this is the
problem right here you can already see
it so let's suppose this was negative 2
that means that we're going to be
fetching so for every Y we're going to
take and we're going to do 2 ahead of it
right the problem is if I subtract a
negative value I'm actually going
forward what we really wanted was this
we just messed up the sign there right
um is that a puss hello puss do you want
to say hi say hi it's up its up here
baby baby it's up here do you see you
see that's the that's the folks at home
the puss don't understand the camera
very well she doesn't I'm sorry she
doesn't acknowledge any of you out there
but she doesn't know about the camera
she doesn't know what that means
she just think it's a little thing that
sits on top of the monitor and does
nothing you know they don't have webcams
in catland they don't do
videoconferencing so I can't really
explain it to the push she don't she
don't like it she doesn't understand
anyway point being that's the way that
should have been written that was just a
sign error there I think the rest of
this looks okay let's just take another
look at it real quick here to see if we
still have an issue with that
all right so waiting is sort of we
probably want to compile in release mode
so that the lighting update is fast
enough for us to actually use properly
but let's go ahead and see here as we
move along there is this jumping into
the next thing you can see it did not
apparently copy correctly it doesn't
look like it did yeah it doesn't look
like added updating correctly at all so
we're still doing something kind of
weird they're not sure what exactly but
we'll take a look I also I'm going to go
ahead and switch - OH - here for a
minute just because the speed at which
it updates now the lighting is blending
that makes it a little bit hard to see
what's going on there so you can see
it's still disappearing there and so I
don't think our copy is is working the
way that that I was trying to get it to
but that's the basic sketch of the
routine so yeah
you
trying to make sure I thought all that
through properly and that I don't
actually want to go like the other
direction or something like that but I'm
pretty sure that's the way it's actually
supposed to be if you go plus to
everything in the voxel doesn't move
negative - that's definitely true I
don't see any way that that could be
false so I believe this update step is
the correct way to do things like in why
you know what no this is wrong again so
I did it when I type this in I did
exactly the wrong way again this is the
same way as the Delta if you write it in
this format right I mean I drew that out
right here right so that's that's just
stupid again
because again this is if this is
negative then this becomes negative
right so you are fetching from someone
who's lower down than you were and
that's what you want in this case where
it's positive you're fetching for
someone ahead of you and that's what you
wanted so this is the correct Upstate
step in both cases and so I'm not sure
what was up with that other than me
being stupid all right one more time
so that looks unhappy there with that
fetch step
you
and again that looks a little bit
suspicious just looking at that code
again so assuming that Y was positive
right if that's trying to fetch below us
it should look like that so I'm not sure
why I flipped that one that was probably
me just being overzealous all right so
it looks like we sort of made a slight
improvement there which is to say that
our forward copy is still borked
but our downward copy was stable you can
see how the lighting did not black out
there right so our upward copy is
you
it's forked there hold on a second so if
we take a look at these right here you
can I just want to verify that I'm not
imagining things cuz that sure looked
like the copy was working in one
direction right so if you take a look at
what happens here you can see that the
top copy is working properly I believe
right and if I was to comment this out
so that we weren't doing any work we
should get a clear in both directions if
I'm not mistaken right I don't know why
I'm restarting
you
well so maybe not I mean we do get a
discontinuing its light jump but it
wasn't going to black
you
so if I turn this one back on
yeah but it still looks like that's a
much more continuous so I don't know I
think this is this one actually is
working although it was less of a
pronouncement so let's focus on this one
now so yeah again looking at this one if
we take a look at what the minimum Y
value would be when we're talking about
how it's going to be copied again we're
trying to figure out how to copy this it
should be from people
you
it should really be I feel like this is
just this is yeah it's just a little -
head spinning this is the kind of code
that I always hate writing it I feel
like you just need you need something
that just shows you how this copy is
working in a little diagram which would
take you know not very long to write but
it's just the third sort of thing that
we don't ever have tools for but anyway
if you take a look at the way this is
working right we're saying D voxel Y is
less than zero that means the user moved
in the negative direction right which
means that the voxel needs to move in
the positive direction so everybody who
is in a particular location if the voxel
is moving in a positive direction
someone who is at I goes to I plus one
which means that I plus one goes to I
minus one which in this case would look
like this right so that is a correct
interpretation of that statement if the
D voxel was positive then people need to
move so people who were at why are going
to move to y -1 which means that people
at Y get their value from Y plus 1 right
so this actually did seem like how it
should have been written here and I'm
saying and when I look at how this value
is supposed to go that suggests to me
that actually yeah these this is pulling
from a negative which means you
presumably need to go backwards where
this is playing for a positive so that
means presumably you have to go
for word order which so this just see
yeah so this this just seems like this
was maybe written slightly different
slightly wrong so if you take a look at
how this works the Y value here we can
start at zero right because you're
always adding something to it and we
just need to stop before we get to what
that maximum value would have been right
so max Y is still the correct thing it's
just the way we wrote these routines
yeah so max Y is still the correct thing
to compute and it's still going to be
you know light large voxel Tim minus 1
minus D voxel Y now right so we were
almost there but not quite and if we
look at how this is going if you look at
how this would be fetched right it's
actually since this is going from that
max Y this this here is fetching
downward as you go so this is not the
correct loop right that we had like the
two loops inverted this one needs to
always go from here and it's going to go
down to a min Y right that is the lowest
that could go and and that in this case
is this right
so yeah just kind of have things spun
around there which was not surprising
for this kind of code and that means
that this here is going to have you know
these two loops are going to be in the
opposite place right that's where we
have them kind of backwards so yeah I
think that's okay and then here we're
just going to take that initial part and
clear it because these are the ones that
you know we we don't actually know where
they would go because there's there's
nothing for them to fetch from right and
this one here we were just saying all
right we have to take that sort of end
of
arrey and clear that out but I believe
that's correct and my only concern is do
I have the two movements in the right
place or are they if it actually the
opposite for D box'll that we'll see
there we go so now that copy is correct
again kind of it's a little bit
difficult to work it all out in your
head like that but when you write out
their team but you know again you take
it one step at a time and you can work
it out so now the voxel is being copied
around stabili so we get sort of a
stable result as we would expect and now
we just need some way of dealing with
that on all three axes right because you
can see as I'm moving around in here we
sort of have a problem where it's
unclear exactly it's unclear how we
would struck this routine to do it for
all three but we could start by making
this a little bit more generic right
let's try to rewrite this so that it's
something that can be done like more
cleanly right that doesn't require maybe
so much iffing around so the first thing
I could say is well what if I introduce
a DX or dy value right so what if I said
like okay we've got a D Y value the dy
value in this case is negative one right
and so I just said Y plus equals dy like
that and so in this case the D Y would
be 1 right so I could have that and that
would be the same loop right I have it
change anything but now I've got like
part of my loop looking the same as it
used to look right and if I run the code
it I should get the same results right
you know nothing nothing changed there
and so the next thing you can do is say
well alright so I have a max Y and like
a min Y I can start talking about these
like a little bit differently for first
so for starters instead of greater than
or equal to min Y and saying well that's
the lowest I could go I could just say
well suppose I just made it like B not
equal to
right so if I wanted you to stop at some
point I could say well whatever negative
voxel y is that's the lowest I can go
and I want you to stop after you process
that one right so if I just added dy to
it right like if I just said well
whatever the lowest value actually is
that I want if I then go one more step
after that that's the one that I should
stop on so I could call this stop Y and
just say well let's change it to a not
equal to right and then that would be
the same thing I could do here I could
just say well that to stop Y value when
you get to it don't use it and this one
didn't process it anyway so I won't have
to adjust the value right so now if I
compile that in theory I again have not
changed the actual rules right but I do
have a problem I can't test it yet
because these routines were using those
values but what I could do is say well
actually if we look at what these are
doing they're really just gonna do the
rest of the routine anyway they're just
gonna skip the they're just going to do
the last part that this thing failed to
do so maybe if I just initialized my
while loop with a Y value that persists
and got rid of it you know like here or
something right what I could do is say
well what if I just continue on down the
road and maybe introduce some other
value that's like a final Y value so
effectively these become Y ellipse I say
you know that so while we have not
gotten to the min Y value or rather I
should say to stop Y value right you
know keep going in this case while I
have not gotten to the final Y value you
know keep going
and then I would just need to know well
what is the final y-value right and in
this case the final y-value is just
gonna be like dy right it's like I want
to stop at zero right but I want to
actually process zero so I want like one
step past zero right it's the one I
would stop at and then presumably I
could do the same thing here so like
I've got a stop by value I can
initialize Y outside the loop to
whatever it should be I could do a while
loop it says you know go until you think
you should stop updating the value like
this the entire way right and then here
I just need to make sure that it just
keeps going until the final value and
the final value is just this and that
seems you know somewhat sane right I
think and let's see if that works at all
no it doesn't forgot one of my
increments sorry folks
you
and so that looks pretty reasonable it
looks like it's working just like it was
working before right but now what I've
done is I've made it so that I compute
these values separately right these
values could actually be computed like
this and then if I take a look at what
I'm left over with for my loops right if
if I look at what they look like they
look the same right so what I've done is
I've just kind of mechanically gone
through and changed out the values
inside the loops till they could be
converged and now my loops are exactly
the same so I only need one copy of the
loops right so if I then take these
outside of here right and I just say all
right these are the values that I need
to actually compute this you know set of
values do you I stopped why why final
why right then I can just compute those
outside and have one set of loops inside
makes sense this is kind of nice because
this means that I don't have to actually
have any conditionals in the control
flow of the thing the entirety of the
way that this loop works can be entirely
self-contained right all right so it's a
little more complicated in this
unfortunately once we actually start to
compose these two but that's just kind
of the basics right if I now compile
this I should get something that works
theory oops did I just one of these
there we go
you
oops snap in there
Oh obviously this must be set anew each
time through
so again this is really just making sort
of a parametric for a loop like a four
loop that we can control more explicitly
as we go and so that's just sort of
collapsing it down into something that
can be driven entirely with like a
little tiny packet of information which
is this if we look at these a little bit
more closely you know we cannot we could
probably see that there's actually some
other patterns here that we could
extract and even make this production a
little bit simpler but what I want to
get to is obviously this works the same
no matter how many dimensions we
actually have right so we could actually
do this the same on XY and Z and the
only really problem that we have here is
that when we're going to clear these
things they're sort of inclusive rather
than exclusive
right so if we actually just want to
talk about the copy that's pretty easy
it would look something like this right
and so these loops could all just work
and that would be all we would really
need this code would be identical for
all three axes right so we could do it
the same on all three of them and then
we would be done the problem that we
would have over here is with this part
right so the problem that we'd have here
is in order to actually do the clearing
we can do the clearing on all of the X's
here but then we kind of have to go out
on the Y's over and over again now and
it's a little ugly but you know what
it's not the end of the world so we
could just do it what that would look
like is this
so here we iterate over the X's we have
then we iterate over the X's we don't
have clearing each one right then as we
sort of fall out of the while loop we
then need to loop over the Y's like this
and say for each of those we need to
clear all the X's right so we're only
doing a portion of the lives but for
each one of those need to clear the
entire X row right and then the same
thing is true for the Z's but it gets
even worse right hopefully that makes
some sense to everybody so this would
then have to be copied right three times
one for each of the axes so you'd have
to basically be like okay you know here
comes the X version right
which just looks like this and then
finally we'd have the Y version I'll
show you the Z version which looks like
this and in theory then that would do
all the copies right
right in theory assuming I didn't screw
something up which I probably did right
don't ask me what it's going on there
and now you know maybe if we if we get
that debugged or whatever you know maybe
there's some bugs in it still but that's
that's what we'd have to do to clear to
process everything in the system
properly let's see if that has everybody
in a correct place before we say what
I'm going to say next
yeah so the only thing we really have to
change is this right here still needs to
have the voxel offset for each of these
things right but other than that this
may be it right
so there's the copy version right and
you know it seems okay and it seems to
sort of be working I do see some bugs
sort of any outskirts but that may be
because our voxel isn't large enough
when the lighting Center moves too far
I'm not sure but you can sort of see
that now we've got that stable copy
happening everywhere okay um but if I
isolate this piece of code what you can
see is that it's really rather absurd
right so if I take this and I put this
out here what we can actually do is we
could take this piece of code and we can
make it just a routine and we can say
it's block copy box so and all we really
need to know is like what's the cell
thing you wanted copied and what's the D
box'll right and then we could just call
this block copy voxel function and then
I'll do the copy and everyone's happy to
a certain extent anyway right but it's
really just I mean that's a lot of crap
right I mean look how many loops there
are and all this stuff we might want to
reconsider right and we might want to
say well is that really all that more
efficient anyway than just doing a clip
right so for example if we instead
decided to just do well all right you
know let's do a four I loop through the
entire voxel
which we would have up here we already
have that in the test caster wherever
that guy got off to here yeah so we
could choose instead to just say well
all right look
we could just loop over the entire voxel
and say we know where we actually are
right our current location is you know
Vox I XYZ we could say we know that the
person moved like a particular amount
and we just want to move by like that
same amount right so this is the you
know this is the value that we actually
want right and so in here we would just
say well the place that we want to get
this from is just the offset right of
these so it's it's really just like okay
I just want to do this right I just want
to do this operation I want to just do
this on the whole voxel but I need two
things I need to know which direction
I'm going in the voxel because I can't
do like the overwrite or whatever it is
right
so I do have that problem but
furthermore I need to clamp clip this so
I need to go like if I you know I will
zero like if you know inbounds do this
otherwise clear right and so this right
here would need to be tested to see if
this this was going to be inside or
outside of the voxel but then this
routine right looks a lot more easy to
manage and like I said the problem is
this test we could write pretty easily
it's just whether or not after you do
the addition you're still inside the the
bounds this presumably would want to be
like this for that although I guess you
wouldn't have to actually now think
about it you could just do this and then
do one test right so you could literally
just do
this so I think that should be
sufficient and those are like sampling
coordinates anyway right so you would
basically say right and again the reason
that we don't do this is because it's
unclear exactly how we would get this to
not overwrite itself so the only problem
and the only reason we can't write it
this succinctly which would be really
nice right if we could and I mean we
could even do it a little bit more
ridiculous than that right you could
imagine this it called again light box
will sell bad we could even write it
even more succinctly right you could
just do this
right so it would be very tempting to
write it in this way because it's a lot
easier to sort of read and there's just
a lot less going on there
what is the what is it complaining about
sorry I missed the error message there
you
and that is um it's just not clear to me
how we prevent it from over writing
itself because we just fundamentally
don't know which order these two have to
go in so if we were keeping two voxels
and we were just updating like a ping
pong buffer we could just run this and
this would be pulling from the second
one right so we wouldn't have to worry
about the override but in this case I
just don't know how we would actually
make that happen right I don't see I
don't see any way of doing that so this
you know because this would have to be
like that right and that just doesn't
seem straightforward because in order to
start doing that at the very least you
would have to parametrize these four
loops to go in either you know which
either the forwards or backwards
direction so it seems like we're kind of
stuck with this crap here you know
because I don't see what the like
obvious other answer is also I'm not
sure why that was there um so let's
leave it that for now because that's
really all I want to get done today and
tomorrow we can focus on what else we
want to do with it but for now let's
focus on that and let's let's go ahead
to a brief Q&amp;A
you
and while we're waiting for any
questions I am going to go in and put
this back to linear because pretty much
now we're I think keeping the voxel
stable so from now on we just kind of
need to figure out how we're gonna do
our blending and then I guess we have
one more thing we got to write which is
the voxel sampler for the light
transport code
but otherwise otherwise we're getting
there
you
since there's no questions I guess we
can pretty
wrap it up I am curious how did the
microphone sound today all things
considered we're gonna be trying two
different microphone setups I'm
currently waiting for a little like
stand thing and I'm going to try a
different microphone but I tried putting
a noise suppressor on the current one
which I thought might help
keep it under control
you
yeah Romans so what happened is the
internet was out here I don't know if
you saw my Twitter it was not super
clear exactly what happened either but
it got restored like it was out all day
and didn't get restored till like 4:00
o'clock so we streamed at 5:00 because
that was as soon as I could I don't know
if it'll be okay for tomorrow stream the
message we received about the internet
was pretty tenuous it was like we will
run the internet on backup batteries for
now and like I have no so I don't know
III don't know what's going on hopefully
we'll be able to stream tomorrow at the
correct time but that's why like I
wanted to stream today at noon and we
kept waiting for the Internet to come
back and it kept not coming back so we
don't know what you know I don't know
what to do about that but that was the
situation
you
really when the episodes just finished
10 reviewing where you are at now what
are some libraries that are added so I
can study before I get to the episode
they are added I open jail or something
along those lines the only thing we use
is OpenGL is the graphics driver
interface that we use we don't use any
libraries other than obviously the C
runtime library is still being called
for sine and cosine but we'll probably
be replacing those as well so we'll be
library lists we also don't use any
libraries for OpenGL either we actually
just call get proc address and link
directly to the driver functions
ourselves we don't use a library for
loading up in jail
you
Krita give a guest completion percentage
on the final lighting solution
so I guess what I would say is I can't
really give a percentage estimate what I
could tell you is that as far as I can
tell we're almost done with everything
except figuring out how we're gonna
blend these values together like I said
we hacked in one today just get started
and we'll leave that one in there
tomorrow I think we'll probably do is
enable full bounce lighting because now
we just can so tomorrow what we'll do is
we'll right the voxel sampler and tried
to bug it and then at that point we can
just turn on full lighting now will give
us full lighting solutions with full
reconstruction what we won't know is how
the heck we blend those reconstructions
as you can see it looks really really
good I mean this part right here looks
awesome I don't know if you've been
watching it for the case of direct
lighting interpolated on incredibly
sparse voxel it really looks kind of
like a real flashlight almost as if you
were simulating the flashlight per pixel
right I mean that just looks so good
right there I don't know um so that part
seems great and so I think we'll be able
to just go with that the question is
just how are we going to plan these
values and I do not know the answer to
that question and so I think what we're
gonna do is probably like I think we'll
be pretty much doing full lighting
solutions maybe by the end of the morrow
if not by the end of next weekend and
that will be like great but then we'll
be like what do we do at these blends
you know and so that's really the only
thing I think that's the thing that will
that is gonna be not final about it is
we don't know how to do those blends
right
you
I'm exploring spatial grits for
collision detection and I'm finding it
challenging to reason about how to
handle collision responses I guess I'm
not sure what spatial grids have to do
with collision responses can you be more
specific because normally spatial trees
are used for determining which elements
need to be checked for collision but
once they service that role they are
typically irrelevant afterward right so
what do you mean by collision response
you
so synchronizer man no you don't really
put colliders inside the grid per se
usually all you do is you just have a
grid and each cell of the grid just
stores like a pointer or something you
know there's a lot of ways you could
choose to store the actual data but each
grid just stores a list of all the
entities that overlap that grid or a
list of all the entities that are whose
Center is inside that grid usually is
the more normal way to do it and then
when you go to do collision you just
take how big is my object versus how big
is the maximum sized object that might
exist in the world search all the grid
squares in that radius and do the M
squared collisions against them right so
the grid is usually just there to like
break the N squared problem down to a
very small end
you
what episode do you talk about the
blending problem you're facing not sure
what you mean like color blending or
some numerical blending um what I mean
by that is that right now we have a
definition of a light-filled that we
know we can reconstruct exactly right
and the definition of that light-filled
is a light source intensity value with
pretty much any fall-off function that
can be roughly linearly interpolated and
a normal right and if we fill those in
the way that we're filling them in here
we get perfect reconstruction of you
know in risk square fall-off light
sources as you saw however while it's
trivial to fill that in if you just have
a light source and you go to each grid
square and say how far away is this grid
square so that's the intensity and watch
the direction and that's the normal
right that's trivial and that was what
our spirit test does that produces
exactly the right things in every square
so then even though we do this really
sparse version of it and then you do the
reconstruction you get exactly the right
thing that's the light field that's what
I talking about what's a light field the
blending problem is once we step up we
already sorted in that situation here
just in this test right here but once we
step up in a second to doing full light
transport what's the light field we
don't know all we're gonna have is
lighting samples that say in this
direction this is how much intensity of
light I saw that's what the light that's
what the light samplers gonna tell us
how do we produce a light field value
from that and the problem that we're
gonna have is if we just wanted to
reconstruct one light field that's
trivial we just blend all the values
together using linear blending and we're
done right maybe we weight the values
based on how bright the light source is
right
but the problem we're gonna have is that
we have the ability to do four light
fields at a time how do we produce four
light fields from samples what we
wouldn't know where to blend them right
do we blend them into light field zero
one two or three we don't know
and so we would need some way of
figuring out what the definition of
which light field is I've been thinking
of ways I might try to do it but I just
don't know and so we're gonna have to
try some things
all right I'm going to wrap it up
all right thank you everybody for
joining me for another episode of hand
made here it's been a pleasure coding
with you as always if you would like to
following series at home you go here to
the game on handmade Yoda or it comes
the source code so that you could follow
along with it that is it for today I'll
be back here tomorrow if the internet
actually working which it might not be
but if the internet is working tomorrow
we will do it so hope see you back here
for that until then have fun for
everyone and I'll see you on the
Internet
take it easy everybody