alright hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hero the show where we code a
complete game live on stream on Twitch
we don't use any libraries or any
engines this is designed to be an
educational stream that covers
absolutely everything that happens in
game development so there's no stone
left unturned and one of the things
that's very important to learn if you're
doing game programming and want to be a
professional at it is optimization of
course knowing when your code is too
slow and knowing what to do about that
and so we're at the first point really
in handmade hero where we're starting to
talk about that in any kind of detail
and yesterday I gave an overview of how
to kind of think about optimization from
a platform perspective like what are the
things that are involved in making your
code run quickly or not as the case may
be but we took all the the time
yesterday to explain all that stuff
because modern processors are incredibly
complicated unfortunately that's just
the reality of it I mean it's it's kind
of a double-edged sword if you will
because not only are they very fast
because they're so complicated but it
also means they're very hard to optimize
or to know how to optimize properly
because of that complexity so today
we're gonna start dealing with that now
we're gonna we just gonna assume that
everyone has had a chance to kind of
digest what we talked about yesterday
and today we're gonna start looking at
what we can actually do in practice to
sort of put put some of that knowledge
to use to kind of go okay what can we do
here to start to figure out what to do
to our code to make it run faster right
okay so before I get started we are
gonna be coding today if you would like
to follow along at home today is day 113
so if you pre-ordered the game on
handmade hero org you will want to
download the source code zip and unpack
112 the day 112 source because that's
what I'm starting with today so if you
want to follow along at home that is
what I am going to be working with now
what I wanted to talk about today again
is sort of the first steps towards
optimization what that process is going
to look like so I'll give you a brief
outline
the on the board here right and so what
I'm going to talk about here is just
sort of the basic process of
optimization that I like to do when I'm
trying to make code run run more quickly
so the first thing that you need to do
is you need to gather statistics right
so you've got to gather something some
information about your program so that
you have some idea of first of all why
is it slow
oops I should say why let's say where it
is slow might be a better way to say
that so we're in the program what we're
parts of the program are really causing
the slowness right and what are their
characteristics right so meaning what do
we know about those pieces of code such
that we can sort of say you know how
many things do they process how often do
they run just what can we say about them
in terms of how they are structured and
what governs their behavior right so we
need to gather some statistics and then
we need to to make an estimate right and
making an estimate involves saying well
okay given the statistics that I
gathered just not trying to be accurate
because processors are fantastically
complicated there's no way you're ever
getting accurate a very accurate
estimate but just complete ballpark
right make an estimate that's nice well
ballpark make an estimate of how fast
you think that code should be running
right so that you kind of have you know
now you know how fast it how fast it was
running and now you know how fast it
should be running right and then you
need to analyze your efficiency and
performance
now we talked about these two terms
right these two terms are important
because they mean different things
efficiency is what work you actually are
doing right a more efficient algorithm
is one that actually just does less work
it's not about how quickly it can do the
work that it does it's about how much
work it actually does do and performance
is about how quickly it does the work it
does have to do right and again you can
think of this as in the most simple case
let's say I wanted to add a bunch of
numbers together performance for example
is just how fast you wrote the code that
can just literally do the adding right
how fast is it how fast is it to add two
numbers together right and efficiency is
about how many numbers you actually had
to add together because maybe you can do
some kind of optimizations in your code
where you know that a bunch of those
numbers are going to be zero once you
can test a few things and you can just
eliminate them from ever appearing in
like the final sum right so efficiency
is about really you know getting better
efficiency is about reducing the work
that you have to actually do and getting
bane per for getting better performance
is about figuring out how to get that
work through the CPU as fast as possible
so once we have this we're going to
analyze our efficiency of performance
based on this information here right to
see what we can say about our chances
for optimizing the code and then finally
we can you know we just got to start
start coding right finally once we have
some opinion of what's gonna make the
biggest difference right can we can we
boost the efficiency of it can we boost
the performance right and when we kind
of have a plan that we think might
actually work then we start actually
programming something that will you know
is designed to be a faster version and
we see if it if it actually works right
so that's that's the process and so the
first thing that we're going to do is
the gather statistics which is just
programming right so we have to go ahead
and start gathering some statistics now
the way we're going to do this is we're
going to instrument our code
instrumenting means kind of adding stuff
to it to make it report the statistics
to us there are other ways that you can
go about
there are commercial programs which try
to analyze our code for you like vtune
and stuff like this we're not really
going to using those we're gonna show
how to write and gather statistics
ourselves but again if you're doing hard
core optimization you may want to use
some tools so tools from Intel or tools
from other places that might give you
some information or insight into the
running program that you wouldn't
necessarily get with the limited amount
of instrumentation that we're gonna
build here on the stream right so we're
just gonna do sort of the first pass
statistics style stuff so the first
thing that I want to know right is
inside handmade CPP we know that our
game update and render call is the
entirety of the code that we are
responsible for you know that's not in
Windows right so what I'd like to do is
I would like to figure out - how many
processor cycles in total we are taking
to run game update and render right and
then I would like to see how many
processor cycles in total it takes to do
some of the pieces of the codes that
happen underneath it so I can start to
get some idea of what part of the
program is actually slow now we know
kind of ahead of time that our renderer
is very slow right now because we saw it
get slow when we did changes there right
so we kind of don't really need to do
some of this work right now because we
we kind of know the part of the answer
already we know where the slow code
actually is but because in general we're
going to want to be able to track down
things that might be a little bit harder
to know in terms of performance I'm just
going to go ahead and do sort of the
general-purpose instrumentation so we
can see how we would find out what's
going on because really if I was just
trying to be as expedient as possible
then all I would do is just get a cycle
count for this routine and a cycle count
for the draw rectangle slowly routine
and compare them right I just see total
number of cycles taken for the whole
game code and then just the number of
cycles taken just for that one routine
and then I'd see kind of how much it was
accounting for right but I'm gonna do
something a little bit
fancier than that just for now okay so
what I would like to do is I would like
to kind of make some way of doing a
simple system which can which can record
processor counts and figure out how many
cycles were taken in between two places
and now if you remember we already
actually did this we have this code back
in call it's called our DTSC we have
this code way way back from when we did
the win32 platform layer if you remember
there is actually a processor
instruction called read time stamp
counter and this is actually the
intrinsic that causes the compiler to
output that assembly language
instruction and what that does is it
gives us a counter out of the processor
that says essentially where it is in the
instruction stream right it says
basically like I have done this many
cycles so far right in cycles of course
is a strange term these days because I
think different processors have
different ways of reporting cycle times
and this sort of thing sometimes with
speed step but I believe nowadays on
modern processors most of the time it
gives you sort of like what the cycles
would have been if the processor was
running at full speed I'm not entirely
certain so if you're in a speed step
kind of a situation where you have a
laptop processor that goes in and out of
power saving and stuff like that you may
have to think a little harder about your
are DTSC's I don't actually know you'd
have to verify that but assuming that
you're on a processor that you generally
have clocked in high-performance running
full-speed you can assume that your Rd
TSE is going to be relatively accurate
to what the cycle count is so what we
can do like we did before we had this
thing where we just figure out how many
cycles are have elapsed by taking the Rd
TSE at the beginning and end of a
routine which says what was the
timestamp counter at the beginning what
was the time some counter at the end the
difference between those is how many
cycles have elapsed during the run of
that code right and we can actually put
that we could do that directly write the
simplest thing we can do is we can do
like you know start cycle count here I
take the RDP SC and then we can do an
end cycle count at the end of it right
like so
and then we can compute a difference
right we could do that
and basically what that would look like
as we do that there and then at the end
we would go down here to the very very
end of it and we would we would put that
in here and this cycle is elapsed when
we got to the end of it that would tell
us what the total cycle count was right
now we have a problem here though which
is at least at the moment we don't have
any way of actually outputting anything
our win32 code of course can output
stuff but our game cannot really output
anything right because our game does not
actually have any we don't even have the
ability to display stuff right we've got
we've got no sort of we don't even have
thought support right so what I want to
do is just have a way of getting this
information out to win32 hand-made
proper and I'm actually gonna do some
you know people get a little overly
fancy sometimes with their performance
counters I'm actually going to do
something pretty simple and you'll see
what I'm gonna do here it's very very
straightforward basically I'm just gonna
do a incredibly simple thing which is to
just make a static table of these
counters that's it it's really pretty
boring right there's there's not a whole
lot to it but I'll basically show you
what we're gonna do so inside like our
game memory right I'm gonna actually
have a thing for timers here so we'll
actually have a thing that's like maybe
something like game timer or something
like this or game we should probably
call it debug right we'll call this a
debug cycle counter or debug cycle
counter sounds good to me we're gonna
have a debug cycle counter in here and
all that's going to be is it's going to
be a UN 64 which is going to be a cycle
count and that cycle count is going to
be recorded and what we'll do is we'll
just have some number of these
all right we'll just have in our in our
debug game memory when we allocate that
we will basically have some number of
these right let's say we have 256 of
these counters off we go
right and again they we can get rid of
these in the shipping game before you
want to that's not a problem at all
right and in fact we're pretty sure that
we probably would want to so what I
might do is go ahead and move those up
here to this handmade internal which we
already have a pound to find for right I
might say handmade internal debug cycle
counter right and then what I'll do down
here is just do an if around that right
so only if handmade internal is actually
defined we will will we actually have
these debug counters in there so then
what I want to do is well because I
don't want to necessarily make things
problematic for people who are on other
platforms you can see that if I use that
our DTSC primitive you know if your
platform didn't support already TSC this
would be a little bit difficult for you
so also what I'm gonna do here is I'm
going to include a little thing and we
can actually use the the thing which
tells us whether or not we're compiling
with the Microsoft compiler for the for
the moment to actually just make this
start and end bit of this code actually
be actually be just something that works
off of a macros right so basically if we
are on a compiler that we know has our
DTSC and we can expand this to include
other ones later if we want to will
actually make this macro do something
like this right so this will be a begin
time block an ID like so and what
that'll do is it'll take that that cycle
start count and I'll sort of use the C++
pasting operator there to append ID to
it just in case you want to have
multiple ones of them in the same area
for some reason and that'll basically
snap that are DTSC and then i'm gonna do
an end time to block same way here like
that and i'm gonna put the other code in
there and we'll just say that this one
is game update and render like so right
and then we'll go down to the end cycle
count and we'll go ahead and lock that
up and okay there we go and so we do
begin time block we do end time block
here and we go ahead and put let's see
this code in there cycle count we can
actually just click the RTT SC right in
there probably and then we can go ahead
and take this cycles elapsed and all we
have to do here is we don't actually
need to to store the cycles elapsed all
we have to do is have some notion of
where it's going to be stored right and
render so we just have to have some
notion of where it's going to be stored
and when we know that we can actually
just go ahead and get it so for right
now I'll assume that's in memory but
we're gonna have to do a little bit more
work than that because that's not always
going to be there like game memory is
not always going to be passed to
everybody so we might we were going to
do some things potentially to make that
a little bit easier so okay where is
that end block so this counter ID'd
there we go and so that will go ahead
and do that that difference for us so
you can see here we save the cycle count
into a local variable we append the ID
to it so it won't name conflict if we
have multiple E's multiple of these time
blocks in the same function although I
don't suspect we'll probably do that in
scope that way but just in case and then
what we're going to do is get the our
DTSC again at the end take that
difference and add it in to whatever the
counter actually is right
now I think what I'll probably do as
well just because why not
I might actually make this something
like because we have enums you know
debug I don't want to do this I guess
we'll do debug counter count debug cycle
counter attack and we'll just make an
enum of these right so what we'll do
here is we'll just say okay there's an
enum of these guys right and this is
gonna be all the counters that we have
at the moment okay and yeah and that's
basically it so what I could do as well
as I could make this a little bit easier
on people and say that okay the ID is
just what happens after debug cycle
counter so for example game update and
render I just go ahead and say debug
cycle counter game update and render and
now when I do that block here it goes
ahead and puts that in there right so I
think that should be basically it
there's a little bit of janky Nasir and
we may actually want to do something
slightly fancier I guess I'll show you
first how I do it how I do it in the non
fancy way and then we can kind of show
how to do it the slightly fancier way
and that way people can sort of see what
the difference between the two things
actually is right so let me go ahead and
compile this and and clean out the
errors before I move any further let's
see this actually needs to be switched
out at the type def there we go
and time block plus equals debug cycle
counter oh right and I need to
dereference that value there there's
that cycle count cycle count like so
alright and now in theory you know we
can if we run the game and go back in
here if we run the game nothing in
particular is happening but now actually
that value should actually be going up
with every iteration of the game code
basically and now of course we also
probably want to start compiling this in
in release mode and I'll talk about kind
of why we're doing that in a second okay
we are compiling it I also think
probably the other thing I wanna do to
cut down on our run times building those
ground chunks is a huge cost stress
right now so I'm gonna turn that off
just temporarily while we get our timer
stuff working and then we can then we
can go back to it in a second so Phil
ground chunk I'm just going to go ahead
and and sort of take that out of the
equation here like so so it will not
impact us at all okay so here is our
game running right and it's still
bleeding those ground chunks it's just
they're filled with yellow at the moment
instead of anything real so now what we
want to do is we want to start getting a
look at those timer values so that we
can see them a little more clearly right
so let's go into win32 handmade we know
that when we pass in memory it's going
to do the debugging it's going to do
those debug counters right and so when I
call game update and render actually
think it's just called update and render
in here because it uses the pointer see
here so when I call game update and
render what I want to do here is I want
to clear out those timers first just to
make sure none of them are actually set
to anything and we already have this
zero sized call which I believe I can
use in here I don't
remember if we exported that we may not
have so I suppose maybe I shouldn't use
it in here I know maybe I should use
Windows as zero memory call
you know what I think I'm gonna do it a
slightly different way
all right so what we'll do instead is
we're just gonna call after we go ahead
and do game updating and render and we
passed that game memory the game memory
will now be filled out so I want to do
is just have a call that's like dump
timers or something like this right okay
and I guess I want to maybe call it
something more like this like hey hey
little debug cycle counters like that
and so I'm gonna go ahead and pass the
game memory there and then what we're
gonna do is come out here and make that
actual call now again that call of
course is going to be one that we only
want to do if we actually have debug
counters all right
so in here when we actually do this guy
so if I do internal void handle T bug
cycle counters and we've got game memory
and there's the game memory I'm only
gonna do the inside of it if we have
internal on that way if the debug
counters get compiled out this routine
won't do anything which is what we want
right we don't want it to actually do
anything we don't want to try and it'll
it would be a compile error right it
wouldn't be able to access any of the
stuff so what I'm going to do here is
introduce a variable that's like the
total cycles I guess we don't really
need total cycles at the moment I'll
have to think about what to think about
how we do that one but as we get fancier
I'll show you more and more stuff we can
kind of do with these counters and
that's getting a little bit ahead of
myself there so let's go through the
counters that we have right we know that
we've got a certain amount of counters
in here let me bring up that platform
let's see here I'm count there it is
counter yes this should probably be
counters counters and we're going to go
through the counter index get each one
of those
and take a look at it so the debug cycle
counter is going to be whatever the nth
one of those was why why did I do that
little Spacey today I feel like it's a
little a little jumbled all right so
once we have these what we'd like to do
is in this loop we're just going to
start by just displaying what the cycle
count actually was and then we're gonna
clear right so that the next time
through it we'll be able to accumulate
its values again right and what I'd like
to do here is just again use the output
debug string which we have we've used
before to just print stuff out and again
this is just for debugging print out
eventually we probably want to build
maybe a little bit more when we have
done our list of things to do to do some
debug services and at that point we
would sort of maybe start to build our
own things like an output stuff a little
bit better than this but for now it's
totally fine to just use Windows to
print the stuff out it's gonna be kind
of annoying you'll see in a second
because you know it's just not that
great but what are gonna do one thing at
a time so anyway in the text buffer here
all we need to do is we want to
basically print out what are which of
the counter indices we're actually doing
and then we also want to print out
whatever the cycle time actually was for
that particular counter right so here we
go and that's a 64-bit number so in
order to print out that as a 64-bit
number we need to actually use the
64-bit print out syntax which I believe
is this nowadays on on Visual Studio
which is kind of weird but I think
that's correct will actually find out in
a second whether it is it's it's a very
strange syntax and not particularly good
but you know that's just what happens
what what it happens to be
I gotta change this to counters so okay
and then my output debug string there I
guess I should I guess I should take a
look at what I was actually doing yeah
we should probably also do a little
thing it just lets everybody know debug
cycle counts so and then that way this
guy will print that out and make it
clear alright so this will tell us right
how many cycles were actually spending
or at least we hope that it will this
should go to our debug output here right
it should say roughly how many cycles we
are spending to run the game
right now this is not including the code
that we're doing in Windows right but
this is what this is the actual cycle
count that we're getting and so if you
take a look at what that cycle count
actually is here right just it seems to
be relatively consistent you can see
that it's a pretty nasty number of
cycles that we are taking to render the
game as it is right because if you
remember we did some work yesterday and
took a look at what you know how many
cycles we actually had I don't know if I
believe I wrote down here yeah so per
core per CPU we calculated that we
needed to be under a hundred and seven
million cycles per frame but if you look
at this you can see right here that we
are already just in our just in our code
not counting whatever Windows has to do
in addition at 310 million right so we
are already missing our budget by 3x
which means that the maximum possible
speed our game could be running at at
the moment is one third of 30 frames a
second right or 10 frames a second
basically it is that correct
and that doesn't work that way sorry let
me make sure I do that math properly so
one thirtieth of a second we were at 107
and so if I want to do one thirtieth of
a second and it's going to be three of
those no I'm right it's fine it's fine
it's basically it's it's gonna be ten
frames a second so we're I wasn't on
cracker sorry about that I just go gal
carry away anyway so if that's the kind
of cycles that we're back like we can
already confirm what we know to be true
which is nice which is that if you look
at this right you can see that it's very
Sutter eight right and you can see that
it's not at all a reasonable number of
frames per second that we would want to
play at and our cycle count indicates
that as well it you know it's obviously
reporting a cycle count that's
indefinitely higher than what we could
hope to actually ship with right so okay
so the next step is taking a look at how
many cycles were actually spending in
any particular place right and like I
said what we'd like to do is sort of
start to gather a little bit of an
opinion about where that time is being
spent so let's go ahead and make another
one in here right just to see how long
for example you know maybe we'll see how
long rendering takes and we'll see how
long simulation takes or stuff like that
right so what we could do for example
we've got a routine which does our rent
which does all of our render retirement
right it's the render group to output
function and so what I can do there is I
can do begin time block like so and I
can do you know stick an ID in here
which is basically debug cycle counter
render group to output that and what I
can do is I can just go ahead and say
begin that
and and that not at the bottom right and
now what that will show us is that will
also show us mm-hmm oh of course
right we got to get to the next thing so
the next problem that we have right is
obviously that these debug cycle
counters are you know we would have to
pass them around to everything and
normally that's something that you would
probably want to do but in this case it
would be very cumbersome right what
we're trying to do is kind of jump in
here do some profiling and jump out we
don't really want to alter the
architecture of our program necessarily
to handle that right and so what we
probably want to do somewhere here is do
is use a global variable that's like
some kind of a debug global memory
variable right to be able to access
stuff like this even when we shouldn't
have access to it right and we would
want this to be something that's defined
only in this internal mode so that we
know that when we compile the game for
release no actual code is using it right
so we want that global to disappear just
in case somebody gets the wrong idea at
some point and actually tries to use it
for something which would be very bad
because we're not expecting anyone to so
we want it to go away basically when we
are not drive in there and well you know
what while I'm at this let me go ahead
and make sure that these two macros
compile out entirely on other platforms
so that they don't do anything all right
so if we want to do that right what we
could do is say all right there's some
external variable right that everyone
can access it's called
debug global memory right like so and it
is a you know a game memory pointer like
this and you know everybody who does
those it's going to go ahead and access
those right and so all I have to do now
is I have to inside the actual game code
I have to make sure that I set that in
game update and render right and this is
going to be obviously only if handmade
internal is valid
so that's it
and that's all we really need to do
there - just to make sure that we always
have access to that this it's nothing
fancy but now it compiles in and out and
now we can get those counters anytime we
want to right or at least we should be
able to all right so now if we take a
look at what's going on you know you can
see our debug cycle counts being
registered there and if you take a look
here what you can see is exactly kind of
what we already knew to be true right
but you can look at sort of the
difference between those and notice that
you know if I were to take for example
if I were to take this which is the
total amount of time we're spending in
the game and subtract from it the total
amount of time spent retiring the render
code you can see that our entire game is
only taking 681 thousand cycles right
like everything that happens in the game
is taking 681 thousand cycles except the
renderer
which takes the rest of the time it
takes the other 300 million some odds
are you know rough somewhere close of
close to that many cycles right so
already you can see we're starting again
a little bit of a picture right this is
far from a precision strike at this
point but you can kind of see that we're
already starting to confirm what we
already knew based on the fact that we
could very easily perceive the slowdown
so it like I said in this case it's not
really as investigative because it's not
like we have no idea what's slow right
so in this case we've we can see very
clearly how many cycles that's taking
and so what I'd like to do now is I'd
like to do just one more step of that
again just to kind of sort of show you
you know we're easing into this here I'd
like to do one more step of that and I'd
like to go ahead and inside our draw
rectangle slowly I just like to confirm
that draw rectangle slowly is actually
where our cycles are being spent right
because again you know that was just my
assumption and it was a good assumption
in this case because we saw it get slow
and we switched that routine which is
like a very clear indication but a lot
of times you may have a hunch of
where the performance is going but you
don't actually know and you never want
to axe on that hunch until you actually
confirm it because you may be wrong and
then you just spent a whole bunch of
time optimizing something that actually
wasn't the problem
right and that's never good so you
always want to make sure that you
actually know what the problem is before
you try to fix it right it sounds
obvious but you'd be surprised so many
people off to my stuff without ever
actually sticking out where the slow
part is right not a good thing okay so
moving on if I run this now and you take
a look at those cycle counts right you
can again see that it's exactly in line
with what we would expect right you can
see that pretty much all of our time is
being spent in that draw rectangle
slowly call and because the difference
between these is kind of minimal now
there is a little bit more you can see
that the amount of time spent in the
game is actually small compared to the
amount of time spent in the renderer
which is small compared to the amount of
time just been to draw a tiny triangle
slowly right like so there actually is
it's probably like the clear or things
like that inside the renderer that are
still taking a bit of time right but
that's a you know that's kind of a good
example but here's a thing that we don't
know right we don't really know if draw
rectangle slowly is slow because it is
slow or if it's because it's called
too often right now we kind of do
because I kind of have an idea of how
often it's called right but technically
let's go ahead and confirm that right
and it's pretty easy for us to confirm
that by extending our counter system
just a little bit so in addition to the
cycle count I'm gonna go ahead and here
and and do a call count right or like an
execution count what should I do this
kick count let's call it right so the
number of times this code path is
actually hit and that's really easy for
me to do all I have to do in here is
when I go ahead and retire this counter
here I can also in addition to changing
the are DTSC I can go ahead and change
the hit count as well to be you know one
one more than it was and that will tell
me how many times I've actually gone
through that particular block and
actually executed that particular block
right
and so in order to in order to do that
what I want to do is I want to go back
out to that win32 handmade where I'm
printing these out and I want to
basically say I want to extend this
print out a little bit to sort of have
like you know the cycle count so you
know something like this cycles and then
I also want to say percent do hits right
so I want to be able to say how many
hits and how many cycles and furthermore
while we're at it we might as well do
cycles per hit right we might as well do
a little like cycle per hit here and the
other thing you know what I could do
because we don't want to divide by zero
but we also don't care if a counter
actually has never had any hits what we
can do is say if the hit count is
greater if the hit counts actually
something other than zero we go ahead we
go ahead and print you back clear it
otherwise we ignore it so these are just
the places where the program actually
spent any time so we've got counter
index we've got the cycle count we've
got the hit count and then we've also
got the cycle count divided by the hit
count right and that's how long it took
on average to go through that function
right not a particularly useful measure
at the end of the day but you know we
could print it out and so we printed it
out right all right so you know there's
already kind of some interesting things
here right in fact just doing that we
saw something that I didn't actually
know didn't think about which is that
we're calling the renderer 13 times and
I believe that's because we're
refreshing ground chunks right but you
can see that right here and I wasn't
even thinking that I was thinking it was
just called once but it's not right and
then you can see here we're calling 64
we have 64 times that it's actually
calling the the draw a rectangle slowly
so you can see that based on these
numbers here what we can see is it's not
a question of drawing too many triangles
or such don't say too many rectangles
it's a question of
the rectangles themselves are large
enough and slow enough that we're
spending a ton of time just to draw any
given one of them right so there you go
so most of this stuff again is just
confirming what we already know but it's
usually a good idea to confirm this
stuff and more importantly it's a good
idea to know how to do this because
sometimes you don't know where the time
is being spent and it's pretty simple
just do a little hierarchical cascading
bracket like I did just now to figure
out where it is okay now there's a bunch
of other stuff that we could do but I
want to do one more here right which is
I want to put in one that I'm only gonna
put in temporarily and what I want to do
is I want to go ahead and figure out how
many pixels were actually you know how
many how many pixels are we actually
retiring so if I go into our render
group here and we're in draw rectangle
slowly I want to figure out how many
pixels were actually filling just at
this you know particular moment so each
time through this loop this is a pixel
right so what I want to do is I guess
I'm just gonna you know do it the most
straightforward way I'm just gonna go
ahead and count the internal block right
so I'm gonna call this like you know
fill pixel or something right and I'm
gonna go ahead and do that from here
down to the place where we actually
retire the pixel right like so that
makes sense so this is fill pixel and
you know what I'm gonna do something
else too
I'm gonna do something else I'm gonna
call this test pixel and I'm gonna call
this fill pixel so we can actually see
how many pixels we fill and how many
pixels we test right does that make
sense so we can kind of see the
difference between those like say okay
and in order to do that I would say just
have to add two more in here this will
be our test pixel and this
okay so now those are not particularly
interesting necessary for the cycle
counts what they're interested in what
I'm interested in seeing there is what's
our actual fill count how many pixels
are we actually filling versus testing
right and what you can see there just
right off the bat obviously we're
filling a tremendous number of pixels
but what you can also see is that we
tend not to be wasting too much time
there most of the pixels we test are
pixels we actually do fill right and so
that's pretty that's pretty good but
there's one more thing that I would like
to check out here right and let's go
ahead and and do that inside the render
group as well one more thing that I
would like to check is how often do we
actually need to fill that pixel because
remember we we have alpha blending right
and so we would be interesting to know
how often we miss as far as alpha is
concerned well you know what I'm not
good I take that back I'm not quite
gonna do that yet
that might be a little premature because
right now we don't really have enough
stuff on the screen to really get a fair
measure of that so that's probably a
little unfair but unsurprisingly our
fill pixel and our test pixel are very
similar and the reason for that is
because we're just we're not really
rotating much at the moment right in
fact if anything I guess I would have
expected that to be a little bit
different it feels like that's probably
me that that might even be part of the
fact that we haven't quite gotten a lot
of our edge stuff correct because you
would think these would actually be
exact right because we're never rotating
so in theory you should pretty much
always fill all of the Piett that pretty
much exact because we should if you're
not rotating we should always be able to
know exactly which pixels to iterate
over so that's a bit of a an obvious red
flag right there that we could that we
should be computing our bounds
differently or computing our edge
functions differently right so that's
something to think about as well
let's see here so we are talking about
filling this many pixels right that's
how many pixels were actually filling so
I'm going to take a look at that number
just for a second go over here to
scratch buffer so this is how many
pixels that we actually filled right or
I should say tested so at our current
resolution how many pixels are actually
on the screen would be the other
question right and it's 960 x 540 which
is 518 let's do that again want to know
how I can like there's got to be some
way to copy that into the buff into the
oh yeah it automatically puts it in the
kill ring yeah nice job you max all
right so that's the tested number of
pixels and that's the total so if we
take a look at these two here right you
can kind of see that actually right now
we're not really operating on that many
more pixels than the total number that
are even on the screen and that you know
suggests to me anyway that we're not
that bad off in terms of what's called
over draw and over draws just of course
how many times you like fill any given
pixel on the screen because remember
let's go ahead and make this a little
more explicit here right Duke Duke Duke
to do so we have this concept of over
draw right which is essentially how many
times do you touch each pixel
right because we kind of know what our
lower bound is we know that we have 518
400 pixels total so if we were to make a
renderer that only ever touched exactly
each pix on the screen once and put
exactly the right color there just in
one go it would have to do exactly 500
18,000 operations right that's like what
it would take and so overdraw is the
measure of how many times you have to
revisit pixels because for example
you've lit one thing on top of another
you are now over writing work you did
before right you're essentially wasting
the work that's on the underside and so
this speaks directly over draw basically
is render efficiency right it has
nothing to do with the performance per
se of the render it's not how fast the
renderer can actually fill pixels what
it is is how efficient is the renderer
right how often does it have to redo
those those pixels tell us exactly how
efficient our render is being so one
thing that we do know is as these
numbers diverge as the total number of
tested pixels diverges from the number
of pixels on the screen further and
further we're getting further and
further away from apt all right now
we're below 2 which isn't too bad
actually but it's also the case that if
you run the game there's nothing on the
screen right now right you know we're
not seeing a whole lot of things
happening on the screen so that number
will probably go up as we go and it's
probably we'll have to create some test
cases to force it up in the meantime
just so we can work on getting that
number down right how much time we got
we're got about 10 minutes left
all right so let's think about this what
have we done what have we done so we now
know some of these things that I said
are the first step we did that work we
now know exactly where we are slow and
we do know some characteristics about
that thing right we know that right now
it's not having a particularly large
problem with overdraw we know that it is
having a particularly large problem with
speed because we can also look down here
and see how many cycles per pixel we are
spending right we are actually spending
400 cycles per pixel
it would appear right if you actually do
this take a look at what this is saying
it's saying that this is how many pixels
and and if we divide this number by this
number we get 400 right so 400 cycles
per pixel is how much we're spending
right now and that brings us to the next
step here which is make an estimate
right is that good or bad
where where is that for it as I close
for pixel you know are we gonna get much
better than that you know what's what's
going on right so let's start by again
doing a little bit of experimentation
here just to sort of get a little bit
more of a sense of what's happening
let's just assume that the only thing we
were going to do we were not going to do
the normal map lighting right because at
the end of the day the normal map
lighting if we couldn't get it to work
fast enough us off render we could turn
it off but also we don't need to use it
for some of the operations right we
don't need to use it for like the ground
compositing and stuff like that so I
want to take a look and just see how
slow it actually is in this other case
where we don't ever do the normal map
compositing at all right so let's go
ahead and do that right so here it is
because again that actually we should we
weren't passing normal maps down so in
theory it should have been roughly that
and you can see that the number is
pretty close right it's like you know
375 cycles per pixel something like that
okay so that's all good if that gets us
kind of just a little bit more
information about what we what we need
to know so that's where we're at now say
something like that is what's being
spent at the moment so we have some
slight loose ends to talk about here
first of all these are ballpark timings
which is very important to understand
our DTSC does not necessarily give you
some kind of an absolute idea of exactly
how fast something is and you can tell
this just by watching the numbers scroll
by they're different right now the game
isn't in a different state it's drawing
the exact same thing right
nothing here is even animating at the
moment okay and yet if you actually look
at what's going on in these numbers here
you can see that they're fluctuating and
the ones that are fluctuating are
specifically the cycle counts not the
hit counts right because hey the
programs running deterministically every
time in terms of what gets executed but
the cycle counts are non-deterministic
why is that why do they change each time
well the answer is of course because
modern processors are incredibly
complicated all of that stuff I talked
about with the latency of going to
memory and whether things are in the
cache and those look-ahead windows and
all that sort of stuff that's happening
coupled with the fact that we're on a
multitasking operating system where
other tasks are doing things your your
process may be interrupted in the middle
of things all sorts of sort of unknowns
are if actually I shouldn't say notes of
variability is injected into those cycle
counts such that we can't say
definitively that they are any specific
value we can only use them as sort of a
general figure to show roughly what the
cycle count is now there are ways of us
getting that number down and like one of
the things that we could do and one of
things we probably will do in the next
pass but not today I don't know about
tomorrow but you know at some point in
the future one of the things that we
might do is make a loop that run
something many times and takes the
lowest cycle count across many runs and
that's
designed to see in the best possible
case how many cycles would this thing
take right which tries to squeeze out
that entropy that's in there and look at
it and also by running the same thing
over and over and over again you can
ensure that the stuff that's working on
is in the cache and try to eliminate
though so you can you can do things to
sort of create little sand boxes where
you can start to sort of poke at
specific types of cycle counts for
things but we have not done that now so
what we're looking at here are ballpark
cycle counts they are roughly how long
it takes to do things they're not
exactly how long it takes to do things
and it's important to keep that in mind
so you have to understand when you look
at numbers when you look at profiling
numbers in general that's always the
case you have to know what is the actual
thing that you're getting this piece of
information is it super accurate is it
super inaccurate is it somewhere in
between etcetera etcetera so that's what
we know now we've got about five six
seven minutes left something like that I
think we started eight minutes in so
let's take a look at making that
estimate right what are the things that
we actually needed to do per pixel right
what are the things that we actually
need to do so I'm gonna go ahead and
grab this loop out here right not
counting those things there I'm gonna
grab those out and I am going to take a
look at how much they cost right so what
do we have here right this is just
renaming some variables so that's not
necessarily something we need to count
but here's a subtract right so we
basically have a V to D so we have to do
two subtractions right right that's two
subtractions to the X and the y right
we've got dot products here right
in fact I guess I'll do them this way
we've got two subtractions or
subtractions it's two dot products
we've got one let's see one two three
four of those we've got three more
subtractions in here sorry for more
subtractions right we've got a negation
one two two of those and we've got these
perps in here but those probably can go
away right the perps are just swizzles
so those are fine yeah so that's only
gonna negate one of them because the
purple negate the other one right so I
feel like those are pretty
straightforward as well it's this is
again a little bit of a ballpark we've
got four comparisons that we've got to
do there let's see here we've got to
create the screen space U and V so we've
got you know multiplies let's see em
with Mac's yeah we're gonna have to do
those so we've got multiplies got two
there we've got again I'm doing this
really quickly this is probably we
should probably actually save this for
tomorrow but I'm just taking a quick
look to more multiplies right two more
dot products in there let's see we've
got two more multiplies two more
subtracts or multiplies to Morris
attracts too much the facts down here
and then the sampling okay
so the sampling let's take a look at
that
we've got bilinear sample is this guy
right here how much is in the sampling
the sampling is gonna be two multiplies
to adds see the problem with these is
well we'll see
so to multiply is two more multiplies in
there let's see adds got two and those
let's see these guys are all custom so
I'm gonna call this bilinear look up
that's gonna be that's gonna be tricky
to try and account for then our sr g gb
bilinear blend got an unpack four by
eight we've got to do four shifts for
right four shifts for masks and four
upconverts let's skip those for now and
then what else we got after the unpack
four by eight so we have to do that four
times and then we've got srgb - linear
which has to run on each of those like
so so here we go we've that's a constant
which can be folded out so we basically
have multiply multiplies so we've got
two four six more multiply seven more
multiplies that have to happen here
right so that's gonna be plus seven all
right there's your feed fifty-five tip
in here there we go we're gonna do
blended v4 so that's a wide one there so
that's actually four multiplies four ads
for subtracts right
oh no sorry one subtract
for more multiplies and former adds and
then we've got another for adds and
another for shifts and then layer one
extra GB for more multiplies three
square roots all right now that was like
I said I just kind of rushed you that so
that's not a good accounting of those at
all but again I'm just kind of roughly
looking to see what this is going to be
and let next tomorrow I guess we'll try
to do a little bit better job of
actually thinking through and making a
real estimate but you can kind of see
the memory look up here memory look at
the side you can see sort of where we're
sort of getting to in terms of how many
of these things were actually going to
have right we've got at least this many
instructions that have to happen not
including the lookup so we're talking
about like 96 of these instructions so
you know again totally fudging it if we
were to say that you know it was a
hundred of these instructions or
something roughly there about and each
one was going to be at least two cycles
or something like this you know so we
figured something like 200 cycles and if
we were actually four wide we would
divide that by four because each one of
these could operate on four pixels at a
time right we would say that just
arithmetic Li speaking 50 cycles per
pixel sounds like where we would be at
and that's super hand-wavy and assuming
that we didn't have to spend a whole lot
of time with the fetch right assuming
that the fetches were pretty well
organized which again is is probably not
likely but what I'd like to do there is
just say okay let's say that we were
super human and somehow actually did get
it down to that many then how what would
actually be our what would actually be
our timing at that you know if we
actually if we actually had to do that
what would our time be right if we got
it down to that our time would be 42
million to fill what's currently on the
screen right and we said we had 107
million so that's actually that would
actually be okay if we could actually
get it down that low I don't know that
we will be able to get down that low but
okay we're right at the end of time so
don't put any stock in this this was a
complete I probably missed a bunch of
instructions too i eivol that super fast
but basically what we want to do is
tomorrow right we want to go through and
think about this algorithm what it's
actually doing try to come up with the
minimal a number of operations that
actually needs to do to do it right and
count how many instructions that's
actually going to take us to do and once
we actually have that we could then
figure out you know if we code this
exactly right how many cycles could we
expect to get it down to and is that
fast enough right and it looks like we
could sort of compute our Headroom here
we could kind of say that you know we're
talking about something you know on the
order of a hundred cycles per pixel
would be acceptable because if you
figure you've got a hundred million
cycles or something like this to work
with and you're talking about a million
some odd tested pixels at the end of the
day you know you could see it being
something like a hundred cycles so sub
100 cycles would be where we'd like to
be who knows if we can get there or not
and again that's not including the
normal mapping so that's gonna be
another whole situation so there's that
you can also see why going wide would
help us tremendously here so if we had
say for example
one of those fancy avx2 processors
that's coming your avx-512 I'm not sure
what they're calling it that's coming
down the pipeline then instead of
dividing things by 4 we'd actually
didn't be able to hide things by 16
because we could fill blocks of 16
pixels at a time which would be a pretty
huge advantage for us right so again
like stuff to think about but anyway
that's just a quick thing we'll get back
into this tomorrow for now let's go
ahead and go to the Q&amp;A let's see here
like so so if anyone has questions on
today's stream you can go ahead and ask
them now save this guy off
why no text labels on the counters well
we just haven't needed them yet that's
why I said like maybe we'll actually go
do them later but I didn't actually want
to do them now because I felt like it
was not necessary that make sense I'm
sorry if this is something you've gone
over before but can you explain the
difference between new and Malak in C++
and when each is useful yes so the
difference between new and Malick is
whether you need to use C++ features
basically right so malloc allocates
memory new basically is something that
would do the same thing that malloc does
but then also calls the constructor of
whatever the thing is that you're using
right so things that have constructors
have to go through new unless you plan
to call the constructor manually
yourself but you're probably gonna do
that by calling new or placement new so
if you're not using things with
constructors then new is completely
irrelevant it doesn't do anything but if
you're actually you know if you're using
constructors it's the same with delete
and free right if you if you're using
destructors you need to call delete if
you're using just plain stuff that
doesn't have destructors you can just
call free it's your handwriting as bad
in real life as it is the tablet no but
it's not that much better it's
definitely worse on the tablet but it's
not fabulous in real life
can you also cut out instructions by
doing more work to save previous
computations like D minus x-axis
followed by D minus X axis minus y axis
yes we will absolutely try to eliminate
any redundant stuff although the
compiler already is probably doing some
of that for us since we're compiling
with optimizations on in the compiler so
there's that do you think we'll do
multi-threading in the software render
yes I do think we will do it we will
probably bin the screen into four chunks
and render each chunk on a separate
thread is it possible to quad pump every
operation I'm not sure what you mean by
every operation so and I'm not sure what
you mean by quad pump either if you're
talking about issuing instructions then
no basically the way issue is structured
issuing works is the processor can only
issue an instruction if it has enough if
it has a spare unit available to field
that instruction so you can kind of
think of like a processor as sort of a
collection of smaller processors almost
or you know they're called units where
you know each unit can do certain things
so for example maybe you have a unit
that can add two numbers together and
then you have another unit that can
shift a number right so if you if you if
that was your whole processor you had
adds and shift right then when two
instructions came in and it looks at the
first it looks at the structure and so
on in the next instruction if it sees
that it has an ADD and a shift that are
independent of each other they don't
depend on each other then it could issue
both of them to the two different units
right on that cycle
if there were two shifts it couldn't
because it only has one shift unit so
even though it could have issued two
instructions per cycle it can't actually
find anyone in the process of issue it
to does that make sense
so figuring out stuff like how many
instructions you can issue per cycle at
every point in the program is actually
again a bit of a hardcore optimization
topic because it involves knowing the
processor well enough to know how many
units of each type it has and whether or
not they would be able to issue on that
cycle or not right and that depends on
when they retired whatever the last
thing they issued was and it also
depends on how big that out of order
execution window that I talked about is
where the processor can look ahead and
pull out things that it might be able to
do so again a very complicated question
and typically it's very hard to know on
an x64 processor it's like kind of the
worst case because x64 processors are
very varied and they have lots of
minutiae and stuff like that and so you
know I don't really know I haven't ever
done that hard of optimization for it on
the Xbox 360 I did do that serious of
optimization at one point and you know I
knew that Prosser very very well so I
could tell you I actually knew like
exactly like okay at this point it could
issue these two instructions because
they don't conflict and this that the
other thing right and again that's just
a question of usually it's a question of
need we probably won't try to optimize
things that far on handmade hero like I
said but you know sometimes you ended up
in position where you do need to and
then you need to know right
brain cruiser I meant put it in a wide
instruction ah okay
so your question from before when you
said can you quad pump any instruction
you're you meant could you put it in
wide so the answer is unfortunately not
and avx-512 I believe fixes some of this
but sse2 and AVX at least I think
AVX at least sse in fact all the SSC is
all through up through four and so on
there's a bunch of things they can't do
wide so for example you cannot do memory
lookups wide right which is a problem
for texture fetching right like we are
going to compute for Texel locations
that we want to load or stuff like this
potentially and we'd like to go fetch
them all but we can't and so that's a
problem right so basically you're
talking about your floating-point
operations and your integer operations
you can usually quad pump just fine but
anything that ends up being in that in
that memory access kind of space sadly
you can't it's it's unfortunate but
avx-512 I believe fixes that because the
Larrabee instruction set had these
things in it and I believe that avx-512
is finally getting them all moved into
the main line and so my understanding is
it'll be in there eventually would you
talk Jeff into doing a separate
optimizing stream where you are the TA
yeah I mean we could try I don't know I
mean I wouldn't do that anytime soon
because we've got so much stuff to get
through that it's not that necessary to
we don't need to have that level of
optimization right now but you know
maybe when handmade hero's done we could
go at say here's the current render or
you know what would you do to to speed
this up
looks like that is the end of the
questions am i right am i right people's
looks like it to me all right
if that is the end of the questions then
that is the end of the stream okay so
basically we're in a pretty good spot
now I mean we sort of have you know we
sort of have an idea of what's going on
we need to now kind of get down into the
the nitty-gritty of these this routine
and figure out what it is that we
actually need to to do to it and what we
can expect to get out of it in terms of
performance if we did it really well
right and the normal mapping we also
probably want to take a look at just to
see what you know how realistic it is to
be able to do you know that sort of
lighting on there and again maybe that
might be something that we can't do in
the Safa render because it's too slow
and we have to do it only on the
hardware path and that's fine too but
either way we just don't know right now
right so what we need to do is we need
to go ahead and actually work out all
the stuff that we need to do and figure
out what our estimate is for how fast
that might ever run in practice and then
we can sort of have a better idea of it
right so that's what we'll get to
tomorrow we will start to try and build
that estimate and build that sort of
understanding of what the routine
actually needs to do and so I hope you
will come back and join me for that
again that's 5 p.m. so Center time same
time same place tomorrow so thank you
very much for joining me it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always I
hope that you have sort of I hope I hope
that you're in an optimization mindset
now and are looking forward to speeding
our game up into to a nice to a nice
clip if you would like to follow along
at home with source code and play around
optimization yourself you could always
peer to the game on handmade hero org by
using the little PR
button again it comes with all the
source code so you can download it every
night I upload it whenever I'm finished
programming here for the day if you'd
like to support the video series we also
have a patreon you can subscribe to that
we very much appreciate we have a tweet
bop at tweets the schedule at you if you
want to catch the the show live that's
the best way to figure out when it's
gonna be live at a given time it gives
you plenty of advance notice and finally
there's a forum site that you can go to
where you can ask questions or look at
ports to Mac or Linux or check out the
annotated episode guide all that sort of
stuff so definitely check that out when
you get a chance until then have a
wonderful evening and I will see you
guys tomorrow for another episode of
handmade hero take it easy - everyone