start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade hero sure we code a
complete game live on stream we are well
we are just in the middle of doing some
modifications to the way we're handling
Z and the engine and we sort of stopped
the stream last week at a point where I
was like I would like to stop having to
have all sprites on the screen be sorted
through the same sort path i would like
to basically have them split up into
like you know tranches basically where
we've got sort of layers that are
handled separately and each layer is
then sorted through the sorting system
so in order to do that what we will have
to do is I we kind of have to come up
with some clever ways of making it so
that the you know the code that's
actually sending the stuff down the
renderer doesn't have to do a ton of
work to do this segregation right
because what we don't want to do is we
don't want to make it so that there's a
ton of work that goes into having to
figure out how to parcel these things
out we want to make that as easy as
possible so there's a number of ways
that you know cross my mind as to how to
do it we talked about one at the end of
last week but probably what I want to do
right now is just briefly talk about the
situation and sort of discuss what we
can do to make it work uh so essentially
here is our problem and I'm going to
move down to a new thing here today is
day 3 15 0
I don't know why but for some reason
Milton always ends up thinking we have a
mouse after a while I think it's got
some kind of a bug they're not sure what
it is exactly all right oops day 3 15 so
layered sorting so we have a couple
different ways that this could go but i
just wanted to sort of explain a little
bit about what i mean and why this is
sort of something that there's a lot of
ways we could do it and we probably only
want to do it in one specific way once
we figure out like what's going to be
the most natural right but we don't it's
hard to know necessarily a priori what's
which is going to be the best so if we
think about what's happening here we
have a set of entities and we've got a
lot of them i guess i should say
entities we've got a lot of them and we
don't necessarily know anything about
them at the outset right we don't even
necessarily know how much stuff they're
going to draw all we have is giant array
in each or entity maybe has some
components to it you know an entity can
have more than one sprite associates
associated with it and what we want to
do is we want to go from this over to
the other sort of representation of it
inside the render which is per layer
right so we want like a layer layer
layer and inside here we want the
sprites that are part of the layer so
the problem is first of all if this were
completely heterogeneous in terms of
where the layers go then this would kind
of be a Swizzle engorda situation right
we would end up having stuff that kind
of goes like this sort of a thing right
we you know who knows what's going on
but we would sort of have all these sort
of crosswise like okay every single
entity is going to get mapped to us up a
specific layer and there's no real
coherence between them and whatever
however if there is order to our
entities then it's possible that that
doesn't necessarily have to happen right
it's possible that if there is order to
the entities than what we could actually
do is just sort of use the use the order
of the md's in here to imply where they
go and make things a little simpler
right so those are two separate
scenarios and let me tell you why we
don't necessarily even know which one we
have so if we didn't have any idea how
the end of these were ordered in the
list then we would have to say well it's
definitely going to be this kind of
swizzle sort of scenario but keep in
mind how we got the entity list in the
first place the way we got the entity
list is we actually did a walk through
our spatial data structure for storing
the entities and we actually walked
through a 3d sort of cubic I don't know
what you want to call it almost like a
voxels right it was basically like a
gridded spatial partition in 3d and we
had something that looked like this and
during that call to begin sim if you
remember we walk through this list and
we grab all the images out of here then
eyes out of here here here here whatever
right so what this means is that when we
built this entity list in the first
place it was actually already sorted by
layer when we grabbed it because we
started with the bottom Z layer or even
if we didn't we could decide to start
with the bottom view layer then the next
day layer then the next you layer right
so we can actually assume that these are
Z layer sorted in the first place right
when we initially unpack them when they
come out of begins sim we know they're
already in order here's the problem we
then go ahead and move them right
because all the entities then get
stimulated and ninety-nine point nine
nine nine nine nine nine nine percent of
the time they are all going to still be
on the same Z layer that they started on
because most of the time in a 2-d game
like this people are moving around in a
room or not moving around at all like
all the trees are just stationary right
so most of the time whatever your Z
layer was coming out of begin sim so too
will use e layer be going into NCM and
so if we wanted to use the order that
was implied by the entity list we would
know that that order is generally the
same throughout the entire sim process
so we could just do something where we
just go okay spin through the list until
we get to the first person who's on an
Uzi layer then we spend to the list for
that sea layer and so on and just it
segmented that way but the caveat there
is like I just said you end up with a
problem which is that people may have
changed their Z layer so some people may
have been simulating and they're just on
the edge and they're about to transition
from one z lair to another during the
sim step they make that transition and
now they're in a different Z layer than
they used to be in and in that case we
would now be putting them in the wrong
layer for one frame on the next frame
they'd be in the correct layer right
because they're going to get packed back
into the spatial partition and then at
that point you know everything's fine so
that's the situation that we're in and
what that means is we can either do one
of two things we have a decision to make
either we can leave everyone in the Z
layer that they were in when they got
unpacked and begins sim and not have to
do any work to sort people into layers
but we would have one frame of lag in
updating the apparent Z layer of each
entity during transitions or we cannot
do that and have some separate system
that does the sorting post facto to
resolve those Z layer problems that's
the choices
uh now we could do a slightly more
hybridized scheme and what that would
look like is suppose that we took the
enemy list and we started sorting the
entity list to produce an enemy list
that was sorted by Z layer well instead
of doing something crazy like a merge
sort or something like this which would
be a full-on you know just like we had
over here a full-on sort that would take
time and you know temporary space or who
knows what we could leverage the fact
that we know that very few entities will
change their position in this list and
actually just use like a bubble sort a
very very simple bubble sort and it
wouldn't even really be a bubble sort it
would be more like a push down sort so
basically what would happen is you know
we would sweep through the list and any
entities that were on the wrong Z layer
we would pick them up into a side buffer
or something right and then place them
back down and swapping out people who
were at the beginning of the new 0z
layer list or something like this right
so we could write a specialized sort
that would sort of fix it up and what I
think my assumption so I'm just again
I'm talking all this out with you so
that you can see what my thought process
is and hopefully it makes some sense my
assumption is the right decision here is
to say well we don't even know if we
care whether we have one frame of lag
and Z layer updating and it seems like
we could write a special-purpose sort
that was very fast to fix up the enemy
list in the case where we do know that
that has happened and we care so maybe
what I would suggest is let's start by
just using the entity list as is and
using the original Z layer of each
entity and then if we find we are having
visual bugs that result from this then
we will go and write a sort that
operates on that a list post facto to do
the fix-up how's that sound
alright so that's what I'm going to do
no mystery to it right that's all there
really is to say I'm going to go ahead
and get started today is day 3 15 so
again if you're trying to follow along
at home you will want to unpack day 314
source code into a directory that's the
directory I'm sorry that's the source
code version that I am starting on so
yeah do that so yeah as I was saying at
the end of last time stream if we do
want to approach this the scheme this
way which I think we do then we do need
some additional information in the
render system and we sort of Wow typing
typing is hard we added it at the end of
last last week stream I think at least
that's my recollection and if if i
remember correctly what we did is we set
a little token in the stream that would
basically let the this order know hey
you've reached a barrier so sort these
guys but but you don't have to sort
anybody else right you don't have to
sort them with anyone else so start all
these guys and then next time sort the
next batch the next time so our next
election so we already now have a way of
inserting those sprite barriers so what
I think we can now do is when we have
our game render what we should be able
to do in the entity code that actually
outputs this stuff is first of all I
guess we need to go into sim region and
just make sure that everyone actually is
coming out in that order right because
the loop where we loop through where is
that at well let me just search for
begins sim we want to make sure we're
going by Z and if we look here it's
turned out our loop is already exactly
in the order that we want it just
happens that way you know we don't have
to reorganize it you can see that we're
going by min chunk Z first and then
we're going up in Z so that's perfect
that means all of the minimums the
entities will be grabbed first the next
tier entities and externally is up and
up and up so we should have then an
entity list that's perfectly in order
the exact way that we wanted it to be
and so all we really need to do now
is insert those barriers when we're
actually doing the rendering so when we
come through here and we actually are in
the entity unpacked enemy list doing the
rendering what we should be able to do
is now say all right before you know I
was sort of doing this map into chunks
face thing finding out what the Z layer
is of a particular entity I don't
actually want to do that anymore what I
want to do is just look back at the old
world position of the entity right I
want to look at the entity as if it had
not been moved yet I one look at its old
position just for purposes of figuring
out the layer is because like I said
we're using last frames position right
so in doing so I want to look in here to
see where it's actually placed I assume
that that is stored in here somewhere
but I don't actually know let's take a
look we should have a world position
somewhere shouldn't we okay I guess we
don't actually store that i'm not sure
why we don't persist it i guess maybe
because we don't need to persist it i'm
not really sure but I guess that's fine
so either way I'm going to go ahead and
put that in here I guess all we need to
store really is the Z layer so I'll just
store z layer like so and all we have to
do now is when we do that unpack I can I
can update that Zieler so inside the sim
region when we unpack here it's really
just that chunk Z that I want to know so
when we unpack one of these guys doing
this sort of pact when we do the desk
when we do this sort of the clearing and
that sort of stuff here I guess I'll
just do it like this I'll just say that
the the Z layer is going to be whatever
the chunk see is here so now everyone's
tagged with which one they are and then
when we come through here we could just
say well okay when we're going through
these entities I just know that I need
to insert that that token basically that
thing that says hey you need to you need
to break the group here I just need to
do that periodically to let the system
know what's going on all right so let's
do that
so first of all I'm going to need are
running I'm basing it a piece of
information that's a running knowledge
of what the z-index that actually should
be so what I'm going to do here is I'm
going to say all right I've got a
necessary to that's like the current Z
layer and that current Z layer is going
to be and I guess I'll say current
absolute zoo layer just so we're clear
on what that actually means i don't mean
one of these things here so we have a
current absolute sea layer and that
current absolute sea layer is just going
to be if we have any entities at all
it's just going to be whatever the first
one of those is right so assuming that
there is an entity count of any kind
because if there's not we could just say
it's zero because we're not going to
output anything anyway so if there isn't
any kind of any kind then really all I
want to do is just grab whatever the
first one is and that's the Z layer that
we're going to start on so you know
whatever that is is what we'll start
with then from then on or we're going to
do is we're just going to update the Z
layer every time we output one of these
entities to make sure that we know
whether we move to a new internet right
so in here this disjunction now we could
we can also pull will be able to get rid
of that which is good like I said I
always want to I want to kind of pair
that down so we kind of just shove that
into the system we should be able to
sort of pair that down now let's go
ahead though and finish what we're doing
here before we embark on that so we have
the current absolute Z layer what we
want to say is if the current absolute Z
layer is not gonna you know not going to
match so if we were about to render
somebody in a layer that isn't their
lair first of all we could assert that
we're always monotonically increasing so
you can say like let's assert that we're
going up in Z because we know that we
need to sort of put them in slices that
go higher and higher and higher so we'll
start that that's true but assuming that
that actually is true then what we want
to do is say all right but let's then
co-op this new zeal air as the Z layer
that we're working on and we want to
then insert a we then want to insert a
what's so we're looking for a tote that
that that's sort of barrier that's what
I
for everything we want to insert that
sort barrier that lets it know so while
I'm doing that let's go ahead and fix a
few of these things here the entity Z
layer we don't need to do this stuff
anymore so in order to figure out the
the sort of relatives e layer here we
can just do that subtract where you take
the Xeelee r minus chunk see because
that's all we really wanted to know in
the first place so we can make that
happen that'll tell us the relative Z
layer I also don't really know yeah
we'll come back to that a little bit I
suppose but anyway we then can can get
rid of this particular piece of
information here but either way you know
I can preserve it for the time being if
I wanted to buy going like this once we
have that information and we have
relative layer we know that only if the
relative layer fits within our layers
are we going to render anything so
really if we want to I think we can
dispense with a little bit of this
situation here I can just move this
inside because we know we're not going
to care about this stuff if we're not
going to render the guy right so we come
in here I see it's different I want to
do this absolute layer thing but then
what I want to do is I want to insert a
sort barrier right or maybe I should
keep our name and kissin say push sort
barrier to the render group I want to be
able to say hey this is a sort barrier
go ahead and put in one of those special
markers that you need to put in to make
that stuff work so back in the render
group we need that to actually happen
and so where I've got push render
element I believe we'd also have another
one here that's you know a push sort
barrier that takes the render group and
all that's going to do is it's just
going to do exactly this operation here
right and since that operation is
relatively relatively simple I'm just
going to copy it because we don't care
about a lot of this stuff right so when
I copy it if we do this we really don't
need the entry to be anything other than
that special marker right we don't need
any of this stuff at all we could just
say that the entry offset needs to be
whatever the sort barrier
ki actually was oops which is in here
somewhere sprite barrier offset value
right so if we push a sort barrier
that's really all we have to do is is do
this push but we have to make sure that
we could that we could actually push it
right we do need to actually be able to
push it on there so we still need to
check in here that we would not be
advancing past the place where we could
legally do it makes sense but that's it
that's all we really need to do for that
there we go alright so that's the basic
idea now we actually I have to make this
go and actually work right I know if we
really got around to finishing this code
so i actually want to go inspect that
this is the code that actually has to do
something with this i don't know that i
actually did this particularly correctly
so i want to actually take a second and
make sure that we've actually got this
code correct alright so inside build
sprite graph now we're doing is saying
let's take a starting value and what we
do is we start at that starting value
and then we go forward to the node count
incrementing by one each time unless we
get to the part where we encounter the
sprite barrier offset value if we do
encounter the sprite barrier offset
value we're going to break now there's a
problem with this which is that then we
return that note index a I think we
don't increment it after so really I
think what we technically want to do
here that that's actually not quite
correct what we technically want to do
here say ok when we hit the offset value
we actually still want to do the
increment we want to break like after
the increment essentially so that's
that's a little bit more correct there
and similarly if we don't initialize the
flags value which we know we wouldn't in
the case of sort barrier we can't assert
on that because it's going to be garbage
right so that's a little bit more
correct down here when we see when we do
our sorting and so on you can see we
start with the first index of zero and
then we're just using that return val
and we never increment it here and
that's the crucial part so it has to be
come back pointing to the next valid
person
so I can start again but I think
otherwise the code is mostly right so
let's go ahead and start the debugging
process as we go alright so first off
we're getting an assertion on the flags
value not being cleared properly and so
I'm not sure exactly why that's
happening let's take a look at at what
we get there and essentially that that
means you know this this value that
we're looking at right is not a is not a
sprite barrier value right because you
can see that it's offset is not set to
like FFF FFF FFF so what I might want to
do just briefly is I want to see what
node index a is 233 I want to see what
the input nodes actually are in this
case and I want to see let's take a look
here XS let's play yeah so that's
actually it looks like it's just
something that has been processed
already so what I want to do here is say
okay let's take a look at input nodes
plus 2 32 right let's look at the
previous one so you can see that the bug
happened exactly where we might think it
would happen right it happened right
after we processed one of this one of
the sort barriers so I clearly just well
I don't clearly just have anything my
mental assumption right that I'm making
during this dividing processes like I
expect to have a problem near the new
code this looks like i'm having a
problem you're the new code so let's
take a look at what actually happens
there okay when we hit that barrier
offset we increment the node index to
the next value and then we break out of
here right so when we come back in and
we start again we're going to be
starting with one that's one after the
one that we are on right so in theory
it's a shouldn't have had any flag set
because we shouldn't ever have touched
it right and we shouldn't ever had done
anything with it because we never would
have checked anyone out past there
that's the Assumption anyway clearly
that assumption is wrong or there's a
more straightforward bug in the code but
that's you know that was sort of the
thinking behind that particular piece of
code right
and so in here looking at the way this
this works you know it looks like that
should have been the case oh but you
know what we have a separate bug here
which is that this is not the correct
neither of these two things are correct
so walk sprite craft is kind of busted
at the moment let's fix that first
before we do any further debugging all
right so what's happening here right is
we sort of have a notion of whatever the
first index is we then pass account here
but really this is going to give us back
you might say last index right it's
giving us back whatever the index is
that we would do after you know and now
I think about it this is probably
something where I'm going to want to not
increment this because in the case when
I actually hit the node count I want to
know that and that'd be a little bit
easier to do here all right so anyway
what we do is we hit the last index we
know that whatever that one is that
we're on was the last is a no no wait
I'm lyin I'm fine I overreacted I
overreacted there it's okay so this is
really one past the last index right so
if I get one of these and I'm building
this right graph here I know that I'm
gonna have to compute a new count right
I need my one pass last index minus my
first index to be these are this is how
many of the things I need to process
right and so I need to pass a different
count cure so I need like a sub count
and I know where to start because I
obviously know that the first index
entries plus first index is the base of
the array and I know the sub cam but
there's a subtly here right and the
subtlety is I get back this one pass
last index it might be the actual one
pass last index and this might be valid
or it might not be because it might be
that the count is now including the sort
barrier and I don't want it to include
the sort barriers they don't want to
actually draw our process the sort
barrier at all so
but what I want to do here is say well
if one passed last index is less than
the count then the sub count should be
subtracted right I should decrement by
little and the first index should be
should be advanced right but before I do
that oh no it does I'm sorry that's it
that's it anymore nevermind that was if
I was doing it the other way the subject
should be decremented to not include the
sort barrier then at the end all I
really have to do is say okay now I want
to advance my first index to be wherever
my one pass last index was and that
should be ok so now at least we're not
calling walks right graph with the
totally wrong information and we should
be able to get a little further than
buggin process ok I really know what
this is talking about here adage front
equals at index yeah well we gotta we
gotta step to this and actually see what
we're doing here let's stop that and go
to hear ok so we call build sprite graph
the first time and we get back you know
a first index we're going to have
prosthetic 0 obviously we're going to
have one pass last index I think of 233
right and so since that's less than the
count that means that our sub count is
actually just going to be 232 right
that's how many we're doing because we
don't want to process that last value so
we're going to process oh hi yet another
bug I already saw so this count value
right is also has to be adjusted here so
all that stuff also has to be addressed
at hopefully that makes sense anyway
like I said we go through here and we're
going to pass you know the standard
count and entry is the first time
through we're going to compute how many
there are we're then going to pass sort
of the offset it array and the sub count
was 232 we're then going to update this
index point to 33 and we're going to
repeat the process right this time
through we're going to actually change
the count and the entries to here so
we're going to start to 32 and go only
201 forwards and we're having an offset
input nodes right so we're going to go
ahead and process all those guys oops
hit me
actually change the file i hope i didn't
and then we're going to do exactly the
same thing walk to a sprite craft again
and so on so forth right okay uh so hmm
it looks like here walk input nodes
it looks like here we are still okay so
yeah we got yeah this is one of those
little nasty situations so we also still
have one problem which is that all of
our indices are based on the wrong
things potentially I guess trying to
think if there's any places where this
actually comes into play but when we
talk about note index a really I guess
we don't we don't want to do it quite
the way we were doing it because since
all of our indices have to be based on
the group we don't want this note index
8 to be absolute right we want this note
index a to be relative so I think we
actually want to do it this way and then
we want to just be able to return
whatever that count actually is like
however many we actually did so I'm
going to take it back i'm going to say
this is the way we would do it we
wouldn't pass this in we would just say
okay let's pretend you just handed me a
group I'm going to do it like I did it
and then return you the count of things
I actually processed right then I can
make this code a little bit cleaner here
so it doesn't have to think quite in
that same way and have sort of the weird
thing it's everyone's indices are based
off of a standard basis right I can then
say sorts pipe bound like sub entries is
going to be equal to entries plus first
index and then I can say well alright
then call it and get the sub count
that's what I'm going to get here I
don't have to pass this first index
anymore I know that's just sort of what
I'm keeping track of so I go ahead and I
say entries plus first index I get the
sub camp by saying okay what you know do
the build sprite graft operation
subtract from the total count wherever
we were first index add to the entry so
we're basically creating a new slice of
that array or just pointing to a new
slice of it and then what we want to do
is say well the the sub count is just
what we returned directly but we still
want to say if that
if that sub count I guess if the first
disposed something out wouldn't have hit
the end we might want to do the
adjustment but I don't know if we
actually need to do that let's take a
look at how that's going to work so when
we come through here i'm going to say
we're going to break with with our node
index a sort of pointing at the right
place so really this this count will
always be correct the only question is
do we need to advance afterwards right
and I think that that's pretty
straightforward we just say the first
index is is equal to it adds the sub
count plus one so it's always going to
move by however many we processed and
then skip also skip the barrier if there
is no barrier because this is the very
end it's okay because it'll just be a
little higher than cow be one over where
it should have been but that'll still
terminate the loop right so I think we
can make this a little simpler here by
just saying okay then we've got almost
everything in a pretty condensed fashion
and that is just a little less looks a
little less error-prone a little more
clean to me so okay so now let's try
that and you'll see starts the debugging
from there because I think that's a
little bit better Jimmy all right so
we've got a bogus clip wrecking deck
here that just suggest that we probably
have a bogus offset ya doing so what I'm
assuming happens there and I think this
is probably actually pretty self-evident
so yeah so we have one more thing we
kind of need to deal with which is that
the push buffer element count if we take
a look at what happens here when we push
the sort barrier we need to increment
the push buffer element count for words
but at the end we won't actually have
that many push buffer elements you know
what I'm saying
so I'm not sure exactly where we're
getting that when we output our things
we're trying to output I'm not sure who
decides how many to draw but I assume
that what we would need to do here is
say well since we're only out putting
things in the wok sprite craft since
we're only outputting things sort of
periodically there and the out index
array needs to get advanced right
because we've got sort of the when we
call what Glock spycraft we're passing
this array that's that's got this many
elements in it but it's only going to
end up with that many minus the number
of times we did this loop right so
essentially we need to modify this value
for every time through the loop that we
go extra we're going to have less of
these so i think what i need to do
instead is say something like okay you
know reset this push buffer element
count say okay that's going to equal to
zero and then when we write things out
here we're going to have to increment it
like each time or something like that if
that makes sense hopefully it does you
can see when we come through here you
know we've got sort of this idea of the
out index right at the out index array
and that now kind of needs to be
something that's going to be a little
bit more sort of proactive and in fact I
might say let's just get rid of the walk
sprite craft thing altogether let's
actually put that may be in here and say
all right in that case we know we've got
sort of this input nodes basis we want
the out index array to be something
that's that's kind of more persistent
like so and what we want to do here is
say every time through this loop we're
going to set the input nodes to the sub
entries and then we're going to actually
do this loop itself right in here
oops yeah zooming so in here you know
we're going to start we're going to say
okay let's these are the input nodes
that we have and now we're saying so
that walk spread craft walk we got the
input nodes damson a hit cycle we're
going to restart the hit cycle part and
we're gonna set the input nodes to the
base array but we're going to leave the
out index there because that's kind of
streaming a streaming pointer that must
keep incrementing as we put stuff out
every time we put one of those things
out we want to increment how many there
are now we don't actually have to do
that manually what we could do instead
is just at the end say well okay
wherever the walks out index is relative
to the base pointer that's how many
elements there were right so it's more
like just saying oh hey this is how many
there are you know and this is like
change the total number of things to
reflect how many there are without
barriers it's like doctors that barriers
you know Sam so yeah so in here when we
do our walk through the indices now
we're just going to say go through
however many there are in the sub count
and and output them that way all right
that's not a hero that's a dot and can't
convert from in 30 okay we know that
there's never going to be that many
sprites so I'm comfortable casting down
we're not going to have four billion
sprites haven't helped us I don't think
our code is up to it at the moment so
anyway here we go and now we're actually
running so that's good but we don't
really know what we're doing right we
are running but we don't know for sure
whether we're actually whether any of
the sorting is actually happening right
and you can see that it doesn't appear
to really be doing stuff right per se
because like that top layer is sorting
below the layer that we're on which
doesn't really make a whole lot of sense
right so we're still a little bit wonky
but
uh we're at least getting there we're
starting okay so let's start by saying
what do we want to do here with think of
where I wanted because there's there's
two separate things that can be wrong
here right wrong here right that's good
there's two separate things that could
be problematic one thing that could be
problematic is the relative layer that
we're actually going to be setting down
or the sort like the sort barrier kind
of stuff that we're doing could be wrong
so we could be sending down wrong
information that's one thing we could be
doing the other thing that we could be
doing is we could be making it so that
our sort is somehow not dumping these
things out correctly after we do them
right so which one is it first what I
want to do is I must step in a little
bit to the entity list stuff and I want
to take a look at what's actually
happening when we call when we actually
push these barriers on because I don't
really have any insight that in a minute
at the moment and I would like to get
some so let's take a look at the end of
the index that Ron number 202 so there's
200 entities before we change layers
which isn't quite commensurate with what
we were seeing because we thought 233
was where it started before it's a
little weird but whatever hear me and
then we've got the current absolute Z
lair I want to look at that oops and I
also want to look at the end of these
dealer
so we are going from 0 to 1 that's what
I would have expected we're doing a push
sort barrier on here so here's what I'm
assuming is happening that could be
wrong I'm assuming what's happening here
is that because we're pushing from the
top down we're just getting the reverse
order so hopefully if I'm right about
that we're actually doing everything
correct we're just getting the reverse
order of the sort right i'm not sure but
i think that could be the explanation
because then when we when we pull
through these things in the correct
order we're getting you know we're going
to end up in a situation where there
we're always going to sort in exactly
backwards so let's see if we are sorting
exactly backwards first which i think we
actually are guess it's really no way to
tell I can't curly up higher without
seeing myself so I think that's probably
what's happening I think we are sorting
exactly backwards and that's not that
hard to fix there's a couple of
different ways we could take a look at
that but one thing that might be the
most interesting way to do that is just
to change which one of these things goes
in order because since we're only
working with the sorting stuff now it
seems like maybe the best way to do it
is just to say well when we push sort
stuff on there let's just make sure that
our source stuff always goes in order
and it's the the other stuff that goes
out of order right and that wouldn't be
that hard all we would really have to do
there is say well okay reverse the sense
of these guys so say okay you know we've
got sort entries so the sword entry at
plus the size of a sort bound is going
to be less than wherever the push buffer
is currently at right I could do
something like that so then we would
just have the push buffer at kind of go
down the sort entry at would go up
something like that all right and that
seems pretty fair to me and because this
is kind of fiddly maybe now is a good
time to kind of make these things a
little more rigorous anyway excuse me my
throat's kind of given out today
all right how much time do I have left
I've got 17 minutes 18 minutes like that
I think it's 18 minutes yeah anyway so
what I want to do here is just say like
okay we've got some understandings about
where these things are and they're kind
of baked into the render commands so you
know inside the platform thing we've got
this this notion kind of in here of how
the stuff is is sort of a little bit
finicky so we have the pushover size in
the push buffer base and then we have
the mask push buffer size and then you
here we've got the sword entry at and
the push buffer element count and all
these sorts of things and I think we
probably just want to consolidate these
a little bit here into something maybe a
little bit more sane right because it's
a little bit it's a little bit twiki at
the moment so what we really want to do
is say okay we have a max push buffer
size that's definitely true and then we
have to sort of separate things we have
like a you know sort entry count and we
don't really need a sword entry at we
can really just use the count and
multiply it by the slides because
they're fixed size so they just kind of
go up so we could just say we have a
sword entry count and it goes up right
then we have just a push buffer at
variable which is where which could
start at the top and work its way down
word as we go and we wouldn't have one
of these right and then we can have
another thing which is eventually I
don't know how we did this before I
guess it's in a render prep so inside
render prep we could say we have soared
industries and sorted index count that
would get us out of the business of
having the push buffer element count be
something that's used in that gets
modified and used twice so that would be
good too and push buffer size is not
really relevant anymore so we should be
able to get away with just this I think
well I guess push buffer base and this
is like data at
I think that's a little clearer
conceptualization of what we've got here
so similarly in there now we know a
couple things now we know we can sort of
make a couple in lines here for example
we could say sorts bright bands you know
get first sort sprite found or something
like that we could have something like
this and when we pass that in Game
render commands and what we would do
there is just return whatever the push
buffer base is yeah so that would be get
the first sorts sorts of a pound and
similarly we could well I think that's
about it it's only real thing that we
probably need so then when we come up
here and we say we want to do a push
sort barrier what we can do there is say
well let's go ahead and assert that
we're not going to move past where we
should move past so we can sort of start
with this and I guess I could call this
get sprite boobs don't know what acts
don't hit there we could call this get
spray pounds
and so when I get the sprite bounds I
now have like a basis of an array that i
can use and i can say well if you know
the sprite pounds plus however many i
have to go so commands sort entry count
I if I take a look at that and it's less
i guess i should say plus one and it's
less than whatever the push buffer data
at pointer is then it's okay it's okay
for us to go right and so assuming that
it actually is i would just say like
commands sort entry count plus plus you
know sort sprite bound bound equals mmm
sprite pounds plus this so that's an ad
bound call basically in line sorts
profound push bound and honestly I could
probably do I could probably do this a
little bit cleverer I don't know you
know what I'm not going to do it that
way let's go do it in the line so I go
ahead and get one of the bounce out and
then I don't need to do that anymore and
I don't need to do that anymore and so
then I just say like okay there's the
bound and we're done
right same thing would happen over here
so we know what the sizes and now we
just have to say like okay let's get the
sprite bands out again since we know we
need those and now we just say okay if
the sprite bounds and you know what I'm
going to cast this to a you ate star as
well because I kind of wanna do a
pointer compare here and so is it's not
safe to do pointer comparison aren't you
ate spyler oftentimes will do stupid
stupid stupid things in the name of
optimization so I want to go ahead and
do the exact same thing here so I'm
going to do the exact same comparison
the only difference now is instead of
comparing the push buffer data at
regular i'm going to subtract that size
so i'm going to assume that i did both
pushes at once if I did do both pushes
at once then I'm going to go ahead and
do the actual operation here so I'm
going to do a minus equal of the size so
the push buffer data at moves backwards
and then the header is doesn't actually
need to do this part at all it's just
going to be at the push buffer data at
value we then do everything else that we
would normally do when we come down to
the sort sprite bounds that again is
just the same push we did up here it
looks like that and then off we go we
don't need to do any of these dupes we
don't need to do any of these and I
think we're done so at that point we do
have the aggregate bound stuff that we
have to clean up a little bit and the
aggregate bound stuff I guess we don't
need to do anything with here but just
to begin and end part of things have to
be done a little bit differently so when
we do a begin aggregate sort key and
we're doing this the first aggregate at
is going to be a little bit different
we're not going to do sort entry at
we're not going to any of this what we
have to do is get sprite bounds for the
commands and whatever the current count
is that's where we want to be right and
then when we go to the end aggregate
sort key we come through here and we're
like okay that's got the commands we
want to get the first entry and the way
that we would do that is exactly the
same way
I in fact I guess now I think about it
if these things are being pushed in
order how did we want to do this exactly
first aggregate at we wanted to start
with whoever our first aggregate was so
yeah so this is just going to be think
literally just that what is for what is
first aggregate at is that just a value
I guess so I guess it's really just this
I think that's what we actually want so
then we would say like okay we've got a
render group spray pounds right so our
first aggregate we start there we go
through however many we had and that's
getting incremented all the time I guess
I don't know that we really need to
count this anymore I'm not even sure why
we were counting it in the first place
to be completely honest with you it
doesn't make a whole lot of sense to me
why we would need to count that it seems
like a Greek account is unnecessary it
seems like all we really need to do
their say well okay when we're done we
knew what the aggregate count is the
aggregate count is just whatever the
count is now minus whatever the count
was then right so it seems like that's a
saner way to do that we then got some
stuffs to do alright so let's take a
look get sword entries is now I guess
that was actually the call that we had
before so we could actually call it gets
or ten trees if we wanted to in fact
maybe I should just do that so we call
this get sort entries like so I and
we'll just leave it at that hmm
cuz that's really what there anyway one
more should be it is alright so if the
you and 8th star spray pounds will the
laws this that's missing one of those i
don't know i had an extra one nobody
knows and let's see push buffer size so
the offset in this case is a little bit
of pointer arithmetic so we've got our
push buffer data at and it's really just
whatever the max fish buffer size is so
it would be the offset is the max fish
buffer size minus however far we've gone
so far and I could just track that value
directly I'm not sure really we're doing
some bunch of 64-bit arithmetic here
when we really could just be doing
32-bit earth that doesn't really matter
but it is worth noting anyway so let's
see a translation for first size u32 a
group aggregate count equals zero so in
this case all we really need to know is
is the first aggregate at first agar at
it does that equal the current sort
current sort count here minus one right
meaning is the one that we just are we
just added is that the first one and
let's get those commands up to the right
part there we go ok so for pushing a
clip wrecked on it looks like the
pushing the clip wrecked on is basically
the same operation as we have above I'm
going to think about whether I want to
abstract that at all let me see what
else we've got here sword entry count is
just now sword into account like so oh
except it's not so sword entry count is
actually prep sorted index cap
what did I call that yeah i did call it
sort of mix down i would like you to
please get out of my way i can't see
when handmade heroes little banners up
on there go away five minute warning i
know i only have five minutes left thank
you you have told me fade away please
say it away all right fine don't fade
away all right so what's the problem
here push by for element count when
we're doing the global show sort groups
that's going to loop through this okay
so that's really again probably just
going to be the prep group there because
that's we really we really want these I
think that was kind of a little bit
wrong before but it's prep did yeah it's
a it's prep sorted in just indices oh
well no because it's trying the sprite
bounds directly so it's sort entry count
and get sword entries and where we go
through here presumably we also want to
make sure
then it's not equal to the sprite
barrier offset value you don't want to
draw that all right let's see the push
beverlyn cow is not a member of game
render commands really and in this case
again it's going to be prep sorted index
count and I probably could just go ahead
and here alright for sword entries this
is just sort of entry count and now up
here where we do push by Elham account
what I really want to do is I really
want to write to prep so really what we
want to do here let me go ahead and see
where that prep is so here's prep for
render and I believe prep for render
yeah it goes ahead and does sort of the
sword entries bit here where it puts the
sort of indices in here but I think what
I would rather do is I'd rather just
pass that along and have it fill it out
itself because it really needs to fill
out both of those things right so what
actually has to happen and here is it
has to say like oh okay game render prep
prep in here we would say you know prep
sorted indices result prep sorted index
count equals whatever it equals
right just a little bit cleaner okay so
getting down to the last ones here a
render command struct we get what are we
doing initially they can enter inside
your list to you eight oh yeah i see so
render command struct we just have to
kind of clean this up a little bit we've
got the width the height the back push
buffer size sort entry count still
correct the push buffer base is also
correct but now before we get into the
things we then have to kind of say well
the pushed buffer plus the max push
buffer size is actually where we would
start pushing data so that's got to look
like that and then I think we're pretty
much good to go and it does look like
that's true all right all right so
pushing clip Rex on push buffer data at
minus the size in this case we just want
to know whether whether that is going to
violate our size so we have our sword
entries for this command set and we're
just going to add how many there
and I think that's about it so then we
would just say push by for data at we're
going to go down by however much we need
and then we're just going to use it like
so all right so that should probably
crash and burn because I didn't get a
chance to actually go back through it
and make sure that it all works right so
that's a bit of a problem I hate to
leave it in that state but it is almost
time for Q&amp;A I'm going to take a brief
look at it just to double check here but
yeah we will see anyway I oh dear that's
an interesting current clip rekt value
to say the very least where does that
fly a comfort by the way that should be
from platform dead hate shouldn't it oh
no it's probably from render group
there's current click right ok so let's
do one quick thing here I just want to
do a couple of things while they're
fresh on my mind and then I can leave it
and we can debug it tomorrow so yeah
when I'm doing this I kind of want this
stuff to be a little more systemic I
don't like how it's duplicated in all
these places right so what I would like
to do is something like a you know in
line you know maybe there's like a
struct push buffer result or something
and the push buffer result will have a
sprite bound sword entry and avoid star
for the data or a header I guess
yeah and I think what I'd like to do
there is make it so that that operation
is sort of some kind of coherent
operation where you like push buffer you
give it the render group and it does the
operation that you were going to do so
in this operation i would say okay
you're going to push the push buffer you
go ahead and start assuming you didn't
get it we figure out whatever the size
is so we say like oh the sword entry
count that you're trying to push and the
data size right so then we say okay if
we want to figure out where that is we
figure out where the sprite bands are we
say however many there are right now
plus however many you are trying to add
is how you know is where that point is
going to be the push buffer data at
minus whatever the sizes that you were
trying to push for data that's where
that's going to be and as long as they
didn't cross then we're okay we would
then update by the data size and that
header would be our result wherever that
is right like so and that's all we would
do then similarly to get the entry it
would just be that wherever we were and
then we would go ahead and increment the
sword entry count by however many sword
entries we were trying to have right so
that way we can just do this much more
cleanly and know that everyone's using
the same code we can just say that you
know there's a push the push equals push
buffer render group
what did you want I wanted one sort
group and no data so that's what I asked
for and then I just go ahead and if I
got it I set it up makes sense and so
then similarly here we would do exactly
the same thing also this I guess doesn't
even need to have that anymore so here
is actually the same thing I would say
oh ok I want to push I know I want to
push one sword entry and this amount of
size on I can get rid of these Thank of
them well I'm going to need at least one
of those mm-hmm but then assuming that I
got it i'll go ahead and say all right I
we know where the header is the header
comes from here everything else happens
exactly the same we know the sprite
bound is right Brown comes from here
everything else happens the same and
then I think we're done right
and then finally there's clear or
whatever was the push clear push clip
wreck that's what it was push clip
Brecht so for push clip rekt again I can
do exactly the same thing so this one's
the opposite it has actual size to push
but it doesn't it wants to push size but
no data I'm sorry it wants which data
but no sword entry because the clip
backs don't get sorted so all we have to
do is say okay assuming that you've got
a sword entry from the push whatever it
is are now sort entry sorry so you got
data from the push off you go and I
think I actually call that header
there we go all right all right so I'm
going to leave that and go to a brief
Q&amp;A I just wanted to make that oops but
then we're going to have to debug this
tomorrow because this is going to crash
because we didn't actually fix any bugs
I just want it to be a little bit
cleaner if that makes sense that's
interesting I actually got to know there
though maybe I'll take a look
ah mr. assignment so actually that is
supposed to be result not spurn entry
and I looks good all right so Africa and
political crisis in place we do and so
then we just have to do tomorrow is
figure out why we're getting ahead of
crash course you guys all get to debug
this on your own what are you going to
do so all right now it will actually do
the QA for reals sorry for the false
teasing QA now we can go to the actual
Q&amp;A and talk about it some more
no questions no questions meet George
Jetson
that clip breakout is so bizarre
I would have expected if it was some
memory trouncing there I would have
expected that to be a little different
no queues so it's just like bogus right
off the bat right off that bat someone
want to tell me why AHA that's why
that's why I right there
because this is initialized to a bogus
value so this clip Rick count so we have
the width the height the max push buffer
size the zero the push buffer and data
at we've got the clear the last manual
sort key and there we go so that was
that that was that problem
can we render it to clip let go and
these should all be initialized to zero
anyway I don't even know why those are
all there
you mentioned earlier that the compiler
would optimize the code making pointer
comparison unsafe when does that happen
thanks for the stream so i didn't spend
a lot of time looking at whether that
was actually a case where that would
happen uh but here's sort of the idea I
so let's say that we have a block of
memory and we help so i think i'm going
to tell you the case where it does mess
up thinking about the case that i
actually did I don't think it would ever
mess that up but I don't know I never
put would put one past the compilers so
there's a thing that's basically I don't
remember the term they use in the spec
but there's basically like a memory
region or allocation or something that
they talk about in the sea specification
which basically says that let's say I
have a pointer to a type okay so I've
got you know a type and maybe that type
is you know 12 bytes if I then have a
type star a and a type star B and I talk
about these two types of the compiler in
some arithmetic way so I say hey I would
like to compute a minus B because of the
spec and the people who wrote it who I
always pretty much disagree with the
default assumption for the compiler
is that these two things are aligned to
each other so that means that a and B
are an even multiple of 12 bytes away
from each other always right this one
can't be 13 bytes away from this one or
something like that even though that
would be totally valid that's not
allowed because what the spec says is
that any two pointers that you do a
rhythmic MIT arithmetic between are
assumed to come to come in a contiguous
array where they would could each be
numbered as a slot right so it's
basically like okay you know if a was
here and be was here then we assumed
this is 12 bytes this is 12 bytes this
is 12 bytes this is 12 bytes and 12
bytes right B cannot appear here it's
simply not allowed right so rather than
a minus B being you eight star a minus u
8 star B / sizeof star a this is what
you might expect right you might expect
to take the difference of the pointers
the action marek values and then divided
by however big the thing was that
they're pointing to that is not what
actually happens the compiler is free to
do all sorts of arithmetic nonsense that
it wants to wear it assumes what these
pointers actually point to and what
their base values are and so you have to
be careful so by force of habit and
having been burned by compiler
awesomeness like this in the past what I
generally do is when I have a buffer
like this where I'm sticking things into
the buffer you know even if they happen
to all be aligned properly I will often
convert to you eight stars before i do
any kind of pointer arithmetic with them
because I'm not confident the compiler
won't have some weird spec think can do
to mess me up
so make sense
hopefully that makes sense
alright
so I think we're done for today it is
630 so I will be back tomorrow to finish
that up for the time being we're going
to have to leave it in a crash restate I
don't think it'll be very hard to debug
this so anyone who wants to do that for
homework go right ahead but I probably
won't look at the forum still tomorrow
because I usually like to debug it
myself on stream and this is going to be
I think not a pic Lee hard one but if
you want a little extra homework to do
download the source code tonight and see
if you can find it because you should be
able to just step through and watch
what's happening with the pointers now
and validate that everything gets put
where it's supposed to be put and at
some point you should find something
that does not get foot where it needs to
get put so that's up to you alright
that's about it i am going to wrap it up
thank you everyone for joining me for
the episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with us always if you
would like to follow along with the
series at home you can always pre-order
the game on handmade hero or get comes
with a source code so you can follow
along at home we also have a forum site
if you want to oh thank you drawing
tablet but also a form fight if you want
to ask questions you can go there and
post them we have a patreon page
transport the video series a schedule
bot that tells you when we're going to
be live in an episode guide if you want
to catch up on old episodes that is it
for today I will be back here tomorrow
at five p.m. pacific daylight time to
show wherever that bug is we will find
it and then we will finish our sort
that's about it I hope you have fun
coding till then and I will see you guys
on the unit tickety's everyone