hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we code a complete game
live on stream oh did this so question I
guess we have did they start the thing
where you have to pass authentication to
the to the to twitch now or they fault
because they said they were going to and
I guess they did what I noticed is on
their website they actually pass
undefined like literally the word
undefined for their for the actual like
authentication key so I'm wondering if I
can update this is this is why it which
basically broke this for us they've
broken it so many times because they
keep changing their API for no reason
whatsoever and they did it one more time
so now it requires oo auth tokens to
actually ask basic questions like
whether a stream is live because you
know you wouldn't want someone to know
whether your stream is live it's not
like you can just go to twitch TV slash
handmade hero and search for the end of
the word or the little live token which
is literally what you can do if you
wanted to scrape the website but it
doesn't matter point being I'll probably
have to update this but for now it will
still be accurate it just it'll say live
soon instead of actually changing this
to the live view but you should be able
to click on the twitch button here and
and you know and go there so anyway what
we're gonna do today is take a look at
what we're sort of going to start almost
a little bit early we're gonna start our
lighting quality work and the reason
that we're going to be doing that today
is because we took a pretty close look
at the raycast err and we debugged the
new grid ray caster pretty thoroughly
and i would say i was relatively
confident after looking at the debug
visualizations of it that the actual ray
casting anyway is a-ok like it didn't
look like there were any problems with
the ray casting so the next step is we
now have to work on light transport so
once we have a ray cast from one place
to another we need to make sure that
we're actually
correctly producing values that make
sense in the system and the problem that
we have if we want to go that step is
that we never actually have done a
lighting quality pass in the first place
so we don't actually know one way or the
other what should really be happening
right meaning ray casting is is the kind
of nice part of the process even though
it was obviously very expensive and it's
taken us a long time for how we're going
to handle it properly so it's difficult
to implement something fast but it's not
difficult to see if it works because you
can literally just draw the raycast
and see if it does what you intuitively
know it will do which is shoot in a
direction until it hits the first thing
and stop there and produce the correct
normal for the service that it hits and
we drew that and we did watch watch it
work properly so we more or less know
that that's working and there's a couple
things we can do today to try to verify
that we didn't miss anything and
specifically what I mean by that is we
didn't do any testing to ensure that the
Ray results flow out because there's
four Ray's cast at a time we didn't
actually verify that like all four get
written to the right place or things
like that so there are a few things that
have to do with the exit condition and I
guess what I would say is we can go
verify just that part as a separate
exercise because we don't really know
about that but beyond that the problem
that we're going to have is if we would
like to take the next step and get the
lighting working nice and try to
finalize it we need to start building an
understanding of what we actually
consider to be the correct results
meaning at the moment we don't really
have any definition of what we expect
this thing to produce
so what I would like to do is I would
like to focus primarily on building a
better understanding of what we actually
think the lighting should produce in
terms of values possibly start assigning
some meaning to our values so you know
right now we're just kind of bouncing
around arbitrary quantities we don't
have any kind of rigid definition for
what they are and in order to finalize
the lighting that we're gonna have to
start having an actual understanding of
what those things are and the reason
that I say that is just because if you
think about how we're going to debug
this well there's only really two ways
to debug this one is to just keep
messing with it until we get lighting
that sort of seems to work right right I
mean for lack of a better term that's
one way we could do it we look at the
screen it looks buggy or doesn't look
right we try to figure out what might be
causing that and we go make some changes
and then we try to see if that looks
better you know I'm saying and that's
just kind of a bit fraught with peril it
usually leads into situations where the
lighting will work okay in certain
circumstances and not okay in others and
then you're constantly in this like
chasing your tail kind of pattern you
know so the other way we can do it and
the way that I'd like to try first is to
actually assign some meaning and it
doesn't have to be physical it doesn't
have to be actually real like from the
real physics of light in any way it can
be made up if we want it to be but we
can assign some like at least pseudo and
almost a pseudo-scientific we can create
our own definition of how we expect the
light to behave and then we can validate
against that meaning we can debug with
the expectation that the system should
produce those results and that's much
easier because if we can come to a
concrete definition of what we expect
the lighting to do that's way better for
us because at that point we can debug
individual pieces of it right we can
look at something and say well we we
said that the way that this light should
behave
when it does a diffuse reflection off a
surface or something right is that it
should do X and if we go look at that
part of the routine and it's not doing X
then we know that that's a bug that we
can look at independently of the rest of
the system whereas if we take the first
approach where the only thing that tells
us whether it's working properly is
whether we like the results it's really
difficult to pinpoint what part of the
routine is working poorly because
they're all interconnected at that point
each part you know okay so is the
reflectance function working right and
the diffuse blur is too dim or is the
reflection function too dim and the
diffuse blur is fine right like if all
you're looking at are the final
intensities that come out of the system
there's many places where those
intensities are modified and you don't
have any real way of talking about who
is operating incorrectly and who is
operating correctly and you're just left
with kind of a giant soup of variables
that you have to tune and not really
ever knowing if you have bugs in there
because maybe you do maybe you don't
right so so what I'd like to do is move
forward on that and that's gonna be a
little bit difficult because it's really
not it's really not something that I do
particularly often I don't work with
light as much as I would probably like I
probably should have spent more time at
some point in my career but because I
was working on character animation a lot
of the time and rendering was really
done sort of external to me I never
really got a lot of experience with
lighting functions and it's a bummer
because you know it means that I'm just
not good with them and a lot of the
things that I should know cold I just
don't know
so as you can see we currently have the
ability to this is a ray cast here we
currently have the ability actually to
step through rays as
we wish let me see what is it f2
probably
you know f3 so what are the things that
you can see here is that if I you know
roll this around that can actually
change like where the lighting is is
actually getting positioned and I can
also sort of change which ray is being
shot out of it and so you can see here
we can debug the raycast are pretty
trivially and this is what I was talking
about before so you can see here the Ray
is getting shot towards this towards
this cube here and it's hitting the cube
and you can see the normal is coming
back exactly as we expect and so for
light transport we kind of know at least
to a certain extent we know that it's
working because we can or I'm sorry
enough light transport for ray casting
we kind of know that it's working
because we can see where the Ray is
hitting you know it's there's a little
white box there as well and you can see
the the back you know the the sort of
like normal that's going to splash
impact from the hit and you can see the
Ray target from you know where where it
was and where it went right and you can
even see the grid squares that it you
know marched along the way and so I
guess you know short of the fact that
I'm probably gonna want to go and do one
more optimization pass on this ray
caster you know there it it seems like
we did our job right so it's like it's
producing the correct results in the
raycast
so now what we need to know is like what
should be happening on that transfer and
if we look if we look at the speed for
compute light propagation as well you
know we again are not far from where we
need to be target wise and I think we
have a lot of opportunity to optimize
this particular routine because it has a
lot more control than the old tree walk
did and there's things we can do that we
haven't done yet that we probably should
as well like making these grid squares
larger because if we for example stop
doing the pre computation of the walk
table and rolled the walk table walk
into the actual rate
caste we could also do some interesting
things there where we actually have our
grid squares be much larger than the
than the underlying geometry to bucket
up a few more of things per cell which I
think would accelerate this routine
dramatically so I feel like we've got a
lot of headway on that so I think we're
gonna be able to get down to our 16
millisecond budget there I think that's
entirely within reason so I want to just
put that aside for now and focus on what
happens at this point so we have a cell
we have a hit and the question is how do
we know what kind of energy gets
transferred from here to here right and
I think the biggest challenge for me and
the reason why I like I said I don't
really know exactly how to approach this
it's a bit tough is that how do we
visualize that in a way that makes it
intuitive as to whether it's doing what
we expect right because if you if you
look at how we debugged the raycasting
that went really fast right remember we
had a completely busted
ray tracer and in like you know four
hours or something total debug time I
don't know how much it was it wasn't
much we fixed like you know twelve bugs
in or something it was it was just rapid
you know every 10 minutes we found and
fixed a bug and every single one of them
right was because we could see it we
could see what was supposed to happen
and it was just obvious what was wrong
you were just like oh okay it's you know
it's not walking in the right direction
so let's go look at the walk you know
thing where you know how would this be
happening right mm-hmm
saying it's obvious what was wrong a
little bit it's obvious where the bug is
right you don't necessarily know what
the bug is till we go look at the code
and try to plug it but you know where
the bug is
but I don't know what would be a good
way to visualize the underlying lighting
in a way that makes it so that I can
tell how this light transfer should be
working right that's the problem so you
know when I look at what's going on in
you know in this system it's like how do
I figure out how do I give myself
something to hold on to where I can
start to narrow in on like how this
lighting transfer should work right
mm-hmm
and so my my only real idea at this
point is to think could I do something
where I draw like some kind of some kind
of like trying to think of how to
describe this imagine almost like we
took the octahedral map and the
octahedral map is 64 directions right if
I took at each Center of each grid
square right and I drew a line out
through the center of each of those
octahedral maps mapped pixels and I just
drew it so that it was like getting
longer the brighter it was in that
direction so the values stored in the
octahedral map at that point is what
would is what would tell me how that was
being transferred right so I'm just
thinking if I started there and granted
again like I don't I haven't started on
the the concept of trying to find these
quantities but if I started there then I
at least have something where
my voxel cells would be showing me
something that I could use to intuit how
on each step the light was getting
propagated and the other thing that I
think I could do once I put that in that
my help is I could bind like a key on
the keyboard
two-stepping the lighting so rather like
right now what happens is I run the
lighting and it's just running like it's
constantly feeding back right and right
now we kind of have this problem that it
massively produces massively too bright
information but you know if I go into
the the lighting code there's actually
in that build diffuse maps here
so we can actually artificially like
really dampen the diffuse blur which
again we have we have not actually
worked out what those equations should
be so who knows we don't know what the
right value is here anyway
but you can watch see how slowly over
time the lighting kind of blossoms out
like that like that's what's actually
happening when you run it slowly when
you run the update slowly what I could
do is I could step the lighting kind of
one at a time and I could look to see
what's going on there right so so where
are these lighting transfers happening
and how is that spread occurring right
and again that's just to give me some
intuition of whether you know whether
it's just a question of not having the
math right under the hood so maybe we're
doing the right things but with the
wrong coefficients or whether it runs
deeper than that and actually there are
bugs in the propagation that's causing
it to get over bright actually that have
have nothing to do with the coefficients
or how we're computing the light and so
that's my thinking right and as you can
see there's really no value you can set
that produces a correct result here so
it's not like we just have one
coefficient wrong anyway because at the
outset the light's not propagating at
all right
and then it kind of like hits a critical
threshold and just propagates out to
fulbright so there's definitely a
feedback loop in there but I feel like
to get a handle on what that feedback
loop actually is I just feel like I need
more information
so when we actually run and we we sort
of look at what we're getting here for
results what I'd like to do as well is
because the lighting grid is is fairly
substantial like the the number of cells
in the voxel lighting grid is is you
know it's 16 by 16 by 24 it's not
infinite by any stretch of the
imagination but it's a lot to draw so if
I were to look at all you know each one
of these little cubes in the entire 3d
volume here they would all have one of
those little octahedral map blossoms on
them and that is gonna be too much right
it's just I it's just too much I won't
be able to actually process that amount
of visual information so what I might
also do while I'm doing that particular
pass over the system for debugging
because I might also introduce a box
that's just look we're just gonna look
at the lighting in a small region right
and there's two ways that I could do
that one is I can actually shrink the
size of the lighting voxel but the other
which is probably what I'll do instead
is I'll just introduce a secondary
bounds and it's just like because I've
done this before
on stream you see me do it for the
lighting system instead of actually
producing any kind of debug information
for all the cells I'll just produce it
for just those ones inside the box and
if that turns out not to give me the
inside I need will figure something else
out I guess but that's what I want to
start with so if we take a look at the
push lighting render values what you can
see is we already have the push line
segment for debug lines in here
so what I can do
is I really have two options one is I
can actually draw line segments here and
not take up any debug lines and that
might be a better solution because
there's really no reason that I need to
do it earlier on in the pipeline so you
know maybe instead of using the debug
line call I'll just do this right oh
I'll just I'll just push him here
oh well although you know what it helps
because it tells the renderer how much I
need so maybe I will use the debug lines
because that would that maybe be a
little more convenient okay
so what I'm gonna do is after we're done
computing the lighting so once we're
done once we do update lighting maybe
I'll just make a function call for this
just just period so after the internal
lighting color core runs I'll just call
the thing that's like you know debug
draw octahedral values and in this
particular case I guess I will need the
spec Atlas and defuse defuse atlases I
think I probably want to find a way to
draw both of them
would be my guess yeah so one of the
things that it occurs to me as well just
in terms of the way we're doing things
so the way the diffuse blur works right
now it doesn't really make any sense
right because it's it's probably
providing too much power to the system
because your base is saying look we're
not actually we're not actually reducing
the reflected power of this thing when
you know if you imagine a hundred
photons came in on in this direction and
now we're basically saying that a
hundred photons also go out in all the
directions only modulated by the cosine
right and while that makes sense for a
single bounce integration if you were
doing it that way
it doesn't actually work probably I
would think for stored values right
because the diffuse
juice values that we're then going to
use are going to be sampled on the next
frame and I'm assuming that the the
feedback loop has a lot to do with that
right
again I just want to draw it first
before I draw any conclusions but you
can you can kind of see why that's a
little bit dicey like we haven't thought
that through because we haven't started
to work on lighting quality yet but
there's definitely like an an element of
that that just you know it makes me
nervous right and and this system has a
property that others the other raytracer
didn't have which is that in this system
one thing that we do is if we early out
we pull from whatever cell we early
doubt in and we put we take that light
quantity and so that creates a possible
reliance in this system on the diffuse
map being power correct that wasn't in
the previous system right the previous
system was never going to do that it
only would transfer if it actually hits
something and so there are differences
there that are important to understand
right so if I loop through the the
actual the the voxel so if I loop
through the voxel here and I just say
I'm gonna like I said define a
particular narrower region inside the
voxel and I'm not sure how I really want
to do that but maybe what I'll do is
I'll just take a predefined ratio of
things so if normally it would be a
certain dimension I'll divide that
dimension by four or something right so
I can say like alright the you know the
number of cells that I want to loop over
for this and if we look at the light
Atlas you can see that it actually has a
V 3 s in here right for the dimension so
I can just say the debug dimension is
going to be the speck Atlas voxel dim
and what I can do is just say we're only
going to use a subset of that so you
know maybe we use only a quarter of the
total voxel space right and then what
I'm going to do is I'm going to say that
well the start you know the
the Vox is start area or whatever is
going to be the debug dim and times two
would be the center so maybe we'll just
do like right because if we divide by
four we have a quarter of the space and
so what I'd like to do is move it up by
one and a half of itself right so what I
want to do here is say like look let's
do debug dim times three over four or
something right something like that I'm
sorry no like that so basically we are
moving it up by one and a half of itself
and that will give us a roughly centered
one so we're just going to pick out like
the quarter in each dimension in the
middle of the voxel and then all I'm
gonna do here is I'm not even going to
try to draw this first time I'm just
going to try and isolate the area in
fact I could just use a debug box call
for now push debug box and that will
give me just just a way of figuring out
whether I'm drawing in the right place
so in order to iterate over this I'll
just do the standard you know Z first
and I guess I can do it this way I'll
just do a standard z Y X iteration
again one of those things that see kind
of makes it annoying to write you would
like that to be way more automatic but
it's actually fairly hard to do those in
C and C++ they're not not particularly
great languages but then again what is
so if we go to the actual coordinate we
want to draw it's just going to be the
Vox start plus you know this this XYZ so
at that point we have where we are in
the voxel and like we know because we
actually have the voxel system here we
know we have calls we can use that to
produce these but unfortunately we don't
actually have this set up for the the
spec atlas right if you remember if you
go back to the spec atlas you can see we
we don't actually store any of that
information so what we kind of need to
do is we need to borrow and I guess we
actually already did this so I suppose I
should have just used it a little bit
more directly in fact if I just do voxel
grid here we actually have the lighting
grid I don't know if you remember this
but we actually did already make one so
the Atlas grid is the one that is lined
up with the spec atlas so we can't
actually use the Atlas grid here to do
our dirty work for us so if we go to
handmade voxel I can get the cell bounds
here and I can just say look give me the
cell bounds of this atlas right I can
also do this which is probably more what
I want because I actually only just want
the Centers but what I'm going to do
just to make sure that I'm doing what I
think I'm doing is I'm actually going to
ask for both of these I'm going to ask
for the Atlas grid to give us both the
center and the bounds
and then I'm going to push to debug
boxes on the first one I'm going to push
on is going to be the bounds and I'll do
that in like a dark blue I don't know
why I just will could do a dark red and
then I'm going to push the center P on
and I'm going to do that in a bright red
and what I need to do here is because I
do want to push a debug box specifically
I'm going to just take the center P and
I'm going to do a rect Center dim where
I just say that's where I want the box
to be centered and then I want the
dimension of the box to be you know
something
who knows what let's say it's that and
this will give me just something that I
can use it looks like I don't have
operators for the v3 s for some reason
which I will fix right now so here's the
v3 s and we've oh no that's not what I
wanted here's where we actually define
the operators for the v3 s and those are
the v2 s these are the VIII's your the
v3 s is and I guess we must have I'm
assuming we at least did add for it but
you know honestly I don't actually see
it so we may have just not done any
operators for these at all we have a lot
of math in this game we've built up here
we go so you know we've got we've got x
a constant on one side but not the other
side and then we have divided on the
other side so we should probably just
say look you can do this in any order no
one actually cares which order you use
it's totally fine with us off again so
once we've done that looks like we have
cannot get to Oxford great oh sorry
sorry about that once we have that done
we should be able to take a look and it
looks like I've got an issue here what
is the issue
syntax error did I put one too many I
did so once we've got that we should be
able to now see like just a bunch of
boxes showing the region that this will
cover and so there's the region and you
can see it pretty clearly and so you
know it looks about right
I would say you can see here that it
lines up perfectly with the interior
boxes which is what it should do right
you can see they overlap pretty much
exactly and so this should give me a way
to to now figure out what the heck is
going on there
so if I go ahead and remove one of these
boxes so rather than getting the cell
bounds here I mean maybe I still will
but I'm just not going to draw them what
I want to do now is I want to draw lines
coming out of the of that center point I
want to draw them based on the intensity
that is seen at the in the spec Atlas at
that Texel and I probably need to drop
both the spec Atlas and the diffuse
Atlas or at least be able to look at
either of them and I don't really know
that I'm going to be able to draw them
both very effectively I mean I might be
able to get away with drawing the
diffuse Atlas first and the spec atlas
on top of it because the spec atlas
should always at the way we're doing it
right now the spec atlas will actually
generally be
we'll have less stuff in it right
because the few setlist is or always
going to be sort of like a spread out
version that has more cells filled in
and so yeah so I guess I would say yeah
like let's just try them both I guess so
if I go over to the light atlas what you
can see here is we've got sort of the
the tyldum system right and I also have
the octa they're inside the octahedral
stuff for the math well actually is it
in here
let's let's take a look so yeah in here
what we want to do is go ahead and and
grab the actual yeah I'm a loop over
this and just say look we're gonna go
through all the texels in this thing
that we care about so not the edge
texels because they're only used in
blending so we probably don't want to
draw those because where would we draw
them they don't have an obvious an
obvious place where they would be they
don't have like a place to be drawn
they're just used for wrapping around
and they really just represent copies of
things anyway so so here where we have
unit vector from octahedral I'm guessing
that really what we need is more this
right because we need it to account for
the fact that yeah we're looking at pic
Euler one we could also not I mean I
think we want to use this one so what we
want to do here is say yeah give us the
direction from this T X to Y so there's
our TX and dy and then we want to pass
the correct coefficient so in this case
we're talking about the Speck
list and it's got the the ktem
coefficient right no it's the o XY
coefficient so we want to pass the o XY
coefficient and that will give us back
the direction in the world right so
that's the direction that we actually
want to draw and so now we just need to
get that value from the light atlas
right so we need to have a way in here
that we can access the atlas like we
need a way to actually access the value
that's stored there and you can see here
if we do light atlas offset with an X Y
Z at 2x and 2y we should just be able to
get what the actual displacement would
be off of the main value and there may
be say there may be a way we already do
that I don't think so yeah so we might
want to have a thing that just does a
sample so we may want to have a thing
here that we could use that just samples
from the map and we don't really have
one of those at the moment so something
that's like well I you know what I guess
get tile clamped does right I guess
that's what we would want so if we do
get tile clamped that'll bring us back a
Texel there's our spec atlas we know our
x or y RZ and RT x and t y and so we
don't really need it to be clamped I
guess yeah so we could just do this
we even had that so I guess we did have
all this already and that should give us
back the Texel right and Texel in this
case is of
I guess it just gives us back a pointer
to the yeah so never mind it gives us
back it gives us back of Texel by just
pointing to where in the map this thing
actually is right so at that point we
now know the are the G and the B so what
we can do is we can just draw the
intensity at this point for example so
what we could do is say well let's just
draw the intensity maybe what we'll do
is we'll take the R plus the G you know
plus the B right and we'll just call
that the general intensity right for no
real reason and then we'll draw a vector
that's that long so we'll do push debug
line we know the direction we'll
multiply the intensity by the direction
and we'll have a scale factor in there
right and we don't know what that scale
factor is but you know it's something so
we'll have a scale factor times the
intensity times the direction and we'll
just offset from whatever the center P
is we can also draw this with the actual
color that it is so for example we can
say that it'll just be that was it to e4
was just before so we'll just say draw
it as the color so that we can see what
color is actually there as well now at
the moment we're not really using
colored lighting the light that we put
in the scene is white and most of the
reflectors are you know kind of just dim
gray or something so there's not really
we're not playing with colored
reflectors yet we do want to we just
haven't done that yet and oops I forgot
to actually pull out the value and so
what I want to do there is just you know
again start to see what's going on with
these lighting intensity
that's a dot operator pushed it along
does not take three arguments I believe
you
there we go
and too many parentheses again today
it's kind of a too many parentheses day
I guess okay um so running this now well
you know it looks exactly like what you
expect right which is kind of good I
guess meaning it does clearly let us see
what's going on in the system is not you
know there's nothing strange about
what's going on in the system we are
literally just getting a slow accretion
of omnidirectional light over time right
I mean you look at that and it's just
like everything is getting larger slowly
and then we are over that when we get
over the value when we start Sparkle we
need to probably clamp this down right
so inside push debug line we should
probably be clamping these so when we
put this color in here like we should be
clamping those right or we should do it
later it doesn't really matter when
exactly we do it right but like maybe
back down here where we're actually
going to do the push line segment and we
do you know
in here what we do is we do an RGBA pack
four by eight so before we hit that pack
we really will have wanted to do a
min/max on this right so in here what we
want to do is we want to do a like V for
color equals minimum I don't know if we
have yeah we do so we have one well we
have one for v3 s I don't know if we
have one for V fours but what we want to
do here is like make them in that will
basically prevent these things right
from overflowing so I'm not sure what we
called this last parameter or if we
called that anything it's a good
question now we didn't did we
oh we did call it W all right I was
wondering if we did I know we had an
issue where uvw versus X Y Z W you know
remember that from way back when all
right so if we have a min Max for this
we can now just drop that in here for
our you know for our V fours and we
should now be able to clamp those
lighting values and we don't really need
to do this but you know I just felt like
we should so I want to take the minimum
and the maximum value here to clamp
these out so that we're never getting
below oh wow all right
looks like we already had clamp zero one
waste of everyone's time there we go
so I'm gonna clamp 0 1 the color value
there that way you'll see as these
things get larger during the light
propagation phase now hopefully we can
get these so that they just stay white
right famous last words
which they don't now why would that be
not sure why they would Sparkle hmm
that's awfully confusing oh yeah
might want to actually use the color
that we computed turns out that if you
want to succeed in the game industry you
have to use the color value you computed
so let's take a look now well it's a
little better but it still actually
seems to have weird fluctuation there in
color values I'm not sure why we would
be getting that so I'd like to take a
look at that hmm that doesn't make a lot
of sense to me oh I see because we had
two of them I guess I guess you can
define the end points
all right so that all looks good and you
can just see so these things things just
grow without bound right so you know I
think the next thing I would like to do
is I would like to be able to I'd like
to be able to step this in a more
controlled fashion so I want the
lighting system perhaps to only update
itself when I like tell it to you know
so I'm not sure exactly what I should do
here to do that exactly but I guess all
I really need to do is if you never call
update lighting so in here if we never
call update lighting then we won't have
a problem I don't think so we do have a
slight issue which is we'd like to be
able to push the lighting render values
but I'm not sure we can do that if we've
never updated the lighting so we may
have to add some guards to prevent it
from crashing in the because it will
never have like allocated anything but
we'll see so
if we have an if zero here we should get
no lighting now but we may also miss
some values yeah
so in this case like we haven't actually
initialized the lighting it's never been
called if we make this contingent on
like pressing a key for example that
would probably be sufficient so not sure
how I want to do that we have the game
input we could do Mouse but I don't know
so where is mouse button so if I do
input mouse button here and we you know
take the
left mouse button what's the button what
do I use for moving the camera right now
so I guess I use all of them for moving
the camera I guess I could also use an F
key press
maybe I just use F key pressed so if I
use F key pressed and we just I don't
know find f9 to it let's say then I
could just say look that that'll update
the lighting one time I think right
so here's me like single stepping the
lighting right and that works real nice
okay so now we're in good shape right
because we can actually go in now and
inspect these actual lighting values and
you can kind of see what they're doing
right and what's I think especially
interesting about these is it looks like
the lighting from the sky is sufficient
to over bright these already like you
can see how much light is coming from
you know up above right you see those
kind of growing and so it's not like
they're picking up the light
particularly rapidly from these you know
but then as these start to get that so
it looks like it's largely a moonlight
issue at the immediate moment so let's
turn the moonlight off and just see
where we're at without the moonlight
just let's just start there to try and
like simplify this problem a little bit
as we start to move into trying to
define these lighting values so where
does the moonlight actually come into
the picture with the grid ray caster so
here's the grid or a cast or and here's
the moon so let's just get rid of this
I'm assuming this is used somewhere here
it is not so in grid ray cast if I get
rid of this does that mean we're not do
that mean we're not using this
yeah so we're actually getting our moon
color from somewhere else at the moment
it looks like it's probably that's an a
a B caster which we're not using at the
moment so we're probably getting the
moon from some kind of initialization
that was happening in here I'm guessing
see Wow
okay so actually I'm wrong so this this
must be a bug then right so if you look
here's the a beer a cast which we're not
using so at the moment this has no
moonlight in it at all and yet it is
saying as I allow this to grow
it is saying that I'm getting a stronger
light bounce from above than below right
look at that so
so I don't really know what's going on
here but we've really screwed something
up so I guess the good news here is we
know we've got a bug because there's no
light up there there's only like light
in a couple places like here and here
and stuff and so if you were going to
find a light you'd find it over here and
in fact some of the people seem to have
what appear to be semi sensical results
I guess I mean but not really but you
can kind of see like there's this strong
preference for like light that people
are finding like over here you know so I
think one thing we probably do want to
do is we probably draw these lights
we're not currently drawing the lights
right now we probably should so we can
actually see where they are because we
also don't that's one thing we don't
know so we should put that in here so
here's the push light call right and we
probably want to do a push cube call off
of that so if I just come down here and
do all I could do a push volume outline
okay that's better
so inside push light I tell you it's
brutal I went to the ENT and they really
don't know what's wrong with me so I
need one those Stephen Hawking things he
has had unfortunately
so in here what I'll do is I'll I'll
push the volume outline and I'll take a
look at the rectangle so I have the Box
min/max here so I'll just do a rectum
and Max and then we'll just draw it
we'll just draw it in white that's fine
we'll just use the default parameters so
if I run now here's where the lights are
right and you can see that we just kind
of stuck them up above like lamps I
guess was you know we we've spent
literally zero time on the world Jen
lighting stuff like we just threw a
light in above lamps I think it was what
we did just so we have some in there so
if you can see what's going on here this
is where you expect people to be picking
light up from right would be here but
they're definitely not and we need to
figure out why so as we sort of step
forward here
see it's for very strange and we would
definitely expect that some you know you
would getting this is where you should
be getting more of that light from but
just there's so much light coming from
this upper area and I just no
explanation for it okay so how are we
going to do this I don't know
so there's a couple of things we can do
but first I guess what I would like to
do is shift this guy over to look at one
of these right like I'd like this guy to
be up a bit so you know I don't know
that's weird what that was about
oh I know why it's because the lighting
stops having those when you don't
actually run it so what I probably
should do actually is those debug values
so in here I kind of need these to be
happening all the time because if they
don't then they don't get updated right
for a particular frame I'm not sure how
I would actually go about outputting
some of those because they don't always
exist right like some of them are only
in here but I guess what I could do is
you push render letting values I could
do the ones that always exist and so I
could do something like this right
so here I could as we are stepping these
right I could go ahead and roll through
where these are and I guess I have to
actually yeah I have to actually step to
to make that happen
that's a pain in the butt
so there's one of them for example 17
912 and I want one that kind of goes
upward
okay there we go
well yeah well is that enough
I don't know if that's enough it's not
enough
that's probably upward enough 90
maybe a hundred and ninety yeah a
hundred so 17 912 and a hundred maybe
you know would be good debug values I
don't know what are these 17 912 a
hundred seventeen and 1200 and so if I
go in here and yeah there we go all
right so now whenever I run I should
hopefully get you know a pretty good
like representative ray cast that goes
up toward the the area that we're
supposedly getting light you know what I
mean why are we above what seems weird
I guess I need to subtract one grid
sheet from it
I should probably also have a way to run
this like several steps at once so I can
get to the point where this actually
starts to happen right so oddly enough
actually like that direction in
particular I guess doesn't isn't quite
the one we want it's really a different
one so let's try that one more time it's
really going up in the opposite
direction meaning sort of this but
flipped if that makes sense so we'd like
to see we'd like to see also I want this
to be I don't know how this ended up so
far out I guess this whole thing was up
too much
should probably just do this algorithm
way or you know what maybe we should
just have a thing where we could pick if
we're gonna be debugging this a lot it
would be this is way too much of a pain
in the butt because it'd be not that
hard to make just a thing where you can
pick right where the heck is this thing
okay where how do I not see it at all
that doesn't really make sense there it
is oh right I forgot a lot of times you
won't see it because it's too large the
exterior voxel doesn't get things cast
from it and this is the next irreal of
exterior voxel index is that right it
sounds right sort of right anyway okay
so now we're at least actually on one of
the incorrect ones which I would like so
it's 17 9 12 wait but that is the one I
picked how did the debugger in index get
to be something other than that oh
because it's just an offset I'm an idiot
Wow all right all right so that was
complete waste of time
but anyway so yeah what we need to do is
we need to figure out how to maybe pick
a a grid direction for the actual cast
that's gonna go more towards the light
that we care about and then we need to
see like what the heck it's returning
because like something in that direction
is clearly returning a high value for no
apparent reason right and I don't know
well that's not awful yeah not quite
so I don't know I don't actually know I
should try to figure out what the Ray
indices I wonder if the Ray indices are
wrong so here's a thought one reason
that we could be seeing the directional
part of the bug is it could be that our
rays are actually going in different
directions than the right back location
that could easily be and we should look
at that pretty much right now I just
want to finish finding there we go
that one's pretty close would you say
let me take a look at let me let these
grow again and see if that's a roughly
close ray to the direction that's
getting the light I'm not charlie
certain it is but let's take a look okay
so if i zoom in now a little bit more on
the on the actual directional system
area yes so that's real close so I'm
gonna call 156 actually a better debug
ray index okay so if for example we were
casting in a particular direction and
then writing back to the wrong part of
the octahedral map that would explain
why we were seeing what looks like
directional lighting coming in to these
things but from a completely different
direction than where the light source is
right so that could be and we should
definitely test that and there's a lot
of ways you can test it so we'll go take
a look at some ways right that we can
use okay so here's an example right you
can see for this particular
well we set it to 156 but that's that's
not that doesn't look right
what am I missing that wasn't what it
was was it or do we dis truncate was it
155 oh so I guess it doesn't round it
truncates all right so I take it back
it's 155 all right so we can debug that
one specifically and we will but what
I'd like to do first is I think it'd
probably be a better idea to go and look
before we go any further to see whether
we're writing back to the correct place
so if I go to grid raycast
and just look and see when we're doing
our debugging and so this function will
have the debug augmentation added to it
I'd like to try to discuss who the heck
is getting written back to right so in
other words in here when we're doing our
store you know who's actually getting
stored to be fair with if debugging was
on we probably shouldn't be writing back
to it axel
I hope the debug system itself is not
causing this problem but could that be I
don't think that could be but anyway
so what I'd like to do here is when we
do this debug I'd like to figure out
which spec Texel we're writing to and
draw that right so in here we're gonna
say look here's the spec atlas and
whether we're debugging when we call
that grid raycast
I want to do a I want to do something
that draws where it what direction we
thought it should be
so inside full cast which is here
if we are going to be doing the debug
which is this one when we get these
texels what I would like to see well
this is gonna be harder so the problem
is we kind of just randomly write to it
arbitrary location here right which we
don't really want to do like this is not
a good thing that we've done here I also
don't know why there's a spec Texel B
because we don't use it so not sure why
we have that right the actual code
should be this but just to make sure
what I want to do here is say okay the
spec Texel a that you're writing to you
can see in here it just it just writes
to it I'm gonna go ahead and just create
a dummy buffer so that we don't that
this can't be affecting us so here's a
dummy buffer and I'm not going to do
this offset from Texel what I'm going to
do is I'm just gonna say there's a spec
Texel and it points to this and that's
it so now hopefully when someone writes
to this spec Texel it'll just be ignored
no one you know it won't it won't do
anything so if I run it now I'm assuming
that that wasn't the problem but I want
to make sure right I want to make sure
that that we don't have some other bug
in here where the debug system is
actually causing a problem I don't think
it could but just to make sure
and yeah so it wasn't a debug system
just want to make sure so you can see
here still the same problem and there's
an example of a cast that cast is
producing you know probably light that
it shouldn't okay so now what we need to
do is add some kind of debug ignition in
here where we actually determine where
this thing is coming from and try to
verify that we're casting in the correct
direction I think the way we would want
to do that is if we look at the debug
ray index here I guess we just have to
figure out how we would have pulled out
the Ray origin for I mean the ray
direction for that thing and see what we
do so here is our example we take the
sample dur here and so this
this is how it would have been computed
so we have a particular octahedron in da
index so you have a specific octahedron
index here and what we want to be able
to do is reverse engineer what that
would have been so here's our debug ray
index right which was rounded so that
was weird that was not yeah that was
weird but anyway if we go ahead and take
our debug der index or I should say do
you by Bray index so if we take our
debug ray index and now we want to
reverse engineer what these values would
have been so we want to know what
octahedron it would have been what we
can do is just divide by the light
sample directions per octahedron so the
debug opt index is actually going to be
this and then the debug I guess I don't
know what we would call this but inside
the octahedron we I guess we'd call this
the the map index is just going to be
the remainder in fact I could just do
the mod here so this is which octahedron
we were looking in this is which map we
were looking in and so now what we want
to know is what direction do we think
that should have been right and you can
see here how we were looping through it
so we're going through sy and then for
sy we're going through the the texels 1
2 3 4 right so what we would expect to
see here is if we got the map index we
now need to know what our T X and T Y
were and those are going to be found
exactly the same
so the map index divided by eight would
be the Y and the mod eight would be the
X right looking in here at the spec
Texel at that point we just have to
figure out where we get the well
actually you know what we don't really
care about this all we really need to do
is say look that's going to give us the
TX and the T y value that are uh knopf
set in fact these are actually about
like the octahedral because they don't
include the border right so we should be
able to look up directly into the
octahedral map for those so in here
where we would call unit vector from
octahedral that's all we should really
need now I want to I I mean maybe I
should call a direction from txt Y and
just make sure that we're doing
everything correctly and if I want to do
that then I just have to add one to each
of these to account for the border right
so that's all well and good and since
this is the spec atlas that we're
talking about here it'd be the spec
atlas of XY coefficient and question
although the Atlas is happening the same
dimension right now
so it wouldn't matter but this will give
us a way of figuring out what direction
this goes in so this is like our
expected direction and what I can do
then is I can after the grid raycast I
can push a line segment that basically
says wherever the Ray origin was right
draw something coming out that's the
expected direction and we'll do like you
know Virgin single Plus that in a color
that I can see really clearly so you
know maybe uh maybe magenta and this way
I can see what direction we expect this
ray to roughly be in and then we can we
can take we can see whether or not the
Rays are going in the rough direction
that we expect them to right that's
supposed to be capitalized
and push debug lines actually what I
wanted yeah and I think that should give
us a little bit of insight into whether
we've got these things lined up right so
let's take a look at the debug system
now and all I'm gonna do is perturb that
Ray index right it looks pretty good I
mean these octahedral maps are pretty
low res so you're only expecting them to
be roughly in line like they're not
going to be exact
right
so uh I wouldn't I wouldn't call that
suspicious yeah it it's pretty close so
so I would call that pretty reliable
like that doesn't look like an issue now
that doesn't tell us anything about the
sampling from the act you don't Matt but
it does look like we're writing back
into the right location so at that point
my question just becomes alright let's
take a look at this raycast specifically
you know and and I'm going to crank up
that that value again so that the single
steps are very large so where we do
build a few light Maps I'm gonna let
those get large quickly
so here's more of a aggressive spreading
parameter there and
here is the first lighting step oops
should I send out and need this up I
feel like I want to be able to see those
early steps more easily so maybe I
should also just make them a bit larger
so where we draw the lines maybe I will
try to well but even that doesn't really
make sense it's weird that we're getting
that getting so much light from such
small values in even initially because
one unit is one meter like one unit is
pretty far right oh but I put a scale
value in okay so did I put a scale of
value in there I think I did intensity
times scale I think I did right yeah so
let's just leave that at one then for
now and we'll see what happens there
although it's still that's still yeah I
feel like so right now there should be
like how are we getting that much light
like visible light from such tiny values
that just doesn't make sense does it
all right so this is only the spec atlas
let's get both of them so I'm gonna get
both of these and then what I want to do
is in here I want to do a spec value and
a diffuse value and then what I want to
do is I want to do a spec intensity of
diffuse intensity and actually maybe
I'll just do this so maybe we'll just
say look this process here we can just
abstract we just want to tell you what
Alice it is you'll go ahead and get it
not know which these are it get tile
unclamped there S's
so you'll just say that and then this
will just happen automatically for you
so you'll get the value it'll compute
the intensity and that's it so here I'm
going to say debug draw color derp I'm
gonna pass the spec atlas for that one
I'll need the lighting solution and the
Center P and then I'll do the same thing
for the diffuse Alice and the problem
here that I'm going to have is I'm not
gonna be able to tell the two apart
right so we're gonna have to come up
with some way of differentiating the
tube and I'm not sure how I'm gonna do
that that's that's that's a good
question I so I think that's all good
and
[Music]
so you can see the diffuse Atlas grows
at a rate totally absurd compared to the
spec Alice right and I guess that's what
you would expect because you're summing
up values from the spec Atlas into the
diffuse Atlas but I guess what I would
say is there's still some unanswered
questions there that I think we need to
start tracking down so first of all it
does look like you know like I was
thinking so starting the lighting
quality pass and working on what that
diffuse blur should actually do is gonna
be pretty critical because it definitely
grows way too quickly with the the spec
lighting input so that's unsurprising
but I think the other thing we need to
do is so if we just take a look just at
the spec atlas here to go back to the
previous debugging step because I want
to track this down I just don't know
where that up side lighting is coming
from so when we look here you know and
we see this like really clear bias up
towards all this like apparent lighting
that is coming from the sky right what
what is going on so maybe we can step in
to this particular lighting calculation
and take a look at what's coming back
you know another thing we could do is
turn off the gather from from outs like
don't do them and see just to see
whether that's the primary thing that's
causing us getting too much feedback you
know which would give us some some like
clues basically to what's happening
so if we take a look in in the raycast
er here where we go grid raycast and we
come out and here's where we're actually
doing our transfer computations so what
you can see here is we do this no matter
what so we're going to compute fox the
radiance no matter what happens here
right what I'm imagining is probably
happening is something along the lines
of like the diffuse and specular sees
like somehow have bright stuff at the
apron so when we hit the apron we record
a bright light coming back that isn't
there or something you know you know or
something like this
I don't know I'm not sure that's it
that's a tough one but what I can do
here is I can predicate this if we want
to where if we take the transfer PPS
values which at the moment are always
being written what I could do instead is
I can make it so that we don't write
them in the case where we didn't hit so
if we look here and we say if the probe
so if if we come out of here and we
don't actually think we hit anything and
I'm not sure that we ever really record
that information so you can see like
something kit would be the thing that
would tell us that whether we ever
actually hit and you know at the moment
anyway we never really record that
information but we easily could so you
could imagine you know doing this right
and it's the exact same loop now there's
no difference between the two but it
also because because basically the first
time this becomes true we exit out so it
doesn't matter that it persists so we
could look at it after the fact right so
when we break out of this loop for a
particular array Oh oops
and I did put it slightly - I know I
didn't put it in right place so when we
break out of this loop we could just
check to see and say look you know if
something was hit you can do this
otherwise
right so that's gonna stop anything but
an actual legitimate raycast from
actually producing color transfer and so
now if I look at it I just want to look
and see what I'm actually gonna see with
with these values right and what you can
see here is it's it's still completely
screwed right you can see what looks
like reasonable lighting results in a
sense but they're just totally the wrong
direction right there there's like no
there's no sense in that at all the the
spec map is overwhelmingly getting light
from a place that doesn't actually exist
there is no light up there at all so how
is it getting that and again this is
only this is very specifically when it
does hit something not when it doesn't
hit something so now let's try the
opposite now let's try disallowing hits
right and this should produce no light
right I don't think there should be any
way to actually get light into this
system so no matter how many times I hit
f9 to step the lighting we should see
nothing right okay so that's good it
doesn't really give us much information
but it at least tells us like oh okay
like we're not doing something totally
crazy all right so we've got some
serious issues going on here and it does
look like we're getting false reports of
hits and
well that's not true we're either
generating false hit reports or we're
miss writing the direction in a way that
we don't currently know how to look at
right like I tried to do a little bit of
verification that the place that the
spec Texel values were being written
back was correct now there is another
possibility which is that when we're
actually you know in doing the doing the
right back
so in the internal lighting core after
we call well after we call the internal
lighting core so this routine debug
dropped heedful values this routine
could be the thing that's wrong right I
mean it could be that we're drawing the
values erroneously somehow so like the T
Y and T X that we're asking for were
somehow pulling the wrong value out so
you know it's possible but I don't know
I think that's going to take some doing
to like actually kind of look into this
particular piece of code where we've
passed the spec texels here you know I
could try to sort of verify that that
code was correct if we look when we step
through the rows of the spec atlas
we're just looking at the one tile that
we're on and we're stepping to one and
then one plus the road that is where we
would expect to start right and then
five and one plus the row which is where
we respect the next one to be and those
both seem totally reasonable like that's
what you expect right and then the
sample Durer has to be updated that it
just I don't see what's wrong with that
it looks roughly correct to me so yeah I
just don't I just don't see
I don't quite see how that's wrong
so since we drew these and they looked
correct the yeah the only possibilities
are that the drawing code is somehow not
correct meaning we think we drew it and
we didn't really or somehow when you
actually call this it's slightly it's
subtly different in a way that we're not
picking up right but I am sorry I just
don't see it I don't see it yet and what
yeah like what what would be what could
possibly be causing that scenario to
occur
because as far as I can tell you know we
looked at the raycast er it looks like
it's doing the correct casting and I
mean especially with the if something
hit part on I think we even verified
that it's not even yeah I mean let's
let's take a look so let's take this
here and color it based on whether it
thinks something was hit or not so we
can see whether it really outed right
again don't expect to learn much from
this but it's just another piece of
information just because I'm not really
sure what to look for I just kind of
need to guess so in that well I guess in
this case we already sort of did the
test now I think about it if something
hit if we use the something hit version
and we're running it then when we look
at that guy it just won't draw right
yeah I mean it just doesn't draw so we
know that it doesn't think that's a hit
right we already know that why are we
getting multiple Ray casts here oh I
know why it's because we're not turning
debugging off in that case right
yeah I don't know that's a real puzzler
I'm gonna put this outside for now like
so and then I'm looking at so I guess if
I want to test this now I want to see I
guess I want to pick you know maybe like
the one next to me this one right here
and look at that direction that it seems
to think that it's getting lighting that
way right and again it's a little tough
to be completely honest with you it's a
little tough to necessarily call some of
these wrong because the octahedral map
is actually fairly sparse and you know
technically if I was looking at say you
know this one right here that could have
come from that light right those would
have probably been in the same spec map
region what doesn't make any sense is
for example you look in here I mean
so maybe what I should be doing is
looking it like that because you know I
should be seeing this should should be
where we're getting the light from like
this right here right like all of these
should be coming from over there you
know what I mean
at least
so if I shift my my guy over here and I
wonder yeah I wonder if there's some
easy way I could do a box pick on that I
just wouldn't take very long our debug
system is just really crappy it's too
bad anyway maybe I can just take a look
at what happens am I going the wrong way
on this I am
so like maybe I can take a look at what
happens from right here and see why you
know like I can't my I'm not hitting you
know this light
they're so 177 88 and that's in that's
in the in it so it's in nope so in the
in it
I want 1 77 88 and then I want to cast
like towards the light let me restart
that real quick because there's too many
too many lines being drawn I can't see
so I just want to pick a ray that goes
to the light source now and I want to
see what the heck is going on because
like why aren't we getting strong light
coming back from the light source right
like why why are we not hitting that
light source ever
apparently start down the lower
it's not hitting nope oh man so close
it doesn't seem like I'm really ever
getting there let's try that one more
time
I mean I guess it's possible that
they're just it never quite picks a ray
direction that can hit that would be
unfortunate and might mean that we don't
have a dense enough sampling of the
sphere over time but I mean that's sort
of a separate issue because we are
picking up a ton of light so the
question is if we're never hitting a
light source how are we doing that god
it's like so close I should just move
the light upward slightly you know I
just move the light upward slightly so
that I don't have to keep picking so
that was 159
that one like kind of goes through it
but it's just on the edge
I'm going to go in for my own benefit
and say I wonder if I can for the debug
ray caster I'm not sure I actually need
to I'm not sure that I actually need to
only run that in the one place that it's
being run like I could run that at the
push well I know but it hasn't actually
do anything so yeah I kind of do have to
so what I could do is just like in the
build a few slight Maps I could turn
that back to one for the moment well I
try to find the thing that hits the
light source so we're not getting those
so many light thinks I could also clamp
the total length of those things because
I guess we don't need to see that we
just need to know that it's wrong that's
probably what I should do actually now I
think about it so I have no idea
what would be a more efficient way of
debugging this short of like stopping
and like writing an actually fairly
complete debug system for picking these
things
okay there it is so there's a direct hit
on the light source 325 right so 325 I
can remember that cast here so some 88 3
2005 and now we should have a stable
debug scenario where when we run this I
can look specifically at what happens
with that cast right
should I not recompile this I didn't
nope I just didn't type it in so what
I'm gonna do is assume I guess I'll save
this for next time but what I'm gonna do
is just now step through the code and
find out you know where is that getting
written in the spec map right because
you can see that's a hit right so we
should be able to loop through and watch
that get hit and why is that not
producing a light spike in that
direction because it's definitely not
right as we watch the spec map
propagates we never see a light in that
direction for whatever reason and we
don't have an explanation for that like
at all right so something's up and we
don't know what but yeah we should be
seeing that grow as this sample picks up
but you know that's not really what
we're seeing so I might call it there
for today because jabba have a lot of
more debugging to do I would like to do
one more thing before we exit someone
had asked on the github
I guess the flowing point mask so the
when we did this to get rid of nad
normals we have this set default FP
behavior right when we did this I guess
control mask in that way that both
Windows and Linux are absolutely
horrible about H files
apparently x windows just define
something called control mask not x11
control mass not X underscore L control
mass not underscore control ISO just
control mask because they were like we
don't care about you you should just use
you should just only use names we let
you use and control mask isn't one of
them so apparently we shouldn't use this
because people who compiled on Linux you
know just had problems with it so we can
change it to something else like that
and again that doesn't change the code
at all it just makes it so that x11
scrappy header files won't screw us up
right so when uplink could or had a good
suggestion I just happened against us
and we should probably do this as well
and the suggestion was to only have one
light source and I totally agree with
that we should do that lower that's
another thing we can do this really easy
because then we don't have to worry
about where things are hitting light
sources potentially so what I could do
is say yeah okay maybe we'll just use
the debug light source so what we'll do
is we'll go in here and say when we
generate the room we we won't actually
so those lamps like that we put in there
we won't actually put the the lights on
those lamps so these I can just get rid
of right
so now when we run there's like
literally only just that one light you
know and I can go back to the build
diffuse light Maps now to be fair
there's still multiple lights there's
lights on the enemies but they're not in
the world right now like like we haven't
hopped to where they are so they
shouldn't even be in the entity system
so hopefully that wouldn't cause any
problems because the lighting system
can't actually access those so if we do
let it grow the fast way just as a quick
check to see what information we get out
of it we can now run it and we now know
that any light that's coming from the
system should be coming from this light
it's the only one there is so here's the
results and again exactly like I said
it's it's nonsensical right all of the
lights are coming from this direction
out here when they all should be coming
from this direction over here so we've
you know we've got some fundamental bug
with how we're lining up directions and
if you'll recall I've said this dozens
of times on handmade here right now but
I'll say it one more time all of these
languages like the people keep talking
about like rust or whatever they're all
designed for catching errors that are so
asinine and uninteresting to me because
they never take any of my time and they
offer me literally nothing for actually
debugging hard problems or writing code
that doesn't have those indexing like
lining up indices and where things are
that is where 90% of my bugs come from
and I don't know for sure that what
we're looking at here is an indexing bug
but I bet you dollars to doughnuts that
it probably is and I really wish people
would stop thinking that like you know
accidentally using a output parameter as
an input parameter or vice versa
or something was like we're programming
it needs like where we need to focus our
time we're like forgetting which part of
the code owns what memory block it's
like these are things that like take
none of my time by comparison to stuff
like this which takes all of my time and
like it's just weird it's like we spend
all of this language development
opportunity just dealing trying to make
trying to eliminate bugs that only
programmers
I wouldn't want on my team make anyway
and like I wish at least somebody and
maybe John is the person who's doing
this right I wish we would spend more
time making languages that don't have
the kinds of bugs that advanced
programmers make right like what are the
word of the people who really program a
lot and know what they're doing they
still have a ton of bugs it's not like I
don't have a ton of bugs could somebody
please take a second and make a language
that tries to lean into kind of bugs
that I have not the kind of bugs that
you know people who haven't don't even
understand but what like allocating
memory does like we've never actually
called virtual Alec like I don't really
care about that there's so many
languages for those kinds of programmers
why is that the only thing anyone makes
you know so like I'm pretty sure this is
probably some new necks problem it's
probably just a problem because there's
so many indices right we are trying to
like create voxels at different scales
we're trying to create maps for the
light that we store and there's so many
indices and they're really hard to get
right and I feel like that's almost
certainly what we're seeing here right
like we are probably doing something
where we think we're recording light
that's coming from here but we're
actually saying that it's coming from
there you know
I mean it could be something else but
that's what it is you know I bet that's
what it is because it sure does look
like that is an overwhelmingly biased
light field it is all shooting you know
directly in that direction and so you
imagine if all of those were actually
pointing this way you'd actually just
think it was right you know what I mean
so it does seem like there is some ray
casting going on but it seems like
totally busted
what I will say is how the heck are
these guys getting those lights I guess
they're getting them by hitting the
ground and then interpolating from these
right which is a problem we're always
gonna have with this kind of scheme and
fortunately for this game I don't think
we have to care about it too much
because it'll probably be fine once we
work it out but even so right you can
you can tell this just totally busted
like because all of these should be
going kind of the opposite direction
all right so we're go to brief Q&amp;A
yeah I agree with trying to move the
light it would give us some some limited
information so we could see like what
the actual you know what the actual
transform was on it so for example if we
know that we're getting light that goes
in if we know that we're getting light
that goes in that direction and then we
just take the debug light and move it to
the side right so we could go into the
world mode and we look at the debug
light right so here I can just add like
a bunch of X to it right now the problem
is I have to keep it in bounds because I
can't move it outside of the lighting
system entirely but I can just like
slide it off to the side so now you know
if you look at where the the debug light
is it should be I guess that was too far
because I don't see it anymore right oh
is it just is it just embedded in some
geometry looks like it's just over there
maybe
so that's just getting that's just still
well I guess you know what it did shear
somewhat this direction let's see if by
pulling it back we can share it the
other direction right so let's suppose
we set it this way and again I don't
know if it's still in bounds but let's
see if we bend it to the to the right
there huh
so no it's but it did change direction
right so actually moving it this way
slid things that way and again the
octahedral map is packed in a sort of
odd way right so you can imagine like
that being a case what I would say too
though is there's there's more here than
just that because this also seems
erroneous in other ways because how
would you be hitting this light from
here at all like that doesn't make a
whole lot of sense
maybe it's interpolated from here but
that's a bit of a stretch right so I
don't know so I feel like there's some
deeper problem going on there than just
maybe that it's that it's incorrectly
placed like I think there's maybe you
know a little bit yeah a little bit
deeper I don't know I'm not convinced
that it's as simple as that right
let's see
one of their two litters in the map with
only one light source well first of all
the lighting is buggy right now that's
what we're working on so part of it
might be that but I don't know that
there really are though if you're
talking about that that's just because
that's just the the the graphics card is
not being told to do anything when the
lighting sample area is out of bounds so
this is the only place you'd be able to
see in the game this just tiles
throughout the universe so you just see
there'd be another one over here another
one over here right but you can never
see over there and by the time we move
over there you know we will have updated
things now of course the lighting system
is frozen in place but by the time we
actually are looking at this area then
if we started to run it you can see that
it would you know actually only be doing
the lighting for this region and then
you would see that region is copied you
know around so that's just actually
because we don't we only simulate
lighting at the area that you're looking
at and if you look at in the debug mode
you can see stuff that's kind of further
than that and that's where that comes
from so I don't think we have any bugs
actually that have to do with that so I
think that's if that's you're talking
about that's that's all that is the bug
that we have at the moment is for the
grid based ray casting we just don't
seem to have any real coherence and what
the maps actually producing which is a
little bit odd I'm not sure one thing
that occurred to me just now that I
hadn't thought up before is since we can
use the lighting grid if we since we can
not use the lighting grid I wonder what
happens if we just use the AABB test or
instead because that would let us debug
the debug drawing which could also be
wrong right so if we do this which is a
correct lighting slew
okay so basically our debug drawing is
wrong right because look
this is the correct lighting right this
is what we would expect to see and then
we come out here and we can do stuff and
yeah so using the eight you know if we
don't use the grid we get reasonable
lighting and those things are in the
wrong place let me actually go to the
world mode here real quick and turn off
the the f9 key press so let's just say
that it's always updating so if we set
it to always updating and now we run we
should be able to like tune I don't know
I didn't think its before we should be
able to tune our debug lighting here so
that we actually see this doing the
correct thing as we move throughout the
world right and so let's just see what
did we screw up so that that was
excellent I don't know why I didn't
think of that before so if I look at
debug dropped a huge L values here this
is doing something dumb question is what
so here it is doing the center we assume
that's correct
because we don't really we probably
aren't looking at the wrong place I
don't know I don't think we are and then
we're just looping over the txt Y values
and asking this to draw them so
presumably if there's a bug it's in here
presumably
if I go over to debug draw color here
and we look at what we're passing right
oops and we look at the indices we say
okay I want to get the tile unclamp for
the X Y Z T X 2y that could obviously be
wrong so we want to look at that and we
also have the direction from T X D Y and
that could also be wrong right the rest
of this is pretty straight forward and
probably couldn't produce a directional
change so let's take a look at direction
from 2 X to Y now that just wants the Oh
X Y coefficient we don't know
necessarily that this is right I guess
I guess we should probably try to test
it more thoroughly I mean I guess we can
do that I thought we did though but we
could test it more thoroughly but we are
passing the X Y coefficient which is the
only real requirement and then we have
the 2x and 2y there they are offset by
one properly which is what we're seeing
here so it doesn't seem weird if I go to
get tile unclamped which is another
story all together in in get tile
unclamped you can see I've got the x y&amp;z
coming in here which I checked to make
sure it's not out of bounds which seems
good we then take the TX in the T Y and
we go to grab those by getting late exit
at texels computing the offset from them
right and then returning that value now
the light Atlas offset I suppose could
itself be wrong like this could be wrong
I guess
but it doesn't seem likely so it's it's
kind of gotta be sort of correct in the
sense that it's definitive though like
so I'm assuming
yeah I don't know like it's being used
for everything anyway so I'm not sure
that we could have really had much of a
bug with it so it's kind of confusing I
don't know
[Music]
hmm-hmm-hmm well at least we now know
though that this this is to blame but it
could be that we've got a bug in
direction from txt why and if we did
that would also mean that there's
problems with our generator as well
which could be important because I
believe that that gets used so in the h8
sphere right so when we actually do the
generator octahedral lighting pattern we
use direction from txt Y now what I
would assume direction that's in the
debug that's in debug that is in a
routine we haven't verified right so I
guess what I would say is this is highly
suspect right so I wonder if our
direction from txt Y code is actually
wrong because if it was that would make
a lot of sense right because then we
also would have directional errors in
our sampler only in the grid ray caster
and not in the a B because the a BB
doesn't use a table that builds that
does it or Mel no it does nevermind so
they both use that
so they both do use that so I guess
that's not as suspicious
I stand to say I thought it was only in
those places so I don't know I don't
know that's that's pretty confusing to
me
I don't immediately see what the problem
is there and like I said I might I might
say this until next time because it
looks like I have to to move in move
into it right
so yeah I would like to see what
direction it is going yeah and end like
and like if you look at it it's pretty
bizarre too because it doesn't seem to
be super obvious what the transfer
between the two are which I guess is
what you'd expect with an octahedral map
because in octave yield map was kind of
a somewhat difficult to immediately
intuit packing and it's easy to see how
it's packed but your brain doesn't
necessarily unwrap things octahedrally
very quickly but like you can see here
right if I move around let me let me go
maybe to an area where I can move around
more freely where there aren't as many
walls so here if I kind of look at the
way this is going
like what it just doesn't make any sense
it's really really strange so it's like
it does seem just totally broken because
like why would it
why would I suddenly be getting a bunch
of light showing up over here right
which by the way I'm not singing so like
if you look I'm not actually seeing it
there so I don't know is is it possible
that the X Y Z's are wrong somehow that
our input to this like I mean I don't
know that's the only thing I can think
of that would be like kind of in that
same general ballpark right I got my a
mine now I don't know um debug there we
go
so I guess I don't quite know it's
pretty difficult to it's pretty
difficult to guess I don't actually know
I think I'm gonna need more time like I
said so I'm probably gonna call it there
and we'll take a look but you know yeah
like this we could re-enable we had some
assertions in here too I think I don't
think we use them anymore but we could
let the light Atlas asserts like you
know check our bounds again but I don't
actually think we're picking things that
are out of bounds we're probably picking
things that are wrong would be you know
my guess I don't know though like you
know for I could see us like passing XY
z-- and Z's in the wrong order or
something like that
I don't know yeah I don't know it's it's
tough to say but I guess what I would
say here is like the we could re enable
this assert so we could just say look
you know it's light Atlas assert or I
guess I could do it like this oops and
that would just force it to actually do
an assertion there just in case I mean
like I said I don't think we'd actually
get one yeah we don't but yeah I just
think it's gonna take too long so I
think I'll save that for next time but
at least we kind of know like alright so
our debug drawing was wrong and that
means like some of our routines are
wrong so we can go try to verify some of
those routines and it actually wouldn't
be hard to make something that was like
a unit test of just those two math
routines right so while there's really
no way we can test the lighting system
with a test that would really work we
could test just the octahedral indexing
in and out and try to bulletproof that a
little bit so there are some things we
could do there and maybe that's like a
good next step for example all right
push debug line parameter order hmm you
know what that's not a bad suggestion I
don't I don't know that we it seems
unlikely but yeah you know could be so
if I go to debug draw larger you know
maybe it is that would be great but yeah
it's it's not right because the color is
the last value and you know here's the
center peep in the center p+ skew
intensity der so you know it's a bummer
right but it's alright
see if there are any other suggestions
for we sign-off direction inverted um it
doesn't look like it's inverted to me
does it look like it's inverted to you
because if it was inverted I would
expect to see it counter rotate with me
you know like if I move over here I
expect to see it start going that way
but it's really not doing that and oddly
enough it seems to like you know it's
weird it's it's just very strange I'm
not sure what I'm not really sure what's
going on here it's very absorbed but at
least we have a visualization that we
can now align to an actual versions
that's roughly working so we should be
able to debug this and get this to the
point where whatever the weird thing is
that we obviously screwed up
it just yeah it just looks weird
and if you look at what's going on here
too you know it's like I don't understa
be seeing it coming down here you know I
don't know it's very odd it's not right
I don't know how direction TX from T Y
direction from takes to you I could be
wrong though
I don't know
does this not pass through the thing we
did for having the 3d texture oh I see
no we don't tilt the line in the shader
these lines are just drawn directly far
as I know so yeah I don't know I think
we're just gonna have to spend another
serious debug session on it which is
fair like I said it's very complicated
code so it's gonna take a while to get
to but we'll get there
you can always break it down into
smaller pieces and then test those
pieces so alright thank you everyone for
joining me for the episode of hand made
here it's my pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with the series at home you can always
pre-order the game at hand made here org
and it comes with source code so you can
follow along with it assuming that my
voice isn't having troubles as it has
been I will be back here next week and
if it is I might take some time off to
let it rest we'll see nobody seems to
really quite know what's wrong with it
so I'm not sure how to give a forecast
on it but that's it for today I will see
you all back here next weekend assuming
all goes well and until then have fun
programming I'll see you ever on the
Internet particular buddy