start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade Hero the show where
we code a complete game live on stream
before we get back to game coding today
we've got some announcements to make for
folks who you may be just just joining
or are not in the know first things
first the handmade Network site has
launched and it is not actually like a
kind of an official launch yet they are
sort of it's it's more like a public
beta they said they're not going to be
necessarily doing
I think they click on the soft launch so
they're still taking feedback and
collecting bug reports and that sort of
stuff but anyone it's accessible to the
public now so if you want to check it
out you can and that is just that
handmade network this is the site and e
there's a handmade hero page on it the
reason for the handmade hero page on it
is because it is now the place where the
forums are hosted and they're a lot
nicer than the old forums and by nicer I
mostly just mean that they are not
infinitely slow like the old forums I
don't know if you remember are just
incredibly incredibly slow to use and
they were in this nasty Joomla craziness
and so it's exactly the same forums that
you're used to there at hero handmade
Network and that's got like the the sort
of landing page and and that sort of
stuff and also the forum's page and
there's a specific subsection if you
just want the forum's the link on the
home page will now go here when you
click on forums your login should still
work so the old law you shouldn't have
to make a new account you should still
have you know whoever you are
username will still work here and when
you log in you can just put in your old
user name and credentials and it should
just work so you shouldn't have to do
really anything in particular you'll
just end up with new forums and by
default just a few things are listed on
the main page and then when you click on
the more you get the whole the full set
of stuff
again still it's it's not fully launched
yet they're still they said they didn't
want to publicize it too widely but they
did say it was okay to announce it and
the forums have been moved over to it so
people who want to use the forums have
to go here now the old forums are no
longer accessible in any way so check
that out and that yeah and that is that
is the news that is the news so that's
about it for business
I think other than that I did take the
opportunity to sort of clean up some of
these things the twitch page now has
some cleaned up stuff at the underneath
it the schedule bot and the past
episodes I sort of changed the schedule
about wording in the past episodes now
instead of going to the YouTube just
goes straight to the episode guide which
again is also it's exactly the same as
it was before it's just it's now hosted
under the handmade Network placement as
well so you know if you come in here
you'll get the exact same stuff you were
used to get but it's just hosted at the
at the new location so yeah so nobody
should really have to change anything
they're doing just hopefully
everything's a little bit better now
because it's out of the sort of janky
old way that was being done and it's now
on a server that's that's running much
more smoothly and gets rid of lot of the
cruft of the old forums so that's it if
anyone has any questions about that
stuff or feedback you can go I think
anywhere on here like I don't know I
don't know super much how to use the
site on handmade network but I think at
the bottom of every page I'm not really
sure yeah at the bottom of every page of
course it's behind my head there's a
contact thing here or you can just put
contact after the the URL if you look
here there's information about who to
contact if you have a problem with the
site that isn't working the way it used
to or something and you're trying to get
to something it's it's it comes in here
at the moment I have been told that
there is a holdup with as far as
handmade hero is concerned right now
there's only the Forbes if sub guide
there's a resources page that's missing
and a thanks page that are missing those
are supposed to be imported sometime
soon so hopefully by the end of the week
those way back those are not super
important pages at the moment like
they're not like the forums where they
get used every day but they are pretty
important so they'll be back they're not
they weren't deleted but they are
they're not here yet
I think that's everything if it's not
everything you can ask the guys in chat
most of the people responsible for this
site are on the chat right now so you
can ask them about it and/or
congratulate them for getting everything
working smoothly I already was playing
around with the forums and they're quite
a bit nicer like I said it's it's kind
of nice to just be able to click through
them and not have to wait at least on my
machines it was always you know you'd
click and you'd wait forever for it to
load up one of these responses and I
think that's just because joomla's is
real bad anyway that's all there is to
say about that so let's go ahead and get
started here today is day 272 if you
would like to follow along at home you
want to use day 271 source code and that
is the source the state of the source
code that I am going to be using today
so if we look at where we left off I had
just started programming some stuff for
the main character in the game because
we have most of the engine stuff that we
wanted to write written and so I was
starting to play around with the main
character and essentially what I want to
do for the main character is there's a
little bit of a kind of a strange aspect
to his motion it is not that similar to
the way most characters move in fact the
exact design that I have for it which we
were in the process of implementing now
is I don't think I've ever actually seen
a game used this this method of
controlling the character so it's going
to be a little unusual and it's going to
take us some tuning to get it to
feel right as well because it's kind of
a new sort of thing but that's okay
that's what game programming is about so
as you can see unlike before the head
and the body are now dissociated which
of course is very disturbing for this
this poor little fellow that is not the
intent in the long run that is just the
way that I was choosing to start
developing how he moved and the reason
for this is because the bottom like the
part of the of the person of the hero
that stands on the ground is going to
lock to a particular location on the
screen now it doesn't actually have to
be a grid we've created a grid here
because I think a lot of the screens
will want to be grid like so it is going
to be oftentimes grid like but we don't
actually require it to be grid like we
may use some very non grid or sort of
layouts of things in the future but what
they will all have in common and you can
see this based on the little squares the
little yellowish squares in the middle
there they're sort of orange squares
that the that the the body snaps to what
you will notice about these is that it
always has to go and be on one of those
points that's where the body has to be
and so what I want to have happen and
what we're trying to shoot for now is I
want the body to always be locked to one
of those and when I move the head what I
want to do is for him to just lean so
what we're going to try and do is make
it so the body part of the hero just
leans you know left or leans right and
then only when the head has sort of
gotten to the midpoint right so when I'm
here then the body actually sort of will
jump right and I mean that literally not
in the figurative sense of its
teleporting from one place to another in
code I mean literally jump like the
character will like push off the ground
and you know go towards the and go
towards the other one so it'll it'll
kind of hop and so you can move the head
around freely and the head will be
movable not maybe exactly like I'm
moving it now
kind of similar like it will feel mostly
like this to move the character around
the only difference will be if you let
go of the motion what if I'm not moving
it'll snap back to the to the neck right
and so what we really need to do now is
I need to essentially take that what
will there's a couple things we need to
do now one is I have to actually write
some real code this was kind of just
makeshift code I need to write some real
code that tries to actually keep the the
body on a particular square so that has
to be done and I also need to write some
code that will stretch the body like do
that sort of rotation and scale so that
the body will attach to the head because
I don't want it to appear like the head
is floating at all I want it to feel
like the head is solidly attached to the
body so we need to do that and then I
need to start working on the code for
doing that animation of sort of jumping
between different locations so a lot of
work there and I think it'll take us
several days because we're only doing an
hour a day I think it'll take us several
days to get this right and since this is
gonna be the main way that you interact
with the game is this kind of motion we
really want this to feel good and look
good so we want to get a good first pass
here it's probably not going to be the
final one because you know we'll
probably tweak it continuously
throughout the entire project but we
want something that we that feels good
to us now so that we know before going
any further with this design we know
that that part is stable you definitely
don't want to proceed further in the
code until you know that the actual act
of interacting with the character is you
know enjoyable right that that would be
bad if it felt lousy turned of the
character and I feel lousy of course I
mean to me because it's my game
obviously not everyone has the same
opinions about how character motion
should feel of course everyone thinks
that they have the only right opinion
about how character motion should feel
but those people are unfortunately
misguided and probably products of a
broken childhood so it's okay you know
they can get therapy it's not the end of
the world and and the rest of us can
just acknowledge the fact that we have
different opinions about how character
motion should work so let's go in here
to handmade code and let's go take a
look at the sort of beginnings of the
code that I put in there it was in world
move dot CPP and we've got sort of the
two different things here we've got the
hero head and here you know you can kind
of see the code that I wrote here here
is dope sorry that's the motion code for
it I don't actually need that here we go
let's see here
zero body and here we go so what I was
doing here is again just sort of
prototyping out this code I essentially
made it so that the body just takes a
look at wherever the head is it searches
for the closest point that it could
stand on to the head and it moves
towards that now if it's already on that
point obviously it'll just kind of stay
on it but if it's a different point
it'll move toward it and it moves toward
it using the standard movement code that
we had worked on already so the problem
with this there's a number of problems
with this but the biggest problem with
this is it's a little - it's a little
too analog for my taste
in this circumstance right what's
happening right now is that body and I
can sort of draw this out for you what I
kind of what I'm what I'm a little
nervous about and what I will you know
sort of try to correct here so what I'm
a little nervous about is you know I've
got the the body here you know here's
the head here's the body and the body is
standing on a particular point now what
I want to do is I want to acknowledge
the fact that they
is essentially two phases here because
right now we only have one phase right
there's only movement
there's just where am I trying to go
right we just have a target and we have
a position and we're just always gonna
move towards that right I mean that's
the way this code we're gonna just read
this code you can see that that's what
it does it basically says like okay I'm
just trying to go here and the reason
why it sort of stops on a point is
because if that target happens to be
coincident with the point then there's
really no motion and so yeah you know we
get a situation like that where it comes
to basic rest on the thing but it's
sloppy and it overshoots and it's it
doesn't even really know the difference
at this point it doesn't it doesn't
really have a conception of being in
those modes the only that could really
do is if I wanted to I could I could
check an epsilon and say how close to my
to the point if I'm close enough then
call it a day right so but but the code
you know is just not aware of that
aspect of it at the moment so I think
the first thing I would like to do is is
increase that sort of state space to
basically have stand and movement as two
separate modes and people asked to like
one person asked me the other day to
explain we didn't get to it
but in the questions they had asked me
to explain finite state machines and you
know we can try to explain it we can try
to do this at some point finance state
machines are are kind of they're one of
those sort of glorified terms that that
isn't really super useful because it
makes it sound like there's a formalism
when really there's oftentimes not a for
muslim and oftentimes you really don't
want a formalism if you go read
something like compiler literature
you'll see a very formal definition of
things such as a finite state machine
usually there's sort of these there's
there's two aspects of these again with
the foremost and maybe we'll explain
these someday
I'm not gonna really talk about today
there's deterministic and
non-deterministic ones and there's a lot
of there's a lot of stuff in here that
that gets formalized for purposes that
are probably quite useful in CS but are
really not very useful in programming
like if what you're actually trying to
do is get stuff accomplished I don't
find these are ever useful to really
think about and the reason for that is
because they approach the problem kind
of the reverse direction from what you
actually are trying to do I think of
FSMs a lot like object-oriented
programming they are basically a way of
trying to pretend that the notion of
like what state you're in is somehow
this like pure primal important thing
and everything else has to like come out
of this concept of the state that you
are in and that's just hogwash it's not
actually true and so again while finite
state machines as a formalism for
certain types of analysis and in
studying things and all the sort of
stuff is probably quite useful in actual
coding it tends to lead people down the
OOP trail I feel like the same sorts of
stuff that's problematic about thinking
that objects are primal and objects are
very important and you should start with
the objects same sort of thing happens
to people when they go down the finite
state machine route they start thinking
that states are this important thing and
somehow it's different really it doesn't
matter at all right conceptually
speaking you may want to start thinking
of things in terms of having some states
when the part when you're at the part of
your program when it's clear that there
are some concrete different states but
really there's a lot of fluidity between
these two things and oftentimes you
don't really want to think about things
being is entirely in one state or
another and so you want to let the
concept of States come out of the
natural coding process and you don't
want to like clamp this concept of a
finite state machine down on to the code
because it has all of those same
negative effects that object-oriented
programming does that doesn't mean you
won't get to something that has finite
state machine like elements in it and in
fact you would argue I think quite
convincingly that there's plenty of
parts of handmade hero that already look
finite state machine like and that's
because in the course of ordinary
you oftentimes will end up with an enum
that says what of a couple different
ways something could work it should be
working right now and inside the switch
statement that switches on those enums
will be what's the rule for
transitioning to it to setting the enum
to a different value that Eden of itself
is definitely a finite state machine and
so again not a bad thing just a bad way
of approaching a problem you usually
want to come at it the other way round
and then you'll just find one day Oh
looks like there's some finite state
machines in here and pretty much any
program of any complexity will have some
finite some things in it that look like
or technically even are directly a
finite state machine it's what computing
it's how computing works so it's not
surprising so what I want to do is sort
of increase the state nough sub this and
saying that when I'm moving around the
body is gonna be in a particular state
which is stationary and when it is in a
state that's stationary no matter what I
do with the head the body is gonna stay
where it is and so to get this sort of
starting is very simple obviously you
know I can just go to the sim entity
oops sorry
it's not in sync entity it's in same
region will probably to start breaking
these files up a little bit as we sort
of get going with them but for the
moment fine so in here I'm just gonna do
like a sim movement mode or something
like this and I'm just gonna say okay
there's a there's a movement mode which
is like body standing or something like
this or you know planted and then
there's a sim movement hopping and I'm
just gonna have those two modes right
now and so when I am talking about the
body it can either be planted which
means it's like on the ground
specifically or it can be hopping which
means it's going to like move from one
place to another right so here's my
movement mode and then in here when we
get to something like Hiro body I can
switch on what the
mode is and I can do whatever I want so
if I say okay what's my movement mode I
can say all right if the movement mode
is similar you know that should probably
instead of it's similar subbing movement
mode so if my movement mode is planted
then I should not be able to do anything
at the moment and if my movement mode is
hopping then I I can you know have it
happen so I'm gonna go ahead and take
this code well I suppose I should also
say that you know probably you've got to
have the head if the head is gone none
of this is gonna happen but I'm gonna
take the exact same stuff I did before
I'm gonna say that in hopping mode for
now even though it's not what I actually
want for now what it will do when it
hops is it'll use this this sort of this
this chasing behavior that we already
implemented and when we're planted we
won't okay so now what should happen if
everything is working correctly that
movement mode is gonna be initialized to
zero when this thing is cleared and so
when I actually try to run this game
when I move the head nothing should
happen right it should be stationary and
the reason for that is because I can't
actually ever get out of that mode
there's no way to trigger a transition
to the to the hopping mode and so what I
want to do here is write some kind of an
if statement inside that planted mode
that's like well what has to happen to
make me start hopping right what will
make that hop start occurring and so I
may want to keep this code for example I
may want to say let's take a look at
what the closest thing is right and so
I'm gonna move that code outside will
say every time we'll take a look but we
just won't actually do any movement
unless we're in the hopping mode so in
here what I could say is well okay
wherever the head is I'm gonna say that
if the if the closest point
um if the closest point to the head is
not the same as the closest point to the
body then that's when I would start
moving let's say right I guess the other
thing I could do is say well the the
distance of the point from where I am
has to be greater than something who
knows right but I can easily do that so
if I said here's my closest distance
squared I could say that the closest
distance squared well that's gonna be
the head so yeah I need that I need to
basically say how far is the point to me
so here's the closest P so I'm gonna say
all right the the body Delta I guess the
body Delta is if I was going to go from
where I am now to where I want to be
that's the Delta between you know that
I'm gonna have to move and so how far is
that right so this is the body distance
and that's just going to be the length
squared again I'm just avoiding a square
root although they're not really that
expensive anymore I'm from I'm from I'm
old enough that I always think of square
roots is scary like oh my god don't take
a square root if they're not even scary
anymore you can go ahead and square root
stuff all day long sines and cosines
still aren't great but square root
nobody cares about square root at all
anymore
even sign the cosines aren't really a
big deal anymore compared to memory
accesses
nobody cares anyway body distance is
gonna be a length squared of the body
Delta and so what I want to do here is
say if that body distance is greater
than some amount that I'm gonna call my
tolerance so whatever my tolerance is
like let's say you know a hundredth of a
meter if it's if it's more than that
then I'm going to switch into the other
movement mode so I'm going to switch my
movement mode to two movement mode
hopping
and I'm going to do the exact same thing
here when I'm in movement mode hopping
I'm gonna say that my transition out of
hopping is just going to be when the
body distance is underneath that
tolerance again this is just for now
this is just to have something that does
whatever it's gonna do so that doesn't
look like it's stopping what did I do
it helps if you actually type the right
transition in so now what should happen
is when I move it should actually stop
or not and you know what I might do here
actually I feel like I should be able to
take the body can I click on the body
wonder why I can't click on the body do
we know why I can't click on the body
because there it's it's not like I can
easily make it so that we wouldn't get
at it but I only I'm only getting like I
can never actually click on that
hmm we're gonna have to figure out at
some point how to make sure we can click
on all our entities because right now
we're not really able to to to view
stuff for entities that we can't
highlight and there's a lot of entities
we can't highlight right which is super
annoying like I can click on these guys
but I can't click on the one that I want
to click on that make sense so that's
unfortunate um what was I about to say
oh right so I want to see why this guy
never actually gets out of his hopping
mode right because you can see here when
I'm taking the body distance from
wherever the closest point is I would
have expected to be able to get my
movement mode back to planted at some
point right
and at the moment it does not seem to be
the case and I'm not sure why so I'm
gonna go ahead and take a look and see
what's happening there it may be that
our the way that we've written our
movement code is such that the drag is
insufficient for it and if so the stuff
we're gonna do in a minute will take
care of that entirely but yeah so I
guess it looks like we never we never
get here do we okay there we go
let's come back around
you know what I think I think I know
what it is or maybe I don't I don't know
we'll see uh do we know why this is
still happening here so this why is the
entity coalition getting set to null
collision do we know why that's
happening still I will say that I'm a
little surprised at that I don't know
what that's still doing there let's get
rid of that just because that is not
supposed to be there okay
so I need to figure out again why I'm
not getting the stopping here when I
switch to the planted mode and what I
want to figure out is it what is causing
me to move out of it so let's let's
again go ahead here and say I'm going to
set both breakpoints so if we get to
either of these now it will happen
so it looks like it's just because we
oscillate in between them and this is
probably because this is a bit sloppy
like I mean you could imagine you want
the collar ins for example of this guy
well okay here's another thing I could
do even with this type of tolerance I
could do something like this I could set
the velocity of the character to zero
immediately upon hitting it so he
doesn't carry forward because that now I
think about it I forgotten that we do
physical simulation on the movement of
the characters so probably what actually
happened there is hey we got close
enough but we don't have any
acceleration anymore if we if we stop
accelerating we'll keep our velocity and
you know our drag will be set to nothing
because our drag will be zero which
means we'll just glide until we're
outside the point and we'll toggle back
so we need to if we're going to stop
actually stop if that makes sense so
actually now that I think about that was
probably yeah that was the entirety of
it so now you can see that we when we
actually get to it we do stop it's still
because of the way we send up it still
has the overshoot problem but there you
go so now that I have that what I want
to do is I want to move to a more
animation style movement of that because
this is a very discrete thing so I want
to make it so that it's I want to make
it so that the the control of it is not
just a chasing vector like that like I
think I don't really want to I don't
want to use acceleration velocity kinds
of stuff for it I think I want to use
something a little more procedural
potentially and that may be a mistake
I'm not sure but I think that's what I
want and the only reason that I think it
might be a mistake and perhaps you might
also say the reason why I can't tell if
it's a mistake automatically is because
I'm not sure exactly what should be
happening fuel lies and I just kind of
have to play with it what I've got is a
situation where there are two places
where the player can be standing right
as per the design of the game which
again perspective on the design of this
game is there is a design and we are
implementing it because this is a stream
about game programming and so the idea
is that if you were in a real
environment where you're actually
programming game
you aren't the game designer you have
been told that this is how I'm supposed
to implement you're supposed to
implement this thing but you need to be
able to polish and tune it properly
because obviously if you don't have
those skills you're not gonna be a very
good game programmer so what we want to
do is take that design which says that
okay you need to hop from one to the
other you know the head is here and the
player is moving the head so we have to
have something that feels good for the
head control and when it gets to you
know somewhere like here we want this
this hop to occur now the problem with
this is I don't really know what I want
to have happen if the if the player when
they're playing
moves the head - like let's say here and
the hop begins right so I'm I come up
here and maybe I'm here and the head is
like here by then but then they like
wail on the left button and start to
move the head back so now as this thing
kind of comes up here the head is back
here now and so now it's clear that the
body should actually
verse course in sort of in its arc and
come back to here right let's take an
even worse scenario and look from the
top down
so here's from the top down here's one
standpoint
here's another standpoint and here's
another standpoint okay
the player is standing here they move
the head to here you know what I should
do is I should draw a square for the
body they move the head to here so the
square this square starts moving and it
gets to like here but then they the head
sort of moves back over to here by the
time the head gets here and now what
does the head do and what does the body
do because there's two ways I can write
this code and they have fairly profound
implications for how the game's going to
feel one is sort of like almost like a
basketball style feel where it's like
once you commit to a move with with the
pelvis it has to complete so once you
get past there once the hop starts the
hop ends here so you can still move the
head and you can move the head back the
other way and you'll be duck it you know
you'll be like dodging this way
essentially but the body will move into
that square right whether you like it or
not that's one way to do it the other
way is you can air control out of the
hop and actually come back to either
here or potentially even to a different
one of these like maybe you can even air
control you know if this is a and this
is B and you're going from A to B maybe
you can even air control out to see in
in that case right and I don't know
which of those is the best thing for
this game to feel like certainly there's
more like consequence to the concept
that if you if you go in a direction you
have to commit and you will go that
whole direction and you can air control
the head and dodge or do other things
potentially but you're gonna touch that
other square and any gameplay
implications that that has you've you've
now committed to that's certainly you
know a perhaps a more interesting
thing but it may not feel good enough it
may feel too heavy weight and it may be
that the player really wants to have a
forgiving enough control that they want
to be able to sort of cancel out that
hop so that they can sort of onion Oh
undo the fact that they made a hop in
that direction before they actually pay
whatever the cost is of stepping on that
other square you know maybe there's no
cost but sometimes there might be like
you know if you imagine that's a pit or
a bomb or a trap and I going there and
then I sort of like emit air correct out
of it do I want to let them do that or
don't I right and I don't know the
answer to that question but it has
implications on how we implement it
because obviously they they're gonna
feel a little bit different so what I'm
going to do is I'm going to implement
this for now as a parabolic spline right
so because this is this is about
somebody who's jumping up in the air and
so when you jump up in the air you're
gonna be in a gravitational arc right
and at the risk of stating the
overwhelmingly obvious in case folks on
the stream have never been to a physics
class you know in high school or
something
gravity's arc is a parabola right and
you know so the the look of the arc that
you jump when you jump into the air is a
parabola and as you know a parabola is a
function of time that is proportional to
the square of the time right so it's
going to be something that looks like
this it's an equation that looks like
this and T is not necessarily even an
interpolation parameter in this case I'm
talking about actual time like the real
time in the real world this is what
something looks like when it is in
freefall and again this is in a vacuum
it's not subject to air drag or anything
like that so there's other terms in here
if we want to start talking about other
physical sort of aspects to it but in
general the arc is going to be parabolic
now why is that true and we've already
covered enough on hand-made here
actually for you to know why it's true
if you go back to the physics
stuff you can figure it out pretty
easily and so I'll just mention it here
and if you care go back to the physics
things and look on the episodes we did
on basic basic equations of motion and
the reason is because the second
derivative of what happens in time in
the real world you know under gravity is
a constant gravity is a acceleration
right gravity is something that happens
in the second derivative right because
remember what our derivatives are zero
through a video first order you know
we've got we've got position which is
where we are in the world that its first
derivatives of velocity and second
derivatives acceleration right so the
second derivative of something
acceleration gravity is a constant in
the second derivative it's it's 9.8
meters per second squared and that is
what it is that is what your
acceleration will be under gravity so if
something is constant in the second
derivative when you integrate it up one
time right it is going to be to the
first power of the thing that your of
the of the independent variable right
and if you integrate it up one more time
you will get it squared so the reason
things are parabolic under gravity is
specifically because gravity is a
constant acceleration and acceleration
is the second second derivative of
position integrated up twice to get that
position and you will have a function
proportional to the square and that is
why this is the kind of thing that we
see when we're talking about an
acceleration all constant accelerations
are parabolas in space that's just how
that works that's math so
given that I know this to be true what I
should be able to do is write directly
into the motion of the character a
parabolic parabolic arc that will move
him from one to the other when he goes
into his ballistic phase and I will make
it so that his hop time takes a certain
amount of time again this is part of the
design of the game I wanted to sort of
explore the concept at for lack of a
better term I'm not a game designer so
you know take it with a grain of salt
but it is my game so I can do whatever I
want I wanted to explore the concept
that you don't move the character as a
unit you move the character as two
pieces and one piece moves sort of in a
more typical gamey sort of fashion where
you just kind of move it and it's just
kind of a sloppy thing that was around
but the other one is very specific and
you don't get the opportunity to
directly control it and tell it where
it's going to be and so that is how this
character's motion works so what I want
to do is say well in the planted mode
then we obviously know that this that we
don't really have anything happening as
far as as any differently right the
planted mode will work exactly the same
way no movement for now and then when we
find that we need to go somewhere far
away from us then we will we will move
to our hopping mode okay so it's really
the only the other mode that we care
about and this is going to be a team
movement variable that I have in here
and that team movement variable is going
to go from like say zero to one okay so
what I'm gonna do in here is I'm going
to say that when we come in here we know
what the DT per frame is so I'm going to
go ahead and use whatever that that DT
for frame is I assume we've got that
here somewhere
I don't know where it actually is up
here it's just DT okay so I don't even
need to do that I just need to say T T
so we have the delta time and what I'm
going to do is going to take that T
movement variable for the entity and I'm
gonna go ahead and add it so as time
goes forwards the T movement
increase when I start my jump I'm gonna
set my to movement variable to zero
so I know that I'm at the beginning of
it and when I find that I have reached
the end right then I will transition out
so instead of this previous thing that
we had before instead I'm going to say
okay I'm gonna say that the T movement
variable if it is greater than or equal
to one so I've completed my whole
parabolic arc and I'm just gonna
parameterize it from 0 to 1 for now
because that's usually the easiest way
to parameterize stuff like this like you
know it's easiest to think about things
normalized to arrange then I will say
okay that's the end of it
so the movement mode switches back well
it's this code right here the movement
mode switches back to planted after
that's done so now this code no longer
exists and I'm not going to move the
player Vyra this at all instead what I'm
going to do is move them specifically to
the point that I suggested so this is
the closest P and so what I'm going to
do is make a movement target and I'm
going to tell the code during that
transition hey this is the movement
target this is where you're going ok and
so now the simplest thing I couldn't do
and this is very very easy so I'm just
going to start with it is since I know
the movement target I should be able to
make it so I can
I should be able to make it so that I
can go directly to that movement target
over time using the T movement variable
without using any interceding movement
code so we're just gonna make a
programmatic parabolic arc that we can
use here now I'm gonna start by making
this well in effect I may actually keep
it this way I'm gonna I'm gonna change
it up I'm gonna say that we keep the
from as well because that actually is is
going to be the easiest way to do this
there's there's a different way to do it
that we probably will maybe want to do
and probably talk about later but for
now we'll actually start here because
it'll be easier to show what's going on
so movement from is always going to be
the place that I started movement to is
that point that I'm trying to get to and
then I've got this team movement
variable so if I know the team move in
variable we can go back and lean on the
exact same thing I say we always can use
which is and you know I'll zero out the
velocity or two just because I don't
actually want any possibility of getting
velocity which is just leaning on that
linear blend right I've got a T value
that ranges from zero to one I know
where I'm coming from I know where I'm
going to and so I can just lurk between
those two and that will get me my motion
and that's a starting place for my
motion right so if I come in here and we
take a look at what that value is you
can see now that when I when I do it it
just linearly moves between those points
right and the answer to how fast it
moves is just whatever I added here so
in the T movement code if I wanted to
make this faster which I do you could
see how slow that was this would be kind
of maddening although perhaps
interesting for a mode in the game where
you accidentally swallow a bad potion
and you move really slowly you know if I
want it to move four times faster than
that then that's just an additional
speed multiplier that gets added on
there right and you can see that I'm
just moving between these and maybe
that's the speed I don't know what the
speed is I probably you know maybe a
little faster even than that so that's
the the T movement again really really
straightforward and you can kind of see
in fact that looks actually pretty good
already just even at linear so but
that's not a hop right that and that's
not a parabola that's just looping
between the two
and so what I want to do now is I want
to sort of add the arc in right eye I
want to add the the that sort of that
hop that that's in there and so the
question is well how do I you know how
do I make that hop happen how do i how
do i get that sort of that that sort of
combination there right and so what I'm
gonna do is I'm just gonna say well what
we need is we need the concept of you
know of this arc I have this point and I
have this point and that's enough to
tell me the line that I should move
between these but what I need to know
right is I need at least one other piece
of information which is how high right
so there's like a height in here that
would tell me how I was going to to hop
now I couldn't use a quadratic spline a
quadratic B spline for this and feed in
this midpoint by construction or
whatever right and that's a pretty
interesting thing but and there's a I
actually have a video up on
interpolation where I kind of explain
how splines work and how to derive them
and all that stuff we could go through
that I'm gonna show you a different way
right now because I think the spline
stuff will come up at other times as
well and so since we're in a situation
that's fairly straightforward here I'm
just gonna show you one other way you
could approach this problem when I'm
like you've got some things you know and
you want to you kind of want to have
some way of of making these things you
know cuz look breaking down a problem
like this so I'm just gonna kind of show
you how to approach it from another
angle of like breaking it apart and just
give you more tools in the way you think
about these things so the first thing
that I would point out about this is we
kind of know right a bunch of things
about it at T equals zero we know we're
at that from point right and at T equals
one we know we're at that destination
point right so we know that whatever the
function is that we're talking about
we know that the
function this magical thing that we want
if we plug in well zero to it right
I want the it to evaluate to whatever
the from was right so I want it to
evaluate to P from and if I'm at f1
right when thing is over I want it to be
p2 so I know these two things about my
equation and I just said that I know
it's a parabolic arc I want it to look
like a parabolic arc so I know that the
structure of the equation can only be
one thing and that's a T squared plus T
sorry plus BT plus C right so if I know
those things and we look at this I've
got an equation right and I've got I've
got two things to plug into it I and so
the question is can I solve it and the
answer is well if you look at the at the
the structure of it here there's
actually three unknowns in it right
there's a B and C and unfortunately from
looking at what I've got for the
information I only got to two things I
know and so I've got two equations and
three unknowns that's not enough to
solve this system you know what I mean I
don't I simply don't have the ability to
solve the system with only that however
we already know that there's a parameter
missing which is the height so obviously
I could write another equation for the
height however what I'm gonna do first
is just say well let's just take a look
at this and see what happens when I plug
these things in to this equation
separately right so if I was to say I'm
doing f of zero equals P from and so
what that would mean is well okay f of 0
into this equation means that 80 0 right
it's gonna be a zero squared
plus B 0 plus C and I say that that
equals P from okay
well if you look at what happens these
two terms cancel which means I
immediately know that P from is my C
term so really I'm not even talking
about that part of the equation anymore
I just know that C equals P from and
this is so magical because this is why
math is always so interesting is because
math just works Mateen when you actually
investigate it and you don't have like a
math teacher scribbling stuff on a
chalkboard annoying you when you
actually go and look at it it just works
what is that saying it's saying that
like the basis for my jump the thing
that doesn't change at all on the jump
is where I start from right it's like
it's it's routing the equation at my
jump off point right which is exactly
what you would think it is it's telling
you exactly what you would have
intuitively thought and that's just so
satisfying right it's very very nice
okay so then the question is well what
about F equals 1 what happens there
so at F equals 1 then I have hmm
a times 1 squared right times B times 1
plus my P from because I know that
that's what that is so now I've got this
equation right and obviously 1 squared
in 1 we know that you know F of 1 is is
a squared plus B plus B from we know how
to multiply by 1 right and we're saying
that that equals the two okay so if we
were to you know look at what we now
know essentially what we could say in
terms of what we're trying to solve here
if we start moving things to one side we
would get another thing that looks
incredibly intuitive right and it's this
if I subtract P from from both sides
look at that term right that's the Delta
that's that's where I'm trying to go
right that's where I'm trying to go to
and so exactly as we would expect it at
the point where we have finished the
jump the some of the other terms in our
equation had better equal the Delta that
we had to go because if they didn't we
wouldn't have gotten there so we also
know that a squared plus B squared is
going to equal our Delta right that's
what we know so you can kind of see that
even I just kind of wanted to show you
that before we even talk about what our
final weight you know prescription for
this is going to be I just kind of
wanted to show you how interesting it is
that when you start looking at the math
you can start to see that the math is
actually the terms in the math are
actually about what the what the diagram
is right it's not like it's some weird
set of symbols that don't mean anything
they're actually really very strongly
rooted in the situation that you've
created right okay
so what do we do with with the rest of
this situation right what do we actually
do with oh that's great I don't know why
the squared term is still there there we
go that's what I actually meant to do
it's not supposed to be there it's the
one that's squared and yeah can you tell
I'm not a good mathematician anyway so
we do know that a plus B has to equal
the Delta right and so what we need to
know at this point is we need to know
you know if we solved for a we would get
Delta Delta minus B if we solved for B
we would get Delta minus a so we know
that whatever part we put into the
squared term the other part has to
balance it out and vice versa right but
what we know is we have essentially two
completely independent vectors and as
long as their sum is the Delta we will
have a proper parabolic arc that will go
from where we want to go to
where we want it to end up and so what I
wanted to underscore by working this
through is that you if you are tuning a
game you don't really even have to solve
equations what you have to do sometimes
is just partially solve equations and
once you now know that you can just
freely make two vectors who have to sum
to the Delta well I can even just start
tuning whatever that ask to D right I
know it sounds a little strange and if
you don't if you aren't used to doing
this it might be kind of weird but let
me show you what I mean in actual
practice here is our equation right I'm
just gonna type it in over here
right here's hopping okay and previously
I was computing it via lerp right now
I'm going to do it I'm just gonna put in
the equation as we had it right and so
we've essentially got a plus B plus P
from that's what we're doing right well
you know more like it's a T squared plus
BT plus P from okay so the resulting
position here is going to be you know a
whatever that means we don't know yet
right here's our T and in fact I'll I'll
go ahead and pull that out into an
actual T value there's the T value a T
squared plus B times T plus that from
parameter okay you can see I've
literally just typed in the equation
it's just the equation and so the
question now is what's a and what's B
okay well we know we only have to put in
one of them right because I just showed
over here that we know that the other
one has to be whatever it takes to make
it equal Delta so if I want to I can say
let's just tune the squared parameter
for our game play tuning we'll just tune
the squared parameter and we'll leave
the other parameter dependent on it so
we know what the Delta is right the
Delta is the entity
- - entity movement from we know that
that - whatever we put in here is B
right that completes the equation so if
I wanted to like it start out with that
just being nothing right if I wanted to
there's nothing there and then
everything is in this this term over
here this B term right that could that
would just work right or at least it
should work oh but you know what has to
happen I have to actually did I just I
deleted the equation why did I do that
that's good I'm like hey let's run the
equation maybe it would help if I didn't
delete the equation first unbelievable
all right so there we go
now I actually have it so as you can see
or at least hopefully you can see that
if I was to make everything be in the
linear term so I set that T squared term
to zero what do we get we get back lerp
right because if you set the squared
part of the equation to zero so there is
no right a times T times T if the a is
zero and the T squared goes away there
is no parabolic part of the equation
anymore right it's gone parabolic part
is gone so if the parabolic part of the
equation is gone then everything goes
into the linear part and we're back to
lerp right and hey what does that look
like the T parameter goes from zero to
one the B parameter is just the
subtraction of the two in the front
that's literally gonna give us lerp back
so now all we're gonna do is we're just
gonna tune what part of the jump do we
want to be parabolic well hey guess what
I probably want the height to be
parabolic right I want it to I want it
to do that right um unfortunately I
don't even know what we're doing with
our Z we don't we don't use Z yet do we
yeah we still don't use Z that's we got
to fix that at some point here I'll
stick it in Y for now but
yeah so you can kind of see now I guess
that's right
it goes up the screen so now you can see
that what I've done is I've put you know
a certain amount of the hopping motion
I've placed that into right I've placed
that into the parabolic part and so now
I'm hopping as on a prayer on a parabola
I guess you better not leave we better
not leave the legal zone sorry about
that
we're not doing any collision detection
anymore I turned it off I think so we
can hopster I think we can stop straight
out of well no actually how do we hop
straight out how am I getting out there
I don't really know what we're doing
we've turned off so many things and
there's so many things weird now about
that I don't even know what's going on
there but so now I've just put the that
part in which means if you think about
what what actually happens the other
parts of the equation right the other
parts the the of what I'm doing those
are not parabolic so the motion between
the two points is still linear right and
it's just that that vertical part that
becomes parabolic so there you go
so yeah so there's a lot more to say
about this but I'm kind of out of time
if that makes sense but I guess what I
would say about this is there's just
remember for now until tomorrow that
concept that if you solve everything out
first
and then just instead of trying to get a
solution to an equation that you're that
you're going to know that you're going
to tune think of it as just reducing it
down to a smaller set of variables and
then just tuning the variables you can
actually start with stuff that you don't
even have a solution to and then just
play with the values that you get the
thing that you want right which is what
we did here so now I will go on to the Q
and the a
oh my god Zen bought banned the hmd BOTS
are you kidding me that's hilarious
the hopping looks so cool can we see a
little bit more of it well I don't think
the hopping looks really very cool yet I
mean the heads not even attached to the
body so it ain't great yeah I don't know
why we're able to to select that at the
moment either I do not know I I feel
like our selection we probably have to
just go look at selection code it's
probably all messed up right but
how did you slip the head from the body
well we just they're just two separate
entities at the moment so right now we
just have one entity that's the head and
wanted to be that's the body and it
jumps around how interesting do you
think it would be to solve for the force
and direction required to reach a
certain height on each jump is it just
more work than it's worth for no
tangible gain yeah I think so I guess
what I would say is it's not so much
it's not so much that there's no
tangible gain in general there is a
tangible tangible gain in general and
that would be that if we wanted to
integrate it into a physic system where
we were doing a lot of physics sim then
we would need to do that because we need
to figure out what the forces so that
all that whole system works you can't
just go moving things around willy-nilly
in a physics system because you need
them to like collide and be able to like
push back and all that stuff right so in
a game where I was anticipating doing
that sort of stuff we might want to do
that that work right but in this game
it's much more logic based it's not so
much physics based so what we'd rather
do in here is solve those sorts of
things logically if that makes sense and
that's why I'm not trying to feed it
through the force part of things I am
guessing that both the familiar and the
enemies will need to move similar to the
hero is there much more you need to do
to make this work with them yes we will
have to we'll have to make some path
finding that knows that it can only go
through the squares and that sort of
stuff so there's going to be there's
gonna be some things like this that
happen can we clean up the extra head
and body on the screen or they're going
to be used later on
yeah actually those are still actual
things
in theory like you know that one will
follow you around I don't know what this
one is I think it has something to do
like it was something that you could I
don't know if it was like a target or
something I'm not sure that one will
probably go away eventually but yeah so
will these weird little plates that I
have that I can shoot out for no
apparent reason
why doesn't the head just stay on top of
the body is that a bug
no that's they're different to different
entities and so they move independently
now and the body just follows and I want
them to actually I I don't necessarily
need them to be separate entities so we
could merge them into one entity we I
think that will depend on how are in
these systems aches out as we sort of
actually build one because right now we
don't really have one as we build out
the entity system we'll make a decision
about whether they should be one entity
a combined entity or whether they should
be separate in these I suspect they
should be separate entities but right
now they're separate entities and I want
them to remain sort of separate like
that and all I'm really gonna do is I'm
gonna make the body like track to where
the head is so that it stretches between
them but but they're gonna stay kind of
independently controlled like that
borrowed mode when writing in a
procedural I'm a swing language I
sometimes end up with deeply nested code
should this be avoided and are there
good ways to minimize this I mean the
only real problem with nested code is
that the is that editors don't handle it
right you know they don't do a good job
letting you work with it as easily so
that's kind of a little annoying but
otherwise it's fine however if you do
find that it's problematic for you yeah
I mean if you want to miss I just take a
chunk and move it out to a function you
know it's not it's not a big deal right
in Janeiro this is starting to look a
lot like crypt of the necrodancer the
design isn't really anything like crypt
of the necrodancer although I haven't
played I I only like briefly played
crypt of the necrodancer so I don't know
that much about it but it's as far as I
know really not at all related
trap master missed a lot are you making
an engine for this game or is that stuff
just there for purely for you us right
now yeah we did we made all this engine
from scratch on the stream including the
renderer you can even render in software
which is pretty cool
I forget where that is it's in here
somewhere
yeah we it's we're not we're compiled in
debug mode right now and of course for
some reason we aren't clearing do we not
clear in software or do we not clear at
all does anyone know like what the deal
is with that hand made so I noticed that
before is that we don't clear instant
software I assume that in that that's
actually somewhat that's actually okay
because there shouldn't be any empty
space anyway but I do wonder whether we
thought we were clearing or not
so in render dot cpp i'm i'm actually
wondering clear so like this is the
clear ah but it doesn't necessarily sort
to the back is the thing so that might
be that might be a problem the clear
like I don't know oh but you know it
should so I don't know why I don't know
why that's why that's not working but
it's but it's not let's let's let's take
a quick look I'm just curious
Brenda Krantz a bitmap render commands
to bitmap so intersect base clip writes
with clip rect see what we got
can we please step into wait that's not
where am i there it's not what I'm gonna
be here there we go I don't want to
watch every thread just want to watch
one thread is that so wrong a visual
studio fine you don't want to show me
more thread I mean you want to show me
all your threads I will kill those
threads and then what are you gonna do
about it not much not much my friend
actually that'll probably still create
one extra thread wallet that's
unfortunate
maybe I should have set that to zero
yeah so what I really should have done
is this that work
there we go so now why don't we clear on
our screen here's the clear call we come
in here doing some stuff we get our fill
wrecked out 480 by 720 that's certainly
a screen what's our color value where's
the Alpha value what the what colors of
e4 right so why is it only have there it
is the Alpha value is zero well who put
in a clear color of zero so is this just
is this operator error did we put in the
wrong clear color cuz that's that ain't
no good that ain't no good at all I
would like to just point out to you how
not good that is is there a clear look
at that look at this so I guess that's
technically okay because if you're doing
it clear then the alpha value has you're
trying to set the destination alpha
value to be something so now that I
think about that's actually right so
probably the way that we need to do this
is this should really set for set that
color you know like this for now it's
and that's not perfect but that's that's
really the problem right
oops so now we should be okay yeah there
we go
so yeah and then of course you know if I
actually did want to see how fast let's
you know while we're here let's see how
fast it is let's just take a look
alright so here's the hardware render
that's running through OpenGL and here
is the software renderer so quite good
right and I think if I remember
correctly in our profile a lot of that
time is waiting for Windows to get off
its but yeah most of that time is we
would actually be hitting 60 frames a
second in the Safa render right now if
Windows wasn't sitting around doing
nothing
although you know part of that's
probably we probably need to just use a
P buffer to transfer the screen so we
could probably fix our OpenGL submission
the way that we're actually downloading
the software rendered bitmap to it we
can probably fix that so so that's I
mean it's kind of our fault
let's see
when CX is defined will up-down hopping
look different I don't know how I mean
it shouldn't probably look all that
different but we we do need we need to
straighten out our Z it's it's always
been a little wrong and now we kind of
know what it should be
we're gonna have to go in and fuss with
that a little Lu minion what our
limitations of game develop using C
sharp I mean there's tons of them right
it's a garbage collected language it's
runs through an interpreter I mean it's
like you know so you have to you don't
really know what the it's got to be just
in time compiled if it's gonna be
optimized like it's it's a pretty
high-level language so there's
limitations everywhere the limitation is
you can never actually control what the
CPU is actually doing there's a huge
stack of stuff in between you and it and
so do I like it as overall language no I
hate languages that that put a lot of
stuff between me and the computer that's
been booed what parts of CMOS are you're
using if you are not programming an OOP
style we we use function overloading
operator overloading and sometimes
constructor destructor pairs for like
block scoping I think that's mostly it
Clemens Val I'm currently using a
Microsoft natural working him up you're
gonna like 4000 thinking about replacing
it with an honor gonna check keyboard
any thoughts I always have trouble with
those those Berger no metric keyboards
the Microsoft natural one especially the
spacebar drives me insane it's so hard
to push so I prefer the non-organic
mechanical ones which is not to say that
I wouldn't prefer it ergonomic whenif
was actually made by a sane human but I
swear the people who designed natural or
gonna occur keyboards don't type much at
least not from my experience let's see
in Janeiro how many aids will this game
have when it's done do you mean like
triple-a I don't know huber Caleb the
trees in the bottom row look like they
are being clipped at the top also
c-sharp has compiled these days to some
extent well I mean it's always jetted or
can be jetted depending on the
circumstance but it is not compiled in
that in well it is not technically ever
if you compiled to bytecode is still
compiled it does not produce machine
code right that is it does not produce
machine code you can control and the
reason I say that is because you know
there's a garbage collector you didn't
write it you have no idea when it's even
running or how it's being built into
your game you have no idea how the how
most of that stuff actually is it's got
an entire like sort of layer there how
the dynamic code stuff is is done you
have no idea you didn't write any of
that so it's it's whatever they did you
know and not only is it whatever they
did it can also be whatever that
particular implementation of c-sharp is
because it's not you know like it's
always gonna be the same even is that a
real clicking keyboard as it just sound
effects yet this is an old dos keyboard
as for the trees being clipped off the
top
I thought we looked at that and I can't
remember I think it's just because we we
we require one aprons worth of pixels
remember we these are assets aren't
built with the way that we ended up
design do the render they were just some
stand and stuff that we used so I
believe that that's part of it although
to be honest it may be also just part of
the art asset and in here
and interval I have not seen Swift
a cruel dragon how come I have to
declare a political party in order to
vote in the presidential primary so the
reason that you have to I happen to know
that Colonel dragon is in Washington
State
so I can answer that question otherwise
I wouldn't necessarily be able to have
to ask where he lived the reason that
you have to clear a political party to
vote in a presidential primary is
because I believe the Washington State
Supreme Court I believe it was the
Washington State Supreme Court I don't
know if it was federal court hold on one
second let me answer this question yes
you can see so the reason it looks like
they're clipped is because it actually
does end like that and this part right
here is actually in the one pixel apron
which we don't render so remember all
art assets in the actual final game have
to be packed with that one pixel apron
and these are assets aren't packed so if
we actually added the one pixel apron
we'd be fine so hopefully that answers
question so originally in Washington
State you did not have to clear a
political party to vote in the primary
you could simply vote in whatever
primary you wanted to unfortunately that
was ruled against by the court I don't
remember the name of the case and sorry
it's been a while and so after that
court ruling they needed to they were
required to revise their primary system
in Washington state and now you have to
declare a political party in order to
participate in that primary but you know
the Y in the grander sense then it was a
court case I you know I mean I don't
know the cosmic why but that's the
procedural why if that makes sense
and and if you want to look at the
specifics of that court case you could
find out for example what what the exact
ruling was in terms of why the old
system was not allowed to continue and
get a little bit more insight into it I
I usually only pay attention to federal
Supreme Court cases state Supreme
Court's cases if this even was one of
those I don't even know if this case
went to the Supreme Court it probably
did I I suspect it was a state Supreme
Court case because primaries are would
generally not be federal it would not be
a federal thing so I'm assuming that
that that case opinion would give you
the information you wanted and I don't
read those opinions so I don't know oh
and yeah this this this thing right here
is blinking I agree with that
I assume that's because this and this
are like coincident and so they sort
randomly in but I'm not sure
all right I'm gonna wind down I'm gonna
wind it on down and yeah
save that off thank you everyone for
joining me for today's episode of
handmade hair it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home with the
source code you can always go to
handmade hair org and pre-order it the
game rather and it comes with the source
code so that as we develop the game you
can play around that at home and
practice the sort of stuff that we cover
on the stream we also have a forum site
which has now been upgraded thanks to
the folks at handmade Network so if you
go to that site and this link they
switch the link around on me so I'm
going to go change it now so it'll point
to the right place as I talked about
earlier in the stream you can now go
there and the forums are a lot more
pleasant to use we also have a patreon
page if you want to support the video
series a schedule bot who tweets the
schedule at you if you wanted to catch
the series live and we have a episode
guide which is maintained by our very
own mid blow on the chat go there you
can also and catch up on past episodes
it's got great annotations and while
you're there consider subscribing to his
patreon because he annotates those those
episodes for the benefit of everyone
just out of the goodness of his heart
and so that is it for today tomorrow
we'll be working on making that hop look
a little bit more nicely animated and
adding some more goodness to it and sort
of attaching that head on there so we're
just kind of building it up in parts the
quality of that and as the quality
improves the feel will get nicer and
nicer so that's it I hope to see you
back here tomorrow 5 p.m. Pacific
Daylight Time until then have fun
programming and I'll see you guys on the
Internet
I'm gonna go to the chat and figure out
why the Samba which I was supposed to
use for twitch has kicked all of our
better BOTS off so I'm gonna go make it
so it doesn't do that anymore those of
you who happen to know how that's
working please stay on the chat for a
minute and I will come ask you okay take
it easy everyone