hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete game
live on stream I have some I have a
surprise in store for myself today
actually I was pretty excited
last time we were programming Oh looks
like we didn't sub-sahara drive I must
have rebooted I'm pretty excited because
we actually got the lighting looking
kind of cool and it's not even done yet
so basically like the the kind of look
started to seem pretty cool like I kind
of liked what this was looking like like
all the little riff like the wall
reflections look really cool and it's
surprisingly real feeling like it's got
all kinds of nice stuff happening there
so I was pretty excited about this but
this isn't even really the lighting yet
because this is not using the diffuse
map at all during secondary bounces so
it's only using a specular version
whereas what it should be using it
should be using the diffuse version we
just don't have that stuff set up yet so
we don't have a way to feed that in and
so we don't end up getting the any use
of the diffuse in here so the lighting
is actually not at all it's not even
remotely as good as it should be because
it should be using a diffuse map for
bounce computations during the like
convection pass and it's not so that's
what we want to do today and hopefully
if I can get that working in you know in
the next hour or two then today we will
get to see what the lighting actually
looks like for the first time using this
scheme which I'm kind of excited just to
see cuz I don't know what it's gonna
look like right we're just we're trying
to put in a good lighting solution but
like anything else if you're trying from
scratch and you don't really have
anything to go on you don't really know
how good the lighting is going to be or
isn't going to be right and so that's
what we're looking at today trying to
get that working and again like you can
see when I'm up here for example you can
see that I don't get a much light
transmission down in there and so on and
when I'm standing you know it's a pretty
narrow light field like you'll see how
little light there actually is
and again that's because this bounced
lighting is specular bounced lighting
right it's just not it's not correct so
we want to use this map which is the
diffuse map we want to use that for our
bounce lighting and that'll push a lot
more light for the scene it's how light
would actually be behaving pretty much
all the time anyway because most
surfaces are not mirrors right
whereas what we're doing right now
basically simulates it as if they were
all mirrors more or less right and so
what we're seeing is more like a mirror
version of the world where as what we
want to see is what if everything was
more of a chalky like you know diffuse
soft lighting surface and so we kind of
want to make sure we get that right we
want to get that feel so that's what we
need to do now let's go ahead and and
take a look I'm going to go ahead in
here to the lighting code and the the
main problem that we're gonna have is
just that we don't actually have a the
same format for you know one of them's
in the the format of the GPU is gonna
pick up which is just a big texture
atlas the other one is a voxel the one
that we were like an actual voxel so you
can see here if I go into the code these
light voxel cells are what we've been
using to do the the light lookups in
here and I think what we probably want
to do is because we know that we're
basically GPU lighting and we're doing
some of it on the CPU and we may want to
keep doing some of it on the CPU or we
may want to move it to the GPU I don't
know which one we want to do that's kind
of an open question but either way
regardless of that the main thing that
we are going to hit here is the fact
that we know we at least want to be GPU
through lined because we know it
computes the lighting at the end and we
know we need to put the diffuse map into
the format it's going to use so I think
what we more or less want to do here is
keep ourselves more or less on the GPU
path the entire time and if we happen to
keep doing things on the CPU that's fine
but we probably want to keep our data
formatted in the GPU style as well as we
go through it and so I think I want us
to start by taking the light voxel cells
and
stop I want to stop using those right so
rather than treating things as light
voxel cells pretty much ever I would
like to treat these as I would like to
treat the light voxel cells as an actual
texture Atlas so that we're just a
texture Atlas the entire time that's
what I would like and yeah so that's
that's the plan okay
so what I'm gonna do is just make the
smallest change I can to produce that
result and if we look at what's going on
here so you can see we've got in inside
this we've got the light voxel cells
system here and you can see that like
how we've got that is it's basically a
light large voxel dim cube worth of
these little you know texture pieces
right and what I want to do is convert
that to an atlas so in place of this I
sort of want like a light texture atlas
thing and at this point since we know
this is moving through the system quite
a bit and in fact you can even see it
like if you look inside like if you look
inside the where the commands the game
render commands are where we're pushing
this town you can see like we've got
this stuff here and we got the light Fox
will dim the light Fox will see in the
light box Lodi and all this this garbage
in there right um we sort of have this
concept now of a light voxel atlas and
we may want to just have that be a like
we may want that to just be part of the
system like we might want to know what a
light voxel atlas is right and we might
want to just have that be something that
people understand so I'm thinking that
we want something like this you know
what I mean where we can just pass
around one of these light atlases and
instead of having all of these constants
and stuff we can just make something
where we know for any given thing if you
just hand someone a pointer to a light
lists they can get the information out
of the light Atlas that they need to do
their work properly right and so rather
than just having it be scatter shot
which is the reason I did it scatter
shot for now so they didn't know what we
needed now that I kind of see what we
needed I think that might be what we
want now the other thing to keep in mind
is as far as I can tell and it's it
again it's a little bit tricky so I
don't really know but as far as I can
tell like when looking at this system I
think that because we're big blocky
cubes I don't think we're actually gonna
need the depth system probably at all
like looking at it I think like depth is
just not necessary it seems like we can
probably get away with just using the
lighting as is and not actually doing
anything else right the reason you would
use a depth buffer and we had it in
there as like something to maintain and
that we should you know keep track of
going forward the reason for that is
just because look we when we're actually
doing lighting per pixel maybe we want
to check to see whether or not you can
actually from this location wherever
we're doing our lighting from we may
want to see like could we have reached
this light source from here or not or
things like that
right so I believe that that was the
main the main reason for using the the
depth information in here and I don't
know that we're ever gonna actually want
to use that so you know maybe we keep it
in there but I'm just thinking we
probably won't so I think I'll leave it
you know because we're gonna generalize
the light Atlas out a little bit you
know maybe I leave it in there but on
the whole I'm not really sure I actually
want it so I'm pretty I'm pretty unclear
about this right it may be that we just
don't ever want this thing in there at
all and it's I write like I don't know
now there is something that's kind of
unfortunate
which is just that there's not a lot of
ways that I know of that for light
atlases to keep them likes whistled
which is probably what I would want to
do here and just to explain what I mean
by that
so when we're loading in and
distributing light atlases and stuff
like that I would like to be able to
work with the light atlases a little
more cleanly and eventually if we
convert the light as Lass's to like
8-bit or 16-bit rather than 30 bit two
bits per channel which we almost
certainly want to do at the very least I
would think 16 bits per channel for the
lighting would be more than enough it
would be nice to basically be able to
pack these things in a little more
densely right and you'd probably want to
pack them in a pattern that would make
more sense than just rows I don't know I
mean maybe not and one of the problems
is like OpenGL like texture submission
without extensions is pretty bad like
you're always sending down things and
like unsold they're just in a row which
is like the least likely way you are to
access things in 3d graphics right you
know back in the day when you were just
talking about displaying an image direct
through the screen and you were scanning
out the screen in rows and stuff like
that then storing images in rows maybe
make some sense nowadays storages and
rows makes almost no sense whatsoever
you typically want to store them at
least in blocks that have a like
dimension so like 8x8 blocks or
something like this or 4x4 blocks but of
course that's not really possible when
you're just talking about straight
OpenGL submission straight up with GL
submission doesn't support any kind of
Swizzle you have to have it in rows and
so that's kind of annoying there are
like extensions and stuff like this but
it's a problem everywhere like basically
unless you're on a console it's actually
pretty hard to have any idea what the
heck the Swizzle patterns gonna be for
optimal submission to a graphics card
and this is just because they use
different memory it's it's a long story
on NVIDIA it's easy because Nvidia
actually I think supports arbitrary
memory bus whistles so I think on Nvidia
you can pretty much just submit any
Swizzle format that's saying and they
can handle it on ambi I want to say they
don't do that so
because AMD cards are less expensive I
think they they use cheaper MIT they
just use whatever one like memory bus
wiring pattern this is my understanding
and so like on AMD you kind of need to
know like you need to query if you were
going to like support a Swizzle pattern
of the card you have to say like hey
what's wuzzle pattern do you actually
use and that could be pretty tough right
because then you'd have to have like
sort of a JIT compiler that like you
know compiles the graphics at that time
to make sure you use the right so it's
it's tough right so on consoles this is
really easy because in consoles you know
the exact pattern that that Hardware was
designed for and you can just go ahead
and like do all your programming to
exactly that format and then
everything's great
you can even store all your textures in
that format and load them and not have
to go through a Swizzle so you can see
why like this is a huge issue right
anyway long story short I think we're
gonna have to stick with ROS for now
because I don't want to get into that
whole territory because it's a really
big can of worms but I just thought I'd
bring it up because it's worth
understanding like what's going on there
right so let's go ahead and start with
the light atlas and I'm just gonna say
here that all right let's before we try
to do any performance analysis I'm just
gonna say let's make this say that we
actually have like the at like the the
voxel Jim goes in here and then the like
the actual like core dim like so the the
dimensions of the and it looks like we
only have an ass for the 3s at the
moment so I'll use that and then the
like the actual little light templates
the little light squares those are also
need to have dimensions now we don't I
think really try to think if we ever
want to make those things be different
size I don't know if we do or not I will
I guess for now so if we if we want to
make sure that those beautiful sizes I
need two dimensions for those squares
I'm not sure what to call those but I
guess I'll call those like tile dim
because it's like they're little tiles
inside the Atlas right so we know we
have this layout of the voxel and this
layout of the tiles and then we know we
just have like a pointer right to the
actual texels so I just want this to
flow around so that when you get one of
these
you know that you can pull the
information that you need out of it like
here and off you would go at the moment
these are going to be F 32 s but I want
to convert these to something else
eventually as well so I'm gonna use a u
8 pointer here and the reason for that
is just to make sure that the dimensions
actually kind of flow through here now
I'm not going to support arbitrary
formats we're gonna fix the particular
format at the moment it could be F 32
but it might be something else later and
so this right here yeah might change now
you know what I could do too
I could do something like this so maybe
we define a switch here like so maybe
while I'm doing this we just prepare for
the ability because I would like to be
able to swap these right so we're just
going to put this in here and we're
gonna say that game light Atlas is just
a thing now that you can have in the
game and I'm gonna convert the two
things that get passed through to a game
light Atlas and then we're gonna go
ahead and try and fix up the code to
make that work in you know a little bit
in waves right so and and this right
here would change to being like okay
this is the light voxel diffuse and then
I could also have the light box or
specular come down here if we want to
because we can also provide the specular
for what that's worth not 100% sure how
we would want to do that but I think I
kind of know I mean I think it's just we
just passed down the map before we do
the blur before we do the filter on it
and that should give you sort of an
approximate glassy specular and so we
may want to put that to add that to the
system and filter that
during lighting to give a specular
highlight to things that are supposed to
be shiny and at the moment we don't have
a specular map like we don't have a
thing that tells us how shiny anything's
supposed to be but we could add that
pretty easily and that way if someone's
making a piece of art and they want up
you know a little bit of it to appear
shinier like there's a bit of metal on
it or something like that then we could
maybe use that feature so we may want to
enable that I'm not sure anyway so what
I'd like to do first is just do that
conversion so I'm gonna say like well
we'll have the game up Atlas in here I
don't know if we really want this
lightbox wildy in there so I'm just
gonna say like maybe that's not there
anymore and so we'll just kind of have
the lightbox we'll see so we'll have a
lightbox we'll see here and that's going
to be that that light Atlas I'm gonna
get rid of this and I'm just gonna sort
of handle all of the errors that I end
up with right and there's gonna be a lot
of them so here we do the light voxel
dim none of this stuff happens anymore
so I think we're just gonna call this
like diffuse light Atlas like that and
in the OpenGL system we're gonna
initialize that thing so in here where
we previously had sort of a bunch of
random crap hanging around I'm gonna
change that to being specifically the
the buffer for this light voxel right so
this is going to be a light box we'll
see here and hope sorry light game Y
Alice this is gonna be the light voxel C
and well actually you know what
this now that I think about it I should
probably just rename these like these
should just be named diffuse light Atlas
everywhere and where's the where's the
game render commands I was just on
there we go I think that's maybe a
little bit more sane all right
so in here where we're working with
these now you can kind of see like well
this is just getting pulled out of the
lead vas man that's actually fine
and the main problem that we're gonna
have here is like the light color lookup
squared dim and stuff like that those
things are all kind of hard-coded in
here and we kind of want to start to get
those out of the the atlas as well so
I'm gonna do this in two phases the
first phase is I'm going to get it
working with using the different structs
and the second phase is I'm going to
remove these values everywhere like I
was gonna get rid of the pound of fines
and have them all get pulled out of that
actual struct itself as a separate thing
so in here where we have to look at the
light voxel and we're pulling these
elements out of here like we're gonna
just do the basic thing first which is
to say alright this is actually the
diffuse light Atlas and the diffuse
light Atlas in this case needs to look
out on the texels right and we don't
actually have this as an f32 so I kind
of want to do that first which is like
diffuse texels and I'm just gonna do
this for now and we're gonna grab that
out of here like so and just say diffuse
texels and then what I want to do is I
want to get rid of the D the depth value
and the reason that I want to get rid of
the depth value at the moment is because
again I really don't think we're going
to need it and hopefully once I have the
once I do the light app game light Atlas
struct it would be free or close to free
for me to add it back in here because
all I have to do is just you know access
it in the same way that is access the
other thing and we should be okay right
so on the whole I don't really know that
I want this to actually be here and
doing anything again like I don't know
that that's necessarily true but you
know my my assumption is we really just
don't want
so we want to just not have it because
it's getting a little too real it's
trying to do a little bit too much 3d
realistic lighting for us and it's just
gonna slow us down without I think
really improving the quality of the
visuals of the game in a way I care
about so I'm just gonna say like having
looked at what the lighting looks like I
just don't think we're gonna need that
so we can really we can add it back in
if it turns out we really really need it
but for now we're just gonna say no okay
so same thing through here like we're
just gonna have when we're actually
getting these light voxels out of here
you can see us doing a bunch of stuff
for you know filling in filling in the
like the parts of the voxel that are not
so weird I'm looking for the the parts
of the voxel that are meant to handle
wrapping cases and so in this case again
we can just really do the diffuse
textile grab here and use it that right
so this is not the full thing we want to
change for these but it's close enough
at the moment that's really all we're
talking about here so again very very
simple oh so I guess interestingly
enough so for that we don't actually
have a way to get these as v3 so it
looks like this was voxel offset C and D
we're actually assuming that these were
VIII's right so it looks like this is
actually a v3 for now I think we
probably want to change that and but
again I want to do it in small passes
because there's enough complexity here
that I don't really want to do anything
that could be that that I want to do it
in small ways so I can see what breaks
cuz it's gonna be hard to debug either
way and I don't really want to be in a
position where I have to debug
everything at once so I'm trying to keep
the number of changes to the smallest
possible amount on each path
through the code so that I can you know
basically verify that what I'm doing
didn't break anything major each time so
that's the goal all right so let's see
here it looks like this is accessing the
same thing each time so I'm thinking
that probably the diffuse texels should
just be something that I pull out at the
start so it's probably just that and
then everybody uses it so all throughout
this whole thing like all of these
commands light voxel C's are all gonna
be diffused texels like so that seems
sane and then the main thing that's
getting used out here it looks like the
only other real thing is just getting
the dimensions of the voxel DIMM
and the interesting thing about that is
you know we looks like we don't really
support the we don't support arbitrary
dimensions there so this isn't really
sufficient and you can see here like all
of this stuff really probably should
have been done in vector right this
should have been done to v3 yes to allow
us to change the dimensions of our voxel
if we'd wanted to now it may be that
that's unwise because you just waste a
lot of stack space or memory space
sorting these dimensions and working
with them or registers you know but I'm
doubtful of that to be completely honest
so I think it's probably more important
to be able to control the dimensions of
the voxel so that you can fit it better
to your scenes especially for example we
feel like we want a certain X Y
dimension that's fairly dense and then a
Z dimension that's sparser which is a
very possible thing we might want to do
especially on lower end systems where
maybe
we decide not to draw like let's suppose
we're trying to figure out how to ship
this game on a much weaker CPU and a
much weaker GPU or something we may want
to do something where we just draw one
level instead of like right now you can
see down like multiple floors sometimes
like we can set our view we haven't
really played much with that but we
could draw like several you could look
down like a hole and see multiple floors
below you for example and if we were
looking at something like that you could
say well we could also just use fogging
there on like lower end machines you
can't really look down and so in those
cases you'd want to be able to set like
the Z dimension of your voxel - like
very low like for even when the other
two were like 32 by 32 or something and
so I feel like that's something we
probably wanted to support at least you
know so this is not great but you know
oh well so what I would probably say is
like okay the hot cell count here is
gonna be a v3 yes probably so let's just
do that for now so we get that out of
the defeat lice at Lite Atlas the large
cell count for now since that's still a
constant we can just duplicate out the
constant to all three channels and then
we can say all right when we compute the
offset well let's just do it as a v3 yes
and then when we look at the hot corner
we don't actually have to convert it to
v3 s because it already is and then we
have the correct value similarly the hot
dim can now become a Hadamard product
and it can become a Hadamard product
with the correct actual count like so
and that's what we want here so that's
good and that just requires moving the
v3 s up into a regular float v3 for
doing the multiplication but again not
so bad right so we were sort of already
prepared for this but we just didn't
actually do oops
got to actually get the vox let him out
of there we just actually weren't doing
quite the right thing so I think we
didn't ever define operator for like
specifically for the V 3 s's
I don't think we defined an operator for
that for the you know dividing we
probably just had a multiply and so I
don't really know where we put our V 3
s's in here there's a lot of functions
in here
one of the things I never implemented in
my for coder custom layer was jumping to
operators by what types they were using
it would be a nice thing just for this
one case like for math it'd be nice to
be able to say like show me the
operators 4 v 3s or whatever right it's
be a nice feature but I just never got
around to it and you rarely actually
need it so it never made it up the
priority list but it you know in a
fairly complete system you would like
want that so you don't have to do what
I'm doing here
so here are the v 3s operators you can
see like we've got minus and plus but
there's actually no x and divide which
you know I think we do want just for you
know just for doing like basic you know
you thirty twos or s thirty twos you
know what I'm saying
so we basically do like all right give
me the divide give me the multiply and
in this case they're just going to be
like that right just going to be a
multiply or divide
so in this case we just you know
implement the the basic operations for
int and because those are pretty safe
and we know we might want to do them for
situations like you know like this all
right
so taking a look here you can see we're
trying to produce the dimension of this
thing and we're taking the solution box
filled in and multiplying by the large
cell count and you can see that this
doesn't really make any sense because
now this is a this is actually a vector
so it's a vector times vector which
means this is actually a Hadamard
product as well which is again fine like
that's not an issue because we can just
multiply through dimensions by
dimensions and everyone's happy so
that's the conversion and the only
problem that we have right now is if we
actually ran this we would crash pretty
hard and hopefully you can predict where
so we don't actually this is the reason
this crashing here's this is the first
place that we write to the light buffer
the reason for that is in our OpenGL
layer you notice like what I did is I
replaced an actual flat array like this
with just this diffuse light Atlas right
this is not getting used anymore and so
as a result it doesn't actually point
anything it's just has like a null
pointer in there that points to nothing
which is not particularly useful so at
the very least it needs to point to this
and we can go ahead and make that happen
so if I go in here to the diffuse
slightly atlas and where that
information is actually being set up so
you can see in here right this is in the
OpenGL begin frame so we're doing that
straight copy this needs to actually
have valid data in it so if I were to go
to you know like OpenGL in it which
actually know where it is here it is
when we do open julen it like what I
would want to do is make sure that our
our light textures actually set up so in
here where we have the diffuse light
Atlas I would want to make sure I would
want to make sure that we actually
initialize all the values of it
so like
the voxel game has to be initialized to
a v3 yes the tyldum has to be
initialized and then the texels have to
be initialized as well and in this case
we'll just initialize the texels to this
for now like to the hard-coded array
that we put in there in the future we
can get a little more fancy with that if
we want to and then we can just say look
we've got the square doom here and we've
got the voxel DIMM here like so and off
we go so here we go so we can define
that light Atlas now which is always a
fun thing for everyone to do and we now
just want to make sure that the texels
point to something that's big enough to
hold them and i believe they're f 32s
right now as the pointer and off we go
so that's a start so we've kind of
barely sort of maybe a little bit worked
towards that and again now I just want
to run things and make sure that nothing
obvious changed because I wanted this to
run basically the exact same way that it
was I don't want to see any differences
here and and I don't really that looks
like about the same to me as it was
looking before more or less like no big
change right okay so now what I might
want to do is the line Atlas is itself
like I may want that to be its own file
like that just has a bunch of stuff in
it for working with light atlases I'm
not 100% certain I want to do that it's
hard it's a hard decision at the moment
but it may be something I want to do so
I may want to start moving that stuff
over so I think I'm going to create a
file for this and I'm gonna use that
file throughout so you know something
like this so in hand-made code handmade
light atlas mm-hmm and I'll make an H
file here and I'm just gonna put the
light Atlas over there and maybe I won't
call it game light Atlas at that point
because it's sort of like more of a
mental type I don't know so I'm gonna
put that in here and I'm gonna say
alright there's a thing called the light
Atlas like so and I'm gonna go ahead and
say that everyone has to use that so if
we look at where like this stuff gets
included as well so if I do a search for
like light Atlas open online at math
page then when we look at where that's
actually happening you can see that a
bunch of different people kind of need
access to that and that's fine so what
we may do is just go ahead and say all
right we're gonna put that into the
various places that need it so you know
we'd basically say like okay well what's
in handmade shared also not much alright
so inside like the various places that
we might need this I'll go ahead and and
put them in there so handmade H oops
oops there we go
and then we also need the open jail
system so right here we'll need that and
again I'm not really doing this for any
reason other than my own personal
organization this is not like any kind
of a like you know it doesn't change
like what code is produced it's not
something that's like some kind of
magical it's not any kind of like a
magical thing that you know you must
divide your files this way or anything
like that people get very dogmatic about
the sort of thing and that's usually
wrong you just want to organize your
files so that you can keep things
together that you want to look at
together and that's really most of what
needs to happen right I think I put that
in the wrong place that's what I wanted
there so now I think everyone's got it
who needs it and now I can go over to
the light atlas side of things and I can
start putting things in here that help
and so when we're in the the renderer
initializing it which was this what I'd
like to do is maybe just make a thing
that we use for initializing
I don't actually know where we like how
we how we do our memory policy stuff in
here it's kind of a little bit wonky
like the render at the moment doesn't
really do a lot of allocation of that
format it's not really something that
happens very frequently in here so like
who who allocates the opengl is is a
little bit Squinkie right and I'm not
really sure so you know in terms of how
that gets done I believe it's in here
so you can kind of see like all right
when we get in here we do a win through
to an end OpenGL and you can see that
that code happens here and you can see
that it's got like a win32 render
alochol and the win32 render a lock call
is like a special purpose thing that we
use to allocate stuff not actually sure
oops
yeah you can kind of see you can kind of
see it in here where just as a virtual
lock directly so I don't really want to
push memory allocation through the
renderer in any particular way here and
you know so I want this to be something
that it can actually push down because
it also might want to get memory that's
specifically pinned for graphics card
access or stuff like that right so it's
pretty tricky to say so I think what I
want to do here is say something like
alright there's gonna be a call that's
like in it light Atlas and in it light
Atlas will just say like or you know
like this and then you would basically
just pass in the things that you
actually wanted to use to initialize it
right
and what I'd like to do here is make it
easy for people to use so actually I
think I might take a void there and what
I might say is like that maybe there's a
pound of fine called like light atlas
size or something like this or like
compute light atlas size and that would
take you know the parameters that were
necessary to figure out what the light
out the size actually was right so I
would like something that the problem is
right now you know I don't know I kind
of want to have that allocation work a
little bit differently like I would like
it to allocate the space in some more
sane way maybe even with a buffer with
backing buffers or something like that
so it's a little bit hard to say what
should happen there so I think what we
maybe want to do is something more like
this maybe like this
so people can kind of call these on the
light atlas and sort of set things in
waves I'm not sure how exactly like I
said I want to do it but I want it
somewhat clean because this is gonna
very probably over time and we may want
to put some additional stuff in here for
tracking and who knows what right so
we'll kind of see what happens there as
we go the only thing that I'm not sure
about is I would what I would ideally
like is you make the light Atlas this
way then you say like get light atlas
sighs I'd like that to to be you know
the way you figure out how much memory
this thing takes and then you allocate
that much right but the problem that I
see here is that at least to maintain
the current way we're doing it without a
dynamic allocation it would have to be
done at compile time and of course
because C and C++ are not very good
programming languages there's no way to
actually just call something at compile
time even if the types are known and the
values are known if this was ji you
would just do this but of course it's
not so there you so anyway not being
able to call it at compile time means we
have to actually do some thinking here
where we shouldn't have had to do any
thinking and that just means you know we
would have to pass the things
individually like we'd like to pass a
v3s but of course the preprocessor can't
use a v3s so that's not really on the
table and so I don't know maybe I want
to go to dynamic allocation here maybe I
don't I'm thinking about it and I'm not
sure which one I want if you look at how
this thing is actually allocated so if
we actually go to the win32 and made up
in jail let me look at the yeah so if i
wants you in win32 and end up in jail i
could just do it so maybe I'll just do
that so I am gonna do this I'm gonna get
rid of this and we'll just have the
light Atlas stuff happen in here all
right
so the way we do that is not
particularly complicated right I just
wanted to be able to make sure I could
do an actual Alec and the reason we do
it here is because like I said I might
want this to actually be in
memory that's pinned for the graphics
card to use so that the transfer can
happen more efficiently I don't know how
efficiently the transfer is happening
right now but I suspect that the CPU is
sitting around doing a bunch of copying
for no reason and we may want to try and
get rid of that in the future by using
multiple buffers pinning the buffers and
letting the Rassvet transfer one will be
right into a different one that's just
something you would often want to do for
efficient GPU transfers and we want to
be able to do that for multiple things
so much like we have the vertex indexed
array bitmap array all this stuff here
much like we might want to double buff
for a triple buffer those we might want
to double buff for a triple buffer the
light Atlas as well that's all so I'm
basically saying so I want it to look
like the same as that system and go
through the same place as that system so
hmm Jimmy so I'm gonna put that in here
and I'm gonna get it out of here so
we're not going to do it in the open
drill in it we're gonna pull it out and
put it in the actual platform side so
this goes away like so and we come back
here to where we're actually specifying
the light atlas
we're gonna make that happen in here now
if we wanted to we could actually
specify the light Atlas information at
startup now so that memory could
actually get pinned at startup and so
you could actually change the voxel size
you know with a runtime parameter right
and so that's something that's also just
kind of a nice side effect all right so
if we set these here now what I could do
is say all right I want to make a light
Atlas which is this diffuse Atlas here I
want to go ahead and use these
parameters for it so you know the that's
the the voxel Jim and that's the tile
dim that's just going to create the
light Atlas for me I'm then gonna say
that I want to set the light Atlas
texels
to be whatever the size of the thing is
like so so just give me the signs back
I'll pass that to win32 render a lock so
that will get me a buffer for my texels
and then it will set it right like that
so we're just gonna say look set the
texels to be whatever whatever you tell
me the size now should be that is what I
will allocate and now I have a diffuse
Atlas right alright so now you can see
that we didn't really have any compiler
so that was good but of course we have
link errors because we haven't actually
written any of these functions
thankfully these functions are pretty
simple right there's not a lot to it if
we look at what these should be and I'll
just go ahead and make these internal
they don't need to be exported to
anybody if I go through and just do the
basics here make like that let's get
light atlas size set light atlas texels
i just need to do the basic
implementation of these so here's the
results the voxel dim just gets copied
the tile dim just gets copied and that's
the end of it the get light atlas size
is again pretty straightforward it's
just the light atlas in float is the
thing that determines what's going on
here I'm gonna make another function
that I happen to want so in here I'm
gonna move this up just as a more
primary function and I'm gonna put
another one in here which is get light
Atlas and this can be au 32 because you
know it's not that big get light a get
light atlas textile size which is to say
how big a particular Texel is just one
texel inside the atlas and if we look at
that function to write things in terms
of that function for any particular
textile atlas then we know that we can
just put this if in here
like so so we can say alright whatever
the light Atlas is in float we can just
say that the result is going to be one
of two things depending on whether that
said or not so if it's in float then we
know that the size of sorry that the
size of one of the texels is going to be
the size of a float times three
components the red the green and the
blue and then otherwise if it's not we
know that the size of the Atlas is going
to be just the size of one you 3 2
because the RGB and a would be packed in
there and the a channel look we don't
really know what we would put in there
but I don't know that we want these to
be RGB packed we could but it starts to
get a little squirrely right it becomes
harder to deal with if you don't have
your things packed for wide so I'm not
sure we would necessarily want to do
that but we might just to save the space
so it's really hard to say like we could
also do this and I don't know so excuse
me so for the moment I don't know that's
just where we're at we'll see so I'm
going to go ahead and say that the you
know result of get light atlas science
is just going to be the get light Atlas
texas-sized like so I'm going to ask how
big each Texel is and I'm going to
multiply it by the Texel count
what's the Texel count
well the Texel count is just going to be
the Atlas voxel dim x times atlas voxel
dim y times atlas box will dim Z and
actually I could just call that the tile
count right and then I could say well
what's the
texels per tile could also call this
tiles per voxel the Texas per tile is
the Vox oops tile dim x times atlas tile
dim Y right and I don't actually know
you can see we could have written area
functions for these which we may have
wanted to write because then you just
say get area on each of these which
makes more sense I'm not sure I'm gonna
go that route but you know you can see
why that might have been a better math
library decision if we were if one were
so inclined so we know the tiles per
voxel we know the texels per tile and so
if we want to we can then say well
whatever the Texas size is we just
multiply out tiles provoke soul and the
texels per tile in fact let me do this
in the other things we go kind of in
order of smallest to largest
so tiles per voxel times texels per tile
times the actual size of each Texel
gives us the total amount of size we
need for the clock for the Atlas storage
and then we're done in terms of setting
the memory now that's just going to be a
simple casting function and I don't know
that we want to do it this way forever
so it's it's going to depend eventually
but it's gonna look something like this
if we want to keep that I don't know
that we do I think this may want to
always be u8 no matter what in fact I
just know that it is I just want to be a
memory pointer so it's it's gonna be
that forever at least for now alright so
now we've got all of that working but
the problem is inside anyone who
actually works with this like in the
renderer and stuff we need to actually
pound include that that actual code
right you can see in here we're not
actually including it so in here we need
anything that we work with like a light
Atlas needs to occur
in here right this did not return the
results other than that I think we're
good I could also just make this happen
in here and off we go so I think we're
good now we should be working if we
didn't put any bugs in there put into
bugs bugs in there well it will crash
like it just did so that's bad um I
wonder what we screwed up probably
wouldn't be an allocation problem what
did we do wrong oh I know if we did
wrong we're not pointing to it hold on
one second so in here I need to get rid
of these right and just need to kind of
run through this real quick and anywhere
that we were using the light color data
before we need to use the diffused light
Atlas texels pointer right and one nice
thing about this is you can see that
this calculation here was actually the
calculation that we needed from before
so we actually want to use the the
information in here now you can see that
this actually because open gel is kind
of squirrelly and does submission in a
weird way for these we need to tell it
what the actual situation is here so we
need one more function right look in
here in addition to get light out with
size we need like get light Atlas Texel
count right and so we want to actually
have this interim copy like we did this
calculation we just don't ever expose it
so what we want to do is just expose it
so this right here where we do the tiles
per voxel times the texels per tile is
the total number of texels so what I
want to do there is just use that
instead so now people can get this if
they want to so I can in here just now
say all right get me the textile count
for the
thing right and that'll be good and then
when you look here you can see well
we've got some other parameters that
aren't necessarily the best parameters
in the world that we would like to know
what those should be as well right and I
don't know what we want to do with that
at the moment I think I'm gonna ignore
those and just say well we'll have to
like think about that a little bit more
in the future but what I could do is in
here we could actually have some kind of
a you know like a I don't know what I
want to call it like a decryption so we
could in here say like alright the light
Atlas here can also have a thing that's
like is float you know I don't know what
we want to do but I'm just gonna stub
that in for now
right and then I can also say like oh
all right well in that case I can just
do something more like I did before and
say like okay if is float Atlas then do
this else do this oops right so you know
I can produce two different versions of
this thing depending on which one I want
and and off we would go I can also do
this a slightly different way which is
set that to the component count and do
this and off we go so now we could say
like alright the is float is just a
predication and it returns like true or
false
in fact I guess I don't even need to do
that I could just do like return light
Atlas and float
or better yet right so now it's pretty
clear and I can say like look is this
light Atlas afloat and if it is it's
that otherwise it's going to be an
unsigned byte or something like that
right and so now we can actually make
this code path probably handle the thing
correctly that we were trying to do and
so this starts to look pretty nice
because now it's like oh all right now
we don't have all these constants
through now and along you know just
clogging up the works right and that
seems pretty good and I can also do like
a you know a get light axis get light
atlas texels here and I'm not sure again
what I'm really gonna be doing I don't
really know how we're gonna handle those
buffers so I'm just blinding them for
the minute and we'll pay attention to
that at some point if we care about the
performance of this so I think that's
mostly what we want I'm not sure let me
see here there's our set and the reason
I have this is the get is we may want
this to come back as a particular type
of pointer eventually I'm not sure we do
but we're just gonna see what happens
what am I missing here
Oh was that actually supposed to mmm
so that actually needs to be a width and
a height right so actually I all I need
more I need even more ways to query this
thing that will compute the right
dimensions for us right so I need
another one which is like get light
atlas width and get light atlas height
something like that right and think
about that so I need a little little bit
more complicated right so in here I need
to do the way you compute the width of
this thing is mmm getting rid of the Z
right so the light Atlas width is going
to be the voxel dim x times the voxel
dim Y times the tile dim X right and the
height is going to be the voxel dim Z
times the tiled my if I'm not mistaken
that is the way we laid out the Texel
and so this is actually not what you
want we don't need the text account
although I mean I suppose since we have
it we might as well leave it but you
know not actually necessary we could
also then say like oh all right like if
you want to know what the act was tax
account is we can actually put that in
terms of that right so we can actually
say well the tax account is the just the
width times the height so now that
computation can just happen
again all in terms of the same stuff
right that all seems relatively
straightforward and so this just has to
change so this has to be like width and
height so I think that's what we want
don't quote me on that and so there we
go
and now we have like a little like light
Atlas struct we can use that has some
nice Swiss Army knife properties to it
and we can start to play around with
that so that now we can have a second
one right which is kind of what we
wanted to do there so I'm gonna go ahead
and say that both of these should be in
the actual OpenGL system just in case we
want to start sending both of them down
so I'm gonna say that we have a specular
light Atlas and a diffuse light Atlas
that we're going to work with right and
again I really don't I don't know what
we're planning to do I don't know what
we're gonna do with these long-term
right I'm just not sure so it's fine
what I will do here is say we're gonna
have it if I'm gonna go ahead and make
these both get transmitted so there's a
diffuse light Atlas handle and a
specular light Atlas handle I'm gonna go
ahead and make that change as well cuz
why not
and then I'm gonna go through in here
and say alright we've got the diffusely
atlas handle and the specular light
Atlas handle these were both going to be
the same and eventually we kind of have
to fix this because like I said we want
these to not always be in float so we're
probably going to want to change that
and at this point I suppose in here we
actually have this value so I think we
could actually make this just do what we
want it to do right so we could do
something where we said okay this is the
width and height so we could just say
like get light Atlas with get light
Atlas height and not have these two
things hard-coded I think and so these
atlases in this case is just going to be
the OpenGL diffuse light Atlas and we
get rid of these similarly we can say is
float and make that an unsigned byte and
I don't actually know what this format
would be up here but I'm assuming we can
basically do the same thing for the most
part and just say like well alright I
guess it's going to be GL RGB like 8
right I think I don't know if we have
one of those
looks like we do um so anyway yeah I
don't really know but that's just my
assess my first thought about what that
should be let's take a look at the
errors here so OpenGL is not typed right
there which doesn't help all right so I
think that's mostly what we want there
let me go ahead and I kind of want to go
back to that though so let me let me
take a look at that what was that again
get light that was with so yeah so we
really don't want we want this to be the
same and the only difference here is
that diffuse and specular are gonna get
swapped for now that could change we may
want them to be different in the future
I'm not sure but alright so off we go
and the light color atlas handle
obviously doesn't exist anymore so this
is just going to be the like diffuse
light atlas handle and specular light
atlas handle these are both the same as
they should be
this is the submission for it and we're
not submitting the specular right now
but we probably should so you know maybe
we'll just do this for now and we'll see
what happens and this is just drawing
two of them this is just the debug
drawing so now we have both of those the
specular light Atlas and the diffuse
light at lists are kind of both there it
looks like we've got a bug here I'm
going to look at what that message is
just so we can see oops invalid texture
format so we may be returning something
but oh yeah so we didn't initialize our
other Atlas so that makes sense in the
win32 OpenGL layer when we're actually
doing our render Alex here we would need
to produce something for our diffuse
light at lists and I'm going to go ahead
and say that we probably want it to be
basically the same so like we're just
gonna say like the light at Atlas voxel
dim and the light atlas tile dim are
gonna be the same here
so I'm going to say light Atlas Fox
lignum and light Atlas tyldum and then
I'm just going to do exactly the same
thing for both of these for now so now
we've initialized both of them and they
both should work hopefully all right so
now we have the two atlases here and
like I said at the moment we aren't
actually using the specular Atlas like
nobody's actually sampling it for
starters but no one's filling it in
either so even the debug pass just shows
black because no one's written anything
to that like no one's written anything
to it anyway so that's fine and then
what we can do is now we can sort of
pong back over to the lighting code
itself and we can start to use these
atlases more directly so that hopefully
we can start sample from the the actual
Atlas and not the voxel anymore so we'd
like to basically use the same like we
want to use the exact same stuff and
again the way that we would do this is
we basically say all right the specular
light Atlas is the thing that we're
actually updating because the thing we
can actually write into and the diffused
light Atlas is the thing we're sampling
from so the main change we want to make
the specular light Atlas that we write
into is the is the part that's currently
it's the part that's being currently
played by the by the actual um voxel and
that's the part that we want to fix so
I'm gonna take some smaller steps now
and say okay let's remove some of the
constants again being very trepidatious
here because I don't really want am I
being trepidatious
it spelled it wrong hey maybe maybe
that's wrong maybe we'll just say being
cautious
then trepidatious might be the wrong
word I want to minimize the amount of
debugging work that we have to do
because this is a very complicated
system and what we're basically doing is
we're sort of cleaning up code now that
we see how it's supposed to work and in
that process I don't want to introduce a
lot of errors if I can avoid it so
that's why I'm trying to go slowly and
do it step by step so in order to do
that I can start to remove things now
for example light data with does that
even get used anymore where is that
getting used
what are these used all right hold on a
second we're gonna take this one step at
a time like shouldnt max light box count
be the thing that's in there for the
light data width I don't know are these
used are they just used for building the
tree yeah
all right so I want to say light data
with should not be used for that and
it's actually that box count thing this
thing for now anyway this is at least a
better name
all right this stuff we don't need
anymore
this stuff is again sort of redundant
and the light probes are gone so we
actually can get rid of light probes
entirely now and should but I probably
shouldn't do that until we're absolutely
positive we don't need them there's like
an entire system that we made to track
light probes so we could try them out we
just don't need them anymore so like
this nonsense here we can just remove
and this was a ton of garbage so
assuming I can get this again this is
one of the reasons so like this you know
the remove indices nonsense like this
crap one of the really important things
that I've been trying to do throughout
this whole process the back of my head
was if we can avoid using light probe
locations as an actual first-class
citizen I totally wanted to do it and
the reason for that is that I don't want
to have to track them over time and so
we already I think have guaranteed that
that won't have to occur so at the very
least I can get rid of the indexes which
is really good like I really want this
light this tracking to go away we don't
want it so that's really good because it
saves us a bunch of time and other code
right so I'm hoping that's the case and
it seems overwhelming of the case the
other thing is can we get rid of the
light present entirely because they're
just taking up their clogging up our
entity stream for no reason they're just
extra processing we have to do every
frame for no reason and so that would
also be a win and I think we're gonna be
able get that too because right now
we're not using them we're just using
voxel centers and it seems to be working
ok so we'll see
all right moving on um let's see what
we've got here so what is max light
depth who uses this in Y all right so
that was only when we were tracking
depths we're not gonna do that right now
so we can get rid of that so these are
now the parameters that we're actually
starting to look at and these are set
inside the tile stuff so the light
lookup voxel dim and the look the the
squared dim that sort of stuff
yeah it looks like it looks like all of
this stuff is now kind of in the right
zone this is what we're looking at right
all right so some of this stuff we can
probably this stuff I think we need to
keep around in the sense that we do need
to make buffers that store like our
clutter stuff but I'm not sure how we
want to do that in the future we may
just push them on to the push buffer and
not care about it and link them up that
way I'm not sure still have to see about
that part it's not super important at
the moment when we actually look at some
of this stuff now we can start to move
this away the other thing I would
mention is like this light floor value I
feel like while I'm in here and looking
at this code I don't think we're
actually using that and we should be so
in the Z bias program we use a light
floor now and in fact you can see that
it's getting the light floor value is
actually in there right so I think in
the light floor value code we should be
using it
not so the place that that would be
getting used right is inside sample
lighting you can see in here we produce
the light result and here's the sum you
can see here we do a minus and we've got
the point two point two point two right
so I think what we want to do is
actually make that be something that
gets passed down and that way people can
reason about it everywhere and it's not
a magic constant that's sitting inside
the shader which is not great so again
hopefully that doesn't affect things at
all should look the same as it did
before but again just want check all
right so now let's start to peel these
away so if we look at these we don't
need the depth phone anymore we just
need the color one and I'm gonna go
ahead and now try to try to put that
into the OpenGL layer where this thing
is initialized so in here I'm just gonna
define this like literally we're just
gonna do this where I make it a u3 to
local and then use it right here right
so we're gonna try that and then
everywhere that's being it's being used
you can see all this usage of it right
we're gonna try to make those things now
work with the light atlas directly
rather than using the magic constant so
in here we have this depth lookup
squared dim and the light color lookup
squared M so these two values are not
really what we want anymore
we want something more like you know
diffuse light square and specular
something like that right so we want the
diffuse and specular tile sizes to be
placed in here and so those are gonna
come from you know the diffuse Atlas and
the specular Atlas and what we need to
do here is at the moment we have to
assume they're square because we don't
actually allow anything else right so at
the moment we're just gonna say alright
the tile dim X tile dim Y like so and if
I did that I'm a little bit worried
that's a bit landmine II so if we then
change two rectangles we'd be in trouble
so what I'd like to do there is maybe
say like okay let's well you know what I
could just start supporting it maybe I
was gonna be something else so I'm like
why not just support it so we'll pass it
down and now it's got it right so now if
I look at the actual code that's using
that we're we're it's in the octahedral
sample so you sampler so you can see it
here you can see the light lookup square
dim light lookup voxel damn right square
dim so what I want to do is when we're
doing the dim C and the dim D we kind of
need those to be changed here so we need
one for the diffuse and one for the
specular and what I could do is start
saying look maybe diffuse and specular
always have to be sampled on the same
resolution I don't know
the reason I'm apprehensive about that
and so you know you can see why that's
good because a that would reduce the
number of computations that you have to
do here but the reason I'm a little
apprehensive about that is if you think
about what you want specular Maps
probably want to be higher resolution
than diffuse maps so if we really wanted
to pursue this a little bit further we
probably would want to be able to do a
bigger specular map than the diffuse map
because the specular map is supposed to
show you some kind of glossy reflection
whereas the few snaps just a general
incoming light and so there's a big
difference between those two things and
we may not want them to be the same
dimensions right we may be able to
reduce the dimension our diffuse map
relative to our specular map so looking
through here where we look at you know
what we have to work with you can see
here these are not dependent on it so
the exterior UV dims and stuff that's
not important so really we're just
looking at at these computations here
moving down you can see that it doesn't
get use anywhere else either so we're
really just talking about two basic
things and the samples are going to be
based on those so you can see here that
none of this cares about it either
so we're really just talking about the
interior dims and that's what we have to
work with so I'm gonna make this one the
diffuse and this one the specular like
so and then I want to use those
separately to produce the samples so the
diffuse and specular and then when we
come through here we have different ways
of sampling these this one was the
blurred version and I'm not sure if you
look at what's happening you can see the
the light color sample and how it's
being blurred again I'm not sure how we
want to do this one way or the other
hmm
so there's a lot of different ways we
could do this and I'm not sure which way
we want to do it if you look at the path
here this is the simpler path and I
think what we probably would want to do
if anything is move this to a function
so I think what I probably want to do is
move that to a function I just don't
want to do that quite yet because we're
trying to do this in a in a more
organized fashion so the first thing I'm
going to do is I'm going to use these
and I'm just gonna throw the specular
away but I want to compute it anyway
so that's why that's still there like so
and then the rest of this stuff can
happen as it was happening before so
sample diffuse and sample specular here
I'm gonna go ahead and try and make
those work properly so you can see the
sample CUV gets multiplied through it's
gonna be sampled diffuse UV and then
it's gonna do its thing
same would be for here and then for the
texture results here we would sample the
other texture right like for the
specular amount and again like we're
just not going to do that right now
so that's gonna be like we're just gonna
delete that right so the result a is not
a thing it's just gonna be like zero or
whatever alright so if we then come
through and say all right we need to
actually make these compute the correct
thing we know that this now
is these two things were defined
differently for specular and diffuse so
look up in here we've got diffuse two of
them and specular tile dim so the first
one's going to be diffused tile damn
everywhere like so
oh there we go
and what you can see here is this is a
little bit off just if you look at
what's happening so it's taking the like
like here let me let me just show you
what that was again it's a little bit
hard to read because it's very hard to
read these inside for code it doesn't
really handle 'having stuff indented
inside here docks so if we take a look
at the achma interior diffuse Tim right
what we're saying is all right so it's
the amount we want to actually use of
this thing so we're gonna take the X
dimension oops and then we want to
divide it by the square of the light
lookup voxel dim so um I didn't mean to
replace that right because that's how
many tiles counted there are across and
then we're gonna multiply that by the
this is just this is just producing the
width right of this thing so the
diffused tile X ends up being placed in
there right and then we have in here the
same thing but we want to do it for Y so
this is diffused tile dimmed Y and then
this is diffuse tile damn Y so and then
now here we're doing the exact same
thing all we need to do is just use the
specular versions so this is going to be
specular tile dim X
specular child impacts and then here we
have oops
specular child my boobs right and that's
what we're looking at so hopefully now
this thing is you know compliant with
whatever arbitrary garbage we happen to
pass down and the only thing it doesn't
do yet is handle the light voxel
differences right so these are just
doing like squares and you know it's not
multiplying out the proper pieces of
those but that's okay because we're not
trying to fix that yet so then we get to
light voxel this one can just use well
so the problem here is now we actually
have a place where it's trying to use
this to define something so I believe
this is gonna have to start going away
so the voxel cell itself is going to
have to start going away and we're going
to have to do something about that
so when we look at like the diffused
weight map that we're computing in the
light fox will sell these have to be
dependent on those numbers and so we're
going to have to make those adapt to
whatever they actually need to be right
and that's not so bad but it does create
a little bit of work for us right so
what we want to do here is say well
actually let me let me go ahead and let
me go ahead and fix some other stuff
first so let's suppose we just made
these arbitrary values here
and I'm just doing that to nerf it just
really briefly so I can look at the rest
of these right and you can see like
we've got a lot of yeah we've got a lot
of issues where things are dependent on
those values being constants which I
don't know that we want right alright so
looking it up here
a lot of this stuff so yeah you can kind
of see I mean I guess what I'm learning
here is one problem we're gonna have is
that this information kind of wants to
be baked right so because I can easily
route this properly so I can easily
route it so that we get the information
we need and use it in a computation here
when you do direction from txy you just
pass the light atlas and it would use
the dimension the problem with that is
I'm concerned that that's going to lead
to a lot more computation doesn't need
to happen because if these things are
constant then the compiler can fold
those constants into pre computed values
or as if there are dynamic values you
can't write and so I am kind of nervous
about that prospect so that tells me
some pretty important information right
and I don't know like it's hard to say
to what extent that would really be an
issue you know just looking at it here
certainly in the case of the four loops
probably wouldn't be an issue
[Music]
but I am a little bit worried about
those direction calls
so here's I think what I want to do I'm
gonna look and see how rough it is to
pre-compute these values in the first
place so if I take a look at what's
going on here it looks like what I would
just need is some way of pre inverting
this right and that seems pretty easy so
really this box why here is a Hadamard
product with the particular light atlas
in question so I think what I could
probably do is say all right like look
if we just say that the light Atlas
itself when you define it starts to have
some dependent values that you can use
as constants so this one right here
would be like the you know the Oh X Y
coefficient right let's say and in that
case what you could do is you could just
say look whatever the Oh X Y coefficient
is for this thing and maybe we do it
this way so you're supposed to pass a
new X Y coefficient down to this thing
and then the X Y coefficient is just
multiplied on here and it's the inverse
of these values so then when you do make
light Atlas and now you can see why I
have this calls because that kind of was
a little bit you know in the assumption
having had a lot of experience
programming that we're gonna have to
compute a bunch of dependent values and
it turns out we do we know that we kind
of do this procedure to get them
right so now we can just say like okay
so whatever we compute the tile dim of
this thing to be we can compute what we
need for the dependent variables just
based off of that and then once that's
stored the light Atlas itself can
provide the value here and hey guess
what it's even a little bit faster
potentially because we're not doing a
divide right although we don't actually
know that that was costing us anything
divides go on a separate pipe in there
unless they're dependent it's not that
big a deal but it's you know or that for
now so if we actually produce that
coefficient then that's actually pretty
much free right so then if we looked at
where that was actually happening I
don't care about that or that so in here
we would just need to know that like
whatever the light Atlas was that we
were trying to operate on this would
give us that information and so in here
where we're doing the test sphere right
and we're looping through this thing
we're trying to write into the specular
map so we would just say like okay like
whatever the specular map actually is
and in this case we don't have that here
so we want that to be passed in probably
to the test fear code I'm guessing so we
probably want like light Atlas star in
this case spec Atlas so in here we would
just say like whatever the XY
coefficient is that's what we're going
to use and we'll just pass that in right
so that seems like a pretty reasonable
solution to that problem to me so the
same thing would happen here inside get
octahedral offset I just want to look to
see to what extent we can fold these
things in looking at this it looks like
we just need a light look up dim minus
three as a constant which again we can
just load in right so this is just our
like
like our ktem coefficient right and I
don't know what we want to call this
really it's not particularly well
defined what that would actually be in
fact it's really wrong because this is
supposed to be for a square and we're
doing it the same in both so I think we
actually want this to be a v2 right
which would be both of these two things
packed together so if you look at it's
actually this value right here so we'd
actually do you know we could actually
do this we could just say like ktem
coefficient here and the ktem
coefficient would literally just be
these two values right so it would be
well I can't do it that way but get the
idea it would be the tile dim minus
three in each direction like so and then
the oxy coefficient is just the inverse
of that right so once we have both of
those this becomes pretty
straightforward right so this value now
this is just a Hadamard between the
ktem coefficient and the UV now it
properly handles rectangles which is
good I think off we go right I think
do I not have what's the what is it
complaining about here so it looks like
this doesn't like one over so do we
really not have that looks like we don't
I guess we don't have a good way to
invert a vector we probably do probably
just have what we we probably named them
so we would know what it does if it's
zero or something like that is what I
would guess but it's been a while maybe
it could have been called like 1 over
inverse any of that
hmm or not hmm all right well I'm okay
with doing it the old-fashioned way
all right so now wherever we're getting
the octahedral offset again we kind of
need to know what we're sampling from in
case of in the case of the compute voxel
irradiance at in this case we're gonna
have to pass down the light Atlas and
this one's going to be the diffuse Atlas
right so in this case we just need the
diffuse Atlas ktem coefficient and then
actually you know this this is what
we're gonna replace so this lookup voxel
clamped is actually going to be
something that we use the diffuse that
lists for and we're gonna stop using the
cells for it but that's a separate issue
um so same is true here so here we are
in the test cast this is gonna have to
take the light Atlas this is the speck
Atlas I guess in this case so
I think that's pretty much it you know
so then we get to the Pyrus places where
we're actually looping over things and
in this case you can kind of say well
alright we can just look these up in the
thing we're looping over so whatever
we're planning to write out to which in
this case would be the spec Atlas that's
what we're looping over so this is just
the spec Atlas tyldum Y and the spec
Atlas Talde max right and those are just
basic light loops we're getting rid of
the D there so that's going away I think
we're good there for compute voxel
radians at in this case like I said we
need to start passing these towns so
we've got the light Atlas here and this
is going to be the speck Atlas and the
diffuse setlists
we're gonna use both of them in this
case don't ask me why I put them in the
wrong order I don't know
and then when people actually need to
use them we need to pass the right one
so whichever one it is that we actually
want to use has to be passed here I
don't actually know you know this may be
a mistake using the address of this
thing we may actually want to do just
copying it in wholesale so we may want
this thing to actually look like this
right because we don't want and again
there's no point to this other than to
tell the compiler hey look like we
aren't aliasing so when we write out two
things you don't have to worry about
that it's a little bit premature to do
that so I'm just not going to do it yet
when we actually look at the performance
this thing will have to look at the code
and see what the compiler is doing to
know whether we care about that now what
is the problem
[Music]
specular light atlas is it not did we
call it speck light atlas what did I
call it
or Addison's not in here
alright so apparently we never actually
copied that thing which was a mistake I
guess I just never went back to the open
Jill in it and actually placed it in
there which is weird but I guess that's
what happened so wait but we would have
to how is that possible because we
allocated it didn't we like when oh
never mind that's just where we set it
in for each frame so yeah I'm assuming
that in here we just need to copy this
forward so specular like that looks like
so and off we go
okay so when we're doing compute voxel
irradiance and we need to sample this we
need to sample the dis few setlists than
that so we're gonna pass that a few that
diffuse atlas to that when we're
updating this voxel here so octave set
when it gets passed to update voxel
that's the spec atlas here so for the
spec atlas we need to pull out the ktem
coefficient right for the get octahedral
offset call in here where we're doing
the cue callbacks for the oxy demand the
octave didim again these are really so
what's happening now is this is the part
where we need to do like that the
updates to things so at this point we
need to start replacing these calls
themselves but again we're making so
many changes here and we're gonna have
to this one's going to require debugging
because remember we have to change the
actual voxel writing part of things so
that's it's going to be a nightmare
it'll probably take into tomorrow to do
anyway so we want to try and keep this
at a minimum so at the moment we
probably want to do here for the oxy
demand the octi dim well I don't know I
guess they're only
being used in Justin here so I guess not
so I guess that's okay so we're gonna
pull that out and we're gonna take these
which are the access ORS and we're gonna
move those into here right so whenever
you're trying to get stuff you're gonna
ask this this code for it in the future
and we're gonna work our way towards
that right so let's see where we're at
in here where we're doing our casting
again we probably want to pull out the
atlases so we just have those around so
we're gonna have those here and then we
have to look at what we're actually
doing so if we take a look when we do
our elect s casting I'm not sure why
this didn't complaint oh because we're
doing full cast if we were doing tests
fearer test cast we would have had to
pass down the atlases here I believe
like if we look at test cast it wants to
spec Atlas scoops so let's go ahead and
pass that I'm assuming tests fear does
as well so that's spec that's there so
those two you can stay the way they are
and then full cast grabs them out of the
work anyway so we don't really need to
look at that so then we come to here and
this is where we actually do like our
blurring and that sort of stuff
and then we do our edge fill so if we
have the blurring and the edge fill that
needs to happen then we look at what's
going on here we need to do a couple
different things so first of all when we
look at the blurring function the
blurring function is reading from the
spec map and writing into the diffuse
map and like I said the way that we want
to do that is gonna probably change over
time and especially if we end up having
a spec map that's a different resolution
so we're probably gonna have to revisit
this routine for the minute I will just
poke I will just make it work exactly
the way that it should
I'll make it work exactly the way you
would expect if it was going to just
continue to be the same dimensions and
we'll sort of try to address it more
later so if we take a look what's going
to happen here we effectively need
to loop over the rows of the diffuse map
and the columns of the diffuse map
writing into the diffuse map so this
value here is just going to be whatever
the interior edge dimensions basically
are of this thing so this is just going
to be the tiled M X so is this
I'm sorry Y and there's X and then
inside here where we're looking at what
the sampling is going to be the sampling
obviously is going to be over the
specular map so instead of sampling over
the instead of sampling over the diffuse
Atlas's dimension we would want to stamp
because that's what we're running out to
we would want to sample over the speck
atlases dimension right like so and the
main problem we're gonna have again is
that how we're computing these diffuse
weight maps that is going to have to
change because it's not dynamic at the
moment so then the primary thing we need
here is we need the ability to get these
voxel offsets like where in the map we
are looking right and in order to do
that we need to produce this voxel
offset C values right and we need to be
able to produce those reliably now we
don't need the D because we're not
writing into the D at the moment but
what we do need to be able to do you can
see kind of here when we access the
diffuse map itself we need to pull from
the spec map and write to the diffuse
map so this is actually not going to be
diffuse texels anymore it's actually
going to be spec texels if that makes
sense so so I shouldn't say it that way
so the cell that we pull out right like
this part of things that's the thing you
know this part is the part that's now
going to have to change to be pulling
out of the spec map so this can stay the
same because it's the right part that's
writing out but this parts gonna have to
be fixed right okay so that's fine
that's what we would you know that's
what we'd expect it's totally fine so in
order to do that I think there's a
couple things we probably want to be
able to do at this point so now we
probably want to be able to do some
strided offsets into these things
because you look at how we want to
actually access this thing right we're
in a lot of pull from the cells more
reliably by actually using some
pre-baked offsets for where we're
writing into these things so that whole
process is probably gonna have to change
a little bit I'm going to push forward
slightly just really quickly just to see
what we have to do here so looking at it
I'm not sure what the N value is
supposed to be here that was just us
trying to look at what the TX should
range to so when we're actually copying
those from one side to the other and
we're doing our plus n so the N here is
actually the X dimension right so what
we want to do I guess is set the n
depending on the situation we probably
want to do something more like this
and this whole thing itself we're gonna
have to run once for the spec map and
once for the diffuse map right so we're
gonna want to do these two maps actually
differently right we're gonna want to
blend these both and so this process
itself I think is probably going to want
to be pulled out into a function that's
like the edge duplication function you
know what I'm saying so we probably want
something like this like that or you
know fill border something like that and
it would take a light atlas and just do
it because I don't think there's
anything else special about it so this
code right here that actually you know
does all this nonsense right that code
is something we can do on an atlas and
we might want to do it on both atlases I
don't know but let's suppose that we do
and so we wanted to be able to do here
say okay after the diffuse down sample
or possibly before the diffuse down
sample we want to go ahead and fill the
spec map border so we do the spec atlas
fill here and then after we finish the
sampling the down sampling which again
like I said well you know I think about
it that doesn't really make any sense we
don't this is not gonna pull from those
values so it doesn't matter so it's
really just this
right so we want to be able to do both
of those and we can by using fill atlas
right and so now this code just has to
be able to work using the the atlas only
and I think it can right this is just
the tile dim X here and then we do the
tiled my here and I think all of this
code works roughly the same as it should
with no real with nothing else really
problem attic in it so then we have to
just do this voxel offset nonsense just
needs to be changed slightly so all we
really have to do is just light atlas
offset well so I'm replacing voxel
offset see right actually and do this
even better so I'm gonna replace voxel
offset see parentheses with lighten
Atlas offset parentheses atlas comma
space and that will do what I want which
is to use a different offset here now
this code wants to be optimized to not
use so many offset calls that's a
separate issue that we'll get to in a
minute but basically other than that you
know we're okay
whoops we'll we'll figure that out so
anyway looking at the light atlas code
where we have this stuff we don't need
two of these now all we really need is
the fact that this is a light Atlas
offset and that you pass an Atlas should
give you all the information that you
actually need so now in here we just
need to fill in these dimensions with
the correct dimensions that you're
actually trying to pull from and off we
go so you know we'd want to say
something like this
like all of these are gonna be off of
the Atlas right like so and all of them
are going to want to be the correct
thing so if you take a look here the
like the hot dim in this case is talking
about the voxel dim and it's talking
about the voxel Jim Xbox lived in why
because it's the Z sheet this is talking
about the tiled MX and the tile dim line
because that's the size of one of those
tiles then we're talking about in here
for a wide sheet that's actually going
to be the X I guess is how much you'd be
going let me just make sure I've got all
this in here this is a pretty
complicated thing so if you take a look
at x times obviously x is going to have
to go by tile dim X's right so that
one's easy Y is going to have to go by
tile dim X's as well right and it's
going to have to go by voxel dim X of
those the text Y is actually going to
have to go a whole row down so that's
actually going to be the tile dim x
times the tile dim Y times I'm sorry I
said that wrong
box load MX times the voxel inline and
then finally times the tile dim X right
so I think that's the correct like code
for an Atlas offset and so finally in
here where we're looking at a particular
where we're filling in light Atlas
border in this case we need to tell it
which of the ones we were looking at
right and that's just a straight pass
through yeah so I think that's all we
really need all right that's wrong okay
so that should do it
and I don't know why I keep typing time
dim no real reason so then when we get
down to actually filling these we just
need to pass which one we're filling
which is pretty simple and then when
we're working with these things here any
other place we use light out let's
offset we just have to talk about which
one we're actually using so in this case
it's the diffuse Atlas and off we go
so for the rest of this stuff now we get
into the nasty part of things let me go
ahead and also just in here for building
the direction out of what we're looping
over in this case
excuse me
in this case we're trying to talk about
the incoming direction and so the
incoming direction so you can see each
of these they're gonna be different
light atlases so this one for the
outgoing that's going to be the diffuse
Atlas and that's going to be its what
did we call this it was the o XY
coefficient like so and so in this case
we just need to compute this value and
it needs to be computed based on those
two things so we need the diffuse Atlas
and the speck Atlas to be passed in
excuse me and then when we actually
prepare these we can do the same thing
so in this case we can say like the
diffuse Atlas tiled my and the diffuse
Atlas tile dim X and then in this case
it's the speck Atlas tile dim Y and the
speck Atlas tile dim X and then I think
that's that's everything right so the
problem that we then run into obviously
is we have sort of this issue where we
don't actually know how big these things
are going to be so we have no idea what
we should actually be doing here and if
you assume that we were able to change
these at runtime which you know at the
moment we don't actually allow you to do
but if you could you could see where
we'd be in big trouble because we don't
actually have a way of coping with that
right so I guess what I would say is the
only they can really think of is we can
either compute it every time it changes
right and that seems sane trying to get
what else we could do
I mean I really can't think of anything
else we could really do there so I mean
I don't know what else I don't know what
else to do there other than yeah like
just computed anytime it changes or
something like that and for the moment
we don't really have to care right
because it will do the right thing in
this case but so like you know in begin
lighting computation for example we
could compute it if it had changed
if those dimensions had changed or just
every frame if we're just being sloppy
because it really won't amount to much
compared to the rest of the stuff we
have to do it's not that bad right but
we do want to figure it out so I'm not
sure exactly what I want to do there
right like I don't know it's tough to
say for now we're going to do it here
and then we'll take a look at it later
so get light atlas texels so it looks
like we didn't include the C file which
I guess makes sense I may have not put
the actual Jimmy I may have not put the
actual C file in here so we may want to
go ahead and do like a handmade light
atlas dot CPP like so it doesn't really
matter where we put that one there we go
so now we are at least compiling but
this isn't actually correct if we ran
this it would just kind of roll over and
die the reason for that is we have these
light box will cells and they're not the
right none of this is the right
information you know what I mean
so we're currently just kind of worked a
little bit if you look at what's
happening here it kind of looks like
it's still working and you know I guess
I'm surprised it's working as well as it
is I guess we did a very good job of
that port so maybe it's not as bad as I
thought but my point is it's not doing
the right thing at all so it's not
actually sampling from the correct map
it's still using these light voxel cells
and we need to so go ahead and finish
that change since we are out of time
I'll end it there for today tomorrow
what we'll do is we'll actually go
through and pull from the correct Maps
so we'll get rid of using the light
voxel cell and that'll be the change
that finally puts us in sort of a nice
streamlined position where everyone's
using the correct map reading and
writing from the correct maps and that's
then we'll get to see like okay as we
tune the lighting a little bit how good
can we get it you know what does it look
like I'm encouraged again by how good
this one looks using just specular it's
not great it needs some work but it's
better than I would have expected right
so you know
it's at least encouraging but but we
don't know how good it's going to be
till we actually play around a little
bit more let's go ahead and go to Q&amp;A
[Music]
the heck oh the control keys held down
there we go
oh so I can answer the question about VC
runtime afforded us oh no we don't use
any dll's
that we didn't write ourselves we do use
the sine and cosine functions from the
static CRT but we will replace those
eventually too but right now we don't
load any non system DLL so we don't use
VC runtime 140 DLL so like sure where
the depends function is here
I don't know how well these things work
Microsoft has made it almost impossible
for any of this stuff to be any good
like because they've made their runtime
linking so incredibly janky that even
just analyzing something to find out
what it depends on is incredibly hard
that's how bad Windows is these days
it's really bad this is why you should
never use any of the new stuff like
manifests your side-by-side assemblies
or anything it's just a disaster really
really bad they've done a terrible job
they should have stuck with the original
DLL system for the faults that it
actually has it's still way better than
what they replaced it with so here's
1/32 handmade and you can see what the
import libraries are and you can see it
you know it's just GDI kernel user and
win mmm
so it's only just the system libraries
we need to call this is the entirety of
everything all of our external
dependencies right and we can also look
at the runtime hmm dll's so if we look
at like the game dll's like like this
right you can see the imports here and
they're basically the same right
it's just kernel32 and nothing else
because we just you call through the
platform layer and finally if you look
at the renderer dll that's just gonna
have OpenGL right as you can see up in
jail and then obviously GDI kernel and
user because it needs to access like the
window functions so we are pretty much
we're a third party library completely
free the only thing we still use is the
sine and cosine routines that were
written for this the standard library
wrote so we need to write our own of
those and then we're 100% clean like
literally no non our code period
do you know why some games require to
restart if you change graph settings is
because they can't reload different
textures runtime it's not usually
because they can't reload textures at
runtime although some games that may be
true it's usually just because look they
didn't want to have to do the work of
making everything properly track what
dependencies there are on those things
so for example let's suppose that you
know you've got a bunch of variables
that are due right we have a bunch of
variables that are dependent on things
that have to do with the graphics
subsystem and we've actually done a
pretty decent job of passing those
through so that you can actually change
a fair number of them at runtime it just
works but there are some that we
probably don't and in fact like one of
the things would be like let's say we
didn't want to actually have a thing
that detects like we just looked at that
diffuse blur coefficient right that
matrix if you just didn't do the work of
tracking the change on that then you
can't change it at runtime you have to
you know restart the game and compute it
at in it time which is where it gets
computed right or something so usually
what happens is game developers and
rightly so don't want to bother because
it's not really something you need to do
like people don't need to be able to
change 100% of their graphics settings
on the fly so typically what they'll do
is they'll say look we just don't want
to deal with having to make sure all of
that code is dynamically responsive and
doesn't introduce bugs when you do it so
it's usually just safer for them to say
look if you want to change any kind of
coregraphics setting just restart the
game and I respect that because it's not
a great place to spend your time it
requires extra engineering to clean all
of those paths completely and test them
so it just like don't bother now I
totally respect people to go the extra
mile and let you do it it's great
engineering to support that but you know
it's Engineering that comes at a cost
because it means you weren't doing
something else why don't all studios use
the dynamic DLL loading it's the best
thing ever right the reason is because
especially if you're like a C++ nonsense
engine where you have like all this
garbage all over the place you actually
can't do it so
one of the things the reasons that we
can do it so easily is because we have
relatively clean code that uses
relatively clean allocation strategy if
you have a nonsense allocation strategy
all this stuff goes out the window right
because you've just got people calling
stuff all over the place and you've got
V tables everywhere and all this other
stuff that can create all kinds of
problems for you and so C code it's very
usually very easy to take C code and
make it hot reloadable C++ code is not
that way and so usually what it means is
they just didn't it's just probably too
hard for them to add write C forget to
upload the previous episode of YouTube
no we just didn't do one on Sunday we
didn't actually end up coding on Sunday
they play us to open source the code
yeah we pre announced when we started
the series that the code will get
released from the public domain two
years after the game ships so it will be
released eventually but not anytime soon
pledged in advance if this was already
answered previously but is there
particular reason you use structs and
global functions instead of classes so
there's a couple of reasons
I guess maybe two reasons one is
obviously the word class as meaningless
doesn't do anything in C++ it was I
don't even know why they have it
it's a stupid a stupid idea a class is
just a struct or equivalent the only
difference between the two is a struct
starts out with a default public : and a
class starts out with a default private
: and what's absolutely hilarious to me
it literally cracks me up every time I
see it cuz I'm just like do you even
program bro is like I see this
right if you type that you could have
just typed this I don't know it's like
they're just like yeah man we literally
just don't care you know it blows my
mind so anyway like in terms of the
literal word why do I use struct instead
of class the reason is because what I'm
actually defining is a thing where I
want all the members to be public and so
it seems kind of stupid to type class
blah Open bracket public : right but the
broader question of why don't I use like
classes with member functions and
virtual functions that sort of stuff
it's just because I find that to be a
poor way of structuring and thinking
about your program and the reason that I
say that is because I've always said
this the problem I think with
object-oriented programming the reason I
don't like it the reason I don't do it
is not because there's anything wrong
with certain things that you might want
to do such as creating API boundaries or
encapsulation or any of these sorts of
things right because every programming
technique tends to have a place where it
makes sense and I don't want to
disparage a particular technique the
problem with a burny programming is the
phrase and the mindset so creating a
class and thinking that I put member
functions in a class that is just
fundamentally incorrect way to structure
a program period in my opinion the
reason for that is that I don't feel
like algorithms ever operate on one
thing they operate between two things
typically and you always want to think
about that pipeline as the primary thing
and so most of your functions should be
operating across structures not within
them and if most of your functions
operate within structures you've
probably screwed something up and you're
probably very inefficient which by the
way is how most opportunity of
programming looks to me when I look I'm
like that is a very inefficient way you
just wrote that and I can see why it's
because you were thinking that things
should be contained inside class
boundaries so I really really really
really like to emphasize the fact that
that's actually very bad now it doesn't
mean that once in awhile you don't end
up with something that can be completely
isolated within itself so for example
the techs
your Atlas thing we made today light
atlas rather this is an example of
something that could have been a class
if you'd want it to be right because it
happens to all be self-contained at the
moment and that may continue but the
crucial difference here and I really
want to emphasize this is that should be
the accidental case not the goal
so the problem with attribute
programming is they say that this is the
goal the goal is to end up with things
like this it's not when you end up with
something like this it's usually an
accident and it's usually very
inconsequential pieces of the code this
is irrelevant like this is not an
important part of our program it's tiny
and it's meaningless it's basically a
bunch of convenience functions to opt to
compute things right the goal of your
code should it be reduced clean data
pathways that work between multiple
Struck's
right and so what you really want to do
is get out of that mindset of I put
functions inside data structures because
functions should not be confined to data
stores that's a very very bad way it's
flipping the actual ways to think about
programming which is that data types are
things that are used by functions
instead you're thinking the other way
around as functions or things that are
used by data types very very bad mental
model so that's why I do it this way is
to you know remind everyone and to avoid
my own falling into a trap of thinking
that things should be lined up in that
way
I managed to extract CL XD for visual
studio but I can't redistribute it has
anyone been sued for redistributing the
free CL compiler so I don't know if
anyone has been sued but obviously
anyone could be sued so I guess what I
would say there is it's a copyrighted
program if you distribute it you are
opening yourself up to a lawsuit by
Microsoft should they choose to do that
at the very least I would say maybe try
to ask Microsoft specifically if they
mind you producing a bundle of that what
is your plan to ensure the orphanage our
hero Lisbon will have sufficient access
to paper products especially toilet
paper
how will hand-washing work in a world
where everything is handmade but the
children have no limbs so this is
actually an issue no question and that
is because limbless orphans which is
what we have in this game would have to
do everything with their mouths largely
which of course is a very bad disease
vector so I guess the way that I would
say it is it's very important that
people who interact with this orphanage
proper basically have very good hygiene
because otherwise they will definitely
have like you know issues with it like
basically have to just make sure you
have to do like what I'm doing right now
is just like not going outside right not
leaving the apartment so that basically
you know that you don't bring the
contagion in because once the contagions
in it's over there's nothing you can do
about it
right so well touching your face is fine
if you're not in an environment that has
any contagions around it right just
don't go outside and do that you know
moved from an array of light voxel cells
to a lighthouse that because of OpenGL
analysis or other yes sort of I
basically want to have one format
through the whole pipeline so before we
were storing these things in the light
box'll cells and that was a convenience
for us and instead I want to move to
everything sampling out of just just
flat atlases and that just allows us to
keep everything simpler removes code
types keep it simpler and also if we
need to offload this work to the GPU we
can because at least then all of our
code is just working with the same
concept the whole way right he's using
mm load PS and mm store PS more
efficient than just casting the floats
or accessing it through a union I guess
the answer would be so it's a little bit
complicated the answer is it really
depends on what the compiler chooses to
do so none of this matters at some level
because what's actually gonna happen is
there's going to be there's going to be
actual assembly language calls to move
the data out of the SSE registers into
memory one way or the other and what you
choose to tell the compiler to do is
going to help it potentially make a good
decision but at the end of the day you
can't control the compiler does the
compiler does what prado does so if you
cast a floats or access through a union
or anything else the compiler may or may
not know what you're doing and at some
point you may care about the performance
of that code and when you go look at the
disassembly you may see that compilers
made it a bad choice using the
intrinsics is a way of telling the
compiler what you were trying to do in a
cleaner way so it has a greater chance
of outputting the assembly language code
you actually wanted but that's all
that's happening there and if you really
want to do it right you have to write it
in assembly language anyway because
that's the only way to actually control
exactly what's happening so intrinsic
sar just hints to the compiler about
what a seminary you were trying to
generate in a way that makes it much
easier for the compiler to know as
opposed to if you just use like unions
or stuff for convenience which I do
sometimes but when I actually have to go
to opt by something that's usually the
case Copiah doesn't really know what you
were doing there and it will generate
like oh that's not as good or something
right
so that's really what's going on there
it has nothing to do with one or the
other being better it's more to select
look-sees not good at this
the intrinsics were a bad solution this
problem what we really needed was
language features that work with wide
vectors types like that and we don't
have them so at this point we're kind of
screwed and we just have to use these
intrinsics and so what you're trying to
do is basically tell the compiler what
you're doing in a way that that is easy
for it to generate good code and not
have to do all kinds of analysis that's
tricky and error-prone to figure out
what it was you were doing would you be
able to do give an intuitive geometric
explanation for what the adjoint matrix
abuse and why you need it for doing
generalized transforms on surface normal
vectors I mean yeah and I think I
already did
[Music]
so I want to see if you go to our search
here oh so I don't like the sound of
that so maybe I didn't
so this is the X the app so this is it
right here right if you go to day 101
this is it and you can see me like
transforming a geometric shape and you
can see how the normal doesn't transform
the same way that the points transform
and that's what the adjoint is for so
this I would go here
so I don't know if we actually got to
the adjoint matrix part of it we may not
have but that's the reason this is the
explanation we probably just never
called it an adjoint matrix so
so actually it's been a while since I've
looked at a linear algebra textbook is
this just the transpose though
can you just write the equation please
all right so whereas a math person can
someone please put the actual equation
in one line I guess it's not possible
probably on thing but normally you
transfer you normally when you transform
normals you transform normals by the
inverse transpose
you think using open jail for making
games is still fine for a couple years
I've heard John blow rant about it not
being valid API but not sure why I mean
it's not good and largely just because
there's been bad shepherding on that
part like I think opengl 4.5 especially
with the Nvidia extensions was a great
API I think someone should have
standardized on that removed all the
cruft and been like this is the new API
we've been way better than Vulcan would
have been as fast as Welkin but they
didn't do that and so the problem with
OpenGL it's just really sprawling and so
it's very unlikely to be supported
properly most of the time especially on
like Intel parts stuff like that and now
it's not supported on an Mac anymore so
you can't use it there so like Vulcan
OpenGL kind of useless should just get
thrown away probably at this point and I
think we're basically looking at a metal
D 3d world more or less unless someone's
ship and stuff on Linux which game
developers don't really need to do I
mean I would argue they shouldn't bother
shipping on Mac either so I think your
base looking at metal on iOS if you
really want to go to that platform
otherwise it's just a D 3d world now you
don't really need anything else I mean
you're shipping on Windows or you got to
write a custom thing for ps4 or Xbox so
Mac Apple does not support current
OpenGL they do not have a compliant like
4.6 implementation they absolutely don't
what do you think about the style of
using a bunch of defiance controller
generated code have it include for
things like libraries I think it's fine
the only problem with it is that it can
get kind of hairy and hard to maintain
but you know if you if you deploy it
judiciously it's fine do you take any
programming courses at college I didn't
go to college
Taylor towers on the Wikipedia page the
to point to the two-by-two generic
example this one
so the
so I want to say that this is not
exactly right
then so I guess it's kind of hard to say
like just thinking it through so like if
you look at what the matrix ends up
being for like an inverse matrix so
here's like 2x2 inverse right and so a
inverse here you know it equals this
analytic solution so you're looking at 1
over ad minus BC D negative B negative
CA right and if we look at the what
they're suggesting here and I like I
said this is just what it came through
for adjoint matrix which is just not it
says sometimes called adjoint so you
know let's assume that this Wikipedia
page is accurate if this is the actual
computation for it then if you look at
the two side-by-side I'll just explain
why I'm nervous about it and like I said
it's been a long time since I studied
that in algebra so take it with a grain
of salt I'm just telling you what it
looks like to me which is not
dispositive in any way so here's what
you know you'd expect the analytic
inverse to look like right and here's
what the adjoint
the ah to get matrix looks like right
and that's not even remotely what I
would expect it to look like like what I
would expect to see is for transforming
the normals I always want to see this
matrix but with the negative B and
negative C swapped this term would
remain here that is gone so maybe this
is not what they mean maybe they mean to
this or some I mean I don't know what
they mean I'm
not sure if I'm bet him if I'm reading
this right no it's like totally not
correct look it's not what you would
transform the normals by at all
so I don't know I mean it could be this
is just the wrong Wikipedia page but all
I wanted to say was like what I would
expect to see for transforming normals
is this matrix but transposed so you
know transpose of the matrix as you flip
along the diagonal right so the negative
B and negative C would swap and the same
would be true for any size matrix so if
you told me I had transformed normals
and three dimensions right watch that's
not true because normal is only really
you would have to go to buy vectors to
go above three dimensions anyway so this
all this stuff is not the way you would
even think about it at that point
but the point is like if you have a
three by three matrix you would do the
same thing so basically you would take a
look at what you got here
so you know you would you would compute
the 3x3 inverse and then you would
transpose it so the BCF and the DS DGH
would flip sides make sense
I don't have a Raspberry Pi for no why
would it support Vulcan instead of just
DX I have no idea you have to ask them
will you ship the game with debug GUI
Mike Acton said on GDC conference that
you should be able to debug the release
version of your game how do you do that
I'm sorry I don't really know what Mike
Acton said about that I'm I guess what I
would say is the release version of the
game can have bugs in it that are that
can't be found in like that don't show
up in a debug build so what I would say
and I have no idea what Mike said but
what I would say is you need to at least
make sure that when you're testing your
release build that if bugs come up you
have ways of tracking them down so you
can't remove 100% of the scaffolding
from your system because if you do you
won't be able to find those bugs now it
may be that you engineered your product
so it won't have those bugs that's
possible but whatever you do you need to
plan for that so that's what I would say
and I don't know if that's similar to
what Mike Acton said or not
all right
oops just make sure we're all saved up
here thank you everyone for joining me
for the notes on a handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to following
series at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade hero org
it comes with a source code so you can
play around with it at home maybe you
can finish the lighting port we did
before I get to tomorrow it'd be good
practice because it's literally just
rote translation but it's meticulous so
you know and it's a good code cleanup
it's making the code better and less
fragile because we're actually
centralizing how a bunch of things are
done so it's a good thing to be in the
habit of doing and knowing how to do
I'll be back here tomorrow morning for
that until then have fun putting
everyone and I'll see you on the
Internet take it easy everybody