okay hello everyone and welcome to hand
made here oh sure we code a complete
game live on stream we are going to take
a look at doing some lighting refinement
today it's actually kind of getting to a
nice spot honestly I have been liking
the lighting more and more as we go
especially because in general these are
not the sorts of systems that anyone
really knows how to do well so it's
always kind of a little bit of a
exploration to figure out how to put
something in there that's nice in
general though we still are not quite
there yet like what what well I feel
like we kind of have to click on that
button how likely is I would recommend
that's hard to say I mean I guess I
wouldn't know what else to recommend so
in that sense I'm extremely likely if
you're asking how much I like it well
it's like a zero or a two or something
we'll say five because I don't know what
rate what changes would just get high
rating much better performance see what
else do we want here I think that's the
biggest one what are the sorts of things
don't pop up license windows and survey
windows in the middle of me trying to
code get rid of all the weird crap like
the yellow flag that shows up in the
corner and the web startup stuff and
stop installing an SQL server and 15
million services just to run the
debugger and probably the other thing
would be don't require an install at all
just make an executable that runs like a
normal program
[Music]
yeah I think that's basically it for
debugging stuff make a way to view
images in the debugger like pointer to
an RGBA and you can specify the width
height make a way to view 3d data like
you can point to a float buffer and view
three floats at a time in 3d window
what else would I like make it
instantaneous to step in the debugger
right now it's very slow update the
watch window instantaneously right now
it lags way behind the step see what
else we got here
[Music]
you
make sure the compiler is just one eggsy
that can be installed by itself with no
dependencies and just called directly
with no VC VARs or or anything like this
for DLL path or nonsense like that
[Music]
output AST to a file via command-line
switch so I can be in a well-documented
format that I can easily load with no
DLL or libraries just a simple single
flat file load and then parse it myself
easily clean up the PDB format so that
it's simple to read and parse and use
etc etc the debugger reads pdbs reliably
and shows the source code and
disassembly reliably which is nice
everything else about visual Studios too
bad these days
[Music]
what source control two's home research
proprietary it house what choice do you
have been using the Skloot tools none
sure
congratulations guys she filled out
survey what do you think all right so
moving on they want to follow up they
can just watch the show they see me uses
a bug relic I'm watch me stepping
through and the watch window still shows
results from like 10 years ago
apparently there's like a watch update
lag parameter that you can actually
change that will speed that up because I
guess it's just so slow that then it
makes stepping slow so what they did is
they decouple the two which is a crazy
it's so nuts you're like wait instead of
fixing the problem you made a new
problem so weird anyway I don't want to
know I don't want to know what goes on
over there I am terrified to know how
the development of this program goes I'm
sure it's a c-sharp
funhaus over there anyway so getting
back to what we were trying to do I was
trying to run the game here I just
wanted to talk about where the lighting
was so based on our current situation
the lighting is actually working quite a
bit better than it was working before
but there's a couple things we want to
do now one is we want to try and push
them forwards a little further than it
is right now because I still think it's
it's too low compared to probably what
we needed to be once we start dumping
more stuff in there now one thing we
could do is we certainly can go ahead
and GPU eyes this potentially if you
want to I don't know how wise that is
but that's something we could certainly
look into but we also have a lot of room
left to improve how we're doing things
currently on the CPU side for
performance so that's one thing the next
thing that we have to think about though
as well is that the getting further rid
of the noise and I think there's some
things that I want to do there one thing
that I was thinking about that I'd like
to check out is we've never really
verified that we converge to a good
solution if we are if we just took a lot
of samples
right so one thing that I think we want
to be able to do is like be able to hit
a key and run like a single lighting
solution that's you know really
extensive that takes a long time and
verify that it actually converges to
something useful or more to the point
maybe make it so that we can just say
look stop updating the lighting solution
from Lix stop assuming that the lighting
solution is changing just let the
lighting solution accumulate over time
and just take the total average or
something right because right now I'll
be honest I'm not a hundred percent
certain that all the flicker we're
seeing is really flicker from sampling
it may be flicker from sampling but it
also may be that we still have bugs in
there that we are not accounting for
properly because I I really just can't
quite tell at the moment if we really
have if it's really correct
how much flicker there is here because
in some places it looks to me a little
like it's maybe more buggy than we might
think
and I'm not sure and as always it's kind
of deceptive because the lighting looks
very consistent right now so when you
look at it it's like yeah it looks like
it's computing the lighting properly
certainly that's true to a certain
extent anyway given the limitations of
the system but on the other hand it's
not immediately clear to me that that
it's all the way right because you know
it's it's hard to look at something like
this and know if you have maybe more
subtle bugs going on in there right then
then what you know about at the moment
so I do think we need a little bit more
I think we need a little bit more
information about our scheme and we need
a little bit better ways to test it than
what we have right now because right now
we just really don't have any way to
know much about subtle bugs that might
be working lurking in the system we can
see gross error like we can see things
that are really egregious Lee
wrong but we just don't have a way of
looking at things that are maybe more
subtly wrong that we that could be like
a source of that noise in addition to
honest sampling error and so rather than
try to fight the sampling error right
off the bat I would like a way of sort
of getting a little further down that
road so those are two things I'd like to
do depending on how much time we have we
can look at both this weekend so if I
take a look inside the lighting code the
question is where do we want to go first
I might go ahead and say let's let's
look at the lighting code a little bit
on the performance side of things today
and see if we can't improve that a
little bit so inside compute light
propagation we have been collecting some
statistics now so for example when we
run this you can see down here we have
some statistics that are being tracked
we know how many castes are being
initiated 120,000 Ray's are being
requested and those are just those are
rays that are just initial that Ray's in
our system don't bounce right we send
light to surfaces and then we bounce it
again on like we keep bouncing it sort
of in a stored State we don't do paths
that go for a long way so that's total
cast one in twenty thousand is the total
number we're casting per frame okay
so then if you look down there and you
look at total leaves tested and total
partitions tested what you can see is
that we're testing a lot more partitions
than leaves right do you think that is
probably not great there's a number of
things that we have to consider when
we're looking at this and one of the
things that we see like we're testing
eighteen partitions per cast and only
five leaves right and so what that kind
of says to me is we're probably wasting
too much time testing partitions because
really partitions are supposed to
eliminate leaves from testing
right and so at some point if your
partition number gets too high then
you're really wasting work because
you're just partition test to tell you
nothing right only thing a partition
test actually ends up doing is telling
you what leaves to test now that's not
entirely true here and I suppose we have
to be a little bit more careful about
how we talk about this I probably need
one more number here which is like and
in fact let's just put it in before we
talk about it since we allow early outs
and we test partitions and use the
lighting from partitions we really need
to consider those to be some other thing
they're not leaves but they're like
partition leaves right something like
that and we need to sort of store this
information so that we know how many
partitions are actually being used as
leaves because that may change our
opinion of what's going on and make it
look more favorable we don't know yet
so this will be essentially like it's
not tested but it's like s used right is
maybe the right thing
so total partition leaves used is the
thing which basically lets us know how
many times that that thing has happened
where is our work we gotta clear those
out of our work table somewhere here not
there it's in compute light propagation
at the top there it is so we're we clear
the whole thing so I guess now we know
so anyway inside here we know this is
our array cast here
and when our ray cast terminates right
we know there's two different
circumstances one is that the close
enough thing will happen or not and so
that's the thing that we have to check
in this case because when we come
through here we're gonna see if this box
has a child count we're gonna count it
as a partition if this box has a has a
leaf doesn't have a child count then
it's gonna be counted as a leaf right
that we're testing but then when we get
down here you know maybe we tested the
partition if we decide in here to push
the box on then it's an honest partition
but if instead we look and see that it's
that it was all true here right that we
that we exited out after just using it
entirely then it's a partition used as
leaves
right so that's then that's this value
so if we take a look at that oh forgot
these have to be padded it's pretty cool
that assertion that just saved us a huge
speed hit so here is the new version
running the same but now we get this
information here oh but I need to
actually output it which I'm not doing
currently hold on one second
so taking a look here at this we've got
a pretty low number actually so we're
not really doing that very much in terms
of early outing we're still going down
further to do the more tests so again
that just strikes me as too many
partition tests so I guess what I would
say here is that you know if we looked
at our split box call just for starters
when we're doing our split box I do
wonder here if maybe we want to split
into say four boxes right do more of a
quad three kind of a thing so or
something like that so you know what we
could do is say okay you know in general
if you take a look at what happens here
I pretty sure there's really no
difference I mean as far as I can see
anyway there's really no difference
between these paths so what we could do
is we could say something like you know
if zero this out
I think this count B just splits along a
plane there right and so what we could
do is say all right if we're gonna split
along a plane maybe we can split along
two planes instead and and count them up
or something like this right
so this for example is the so this is
the the one that's KD tree like right
it's saying that we're gonna take for
any given me grab the mill tongue today
is today day for 33 so this is the one
that's basically saying alright we're
gonna split things in half and then
we're gonna split them in half again
right so we would do this is you know
box a this is box B this is box C splits
these in half what we could do instead
is something like okay pick two planes
and this these are both split plates are
both applied in block box a and then
another one just split in Box B right so
a quadtree or an octree kind of approach
we're basically gonna say let's just go
ahead and split these up more
aggressively and I don't know if that's
that's another way we could do this so
if we go ahead and and pursue that a
little bit further what we could do is
just say look anything that's a certain
number yeah this number here is also
obviously tunable I mean one thing so
before I even do that right
we can also take a look at what happens
if we just say look you can have eight
leaves in a child instead so just to see
what happens if we make a shallow err
hierarchy for example would be another
thing to take a look at right and it
looks like that doesn't really change
the runtime much appreciably but you can
see that it reduced the number of
partitions per cast right and it
increased the total number of leaves
tested so we could also print out and we
could print out some other values there
to help us just understand what's
on more quickly than not so that we
don't have to you know write do the math
in our heads so we can do something like
partitions per leaf and that would just
be total partitions tested over total
Leafs tested syntax error huh I agree
so if I run that now then we can also
see like how many partitions we test per
leaf so that's about one partition per
leaf whereas if we change the source
count to four here that's a three
partitions per leaf you know and you can
see those numbers change it doesn't
really change uh speed much though
yeah I'm also you know what I be it
should - no - if we don't call compute
light propagation what's the speed
I'm not sure why we would get a stack
check fail on that
what
so now we see that we actually have
bigger problems here so I guess we kind
of saw this the other day it guess it's
worse than I thought
so at the moment we are actually in a
situation where our lighting is not the
problem so we can't really profile below
that unless we fix the problem with our
shader right I mean you can see that
very clearly so I guess that is that so
we got to go finish up that stuff first
otherwise this is irrelevant so what
happens what's going what's going on
here so I guess what's interesting about
this is because this is overlapped it
gets over counted so this is this is not
really telling us so yet so this view
actually tells us more what we needed to
know right which is that this stuff
completed way sooner and there's this
huge chunk here that's a problem right
so we do have to speed up the lighting
but we can't speed up the lighting
before we speed up the shading is I
guess what we've learned so yeah good to
know
so if we take the shading out of the
equation right then we can actually see
more accurately what our time is let's
see here no there we go
so you can see how dramatically this bar
kind of grows right and then when we get
to here
I'm guessing that that is now just like
the vsync bar or whatever right
so I'm interested to know let's take a
look we'll take out swap interval it I
wanted we'll take out swap interval and
take a look here
so I'm really not sure what this time
delay is we may need to investigate that
further right I don't know what's taking
the time here because it's not pixel
shading anything at that point and that
bar doesn't seem to be responsive in the
same way that I would expect it to here
so something's weird
so you can see very clearly right that
we're at 19 milliseconds here or so or
20 when I come in here
I've spiked all the way up to 29 almost
30 milliseconds per frame right and if I
look at the threads here that part's
very large right frame display debug
collation is really not that long but
frame display is huge and now if I if I
draw us out
it definitely shrinks but now as much as
you would think now that may be because
the debug system right I'm not 100%
certain about that I think we have a
knock at the door hold on a second
look at this graph and figure out what's
going on and while I'm gone
[Music]
all right so there they are fixing the
heater or in theory fixing the office
heater today so they will probably you
will see people come in to that I can't
put point at to that breaker box right
there
and reset it at some point assuming it
works all right so anyway you know I
think that this is a little bit
misleading looking at this thing right
here because these these lighting
threads are accounting for a fixed
amount of time that we know about right
we can see how many cycles that that
sort of the game update is taking total
and the lighting is accounting for most
of it right so we kind of know roughly
what's going on there the thing that we
don't know is exactly what's going on
here now there's a lot of reasons why
this might be relatively long for
example just the the fact that we're
still doing a lot of texture changes
there and so on we don't really know
what's accounting for most of that time
we can profile that using insight
probably a little bit more specifically
and then we would have a better idea but
again it's pretty hard at this point to
get a sense for how much time the
lighting is taking looking at this
number so I think what we're gonna have
to do is get a little bit more specific
about it and be able to print out a
number that's that's more reasonable
that sort of more accurately reflects
the total lighting time and so in order
to do that I think what we want to do is
is just profile this one directly and
then print out the timer directly just
for that one so that we know exactly how
long the lighting is taking in a more
specific way I think that's probably all
we're gonna be able to do for now until
we bounce back over and improve the
overall throughput for all this stuff so
I'm gonna stop looking at that
millisecond number it's just we're down
to the point where that's just not going
to cut it as a way of actually analyzing
this information but what we want to do
now is we want to go ahead and take
take the extra step of putting in some
kind of profiling for this that we can
measure more directly so I'm going to
take a look at how we might want to do
that it's sort of something we may want
in the debug system more properly I'm
guessing I mean I'm not 100% sure where
that should go but if you take a look at
how we're printing it out here we
probably want that to be something
that's going to be usable more than once
[Music]
hard to say yeah so I'm not 100% sure
how we want to do that so you know
normally we've got these timed block
things and so each of those you know in
the debug system it's it's possible that
we could do something like say this here
where we do like the lighting test and
we've got you know time function maybe
we could do something here where we
specifically say that we want a function
to always show up as its timer so
something where we could say like okay
we want a like a HUD timed function and
the HUD time function would literally be
exactly the same
it just it would pass something here
that lets us know you know that it's
special right and that seems pretty good
to me so if you take a look at what
happens here right the debug table
that's the stuff here that's that's
globally applicable we should be able to
tell it when it outputs the HUD to grab
a specific event value out and to show
just that value or that just that timer
and that seems like the best thing that
way in here we could just do HUD time
function and then it would show up there
and we wouldn't have to expand the debug
window too
show it and we'd get a more stable view
of that thing that's what I think we
want to do so let's go ahead and make
that happen as best we can so let's say
we've got a HUD time function here
that's gonna call this time block stuff
right and inside the time block stuff we
probably want to have some way of
setting the debug tables information so
that it knows that this is important so
the global debug table in here right it
just kind of knows some stuff yeah so we
should be able to do is put what we
actually wanted to print out we should
be able to put that in here and I guess
we can just put that by string probably
so we could put like that maybe I don't
know but that that seems reasonable to
me so you know maybe we go in here and
we just say ok so a time block is really
just where we say global debug table HUD
function equals function and you know
the debug name I guess we could even do
see bug name of the function I don't
remember if we need that I think we do
because this is what it'll be recorded
as in the system I think so I think we
probably just want to set it to the
whole thing so we want to say like okay
you know the debug name the problem is
the counter value will I think I think
increment twice here so what we may have
to do is do something like this where we
say like okay HUD time function dot dot
dot is going to call this
so that I can put out the name twice you
know I'm saying no I don't know why we
pass the name and the debug name I guess
those are just for friendly printouts
probably but I'm not sure so don't quote
me on that I don't remember when we
wrote the system why we had to do that
but yeah we'll just assume that that's
the case so in here we've got the HUD
time function and we're gonna go ahead
and delete this part from it and we'll
just call this separately with the debug
name so that can get used twice and it
doesn't need anything else other than
the VAR ours I think you need to paste
on there right so in theory that should
just work and should create one of these
things and I as long as we fix the
compiler errors here which I don't know
if there are any there aren't that
should still just do what it was
currently doing like it shouldn't do
anything different the only difference
is now it's setting that global variable
so that we know which one of those we
were inspecting so compute light
propagation well it wasn't that when
it's lighting tests actually somewhere
in here right lighting test so lighting
test is still getting counted just like
it normally would be and we can go from
there so now if I go down to the debug
system proper in theory where it prints
out that HUD which is probably in the UI
I'm guessing see where does that get
printed actually those blocks
oops so here's where we print this the
HUD line out there
so you know what I want to do is I want
to be able to add something to this that
just shows us that HUD function if we're
looking at the HUD function so you know
if there is one we'll just like stick it
one line lower you know or something
like that where we can just print out
what the information is now I like how
input Mouse and house wired thing passed
here for some reason even though they're
not getting used which is pretty great
in fact I don't even know what what this
versus that is none of these are getting
used right we've got one two three four
five six one two three four five six so
probably used to print them but we don't
print them anymore
so if we take a look at at what this is
doing the question here is like how do
we get access to that particular
function that we've now got the name of
and so we've got to go double check like
how that stuff gets handled and I think
if I remember correctly right we we
basically have like ways of looking at
the events in here by their name I
believe that's how we do it right
because that's how we were like
collating blocks with each other and so
on so here's like some of that stuff
let's see here
element top clocks list about there's a
lot of stuff in here
profile bars debug ID debugging
interaction Wow you know this is there's
a lot of stuff in here
so I think this is probably what we
would need is to to it like that that
debug name is going to be the gooood
that we've got there and so once we have
well I guess this gives it to us
directly once we have that I think we
should be able to get the element from
it right and presumably that would be
all we should need I think we don't need
to parse the names because that will be
done for us so I think this is all we
really need and that would give us a
debug element now the question is does
the debug element get us enough let's
find out
let's find out
so this does give us the number of
frames and all the events that were
stored but it doesn't necessarily give
us anything more profound node yeah we
kind of want we want this stuff so you
can see here where we do our profile
bars right
in here this debug profile node is
something that we store inside the
stored event right so we have that
information for the stored event but
there's one of those for every frame so
I guess in theory if we just query the
debug element that will give us all the
frames we can then do what we wish with
that information we can either knock out
the like just get one of the frames and
print it or we could look at like the
running average or the min max or
whatever right so I guess that's what
I'm gonna try so if we take a look at
where that was happening did I actually
make a change it says I did yes okay so
in here after we do all of the updating
in debug and we're ready to print stuff
out so I should be able to do a format
strength here and I should be able to do
this you know based on whether or not we
have something in that slot so you know
what I can do is say whatever is in the
global table and I don't know if we've
referenced the global table out to a non
global table here it looks like not so
we'll just take the global table so if
we take the global table and we look at
the HUD function what we can do is do
get debug element that by ID like that
element from grid right and I think we
can get it out of here
so debug elements HUD element or if your
HUD function we can get the debug
element this way I think we have to pass
the debug State for that probably and
then if we have one of those we can
print it out right and so let me just do
that at the moment how do we print out
strings here probably this way
and I think that's probably all I'll do
for the moment I'm going to take a look
at the route info route info size thing
so I feel like for the route info route
info size thing so we have this tooltip
thing I feel like we basically want that
right for the most part so the draw
tooltips thing I feel like we want to
just expand that to be a thing that we
can use for everything so something like
something like a debug line buffer or
something like this right so that when
we look at the tooltips here we just
have instead of it being about tooltips
we just have like a line count in a line
text something like that so that we just
can make these as much as we want so we
have tooltips and hood and I feel like
that is probably the right thing to do I
don't know it seems like the most useful
so if we have those two then instead of
the route info we would just print into
one of these and so if we take a look at
where the tooltip stuff is which the
compiler will actually tell me because
it's going to not be able to find what
it used to be doing so this stuff right
here we have add tooltips and draw
tooltips we would really have instead
something like
and here these would be based on the
line buffer so instead of passing debug
state by itself and not saying which
line buffer to actually use we would say
give up line buffer buffer right and
then when you do that it would know
which one you wanted to use so it goes
ahead and does exactly all this stuff
here but now with the new format so
instead of tooltip text its line text
right and then it says okay debug state
tooltip count again that's buffer line
count and this is buffer line text right
then in here where we actually do this
result stuff can is ignore ball at the
moment because it's still gonna work a
sack the same way plain text again and
again all I'm doing is just trying to
reuse this code so we don't have two of
these sitting around at buffer up some
number of lines cuz that's just wasteful
and yeah no point to it so once we've
got that then the same thing would be
true for draw tooltips the only
difference is here when we call draw
tooltips now instead you can see we're
doing a like a particular layout here
and then the layout gets things put into
it what we can do is just pass in
different layout so that way we can pass
a different layout and print the route
tooltips into the route one in the mouse
went into the mouse one and everything
will be fine right so here we've got our
draw tooltips we need to be able to pass
the line buffer we probably need the
debug state as well though because we're
gonna need like the render group and
things like that yeah yeah because we
need all like the font metrics and all
that stuff right so what we're gonna do
here is anywhere that we were looking
for the tooltips before we're gonna
instead look for the buffer or line
count and then here we're going to use
the buffer line text like so and these
are going to be like draw line buffer
and line
something like that yeah
so let's keep going here at tool tip
it's gonna be add line debug state tool
tips oops and anywhere we see that it's
just going to be add lime chips just see
tooltips so that seems all pretty good
and now we've got let's see this stuff
doesn't matter
[Music]
name so this is actually the root group
of the of the debug system that you can
like pop down right which I guess we
want to keep although not really
I'm not sure how we want to do that
because the names can't have space in
them and we want potentially multiple
wines to be printed up there at the top
I mean I could create another group for
it I suppose and not do it this way but
I don't love that right meaning this
this thing is one of those little UI
elements that you can kind of put on the
screen and we could just put another one
up there like if we see a HUD function
then we could have another one up there
I suppose that's not awful telling how I
feel about that
I don't know how I feel about that I
want to keep these changes though there
we go and so this should still work
exactly the way it was before I'm just
gonna nerf this meeting our tooltips now
just go through that so we can do more
of those if we want to but I guess so
the way we could do this right is if you
look at what's happening with that root
node that we could just put another node
up there that actually is a its own UI
element and yeah I just don't know if I
just I'm not sure how I feel about it
like maybe that's good maybe that's not
good it's really hard to say but if you
take a look at what's going on here in
you know I don't even remember how this
works
because I thought you could like pull
these things off or something I don't
really remember how that stuff worked it
doesn't seem to look we used to have
something in there clone things I don't
even remember anyway so when we put on
this route group thing here that's just
printing a different name into that
buffer that you know was already set up
specifically for that so what we can do
here is just I guess take the the route
group that was placed there because you
can see here we can just add another
tree to the system that just works so
you know in theory if we wanted to we
could just say like okay yeah you know
[Music]
something like this or we just say all
right there's another one here called
functions that we use and I guess this
thing takes the count 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 9
don't ask me why so we can if we want to
just say like okay we're gonna have one
of these things I don't know why there's
the route group name and the route info
I guess like I don't know why we chose
to keep those in two different places
for some reason it doesn't make a whole
lot of sense but
we can't make another one of those for
you want to so the route group so I
guess that's roughly it right and that
would create a new one that we could
then add to whatever we want if that
makes sense so we can add another tree
here if we wanted to for example it
could be down at the bottom of the
screen instead or whatever we wanted to
do or on the other end right so we could
put that one at like right in the middle
let's say you don't really need the and
I think that would effectively add it to
the top as a separate drop-down kind of
a box which I guess is just more the way
we were doing things in the debug system
so that's fine with me so it's been a
long time to be doing anything here so I
don't really remember how we like to do
things in here or what the design was
but inside here when we print this out
if we print this out to the function in
fair-sized function that's right
debug state function info then in theory
should be okay I would think so make
sure that's correct
we set up this group correctly and we
added it but of course there's nothing
in it which I don't know to what extent
that makes the problem let me just
double check so when we try to add this
tree it's does not like it however I'm
not sure why cuz it should be okay
since there's nothing particularly weird
going on there I should compile in debug
mode as well so we can step in
double-check
so the problem here is that element is
no so when we go here to draw these
right you can see we're calling draw
trees when we're in draw trees we're
going through the trees and we get to
the one that we just placed right so it
goes into its group and it's got two
children here it looks like
so you can see that we did print out the
name properly right so there's the name
it's listed as having an actual group
let's step in here
so here's our first tree and this is the
regular tree the one we've had for a
while
and so I'm not sure how we got to there
from here because we should have had to
loop through this again so draw tree
link is doing that from here that's
making sense does it
because you can see oh that's the next I
was looking at so this actually is the
initial and sorry I was looking at the
next one alright so then it goes to do
the draw tree link what so what's our
layout look like here so this is this is
the actual new one right there's the
zero so the other one is at negative
right it's in the corner this one's in
the middle so looking at the next in
previous the next one that's our old one
that we used to have it's normal it's
looking at our group our group does have
a child listed in it which doesn't make
any sense because I have no idea I guess
it must be us or oh so it's just a it's
just a circularly linked list is long so
it doesn't have any children in it and
it just has this one name and it's got
no element so I'm wondering but it
shouldn't have an element there's
nothing there so what did we do for this
other tree right what does it do for an
element because it's got an element of
null as well but it doesn't seem to have
any problem with that right so I'm not
sure what it's doing that makes that'd
be fine
I guess it's if you don't have children
or something right so let's take a look
at that
so it says it does not have children so
it should skip that which it correctly
did and of course the link element is no
so I guess the reason it was working the
I guess the problem is that if you have
no element and no children we just never
handled that case I guess which doesn't
really make much sense cuz you would
think that would have to happen I guess
it never did it's a bit strange don't
you think I mean it seems like that
should be there but maybe I'm wrong
about that so in here right this this
part I'm not sure what we want to do I
mean maybe the smarter way to do it is
just in debug draw element right where
we would be using element like all this
stuff right to figure out what element
it is you know you want it to just do a
generic default print out here right I
mean that's all we really wanted it to
do
so in some sense right we kind of have
and I guess one one way to look at it
would be in here linked out elements
only used if we get past the has
children thing so it might be more
correct to say like hey look the has
children thing is going to be something
that we assume if you don't have an
element you must be a child thing you
must be something that can have children
right don't know where that
function is here we go so I don't really
know like has children and can have
children are kind of two different
things so I don't know the degree to
which it uses that it's like has
children is really the wrong way to look
at it it's really it's it's not has
children it should be can have children
right and to degree to which you can
have children is presumably predicated
entirely on whether or not you um are an
element or just a node in a tree that
doesn't have any corresponding element
that would be my assumption so it seems
like this should really be can have
children and can't have children is if
there's no element that seems more like
it I don't know and maybe I'm wrong
about that but looking through here that
seems a little more sane to me and I'm
not sure right but so let's go ahead and
switch back to release now
so now we correctly have this guy which
in theory you know we can do anything we
want with we've got to put some
information in here and just so does
this thing remember how this stuff is
supposed to work
I really felt there was some way to
clone these things there's even a clone
function there I don't know anyway so
once we've got this up here we can now
print out the information that we were
actually looking for and maybe we don't
want to print the whole thing out like
that because this is just the query name
and so we want to actually just use
maybe the proper name for this thing
which is you know it's not this unique
identifier sort of situation so in order
to do that inside the debug system where
we do that print out I believe once
we've got the debug element itself then
we actually already have that
information parsed out for us I think
let's see here so like we've got sort of
just this regular name parameter and I
think that might be more what we're
looking for right so maybe we just want
to print out just the name of the
function and that way we can see like
okay yeah it's just lighting test right
now if this thing is expanded or not we
should be able to like insert things
below it I would think so we could try
to do that and we'll see what happens if
we do that but at the moment what I what
I want to do too is I want to just print
out here the millisecond ink total time
and so inside the debug system when
we've got those profile nodes so it's
got duration and duration of children so
I don't know exactly how we're tracking
duration and duration of children but
assuming that duration is the total
duration that's the thing that we
actually want right we want to know like
the whole time that it took so what I'm
gonna do here is I'm gonna say like
let's print that information out let's
do a like a point Oh - I don't
no if we have a way to relate cycles to
milliseconds at the moment and it's
always a little bit dicey to do so
anyway so that might not be right so
what we could do instead is just print
out like the cycle count here in some
way that's relatively easy to met to
internalize let kilocycles
let's say or something like that or
megacycles gb megahertz so we could
print out like kilohertz or megahertz
something like this and that seems a
little bit more sane so maybe like
kilocycles I guess we could do well it's
not cycles per second so it wouldn't be
Hertz right it's not it's not per second
it's just her frame so yeah so we could
do something like that and and that
seems reasonable so let's try it so if I
print out this let's print out
kilocycles all right we could just get
so if I want to know what this is and me
you know maybe we also want to do like
the minimum one as well so let's say min
duration here equals 364 Max and I guess
we don't have that all right so we're
gonna do the loop over all of the frames
for this function that we've got and
we're gonna see which one is the most
the lowest and maybe we'll see which
one's the highest as well and we'll go
from there we could also take an average
if we wanted to so let's go ahead and
loop over that so proof the debug
profile node here let's get that out so
the HUD function profile node that's
under stored event get that in here and
so for the sort event so inside this
element we've got these frames and the
debug element frame has all of the
events for this right so we have to kind
of loop over each frame and then look at
the events so I'm not sure exactly how
we have this structured in here like how
we would know necessarily which one of
these we're looking at because I don't
remember exactly how we saw it functions
right but if we look through each of the
ones that we have here this is how many
events we would have and we can go
through them all and look at what the
event is or what the profile note is and
again I'm not sure how to know which one
of the two we have but presumably it's
it's specified in the debug type I'm
guessing
I mean that's my assumption anyway so
I'm assuming that in here it's like okay
depending on which one of these you are
that's gonna tell us that's going to
tell us which of the things you have
look whether you have events or profile
notes or whatever so I guess we don't
really know which of these we've got and
we may need to do some investigation
here right so let's actually do that
let's let's do this so we know we've
gotten this many frames and we know on
each one we have give a government frame
so for each one of these we now know
that we've got a particular frame of
data that we can look at and it's got
this many events in it for that frame
now for this we would expect to only
have one event per frame well two events
that they're open and closed I'm
assuming so let's just go ahead and loop
over those
like so so we can't look over all these
however these should have already been
collated as well so again I'm not 100%
sure we may want to look this up inside
the profile tree right because remember
the way that this worked was we have a
route profile element and so maybe we
need to look at this a little bit
differently but let's take a look here
so here's where we actually do this
profile elements
so you can see here the element that
you're viewing comes through here as
root element and it looks through each
of the frames each of the events and
those events are profile notes because
it's in the profile tree right so for us
I mean it's a little bit tricky because
yeah I don't know how to get directly to
the profile tree from just the debug
events because they're not necessarily
going to go into the profile tree I
don't think now maybe that's not true it
may be that functions that's where they
go right so let's take a look so
interesting enough that does look like
how that works so you can see here we
need to get element from event it's
doing it off of the debug profile group
here so maybe that is how that works I
don't know we're going to find out in a
second
let's see here just going to stub these
out
just so you can have like a min average
Max something like that
so if I have
I suppose these can just be D so I'm
gonna step into this line now and see
what those actually are
so inside debug and where we actually
groups where we actually look at it
inside here I'm going to go ahead and
just set a breakpoint so I can find out
what we're actually looking at why that
is there a reason this does it did it
not recompile what's going on there
did it uh-oh cuz we're still in snow
Marty we're still an ode to so it just
optimized out the whole loop which good
for it it doesn't do anything that's a
good a good idea I would have done that
too if I was an optimizer um so there's
no events for this thing okay
then there were just on that one time
that makes sense I guess actually I have
to let the frame buffer kind of fill up
here so once we have enough frames to
actually fill then I suppose we're okay
right right as this moves through and
fills up frames then when we stop here
we should start to see some so there are
some events in this particular frame
here's the most recent one
so if we take a look at what's on here
here's the event and the profile node
version
so let's see what does HUD functions
type evaluate - it's a begin block type
so a begin block
I mean it looks to me like that actually
will store the profile nerd into here
right so I feel like if we just look for
the end block that is what we want so I
think this does have the exact
information that we're looking for I
think don't quote me on that so I think
in here if we just say although I guess
we need to know where the end block is
for this begin block though so when we
come through here since it's this
element is actually in here this element
itself is the begin block right so I
don't know how that necessarily squares
with the way this works here
yes I don't think it gets one of those
right I think it should have one of
these so yeah this is probably inside
the profile node
I mean I think this is what we need so
let's try it and we'll see
so just inside here yeah
[Music]
just looking at the events I think would
tell us that now the question is per
frame if there's more than one event
what do we want to do about it
I assume we still just want to use the
duration either way but we'll see so
when we come through here and we look at
all the events I think we just want to
do debug profile node node equals frame
node and once we have this we can just
look at the duration of it and I think
that's all we really need so we can say
you know if the minimum duration is
greater than the node duration then the
mid duration equals the node duration if
the max duration is less than it equals
the total duration can just sum and we
want to keep it count
right and the count isn't there can't be
that many of them so now we know how
many we did so as far as figure out what
the current cycles are I that one I'm
not sure exactly how to do because I'm
assuming we would have to look at what
debug frame were actually on and so I
guess that's technically we do keep that
in here I think that's the viewing frame
index right so I think that actually is
in here that is in here so I think if we
just said like okay you know if the
frame index listed in the node is the
one we're looking at
so essentially we say all right if the
event frame index you know equals
whatever the framer knows they're
reviewing then I think that the curd
duration is set there don't quote me on
that because I don't know but let's just
say that's true so then I think all we
really have to do is just multiplied
these here max min and the average we
don't actually keep we only keep the
total so we want to do 2 divided by 1000
times the total count which is how many
of these like we summed up right so yeah
I think that's about right the only
thing is you know it's not this is not
100% accurate here because we really
should summer right this should really
be summarized outside I think because
we're looking for frames so let's say
the thing hits multiple times for frame
I think really what we want to do here
is some the duration this way so I think
we want to do like duration equals zero
then we want to drape in plus equals you
know event duration or sorry note
duration like that and then this
actually just wants to work off of that
value so that way it's like okay if this
hit many times in this frame we're it's
gonna sum them all together and get the
frame the total time for this frame and
then we're gonna work off of that
is it frame frame index what is how does
this actually work
so in here
inside the profile node we don't know it
inside the event we do know it and so
yeah I'm not sure I'll be honest I don't
really know why we store a frame index
here necessarily because it seems like
you wouldn't really need to do that
since it's here where that would make
the most sense so I don't quite get that
like that doesn't that doesn't make a
lot of sense to me it seems like the
frame index so who who looks at that and
why
so
so you're telling me that that is
literally not used
okay well my intuition was right about
it I guess I'm not sure how that still
stays in there but I guess it shouldn't
be in there I guess I'm right about that
well good so I assume then is it safe to
say that this frame index here I mean
that doesn't necessarily line up I mean
does it or doesn't it line up with
whichever frame were actually viewing
right so these events in here you know
they're stored in this array does that
array necessarily correspond with the
ordinals right or are the ordinals
unrelated to that and I'm not sure so
you know we could do this and just
assume that they are right just say oh
you know which which one of these are
you looking at but that may not actually
be accurate
not that we super care because that's
not actually a value we particularly
care about necessarily but that is
roughly what we want to know right all
right so let's take a look here
[Music]
all right so we should be able to get
some print out now
and I don't know whether we want to go
from oldest to newest so this is a
singly linked or list right and it goes
in one particular direction so if you
take a look at
it's got oldest event two most recent
event and then it's got the next pointer
and so the question is which of these
two does it add on to right oops so
looking through here when this gets
added on so you can see that it's
chained off of the most recent so it
starts at oldest in ghost
it goes from oldest to newest so now
we're printing out the min the max and
the average as you would expect the zero
value is in there until we roll the
counter because there's always going to
be frames in there that didn't have this
getting called until we fill up that
entire array so I think that's mostly
all we wanted at this point so if I go
back and switch us to the optimized bill
this would give us the actual cycle
count that we are taking in order to
fill the lighting right so here's our
sort of mid max average print out it
doesn't look right though so you can see
here like the average value can't be
higher than the max but it is right so
that's a little busted so not quite
there yet get in there but not quite
there yet all right so let's go fix that
oops
alright so on here we're gonna loop over
all the frames we're gonna sum up the
duration which i think is now correctly
adding all of the times that we've seen
this thing get profiled right and then
we're gonna produce some values here
based off of what we've got so we're
gonna sum the total count and the total
duration like so and then we're going to
print cur min okay well that's probably
the most of it alright so once this
stabilizes and what we could do is we
could drop zero values so what we could
do is say look if in here if frame
oldest event so you know don't don't
actually count it if there's no samples
on a frame just just leave those out so
just just only sample things only sample
only tell me about frames when we
actually called this function so that'll
get rid of the start up and also we
found a particular frame it didn't get
called it just won't profile that one
right so taking a look here this this
looks like what we want right so we've
got the average we've got the minimum so
that's the fastest we can be we've got
the max which is the slowest we can be
and we've got our average so you can see
here that to compute the lighting
according to this if it's accurate it's
taking about 61 million cycles right and
that's you know that's still probably
way too much you know I'm saying
so our job here is to get that number
down right we want to get that below 61
million for sure
and what I'd also like to do is you know
yet now take a look at these here so you
can see that we've got the this some of
these stats that we were looking at here
where we were trying to say okay how
many you know what's the right balance
here for partitions forecasts or leaves
forecast or whatever and I sort of
played with this value and we were
looking at this here and so now we can
sort of see more specifically if we look
at split box so with the source count
here if we want to change what that
number is right we can look and say okay
it's you know it's a certain value you
can see how the value changes as we go
what the like the minimum is for example
or something like that because the
minimum is a good indication of like
just how fast the thing can be it's like
never gonna go any faster than the
minimum right um I'd also like to get
out of the business of having this do
that crashes on strings so I wonder if
we can also make that not happen we'll
see when we get there but so if we take
a look at what happens here you can see
if we change it up to eight it actually
isn't flattering for us right this
actually went up and our our average
appears to have gone up as well right so
it doesn't appear like flipping that up
to a higher value really does anything
particularly good for us you know arm in
arm in definitely went up you know maybe
another in-between value is better I
don't know hard to say but you can see
like it goes down right so so as we sort
of reduced that number
it was definitely going down there right
so there's a you know sort of sitting at
55 average of 63
let's see if we drop it way down so then
we kind of go back up a little but
actually no that's it's kind of hard to
say right it's a little bit variable now
it looks like it's it's almost more
variable and that's where we're testing
just a lot of partitions forecast a lot
more right but either way so just
looking at it in general what you can
sort of say though regardless of
anything else is there's not a lot of
play in there right it's not like
changing that number gets us to X or
something no matter how we might fine
tune it
we can probably tank the frame rate by
making it very high potentially maybe
but you know even that we really can't
so so putting a lot of leaves in there
really doesn't affect it as much as you
might think so let's keep cranking it up
so yeah I mean you know it's it's not
nothing but it's just it's not as as
dramatic as you might like and so I
think one of the things that maybe that
tells us a little bit is that which we
kind of already know is that our spatial
partition is not fantastic right which
we kind of already knew but you know in
theory modifying the spatial partition
that much we would like it to have a
pretty dramatic effect on the frame on
the total cycle count and you know maybe
at the moment it's maybe not having as
much as we would like but it did you
know did have some you know going from
54 to like 80 or whatever that you know
it's getting closer to doubling right
that's so that's something I don't want
to be too harsh on it all right
so looking at those numbers and again
one of the nice things here is so you
can see as we start to do this stuff
right those numbers really don't change
a lot and that's what we wanted so we
can sort of take that out of the
equation so that instead of looking at
very variable millisecond times that can
change a lot depending on like what
we've got open here and how much we're
drawing and all this other stuff you can
see there's like it's going it's a very
wide range it's it's a there's a whole
range of ten milliseconds it can run
through there these values remain much
more stable and so that's the reason I
wanted that so that we're not sort of
chasing a phony thing up here that's
going to be variable and weird this way
we can actually see the information more
clearly as we're testing all right so
there's a couple different things about
this that's worth looking at so the
first thing that's worth noticing is
like so if we take a look at our raycast
function you know probably if we're
gonna stick with box a a B based testing
one of the things that we're not doing
right now is is we're not really doing
that in a very good fashion so if you
look at how we're doing it we're
actually still looping over axes so
first of all like right we could unroll
this certainly and just have all three
cases sort of stacked on top of each
other so that there is no loop because
we don't know to what extent the
compiler is able to understand that
particularly well and it may be that we
can help it out quite a bit and do less
work if we were doing the the
intersection more cleanly also we don't
really know if we're if that's a
particularly smart way to do that
intersection so for example it's it's
actually very simple to do stuff like
closest point on an a a b2 and to am
closest point on an a B to a point is a
much simpler function to do than Ray
intersection and so I don't know if
there's also a similarly easier way to
do the Ray intersection than what we're
doing right now but my guess is there
probably is
so it might make sense to look up some
good fast AAB test and just see what
people have done that are that are
particularly good
Blucher coordinates oh yes
so yeah I mean
it seems like going this route could
simplify things quite a bit let's see
what this fellow says here it's a basic
Ranger section
so you can actually see going through
time here we are the old school right
every face of the AAB t-test right which
is the old way and you can see them
going through different ones here which
we couldn't actually we you know we
haven't done but this does seem like a
pretty nice one if this actually is a
good way to test we'll have to work
through the math here but looking at
this since all of these are ORS we
should be able to do this SSE wise
pretty well as as well right you stack
them up and then just do one check at
the end to so it should be pretty easy
and since we are testing the Ray against
multiple boxes it does line up well with
what they were anticipating here right
which is that you pre compute stuff for
your array which is this information
here so the X Y Z IJ K starting
directions tough thing gets expanded out
into a bunch of things like the inverses
of the Ray directions and some
information regarding the cross like
cross terms of those and so yeah
so that seems pretty good as well so we
definitely could do something like this
and it looks like we would get a massive
speed up from that because we're just
kind of being really dumb right now with
how we're doing it so just cleaning that
up could be a pretty reasonable approach
and so what you can see let's without
actually going through the paper yet so
what you can see here is what they're
suggesting at first is just saying like
okay so let's suppose that we've got all
of these planes let's just clip the Ray
to the planes first and then we'll just
see if we have anything left was
essentially what they were saying so
what they said is like alright first
flip it to this plane which would give
you here right then clip it you know to
that plane which would give you here and
you'd that would be further so you would
throw that clip out then clip it to this
plane which would give you here again
further you'd throw it out then clip it
to this plane right which is I guess
well that would give you like here
so I'm not sure how they deal with that
part of it I'm not sure how they deal
with the fact that if you clip it to
well I guess what you're trying to say
there is that you always take the most
interior value of the two clippings so
when you clip to here and here so now
I'm not sure how you deal with that
because they're not really taking it
yeah I don't know we're gonna have to
read this because they're not really
checking them together with each other
how was this person this person's was
not as simplified
because you can't see you know for any
individual clipping pair you're gonna
get a range that is inside that pair so
I assume you first have to use the pair
you have to respect the pair's
in in and of themselves meaning you have
to you have to find the min and the max
for these two and then you can clip
those that min and that max to here and
here and then it would shrink it in
right I think you've got to do it that
way and it does look like yeah so that
is what they're doing so they just say
like look okay let's produce a pair and
then we'll clip that pair to the next
pair so we just keep moving it in that
makes sense and so then you just say
look whichever the furthest one away was
and the closest one I'm gonna narrow in
that only that much I'm not gonna ever
accidentally flip those two which would
produce the case that I was talking
about before where you're like I don't
know what to do with this one right so
you wouldn't have that problem because
you're comparing this one and this one
and then you take this one of those two
right so you produced this two here then
you'd get these two and then finally
you'd have the ones three dimensions so
yeah so this seems probably it's pretty
these these are pretty darn similar
actually but this looks a little worse
because it's got a lot of min maxing in
there
whereas this looks like they've got it
down to actually no min maxing right
it's just zero tests so basically you
just compute this value this value this
value this value this value this value
and then you just do tests against zero
or those in with a few greater than or
less than tests and then you're done
now one of the problems with this I
suppose is that it doesn't tell you
where so one problem is from this we'd
have to figure out whether that gives
you enough information to determine the
hit because that may be a reason like to
prefer one that looks like this because
one that looks like this would tell us
where since we know that the team in
value or the T Max value depending on
which one if they're greater than zero
right would tell us nice suppose it's
always the T million min value because
if the T min value was less than zero
the T max value was greater than zero
that would mean we started inside the
box and so we would take the other
branch so it's always the team in in the
actual case for processing an
intersection it would always be the T
min so that should be able to speed us
up quite a bit beyond just just because
this is a crap function at this point I
mean it's not that much stuff in it but
this loop needs to go and so if we were
to use a more simplified method of
checking then we could get rid of this
and we would be out of this business
right so I think that's probably what we
want to do here I guess we'll do that
tomorrow because we're already over time
and we'll see if we can't get those
numbers down and then we can try to
improve our our spatial Harkey as well
but at the moment it seems like that
would be a great thing for us right
because we can definitely I can
definitely write it this way I already
know how to write it this way we're
gonna have to read more closely because
you know just looking at this I have no
idea what that tells us right I just
have to take his word for it so yeah I
would have to take
well it's not his word I guess I would
have to take Iceman Grosch Muller and
Magners word for it oh my god so we need
to have to take a look at this one and
see and understand what this is actually
doing it looks like it would potentially
be faster than what the other one is
suggesting if you actually get the
intersection T from it if you don't get
the intersection T from it then I don't
know that it's actually that useful
because we actually need that
information
um oops I did not mean to go to the
bibliography how do I go back I can't
okay they don't seem to really talk
about this in here
so I guess what I would say is this
sounds less good because they are
already saying and assuming they
understand their own routine they're
essentially saying that they don't have
the computation necessary to determine
where the actual intersection occurred
so it may be that we just want to do a
tea based test and this is pretty
straightforward it's just the series of
plane tests right so we can implement
this one really simply and it would
still be an improvement over what we've
got now and it doesn't look like it's
quite as good in terms of the minimum
number of tests to see whether we
intersect but because we really do need
to know the T value and you're
implicitly computing that directly in
this anyway that just seems like a
better plan right
and it's not like it's that much more
work than the other one
it looks pretty comparable right this is
only doing two backsies so you you have
to add you know third in there and at
this one this becomes another like this
comes become stacked right so you're
gonna do another another round of all of
this but it still seems pretty
reasonable and it does the same sort of
stuff as the other one meaning that it
does the inverses precomputed which also
seems like you know pretty reasonable so
yeah
I am contempt to write that now because
the gist gets rid of a lot of this let's
just see how long it would take so let's
suppose that we wanted to have this part
here
so let's suppose in here we just said
okay we know we want to do the inverses
first right because the reason for that
is is simply that if simply that we want
to avoid that divide we want to just be
able to do a multiply if that makes
sense and all you know we can we can
check ahead of time to see for the zeros
and if so we can just make this zero out
right I think that makes sense so we
should be okay let's let's take a look
and they talk about that a little bit
here right they basically say like okay
we're component direction is zero the
there'll be infinite which will make the
team in the team acts do what we want
them to do right so in theory we should
be okay with that and off we go so all
right so let's suppose we want to do
that first I need to create one of these
guys one of our v3 for X's which is
going to be our inverse ray direction
and that's just going to be 1.0 divided
by the actual rate erection we still
call it r ad for X that was just rady
yeah right so we want to produce our
inverse and we can just trust the
that'll produce an infinite infinity in
the case that we divide by zero here
because this is going to happen on the
Sindhi unit which should have the which
should have the exceptions turned off
for divided by zero if it doesn't want
to deal with that we can test that
so once we pre-compute that this stuff
is going to happen essentially the same
way that it was before we have to
compute the I mean we have to pull the
box out of the stack and look at the
various children that it has and then we
still need to compute the same stuff we
need to know whether or not we're going
to you know descend into the box and so
on so we're gonna start a pure though
and you can see what we want to compute
here is we want to compute the X the we
want to compute the x and y and z
intersections for those slabs in T right
so let's just work that out ourselves
instead of reading the paper because the
paper told us what to do so I shouldn't
say paper the website publication tell
us what to do but let's make sure we
could do it for ourselves right because
it's very simple and we've already done
this before so if we want to do a pair
of these two things here so let's
suppose that we've got our Ray so we've
already done ray intersecting plane and
we know that this is a plane right and
we know what furthermore we know exactly
what kind of plane it is so let's say
this is an X plane an X plane is going
to have a normal which is very
structured right it's going to have
negative 1 0 0 as a normal or 1 0 0 as a
normal so this is negative 1 0 0 and
this is 1 0 0 so then when we go to
actually determine the intersection in
question here all we're really talking
about is where these things are we know
that that's the case but we also know
that there's a specific location where
these are as well right and we have to
deal with that problem too ok so we have
a ray origin and we have our ray
direction and we know that what we're
talking about here for an equation is we
have a ray origin plus T times the
Radian
and what we want to know is when will
this end up producing a zero value for
this plane right so we want to know if
this value right here is our new point
that we're talking about we want to know
when we could dot it with this normal
right
and produce zero that would only be true
if was on the zero itself so we really
also want a displacement there so we
want to know we want to know a
particular value here which is the
location of the plane right so I don't
know what we want to call that value but
that's our constant right so we're
really talking about this we're saying
that it you know if we add a constant to
this thing then we're going to get zero
we want to know where that's going to be
true and if you look at what this ends
up being when you write it out you're
going to get C plus the normal being
negative one zero zero right this dot
product is going to be a pretty
straightforward dot product it's going
to get rid of because remember a dot
product is going to be you know NX we'll
call this little thing right here
we'll just call this whole thing capital
R so it's going to be our X plus and yr
y plus and Z or Z right right now and
that dot product in there but rather
than having to deal with that we just
look at the fact that it's an a a being
we say well these are gone right because
the only thing in here is that X
component and it's either negative or
positive one so the only things that
change are the C and whether this is
negative or positive one so really what
we're looking at is a C plus NX times
this here right our 0x plus T our DX
right that's all we're talking about
equals zero and that's the entirety of
what we need to compute for that now
furthermore you know when we solve this
the NX only changes between
negative and positive one as well so
that's even simpler so we we end up with
a c NX r 0x + t + XR DX equals 0 and if
we factor for T here we would just get n
we move this to their side negative C
negative NX r 0x
/ this term here which divides through
right NX r DX right now what an
interesting things here is in this case
we also kind of know I'm tempted right
to just say well you know I I would
probably left to my own devices maybe
even say let's multiply this by NX / NX
right we know this is positive or
negative 1 so if we did that we would
end up with negative n XC minus r0 x
over our DX I think the reason for that
is so these become squared and since we
know this is either positive 1 or
negative 1 if we square it we just get 1
so I think this is really all we need to
do would be my guess I think it would
just be negative n XC minus r0 x / r DX
i think so
this value you can pre-compute for the
box
and the other two values are just the
Ray origin in the right direction
I mean that's what it looks like to me
anyway so it looks like you would just
have
yeah and that looks like exactly what
they do
now what I'm not sure about there is why
the sign is the same for the TX 1 and
the TX 2
I guess because you don't care so I
suppose that's another way of looking at
this right I guess you could say you
don't care which way the normals facing
so why bother doing that part that I did
why bother saying that like why not just
say they both point that direction
cuz who cares right and that does seem
pretty smart because then are actually
just both point that directions so it's
just both ones so then really you don't
need that value at all you really don't
need that part at all so that seems even
smarter I did the squared thing but
that's it looks like the other way is
even better right so if we did do it
that way so if we did say okay what we
want to do here is we want to do you
know the C value plus normal transpose
rate origin plus T rate Direction equals
zero if we know that this is literally
always just one zero zero no matter
which one we're doing right then what we
can do is just say well okay if they're
always pointing in that direction then
when we hit the plane all we really need
to know is that we've got C + bar zero X
because again we're just picking out the
X component now plus T times our DX
right equals zero and then we just need
to solve for T so T equals negative C
negative R zero x over our DX and in
this case if we wanted to simplify from
the two minuses we could multiply it and
say C + R zero x over negative r DX like
so right
so the other thing we could do is just
store see negated and that actually
makes a lot of sense too because if we
assume that these were actually the min
and the max values they would appear on
this side right so we would actually
have this let's say right or constant
and at that point again even easier our
0x plus t rd x equals c and then when
you saw if you get T equals C minus r0 x
over R DX so yeah I mean that's pretty
great and pretty straightforward and
then C is just the minimum than the max
on the x axis I love it I'm a fan yes
good so I feel like we understand that
pretty well it's really simple it
matches what they've got there and it
makes perfect sense
right so I feel like that's pretty easy
to do all we have to do is for our boxes
we need to produce the actual mins and
maxes now unfortunately we are not
storing in a min max form so we may want
to change the story to MU next more now
that we know that that's will be
intersecting against but it's pretty
easy to produce min max temporarily with
just one op so you know we can play with
whether we want to get rid of this act
these two extraneous operations here but
in the meantime it's just plus the
radius and minus the radius right so
we've got the
we can get the Box mint-in-box max
really easily it's just it's unclear we
may want to we may want to get rid of
that by storing them in min max form
that's all we'll see if that could be
costly or it could be trivial probably
is trivial so we probably want to do it
so once we have the Box min max then we
can just do the exact intersection
testing on it so again we know what it
is here it's just the min well we'll go
ahead and do it and we do it for it we
can do it for all axes at the same time
I believe it's I don't don't think
there's any problem with that so what we
would want to do here is an F through
two for X which is our T value for the
Box min and then our T value for the Box
Max and it's just going to be that so
we've got our box min - are our Ray
origin right that's our Ray origin and
then we want to do the divide by the by
the rate erection
and that would actually produce and I
guess this is still a v3 right that
actually produces the XY and Z box mins
all at once because remember we can just
do them that way there's no real reason
not to it's not any faster it's still
doing all of them it's just we've got a
utility class that does three at a time
right so so this would produce all of
them and then our question is just
processing those right so now we need to
do is we need to take our team in and
Tmax and actually produce a single one
from that right now this parts a little
bit squirrely here so we now need to
think about how we're gonna do this so
first of all we have our x-men in our
xmax
which is you know the bounds for the X
so we need to like shrink down shrink
down shrink down I think is the way we
want to do it I'd have to think it
through but you know it would be
something like okay you know the f32
forex team in here we need to take a
minimum of
tbox min X
well let's think about this for a second
actually let's go back to our little
drawing here so once I produced my
intersection I have a minimum and a
maximum value but really I don't know
which those are right because I don't
know if the Ray was pointing backwards
or pointing forwards in reference to the
mins and maxes so this is my box min and
my box max but the teaming and t max
might go in either order so if we were
to do it sorry if we were to do it fully
sequentially and we can probably opt by
this and we'll look I'm sure they've
done that so we can go look with a
device want us to go through it once
first to make sure we understand it
right I never like to implant something
I don't understand
some maybe random number generators
anyway
so if we take a look at what happens
here right what we would need to do
first is figure out which was the min
and which was the max right so to start
off with we might say okay the t-box min
X and the tea box
max X we actually need to take the
minimum of those two to figure out which
one we actually have
so that would tell us right which the
minimum is in which the maximum is there
and we probably just need to do that the
whole way round right so now we would
have a team in in a team ax value that
would actually be proper for each of
them it would actually be the balance
for each of them and then we could
successively narrow right so then we
could say like okay then we've got an f3
2 for X and maybe this is like something
like that and then we could say for each
of the axes we will successively narrow
so we would say okay whatever the team
in 3 is I need to take the minimum well
okay so I now know from each of these
what our minimum and Max was each to
mention we then need to push them the
opposite direction right so previously
what we were doing is saying let's take
the min and max so that we sort which
ones we have here right so that we know
that they go in order and then what we
need to do is we actually need to push
them as far in as possible so if pre you
know if these are our intersections
along the Ray then these are our two
maxes these are our 2 mins
these are our two maxes right we need to
take the maximum minimum to get this and
the minimum maximum to get that right so
here we actually need to take Max's of
the mins as weird as that sounds and
here we would need to take minimums of
the maximums
and that way we now would know what our
actual bracket was so now what we would
say I think is our t max value should
tell us whether we're whether this box
is rejectable right so I should then be
able to say if any if any are true so
let me go ahead and do the test here so
we sexually have after 2 0 F 32 for X so
if our T max is greater than zero we
know that the box isn't entirely behind
the red now we may be starting out
inside of it so that we need to know but
we're not in it's not entirely behind us
and that's important
so if anything's true in max paths then
we know we actually can process this ray
this box if not then we don't care about
it at all because we can't it literally
can't be hit by us it's behind us we
can't see it from this Ray ok so then
this actually needs to put B up above
probably to be honest with you so this
probably needs to get that pushed up
here too actually if we're going to try
and count that statistic properly so if
we go ahead and take a look at at this
any true here then what we can do is we
can figure out whether we're in the box
by now computing whether the min passes
right so if the min passes that's if
mean is out in front as well if I mean
there's also inference that means we
actually hit the
if means behind us but max was in front
of us then we're actually inside the box
and then we need would need to descend
into it for child testing right so yeah
so if any is true in the max pass or I
guess and in the min pass we don't
because if we know that max passed and a
min passed then we know that the min and
the max both passed on that one it would
not be possible for the T max to have
passed on a different Lane than the min
pass min pass has to pass at least on
the same rate the lane as the max pass
if any do right so once we're we know
that is in box is just if any are true
if the child so let me get rid of this
here right so once we know min pass if
any true in min pass then we know we're
in then we know we're in the box right
and so we can actually just do that in
here otherwise we got to do the rest of
the work right so I'm pretty sure that's
right so we just test to see if any of
the Max passes are true or then we need
to look at this box if any of the min
passes are true as well then we are
inside I'm sorry I have that backwards
we need to know the IaaS so I've got
that I've got that backwards sorry it's
not min pass its min fail basically and
we do need to check to see if they're
the same
yeah I take it back I take it back
so we do need to do
oops we do need to do this check and
really I guess the we don't even really
need to produce quite this so we just do
max pass and I think that's really all
we need to do here so we basically say
okay if the max pass is on the same Lane
as something that was also the teaming
was less than zero then we started out
inside the box and we have to consider
the box if we can write for starting out
inside a box that's a that's a leaf box
I don't think we do anything about that
specifically that's kind of just an
error to cast from inside the leaf box
but you know I guess we'll have to deal
with that a little bit separately but
anyway if we take a look in here at the
rest of this stuff so this stuff all
goes away now and hopefully that's why
we're hoping for a speed improvement
using this technique obviously what we
want to do here is now skip right down
to this part which we should be able to
work out just from the key values that
we actually already have right so what
we should be able to do now is we should
be able to say okay the T value that we
care about is updating is out here
somewhere this right here so this tier a
value that's what we actually need to
update correctly and so you can see us
doing the Select on it here so we have
to produce whatever the t hid value is
and it's gonna be T min basically for
anyone who actually hits so what we have
to do here is just figure out who
actually does hit and since we've
already produced the team in all we
really have to do is know which ones
aren't flipped right so really all we
have to do here because here we've
checked greater than zero and less than
zero right
here we have to check T valid
essentially and what that would be is if
the T min is less than the T Max if the
team in isn't less than the T max that
means that we didn't hit that lane right
so T valid is our Max for who hit and T
is our actual value that we care about
so we need to know that the T is valid
and then what we need to know is what
the actual tear a is and to do that we
well I guess that's just the team in
right so the mask value that we're going
to pick here again is just that T valid
oh no it's not and they've got to be
closer so the other thing we have to do
here to produce our masked value is say
we need the T to be valid and we need
the team in to be less than the one we
already had so if it's not a closer hit
we need to throw it out right close
enough is presumably got to be
calculated the same way which is this
and we can change this to be close
enough so and just pull that out so that
both sides will use the same value and
that can be tested the same way right
so that'll figure that out and that will
decide whether or not we have to descend
or not now we can in theory collapse
these two a little bit so since these
are pretty simple checks we could do
something like say look let's just do
these like this and then we could say
like look if it has a child count and
either of these two things are true
[Music]
then we need to make that scalar
decision otherwise then we can go ahead
and look to see if we need to deal with
this branch right uh so yeah I think
that's roughly what we need and again
this divide can be changed to a x pre
inverting the Ray which we can you know
let's make a note of and let's go from
there remember what we specify for this
to load you don't need that yet
we got to do something about the fact
that we don't do a Hadamard product like
that yet
see what else we got here though and we
don't have min max so we've got to add
those is that it oh right I meant
regular ant it's confusing because these
are scalar so they have to be and the
regular kind well they don't have to be
I suppose this is there was that
all right so yeah so now we kind of have
some issues to address here and this I
guess will be a little bit more
troublesome here so the problem is we
have to be able to return which of these
we were actually dealing with which side
of the box we hit because right we need
to know how to use the color information
that comes back and that's actually
pretty tough to determine because that
information got lost in here because we
don't know which min value we actually
used right we have them all but we don't
know whether we used the X the Y or the
Z and we don't know which one of those
it was so really trying to back out that
information is pretty tough to tell so
that's going to be a pretty big
challenge actually yeah
Lake
I mean the only way we can really do it
I think is seeing where the value we
ended up with actually came from
I'm not sure how else to do it right
like in other words at the end we've got
a team in value and the team in value
that we've that we end up with he's
going to be from one of these mins and
Max's right it will be tea box min X Y
or Z or tea box max X Y or Z right and
which one of those six it is tells us
which face it is but testing against all
of those is kind of expensive now we
only have to do it when we actually
record a hit so that's a plus but it's
still nasty and I'm not sure how to do
it in any particularly good way because
it's kind of just this nasty select
operation that just like literally has
to check right
so I mean
you
yeah I mean I really don't know what the
what the right way to do that is but if
you imagine what this is going to look
like it's really bad so it's like so
these are the possible values that we
could have ended up with after doing the
mins and maxes and so essentially what
you're doing is this so this will
produce the mask value and you just got
a byte six comparisons right I don't
know any other way you would do it from
that the the price of getting a cheap
check is that you don't end up with the
information at the end right so then you
would have to do a thing that says well
box surface index right is going to be
an end of the loaded value that
corresponds with whichever you know when
you're looking at and you just got to do
them all I don't know any other way to
do it so you'd start out and say well
okay the Box surface index I guess we'll
start out we don't really need to check
this one because if the X if the minimum
x value I don't know how we ordered our
faces exactly so let's just check
where's that box side thing
I want the function that actually gets
get box surface is the function I
actually want this one
[Music]
so for each of these the normal equals
its spacing to negative x positive x
negative Y positive y negative Z
positive Z so I'm pretty sure it's just
this right so just the minimum X is T
min maximum X 2 T min is if it would be
1 and we just were in the you know the
ones that pass right whichever one
passes is the one that carries the day
in any particular lane and yeah it's
ugly
right that's 1 2 3 4 5 6 verses 4 to 2
and the load so it's you know you're
talking about something nasty like 1 2 3
6 like it's like 18 operations or
something just just to recover that one
piece of information that that gets
destroyed in the process right and
enough to go so yeah on the plus side I
think that is it so that would be the
entirety of the P it's still probably a
lot better than our old routine
I think it's hard to say right who knows
how good the compiler was at dealing
with this I'm not sure but I feel like
chances are that this this is if once we
debug it will be faster and we can test
them against each other certainly so
let's take a look and just go ahead and
finish off the implementation of the
cindy side of things so we need mins and
maxes here but that's pretty simple so
let's take a look if we have an A and a
B
and we want to do them in how do we do
that
so it should be pretty straightforward
right all we should really have to do is
do the actual min max calls because I
believe they both exist in sse2 so in
theory that's all we have to do for the
men in the Max's and then to do them in
the max for the v3 4x that should be
really straightforward as well because
that's just going to call the other ones
right so for example this could be made
like this and I think that's all there
is to it so the only thing that we're
left with is the divide and so for the
divide I guess we probably since its
vector divide doesn't really make a
whole lot of sense
it's really a Hadamard product here with
the inverse right it's kind of what
we're talking about we're doing straight
across rows so we can implement be the
divide operator I just don't know that
we necessarily want to I mean it can't
really mean anything else so maybe we
just do you know who knows but here's
what it would be right it just be scalar
Lane divide oh whoops
that's 4x I don't want that I want the
3x
so the v3 for X if I just take operator
plus here operator divide just divide
the lanes than that then you have that
right so yeah so we can run that now but
you know we would assume we get some
bugs in there I don't know it's hard to
say
although honestly that looks pretty
similar so maybe we don't have any bugs
in there but you can see that it
definitely got faster right it's not
like order of magnitude faster
but before we were quite a bit higher
here we were more like 50 60 and now
we're down below 40 right and so it's
not nothing right and we can double
check that because we left both routines
and so we can try compiling different
ones in and out interchangeably look
here so we're at 38 min there yeah and
that that jumps up to like 60 so the
minimum is yeah it's at least 20 million
cycles hot you know saved which is great
right which is very good so I'd say
that's a win across the board it's still
not clear to me that we're doing it
right be the way that we should be
because again having to produce this box
surface index is kind of expensive there
so that's just kind of a nasty side
effect
and I'm not sure there's a lot we can do
about that we could take a look at what
happens if we pre compute the REA so if
we wanted to do a straight across
multiply there we can and that just
looks like V 3 for X in brady equals and
we had this up here before i coups this
just looks like the the end of the
inversion of the right direction like so
right of course I don't know we have to
do this
yeah so you know this is what's the men
running apps running at 37 642 hey you
know it's it's a little better right but
it's really not particularly noticeable
you know that's not really gonna make a
huge difference I guess I so the other
thing is that we don't really know here
right we don't really know the breakdown
of what's taking what time you know if
this stuff here was important we could
switch to min Max and that would be
something interesting we can also get
rid of some of our of our checks here we
don't know how expensive those are so
you know for example we could take a
look at what happens if we get rid of
some of these checks so you know here's
the 36 784 minimum right if I get rid of
that check you know it's actually kind
of expensive right to store the
statistics so we know the stats are a
little bit annoying potentially although
checking things like that can be kind of
if you're if they're that tiny can be
kind of hard to do because you don't
know if maybe just the alignment of the
code changed or something and it's not
really the gathering of the scat that
was important it was like the way that
it changed where things lined up on the
stack or things like this right so hard
to say but anyway you can sort of see
where we're going with this
yeah and off we go
we can also see what happens nuking this
assert you know to what degree that
affects the runtime
again not too much so there we go so now
that we have that information yet we're
also I don't know what's going on here
exactly it's around freshmen so now that
we have that information and we can also
go back and look at the profile now to
look at the threads you can see that
that definitely took these down a bit
right and we're spending a lot more time
up in here so I think you know our
lighting is actually at least the the
computation part is actually doing a
pretty good job of staying within a
reasonable frame budget so that's pretty
nice as well so one of the interesting
things too is we can see too how elastic
this is at this point because we can
always for one of the things you can do
for optimization right is we can just
crank the stress on the system up way
higher and and you know use that as
another way of figuring out how our
speed is doing right so if I crank that
up we should tank our frame rate
massively right and so now we should see
a lot more yeah we would see a lot more
variability I'm sorry a lot more
variation from small changes because
since we're doing a lot more in theory
right that would have more of an effect
hard to say anyway still pretty cool
that we've got still interactive rates
with that many rays per point being
sampled but you know another thing again
like I was saying I think we need to
look a little more closely because I
think we still have some bugs with how
things are getting recorded it's only
supposed to be able to change up to a
tenth and some of these still flicker
even with 256 rays cast and a framerate
this slow it's just I think we've got
some other bugs in there so we've got to
do a little bit more work on on that
part but anyway I'm happy with that so
let's go ahead and
- a brief Q&amp;A here I'm happy with that
new way of doing the box testing there
surface index lookup table move math
team in equals box min and just choose
the first bit set in the return from the
move max for which index well but you
have to do that twice right 40 minute
and T box Max and then two table lookups
and then and then you have to do a bit
scan right well though I guess what
you're saying is use surface index
lookup table to pick the first bit set
well no cuz move mask does it by byte
right so you're actually gonna you
couldn't really use a table for that
could you because the table have to be
too big
am I wrong about that we would get an
improve switch all the V 3 2 V 3 4 X
with a little bit value into the M 128
each frame potentially yes but I don't
know usually you want to minimize the
memory traffic so I don't know that that
would actually help
yeah I don't think a 256 entry lookup
table is such a good idea there though
and are you sure that it would be I
don't actually know that that's true
log scale book could you recap how we
retain the state of the debug UI between
frames this state of the debug UI it's
just it's actually stored in an actual
hierarchy in memory
yeah so what I'm trying to say here
about the move mass construction right
is that we have we have four bytes four
bytes four bytes four bytes so it's
gonna put four ones in four ones into
the result for every one true we
actually have June I'm saying
so the lookup table for the move mask is
gonna be huge
if you don't first condense it right
because it's byte wise and there's 16
bytes so it's gonna be 16 bits worth of
data isn't it
Gina I'm saying it ain't gonna be 256
bits unless you first you'd have to
first opt to condense it you seen him
saying you have to do like a move mask
and then shift the move mask over and or
it in dude I'm talking you and I'm
saying yeah yeah exactly so then by the
time you do all that I don't think
you've saved any instructions right cuz
now you need to do you need you two of
those so you do two table lookups with
to move masks both that have to op three
ops per to collapse them I think that's
slower dude if anything I think that's
slower because if we don't do that much
right I mean we'd have to test it to
know which one was faster but here you
can see exactly what we're doing here
right you got a load these values in
right and you know who knows how exactly
the compiler is gonna decide to do that
but otherwise you've got an and it
equals in an or for each step and you've
only got one two three four or five of
them and then two more here right so
you're talking about a very low number
of ops right and so if you have to do
you have to do the move mask in any case
right you've got to do that move mask
you've got to do the move max twice once
for the min and once for the max so you
still have to do two of these equals and
then to move masks right then you have
to do the collapses on the move masks
which will be at least what two more
instructions per sets for more
instructions there then you have to look
up into the table and then you have to
actually keep it per Lane right there's
no way there's no way what you're
suggesting is faster I mean in go
implement it and prove me wrong for sure
but that just
it does not sound good that sound that
sounds like like definitely slower table
lookups in general are a good idea like
what you're suggesting is a good idea I
don't want to dismiss it it's a good
idea just not for this particular case I
think because it's so simple if we were
doing something more here then we you
know table lookups can be very good it's
just I think this happens to be simple
enough that I'm and the in the table
lookup happens to be troublesome enough
is the other part of it right sometimes
the table lookups really clean and in
this case it isn't Rome says team in
three will always be the closest in
distance to Rea origin since rady that
hits box max will result in tea box max
less than two box big no-no so if the
Ray is pointing in the negative
direction then box max will actually hit
sooner than box min right because
remember the array can be going can be
going negative Direction down negative X
instead of positive x for example and
then it will hit the X max first then
the X min whereas if it's coming from
the low and going high then it will hit
min first and max right so so to be more
specific
let's just take a one dimensional array
right so here's my bounds here is my min
here's my max if the direction of the
Ray is going down the positive right so
it's starting somewhere and going
positive it will hit min and then max
right first min then max but if I
started high and employing negative then
I will hit max first then min so we need
to do some tests to determine now we
could just do that test on the raid
erection right because we know it ahead
of time actually so in in theory we
could instead do it this way where in
addition to doing in Grady here we just
do one two
that's the mask for that so we could say
like okay you know ray positive or
something right and that's just like
okay you know is if I take the zero
vector and I want to know if if if the
the raid erection is is greater right so
I just want to know if the Ray is
positive down any dent down any
particular axis right and then in theory
you know down here instead of actually
doing the min or the Max we could select
it with a mask that was based on this
Ray position right
but it's just not faster right this is
one operation so there's just no need I
don't think for this to occur we still
need the men in the max because we need
to know whether they're ray intersected
at all so we need to make sure there is
room between these two in that way so
you know I just don't think you'd do
anything with that does that make sense
so I'm pretty sure that's not soon can
actually take advantage of unfortunately
and so you know
yeah it is what it is
alright no more questions so I think
tomorrow what I'd like to do maybe we'll
take a look at the facial hierarchy just
to like finish off some of the
optimization stuff I don't know what to
think about the cycle counts currently
36 million isn't isn't awful certainly
and it does look like the work is pretty
reasonable so let's pause the profile so
you know I'm just taking a look at this
here so one of the things that you have
to think about when you're when you're
looking at multi-threaded programming as
well is you have to make sure that
you're not like wasting too much work
and so as you can see with the
multi-threading part of this is we
really don't have too much of a problem
with with drain out like we don't have
problems where there's huge gaps up here
so we're pretty well balanced and you
know I'm pretty happy that the amount of
time we would save by trying to like use
smaller buckets probably isn't much
right but you can imagine if these
buckets were too big like so for example
let's just let me just show you what I
mean
so in here right when we divide up the
work so you know let's just say that we
divide up the work into much larger
buckets then then we're talking about
here right so when we take a look at
that and we look at the threads and we
pause that you can see that the gaps get
much larger and the reason that the gaps
get much larger is because the size of
the work that we're allocating out is
just too big right so you end up looking
at these threads here and there's what
how many one two three four five six
right they each get one batch of work to
do and then one of them gets the tail
end and the rest of them just have to
wait so you end up with a lot of unused
cut these threads are just sitting here
doing nothing during that time right so
you typically want to make sure this
quanta is low enough right and we could
imagine you know dropping it down and
down and down but I don't think we want
drop any lower than 256 but you can take
a look at how that's breaking down and
you can kind of see how much empty space
you're wasting there and what you want
is usually the largest quantity very
little empty space because that way you
know you're not spending a lot of time
on the bookkeeping in the overhead but
you're still getting you know up
reasonable amount of that still keeping
it very flush so that's one aspect the
other aspect and this is the part that
we're not looking at currently is your
dead laying count right so the other
thing that happens is you've got you
know multi-threading and so there's one
way of looking at dead time is threads
are sitting there with nothing to do
because there's no quanta to give them
there you're out of work and they're
waiting for the last thread that got a
quanta of work to do to finish that
quanta right the other way to look at it
is on any particular thread you've also
got lanes in our case we've got four
lanes that's good four lanes worth of
work and what we're counting on is that
these lanes all have active stuff
happening in them but what actually
happens is that at some point lanes get
knocked out they've already computed
their results and the other lanes are
still active so they're just along for
the ride and at some point you can get
into pretty bad scenarios where one ray
is still causing the whole thing to go
but the rest of the rays were already
done and so you're essentially losing up
to 75% of the computation power
computing dead rays so one of the things
that people will do is they'll actually
for lack of a better term multi Multi
threads the Ray I don't know how to say
this exactly but one of the things that
they'll do is so in here what we do is
we just stuff the Ray value as one value
and do the whole thing you know straight
through right so we get four Ray's in
here and we do them all and that's all
we do if at some point we found that our
lane masked masked out so we were like
this Ray is done we don't need to
compute it anymore it found its hit or
whatever and we know that you could
replace that ray value with a new ray
value right and so one way that people
will do this is they'll actually the
Quan
it'll pull in new Ray's as the Rays
finish and just stay in the rach ekang
loop pulling in new Ray's that you never
lose Lane fill that might be a little
bit too advanced for us because then you
have to architect your whole thing as
like a ray pipeline so rays are coming
in and getting distributed and they're
you're traversing the hierarchy and you
remember we're in the hierarchy you are
per ray and it just it's a lot more
complicated but it is more not more
complicated to implement more cop gating
and you got to work through a lot more
stuff that may be a bridge too far but
point we just wanted to point out that
is something we're not measuring right
now we don't really have a way of
knowing how much dead computation time
we have how much computation time we're
effectively
spending on things that we really just
don't care what the result is because
they're just sitting in lanes that are
never gonna get used anyway right so
that's something to be aware of I go
down the stairs here sue yeah
[Music]
I don't really have much more to say so
I think we can probably end I really
like the way this letting is shaping up
I mean it's so cool that you can get
like the lighting in here it's bouncing
off of there and hitting here and stuff
and it gets a little bit of that shine
and it's pretty Pleasant
anyway alright folks I'm gonna close
down I'm gonna try to anyway
yes you can see and this was we never
really finished looking at this cuz we
just implanted ourselves but you can see
what they did the same thing right so
they take the min and the max to figure
out which one is which cuz they don't
know right they don't even call them min
and Max to start with they just they use
the min and Max in here for the bounding
box with things calm one and two then
they use the min and the max to figure
out which one is them into the max then
they use the max of the minimums right
which is whoa this is editable okay and
so that's exactly what we did as well
which is what we would think so yeah all
right thank you everyone for joining me
first on a handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow my series at
home you can always peer to the game it
comes with a source code so head to hand
made here org if you want to play on the
source yourself I will be back tomorrow
when we will either continue with the
optimization stuff or maybe start to
drill down on why we're doing that
flicker I don't think that flicker is
entirely due to sampling I think we've
got bugs then we need to fix those bugs
so we'll do a little more debugging on
that really like how the lighting looks
now I'm pretty happy with it I think at
some point we have to go try playing
with the world generation code so that
we can actually use the lighting points
more effectively than they're being used
now so we've got to kind of work on that
back end a little bit we got to like
work on how we're actually gonna you
know use the lighting artistically in
the scene so we're kind of moving slowly
towards that part where we'll kind of
have a different look at a different
side of the lighting which is you know
now that we have ways of computing it
and as we get that way of computing it
good enough that we think we could use
it in the ship and game we actually need
it for how we do want to actually use it
and so that's kind of where we're
looking at now all right
until then help us see everyone back
here for that until then have fun
programming I'll see everyone on the
Internet
take it easy everybody