hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here the show recode a complete game
live on stream we are doing lighting
optimization right now and we've got
some stuff to do we have you know I'm
mostly working lighting system in terms
of how the architecture should go but we
don't really have a solid idea of how
we're gonna make it run at 60 frames a
second right we're too slow right now
for the size of things that we want to
do and there's a lot of things that we
can consider in terms of speeding it up
but at the very least we should probably
finish our spatial hierarchy stuff that
we started down and that is to say that
we implemented a spatial hierarchy for
accelerating our raycast but we never
really played with it
we haven't even drawn it yet so we don't
even really know how well it's working
we could have like obvious bugs in there
and we'd never know so our job now is to
start taking the lighting system and
actually refining it in terms of
performance and then also we need to
make the front-end to it which currently
just drops down equally spaced points on
our little environment cubes we need to
actually do something more intelligent
there right we need to have the thing
that actually creates the world be smart
about where it's gonna put down lighting
points so that you know you can be be
more reasonably assured that you're
going to get decent quality out of the
lighting based on on what you put into
it so let's go ahead and take a quick
look at what I'm talking about here
and again lighting is one of the hardest
things in graphics it's it's basically
the thing that causes all of the
problems so you know you can expect
always for it to be a little bit of a
struggle and it's just because it's one
of the few things in graphics where
everything affects everything else
obviously when we talk about the cost of
things and how difficult they are to
achieve anything that only involves
working with a single thing is usually
something we can manage these days we
have a lot of horsepower so o n problems
like ones that are proportional to their
input size are not that big of a problem
lighting is not that way lighting is
everything affects everything else
because light down
is off surfaces and hits other services
and keeps bouncing and so on and so it's
just a really nasty problem because it's
an M squared or worse kind of a problem
where you end up with the difficulty of
the problem the amount of work you need
to do to do it correctly scaling
nonlinearly and that's like the worst
case right well now there's super
linearly obviously something early would
be great so anyway if you take a look at
what we've got here now you can kind of
see that our lighting is is working for
the most part meaning that we get
predictable results as we move things
around we get bounce lighting which we
want we keep things relatively smooth
but there's a couple of things like I
said we need to do one is on the front
end like you can see like right now we
don't do lighting translation for our
sprites these sprites are just kind of
stamped down here so only our little
actual geometry cubes are getting lit so
that's something that we need to fix now
the other thing is our frame rates just
not good enough right
and it's especially not good enough when
the entire lighting region gets it you
know increased over it's something like
over here where we've got more things
that are being lit so there's just a
bunch of stuff that needs to get sort of
improved and smoothed out so yeah I
don't know exactly what the best
approach is but we've got a couple
things to do the other thing we need to
do is we changed a little bit how the
renderer was handling submissions of
things and one of the problems that we
hadn't actually looked at there is we
still did one thing wrong you can notice
we're not getting our clear of the back
buffer is not clearing properly because
we're you can see it's black and it's
supposed to be the clear color which is
gray actually so we've got a bunch of
things we can work on the day after
doing the debugging we did on the
lighting last week we've got basically a
number of things we've got to do that
are not necessary debugging but they're
like code improvements code
restructuring opposition that sort of
stuff and so that's what we need to
start working on today so I'm gonna
start by saying let's go ahead and try
to fix that render a problem because I
don't really want to leave that lying
around for too long it's not the end of
the world but it's just I don't want
like bugs lurking in the renderer for
too long we're gonna go through and
once we're totally sure that everything
in it is correct so it's not essential
that it be completely squeaky clean but
it just I don't want it to be too
ridiculous so what you can see here is
we've got the render entry begin peals
section here this is when we come
through and we do our depth peeling
passes we're going to render the same
information multiple times and so one
thing you'll notice is that each time we
go through to clear one of these peels
we end up in a situation where we need
to know what to clear it to and what we
want to do is we want to clear any of
the peels that we hit we want to clear
them to nothing first which is you can
see it's zero zero zero because we want
if there's nothing on that peel we want
it to show through to the peel below it
right that's the whole point of doing
the peeling and so when we finally get
to the bottom most layer what we're
doing is we're clearing that bottom most
layer to the clear color or at least
that's what we're supposed to be doing
and since I don't actually have any
verification that that's actually
happening I don't know if we're doing it
wrong or right or what's happening so
what I want to do is I want to take a
look in here and see what's going on
with our clear do we have something
messed up in there
did we just set the color wrong you know
I don't know so I want more information
about this problem so I can start to
debug it and that's what I'm gonna go
look for now so the first thing I'm
gonna do is I'm just gonna set a
breakpoint here I'm gonna turn off
because we don't care how fast this is
running I'm about to turn off
optimizations so it's easier to step
through the code and we can inspect our
variables better so I'm gonna go ahead
and look in here what you can see is we
made good to begin the peels we can see
what the peel index is it's zero on the
first one through which is what we'd
expect max render target is three which
is also expect as we have for render
targets zero one two and three so the
maximum is three we should clear this to
zero and we do we should clear the next
one to zero and we do we should clear
the next one to zero and we do and now
this final one should be cleared to the
okay well
there's your problem right there here we
go this is our problem we reset the peel
index at the end to zero
so and that's because I guess we don't
want depth peeling on so that's our
problem problem solved
we just need to figure out a way for
these loops to work better with each
other so when we hit this right here
render group entry type render entry end
peels when we get to the maximum render
target index it looks like well actually
I don't know if I agree with that
because this should have incremented the
peel index and we should have come
through here at least one time with the
max render target index right because
this is only once on peel index is equal
to it so I guess I'm not sure why
exactly that happened that looks to me
more reasonable actually so what's going
on there let's let's take that one more
time I'm not so sure I mean I see what
caused the bug we didn't come through
here on the on the final one but but I
don't know why we didn't and that's
that's not great so I'm gonna look at
both sides of the loop now to find out
what's going on so I'm gonna tag in the
watch window on peel index so that I can
see exactly what it is at each step so I
started PL 0 I end peel 0 and I
increment to peel 1 and jump back
so somehow when we jumped back
oh we're not actually entering this so
you see what happened here this peel
header restored that snaps header at so
what we were doing is we wanted to
create a loop through our render
instructions and this is the thing that
restores the pointer that we're reading
from but we saved the pointer at the
wrong time
we saved the pointer and we really want
the pointer to point to the header right
not header at so we really want this we
want the put that header restore to
point to the header we're on so that we
run the begin loop again so does that
mean we were never clearing any of those
somehow no I step through it so how is
that possible that's just very strange
so looking at this here so it's a little
bit wonky so if you take a look at what
happens we're stepping through the
header here by doing an increment of the
of the entry size but that's a little
bit odd and I'm not sure why we're doing
it in that way
I mean basically what this means is if
we wanted to set up the pointer properly
for the end of the loop because this
here happens at sort of an odd time I
would almost say I would like to move
this out so the increment I feel like it
might be nicer if it actually happened
here
right because then the header pointer is
still the right pointer to set this to
and that seems more sane to me let's
find out if I'm right about that so
there's that clear increment here's the
clear again and the increment clear
increment and there's our clear to the
correct color off we go
so now we're getting back we've gotten
back to the correct behavior it looks
like to me so that seems much more sane
let me make sure because I don't
actually know I'm gonna switch to
optimized so we can take a look a little
more cleanly here yeah so that's looking
more like it
still get some artifacting there were
two things overlap exactly for our death
feeling but otherwise we seem okay all
right
so I think that was the only problem
that was the only thing that I was
really wanted to make sure was solved
and it is solved let's double-check also
our profile right now so we know where
we're at you can see here it's exactly
what we would expect our lighting is
taking all of the time so the entire
game is running in very little time but
the lighting is taking forever and so we
essentially know that that's our giant
you know our big target that's that's
what we need to focus on and figure out
how to you know speed up and so that's
what we you know that's we're gonna look
at now all right so I'm fine with that
let's take a look at the current state
of our optimized our attempts to
optimize our lighting so there's a
number of things we want to do here some
will make things better some will make
things worse actually not just in terms
of optimization but just in terms of the
way the algorithm is structured so we
know that basically all of our time is
spent inside the movies app if spent in
time inside the lighting propagation
right so the compute light propagation
function which is this guy right here is
what takes all the time and it's pretty
easy to see why it takes all the time
it's just this giant set of loops right
everything multiplies out so we do a
certain number of iterations over a
certain number of emitters over a
certain number of rays each of which
then has to loop over all of our
collision geometry or started lighting
geometry and that lady's Gemma tree is
broken into spatial hierarchy but that's
still it's still a lot of checking right
and so loop upon loop upon loop upon
loop each loop just multiplies out the
amount of work that has to be done right
and that just creates a really bad
situation so what we're trying to do
here is figure out ways that we can sort
of continue to make this more likely to
you know run in a nice sort of pseudo
fixed amount of time so one thing that
is going to mention is we never really
got our skylight in there and one of the
reasons we don't have a skylight in
there is the way that we're currently
doing our ray casting is we we choose to
shoot rays from our
meters out bird and that makes actually
pretty good sense at first meaning when
you start you probably want to do that
but it definitely makes things harder
for things like skylight where you don't
really have any particular location that
light is coming from skylight is
something that just kind of radiates
inward to everything and you know that's
a pretty important component of lighting
that you know it would be nice if we
captured so we had kind of have some
some issues with that as well where we
don't really know what we are we don't
have a solid plan in here for how we
would do that obviously one thing you
could do was constantly irradiate
everything with skylight but again the
more you do that the more extra rays
you're casting and blah blah blah so
it's hard to say exactly how we want to
do that I'm not sure whether we want to
retain an emission based scheme or not
but my suspicion is what we probably
want to do is do something where we have
emitters we do sort of a shoot out from
emitters to distribute light from the
emission sources but then we probably
also want to do gathers which we played
with a little bit having a mission and
gather we may want to have both
happening you know you know again just
because that's probably something that
makes a little bit more sense alright so
the other thing that I'd like to do is
point out that I think we're getting
pretty low leverage for what we're doing
right now because we recompute the
lighting every frame and then blend it
with the lighting from the previous
frames and the problem with that is I
think we're getting very low leverage
from our computation from that because
once we figure out what the lighting is
on a frame we might as well use that
lighting on the next frame and continue
to propagate it around right I feel like
that's the smarter way to do things
where we can basically say all right
whatever the amount of light we want to
keep from frame to frame is let's just
make that be the starting emission for
those surfaces whatever the reduction is
and we'll go from there right so that
might be the first thing to start with
just so we can get back to something
that's that's properly retaining
actual light and not just blending with
the old results so what I'd like to do
is go ahead and take this routine down
here so this is the routine that
basically goes through and and you know
averages that lighting information what
I'd rather do is have this seed the
initial lighting information so I think
we can start we can do that relatively
straightforward actually by just coming
up here and just doing that right so
right here where I've got this to do
this is reload the previous emission and
direction the starting point that that
whole situation right that's exactly
what I want to do here right that's
exactly what I want to do here and we
can get some nice synergy here because
you can see this box index thing this is
the same loop that we're doing to
generate these points to begin with and
so what I can do here is just say all
right let's go ahead and grab the the
parts of this that are actually relevant
and use those to seed the lighting so
suppose I come in here and say okay
let's take a look at and you know what
else I can do actually let me do this
too as well let me save this down here
and just nerf it so if we want to turn
the blending back on we will be able to
okay that that'll be something we can
keep in there but let's go ahead and
grab inside the boxing next stuff here
I'm gonna go ahead and say we're gonna
load up in that emission and you know
what else - we don't have to care about
this check anymore because the emission
just would be what the emission is right
so if the emission is zero it just won't
add any emission so all we're gonna do
is just add that emission in and so
that's pretty trivial for us to do right
so all we need is this basically we need
to go ahead and here where we set this
emit C zero we need to just add into it
something like this so we need to know
for the given box what the local index
is that we're on right and you can kind
of see how we were doing that already
here we've got this light index here
that's that's coming off the box
lighting next if we wanted to know what
the local index was off of the box it
would just be the light index - this box
index right which is not something that
we currently store but easily could so
if I take a look at where we're using
light index here but you can see that
it's really only used in in these sort
of simplified ways here and what I can
do is I can just change these checks to
be a little bit more well you know what
I could why even bother I'll just do it
this way I'll just reverse computed here
it's fine right so that's the place in
the box where the emission value is
actually being stored so that would seed
the emission for this frame with
whatever it was computed to be on the
previous frame and so that is you know
it's all we want to do there however
remember we don't want to use all of it
so we want a retained emission
coefficient because we don't want we
want the old effects to fade over time
right so we don't know what that
efficient could be it's like what that
coefficient should be because again this
is an ad hoc solution where we're taking
something that we do know how to do
which is slow global illumination and
we're trying to make it fast by making
approximations so this value is
literally just whatever will make it
look the best right and we have no idea
what that is so we'll have to tune it to
whatever looks the best once we run it I
think then we're done I don't know that
we need anything else to happen here I
could be wrong about that but we'll find
out oops that's not index that's light
index and in fact I can here also say
what the local index actually is because
the local index is still a valid name
for that
so let me just pull it out here and
that's I think all we would have to do
to kind of preserve the light so that
the light kind of comes through granted
that is not a particularly flattering
effect for the wow that is pretty
interesting um I'm not sure why it's
quite so flickery I house very odd I
think this is correct and we are
retaining a fair bit of the light there
box storage you know what it's not
getting written back though so the one
thing we do have to do is we do need
this routine to be still enabled and we
just need the box storage omission to be
saved so you can see that happening here
oh and you know what this normalization
also so okay I was a little premature
when I said we could nerf that we can't
actually nerf it the only thing we can
really nerve is this right we still have
to come through here and we still have
to record this information although you
know what actually we don't even really
have to do that
all we have to do is always set valid to
false because as long as valid is always
false then what it will do is it will
always use this branch which all it does
is do direct right backs which is what
we want right narrow blending just right
backs so that should be fine
but yeah we have to do that final loop
because we have to do the normalization
of the direction and we have to store it
so that's all good so this retains I
guess too much light to say the very
least unless I've got a bug there so
let's let's retain less light than that
we're also getting a lot slower I think
because there's a lot more services with
light on them if that makes sense so
it's kind of hard to because so we we
end up doing a lot more propagations in
that initial one but we should also be
able to turn down the lighting quite a
bit from there let me actually see to
what extent I can do that because now we
don't need to do the sort of Jack Trey
count thing you know the rate count gets
gets sort of diminished as we go out
here we don't really have to do that
anymore this can sort of be a flat
number that we can tune because we don't
really have to worry about that initial
lighting part of things right so I don't
know so yeah like still like very
flickery right unfortunately and you
know I'm just trying to think through
exactly how I want to approach this
problem because I would I mean maybe
that's dumb right like maybe you just
don't ever want to remit values in the
previous frame but it seems like you
would want them to be able to propagate
over multiple frames right that just
seems like what you would want to do for
efficacy
efficacy but again I don't really know
these are sort of exercises in in
figuring out what is the you know most
palatable choice so anyway but looking
at this I'm interested to know what
happens if we cast few Ray's but have a
higher retention coefficient just want
to see what happens here
so you can see what happens when the
retention coefficient is high enough you
can see the light kind of spreading it's
interesting actually let me go ahead and
change it on the fly so let's change it
down to 0.5 it's really fascinating
but you can definitely see like so for
example right underneath one of the
problems that you get if I do this right
is that because it's not just blending
results with other results you end up in
a nasty situation where you still get a
lot of flickering because well at this
stochastic part of the process which is
doing that transmission is obviously
going to introduce the noise and you
don't get a lot of reprieve from that so
if we wanted to do something that's
gonna be you know Flickr reducing what
we'd have to do is in you know when
we're actually doing yeah for example
let's suppose we just said you know what
the the light is always going to be you
know we're always gonna propagate the
exact same light and we just want the
light to decay more as it goes right we
could just just take more energy out of
the system as we're doing bounces right
and and not use as much of it let the
light sort of drain out as part of the
bounces and have those bounces effect
surfaces less right and I'm not sure
exactly how we would do that so you know
let's suppose we set this to one so you
just retain all of the light from the
previous frame but when you come in here
and you know you've got this light
retention value instead of this being
power conserving it will just be powered
decaying so for example when you come
through here and we do the retain see
minus equals accumulate sample and you
you know we've got the power value in
here right what we could do is say that
that power value is actually going to be
a lot less than 1.0 right so the total
power that can get distributed out will
be much less than that and they retained
light will be much higher so for example
what we could do is say well you know
we want to do it over ten frames we've
said that say that our power was going
to be a tenth of whatever the amount of
power actually distributed was and so as
we come through here we will retain most
of the light that we had at the start so
we won't change our lighting values much
we will just diminish every time we
actually transport something by by this
blend amount right and I don't know
exactly how we would have to balance
this I'm assuming these or should
basically be equivalent
we're gonna have to work this math out
on the blackboard actually cuz I'm not
sure
but as you can see this is starting to
be more more reasonable so let's go
ahead and say let's let's take a look at
this so let's say we did even less than
this
and you can see that gets us down to a
fairly low amount of flicker right it's
still not quite as much as we would like
but it's getting lower and I'm not sure
how much flicker we would have if we
were to crank our ray count up more I'm
not sure how much thicker we're getting
from the that that could be resolved
with with denser sampling it's like
doesn't help that much it appears to
flicker or less just because the frame
rate gets lower as we crank that value
but it's still quite a bit of flicker so
let's say we set it down even even lower
there I also think maybe we only want to
run one iteration of the lighting now so
what I might say is the iteration count
I may I may actually just nerf this so
we just run one pass for frame right and
you can really see okay so the and this
is running it you know obviously also
have much higher frame rate but you know
you can kind of see how it's like yeah
if we just could get the sampling a
little more stable it starts to be
something fairly usable so I do think
you know I think that's kind of the what
I want to look at I think I want to look
at doing something that just does a
single pass so it doesn't iterate it
does a single pass on the lighting and
then it just refines that one every
frame refract refines the lighting you
know every frame and goes from there so
and the other thing is I don't know
maybe we change it to being pull based
as well too because that's flatter if we
go over everything once and pull from
neighbors
instead of doing push then it doesn't
change based on the lighting environment
the speed of it it's more stable in
terms of frame rate which I think I
so want so let's just try to simplify
this loop down to something that works
like this we're gonna run it one time
we're gonna run over the collection
services they're gonna cast out and see
what they hit and that's all we're gonna
do maybe and you know I I'm a little
nervous about it because I do think
there's a plus two going from the
emitters so we may have to do a
distribution pass where emission
surfaces with high emission will get
some special treatment where they'll get
to shoot rays out as a separate part of
the pass but I don't know it's pretty
hard to say the other thing to remember
is if we again if we add that skylight
in there where we're getting light from
the sky that's gonna even out of the
lighting a little bit by giving some
under you know some ambient to the
lighting that you're getting from from
the outside which will also help but of
course you know for indoor situations
that's not going to be true so you know
your mileage may vary but anyway so
let's let's yeah let's kind of move
towards this a little bit and see what
we can do so let's take and and look at
what maybe this this guy right here and
and sort of transform this loop into
this loop maybe also if we cast from the
light points out that actually might
give us a more useful way to to sample
what lighting we hit I'm not sure about
that but I
there there's right now we're just
whenever we hit a surface we give light
to the surface point that we were
closest to hitting and what we could do
in the future is take
from points that you take lights from
all the points that are nearby much like
we do with our interpolation so I'm not
sure again exactly how we want to treat
that but but I do think that collection
that you know basically doing the
collection basis system would be more
consistent just for Speed purposes
because the speed will remain the same
no matter how much lighting there is
going on in the scene and I'm just
afraid that if we go with an emission
based scheme we're always gonna have
these nasty spikes in the amount of time
that the light takes whereas as you get
more emitters you get slower and I don't
love that so I don't know this may be a
big mistake and I apologize if it is but
I just got to go with with my gut on
this because I don't know ahead of time
exactly what the right solution is going
to be right so let's get rid of these
occlusion counts here
I mean iteration counts and let's
replace it instead with a point
collection style scheme so what we're
going to do is we're gonna go through to
the points here and so for every point
we're gonna do a collection pass and
yeah you know this is exactly what we
would we do right here
so we're going to take a scent this is
sample point index really where we're
going to sample the lighting from so
we'll grab a sample point and in a
sample direction and we'll sample the
hemisphere out from that direction I and
yeah once we do that we're going to want
to throw the Ray out and we're going to
want to see if it hit and then from
there we're gonna have to decide how
we're gonna do our transfer right so I
want to do something like this we go
through everything once one of the nice
things is now emit see one in emit c0r
it's really just a source and a destiny
gets used once so you wouldn't really
have to do the right back here at all we
would not have to clear this to zero now
that doesn't matter that's not taking
much of the time or anything so we can
retain this but then when we go to do
the final cleaned up version of this we
won't have to do that right so this is
so assuming we stick with one-pass we
can eventually get rid of this concept
and we can just have a source and a
destiny so are you the best and we're
done and we don't need to re clear the
desk in any particular way because it's
going to get seeded with the inputs from
from the next time I think again not
100% sure about that but I'm pretty sure
about that yeah because everything has
to come from a lightning box those
lighting boxes are the things that will
be cleared so yeah so this will not
really have to happen anymore because
the sources will just be correct and the
destination will be what we read from at
the end and so everything will be fine
so that's fine I think that's all good
and then what we want to do now is start
to think about how we're actually going
to apply the lighting here so accumulate
sample is still you know the same thing
we want to use we're just going to want
to be passing different information to
it so the sample point that we're going
to be talking about we already know now
so we know it's going to be the sample
point normal here is the normal that
we're gonna get for surface reflection
we also have this decimate c+ closest
point index here I guess that's the
target that we're writing to and so
that's again just going to be the sample
point index right that's that's what
we're writing into the solution average
direction to light plus those pointers
same thing again this is just a sample
point so that's what we're writing out
and then what we need to know is emit
see the power and the the emit direction
so the emit Direction here this actually
isn't going to be negated it is actually
the sample direction because again we're
shooting we're gathering out not you
know talking about an inbound point so I
believe that should be sampled e because
sample D and sample point arrow n are
pointing the same direction which is
what we want for the dot product and so
really it's emit C and power that are
the two things we need to be computing
here
and those need to be computed based on
the box that we hit power
probably not but emit see definitely so
we got the same sorts of problems we
have before where we got to start
thinking about this stuff
that'll look sign to me uh so yeah
taking a look at this we don't care
about we don't care about really how we
were doing this before because we're
gonna have to change the stuff I also
want to grab the sky information stuff
here there we go and what we can do now
is we have a Sun Direction a Sun color
in a sky color I don't know why that's
like that um change the way these work
so once we have a sky color in a Sun
color that means we can also make
whenever we miss so before every time we
missed we did nothing now anytime we
miss we can use this sky color or the
Sun color and we also need us I guess a
ground color which is something for
casting down and don't hit anything so
we kind of just need to know what kind
of it of a situation we're dealing with
I'm gonna set this to something sort of
a dark brownish color I so this stuff
right here will give us the information
we need to fill in our missing emissions
with something related right and so
something that that does like lighting
from the environment so that'll be nice
too because then we can do this sort of
thing we were doing with our with our
son information here and we can yeah we
can we can basically make a more
interesting lighting environment that
way I don't know that we ever have a son
I guess there's a moon in this game but
it doesn't take place in the daytime so
it's gonna be moon color for what's
worth and probably I'm guessing the moon
is you know probably still pretty dark
we're gonna have to set these to
something reasonable I don't really know
if those are even in the ballpark of
correct but we'll mix the colors later
all right so getting back to what we
need to do here so this single pass here
where we're just going to do compute
light propagation we're going to do one
pass over all of the sample points we're
going to compute the ray casts from each
of them and then we're going to write
back and what we need to do here example
D in there uh does recast
so skip index has to be the box that we
were coming from and we don't know the
box that we're coming from which makes
it kind tricky right I think we can
probably just not bother with that
anymore because we know that we're
always sampling from boxes and we're
always we don't check the back faces of
the boxes so I think we're probably fine
at least at the moment
to not do the skip check the problem is
if we want to do something like that in
the future I'm thinking about for bigger
boxes
because if I'm not mistaken didn't we do
something gnarly where we said like okay
when we're splitting the boxes and we
come through here and build them didn't
we do something weird like negate the
radius where did we not do that I guess
we actually checked to see if we're
inside the box so I guess we're okay so
I guess we can if we want to get rid of
this and we'll be okay all right so
anyway in here where we're doing our
sampling we can just get rid of this
sample point next to when we do the
raycast it just doesn't take a skip
index anymore so that's just taken out
of the equation and so yeah I think
we're left with just how exactly we want
to find out what point we're grabbing
from once we get a ray box here if we
don't get a ray box then again the
things we need to set are the emit C and
the power now the power again I think
should be the same it should just be
what what it was going to be tuned to
before or you know since we don't really
know how we want to tune that light
retention we can play with all this
stuff later but it's gonna be exactly
the same it's gonna be set to some fixed
value and we don't really need to worry
ourselves about it other than we need to
tune it later and probably work out some
math on the blackboard to figure out
what a plausible way of doing it would
be thankfully min emission is gone now
so we don't need to tune that so we're
really just looking at at some pretty
basic tuning here which is what we want
we want the least number of tuning
parameters
possible in any in any algorithm right
to keep it simple and more likely to be
correct so when we loop over the rating
to cease here again we need to know what
the omit C is going to be and so in the
case where you don't hit anything for
now we're just gonna say that the omit C
is gonna be the moon color which is this
thing here right and that's all we need
to know the harder case in fact I guess
we don't even have to do that I could
just well yeah we kind of do in fact we
know who said that
so what we need to do here now is set
this emit C to something in the case of
the box and then we've got all the
information that we actually need so all
of this stuff is not necessary anymore
right we don't care about any of this we
do need to put our sample point in here
we need to grab this so we do need to
grab the sample point in X out but we
don't really care about the rest of this
stuff we just need to know how to grab
this thing we'll talk about that in a
second and what that's supposed to show
get rid of all this stuff and then if we
wanted to grab from whatever the closest
point is this would be it and I guess in
here I'm not really sure how you could
end up without a closest point index I'm
not sure why that was being checked
because if the closest point index I
guess the only case would be if there
were no points on the box but if there's
no points on the Box we probably could
just if out on that and not have to do
this whole thing but anyway let's get
rid of all this
so really we're just looking at this
scanning process here and you know I
guess I'm inclined to say mmm so let me
explain on the white bus sorry
blackboard why I think we maybe want to
change the way we're doing that a little
bit
so if we have a surface that we hit and
we know we have some lighting points on
that surface we know we're going to hit
in a particular location and the problem
is we have to decide if we hit in a
particular location so before we
flipping the meaning of this problem
around but the problem remains the same
so you can see what we were doing was we
were saying we have an emitter we're
gonna send a ray out from the emitter
and we're gonna see what it hits and
we're gonna add light to whatever it
hits so this would be the point we're
adding light to and thus we snapped it
to the closest one and added light to
that point that's how we were doing it
we're flipping it around now and saying
okay now instead what we're doing is
we're sampling right we've actually
we're trying to light this surface over
here this is where the light is going
but we're grabbing light from a surface
that we hit we hit here and and if we
want to follow the same procedure we'd
snap to one of the points now why do I
think this is maybe not a good idea for
our final way to do things the reason is
because if you look at the problems
we're gonna have with lighting and
they're probably already have its
lighting its noise right it's the
flicker we don't want a lot of flicker
in that solution where does the flicker
come from well the flare comes from the
fact that we have insufficient samples
to capture the full lighting function
now why why do we have insufficient
samples well the answer is because the
lighting that's incoming at a point
isn't this really ugly discreet problem
where if you shoot rays out along this
hemisphere you don't get a nice smooth
like curve like this of incoming light
if you did you could just say do a
couple samples to find the shape of this
curve and then integrate the curve and
have the exact answer the real answer is
because because all of the surfaces are
hard edged and weird and different
services reflect differently the actual
incoming light looks like this right
it's this horribly ugly super cut
discrete jumpy discontinuous function so
we dismissed
perfectly the discontinuity in the
incoming light that creates the flicker
because depending on where we sample we
will think drastically different things
about what it looks like if we only
sample here here and here we would think
it's this giant incoming bright light
thing if we only sample here here and
here we think it's really low if we have
a mix of the two we get more of an
average right and so every frame when we
shoot things out we get drastically
different results in the only way to
really solve the problem is to shoot a
lot more rays which is exactly what
offline rendering does you know think
yeah the pipeline for blue sky or Pixar
where they spend several hours rendering
a frame potentially or something like
this they can do enough to make sure
they get good results but we can't we
only have a sixtieth of a second and
we've got a lot of other things to do
besides rendering as well right so given
that fact what we need to do is we need
to figure out how to make our samples go
as far as possible and so one of the
things we want to do is not introduce
any more discontinuities than there
already might be and that's exactly what
we would be doing if we snap because
what a snap does is think about what
that means that means that as rays hit
this surface and try to sample the
lighting from it there's basically
what's called and that we've never
covered this so forgive me for using the
phrase but if you want to look it up
I'll just mention it we're basically
creating a Voronoi partition of this
space and that Voronoi partition you
could also look at its dual which is a
Dylan a triangulation these two things
are the basically the inverse of each
other well they're tools that's a
different thing this is way too much
this is forget I said any of that
basically what we're talking about is on
this surface we have a set of points and
what we're doing is we're snapping to
the closest one that creates a partition
of the space which is called a Voronoi
partition which basically splits it into
this set of shapes right anyone who
lands in here will snap to this anyone
in lands in here will snap to this and
and that right and thus we have created
four hard discontinuities along the
surface that weren't there to begin with
we've added them so I think what we want
to do instead is take our points and
average them together to figure out how
much light we're gonna grab and we
should probably blend them together
based on our distance so if you land
really close to this one it's this one
but if you land in between the two it's
half and a half if you land in the
middle it's all four right and so I feel
like that's a better way of approaching
this problem because now we can say
definitively that we have not introduced
a discontinuity we are still left with a
ton of discontinuities that are there
because of just the surface geometry and
how that service geometry affects the
lighting but we don't we're not
introducing artificial discontinuities
that will add yet more flicker to a
system that already has too much right
because we're trying to reduce that
flicker we certainly don't want to do
anything that's going to exacerbate that
flicker so I think that's what we want
to do if we get back a box I think what
we want to do is loop over the points of
the box in here
and then for each one of these surface
points I think what we want to do is
rather than just doing a check I think
what we want to do is use that closest
distance squared as a blend term so
basically take our total distance
squared summit so now when we come
through here we know exactly how many
how much total effect we're gonna have
and then when we sum our omission up
what we're gonna do is say okay take the
omit C and add the distance squared we
probably want to do an inverse of it
right actually so something that's going
to decay as you get further away so we
can do in fact this is exactly what we
did before we can do like 1.0 f over 1.0
f + distance squared so basically as you
get further away you get lower and lower
and lower and lower so something like
this
so we'll sum up those inverse distance
squared we'll use that as a multiplier
on the thing that we would have done if
we were just taking it just from this
point so the hit points like so
so you can see what I'm doing here right
I'm just going through and saying all
right where is that point that we hit on
the box and again we haven't actually
pulled out the box values yet but we
will in a second take the inverse
distance so we're gonna get a thing that
Falls up and if you want to know what
this looks like
again you can actually use nowadays you
can like just ask Google even to graph
it you can say graph 1 over 1 + X there
you go
so if you take a look at what this looks
like right I don't know if you can zoom
in here there we go so we know that this
is always going to be that the distance
squared is always going to be 0 or
greater right so we're gonna start right
here we will never be back there we're
gonna start right here and just as we go
we get less and less contribution right
so as you get out to one unit away
you're gonna be here this is distance
squared so 2 is not 2 units away 2 is if
the square was 2 units away does that
make sense and off you go I don't know
if you can do this okay
so here's what it actually would look
like this is a better graph because this
is distance squared so if this now this
x axis shows actual distance so here is
1 unit away we're at what I'm sorry 0
units away we're at 1 right at 1 unit
away and I can you know what let me zoom
in to just the positive since that's all
we care about can you do yes I can no I
can't
there we go there we go perfect thank
you google okay so here we are at one
you can see us fall off I say here at
zero we're at one you can see us fall
off at one unit away we're gonna be at
like point five right you can kind of
see it doesn't unfortunately highlight
where it is on this axis but you can
read it up here I guess actually so
there's you can see 0.5 and then when we
get to two units away we'll be at Point
2 we get to 3 units away we'll be at
Point 1 four units away 0.05 so you can
see it's just a smooth fall-off curve
the only reason I'm using this right now
we haven't done any analysis or anything
on it
bleh resume using is a convenient
function to start with for just fall off
that doesn't need to be checked right
meaning I don't have to check to see if
the value is zero first which I would
have to do if I just did one over the
actual value so one plus the value here
is preventing me from ever having to
check whether it's zero because I know
it can be zero I could be right on the
point or at least very close to it and
then my function would explode and I
don't want that so I want this this is
well behaved everywhere we care about
right so there's a way to get an inverse
distance on there and then when we do
the total distance and and you know I'm
H it change this because it's not really
told distance squared really what it is
is total weight if the total amount that
we've added in right so we're gonna go
through rent sum up this total weight
and in addition we're also going to take
that how to my product like we were
doing before to produce exactly what we
think this point should contribute and
that's going to be our omit C value once
we have our omit C value at the end now
we know this was a summation of various
weight we don't know how much weight in
toto we summed so what we need to do is
now normalize both values up so here is
the one place I will have to check if
total weight is greater than zero now
totally it will always be greater than
zero if we had any points at all but I'm
just checking to make sure that we do
have some points right because maybe we
put in boxes that don't have any pole
in the future so you know that's all so
then what we can do is we can produce in
total weight that's just 1 over the
total weight and now we can normalize
everything out so now are we can do a
Hadamard product or actually going to
emit see it's not ahead of our
approaches to regular scalar product we
can multiply the omit C by it and that
will tell us exactly what our emission
color should be averaged based on
distance from the points that were
involved now there's one nasty part of
this and in fact I guess this is yeah I
would like to do this with only one loop
but I'm not sure how I could because in
order to know how much light I'm taking
away I need to know what the
distribution of energy that I'm taking
away from each point is and so in order
to do that I need two loops one to
figure out what the total weight is and
then one to actually apply it and that's
kind of ugly but I'm not sure any other
way to do it right
so I don't really know if there's any
way around that
I mean I guess we'll have to find out
how bad it really is to do the loop
twice
it just seems nasty I don't even like
doing the loop once it's not fantastic
so doing the loop twice seems like
really not fantastic but I just don't
see any other way you could really do it
you could fake it and say that you just
take the same amount of light from each
of them even though you aren't doing
that so you know you could say this is
the total amount of light I'm going to
take I take it evenly distributed across
all of them you know even though that is
not how much light I actually gathered
from each of them so it's an
approximation that could have
deleterious consequences it could add or
remove light from your system in
potentially a bad way you know and one
of the problems I guess yeah is that
it's just really hard to say so
probably what I should do is do the two
loops first right and then back off from
the two loops as much as I can
in the end I'm not sure really any other
way I could do it because yeah it's just
like if you want to do a scattered point
interpolation like that I don't know
that there's a lot you can do to prevent
the double summation
yeah I mean or at least I'm not able to
think of what it would be yeah so I
don't know yeah sorry
so yeah so this is a this is a tricky
bit and and I'm not sure how exactly
we're gonna deal with it man but we'll
start with this and we'll go from there
so yeah if we come through here we'd
have to do this twice and then we would
have to do something smart about it
I suppose what that does mean is if we
were gonna do it twice we could avoid
having to do this actual extra inversion
here because we could just pre invert
the value and multiply it through on the
second pass through the loop so if we do
end up having to do two loops I guess we
can make them slightly more efficient
and that's slightly good but not that
good so certainly not as good as not
doing two loops so okay so let's finish
off what we're doing here let me go
ahead and grab the the information we
actually need from this so inside the
ray box stuff we want to figure out
which box we hit in fact I guess we
could just do this if there is a hitbox
then we need to grab out the starting
hit index there and we need to know how
many points there are these are both
exactly what we want to do here so
that's all good but we don't need these
two but we do need the repas ition so we
need to compute that by stepping out
along it after we do that we can do this
loop properly and that value will be
correct we can also do it again down
here in the nicely piggy way
and then but we you know once we get
down here the thing that we really need
to do is take that omission that you
know you know that new emission that
we're creating we need to remove some of
that light from the result and so that's
the next part that we have to do and so
we'll figure out how we're gonna do that
and second once we finish that then we
really are ready to do the emit C so we
can finish accumulating the sample and
everything is happy yeah and off we go
all right so let's take a look at how
this is working we start out with our
compute light propagation you know off
we go here and we're going to accumulate
into the desta mission values all of the
light that we gather and the only thing
that we haven't done yet is in here we
need a way to record the fact that some
of the emission got nerfed right this
can't happen in line actually so we can
get rid of that this has to happen at
the end so when we do our final loop
over all of the points this is the place
where we can actually reset the values
so yeah inside here yeah we can reset
these now I don't know we may at the
moment actually want to do these here
this way we always process every point
and so this will do that sort of final
push to get everything out of the
destination and clear the destination
and again we can probably clean all of
this stuff up once we notice that
everything's working because we can
structure our buffers properly to not do
any extra clearing or any extra anything
that we don't need to do so looking at
this here when we do this pass through
what we should be able to do is say well
however much we wanted to remove from
any given point what we should be able
to do is now say well whatever the desta
mission value for this point was we
should be able to remove as much of the
power as we wanted to from there right
so we're going to do something like this
we're into the decimate see we record
the fact that we've taken power out and
we're make sure we can never take out
more power than we had to begin with
just to make sure it never goes negative
so in here we know which one this is
this is the hit point index and what we
want to do is since we know we took
power out of it here and we know exactly
how much power we took out yeah we
should be able to
do the exact right amount of output
power so if the amount of power that
we're taking out is this power value
then how much we would normally take out
is just the power times that right like
this but we know that we're not using
all the power so what we're actually
doing is we're taking the inverse total
weight here and I'm gonna go ahead and
do it like this we're gonna need the
inverse total weight to normalize our
inverse distance squared and that's
going to give us the modification for
the power so we'll take the power we
want to multiply it by our contribution
which is the inverse distance squared
and then normalize by the by the inverse
total weight grant
so this says however much power we were
going to use total which is just
prescribed however much power we want to
remove on a particular sample we will
then use our distance squared as the
weighting value our inverse distance
squared is the weighting value and then
we'll divide Li divide that by the total
weight we know is there so that way we
take the fractional part of the power
that's respond that we're responsible
for and we only remove that much power
from the destination so I believe that's
correct we got a couple things we got to
do here so the Ray point this emit P so
the Ray is going to be the sample
direction oops
sample direction and the sample point P
the moon color we just want the RGB part
of that
retain see this is really not relevant
I guess although I suppose what was that
actually doing this was taking that fall
off into account as well I don't know
that we really want to do that
like I'm not sure we really want to do
this anymore this tells us the total
amount of light that came back so we
could if we wanted to do it after the
fact and actually remove the correct
amount of power based on how much we
used but I'm not so sure that that makes
sense because I don't we I don't know
that the amount that we actually
transfer here is related to how much it
should be giving off because it depends
on how you look at it the light gets
emitted one way or the other so yeah but
you know what since we did it that way
before I'll keep doing it that way for
now if we do want to do that all we have
to do is just this
so if you take a look at what's going on
here
this information right all has to come
from the hitbox stuff we can actually we
could actually do this all in line we
don't even need really need to do much
in the if statement if we don't want to
so what we could do is say okay this box
this whole thing here with the hit index
and the hit point count I think we
should be able to do this like this
right so if we look at what's going on
here Jimmy we should be able to do a
thing where we just
keep most things happening exactly the
same like so uh yeah like all of this
stuff can be exactly the same
effectively and then when we get down
here hit point count will be zero so we
will never enter these loops in the case
where we didn't hit a box but everything
else will proceed exactly the same so
then when we figure out how much point
point light we use there right so we
accumulate sample we get back our youth
see now we just know it's actually just
that amount of the used light would come
out here right now the reason that I'm
just not sure about that is because now
the color yeah see see that's just not
going to work because the color is gonna
be wrong it's since the color is a blend
of the multiple points yeah we can't we
can't keep doing it that way
so since we're using a blend we're gonna
have to we're gonna have to stick with a
way that doesn't that doesn't require us
to do that right
so I think we're gonna have to just nerf
this concept because once we blend the
colors together we can't keep them comp
like we can't keep them conserved
because we we wouldn't know exactly how
to reapportioned that information so I
think we do have to do it exactly this
way and this information just has to go
away unfortunately that's just how that
has to go and that's okay again if this
is all approximate so I don't think
there's we don't need to perfectly
conserve the energy in the system at all
all right so when we come on the app and
of this loop
I guess I'm going to do it let's see
yeah iteration counts not happening
anymore and it's not showing up there
all right so now we just have to debug
this which is not gonna be fun
obviously and yeah that's not a great
start as you'll notice we get no
lighting at all all right so let's go
ahead and start stepping through on the
plus side you will notice really great
frame right when you don't have any
lighting as it turns out oh it's not
it's not no lighting there's a little
bit of gray in there so I take it back
it's not quite no lighting it's very
very little light so let's go ahead and
step through there
and I'm gonna just basically walk myself
through that sort of new structure for
the routine and see how we go all right
so here we are we're gonna go over these
sample points take a look at here so you
can see there's the location sample
point there's the color that it's
reflecting and here's the normal
I don't think next free is ever used
anymore is it actually
yeah I don't think so so let's just get
rid of it so in we go
here is our sample point we are going to
take a random raid erection and that
should be pointing in the same direction
as this is which it sort of is it's a
pretty angled that's a pretty steep
angle to it but you know certainly still
correct and then we're gonna go ahead
and do our array cast here is the Ray
information we got back there was a box
that it did hit here's the information
for that box so when we come in here we
should enter this loop than we do and so
now we're going to take a look at what
our first point index is for this box
there should be four and there are and
it starts with that one we're gonna take
again our sample point and we're gonna
add however far we went along this ray
which was 2.7 meters here along that Ray
and again that sample Direction is
normalized so that's exactly how far it
should go we then have a total weight
value here this I assume it's normalized
we should we have total weight value
that we initialize to zero and we're
gonna sum we loop over the surface
points and we get the distance squared
to them that's how far away we are from
that one so it's inverse distance
squared is 0.8 there and so we sum up
the point eight and then we do using
that as a weighting factor we take the
reflected value and the source emission
here which let's find out what that
actually is
so this point source it doesn't give off
any light at all which I suppose will be
true for most of these so you know what
we may be seeing here is just the fact
that we're two under sampled to pick up
because we're not going from light
sources as with before again I don't
know if we need an initial seed pass on
the light sources to get the lighting
out into the environment but actually
that can't be true because we should be
picking up moonlight so I think we've
got just a bug in general anyway so if
we take the total weight that we picked
up there that's a reasonable value for
that to be taking the inverse total way
to strip the opposite of that and biz so
then we go over the surface points here
and we just decrease their power right
power values very very low
I feel like maybe we just need that
power value to not be quite so low
that's kind of way too low yeah let me
let me go ahead and also the moon color
is never actually getting multiplied by
the oh no just get math of the power
there yeah I think that power value is
just way too low I know how we would
ever accumulate Athan with that I guess
the previous one because it was
transmission paste it's not quite the
same but yet so I think here the power
yeah is just gonna be I don't think
light retention gets used anywhere else
so I think all we really want to do is
just say something like this right and I
don't know what those values want to be
tuned to yet but we'll have to see
so still really problematic in terms of
the sampling I'm not sure what's going
on there it almost looks like it doesn't
retain from frame to frame to me I
wonder if we just have a bug in how
we're doing our retention there let me
just double check something here let's
make it go really slowly
Yeah right we got to fix that we got to
clean up the game code one of these days
I keep putting enough because well it's
game code not injured code but
let me just take it what happens here a
lot of rays
yeah so something's kind of weird so I'm
doing something definitely wrong that's
not just because of the inbound versus
outbound lighting so something's up and
I'm not sure exactly what it is so let's
double check this again okay oh yeah
it's quite obvious actually so we are
never actually summing forward the
destinations emission so yeah we weren't
propagating forwards at all in fact so
in order to start with every point has
to get its emission from the last frame
added in to its destination in order for
it to persist the next round so yeah
that was just dumb so we were
effectively getting no no benefit from
the the actual previous round it was
just purely the original sampling right
so now I should be able to set this down
back to where it was and we should be
able to see sort of more where we're at
correctly with the lower sampling right
here so yeah so you can see first of all
is we do now that we've got moon light
in there you can see you get flicker
from the fact that you know the
moonlight samples are kind of
unpredictable and the blend amount also
is something is set you know pretty
pretty randomly now too we could we
could see what happens if we smooth
quite a bit more and it reduces the
lighting quite a bit but doesn't really
reduce the flicker enough so I feel like
we're still kind of not handling that
properly right it seems like the flicker
stays the same regardless of the blend
amount it's just the the brightness
right
that's pretty awesome
you get enough light in there you never
get rid of it
so yeah I am actually relatively
optimistic about this again we're still
gonna have to fight this this liquor
quite a bit but we're getting closer
all right
so yeah what we want to do now is start
to focus on how we can yet keep our
sampling to something that's going to be
more consistent obviously one way is to
require increase our sample camp but it
seems like maybe we've got other sources
of flicker I'm not entirely sure because
it didn't seem like increasing the
sample count reduce the flicker as much
as I would have expected it to to do
four is a very low number and when we
increased it to 64 I don't remember
seeing particularly great improvements
in the flicker right
so maybe what we want to do here is say
okay in this case here we're keeping the
same here's the thing that doesn't make
less sense to me so we're keeping
however much of the of what we had last
frame right so if I set the blend amount
to zero
oops it should say the same I guess we
don't want to do that out right off the
bat but if I change in the middle of the
lighting solution right so let's just
say we get a lighting solution the first
thing we should verify is that if I
actually go through here and pick a
particular spot if I come back and I
change the blend amount to zero
I should get a frozen light and I'm and
I don't
so something weird is happening here
right because if I if I literally can't
transfer any power away something's
busted I mean this value should always
be zero so I'm not sure how the
destination emission can ever get to be
anything else oh you know what retained
emission coefficient is exactly what's
happening there so let's say the
retained emission coefficient is always
one
so we keep everything undecaying in
theory now right if I come down here
let's turn it on
also it doesn't actually need to be
doing that weird large one right so here
is a retained power of one so there's no
decay factor at all and it's kind of
spreads out ad infinitum which I so I
guess in
in terms of decay here we want the decay
to come from this loop now let me just
go ahead and really quickly I guess it's
the skylight to that always because the
skylight is always adding power to the
system right I mean I don't know let's
let's take that out of the equation for
the time being
so here's no skylight right
so now in theory if I go ahead and turn
off the power transmission I should get
no change in the lighting it should just
be the same which looks like it is and
then when I turn it back on I should get
transmission there's a lesser
transmission all right so at least we
know that's correct there so the thing
that I'm focused on I think I still have
kind of a buggy approach to here is that
I feel like as the blend amount goes
down the flicker should go down but
that's not really what's going on I'm
still seeing a ton of flicker even if
the blend amount is 1/100 of the total
light transmission and moonlight is off
right so something's busted about how
this is working I'm not thinking about
the problem correctly because that
should just not be the case
so let's take a look at a couple
different things here
we know the destination Amit si will
always be zero zero zero at the start we
know that we come through the loop we
will for each sample point we will start
out by initializing its destination its
output emission to be whatever its input
emission was and that seems good and of
course we won't overwrite any
transmission that already happened if it
got transmitted from a point prior that
happened earlier in the loop as we come
through here we're going to take a
weighted average of these points to
permit to create our emission value
and the amount that we're going to add
for light into the system is going to be
the power right because we're gonna do
that in inside accumulate sample here I
don't know why we're using the length of
the light color oh because we are trunk
yep
nevermind that's just trying to figure
out that for the average direction of
the light so we're gonna use whatever
the power was times the light color and
we're just using the angular fall-off
factor there so we should be adding less
light to the system than we're taking
away because the angular fall-off right
should be taking light away from the
system so what I'm seeing happen is the
exact opposite of what I would expect so
I know we've got a bug in here somewhere
because that can't be correct right that
just can't be the case there shouldn't
be any way for it to be getting brighter
over time we should be getting dimmer
over time
hmm but again I really don't see it
I guess let's double check here let me
make sure that we're summing these
exactly the same way so in here where we
do our omit see I'm just gonna take this
power right if we were just summit
exactly and we could take if you if we
look here
we know that this power is going to
multiply the emit see here we can just
say all right the emit see here's our
weight it's going to be the inverse
distance squared times the inverse
totally we can even assert if the weight
is less than one and I mean we may have
to put an epsilon in there but we'll see
and then what we can do is say alright
we're going to reduce it by the power
times the weight and we're going to
increase the emit C by the weight we
even know that the contribs
is the same in both cases it's this so
that's how much we're contributing we're
going to remove that amount of light
from the surface we took it from and
we're going to put that into the amount
that we're about to distribute we don't
love to fly it by the power because
gonna get multiplied by the power down
here I don't expect that to do anything
different but I just wanted to sum them
in the same place using the same values
just to keep things a little clearer and
it's really not right it's that's
exactly what it was doing before right
so we have to figure out why this is
producing such a drastic difference and
so I'm going to do here is I'm going to
take a look at a couple things first
thing I'm going to do is I just want to
step through this and see what this
comes out to be so the weight values are
all this assertion is not firing so we
know the weight values are all exactly
as we would expect you know and the want
to make sure I present to you bug mode
there so I can look at everything and so
if I take a look at what's actually
happening here
it all looks exactly right to me I don't
know why I can't step in to accumulate
sample did this not come pre-compile or
something I was moving why is it moving
that down there there we go all right so
if I take a look at what's happening
with the yeah with the Destin bitsy
additions here I mean they're just that
power value is so tiny right basically
something's up
I kind of want to measure I kind of want
to measure the total light removed and
the total light distributed right so if
I was to to take you know these two and
I guess I can just reinstate this
temporarily or I should say total added
total removed so if I just measure these
two together right the total amount of
light that we add to the system at any
given time is going to be this and the
total amount removed is going to be this
so yeah you start with the same light
use that you assume you end with the
same light you started with and then
this is the thing that determines the
balance right so whatever you did in
here and whatever you did in here those
two things there
if total removed is more than total
added you should get dimmer if the
opposite is true you'll get brighter so
I'm just curious I want to see now what
those values look like over time and so
those values look exactly like what I
would expect them to look like the total
amount of light removed is always
greater than the total amount of light
added and so I would have thought that
we would get the opposite result from
what we were seeing right because of the
angular fall-off involved I would have
expected
[Music]
I don't understand how it's getting
brighter and now we have like numerical
proof that the thing that I'm assuming
should be happening is what it thinks is
happening as well so there is some bug
in how we're doing this computation and
I just don't know where it is but that's
our job we got to find that because you
can see this is not getting dimmer over
time it's getting brighter over time
like you can see that happening very
clearly right and yet the opposite
should be true now I guess technically
maybe I'm looking this the wrong way
technically we do add light to the
system though because we do add the
actual lights themselves so I guess what
we could say is that because we're
adding those lights themselves maybe
that's enough to tilt the balance in
favor of light always I mean
that certainly seems possible and you
know if you just don't have quite the
amount of sink but I mean it still seems
like an awfully fast spread rate for
such a small blend amount look what
happens if it's just ridiculously low
and so you can see that even when the
blending is incredibly slow you still
get a very high flicker rate right which
is totally wrong because if the only way
that something can change is by getting
samples from this small of a coefficient
how is it possibly flickering it should
not be able to change how much light it
has by very much at all on any given
frame it should be almost impossible
right to have to affect any change so
the fact that we're getting such an
obvious flicker even it's such a small
framerate
suggests to me that something pretty
majorly wrong is happening with how I'm
doing this and I just don't know what it
is
but I'm going to have to figure out a
creative way to look at it
and again I thought and I mean will
Rivera fie it but I also thought that we
have no flicker nothing changes if I
just take a particular state of the
lighting system and turn the blend
equation to zero and I guess you know
what I can go back to real time now
right so you know flickering like crazy
right just absolutely nuts how much
flickering despite the fact that it's
supposed to not be able to change hardly
at all if I go ahead and change the
blend amount to zero and I mean that the
nuts thing about that is look at what
happened instantaneously these went from
red to black even weirder so I think
this flicker is coming from a bug in
terms of how we're treating the the
lights on output and not from anything
else because when you can only change
the lighting by that much every frame
per ray and you're only casting for rays
I mean it should be impossible to get
flicker it should be almost impossible
to get flicker
even if lights were a thousand bright
they could only affect the RGB color by
one like frak by one 100th of its
brightness in a perfect scenario if all
four rays hit a thousand bright light
and that's just not common that's just
not the common case so let's double
check our assumptions maybe something
outside the loop is screwing a set so
let's take a look here when we're coming
through for outputting
the results of the lighting here you can
see me going through and we're never
going to hit this case anymore because
valid is always equal to false we're
always going to come through here and
for each point we're gonna copy back the
emit c0 into the permanent storage and
we're going to take the direction and
we're going to normalize it
which makes sense right that's what we
want to do it could be that that average
direction to light is what's flickering
you know what maybe that's what's
happening maybe because we don't know
what the average direction to the light
is yeah yeah yeah
that's what's happening because we don't
know what the average directional light
is if it's zero we will get no lighting
so that's the flicker it's coming from
the average direction to light not being
set so if instead when we seed our
lighting we also seated our average
direction to light here I bet our
problem goes away right so here where we
take our light in like so I'm going to
go ahead and also take the average
direction to light in as well so we'll
seed with that initial value and let's
see what that does to the situation
so now I'm still getting a ton of
flicker there did I do that right
average direction delight lady indexical
smack storage local index direction what
do we do with that we clear it that's no
good so I did absolutely nothing with
that try that one more time there we go
now that's what I was expecting okay
finally got to the bottom of it now
let's try a more reasonable blend amount
much better and finally now we need to
work on our transmission amount this is
the light retention factor here so what
I think we want to do is again you know
I don't know how much light we want to
remove per frame I'm not sure exactly
how we want to do this we got to work on
how we want to do this this may require
the blackboard this might be tomorrow's
job because you can see we get a lot of
flicker if we have something in that
actually decays
so I'm gonna go ahead and say let's get
rid of the retained emission coefficient
there copy those two pieces of
information out okay and furthermore one
of the nasty problems about this is we
also need to know how much we want to
weight this average direction to light
here so that's a little bit hard to say
as well but hopefully that that will not
be too much a big deal we also don't
know that we ever really want to use the
other direction light we may just decide
that that's a dumb thing and we can
should get rid of it but so you can see
that we're getting a little bit too much
instant popping of light that as it
comes in there so there's something
still a little busted with how we're
doing our transmission here that power
the blend amount power it's seems to be
much too powerful and I'm not sure why
so our omit C is somehow much too large
even though it should be quite a bit
lower and I don't know why that is now
that could be because the max light
value is too high and so we're just
transmitting way too much light it's
hard to say
yeah I feel like we're gonna have to do
some black boarding on this because I'm
I'm kind of now just tweaking a value
for no apparent reason and we kind of
want to make sure we know what's going
on with that right so there's clearly a
balance here and it seems like light is
never getting removed the systems in a
sufficient amount compared to how much
is getting put in which is kind of odd
as well so so if you take a look at max
light emission here for example you know
I wonder if this is really the thing
that wants to be coefficient
like how much light you put in the
system is a little bit more conserved
so the amount you preserve is the part
that's kept up and the part that you put
in is much less it still looks like
that's always gonna add light though you
can see it's always adding light to the
system no matter how low we make that
value so yeah we're getting closer
though what time is it I got four
minutes left all right I'm gonna call it
there because we got rid of one of our
major bugs and we rewrote this routine
to work more properly so what I'm gonna
say is we just now need to work on our
light power distribution how we're gonna
decay and how we're gonna make sure it
propagates fast enough I think we're
getting close though I think we're
getting close
what I might say is like let's say you
know as just an example test here
suppose we did emit see this this part
here we do a remove see suppose we
always remove you know removal ratio or
something like this suppose we had a
thing here where we could remove a
certain amount of power on bounces and
so our removal ratio you know what's
going to be higher like for example we
don't really want this to go negative so
we would probably have to threshold it
but basically this part right here will
just clamp so at the end here we'll say
can we do a whole vector clamp here I
just want to check that's greater than
zero so
let's do it this way so something like
this so that way I can make the removal
ratio be something higher so we can
remove twice as much light as we tried
to add even on top of the previous part
right it's so weird that that still
doesn't seem to be enough I feel like
there's maybe one more bug in here
okay it it's got to be the case that
we've got a bug where we're just not
removing white
like it just looks like the light never
really gets removed
I'm just going nuts with this value now
just to see so I can crank it high
enough to make it so that it kills any
transmission all right
super-weird alright so basically we've
got some weird stuff going on here and
we're gonna have to debug this tomorrow
so that'll be our job tomorrow is to
figure out how to get the light balance
to be correct because it's not correct
at the moment
something something definitely is odd
there let's go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A
I'll be finishing to see exactly what's
going on with that light it's
interesting it always seems to retain a
fair bit of it there's something still
one more thing in there that I just
don't get it's kind of cool
what's happening right now but totally
not it's totally a bug
mmm-hmm and go I don't think you're
laying prone kind of like photon mapping
but weird will work I think it's worth
rethinking well we've rethought it a
couple times so I'm totally not adverse
to it however I'm not sure I'm ready to
say that it won't work yet it would help
if you said why you don't think it will
work also so we could discuss that
doesn't service need to need a hit to
have its light reduced if nothing it's
the surface the light will remain
constant yes
which i think is okay
actually so you know what's interesting
is actually this should be
bi-directional too shouldn't it like
when you have a Ray between two of them
they should they should transfer light
between each other
technically this is running on only one
core of the GPU by the way so when we
actually see if we multi-threaded it on
the CPU side or move it to GPU it would
run very very fast compared to what's
running now
and you know and have wait emit see plus
equals wait times contribs see no I I
think that's correct that's what I
intended anyway
whatever using for coder is the rpi
still a thing what is the RPI
it's interesting yeah I was just
thinking about the bi-directional nature
of this so when you hit something you
should transfer light between the two of
you technically
you know what and also there's another
aspect of it is when you're transferring
light because you're using the previous
lighting to do the transfer you also
it's unclear whether it's correct to not
use the same array because sampling from
the previous light solution is going to
allow you to multiple use the amount of
light coming from any given source right
so if you take a look at this it's
really not correct to have to to do a
previous in the next you pretty much
need to make it so that as you do hits
you are moving the light around that you
have but yeah
but hango this is radiosity that's what
we're doing the previous loop was more
like radiosity because it goes from
emitters out which is the traditional
well there's both kinds of radiosity
right but this is literally radiosity so
the thing you just told me to Google is
what we've been doing so yeah it's not
over the top for a live game
it's what live games do granted they're
not 2d games they're usually full 3d
games but
does anyone know what the rpi thing was
there we still
I just need to know what acronym RPI is
referring to here cuz I'm not sure what
the question was
Oh Raspberry Pi yeah I mean that
definitely at some point when we're done
will port to Raspberry Pi whichever
incarnation is popular at that time we
will have to turn off a bunch of
graphics features for that because the
Raspberry Pi just doesn't have much in
the way of graphics horsepower so like
we won't be able to use full lighting or
any of that stuff on a Raspberry Pi but
we will be able to run the game part of
the game just fine and we'll have a
reduced you know unlit version let's say
at prop at not you know not 1080p and
not lit but you know the rest of the
game will be fine
all right so in bits end of queue so
tomorrow I'm gonna try making this
bi-directional and I'm using one array I
think that's what I'd like to try and
we'll see how that goes again just in
case since there were some fusion this
is absolutely how radiosity works this
is exactly how radiosity works you can
even literally look at the previous loop
was like straight out of radiosity I'll
show you what I mean see where we get
sampling approaches right so here you go
[Music]
so this is what we're talking about
right here a sampling method for you
know without having to update everything
at once and they're the predominantly
ones that are probably used for obvious
reasons and what you can sort of see is
this is exactly what we're doing right
we have a path tracing program that uses
the past that it ends up with to
transfer light between two surfaces and
there's a shooting based schemes is more
specifically what we're talking about
right in the previous loop and a gather
based scheme is what we have now so like
a shooting based scheme which that this
page is not very good because it's
asking you to look at something else
there's probably a better page
if you could look for if you wanted to
no I don't know if this is good or not
but like the previous one was a shooting
based scheme because it basically starts
at the emitters and looks outward right
and the new one is more of a gather
based scheme because it starts at the
receiver and works outwards but what I
just realizing is we might as well just
do it by directional because every one
in this case is both an emitter and a
receiver so there's really no reason to
do them separately like that um so yeah
so yeah just just to be clear again
since there was some confusion there
this is absolutely radiosity there's no
other description for it you ain't
photon mapping because photon mapping is
although they're similar because they're
both path tracing based right photon
mapping just basically says I'm gonna
start at the emitter I'm gonna shoot
photons from the emitter as particles
every time they hit a surface I'm gonna
either decide to keep the particle on
the surface or resend it and then at the
end I just take the total number of
particles on every surface and that's my
brightness right and that's not what
we're doing here again the difference
being radiating photon tracing is
actually very small but keeping the
transfer between surfaces and the total
number of light on the surfaces as
actual values is what makes something
more like radiosity whereas just
treating it as a single set of particle
shots is what makes it more like photon
tracing but thinking of them as two
different techniques is really not
correct they're very similar
mm-hmm I thought radiosity approximates
the light for one area and not tracing
glorious areas no so radiosity can be
implemented in multiple ways so there
are radiosity techniques that just do an
N squared pass over all the surfaces and
try to solve in a giant in one giant
solve try to figure out how the light
will normalize that is not the common
way to do it anymore because it's
intractable in a lot of cases so the
common way to do it now is iterative
with sampling based approaches so you
basically just count that you try to
structure your solver so that as you
sample you converge on a valid result
right in game development it becomes you
know difficult because you don't have a
lot of time so you tend to spread it out
over multiple frames but it's the same
basic idea Kurush crust says McGuire's
2016 paper deep g buffer for stable
global elimination has a very good
implementation of radiosity and his
implementation of a deep G buffer is not
just the def peeling you are using and
handmade hero oh that sounds pretty good
I have not seen this paper maybe we
should look at it
so it looks like they do that's
interesting
you
I'm not sure we really want to go this
route because this is entirely screen
space even though it's depth field
that might be fine for us though I mean
it's hard to say I'll have to read it in
more detail and they do keep it from
frame to frame just like we are
are we implementing transparency yes we
do do transparency to a limited extent
like you can't stack up an infinite
number of things you can stack up like
one or two things right that's already
happening in fact do we did we turn off
the particles let me turn back on the
particles
so you can see the although these guys
fall through the floor since they don't
bounce at the moment but you can see
that these guys are actually transparent
right and they fade out I think that's
the only objects in the world that we
have that are transparent at the moment
that's transparent right there obviously
it gets transparent it's gets close to
the camera so there's a transparent
surface as well the depth feeling just
handles that and you know and if when
you remove the light of the current
frame remove see after say five frames
you have to in some way clear Desa see
and add only source see and restoreth
the blend otherwise it will add forever
very small portions will get added
constantly did I misunderstand something
um so in theory anyway the I guess why I
say is I don't know there may be a bug
in it so we'll start with that but in
theory anyway
the we're adding light to the scene
every frame because the lights
themselves are getting added in so it is
true that we add light and that is
something we have to account for but we
also remove light every frame by the
fact that angular fall-off is not
accounted for so we are removing about
twice as much light per frame as we
we're removing the amount of light
that's transported per frame is about
half as much as the amount we take out
yet that's still not enough to balance
out the fact that we're adding light
every frame apparently although we could
also just have a bug so I really want to
make sure that we don't have a bug first
if that makes sense but yeah and the
other thing I'd like to do is click
switch to using just one array because I
feel like that's another source of
problem
because basically when we create the new
array we have sampled from the old array
so here's this do you want to hear a
really dumb idea I have a dumb idea just
just just bear with me for one second I
was just thinking of a really stupid
idea that I want to try so one thing we
could say is what if we just said the
total amount of light has to be constant
right what if we just said that so so
what if we just said okay when we start
we're just going to assume that we have
a total light value and every time we
come through here we're gonna say that
the total light is gonna be you know
whatever it's gonna be added right I so
we just say and in fact you know what
we'll just do it I don't even do it
there I'll do it over here do it at the
end so we're gonna come through here
we're gonna do our our point index some
twice total source light total deaths
light like I just go okay
i sum up the total source light and the
total test light and I see how much
light we have and I just make them they
have to be the same just throwing it out
there as a really dumb idea so I say
okay my source emits E
and my destiny at sea I've got so uh see
I'm going with this so I then know the
ratio of these two things so assuming
that my source sum is greater than zero
which it always should be if there's any
light in the scene at all right the
other thing too is the moon here is is
not really getting totally accounted for
so I mean maybe I say this starts with
moon color I don't know right
so you know let's some power times the
moon color there I don't know this is
again very very stupid as I said before
so then when we come through here we
just say all right look the we're just
going to go ahead and we don't even care
about the subtraction part like it
doesn't matter or something we don't
care what happens there we do our remove
C value we don't have to worry about the
clamping because we don't have that
removal coefficient here so this doesn't
happen so all we do here is say look we
know that we want our sort of our
normalization ratio right our
normalization for the color we want the
desk some two we want the desks we want
to bring ourselves back up actually so
how do I want to do that I have the
total I want it to equal the previous so
actually this is backwards right so I I
have a destination I want it to equal my
source so I'm just gonna literally
multiply when we come through I'm just
gonna literally multiply the destined it
C by the normal coefficient and that's
just how we're gonna restore our light
amount period again I have no reason to
suggest this is a good idea it's
probably not I'm just gonna do it anyway
because I can write so this should in
theory normalize our lights so that we
can't add light the system of course it
doesn't seem to be working but it should
right did I get that right
I'll leave out the room color for now
so I feel like that should be keeping
our light from expanding like it is and
yet it isn't I mean let me go ahead and
step through that I'll see what that's
doing sorry I know we're supposed to be
done but I just I want to see what
happens here
very interesting so we just we do just
have a bug here and I guess that's the
amount of light that's being put into
system so let's take a look at this just
one other way what if I simply said the
source zone was fixed to a particular
value
so you could only have a certain amount
of light in the scene okay I'm just
making this up as I go don't know how
much light should be in the scene not
sure why that would have created such an
odd effect
unless I'm just too low
seems about right I don't like how spiky
these numbers are
like those are just a really high
numbers way too high for floating-point
really to be sadly
let's get a little more light in there
it's basically exposure control in a
sense right we're basically saying like
okay there's going to be a certain
amount of exposure control here
just playing around that moonlight
it's certainly interesting
gotta make sure I fix the make the
lighting volume properly track the
camera it's currently room based which
is dumb that's why I get that white
flicker over there
it's really weird the way the flickering
still works I don't know I'm still not
willing to believe that we don't have
some issues here I wonder if that's just
because our light max values are too
high
because that again the total amount of
light remember is supposed to be being
clamped here right we're forcing it to
be a particular value and in fact I
suppose I should be able to actually
double-check that there's a thing that
we can use to check the destination
light as well all right let's play with
this value again
it's weird you can actually see that
exposure control like it's actually sort
of changing the overall brightness
that's pretty bizarre let me go and
change that moonlight back now all the
lights are max power one
yeah I don't know I still think we've
got issues and I'm just not quite sure
yet
so we'll see but we got to play around
with it a little bit I'm gonna I'm gonna
see what happens if this value is made
you know something not ten
and so you can see that like the I guess
one of the problems is on every frame
you will concentrate the the light
concentration at the actual light source
becomes quite high because not very much
of it is coming out and so when you sum
up all of that transmission amount you
end up counting from mostly the light
that's in the light source right it's
interesting so I think yeah I think
we're like maybe one more sort of
transformation away from having this
working in a way that we can use
reliably I think we just need to go over
how we want to transfer light between
the surfaces and get that dialed better
and again the idea is to slowly diffuse
the light over time while not adding or
removing light from the system in a way
that produces objectionable artifacts
right and part of the problem there is
we have the concept of an emitter which
is something that emits light so we'll
also need a concept of saying that that
takes light away right and so I think if
we just kind of balance those out and by
doing it by directional which I think
I'll do tomorrow I think we could do
that because the sky light would take
light away and in general that transfer
takes light away in theory I think we
can get something that allows slow
transmission but still actually works
right so we'll see
what comes after lighting any ideas
after lighting we gonna go we're gonna
go clean up the game code since now we
kind of know exactly what needs to go on
in there we're gonna just go to go in
and make it so that like you know add
some nice controls and like basically
allow you to kind of play through a bit
and sort of in tandem that will we'll
probably do some will clean up the art
asset stuff so we can put in some real
art assets just got a basic start on on
game stuff game passes the current code
base is pretty manageable it's not that
big there's a clock we had a clock
program but I don't know that it's
installed on this computer when I change
computers I can go grab that will you
that up because I would like to read
that paper
I don't know what that means does that
mean SourceForge is down
here we go
uh so I don't know if this is installer
or not I'm assuming not but it might be
nope
so we should be able to do it so there
you go I think that's accurate probably
possibly
John must know if I can work yakety sax
into the program somehow the question is
not whether I can work it in but how I
would avoid the copyright violation and
imminent lawsuit right because I think
we all know that handmade hero once it
is released on Steam will make like
literally billions and billions of
dollars right and so the problem that
you're gonna have there is that then the
people who make yakety sax are gonna
come and take all the money right so the
question is just how do you solve that
problem so if John you wanted to
purchase the rights to yakety sax and
then donate them to the handmade hero
project I feel like that's totally
acceptable to me and we would have to
create them in after you've saved that
may 31 note like Vanilla Ice did or or
Ray Parker jr. would be because there
would be the other one to look at
I feel like handmade hero could feature
a suite of Huey Lewis and the news
modified songs
right uh all right I'm gonna go ahead
shut down all right Thank You Vern for
joining me for an episode of handmade
hero it's been a pleasure coding with
you as always if you want to follow
along with the program
on the stream you can always figure to
the game on handy hero or it comes with
source code so you can could follow
along at home just like you know picture
pages if you were a kid and had picture
pages uh anyway I will be back tomorrow
when we'll take a look at changing the
light transfer there because it's mostly
where I want it to be but we just have
to get a little bit more rigorous about
the math of the lighting transfer before
we can actually use it as something
that's that's you know valuable and
useful and contributory to the game
that's about it I will be back here
tomorrow so up to join you hope you will
join me for that until then have fun
programming everyone and I'll see you on
the Internet
take it easy everybody