hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete game live on
stream yesterday we sort of did some
pondering regarding lighting and you
know where we ended yesterday's stream
was kind of at the point where we're
like well there really isn't any obvious
solution here I mean that's sort of
where we were at and that's not
surprising that's just how lighting is
lighting is one of those things that's
just still prohibitively expensive to
implement in some kind of like first
principles way where you're just really
simulating light the way light really
works or something like that and so the
approximations are always pretty drastic
and it's very hard to know what the most
economical approaches for any particular
situation especially since I'm not a
rendering person you're not spend all my
time working on rendering and there are
plenty of people who do exactly that in
the game industry there's people whose
entire job it has been for many years to
just think about rendering and when
you're talking about just thinking about
rendering usually you are just thinking
about light most of the time right
that's a lot of what rendering is its
light how it behaves off surfaces how it
behaves in camera lenses how it behaves
in participating media that sort of
stuff and so you know someone who was
more of a day-to-day render programmer
than I am probably has some stronger
opinions about these things doesn't mean
they're necessarily right in some
abstract sense but it does mean that
they usually have you know here's how I
like to solve these problems so they
would probably look at our game and they
would probably say here's how I want to
approach this because they've already
done lots of experimentation and lots of
circumstances and they know what they
like right other render people might
have a different take right but again
they would still know what they like so
I think that there is a pretty
reasonable chance that a more
experienced render programmer kind of
person would would have a direction they
really want
to go but I don't because I don't spend
my time doing rendering programming very
often it's one of the smaller parts of
what I tend to do on a day to day basis
and so I don't have a like
overwhelmingly strong bias towards
implementing the lighting in one way or
another as a result like sort of where I
ended yesterday stream was saying well I
don't know I mean you know here's some
ways we could do it I'm like I don't
have any particular opinion about it I
and where I sort of ended up was like
well let's try something that light
probe asked right that's sort of where I
ended up so the thing with doing light
probes is basically how that you know
how light probing works is you have
points in your scene that are find as
light probe points those light probe
points are kids to the render about
where it should spend this time trying
to find lighting solutions and then
anything that wants to get lit typically
uses the light probes to interpolate the
lighting between them right so that's
basically what we're looking at now I
wanted to to sort of point something out
here that's a little confusing but I'll
just start by doing it out let me also
mention today is for 92 so if you want
to follow along at home you want to used
a 3/4 90s good 392 you want to use days
day 3 91 source code because that's what
I've got here that I'm starting with so
I if we take a look here ooh that Visual
Studio started up much quicker maybe
uninstalling the throw
I don't even know so it's amusing
literally I folks who are watching this
in the youtubes won't have no myth but
literally moments ago in the pre stream
I was talking about how commercial
suffer is like unusable these days
because licensing makes it impossible to
maintain a same development environment
because things are always breaking and
they usually break as the licensing
doesn't work well as if on cue
here we are with our Visual Studio
community 2013 edition right which I'm
only using normally I use Visual Studio
2012 because that's what I have a
commercial license for but I was using
Visual Studio for me 2013 edition
because when we started this project I
wanted to use something that people
could access who don't have a lot of
money so we picked the version back but
even though it's a freely available
product Microsoft of course has decided
that it will break every once in a while
right now who knows why they decided
break maybe they thought it was just a
good idea to make people renew their
licenses because you got to check in
with Uncle Bill to make sure that you
know he's ok with you using the software
or maybe this is just a bug because hey
everything else individuals to do has
bugs in it so of course the licensing
problem probably the licensing software
probably would - right
but either way this is exactly the sort
of thing that now happens with pretty
much all commercial software cuz it's
happened to me with my commercial
license of Visual Studio 2012 that I
actually use for work at work right and
this is what acceptable I don't know why
we think this is acceptable right I I
don't think anyone would be ok with this
in other realms but software is like
grooming people to be ok with it if you
went down to try and start your car
in the morning and it says that you
couldn't drive to work because you
hadn't checked with Ford to see if you
still own the car I'm pretty sure people
would be furious about that right if you
went to your refrigerator and opened it
up and you found that all of your food
had rotted because the refrigerator said
that it could not verify with Frigidaire
that you still owned the refrigerator
these would be ridiculous things right I
don't feel like anyone would be okay
with that I feel like that company would
probably go out of business
yet somehow and I don't know how people
think this is an acceptable way to ship
software and again not just free
software like Visual Studio community
2013 but actual community but actual
commercial software because the
commercial version of Visual Studio does
exactly the same thing trust me I have
it and it does so basically what it is
is you're paying people to create
problems for you which is absolutely
ridiculous right it should not be
something that that people put up with
and I don't know why they do so I don't
know there's two things we can do here
one thing we can do is we can you know
we can take this machine and say all
right let's let's check for an updated
license and try to get Microsoft to
agree to license this thing to us that
you know ostensibly has but you know you
can go on my stream and watch me having
use it for two years and apparently
that's not sufficient to verify that it
actually was something that I should be
using but oh well
or we can decide just never to use this
piece of software again which honestly
at this point I'm a little bit more
inclined to do so you know the other
option we have is install Linux on this
machine and just get rid of the
Microsoft software entirely which
honestly if this point seems like a
pretty good idea the other thing we
could do is try to switch to something
like clang and get rid of
Visual Studio on the on the sort of
window side of things while still using
windows I don't know which of those is a
particular good idea obviously we have
some issues the same issues that
everyone else has and the only reason
that I assume people ever are still on
Windows anyway which is that you sort of
have a vested platform buy-in where
various pieces of software that you use
are only available on particular
platforms so for example we need to be
able to use for coder for our editing
and we need to be able to use OBS for
our video streaming and we need to be
able to use Milton for our blackboard
right that's what we tend to use now of
those pieces of software I'm pretty sure
that poor coder has a Linux version I
don't know if Milton though so let's
check
[Applause]
so some are on here there's a downloads
right download and so let's see what
it's got where's the github there it is
yes so I'm pretty sure I'm pretty sure
this is Windows only now I don't think
it would take a lot to port it right
here's the source code here's the source
code and you can kind of see that
there's even some a little bit of Linux
suggestion here right like the platform
Windows UNIX Mac svl right so I don't
know to what extent this is supported or
going to be supported on other platforms
it's a good question we should ask
surgery about that yeah you can see here
this Linux and OS X port is tended for
the future so but here's how you do the
build for example and so you know it's
not out of the question that we could
get to a point where we could use this
for drawing on Linux right so that's
good right we and we have a source so if
we had to court it ourselves hey Sergio
if we had to port it ourselves we could
probably do something like that as well
right so those are really the only two
things we need because I'm pretty sure
OBS I already works on Linux right OBS
studio which is the latest version is
Linux compliant so I think that would
not be a particular problem either
so I guess what I would say there is
what do we want to do it's a really
tough question right it's a really tough
question I feel like we should take a
poll about what we should do here do we
want to try to get Visual Studio working
or do we want to switch to Linux I feel
like there's a lot of cost of switching
to Linux right we won't have a
particularly good debugger anymore
because there really aren't any dividers
for Linux that that are any good so it'd
be pretty rough we did that we could try
to use Klingon here but then of course
we have the same problem we wouldn't
have a really useful debugger right so
it would be pretty tough if that makes
sense so yeah I don't know I guess what
we can do is we can try to see I don't
know what this is really asking me for
here I don't the only reason I would
have one of these is for when we
authorize this initially so I can look
up the password for it I guess because I
would have saved it and then try to get
it to work so maybe we'll do this this
seems fair
I will try putting in my account
credentials here and if it works we will
keep using Windows if it doesn't work
then we switch to Linux that's I think
the fair the fair option right I don't
think I mean if they don't want me to
use their software they don't want me to
use their software right Microsoft makes
it abundantly clear almost everyday that
they don't want me to
their software and this is a pretty
blatant example of that so we'll give
them one more chance and if the doesn't
work then we move on hold on
all right I have gotten my personal
laptop out and I am looking up see what
what we've got
all right so I don't really know if this
is accurate here whoa okay I did that I
think that worked all right here we go
we're going to enter our our password
here and everyone will now know how many
letters there are in my password or
numbers I guess but that's fine because
honestly if somehow you decided to
brute-force my Microsoft password this
is the only thing on my Microsoft
password so all you would really have is
a nonworking version of Visual Studio No
I is this a joke I mean really is that
are you actually showing that who writes
this stuff did that work
I have no idea if it worked it looks
like we're able to launch fizzle to do
now all right
thankfully I happen to save that
password Microsoft is saved for the time
being I have no idea what that dialog
box was asking me
all right well that was fantastic so
productive so all right I was trying to
if I can even remember what was going on
here oh good and it forgot which
projects we normally have loaded
apparently because it was like I got a
load my license file that's the
important part not what you were working
on Casey you're working on stuff that is
irrelevant to me so what I wanted to
talk about was the fact that if you
recall we are a fake 3d render in a lot
of ways because we have to work with
sprites which aren't actually 3d so we
have to kind of do some shenanigans to
make that work properly and what you can
see here is that when you are working in
the normal view that we expect that
spine to say that's the angle the
sprites are drawn to look like so
everything's good but if we look at
other camera angles like you can see
here we end up in a situation where the
you know the individual sort of sprites
wouldn't really be looking like they
look if you were looking from this angle
right and you know that's fine because
we never look from down here but
obviously when we're talking about doing
stuff like rendering light probes or
something if there were if these things
are going to occlude light they need to
be standing up straighter right they
need to be standing like upright so we
have a fundamental disconnect again with
our two and a half d miss or whatever
you want to call this 3d with sprites I
don't know what but the fact that we do
our rendering in sort of this way to
support sprites which we need to because
that's how the art goes we have a
problem of trying to figure out exactly
what we're going to do as far as doing
like light occlusion and stuff like that
because we probably can't render things
in
this way because if you were looking
like this you'd see nothing along the
rest but you should see a big wall of
trees blocking it right as far as
lighting is concerned so it sort of
strikes me as being the case where when
we render when we render the world for
lighting we almost need to do it in a
sort of different way than when we
render the world for visuals right so
this kind of got me thinking you know or
I should say gets me thinking I haven't
really thought it through yet but this
makes me kind of think a little bit
harder about how we might want to treat
the lighting versus how we treat
everything else and so what I wonder is
I do wonder if maybe what we need to do
is something more like a voxel ization
path or something like this on the game
that's really more about splatting sort
of vague colors in rather than trying to
render actual stuff and the reason that
I'm thinking about that is just because
since our game is not at all
geometrically accurate in 3d I'm not
sure we can really do something like
rendering light probes in a traditional
sense in the way you normally would
because I'm afraid that they won't
really capture anything that we need
them to capture right so what I'm
wondering is if we need to do something
more like splatting colors into a
texture that we then kind of just blur
out and use for the lighting or you know
something like this and I'm not really
sure I don't know I don't know what we
want to do in
regarde so I still think we don't quite
have what we need to know in order to
really produce reasonable lighting but
given all that I guess what I would say
is I think we might want to skew more
towards the taking a sort of pseudo 3d
texture approach screen space 3d texture
sort of a thing and then sampling that
and that seems like maybe a little bit
more of a of an approach we could take
right so let's talk a little bit about
that and then let's me me what I
thinking I might do is try using a 3d
texture to do non directional lighting
so that we could get that working and
then figure out how to sort of bootstrap
that into something that worked for
directional lighting right so what do I
mean here so let's imagine that we just
wanted to do the exact same lighting
that we're doing now but we wanted to
look it up in a texture right so what
are we doing right now well right now
what we do is we say all right here's
the world we know that there is a point
light source in it we gave it a
particular fall-off right that it has in
the world and so from there we just know
okay if there's a thing here we compute
the lighting based on its distance from
this thing and off we go
right but where it's always a point
right it's a vector that's like a
position of the light and a strength of
the light I think of the two things we
did so how bright it is and where it is
so if we wanted to do this instead in a
texture you can imagine doing sort of a
reverse process right if we wanted to
make a texture for this what we could do
is say well all right let's suppose that
something was here what
do is just sample from the texture what
if lighting is and then what we would do
is we'd say go the opposite direction if
I've got a light that's in here I render
the light into the texture as a big blob
and then I'm done right and then when I
come in and I look it up I get what the
lighting should be at those points right
pretty straightforward
uh so so allergy there's lots of
construction in Seattle and I feel like
it kicks up this is my like crackpot
theory I feel like there's so much
debris in the air that I'm always sneezy
about it it's probably not true
so shall we just plants anyway so doing
this is not particularly difficult to
conceptualize right it's just that it's
the these two processes sort of like
Reverse from each other in one you just
take the light source and you store just
the like two pieces of information
necessary to reconstruct it and then
every time you want to shade a pixel you
just use these two and the lighting
equations to reconstruct with the
lightest at this point the same thing
happens here in Reverse we take those
two things and we rasterize them out
into the whole texture then we sample
from it right and you can see why this
is something that I'm interested in
doing it's because this allows me to
start getting a lot more information
into the lighting if I wanted thousands
of licen here I would have to every
pixel compute the lighting equation for
thousands of lights and that's not going
to fly on the other hand if I do this
rap forward rasterizing a thousand
lights into this texture is relatively
cheap and when I then go to look up a
pixel it's just a constant lookup time
to just fetch out what the lighting
ended up being there right
now it has some downsides which is that
the the bat texture obviously only has a
certain limited resolution and the
higher resolution it is the more
expensive it will be in
blah-blah-blah-blah-blah
right so there's definitely costs to it
it's not free and there's all sorts of
ways we might encode it and things like
that but it's you know reasonable so you
might imagine taking this and extending
this to three dimensions as well if we
took the view frustum for example and we
said alright let's take the area we're
viewing here is the far clip plane here
is the near clip plane which are
whatever we want them to be and let's
divide this up into cells
now that's a 3d texture right because
again this is a frustum so it's actually
this sort of thing right
so you can imagine us taking a
essentially voxel lives version of the
view and just creating out of that our
lighting right and so that seems pretty
reasonable to me right the only thing
that's kind of tricky about it is again
figuring out then I guess what I say is
the resolution might be an issue hard to
say the cost of rasterization costs will
look up those sorts of things but the
biggest problem that we will have here
is when we want to simulate the
directionality of the lighting right so
the problem that we get is lighting
intensity and color can sum together so
I can splat as many lights as I want in
here and in the places where they
overlap like in here I can just sum up
the RG and B intensities and get a
perfect representation of the brightness
of those lights at that point right no
problem what I can't record is what
direction the light is coming from right
because each one of those lights was
coming from a different direction so
when I sum up the intensities that's
accurate if I were to sum up the
direction I get the average direction
the light was coming from but the
average direction the light was coming
from doesn't really mean anything right
so the surface response is going to be
completely wrong if I've got three
lights let's say and I only keep one
direction which of course as we all know
is the best band one direction and so
what we're really talking about is
keeping the band one direction at every
Texel here but in addition to keeping
the band one direction we also have to
compute the lighting equation and
unfortunately one of the things that a
lot of people don't know about the band
One Direction is they don't actually
know very much about physics so
unfortunately when we go to use
one direction to figure out what the
lighting is we will not get a very good
result right and to make this more
explicit you can imagine this yourself
here is a cube looking top-down these
two faces obviously point in opposite
directions here is a set of lights that
are overlapping the cube here is a red
light here is a green light I would
expect when I compute the lighting for
this face to be almost entirely green I
would expect that this face should be
almost entirely red right but if all I
store is the intensities here they will
both be sort of greenish red right
because what will end up happening is I
don't have any way of storing which
direction each of those colors came from
so that's the problem right that's the
problem you end up getting so what do we
do about this well probably what we want
to do about this is take some sort of a
hybrid approach right what we want to be
able to do here is store something into
our texture that allows us to
reconstruct the directionality of the
lighting a little right that gives us
some ability to do something with the
directionality of the light if possible
right and so what a lot of people tend
to do with stuff like this is they'll
use for example in coatings so you may
have heard of like spherical harmonics
spherical harmonics is one way of
encoding a mush of lighting in a way
that keeps the the light values in a way
you can reconstruct some directionality
from them
and you can think of this as being very
analogous to like the Fourier transform
for audio for example
where you're taking this complicated
signal right this sort of like you know
here's my audio signal and turning it
into a series of like a graphic
equalizer version of like various sine
wave frequencies right so spherical
harmonics is exactly the same sort of
thing circle harmonic says let's go
ahead and store some directionality to
the sphere right the incoming sphere of
information let's store like the primary
lobes of that incoming infinite light
right and it's again in order to really
reconstruct the lighting in its entirety
you need to store lots of coefficients
on the sphere and I can try to show you
those that there's a good diagram here
on the spherical harmonic coefficients
oops I didn't month here you go
so this is a tree of lobes and these are
sort of intensity lobes you can imagine
of the the intensity of this function in
the direction that it goes right and so
you can see as they start getting more
detailed it gets more and more lobes
this is because like I said spherical
harmonics are very analogous to
something like a Fourier transform and
for those of you don't know what a
Fourier transform is Fourier transform
it's something that converts a amplitude
based signal so like I said something
that's like audio like an amplitude just
kind of like fluctuates into something
that's the sum of a series of of
transcendental functions so some of the
series of sine waves so for example and
what this is a pretty interesting aspect
just a signal processing theory is that
any signal can be approximated and
eventually masked exactly by a series of
sine waves to a certain degree right so
what you end up with is you end up with
sort of a series of sine waves at
doubled frequencies right it's a really
bad drawing you know what this is not
going to work let's try it this way
so what you get with something like a
Fourier transform is you essentially get
these various coefficients of which
kinds of frequencies are present in the
signal and at what strength right and so
what you get is like you know
coefficients going down in terms of
their effect you get these sorts of a
sine wave decompositions of the signal
so you know if I had a signal that kind
of looks like this right you would say
well obviously it's got a very strong
first coefficient here that sort of
matches that and then it's got a little
bit of this signal in it here for that
wobble right and you keep summing these
together to get eventually back to the
actual signal that you had right now the
idea behind this and why people tend to
want to use things like Fourier
transforms or like the discrete cosine
transform which is a similar version of
it of the same process for graphics is
that you want to be able to throw out
the higher frequency stuff because it's
usually humans are less sensitive to it
so for example if I want to approximate
this if I want to approximate with
something like that the Fourier
transform becomes very useful because
you can just keep the bottom part and
throw away these top parts when you're
trying to kind of compress that signal
down to smaller space right so spherical
harmonics are the same way and much like
sine waves they have like a positive and
a negative weighted lobes right and I
don't know which one they're trying to
show here like probably blue is positive
and green is negative I don't know it
doesn't matter the point being they add
in one place while they subtract in
another right so at the top you just
have an overall color of the function an
overall bright strength of the function
and then the next down you get the three
primary axes right XYZ have lobes on
them that say how strong the function is
in those directions and it subtracts
from the other direction so it adds from
two one direction it subtracts or the
other then you get other shapes that you
get down to the lower coefficients and
so on and so forth
right and again the idea behind these
functions is hey let's suppose for a
given channel like the red channel I'm
willing to store four numbers well I
could store the four coefficients of
these things and sort of have some
directionality understanding to my
lighting right anyway the point of this
stream is not to teach you circle
harmonics because hey I don't even
really work with circle or mark so I'm
the wrong one to teach you anything else
real Carmack's it's more to just kind of
mention as we go here that what we need
in this case what we would need to do if
we want to recover directionality from
the lighting is we need to store
something in our texture map that helps
us reconstruct something we can use for
the direction of the light right okay
so let's talk a little bit about what
that might look like and we can play
around the bit right it'll be an
experimental process of once we have
things working we can kind of play
around with what we store there and see
how it does
but anyway so remember if you recall
what we want to do right is we want to
produce a lighting equation for our
surfaces and remember we started to talk
about this lighting equations are things
which want to be able to compute for a
specific eye direction here's my I write
for a specific way that we're looking at
the surface we want to take the inbound
light that we know is hitting the
surface and produce some kind of RG and
B intensity that goes out along this ray
so if the eye can know what it is that's
what we want right and in order to
produce that we actually have sort of
two distinct categories of lighting that
are going to happen here right we have
highly reflective elements of our
lighting and highly
use elements of our lighting right we
can kind of separate those into those
two broad categories remember a mirror
is something that reflects something
directly and that behaves kind of like
the sort of flows specular thing that
I've got in here right now right
remember we play with this that's a very
reflective surface it's it's the surface
that narrowly re reflects the light
incoming on it right and you remember we
kind of played around with this in in
the limited sense but we can change it
over even with the limited thing we have
right now we can change it over by
playing with these coefficients we have
a 2.0 specular coefficient put a 1.0
gpus coefficient we could instead turn
off that specular and just use the
diffuse and what we would get is
something that again is more like a
highly diffused surface right a surface
of just scatters light in all directions
and then when we have a light on here
right we get something just more kind of
flows out around doesn't really reflect
and when I move my camera around right I
don't get a lot of change in how the
light responds because again it's
diffused it's radiating in all
directions so it doesn't respond that
much to how I'm looking at it what angle
I'm looking at it okay so again we have
two broad categories of light there and
what that means is that when we're sort
of developing our approximately equation
even though real lighting requires us to
take every four-dimensional pair into
account every light direction has to
then take into town every possible
two-dimensional angle set and sum all of
those lights with different weights all
of those incident lights you know that's
not we're doing right that's a ray
tracer job we're doing approximate
lighting so we really have two things
you want to consider we want to consider
those two categories the specular in the
diffuse right and so what we want to do
is we want to come up with some kind of
a lighting lookup that allows us to
approximate both of these if we can and
obviously again this is a highly
proximate process so we're not really
going to get great results out of either
but we just want something that looks
pleasant right this is a game with
cartoon art style we're not trying to be
photorealistic here so we don't have to
sweat it too bad so how would we do this
well if you think about what we've got
here what we want to do is have
something that can produce a a
directional light for specular and a non
directional light for diffuse right but
non directional is kind of in quotes
here because even though it's sort of
non directional it still has a
directional mask on it so remember we've
got the cosine theta law here which
tells us that as the angle gets steeper
as the light comes in it reflects less
of the light out proportional the cosine
of the angle so we will still want
things coming from this direction to
contribute more heavily press
potentially to the result then things
coming from this direction so it's non
directional in the sense that we would
like to know all of the incident light
that's coming in but it is still
somewhat directional in the sense that
the direction at which the light is
coming in might get attenuated on the
other hand the specular doesn't want to
know all that the specular just wants to
know for the reflection angle of this
surface whichever it is I just want to
know the color in that direction right
and I don't want to know the colors and
I don't want these other colors to
contribute right so what we want here is
something that can reproduce those
angular queries basically now we want
something that given a normal well I
should say normal given a reflection
vector so the eye comes in and we give
it this vector here right and then given
a normal which is this vector here so
given a normal we want something that
will reproduce the diffuse lighting
and given a reflector this year like our
and giving a reflector we want something
that will give us an approximation to
the specular so that's really what we're
looking for in terms of our lighting now
if we get an incredibly amazing
wonderful superb job at doing this
somehow the specular would be able to be
cranked all the way to a perfect
reflector that has no glossiness
whatsoever and if you do like mirrored
surfaces right like mirrors and stuff
like this we're not even going to
attempt that for this project and the
reason that we're not going to attempt
that in addition to requiring like a lot
of work on the rendering side of things
is because we can't actually do that
since we don't even have the ability to
render what our art looks like from
other directions and once you start
talking about reflectors you have to
know that right
so we actually don't want mirrors in
this game because we don't have the
ability to really render stuff in
mirrors so for example let's suppose
that the hero is standing on a mirror
when I look down here I should look up
and see what's under his chin right that
art doesn't even exist so the only thing
we could really even attempt with things
like real true specular reflectors are
fake reflections ones that are the kind
that people complain about
[Applause]
see if we can get a good one here there
you go so that's kind of a good example
of the kind of thing we would have to do
right if you take a look at that image
you can see that all they really did was
mirror the thing that they were looking
at and the it you know literally mirror
it in Photoshop and then draw that
reflection but that is not at all what a
reflection actually does right a
reflection does not work that way at all
right it is it is not that kind of an
image I trying to see that that looks a
little bit better let's see if we can
get a good see if we can get a good one
here
well that's that's an obviously very bad
reflection it illustrates the problem
very well here we go
I think that's probably that's a really
good one okay but anyway yeah I apropos
of nothing I just there's a there's a
limit to what we can do with specular
reflections because reflections aren't
mirrored versions of the same thing you
see when you look at the mirror the only
time that would be true is if you
couldn't see the mirror so if I was
looking at a mirror directly head-on and
I had a sphere above it that sphere
would be reflected exactly perhaps
through the mirror in a sense shape wise
sure right but I can't see the mirror
once I can see the mirror then whatever
is on it I'm actually seeing the
underside of that thing right I'm seeing
the top when I look down here but I'm
seeing the underside when I look through
the mirror because the mirror bounces
the light it doesn't reflect what I the
light that I'm looking at it reflects
the light that hit it right and so it's
a very different thing so I'm not really
even going to try for those in handmade
here oh I we could try to go through
jump through a bunch of Hoops to get
them to work in a fake way like I said I
don't really want to do that I think
it's just better to say we're not going
for reflection reflection yes they're
cool by all means if you like them try
to do them and you can come up with fake
ways to try and do them with rights but
I don't really want to go down that road
so really more what I'm looking for is a
general glossiness right something more
like a surface that kind of reflects
color a little bit
in a directional sense more like maybe a
varnished floor does but does not try to
really reproduce the the image so if
you're going to you can't really see a
clear image in it that that is 100%
pixel identifiable right we want
something blurry but I would like that
right if we can get a nice blurry
reflection a nice glossy reflection in
there it has a lot of character to the
scene because as things move through the
scene and you kind of get this nice sort
of glassy quality to them maybe that's
it adds some variety of the material
instead of being kind of dull and chalky
so we would like to get some of that as
we can so what we want to produce is
some kind of function where we can pass
a normal and get a diffuse and pass a
reflector and get a specular right and
honestly like I said I don't have a
preconceived notion about how to do this
but if we were talking about storing
this in a texture right then what I
would imagine is let's suppose we store
three textures an R a G and a B texture
and each one of these can be like four
channels right so we can have let's say
for 8-bit channels or something or maybe
if we're feeling really gung-ho for
floating-point channels I don't know if
you've got that kind of bandwidth to
spare but that's what we've got right
we've got the ability to store these
things in two channels here and we can
store one for red green and blue right
so rather than just the intensity of the
colors which we know we can store so we
know we can use one channel to store the
intensity and that will be exact if we
wanted to let's say what if we give
ourselves four channels could restore
something more than just the intensity
yeah and it's hard to say but for
example one thing we could do is in code
let's say the cube without the bottom
face or something
right so instead of something like
spherical harmonics maybe you know we
could do something like encode these
faces of the cube like or you know what
we could even just encode encode
something like this since we're looking
top-down we could encode how much light
was outgoing in each in each of the four
directions right what's the red outgoing
intensity in each of the four directions
I know it sounds ridiculous it's
incredibly lossy but we could do it
right and furthermore if we wanted to
make if we wanted to spend even more
resources on it we could get even more
accurate right another thing we could do
is say we have six textures one for each
face of the cube and we've got three
channels for texture RG and B leading to
a six times three storage requirement
right and I don't know again that could
be in 16-bit or it could be you know so
maybe it's by two so we end up with
something that is 6 times 3 times 2
that's 36 bytes and who knows maybe it's
maybe it's 512 by 256 so it's about 4
Meg's of slice so if we did 256 level 4
so we could have 64 depth slices of that
which would be massive I don't even know
if we can spare that kind of bandwidth
right so we can certainly slice it up in
a number of different ways and then
store a bunch of lighting information
into those textures once we store the
lighting information into the textures
we can then down sample it to get
various resolutions of that
right and again I don't know if this is
a particularly good idea I'm not trying
to say one way or another whether it is
or not but it's certainly something we
could try the other thing we could try
to say well what if we just stored an
average direction and intensity so we
had only four you know we had three
textures one for r g and b and we had
four elements per texture we had
intensity and direction right I don't
know which of these would be good but
you can see that there is like room to
play around here and so what I would
propose we start with just to get things
rolling and we'll tackle a little bit
more next week is let's just try making
one of these things with some
flexibility so we'll try to parameterize
it on how many textures we want and how
many elements per texture there are so
we can try either of these schemes or
any other scheme you come up with right
try making a 3d texture then rendering
something into the 3d texture
yeah render something in the 3d texture
and then sample from it right now one of
the tricky things about 3d textures is
I'm not really sure to what extent we
have control in this version of shading
language over drawing into 3d textures
in a deep sense like I don't know if we
have to render lots of slices for our
light in order to properly fill the 3d
texture I could be that we do could be
that we don't it could be that we can
fill it in a more creative way but we
might want to do that anyway just to
avoid over filling so we might need to
slice our lights up into several
primitives or something like that that's
why I'm not sure but yet what we would
want to do here again is just figure out
some way to get this process started by
just creating those textures and drawing
into them one thing we could do is do
this in screen space what we're going to
do is screw this with only one texture
at first that I only want texture only
one depth level at first so instead of
making a 3d texture we make a 2d texture
and we just do the lighting in a plane
first and then we try to extend it out
after that to a 3d right so there's a
thought I don't know
what I do know is that going to produce
copious amounts of mucus to Annoying
anyway so if we wanted to do something
like that then really what we're talking
about is at startup here we want to
create some lighting information so
inside our OpenGL startup code we're
going to want to put something in here
where you know normally we don't
allocate much in the way of texture to
startup but here we actually would be
doing exactly that
so we'd have in here a texture handle
that's like our light textures and like
I said we don't know how many of those
light textures there going to be but
probably we're going to have to keep
that to a relatively low number so I'm
just going to throw in an eight right
now and so that we you know have the
ability to do some of them but where
they're going to be relatively modest
and here we'll also say a light texture
channel count and that'll give us the
parameterization we want I could also do
light texture count so we know how many
textures there are we know how many
channels there are per and so in here
that we could also probably in here now
think about there's the light texture
width height and depth right so what I
would venture to guess is that these
might want to be settings so the texture
count in the channel count are going to
be things that probably get fixed to the
algorithm that we choose
but the settings are probably going to
control the width and height because on
lower end machines we would probably use
worse sampling on the lighting right so
much the same way that we can reduce the
resolution of the game on worse machines
or increase it on higher end machines to
give better or worse results we could do
the same
sort of thing with no lighting so at the
moment we'll just set it to something
like this but in the future we might
play with it more so the other thing we
can do here is say what's the mid-level
count all that it might actually be
implied something like this right so
let's go ahead and and see what we would
have to do to make this happen so now
that I think about it this is probably
not a gluant this is probably a frame
buffer and the reason for that is we're
going to render into these things in
addition to reading from them so they're
not really just going to be a text or
handle they're going to be a text or
handle plus a frame rubber handle so in
the process of starting if OpenGL we
need to do some work here if you make
these things happen and probably since
they're going to be settings based what
we want to do is actually do it up in
the part where we have the settings
change right where is that I'm having a
spelling there it is have a spelling
problem today having typing typing
problems so in here what we want to do
is when we create all of our other
resources like our depth field buffers
we want to create in here our light
texture buffers as well and what we want
to do is we want to make sure that we
free these two just Alessa graphics card
know that when we change settings it can
free up space to get rid of everything
basically so it can free up space to
create the new things so we'll go
through here
[Applause]
and just three these frame buffers so
they will go away and then down here
when we actually need to compute the
rest of our stuff we're going to do the
opposite process so when we create our
frame buffer here and you may have to
add some parameters to our create frame
of a call but for now we won't so you
can kind of see here we are we know some
of the stuff we're going to pass we're
going to need a render depth there
eventually probably so we're going to
have to pass the current settings where
is that
at we want from the settings the light
texture with white texture height and at
the moment we don't have a place to pass
the depth so we're not going to but that
will create a frame buffer for our youth
there is a problem with this and the
problem with this is that we don't want
to for creating the frame buffer here
we're going to want to specify a
specific type of storage that may not be
the same storage as we use for like Def
peels and stuff like that
so when it creates a frame buffer you
can see in here we've kind of got this
you know filter type and slot and those
sorts of things
obviously we can we won't be wanting it
multisample so that's fine
filtered we will want it filtered so
that's fine
we don't want depth so that's fine but
we do want color so that all works but
the OpenGL default frame buffer texture
format part of this that part kind of
has to get fixed because that actually
will not work right so that has to get
replaced with some ability because we
what we don't want srgb probably I mean
maybe we do maybe we don't but we might
want to store at the floating point we
don't know we really don't know what
we're going to do here so that's a that
one's a little bit trickier I think all
right so just looking at that the other
thing we would need to do is for a frame
buffer text image here we would also
need this guy to do 3d textures so width
width and height it would also need a
depth in here
and so we would need to be able to do 3d
multi sample or 2d right which is one of
the really annoying things about OpenGL
is you have to call a different function
if you want a different dimension
texture so it makes it harder to
parameterize but that's just the way it
goes okay but that's really all we're
talking about for first steps here did I
not actually add these into the render
settings there we go so we now compute
sort of these values from it now these
two are going to be fixed based on the
algorithm so the light texture can't for
example let's say we were going to do
one where we tracked for example the
average direction and the average is
envy and the summed intensity or
something like this right so all we're
going to do is is do three textures one
for r g and b and four channels right
for XYZ direction and intensity the
miscount
is something that we want to know for
other purposes right because we're going
to want to miss map these textures down
for various reasons that we'll see later
we're probably cubes we want to be able
to sample from lower for more blurred
versions of them for a number of reasons
I suspect and so that at the moment is
something that we're going to have to
compute from the information we're given
in terms of the width and the height so
in order to figure out the the MIT count
I guess one thing we could do here to
make this a little more precise since we
need these to be power of two is we can
also make it so
that when we are talking about them we
could talk about them in terms of their
power to write so rather than calling
them you know with the height or
whatever will actually just specify the
power of two here so in this case we
would say that this is you know 981 so
then if we want to know what the actual
values of these are we would then say
the light texture with you know the
light texture high light texture depth
are all going to be equal to whatever
the power of twos are raised and that's
just a way of enforcing the fact that we
are not going to let you specify
arbitrary settings for these you have to
specify a power of two in all cases so
this is with power to hight power to and
depth power to so then the miscount is
easier to determine the miscount is just
going to be whatever the actual texture
with is don't miss our power to for the
width
if the width is the highest thing if
it's not then it's just whatever you
know we can we can just keep going here
[Applause]
whichever one of these is the highest is
the number of MIPS we would have if we
went all the way down to a single pixel
our single textual I should say so you
know that's the myth count right that's
how many lower resolution versions there
would be of this thing so then when we
create one it would look like this and
again we're going to want to adjust how
we're doing this but for now we'll just
say like okay so we
got one it's fine
so that's how we would create our light
textures and we would create one for our
for g4b
so there's going to be three of them and
again their channels would be X Y Z
intensity so like Direction X Direction
Y directions the intensity I guess I
mean if you think about it I guess
really we don't need to specify three
there because if we just sum up the RG
and B values in their entirety
you could you could just go with three
channels so you could use like three
16-bit channels rather than for 8-bit
channels but I think we probably want
for 8-bit channels would be my guess
it's hard to say
so what I'm thinking about here just to
be a little bit more explicit about it
so one thing you could do is let's say
you have three floats you could just
take the direction to the light and its
intensity and scale it so we have
direction and we have intensity we would
just do the direction times the
intensity is a vector that's as long as
the intensity is we would just sum those
together so it would just be the sum of
all the directional the intensities
multiplied by their directions and that
would just give us one value that's like
here's the direction of the red light
and its intensity roughly right now the
problem with doing something like that
is it means that opposite direction
ality is canceled and maybe we want that
or maybe we don't I have no idea but for
example let's say we have a strong red
light coming in this direction and a
strong red light coming in this
direction they would cancel each other
out that doesn't seem like a very good
thing to me right so what I assumed we
would want to do instead is while we
might want to do this in terms of making
it so that brighter lights dominate the
directional components we probably want
to sum the intensity because otherwise
we'll get all these weird anomalies so
that's why I'm thinking what we want is
three directional ones and one intensity
one and the intensity one just gets
summed whereas the directional ones have
that ability to cross cancel because
there's negatives in there right there's
no negatives in here these are all
positives but this one has positives and
negatives I so yeah that seems
reasonable
the only issue there is this is going to
require more than 8bits probably if
we're honest at least
if we do want there to be a strengthened
astute
[Applause]
so that's hard to say fortunately it's
an easy thing to determine what we can
do is use floating point textures to
start with so that we know that we have
pretty much infinite flexible you know
flex room and then what we can do is
scale it down to 16 see if we can make
it work scale it down to 8 see if we can
make it work right so we can basically
start with a very bloated representation
that we know won't have problems with
range
we just you know successively get
simpler as we move down the line that
seems like a pretty good strategy to me
so yeah all right so here we create the
frame buffer what I want to do in this
case is make that create frame buffer
called I would like that to have a flag
in it and see if what we've got here
flipped up format yeah so what I would
like to do here is I'd like to make a be
32 X that says you know give float or
something
[Applause]
and if we use is float then when we
determine what the type is of the
texture we're going to force it to be a
floating-point version right so what I
want to do there is this default frame
buffer texture format thing probably has
to go but what we probably want is our
frame buffer textures sRGB or not if
that makes sense and you know we
probably have to expand this a little
bit and then OpenGL depth component type
you can see why this is a little bit
nasty right because this again also kind
of wants to know this information we did
we test to see whether we can use a non
floating-point depth buffer by the way I
don't remember if we did that let's take
a look at that
so there's with our floating-point depth
buffer I could also turn off the
lighting for that
[Applause]
so look at this probably want to keep
some of that there okay so looking at
this here you can see where we're at in
terms of render quality with the
floating-point depth buffer and I had
not really tried playing to see whether
we need the 32 F or not so we could try
the depth component 24 and see how it is
unfortunately with the lighting on
directional like that it's pretty tough
to tell
but you don't see obvious artifacts in
normal play so it does seem like we
could probably get away without
floating-point depth buffer
so that doesn't necessarily mean we want
to so yeah like we have some options
there and yeah it looks like that's
probably something we could parameterize
in the future I don't know that there's
much reason not to use the
floating-point version but we might save
some bandwidth or get a little bit of a
performance win on some situations by
not requiring such a heavyweight
z-buffer right so anyway I we're pretty
good here and we're actually creating
those light textures now actually even
though we don't use them for anything so
now what we really want to do is we want
to be able to sample from these lighting
textures when we're actually doing our
drawing right so what we want to do here
is inside of our lighting we've got a
but you know ton of code here that we
were using for our lighting so here's
all of our lighting code right that
we're doing and we don't really want to
be doing that stuff anymore the end is
correct right we do want the total light
value to come out but we're going to
want that to be an actual vector for you
know so we have an RGB an RG and B light
there so we actually do kind of want to
play with this last part a little bit
but we don't want the rest of this
involved at the moment probably although
I guess now think about it I guess we
just can't kind of use it because we
will well we won't necessarily have this
part here right so this part kind of
goes away
[Applause]
well that part kind of goes away so we
just we just have cosine angle equals
dot like to light world end there the to
light part is going to be is going to be
the thing that we read out of the
texture right so we're going to read
that to light direction out of the
texture directly and use that
similarly the lighting distance part is
exactly the same that part's going to
get read out as well so let me just kind
of organize this up here so what we end
up with right is we've got a diffuse
coefficient for the surface which is
something we may actually put into the
vertex U at some point we compute the
diffuse light by just sort of
multiplying in by that lighting value
and what we really want to do here I
think is we just kind of we want to
start treating these as vector equations
so that we can do an R a G and a B
together so I think what we want here is
we want this to be a v3 where we have a
diffused coefficient times the cosine
angle which will be different per
channel so that'll be a vector3 right
this will actually be a vector3
and then we've got that light strength
which will also be a vector3
[Applause]
same would be true here we'd have the
specular specular coefficient which is
still a floating-point value that's just
a property of the surface we have the
cosine reflected angle and again that's
going to be exactly the same thing here
it's just going to turn into a vector3
and then we would have the light
strength again is also a vector3 right
then when we compute the total light
that will produce an
vector3 again turning this into an RGB
separated equation so I'll make that
work with the current way we do lighting
just because that way we can sort of
just test to make sure it's working at
all so the way that this would work is
the light distance computation now is
something that is going to happen per
channel so we kind of have to take this
and and blow it out the same is true for
the dot product there's really three dot
products now that makes sense so it
looks more like this and again same here
where we get three of these all right
for critter will look like me on that
[Applause]
okay oh yeah so there's so really what
we're looking at now right is we're just
trying to expand this out to handle the
fact that soon we will have different
light strengths and different light
directions per color channel so the two
light vector will be to light our to
light G to light B and the light
strength will be like light strength our
light strength do you like strength B
then the rest of these equations are
still fine right there's nothing else
that we need to do in particular oops
get it this one's got to do the same
thing the rest of the equations just
flow properly they're just done per
channel now instead of per for once for
the entire light probably since I can't
quite see the parsing of these things
I just am missing parentheses or
something in here
yep and so this is the exact same thing
we were doing before right and we don't
see any change because we're not doing a
different R a G or a B right but what we
could do if we wanted to is since the
light strength is specified here what we
could do is actually do a light strength
bar for this now think about not going
to do it here
so in this case right we've got a light
strength r g and b light strengths are
see my 6d so I could make my light be a
color it could be sort of you know
orangish or whatever and then when you
know it lights the surface it's kind of
tinting it right and similarly I could
knock out the blue entirely and then I'd
been in the you know there's no more
blue light so now everything is like a
greenish yellow yellow yellow is tinge
to it right we can make it read only
oops and now it's kind of like like
handmade hero photographer darkroom
edition and so you know that's just
prepping for flowing these things in
from a texture so then if we wanted to
start flowing them in from a texture
then what we would do right is instead
of passing down a light P here where
there's a specific value that's set as a
uniform we would actually okay I'm out
of time so we'll do that next week we
would just pass in here textures to
sample from and sample out the light
direction and light intensity for each
channel from the corresponding three
textures and that that's all we'd be
doing so pretty straightforward that
make sense okay we can go ahead and and
go to the QA I don't want to start doing
that because we won't have a chance
finish doing that
oops that didn't work
well inside out 12 minutes into the
mainstream
why does in sebat think that is the time
set wrong on the schedule
no set right what happened in sir bot
blow on a scale of 0 to 15 how
disappointed are you that Visual Studio
continued working as normal today
I'm not disappointing to continue to I'm
actually relatively happy continued
working as normal today just because I
don't like having to change development
environments in the middle of a project
right I like being able to just stick
with one reliable that's that's why we
also don't update Visual Studio like we
could go switch to vigils - or 2017 but
I don't want to do that because it just
brings a bunch of hassle like there's
different things that has different
errors there'll be different bugs right
so mostly I wanted to start it on
Windows I want to finish the development
Hammad here on Windows and then never
use Windows again free but I don't
really like switching purse you know
infinity
I don't like changing horses midstream
to quote wag the dog disused don't you
find this lighting way too advanced for
a 2.5 da m-- I don't really think
there's any such thing as too advanced
lighting for lack of a better statement
if that makes sense
lighting makes games look awesome you
really can't have too much lighting in a
game you can have bad lighting in a game
or lighting that doesn't isn't
appropriate sure but having a good
lighting scheme makes games look really
good and I think when you see two and a
half T games that have good lighting you
notice - like they look really nice - no
I don't really think so I so yeah
uplink coder can i stream C to D
conversion of handmade here without
infringing on the copyright yeah just
email me and I will give you permission
to do what you need to do I basically
like I just try to keep the source code
is private to people who haven't
licensed so as long as you keep the D
source code private you know you could
put it on the handma hero github for
example if you wanted to which is
private until the codes release from the
public domain then then that's fine but
yeah since obviously the streams are
free anyone who wants to can can watch
the handmade hero streams for free so
watching D streams of the same thing
seems fine to me
how excited are you for pears project I
have a theme pears project is it on hand
a network
what's pears project
[Applause]
I'm assuming you're talking about pair
this pair
what is Paris project is there a link
shucks 93 note he is making an entire
computer from scratch using fbas and
hardware FPGAs and hardware that sounds
cool I wonder if it could run handmade
hero
there is another person who's doing that
as well
risky five is doing that I think
Uncle John never do handmade compiler I
don't know he threatened to do it but he
hasn't done it yet maybe he will want to
do that sometime soon I don't know
know so mid blue I'm not talking about
me a Tatsu I'm talking about risky fives
project
he did a FPGA I don't know how to search
for this but he did an FPGA that plays
games and he asked about making one that
would run handmade Hiro
if not risk five the persons handle is
risky size but it's not about the risk 5
whereas yes Mia Tatsu is doing a risk 5
handmade tool chain thing but that's
different I know this gets confusing I
get confused I can't remember who is
doing which sometimes for the handle
especially because people I may know
someone's actual name I don't know their
handle
alright looks like we don't have any cue
columns here so I can wrap it up Oh
jeepers Caleb short of the fact that
most gamers use Windows is there any
reason to do most of the development on
Windows yeah it's more stable for
debugging by far my experience with
trying to debug GPU stuff on Linux has
not been good and the debuggers on Linux
I also find to be not good
so editing on the next is fine compiling
on Linux is fine like clang is good it's
you know if anything at this point
probably better than visual studios
compiler like right but trying to like
run debug and analyze graphics intensive
applications on Linux is not good in my
experience so part of that is probably
because I'm probably a little more
biased against it than I should be like
I can say definitively the debugger suck
like Linux does not have any debuggers
that are have good human factors in my
opinions graphics debugging is probably
I'm being a little unfair and the reason
for that is that when I've done when I
did graphics work on Linux I was using a
laptop and the difference between
Windows and Linux in terms of handling
laptop graphics is like you know an
unfathomable huge Gulf that's not true
for desktops desktops Linux is much more
comfortable when it just has one
graphics card to deal with so it's
probably much better in that regard so
that part probably gets better just you
know get a graphics card that's a
well-tested Linux graphics card
whichever one that should be and you
know whether it's Nvidia AMD these days
I don't know who
better support and that part probably
takes care itself a lot more on what I
found was that for trying to use a
laptop with its support for you know
optimists you know discreet switchable
graphics is just really bad so
ray Kassar do you have any anecdotes of
horrible debugging experiences using
Linux of errors oh sure
so my experience using Linux the buggers
you don't even have to get complicated I
found that when in a full debug build so
no optimizations enabled I found that
most Linux the buggers if not all except
for direct use of gdb command-line gdb
none of them could even display the
elements of a lot of my structures a lot
of them couldn't display local variables
and this would tend to be fairly random
so it'd just be like yep that function
we just we don't know where the local
variables are sorry or that structure we
can't we can't I don't know I'm sorry
and this happens all the time so I would
just generally be in cases where you
know just does work when it does work
it's incredibly slow single stepping
took an eternity on a very fast laptop
right I could watch the time it took to
let get from line to line you know and
it's just nuts right so I found the
debugging experience on Linux is just
horrible there's no reason that I know
of that it has to be horrible like I
don't think linux as an operating system
has some core problem you know at its
root that means debugging can't work but
whatever the reason is whether it's the
fact that everything is like a tower of
cards built on Jesus gdb or something or
whether it's the dwarf model is bad or
something and I'm studied it I don't
know what the problem is
there are problems
[Music]
have you considered Visual Studio code
over visual studio still Microsoft but
much more lightweight and you get the
visual studio debugger are you talking
about on Windows or on Linux ray caster
asked have you tried visions bugging
using QT creator does not seem to have
the issue who described these nephrons
parts that actually was specifically the
debugger I would say had all of those
problems because I did use that one it
was the least bad and it has all of
those problems that I just described
demon Sookie on Windows on Linux you
don't get the VC plus listed burger on
Windows no I haven't
[Applause]
I'm happy to try it though is there a
64-bit version probably not there isn't
a 64-bit version of Visual Studio so
if you want to know what that agreement
said
I like it how like just a thing that's
just an an editor debugger has to
install like 8 billion files it's like
why isn't just an executable or like to
dll's or something I have no idea got to
have more JSON
I guess so let's see here's here it is
no what happened there so here it is
I want to bug something can i D bug an
executable somehow debug ad
configuration open a folder ok let's
open a folder w hand-made misc
build
can I be bug now debug debug open
configurations
[Music]
I really don't want you to use git for
anything
all right
install is it installed
all right how do i do bug to bug bug the
program as configuration c++ i want okay
I want that's this is what I want to bug
the program please start debugging I
want C++ that's the environment okay
I would like to debug now please to bug
my programs please debug it will you and
debug the program now debug the program
so how do you devote the program
reload okay
I will reload I have oh god okay
I have reloaded and now I need to reload
again okay here we are
I want to start debugging with Windows
C++ I want to do some thing here into a
program name here is the program name
it's W build win32 handmade exe right is
this the working directory so the
working directory is W build no it's not
the working directory is W handmade data
right
add some cigarettes oh okay I'll wait a
mess with the square on the screen all
right I don't have know what to do now
so okay I have put that in there
there is the configuration and
[Music]
everyone's happy right
there we go all right so we got it
launching so I'm assuming can I step
into it now step in step into the tip
okay that just changes it to full screen
how do we step into the first line of
the program right well let's set a
breakpoint then I guess can I set a
breakpoint new breakpoint just a
function breakpoint set breakpoint how
do you set a breakpoint debug new break
point function breakpoint okay so that
didn't work at all
debug new breakpoint conditions a
breakpoint that didn't work either
all right we're on a roll here we're
really getting some debugging going
can't seem to set any breakpoints so
that's fine I guess I'll just hit start
to bugging and then I'll hit break so
break nope that wasn't break that would
stop start debugging
that break okay so we broke there we go
here's our main thread and it has no
idea where the source code is all right
how would I tell it where the source
code is debug load symbols anyone so
open folder select source folder okay so
this handmade code select folder what
just happened
okay so that no so I guess my short
answer is unless I'm really missing
something no that's awful so far did
that leave crap in my directory in my
build directory as well or did it thanks
it was it mercifully yes awesome
so it also crapped out whatever this is
which is that launch program we did um I
would have to play with it
a more more to see whether I cared but
chances are no that I have a lot of
doubts that that is going to be a
particularly good way to debug stuff
[Music]
but yeah I mean I also don't know that
this is necessarily designed for
something that I'm going to want to do
either right I mean it's designed as an
IDE and I just want it to run the
debugger so it's by definition probably
going to be something that doesn't
particularly work but okay just to use
if you think I'm being dumb walk me
through it allow me to debug my program
at source level with this tool hit me
I'll follow the steps that you type in I
mean obviously I'll launch the program
for you well I don't know where it went
but hold on a second we'll get it back
there it is all right so we're launched
we don't need get for anything at the
moment so hit me what's step one
[Applause]
okay open folder code that is wait so
you're saying the best what we have open
right now right add configuration for
C++ so that was this right windows I'm
assuming and we got to do this again so
this w build winter cue handmade egg Z W
handmade data right and I'm assuming I
have to save this but it might save it
automatically but I'll save it myself
just in case all right so now add break
point wherever you want start debugging
okay so I just wanted to step in to the
first line to program
so here's the first line of program
debug toggle breakpoint run there we go
so I guess the answer is it can't load
source out of a PDB so what do you do if
you have multiple source folders do you
add source folders somehow like let's
say there was another source folder in a
different directory how would I specify
this can I not do that
you can add more include directories so
how do do you have to do that manually
like would I do that
in a project file somewhere all right
well anyway so let's see now that we
actually can look at something let's see
how the single stepping speed is okay
dude seriously though I really don't
think I'm being dumb here are you
looking at this did you see how long it
took to step over this is what this
isn't and this is that that was nuts how
long it took the step-over desired
schedule MF equals one look at how long
it took the step over window klass
equals nothing those were a little
better but man that that speed is awful
that was fine because that's an it open
jail that that might actually take some
time but that should be instantaneous
and it like those two should have been
roughly instantaneous and one was way
longer than the other look at how long
it took a step over that I mean that
feels exactly like the Linux the bugger
to me all the latest burgers actually
weren't that slow they were they were
faster than that that was setting
monitor refresh Hertz to 60 that's how
long it took to step over I'm assuming
this is because this window is really
non performant like if I closed that all
the sudden is totally fat right so it's
it's this is this is really bad for some
reason they must have a really slow
version of that
so if maybe maybe just leave the watch
window is the only thing open right now
now the feed is actually usable oops now
the speed is actually usable so maybe if
you just use a watch let's see how this
is so there mm have one watch open that
seems that seems fine right so it seems
like maybe if you just you just can't
like don't look at locals or whatever I
could I could live with that
[Applause]
I see they inherited some of the
badnesses of visual studios to bugger as
well like for example not being able to
look at a variable after the instruction
of a loop when you hit the closing brace
I hate that but visual studio debugger
does it too now didn't used to that does
now so that you know I could I could
deal with that assuming that it doesn't
get a preacher bleah what okay I don't
know it's now it's extremely slow for
some reason but I have no idea why
all right where is the cursor does
anyone know even where the cursor is
what
wait what we're down here now oh because
I'm us ahsoka all right well let's see
can we step through the assembly how do
I see the assembly code
des Utes how do I step through the
assembly code
helped our developer tools alright
that's not useful can I step through the
assembly
it can't do oh okay so you can't even
see a disassembly even a stuff it can
step through so what why are we even
talking about this then I mean we need
to be able to step into assembly right I
mean that's it yeah so all right I mean
that that if someone had told me that at
the beginning we wouldn't bother trying
it I assume that since it used the
visual of a team matsuki says you can
step through the assembly how do you how
do you step into this assembly gives you
bug with - exact disassembly
hmm what is - exact disassembly is where
do you set those parameters are they in
the launch JSON file or they are they a
parameter to the actual program
it's in args so it's in here can I just
put it in like literally in here or is
that what's this I don't know what the
format is for bees obviously but that's
the arms to my program so I mean I
wouldn't pass that to my program right
doesn't really make sense
okay in the debug console alright so so
let's say I want to view this assembly
here so you're saying I could do it here
[Applause]
oops where do I wear what I suppose this
wants an actual command right put it in
here
yeah I know
it doesn't know that as an actual thing
to type in here maybe you type debug
exact buggers and we would need we need
some kind of a tutorial here to say just
disassembly is the command ok this
assembly
hmm I mean I can't say it's looking
encouraging at the moment I mean there
should just be a thing like show me the
disassembly like I don't understand why
would have to have some kind of fancy
mumbo-jumbo
control shift key this assembly yeah
[Applause]
[Music]
so I guess I should ask the other
question is was that to imply that
there's also no memory window
yes seriously man I don't know about
this like this seems like it really does
not have what I would want but I mean
you know maybe if you know if you're
very familiar with it maybe you know the
secret way to get some of this stuff but
you know I obviously want the ability to
just like see the disassembly at any
time and I need to be able to see the
memory like view memory at any time
[Applause]
what's the reason behind checking out
this atrocity or program someone asked
on the frame so I checked it out I would
say like it looks like I said originally
it really looks on promising I would not
suspect it would work very well based on
what I saw there but you know maybe if
you learn all that I mean to be fair you
have to learn how to use Visual Studio
as well right and I just happen to know
how to use it so it might be that
there's some kind of specialness there
but I don't know so I wouldn't say that
looks very promising now as for Liza I
would love it if that was working now or
also there's that there's two handmade
debugger projects now there's ly si and
also the what was it recent thing dB
[Applause]
remedy BG so there's this one too
there's actually two projects debugger
projects going here's one here's the
other and they both just just made
patrons recently unfortunately as far as
I know neither of them are actually
available yet hopefully one of them will
work I don't know
uhh frosting ninja how do you feel after
today's stream we nearly switch to Linux
and now you're looking at four answers
regarding to web editor on stack
overflow yeah it's not great this is why
development is just not very fun anymore
and I try to isolate myself from the
world of development at large it's just
not a pleasant place ray caster are you
still tempted at moving the product to
Linux I would not like to move till
we're done i but like I said you know I
will probably move Molly Rocket over to
Linux next project because you know
Windows is not really viable anymore in
my opinion as a thing to like base your
company on it's way too unpredictable
and it has to be connected to the
Internet and it's just if bad right so
it's it's not really something I would
consider for the next rena so I'll be
moving to Linux in the near future for
my own stuff handmade hero I'd like to
just finish on what we started the same
reason I don't move to Linux in the
middle of our current project at Molly
rocket right because it just figure it
throws a lot it just is a big disruption
so I'd like to be able to finish and
then you know do a switch in between
projects that's kind of better I think
so yeah oh yes don't forget to delete
the vs code folder thank you
I love those just drops you don't even
ask it to do that but it like creates
its own like yeah it creates its own
stuff everywhere tercer flashes or feeis
okay
I think we've got it thank you for that
reminder that's off
all right I'm going to wrap it up thank
you everyone for joining me for episode
of hand made here at some pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along with the series at
home because period of the game and it
comes with a source code
maybe you should go running on Linux in
fact as you saw today you can't really
trust Microsoft tools to run day-to-day
they may just decide that suddenly they
need to talk about a license yeah so if
you would like to ask questions we have
forum you can go to the patreon page
where the view is serious you have a
schedule bot you can go to if you wonder
when we're going to be live and an
episode guide with past episodes on them
if you want to catch up on the series
we'll be back next week to work on the
lighting which we now created some
textures for and we will have to fill
those textures up with something that's
about it for this week until next week
have fun programming and I'll see you on
the Internet take it easy everybody