hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream we finished yesterday
debugging a bug that we had and well I
guess I wouldn't say debugging is
probably the wrong term because I pretty
much knew immediately back when we first
in Canada but what the bug actually was
but it was two streams worth of mass
explanations to explain the bug and then
say how to fix it so I guess we didn't
really spend finish up the debugging we
finished up the explanation so that we
could go and fix the bug and that is now
done which brings us back to where we
were before which is to say that at the
moment our game is actually has more
features in the software renderer than
it does in the hardware renderer because
we implement things in the software
renderer first so that I can show how
they work and so if you take a look at
what's going on in the game right now
you can see this is debug mode so it's
running a little slowly in the software
renderer since the software ender really
needs optimizations compiled on but what
you can see here if I laborious Lee
slowly sort of hop over to this part of
the sort of makeshift rectangular blob
thing that we've created is that we have
the ability now to do this sort of
overlay right this sort of alpha bunted
overlay in the software renderer but we
don't have that ability in the hardware
render so if I go in here and i set the
render type to be back to hardware
you'll see that we immediately hit a
certain in our in our hardware renderer
that's just like hey there's a thing
that you told me to do and i don't know
i like never heard of it right so it
doesn't have a case for this thing so we
can't even run in hardware now and
actually support all the features that
we support in the software renderer
because we just added it so the last
thing that we have to do to really say
that we're done with that alpha blended
overlay feature is we're going to have
to have some way in the hardware
renderer to duplicate the results of the
software renderer right and so that's
what we need to start on today and this
would be an extremely simple task and
wasn't for the fact that 3d graphics API
eyes are always swell and when I say
swell I mean the kind of thing that
happens when you have a severe traumatic
injury to one of your
limbs and it gets really huge huge and
purple and disgusting that's what i mean
by swell so let's go ahead and open up
our project not that and compile it here
and if you take a look inside our opengl
subsystem you can see the part where we
were getting that illegal default case
it's right here and the thing that we
were trying to reproduce if we go over
to the software renderer we can jump
down there it's this guy right here so
this is the case that we're missing it's
the the the render target blending case
that was the part that was triggering
but if you take a look at what's going
on here you will see and I mikhamet
those out because they don't really do
anything right now if you take a look at
what else we need to think about here if
there's more to it than just that and
the reason I say there's more to it than
just that is because every single render
command that's coming down the pipe now
has a variable output target so those
output targets per you know / sprite
that's coming down the pipeline any
sprite can be vectored to any render
target in the game right now so we can
have you know the renderer could
actually support just arbitrary numbers
of render targets well you could say
want for render targets these sprites go
this one these sprites go this one these
fresco this one happy birthday right so
given that that's the case we need some
weight of duplicating that functionality
inside the hardware render we need some
way of saying hey every specific sprite
wants to be pointed at a particular
render target and of course in OpenGL we
don't even know what that means we've
never done anything with render targets
in OpenGL so we don't actually know
anything about how we might do that in
our software render because we wrote it
all it's very clear that all we need to
do is create an extra piece of memory
that we can point at and say here is the
memory to scribble on when you're
bleeding those rights and we've got
another render target that's about all
there was we had to clear it obviously
but other than that there wasn't very
much to it but now in the OpenGL side of
things we're forced to say well okay we
need that functionality but we don't
actually know how to get that
functionality because that's all inside
open jail so what we're going to have to
do is learn how to talk about render
targets to OpenGL so that it knows what
we're trying to do and this is even more
complicated than that simple statement
might make it sound because if all we
cared about was multiple render targets
well that would be one set of annoying
OpenGL calls we have to make but
actually because we care about something
else besides just the render targets
which obviously makes sense when you
think about it we also care about using
those render targets as textures right
so what because what we want to do is we
want to take that secondary render
target that we were putting all the top
level those top floor sprites on we want
to take that render target and then use
it as a texture to alpha blend it over
the existing render target that holds
everything else right so hopefully you
can see there that we actually have to
sort of sets of things that we have to
learn how to do in OpenGL one of them is
to ask OpenGL to give us more render
targets than just the one that we get by
default when we start it up and the
other one is to say hey I've got a
render target and I need to talk about
it as a texture later on as well so keep
that in mind right because those two
things are sort of additional concepts
as far as open gel is concerned so you
obviously already know everything there
is to know about the software side
because we implemented hopefully that
was so clear to you so really all this
is is just fussing with graphics api's
to try and get them to do the exact same
thing we just implemented very
straightforwardly in our software
renderer so let's take a look at at the
OpenGL side of things I always forget I
think it's like GL doc someone told us
what there was a good link Doc's GL for
looking up opengl documentation because
i had been using other docs when we were
doing up to a parent someone was like
hey you should use doc doc gels better
they are correct it is definitely better
and look at that you can even specify
the colors so we can harmonize
those cars with it you know if we want
to anyway uh so very much like you
remember we had GL gen textures to
generate texture handles that we could
use there's a corresponding call that
allows us to generate frame buffers and
if I go ahead I guess I don't really
know very much about why these links are
I don't know if he's actually give us
different documentation pages but anyway
here is GL gen frame buffers and you can
see that it works essentially the same
way as the texture handle stuff works
now in that way that I really didn't
realize this until I think someone
mentioned it while I was doing him a
hero I always thought you needed to ask
for frame buffer names or for texture
names but it turned out you don't you
can just use names and as long as their
unused it doesn't matter I believe that
is true for frame buffers as well so I
think if we say buying frame buffer I
think we can actually just use the frame
buffer handles that we are actually
using right and if you look here it says
like okay it becomes target frontier
free respectively until whatever blah
Blau it talks to chill frame about 30
prefer his name and fame before object
please return for called Jill Jeffers or
0 to break the existing binding of frame
so that makes it sound like you can't do
it but I'm not sure let's see if they
use the same verbiage in GL bind texture
and I'm not sure GL go flying texture
hello there we go let's see the people
to show the texture names of the
corresponding texture contests are local
to the shared objects based current GL
turning a spell you must use gel genders
to generate a new set of texture names
so it sounds like these or documentation
are not really correct for the most part
because we know this isn't true right we
know that we don't have that maybe is it
possible that it's only in later
versions of OpenGL that it says that it
says you may use and now it says you
must use so it kind of sounds like you
don't really have the option that's very
interesting once you go up out of OpenGL
to it looks like they require you to
have used the generation calls that's
very interesting so maybe I wasn't quite
so wrong when I thought you need to call
that maybe only old-school opengl allows
you to do without calling gen textures
very interesting so in that case I'm
going to go ahead and use the gen calls
even though it would be a little bit
easier not to because it looks like
based on reading that that as they went
up in OpenGL versions they may have
tightened those restrictions so anyway
geo jen frame buffers it's exactly the
same as Jill gem textures call I say how
many frame buffers I wanted and I get
back the IDs so what I can do here is I
can say well we we know essentially at
the outset here when we do OpenGL render
commands we know when we start things
off that I can sort of go through all of
the render targets that we have and I
can sort of prep you know do any prep
that I need to do so what I could do
here is say well you know however many
render targets that says there are if I
need to allocate more render targets
than that
then I will write or something like that
the other thing i could do is just say
look we're going to support 16 max and
render targets which will never use look
we won't use that many render targets
I'm sure we can just allocate a bunch of
render targets perhaps and then just you
know assert that we never go over right
that seems like an easy thing to do as
well so what happens here when we come
into OpenGL render commands we do have a
little bit of a problem which is that we
don't really have anywhere in particular
to store these things right look we
don't have any any good place to put
them and so you know we could use sort
of a global variable to hold them I
don't know if we wanted to like Fanchon
that I'll use a global variable for now
and we'll just see whether or not we
want to do something fancier after the
fact is it just global variable what's
my what's my global there we go so what
I'm going to do is I'm just going to say
that we can have a maximum number of
these and you can see they're glu ents
right in the documentation so i'm going
to say I've got a global variable glgl
Union so this is just going to be frame
buffer handles and I'm just going to say
that we can have like 16 of those max
right and i'm also going to create a
variable here right which is just a
global frame buffer count ok and i'm
going to start out by assuming that we
have a global frame buffer count of one
and the reason that i'm going to start
out assuming that is because the default
value frame buffer handle of 0 and I'll
notate that here even though I don't
really have to just to say hey by the
way there is a zero the first one is
zero I there is a frame buffer handle 0
which is the default frame buffer right
and we want to keep that concept around
that 0 is the default frame buffer
because that's kind of a convention we
adopted in the renderer and so we don't
want to deal with frame buffer 0 ever as
anything other than that default but all
the rest of the handles we would like to
be able to prepare ok so what I'm going
to do here is I guess I'm going to go
ahead and sort of mimic what we are
doing in the other one we've got sort of
this notion of a clear color and a color
buffer
here if I take a look back at the
handmade render you can see how we do
right we clear each one of these things
and we can actually do that now we
probably should have had a way to do to
specify a clear color / render target
which we don't currently do but you know
since we don't really need that yet we
don't need to do it yet but if we ever
find it we need to we could certainly so
what I want to do here is I want to go
ahead and and mimic exactly what we were
doing before so I'm going to come in
here and say alright we've got a GL
clear color of whatever the command said
to clear it too and then we want to
clear the color buffer bit of a frame
buffer and we're going to do that for
each of our frame buffers right but
before we do I want to make sure that
I've actually allocated enough frame
buffers and you know what I could do
here since we're really not constrained
could just say hey go up to a lot if you
want to write because we're not actually
allocating them unless we need them so
what I can say here is like all right
assert that the array count of the
global frame buffer handles assert that
however many you're asking me to do is
going to be less than that right look I
don't want you to give me anything
that's going to be more than that but
assuming that we're ok then all I want
to do is say if the max render target is
greater than or equal to the global
frame buffer count then we need to
allocate more right and what I can do
there is I can just ask the GL at that
point using GL Jen frame buffers I can
just say ok and it's not going to be
quite as simple as this for reasons that
you'll see in just quite one minute but
let's pretend temporarily that was i'm
going to call GL jen frame buffers and
then i'm going to say ok the number of
frame buffers that i actually need is
however many it will take me to get up
to here so i'll just say like ok the
global frame buffer count right is going
to then have to be equal to this right
so what I could say is new frame buffer
account
like so and so I know that my new frame
buffer count is however many i would
need to store right in fact i could even
do this we go i could say the new
framework countess everybody i need to
store the max render target index right
that's how much i would need and then i
can jenn frame buffers for however much
gets me up to there right so if this is
my new frame buffer count i can just say
how many would get me up to that from
where i currently am and i want you to
put those in the global frame buffer
handles array right I want you to put
them at whatever the current frame
buffer county is so starting we're
starting at the end of the currently
used ones generate me however many more
than I need and then we'll say that
we're done right so that gets us all the
frame buffers we need and so that all we
have to do is actually bind the correct
frame buffer right so the same way that
we bound textures in geo we can do I'll
look actually I know happen to know this
command but i will i will look it up
just so you can see it where oops that
that the cintiq has a bad placement of
that particular buttons i always reach
for the mouse and I hit it ok so there's
GL bind frame buffer go ahead and go
there please and here you can see the
call to it essentially what we have is a
a target so if you remember buying
texture we have the same thing where
it's like do you want to bind the 1d
texture to use extra 3d texture what
kind of texture you're trying to bind
and then which texture are you binding
right and the same is true for GL buying
frame buffer we have a couple different
things we could bind right we can bind
the draw frame buffer which is the frame
buffer we're trying to draw to the read
frame buffer which is the frame buffer
you would read back from if you made a
jail call that said give me the contents
of the frame buffer or GL frame buffer
which is basically binding both of those
right now we might as well buying both
of those even though we don't really
need it because I don't really care but
you know if we were being more Civic we
might
just only bind the draw frame buffer
because we're never reading back from it
anyway so you know six and one half
dozen together so anyway our target here
is that is going to be this right and
the frame buffer we're trying to bind is
just whatever the global frame buffer
handles is for this target and that will
come back as zero for the first one
which of course is the default frame
buffer and I'll come back as whatever
else it should be for any of the ones
that we generated okay so then when we
come out of here we'll set ourselves up
to bind the default frame buffer because
that's probably what we'll be drawing to
most of the time and we'll also set
ourselves a little memento which is
basically like frame you know current
frame buffer like so so now we know what
the frame buffer is that we're drawing
too and then down here we can sort of
say like all right let's go ahead and
you know pick up the values we actually
needed to pick up you can see in here
the clip render target index is the
thing that we're looking for so we can
go ahead and say what we want to do is
look at that clip render target so say
like if the clip round target index is
not equal to whatever the frame buffer
is that we're currently using you know
what I I'd like to write these this way
I usually write code like this such that
the thing I'm assigning to stays on the
same side to see what I'm saying like if
I'm going to do a test for naught equals
and then assign I usually like to make
it so that they line up like that anyway
so you can see your service just saying
okay if the current frame buffer is not
the one that you want me to use I will
go ahead and bind the new one otherwise
I leave the old one bound whatever one
we were on before and just to make it
again a little bit cleaner it's not
really particularly clean either way I'm
going to go ahead and after we're out
I'm just going to undo any like leftover
binding that there might have been just
so nobody below us gets confused right
so that's basically it for the
sort of the basic I need to like
generate and bind frame buffers but
obviously as you can see this isn't
really going to do us any good because
even though we bound those frame buffers
we don't have any access to their
contents we haven't done the additional
work that I was talking about before
where we actually to create a texture
that is the backing of a frame buffer so
that we can use it to draw with because
we still have no way even though I like
implemented that code we don't have any
way of making that work in here in in
this blender render target I need to
draw a full-screen rectangle right here
using some other frame buffer as the
source but I can't I don't have any way
to get at this stuff through the through
the GL at the moment not as a texture
okay so let's go ahead and compile that
and we'll see the first problem we're
going to have which actually has nothing
to do with that and that is simply that
we don't actually know oops I guess I've
got a different problem here what is the
problem whoops cgl on there that's Casey
notation at work i use cgl because i
have my own defines for everything but
that's a separate point this is the
problem I was actually trying to point
out and let me go ahead and fix the
other place I used to do there we go uh
so in GL gen frame buffers and GL buying
frame buffer I you'll notice they're not
there neither is the identifier this is
the thing I was saying where it's not
quite as easy as I make it look I just
typing it in and what's the problem
there well the problem there is the same
problem we ran into before with our srgb
stuff frame buffers for something that
was added after OpenGL one point X that
means that it is not natively defined in
the windows header files because of
course windows doesn't keep open trail
up to date why would they they want you
to use direct x so if we want to use
these we have to add them to our
extension querying and we pretty much
will require these so we need to kind of
have a thing here to say whether or not
we allow the whether or not we have them
and we need to kind of fail if we if we
don't have them so let's take a look at
what that frame buffer
extension actually would be okay that's
not what I want to do help what is
happening okay so let's see here buying
frame buffer extension so here is deal
our frame buffer object I believe this
is the extension we're looking for so I
think we can probably use this one to
indicate whether it's there or not let's
find out well not really a chin from
Bedford mine for about 4 yeah I guess
this one has them originally I think
this would probably be the right one GL
ARB framed by four object it might just
be our frame buffer I want to take a
look at just a see let me see here is
there a GL ARB frame buffer just by
itself no ok so let's take a look at
this and assume that we can get that
extension let's find out what happens if
we can or can't so let's go ahead and
put that in here GL ARB frame buffer
object result GL our frame buffer object
equals true and so in here what we'd
like to do is you know probably we'd
like to say that we just can't render an
open jail without that but I don't know
look I'm not sure exactly how we want to
I'm not sure how we want to deal with
that like should we just not draw the
top floor alpha blended because we could
do that and maybe that's the best thing
to do so yeah maybe I'll support that
maybe I'll support that anyway so what
we do need though regardless is we need
GL gen frame buffers in GL bind frame
buffer we need those to actually be
available to us right so what we need to
do is we need to define these somewhere
where we can actually call them and
we're not using a wiggle get proc
address in here it looks like yeah so I
need to go back to win the wintry to
code here right we're go get proc
address you can see it in
here and you can see us sort of grabbing
these various wiggle functions we need
to get the ones we need to use we go get
proc address to get those extended
functions here and so in order to do
that we're going to have to probably
pass these two open jail in it or
something like this i'm not sure exactly
how we want to do it but point being we
have the exact same problem we'll see
maybe I maybe I I kind of think I know
roughly how I want to do it let's see
here so you can kind of see how we did
these here right we have these wiggle
create context ribs are you know when
API kind of stuff that's happening here
so what we need to do is we need to go
grab the definitions of these from some
source that's going to have them define
the way they would be defined in side
the win api system right excuse me yeah
windows geo extensions i don't know i'm
coughing so much all right uh let's see
what we've got here so yeah we want GL
blind oops fine frame buffers and here
it is right we've got geo buying frame
buffer XD GL dilip frame buffers exe
Jill Jen frame buffer so this is really
what we want here and while we're at it
I'm just going to grab some of the other
ones that we need I think we will need
GL framebuffer texture 2d I don't know
if we'll need any of that thing that
might be it if we're lucky but will we
be lucky I don't know alright so what we
need to do now is we need to kind of
have these be defined in a way that they
can be seen and accessed by the OpenGL
layer under windows so I'm going to go
ahead and sort of get these defines well
actually I don't need 1d or 3d texture
render target
so I only need a 2d one I don't really
need to check the frame buffer status
because we'll assume that we're going to
be okay with that and so here we go with
our calls that will actually need we've
got our definitions all in a row here
right so that all looks pretty good and
so all I really need to do now is just
sort of change the names of these around
a little so that we can have a typedef
as well so GL delete frame buffers geo
and I don't really even need that
because i'm not going to free them frame
buffers GL framebuffer texture 2d and
that's it so yeah GL bind frame buffer
little variable geo jen frame buffers
variable geo frame buffer texture 2d and
that's about it right so API entry in
this case I think is just winapi I don't
think there's anything else you have to
do I don't even know if when appies
defined as anything anymore i think
that's mostly for if you're doing 32-bit
i don't think we need any i don't think
we really need it there but that's
neither here nor there anyway so we've
got GL buying frame buffers Jill Jen
fame breakfast Jill frame buffer texture
2d these all have to be actually loaded
now at some point and so where we do
wiggle swap interval X and those sorts
of guys we just have to go ahead and
unload these these folks into memory so
we've got GL buying frame buffer and
that's going to you know have to do
Whittle get proc address oops proc
address
on its own name same thing is going to
be true of these two fine fellows here
there we are and finally the frame
buffer texture2d there we go now we have
some other things that we're going to
need and you can kind of see them here
we need all of those defines that we
might call that we were using like for
example the GF draw you know the jail
thing we're saying which which kind we
were binding is it the reed frame
buffers the draw frame buffer that sort
of stuff right so we need to get this
pound to fine as well that's got to come
up here and then we also are going to
need the attachment like I think we're
going to need color attachment and some
of these types but we'll go I guess I'll
just leave this up and we'll see which
ones we actually need and we'll grab
them out so let's go ahead and compile
this and see where we're at so GL
framebuffer oops that i did i cut and
pasted the wrong one I guess I did where
is that
and actually know where that is signs
that your graphics API is too large 22
22 22 22 22 22 22 22 there it is that's
one looking for all right so we've got
our frame buffer there let's go ahead
and pile so now we're compiling and in
theory you know we probably can run but
you know we won't oh and I should switch
back to defaulting to the OpenGL
renderer since we're trying to develop
the OpenGL renderer so let's go ahead
and switch we go so here we are on the
OpenGL renderer and you know as you can
see everything's going along swimmingly
but when we come up here you can kind of
see we're getting some kind of weird
like really slow stuff like gets super
slow when we're in the middle of those
two so something Bad's happening right
we don't know but at least we're not
crashing so you know that's always good
but we do have sort of a bit of a
situation there now like I said we don't
really need to bug that yet because we
haven't actually implemented all the
stuff we actually need to implement to
even get the get it working so we don't
really care about the fact that it
happens to slow there because we haven't
even actually made valid render targets
we've made totally bogus render targets
that don't even have anything to draw
into so there's that but ignoring that
for a second let's go ahead and flip
back to the open trail thing here at
least now we know that we've got the
stuff that we needed so what I want to
do here is say well ok we really don't
want to to do to allow the max render
target thing to be used in any situation
where we don't have access to those
additional Frank frame buffer texture
calls so I'm just going to say max
render target index I'm going to say
that that equals what comes in but I'm
going to say if for example if the
OpenGL info doesn't have the extension
that
need so i could say like you know if we
don't have GL buying frame buffer then
we won't do this extra stuff right in
fact I could do this if GL fine buying
frame buffer is actually valid then i
will say that i'll use the actual ones
you said otherwise we'll just pretend we
only have one right then we can go ahead
and say the max render target index
everywhere else that we were using it
it's like that and here we'll just say
the same exact thing so we'll say like
used render target index equals zero and
we'll do you know we could we could do
the same thing I suppose we could just
say and I can even make a pool for this
so i could say pull through to use
render targets not equal to 0 so there's
my use render targets question and so
everywhere in here we'll just say like
ok you know use render target index
equals the clip render target index in
fact you know what I don't even have to
do that really now I think about it all
I really have to do is allow this to do
its thing and I can just say and clip
render target index is a less difficult
to the max render target index right I
can just say like don't allow anything
that's outside the range right so that
should be fine ok so use render target
index or use render targets is there so
there we go and so now in theory will
get a little protection there we should
also in here not bother to try and get
any of those if the extensions not there
so we could say and I don't know where
that we actually do that call where we'd
get the info
where do we do that
don't we get open Jill info somewhere
Jill get info so we do that here that's
not very helpful to be completely honest
with you so when we call in it we would
like to know whether we should try to
load these or not right I mean you know
we want to do something like maybe this
so this is Jill arm frame buffer objects
so if we have that then we will get
these otherwise we leave them as zero
right and that seems okay so yeah so
that's the the basics there but the
problem that we will have now is that
we're not actually doing anything with
those frame buffer so we've got to go
rectify that right so yeah you know it
is um so close that up so let's go back
in and see how to do the rest of the
thing that we need to do in our open
Jill code to actually get render targets
that we need so basically what happens
is when we do these frame buffer
generations what we've done is we've
created like basically blank frame
buffer objects that don't have the
necessary set up to actually be used in
the way that we need them to use to be
used and so what we have to do is we
have to go actually say to opengl hey
there's a texture the texture is going
to be used as a backing store for this
frame buffer so when you render I want
you to render into a texture and I'm
going to use the texture later we need
to make that statement that I alluded to
and we need to to give open jail that
information right and so the way we're
going to do that you can actually see
sometimes it's actually easier to read
the the extensions by the way because
they bundle the related calls together
but you can see that one that I was
grabbing out here this frame buffer
texture2d right
and that's what we actually have to call
and what that frame Buster texture2d
thing allows us to do is to say that we
have a texture that we want to use as a
as sort of the the thing that the frame
buffer represents so let's go in there
so you can see we have to pass through
this first of all we have to tell it
what we're trying to talk about here and
obviously we're talking about the frame
buffer that we we have bound to the
frame buffer slot so we need to do this
after we do the gen the frame buffer is
right so here we're going to have to do
essentially this right so we need to do
a target index that loops from whatever
our previous frame ever count was up to
our new frame buffer count go through
those targets we need to set you know we
have to bind one up so that we can start
talking about it to the up to the GL we
then have to call that GL framebuffer
texture2d that I stated before and we
need to pass these back parameters say
hey we're talking about this thing that
we bound right here then we've got the
attachment we don't have depth or
stencil buffers but you can am at you
can understand when you do rendering
right we talked about Z buffering or def
buffering as it's called right stuff
like that anything that has a buffer
that's associated with rendering
obviously has to be there and be talked
about when you're talking about a frame
buffer so if we were going to use the
buffering we would need to create a
depth attachment where we said this is
where you start the depth data and if we
were using stencil by frame which we
haven't talked about and aren't going to
talk about we would need to do that as
well right but all we're actually doing
is color buffers right all we need is
just one color buffer so we really only
need just this color buffer attachment
zero right that's the only thing that we
need to bind and so then we have a
texture target which is like what
texture target we're trying to do yet we
want a 2d texture target here obviously
right because we're not trying to render
to a cube map or anything fancy like
that we just want a plain old texture we
have to specify
texture or object we're doing so we're
going to need like global frame buffer
textures or something like that right
we're going to need a mirroring array
that has the texture handles in it and
then finally we need what mipmap level
and that we're not using any look
mapping here so we can just say 0 and
off we go that's about it all right so
that's pretty much everything that we
need to do to attach the frame buffer
texture there but we do have another
problem which is that we never actually
generated a texture right so we actually
need to get these textures to stick them
into the frame buffer so that it those
here is the textures that go with the
frame buffer so we basically have the
exact same problem we just had and now
we have to do this for textures as well
right so you have to do that all right
so we've got our global frame buffer
textures we need to do the exact same
calls essentially right Jen textures
where we're going to say like you know
we can probably do like new text you
know this is the new count or whatever
here go so we need to generate that many
more and the same thing here right so we
generate frame reference to generate
textures then each time through we're
going to have to actually generate the
texture as well and create it at the
size that we actually need it to be in
order to have it be bindable to the
frame buffer and used for rendering
right so we have to do the same exact
thing that we would do with a normal
texture right and
might as well pull this out it's easier
to see if there's the texture handle
right so we do the GL buying texture for
the texture handle we passed that same
text for handle here saying hey that's
the texture I want to be back in here
when we do our bind texture I'll unbind
it here as well so it doesn't isn't left
found oops so there we go and now all we
need to do is specify the information
about this texture that we that we
actually care about right and I believe
we have this call in here somewhere
there it is where we do allocate texture
and when we do on the K texture you can
kind of see how it does it here like
width and height and it sets some basic
parameters of the texture now in my mind
I feel like we might as well just reuse
this code right we don't need the GL
flush per se necessarily but then again
I don't think we really want the flush
there either that was the thing to avoid
us having a problem when we were using
the multi-threaded texture stuff which
we found out really wasn't going to work
anyway so you know there's that so we
can probably just reuse this code I
think that's probably a safe thing to do
yeah I don't see any reason we can't
just call this so I think what we can do
is call allocate texture and let that do
what we wanted to do and you know it
returns this pointer from u32 handle
nonsense here so we can actually cast
back using u32 from pointer and be done
so I'm going to go ahead here and say
well such as contentious oh yes so so I
don't even need this this gem texture
batch thing that I did here I could I
could actually just do it this way okay
so what we need now is the allocate
texture call to actually fill in you
know we need the parameters that we're
going to do there and you can see we
just need the width the height and the
data right and when you do when you pass
data down I believe you can always just
pass 0 here if you're just trying to
specify the size but not actually the
contents right and we don't really want
to specify any contents so I believe we
can just say hey we want this thing to
be whatever the width and height are of
the rendering and we don't care what you
stick in it it can be 0 we don't care
right and so allocate texture here in
this case since their actual things that
we're now calling they need to be
elevated up at a summer where they can
be seen so there we go so last but not
least we need to grab member I said
leave this open because we're going to
need to grab something out of there this
is the part where we need to grab
something out of there and it's this guy
right here which is how to specify color
attachment 0 which is just the basic one
now why are there multiple color you
know why are there multiple tetris the
reason is because in later revisions of
graphics cards you could actually target
several different render targets from
the same pass so when you draw like if
you drew a single triangle you could
actually have an output to multiple
render targets at once so the color
attachments 0 1 2 3 4 or whatever is a
way of saying oh you can actually render
to more than one target at a time if you
want
so that's why you have to specify which
one you're talking about alright so now
we probably need to step through this
and see what we're actually doing
because it's probably not going to work
nothing what you do in graphics works
the first time out but at least you can
see that we've gotten a little bit
better so you know I mean I don't want
to say that maybe it worked the first
time out but maybe it did I don't know
because you can notice we don't get that
slow down anymore right which means that
we're we're at least partially perhaps
maybe filling out those frame buffers
correctly now right but we don't know
and so we'll certainly have to go in and
look you know we don't know what's going
on it might be good it might be bad for
not sure so uh now what we need to do is
go in and actually you know we've done
the work it ostensibly depending on how
much we may have screwed up we've done
the work ostensibly to actually do the
frame buffer stuff all we need to do now
in order to complete the the first pass
on the code is actually pull out the
render targets themselves and use them
as textures to blend right to do a bland
that's all we need to do so we have a
OpenGL a rectangle blit thing here and
yeah yeah now now we just need to take a
look at what's going to happen here so
yeah you can kind of see we've got the
yeah we've got I think we've got
everything pretty much sit up straight
this is all we need to do is to just
draw a full-screen rectangle right
that's pretty much it so I think we're
still in screen space here so I think
all we really need to do here is to sort
of take this code like this code here
where we're doing our bind texture okay
and is OpenGL rectangle does that to a
GL begin it does okay
so we decide to come in here and say all
right we're going to bind a texture we
need to find out where that texture is
so we're going to leave that out for a
second and then we are going to call
OpenGL rectangle and we're going to call
oops I wanted Joe rectangle we go we're
going to pass in the min and the max
we're going to pass in color value right
and that color value is just no
modification right 111 no modulation
just full and then the Alpha value okay
and then we've got the UV de min max UV
but they're already set their default
values are exactly what we want them to
be right we've got to deal with the
source target index here but that's the
only other thing and so now what I need
to do is I need to use that source entry
index to just grab out of the render
target or sorry the little frame buffer
textures I just need to grab the texture
handle that represents whichever texture
thought we were targeting and then
render now what I want to do here is
before i do any of this i want to make
sure we're actually using render targets
because if we're not then we just want
to ignore these commands because there's
nothing we can do about them right so
just going to do it straight up that's
all good and conversion from you 32
what are you talking about from you
shoot you real 32 oh I see so what we're
doing here I say hey all right we need
to draw a rectangle we need to draw a
rectangle over the entire screen so what
we need to do is go ahead and grab out
the texture that represents the target
we were trying to go from then we do the
Alpha now we've got one problem here and
that is the state our blending state is
actually not what we want it to be and
the reason for that is we did not use
premultiplied alpha so we can't use this
blend funk right so even though we want
to to leave that blood funk on Just In
in here right for just this one
operation we need to modulate the
incoming source by the Alpha value right
because remember premultiplied alpha non
p multiplied alpha they are two
different plan modes this is the blend
mode for premultiplied alpha this is the
blend mode for non p multiplied alpha
and if you don't remember what that is
you got to go back and look I can talk
about in the Q&amp;A if people have
forgotten but that's basically what we
need to do now we're almost out of time
so we probably won't get a chance to
debug this and get it working but that's
the basic code that we needed right and
so hey that's actually not too far off
at least now we are blending something
in unfortunately that something is just
a solid white nonsense right so not
quite there but at least we're getting
closer right um so that is pretty much
all there actually is to it there isn't
a there really isn't much more other
than the debugging stage of things
that's about it so yeah I assume that
yet texture2d is is always on so that's
good um so yeah so really all I think we
have to do is just just actually make
sure that we're getting the correct
stuff set up for our frame buffers here
because you know I probably did
something wrong or you know something
bad happened here i'm not sure what
where we where it's not working properly
who knows what else right so probably
that's all we need to do is debug what
we did wrong with our textures and then
we'll be good to go now the other thing
that we could have done wrong here i
suppose is the front of target index
talk remember so i think i think
everything else we did here makes sense
though i don't quote me on that but i
think we're okay yeah yeah this all
looks roughly right so i don't think we
have anything majorly wrong but we
probably forgot something specific now
one thing we could do is we can also try
to determine whether or not we've got a
bug here by I don't we've never used the
debug services from OpenGL but yeah but
that's one thing we could consider going
and doing I don't know if we should do
it not the other thing that I could do
here is just take a look at to see if I
forgot anything so we could
geo fir textures and just look at you
know some code to make sure that I did
everything that I was supposed to do
let's see I don't want to bind a render
buffer a render buffer is like the sort
of thing that you get by default when
you don't try to do render to texture
it's like you know it's effectively a
texture but one that was like the kind
of the kind that you have back when you
don't have a tech where you have
rendered texture the default thing you
have that's a render buffer um let's see
this is not what I actually wanted right
strove I framebuffer name gel viewport
lay out a framework for storage def
component know from remember fur gives
us attachment render buffer death
Jennifer for Jill Jen render buffer is
no writer texture when do they actually
set the texture there it is right so
that looks all correct so what I could
do here too is like a call check frame
buffer status and see whether we have an
obvious error or something like that
right and I guess I might as well do
that while I'm here I gotta just a few
seconds I can I contribute leak all that
and and check it right so up here when
we do find frame before I can just go
like okay check the frame buffer and do
like a what is that going to return deck
frame buffers status oops just check
that little frame buffer status check
that little frame buffer status there we
go so in went through to handmade where
we get the rest of our calls from there
we go we can just say okay global
variable
she'll check frame buffer status typedef
winapi feel check frame buffer status
chilling them target and so then when I
do the rest of these guys here I can
just do the same thing and and now we
should be able to at least see whether
it thinks are our frame breath or is
valid or not
it's an enum right so at that point we
just need whatever that frame buffer
complete identifier is oops clear and
just grab that out there we go and so i
will post that guy with the top here and
then I think we can run and just see
whether it thinks that we made a frame
buffer correctly or if we didn't right
now we have to actually trigger it so we
have to kind of come up here to get it
going but in theory you know that would
have fired in that case so let's let's
all right I so let's see what we got for
status 360 53 you know what let's take a
look at that impacts OCD 5r sorry aight
CD 58 CD 585 so it thinks that our frame
buffer was valid apparently right so
that's a good sign I want to take a look
at what we're clearing the sky two
commands a clear color so we're clearing
it to some grayish thing with an alpha
value of zero so that seems reasonable
as well i should think so that seems ok
i guess one thing I don't know is
whether GL viewport is per frame buffer
to be completely honest I cannot
remember so I'm going to look
let's see you frame buffer object field
viewports Sophie glv part is not
implicated in this at all so I don't
think it should be so clear so I I feel
like these should just work right I
don't think there should be any I don't
think there should be any weirdness
there uh so yeah current frame buffer
and a target index if clip which is not
equal to set the scissor and that all
seems fine and then down here where
we've got use render targets we're going
to bind which ever want to do is source
targeted oh wait that's my problem
that's my problem right there I never
stored the texture handle so maybe we
did everything right and we just never
stored the texture handle so like I do
global frame buffer textures equals
texture handle right because we use that
later so we were just using a bogus
texture handle so obviously we weren't
going to get your results there okay hop
along mr. hero Hey look it worked so
we're sort of working now you know we're
sort of multi render targeting and off
we go and it all looks good so I think
we're in good shape and we can go to the
unit so let's go to the QA QA um yeah
good deal
so like no Q&amp;A at all
the any key what are the biggest
challenges you have faced with the game
thus far well this is like an
educational stream so I wouldn't really
say that we face a lot of challenges
really I mean the thing that was most
forward to me is I normally do 3d games
I don't usually do 2d much in 2d and so
the sprite sorting stuff is a little
weird because I don't really know there
doesn't seem to be much of a right
answer to it we had to kind of do
something you know kind of hockey and
we'll see how it works when we put the
real art in there and and finish the Z
finish this evening but I mean I yeah I
wouldn't say that really like it's not
designed to be challenging it's designed
to be educational so we're not trying to
tackle like you know any unusual
problems here you know we're just we're
trying to do just a nice professional
quality job on the various parts of a
2-d game that you might have and we go a
little further than a lot of 2d games go
that's for sure you know like most
traditional 2d games don't have the
ability to see down multiple levels and
all that sort of stuff necessarily but
you know so we're kind of I guess we're
trying to be like higher end in terms of
the features we support for you know a
2d exploration any kind of game like
that but we're not you know we're we're
not trying to do anything particularly
weird so yeah
does AZ do work across Nvidia AMD and
Intel so I guess what I would say is AZ
do is is something that's taken pretty
seriously by Nvidia less seriously by
AMD and even less seriously by Intel at
the moment so for example stuff that you
really want like envy command list I
don't think I don't even know if anyone
else supports it besides them so some of
the AZ do stuff just only exists on
nvidia others of the eighth of the azo
stuff like pinned memory and stuff is
definitely on AMD but not so much on
intel like there's a bunch of things
that Intel doesn't do with respect to
bind list Mindless and pinned memory
things so I haven't tried really hard
yet it's on my list of things to do I
haven't tried really hard yet to see how
easy do you can be on intel and AMD on
nvidia you can get real good but on AMD
and intel not so much at the moment but
we'll see maybe that'll change as i as i
pound on it more but that's the current
situation so the answer is sort of to
eliminate extent they all support it and
video supports it quite a bit on the
other two your mileage varies compare
the handmade hero engine complexity
versus 1935 they're not even I mean
they're they're like night and day
probably i guess i would say
q for catching up to the previous
episodes do you recommend going through
all the videos or to try to understand
the current code base I would say that
catching up is not probably a useful
thing i would say that usually what you
want to do is just start at the
beginning it's meant to be an
educational stream it's meant to kind of
go through everything step-by-step and I
think that's where it's useful being up
to date isn't really relevant I mean it
doesn't matter if you're if you're
watching it live I mean you know if you
want a tuning occasionally and ask
questions and stuff that's always great
but there's no real overwhelming reason
you need to watch it live right so I
would say the most effective way to
learn from the series if that's what
you're trying to do is to just watch the
the episodes in order at your pace
whatever you feel comfortable watching
and learning you know and and don't try
to push yourself for for any particular
reason if you're finding you're going
through them fast and it's all pretty
obvious then you just you'll watch them
really quickly if you get stuck on
places just stop there and figure out
what it is that was you know that you
didn't understand what I was doing or
whatever to figure that part out or what
I would say that's the right way to
learn from it and not you know not
feeling like for some reason you gotta
catch up because it's not going anywhere
when we do however many it takes to
finish the whole game six hundred
episodes or whatever it is they're just
going to sit there right and so even if
you you know were 200 episodes behind at
that point well I'm going to stop and so
you will catch up eventually if that
makes sense
all right no more q's just think that's
the end of it
thank you everyone for joining me for
their soda handmade hero it's my
pleasure coating with you as always if
you would like to follow along the
series at home you can always pure to
the game it comes with the source code
so that you can do your own
experimentation and learn from the from
you know from experimentation from doing
always good we have a forum site you can
go to if you want to ask questions a
patreon page if you want to support the
video series we have a schedule bot you
can go to if you want to know when the
series is going to be live and we have
an episode guide you can go to trying to
catch up on old episodes that's about it
for today I will be back tomorrow 5 p.m.
pacific daylight time with till then
have fun programming and i'll see you
guys on the internet tickety's everyone