hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here or sure we could a complete game
live on stream we are in the middle of
debugging or PNG reader which actually
hasn't been too bad so far which I guess
maybe that just means the worst is yet
to come
who knows so far it's been pretty smooth
sailing in terms of interpreting the
specification and so on we did run into
a little bit of a weirdness last time
where there seemed to be some confusion
the spec seemed a pretty clearly state
in two different places to different
rules for interpreting bit values for a
certain part of the spec and what we do
know is that Sean Barrett was on the
stream and he's already written a PNG
reader obviously for STB image and he
was pretty strongly suggesting that's
the part of the spec that said that the
bits were reverse was wrong and that the
bits were actually forward hopefully he
is right I mean he should be right you
were at the PNG reader so we had to have
gotten that right but hopefully that's
true because if it's not true then we
have to actually reverse bits as they
come in which is a real pain in the butt
right we'd like to be able to just read
and use the value without manipulating
the bits at all so hopefully that is the
case I don't know if it is or not we're
gonna find out but we'll start looking
at that today and then we'll try to push
forward we're actually there isn't much
more code to write we've done most of
the decoding work so far there's just a
transform thing that we have to write
which probably will pretty simple so
most of the work left in finishing the
PNG reader which has been pretty
straightforward even though the spec is
kind of old and weird most of the work I
think that we're gonna have to do going
forwards is just in debugging our
interpretation of the interpretation and
implementation of the deflate spec so
you know and this is again since this is
the deflate spec it means that we could
use this code presumably to do other
things as well if you want to
to read like a zip file or something
that was compressed with the deflate
speck presumably this would read it so
it's actually kind of a generic piece of
code in that sense where this this
particular bit stream decode is
presumably usable in a number of cases
where the deflate compressor was used or
the deef the encoder for the deflate
complete compressor it was used however
you want to say that we're the deflate
algorithm was used so what we think we
know so far when we come down through
here and we produce our decoding tables
so far it seems like this is pretty
accurate the reason why I say it seems
like this is pretty accurate which mean
when I say that I mean it seems like
there aren't huge glaring errors in it
there might still be some subtle ones
that only happen once in a while but the
reason I say that it seems pretty
accurate is because when we actually
come through here this assertion does
not fire which means that we actually do
decompress the information in the tables
and get exactly as much table data out
as we expect so if we were like totally
decoding it wrong we would expect that
to fire and now that we've gotten to the
point where it doesn't fire we can sort
of assume that we're you know closed
right on this part we then do Huffman
generation this is basically they have a
certain way in which they've encoded the
Huffman tables to try to make them
concise this right here decodes those
Huffman tables from their sort of
encoded version it's not really that
compressed per se it's just sort of a
concise encoding that is compression
obviously but anyway this concise
encoding of the Huffman then gets turned
into something we can use to decode the
Huffman more quickly by generating
tables now we don't know whether that is
working properly right we implemented
what we thought was a reasonable way to
do it
we don't really know so
that's just purely speculative then we
get down to this loop and this loop
again we have no verification of yet so
we don't really know if these are proper
we don't really know if this is proper
here we cannot at the moment I think
decode a full block correctly so we know
that we've got at least one probably
glaring bug in there somewhere that we
can fix to get us to a slightly smoother
run but at the moment we will be
focusing on from here down because we do
have some reason to believe that this
part is working relatively correctly now
again that's not necessarily the case in
its entirety there could be some subtle
bugs in here that just allow you to
produce the same number of lengths but
you've got one or two of them wrong or
or all of them are wrong in some subtle
way that doesn't affect how many of them
you did and things like this so we don't
know much about this part here in terms
of the accuracy of the Huffman tables
but we do know something about that the
bit encoding and we think we've got that
part right
everything else is still suspect and
then this part right here is the first
time we really did this code last week
Sunday I guess I'm sorry two weeks ago
Sunday we were off last weekend so this
part right here is probably got plenty
of issues in it and we'll sort of start
to assess those out as we go what I will
point out is we're now at the part of
the process where structured art can
start to help us I don't know for quite
there yet but we're close to there yet
what do I mean by that so if we open up
this file with that I made as our
test look at these lovely mushrooms we
can go in here and look at the first
part of the file that we created or at
least I thought we created where is it
sorry that's not the top there it was
right there and what you can see is I've
been very careful to put in the first
row of the image here I've put a red dot
and then two black dots and then an
increasing alpha now in the last row of
the image I've done a similar thing I've
put one green dot and two black dots so
what we would expect to see when we
start decompressing this is one of those
two things now I don't remember seeing
in the actual spec yet I'm sure it's in
there somewhere but we didn't go looking
for it whether these images are encoded
with the bottom as the first line or the
top is the first line but regardless of
which you can that's why I put one on
each regardless of which one it chooses
we will expect to see that structured
art appear and that should start to give
us a clue as to whether or not we are
even decoding anything correctly now the
thing you remember here is we can modify
this and we can in fact start with much
simpler things too in fact I might go
ahead and do that that here is well
create another one for us to use I can
do something like just make a single 8
by 8 block for example and I can make
sure that we know all of the values in
this 8 by 8 block let me make sure that
it has an alpha channel but what I can
do here is I can make sure that we set
these values to things that we know as
well and then it's a lot easier again
for us to just kind of plunk through
what we're looking at as we start and
again this is just the reasoning behind
this is very simple the idea is that if
you know what you expect to get when you
decode something you can read in the
debugger exactly what kind of data is
coming out of the decompressor and you
can start to have an idea about whether
or not it's even remotely working
properly right and furthermore if we
create a highly structured piece of
artwork we can also potentially like see
where we're starting to go wrong
you know what I mean so we can sort of
start to see what happens
when we when we get to the end of lines
or things like that and we can sort of
start to see like where where do we
start to screw up if we get some correct
values and then get some values that are
incorrect you know why is that happening
so we should be able to create some
things that help us and are sort of
waypoints for us in that regard and so
here's an example of an image that that
sort of does that and I'll just make one
more here sort of behalf right versions
um so this you know gives us a pretty
clear you know we can all understand
what this should look like when we
actually look at it in binary you know
we've got eight pixels across we have an
own color on the first pixel of every
row and we've got a blue pixel at the
end of the first and last rows just so
we can kind of see where that watermark
is and that I think is again totally
reasonable let me just go ahead and and
you know maybe I'll do one more thing
now no you know what so let me go ahead
and export this as a ping as well and
then that way we can also load this in
and have a smaller test thing to look at
because the other one's pretty big it's
more of a complete test here and so we
can load that one in and just get a good
and we can also force it here we know we
want it to use the 32-bit format that's
what we're looking for here and I guess
you know we've also got this compression
level stuff which we could play with but
again that's that's just if we wanted to
try like making the file simpler you
know if it's zero maybe it doesn't use
any compression I don't know in which
case we could look at the D at an
uncompressed one so we probably do want
both of those like we could do something
like this right where we export one of
them and then I can also export another
one of them that's specifically
compression zero
where this gets cranked down to the
bottom I don't know that we care about
any of that
we skip those blocks so those should be
fine and yeah there's really nothing
else in here that we care about really
so if I just set that to zero we can see
if that creates a materially different
file compression wise and if it does we
can see like again get some more
information about where we're storing
screwup so that's really all I'm talking
about they're just again creating
opportunities for us to find our bugs it
can be hard when you're dealing with
really robust intricate data because
again you just don't know what you're
dealing with so if you just have
something very very simple and basic
that can really help you zero in on
those bugs quicker than spending all
your time trying to sort through what
you're looking at in the debug view okay
so if we go ahead and launch this here
let's let's actually go ahead and take a
look at that uncle well I don't know if
it's uncompressed it's compression level
zero
maybe still does some light
compression on it I'm not sure but I'm
interested to see what happens just if
the file like doesn't have the
compression part in it I just interested
to see right because it could have
remember there's this be type zero block
it's a block that just doesn't have any
of the deflate encoding specified in it
it would be interesting to get something
with a little bit of that in it because
we would like to handle that as well and
we also thought that we had a to do here
so this we need to do this as well
Martin's correctly pointed out that
that's not and you know what I should
sooo if we look here first of all this
read the huffman stuff here is actually
done now this is the place where we
actually want this I believe am I right
about that so I think yes so I think
what happens here is be type 2 is the
one that actually has the tables in it
be type one is one where we actually
have see the huffman with the built-in
huffman tables this is one that we are
going to have to handle sooo if we now
take a look at what will happen on the
compression zero one I'm just curious
again before we get started this is 8 by
8 compression 0 I believes the name of
the file am I right about that
let's take a look yeah
so it's 427 bytes long let's go ahead
and step into the PNG read here so when
we get in here this is marked as
supported which is good we come through
here and we look at the pixel setup it's
not be final which of course it's a
little weird because you'd think they'd
only be one block to encode that but
maybe it's every row is different I
don't know anyway let's take a look ok
so it did it did exactly what I hoped
which is that if we set the compression
level to zero we just get this kind of
file which is a file that has no deflate
encoder in it or at least it doesn't
look like it does yet so it will allow
us to test this part as well so if we
consume I use 16 here in both cases we
get a Len and the
in the end Lin is not a value we
actually need it's just a error-checking
value it looks like it's the supposed to
be the ones complement of Len and so
we'd sit to see if that's right so it
says here that those don't match let me
see what's going on there I think I did
that right maybe I did that wrong so
there's Len right and sight we can look
and there's n Len so that is definitely
what did I do
because that looks exactly like it
should look my
[Music]
ah okay so is this actually doing
integral promotion on this it looks like
we're getting integral promotion here
assuming that this is doing the same
thing that we'll do so I guess that's
forcing us up to above a u16 which we
really don't want let me go ahead and
force it not to do that or try to you
anyway just to really make sure not sure
why it would do that but yeah there we
go
so it was just the integral promotion it
wanted to expand when you when you did
this operator it want to expand it out
to 32 bits just using C's internal
promotion rules which I will never for
the life of me understand why they are
the way they are I'm sure there's
historical reasons for it they're not
reasons I would probably agree with but
whatever no one cares what I think
so it's fine we go in here we need to ne
and swap this because I believe we read
that the length value is actually wrong
it's concluded the opposite way round I
think now I don't know if that's
actually right because we said is it
supposed to be so if we look here we see
264 if we were doing an 8 by 8 right and
each one was supposed to have 4 that
would be 256 which is how many pixel
values we'd effectively included now we
would also expect 8 row transform values
because they four because they didn't
know very much about image compression
which it's hard to blame them it was a
long time ago and people weren't that
knowledge about that sort of thing in
general case back then they weren't
experts you don't generally want to do
transforms per row they didn't know that
so they put one transform per row and so
I suspect that that's just what we're
seeing here 8 times 8 times 4 plus 1
transfer vibe for each row would be
Tuesday before what that suggests to me
is regardless of how we interpreted the
spec it looks like that length value is
not Indian swapped right
because the Indian swapped version of
that's going to be huge and I don't
think there were 2049 pieces of data in
this file so I suspect if that's an
error and underflow right so I think
what we want to do there is we want to
sort of fix this right and we can also
check on this here you might as well put
a we don't really care about making this
robust we might as well so I think we're
just gonna say that that based on our
experience here is not supposed to be
Indiana swapped I had to do there so
that meant that I wasn't really sure
what the spec was trying to say so that
seems fine and so here we go you know
sort of reading that data out and that
looks like that read correctly so you
know the nice part about that is it
looks like we already have the ability
to read you know simple PNG so that's
good and if I look at where's that there
it is so you know this all came out
correctly and I think probably the data
is correct here I don't know we should
probably find a good way to look at the
data but in the meantime in Leo of doing
that at the moment I think what I'll do
is I'll just go ahead and look at what
decompressed pixels ends up being so if
you take a look here we've got
decompressed pixels where it does this
allocation here with the width the
height the four and the extra bytes so
this is the decompressed it's not really
to compress opposed to compressed data
goes in there let me see here do we just
copy that in to dest we do so yeah okay
so when we're done in this supported
section here I'll just go ahead and skip
to the end why did we not why does it
not break on that line
yeah all right great visual studio as
always making debugger and harder than
it has to be visual studio always excels
at this here's we compress pixels let's
take a look at what is in it so what I
want to do is I want to get this to show
basically the bitmap I think I can force
it to nine potentially hopefully yeah so
here is the road transform value here
are the pixels that we're seeing in that
oh sorry
and I want these to be 32-bit so they're
right oh you know what no I take it back
I can't do that because of that row one
is the one that one's off so I'm gonna
have to actually do you know it's 8
times 4 which is 32 plus the 1 so it's
33 so this is the actual sort of scan
I'm gonna want to use I guess right so
as we come through here we're gonna be
writing these pixels you can see us
writing them in in here right and so
what I'm gonna look for is I'm just
gonna look to make sure that this does
come out to be what we think it should
be and this will also tell me something
really important when I look at this
because it is again structured artwork
this will give me a clue as to what the
actual encoding value is here does our
bread come first does green come does
reckon first or just blue come first and
so on so taking a look here at these
values I so wait a minute did I do that
math wrong or something so there's
supposed to be eight pixels each one
should have four bytes which should be
32 is doing what am I missing here so
there's the Road transform value that
should be one pixel right and you know
again what I can do I don't know why I
closed it probably because I wasn't
thinking
but if I go ahead and and open this I
like open you can open in Visual Studio
okay
that's interesting uh let's see here
open with that was probably talking
about different file that's what that's
what was going on there
so let me go ahead and zoom in here so
if I look at this I expect red blacks
and a blue all of the Alpha values
should be full I would think
but then again I don't really know how
they're choosing to encode this I guess
I don't know what is thinking there
so let's let's do this just I don't know
so if I make a new layer and I put it
down here so all of that stuff was
supposed to be opaque so I'm not sure
what to make of that
maybe that's not true until I just did
the thing I did where it's not the
bottom layer but we'll got to look at
this a little bit more closely because
you see what I'm seeing here there's all
these zeros in here I don't really
understand I also don't understand what
that is doing there I guess that's
because my assumption and again this is
just purely speculative is that when I
paint into this pixel is off a
little bit on its radius and put a
little tiny bit of red into the next
pixel over just a tiny little bit that's
my assumption anyway moving forwards as
you look at this you can sort of see my
confusion looking over here you see this
FFF value that is blue but it's still
zero so here's here's my guess and and I
I don't know what else to make of it so
this data does now line up if you assume
that the Alpha channel is just wrong or
cat
arbitrary I don't know because if you
look at what what we're looking at here
this all like looks somewhat plausible
right although actually no it does it
cuz that's that looks like a green there
ah so you know what here's the thing I
will say we don't know what these road
transforms are so now that I think about
it and they're actually set like one set
to one one set to two or two of them are
set to two so I guess here's the thing
we'll have to go look at what those road
transforms aren't that probably is what
it is right because those even though we
said compression zero maybe what
does is get still applies Road
transforms even though compression level
zero turned off deflate maybe it still
applies Road transforms and that would
explain why we're seeing sort of like
values that line up a little bit but
don't really make sense the way we would
expect them to that seems logical to me
like so for example if this was a
difference between the pixel above you
and you this would make a lot of sense
right in fact it looks like a difference
between the pixel oops I had to do too
soon it looks like one is difference
between you and the pixel to your left
and two is you and the pixel to your top
that's what it looks like
so just purely based on what I saw there
that's what I expecting this in this
back this is good I'm glad we're in this
place because today let's forget about
the Huffman for now let's get those
transforms working because we need to do
that and now we have what we think is
good data coming out that's not
compressed that gives us an opportunity
to get that transforms working without
worrying whether the Huffman's working
which is a more complicated part so I
feel like that's really a good thing
here right so
let's go ahead in here and take this
this decompressed pixel stuff to the
sort of make that happen out here
I'm gonna go ahead and have a thing
that's like final pixels which is like
the thing that we take the decompressed
pixels and sort of wrap them into I'm so
I'm going to do a set it to zero here
and then I'm going to allocate pixels
once we actually know that we're
supported in here and we are able to
actually do a decompression on the data
in the file then I'm going to decompress
I'm gonna allocate final pixels worth of
space that we will like sort of extract
the decompressed pixels into right so
once we get to the end here we're just
gonna assume that we're okay and we're
gonna go apply those transforms those
Road transforms as written do if this is
the right place let's take a look here
yeah so coming down here we're gonna
have to go row by row Oh No
what happened to for coder I don't think
we've ever had a crash on stream before
that's the first time
[Music]
let's take a look here what's going on
draw file loaded
should have probably installed the
source on this machine because we
actually could look at it hmm so that's
a drawing problem which is kind of
bizarre I wonder if that's related to
all those flashes we're getting I should
update the version of for coder on this
machine it's a little out of date that
close this No
that may already have been fixed I don't
know but I don't think so because I
don't think there's been any rendering
updates at some point we should try to
debug that purple flash because it's
weird and it happens a lot on this
machine and it doesn't happen on other
machines that I've seen like I don't I
get that once in a blue moon on other
machines but this one happens all the
time makes it seem like maybe it would
be a good idea to debug it on this
machine since it seems like it's pretty
it's got a pretty high hit rate whereas
debugging something on a machine that
doesn't have a high hit rate is very
hard alright so let's try that one more
time again all I want to do here is just
have final pixels if this is just a
thing where I could put the final data
that will get passed back to whoever in
the application is like asking for this
thing right so when you said parse PNG
you know you called me and you handed me
this this PNG file and I'm supposed to
return you like some kind of a set of
pixels so that's gonna be what that what
that value is so when we find that the
thing is supported right here we're
gonna go ahead and allocate space for it
and then at the end we're going to go
through each row that we ended up with
and we're going to try to put the put
the transform data into the
untransformed state so we're like
undoing the transform that the PNG
compressor
did when it compressed before it
compressed the road in this case didn't
compress the roast there was no need for
it
but think that it I'm sorry not pink
did it anyway
sorry apologies rad game tools alright
so if I go through here and I just loop
over my rows I know that I have height
number of rows and what I want to do is
I want to go through each pixel here you
know I could just make it easier on
myself just make this be Y and X I mean
we know what those are so for each of
these what we're gonna do is at the
beginning of the row and I can sort of
set up two things here which is like and
I can pull this out in a separate
function a second cuz it's gonna be
pretty self-contained so we know that
our source is coming from the
decompressed pixel buffer which has that
row thing in each part of it and then
our desk is going to be the final pixels
so what we're gonna do first is we're
gonna read the transform and that's just
a single thing that comes out of the
source and then what we're gonna do is
we're gonna read the RGB and a values
out of the source and then we're gonna
apply potentially some operation to them
and from there you know go from there
right so what we need to do now is we
need to and I like I said looking at it
it looks like their left neighbour
difference and top neighbor difference
we're the two that looked like they were
in there I don't actually know that was
just my guess so we got to go look at
the PNG specification and find out what
the actual what those actually are so
where was that stuff
let's transforms
a number of transformations are applied
to the reference image to create the P&amp;G
intra-coded tracers are applied in the
following sequence where square brackets
mean the transformation is optional
alpha separation indexing or RGB merging
and then sample depth scaling okay when
every pixel is either fully transparent
if I pick the Alpha separation alpha
compaction and indexing transfer aces
can cause the recovered reference image
to have an alpha sample depth different
from the original reference image or to
have no alpha channel this has no effect
through capacity of any pixel truther is
considered equivalent of the transfer
circuit sort of lossless encoders that
nevertheless wish to preserve the Alpha
sample depth may elect not to perform
transportation is that okay all right if
all alpha samples in a reference image
have the same have the maximum value
then the Alpha Channel may be omitted
resulting in an equivalent image that
can be encoded more okay so that
actually was the case with our image it
just doesn't seem like they actually did
that unless when they say omitted they
mean just wrote zero or something but no
they didn't they actually encoded it I
think I think it looks like because it
was the right row length I think's with
alpha in it so I don't think that
actually removed the Alpha in either
case we probably don't care about that
because we will never have an image that
probably does that but we can look so
one thing I don't like here is they're
not telling us how to do it so this is
really the wrong section to look at
probably but hey it's a good background
or we need to look close like it doesn't
say how it encodes that fact right maybe
it encodes that fact by just saying that
the file isn't for deep it's three deep
right maybe that's what they mean
indexing if the number of distinct pixel
values is 256 or less and the RGB sample
depths are not greater than eight and
the Alpha Channel is absent or exactly
it's deep or every pixel is either fully
transparent you know what
and here's probably why gimped into it I
manually selected RGB a8 so even if
their compressor would normally look and
see if was going to emit the alpha table
I sort of force them not to right so
maybe we should allow them to do that
just we can make sure we handle that
case we may need to handle that case
because for like a backdrop scene that
doesn't have any alpha maybe I don't
know hard it's hard to say we can cross
that bridge when we come to it shouldn't
be a very hard modification to make to
say the least
alright so bla bla bla bla bla bla bla
no one cares so let's see assuming we
don't care about indexing RGB merging so
it's basically saying can reduce to
grayscale
this one yes so these are these are
things we probably just don't care about
this would be these are all if you
wanted to support the full spec and
cared a lot about it we don't we only
care about the things we're likely to
see so unless we see that we're not
going to do it
okay so this is just something that
expands values that are a different
sample that's we don't care about that
either
each scanline is transformed into a
filtered scanline we're more defined
filter types compression chunking
reconstruction okay
not sure I follow this here fourth
reduced image fifth reduced image sixth
reduced image seventh reduced image I'm
not sure I follow that
pass extractions splits a PNG image into
a sequence of reduced images where the
first image defines a course view and
subsequent images enhance this course
view until the last image completes the
PNG image the set of reduced images is
also called an interlaced PNG image two
interlaced methods are defined the first
method is a null method they're stored
sequentially so I think I don't care
about that either this makes no sense to
me what what this here makes no sense at
all
I mean I can see I guess they chose I
guess this is just how they chose to
encode smaller versions of it so here's
the 4 pixel version it does this one
this one this one this one right and
then so rather than doing like a wavelet
where you would blur out the you take
the average of like all of these or some
other wavelet transform and then you
would do the difference from the average
and code that progressively they just
actually literally take specific pixels
who knows why probably memory bandwidth
concerns or maybe they probably cuz they
didn't know about wavelets I don't know
both of those two things probably
wavelets are bad for the cache so let's
see here okay
PNG standardized one filter method in
several filter types that may be used to
prepare image data for compression
transference one bytes you get scan line
to decode length sequence of bytes
preceded by a filter type byte that's
what we're looking at flow type byte
define stick meaning to plastics and
line the encoder shall use only a single
filter method of an interlaced PNG image
may use different prototypes for each
scan line and a reduced image so we're
using the non-interlaced versions here
so we're talking about multiple filter
methods so exactly as we expect here so
what are those filter types that's what
we really want to know that's not in
here so let's go ahead and look at the
filter type section presumably that's
defined somewhere filtering
here we go okay so filtering transforms
the PNG image school of improving
compression
yep that we know that only filter method
0 is defined by this international
standard other fill nurse or reserved
for future use so they're talking I
believe though about this so I believe
they're talking about this one so filter
methods 0 is the part they're talking
about only has a 0 in it that's just the
overall filter Bank type each individual
row for filter method 0 has a different
filter type for that method so that's
what they mean by only filter method 0
here's the actual set of filters so here
you go 0 just means hey use the original
1 means oh subtract from the I assume
these are was at the byte to the left
the byte in the previous day on line the
bike corresponding to be in the pixel
immediately before the pixel containing
B so does that mean the pixel 2 pixels
back
[Music]
I I don't quite know what they mean by
that but I'm interpreting that to mean
two pixels back so X is the bike being
filtered a is the bike corresponding to
X in the pixel immediately before the
pixel containing X right so basically
that's saying if we were talking about
the red channel of the current pixel we
would talk about the red channel in the
pixel one to the left right that's all
be is the bike crash X the previous
scanline so that's just again the same
thing but top so this is exactly what I
thought right in C is the bike
corresponding to B in the pixel
immediately before the pics contain D so
that's two pixels back I'm pretty sure
so my guess I mean I don't understand
why you would have C in there but my
guess is it's because since this was
like low res and had an indexed mode and
stuff like that differing was probably a
thing so I'm guessing that maybe that is
a like alternating pixels is a common
thing you would see in like bit to Italy
like pixel art right and since this was
made in that era potentially for that
sort of thing that makes a lot more
sense than if you were making one today
you pry don't that doesn't sound super
plausible like sure that might be one
thing if you had lots but you would
probably like you'd probably want the
pixel up and to the left before you
would want the pixel to to the left most
of the time I would think so if you're
gonna pick one more thing to have it
wouldn't be too to the left but you know
I'm just guessing that because of
differing maybe that's where that comes
from I don't know
hard to say anyway those are pretty
straightforward assuming that I'm
interpreting C correctly as to the left
those are pretty easy to understand we
wouldn't have much trouble implementing
those so that's fine so here are the
actual filter types encoded based on
these prior values
so to reconstruct type-0 it's just the
value that means no filter is applied
type 1 we add in the prior pixel value
now I don't know how we add it in I
assume that it's just an 8-bit wrap not
an 8-bit saturates here we go
unsigned arithmetic modulo 256 is used
so that both the inputs and outputs fit
into bytes so it's basically like saying
if we were at 2:30 and we were supposed
to add a hundred we would wrap around
rather than saturate to 255 we'd go we'd
end up at a lower value right so we're
doing a wrapped a wrapped unsigned add
which I mean just a wrap add doesn't
matter with signed or unsigned so we're
doing a raft add there and that's pretty
straightforward so I'm glad they
specified that okay so we add either the
pixel to our left the pixel to right
above us and I should say the channel
right above us because it's it's a
specific part of the pixel it's the red
green blue or alph channel then we have
this sort of average which takes both
the previous two pixels and splits the
difference okay and then we've got a
path predictor or path predictor for
with a B and C pass into it and that is
this function right here
it says that the calculations shall be
performed without overflow which
suggests that they should be
I guess computed in 32-bit or 16-bit so
that if you add 255 to 255 you actually
get a value greater than 25 not a
wraparound value just assuming so that
seems reasonable I don't think we really
need anything more than that so let's
set ourselves up to apply this transform
so looking at what's going to happen
here we know that we need to prior
pixels and we also know that we need a
prior scanline now when we look at how
this is accessing despite what I weight
might have assumed they never use values
to the left of the top pixels like they
never look a scanline back and then over
at least if they are I'm not seeing it
it looks like they only look behind us
on this row and they only look above us
directly so the reason that I bring up
this is being odd is I would have
thought they would have they don't seem
to I also think it's a little weird
because they say for filters that refer
to the prior scanline the entire prior
scanline and bytes to the left of the
first pixel in the prior scanline shall
be treated as being zeros but when would
they ever look at a value that was to
the left of the first pixel in the prior
scanline how would you get there can you
see it because I don't I don't see it
bonus points to anyone who can see how
that ever actually happens for right now
I'm going to assume that that doesn't
actually ever happen because if it did
happen that means that I'm
misunderstanding this because the
understanding that I have about what
they're asking me to look at can never
look there so if you actually can look
there somehow I then I messed it up like
I'm not thinking about this properly
unfortunately so that's just that's just
how that is so what we want to do here
is we want to do a prior row value right
and looking at the prior row it's
telling us that it wants us to have it
be all zeros
when we look back there we're supposed
to find just pure zeros right so what I
would probably do is I will probably say
that we want to have a zero row here
that we look at and then every time
through we just set the prior row equal
to the row that we just did right you
know something like this actually
this sort of thing right so every time
through will remember where we started
this row and then at the end of that we
will swap that back in so that the next
person looks at that that row separately
right um so so we would have liked to
have done this we would I mean this is
the kind of thing we almost would like
to do in Cindy because we're going to do
the exact same thing to every channel
since the filter type is only allowed to
be a one filter type we are going to
apply the same thing to RGB and a so the
right way to do this would be to load it
into an m1 28 and just apply it there I
don't really want to do that here
because it seems like maybe I'm gets a
little bit overkill for this reference
code but that's what you would do
because you're doing literally exactly
that furthermore you're doing it for
everyone so you can't actually you could
actually do this if you're trying to
load PNG as quickly you could apply this
filter using cindy really efficiently so
I'm just gonna put a note here about
that
so I would just point out the fact that
if you did want to make this this part
of the process run quickly I think you
certainly could now what I would point
out is that may be one of those cases of
just being an optimization person for no
reason
because I would assume and I could be
very wrong about this but I would assume
that the Huffman D code is gonna be the
disaster here because it's such a bit
twiddling serialised process that really
can't be accelerated very easily no
matter what you do at least not to the
kinds of speeds you would want so this
is the part of the press that could be
trivially sped up a Sindhi not to
mention trivially multi-threaded because
every row is only dependent on the prior
row so I feel like you could do some
pretty easy stuff there where you just
broke the image up into bands that could
be done separately I suppose although I
guess the look back makes it a little
bit harder to do it that way so maybe
it's not quite as easy because of the
way the look-back works to do the multi
thread but I'm sure you could still
figure out some way to do it anyway
point being the Cindy part though it
seems really easy to do because for wide
would just be for channels at once and I
feel like that would would be good maybe
I'll just say that not to overstate the
case but since RGB and a are all handled
the same this would be a pretty easy
case to be for that however I don't
think this is probably the slow part of
the process we'll find out but I don't
think it is so in here we need to know
the row filter type so we're gonna have
to switch on this transform and because
we get it every row it changes right so
we're gonna have to handle each case
separately here for the transforms
and if we look back
we're only expected to go up to four so
in the event that we actually found a
value that wasn't one of those values
that's an error so I'm just gonna print
it out if that's the case now I was
calling these transforms they're really
filters according the spec I mean I
don't know what the difference is
between those two I wouldn't have called
this a filter this call it sounds like a
transform to me but all right so
assuming this is you know this this is
called a filter let's just name it that
so you know in the spec what we're
looking at so we get an unrecognized row
filter will complain each one of these
them is going to be its own loop where
it does something different so each of
these is going to behave a little bit
differently in this case this is just a
straight copy so this would be something
where we just copy all of the pixels to
the source and we can do this 32-bit
wide if we want to because you know we
can do this right
because we know that we're gonna copy
entire chunks of for every time and and
we're only supporting the the four wide
values at the moment now I don't know we
did bit-depth eight color type six which
I think color type six is our GBA right
yeah so we know that we're always that
format and the artist just has to react
sport it if it's not in that format so
we're just gonna say that that's the
case for now we may have to support
color type two at which point we would
have to make this be a little bit
different because it would have to
support like even filter mode zero would
have to support and like an extraction
phase right it has to go from three
components to four so it has to read
three pad to four and right so you know
just pointing out that's a little bit
different this would be a plus four but
this would be a plus three and the Alpha
Channel would get wrapped in it would
get add it in there so we can't support
that eventually if we find that we want
to and we may have to write alright so
moving along if we're in case you know
so now we're looking at something
similar to this certainly in each case
but you know we've got sort of a
different process to go here so what I'm
going to suggest is when we're actually
going through these I might suggest that
we just do per channel since each
channel gets handle the same way I'm
thinking that maybe it's it's more like
this sort of a thing and so now what we
want to do is start to change that it
starts to make this a little bit more I
think it was called little X was the
value I don't really want to do that
let's let's call that the V or something
so what we want to do here in case one
is now start to follow that table here
it is
so the reconstruction filter of our case
one is we just want to add whatever the
previous byte was the previous pixels
was so what we want to do here is say
that trying to think of exactly how to
say this
so we want to be able to read from the
previous pixel or in the other case the
previous two pixels right so there's a
couple different ways we can do that one
is we can just back fetch from them the
problem is if we want to write tightly
into the result then we have the problem
of how to handle the gaps basically like
the sort of the parts of the image that
we haven't quite gotten so I guess the
question is do we want to make it easier
on ourselves to filter and just allocate
more space and fill that space with
known information or do we want to do
something saucy er than that I don't
know
I mean I guess the other thing that we
could do here is actually still do
32-bit and just reconstruct and that
would allow us to do something like I
guess it's a pixel and see pixel so we
could save those two pretty easily so
for example when we come in here you
know we would say a pixel and see pixel
are both gonna be equal to zero then
when we come in here you know we sort of
say that after we process one pixel
right so if we were to actually do it
this way then what we could say is oh
all right
so whatever we end up with at the in the
destination the a pixel is going to be
equal to that and the C pixel is going
to be whatever the a pixel was right so
it's pretty easy for us to store those
two and write tightly into the things so
maybe we should do it that way the
reason I didn't really want to do it
that way is because if you do it like
this then the problem that you end up
with is you have to now process each
channel separately which is kind of
annoying you know kind of kind of an
annoying process in and of itself
but let's suppose we want to do that
then what I could do is just say okay
you know give us the value so this is
the sub function so it's like trying to
think of how to write this here so if I
said well you know I can do let's just
do this so if I said hey PNG filter
here's the source pointer here is the
destination pointer that I want you to
write to I could just say look here's
the pixel index right
I'm the channel index 0 1 2 &amp; 3
and it'll just pick out which one it's
going to do so I can do that and that
would work and since we know this takes
the a pixel and the C pixel we can just
give them those two and write that
function right that seems reasonable to
me it doesn't really need to read from
the desk well sort of does this to end
into the desk maybe yeah let's do this
right
so if we just wrote each of those in
here again not sure how the compiler
will what the compiler will think about
that hard to say but again each of these
then becomes pretty easy for it to
access because now it just doesn't
bracket on each of them and it would
just work that seems like it'd be pretty
I'm just going for easy to write here
not efficient so we'll leave it at that
so and I think that allows us to just
keep going and I think that's about
right for the loop so then what we would
need to do is we need the same thing
here for each of these oops know what
happened there
soory each of these we need to base the
same thing case one was the neighbor
pixel two is the upward pixel so that
one doesn't need to track these two so
all it's doing is it's just using
basically a top trimming pointer and
that's gonna be the Prevot or prior row
and so when those go through that's
again that's gonna do a plus equals four
here so that prior row is the thing
that's going to be placed in here so you
can see okay we've got filter two and
that gets the input that it needs
because it's only using a I'm sorry only
using B as it goes there so then we have
the average that takes both so okay so
that's the average of the top pixel and
the left pixel right
oh it's ok so I was reading this study
wrong never mind
so this makes a little more sense that
you use the pixel to to to the left
because it's doing a predictor based on
the gradient of those two that makes
more sense so never mind I take it back
that's not just for differing that's a
reasonable predictor that's basically
saying hey look I'll look at the two
previous pixels let me see what their
difference is we're gonna use some
predictor to figure out based on that
what we think this one will be and we
also look at the top one you know so ok
never mind never mind take it back so
that that is a reasonable predictor it's
probably not great but it's reasonable
so okay so case one case two are handled
case three is not using C so that's just
this one here C pixel goes away eight
pixel remains so in here we've got prior
row so that's good and then finally we
have the path predictor case and that
one actually needs everything so that
one needs prior row and in both these
cases prior row has to be advanced as
well and we need to track 2mp pixels so
yeah oops that's not right I guess I
should just call that B pixel
there we go so yeah what we want to do
here is make sure that's all kosher can
I get this out from behind my head that
would be helpful so what we want to do
in this case is we need to pass all of
them to the you know this for one here
and then we have to actually write these
so I guess these are going to return a
u8 that's the result of the filter
they're going to take an X and a a b a c
and a channel and yeah some of them have
some of these some of them don't
so 1 2 3 4 there I believe what we said
was that this one has only an A this one
has only a B this one has an A and a B
and this one has all three okay so if we
look at what's happening here
if we take
if we take case one it looks like we're
just adding them together now I don't
know again
I don't want it to do integral promotion
here I really want it to do
8-bit addition short of using Symbian
but before we can actually manhandle
that a little bit more I'm not sure how
to convince it otherwise so I'm hoping
that will help here's the reconstruction
4b same deal really these two are the
same so we could just call it P&amp;G filter
one and call it in both cases because
it's just you're just passing a
different thing you could just say right
because there's no there's no difference
between those two things
yeah
right so you've got a pixel here I don't
know why I define those up here there's
no point to that at all so let's not do
that okay so we got one this will be
calling one and two because they're both
the same this will be calling one and
two as well so we have a pixel in one
case B pixel in another and we remember
our destination version here as we go
that's all fine this is the first one
that actually is different so these two
have their own calls and they're on well
they're on everything really yeah so
current locals dest and rio equals
current row so that's all what we want
and that all looks pretty good okay so
getting back to here
PNG filter 3 that's pretty basic as well
it's just taking the average right so
you want to add a and B together divide
by 2 and take the floor of that now I'm
assuming that the that wants to be done
non wrapped don't know if that makes it
I well it definitely makes a difference
right
so the reason that I'm a little
concerned about this is because if the
averaging function if this line were to
be taken taken literally then a plus B
divided by 2 would only actually produce
the average of the bytes for values less
than 128 right because for two values
greater than 128 or where their sum is
greater than 25 I should say it will
wrap and then the divide will produce a
much lower value than it should have
so it seems to me like you would want to
do the result in that just doesn't make
sense
I can't imagine you actually wanted to
do wrapped 256 there ah here we go
the sum a rigged a plus or maybe shall
be performed without overflow using at
least nine bit arithmetic that's ah I'm
like that can't be true I like how you
literally said that and then immediately
contradicted it it's like okay yeah so
so what that means is this actually is X
well
so it's X plus the average yeah so this
is actually X channel as a UA plus the
u8 version of the non u8 right average
of these two so that we do want to be
done at the higher bit precision so we
do the average at the higher bit
precision then I want to divide by 2 so
that will floor because integer division
will floor automatically so we don't
have to do anything careful to make the
floor happen I don't believe so then we
can go from there let's just make sure
this let me do this I want to make this
a little bit clearer so there's our
average that we've computed yeah and now
I'm going to go ahead and cast that
average to a u8 for adding and then off
we go
okay so now we get down to this path
predictor PF predictor I don't know what
you want to call that we sort of have a
lengthy set of stuff that wants us to do
here so we need to be able to take the
absolute value of these differences here
so yeah I don't know how we want to do
that cleanly in this case I might just
actually use and if just to make sure
we're doing it 100% correctly here but
anyway here's what we want to actually
have from the spec why am I not able to
poop I guess that's not something I can
pace
alright so P equals a plus B minus C so
all right the algorithm uses this
experience the adaptational took you to
Allen path the path which put a
difference to go below the last election
location ABC okay so again taking them
at their word we need this to be wrapped
Oh nope without a so they're like hey
unsigned errific modular true this is
used parentheses only here in here so
half of the things don't obey that but
off we go so I guess the there well I
guess it's this part right here so this
subtraction or rather this addition is
the only part they should have just been
this plus right is the part all the rest
of this stuff is always not that so
happy birthday anyway okay so what we
want to do here is we want to actually
do at the end one of these again so we
want like our path result here to be
something and then we're going to do
that add again in a in a raptor
arithmetic fashion but up until that
point we're going to be in la-la-land
so we're going to
go ahead and use utha choose for that so
the first thing we're going to do is
compute this p-value here that they're
asking for and that's the that's
basically like the basis color or the
basis channel level that we're going to
then difference to see what all the
differences are between the various
pixels and that basis value all right so
we've got PA PB and PC so here what our
problem is I mean what we could do is do
this signed right and we could say okay
we're gonna do this up conversion here
put it into s 32 s let's subtract each
of these and what I can do is just say
if PA is less than zero equals negative
PA so if we now we'll just do it
manually we could try to think of doing
something clever later on but I'm not
gonna bother right now so what we're
gonna do there is just we'll do the
subtraction we'll test to make sure
we're not negative for you're negative
we'll fix it right so now we know that
each of those is absolute values so then
we get two down here so we have a PR PR
looks like the that looks like the
payoff value so that that's what we want
to actually compute so basically we're
saying here is okay if PA is less than
equal to PB and PA is less than or equal
to PC then we set our path value here
- eh whatever
a was coming in so I said I should
actually get those values - all right so
read out each of those values I produce
my little dance here I check all of the
differences off the basis to get those
done then we go ahead and do this like
this little dance here so it's P be less
than or equal to P see there we go so we
grab all those values out then when
we're done with them we're basically so
we're based going to pick one of these
predict one of these things to use
either the top value the left value or
the to the value two to our left we're
gonna pick one of those to start with we
return that and then we're gonna encode
the difference off of that it's
basically what's doing right so yeah
that's really all that is P be listening
to PC otherwise we just use C okay and
you know if we want to encode this
exactly like it was written it'd be this
so I think that's all of the filters in
this case we have not actually created
that zero thing yes we are hiding a
previous value I don't know that I care
about that but here let's do this
so here's our reconstruction function
for the PNG filters I'll just copy this
whole thing out and put it up there that
way we don't have any variable shadowing
and stuff for common names like best or
whatever else we can remove that outer
layer of bracketing as well so and then
this thing can just send us the various
things we need so we need to know what
the decompressed pixel thing is we need
to know what the final pixel part is and
then we just need the 0 row we can talk
about that in a second
that's sort of a separate issue and
there's a couple things we could do
there
there's a couple of different ways we
could create that and in fact you know I
probably will do it that way so so I'm
gonna say that we just do those two
we'll talk about that in a second but
what I'm going to do now is when we come
down here after we're done with
everything where we were doing that
before so in here when we reach the
final block and you know after
everything's be been decompressed then
I'm going to do is I'm just going to
call that filter reconstruction function
and have it reconstruct so let's see
what else we need okay right we need the
width and the height
that's pointer service that's all right
so now the question is well what are we
gonna do about this here's what I'm
suggesting and I realize this is a
little janky but again just for ease of
implementation at first so let's just
make zero real point at a single zero
and then what we could do is have there
be prior row advance set to zero so
everywhere that we were doing a B pixel
here we'll just make that the prior
advance all right so what we'll do is
once we actually get a valid row to
start reading we'll set it to 4 up until
then we'll just leave it at 0 so it'll
just keep reading out of the same zero
right here and that'll be that
seems pretty straightforward right
so I think that's a reasonable sketch of
something that handles all of the
transforms don't quote me on that but I
think it's roughly right so you know
when we get down here we should be able
to now take a look at what that's doing
so let's just see if we're even in the
ballpark I'm gonna go ahead and take a
look at the final pixels see what that
value actually is can I get a kind of
watch window here let's let's do this
let's get memory down here there we go
so what I want to do is I want to grab
okay this is all care about so I'm gonna
grab final pixels and put it down here
this is what we're actually running into
we now are 32 columns that's our entire
image so I just want to see what we end
up with here right
and so that transforms working pretty
good so far this is now exactly what I
expect to see which is good so there you
go that's it that's exactly the row that
we thought we should get let's see what
happens now okay now we're into case two
again that is what I expected to see
so that's totally right what we can see
here as well is if we assume that we're
looking at this it looks like it's
top-down right this was the first thing
we saw so it's not bottom-up it's top
down for the PNG red is encoded as the
top or bottom looks like it's encoded
this way so it looks like it's our comes
first then GB and a RGB a looks like
what they've encoded right so the weight
no I lied it's alpha channel first right
no no this is gamma this is by twice my
brain wants to always look at these
things reversed because I'm so used to
looking at them in but so this is byte
wise RGB a RGB a yes RGB a RGB a RGB a
so it starts with our ends with a that's
all we needed to know and off we go
so do we ever hit this path predictor
case or this averaging case I don't know
let's find out No
so so we don't know those could be
totally wrong right now it looks like
our basic predictors we're fine because
we look at this image this looks this
looks right so yeah I think we've got
all of those working ok but but these
you know these could just be wrong so we
should try and get those tested somehow
as well but at least we got the basics
in here so let's see
so maybe what I'll do is I'll force a
crash the first time it goes in there
that way like when we find one will know
and we can just you know verify that
it's working at all because they might
just be buggy we don't know okay so hey
guess what we correctly encode decoded a
PNG image that's the good news the bad
news is it's only the very simple kind
so we still have a lot of work to do
because now we've got to get to go get
the Huffman stuff working but at least
now we know the filter part and we've
got code for the filter part that code
looks like it'll be pretty easy to debug
I suspect now I say I suspect because
well there was a bunch of stuff about do
you want wrapping or not and you know
maybe we got something wrong where we
didn't quite do the wrapping correctly
so it's still not a hundred percent sure
that we are doing it correctly there
could be bugs in there we don't really
know let's go ahead and now try the
compressed version of this image I'll
leave that up actually gives me to refer
to it and try to get that working and
that'll be probably we won't have that
working by the end of the stream because
we have that working we would be
basically done and I suspect it's gonna
be at least one more episode before that
okay so let's start down that path and
let's see where we're getting I don't
really remember exactly where we're at
here in terms of what we have for the
Huffman stuff so I don't remember really
how close we were to decoding anything
let's see if we get yeah so we we
managed to get this to code it properly
as I suspected that part there we don't
really know if it's generating this part
here we have no idea where
doing either but let's start to look at
destination pixels and see what we
actually are you know putting out oops
meant decompress fix can you just type
does that work no it doesn't so it won't
remember what we put in there
unfortunately
always converts it to an address first
visual studio being super helpful as
always by like not doing what I want
okay wait now I got it oh there we go
okay so I gotta click that button I
guess I don't know anyway so let's see
what we've got here there's an o1 that
is what we expected to see
still outputting stuff here so this is
the simple case and the simple case you
know unsurprisingly appears to be
working here so that encoded a big old
run of zeros which is also probably
correct how many of these we got let's
just slide this over so we can see where
the end is
that looks writing ly correct so we did
Huffman to code one row properly I think
that looks like the right answer I'm not
sure about that
no that's correct so if you think about
what's gonna happen there it's using the
leftward predictor it's gonna load this
into the color channel it's gonna add
one to the red channel which is gonna
cause it to overflow from two to five to
zero which is the correct red channel
and then it's just going to be wrapped
the entire way alpha channel F F F F F F
F F F F F F so so this is the right row
like we got the right row so now it
looks wrong
Oh oh no it doesn't no it doesn't it
doesn't you may be okay here we're all
right I'm like it's one off but no we
had changed this 232 before because we
were looking at just the decompressed
image okay so now let's see how we do
here
what's our Len value here 24 that seems
reasonable too
off we go that'll looks good yep that's
right so you know I'll be honest this
looks really good so yeah I mean so far
we seem to be in pretty good shape for
these rows here
so you know that I mean that seems to
have decoded the image properly to be
honest let's take a look at what happens
when we when we reconstruct it just to
see you know what we end up with here so
if we feed that image into here and can
we get another memory window
you can have exactly four memory windows
ladies and gentlemen because everyone
knows there's not more than four places
in memory that anyone might want to see
all right so let's go ahead and get
final pixels in here okay got to put
that little thing in their final pixel
okay so let's see what final pixels has
to say about this this one should be
thirty-two wide I mean that looks right
that looks like the image so okay so now
we have decompressed both we have
decompressed a Huffman stream and a non
Huffman stream paying both correctly so
that suggests to me that our error
because if I remember correctly
decompressing the other image though we
failed that suggests to me that we have
a subtle bug not a you know not not like
a really egregious bug but like one that
you know only happens when the numbers
are right or in this case or whatever
right so that's that's good that's
reassuring
where is the thing you're okay so
there's a couple of things to be happen
here first of all one thing I would note
is that this is in a PNG that has an ID
at chunk that contains the entire thing
and so one thing that is different about
the other image that we're having
trouble is it has multiple Ida chunks so
one thing we could look for is do we
have a problem
striding IDOT chunks so did the thing
when we under flow and I that chunk did
I screw that up you know is that
possibly where the bugs coming from so
one thing I do want to do is let's now
we got this image under control I want
to just like
dribble some stuff in here and make a
more complicated image and so and save
that office sort of another test
okay so
so I'm gonna save this out and you'll
notice I kept these pretty hard these
first ones just cuz I wanted some way of
still correlating some semblance of like
where the start should what the starch
should look like so I'm going to go
ahead and export that
I'm going to compress it at zero and
then I'm going to do the same thing we
did before compress it as normal at nine
and then I'm going to try loading those
just to see what happens and if we get a
little bit more of those like weird
results there okay so I mean one good
thing is that we we one positive aspect
there right is we've got the other
filter types here so that that pay F
filter is getting used so we can start
to debug that one now the other thing I
would say is
I don't know why this thing so this
doesn't this didn't actually do what we
asked it to do which was to always do
final pixels
so it looks like it starts off with some
rows that aren't that way okay
yeah it starts officers aren't that way
and then it hits right here there's the
four right so we've got one forward in
the middle of a lot of other stuff no I
just sorry I accidentally hit the mouse
wheel all right so I think that should
be good so let's go ahead and let's go
ahead and get this started them so that
seemed to decompress properly as well
I'm not sure what's up with that but
yeah accurately it was actually
decompressing but didn't error all right
so now let's take that assertion out and
actually step through that and see
whether we're getting what we think
we're getting here
okay so jumping in here's our a pixel
and C pixel they get initialized this
year our B pixels the prior of prior
right now is also 0
so we go through doing our 0 1 2 3 4 a B
and C pixels we then remember what the a
pixel was for next time C pixel we
remember what the desk we outputted was
for next times a pixel we should advance
by oh well no it won't be 0 because this
this actually is the prior row here so
the prior row just happened to be 0
there I guess that's actually true if
this was the prior row it actually had a
red channel 0 so that's okay
alright and we advance both of those and
we come back through so that does look
correct whether this is correct I don't
know we read a B and C here so that's
reading full red oh sorry no that's just
each of these okay never - that's
channel 0 that's reading the red channel
of a B and C so that's getting the pixel
to our left was full read the pixel
above us was not full read but that's
not true
was it don't I get
is that you okay it's so that is true
it's wrong pixel one right so that is
true picture before us was full red fair
enough
so we do P is three to five a is three
to five piece so it's that right a b c
get is so that's all correct assuming
that looks reasonable so what was the x
of that channel was one so this reduces
zero it does okay I mean that looks
reasonable to me we should go check what
the actual image values are to see but
like we're producing the correct value
for the Alpha Channel which seems pretty
unlikely if we were super wrong so we're
probably only subtle if we're wrong on
the pass filter we're not like way off
we're we're only a little off all right
so let's finish that up
yeah yep yep so I mean you know that
looks pretty good let's try this part
still work - yeah by no means don't
don't remember that setting okay so
let's see we got all that so yeah yes
this is looking pretty good so I guess
we're kind of now down to a question of
like what's going wrong with the more
complex ones and I don't know so let's
go ahead and start I guess we got to
start looking at the more complex case
and we're gonna have to we could try to
make a like a we could try to break that
case down into which parts are causing
us the problem - like we could try to
isolate parts of that image and actually
go like okay here's the thing that
appears to be causing us the problem you
know so that you know we can kind of see
how that goes but like we crash
somewhere right yeah so we like
overwrite where we're supposed to be or
something happens we see where we're at
I just I just remember this is where we
were at last time so yeah I don't know
if the source is bad the death is
definitely bad so we we definitely just
advanced too far with the length value
so we know that something's busted here
what I would like to know is I'm curious
about that I that chunk situation I want
to know whether or not the I that chunk
state is part of the problem here so I'm
gonna go ahead and say let's set a break
on when we under flow to see whether
that
screwing it up it's unlikely I think we
probably just have a bug in our Huffman
decoder but I just want to check the
obvious stuff before we go diving into
that because might as well check the
obvious before the hardest death so here
when we do a consume size we look to see
whether we have any more stuff to output
first of all we didn't hit the underflow
did we No
all right so first things first my hunch
is at least correct to one degree which
is that this is the bug that we know
about like the the tell-tale the crash
right the obvious symptom that there's a
problem that is coming after the IDA
chunk changes over so it's not obviously
the case that my sort of thing I wanted
to check is safe it could be that we
actually have that problem so let's take
a look at what that implies so that this
here's the file thing we're reading from
we have drained out our contents
entirely here so we have another one
that's 8192
chunk and it's got a pointer here to the
contents and then that's got an X
pointer to one thing I don't know
so is file first I mean I'm assuming
that this hasn't already been consumed
but I don't really know if that's true I
guess what I'm asking is are we
accidentally reading the same chunk
twice so how does that work right now
all right so every time oh so maybe this
is the first one though yeah yeah yeah
so oh so maybe we haven't changed either
chunks yet maybe I'm just wrong okay
yeah yeah I'm just being stupid this is
just the first one so it pulls the first
one and this now we expect this one 2074
that one should move up to be first
right so that one goes ahead it gets the
content size out it should get this
contents pointer out and it does and now
it should move this up to be this one
540 right yeah and it does okay
so nevermind everything I just said it
was incorrect let's run again and see
what happens okay so no no no we have
proven that it's not that we do not
change
IDOT chunks before we hit the bug so my
previous suggestion that it was unlikely
that that was the problem
proved to be true and we know there's a
bug somewhere in the Huffman decoding
that you just don't have happen when you
don't have a big enough image right or a
certain sensitive values or whatever
right now this makes sense because like
if you think about how this thing was
set up if you remember all the stuff
that we've been through so far to talk
about like things like the extra bits
and a lot of stuff if you have a very
small image then the LZ runs that you're
encoding where you're doing you know
you're the backwards look up stuff and
all that those pieces are not going to
be very large right when your entire
image is only what 260 bytes long its
entire encoding decompressed there's not
going to be a lot of
for you to do runs of 10,000 things
right so all of those fiddly little is
the table set up correctly to decode the
number of extra bits and this that meant
right
all of those things are not really in
play as much with a small image so lots
of little bugs that we may have had when
dealing with some of the TWiki er parts
of decoding those run lengths and things
like that those just wouldn't have come
into place so it makes a lot of sense
that we're seeing a bug on a big image
that we don't see on a small image and
so you know this this is hardly
surprising that said unfortunately it's
hard to know where to look one thing I
will say is it does look like we don't
need to reverse those extra bits so that
was good because that was gonna be
really annoying anyway so looking at
where we're at here one one thing that
might be good so we don't know if maybe
we've got an error in our tables here we
could probably spot check our tables
just one more time to make sure that
there aren't errors and the tables could
be samaras in these tables so that's
something we should probably look at
I'll definitely take a look the other
thing that I want to see is it would be
nice to do a coverage check so when we
have the the simple images if we know
that we're decoding a simple image
correctly but we're not in encoding
complicated image correctly what I might
ask is are there entire code paths that
aren't being hit on the simple image
that are being hit on the complex image
so before I end I'll end for the day on
that note before I end though I'm just
going to go ahead and put in a search
here Oh even like every path
uh and we know we're hitting this one
and we know we're hitting this and we
watch them both happen but what I've
done is I've put ones in each of these
so now I can just run it on the one that
works and just see like I know that
works and I can actually do it on this
one which is probably them
well actually this one has more runs in
it so let's use this one where it should
add more in soon anyway okay so we know
we hit encoded Len less than or equal to
15 we hit encoded Len equals 18 now
remember this doesn't mean these Co
paths are right it just means that they
have been run we've hit 17 we've hit
okay so wonder same thing here is write
this code never got used in the good in
the ones that actually work so this one
has not been used it's worth noting
right and it you'll note it's a
relatively complex case right it's a rep
foul like looking at a previous one so
like you know probably want to look at
that more closely and just see what's
going on you know are we actually
reading the right number of bits or
doing the rep count there you know who
knows we probably are at least reading
the rep count right the rep vowel maybe
not though right but probably because
yeah I mean we're looking backwards one
on it so yeah anyway but sorry where
were we we were on this case so the LEM
tab bits used here this case with where
we read the extra bits and add in that
case was getting used so this
this one right here this case was
getting used as well all right so if we
look they're just purely like whether or
not a case was used at all we still
don't have any idea what weather our
weather our averaging case works but
that's neither here or there because
nobody apparently uses that one yet this
case encoded Lin equals 16 we did not
call on the good version of this thing
now let's take a just a real quick look
I'm gonna go ahead and put complex in
here and see if that one calls it so it
doesn't I'm gonna go ahead and see if
this one calls it it does so you know
still not really that indicative that
there's probably a problem in it but
it's worth noting it's just worth noting
that we do have one code path that is
only called on the case that fails and
not called on the case that works
probably not really all that much to
read into it but it's just worth noting
so let's take a closer look at encoded
line equals 16 just to see whether
there's something there that's you know
kind of obviously busted so where is
that again that's in not in here or here
it is copy the previous code length 3 to
6 times the next two bits indicate the
repeat length 0 equals 3 3 equals 6 so
we're going to consume 2 bits
our rep count is three plus that that
does seem right
codes 8 comma 16 plus 2 bits 1 1 plus 2
bits I don't know what that's trying to
say I don't understand the example
LIC was saying so it's saying if the
first code was eight which is actually a
code like debate then the next code was
sixteen plus the bit 1-1 the bit pattern
1 1 then another 16 of bits 1 0 that
will expand to 12 code lengths of 8 so
the first 16 is saying repeat 8 3 plus 3
times or 6 times
the next one is saying repeat it 3 plus
2 which is 5 so it's 1 for the first one
which already would have been handled of
previous case 6 reps and then 5 reps I
mean it looks like that's what we're
doing
so I don't think we've done anything
wrong here so even though that case and
I I mean I can certainly take a closer
look at it and just make sure that it's
functioning properly but it seems likely
that it is so we're on value 282 so
we're down here at this so what we're
gonna do here is we're gonna say we want
to repeat three sevens right one two
three
seems reasonable so that seems like I
don't think that's wrong that seems
right so I would say we just still have
a bug in the decompressor here somewhere
I'm not gonna look for it any further
today I think we have a complete PNG
decompressor right now for the cases we
care about except for this so we have
one more thing to implement which is to
put in the built-in Huffman tables
hopefully that's not too hard to find
from the spec but the only thing I think
we need to do is figure out what we're
doing wrong in here like where we've got
something a little bit wrong because we
are decompressing now Huffman and non
Huffman pings as long as they're simple
so we've just got something wrong when
we try to go to something more
complicated I'm gonna go ahead and go to
the QA but that's pretty good
we're pretty far along here hopefully
this means it won't take us too much
longer before we're done
ratchet freak said the Len and Lana so
the decompressor can resync with a
compressor if a block uh corrupted the
compressor admitted an empty block by
looking for the byte 0 0 0 0 ffff mostly
handy for byte streams but how often
does the compressor output that block
and why wouldn't you just have a magic
value or something that you're a block
or something I mean if that really makes
sense or why not just make the i dot
blocks restart themselves just seems
like a bad way to do it rook tag says c
is up and left
is that true did I read it wrong
the bike corresponding to be oh you're
right okay well that is really nice if
that's the case because if that's the
case then it explains this part right
which was the part that was really kind
of annoying to me because yeah I could
not figure out I could not figure out
why they were saying that okay so it is
what I when I was like oh that's weird
that they would do the two over they
weren't and I was like they should have
done up into the left it looks like they
did do up into the left let's see here
so that means see pixel doesn't really
ever have to be there per se well I mean
I guess we can do it it's just the
previous see pixel is just the previous
be pixel so instead of see pixel equals
a pixel it's it's really just this right
so the up and to the left pixel is just
whatever pixel we read as B this time
around
before we advance B
he can Gail did I see four semi constant
on your code what's that for and how
does it work so you probably did see it
in the code I don't necessarily know
where it is okay yeah here it is
um so for reasons that I couldn't really
tell you I'm guessing that there because
the compiler was crappy Visual Studio
used to give you an error on that they
used to say that you had a while loop
that always evaluated to one like
conditional that always evaluated to one
and it would give you a warning which of
course if you have warning treated as
errors means it won't compile your code
the fix for that was just to use a for
loop with nothing in it because if you
put nothing in a for loop then it just
is an infinite loop and so this is the
way that I now habitually do it instead
of doing wild one to avoid those
previous warnings I don't know if they
still happen but they were quite some
time like Visual Studio 2005 through
2013 or 12 at least I think so anyway if
you want to have a loop where you just
want it to loop forever until you issue
the break statement that's just how that
works in the memory window when you were
writing the decoded pixel you were
writing to some memory that you have not
allocated according to the ASCII
representation there were some strings
about a path in Windows I don't think
you're right about that I mean what you
have to remember is when you allocate
memory you get memory that's been used
for something else potentially right
when you allocate memory with virtual a
lock the page that comes back will be
filled with zeros I think by requirement
I think virtual Alec has to fill a page
with zeros for it give it to you
I think that's required but everyone
upstream of the actual virtual Alec all
can just recycle memory so when you call
malloc you're not gonna get a cleared
page you're gonna get a page that
somebody used and freed before you does
that make sense so I don't think we were
writing to memory that we didn't
allocate in day 55 we create the hash
table you added your to-do on getting a
better hash that was a joke right cuz he
I didn't think we'd ever really need a
better hash I was just saying that
everyone always puts in use a better
hash function and then it ships like
that right so that was kind of a joke
but what you would see if the hash is
not good enough is that you end up
linearly probing most of the time which
just degenerates to a linear search like
you can answer this question yourself
sort of so a hash table which we usually
use hash tables with exterior chaining
right so what we do is we have hash
tables and the entries in the hash table
point to expect to be a linked list of
everything that hashed to that value so
let's suppose that your hash was awful
and always returned the value five or
something like that right well if it
always returned the value 5 then
everything that you put in will go into
hash bucket five that means that
everything that went into the hash table
would just create one giant linked list
and every query into the hash table
therefore is just a linear search of a
linear linked list which obviously
defeats the purpose of having a hash
table so the thing that is a problem if
you have a bad hash function if you
start feeding a lot of things to hash
function that all hash to the same
location you end up not getting the
speed of a hash table you get the speed
of a linear search so the worse the hash
the closer it is to linear search right
the better the hash the closer it is to
oh one instantaneous right
there's a visual city a plugin with that
lets you see images in memory it's
called image watch it was pretty useful
why did the PNG decoding yeah so that I
agree that probably useful I don't super
love plugins to visual studio we've had
a lot of issues with like trying to do
stuff with just the one insight one or
whatever and it just I don't really want
to go down that road that should be
built individual studio it's kind of
flame that's not but John to Resta okay
it's that looks trained usually it's so
with oh XD d or Oh X CD if I remember
correctly or maybe just stack memory so
when you allocate memory you absolutely
will never be filled with oh XD d or Oh
X CD or anything like that
unless you are using a debug allocator
that explicitly does that fill so
basically allocating memory is supposed
to be as fast as possible so a memory
allocator will never fill it with values
if you get back memory that's filled
with values that value should be 0 if it
came from virtual Alec or it should be
garbage but never a constant value if it
gets filled with a constant value that
means as a debug allocator and you'd
better have known you were using a debug
allocator because if you weren't
expecting used to debug out here or
something something's up right
this same should be true for stack
memory because again stack memory should
be filled with zeros or garbage but not
a constant value unless there's a debug
unless debugging is on now I don't know
if they've changed something recently
where like stack memory memory gets like
flooded with something to avoid like
stack attacks like stack overflow
attacks or something like this but I you
know I hope they didn't do that so guess
what I'd say
all right I think we were I don't think
we I don't think I see any other on
topic questions here try a big image
which compresses very well
yeah well the image wheat that is what
that is we did provide a big image which
compresses very well probably what we'd
be more likely to decompress okay even
including whatever bug we have is it as
a big image that doesn't compress very
well because that would be filled with
lots of tiny runs and literals and that
would probably work fine right so yeah
so you know I suspect that you know if I
had to guess if we look at what's
happening in the test image there's just
a giant run of white here and a giant
runs of all zeros here and my suspicion
is that we're not interpreting some of
those larger run Huffman's correctly or
something like this you know if that
makes sense
so if we actually had an image that was
filled with data like that like a photo
like a photographic image where it was
very mixed in terms of the pics of Iser
runs or anything I suspect that one
might actually work right like because
again that's not stressing the the LZ
it's like a fairly uncompressed image
and so I think we'd have more luck with
that quick shift on Linux would you use
sialic instead of rich luck or is there
an alternative yeah that I think you'd
use mem map so mmm ap is probably what
the low-level allocator is yeah so it's
this is probably what you'd be calling
instead of so instead of virtue like
virtual free it be mem map mem on map
not not see Alex II Alex I or whatever
is gonna go if that's gonna go through
some interview
nonsense sergeant REM be will you
integrate the Dakota directly into the
game or into the sim professor directly
into the game it won't be used at
runtime well it won't be used in the
shipping version but in development it
will be used inside the game to hot load
next quick exports from Photoshop that's
why we're doing it
oops
close everything down here
all right thank you for joining me for
that said handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with
series at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade hero org and it
comes with the source code so you can
play around that if you want to try your
hand at debugging the PNG stuff now be a
good time to do it it's mostly working
but we know we have a few problems in
there trying it's a pretty tough little
debugging problem right it's involves
like a fairly complex and put output
stream and in a spec to look at to see
what you're supposed to be doing and so
on so I would say if you want a little
bit of a challenge spend a few hours
tonight see if you can find the bug or
any you know they're probably my more
than one bug see if you can find them
before tomorrow stream before we start
looking for them together it's be a
pretty good exercise alright that's it
for today I'll be back here tomorrow to
finish up that debugging process
hopefully we'll be finished by tomorrow
because we actually have all the filters
in place to so maybe if we're lucky
we'll either be finished or mostly
finished by the end of tomorrow who
knows it's hard to say with debugging
you never know how long it's gonna take
to find a bug two hours may not be
enough we'll see until then have fun
pouring everyone and I'll see you on the
Internet take it easy