hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could complete game live
on stream so a couple things we want to
do today we'll see what we have time to
get to but if you remember where we left
off last weekend we had done I think we
can give ourselves a little pat on the
back for doing a bunch of good debugging
on the lighting system and I think we're
now ready to start pushing it forwards a
little bit and and starting to do some
more interesting stuff our goal is to
just get delighting to a point where
we're happy enough with the performance
and happy enough with the look to move
on and one of the things if i zoom out
right now you can see is I'm like I'm
really happy with how this is converging
there's a couple things about it that I
think we need to improve in terms of the
backend side of things certainly the
sampling we want to blur across the
voxels a little bit better so we have
less query interpolation on the lighting
I think that's a performance concern
meaning we'll have to do some work to
make sure that doesn't hang the
performance but it's not really to worry
some like it's not like I'm like huh
what would that look like right so we I
think that'll be pretty easy for us to
deal with and then the other thing is in
terms of reducing the sampling noise may
be getting some less flicker in there
those are really the two quality issues
there's not a lot more or honestly on
the quality side of things it's it's
looking surprisingly good for completely
dynamic lighting no pre-computation
whatsoever here and that's pretty
unusual actually so I'm pretty happy
with how that's turning out and so I
think we want to do those certainly but
what I'd like to do first is refocus on
performance a little bit now that we've
gotten the bugs worked out I want to
flip back over to our standalone
performance tool and really turn the
screw a little bit on the cube tracer
because now that I'm pretty confident
that it's what I want there's a couple
things I want to do to try to get its
performance
significantly higher and that'll let us
do two things one it alert it led us
target 60 frames a second on high-end
machines even with lighting in software
completely no GPU assist and the other
thing that I think it will do for us is
if we would like to we can also do
another thing which is targeting 30
frames a second which much with much
higher quality lighting because we could
double the number of rays per frame if
we wanted to right so we have a lot of
options there but regardless of what we
choose to do with it
there's never you never don't just want
faster performance from the Ray caster
right so what I'd like to do here is
just start taking a look at that so
let's take a look at the stuff we have
set up for that and what I'm going to be
using mostly for this is our HH Lite
prof that we've made and so what I
really want to do today is now that
we've done a bunch of work on the
lighting system to kind of extract out
the eye you know we can switch between
the a a B and the regular I'd like to do
a fresh capture of a particular lighting
environment into HH light prof and then
I'd like to run the profiler on it and
that'll require a little bit of work
because we changed how we're storing
things so we just need to change how
we're dumping them as well so if you
take a look at the update lighting call
what I want to do see here so what I
want to do is if you take a look at the
update lighting column you can kind of
see how we come through here and we do a
bunch of work to like you know do the
build diffuse lighting maps and all this
sort of stuff and and all that lining up
the voxels we do all this stuff and then
we call internal lighting core an
internal ending core is the thing that
does all of the work and so what I'd
like to do here is I'd like to take
internal lighting core and I'd like to
make that be runnable again outside in
HH light profs so here's internal
lighting core here
and what you can see is we pass all the
same stuff to it here right you can see
here we've got basically the same thing
but we don't have the occluder and
occluder account thing like if we
started building HL I / if we get errors
there and furthermore I we would need to
load different stuff so if you look here
we load these pieces of information
those pieces of information are not
sufficient what we actually need to load
now I if you look at all of these here
we we do want basically all this stuff
the only difference is the result light
boxes and result box refs those are gone
because we don't have such a thing as
those results and then in here with the
source lighting dump and the source
light boxes dump I think all we need at
that point is just the occluders right
so I think the occluders are all we
would need there now we can also choose
to dump the the other table information
but I'm not sure that there's any real
reason to so if we look at the other
pieces of information that are stored in
tabular form inside the lighting system
because here's the lighting system here
what you can see is that there's a walk
table there's a wait map and they're
sampling spheres the weight map will be
stored automatically because the weight
map is just if we write this out the
things that won't get stored are like
these pointers right and if we look down
here you can see that we've got you know
just a few other pointers here but they
are going to get built as part of it
right and you can see here I'm even
saying that they're allocating the
temporariness so we don't have to
preserve these because they will get
rebuilt by the internal lighting Corp we
don't have to use the debug lines
because we're not going to be storing
the debug lines anyway and so if you
take a look up here at what we're doing
really all we have to do is
is rebuild the light sampling walk table
and the sampling spheres and as far as I
know there's no reason why we can't just
do that right okay so I think we should
be able to just proceed directly and
what I want to do here is I want to go
to the internal lighting core code and
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
write before here where we do the debug
dump I'm going to delete the part where
we were doing the result dumps because
we don't care about that these results
we do want because this is what we're
going to compare against and these we do
want but we want to modify it slightly
so in here where we do the lighting dump
that should just work because it's still
the same thing it's just a different
struct now and then in here what we want
to do is have a new thing called like
source occluders or something right and
all that's going to do is in here you
can see we have an input box count and
an input boxes so I'm just gonna say
like look input box counts and I could
just call this boxes because why not an
input box count which is going to be the
size of whatever this input box this
thing is and then it's going to be a
pointer to the input boxes right
so that'll dump this this series of
dumps will dump everything I think that
we need and then what I'm gonna do is
I'm just gonna pop over to HH light prof
and I'm gonna say okay now if this is
called and I guess we can leave it the
same name even light boxes so now if we
just continue loading this up right I
don't really know what this is for I'll
have to see
I guess it's because we don't know ahead
of time yeah what is that about oh I see
so this was just telling it to give it
some extra space because we might need
to use we might push off of the end of
that array I don't know if that still
happens in fact I'm pretty sure it
doesn't so I think we can just get rid
of that I'm gonna go ahead and pull that
out and just we'll leave it in here
because there's no reason not to leave
that feature in if you know it's not
hurting us to have it in there it's just
an addition that happens here but
otherwise I'm gonna get rid of it
and so if we look at recompiling the
lighting code here you can see that that
compiles cleanly and what we were not
compiling HH light prof right now so I
gotta jump back in there and and add
that so if I go back to HH light Bravo I
guess I was already in it sorry what I
want to do is take that build and you
can see here that like I've rammed out
some things and so one of the things I
rammed out here was HH light prof so I'm
gonna go ahead and rebuild it and what
you can see here is there's a bunch of
of compile errors those are the
differences in the old way we had the
lighting setup and the new way we had
the lighting setup so we just have to go
through and basically excise the the
parts we made things a lot simpler and
better we cleaned up the lighting code
quite a bit because you know was kind of
old and crusty and now we've got it sort
of minimized it's still a little
craftier than I would like and that's
because we're still able to run both
systems in place we can run any be
caster and we can run the grid caster
I'm pretty sure I want to stick with the
grid caster but until I actually do some
performance analysis and improvements
here I'm not quite ready to say yet so
we're still a little craftier than we
will be in the end but we're a lot
cleaner now so a lot of this stuff we
were doing when we were just sort of
hacking on it to try and explore we can
now get rid of so we don't have to do
any more of those transforms
and we don't have to worry about a lot
of these like solution box count any of
this stuff none of this stuff matters
here I think we can just go ahead with
it the light boxes when we load them the
size of that system is what's going to
tell us how many boxes there are so what
we need to do here is we need to say
okay the input box count
so like the occluder count what we're
calling the four that's actually going
to be the source light boxes divided by
the size of one of these lighting boxes
right so we need to just get that out
because we're going to have to pass that
to the internal lighting core when we go
to run the eternal lighting core so like
in here right you know if you take a
look at the parameters this thing has to
pass you can see that we've got some of
them we've got the spec out let's do the
fuse that lists the lighting cue we're
nerfing because we're not trying to run
multi-threaded we've got the input box
count which needs to go here so that's
the occluder count and then we've got
the input boxes here I don't remember
source light boxes with that I'm like I
don't remember that's called and then we
got through a peak count and the source
light boxes I think I don't really
remember what a buffer looks like but I
think it's just excite oops there we go
so you could see it as a counting of
data right so I should be able to just
pass the data here like so and and maybe
I won't cost me a class sourced light
box count that's just going to be the
count divided by the size there so we'll
just go ahead and say source light box
count and that will give me a correct
pass-through for that data right so
hopefully this can be called now it
looks like this is unhappy about that
though oh because this is you thirty-two
and we don't actually know that it has
to be but trust me I'm not going to be
writing out that mini we're not going to
overflow a 32 bit didn't share with the
number
boxes heaven help us that would not run
at 60 frames a second so I think that's
all good the total input boxes is
getting printed out here there's no
reason not to continue doing that I mean
we have it I don't know that we care
about that information pickly much but
there it is okay and so now in here we
have an issue with the lighting box this
has not been casted so let's just cast
it here because it's just a blind buffer
we load it off disk it doesn't know what
the type is you 32 to you 16 so I guess
this number here has to be a safe
truncate to you 16 it can't be a large
number because the system doesn't
support it if we look at result light
boxes in here you can see us just like
checking to see if the results of the
light box modifications worked out like
I said we're not doing that anymore so
that can just kind of get removed and if
we look down in here same thing right
this is not none of this stuff is
relevant anymore so once we're done with
that I think we're pretty good to go
with the exception of there's some setup
work here that's not really appropriate
so if you look at here where we load in
the solution for example one of the
things that you'll notice that we're not
doing is we're not building those tables
and if you take a look at what's going
on in the actual lighting code itself so
an update lighting you can see that it
does some table builds so it does a
compute walk table and it build a few
slight Maps build diffuse light Maps is
fine
because like I said that one's like
welded directly in the compute walk
table call not so much compute walk
table is a blind pointer it's not gonna
get written out we could write it out
but there's really not much reason to do
that when we could just say look we
loaded all the dependent data so just
rebuild it here we know that we can and
you know it just doesn't seem like
there's any reason not to so what I'd
like to do there is just say alright we
know that we
an arena anyway and so let's just build
it so I'm gonna go ahead and say after
we initialize the arena which happens
right here I'm gonna go ahead and build
the sampling walk table here we're gonna
pass the temporary now and all of this
stuff I think should remain the same
because all of this stuff has all been
written out and off we go so we need to
do that and the other thing we need to
do is we need to initialize the sample
Direction table but I think because we
switched to doing that as a direct
lookup rather than looking it up from
inside the to the the lighting solution
I don't think we actually have to do
anything there because we could it's
just a global it was just a include
that's just the hard-coded table that we
welded in so I think that would get us
everything we'll find out pretty quickly
because if I forgot something we will
immediately die horrible death and we
try to run it but let's go ahead forward
with it so what I'd like to do here is
just get us to a place where we can
where we can do the write out so if you
take a look at internal lighting course
I'm gonna go ahead and run here and I'm
gonna set a breakpoint and turn a
lighting core and if we take a look at
at that code so I don't actually know
why it's not very good so if we take a
look at internal lighting core here you
can see that we've got this light box
dump trigger and if the light box dump
trigger global variable is set to true
it will dump the source lighting out and
so what I should be able to do here is I
should be able to set this to true I
don't know I guess we I don't really
remember
I don't think remedy can edit values
though I think that's something that
George hasn't added yet so I remember we
didn't quite do it this way for that
reason normally what I would do is I
just edit the variable here I don't
think
remedy supports that yet it might I mean
I might just not know how to do it
properly but I don't
it does so I'm pretty sure the way we
did this is we just set the value to
true once and then we let it clear it to
false here using the dynamic reload the
problem with that if I remember properly
is I think we will have to fix the
dynamic reload first because I think
dynamic reload is kind of busted right
something about the table offset was
like not correct and to be honest with
you I'm not sure what it is so let's
let's we should we should investigate
that anyway so let's just fix that bug
first so you can see the Lighting's
working just fine in here and here's
like a debug draw of the table walk
right let me just go ahead and do a
dynamic reload I'm not literally not
gonna do anything I'm just gonna
recompile right so it's just gonna
reload the same exact code and I just
want to see like do you see how it broke
right it's like now there is no there
are no steppings right it's like the
table just went away and so I don't know
what is going on there like I I have no
idea why that's happening and so we
should take a look so it's it's like it
won't be re-entering this piece of code
but I'm not sure why that wouldn't
matter June and I'm saying like this
piece of code it just it sets a bunch of
memory to point to stuff but it should
just work and I don't know why it
doesn't right we probably could patch
over it by going in here mm-hmm and on
reloads forcing it to redo this code
path but the fact that we have to do it
seems odd to me and so I'd like to know
why before I do that like rather than
just patch over it I want to know what's
going on because I don't see what I
don't see what would be going on there
this shouldn't be getting reset unless
we reset it so what change
right and we are we are using this
sample Direction table right which is
this sort of like hard coded table that
we're accessing off that's all well and
good but we don't weld anything into it
I don't think like we don't weld
pointers into it anywhere unless I'm
just misremembering
so they're just offsets and if they're
just offsets then I would think that
this would just run fine and plus where
the table should be the same in both
versions of the DLL anyway so I really
just fundamentally don't understand
what's broken so what I'd like to do is
go ahead through here and see if I can
if just by stepping through the code
perhaps I can see like what's going on
and why we're getting such a weird
result okay so I'm gonna switch this to
a debug build real quick and I'm gonna
verify that the problem still occurs I
mean it's always possible that you have
a bug that only happens in release mode
we don't really have very many of those
hardly ever on handmade hero so it's
probably not but rather than you know
hunting for something that I don't know
exists I'm gonna first verify that if I
do a rebuild here the lighting will shut
down and it does right you can see that
as it finishes blending out the lighting
now we're not taking any steppings right
and it seems fairly clear that the
problem there is one of the of the walk
table not working and so I want to take
a look at what's going on with the lock
table now just to refill your eyes
myself with that you can see that here's
the walk table entry it's just like a T
terminate and a D grid value that's all
that's in there and if you take a look
at the walk table itself you can see
that there's just a giant there's a
pointer to just a giant set of memory
there right
and if you look at what happens during
compute walk table it takes the solution
table memory which is just a thing you
know like any other piece of memory and
so again I'm not sure why it would be
having any trouble looking through this
routine just to make sure there's
nothing weird going on you can see it
just does a standard push of that memory
that's you know that's remembered by the
table and it just does a straightforward
build and writes the data in right so
again I I don't see a lot of explanation
here or a lot of like clues as to what
would be going on so what I want to do
is I'm gonna first because I happen to
be in the broken mode right now I want
to go ahead first and just inspect these
values to see what the heck is happening
so I should be able to pop a breakpoint
in here in the internal lighting core
and just quickly use the debugger to
look and see what I'm getting in all of
my you know data here you can see like
things in the diffuse map and stuff like
that here and I can just spot verify
that they make some sense and they do
I wasn't assuming anything would be
weird about that sort of stuff anyway
we have pretty much what we would expect
for all this stuff I'm gonna concentrate
on exactly what I said on just taking a
look at the the walk table because
that's the thing that I don't really I'm
not confident that that it's remaining
correct cuz the the bugs I'm seeing seem
to be related to that so this is the
light sampling walk table and I just
want to look and see what's in there
right so I'm gonna go ahead and say
light sampling walk table and I'm just
gonna look at some entries right oops
so here's what the light sampling walk
table looks like and if we kind of just
go through it you know there's there's
nothing particularly odd about it it
looks like kind of what you'd expect
right those are just stepping in certain
directions so you know I don't really
see much in the way of a problem right
that just looks looks like what I would
think it would look like so I don't
think there's really much that I can
tell about that like I I can't really
see what the issue would be so I'm gonna
have to look a little closer and just
find out like what's happening with the
stepping we may have to turn off
multi-threading for this because I don't
really have a good way of of making sure
that like I don't have a way to single
step just one thread so I kind of need
to figure out what's up with that if I
go take a look at where the stepping
codes actually happening before I turn
it off before I turn off multi-threading
I should still be able to see pretty
easily what is coming out of the grid
raycast
so if I take a look here at the at the
grid raycast which is right here I
should be able to see like what walk
table things I'm pulling out here so if
I just go ahead and run mm-hmm I should
be able to see what's going on with the
walk table when I grab one of these out
right so there's the walk table there
you can see that the you know the values
are nothing particularly fancy right and
if I take a look at the sample
directions I guess so you know this is
interesting so this could be an
explanation for where we're getting the
error
so this pointer when we load up the
sample directions this is going to be
different between the two runs because
it's static data that's in the
executable I don't have any reason to
suspect that like I don't know why that
would fail because when you load the new
one it should just use the new table but
the new table is the same as the old
table right so I don't know oh yes I do
wow that's subtle I like it
here's the problem and we probably
should fix this so the problem is that
if you take a look at what happens is
when you do the build so in there where
we do the walk table build if you take a
look at weight the way we chose to do
that which was kind of not really a
choice it was just a quick thing we
hacked in there
this gets filled out by the build so
we're actually writing into the static
data table when we then reload the new
set of daybut static data table it's
wrong you know I'm saying so I think
probably what we'd rather do is block
copy this data right I think what we'd
rather do is just block copy this data
now I think we may end up eliminating
this anyway so I'm not gonna spend a lot
of time worrying about this to be
completely honest with you so you know
there's that but I think what I'd like
to do here is say alright this sample
Direction table that we were using here
I think that's all we really need I'm
just gonna go ahead and nerf it for a
second and so what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna see all the places that use it and
I'm just gonna change those to accessing
a local copy right that's all I'm doing
there okay
and so I'm just gonna copy this table up
is what I'm gonna do for the immediate
moment and it's a bad solution to this
problem because we shouldn't really have
the problem to begin with but I think
it's good enough for now
so inside compute walk table here what
you can see is we every time we go
through here you can see us right into
the direction here and so what I want to
do here is change the way this is
working what I want to do is I want to
take the light sample direction or its
are the light sample direction and I
want to set both of these so I'm gonna
do a copy of these two right and what I
want to do here is I want to just pull
the just this out so this will come out
of the table and then the actual thing
that we write will not write that way
this is just a copy that we keep for
ourselves internally so then in here
when we do sample directions this is
just going to be a push array in the
memory for the array account of the
sample directions table and that just
gives this was a light sample direction
that just gives us the copy again not a
fantastic solution and probably not will
go with eventually but it's good enough
for them
okay what is it called what's the
problem
sample direction table sample direction
table oh yeah okay a sample Direction
table sample Direction table and in this
particular case I guess we kind of need
the solution what we could do here is
just just have this be done outside as
well so we're we're doing the compute
walk table here I can just do that and
know that that'll get lofted later so
that's actually fine
so this interesting so I think we would
want this to actually look like a source
and a desk at that point maybe
all right and again that's just so I can
have some way of of copping these things
back up
this looks what's the problem here
undeclared identifier I agree with you I
thought we had sample direction table oh
yes well um we'll unnerve that now that
all seems fine
this needs a source though so I guess we
need to do two of these like so again
this is ugly because I just don't care
at the moment I want to do this a little
bit differently and I just don't want to
do it do it right at the immediate
moment okay so compute walk table here
needs to do the same thing so exactly
what we did before this code has to
occur in the the test routine same way
otherwise we're good okay so let's see
if I can get that to work properly now
and we'll just take a look at what
happens through here
run please okay so if I now go back and
recompile and force a reload just want
to make sure of things kosher
looks good so let's go back to our
release builds here we go
so here's the release builds and I
should now be able to go somewhere like
say right here and I should be able to
do a rebuild and the lighting should
remain correct and it does and so all
I'm gonna do here now is literally just
the take the dump the lighting debug
dump and whatever that thing was called
I don't remember a lightbox dump trigger
I'm just gonna do a build with that set
to true to dump this exact data right so
during the reload now it should dump the
data and now I can just put it back to
false and in theory now inside the
handmade debug directory we should have
a bunch of dump files so here you can
see the two atlases both they're
starting and ending values you can see
the boxes that were input and you can
see that the base lighting setup this so
one of the things that's stupid about
this you can see here
is like that size is really large and
I'll be honest I think it's just the
diffused weight map so I guess it's fine
it but it's literally just this this
huge piece of data and you can kind of
see why this sucks this is why this
diffuse weight map is bad - right it's
one of the reasons the diffuse blur
probably sucks is because you can see
that like the diffuse weight map is this
huge 1 megabyte thing right we'll be
talking about that a little bit later as
we go to do optimization on the non
raycasting part of the lighting system
but it's just worth noting that it's you
know it's it's not good so let's go
ahead and try to get our HH light prof
system working and this is just going to
be trying to debug any part of this that
had to do with the new way that we're
dumping things and we just have to go
make sure that that actually works at
all right so if we run this we should be
able to start debugging anything that
doesn't work properly we're having some
oh yes right that has to be that that
those aren't Arenas at the moment so we
have to make sure that when we're doing
the HH light prof we always use that the
little dummy arena we set up to push
things on just make sure that's right
one more time
okay so debug lines we don't have setup
here so what we'd like to do here is
make sure that debug lines are nerfed so
inside
update debug lines probably want to
force that to false so no matter what
happens once we load it we just want to
say look don't draw that right we really
really don't want you to do that
because we don't support debug lines in
the external there's nothing to draw
right so if you take a look at what's
happening now you can see that at least
we are running it the total error is
pretty low it's hard to say to what
extent it is or isn't right again
because floating-point will change
between these two builds hard to say
this is the debug build as well so it's
going to be even more different we'll
run the release build in a second and
then we can get perhaps more of a sense
of it but yeah so let me go ahead and
actually run
[Music]
oops so one problem with that is it
exits before I can see the results so
let's just run it outside so this is H H
light province run and handmade debug so
I can do the exact same run here and
again I'm just curious what what the
results are that we get right so I think
we're in good shape here because that
seven point six four is actually a
really really really good number because
I think I can improve the speed of the
grid caster like dramatically from where
it is right now with not too much work
and that's already like the same number
that we were getting out of the a/b test
or roughly so let's just see I mean it
could be way worse because we could have
not picked quite the same location so
you know apples and oranges so I'm just
going to switch this to the used
lighting grid off case to run the a a b
b tester so the a beat tester may still
beat us here right and we'll see
obviously the error protects it will be
totally different because the a/b caster
is different but yeah so what you can
see here is actually the difference
between these two is not particularly
high and that's exactly what I was
hoping for because I think the grid
tester is currently quite slow compared
to what it could be now one of the
problems that we have here is you know
we're just
we are not accounting for how much time
the diffusive ler is taking so if like
we literally didn't cast anything we
don't really have a baseline for that
either so I might just quickly say look
let's do a quick will open up speed
crunch here and I'm just gonna copy
these numbers hen right oh you know what
let me use a notepad or something so if
I just really quickly or you know what
maybe I'll just put them up here who
cares
it's my source code so I'm gonna say
here that like so the grid caster
started at six point well you know what
and the a baby tester was there and what
I want to do is do a run where I don't
cast at all so we'll switch back here
and in grid ray cast like if we assume
that like literally we just don't do
anything so it's like hey what we're
gonna do is that like that's the work
we're gonna do right
are you happy now compiler piece-of-crap
so if we're not debugging by the way if
I may for a second because it seems like
compiler like language spec authors and
compiler vendors seemed to be completely
divorced from any notion of how people
actually make code at all right
in any sane world whatsoever there would
be no such thing as a compiler error or
compiler warning there would be two
separate things called I could not
compile this like I literally could not
figure out a way to produce code because
I don't understand what the input is and
you can call that an error if you want
call whatever you want
it's a compiler didn't produce the
executable that's one thing okay and if
if that happens you don't piss acute
Abel then there should be another thing
called things I noticed about the code
and those should go to a separate
frickin file and if I want to see them
I'll load it up right I always want it
produced and I always want to see them
but I want them separate so what ends up
happening is you have to treat warnings
as errors because otherwise you just
have all these errors warnings streaming
through and you can't find your actual
errors you don't know which errors are
wrong or right right it should I put
them to a file and then just let me mark
the ones that I am okay with and and
then those just don't just put like I
put the I just copy it from the file
into a separate file that's like ignore
these specific warnings because it's not
like the type of warning is the thing I
want to ignore it's that like yes I know
that code was unreachable it's supposed
to freaking be unreachable that's what
the return values for let me tell you
that but of course I can't another way
you could do it is just say like
like give me a keyword that I can just
stick in here that's like I know it's
unreachable it's supposed to frickin be
unreachable right absolutely freakin
wasting my time all the time like figure
something out instead of spending like
all your time on ridiculous stupid crap
no one cares about and it never works
like your next weirdest template
nightmare try making a feature that
actually a programmer can use to make
their program more convenient to write
or debug like it's try you know spend
spend one day on that instead of how are
we going to you know make this
ridiculous ra - thing with twenty
seven levels of exception handling and
34 different templates to try and figure
out that the thing needs to be allocated
from a pool it's just like unbelievable
okay so I now want to try and run with
no cast so what's gonna happen is every
time it tries to cast it will just
immediately fail out and so will get the
measure of the timing with none none of
these things right and the only reason
that I wanted to do that was because I
need a baseline value to know like you
know it is what I thought it was but I
just wanted to make sure because if you
take a look in here without that none
value like you look at these two values
and they look really close together
there's only point for a seconds
difference between the two across all
those runs so you're like okay the grid
rate caster is very competitive with the
abb cast or even though I haven't tried
to accelerate it much yet but if without
running any caster had been like seven
seconds right then that difference is
huge because it's actually three times
slower right or something so I just
wanted to make sure that most of the
time was taken up in the Ray caster and
it appears that that is true again I
can't really tell because it could be
that the compiler did something saucy
but Microsoft's compiler is not so
aggressive as clang at doing those saucy
things so I think I can probably
say that hopefully we're okay alright so
let me go ahead and do a build here and
there we go
so now what I'd like to do is I want to
take a look at changing the way
fundamentally we're doing the grid block
because I think I can speed it up really
dramatically there's just one rub to it
there's just one issue so the problem
that we have currently with the grid
rate caster is if you were to take a
look at how this is working this is a
core high speed loop right here it goes
over the actual a B B's that are inside
also this is stupid
well I don't know why that's here that
should just be this
like I don't know why we would do that
each time through the loop that's kind
of nonsensical and weird right
is the cost metric yet is so yet don't
know what's up at that it doesn't really
matter I guess where is the actual so
there's the cost metric - equals one
millisecond so I'm pretty sure we can
just do that so that way the cost metric
just goes down monotonically unless
you're actually doing some tests in
which case if you're doing a bunch of
tests then it goes down much more
rapidly right and we can tune this cost
metric to see what we actually want to
do to you know make sure that the rate
casting is reasonable and so on now the
thing that I wanted to point out here is
that if you take a look at how this loop
is structured what happens is as we do
the walk sure there's all this debug
crap that eventually will pull out
that's just for us you know that can be
if zeroed out and in fact we can start
if during the stuff out right we can
start getting the stuff out of there for
now and and just you know re-enable it
when we actually need to do some
debugging so anywhere that the debug
stuff was happening I can I can nerf and
I probably should take a sample with
that stuff nerfed because there may have
been some optimizations that were
prevented by that I don't suspect there
would be a lot of them and perfectly
predicted branches don't really cost you
anything in x64 so I don't anticipate
that having been something that would
that would create a lot of of slowdown
right but we should just double-check
that it doesn't because you never really
know there could be something that it's
doing in there that confuses the
optimizer or that actually requires the
optimizer to do something bad and at
that point you know that you will see a
fair fair difference between the two so
looking at these I'm just going to go
ahead and and nerf out anything in here
that I see inside the loop that
could be negatively affecting the
optimize or and then I'm gonna take
another run at it
and I don't see anything else ste bug
related it's a moment so I'm gonna go
ahead now and and let that go and again
because I think those code paths will be
mostly removed
I don't expect a huge difference and
there isn't it doesn't look like there's
a huge difference but there is some
difference right so again those numbers
are even closer which is great okay so
the problem with the loop as it stands
currently is that if you take a look at
what's going on in here you can see that
this is meant to be like a high volume
loop that's going to do the actual AABB
testing and while we want to the point
of our spatial data structure is that we
don't want to loop over all because
there's gonna be like 8,000 of these
right
and so looping over 8,000 things for at
a time is still going to be 2000
iterations of a loop and 2000 iterations
of a loop even if it's a very fast loop
is going to absolutely tank our frame
rate because of the number of rays were
casting so we need to keep the number of
iterations of this loop relatively low 2
3 4 or whatever and that's fine but what
we really don't want to do is we really
don't want to run this loop empty so
what's going to do is this is going to
cast this can cast against 4 bounding
volumes at the same time we want to make
sure that most of the time we are doing
that so we want to make sure that most
the time when we're casting against
volumes were casting against all four
volumes and at the moment we're
definitely not and the reason that we
know that we're not is because we happen
to have picked our lighting voxel and
our spatial voxel as being the same size
the reason we did that was to use pre
computed walk tables I would imagine
that that was probably a bad decision it
was motivated partially by the fact that
I thought the walk table stuff was gonna
be more complicated than it was if we
actually spin back over to the luck they
one of the things you can see here is
this is not particularly complicated
right so there's some setup work which
is here but if you take a look at the
actual code that's happening it's
incredibly simple right here's the code
that has to happen on each step and so
if we wanted to it would be really
pretty simple for me to just do this
dynamically right and so one of the
things that I want to be able to do here
is I want to be able to have a way to
decouple the spatial grid size from the
voxel grid size because I actually need
the spatial grid to be way bigger like
ideally this loop probably wants to
execute you know four times probably or
something like that like we probably
want to make sure that the spatial grid
gets some lifting out of this because I
have to do a bunch of work to get here
right and I don't just want to skip over
everything because the actual loop
overhead of like loading up this node
and seeing what's in it is not nothing
and so we want to make sure that we can
test for a few hits each time through
otherwise we're really just wasting our
time with the actual walk right the
actual grid walk so what I'd like to do
there is just see to what extent we
could make that be a faster thing and I
think we have some ways of predicting
that so if we take a look at the cost
metric here and we look at what the max
cost per Rea is at the moment that max
cost per Rea is 16 which means it will
look through a lot of these right and so
what I'm interested in saying here is
like what if this were much lower so
what if we were gonna do much fewer grid
cells right what would that look like in
terms of performance and I'm just going
to try running it to see what the
for instance of being roughly speaking
again this will be erroneous result so
it's hard to say so if we were going to
loop through a lot less stuff you can
see that we get a reasonably big
speed-up it's not as big as I would have
hoped it's about a one-second speed-up
it's not as good as I would have hoped
so it's a little bit hard to say it's a
little bit hard to say why right another
question I have here is we'll wait a
second so suppose I were to break out
immediately so suppose I were to do
something like this so we're not going
to write over anything what a
performance if I get then just curious
so one of the things that you can see
here that's pretty interesting is if I
actually look at what that's telling me
about the code so this is with just like
I know what you want to call it this is
just with grid bookends only it takes me
four point six seven nine it takes me
four point six seven nine two eight
eight these are all in seconds to do
nothing so literally just to come in
here and leave right that's all we're
doing so it it really just has to set
those two things and then and then exit
out um and that's kind of scary
right because that means that literally
just the load ops on the texels like
just this here is sufficient to tank the
performance like hard
I'm not really sure how else to
interpret that I mean I could be missing
something there but I'm not really sure
how else to interpret that let's talk
about a couple things though here
because actually I want to make sure
we're not doing something dumb so if we
look at how these are getting stored so
yeah so here let's take a look at this
real quick because I realize I'm
actually very nervous right now so let's
suppose we go look at the grid raycast
call I wish I actually I believe is in
full cast right so if we look at what's
happening with the grid raycast column
and we extrapolate what's going on here
you can kind of see where we're doing
this spec Texel a spec text will be
stuff where it's being written to so if
we think about what's actually happening
here and we compute these numbers they
are actually really mildly terrifying
let me just see let me just see if I'm
right to be scared so if I come in here
and I ask some basic questions about my
data I want to know what the alignment
is of my atlas cells
so if I take a look at this and I say
what are the alignments going to be on
these things well I need to know a
couple pieces of information right if I
go I think that's over in the OpenGL
side of things I don't actually remember
where that actually is but I think so
yeah so you can see here we have an X Y
Z I don't really care too much about
that because I know that I'm writing to
one of these at a time and we take a
look at this light color lookup squared
and we have light octahedral map dim
plus tubes so lighting octahedral map
gym plus 2 and so currently it's 8 mm
and then it's gonna be plus tude here
right that's that's just what says so I
know that I've got something that looks
like this
right and then around it
I've got something looks like that you
know and what is actually gonna happen
here
you know I'm saying well I'm gonna have
this right and this is going to be like
my Atlas oops
and each one of these is gonna be a
ten-by-ten right I mean that's what
we're saying here because there's a one
pixel border on each side so we've got
little 8x8 in here and then ten by tens
and these are stacked right no that's
fine I don't have a problem with it
it's all great everyone loves it science
cool but inside each of these cells
we're storing an RGB value right I want
to say and the RGB value at the moment
our floats so an RGB triple assuming
that this is what I think it is is going
to be that's three channels right times
four bytes per float so that equals 12
bytes so each one of these is going to
be 12 bytes long and if I look at what
that equates to in this particular
system here is where the terror comes
from a 10 by 10 square and I don't give
a crap about why so I don't care about
why but a 10 wide tile size at 12 bytes
per Texel is going to be a horizontal
span of 10 times 12 equals 120 bytes
right and I know that I'm issuing my X
slices per thread right I mean that's
just what we're doing and so if I'm
issuing X slices per thread what does
that tell you about where the threads
will be writing well if we look at where
my threads are writing if we take a
blow-up of this
tickler situation this is going to be
say thread a and it's a hundred and
twenty eight a hundred and twenty bytes
and this is going to be thread B and
this is one hundred and twenty bytes
right well a hundred and twenty bytes
where does that fall on the cache line
boundary on X 64 a cache line is 64
bytes right when we allocated this it
probably got cache line aligned because
that's probably just what happened if it
didn't get cache line aligned then we're
in even worse shape and to be honest I
don't know that we ever bothered cache
line aligning in the first place so we
could be even worse than what I'm about
to say but honestly I don't think there
isn't even worse because I think it's
just worse so let's suppose that we
cache line aligned this thing so that
the starting offset is actually on a
cache line boundary well if this is on a
cache line boundary and we go 64 in
we're gonna be like well no that's wrong
there we go 64 in we're gonna be
somewhere like here and we go another 64
in we're gonna be somewhere like here
right we're gonna be eight bytes
specifically right this distance here is
eight bytes we're gonna be eight bytes
into the next tile for the cache line
boundary what that means is that these
two threads who were trying to operate
completely independently now have a
mutex a lock that locks them up right so
thread a and thread B which we're trying
to do completely parallel work are not
doing that and they're not doing that
because they now do a hardware mutex
between their accesses right
so while I can't say for sure how much
of a performance impact that's having
that's freaking terrible and very very
bad we absolutely don't want to be
deploying a mutex in routines that don't
need them and we are we didn't write one
but we absolutely are this is one of the
things that's always very important to
know when multi-threaded programming
generally speaking well written
multi-threaded programs just don't have
mutexes there's usually a dispatching
kind of a mutex somewhere but well
written code for multi-threading just
doesn't use them you basically figure
out ways to make the work so that once
it's distributed it just happens and if
you have highly contended data
structures you typically try to attack
those with others schemes so I think in
this case we've ended up with a mutex in
our threaded code and that's terrible
you should really never have them and I
don't want them in any high performance
code if you're doing a low performance
code and the multi settings just for
like background loading or something
that's totally fine we've Texel all you
want but in high performance code you
really shouldn't have them this is just
very bad right because what's gonna
happen is inside the actual x64
cache controllers they're going to be
doing locking all the time between my
threads it's going to lock thread B well
thread a is running that line and then
it's gonna lock thread a well thread B's
running to that line and while I don't
necessarily know how much time that's
going to cost me I definitely know that
it can cost me time as any mutex can and
so rather than try to measure the amount
of time that's that that mutex is
costing me I think what I'd much rather
do is just get rid of it because we
should be able to okay so I think what
I'd like to try and do here you see
whether I can get away with not having
to do
change anything about the structure of
the system and I'm just gonna see if
there would if there might be some way
that I can change that writing process
to not have the fall sharing so if we
take a look at the way the work callback
happens here you can see that we do zy
loops and X is the distribution variable
so what that's going to mean is that we
are walking downward right it's it's
this level walk so what I'm wondering is
because it's not too much worse to just
walk on X's it's a little bit perhaps
worse for it might be slightly worse
because it's you know not as good in
terms of the dimension in terms of
splitting I'm just wondering if maybe we
can just walk the other way right
because there's two things I can do here
one is we can walk the other way one is
I can change the orientation of the map
just change the look up right so that
we're actually dispatching the other way
around so that on X as we move down
instead of over right so I could do
either one and I think for the sake of
efficacy here let me just check to make
sure what those what those sizes are cuz
I don't remember so
so like it's 24 16 16 so the fact that
you know just to be a little bit clearer
about this because it's going on in my
head but you don't necessarily know
what's going on in my head when I look
at that breakdown you know I want to
distribute the work over X's because
there's more individual units of work so
let's say you're on some fancy new
processor like a thread ripper and you
have 30 core 32 cores 32 cores lying
around well I can't actually use as many
of those 32 cores if I'm distributing on
a 16 on 16 separate breaks
whereas I could write if I was doing 24
or separate breaks right I can just hand
work two more cores if I have more
individual pieces to break up and so you
know we can look at this in different
ways but the other thing I could do also
is is split along y&amp;z let's say but then
write in X's right so there's I think
there's things I can do to make this
work so I'm just gonna do it that way
the more advanced way to do it and what
I would do if I weren't on stream which
always makes it take forever to do
everything if I was just programming it
myself and could be fast about it I
would probably just change the Atlas to
be X indexed going down so I think
that's probably a better solution
because we're on stream I'm going to do
a slightly weaker solution but you know
hopefully everyone can understand how we
would do that I just anything where
you're changing indexing there's a bunch
of bugs that you could make and it's
hard for me to concentrate when I have
to explain everything and also there's
the fact that it just takes a little bit
longer to do on stream all the time so I
think what I would say here is let's
just try doing this split a little bit
differently so if we were to pass wise
here instead of X's and loop over the
X's so something more like this right
there shouldn't be really any difference
between these two things so if I just do
that
I shouldn't really have to do anything
different
it should all just work but now each
thread is writing to its own series of
cache lines and there wouldn't be that
sort of false sharing across each of the
boundaries so I just want to do this as
a test to figure out whether or not this
is costing me anything huge and again
this comes from looking at this number
and being concerned about how large it
is because that means that really the
raycasting itself was accounting for
less than three seconds out of the whole
out of the seven seconds time that's a
huge amount of time to be spending not
raycasting right and I just want to know
where that number is coming from and so
this is one place that I kind of got
sorted I just want to get it out of the
picture so that I know that I'm not
looking at just a bunch of mutex crap as
I go to start trying to Ferrara where
that work is coming from so I'm gonna
change this to dispatching long why is
again that should be really really
straightforward
I would hope I mean I guess I don't know
write the X odd value I don't know if
we're using this right now I don't think
we are so I'm just gonna get rid of it
and I'm just gonna distribute the work
online so now I'm distributing the work
on Y and in theory I shouldn't really
get substantially different results
right I should basically be producing
the same general results here but I want
to see what the difference in speed is
so it's not particularly much right it's
not it's not it's still not really
telling me where most that time here but
it is substantial I mean it was a
measurable this difference so unless
that just comes from some you know other
artifact of it I think I would probably
leave that in place for now as we go
forward just to get that extra time out
of there so at this point I'm tempted to
wonder if maybe again also one of the
other things that's happening at the
moment is because we're using actual
floating-point values the size of these
maps is really substantial and I'm
guessing that you know we could be
seeing there's honestly just a lot of
memory traffic as well and so just
thinking about how the perf on this is
going to go it may mean that we are at
the point where if we want this perf to
be getting better we may have to also
switch the lighting at list from RGB x'
to something more compact right so if we
take a look at how big these are if I go
ahead and where was that here it is so
if I take a look at how big these
atlases are it's seven megabytes right
I don't really think there should be
much of a problem with streaming the
seven megabytes in so the only thing I'm
worried about is I'm wondering if
perhaps the problem here is that the
cash is in the the streaming predictor
is not able to actually know what the
heck it's supposed to be doing and so
we're stalling out on each of these
loads well it really just be one load
the first one it's a weak hypothesis I
don't think it's probably very important
so that could be something
another thing that's highly likely is
that this is the culprit here because
this code is slow and crappy right so
again because we're seeing such a huge
amount of time spent outside the raycast
at the moment I feel like doing the
performance analysis of that is gonna be
way more important right now than what I
was about to do which I also want to do
that I think will be fast but I mean you
you got to focus on where the time
stinks man and right now over half the
time was being spent not raycasting so I
think we got to get that down and my
only goal is to make this faster I don't
care how so I'm gonna go ahead and try
to figure out how we get that to happen
so I'm gonna take a look here at what's
happening inside for example the compute
voxel irradiance at part of things I
want to see if nerfing that particular
routine are simplifying that particular
routine drops the timing dramatically as
well so if we go to compute voxel
irradiance at what if I just make this
be much more simplified so rather than
doing say this advanced light look up
here where we do a bunch of blending and
various other things what if instead I
just used like a single one so maybe I
do an else here and I see like how much
does it cost if I just did one lookup of
the tile something like this
and let all of the math still happen but
we just keep it you know where we just
have lots of spam in there and we don't
actually have to do what what is the
problem here
get tile clamped light out its Texel
alright and again this is just me trying
to investigate by poking because it's
usually the easiest way to get real
results out I just want to see what is
taking my time so you can see that
getting a reduced down to 3 there which
is good but still not probably quite as
low as I would hope let's try to be a
little bit more aggressive rather than
getting rid of that let's get rid of the
whole thing and see what happens so I'm
just going to do just the get relative P
computation and then I'm literally going
to return that as the result ok so now
I've nerfed that entire routine so it's
just not happening at all
and I'm gonna go ahead and run it and
just see what happens here okay so now
we're approaching the none value which
is what I want so I guess it it has
gotten to the point where we probably
need to start addressing this routine
because it sucks right and there's a lot
of things that we can do to try and make
this routine not suck and and I think
we're probably just going to have to do
those things now that's basically all
there is to say
so let's go ahead and see to what extent
it's just the lookups that are our
problem here if I go ahead and take this
whole clamping if zero
blah-blah-blah-blah-blah if if we get
rid of just the tile part of this right
and we're we're doing these tile samples
here I say okay do do everything that
you were going to do before so it's it's
literally all the same math that you
were gonna do but instead and you know
what
what does clamp zero one do at the
moment can we just look at that please
yes a clamp clamp is kind of a piece of
crap
is another problem here so I'm gonna get
rid of clamp as well just because it
makes me nervous and then I'm gonna do a
little bit of stuff here so what we're
gonna do is we're gonna do an else here
we're gonna take this and I'm going to
just get rid of the clamp right so all
the rest of this stuff can happen but
just not the clamp and then now here
where we're going to load up on these
tiles what I'm gonna do here is just
create a fake version of the of the
light at Lestat's light atlas Texel
stuff that just points somewhere that I
know right so if we take a look at light
atlas Texel you can see that it's just a
v3 so what I should be able to do here
is say like alright you know there's
some dummy values here
and what you can see is that we're only
going to use eight of them anyway
because we're just looking at the these
tile values so what I should be able to
do is just have the tile point at that
so this is just a way of trying to keep
the math the same at least to a certain
degree I'm doing the best I can it's not
perfect right I mean I guess another
thing I could do is try to make this use
values that this thing can't see ahead
of time having these because this is a
problem because it will be able to fold
some stuff in here but you know just
looking at it it's probably fine because
most of these things are not known
because they're based off the UVW right
oops there we go okay so again what I'm
trying to do there is just to the extent
that I can just trying to leave the math
roughly intact and and just sort of get
a sense for how much that's actually
costing me so if you take a look at
what's happening here you can see that
it's still even just that right which is
which is really kind of basic is still
pretty expensive you know what I mean
and what I might want to do at this
point just for my own just for my own
edification is I kind of just want to
look at what the assembly language code
looks like there so in terms of calling
compute voxel readings at
I just want to know like can you tell me
what this what this looks like right
because we are compiling in release mode
right yeah so this should be the
optimized code and I just want to see
the disassembly and I just want to see
what it's doing right because I don't
know to what extent this is actually
costly and what to what extent this
compiler is a piece of junk so if we
loop on through here yeah you know I'll
be honest this is kind of just a stack
spilling festival at this point so you
know let's just try to let's clean this
math up before we go any further because
that's just it's just not it's just not
feasible what we're doing here okay so
what do we actually need to accomplish
so what we're trying to do here is we're
trying to do we're trying to do a result
where we we produce an floating-point
RGB value for the lighting now we have
to remember that we probably don't want
to use floating-point in the end we
probably want to use more like you
sixteens in the end for this stuff
potentially it's hard to say because I
don't know so we probably don't want to
go too far down the optimization rat
hole here because ideally we probably
want to half the size of these right I'm
just thinking I'm just thinking we
probably do so it's a little bit hard to
say so when we're computing this I'm not
sure that we really want it to be
floating-point values but for the moment
it is so let's take a look at how we
might address this going forward so what
we're gonna have if we were to
if we were to look at this as just a
simple like not trying to get
particularly high performance out of
these wide values there's a couple
different ways we can go one of them is
to just put the RGB you know inside a
wide vector and you know in terms of
doing things like this summation that's
actually pretty straightforward because
you can just actually do the mole and
then the sum all some Mulsim right and
it's pretty straight forward so that's
actually not that bad but again it's
like you know it means you'll never get
the forex beat up from Cindy you're
gonna always get something a bit less
they're looking at some of this stuff
like where we're doing these weights I
don't know really why we bothered having
this be a weight zero these don't really
need to be indexed by array in fact none
of this stuff does and so that's
probably just harder for the compiler
compilers don't really like array stuff
because they don't know ahead of time
that you don't need it to be arranged in
memory a particular way so they don't
always notice that they can get rid of
the array stuff sometimes they do clang
is really aggressive about that but
sometimes they don't so we can also
probably simplify some of this stuff
anyway if we take a look at what's going
on in here we can also see that we just
have a ton of multipliers and we should
be able to get more of those multiplies
by packing these values together or
doing other stuff like that too right so
what we want to fundamentally do here is
figure out ways of reducing the number
of operations we're actually doing here
by doing more of them at once and that's
just basically what we want to do so I
think we should be able to do that right
and especially with the clamping we can
also do that so let's just start with
some of these and see where we can go
with that so the first thing I want to
do is let's take a look at this and see
if we can't you know do four of these at
once or something right let's let's see
if we can't
get somewhere with it so if you take a
look at occlusion and and you know we're
trying to do inner products here and all
that sort of stuff
all of this looks like stuff we could
have just done wide and the reason I say
that is because UVW is something we
compute and we can easily spam it to be
wide and then we could do all of this
stuff wide right if we take a look at
just one of these where we're doing you
know a UVW - is 0 0 0 and then occlusion
and and then a clamp if we imagined
writing this wide what do we actually
have to compute well we've got you minus
0 right I mean just take a look at one
of these inner products I guess is what
I'm saying right so this inner product
is going to be something like UX times
I'll call that occlusion dot X right
this year and we have a subtraction
there so it looks like this and it
happens to be nerfed here but some of
them have it so let's just keep in mind
that that happens we're going to want to
do this for the inner product and then
we're going to want to add right each of
the components manually or separately
sorry like so
and then we're going to want to do a
clamp on this value comes out and so if
you look at what happens there what we
would probably like to do is recognize
the fact that we can do this whole thing
in a much more straightforward fashion
just by well and honestly not I'm
looking at it because we know that these
inner products are all actually kind of
going to be the same like we're sharing
a bunch of terms here too so let's take
two of these so that these two
back-to-back right if we were to compute
those two back-to-back oops
looking at those two things the only
difference is that right so actually
these back terms here are pretty much
all the same
they're the only difference is that we
subtract one or we don't subtract one
right so fundamentally if you actually
look at what all of the values are that
we need to produce we actually know what
all of those values are ahead of time
they look like this right there's
basically just that those are all the
values that we actually need and so then
all we do is we some different you know
sets of them but those are all the
values that we ever actually computed we
didn't need any any other values we just
needed to get those values and then we
needed to sum them right in different
permutations so at that point we just
need all the different sums that we can
produce out of these right is all all
we're really doing
we don't actually yeah we didn't really
actually need to to do anything else so
I feel like we can probably figure out a
way to do that much more straightforward
than probably what we were doing here
and the compiler may have been kind of
confused about that as well hard to say
so if we were going to try and pack
these together so let's suppose that we
were gonna try and fit these into two
vectors somehow right so that we would
just have like something that looked
more like this well I guess I can just
use this so let's suppose I was going to
try and do these you know first ones and
then these second ones are something
like this right and so what I want to
have ending up in here is like I want
the result of this inner product to end
up in the first one and any no and so on
and so forth how would how would we do
this right so I want to have you know if
I look at what these values are let's
say just trying to figure out how this
would work if it will work so what I
want to do here is I want to produce
inside this thing maybe I'll do it this
way so we can kind of see what I'm
talking about so I want to produce
inside this thing the inner product
where it would be a plus B plus C right
that's gonna be what I would want in the
first column there in the next column I
would want D plus B plus C right in the
next column I would want a plus what e
plus C and in the final column I would
want D plus E Plus C right so that's one
thing I and if we look at what's going
on there I mean I can save the plus C so
I would get one whole ad moved out of
there but you know is it much of a
savings not really right let me just
scan down here and see what we can do so
in here in here it's a little better to
like if we look at how that's getting
lost at up like yeah this is one of
those things where this is really not
work that humans should be doing like
this is a work that you just wanted a
super optimizer for so it's pretty
straightforward actually it's just we
don't have time to grind through and get
that the real optimal out here but this
is just you know you would just a super
optimizer would just find the minimal
number of wide packings you could do and
off you would go but anyway so we can
absolutely do that part and then the
clamping would be really easy it's just
a min followed by a max so that's the
clamping would be trivial and we'd save
a ton of work there as well let's just
work backwards a little bit here because
I feel like I need to kind of know where
I'm headed before I know how the
packings will actually work out in terms
of producing this inverse some value the
inverse some value
is true across everything and has to be
multiplied as a final coefficient so
that's just the case where it doesn't a
wide RCP doing this sum is going to suck
because it's a horizontal sum I don't
really know what we've got these days if
we assume that we're doing SSE I don't
know what we can do here so how bad are
these guys at adjacent pairs and pack
and dest right so so the horizontal add
isn't horrible let's just take a look at
where are you up info says we are on
that so I'm assuming it's had PS
actually don't even look yeah it is
happy yes I'm assuming it's had PS and
if I was gonna do it had PS how bad is
that and I don't really know so let's
assume that we're on skylake for now
because we are so you know it's it's not
great
it's two cycles on port five which is
like brutal right but like
yeah two cycles on port five is is rough
right anyway so if we take a look at
what we're going to be doing here
assuming that we do this relatively
straightforward if we did it in the
lanes here really we get royally screwed
when they come down here to do the some
I don't know how we would do this you
know these weights would be separate so
I guess the first thing that would
happen is if we do like this sort of
thing so we we first add zero through
three and four through seven together
and then we have a some vector that now
needs to be horizontally added you know
itself and
I don't really know that there's much we
can do other than just waste time and
compute it right so here we would do a
thing where we're like compact it one
more time and we would just do like a
horizontal ad on it and worse waste
images we're just full-on wasting a ton
of cycles and it's just I don't know but
I don't know what else you would do so
we'd produce the sum here and then we
would do reciprocal square root I don't
know if we actually have great naming
convention there we've done so we would
do approximate one over of this which
gives us the inverse and then we would
you know I'm gonna I'm gonna move all
this stuff up here now as I do it so
this would produce our sum for us and
then we would be able to multiply and
some this stuff together so then in
terms of actually producing our result
value what we would end up with there is
something like a you know result X
result y
result Z here and we're gonna have the
exact same problem which is that we are
trying to sum again after having done
the weight sum we have this problem
again right because we had to do it to
do the reciprocal and then we have to do
it again after we do the the the
weighted blend so again it just it's
really sucky right and I guess I should
say RGB right so it's really not good
but again I'm not sure that we have a
lot of options I'm not sure what else we
would really be able to do about it you
know probably not much so we would end
up with yet doing like a V 3 for X out
of it I guess and the values are just
there's only one thing in each of them
right no I guess I guess that's not true
so we can at least do we could at least
do the RGB together right so I guess
what we can do is we can do this and we
can do the RGB together by just saying
look these are all gonna be RGB values
so that's actually fine right we can't
actually do that and the multiply would
work there so yeah okay you know that
that saves a little bit for us so yeah
so we can do the approximate number some
we've got this and then we can just do
the RGB and we can do this wide so that
we're wasting one lane but at least we
get three times the throughput on that
right so that's that's not actually
awful you know that that there's worse
things in the world than that right
so I'm going to go ahead and pre suggest
that we have a a contraction of these
down to actual values that we care about
so I'm gonna want to do this sum and
then the inverse sum that would produce
the result RGB value and then we could
just return that and it would go out to
whoever's on the outside and they do
something with it and we can make that
happen
for now we can also just just extract it
and that's fine too
really it's just this and in it you know
so we'll get a little speed up from
doing it this way but yet you know we'll
we'll just downshift at the end anyway
so okay so we have our summations here
we would produce you know the the result
values this way in terms of weight
values I think that if we did the
multiplies wide we would probably save
two multiplies on each of these which
seems good and then we would have to
Swizzle out to get these this this is
the problem here is that we need to then
do replications and those replications
are kind of costly so we'd save
multiplies but we'd spend you know again
port five is just gonna be screaming for
mercy one of the really really sucky
things about skylake is that it just
doesn't have nearly enough bit
rearrangement for how much horsepower it
has everywhere else so like
you know port five just absolutely hates
itself 24 hours a day basically because
anyone who does anything that rearranges
data is just lying on sitting on port
five all day long right so you can see
in sky like it's just like any time
you're trying to rearrange data right
you're on port five like there's chef PS
here's pfb just any anything that you
ever want to rearrange data on skylake
is just it's just lined up behind port
five and port five is just a frickin
disaster right so port five on skylake
is horrible and that's why I'm kind of
like going 'god this can be awful like
this is gonna be back backed up on port
five this if i did it this if i unpack
these guys that are gonna be backed up
in port five doing that replicate i
don't know if there's a way to replicate
not on port five i'm guessing there
isn't but there's no broadcasts on i
mean you can just see like just look
here's everything that has shuff in the
title right port five point five four
five four five four five four five four
five port port port port right so it's
just like you know just a disaster
um so yeah I don't really know I don't
really know how to make this routine
good I wish I did so taking a look at
what I have to produce here because
these are just n X's and P X's in
different combinations maybe I'll just
go ahead and and do them as chefs
because if you take a look at the split
here it's like you need n X n YP x and y
and X P Y P X P Y right so if we were to
split those out just as as it is so like
you have one vector of just NY n YP y py
you can see that that just happens in
both cases so I think if I did this so
somehow this thing gets that this gets
that the whole time right which I guess
we can just that's just a load up right
that just loads that up we don't really
know where we're gonna get this this
this may actually end up being a shuffle
so actually let me just write it in this
notation for now so that we know that
like these aren't final they're just me
thinking out loud so those two are
pretty straightforward because then that
means like when we look at what happens
with W 0 3 it's just going to be
something x and y py x and z times c0 3
right and then W 4 7 is going to be
something x and y py x pz
so you know okay it's not like that
would save a ton of work it's true and
then how we get it out here I don't know
exactly but and honestly these
horizontal ads probably go away at that
point because once you have it blown out
you probably just do the sum directly
you know what I mean
because ad is on more pour like so so
oops so add PS is on zero and one and
more importantly not five so you could
slip you could get two of those ads per
cycle going while you were shuffling so
this probably doesn't oops
this probably is not that so probably
what we actually have here is something
more like this
and so all I'm doing here is I'm just
contracting these values hopefully you
can see I'm just zippering them together
so that we use the minimal number of
dependents right so one way you can do
this is just add like I add this to this
this to this this to that like so I do
like I do W 0 plus W 1 equals some 0 1
and then I do plus equals W 2 plus
equals W 3 plus a equals 3/4 and the
problem is that's just one big long
serial dependency chain each of these
ads is independent so on the first cycle
it can issue both of these because one
goes to port 0 1 goes to port 1 on the
next cycle it can issue both of these 1
2 0 1 2 1 on the next cyclic an issue
both of these 1 2 0 1 2 1 right and then
on the final cycle right so if I do it
just to I don't know if we've ever
talked about this before in terms of
cycle ordering and something that but
just to give you some perspective right
if I do this or I guess I'll just do it
this way
[Applause]
so if I do this right how many cycles
does is take well this is cycle 1 this
is cycle 2 this is cycle 3 4 5 6 7 and
the answer I mean and the reason why
that is is because there is no way for a
process or to use the result in less
than one cycle that's just how it like
processors don't usually have throughing
for anything like this and plus it takes
one cycle are doing at anyway and so on
the first cycle it does this and the
second cycle it has to it has to wait at
least one cycle to get the result of
this before it can start the add right
so it's going to be seven cycles to do
that whereas if we make these
independent then these both happen on
cycle one because they're independent so
they can both issue and we know that
there's two ports that can do adds so
one goes to port 0 1 goes to port 1 on
the next one the same thing is true each
of these can it executes on a separate
port and these will be ready by then so
we're going to be able to issue on cycle
2 these will both issue on cycle 3 and
then our final one which is just the
total sum right which is the last two
added together that will issue one cycle
4 and so we've saved 3 cycles right off
of that which is almost twice as fast
not quite but it's almost twice as fast
and all we did was just change the order
we were doing our additions do you know
what I mean
so I think it's important to just keep
that in mind like there's there's a
pretty there's a pretty big difference
in how you write routines sometimes if
you don't really know what you're doing
you can accidentally lose performance in
your critical sections without actually
you weren't actually doing anything
other than just organizing things like
adds wrong you know so I don't know to
what extent compilers will rearrange
that for you these days so sometimes you
may be okay because the compiler will go
like oh wait I can just do this
zippered instead of sequential so some I
don't know sometimes it may pick up the
slack for you but I don't really like to
rely on that because
enough to just write this way so I just
like to tell the compiler straight up
look here's the way you should do this
and usually it'll listen to me sometimes
it doesn't so anyway at that point we
know that we can do this whole thing in
four cycles right and if we've done it
all that way that's probably better than
our horizontal ads would have been
anyway so since we know we need these to
be expanded out later might as well just
do it okay so then what we need here is
we need to do replications here
unfortunately like I saying so all of
this crap this is the part where port
five becomes the epic disaster zone but
what are we gonna do so this is
literally gonna cost us eight cycles on
port five I literally have no idea how
we would do anything different so it
sucks and I'm sorry I just I just don't
know so from here what we do is I want
to do like a broadcast I don't know if
we have one of those but I want to do a
broadcast zero here right I thought we
had two like a shuffle thing
yeah so so we do have it so it's just
this so that's fine
um and so again all I'm doing here is I
just need to spread these out and it
sucks
and again there's fraught we probably
could do better here right we probably
could make a routine that was that was
more clever about how it arranged its
data so that you don't end up with these
large broadcasts we have not done that
so I'm sorry but that's just yeah where
we're at right so yeah so if we take a
look at these and actually I can start
gathering these up a little bit more now
so if I grab this and put it in here and
get rid of ants I should be able to then
move this up as well well I actually
need I need this for one one hot second
like so and so what I want to do here is
just then say okay we have to finish
actually creating these so you can see
we have n xpx &amp; xpx &amp; xpx &amp; xpx that's
actually the same on the x side as well
so in theory I should be able to do
something like this right
so if if n xpx is all I needed at the
front then again you know that's
starting to actually look not terrible
like this sucks but man did that save a
lot of cycles and we know that we wanted
these clamped originally right yeah
sorry no that's the C values that we
wanted clamped yeah we should get rid of
this now we should get rid of all this
stuff because we got to work we got to
work that stuff out so let's get rid of
that
let me put all of this up there where it
belongs so here's the old routine there
it is
and we don't care about this part at the
moment okay so yeah so this start flips
this clamp the W values were not right
so the W values were not clamped and we
don't have to worry about that so this
is how we would actually produce all of
our W values and then we just broadcast
them out so I think actually all we're
left with is how we produce these
particular values and if you look it
would seem like
it would seem like if I shuffled these
maybe that wouldn't be the worst thing
in the world so like let's suppose that
I changed this so I'm just thinking out
loud here as I try to do as much as
possible on the stream so you can hear
what I'm trying to think through so if
we were to swap okay so that wouldn't
work okay so the only complexity that I
see here is that if we were to keep this
the same way without reorganizing this
the nxp x-value is a little hard to
build potentially I guess we'll see but
I don't need these anymore because we've
got what we want them to be in here so
that's fine so the real question is how
do we want to compute the UVW stuff
dovetailing it with what exists up above
right so we're gonna not pay attention
to see for the moment and what I'm gonna
do here is I'm going to expand this bit
to include these folks right here right
and I guess this stuff is totally
independent so that can probably remain
and so I'm really going to take a look
at more this right this part here what
I'd like to do is yeah I'd like to just
have that part there be something that
we can rewrite wide you know so this is
what we need to compute this UVW this
voxel index is actually used by the
other part of 13 we probably need to
compute it but it's less important for
what we're doing right at the immediate
moment so what I want to do is take a
look at get relative P and we want to
just take like this
crap here and we want to see what we can
do with like the with this part right so
what would we do to get to get this
value this is what we're trying to do
what would we do to get that value more
quickly right and if we look at what's
happening here okay so most of this
stuff is things we probably could just
load we could just run this directly
right so if we did an f3 V if we did an
f32 for X of the inverse seldom and we
literally could load we could load that
straight out probably right like we
could just say this with a zero on the
end of it or whatever right or whatever
we want doesn't matter what's on the end
of it and then we did the same thing
with the world P right and the total
bounds then we could just compute this
directly so the F chord vector would
just be the in seldom times the world P
minus the total bounds like that I'll
just call that PE for now so that can
just be a direct computation we would
then want a floor and I don't actually
know if we have a floor we don't so
we'll have to look at that because what
we want is this we want the actual floor
floor SS here it doesn't look like we
actually have it so we want here to
implement that
and it would be something like this so
that's the index value right that we
have we just haven't converted it out so
this is like the floating point index
value or in this case I guess we called
it V chord right so we can compute the B
chord directly and then the UVW value
just comes out of that subtract so it's
just the F chord - the B chord so that's
fine right and then to produce these
values we just need to actually do some
shuffles the NX px is hard to produce
the NYP Y is really easy to produce so
you know this this one this one's ugly
the rest are not so we have UV already
and then we have the negative version of
UV W and that would just be like the one
vector minus UV W so from here it's
pretty straightforward we would just
take the broadcast of the negative u
VW's second component and from here we
would take a broadcast of its second
component from the positive one right
this one's an actual shuffle it wants
two negatives to positives right so what
it would want to do is it would say well
I want the negatives and then I want
oops and then I want the positives which
I think would just work we'd have to
double check that that shuffle that this
goes in the order I think it does so
there's that but hmm and then finally
this one and the reason I said this is
difficult is because there's really with
without a pshh FB I don't really know
how to get that
in fact even a pea chef B can't get it
because you can't take two vectors so
you kind of just need two shuffles III
really don't know how else to do it so
if we take a look at the nxp X here we
need to shuffle twice and again the
reason is because of the lane
restrictions on shuffle I need to be
able to get a negative and a positive in
the bottom but I can't do that because
the two bottom values have to come from
the same vector
there isn't a 32-bit unpack is there
so I could do an I could do an unpack
low but but again that only gives me the
bottom to correct and then the top two
aren't correct so I'm sorry I can't
think of how to do this in one
instruction I don't know if you can like
I said you know probably the right thing
to do is you just you go through teen
really meticulously and you reorganize
all their to be the minimum number of
shuffles I'm just and I'm not going to
do that but
in terms of of the way this is
interleave I don't I don't see another
way to do it so I think what you have to
do is you have to build like an X temp
and what that's going to be is you're
just putting everything into one vector
that you needed right so you say look
I'll take the negative one and the
positive one and put them into one
vector and then we can shuffle right so
then it's a shuffle of okay I take
negative positive negative positive
right and now I've got all the values
right so you can see now we've got a
streamlined version of this the number
of cycles we can probably save is
actually quite dramatic here but we're
gonna have to save it for tomorrow
because we're out of time
so I'm gonna go ahead and just save this
inside the if zero and just make sure I
can turn on the old path well enough
right looks like I accidentally deleted
the NX stuff so let me just put that
back in
see they weren't -1 they were 1 - right
so don't know why I type that and then
these are just direct um so I just want
to verify that everything still runs ok
you know and in order to do that I can't
actually just run it because we nerve
some stuff so I'm gonna have to really
quickly reenable the actual cast so the
cost metric here that we nerfed
has to go back in real quick and that is
back to normal looks like that's good
okay let's go to a brief Q&amp;A and then
we'll pick this up tomorrow where we'll
try to finish up that routine and see if
we can get some good speed improvements
there
with things go better if you started
with uvw each for wide
I don't think so I mean again I'd have
to try it and see but the problem that
you're gonna have there so you'd start
by blowing that out I guess like here
right and then the problem that you're
gonna have is like how do you speed up
these computations if if those are for
wide right cuz if they're four wide
you're doing all of these like you're
doing this whole thing so how do you
make this faster if they're four wide
right it seems like you're kind of
screwed but could you not pad by eight
bytes to fix the overlap um so you could
but why would you
you just get worse cache usage and more
GPU transfer time right you never want
padding if you don't have to have it and
so you could but but why the l0
determines how many cache lines the CPU
can hold so I've I don't know what is an
l0 can you tell me what is an l0 first
and then I could try to answer the
question l0 is not something I think
I've ever heard of but sometimes people
use terms I'm just unfamiliar with so
would you consider going over explaining
how operation takes X minus CP USR will
that be in the introduce see ya in the
upcoming course we will be covering that
in the Advanced section yeah do I
recommend learning via keybindings Emacs
key bindings are neither I guess I would
say I don't specifically I wouldn't
specifically talk about VI or Emacs what
I would say is modal is better on your
hands I think pretty definitively so I
would try to lean modal I don't use VI
key bindings but I do use my own modal
bindings so they're more similar to VI
than they are to Emacs in that sense I
would say it's much easier on your hands
and you'll have less repetitive strain
injury problems if you use a modal key
binding because Emacs is based on
holding down a lot of modifier keys and
that's just not very good on your hands
so I would say I would say lean towards
a modal binding doesn't have to be VI
because VI has its own kind of issues I
think but okay so just to be clear like
I don't think I've ever heard the term
l0 before so if someone actually thinks
there is a thing such as l0 you should
tell me what it is or how to find that I
mean I can look but I don't think there
is an L 0 cache unless that does that
refer to like the rat or something I
don't know what that means
so here is someone suggesting there's
some kind of thing called an L zero
cache but but I don't like I'd really
just don't know like I don't know what
an l0 cache would be yeah it's not it's
not in the Wikipedia article so I'm
gonna proceed with an explanation that
just assumes that l0 is not a real thing
because I've literally never heard it
but it
might be a real thing and if it is
you'll have to go look up what it is but
like I don't know there are things on
for example a sky like chip like this
one that someone could call l0 you could
call the register file in l0 if you
wanted to but I've knit I've never heard
it called that that's the only reason
that I'm kind of weirded out right so
I'm going to assume that we're not going
to use this term because I've literally
never heard it before and I'm not sure
what part of the chip it would actually
be talking about
there are l1 l2 and l3 parts on this
trip so so these do definitely exist on
a sky like this there are things so
there's the register file
there's the trace caches so I guess we
call this the loop cache and like
there's the decode I don't know what
they call it in sky like almost I can't
let me look for this chip I forget
there's - there's actually two caches
micro op caches they might just call it
the you up cache but I'm not sure can I
I wanted that diagram can we have that
diagram back where did it go
okay um so assuming I got the right
diagram here for skylake it means it's
this guy like so should be um if you
take a look at this diagram it's it's
not really how the chip works or
anything but it's just kind of like a
flow diagram to give you some idea of
who's doing what when just roughly so if
you take a look at again l0 I don't
really know what that would mean but if
you take a look at where the l1 is and
the l2 those are your encore caches so
generally what happens is that each of
these cores that stamp down on a sky
like this thing has like 4 cores I think
yeah so this is a 4 core chip and each
one of those cores runs 2 hyper threads
that's where there's eight of these but
there's only four cores but you can see
logical processors is 8 but the number
of course is only 4 right so it's for
real cores and so the number of real
cores you have determines how many
on-chip caches you have so a skylake has
an l1 and an l2 on on the core so each
core has its own so when you're talking
about how much caching you get you know
you have 32 K of instruction cache right
and 3 2 K of data cache here right in
your l1 and that's your fastest that can
be accessed at 1 cycle basically so it's
it's almost free there's some cases
where it's not free but most the time
it's like literally free so you know
you've got 32 K in the instruction cache
is only for the actual instructions so
that doesn't really matter but the data
cache we have 32 K I mean it matters but
not for what you're talking about
so the 32k of l1 cache is per core and
then the 256 K of l2 cache is also per
core right so that means we actually
have
32k of l1 206 k FL - there's a concept
of cash inclusivity and exclusivity I
believe the cash is on x64 generally
inclusive meaning if if you look at the
total here there's two ways of thinking
about this one way is that you have 206
k FL 2 + 32 K of l1 that would mean your
total amount would be 256 plus 32 okay
right if they're inclusive however which
means that everything that's in the l1
has to also be in the l2 that means you
just have to fix K because this 3 2 K is
just a subset of this tuner 56 K I think
these chips are inclusive meaning I'm
pretty sure anything that's in the l1
has to also be in the l2 unless you're
using some kind of like streaming
construction that makes that not happen
for some reason but I'm pretty sure you
don't get both don't quote me on that I
haven't looked recently so I don't know
maybe it's exclusive maybe it's
inclusive I don't know but either way
that's how much you have per core so on
this particular machine it means I have
four times that if I'm running
multi-threaded I have each core has 256
K right so I actually have a total of
one megabyte cache addressable right
because if each if I do a perfect job
segmenting my workload I can actually
use 20 56 K on each core and I have four
cores right and again I think it's
inclusive which means we don't get an
extra 32 that is just how much L 1 I
have so I have 4 times 32 l1 so on time
on l1 I have 4 times 2 and 56 if I want
to talk about total on core cash because
again I think it's inclusive so you
don't add and then I have off chip cash
and that's the l3 that takes longer to
go to it's like more than twice as slow
than as the l2 usually the l2 by the way
is like 14 cycles so this is like one
cycle this is like 14 cycles I think
this is like 48 cycles or 40 cycles or
something just a lot worse but still
better than memory
can be like hundreds of cycles the l3 is
shared so the l3 is actually shared by
all the course and you can usually yeah
there you go um so you can usually find
diagrams that show this stuff stamped
out so here's like the chip that's
probably like roughly like the chip
that's in mine maybe yeah I don't really
know I'm not sure which sky like this is
taken from obviously there's differences
between them but if you take a look at
how it's laid out so if you imagine how
the cache is work you're gonna have
something like there's cash in here that
we all talk to and then there's cash in
here that only this core talks to right
and there's a huge chunk of wasted crap
off to the side because until frickin
doesn't know how to make things useful
so this is just garbage so basically
like the problem that we have is that
you know the perk or cache has to be
thought about carefully to make it good
use of it the shared cache just kind of
works right so that part no matter how
bad your multi-threading is you're going
to get that much caching because
everyone's asking for it from the same
place but the perk or caching is
important to think about because that's
a smaller size the l3 is always bigger
smaller size and it's like gotta be
managed properly per core right so so I
don't know if that answered your
question at all but again I've never
heard of an l0 cache I don't know what
that would mean there are other things
on here this is what I was trying to say
that you know maybe someone calls it
analysis your I have no idea I've never
heard of that
but if you look what happens when you go
through here so ostensibly there's like
16 general-purpose registers on an x64
core or something right hmm 8 xmm
registers 16 why am i matters 32 CMMS
and all that right but actually those
are just names they actually are just
names for things that's not actually how
many registers there are the actual
number of registers come from the
register file and this thing here the
register alias table I always called the
register allocation table but they call
the register alias table so oh well um
or rat for short the rat actually hands
out slots where things are stored and it
can reuse those names so you can
actually access way more registers than
the number of registers that you
ostensibly have names for because it can
reuse them right so in some sense this
which is the thing that this hands out
accesses to these are the ones for like
general purpose and these are the ones
for the wide registers there's actually
you could think of that almost as in l0
cache if you want to because it's
actually 180 memory locations like
64-bit memory locations or 128-bit
memory locations and this side or
whatever actually on this chip it would
be xx face turn 56 bit that are closer
even than the l1 right so you know
okay cool yeah so l0 I just haven't
heard but yeah if that answer your
question great l 1 is the first cache on
a sky lake the first real cache is out
one they don't call it l0 there's no
reason they couldn't but they just don't
how much time I expecting to shave off
by making the routine wide so I don't
know because that assembly language code
that it generated was so bad that I
could believe we'd shave a lot off the
street
um a lot I would like to get under four
seconds yes I think we can make dramatic
speed improvements to this code now now
that it's all set up the way I want I
think we can get pretty low and yeah
just to Risa mirai's so if you want to
know how many cache lines the core can
hold you just take the number that you
see for the particular cache you're
wondering about so 32 K in this case and
you divide by the cache line size which
is 64 bytes right so
[Music]
there is a sort of separate thing you
have to worry about and it's this part
here so one of the things that they do
in cash is just because they're hardware
and they can't be super fancy they've
got to be fast is saying that you know
so so the naive calculation is just like
well you know it's 32 K right
and it's a 64 byte cache line so like
it's 512 lines right but it doesn't
actually store 512 lines arbitrarily it
can only actually store 512 lines of
cash if those caches don't overlap if
those lines don't overlap their
addresses right so what this 8 way means
is that when it goes to look to see if a
particular memory address is in the
cache there's only 8 slots for any
particular lookup formula so like if you
imagine and you could do some reading on
this here right so I don't know why
there's little creatures in here but you
know there are the point here is that
basically when you actually go to put
stuff in a cache there's some kind of
tag they used to identify the memory
address that is not the full memory
address and it goes into the cache in a
slot like a hash table using that tag
basically and then inside that slot
there's whatever the way whatever that
number is this that's how many different
cache lines at stores in that slot so if
all of the data
that you happen to want to store in the
cash all has the same tag you actually
only get eight cash lines right so you
may have like drastically drastically
less cash than you think you do if your
particular addressing scheme that you
are using it doesn't play well so like
let's say that what it uses for the tag
is like we know it's an eight-way cash
so like we know that it's 32 times 10 24
divided by 8 so we know that there's
4096 actual slots right and each one of
those slaw oh no that's not true because
the it's 3k so we have to first divide
by that so it's the 512 so it's 5 till
divided by 8 so there's 64 slots and
each one of them has 8 things in it
right so let's suppose that it just uses
the bottom 4 well it's not gonna use the
bottom 4 bits cause it's 64 but so let's
suppose it uses it gets rid of the
bottom 6 bits and uses the next 4 bits
to figure out where in the cash this
thing should go if you just so happened
to be strided by that amount when you
are when you're walking through memory
all of your accesses will hit the same
cache line and you'll only end up with 8
times 64 bytes of cash you'll have 512
bytes of cash right so that's called
aliasing usually and it's a very hard
thing to know is happening so you kind
of have to think about your cash
addressing it's a really advanced topic
so it's probably not so much to go into
now but it's something to be aware of so
nominally speaking if you're just
addressing flat linear blocks of memory
the cache will probably get you 32 okay
if you're doing is something weird you
may have to quickly just go verify that
your addressing scheme and the CPUs
cache tagging scheme
don't conflict because if they do you're
in a lot of trouble hopefully that makes
sense okay all right thanks everyone for
joining me for hopes on handmade here
it's about pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
the series at home you always peer to
the game on handmade here at organic
come to the source code so you can
follow along with it at home I'll be
back here tomorrow to finish up that
routine and hopefully we'll get some
good speed winds out of that and we can
continue optimizing our lighting I think
it's gonna come out really nicely
because then I Chi said there's also a
thing I want to do that I think will
make that raycasting much faster so I
think as we go I think we're gonna end
up with some some really good
performance here that's it for today
hope to see you back here tomorrow till
then have fun printer everyone and I'll
see any internet piggies everybody