hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero sure we go to complete game
live on stream um we
are going to start doing our asset tag
matching stuff today where we were just
cleaning up that system and i think we
had a really
simple way of just making it nice so
we're just gonna finish doing that
uh and start kind of poking around with
the implications
before we get started i did want to
mention at molly rocket we do have
a sale for the holidays on
yeah the infinite so if you
are in the mood for cat space adventures
or space cat adventures if you will uh
all of the
stuff is on sale as you can see here and
in fact i've got one
on my desk even you can see it
it's like a really really good it came
out fantastic
like we could not be happier with how
good this thing looks
the printers we worked with on this were
absolutely fantastic
so if you're looking for some cat space
adventures
um this holiday season for you
or the you know space and or cat lovers
in your family we've got you covered and
that's just me on the infinite.com you
can also
find it on mollyrocket.com in fact you
can even find
little buttons at the bottom of our page
now um
i finally started to clean this stuff up
i haven't really had a chance to do it
all
yet though but our our sites will slowly
converge on something more usable so
that should hopefully be good
um international ship included no
uh domestic shipping is included
international shipping isn't included
because international shipping
is so expensive these days that it's
more than the entire cost of
like the entire price like it's often
twenty dollars or more to ship something
to uh to ship a one pound book which is
what it is
um so like yeah international shipping
is fantastically expensive
uh probably for good reason i mean i'm
sure it
just takes like we don't have low fuel
transport
solved yet um so i'm sure it's just
very expensive to get something from one
place to another even if it's fairly
light
um as long as it is a package of some
kind and not just this
you know infinitely thin little letter
or something
i'm assuming that there's just no way to
get that price down to like
you know reasonable price domestic
shipping is already quite expensive it's
ten dollars
um at least but the
international is ridiculous it's like 20
or something and so it's it's ridiculous
when you think about just how expensive
that is
compared to the cost of the actual
product right
um but that's just how it is right
someday hopefully they'll get that down
because it's nice to have physical goods
but you know they're
they're just they're difficult to move
around
all right so
let's go ahead and get started um i am
going to go
ahead and switch to
handmade code directory and get us back
into four coder
so uh also i'm going to turn off the i
gotta put in an automatic toggle for the
cursor trails so essentially where we
left off
i believe we left compiler in right yeah
so essentially where we left off is when
we
go to get an asset uh previously what
we'd been doing
is we'd been taking the tags
that we got as vectors and we would
basically say
look for each tag
you've got a like
you you had like a weight for how
heavily you wanted to match that tag
and then you also had like whether or
not you know what the particular tag was
and whatever
and that was just kind of ridiculous
because we didn't really need it like it
was massively over
generalized for what we ended up needing
in the asset system
you know it's that's system's been in
there since like
really really early on it's just the
first thing we threw in
and now that we know like what the
actual
situation is it's you know we should go
ahead and and make sure we've got
something reasonable like so
we want to make sure that we have
something that aligns
with the actual asset lookups we need to
do otherwise we're just wasting a bunch
of time
and adding complexity and difficulty
into the system for no reason
so what we want to do here is
we want to change from this system where
we're passing this
match vector and instead just using the
tag hash so i believe we want to just
get rid of this
entirely right so if we look down at
like when we do
get bitmap and so on uh what we want to
do is change these to just take
uh asset tag hashes and then
the match vector oh i guess we already
did change it to a v4
so it's just it's only this one it's
wrong so then the match vector
uh is just going to be the thing that
looks up
into like the grid right
so what we're gonna assume uh is that
you know there's there's essentially a
tag hash which tells you
which source template you were looking
at so
for example you know it would identify
roughly the png that you're looking at
and then the match vector would be
something that tells you
okay inside that specific png
what were you actually going to pull out
of it right
and so the tag hash basically tells you
what and the match vector tells you
which and since we don't want to have to
worry
about exactly how the art assets are
created in this sense what we want to do
is make it so that the tag hash itself
when you look up and you find the asset
in question
we want that asset to tell you which
portion
of the match vector it should be
extracting
right so the match vector
that we pass in will now instead of
being some big strong thing it's just
always going to be
fixed v4 and it will have in it a couple
different parameters
that you can pull out for matching and
there'll be things like facing direction
and expression or something so like
facing direction
expression and you know variant
maybe i don't know what they would be
but there'd be like three or four
things in there right and then when we
look up in the tag hash
you would apply the match vector by
at the tag hash would tell you how to
you know grab the pieces of the match
vector that you actually need
if that makes sense
so looking at this what the first thing
we need to do is just
say all right so if we're going by asset
tag hash
then you know this also needs to be a v4
it's not going to be an asset match
vector in fact
asset match vector would not really be a
thing anymore so these uh are just not
gonna be important anymore i don't think
uh unless
i'm unless we already changed it and i'm
misremembering
um because oh well no you know what i
think i was
i think maybe we changed it to this
already just so we could have
an integer that lines up right so
so that this code doesn't have to be the
thing
that changes floats to ins as they come
in
we just assume that the uh the code on
the outside
like did the did the mapping did the
truncation to
uh the correct values so yeah i guess
that's just basically saying look it's
picking it out
from uh this set so it's really this one
that we want to change
like so uh and the same would be true
from
basically everything else so instead of
having asset vector which would not
exist anymore
and i don't know if that still does it
does
so the instead of these ridiculous
things which are unwieldy and terrible
uh we're just gonna get rid of those and
now everybody who
does a match uh will always
take just the the tag hash and a match
vector
and that's what they'll use from now on
and you won't need the basic category
anymore
either uh and we also don't call like
this
get random bitmap from so we'll just you
know get rid of it we can always add
them back in but it wouldn't look like
that anyway there wasn't like an
important piece of code to
save so i also don't know like
if get first bitmap in this case is
relevant anyway like i don't know
if we ever actually use that um
i don't know can i search for a string
get first sound
or bitmap from
so i don't see any evidence that that
ever gets used
anyway so i think we should be able to
get rid of that
whether for sound from
uh exists doesn't look like it uh
so i'm guessing that we can just
actually stick
with real mass matching
at the moment so i'm hoping that we can
just you know do something like this
where everybody now will take the tag
hash and the match vector
and we will be able to
always just pass those through and have
the matching system work fairly
straightforward
so the only thing i'm not sure about is
since
fonts are kind of a special case because
what gets pulled out of there is just
characters
obviously the match vector weight vector
nonsense uh
wouldn't really make any sense i don't
know why we would want to
bother with that but it may be the case
that just
this system still sort of works so for
the for the immediate
you know for just the immediate test i'm
gonna assume that we can
still use this this way but since we're
in the process of optimizing if it turns
out
that looks a little too onerous if it
turns out
that i don't like the look of that we
may make the font code take something
different
on purpose there so
assuming that we call uh get
best match asset from um
if if that's just now gonna be called
get asset from because we're not really
doing a best match anymore
it's a direct lookup or at least a close
to a direct lookup
then now these functions are all correct
and really we're just talking about this
one now
right and what we'd like to do is
we would like to go ahead and
make it so that it's very clear what
happens
when we you could you could even see
that we've sketched it out
um unlike the old one we want to make it
very clear what happens
when we go to look up an asset we want
that to
um produce a result extremely quickly
so what you can see what we did here is
we said all right so
suppose we take the tag hash which is
like
a pre-hashed value right
and then we take the match vector which
is
like additional information so like the
tag hash rate is something
that would be um
when you actually specify it you can
pre-hash that and just store the hashed
results
but the match vector has to vary like
per frame so if you imagine something
like facing direction
when the character's like turning around
and such
it's going to change what's in that
match vector so effectively what we're
doing here is we're passing
passing it almost like a partial hash um
and then we're passing in like an
additional part
to go into the hash so then what we do
is we're pulling out
pieces of the hash right so we're
basically saying we're gonna take these
things and then we're gonna hash those
together
like so right and the thing that
you know strikes me about this is
honestly i'm not sure that we really
need to bother
so if we take a look at like what
happens in something like hash 32
what you can see is we are already doing
a fold here where we do uh
and you know where we where we mix in
um
i'm not sure how to say this correctly
so
what you can see here is we've got our
hash set up so that we start with a
initial value which is these two u64s
and then we're going to like run it
through aes deck
to like basically you know permute those
values and turn them into a fairly
randomly distributed
set of bits that's still unique to the
the input values
but my question here is just should we
just go ahead
and make that be something that happens
for all of the input values
because if we assume that there is a
limited number
of these match vector entries that are
actually important
um like we've done here where we said
well we're just going to put
four of them in their total anyway
if that's the case then why not just
hash that in
with it you know so
for example in here where we have this
value in this value
the uh what's going to happen with aes
deck for example
right is aes deck is effectively bit
scrambling and an xor
so it will do the bit scramble
in fact i can show you
maybe in the intel intrinsic skin
i don't know if it actually
uh will show us or not
yeah so what you can see here
is the action of this instruction is
it's going to do a bunch of bit uh like
randomization right so it's going to
like shuffle the bits around
all over the place like so
and then it's going to xor in whatever
the the extra parameter was
right so it's the shuffling that we
really
care about we don't care about the
xoring but the nice part about the
xoring
is that what we could do is xor in
the other values right so i don't know
how strong of a hash we actually want to
have here but for example what we can do
is instead
of folding in the seed like so
what we could do here is fold in an
additional
value right so
uh because we know we really want this
to be
like i said something that something
that wants to be
really efficient uh what we can do is
just say
why don't you just pass us like you know
the
the address to hash from uh so something
like
you know
i'm trying to think of like how we were
doing that tag so
if we did something more like this so
we we said um
there's a an extra like 128
bit so there's there's you know like
i'm not sure what to call this but
something like uh
the extra 16 byte thing to fold in here
it would just be like it's not
free but it's like close to free
right so we can do this where we
effectively say
if you want us to hash two hundred and
you know
two in a sense two match vectors
right um we can we can do that for you
you know what i'm saying so especially
another thing we could do
is say like you know if we said this
right now what you could do is say that
there's two match vectors
one that's the got the hashes in it and
and the other
that's you know something else right
um and so we may even want this to be a
uh like a very specific kind of function
that actually takes
you know something specific here and i'm
not sure
um again i'm not sure exactly how we
want stuff to flow to that but
this would give us a fairly well
distributed hash
from any two
uh 128 bit values like that and so
you know um
let's let's just let's just see about
what we're going to pass here
so where where are we actually so here's
here's where we're actually doing this
right so you can see
like an example of us producing these
values
like the you know weight vectors and and
whatever else garbage
uh that we're making here um and you can
see us calling the get best bat
uh best match bitmap so we know we're
gonna come
into here uh with some kind of a tag
combination right so it's going to be
like a bunch of tags
that we that we combine together um
and just looking at that you know yeah
it seems like we're probably just going
to want to store
i mean there's it's really just pretty
straightforward for us to just store
these as hashes
so i feel like what we want to do is
almost introduce just this hashtag
as a thing because these tags as well
are you know what when we're doing these
tags what are they going to be
like they might be just like a series of
16s or something
and so i feel like we maybe just want to
make this a little bit more general so
like maybe we pull this out
actually and we go into here oops
um into the intrinsics
and we maybe you know make like a hash
thing i don't know like handmade hash
sounds that sounds
um yeah
it's handmade hash um so if you imagine
like
a thing that's got the hash stuff in it
right um and
you imagine that we we think about this
a little bit more um and
you know i could pull the intrinsic into
the intrinsics file we could have just a
uh something here for for
bit scrambling so you know we make a an
intrinsic
that's like bit scramble or something
like this
and it would just need i i guess i don't
know
um how we would be exposing that
because one of the problems that we have
yeah
we'll leave it maybe for a little bit
later because i feel like
in simdee we already kind of did
put this stuff in there right so
we probably want to unify those uh
into like we want to put that stuff
into a more centralized location at some
point but now is probably not the
the time to do it but the point is
if you imagine something that looks like
this
so we've got sort of a you know like a
a hash value
something like this
and we just assumed that everyone uses
this thing
when they want to communicate with the
hashing system so you can
stick four u32s in there or two
you know these or even like for tags for
example
you can put eight tags into one of them
and then what we would do is just
there's gonna be
a thing that says that if you give us
two of any two of these that you've
filled out and we don't care
like which you know what they are um
we will produce like a a well a
well-distributed hash
from um from those and
and you know maybe these should be
called like hashable value
in the sense that this is the things
that you put in these are not
hashed at all they're they're just
things that you
bear stuck in there um and then you
would pass a hashable value to one of
these things
and like so and it gives you back
the 32-bit lookup value that you
actually need
right so if you
want to do something like that pretty
straightforward you you don't have to
use this
set anymore instead what we would do
is we just say okay we are going to
uh do the load so
we're going to take the the value here
and in fact to be honest this really
doesn't have to be here
we know how big the thing is so it's
really that's fine
we're going to load it unaligned anyway
it doesn't need that
um additional piece of information so we
can just leave that be
um so basically what we'll say is load
the 128 bits
out of this thing um which is the whole
thing
go ahead and munge it with the seed
uh like so so you know go ahead and
munch the value
and well that's a bug
in fact why do we have two i don't even
know why we have two of these like why
wouldn't this just be
load the hash value and hash the hash
value right
like so so yeah
i think that would be all we would
really need and
you know maybe i was a little
overzealous uh
in making this a separate file you know
i admit that
because if we look at what this is doing
um it's arguably a little bit stupid
right like i mean how simple is that uh
we don't really need a separate file for
just these two things
um so you know maybe but maybe we leave
it around as an aspirational fantasy
in the sense that you know maybe we want
to have
in the future some more
fancy hash stuff uh that we're gonna use
for i don't know like verifying a file
or something like that
um you know there's obviously sort of
bare arguments we could make
uh about that um they're not probably
good arguments
but you know what are you gonna do
uh so yeah so i think that's probably
good enough for now
um and then what we can do is any place
where we were previously gonna do
something like that
we can just sort of have you know
uh we can just sort of have that in
there so
i i think what that would generally mean
is that like
in this asset hash entry thing where
we're gonna have the hash table
all we're really gonna do is you know
match
against i guess the source hashable
so if we want to do
yeah because this would have all of the
information in there so if we wanted to
we would just store
uh the hashable in here and say
that's the full set of things so two
64-bit values
is what we're going to match against um
because that should be able to uniquely
identify
the thing because that would give you
assuming that you actually just kept
everything as u16s
that would give you eight values which
is like the four tags plus the four
uh vector values and that should just
work
right um i mean you could even get
fancier
and have you know it by bite
if you really wanted to and that would
allow us to do stuff like
having the indexes be only eight bits so
you could have
more of them or more tags right um
so i don't know like there's a number of
different ways we could do this
i'm not sure which ones make sense we
could make this thing
be a little bit clearer laid out as well
in the future if we want to i'm not sure
um but we just would want to make sure
that it's still the same
basic 128 bit structure because that's
what we know we can hash quickly
right um so in here what we'd like to do
is just make sure that this thing now
takes
all of the hash stuff that we had before
and just feeds it into here so
but i think at that point like we
literally just have i don't know
if we actually bothered to put in the
hash in here yet
um looks like we already did right
um and when we say does this need to be
a prime hash
i'm not sure why we asked that question
because
we must have not really been thinking
particularly much about this uh because
obviously
if we've gone through and done a
well-distributed hash then it doesn't
need to be a prime hash
right so i don't know
i don't know why we would have thought
that would have needed to be a prime
hash
it's a reasonable question but i don't
know the answer
um the other thing that's interesting
about this is we could
you know if we wanted to now start to
think about potentially
eliminating the centralized asset store
anyway like we could just say that
everything goes through the hash now
so as this becomes more powerful we may
decide to start eliminating some of
these other things
this for example is now completely uh
unnecessary so we wouldn't need the tag
arrays at all
i don't think which would eliminate a
huge amount
a bunch of complexity from the system so
that seems pretty good um
as well like just looking through you
know what the
yeah like what
just thinking about it it seems like
that would be pretty good
so i think that's all well and good um
so let's go ahead and keep going from
there uh but yeah but this is a little
suspect now because you're like well
can't we just you know maybe we can just
sort of store this stuff directly in
there
it's the thing i'm thinking you know
like like why do we actually need like
this right here
um we could just make that be the thing
that's in the hash directly
and so i'm not sure
why we wouldn't do that
in fact i'm going to go ahead and say
let's just go ahead and do that
right because the only benefit the only
thing we would get
is over mapping of tags well you know so
i guess
i guess if you we should probably do it
without that first because if you assume
that there will be
multiple tag sets that will all map to
the same
asset then we would want
this right we do want an indirection
here because we want to be able to map
multiple tags to the same asset but
my assumption would be that if we were
going to do something like that or if we
are doing something with that currently
it's probably being done in more of like
a range
fashion right so
we would be doing something like mapping
a interval of hash values
and it seems like we can probably make
that work
in some other way like for the the cases
we actually care about
having an asset respond uh
specifically in that way i feel like it
should be able to work right
um
i mean i could be wrong uh but it feels
like it should be able to work
hmm
so i guess here's what i will say
maybe that's not true like maybe i was a
little bit overzealous here and the
previous thing was actually a bit better
so think about this so let's suppose
that we had a
entity that wants to map
a bunch of different match vectors all
to the same
thing if we go through the hash
table for that yeah so so all right
i will admit to being dumb here um so
or rather i will admit to being smarter
in the past than i am
in in the present right so if we
consider what was happening here
with uh the with the asset
with having these two things be separate
then i guess the reason why this is
actually a better idea
meaning why we why we would prefer
this to the the previous
uh way of doing thing or the the the one
that i just sketched out
is because if we actually do do it this
way
and fix the bug so don't you know
don't leave the bug that was in there so
that part was a good change
if we leave it this way so that we're
taking in
a tag hash we're looking up a particular
asset piece of information and then
we're matching against it or whatever
so i i think we can safely remove
the the part where we
um we can safely remove
the part where we do packing or any of
this stuff here
that doesn't have to happen but what we
would do is still do a tag hash
look up to figure out which um
or or more specifically maybe we just
use the tag hash
to look up the cache line like of the
hash line like we would normally do
we loop through those and then we just
match against the entire match vector
as we go right so the hash entries
are just like this sort of a thing
um we don't do this so we don't need to
load a category
we just go ahead and take
the hash of the thing that we actually
get
right we do not hash the coordinates at
all
so those don't happen
um we map into the tag array
um i'm sorry the uh assets by tag
table we look up in there and we just
step through
each asset looking to see which ones
match
and that i think would just give us
what we want as long as the asset itself
has a suppression field
right so as long as the asset itself
can mask off parts of the match vector
that it doesn't care about it says i
match
everything in this part of the match
vector then i think
it just works right
so that's actually just fine and then we
you know i'm sad to say
um you know i'll
i'll go ahead and do the you know the
sad sort of like
where we delete our our code that we
just added
but it's okay it was it was learning
experience so we don't actually need the
hash
that's gone uh but you know maybe we'll
come back someday
who knows
so oh whoops i turned on power mode
i mean every power mode is excellent
maybe we'll leave that on but i'm going
to turn off battery saver mode
so if we go back to get asset from um
uh so yeah so i think really all we have
to do here is take the tag hash
oh power mode is broken it looks like
no it's not so i guess something i guess
the i'm not sure what was happening down
at the the base of the thing there but
uh all right so anyway if we go ahead
and we
yeah so so why why is it i wonder what's
going on there there must be a bug in
power mode which is terrible because
power mode's like the most important
part of everything
um so what we want to do here
is once we grab the hash slot in
question
we just want to loop through uh
the assets in that hash line so in the
asset
system here
i need this to not there we go
so if we loop through the the assets in
the system
like i said we can probably say like all
right we'll get rid of hash entry
um and instead what we'll do is we'll
pack the hash entry stuff directly into
the assets so that we don't have to like
hop around
for no reason and we'll go ahead and
place these in here so
you know in addition to the stuff that
we have for the asset otherwise we'll
have the match
vector um and the tag hash
uh and so those two will
though those will just be there for us
to sort of step through and grab
uh and so we need an ability to link to
the next one i don't think there's any
reason we can't just use a pointer here
so we can just do like next in in tag
hash sort of a thing
right and what we can do is
grab the first one out so
we'll like you know loop through the
assets that we want to check
uh this is called the the assets by tag
right and we know it's the hash slot
that we're looking up here
we would then just loop until we're done
and so that's all the stuff that we we
would actually need to loop over
i don't know again i don't know why
farcoder's indentation is all broken i
don't know if that's something that
you know when that changed or what
happened someone should tell me at some
point what's going on with that
because it used to do the right thing
like that and now it doesn't
i don't think so i'm not sure what
what's going on there but
who knows um anyway so
once in here we just need to validate
these two things
so if we match both of these the match
vector and the tag hash
then we're good and the part that i was
talking about before
is like essentially these are just going
to be self masking
so when you look up a particular asset
you're going to go ahead and say that
that
asset could uh and this replaces sort of
the fuzzy matching we had before which
is something that's much more concrete
we just need something that will mask
these values
like we just need something that will
take these values
and get rid of ones that we don't want
that this asks
that are not important for this asset so
if the tag
hash matches it will then say okay let's
build the appropriate match vector by
trimming off the pieces that we don't
care about and so all we need is like an
efficient way
um of like creating that mask
and to be honest i'm
not really sure what the efficient way
is
to create that mask
i guess we don't really need to think
about at the moment but it's like what
you'd want to do is have a thing where
you could load
you'd want to be able to load like a
value out that would then
select
select the lanes of like 30 bit you
you could probably do it pretty easily
with like
a shuffle so like you'd you'd load like
the shuffle pattern
uh for sse or something like that and
you'd just like
allow it to shuffle for you
a thing that had you know
imagine in cindy loading something in
that had 32-bit lanes where like
you know the first 32-bit lane is all
ones and then the rest are zeros
and you just load in a shuffle pattern
that says
which to take for each lane that could
trivially replicate out
you know ones zeros one zeros right and
then you just do the
and um so
i'm going to put a little to do in here
that basically says like to do
um the matching
test could be done
potentially quite efficiently
in cmd and so we're gonna say that
there's
like a you know some kind of a thing
here that's like the shuffle pattern or
the the like
uh the match pattern
and i'm not sure what the easiest way to
do that would be
but i'm guessing what we want to do is
just use like
the the pieces of that to tell us um
which one we're going to use so you know
you could imagine it basically
being packed like something like
um every two you know like uh
it's it's set up like that um
you know what i'm saying so like it's
bit wise
it basically has uh you know four
settings it's which of for each one
corresponds
to a piece of the match vector
and we could just say that like zero or
one um
in each of those bottom slots uh so we
could say like
you know
i probably want to do it in bit order
right
so we probably want something like that
and each one of those would tell us
like whether we need to care about that
particular match
right so what we would do here is say
all right we know we want to check the
tag hash
so that has to match so we'd say if
the tag hash value that we were passed
in
equals the assets tag value
like so then that's the first step
but then we also need to do a check
um and we'll build the check uh here as
well
we could just say okay we've got a match
vector
that is the uh you know the kind of
neutered vector if you will well you
know what i could do too is i could just
do
this
so you just do this uh we'd say for each
of the
indices in there so for each of the
uh the elements that we're matching
against
yeah so for each of the elements that
we're matching against
uh in the in the tag hash we want to
look up
the corresponding bit value in the match
pattern
uh and make sure that we just don't
bother
with ones where it's zero so we would
say
like you know if um
you know when i think about it i might
just write this out long hand because
it's gonna be easier
yeah i think i will so it's going to be
easier to write longhand so let's just
do it
so if we go ahead and take the match
vector
e0 and the check
match vector we can just write it like
this
so we've got these two things if they're
equal
um we just need
something in here which also says well
if the match pattern
um and you know three
right shifted down by however much we're
on
um that's the rule for each one
of the of the elements right
and so what we could do is say all right
so there's
you know uh matches it's true and you
know i guess i can do this in a for loop
if we want to write the explicit this is
one of the things that c
sucks is it can't have a for loop for
loops don't evaluate to a value which
you know
much like if statements it's just stupid
it's just a bad idea
um
but anyway so you could basically say
like
all right we start with matches
we basically just like uh and
you know we we we want to take like this
is matches
and right so we and in
all of these and then at the end if
we've got
a match uh then we're we're good to go
right so we would say result
equals whatever this whichever asset
this actually is
and i guess one problem we have here is
it looks like for pointer wise
we want to know the asset index because
that's
we actually use the asset index itself
so we could just stuff the index in here
but you know in order to
remain compliant um we could just do
u32s here right so we could just say
like u32 like check index right
and then we would say like asset start
asset equals get
asset and we would just say you know we
want
this one or something right
so assuming that we want to do that it's
the same exact code
it's just we uh we would need this
like this part has to come out so you
know this becomes a while loop because
we can't
access the variable that we need so
while check if
index is valid um we would just sort of
chain through here so we'd say
all right
loop over the indexes and we pull them
out as we go
um there's a weird so yeah someone
ryan's not here today is he
well doesn't sound like so
yeah i have to find out what's going on
with that power mode we'll have to to
to take a look at it but anyway um so if
we loop through the
the different uh indexes here then what
we could do is just say like all right
uh you know we're gonna return this one
so it's pretty straightforward so
looping over these
oops
so looking over these we just checked
the pattern we see whether or not
um these are valid
based on whether or not the pattern says
we should so if the pattern
is zero then
we will check them if it's one then we
won't
right so instead of calling this a match
pattern i guess
i'll call this a like match any
right because basically what it says is
if there's a one
in the two-bit lane that corresponds to
the thing you're checking
you match anything
and off you go right
if they're all zeros then you have to
match exactly
and if any of them are ones then you
don't have to match that lane and you're
still considered a match
now i think um
like i think that's mostly it and so
there's a couple things we have to care
about here
sort of a little bit i guess uh
which is is this um the way that we were
doing this
before we need to handle the wrapping
part
correctly um so we we do want to like
just double check that we're we're gonna
map the like facing directions
correctly and and stuff like that so
we're gonna have to take a like a look
at that
um eventually as well but you know we'll
we'll get to that we'll cross that
bridge we'll burn that bridge when we
come to it um
so now um the only thing that i think is
implied here is that
this is now like an asset id effectively
right
and i don't know if we have asset ids
as a thing
we don't um so anyway
so that's what we need there and
if these are u32s then oops that
shouldn't be a pointer
um then everything should just work and
we loop through these
it should all be fine right uh
and off we go this is not called
asset it's called check
um that is supposed to be
a c value and there we go
all right
so in theory uh that's
all we needed to do right
and now yeah like
so we have a couple different things
here that i'm not sure about so it looks
like
what we did here is we we plow an asset
category
in and then we put i mean i don't know
like here you can see who knows what
we're doing right like we're just
we're just munching these together into
a value that preserves as many bits as
we thought that we would need right
um and you know that's all fine
this semicolon you know i don't know
what that's doing there because
you don't put a semicolon there but
apparently that's that's where that is
um and if i look at this
right that if the indentation was
working which it's not and i don't know
why
um then we should end up right with with
that being the correct set of things
all right so
now what right like what do we do now
so now i think we just need
like that function we were just looking
at right like get tag hash
so i think all we really need to do now
is like this code just kind of gets
simplified quite a bit
i think
so i don't really know
why it says smoke for a particle that's
fire system probably because we were
just screwing around with it but
whatever
so we are going to say like uh
we'll just call this tags for now so
we're just going to say like get tag
hash here
right and what we want to do is we want
to say that this is particle
smoke because that's what we were doing
before
uh and then we just need asset particle
as the category
and then i think instead of get bet best
get best match bitmap from you can see
how much
smaller and simpler this code gets we
just say
give me you know this this thing right
uh i think the problem we would have
here
is just that like we probably want
multiple of these so
you know presumably you would want to
get more than just one bitmap but that's
a limitation of the particle system that
we haven't actually done anything with
uh so you know we don't really have to
care about that particularly much
now for these we don't want to have to
always pass
in all of the tags so i'm guessing that
what we probably want to do
is just say like all right for each of
the asset tag ideas that we have here
we'll just assume that they're none
unless somebody says otherwise
right
so
just to read that a little clearer there
so we assume that there always has to be
an asset category maybe we should say
there's always at least the first one
there
um but uh but i don't know
uh and then we just do get bitmap uh
is it just get called getbitmap no
what's it called get best bitmap
guess matt get best match bitmap from
yeah
uh and then for the asset matching here
what we would say i think
is just like look if you don't have a
match vector
then you don't right because you
wouldn't need to have one
if you just pass in all zeros then if
there's a
basically a default uh value
that's what you'll get right um
i think that would be pretty much it so
at that point uh now we just have to go
clean up
the code that was doing other stuff and
i think because we sort of
i don't know maybe we did a good job i
don't want to say that offhand because
maybe we didn't
but i feel like we ended up doing a
thing that's like really direct and
straightforward very simple
would be quite fast and
as an extra added benefit uh
is super easy to port so in this case i
think when you say get
uh best match sound from like in this
case you can even just collapse this
whole thing
like down to like just this one line
right because all it was was a tag bloop
here uh so all you would say
is uh
get tag hash
tag hash there you go um
is get tag hash with the two things that
you were passing before and then you
delete all this code
right uh and i think that's it
like that's that's all there is to it
right so that seems really good
uh and so all we now have to do is port
all that code
that was doing that into something
simpler that's nice and efficient and
clean
um we don't have to worry about all the
garbage we were doing before which seems
really good
now here's the part where we care about
this little snippet of code
um so in here right we want to prepare
this match vector and we want the match
vector
to like make some sense um and so what
we have to do is figure out what are the
things that are actually going to go
into this match vector
and the problem that we have here is
like i have absolutely no idea how we
want this thing laid out
and so what we probably want to do is
make a wild guess
about like what this match vector is
going to have in it
um and
probably it's going to be something like
you know
i have no idea what it's going to be
like
we know a few things that we have right
so maybe we just start by talking about
what those are
so maybe we say asset match
vector elements uh and we just
say like match element
and we've just got these four here right
and
it's similarly like you know we can just
say like oh it's
well there's however many there are
right
so we could just say well what are you
know what are these things so like what
are the different values that we're
actually going to talk about having in
here
and we knew that facing direction is one
that we look up on we know that variant
is one that we look up on
and i i don't actually know
if there's any other things at least at
the moment
that we actually you know that we
actually
want in there um because we don't have a
lot of other
parametric stuff so it may be that like
you know like that's
it for now right and so it's not even
like you know
and we could we could try to always make
sure this is like reserved at the right
size or something and i don't know what
we want to do there but like we could
just say that
right uh and another thing that we could
do here
is we could say if we wanted to there's
more
that there's like less room
because we we don't have like we know
we're not gonna have four billion
variants of something right that's not
gonna happen
um we don't have the art budget for that
that you you know red dead redemption
probably has
4 billion assets in it but we're not
gonna
so anyway
what i was trying to say uh is
i would like to um
make it so that this is as like
self-explanatory as possible and
as simple as possible because this is
the one part of the system that doesn't
get handled by the hash
right it we have to check individual
elements to make sure
to see which one we've got and so
you know it's the one part that we can't
that has to be sort of like a
a slower traversal of some kind right
and we can still try to make sure that
reversal isn't too slow but
it's it's not like the tags which are
exact matches
so the exact matches can just go
directly through the hash table and we
can know that they'll be like very very
efficient
so you know we'll see
all right so moving along from there um
if we go ahead and assume
that we're just going to use
facing direction and variance then i
don't actually
know if we care about variant much in
here
but if we take a look at the match
vector
which is going to be this
then really all we have to do is fill in
that one
facing direction value
and the problem that we're going to have
here is that the facing direction
uh whatever that may be and
oops i
forgot what it was so it's this this
right here
um that's going to be a floating point
value and we need to like
bucket that floating point value in
there somehow
right and
we want it to be periodic so
the facing direction itself like i don't
know where that's actually getting
um computed
so yeah like it's just an
angle right it's just an angle from zero
to
two pi probably
which is you know dumb but
so if we imagine that we want this thing
to map into a facing direction the
facing direction should be
between 0 and 4 where 0 is what the
match you would get
when the thing is you know
facing right my assumption is that we
could just do something at least for the
time being here where we just say
all right well so really what we're
talking about here
is that we want to like take the facing
direction
and we want to like remove
from the facing direction probably like
pi 32 uh over four so like right we we
want to take
uh
a quarter um
of the so if we imagine the circle right
we want to take a quarter of a circle
um not a quarter of a circle a uh
eighth of a circle and move back so that
we're talking about the quarter of a
circle
um that that would be encompassed there
so
if you imagine like the facing direction
is
0 to 0.25
that would map to zero but so would
uh the yeah so i guess
um
so i guess what you really would do is
something like this
is that right so you would effectively
say look i want to divide the facing
direction
by a quarter pi so
you know if we imagine this constant
here
right like called quarter pi
um we would multiply this by quarter pi
and then we would round it to a real
number
right i mean to an integer
and so if we did this we would now have
like which
qua quarter uh which uh
octant of the circle you were in so
zero is the first octant one two three
four five six seven
and now all we really need to do is we
need to make sure
that seven and zero both map to zero
one and two mapped to one
and etc etc right so
yeah like i think we just
take this
we take
it's not it's not particularly pretty
i'm going to do a little mapping here
so here's what we would want to happen
again what is up with the indentation
like so indentation in foreclosure used
to work and now it just doesn't at all
is that some aspect of
fork or flurry or did did the
indentation
break at some point
is the energy because virtual white
space is disabled but indentation is
supposed to work
anyway right like indentation's supposed
to work whether or not virtual white
space is
on or not right like it's supposed to be
able to indent the code so
so i'm not sure um
so yeah i i don't know what to do about
it like indentation's like really
severely broken as far as i can tell um
but i'm not sure
we may need alan to like fix it because
it used to work
that's the thing like so so it broke i
guess
or something and probably needs to be
fixed
um so
that should be fixed because it used to
work you know what i'm saying
like it regressed
i mean at the very least you need to be
able to have a comment
like that's not gonna work right like
that's
that's not good um and that used to work
just fine
so
okay that's even weirder um
what the heck
all right well i don't know what to make
of it
um so anyway
uh what i wanted to do here was just say
look let's
try and say what we want to have happen
here
all right so these
um
or what we would get uh if we divide
it into quadrants we're going to get 0
to 7
and we want our mapping to look like
this
right so we want to say
after we've divided out we want to go
ahead and take
zero and map it to zero we want one and
two
to map to one we want
three and four to map to two we want
five and six to map to three
and so on yeah and
so if you imagine what's gonna happen
here we can pretty easily
accomplish the middle part because that
is just
negative one you know subtract one
divide by two
right and that gives you
uh what you want or i should say add add
one and divide by two
right so if you imagine one plus one
divided by two equals one
right um and well
i should right so if you imagine that
our equation here is just going to be
you take the thing you add one you
divide by two
uh then that's going to equal what we
want right and the same thing would be
true here
2 plus 1 divided by 2
is also equal to 1 because remember
we're integers here so we truncate
3 plus 1 divided by 2 is actually equal
to 2 and so on
so we know that we can produce the
middle part of the table
by just doing this value here
and in theory this part the first part
where we do zero plus one divided by two
that will also produce zero
because again because of truncation we
haven't quite hit 2 yet
so our only real problem is that mr
7 down here so 7 plus 1 divided by 2
is actually going to be equal to 8. so
i think all we really have to do
is just handle that one case and we
should be able to do that
by modding by eight and if we mod by
eight
that should be able to turn into just a
mask because modding by eight is the
same
as just masking off the upper bits right
so i think we can produce an extremely
efficient
uh way to produce this
we just do one floating point multiply
to produce the facing direction index
um
and all we have to do here is say like
okay it's just going to be equal to
the facing direction index plus one
divided by two
right which as we know would just be a
shift down right so we just shift it
down
once um and then we end off the part we
don't care about so we know that we want
the bottom
three bits
uh but anything higher than that we
don't want right so we want bit one and
bit two
and bit four right so we just want
that so i think
this is a pretty efficient way of
producing the actual index value we
actually wanted
right which is a number between zero and
three
that tells us which uh of the facing
direction sprites to pick out
um so i'm pretty sure that that's
you know going to be a nice efficient
way to do that right you can see
that it's pretty straightforward it's
literally just a constant multiply here
um and uh that that was wrong
this should have been
invert that right
this is m quarter pi
so we do the divide that puts us into
integer space we apply the magic formula
here and then we should
effectively have and i guess i don't
even need to put that in there i could
just put it there
right um we have the value that
we actually wanted right
and i don't know
if there's really anything else um
that may just be it so okay
so hopefully that is just it and
uh we can go from there it seems like
there's some complaints here oh
that's probably because this has to be
u16
so let me just uh let me just make this
the same way that it was before real
quick so
there's facing der index
equals facing dirt index
and i don't know if this is smart enough
to
yeah so you know we just ended this with
so like it should know that that's
totally legal but yeah whatever
cannot convert argument to
well you know what you've got a point
there
so this we probably typed in
um before we had
this as the type so it probably should
look like that
is asset tag hash like not defined
yet because of the you know the miracle
of c
um so
this is in the entity file and i guess
the
does the asset system not uh come before
that
is that the main problems i mean there's
acid.h and there's the entities so
i guess i guess yeah the answer is it
doesn't so
i guess what i would have to do there is
just say well
um you know um
maybe we put that up in file formats
and yeah i don't know if that's
sensible or not um might not be
uh but but you know i
i could see this being something that we
want to have in the file format section
because we may want to start storing
these i'm not sure
we may or may not um but we can put
those there for now
again things that you only care about
because c
plus never did bother to do the work of
actually letting you
compile your code without having to
pre-declare everything
yeah so anyway uh taking a look at what
happens here
these are all just tag hash things again
so this is again really probably pretty
straightforward so
all we would really need to update here
is the part with the
where we actually picked the variant um
and i guess the thing with the variance
is
we don't really know how many variants
there are of the things so what we were
doing
here before um
is is we let the automatic matching
system
like just kind of find
which
we let the automatic matching just
use the range from zero to one
to pick variance out and
i don't know how i feel about that one
way or the other to be completely honest
with you
um you know one one thing
i would suggest is that like probably
i it seems like a good thing to support
because you want to be able to just dump
more like grass sprites in and then they
get distributed out
so it seems like something we want to
support if we want to support it it's
not particularly hard what we would
have to do though is we'd have to have
some kind of a of a mapping piece of
information for the assets
that they use when you look at the
variant
field you'd have to do a masking
to always make sure that the tag
that you're matching against is in the
range of the assets that were actually
recorded
and
i guess i just don't have a strong
opinion about that and i don't really
know
i don't really know what i want to do
there
yeah my intuition kind of says like hey
that's like why make that system more
complicated for no real reason
when you could just say look when you're
actually talking about what the game
does
it's always going to just be in a
situation
it's always just going to be in in a
state where you do know what they how
many there are
because you know how many art assets
you're going to put into the thing
so you could just always say well you
know there's this many variants
you know this is how many variants
things get for things like grass and
smoke and whatever
but on the other hand i'm like well it
would be nice to basically say like look
just
record how many of the thing there were
and then
yeah but if you so if if you
you can't merge assets anyway because
you have to be able to distribute them
along the uniform uh
like because it's picking a random
unilateral here even the old system
couldn't have merged assets properly
because you would have had to
redistribute things
along the random unilateral which you
would require you to reprocess the art
assets anyway
so at some point you needed to know how
many there were and so what you could do
is just store how many there were
rather than complicate the matching
system what you would want to do is just
be able to look it up here
right so you wanna be able to look up
here like how many of this thing are
there
so tell me um and then i will
you know i will pick a variant
inside that range right
i i assume um
my my assumption right
so yeah i guess
so yeah i don't know that's that's a
tough one i don't think there's a good
answer to that exactly but i don't know
um also you know what i was just
realizing this is probably wrong
uh because we already did the divide by
two
so actually we really only need
to mask off we only really need to keep
the bottom two bits right
and then we should be fine
so i don't know what to do with this so
the rest of this code is trivial to
port right so if we assume that we have
the asset tag hash here
um then all we really need to do is for
each one of the things in the spec type
here
we would just do like tag hash value
or sorry tag hash equals get tag hash
um and we just patched the tags that we
were talking about
right so
um in these cases too like where we have
like cover type
i mean we could just pass the tags
instead
i i that may not be a good idea
um because we might want to do more
complex things here so i won't pull it
out
just yet but it's entirely possible that
we can like
now that we've got this we can simplify
that part rather dramatically right like
it could compress down to to very little
um because we could just have those be
stored in there
so i don't know what size being
zero or one here um that sounds like
that wants to be another parameter right
so that would be like the match vector
dot size it's assuming that size is a
thing we actually want
sorry um
what did we end up calling this match
element
yeah so assuming we actually want this
like yeah i don't know what these should
be but we're basically saying like okay
so there's
size is a thing i guess
uh and these would be
smaller
now i don't know if that's the way you
would really want to do this
because you may just want to have two
different tags like large and small
so you just tag tag cover large and tag
cover
small so i'm not sure that the size
thing really makes a whole lot of sense
there actually um
so i don't know so it's hard to say
and and i don't know i don't really know
what we would want to do there
uh that's a tough that's a tough call
we'll have to think about that
so assuming that we go ahead and do the
the tag hash thing
then in here we know that these are
always particles
so that can just be assumed
and and then we need the asset match
vector here
uh and that should just work as well
and
the rest of this code should be fine
this is the only part that's
that's a problem um the match element
very
variant here i
this would be like a random choice
essentially and it would be in some
value that we don't know what it is
right so what we need is like
max you know like the variant count for
this
thing so you'd almost need like a get
variant count
for a particular asset category so like
for this particular tag hash
what is the variant count and
that would just give you back like the
value that you need to do the random
choice in
right
um
so i mean i think it's good like i just
think yeah we probably just want to
i mean that's probably just what we want
to do like we probably just want to have
this be an element of the asset system
where like when we process the assets we
remember how many there were
and off we go i guess
i don't know so anyway that does seem
reasonable
and we could just assume that that's
what we're going to do and then this is
the only thing that really is
you know a problem here this is going to
be u16
and and so it would really only be this
that would be the problem
as far as size is concerned like i don't
know
that we really want that in there
um and so i want to look and see
in the sources like
so if i look at the base game hht
right and we go looking for like
what's happening with the size stuff
um so here you can see like there's like
a size
parameter and so i i just don't know
i just don't know that it makes sense to
like have that like why not just have
large as a specifier right
so let's take a look at the
there i mean presumably the particles
yeah so you can see like we've got
particles there's like zero
and one and stuff so i would say like
that should probably just be another tag
so so i i don't think we actually want
to actually use a match element for that
because i don't know that that we would
get much
out of it like what's the point right
like
we're not going to have like 30
different sizes of something
so there might if we want to say that
there's a large one of these and a small
one of this then that seems like
something we would do
but i don't know that that we need like
some other thing um
that's just my i don't know it's just my
intuition it may be wrong
um but like
so if we and and so in here right if we
just imagine
instead of saying matchmaker size equals
one right we just said tag
large um and here we could say tag small
but really like maybe that's just
whatever it is
right um
so something like that seems better to
me um
oh is this what was happening maybe this
is what's happening
with the indentation code is that what's
happening i don't know
maybe maybe the problem is the key
bindings not four coder
i'm really confused so let's let's try
this heck out here
i mean the auto indent is obviously
busted
no no it's just it's just broken i don't
know all right
um so yeah so i think that's all right
and we just would need
that tag so in the tags themselves
um like size would have to go away
and we would have to to just have large
so like
particles graso1 would not have a thing
um and this would have a tag that was
like large
right um and and this would not
uh and
and this would not either
um
i don't know what that is about and this
would
have it and
this would not and this would
right um
yeah and so
a lot of this stuff like yeah with these
scenery tree like these
these tag nonsenses right
um we would just change the way this
would work a little bit
so in here this is saying like it
doesn't have winter dark or fall
i guess um it just is damaged
but now we don't need that anymore right
because the way the tag system would
work is it will go
it will jump like directly to that thing
so i'm pretty sure we don't need this
matching nonsense
because i think this was just to work
around the system before was kind of
just
being broken so i think you would just
say that
right you don't need to specify all the
things that you're not
you just you can just specify the things
that you are
and it should go directly there right
um that's my assumption
we'll see that may be totally false
right
but but hopefully it's it's it's
actually okay
um i think that's everything
that we needed and so we just now need
in the file formats themselves
we need one of those tag large things
so like you know
just add that in
um and there should be a way to
presumably add this pretty simply yep
and off we go
so i think that would work um
and this is the only thing that we don't
know so for right now rather than try to
shoehorn that in here
i think what i'd probably do is just say
all right so
you know maybe at the moment there's
gonna be
like a thing that says
that the variant count is like always
by the way that that situation right
there just
this is why i think it should go in the
opposite it should go like here
right like i feel like it should always
go
or what you could do is test where the
cursor is and put it at the top if
you're at the bottom
right i think it should always be like
out of the way
um sort of a separate issue anyway
uh so yeah if we take a look at the
asset system query here where we have
uh
game assets
we're just going to assume that in the
future somehow
right we will be able to look up um
an asset tag hash and we'll be able to
get
a way of you know reading
some measure of how many variants there
are and we'll just say
for now we're just going to say hey
there's there's you know i don't know
there's eight and we'll just say to do
need to actually remember and store
uh the total number of assets
variance you know
um so i think that's probably all good
and now we need to do is just change
any of the plumbing that doesn't you
know align with that right
so in here we have a asset basic
category and we've got the asset
category listed here
um this is actually not going to provide
that anymore it's it's going to provide
the asset tag hash
right um
and that's going to be nice because that
will allow us to do a bunch of stuff
that we weren't
able to do before um so that's going to
be good it's just going to be easier for
us to specify art assets which is the
whole pro
pro the whole point here even though
this will also speed up
the asset matching dramatically
um it it also just is easier to use
which is the main reason we actually
cared about it
um not it was not actually the speed
because
we weren't actually trying to optimize
it at this particular time it just so
happens this will also
optimize it
all right so we're now in the um
so we're now in the cutscene layer
and
so looking at this i feel like pretty
much
shot index um
is probably something that should just
be collapsed down to like variant or
something
right
like i don't think we for any particular
reason
need the shot index to be an actual
thing
right because that could just be the
variant
so here's the way we've got this set up
and you can basically see like we've got
two things here we've got shot index and
layer index
and yeah i just i'm not sure we actually
care about that now we could
we could potentially say that we care
about some
aspect of it
so layering for example
might be something we want
uh to have its own vow
value
um
i guess i don't i don't know
what i would say about that
like i like i could like if somebody
made the argument
that asset match vector
should have
layering as one of the parameters like i
could believe that
um and so maybe you say like well the
shot index
is the variant you know and the layer
index is the other one
but really when we look at this i that
that to me just doesn't seem like
logical
so you know i would think that instead
what you would do
is is rather than having these be
matched because these are direct
look up like there's no ambiguity these
are cut scenes they have to be
exactly the thing that they are
you really would rather those things
just get plowed in
uh to the tag hash
itself right so
i feel like what you would want to do
is
is really just have those be actual tags
i mean it's a little bit annoying it's
it's annoying from the standpoint of the
person who actually has to sit here
and do this garbage like so
uh in the file format
like if you actually have to sit here
and do this
like that definitely sucked right but at
the same time it's like
well it it only really kind of sucks
because c
sucks or c sucks i should say
uh it is actually the right thing for
the system
because it allows you to just wrap those
tags directly up and look them up
instantaneously so it's what you want
and the fact that c makes it annoying to
do is not necessarily
the reason not to do it right so if you
just assumed that you had
some ranges reserved you could write
some code
that would do this as well like it more
efficiently where you just said like
okay we're gonna reserve this range
and then when we see like a
parenthetical with one of these things
in it
i'm probably not gonna bother doing that
because i think this is fine
the way it is probably so we can
probably just go ahead and
you know do this and call it a day
right um
so i would say let's just do it that way
because i think that
i knew i don't know what that's about
but that is a
yes my phone ringtone is the monkey
island theme song
i mean clearly that's the right decision
i don't think anyone you know
could argue with it does anyone know
what ron gilbert's doing these days i'm
i'm gonna send ron gilbert an email
um i think on a previous stream like i
don't know a couple streams ago
i think i said that i thought that ron
gilbert was one of the best programmers
like in the history of gaming and and i
was thinking about that the other day
and i think that's probably
just true because one of the interesting
things so so here's
here's something let me go ahead and
just just lay this out for you
so there's different ways there are
different skills
that great programmers need to have um
or can have right because when you're
great like it's the same as being a
great athlete
like i mean everyone knows what happens
when
like you know michael jordan went to
play baseball or whatever like he wasn't
the best baseball player right but he
was
certainly one of the best basketball
players right
so you know when you talk about
programmer programmer is sort of like
saying athlete there's different
disciplines inside it and you know if
you're
being a great programmer does not me
mean being great at
everything it means that you were great
at something usually because nobody's
great at everything like there's no
programmer who's great at
everything that doesn't exist you know
so some programmers
get more credit than others uh for
various things because a lot of times
the emphasis
when you talk about people who are
famous for doing programming things
the emphasis is on things that are
are not necessarily they don't
necessarily line up in any particular
way
um with the actual
like with how
good you were at the thing right i mean
you could
start really start with certain things
like you know maybe like
uh you you could say that that somebody
i don't know like mark zuckerberg is a
famous programmer in a sense right
um probably a pretty lousy programmer
right because like what you're famous
for
is has really very little to do with
whether the programming was any good
like in it and
and from everything you can kind of see
about facebook the programming
especially back then but even today is
is actually is not good right so so
we we wouldn't say you you wouldn't
imagine that
that that the actual programming skills
are particularly good there but you're
famous for some other thing right
because the thing you
built became famous or something like
that right
um so so there's some of that but then
there's also programmers who are famous
for actually being good and like an
example of that would be like john
carmack
or mike abrash or somebody who's like
you know their names are known pretty
well because um
they they actually did do like
programming things that were important
to people uh
and their like skills and programming
were actually why they were
famous in a lot of ways um
and so that happens too but i would say
that one of the like
least likely things you will to be
famous for
in programming is uh if you are
a a brilliant architect
so if the thing that you're best at in
programming is figuring out
what to do when and how to do it right
like like how it should be organized
and less about coming up with some
specific fancy algorithm
um then i i think you oftentimes maybe
don't get
the credit you deserve and i think you
especially deserve some credit because
that skill is is seems to be incredibly
rare and like when you look at things
like yeah if you go back to like
programs that are famous like facebook
or something and you look at how
incredibly terrible their architecture
is
on all levels like from from the network
architecture
to the server data center architecture
to the like code itself the architecture
is terrible like
it's just just absolutely horrible right
from start to finish
um and and they've gone through like
billions of them right and then they
keep updating these things and they're
always awful and they continue to be
awful and there's just no brilliance
there right
um and that's true of like a lot of
things architected so
my argument for uh ron gilbert being
very underrated as one of the best
programmers i think in the history of
gaming
is if you look
at his track record for game
architecture
it is absolutely insane
just how good it is so
he did basically scum
um as an architecture
for literally from the c64
through to like modern
cd-rom based like and then hard drive
based
large asset systems
basically continuously so that same
system you know with being revised over
time
ran everything from maniac mansion all
the way
to like you know putt-putt saves the zoo
and stuff right um
and i feel like the level
of like the the degree of like
level-headed decision-making
that has to happen to be able to like
make graphic adventures for an unbroken
period of like 20 years
um and have it ship
so many titles so reliably across so
many platforms
it's just kind of ridiculous right
um so i feel like
you know that's that's one of those
situations where i feel like
you know we don't have metrics for
saying who is and isn't a great
programmer
and it's it's not you know like when
when we want to talk about
like athletics you can see why it's so
much easier because there's all these
obvious statistics that people gather
right like we know how many times
you know michael jordan scored a basket
and and under the what conditions and
all these other
sorts of things and so pointing to a
particular set of statistics
is a good way to bolster an argument
that somebody is great at something
and so i do think that you know we
suffer in programming because it's very
hard to point to anything
that's a concrete statistic and the
success of a piece of software has very
little to do with how well it was made
because a lot of times something can be
successful simply because
you were at the right place at the right
time
or you had like a good monopoly
advantage in some way or
other sorts of things so it's really
hard to point to things like well the
software succeeded because lots of
software succeeds doesn't mean that the
programming was any good
um and so uh you know it's really
difficult to
uh to assess those things and so i feel
like because we don't really have any
metrics it's hard to talk about things
especially things like architecture that
are very diffuse
very difficult and very poorly
understood and so i feel like you get
someone like ron gilbert
who maybe hasn't ever developed a flashy
3d graphics routine or something like
that
that's kind of the more obvious thing
that people get credit for
but when you look at i think his
track record of really just
delivering incredibly high quality
stuff from the architecture side way
earlier than
anyone else was able to as well and
to have that architecture hold up over
time
and be able to like more or less
seamlessly
go from being something that ran
the first real point-and-click adventure
on a c64 to something that ran
you know like a modern like full talk
like full fully voice acted
cd-rom streaming um
system i just feel like that's one of
those things that i don't know
anyone else who did that like i can't
point to another
uh example of such a long unbroken
architectural track record
and to be honest i think if graphic
adventures
weren't kind of crappy from a game
standpoint like
you know we we kind of the game doesn't
that the game
design of graphic adventures failed to
evolve
and so they kind of died out in a way
um if that hadn't happened
that track record might just have kept
going right
like the reason that ron stopped making
those
was not because his architecture fell
apart or because he couldn't figure out
how to make like modern technological
versions of them
it was because the market didn't want
that type of game anymore
right and so in a way
you might say that the architecture
itself like literally never failed
like he never actually got to a point
where his architecture skills didn't
continue to take him forward
it was simply a fact that the market
didn't want this thing anymore that's
the only reason we didn't have an even
longer unbroken period
um of like you know that system
delivering so i think that's
that's my argument there then and i'm
sticking sticking to it so i feel like
you know i would say like ron gilbert's
probably the most underrated programmer
in in game history because like i feel
like he was incredibly good
just incredibly good and and and doesn't
doesn't really get the credit he
deserves in my opinion
i mean he does get credit so it's not
like he's like it's not like no one
knows who ron gilbert is like i mean he
has a massive following awesome it's
like
i just don't feel like people give him
the level of credit that he deserves so
he does get credit but i think he should
get even more let's put it that way
another way is i think he gets credit
more as a game designer right in other
words like i think people credit him
more because they like the games he
designed which is great
but i feel like he deserves more credit
as an architect because
and i don't feel like he gets that
credit because i feel like
he did some incredibly pioneering work
and
demonstrated throughout its history just
how
brilliant and resilient that it was
right
um and how smoothly it was extended and
how
he never made those wrong decisions
right like he didn't
ever ship a dud on the engine side like
and that's yeah it's pretty cool
so
all right um
i think we're almost out of time but uh
let's see what we were doing here oh
this this is just a
again another straightforward thing so
um what we want to do here is just be
able to pick out which shots we're doing
uh instead of shot index now we could
actually just make this be a tag
um so uh but
since these layers since these actually
go in order i think i'm just going to do
this mathematically because we can
so i think what we want to do is say
there okay so there's an asset tag
hash here um and so we're going to go
ahead and pull that out
um and we want to say
oops get tag hash we want to say here
like um
where's the thing that actually
so here is what we want right so what we
want to be able to do
is we want to be able to say like tag
layer
index you know
uh and then we want to do like a plus
here
right so we want to do like layer index
plus the layer index value
i think these will be off by one so i
mean i think we'd have to do this
because it seems like
well which i guess i don't know um
how do we line these up so
hey well looks like
where is the layer index value
so so here it looks like we like
pre-subtracted it
right so if we just don't do that so if
we just go back to what we were doing
before
um before we introduce that
uh one offset then this is actually just
correct
so if we just assume that it's like the
offset of the layer index
then that's what we would want and then
for the shot index the shot index
presumably
also like has to be adjusted
to not be up by off by one in this case
intro shot and we just have these things
here
this actually i i i guess is
fairly straightforward because actually
this part here
um where we create the thing that would
normally have the acid information
in it seems
like we should just be able to
change this into like
that you know what i'm saying like
we should just be able to paste the tag
value in there
so in layered scene
we could probably replace shot index
with like a tag
um
i don't know what's the actual tag id
um so we should be able to replace that
with just which
you know which shot tag is it right um
and so in here i would say
like that shot tag is just gonna come
from
from this
and then the layer comes after it and
so here i just had a really interesting
thought
yeah this this is okay okay okay okay
bear with me here
so one of the things that will happen
currently with our tag matching is that
if the order of the tags is different
then you wouldn't match right so if i
said
this shot with this layer it wouldn't
match something that was recorded with
this layer and this shot
so my question is should we
like should we fix that and i guess i'm
gonna go with
no because it's less efficient to do so
because of this because of the fact we
don't have enough things to do
but what i would point out is if we
wanted to we actually could make that
work
so the way we would do it is we would
aes deck
each individual tag into its own
32-bit hash and then we just xor them
together because xor
is not order dependent like if you xor
things together
um you know you'll get the same result
either way
if i'm not mistaken about that right so
if i just xor
this you know if i if i xor uh
if i xor a and b and i switch them
around in x or b
to a i will get the same result
regardless
right so that should mean
that we could put the tags in any order
and then they'd match
i don't really want to do that though
because we can
aes deck more efficiently if we don't
have to do that
you know what i'm saying um so i think
i think i won't but i just wanted to
point out that that's an interesting
idea like we could do something like
that
if we wanted to so i don't know which
kind of asset we're getting here i think
it's a plate
asset probably it looks like scene asset
type
is actually what we're trying to get so
so i guess we'll just we'll just keep
doing that
um you know why why mess with success um
we don't have a weight a match vector
here
um of any kind really so so that'll just
kind of stay
and yeah i think that's it
yeah so i think that's all we need so
the shot tag should be correct this
asset tag id part this has to be cast
here because
we don't have a way of um yeah we can't
actually do those offsets properly but
um this is just tag none
right and this is
what is this title screen shot index oh
so this is just
the same thing um for the the
title screen as opposed to the um as
opposed to the cutscenes
so again uh get tag hash solves the
problem
you can just see like this this code was
just terrible before right i mean not
terrible from any we weren't measuring
anything it would have been very slow as
well but
um i just mean from just having to like
deal with it like you could see how what
a pain in the butt this was
and so now that we know what we actually
need we're just able to simplify that
uh quite a bit right and furthermore
like the shot index layer index thing
i don't actually know that we care about
that here because
i don't i don't know like what there's
only one title screen so like i don't
know what
this is about like i don't know why you
need shot index
one layer index one but you know i mean
okay like you know if we want to leave
that on we can
maybe we want to put more stuff in there
later i don't know
so uh again
nice and clean here
um and you could even do that in one
call if you want so you could just put
that right i mean not in one call but in
one line by just putting it in there i
didn't see any point in doing that but
you could have
all right so in this case yeah same
thing like just this just gets a lot
cleaner
like um it's just a lot more pleasant
because now it's
like look at how much nicer that is
right just as code it's just a lot
easier to
oops to deal with the simple case and
uh and you know it just makes it much
more pleasant
right uh
what is this complaining about
cannot convert argument to
oh um
oops
does the font do something different
it's just assets and and asset tag hash
right
what is font type debug i guess there's
mic
there's the part i don't know oops this
is just
this is just going horribly wrong so one
of the problems that i have is i think i
need to fix my key bindings i should
write this down
um j should work everywhere
so i for some reason i had the j turned
off in other buffers that's just a bad
idea
i obviously want it to work everywhere
um
so yeah so something about this
situation
is a problem um this get tag hash
uh probably because the font type debug
thing
is not um
yes so so i don't know
what that's supposed to be about um
i mean if we're i i feel like all we
need to do is just just
i don't know why font type is like a
thing i don't know what the point of
this is
um probably because we were trying to
use the old matching system
so i'm not sure like that we probably
just want to like clean up
if we look into fonts so we've got
some fonts here right and you can see
that we did a tag for some reason
font type 10 like what
okay i don't know what the point of that
is
um but that's the way we did it and so
i think we just want to get rid of that
garbage completely so
instead of that what we would want here
is like this is
um our debug font right
or something right and then we've got
the other font
which is this one um
and wait how are they both
the same type of font
wait if they're both debug fonts then
which one do you get
when you ask for one
what the heck
that doesn't really make any sense does
it i'm sure there's if we go back and
look at the stream
we go back to the instant replay we'll
be able to figure that out but
yeah i mean what so which one do we use
is it just because we picked like we
randomly were picking between
them
so it looks like we only include
liberation mono
is the answer so yeah i guess we did so
all right well guess what the tag is
debug font
all right so now um i i argue
uh what we want to do is just say
that this is the debug font and then
in the file formats we would just
there's no more
font type that's not a thing and then we
just have
like hey it's the debug font
right and that's what we actually
actually wanted
and eventually we'll presumably have a
game font but we just don't have one
right now
all right um
looks like ad piece was not actually
defined
uh anywhere because presumably we've got
in here the old way of doing things with
the asset tag
uh
well
where is that defined then that's weird
because
hmm either way this is not
correct anymore that would still be tag
hash um and i guess i don't know
where the ad piece definition is
let's find out because this must be
wrong somewhere
here it is so this just needs to be
replaced like so
uh and there we go
all right so
i think this allows us to fix all the
problems we were having before or two
about like
not being able to pick who
was who so like when we add the pieces
for different people we can now say like
oh which
which of the characters were you and
whatever because the pieces themselves
and they can mix and match right so a
piece
could have a specific thing associated
with it
so i think this is just like get tag
hash
right uh and the only thing we need to
do is specify like which one it is
so i'm pretty sure it's just like tag
hero right
um but i just want to check
so inside handmade uh oops inside base
game
so if we look at like body hero right
it's got orphan
hero are the tags and
so we would just put orphan and hero in
there i think and that would be
and that would be that right and then it
would use the facing direction to pick
it out so i want to go see
like because we're going to have to do
some reorganization here obviously
i want to go see like what that actually
looks like but
so in here if we take a look at body
hero
right so the facing direction would pick
and then the the expression
axis there we don't care about um but
i'm pretty sure that works for everybody
yeah so it's just like facing direction
tells you the up down
um and then there's other garbage over
here that we don't have to worry about
because we don't actually use that right
now so this is all going to be
like a body orphan hero or whatever
there and so one interesting thing about
this
is that it does kind of
it's sort of wants in a way the ability
to
change the asset type of a tag hash that
you already have
so you would want potentially to do
something like this
um as just a sort of a service
so if in here we had something like um
like base tags
so here we would say okay the base tags
is just like you know asset none because
we don't care about that but then like
tag
orphan tag hero right
um and why we would now
have tag orphan in the first place i
don't know
uh because we don't really care about
that but maybe
you know i'm not gonna delete that at
the moment but anyway
so now what would be nice is if we could
just do this right
so effectively there's just another
version of oops
that's going to kill me i got to fix
that
there's just going to be another version
of
of get tag hash here where instead of
passing any of those other elements of
it
you actually pass an existing hash
um so that has all the tags in it
and then this just merges them together
so
it basically takes the category um
that you pass in and orders it with the
tags
that you actually have like so
um and produces the result that way now
the
the only hitch here is that that bottom
piece right is an is an eight bit value
and we
want to make sure that it's not like
adultered
so we want to make sure oh wow i can't
type tilde for some reason
that's weird so shift tilde doesn't work
that's a huge problem watching that
shift tilde
doesn't work
hmm all right
um that's an issue not sure how we fixed
that i still talked to alan about it
um so well you know what no i do know
how to fix that we just bind
we can just bind shift tilde to insert
character that should work fine
um anyway uh so yeah i just need to
borrow a tilde from somebody else
i guess of course how to find one i
don't know um
but
i need to be able to not this um
because i i want to be able to say like
look the bottom
so the bottom eight bits right
um we want to make sure
aren't like are clear
when we order this in because we don't
want the category
to get you know mussed up from it
right so that that seems fine and if we
had a till day well we'd just we'd just
do that
but we don't so off we go um
so let's go ahead and see if we can fix
this so in the binding file
so that would be in apps for coder
bindings um so the teal day so it's tick
right and so i don't know
like exactly what i would bind here per
se
i guess it's like right text or
something
but what i would need to do is pass like
shift here
and just say like if somebody does hit
it with the shift key then they're
supposed to be able to insert that
actual character
right um
now we will need
something to bind it to
and i don't know what that is
um we need like insert text
right and
and i don't know what is that function
it's like
write text there is a function for it
i just don't remember what it was
thought we used it in here but i guess
we got rid of
the places that we actually needed it
because there were existing things for
it
and so it never actually happened um
which is too bad
so yeah right
right
so it might be that like write text and
auto indent
no but that's the bind text input so i
don't know
write text input ryan says so right so
let's try let's try right text input
because ryan says so
let's try that and we'll see
i just saved that so yes
all right so let's take a look and see
if i can type a tilde now um
i can't still
so i don't know i don't know how we how
do we type a tilde
folks because it's bound yeah
i don't know is is there some other
magic to it i'm assuming that that's
what that looks like
i guess we'll just half talk allen all
right so until next time
um i guess we'll just say like insert
teal day here um
and and we'll go from there uh
yeah uh i could cut and paste one if i
could find one
but of course i can't search for it
either probably
because it would
it wouldn't let me type it into the
search right
otherwise i would have just searched for
one so i have to like
just hope that there's a not oh so
maybe in like the intrinsics would have
one
because we would have had to have nodded
something in here probably
it's the kind of place you would not
something
um or maybe in the math
uh stuff there it is
so we could probably um
probably just
smoosh that in there
there we go
all right um
all right so i think that's that's it
right
and so now we would just have to kind of
like
uh to to modify some of these
did we not save this maybe we didn't
save this
didn't we already do this particular one
though all right we're gonna do this
next time
because i don't really want to do this
at the end of this but if you look like
basically what we're looking at here is
all we really have left to do is just
map
the pieces that we've added um to all of
our
you know to the to the in the level gen
we just have to
map those to the right thing you know to
the new system
that seems pretty straightforward so
we'll just leave it at that
um and maybe after the stream here i'll
try to coordinate with ryan i
i owe him the send the changes back
uh and uh and i do have to figure out a
way to fix that tilde so that might
that might require alan because it
doesn't look like that has anything to
do with ryan's code
um that's just for coder
mispicking the binding i guess i'm not
sure
um i'm not i'm not sure what's going on
there
maybe the problem is is not that and and
then
we're just missing the like like let's
just double check before we
assume
it no but it seems i mean that's the
only place that that really
happens so
so i don't know
i i don't know
all right well anyway thanks everyone
for joining me for another episode
of handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you
as always and if you do want to follow
along series at home you can always
pre-order the game
on handmader.org and it comes with
source code so you can follow along with
it
also on handmadehero.org i'm starting to
consolidate things
um i've got a little more work to do
this this needs a full screen
option i guess but on the homepage now
there's the pre-order place there's the
schedule
and there's the episode guide that you
can search and stuff
for things like you know whatever you
want to know
um so hopefully this will start getting
better also we've got the links to our
other projects at the bottom
and the mailing list so it's kind of
just all in one place now and you don't
have to click around which is a little
bit
handier um and
uh the other thing that i would mention
is two things one
our graphic novel is on sale right now
for the holidays if you go click on meow
the infinite down here
you can watch the trailer and you can
also get a discount
on any of the versions of it that exist
currently
i think i showed it at the beginning of
the stream but it's really pretty baller
and it looks awesome and we were really
happy with how good it came out
so if you're interested in that please
check it out
um and furthermore uh starcode galaxy
uh also is has this the same mailing
list
so for people who've been wanting to be
notified
when the c programming and low-level
programming course
it's just generally a programming course
that has everything i think you need to
know in it
um is ready that's the same mailing list
so you can
as long as you put your name on our
mailing list we really don't send out
anything other than announcements of
when things are updated
so if there's like a new chapter of me
on the infinite if there's uh
you know a new announcement about star
code galaxy
or about handmade hero we just send them
out only when there's something
so we don't really send anything else
out on the mailing list so you can just
put your name in that
and you'll get um well if it doesn't go
to spam because
gmail always of course likes to send
mailing lists stuff to spam
but if you somehow manage to get gmail
not to market as spam you will
be able to get notified so hopefully uh
sign up for that if you're interested in
hardcore galaxy we'll be sending out the
information about that
uh as soon as we are ready to to have a
broader
access to it all right that's it for
today i'll be back here
next week as the schedule says until
then have fun programming everyone and
i'll see you on the internet
take it easy everybody