echo the recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade hero the show where
we code a complete game live on stream
except we've been on our side break for
two weeks which we are cautiously going
to stop being on our side break this
coming week and see how it goes no
promises I don't know if it will go well
or if it will go poorly we will see what
happens but next week we will start back
again cautiously doing some coding I
don't think we'll jump into handmade
hero coding what I'd like to do instead
is maybe do a little bit of four coder
coding get ourselves a modal editor
which hopefully helps with the RSI as
well and assuming the fat goes well then
the week after we can start back on
handmade here again which I would like
to do and I'm sure you would like to do
as well in the meantime as we have been
doing I've been taking questions that
people want answers to and I have three
things that have come up that need
addressing two of them are quick one of
them is not so quick so i will do the
two relatively quick ones first and the
first one is from twitter which is the
discussion that was going on at the
moment involving mr. sean barrett the
person who wrote the FTB libraries which
we have talked about many times on
stream as being a good example of code
that people can actually use that helps
them but this is the references prevent
null pointers question
so I want to make it clear because I
believe this is kind of a statement of
fact and not a statement of opinion so I
want to make it very clear what the sort
of concept is behind these statements
and why this statement in particular I
think is just objectively incorrect not
subjectively not a matter of purring
practice not a question of opinion but
actually factually wrong and I want to
be very specific it's this word right
here that is wrong so I will now try to
demonstrate to you why I believe this is
just factually wrong this doesn't mean
you shouldn't use references it doesn't
mean that I would argue with someone who
said that they prefer using references
for various semantic reasons it would it
would not mean that i would say that
something was wrong who said they like
to use references as a way of notating
to themselves what something meant all
of those things may be fine programming
practices that people can choose to use
or not use based on their own personal
preference but this comment is just
always incorrect just factually as far
as I'm concerned and I wanted to explain
why okay so the reason is that if you
are claiming that using references in
c++ somehow prevents you from having
null pointer and when I say prevent to
having no pointers what really mean is
null pointer dereferences right and we
all know what that is right that's if
you have something like this int star a
equals zero and then I do star a equals
anything this is attempting to write to
a memory location the memory location is
zero or as we might call it null right
which just means it's pointing to
nothing and specifically so this will
immediately cause a fault and we know
this we see this all the time we've seen
this on handmade hero when we've had
bugs or something like this we know that
if we dereference the null pointer we're
going to get a fault it's just like a
divided by zero or other things like
us where the processor can be programmed
and put into various states that causes
it to immediately trigger a hardware
style exception not C++ static section
but actually a literal you know hardware
exception in the case where this occurs
and the operating system will catch that
and let us know so this is a hard fault
if this occurs so obviously we never
want it to happen in the run of our
program unless something very specific
and weird is going on and we have some
kind of exception handling at the
hardware exception handling set up to
deal with it we don't ever want this to
happen so it makes sense the developer
would always want to do things that
would prevent them from getting into
situations where they dereference a null
pointer it is almost always 99.999
percent of the time going to be a bug
okay so some people claim that using
references instead of pointers prevents
this from happening and what does that
mean exactly well what they're saying is
that if for example I was to make a
function in fact I guess I'll make it
void because it doesn't matter at this
particular point let's say I had a
function void foo and I take an int star
a here and on the other side I have a
void foo that takes an int reference a
ok and in this case we have you know
this star a and i'm going to say star a
oops equals 5 and in this side I'm going
to say a equals 5 these are essentially
completely equivalent pieces of code as
far as the compiler is concerned ok they
will produce exactly the same operations
the only difference between these two
pieces of code is that in one case I've
used a reference which means that
semantically speaking wherever I refer
to a I am talking about the thing that
the pointer points to because this
really is just still a pointer ok under
the hood it's going to pass a pointer
but in this case I'm leaving the pointer
as an explicit thing so when I want to
actually write to the pointer I put a
star in here okay a very simple very
straightforward the compiler will in
both cases produce some code that moves
five to an address that is passed by the
collar but in one case that address is
passed as a reference in one case that
average average address is being passed
as a pointer semantically that's it so
again code is the same semantics are
different so now someone tells you hey
if you write code like this that
prevents null pointer dereference but if
you write code like this somehow it
doesn't the implication is this will
catch some bug for you that this one
will not and my assertion is show me how
that's possible tell me what you're
seeing that makes you believe that
that's true because I am going to make a
claim that will I'm sure ignite the
people who make this claim they will
they will explode in a giant fireball of
rage but I am actually going to claim
that if anything the opposite is true
meaning this is the code that will
create less null pointer dereferences
and this will create more don't believe
me well let's see if you believe me
after we're done okay so I've got to
function so I can call foo star F
through reference I so what does that
look like at the call site well at the
call site it looks like this I've got
int B equals 6 and then I call foo
address of B right on the other hand I
have int B equals 6 foo be okay both of
these will pass the pointer both of
these will modify be so that it now
actually says five instead of six after
we come out of here so they'll both do
exactly the same thing but on this side
I take the address of the be first and
on this side I do not now in this code
obviously there is no way that we could
have a null pointer dereference in
either case right because if we didn't
have a pointer to begin with then taking
the address of it certainly isn't going
to introduce a no so no savings here so
let's take the only other case that
actually exists the one where we already
had a pointer so now we have int star B
equals something and over here we have
int star B equals something well in this
case I call foo with the B and if
perchance this was 0 this code will
crash right on the other hand if instead
I call this with star B which is the
only way I can call it because I have to
turn it into a reference first guess
what this code will crash no compiler
warning no error checking no nothing
they're exactly the same so tell me
where exactly is the compiler doing
something to help me prevent a null
pointer dereference the answer is
nowhere because either you didn't start
with a pointer to begin with in which
case neither code path crashes or you
did have a pointer somewhere to begin
with and you needed to turn it into a
reference which means that code path
will crash as well if in either case you
were trying to handle the fact that this
could have been zero you had to put in
an if and neither one will be stranger
here right they're both exactly the same
that's it so either the programmer is
guarding against null or they're not and
it's whichever they chose to be right so
again in this particular case
if you were to tell me Oh Casey well the
way that I explain to somebody that
something has to not be no in my
functions is I whenever something's
passed by reference they know that it
can't be no so that's a clue to them
that they should check for if right
again you want to make that statement
and that's your code convention great
like I said would not argue with you but
the concept that their references
themselves have anything to do with
preventing an OD reference is wrong and
now I'm going to tell you why I think
the actually the opposite is true in
practice why because very few
programmers are actually any more
diligent about not doing this than they
are about not doing it here they really
aren't right if someone needs to call
something and they don't think the thing
could be no they typically just do that
even if it turns out it really could
have been null in some way or whatever
happens right so if you wrote this code
right if we'll go back up here for a
second if you write your code like this
typically then you're very likely to
down here perhaps add some checking
right but you're never going to add any
checking here and this gets a lot worse
as you go down the chain this might not
just be one little function but once
I've turned it into a ref a nobody I
ever call is ever going to check that
pointer again right I could pass this
through 17 layers of code all the way
down to somebody at the end who finally
uses it they're never no one's going to
check it because it's a reference it
can't be null right so you get
absolutely no fault tolerance this is
the no fault tolerance path it means
that you had better have been right
everywhere because if you were ever
wrong you will absolutely crash whereas
this one hey computers are pretty fast
nowadays and if that's almost never
false is really not very expensive you
can throw a bunch of those in here and
all of a sudden you've got some fault
tolerance right this code is actually
the code that's much less likely to have
an ulterior then the other one so the
more you actually insist on using the
references the less likely you are to
put any heat shielding on the code at
all now maybe
you should argue you don't need any heat
shielding well okay great start showing
me some of these C++ programs that don't
crash all the time because parenthesis
all the ones that I use everyday sure do
and then maybe I'll start to believe you
but the point is from the actual actual
implementation and semantic layer if you
want to talk about which one is more
likely to produce code that has a null
pointer dereference I actually say it's
this one and the only way in that week
in that this kind of code is ever better
is if you magically have a team of
programmers who never ever ever ever
forget to absolutely check every time
before they change something into
reference which i rarely see people do
all right so that's the end of that rant
and hopefully that makes it very clear
what my position on that is and I
suspect that that is pretty close to
what Shawn's position on it is but I
don't really know all i know is that he
was of a similar opinion to me in the
Twitter comments on this where he was
saying that he did not believe it to be
a viable technique for catching errors
all right
now on to the more media subjects
because also as a coda to this I don't
care at all about this at all right this
is one of those programming debate
things where you're just like who cares
if this is where you're at that you
think that arguing about this one way or
the other for some extended period of
time is like a good idea like you're
already fired like you're off the team
don't even talk to me hmm don't even
look in the direction of our office
because you're just going to make our
code worse all right so let's move on to
more profitable things canoe khals who
is I think asleep at the moment he is I
think in Moscow I want to say he asked
the question that I'm not sure I
understood so I'm going to try to answer
the question but I may just be answering
a question that he didn't really care
about so I apologize k'nuckles but
heroes this question he wanted to know
is what he wanted to know what the
difference was between interpretation
and translation and as far as I'm
concerned it's an AMA clay chur thing
it's not the kind of thing I sell at
pedantic sort of you know specifically
what does this term mean versus that
term not something I've ever been
particularly good at but I can give you
what my reaction to that comment is and
hopefully it helps a little bit or at
least helps you look in the right place
so when I hear interpretation and
translation use together then again like
I said it may not be understanding the
question correctly but what I'm thinking
of is what happens with a binary command
stream so machine code right let's say
as an example so x64 instructions like
an executable something that the
processor is executing all right if I
say I am going to write an interpreter
oops and I spell it right if i say i'm
going to write an interpreter for x64
then what i mean is i'm going to write a
piece of
code which itself is actually running
and it's going to look at the individual
pieces of the instructions as they would
be executed and it's essentially going
to act like an Intel CPU so we do
software these acting like an intel cpu
stepping through pulling out pieces of
the code and actually running them using
its own simulated model for what should
happen okay so it's basically like a
software version of a cpu so it's
running on a cpu but it itself is part
of a cpu that's doing sort of the work
of you know okay read the next byte what
does that bite mean okay read another
bite ok that's an instruction what do I
you do that structure need to add okay
where's my code for adjunct to the code
for adding where's my registers oh
they're here in memory pull pull out
these two things are you know registers
add them together put it back into the
register right so it's actually a
complete piece of code that basically
emulates what a CPU is doing in hardware
it's actually doing that in software so
an interpreter is is more or less an
emulator those are not particularly
different terms to me yeah translation
on the other hand implies a single
process applied once that produces a new
piece of code so again this is
interpretation translation is when let's
say I have x64 code and I need arm code
okay well if I wanted to run some x64
code on arm I could use an interpreter I
could write a piece of code which runs
on arm which reads an x64 instruction
stream and has a simulation of an x64
CPU in it and off it goes right it just
does the operations of the operations as
a separation as it goes so it's
basically code for an x64 running on top
of an arm right so the x64 part is in
software the arm is the hardware and
it's it's running an X 64 emulator
essentially on top of arm but another
way I could do it is with a train
hands later and what that does is it
takes an executable written in x64 right
so it's exited for native and it
actually just translates it into an
executable meant for arm so it does the
same sort of process of reading the exit
for instruction stream but instead of
trying to execute it as it reads it it
just tries to translate it over to a
different instruction set perhaps one
that's native for the processor that I'm
on now but perhaps not I could be doing
it to a PowerPC for example so I could
have a arm cpu running a translator
written on it that translates x64 to
power pc if i wanted to write and then
once I've translated I've got a PowerPC
executable I can go run that on a
PowerPC native or if I had an
interpreter for powerpc coat I could run
the property code through the
interpreter and see what it did right so
that's I mean assuming that I understood
your question correctly I'm not sure if
I did that's interpretation versus
translation in my mind and so I hope
that helps if that was a question if
it's not the question please feel free
to email me sometime and and just tell
me what the actual question was if that
makes sense alright and so now we get to
the question I think we'll probably take
the majority of the time on this stream
which is sort of i'm going to broaden
the topic a little bit even from what
the question was that was asked and it
was asked by by Elvin who I don't know
if he's he's here too oh I think yeah I
saw him I think I saw his name go by it
was asked by him an email and what he
was asking about was the sort of
time-honored process especially in the
OL in older times although still happens
to this day the time-honored tradition
of games using offline rendered art for
certain elements while still using
real-time rendered art for other
elements and now this can be as you know
you could think of it the
earliest version of this is just the
fact that we have like sprites right the
fact that we pre rendered some images
somehow maybe they were hand-drawn
whatever and then we're compositing
their locations and changing their
locations that in a sense is using
pre-rendered stuff and composing it at
runtime right but those techniques
continued to get more and more elaborate
as you know games went on until some of
the months that Alvin was mentioning his
email for example Final Fantasy 7 where
you had a 3d rendered character who is
running around on 2d pre-rendered
backdrops for the overworld maps for
example or games like resident evil
which had pre-rendered backdrops and 3d
characters and monsters and stuff like
this moving around on top of them and as
he pointed out some of those games
actually had very elaborate effects they
might do so for example they might have
a situation where a character is
standing on the floor of a pre-rendered
backdrop and you're seeing the character
who is being rendered in 3d but you're
also seeing their reflection in the
floor even though the floor was a
pre-rendered thing right and so
hopefully you've all seen some games
that do this or maybe even non games
that do something like this and what
elven was asking is could I sort of give
a general overview of this and how you
go about doing that what the sort of
techniques are how they work that sort
of thing and so I kind of wanted to
broaden that topic a little bit and just
talk about it from the standpoint of the
sort of category of algorithms that this
falls into which is actually broader
than just this specific application it's
a category of algorithms and I shouldn't
say algorithms the category of computing
a category of something I don't know
what you want to call it but it's a it's
a well defined term it's called partial
specialization and you could also
quickly call partial evaluation
and what this means is actually very
very easy to see if I just write a very
simple piece of code for you and it
generalizes all the way out to resident
evil right it's kind of interesting so
let me show you what this means so
normally what happens in a piece of code
is you have something that maybe looks
like this let's say I've got a function
I my ubiquitous foo or actually you know
what I'm going to return an integer
integer foo and it takes an int a and an
in to be okay and I'm going to write a
function here so I'm going to take it in
produce my aunt C which by the way will
be my return value I'm going to taking
in C and the way that I'm going to take
to produce my NC is I am going to take
five times a and i'm going to add it to
six times B okay so this is a function
that hopefully everyone understands it
is extraordinarily simple it does some
of the most basic things you could
possibly hope to have done in a function
and you can see that it is in fact a
functional thing right this is when we
talk about functional programming right
it's something which has no side effects
it simply produces as a result and that
result is based entirely on its two
input parameters and it is entirely
dependent on those two input parameters
change a and you will get a different
return value change be you get a
different return value it is fully
dependent on both of them now let's
suppose that I am in a situation where I
don't know we're on the world's most
primitive cpu we're all the way back to
the old old old days and this is
actually something that's expensive for
us to compute for some reason now
nowadays that's a laughable concept to
even say but let's suppose we were
because as you can imagine when we
generalize this out that is the sort of
thing we're going to be thinking about
but in our specific case let's pretend
for some reason that we profiled this
program and somehow this took tons of
time like this took eighty percent of
our time this line right here and we
look at this code and we go what can we
do how can we optimize this program
because we need to do five times a plus
6 times B all of our time in the
execution of this program is spent there
and we simply just don't have the
computing power to actually do it what
do we do well we analyze our code and we
find that say in fifty percent of the
cases and maybe I'll change that to a
little bit more break down in twenty
percent of the cases be is seven in
thirty percent of the cases be is nine
in twenty five percent of the cases be
is 10 and then the rest be is random
right so let's suppose that I did this
analysis well now when I'm looking at
this I'm going okay well twenty percent
thirty percent that's fifty percent plus
twenty-five percent that's seventy-five
percent of the time I actually don't
really need to do this operation right I
mean I kind of already know what it is
so wouldn't it be a good idea to create
four versions of foo each one being
specialized to a certain parameter space
while still allowing some freedom in the
rest of the parameter space right and
maybe for good measure let's say that we
actually knew it entirely just to make
it a really great case for us let's say
we always knew it was 79 10 or 15 now we
know we could replace food entirely with
just foo 7 through 9 through 10 and when
I say foo 15 we could create four
functions and each of those functions
can be specialized to actually have a
hard-coded constant in here for be so
now instead of computing this which is
two multiplies in a mad I go down to
having it be in C equals five times a
plus some constant right so now we
remove one entire multiply which is a
third or more of the work and let's
pretend this processor multiplies were
very expensive it could be more than a
third of the work right and we just have
a different one different constant for
each of these things right similarly
what we could do instead is just have
the same foo but instead of six times B
we just have it so that we pre know
which one it is right and we pass in six
times the value and get rid of the
multiply so that's partial
specialization in a nutshell right it is
specialization because you are taking a
general equation and your specializing
it by removing some of its parameter
space and it's called partial because we
are not specifying all the parameters
we're only specifying some of them right
so we're knocking out this part of the
parameterization but we're leaving this
part in and that's where the partial
comes from so how does this apply to
resident evil or final fantasy or any of
these games well if you think of the 3d
rendering pipeline as a basically a
giant equation right something where I'm
going to render a bunch of things and
then i am going to display them and
there's multiple steps involved in this
and there's a lot of work that has to be
done you can think of any given pixel as
essentially having that equation right
you can you can think of it as having an
equation there and for example if i was
to render something like let's say i do
a full 3d render again no trick sir no
2d no nothing like that let's say i'm
going to render something i have a
screen and i'm going to render all my
stuff so i've got a bunch of complex
geometry back here you know maybe it's
like some kind of a hallway thing
and maybe there's like a bunch of wood
slats and adore thing and you know
there's there's all kinds of like you
know stuff on the walls and a torch and
who knows what and I don't know that
sort of thing and then there's just like
an ogre here and maybe for good measure
up in the front here there's like a
little altar thing some kind of
sacrificial altar you know that's in
front of the yogurt well if I was to
take a look at one specific pixel here
let's say that I'm going to take a look
at a pixel that's right there okay
that's that place right there well if
I'm to look at that well what do I see
the equation for that pixel write an
equation kind of a loose term here the
program write the code the equivalent of
int foo for that pixel if I rendered
everything using the z-buffer doing
whatever the game was doing might look
something like all right first I have to
do you know the door pixel here so
that's like whatever the door material
is right door material and then i have
to like light that using the complicated
light equation so i'm going to start off
with my base color for this thing right
base color is going to be like call the
lighting equation on the door material
using you know 50 different lights some
light array who knows and it's going to
do this is super expensive doesn't much
ray casting who knows then i'm going to
have this ogre right I've got my ogre
here that's not a spell ogre right so
now I've got to do my auger because it
turns out the ogre over writes this so
you know what I'll just call this the
I'll just call this the output color so
the ogre over writes this it says okay
you know whatever this guy is here this
output you know I'm gonna do this even
better than that I think but this is
even a little bit better I'm going to
say that we do out equals light there
and I'm going to say if you know the
ogres z value right is is closer
then the doors z-value okay then we're
going to come in here and say all right
well then the out color is whatever the
ogre is so I've got the ogre and I'm
gonna have to light that guy right it's
got the ogre here and the ogre is like a
dynamic guy so maybe he's not light it
light in as good so maybe there's a
single light that gets passed in here I
don't know right and then finally if the
altar Z is closer than the i guess the
outsi this should really be out see here
go then the current out Z then I'm going
to say ok well now we've got to light
the altar so there's the altars thing
and then there's that light array again
and so on so yeah again is this really
happening exactly like this not exactly
like this but you can think of it as
being very much a function that produces
the color of the pixel right the GPU is
essentially or i should say let's say
this is again ignoring GPU ignoring all
that stuff we're just writing some kind
of offline crazy expensive renderer it's
Pixar it's who knows what we're creating
the full version of this thing that's
that's beautifully lit and all that
stuff then you can imagine looking a lot
like this it's like all right well we
start off by saying we've got something
here we've got the door we're going to
evaluate that first we're going to do
all our lighting calculations and all
our material calculations we're going to
produce an out value of the app has a
color and the Z value which is how far
it is from the camera we're then going
to say ok now we got that augurs there
if the ogres point at this location on
the screen is closer than the one we
just computed for the door then we're
going to overwrite him right and here we
go we compute the ogre values and when
we overwrite the color value with that
finally if the altar was closer than the
ogre at that point then we're going to
go ahead and do the lighting and so on
and now we know that since we're talking
about a pixel here we know that actually
all we end up caring about is this value
because the altar was actually there and
it was in front of these guys right and
you could also imagine the torch being
in here as well we don't happen to hit
the torch but you could imagine it being
tested to see if it was all that sort of
stuff ok so it's sense
what happens when you're talking about a
thing where you did like the resident
evil model or any that stuff is we're
still just talking about partial
specialization what we're talking about
is saying okay there's this giant really
complicated function that's happening to
compose the scene but if we were to say
that for example this term and this term
work we're going to be partially
specialized right we're going to
partially specialized to those then all
we would have to compute at runtime is
this one right if we knew what the door
color was at that pixel all the time and
we knew what the altar color was it the
pics all the time and furthermore we
knew that since you can only see one or
the other right we know that we can just
store the alters color as the only one
at that point in pixel well we can
produce an image that is essentially the
partially specialized constants
necessary to reconstruct this function
if we have the ogre if we still do the
ogre at runtime and how would we do that
well like I said we know that this guy
can never be visible so the first thing
we can do is just say well if we take
out the ogre and we're just talking
about partially specializing these two
we just need whichever one's closer so
when we actually render everything minus
the ogre we'll just keep whichever one's
closer and we know that this one's
closer right that's we know that's true
so we don't need this one anymore but
now what do we need to keep well we need
to keep two things right first of all we
need to keep whatever that output color
was because if there's no ogre there
then we know that this is actually going
to be the color of the pixel but we need
to keep something else as well right we
need to keep the z value because we
needed to test the altar Z value against
the ogre z value in order to know
whether we're supposed to draw the ogre
or the altar because the ogre could move
around in front right and then it would
be the ogre that shows up and that just
by again thinking through what the
function what the actual graphics
function is that you need to evaluate at
every pixel is it directly tells you
exactly what you would need to store to
reproduce what you wanted to do after
you partially specialized color and Z
value and that's exactly what you store
if you want to do post compositing you
store the color map and the depth map
and then at runtime when you do your
real-time rendering you just real-time
render into a context where you already
have the depth map so it'll test against
the debt math and if the depth map is
closer at that pixel then whatever the
thing is that you're rendering then you
don't put anything there and you let it
the color map that you say it show
through and if you do find that it is
closer than you render the thing right
and so partial specialization as a
framework for thinking about these
things lets you understand immediately
what you might have to pre-render and
save in order to reproduce any kind of
complicated thing you might want to
reproduce any kind of complicated
scenario given some things you're
willing to specialize around and so in
this case you know what did we
specialize around well you could think
of this as taking the location of the
door right and the location of the altar
originally those were movable right you
could also say the location of the
camera all of those things right were
originally parameters and I guess
obviously the ogre as well so we had a
function that was taking the door the
alter the camera in the or ogre and it
was able to produce any image we might
want to produce with any location of the
door any location of the ogre any
location the altar and any placement of
the camera and then we wanted to do
again Resident Evil style if we're
talking about a fixed camera location
with a fixed scene and only like one or
two moving things is we just said will
partially specialized everything except
for the ogre so the cameras fix the
alters fix the door is fixed now all
this stuff pushes down and we're left
with just a color map and as a map for
our for our sort of image that we start
with and all we have to do is render the
booger and depth taps Tim against the
death map to know whether we pick the
colors from our pre rendered result or
the colors from our you know real-time
rendered result okay so hopefully that
makes some sense but you're probably
wondering why did I go through all this
trouble of explaining partial
specialization if all I'm going to talk
about is color map the depth map and the
reason is because I want you to start
thinking about it a little more broadly
don't just think colormap depth map
think anything I want to compute right
so let's take another case like in
Resident Evil where I have a scene that
has a floor ok and there's stuff you
know behind it or whatever and here is
my guy who's standing on it I now want
to render reflections of the person in
the floor ok so now you're in exactly
the same situation that you were before
if you understand partial specialization
as long as you can write the renderer
for this offline as long as you could
write the code that would have rendered
it you're in an excellent position to
figure out what you need to save to do
it runtime with the background fixed so
what might we need well it depends on
what our goals are if only the floor is
reflected right so it's just the floor
which in Resident Evil it was then we
get a little bit of a bonus because the
floor is just a plane and a plane has an
equation I don't know if we ever covered
this on handmade here probably not but
the equation for a plane is ax plus B y
plus cz Plus D equals 0 I'm sure we'll
get to this some point probably not I
guess we only did equations for walls
which is basically the same thing and so
ABC these things the ABC actually is the
normal to the plane right so if you
imagine there's a plane and there's a
vector pointing out of it the ABC is
actually this vector right here that's
the normal and the D value is how far
from the origin you would have to go
backwards along that value to get to a
point on the plane neither here nor
there doesn't matter at all for this
case just thought I'd mention it but
point being we need a plane right we
would need the reflection plane because
we're probably going to need that to set
up the set up the reflection in the
runtime version as well but point being
so what are we going to need here ok so
we've got our food and we're going to
need sort of the whatever the scenery is
that we're going to render I don't know
what this guy is I don't I didn't I
played like one resident evil game I
think goes Resident Evil 0 I I want it
is let's say is there someone named
Veronica may be 0 or something let's say
this is Veronica I don't actually know
but maybe that's Veronica I think you
can tell just clearly from this drawing
it looks like a Veronica doesn't it I
mean it says Veronica to me clearly I
feel like she also had like a beret on
thing I don't know maybe not point being
let's suppose that that's Veronica and
let's suppose that resident evil is a
story about someone named Veronica which
it probably isn't and what we need to do
is we need to pass in Veronica right
then we also need to pass in the plane
of the reflection right that's what we
gotta pass it all right so now we have
our code and we need to actually write
the code for this well it's basically
exactly the same as the code we're going
to write before for the most part right
you know again just to doe coding it I
got to produce an out value and so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to light
you know my scenery with some lights and
I suppose I should have listed the
lights before here too I mean right this
there's so much stuff that's being
partially specialized out in one of
these things the light array is all in
there right so we have a light array and
then we also have a primary light and we
chose to specialize out all the other
lights but just keep one of them for
lighting our ogre again if you really
want to write it all the way out if I
was being very diligent here you could
see that we're specifically choosing the
light in the ogre as the non as the
still varying parameters and everything
else gets partially specialized away
right but in some sense in some sense
that's even that's really not sort of
true this is even getting partially
specialized array a way really what's
happening is we're using an
approximation for this but neither here
nor there okay not super important so
here we are we got to like this thing so
we like the scenery with with our lights
and we produce whatever that is and then
we need to do our our our out here we
need to light our Veronica with our
lights as well and then we would have
our proper scene with no reflection
right but like I said we do want our
reflection there so what we need to do
in in between these two you might say
like in fact let me go ahead and put
that in here right is we need to do our
standard if we need to say like if
Veronica z
e is is less than the scenery Z then the
out equals light Veronica lights but
what we need to do here is we need to
say well okay we were sort of saying
that we wanted this reflection to occur
and so far we have not had any way for
the reflection to occur so what we need
to do there is we need to have some
parameter that tells us how reflective
the scenery is at any given point right
so when we compute this and we render it
this would be a property of the
materials in the scenery how reflective
it is and if that thing is marked
reflective then we need to create the
reflection for it right so what we need
to do here is we need to say if whatever
are out dot like reflection is if the ab
dot reflection is greater than zero then
that means the surface at this point is
reflected so we're going to have to
compute the reflected Veronica right and
really they're reflected everything and
we're going to have to render it in
there right now fortunately we already
have what we need if we consider our foo
to take a camera position then right in
here what we would do is say alright
when we have our reflection we are then
going to like go ahead and mix our
output color right and using that output
reflection value let's say we're going
to go ahead and mix that with just
another call to our cells with the same
scenery the same Veronica and now the
camera is going to actually be reflected
right so you can think about this is
basically saying all right we're going
to have to create a reflected version of
the scene so we're going to create
temporarily a fake camera which is just
pointing in the direction we would need
it to point in order to render the scene
reflected and that would involve a
mirror and all that stuff all that good
stuff that's outside the scope of what
we're talking about here because again
I'm I'm trying to sort of avoid the talk
about how you actually render any things
because that's I like how do you do
offline 3d rendering talk which is a
whole nother thing but assuming that you
do know how to create the actual
reflected version you're going to want
to do that and then mix it into the
color at this point right so now you can
immediately see what actually needs to
happen in order for you to get the
correct color at this point now instead
of just the Z and the color right we
need the color and we need the Z because
we need to save those we can partially
specialized this part right here but we
still have the possibility that Veronica
is going to be reflected so what that
means is we need another map right we
need a map that tells us whether
something is reflective at that point so
we need to save all three of these plus
we need to save the plane because
remember we need to be able to create
that reflective camera at runtime to for
rendering the reflected Veronica because
the fully partially specialized version
of this thing includes the recursive
call to itself that has to render
Veronica twice right we asked to render
branca once normally and once in the
reflected camera so now you can see that
we actually need to store three Maps
potentially one that's the color one
that's the depth and ones that the
reflect that's the reflectivity at that
point and by the way this gives you
because there's another parameter here
again that gives you pretty much I guess
what i should say is this equation this
this sort of stuff that happens with the
blending here can be as complicated as
you want it just may mean that you have
to start storing more
makes this is just standard material
rendering equations that you would be
doing here in your off line renderer any
one of those things that you need to
that depends on when you look at the
actual function that depends on a
dynamic element that could move around
you have to anything that you can't
condense down into folded constants
right anything that doesn't collapse out
as constant that still depends on a
varying parameter those things have to
be stored as Maps because they have to
be read again right in much the same way
that you can't get rid of Z because you
need to test it against something that
is not known at partial specialization
time you need to store reflection
because it needs to be tested against
something that is not known right this
thing that's going to be tested against
it this this extra rendering step has a
dynamic element in it or go this if
cannot be optimized out it cannot be
specialized away just by looking at what
actually happened on that that pixel in
the offline render stage so in a lot of
ways you this is very similar to the
concept of optimization right partial
specialization is very much like what an
optimizer does when it takes your code
and sees that there are constants that
it can deduce that allow it to remove
whole portions of that thing and
furthermore it's exactly like what
happens in you know like when you have
an inline function let's say and you
call it in multiple places it may
produce multiple different versions of
that inline function as it gets in lined
that are based around the conditions
that surrounded the call to the inline
function because it can see some things
are constant and can be optimized away
in some cases can't necessarily be
optimized or the same things might not
be a prize away in other cases right and
so that is the way to frame these kinds
of problems right what you want to think
about when you want to think about how
do I offline do a bunch of work you want
to think about it in terms of partial
specializations sit down and actually
write the full rendering concept what do
you want to actually compute
at this point if you were writing a ray
tracer what would you actually and had
all the time in the world what would you
actually compute and then you start
condensing that work into pre computed
values this is exactly again the same
thing as light maps right let's elevate
it up to 3d rendering now forget
resident evil think quake all right now
we've got a situation where we've got
these walls they're being rendered in 3d
okay and we're actually be able to move
around them so the camera is no longer
fixed it's no longer in a single
location it's not like Resident Evil we
can look anywhere we can go anywhere we
want but it's still way too expensive to
compute the lighting the fundamental
render equation at any pixel that we
wanted to compute involve not just the
diffuse color of the texture at that
pixel which we can reproduce at runtime
now but also a bunch of Ray cast into
the environment that look at where the
light is coming from so hey guess what
we partially specialized again instead
of calling light you know this wall
element with some kind of crazy array of
lights and the rest of the scenery and
shadows and all that other stuff in
material parameters you know what we're
just going to consider that a constant
that we creek that we compute offline
and we bake it into a map that we look
up that now instead of being mapped to
the screen is mapped to the wall and
even to this day a huge amount of what
happens on a 3d engine rendering team in
terms of what they're actually doing
it's partial specialization what they're
sitting around doing is trying to figure
out new ways of capturing stuff that
they can render and compute offline
while still maintaining the maximum
amount of dynamic activity at runtime
and as 3d graphics has progressed and as
processing power has gotten more and
more and more and more abundant on
gaming machines and gaming hardware
they're able to move things from
was previously partially specialized in
two things that are now dynamic and the
story of 3d graphics and progress as you
move from you know Resident Evil 2 quake
to something like Call of Duty now or
you know whatever pick your current
frostbite engine whatever you want
unreal the story of that progress is
constantly changing what we partially
evaluate and why right and moving more
thing so dynamic and changing getting
more richer equations that we're trying
to simulate as we can do that in
partially specializing different parts
of them that's really what's going on
because at the end of the day we know
what we're trying to do we're trying to
evaluate the rendering equation right
Jim koteas rendering equation right
we're trying to evaluate that for every
pixel on the screen and we've never had
enough horsepower to do it and so
everything we do is an exercise in
partially specializing that equation and
there's so many ways to do it and it all
just depends on what you are holding
fixed right Resident Evil was let's fix
the camera let's fix the environment
let's fix the lighting and we'll just
render the dynamic characters right
quake is let's just fix the lighting
right will render will let the camera
very will let you know blah blah blah
but we just fixed the lighting the
shadows that's that's not dynamic right
and even it something like quake you can
see they actually partially specialized
part of the lending question and others
of it right direct lighting was actually
still computed in the quake engine and
often is in most engines today right but
the indirect lighting has to be pre
computed because it's too expensive to
compute dynamically a lot of times and
so you often either precompute it or
like some images nowadays do iterative
refinement to sort of constantly reap
recompute the lighting if you will so
that you can have some measure of
dynamic lighting happening dynamic
indirect lighting happening as geometry
potentially changes in the game so yeah
so like I said I kind of wanted to
broaden that topic because really the
concept of what Resident Evil was doing
or what quake was doing they're all kind
of the same concept the concept is you
have an equation you'd like to do it's
incredibly expensive there's no
we are going to do it at runtime what do
you partially specialized which terms of
it do you start folding out what do you
pre-compute and what do you keep and you
can do a remarkable amount of stuff by
choosing to keep certain things as maps
right that are either screen space or
mapped onto geometry or whatever you can
do a remarkable number of things there
you can do a lot of interesting and
different effects just by saving
different elements of the process so
that's about it and I think we're sort
of roughly roughly out of time hopefully
that made some sense and I don't know if
Alvin is actually here today he was the
one who recently asked the question but
hopefully that answered it to a
significant 22 enough precision that
he's sort of he sort of gets my my mind
set on anyway let's look at the chat
what is going on in the chat how is the
chat going guys it ain't got time for a
couple questions probably
oh so Alvin is here this for me is by
far the best handmade stream ever well
alright I'm glad I hope that means your
question was answered a couple of
questions so I guess they did something
similar to reflections to implement
real-time shadows yes how did they
achieve other effects like camera
panning and lightning you still need an
invisible level collision mesh correct
uh so I guess what I would say is again
there's literally take that to think so
let's say I want to implement lightning
right well I can decide what my original
lightning equation was if my lightning
equation is going to let me let me give
a very a very simple example here right
so if i have a a way to compute some
lighting at a at a point so this is this
is an offline renderer we're ray tracing
our thing whatever i'm going to compute
some lighting and I'm gonna say okay I
want to light you know the scenery and
I'm going to give it this light array
and this is all the lights in the scene
and it's going to produce you know the
output color okay you can also imagine
me doing this and I'm actually knowing
to call that out we call that a you can
also imagine me doing lighting the
scenery with just the lightning light
right now I have two potential
Lighting's for the same scene and I can
blend between them and I wouldn't blend
between them because lighting is
additive so really it's it's it's a plus
TB is what it would actually equal this
is the out color right where this is how
much lightning
now I've got lightning you know I've got
the scene lit just by the lightning and
I've got the scene lit by all the normal
lights in the scene right and I add them
together at runtime I can dial this
between zero and one to get turn the
lightning on or off or even part of the
way if I want it to like kind of fade
out over a couple frames or whatever
right i can do like 1.7 point 20 1.7
point 20 for like in that lightning look
or whatever right because fundamentally
light is additive right lights add
together i shine a light on something i
shine another light they add together
the amount of light that i see so it's
completely separable which again means
it's great for partial specialization so
this means if I want to I can just spend
more memory to store the a and B
separately see normally what I'm doing
when you know in Resident Evil scene I'm
rendering it I sum up the lighting for
all the lights right that parcels but
you know when I said light and I say
scenery and I'm like light array sorry
for the scribbles here I'm talking too
fast I gotta write fast what is this
what does this actually look like if we
actually start looking at the actual
equation well it's it's you know it's
actually a series of like light the
scenery with light like a plus light the
scenery with light be and on and on and
on right it's just a sum take the
contras general a day at the country's
light be light see like deal ie if I had
infinite memory and didn't care I could
store each of those as a separate map
and then at run time I pull from all the
maps I add them together and I get my
result now why would you do that well a
it takes way too much memory way too
much DVD space and furthermore your
graphics card may not be able to pull
from 30 textures at the same time that
may be too much texture bandwidth for it
right I mean 30 full screen textures
nowadays on like a you know crazy nvidia
card actually isn't too much but you
know on a Playstation or whatever they
had for as usual it would he would have
been right the point being this is an
entirely separate vil equation which
means that each term of the equation
could be stored as a separate color map
and added back together at runtime which
means that if you wanted to you could
actually control each individual light
at runtime and in fact you can actually
see this being done in a different
domain just by looking at for example
something like maxwell render where they
use what's called multi light and what
multi light is is when they actually
compute the fully metropolis light
transport solution like the Monte Carlo
integrated rate race version of a scene
they just store whichever lights
contribution they had computed they
store that to a separate map which means
that it's free for you after the fact to
just dial the lights up and down and
back so this is actually a single image
output for maxwell render that someone
is now playing with the light sliders
from same exact thing can be done in
games and you know me I don't know the
light that I've never looked at in fact
I don't know anything about Resident
Evil's lightning or how they did it or
whatever but point being the general
solution that problem is actually very
straightforward and in today's universe
where you actually have a tremendous
amount of memory typically to work with
it's not a big deal for you to
pre-render 3 4 5 6 Lighting's for a
scene and grab from two three four maybe
even more of those when you compose this
unit runtime so if you were doing a
resident evil today you could have a lot
of control over the lights could be
dynamically flickering and doing
whatever you want and they'd actually
cast the correct shadows and all those
other things right so that's certainly
very easy to do now the problem that you
run into if you do this ain't with the
background cuz like i said perfectly
separable really easy the problem which
of course you always run into is your
dynamic objects those are still being
rendered at runtime and those are
obviously more difficult to deal with
because you've got to do dynamic
lighting on them now for lights on a
character not a big deal but remember
that the environment is not really going
to respond properly the fact that the
guy
is standing in front of the doorway
isn't going to make the rest of things
behind the doorway darker because all
that lighting was pre computed and so
again you're always limited when you do
these partial evaluations you're limited
because now all the things you may have
liked to have had dynamically computed
are no longer being dynamically computed
that's just you know a an artifact of
freezing some of the things and
approximating some of the things so yeah
and it looks like also yet another
question which is you still need an
invisible level collision mesh correct
and the answer that is of course yes you
know you don't necessarily need a
collision mesh but you need some way of
knowing where the character can and
can't walk because you no longer have
necessarily any level geometry because
you're just storing an image of what it
looked like you rendered it offline so
you need to store something that tells
you where you can go some kind of a walk
map of some kind and that could be level
Clinton geometry that could be a pre
computed set of polygons that you know
you walk around but you need you need
something as for how they implemented
real-time shadows I suspect they just
used a planar projection of the person's
geometry onto a plane that again was was
pre computed and sort of placed there
but I don't really know like I said I've
never really even played resident evil
what if you're constrained on space as
well as computing power could you
precompute parts of your graphics eg a
shape from multiple angles of 5 degrees
then do interpolation to get values that
lie in between eg a view of the shape at
seven degrees well if you are
constrained on space and computing power
then you're just you're I mean there's
not much you can do right pre computing
is is the act of trading space for
computing power or rather using space to
eliminate some of the need for computing
power so if you're constrained on both
of them it typically is not a win to
pre-compute things right because you
could if you're constrained on both you
don't have extra space that you can use
to store pre computed results
alright think we're all good so I'm
going to wrap it up I'm just going to
add a little a little sort of co2 here
or a little sort of note so partial
specialization like I said a really good
way to think about this and the
idealized way to think about this but
what I'll also say is obviously there's
always also this right because sometimes
when you're looking at this in fact
often you'll get to a point where you're
like well there's no way to actually
partially specialized this per se but I
could just approximate this term with
something else entirely right so plenty
of the things that you end up doing our
partial specialization yes on a better
on a good day but on other days you're
straight up replacing a term with
something not as good right because
sometimes you partially specialized and
you really are still computing the same
thing but you're just not allowing it to
vary at runtime and that's pretty good
you feel good about yourself doing that
yeah you lost some dynamism but you're
still producing the same equation and
that's pretty cool other times you can't
even do that and if you can't do that
hey you know what the story of 3d
graphics there's a lot of hacks so what
can you do so don't think of your don't
think of it as always happy to be
perfect partial specialization that's
not true a lot of times you do just have
to straight-up hack it and that's fine
too but partial specialization is still
a really good framework for thinking of
it in because even if you just allow
kind of a hack in there it's like a
great this wasn't really personalize
this was just like straight up replace
the term with a simpler term you know
what still a good way to think about it
right is to taking that start with the
real equation and know what you're
simplifying know what you're partially
specializing because that always tells
you where your room for provement is and
it also keeps you very close to a good
result and you know where you have cut
corners so there's no surprises and
that's kind of nice that's it for today
I'm going to wrap it up
thank you everyone for joining me from
those sort of handmade hero this is the
end of our chat streams we're going to
try coding again next week we'll see how
it goes no promises but I'll make an
attempt till then if you would like to
be kept up to date on the schedule this
is the place for it tweet bot right here
the tweet pot treats to schedule at you
you can see that luscious scheduler
right there and so there will be another
one popping up here this weekend that
tells you what schedules for next week
check it out subscribe to it or follow
it or whatever you have to do on twitter
to get notifications if you want to
catch the stream live and i hope you do
because it'd be nice to see you back
here next week for some for kodir work
until then have a good weekend of
programming and I will see you guys next
week taking these everyone