hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode complete-game live on
stream we are gonna have some unsavory
tasks to do this weekend and so yeah
it's just something we're gonna have to
dive straight into so where we left off
last weekend is we pretty much you know
we kept everything that we were doing
sort of well okay I could split this
into two halves I suppose there is
something we could do before diving into
the unsavory Ness but we basically took
a look at everything we were doing and
we went ahead and made it so that our
our camera behavior was reasonable now
and our our lightning behavior was
reasonable in terms of tracking where
the player moves and stuff like this so
now we can reasonably walk around the
game and do what we're gonna do but we
don't have any artist that's in here at
the moment and that's a problem so that
was the next big thing that we had to do
was have a way of figuring out how we
were going to specify that that piece of
information like how we were gonna get
the art assets in in the new that we
want to so let me talk about the two
things that we could do today and I
think probably we should just get right
into the art asset stuff because the
other part of its not as important all
right so one thing that we could do
today that I think that we should just
skip and we can leave to later is that
for large rooms we wanted to have camera
scrolling and right now that's very
simple it's not a lot to do with
anything it's just a very simple thing
we would have to do that would allow us
to to know that this room is too large
for the zoom out because we said we only
wanted to zoom out about this far well
this room is too big so if you only zoom
out to the maximum zoom out you end up
in a situation where you can't actually
see the whole room so we need the camera
to follow the player around that's not
particularly difficult we've already
done it before on handmade hero we just
need a thing that basically says that
it's doing it now so that would just be
coupled with pulling the camera code out
and adding a better interpolator right
now we just have a sort of makeshift
interpolator in place and we can do a
lot better than what's in there right
now so that would also be something we'd
discuss and then do the reason I don't
think that's particularly useful right
now is
really not a blocking factor and
basically anything I mean you could play
the whole game like this honestly and we
could just make the zoom out be a little
bit further and then just play the whole
game like this so it's really not
stopping us from implementing the rest
of the game the thing that isn't
stopping us from the plantiffs the game
right now is the lack of any art assets
in the game other than just the
Testaments that we brought in originally
so that's the part that I wanted to
start addressing now because I think
that's the biggest obstacle to starting
to tune anything in the game and so the
problem there that we have is we made a
thing that would allow us to pack our
debts into a pack file and load on the
pack files so that all stuff just works
fine but that was created at a time
where and we didn't really know that
we'd have a artist potentially working
on the project so we didn't know that
we'd have someone who could actually
like play the game and perhaps want to
be able to tune art assets while playing
the game and see them reload and stuff
like that and so one of the things we
didn't do was any kind of a hot
reloading path and the reason for that
is really pretty straight forward it's a
real pain in the butt
now oddly enough it's not a pain in the
butt in terms of the actual
architectural issues that we have
we pretty much would already support it
it'd be trivial to drop it in it'd be
really really straightforward I think so
that's really not that big of a deal
because our asset system already does
loading on-demand and streaming and that
sort of stuff so when you have an asset
system that does that you're pretty much
good to go like you know hot loading is
just you can just pretend the asset
wasn't loaded you just say this asset
wasn't loaded and then it'll try to
reload it again right so hot loading is
really really simple when you've already
done the work of having a streaming
asset system so that's the good news the
bad news is if we actually want to load
things in that way then what we need to
do is we need to load a format that an
artist actually might save and one of
the things that's really annoying for
example about Photoshop is Photoshop
doesn't really have a quick export path
for say a BMP or something simple to
load all of its quick export paths like
the simple buttons for an artist to hit
inside Photoshop that will quickly
export a bitmap to a drive for use in a
game for example are all PNG based and
so our problem that we have the thing
that would stop us from being able to
load art assets into the game in real
time like that is that we don't have a
PNG loader so that's really the problem
that we have so what we need to do is we
need to go through and figure out how
we're gonna get that happening and
that's why I say it's very unsavory
tasks because there's nothing fun or
interesting about loading a PNG it's not
even a good data formats really pretty
lousy but it's pretty much what you have
to do and so what we need to do is we
need to look so for example inside our
code base here we can look for BMP and
what you can see is that we've got a BMP
loader that we wrote inside the asset
builder here and you can see how simple
this is right I mean this is basically
one function long that has almost
nothing in it it just reads it does one
simple read of a file to read a header
so basically you know you see you in
here at capacity filename it just reads
the file in it does one simple it's not
really read just looks at the memory it
looks at the first part of the memory it
knows that's a header it pulls out of
that header what the width and height is
it looks at some masked values to figure
out where the red green blue and alpha
bits are in each pixel and then it loops
through and extracts those and that's
all it does right it doesn't really do
anything else so you know that's the
simplicity of a file format that really
just doesn't have any complexity to it
there's no compression to speak of here
or transforms on the data
there's no extensibility that we need to
concern ourselves with so on
to be honest BMP is actually a pretty
good format in that sense it's pretty
straightforward there's not a lot you
have to do there are some things about
it that are kind of dumb like the fact
that it allows up up down and down up
bitmaps and stuff and things that are
just adding complexity for not really
much value in my opinion but that's kind
of a separate issue and it's still
pretty straightforward to read PNG is
not that way that it's not really the
way PNG works PNG is a much more
traditional crufty file format it's
based on blocks those blocks just get
slammed into a file they're not
particularly well thought through and it
doesn't really stake out a very good
place in terms of complexity versus bang
for the buck it mostly just adds a lot
of complexity without really giving you
much beyond an hourly bitmap you get a
little bit better because it uses what's
called LZ compression which we actually
sort of covered really basic LZ
compression in the stream on compression
that we did one time is a one-off I
think it was because Midler was talking
about implementing I'll see stuff maybe
I don't remember if we did philsie or
not we may have only done basically I
just can't remember but anyway point
being you get very little extra stuff
and you add a ton of complexity for
having to handle it now fortunately for
us one of the things that is nice about
our situation is again we're only
talking we're not talking about
releasing this out into the wilds where
the program itself is expected to read
PNG files like you would if you were an
art package right so we're not releasing
this PNG code out in some way where
we're gonna be making sort of some kind
of a warrant to the general user that
we're gonna load a PNG file because if
you do that then you have to support
like all PNG files right and PNG files
because again they have a lot of crufty
complexity to them there's actually a
lot of different ways that a PNG file
can be stored they have like palletized
versions for example and other things
like that which we won't have to support
because we know that our art is always
going to be saved in 32-bit color format
24 bits RGB and 8 bits alpha right or 8
bits each of our GBA might be another
way set so we do buy ourselves a little
bit of a better time there because we
don't have to go through every aspect of
the PNG spec and make sure that we get
it right because we know that we'll only
be looking at a few basic export sources
for example we can support Photoshop
which we know we need and maybe
which is a freely alternative freely
available alternative
gram for example and so we can focus our
attentions just on doing the bare
minimum necessary to read pngs that come
from those two sources and that is nice
it's not still the best thing in the
world but it's better than nothing so
that's the situation as it stands and we
need to to just attack it head-on
there's nothing else we can really do
other than what I just said if we want
it to be inside the game then we have to
write it ourselves that's the rules on
handmade hero so here we go the first
thing I'm going to do is I don't even
know if we have installed here we
probably don't do B yes we do no we
don't this is the search thank you for
loading up a browser that I don't use so
if I go here and just search for
I'm gonna download this and the first
thing we're going to do is create a PNG
that we'll start with and try to use for
our hopefully this has a just have a
Windows version let's see get for
Windows there we go we're gonna load up
will create a PNG and save it and
then we will start to try and read it by
working off of the specification for PNG
which is freely available so we can just
look at it and try to figure out what
the most efficacious way would be to
read something that comes out of
and then we'll take a Photoshop file
when we get that working and we'll see
if there are any differences between the
King for the Photoshop versions in terms
of what they're likely to spit out and
then we'll have a reader that reads from
those two sources and we'll just say
look anyone making art had better
produce PM G's that are compliant with
these two packages or and if the source
code yourself if you want to use
something else so that's the current
situation this has downloaded here so
that's good we'll go ahead and run that
setup program and then we should be good
to go
I don't really care about that but
whatever I don't really think I want any
of that stuff just sounds a little bit a
little bit much
you don't think we you know I don't
really want any of this any stuff at all
just install the thing all right
so while that's doing its thing I'm
gonna go ahead and look up the PNG spec
so here's the w3c version I'm going to
look at a couple different pieces of
information here just in terms of
anything that I see that I you know I
might be interested in so here's the w3
C's version here's sort of looks like an
old version from 96
looks like that just kind of goes back
up to there so maybe we'll leave that
out for now I don't know what the
difference is between these two here
this must be an older version maybe but
I'm gonna leave both those up I don't
know which one will be more useful to us
but I'm gonna leave those two up all
right so we've installed and again
that's something you can do at home
because it's free software I've never
used goop goo that's good
2.10 I even know there was a
2.10 ik the last version i used was 2.8
I like to use single window mo but it
looks like it's the default now that
didn't used to be used to have windows
floating all over the place and it was
kind of nuts but it looks like this
defaults to that now so that's kind of
nice all right I'm gonna go ahead and
make a new image here I don't really
care at the moment what we do in terms
of sizes so I'm just gonna make a square
texture for the moment actually I
suppose we're always gonna be loading
square textures from the art so I'll
just make one because that's the the
common thing that we're gonna use and
we'll be using a power of two sizing as
well so we know that that's always going
to be the case
we do want RGB color we do on 8-bit
integer space we do want srgb and I
think that's really all we need for our
thing now normally like I said if we
were writing an arbitrary loader I
wouldn't make a square texture because
you want to make sure you handle the
width and the height separately and I
also wouldn't use a power of two with
because you'd want to make sure that you
didn't have to worry about some padding
that was happening but like I said this
is the only thing we're gonna support
we're only going to support multiples of
1024 and by 1024 in general and we're
mostly only going to be allowing squares
so I am fine with that because this is
not
to be a general PNG loader now what I
want to do here is I want to make
something that I can reasonably test and
make sure that we're you know doing
something right so what I want to do
here is I would like to make a little
bit of information just up in the top
corner of the PNG and then in the bottom
corner of the PMG because I want to be
able to quickly know what I'm looking at
so what I'm gonna do here is I'm gonna
put in the top corner I'm just gonna put
loops it's not what I wanted at all I
want just a pencil I want a simple pixel
but doesn't look like I'm gonna get that
so I guess I got to go in here so it
looks like it looks like there we go if
I want to make just one red dot there it
looks like now I have done so so I just
wanted one red dot up in that corner and
then I'm gonna go down to the bottom
here and I'm gonna put one green dot in
the bottom and this is just a way again
we've talked about structured art a
couple times let me go ahead and make
that size one I'm basically just setting
myself up so that I can look and see if
we've got something I don't want a
complicated image because a complicated
image is hard for me to visually inspect
so I definitely don't want that right I
want something that I can easily look at
very quickly now what I would like to do
is make sure that we've got an alpha
channel here so I also want to go ahead
and erase part of the image just so I
can see when we actually load something
in here I want to be able to see that an
alpha comes through as well I can't tell
which those as a racer I suspect is
probably that one that looks like
they've changed all the icons so I'm
gonna go ahead here and it's
an opacity that's lower why is that not
I don't know why that's not erasing 100%
where I am don't ask me but there we go
so now we've got some alpha happening
and we can take a look at that as well
so that's all I really wanted out of my
PNG and then just so we can look and see
if the thing looks correct I can go
ahead also and make the middle of it be
something we could visually inspect at
some point if we wanted to so just an
empty area there and then I'm gonna load
up a brush here of some arbitrary color
something like this and I'll just write
oops I've got to get a little bit
thicker there our name in there and then
we're good alright so I think that's all
we really need I'm gonna go ahead and
export this and I'm gonna put this into
W handmade and I feel like normally this
would go here in the data directory the
data directory doesn't get synced and we
might want this to just be a test ping
so inside here maybe in one of these
directories like misc or something we
could put or maybe I could make a little
test directory that we start sinking or
something like that I'm not sure but let
me go ahead and try it let's just have a
test directory here and I'm going to
call this
PNG I guess we can just call it Gib test
PNG and all I'm gonna do here is just
export this and let it do whatever it's
gonna do now I don't want it to do an
automatic pixel format I'm presupposing
that I only want eight bits per pixel
RGB a and so I'm gonna force it to do
that I don't care about the rest of this
stuff really these will presumably
create things that we don't actually
care about anyway
so we're just gonna leave it as it is
now and hit export so that creates a PNG
file and hopefully if I now go in and
try to reload that PNG file I would just
get exactly what we just looked at and
nothing weird would happen right so
there's our PNG presumably there's an
open with there it is
and so there's our image so that's what
we want to do now is just get that basic
operation working so what I'm gonna do
at the outset here is I'm gonna just go
ahead and probably make this its own
little file so we've got in our build
process you know there's a sort of the
test asset builder here with forgot the
line commented out and the simple
compressor line here these are not
things that are being used they're just
things that we had played around with
I'm gonna make another one of those that
we can go in here and say alright I want
you know maybe let's let you know what
we could just make it be code we're
actually gonna again let's just call it
handmade PNG dot CPP and what we'll do
is we'll make the handmade PNG code that
would normally operate inside handmade
hero and then what we'll do is we'll
just stop compiling it as its own thing
later when we need to to put it into the
game so I'm gonna create that handmade
PNG dot CPP here oops that's not the
load command and PNG CPP and then what I
want to do is I'm just gonna go into
like simple compressor for example I'm
just gonna copy out basic startup stuff
and one thing I would like to do is I
will go ahead and see if I can just do
this and we'll see how that goes ok yeah
we're
so this way I can create a main here and
I can just make something that reads a
PNG and parses it and we can just have
it be its own program that I can step
into and test separate from everything
else and then once it's working we just
weld it into the mainline code so
assuming that we've got a main here
here's us loading a PNG quote/unquote by
just printing yay so what I want to do
now is I want to go ahead and take a
look at what that did you can see it
should have in here made that handmade
PNG you can see that it did right so I'm
gonna go ahead and run that and it'll
just print PNG literally a so that just
means we now have a little test area
that we can make this thing in and off
we go so the first thing I want to do is
just load the entire file and we
actually already have that in our simple
preprocessor I'm sorry our simple asset
our test asset builder we have read
entire file and I just want exactly that
so I'm just gonna sort of pirate that
over here and that'll just serve as a
pretty simple way for us to get the
entire file into memory so what I want
to do here is just say okay if the Arg
count is equal to two then we can load
otherwise we can't and what I'll do is
I'll just print out an error if you
don't use the right number of arguments
to the program so we know that's how you
use this thing we know that the zeroth
argument is always the name of the
executable so that's fine and then we
know here
so again nothing really revolutionary
there just one say like okay so if we
say ham a P&amp;G it'll say okay give us the
file load if we give it a file to load
then it'll try to load that file right
so once we know which file we want to
load we just say okay let's go ahead and
read that in and now we have the entire
file so then we can do
why don't you parse this file right go
ahead and okay so I don't know what this
wants to look like it's I'm just gonna
literally do exactly what it looks like
and presumably what we want to do here
is pass the file in and we'll just have
something that will start out with just
the real basic stuff of trying to parse
what's in the file that's all we're
gonna do right so nothing fancy just see
if we can get the basics of what's in
the file working now another thing that
I want to point out here is this is
strictly this is not something that's
meant for robust use so basically like
we are not going to even remotely
guarantee in fact I'll put that right in
the top here
basically we are not going to handle
anything special we're not going to
handle malformed pngs we're not gonna
handle malicious pngs we're not going to
anything like at all so this is going to
be the most simple it's designed only
for use with an artist that you trust it
is not supposed to be robust to
tampering or anything like that so we
really just don't care any other things
we're just gonna write the simplest
possible PNG load that is not even
remotely capable of handling any kind of
malformed input and again that's because
we really don't care about that at all
that's someone else's problem okay so
let's take a look at the spec here and
also let me get myself set up with the
debugging context so what I'm gonna do
is I'm gonna do MS dev here I'm going to
say that we want to debug it handmade
PNG eggsy
and then in here I'm going to go ahead
and set the properties of the loading
code the arguments to it I have that
piece of test data that I made there I
believe it was called oops test up
PNG and so when we build this program
here as part of this process if I now
were to step into it I should be able to
see this happening you can see the
arguments come in here and like there's
the maybe cue ball so on so we should
see us load this file I don't need to
step into F open thank you
alright never mind forget it doesn't
matter so what I should probably do to
avoid that eventually in future is we
want to be able to set this to OD cuz
probably what happened is the optimizer
welded that all together so what I want
to do now is we step into it just this
way well it's gonna show you so when we
do an entire file we should see it open
the file we should see it read the
entire file in like so and then close it
and then the thing that we're left with
should be a result that has the size of
the file and the Const of the file in it
so we have the entire file loaded into
memory now it says that files 30k let's
make sure that is actually how big it
should be just to make sure we're not
doing anything obviously stupid that's
the size it should be
so as you can see here everything's fine
so then we've got the file in memory and
now we can press it and now we just need
to write the code that actually starts
so look at that and does something
reasonable so I'm gonna make another
file here I'm gonna make a header file
that accompanies handmade PNG and the
responsible for that header file is just
a dumping ground for all of the sort of
specific code specific structures that I
might use to extract information out of
the PNG to make it easier on myself now
we may not be able to do much of that I
don't actually know how structured PNG
is as a format so we'll see it may be a
very short header file I'm not sure but
that's what we're I'm going to put that
stuff to the eliminated any so here's
handmade PNG again I'm just gonna copy
this in there like so and then inside
here I'm gonna go ahead and include
so now we can start looking at this here
there's a bunch of sort of concept stuff
and whatever we don't really want to
look at that stuff quite yet we're gonna
kind of work our way backwards through
there
we want to start looking at first is the
data stream structure which is just the
thing that lets us know sort of how we
should start to break apart this file
and what you can see here is they give
this is very common specifications
there's basically this this notion of a
RIF file format our iff we saw it with
wave data when we were playing sounds
this PNG is that kind of a file format
it's based on chunks of data which tend
to have two things in them they tend to
have a length which says how long it's
going to be and a type field which is
often times but not always a
four-character field that just says some
identifiers like HD are two for a second
version of the header or something like
that that tells you what kind of chunk
you're looking for are looking at and
what you're expected to do as a parser
of the file format for better or for
worse is to scan through the file
looking at these chunks and you can look
and see okay here's the first chunk
here's how long it is here's what type
it is do I understand and/or care about
that type if the answer is yes I look at
the data inside there at the answer is
no I used the length field to skip over
that chunk right so that's typically how
that works now I can't say I necessarily
know because I've never written to PNG
reader before I tend to read Photoshop
files directly that's that's what I do
in my engines speaking of things you
really don't want to get yourself into I
have no idea what this kind of chunk
means because this is like I guess if
you just want to put in a type that has
literally no data like I'm just trying
to tag the thing then I guess you have a
length that equals zero and then it's
just a CRC of nothing so that's kind of
interesting but yeah I
there's probably tag-based stuff you'd
then do in a PNG that makes sense sir I
don't know I'm sure we'll find out as we
go along but point being you can see
that this part of the reason I jumped
right to the datastream structure part
is because this is the part reaction to
start with now as we work our way
through here we will find things we
don't understand and that's when we'll
have to go back to the previous part the
rest of this this is not useless we do
need to read it all it's just not
relevant to us just yet because we
haven't really gotten to the part of
parsing where we need to understand the
concepts that are being talked about
instead what we need to do is just
extract the basic data that's there so
the first thing we can expect to see it
says right here is that the eight bytes
that begin a PNG file have to contain
these decimal values so the first thing
we're going to look at is essentially a
eight byte field and so this is gonna be
something I can put in this header here
I'm gonna go ahead and do a pragma and
you've seen this pragma that we've we've
used this pragma before it's called a
pragma pack and what it does is it says
we don't want the c compiler to
introduce any padding and the reason
that we don't want the cecum power to
induce any padding here is just because
if the C compiler introduces padding
then it will align with what's in the
file so the file has its own ideas about
what should be padded and what shouldn't
be so if we create structures here that
are meant to overlay exactly with memory
read from a file if we then go ahead and
say okay the C compiler can introduce
any kind of padding that it wants to
hear we will end up with something that
doesn't actually line up with the data
in the file so this is a pretty
important thing to do so the first thing
we want to do is is talk about the PNG
header we now know that the PNG header
has to have exactly this and it's going
to contain this this string if you will
137 80s 78 or you know that that exact
pattern is going to be there but these
decimals and so what we want to do is
say all right we know there's going to
be 8 things in here this is for lack of
a better term this is the
signature it's eight bytes long
we know that the PNG signature has to
look like this because the spec told us
so soon when we load the scene we can do
a comparison on those two and we can
verify that that is what is there right
so that's all fine we then have the
chunks and so you can see it says here
the signature in the case is remaining
main the remainder of the data stream
contains a single PNG image to a series
of chunks beginning with an IEEE header
and ending with an int ankh now what
that says to me is that it's not going
to tell us the size of the file we know
the size of the file that we read so we
could do error checking on it if we want
to like I said we don't care about that
so really what we're gonna do there is
start reading chunks one at a time and
the chunk layout is very specific you
can see it here it's got a length of a
chunk type and then the chunk get a CRC
stuff so right here inside the chunk
parts they're gonna tell us how to read
that it says that the length is 4 bytes
giving the number of bytes the chimes
data field it's only the data field not
the chunk type of the CRT so when you
say it's 0 it means that there's no
chunk data it doesn't mean that there
isn't one of these one of these there's
always those two so effectively since
this the trunk type is 4 bytes and the
the CRC is 4 bytes for the cyclic
redundancy check that basically means
that there's 4 bytes and then 8 bytes at
the I'm sorry there's 8 bytes to start
and then 4 bytes at the end the length
does not include those 4 bytes on either
side here the chunk type or the CRT less
CRC sir so we have a PNG chunk header
and a PNG chunk footer and again do we
really need these no these are here
because I want to make a record of the
structure of the PNG that's easy for me
to see and easy for others to follow
along with if they look at this code or
have to debug it so we could just fly
you know
go ahead and not have these but I feel
like this is a good way to document what
I think the file format is and that's
just helpful right that that's really
all it is okay so that's really all we
need to do to start printing out what
chunks are in this file and what we can
see here is we've got a list of all
these sort of things that we might see
in the file so what we what I think we
should do here is just make a thing that
now can dump this aspect of the file
right because now we know enough to
parse the entire PNG file we just should
we won't be able to understand me of the
data in it and that's fine but that's
step two right so let's get started here
so we want a header and the header it
should be in in this file contents here
now what we're gonna see is in fact one
thing that we could do is and I think we
should do is we're gonna have this
entire file we got this contents here
and what we'd see is we see the same
pattern sort of appearing many many
times right which is to say that we
would do something like this where I'm
saying look I'm gonna start with a
pointer to the file contents I'm gonna
get out one of these things right I'm
gonna look at the first part as a header
and then I want to move past whatever
the header is so I'm gonna do this
that's gonna be a really common pattern
that we would do right and so what we
could do instead is just make it
something that's easier to extract from
there and furthermore if we want to we
can do something that's even fancier we
can do some some pretty wily stuff if we
really want to we could do something
like this
I don't really want an something like
this let's say where we pass in the size
of the thing that we want to consume and
we pass in the the file pointer and it
just gives us back the correct amount
and advances the pointer right and then
what we would do is we define a macro
like so and we just say oh yeah like
tell us what type you wanted and to
extract out of here and we will extract
that for you and make sure it's casted
properly right furthermore this gives us
the opportunity to assert because we can
assert that the size left in the thing
is enough to give you back what you
asked for so that also gives us a little
bit of insurance that we don't have a
bug in the code right so here's my
result pointer my result pointer is
whatever the contents is right now and
the other thing I'm going to do is I'm
going to take the result contents and
I'm gonna advance it by whatever the
size is so you can see what I'm doing
here right so I'm gonna have a macro I'm
going to say consume from this file
consume one of these whatever it is and
then what that'll do is it'll pass
whatever the size of that thing is that
you asked for it will find out where we
are in the file right now and return
that to you
casted to whatever the put type is that
you asked for then it will go ahead and
take whatever the file contents are and
it will advance it by however far it was
that if by however much we actually are
going to look at it'll advance by that
much right so what I can do there is now
instead of writing code like this all
the time about what I can do here is say
I've got a thing that's like I don't
know
like that and now what I can do is just
say this pointer right here is how I
will get all of my stuff so looking at
this I know I want to hit her
and then I know that I want to basically
lock into a four loop where I'm going to
have a chunk header and I'm going to
essentially keep going through here I
could you know what this is probably be
a while loop it just says while at
what's working for a while at
content size like no that's your summer
yeah well that content size is greater
than zero we'll keep going right and
this assertion will tell us that we
haven't at the end of the file what we
could do too is we could make this just
a regular error what we could do is say
like if the file content size is greater
than or equal to the size then we go
ahead and do what what it is that we
were going to do and that should be fine
if we don't we'll set the content size
to zero we could also do something here
where we do this and that way this code
could if on that write something like
that
here I'm saying so anyway while we're
doing this we can just do these consumes
and the consumes we'll just go go go go
go and each time we go through here
we'll get one of these right and off we
will go and that should just be fine I
think that's all we would really need to
do and then what happens in here as we
go through here and we get chunk headers
out when we see a valid chunk header oh
you know what I should also do here is
I just put it under flow message in
there alright so what I want to do now
is when we get back one of these chunk
headers it's not as simple as just you
know we can't just loop over this we
have to remember that the chunk header
has a length in it and that length tells
us how much further forward we actually
have to go in order to read that part of
that particular chunk right and then we
also know we've got a footer that we
have to read as well like that right so
in between here this is the chunk data
we know that the chunk data is always
going to be exactly the size that it
tells us right so in the chunk header
that length field we always need to
consume that data now it might be zero
right and so this might do nothing and
that's fine but we always have to
consume whatever the length is so we
read the header out we consume however
much data it says in there and then we
consume the footer and then we continue
until we can't continue anymore so let's
go ahead and make what's this what's
what is it global variable is that the
name of it yep
oh whoops yeah umm cannot convert entire
file oh right this is supposed to be at
not file
[Music]
let's see here looks like we've got some
kind of a complaint regarding the type
oh right so probably I should have that
because we actually want to consume size
at various points as well right that's
not a struct at that point so that's
what we really need to do there now
we've got sort of a we've got something
now that will loop through it but we
don't actually have anything that it
will print out right so you know there
the program ran right but we haven't
actually put anything out so what we
want to do and if I do it out here as
well just so we can see what it looks
like if I say handmade PNG do we
actually have now if I say handmade P&amp;G
W handmade test PM test at P&amp;G what you
can see is we don't actually get
anything own we get that under flow
there so we were reading something a
little bit incorrectly there it would
seem so what we want to do now is start
looking through this and getting this
working correctly and that's about it
right so let's go ahead in here let's
start by looking at what this equals at
the moment thirty five to two oh forgot
something relatively obvious when we
advance this file content size needs to
go down by the size obviously
okay so let's start in here we get back
the file header and I'm gonna take a
look at it
oops I suppose I should also have double
check since I had that type over there
let me just make sure that it goes down
right so should I go and put down by
eight and it did so now if we take a
look at the file header what you can see
is that it has that series of things
that we said it should have actually we
haven't checked them in our code yet but
it does seem to have that right 137 80
78-71 bla bla bla right it's got that in
there so we know that the file header if
he is apparently correct right so now
we're gonna read the chunk header and
there's the chunk header now I probably
should have said that the chunk header
was a Kara star because it would be
easier for us to debug if I do you can
see this is an AI header right and
there's the length that length looks
totally bogus so I think I must have
made some mistake here because the AI
editor cannot possibly be that long
right so I think I just I got to go back
and double-check that I didn't do
something stupid there I probably did
and so we have to fix that let me just
for byte unsigned if you give the number
of bytes in the chunks data Felix's only
two Phillips head or the Searcy's yours
well although cords dicker should treat
the length is unsigned its value should
not exceed two or three first one fights
although it does seem is it just me or
does that just seemed really large that
does I mean that's where it should have
been
I would make one small change we're
coming back in a second so what I was
gonna say here is if we treat this like
so and you know I could even do it this
way last something like that then that
would allow us to look at it a little
more easily so you could see here in the
debugger now it that's just basically
the hint to the debugger if I don't have
this that's just a hint of the debugger
to show it to us this way which lets us
see that much more easily right and so
that's it's just the same value as this
but it just allows us to see it so what
you can see here right is this chunk
header is supposed to have a length on
it but the length value doesn't seem to
be real because if that was the actual
length it'd be longer than the entire
file right so what I'm having trouble
squaring is the fact that it says here
the first eight plates the PNG a
streamer always contain the following
decimal values we saw that right and
then it says the rate of the icer gives
the single PNG was Christa have a series
of chunks begin with an I hit her chunk
any with an I end chunk right now the I
header chunk says it's going to include
that right and then it's got you know
just a little bit of stuff in it with
height bit depth color compression it's
so on right I that should be relatively
small so what I'm not sure I understand
is why the length field appears to be
some very large value because I it
shouldn't be right that doesn't really
make any sense so when we try I mean
that explains why we get the underflow
there right if we come in here what
we're gonna see is we get a file
underflow immediately because we're
asking to read this giant thing and it
can't do that right so these two will
both underflow and
then we'll exit out so that's a little
confusing because I'm not sure what else
we could really do about that if that's
the spec so is this spec a little bit
off you know what do we make of that or
did I miss something here that that I
didn't understand so let's take a look
at the chunk specifications let's see
PNG diffuse cigs your philosophies which
sense each chunk of chunks as a chunk
type so it's function the clause defines
meters not standardized in this no
section minus Phi's you structure this
also the order which chunks may appear
for details for the encoders chunking
[Music]
I'm gonna look just before I go any
further I want to look at the contents
of the file here right from when we read
it in at the beginning I won't look at
the contents of the file as just raw
memory just so I can kind of see there
we go
what's actually in here so if I go ahead
and switch this to four byte integers
you can see the PNG header part is here
in here you know what I mean
so that's the eight bytes and then in
here so it looks like to me that this is
an ND in this issue right because look
at this value it looks like that would
be the correct length but it's in the
high bit instead of the low bit so it
looks like PNG is big endian god I hope
that's not true is that really true
does it have a section on Indian Asst it
might be switchable I'm assuming it
might be switchable but I don't know I
would say I would have expected them to
talk about this the fact that the phrase
Indian appears nowhere in the spec white
border there we go well let's use the
chrome relevant bytes shall be in
network byte order the most significant
byte comes first then the less
significant bytes in descending order
yeah bad wrong incorrect false but there
you have it right and so what that means
is that when we read one of these we
have to reverse the byte to come in them
so this length is not actually the
length it's actually the endianness
swapped version of the length so when we
read it we've got to swap it in like so
we've got to swap it round I should say
and so what I want to do then is say
okay when we read one of these like this
I got to do this and there's really not
much we're gonna be able to to get
around that
that's just how that's gonna go so when
we read the thing in we have to consume
the data in that format I really hate
that stuff I can't stand the fact that
we still have big endian it's just a
waste of everyone's time to even have to
think about it at this point
it drives me up the wall but sadly
that's just where we're at anyway it's
pretty easy to end even swap a value I
don't remember if we talked about the
Sun handmade here or in the past but if
we get a 32-bit value where we've got
it's the wrong way round so that we've
got you know the least significant and
most significant buy it's swap so
basically if we want the order of bytes
to go least significant bop-bop most
significant and we've got the opposite
so we're getting most significant
bop-bop least significant or something
like this either one of those two if
it's just which whichever one of those
two it is if we want the other one
to swap them all we have to do is
exchange the places of the bytes so if
we've got four bytes zero and three need
to get swapped and one and two need to
get swapped of our bytes right so we we
know how to do that we know how to pick
those out of a data stream right and I
can show you pretty d constructively how
it would work here so let's suppose we
have our value let's do it like this
so let's suppose we have our value here
we know if we want the first byte the
let's say the least significant byte of
the stream right that gets us the least
significant byte another way to say that
would be you know don't shift it and
just end it with XF that gives us the
lowest bite right here I can shift
again here I can shift down again here I
can shift down again right that would
extract each of the bytes in order then
if I want to build up the new value
right I can just say okay I need to
order these together and what I want to
do is put them back in the opposite
order they came so what I can do here is
say okay b0 used to be at the 0th
position I want to put it up at the 24
position now right and then I can take
b1 and put it up at the 16 position and
then B to put that up at the 8th
position right and b3 at the zero
position right so that's wops the order
of those things around oops that's not
we're doing here we're signing it back
right so that swaps the order of those
values for us and it swaps them you know
it replaces the existing value with the
swapped value now the thing that you can
notice here is that the I the compiler
may be smart enough to just realize what
we're doing and do it correctly but what
you can see here is you don't really
need to quite do it that way because
what you can see here is b3 gets like
shifted down 24 ANDed and then shifted
up 8 or whatever b2 is shifted down 16
and then up 8 what we could do instead
is just do one shift that shifts it into
the right position and then one mass
that masks it out correctly right so you
can do a more condensed version of the
swap if you want to so for example
if you take a look at what's going on
here let's suppose we just inserted b0
as a term b1 as a term b2 as a term and
b3 of the term right so what we see
pretty early on is that like b3 for
example just works that is exactly where
that value needs to go right it just
gets shifted down 24 and masked off by
FF but do we really have to mask it off
by FF no because this shift will shift
in zeroes for us and there's nothing up
above it so really that's all that's
happening right all we're doing there is
just saying okay we just need to shift
it down 24 that'll just leave the eight
bytes exactly in the lane that we want
now this one that shifts down sixteen is
then getting shifted up by eight right
so it's going down 16 but then it's
going back eight the other direction
right so really all that has to happen
there is it just has to get shifted
eight that's it right but in order to
when we do shifted eight we need to
block out the part that we're talking
about there right we need to block out
the the part that we're actually
interested in because it still got cruft
on either side of it right so what we
want to do specifically there is make
sure that we're we're knocking out only
that one part of the value that we're
actually trying to put in right which is
this part right here because that's
trying to get that Lane right so we got
the least significant byte we've got the
next two least significant byte we've
put it in place and we just need to make
sure that this cruft isn't still there
right and that's all we need to do for
that now this one is the opposite of
that this one's going down eight to mask
it but then it was going back up 16 so
instead what we can do is just say look
that's just a shift upwards by eight and
now the same thing happens right we just
need to mask it with something that will
make sure it clears out the other
part of the craft so that we don't have
to deal with that right and furthermore
if you look at what's going to happen
here there's a number of things you can
sort of see going on one of the thing is
well it'd be nice if these two masks
were the same we actually can make those
two masks the same because if you think
about what's happening here we could
just choose two masks beforehand right
if we mask this guy beforehand here like
so then this would be the same mask so
we could use the same mask twice and not
have to neat use an additional mass
because we just an first and then shift
right and then finally this one is one
that's just up in in the that needs to
go up in the top it starts at the bottom
same things true here right we can mask
that off early and not have to load a
large mask in and then we can just shift
it up by 24 to put it into the correct
place now here's the thing why would we
mask it at all if we're gonna shift it
all the way up 24 places all the stuff
that would have been there he's just
gonna get obliterated anyway so we can
again just like we did in this case when
you shift one byte from the bottom or
the top all the way to the position all
the other values get shifted out so
we're left with a pretty straightforward
way of doing this once you work it all
through that you can kind of see here we
end up with this fairly nice-looking
little bit of code here right shift V up
24 we or that with V and F F shifted up
8 we shift it down 8 and and it with F F
again and then we shift it 24 right
and so that's the concise way of writing
it it's pretty nice right
and so that's nice and clean right it's
pretty good so what we want to do here
now is just verify this actually works
at all I mean that would be nice right
so if I go ahead and say let's make
value to start with something that we
understand right that's a really easy
bit pattern to see and so now we can do
is we can watch it swap and put it into
that position right so let's just do
that there we go
so I'm gonna go ahead and run to there
and if I go ahead and watch here's my V
value in hex and here's my actual stored
value and when we're done you can see
you see how that flipped it so it was
four or three to one and then it's up to
one two three four right and so that's
the nd in reverse that we need to do to
make sure that we get out the value that
we expect okay so now let's get out take
out the nerfing there like so so now
this will actually swap real values for
us so now we can jump in here and take a
look so when we come through here and we
look at the chunk header when we endian
swap that now we're gonna see that the
length is actually a much more
reasonable value there we go now we
don't know what the padding algorithm is
here so I don't know if these numbers
should be padded out that's something
we're gonna have to look at and see but
we should know right away if it is or
isn't because remember this is a chunk
data format so he's fixed each chunk
chunk chunk chunk chunk if we jump
forward by the amount as specified which
is 13 now that we've read it in
endianness format correct right what
we're gonna see here in this in this
next go through on the read is we should
now see another valid chunk header and
we do right so it looks like they're not
padded out so here's our bkgd that's a
background data trunk probably I'm
guessing just by the name
again a short one so there we go and we
just you know keep on reading here and
off we go so now let's go ahead and take
that because that's all well and good
and fine now that we're reading this a
little bit more correctly and we figured
out that a little endian problem what
I'd like to do now is just have this
print out what we're actually seeing the
files so we can look at it cleanly so
when we come through here after we do
our Indian swap I'm going to do is I'm
going to print out what the type is for
each of the chunks in the file so when
we get the chunk data out here what I
want to do is now I'm just going to
print the header in fact I could print
it right here there's a probably I could
have done that a little bit differently
I'm not gonna bother though who cares
there we go
so now we should be able to do is run it
like on a file like this and it should
tell us all the chunks and now we could
see that we're actually parsing the file
correctly at least for this kind of file
because you can see we didn't have any
underflow like we've read exactly the
amount of data we should have read and
you could also see that we got exactly
what the spec said we should get an AI
header at the beginning in an AI end at
the end and then all of this is just
data information that we can choose to
parse if it's something that we think
affects the image we actually care about
and not if it doesn't so for example T
ext chunks I'm guessing just based on
the name that that might be something we
don't really need to parse yeah and you
can see here it just contains a key word
and texturing in the following format so
there's a key word character string a
null separator and then some other text
string here so what I could do there for
example is just look and see if I if I
want to to check like that could do
something like this
[Music]
can you do so here's the question for
you this is macro land for CC is usually
the name of these kind of codes they
like four letters for a type code thing
for whatever reason um can you do that
by extracting the letter information
from this I'm just curious
so for example if I have to do the
following could you just say alright I
want to take the string that you give me
and I want to extract the 0 the 1 the 2
and the 3 from it like is that on the
table I don't really know
guessing the answer is now it's one of
those macro things I just don't really
remember and so what was this it was
like txt yeah oh let's see here so I
want this to be cast to AU 32 actually I
want that to be true prior to this so
I'm really surprised that that worked by
the way if it worked that's pretty cool
so does that actually work so where is
the Derrida's holy cow
well that's pretty great alright so
that's a pretty easy way to take a
string and turn it into a 32-bit
identifier just automatically I wasn't
sure if that was kind of work but that's
pretty cool you see I've seen a lot of
times let's see if I got I've seen a lot
of people do it like yeah like that
right I've seen a lot of that garbage uh
and it's just dumb like this stuff is
just like look at how stupid this is
right and like this is way better if you
can do it I don't know if you can do
that
maybe you can do that but this seems
really good if you can't write my that
was this was another thing I was going
to try I'm not sure if that does work
may see if that other way works too but
anyway the only reason I want to show
you that was I didn't know I've seen
I've seen a lot of people do it where
you have to put commas in between like
that and that's just annoying so anyway
let me see if you can do it that way I
didn't think you could do this then
again I didn't think you could do the
other way either
that's great so these are real easy then
those are so much better than the
comma-separated versions so that's cool
I'm happy about that
all right so that makes it really easy
for us to sort of switch on which type
of chunk we're getting um so what I want
to do here is like here's the thing that
consumes the chunk data right and what I
probably will do here is just say look
well consume the chunk data at the
outset and then I'll just do a switch on
the type and then we'll just put some
cases in here so here's the cases that
we saw can I do those as constants
so there we can now see the benefit of
this approach I guess so mine is better
than the Castillo pointer because this
weight properly evaluates to the
constant as well as the compiler is
concerned in the other way didn't
so that's relatively important so I
think that's where we're at
alright so we had an I had our chunk a
bkgd chunk the phys chunk at T IME chunk
a text chunk I'd at chunks and an end
chunk so that's what we saw all right so
a txt chunk supposedly it's like just
textual data you could print that there
so in theory we should be able to just
do this where we just say okay the chunk
data is just a string now there's I
think there's two strings packed into it
actually
so we actually would print out more than
that one
but in theory so there you can see so
let me just see what this says in the
spec for what's in there we can go ahead
to txt textual data oops that's the
wrong one
so for textual data it just says the for
my Trinity of just with values each text
chunk it takes a keyword and a text
string in the format keyword null
separator texturing it's so I guess we
just say keyword string care star key
word equals chunk data care star spring
goes keyword while star string plus plus
string right so we just basically say
look go till you hit the null terminator
and give me what's what's after it right
it looks like they don't know terminate
the other one right because you're
seeing garbage at the end there so it
looks like you're expected to null
terminate it yourself I'm guessing at
least that's what appears to be the case
so like wherever the chunk footer is at
that point is the part that would need
to be the the null terminator so what we
can do here is to say RA like you need
to
print out only a certain amount of this
string and the amount that you're going
to print out is going to be whatever the
null pointer that whatever the end of
the chunk was we'll just say that that's
that's as far as you can go because it
looks like that's not null terminated
only the first part is looks like yeah
so and also I guess the problem here is
that it's only gonna accept that on the
printout which is fine we know it's not
going to be more than that so that's a
text chunk that's gonna be the easiest
thing probably that we can interpret
let's see which other ones of these we
care about we that was just a little bit
of practice we probably don't care about
most of the other ones here but let's
just verify that's true I don't know if
it is or not so we want to just go ahead
and see what all the rest of these
chunks are before we decide what we need
and what we don't need because who knows
all right so let's take a look at the
first chunk we've got here which is the
bkgd chunk we know we have to read the
header what one it's the default
background to present against if there
is any other preferred background
user-supplied yes so we don't care about
this color because our background is
always transparent if nothing specified
there so we don't care about this right
this is ignored let's take a look at the
fizz tunc
took the picture size an aspect ratio
don't care about that the time chunk
don't care about that and technically we
don't care about the text chunk either
so at that point we're just down to this
it looks like these are the only things
we care about the header and Alice see
the end chunk I don't even know if we
care about is there anything in it no so
if we're looking at that we're basically
looking at I think all right seems like
that's all we really care about so at
that point we're just like all right
that's all we're looking for in this
file that's the only thing that's
actually gonna have information that's
you know relevant to us we're parsing
them out so now we've got the two things
we need let's start with the IEEE header
chunk because that's the one that's
probably easiest because it's not going
to have any compress data it's just
going to tell us like what we're
actually doing so you can see that we've
got this nonsense going on here it base
says width height bit depth color type
compression method filter method
interlaced mess it's just telling us how
to read the file right it looks like
that's it so it looks like really the
rest of this is just telling us what
these things could be so let's just go
ahead and get those values out let me
make a structure that leads out that
exact thing
PNG I header so that's going to be the
width
oops the height the bit depth
color typed oppression filter interlace
so you're fine go ahead and consume one
of these I actually don't have to
consume me because we already got it
it's right there so if I go ahead and
get one of those then when I look
through here I should be able to print
all these out so again the width and the
height are actual have to be any in a
swap right because they're gonna be
stored in net reporter much to our
chagrin but then everything else we
should be able to print out doesn't see
whether that's an unsigned integer or a
signed integer I'm gonna go ahead and
treat it as unsigned cuz I don't think
you're gonna have negative with the
height that may not be true it may be
that no it says right here for byte
unsigned integers so that's good there's
no negatives sometimes they like what we
saw when we parse bitmap oh so long ago
negative means that's flipped in that
along that axis it looks like we will
never have that here it'll always go in
the same direction so that's nice that
just makes things a little easier so
let's go ahead and print out the rest of
this
so what else we got clark's i freshen
method filter method into lace method
okay so now we should see data about our
image coming through hopefully it's all
correct
there's the width the height the bit
depth color depth compression filter
interlace what you can see here is these
are exactly respect the only thing I
don't see here is anything like how many
bits per pixel there are things like
that I think that's because color type
is probably just a value it's going to
tell us all that information and we just
haven't looked at it yet so color type
six probably means our GBA we'll see you
in a second compression filter new lace
method I have no idea what they're
actually telling us I assumed interlaced
method 0 means non-interlaced I assume
filter based filter method 0 means
non-filtered I assume compression method
0 actually does mean compressed because
this image is smaller than it would be
if it wasn't compressed I assume 0 is
actually defaults to LZ or something
like that we're gonna see in a second
what that is so let's go ahead and take
a look and see what those values
actually translate into it might be the
compression a zero actually means
uncompressed and it's actually talking
about some other thing that we're that
it's not the bit plane did or something
I don't know but let's see so bit depth
to the single byte integer number but
for sample that's that we respect we
want that to always be 8 so that's gonna
be a requirement probably if it's not 8
then that's an error I would say
probably color type is a single byte
enjoyed 5 PNG image type of values are 0
2 3 4 and 6 so here's 0 2 3 4 &amp; 6 we
only accept true color with alpha so we
are only accepting 6 so 8 6 is the only
thing that we will actually accept right
so this right here 8 6 that's the only
thing that we'll accept right so
basically we'd say if the I header bit
depth is not equal to 8
or the I header color type is not equal
to six unsupported it's gonna equal true
or something like that right so there's
gonna be basically a boolean here that
says that this thing's unsporting what I
might do instead is something like this
I might do it affirmative Lee just
assume it's not supported it here will
actually set it to supported when the
bit depth and color type and everything
else says exactly what we want so if
those two things are correct then we'll
say it's supported and off we go
all right what what what was the problem
syntax error yes I crave that all right
so what we want to do now is look at
these compression filter interlace
things cuz we don't know what those mean
so let's take a look at that compression
method is a single interesting just
immense to do suppress the image only
compression method zero is defined in
this international standard so that
basically means that we're going to be
using compression method 0 these are
Ann's now so compression methods gonna
have to equal to 0 that's one thing
we're gonna support so I think it's even
in the spec filter method single-byte
interested in kiss Priya has some other
deposit image data for question filtered
zeroes defined that means we're you know
another good spot there because we only
have to handle one case although that
probably there's a bunch of cases inside
that case but whatever you don't I set
this thing about if it's shorter the two
values can find these just there's 0 no
delays or one atom 7 we may just require
okay so that's gonna be what we require
in terms of what comes out of here so
we've got the I header just fine now we
just need the I bat and that's gonna be
where all of the grievances come in
because that's gonna be the actual place
where it's compressed and has all kinds
of crap in it and whatever else so let's
jump down there and see what we've got a
four byte chunk field edge to the actual
image data that mr. compression
algorithms see Clause nine filtering
close to and compression details there
may be multiple I'd add chunks they
should appear consecutively with no
intervening chunks which they did the
issue is the concatenation of cost at it
fields in all the Ida X so who knows
what that means but we'll see you in a
second so let's start by looking at
what's going on here filtering
transforms PNG and just the goal of
improving compression so check your
method zero we got a bunch of stuff here
averaging we'll talk about what these do
in a second here
let's deflate inflate oppression of a
sliding window with super valid supreme
blah blah deflate compression lz77
derivative deflate compress data streams
within PNG restored in the Zeeland
format which has the structure this crap
further details on the form are given as
you look specification for PNG
compression method 0 0 the compression
method flashcard specify method 8 assume
this is telling you how to set it up if
you were calling the other piece of code
I guess whatever
[Music]
tu-tu-tu-tu-tu-tu so this is really not
so I guess we're gonna have to look at
the Z Lib standard to figure out what
the actual data stream encoding is is
that really the case you didn't bother
to put it in the actual spec that's
really bad but okay
would have been nice so where is this
actually to find let's see data format
is probably what we want on page four as
either stream at the following structure
CMF FL g if FL g f2 said it could press
data adler 32 any data which may appear
after the others they're not fuzzy them
streams see him as compressed method of
flags pressure max is 0 to 3 the infos 4
to 7 compression method file CM 8 just
to deflate compression method for window
size up to 32 k so i'm guessing that
that is not stored in the actual PNG
file it's just assumed that that's there
seems like it for compression method a
Chris Jess or the deflate compressor for
it turn the document to flake for
service are you kidding me
so they referenced a file which itself
references a file that actually has the
format you could have at least
referenced the file that actually had
the format in it fantastic
see why I said this would be a pain in
the butt here we go
all right so overall clinch the diagrams
little box like this represents one
buying two box like this it's a variable
number by its original bit order
associated you never bite consider
intermediates or fire bla bla bla bla
bla bla bla when in the computer okay
yes that's all good packing the bytes
the time does not address the issue of
the order in which bits of a byte are
transmitted on a bit sequential medium
since the final data format described
here is byte
rather than bit oriented however we
described the compressed block format in
below as the sequence of data elements
of various bit lengths not a sequence of
bytes we must therefore specify how to
pack these data elements into bytes to
form the final compressed byte sequence
data elements are packed into bytes in
order of increasing bit number within
the byte sorry with least significant
bit of the byte that omits other than
Huffman codes are packed starting with
the least significant bit of the data
element often codes are packed starting
with the most significant bit okay
in other words if one were to print out
the compressed data as a sequence of
bytes starting with the first byte at
the right margin and proceeding to the
left with the most significant bit of
each byte on the left as usual one would
be able to parse the result from right
to left with fixed width elements in the
correct okay well.alright prefix coding
orifices symbols with from an a priori
known alphabet by bit sequences one code
for each symbol in a manner such that
different symbols may be represented by
bit sequences of different lengths but a
parser can always parse an encoded
string on a biggest Lee symbol by symbol
we define a prefix code in terms of
binary tree in which the two edges
descending from each non leaf node are
labeled zero and one in which the leaf
nodes correspond one for one with are
labeled with the symbols of the alphabet
then the code for symbol is the sequence
of zeros and ones on the edges leading
from the root to the leaf labeled with
that symbol for example and here we go
you can see how they've got the tree set
up now this is setting us up I guess for
just straightforward use of Huffman
coding Huffman encoding of course which
I don't think we've really talked about
the stream before but let me just give a
really quick overview of what this
actually means it's it's pretty
straightforward but the implementation
stuff can get kind of hairy so I don't
know how crazy it will be in paying
but here you go
so this idea is really pretty
straightforward let me explain how it
works so normally what we would do when
we go to encode say a just a simple
piece of text even right is we have
something like an ASCII code which is
just to say that look how many things do
we need to encode well we need to encode
like about 128 things right that's
roughly how many we have to encode for
ASCII so what we're gonna do is say well
128 things well that's 2 to the seventh
power right so what we're gonna do is
we're going to use 7 bits of information
and we're just going to give each thing
that we might want to say each symbol in
the alphabet if you will ABCD efg
semicolon return space whatever we're
gonna give that one combination of 7
bits that says which one it is so if we
then look up what the ASCII
specification says as I spell that wrong
if we look at what the ASCII
specification is you can then see here
is the table that unambiguously assigns
a 7 bit code to a specific thing so you
can see 0 2 128 you can see what all of
it corresponds to and you know off you
go
right very very simple and
straightforward it's great it's fine
it's wonderful whatever so the problem
you get into coding stuff like this is
this not very efficient because well let
me bring that tree back up again
actually the chance is if you're
concluding a piece of text that you
might want to code say the letter s are
actually quite high whereas the chances
that you're going to encode s 0 H start
or Soh start of heading a code which
literally no one encodes anymore for any
reason I can even think of is very very
low so even though you know that s will
happen all the time and start of heading
will happen like never you end up
spending the same amount of bits to
write both of them so from a compression
standpoint we're wasting 7 bits on an S
right which we'd like to store it much
more concisely and it's also 7 bits to
store our
of header which as far as we're
concerned could take like 50 bits
because we're never going to store it so
in terms of the size of our file storing
seven bits for both of these is not a
very good trade-off because this happens
almost not at all and this happens all
the time right that's the fundamental
starting point for compression is to say
look what am i storing most often and
let me try to use the fewest possible
bits to do that because I want to assign
the fewest possible bits to the things I
store a lot and then I'll use more bits
to encode things that I don't store very
often that's the trade-off right so
fixed in coatings are really bad at that
because they assign the same number of
bits to everything and that just wastes
space because not everything has an
equal probability of being specified at
all times right so a Huffman tree is a
simple way of starting to attack that
problem what it says is well look what
if I made a tree of bits such that you
didn't always have to use all the bits
so for example I'll just start with one
bit and if that bit is zero that's an S
just period if the bit is one then I
will actually look at the next bit and
let's if that's zero maybe it's an E and
then if it's one i encode other things
right and then maybe I've got a tree
that actually branches out a little bit
here to do the rest of them right and
what you can see from that is it ends up
allowing you to say if you just read a
bit at a time instead of multiple bits
at a time and start deciding whether or
not to output a particular symbol from
only reading a few bits that allows you
to use say two or three bits or even one
bit to represent some of the things in
your stream that happened a lot and then
you'll use a lot more bits to talk about
things that happen rarely right so
that's what we're starting to get into
here when you can see in
are we there here we go so in the
deflate you can see them making exactly
such a tree you can see that they've
said well okay if you see a zero let's
keep reading if you see a one that's
just going to be the symbol B right if
you see a zero then it'll be the symbol
a if you see a one after that we'll keep
going and then a zero and that's a D or
one it's a C right and so then you can
see here the code lengths for each of
these differ dramatically a B costs only
one bit to output and a cost to bits and
C's and DS both cost three dates three
bits so what you can see there is
they've taken something which used to
cost because it had four symbols it used
to cost two bits for every symbol and
what they've done is skewed it so that
now it takes three bits toutput c's and
d's
but only one bit output a b and only two
bits that put an egg right so it's again
it's just shifting how you allocate the
bits okay so what you can see here is
it's saying given an alphabet with known
similar frequencies the Huffman
algorithm allows the construction of an
optimal prefix code one which represents
strings with those symbol frequencies
using the fewest bits of any polish
previous codes for that alphabet such a
code is called a Huffman code and so on
now that's not actually true I think
that's actually stated a little bit
incorrectly there so Huffman coding
doesn't actually produce the optimal
prefix codes the reason for that is that
it requires an integral number of bits
it is optimal for integral numbers of
bits if I remember correctly but
arithmetic encoding or other coatings
that are similar to arithmetic encodings
allow you to use fractional number of
bits and that's important because what
you can sort of infer from what we
talked about before is based on the
frequencies that symbols occur you want
to assign the number of bits exactly
proportional to those frequencies well
the frequencies are probably not going
to be exactly integer it's not likely
that a occurs exactly twice as likely as
B right a probably occurs in the bit
stream maybe 1.7 times more likely than
B in which case we'd like to have a take
one
seven times more bits than B not twice
as many bits as B and that's where
Huffman falls apart because Huffman can
only do integer numbers of bits because
as you can see it's a tree shape
arithmetic and other coatings like RNAs
or things like that or just ans in
general those are about assigning
fractional numbers of bits and they're
more advanced codecs they're better
right but if you just want something
that's more straightforward and it's
you're okay working with integral
numbers of bits then Huffman's puffins
you're your jam right okay
so let's see how they use it here
because you know Huffman can be
implemented all sorts of different ways
usually the Huffman coding is a format
the Huffman codes used for each alphabet
the deflate form have two additional
rules all codes of a given bit length
have lexicographically consecutive
values in the same order as the symbols
they represent so I think that
I don't understand the use of
lexicographically in that sentence to be
honest with you so I'm gonna have to
keep reading I'm not a compression
person so it could be that that use of
lexicographically is very common but
it's just I don't really do much
compression stuff so I'm gonna have to
take a mulligan on that one and keep
going we can be cured the example above
to follow this rule as follows assuming
that the order of the alphabet is ABCD
we get ABCD so it looks like what they
mean is that the code as interpreted
from left to right will always the
higher code goes first I guess I mean
I'm not sure how else to interpret that
because you can see here that they were
just like oh yeah well you know C and D
I had 0 1 1 and 0 1 0 before
that's becomes 1 1 0 and I mean well ok
so they did two things
first of all they inverted the tree
right so they they're actually doing the
tree slightly differently they're 0
precedes 10 which precedes 11x
in our example the code is completely
defined by the sequence of bit lengths 2
1 3 3 the following algorithm generates
the codes it's introduced intend to be
read from most less food cooks are
initially in treat Outland the codes
produced in tree i dot code interesting
so I get what they're doing here I'm
still just not sure I totally into it
exactly what they meant by that so what
they're doing in a high level though is
quite clear they made that quite clear
what they want to do is make it easy for
them to announce the format of the
Huffman tree that's going to be used and
obviously one of the things that you
want to do if you're doing compressed
file format is you don't want to spend a
lot of extra space describing the thing
that you're using for a compression so
if they have to give us information
about this Huffman table which of course
they are sorry I should say trait
Huffman tree that we are going to be
using to decode the thing they need to
specify it in a way that doesn't take
more space than necessary otherwise
they're wasting space in what's supposed
to be compressed file announcing things
about how they're compressing it so what
they wanted to do was say look let's
take all of the ambiguity that doesn't
matter out of this table and just say
here are the rules for how we will
specify Huffman code so we can give you
the least possible amount of information
so what they want to do is transform you
know I mean you could imagine a really
piggy way of describing this table of
actually sending down the tree with like
nodes and which nodes point to other
nodes right we could actually send down
a whole tree descriptor obviously that
weights a ton of space so what they're
gonna do instead is they're gonna say
look I'm just gonna tell you what the
bit lengths are and then we'll just have
a rule that says when you're assigning
bit lengths you do it exactly like this
so if I say that you've got a 1 bit
field here here's what that means right
so they've sucked all of the ambiguity
out by saying look we don't care how
these bit streams are necessarily
allocated right we just know they have
to be these lengths so if we just come
up with rules that go directly from the
bit length to what the bit field should
be then all we need to do is transmit
the lengths not anything else about the
table and you can fill it in the rest of
it yourself right so that's just same
space and that's just what they're
trying to do there right so that all
makes sense that's we'll come back to
that in a second ok so that's a B C F
with bit links 3 3 3 3 3 2 3 2 4 4
this expands it out so we've got that
step which I don't quite totally
understand yet but we'll go back to
later
it's basically saying this piece of
information came in from the stream we
need to go from that piece of
information to this symbol table which
says what the code is for each of these
things right and then we go through here
and talk about how that's actually gonna
come about so let's move forward and
we'll go back to that later
okay so each block of compressed data
begins with three header bits the first
bit says be final the next two bits say
b-type be final is set if it's the last
block so that's how we know that we're
done I guess and b-type says either it's
uncompressed it's compressed with fixed
Huffman codes compressed with dynamic
Huffman codes dynamic Huffman codes
means they change as you go and 11 is
like we don't use it yet right so then
we go alright the only difference
between compressed cases is how the
Huffman codes are defined in all cases
that a coding looks like this read the
header if it's no compression we just
grab everything we need otherwise if
it's dynamic Huffman codes we read the
representation of the code trees and
then we loop until the end wheel to code
literal if the files which we copy the
value otherwise we get out of the loop
and we use a lookup this is an lz77 loop
here we'll talk about that doesn't a
second move backwards copy the length
from a blob the duplicate string
reference may refer to a string in a
previous block docker just may cross one
of our block boundaries every distance
cannot refer past the beginning of the
app extreme that's all fine we'll talk
about all of that in a second preset
dictionary might discard part of the
output stream a distance can refer to
that part of that machine anyway yeah
this this is all fine so now I'm
compressed blocks are just a chunk of
data that's gonna be trivial right
compressed blocks are basically an lz77
thing which we'll talk about in a second
let's see here
compression with fixed Huffman codes
chests are fixed and are not presenting
to us today therefore code thanks to
literal are Oh
the Hoffman codes to do us are fixed and
are not represented explicitly in the
data the Huffman code thank she's a
little length alphabet are
interesting are they saying that it's
actually a thing that you just use
that's not even stored in the stream I
assumed fixed meant it would put it in
the stream maybe that's not what they
mean we'll look at that in a second
with dynamic Huffman codes shows for in
the blood the huffing codes the two
alphabets appear in the block
immediately after the header bits and
before they okay so this is not these
are not what I thought they were very
interesting so what I assumed when I saw
fixed and dynamic Huffman codes what I
thought they were talking about was that
fixed Huffman codes would be ones where
it just put the Huffman codes directly
in the stream you read them and then
used them and that dynamic Huffman codes
were ones where as you saw symbols you
updated the Huffman tree yourself that's
like an adaptive it's called adaptive
Huffman usually I believe that's not
apparently what they're talking about
they're actually talking about a fixed
Huffman code is one that's just pre
stored like I guess it's just in the
compressor and it's just saying use this
known set and it maybe that's like just
because they find a lot of data has this
pattern so they just I guess so it
sounds like it's saying here don't quote
me on that yet and that dynamic Huffman
codes are actually what I was thinking
of as fixed up in codes meaning it
actually just stores the Huffman codes
in there it doesn't look like adaptive
Huffman makes an appearance
it looks like adaptive Huffman is not on
the table which is nice it makes it
easier for us if that's really true
maybe I'm mistaken about that we'll see
as we go a little little further on all
right so moving along here let's see I
think that's it so this is the this is
what we're gonna have to start parsing
out of the IDE at again this is where
all of our work is gonna be like I said
you can see it's pretty complicated as
formats go it's not that complicated so
at least that's good it's not a jpeg or
something like that where we're gonna be
into like IDC T's and a bunch of stuff
that we really don't want to be spending
time doing so it's not that bad but it
is finicky and so it's gonna take us a
while to get this going thankfully
they've given us the outline of how they
believe the compression code generally
works so we can work from this
pseudocode and sort of start to get into
something that we're that we'll be able
to use right so let's get just the very
basics out we've only got about ten
minutes left so I'm not going to try to
do anything fancy here tomorrow we'll
start on the eye that's in in more in
earnest and so what I want to do here is
just say all right we know that we need
to create some room for this data to be
sort of decompressed and so what I want
to do is create sort of a buffer here
that's the resulting image so this is
the decompressed pixels here that's
going to start out being 0 then what I
want to do is if this is a supported
bitmap here then I want to go ahead and
allocate the the data for it in here
right so what I want to do is I want to
allocate the pixels here I want to use
the width and height as we talked about
so I know that it's going to be the eye
header width by the eye header height
and I know that we've got 4 bytes per
pixel so I'm going to go ahead here and
just stub this in because again this
will be something that we only care
about a little bit later on when we go
to merge this code into handmade hero
we'll want to allocate this from like a
data store that we actually know about
right so here's the result we got our
width height and our bits per pixel so
what we want to do is malloc exactly
that amount and return that so here
we're going to get the width times the
height times the byte per pixels which
should give us enough room to decompress
the thing that we wanted
so we're gonna take the decompressed
pixels here allocate those and then when
we get into this I dot chunk what I want
to do here is I think the i dot chunks
it's the thing that's a little bit
confusing about them is I don't know how
ident chunks writing works so what they
said is there there can be multiple
idaite sumps in the file I don't know
why there's multiple itit jumps in the
file maybe there's a good reason for
that we'll see maybe you could specify
different compression information for
each one of them or something like that
so I don't know why there's never an eye
on the file so there's just one eye that
trunk that's all the data in it maybe
we'll find out later
maybe there's no good reason I don't
know but what it does mean is I don't
know if we're gonna encounter a
situation such as oh yeah I put a bunch
of deflate data in here and then the
deflate data would have needed to read
more information from the I dot but it
ends and then the information that the
deflator needed is in like the next item
right so if that ends up being the case
then what we may want to do eventually
is take these i dot chunks and make
something that virtualizes across them
so that when we go to get information
out it can pull from the idaite trunk
seamlessly I don't know which over those
gonna be true so I won't go ahead and do
that yet because it'd just be
unnecessary complexity if it turns out
not to the case but that's something you
have to be aware of because that could
be what they're setting us up for here
just for maximal annoyance I don't know
yet though so what I want to do first is
I just want to say like okay we need to
decompress pixels thing and it's
supported so I'm gonna say supported is
the trigger that lets us know that
decompressed pixels is dr. gonna have
something in it so let's start looking
at the Ida chunk to see if we can just
get the basic stuff out first and then
we'll come back to the deflation part a
little bit later on so looking backwards
here at the compression format stuff
what I want to do is start to look at
what's going to be in here
again we don't really know exactly
what's going to be in the IDA chunk
because it's it was kind of a a so we're
looking for it was it was a very poor
explanation right it just kind of waved
its hands around and said I don't know
there's some stuff in it right
so we look at an image chunk it just
says here's the decimal values for the
thing that's that's just the thing says
I'd app and then it contains the image
data and it says nothing else about it
right nothing else about it so what we
want to do is look at these two to see
what it actually says and that's what
we're gonna have to try
so filtering transforms the PNG image
with the goal of putting compression PNG
last number of filter methods and all
the bah-bah-bah right what these are
going to be I'm almost certain is
filtering is going to be something that
tells us how the pixels relate to each
other and so what you often times will
do if you have an image right you know
that you're gonna be feeding it through
a certain compression algorithm at the
end right and that compression algorithm
was gonna do things like take chunks of
repeating data and compress them down to
smaller amounts right so if you see the
same pattern over and over again whether
that's a big run of zeros or a bunch of
you know repeating little pieces that
all like happen again that's the sort of
stuff that will start to suck up in the
deflate algorithm which we'll talk about
a little bit later so typically what you
want to do with an image beforehand and
PNG does a spectacularly bad job of this
their filters are awful but better
filters are not awful what you do is you
say well look but instead of just taking
all these pixels and feeding them
directly to the thing what I should do
is have some transform on the pixels
that tries to put them into a space that
might make it easier to compress them in
that way for example maybe one thing I
could do is take the average value of
all the pixels and subtract that away so
I just get like pixel differences or
something right that would mean that
only subtle changes would have to be
recorded which would reduce the size of
the pixel information which would then
allow the compressors Huffman tree to
use less space to encode the small Delta
s blah blah blah blah blah right so the
filter part is just a pre pass on the
image that tries to get it into shape
what we're gonna have to do is reverse
up that that change right so in theory I
expect this to happen after compression
so I'm gonna assume that the compression
parts what happens first notice they
didn't bother say that right so the
specs a little annoying us what I was
talking about but what are you gonna do
um so if you're looking at here I'm just
gonna start with this and assume that's
what's in the data stream in the eye
that chunk even though nobody brought
him to say that why would you it's only
a speck and let's go ahead and see what
it says it says compress the method
zeros for me in our standard our values
are reserved
PNG gigabytes to 0 is deflate inflate
compressor a sliding window which we
have inspect for over there
it's an lz77 derivative which we know
and which we said and it has this
structure right so let's look and see if
this is what we see right let's just see
if that's what we see so we expect to
see two bytes one that's the z lib
compression method and flags code and
ones it's additional flag and checks
bits and let's see if that's what we
actually get when we look at the stream
so that says and
and then we've also got a check value I
don't know what that means
probably something to let us know if
we've done our thing correctly let's
find out the feeder gauge mesazero
the sealer compression method slack code
shall specify method code 8 and Elsie's
the window size of not more than 3 to
768 the sealant profession Method number
is not the same as the PNG compression
method number in the I adore chunk the
flag shall not specify a preset
dictionary oh well that's good because
that means we don't have to implement
that code path presumably if the data to
begin press 15 blah blah blah you go to
Mesa the window size we're running up to
a power of 2 excretes the memory
required for mythic oh dear without
aversive Heather kris radio the compress
today within a suitably extreme are
stored as a series of blocks each of us
can represent raw data that's so good
the check 5 sword is calculated on the
uncompressed data represent data stream
that the algorithm you screw strikes
it's not saying seriously used to PHP 0z
check files to be a cross-check deflate
inflate does it say does it bother to
specify what is it just me or do they
just totally skip how the CRC was good
it is not the same as a seriously
calculation for the PNG chunk oh so I
think they just it's just whatever
Zealand would have done so I think they
just kind of they're just leaving that
to the Z Lim spec so that's fine alright
so let's take a look at what does this
look like right so let's take a look at
the at the PNG i dot header and just
look it looks like and that's we're all
in the stream and the tomorrow we'll
tackle the that part we'll tackle the
sort of like starting to get the
deflate coder working right so here's
the i dot header and i'm gonna go ahead
and just say look let's let's take a
gander at that data that's going to be
this where is this
trunk data here and what I want to do is
just inspect those values I guess and I
can inspect those values based on what I
read in here there was information about
how that was going to be stored right in
the Zealand part of things
mm-hmm so this is what it told us we
would be seeing it told us we would see
a compression method and it's saying in
the P&amp;G spec that this has to be 8 so
what we can say here is if bits 0 2 3
have to be set to 8 then 4 to 7 is the
the information we need to figure out
what the window size is right so let's
just see if we can get those two values
out and then we'll call it a day oh and
then we can also look at the flags we
can get out the F check the F dict in
the F level right so let's try to get
all of those out so let's go ahead and
get the CM the C info of the F check the
F dict
and the F level so the compression
method is going to be in the Z Lib
method flags that's going to be in the
bit zero to three is the CM so bit zero
to three is just the first four in
theory so the Z lib method flags and oxf
should give that to us and then if we
shift down the remainder by four that
should give us four to seven assuming
that we're looking at that correctly
four or five six seven zero one two
three so that's both tabs of that so
it's just two nibbles right we're just
getting one nibble out in each case the
F checked value is zero to four that's
in the flags and check bits for cmf and
flz the answers that see when viewed as
the city of Baton Rouge so is that it's
just is that just the thing
it looks like F check is just a like a
basically it error redundancy thing I
guess I don't know why that's there but
it looks like just another way of
checking things so we'll look at that in
a second I guess that the preset
dictionary is just bit five it's just on
or off right so in theory we should be
able to take well I guess we shift it
down by four and we'd get bit five right
that's bit five and then we want the
okay no sorry I'm off a little bit there
so they want 0 1 2 3 &amp; 4 so they want
the first 5 bits here so they're
actually looking this is a bigger value
so it's actually that right where we're
saying okay
Oh what's the wrong one there it's
actually that is what we're talking
about here so this F check is the first
5 bits then we shift this down by 5 and
get just the 5th bit out then we look at
big 6 and 7 for the F level okay
so now let me go ahead and print these
out just so we can see what they are and
then like I said that'll that'll be it
for today there's see em there's info
there's effect there's the F dickin
there's the F level so if I go ahead and
run this now what we'll see is what we
think those values are right for the
iTap chunks and I thought I should make
this a little bit easier to read here I
just can I get again these so they're
more like a tabbed text file sort of
thing so here's our various ah dat
chunks and you can see here we've got
you know different values for each of
them what I would say just looking at
this here what you can see is the first
I'd a chunk has a values that look like
what we do expect let me double check
that so F dick predicts that dictionary
if after to set the dictators present
immediately after the flak if after you
said the dictation err identifier is
present immediately after the flg bite
the dictionary is a sequence of bytes
which are initially fed to the
compressor with that producing
compressed output dicta Sadler okay so I
think we do expect that to be zero so
looking at this here I would say that
and what's seven again it's the window
size that looks correct these don't look
at all correct so what I'm going to
assume is true is that these Ida chunks
that follow are just raw concatenations
that themselves do not actually mean
anything meanings so like they don't
each have a header it's what I expected
there are actually just things that will
get consumed as part of the main IDOT
chunk right so what we need to do here
is we need to sort of like aggregate
those forward and that's not a huge deal
like we can do that just fine but that's
what that tells me so we'll think about
how we're going to do that later but it
looks like we're okay there so let's go
ahead and go to the QA and tomorrow
we'll take a look at how to start
compressing this I - honks and off we go
instead of using the 4c Macker why not
just use a single coated literal for
example if chunk header type three
vehicles I header are you allowed to do
that everywhere is that only allowed in
Lexi xx you know 11 or 17 or something
what is wrong about using imagemagick
from the build system to convert all the
images because we want the artist to be
able to save out of Photoshop and load
and this will load directly in from the
game the game is supposed to load the
output that the artist six in the
directory just immediately
you see this don't think so
you used it 20 years ago really so you
mean this entire time when people have
been doing because I've seen so many
macro set you're saying you could have
done that that's pretty awesome and I
did not think that worked well so okay
but it's the wrong order is the only
thing right so you'd have to actually do
this right which is which kind of
annoying so that's probably why NPC 743
what mass which I need to know to follow
along should I learn linear algebra well
it depends you do need to know some
linear algebra to follow along but we
don't do much work with matrices it's
pretty basic so I would say that you
don't need to know much about like
matrix factoring and those sorts of
things so I would say probably just
basic vector like working with vectors
is probably all you would need a little
practice in falling along
just little bit brainstorming can
somehow zip F's law be used for benefit
on presumably meant huffman zip F's law
I don't think I know what zip f slaw is
it work if you beat about the type yeah
I mean like I said you kind of have to I
mean yeah we could do this right
I suppose that would work which is kind
of cool I I definitely admit I did not
know that that would actually work so
I'm totally down with that because hey
it gets rid of a macro that the way
doesn't do anything so I'm flying with
that
so somebody is posting zip f slaw okay I
will look at it many types of data
studying the physical inertia has to be
approximated with a zip fee and
distribution to one of a family related
to power law property issue oh so I
think I see what you're saying you're
basically saying are you just saying use
a preformed distribution
[Music]
so I guess I'm not sure exactly what
you're asking about the zip s law but
here's what I can say so compression
generally speaking when you get more
advanced compression they don't
generally ever want to use a
pre-designed distribution I don't think
because you want to be able to adapt to
your data better than that so I don't
think anything as simple as just
assuming that the distribution is a
particular type of distribution is
something that they do I'm not a
compression person so you really want to
ask someone like Charles bloom but if I
had to guess what Charles would say I
think he would say something like what
you want to do is create systems that
can articulate their distributions
cleanly in a very concise way so that
depending on what kind of data you see
on the compression side you can quickly
articulate the distribution as easy as
possible to the decompression side so a
lot of times they'll use adaptive
alphabets right so as you see symbols
you adjust the tree so the decoder never
has to be sent a dictionary it just
figures out what the dictionary should
be as the compressor is doing it and so
on things like that but again that's a
question more for compression person not
for me I don't do compression how could
someone abuse the PNG loader you brought
up malformed code yes so the all I meant
was if you want your program to handle
like possibly garbage input you need to
put checks in and guard for that we
won't be doing that so someone could
construct a PNG file that would cause us
to crash or produce an exploit in our
code for example by setting the bits of
the i dot chunk for example to make our
lzd coding loop crash by looking into
memory that doesn't exist or something
like this right
and so if you want to ship something
robust that you expect other people to
be using this not during development
like we're here doing here but actually
like as part of like Photoshop or
something you probably want to put in so
resiliency there so that if there's a
malformed data stream you detect it and
just produce an error message rather
than crashing or who knows what else the
PNG i dot footer should be 4 bytes oh
yes you're right it should be thank you
why are there several itit chunks and
not one single one I don't know you know
that was something I said before I did
not understand why that's the case I I
couldn't tell you I could not tell you
they obviously thought it was important
for you to be able to put multiple itit
chunks in but I do not know why it seems
like a strictly a waste of bits maybe
they wanted it to be CR seed in parts or
something or I don't know I didn't see a
rationale in the spec there in the part
we were reading so I don't know what
they're thinking exactly but they might
have one I just don't know what it is
not using be swap intrinsic instead no
is there a particularly is there a
reason why we would
because what actually what does that
actually supported on anyway
so are these just always available in LX
64 because if so yeah we could totally
use one I wish this stated explicitly
so it should be it should be in any x64
chip right so yeah we could do if we
wanted to we could do this let's see if
that works
wait a minute what was the intrinsic
says it's an IMM inte R in which I
included and it says its underscore be
swap why are you complaining about that
I'm not sure why it doesn't like that
let's let's take a quick gander cuz yeah
I don't know why I guess I have not used
that instruction but I agree it should
it seems reasonable hold on a second let
me just find out why it's not happy
about that
so in here if I include X amendment R in
let me just see what happens if I touch
B swap
so X mm and Trin is in this directory
right yeah so what I could do is say all
right look tell me where that is and
let's look at what what why doesn't want
to be you know what would I have to
define for you to give me that macro so
if I just say look in here tell me where
be swap is it doesn't seem to want to
give it to me oh so it looks like it
just they have their own built-in macro
for it is what happened right so they
they called it byte swap you long is
what actually happened that's look like
what actually happened so probably
that's it even though Intel defined it
as a be swap probably what happened is
they were like oh yeah Visual Studio
already had its own idea of what that
act 64 intrinsic was going to be and so
that's what it used right that's
probably what happened so what we can do
though here is to now take a look and we
should get that instruction getting
issued so here let me jump in there so
if I'd go to the disassembly here you
can see the beef swap is now getting
executed right so off we go
so yeah that's totally cool by me
I don't think that's the part of the
code that really matters much at all you
know what I image to know how smart is
the compiler there so if we do that if I
switch the build to optimize is it smart
enough to figure out it's a beef swap
and to insert the B swap instruction
assuming the VCR instruction is the
fastest way to do it which presumably it
is let's find out so here's this hey
check it out
it's pretty cool right the compiler
actually figured out that this sequence
of instructions is a byte swap it
pattern match that and just output it a
B swap anyway so hey you don't even have
to find the intrinsic it'll just do the
right thing so I may leave it like that
because this works everywhere and this
doesn't right so I may leave it like
that for now because it's it in an
optimized bill that actually generates a
piece off anyway
is the PNG loader to support allow live
art iteration on stream not on stream
just when Anna's working on the art
sorry if I missed it was there any
reason that rim types have the weird
mixed case like te XT and phys I don't
know here's what I would say about it I
don't know what the again I don't know
the rationale by most things in the PNG
spec and this is my first time ever
looking at it right is on this stream
I've never looked at it before what I
will say about it is if you look at the
actual chunk where is that list of
chunks error we had a second ago here it
is what I think what what it appeared to
be to me is that chunks that are not
super necessary had lower case first
characters right and chunks that are
super necessary had the capitalized so I
think that that was sort of their way of
saying look anything with a caps is
trying to tell you this is important
anything with a lower case is like other
sorts of information that maybe isn't so
important right
what's the 32-bit CRC for it's just for
validating the stream right in case
there was errors introduced in the
stream you just you'd know file formats
often have CRC's in them so you can tell
if they've been corrupted just in
transport or whatever else
it's
alright looks like we're all done
alright so I'm gonna leave that stuff up
oops I probably want to didn't really
want us to okay I'm gonna leave that
stuff up because I want to have access
to all those specs tomorrow when we get
back to it let me go ahead and clean
that up there we don't need that anymore
all right thanks everyone for joining me
for this set of handmade hereit's and a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you want to follow along with the series
at home you can always preorder the game
hand me a hero or gonna comes with a
source code so you can play around with
it I you can actually try implementing
the IDE at chunks tonight if you want to
that's what we'll be starting on
tomorrow I don't know how long it will
take I don't think it'll take that long
to just sketch out the decompression of
the eye that chunks the problem I'm
suspecting is when we get down the nitty
gritty there'll be a lot of little bit
twiddling things that maybe we
accidentally get wrong or whatever and
they'll take a while for us to suss them
out as it is we've at least gotten it to
the point where we know how big the
thing is going to be we can allocate
space for it and now we have a chunk
data and we know the format that it's in
so we're in relatively good shape to
compress them so hopefully it won't take
too long to get it to the point where
it's usable but that's what we're gonna
have to start on tomorrow so hopefully
we'll make some sniffing you're headed
by here hope to see you back here for
that until then have fun programming
I'll see you everyone in the Internet
take a desert buddy