hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Heroes show recoat a complete game live
on Twitch no engines no libraries it's
all us and we are actually at the point
where we have just wrapped up doing our
normal map code which was kind of cool
we still have some stuff we want to do
with lighting we we finished the normal
map stuff to a large extent but we have
some stuff we want to do with lighting
there what we kind of decided when we're
in the middle of that was that we was
really getting the point where we had to
sort of lock down all of our coordinate
system stuff in the renderer because
we've never really done that and it was
kind of getting to the point where it
was getting kind of silly because it was
really ad hoc and so we wanted to do
this week before finishing up the
lighting which is going to involve us
sort of playing around with a mapping
like some kind of a mapping to get
localized light sources we have our sort
of sky and ground stuff working
relatively well right now but we don't
have sort of local around you sort of
light stuff working well we wanted to do
before we went and did that was we just
kind of wanted to take a little bit and
go through the render as it stands and
sort of lock down okay what's the
coordinate system who's in charge of
doing what when you know what is the
format for the fit map at the end of the
day is it bottom-up top-down all these
sorts of things and so we you know it's
it's not glamorous work certainly but
it's the kind of work that you want to
do periodically because you don't really
want to let things kind of get into this
state where everything is sort of Rube
Goldberg II relying on hidden knowledge
about who flips what when and there's
lens up being twelve negatives and then
you add the thirteenth one so that it
can actually flip and they're all cancel
each other out and all these sorts of
things you don't want to get into those
situations so periodically when you kind
of get that feeling that it's a good
time to sort of start to solidify some
rules you kind of want to take the time
to go through and do it so that's what
I'd like to do this week I don't they
don't know that it's going to take a
week obviously but what I'd like to do
is start the week with that and just so
we have plenty of time
we need it to go through and just clean
out all of that stuff and you know sort
of have a really good idea of exactly
what the coordinate system is at all
times and there's there's some nuance to
that as well which is that Z is kind of
up in the air at this time as well and
so I feel like what we kind of want to
do in that in that process as well is
get our Z handling straightened out as
well because there was a bunch of things
about like when things get displaced off
of the ground
you know because since we're in
pseudo-3d we kind of have to have little
weird things that we do like moving
things up off the you know moving things
up in Y even though technically they
would only like be coming out of the
screen all sorts of things like that
so when we do this pass I'm also going
to be trying to get that stuff corralled
a little bit more because one of the big
reasons that we decided to do the
renderer at this time in the first place
was because we really wanted to get our
Z handling nailed down right and so we
kind of have to remember to keep an eye
on that at the end of this process when
the renderer that we're doing is done we
want to have that good Z handling in
here and so through that entire process
we kind of have to cop keep looking at Z
and going how do we want to handle this
what are the the you know different
rules that we're going to use what are
the different things we're going to
support and so that's the other thing
that when we go through this process to
sort of clean up our screen transform
stuff now would also be a good time for
us to think about how that zinnias get
cleaned up so today is day 104 so if you
have pre-ordered the game on handmade
hero org and you have the latest source
zip go ahead and unpack day 103 out of
sources out of there that's where I'm
going to be today and so you'll be right
on right on target you'll be right where
I am so if you remember where we left
off last week when we finished
everything in terms of the normal
mapping we sort of finished off just
having the sky and the ground reflected
and we were pretty happy with where we
ended up with that but of course we
still have you notice the middle of our
sphere is not reflecting anything that's
the
Green map here which we have not done
anything with yet and so while we have
sort of a a notion of how the sky and
the ground is reflecting we haven't done
sort of the near-field reflection stuff
and so we're going to just post or we're
going to leave that here where it is
because we're relatively confident that
we're doing the basic reflection stuff
correctly although we you'll notice the
ground one of the motivations for going
through and doing the coordinate system
fixes because right now we actually
don't have the ground and the sky into
in the right places right the sky was
the blue one and the ground was the red
one and that's part of that whole y flip
coordinate thing so there's a couple
things like that that we want to take a
little bit closer look at and then of
course we want to start working on our
near field lighting the middle of the
reflection here and we also have some
stuff we want to do with glossiness and
other sorts of things like this so we're
just gonna put that on hold for a second
remember at all and we're gonna then
just pop over to doing the coordinate
system pass and see if we can't nail the
cornices and pass down then pop back
over written you know sort of return to
the normal map stuff at which point we
know that we straightened out all of our
coordinate things system things we want
so we can make sure that all of the
normal map stuff now is absolutely
working in the correct coordinates paces
because that's one thing that we you
know again don't really want to do we
don't want to go in here for example and
fix this so that it's reflecting the sky
in the top and this in the bottom when
we already know that the coordinate
system stuff is not really being handled
correctly through the pipeline because
at that point what we're doing is we're
just adding a bug on top of a bug you're
sort of adding you know making adding
that second negative to reverse a value
that shouldn't have been negative in the
first place right and so you really just
don't want to do that you want to make
sure that you have the minimal number of
Corrections in a pipeline as possible
you want Corrections to actually be
correcting for something real you don't
want them be correcting for things that
were done improperly up in the pipeline
because later on if you then go to
correct the things in the pipeline up
you will break the stuff later on that
was depending on those bugs right and so
that's again just to reinforce it that's
the reason why from this point here
where we're at I feel like it's a good
time for us to address those other
issues so there we go that's that's
basically what we're looking at so let's
just start we have sort of a lot of
looking to do here so let's just go
ahead and start defining things so we
have our handmade render group right
which is the what we're sort of using at
the moment to build out our renderer and
the way this is working is we have our
push buffers and the push buffer is the
thing that we put all of the render
elements onto like everything that needs
to get rendered could gets an entry into
this push buffer and then it goes out to
the renderer and the renderer just does
whatever it needs to do to make that
happen right to sort of go through all
those commands and make them occur and
so right now we don't really have that
many different types of things we push
on there but what we can already see
even from the basics and you know we can
discount the coordinate system at the
moment right so this one is our test one
right this guy right here this is only
for test this guy is is the thing we
were using to do our normal mapping and
stuff like that so we don't really
necessarily care about him too much but
we want to do is start to look over
these guys here and maybe what I'd like
to do is go ahead and switch back to
rendering the game that we have it as we
had it before we were doing the normal
mapping tests and sort of work from
there to figure out
you know how we want to start
rearranging stuff that get submitted to
the renderer to make sure that
everything is okay and so this is the
code right here that we were we were
using and so I'm just gonna go to draw
the normal map stuff I'm just gonna go
ahead and get rid of that for the moment
right I'm just gonna go ahead and get
rid of that entirely and so if we run
the game now we should see that we don't
actually render it we don't do any of
this mapping stuff we don't draw any of
this coordinate system stuff none of
that should be happening as you can see
we just have a much more straightforward
situation okay and then we have to kind
of come up here and get us back to a
situation where we are actually drawing
everything in the game now if I remember
correctly we actually also had a thing
I'm trying to remember how we ended up
commenting this stuff out so we had our
standard room stuff like it's been so
long we were working on the renderer I
don't even remember what stuff is is
turned on and turned off with the way
that we were doing things in here but
anyway so we it looks like we're still
constructing our world properly I
believe it looks like we that's just
initializing like ground chunks and all
those sorts of things we turned off
generating our ground buffers I suppose
I could turn those back on for the
moment let's go ahead and do that just
to make sure those are still working
although it doesn't appear like they are
although I guess that's only on
executable reload so presumably that's
just the thing that all that actually
does this is force them to regen so I
suppose I don't actually need to turn
that on and so we come through here
here's our you know our adjustment code
for actual controls here's our world
chunk rendering which still looks like
it's active so it looks like we still
actually built everything so I'm
guessing that really I thought we'd
turned off a bunch of stuff but I guess
we didn't I guess all we did was just
inside the render group did we just turn
off the render calls I guess that's all
we did it looks like we just turned off
the bitmaps so I guess we really don't
have to do much to get back to the state
that we were in if I'm not mistaken
about that it looks like this is it just
just turn that bag on and there we go
looks like I also have to update that
for the fact that we changed it to have
a color an actual color value there so
yeah okay if I run this now it looks
like we've got we've got our whole world
back so I guess they're really high I
thought there was I thought we had
turned stuff off we hadn't so we're back
to exactly our game state that we wanted
to be back to so now we can just go
ahead and start trying to make sure that
the render is doing everything that we
want to do I'd like to turn off so that
we can see the edges between those
ground patches
excuse me I'd like to be able to see the
edges between those ground patches and
in order to do that I'm gonna have to
turn off those yellow lines the reason
that I want to do that is because we're
gonna be playing a little bit again with
scaling things up and down now
and because of that I'm a little bit
concerned that if I didn't have if I
have those lines on I won't be able to
see seams or edge problems between the
world tiles so I want to turn off those
yellow lines that we're using for debug
because they're they're gonna be
counterproductive at the moment even
though there are handy so we can kind of
see where our ground tiles are at some
point we you know they're actually going
to obscure potential bugs and so I want
to remove those so let me go ahead and
turn that off I believe it's just this
guy right here and so that'll get rid of
those lines and you know we can even see
actually right now there there actually
are seams between these guys that we
weren't seeing right and so somewhere
along the line when we had those on
probably because of our Y flip again
right because you can actually see these
are these kind of look let me double
check here yeah these kind of look
exactly like they're out of order so you
can see that that little splat right
there looks like it's probably the
bottom of that thing right so these are
kind of going in the wrong order as well
so yeah again just wanted to turn those
off so we can see it because we're
playing we're gonna be trying to get all
this coordinate stuff nailed down we
certainly don't want things that are
gonna obscure obvious bugs like that was
doing so first thing we're going to do
is we're basically we're going to sort
of define a couple of things up here so
we're gonna talk about what the render
has sort of how the renderer is working
here so we're gonna say a couple things
because based on what we've done so far
we kind of know what they are so
everywhere outside the render
why always goes up upward right so it's
always X X to the right and Y upward and
I feel like there's really hasn't been
any problems with that so far our only
problems that is where we have allowed
sort of Y up versus Y down stuff to leak
you know in and out so we want to we
want to go through and make sure that
that's always true the other thing we
want to do is I think at this point we
might as well switch to a bottom-up
bitmap because we actually did work to
give ourselves a top-down bitmap but now
since we're doing everything in that
bottom-up fashion it seems like we
probably just want to switch to being
bottom-up everywhere right and so all
bitmaps including the render target are
assumed to be bottom-up meaning that the
first row pointer points to the bottom
most row when viewed on screen right and
so there's a couple things that we have
to do to make that happen one is a lot
to go back into the platform where and
change a little bit about that
potentially and another one is when
we're doing our bitmap loading we may
have to do a little bit of changing
there so we'll do that finally I guess
probably what we would want to say is
well you know I think that may be it for
now I was gonna say we might want to
talk a little bit about what things are
specified I guess what we could say is I
guess everything like unless otherwise
specified all inputs to the renderer are
in world coordinates which are meters
not pixels and so we'll have we'll you
know anything that is in pixel values
will be explicitly marked as such so the
assumption can always be basically that
everything is going to be in meters
unless otherwise marked
and I think that's probably a pretty
good idea finally as far as the Z stuff
is concerned I think there's maybe one
more thing I want to say which is that
at this point now that we've sort of
gone through enough things I think I'm
kind of comfortable saying I think the
world should just be broken up into
discrete Z slices it really feels like
that's just the way it's going based on
everything that we've done and you know
when we're talking about having sort of
the reflection mapping as well and and
the different layers it feels like we
just want to say we just want to put our
foot down say we're not going to get any
benefit out of having anything other
than discreet Z slices there can be
holes in the slices potentially but I
think we want to say that there are and
so you know I guess I just want to say
something like the world is sure I
should say Z is a special coordinate
because it is broken up into discrete
slices and the renderer actually
understands these slices potentially
meaning that we we're not going to force
the renderer to be Z agnostic the
renderer can if it wants to think about
the fact that there are Z slices for
sorting purposes and all these other
sorts of things because it seems like
that's going to be the way that things
want to go just to based on everything
we've done so far it feels like it's
gonna be hard to make the code work
properly if Z is arbitrary because
there's so many things due to the 2d
nature of how things are working that
really want to know about sort of these
chunked aspects of the ver of the sort
of depth part of the world I think
that's pretty good I'm gonna go ahead
and start with the easiest one today
which is just that the render targets
are going to be assumed to be bottom-up
I think we can get that done relatively
easily and so I'm going to make that be
today's task so let's go ahead and take
a look reach back into your memories for
when we were working
this code way back at the beginning and
we had our resize dip section and the
resize dip section code of course did
this sort of allocation where it was
grabbing using virtual Alec it was
grabbing a chunk of memory and that is
what we were using for our display
buffer correct and so I believe that
what we were doing per the window
specification is if you take a look at
this specification that we were giving
to windows here this is the actual spec
we pass it this this buffer info thing
you can see that that gets passed when
we actually display the buffer this
buffer info is the thing that tells
windows how to interpret the memory that
we allocated so that it can blit it to
the screen and one thing that you'll
notice is there is a negative on the
height and that is windows convention
for saying that something is top-down
windows by default because of the os/2
days long story not worth getting into
they started using bottom-up as their
convention for how things were stored
and something still wanted to be top
down so they introduced a convention of
a negative height means that the height
is going to be interpreted top-down
right so it's almost like a flag they
just used that that high bit to say so
so all we really have to do I think at
the platform side of things right is
negate that right so if we go ahead and
negate that then when we actually run
this we should have at least I would
think I guess I lied I feel like that
should have flipped us around
did it not buffer in photo buffer height
and stretch di bits actually does but
for info
they both use buffer info so I feel like
that should have done it yeah that's
kind of unusual to say the least but
that definitely did not flip this upside
down I mean our guys is there oh alright
I guess I just did not restart I was
like that should have done it so there
we are we're upside down now right and
that's exactly what we want cuz now at
least we know that we're drawing that
our first row is kind of that bottom
round and so now what we want to do is
we want to go into the renderer and
start to work out how to make sure that
it's now going to render us flip to the
right way given this okay so that's
pretty pretty straightforward so be
coming here to our render group and
let's go ahead and take a look in here
and we got quite a bit of stuff that
that comes through here that works with
coordinates and you can see a lot of
things where reduce these negative
offsets so really there's not much we
can do about this other than kind of
going through and taking a look at
things one by one again this is sort of
why I'm saying now is a good time to do
this because you know we've written a
bunch of exploratory code but we're
starting to write real code now like
especially when we go to start
optimizing things that's gonna be code
that we're gonna want to keep and once
you start getting a lot of code in there
that you want to keep it becomes
difficult to go in and make subtle
changes like this and you know your end
up having to look at a lot of code and
see what it's doing and so that's again
kind of the reason why I want to do this
now I want to make sure that basically
where we're sort of set with a good
coordinate system from here on out so
that we will never have to worry about
fussing with that again so all of these
things let's see bilinear sample that's
you know these are using wise that are
going upwards it looks like again we've
got kind of that convention in here for
all the new stuff that we wrote it looks
like we wrote it so that our Y's were
generally going upwards and so that's a
good thing sampling the environment map
again that looks like that's going
upwards as well and so on let's take a
look at this here we've got the x-axis
y-axis stuff that's coming through
the origin properly and so on that all
looks good yeah this all looks good
nothing really unusual here now you can
see this is also its pre stepping and
it's pre stepping properly so this is
not adding in any kind of displacement
so that's also correct not going why up
so this all looks pretty good I feel
like for the most part that looks like
that is it's kind of working the way
that we expect it to so I'm gonna leave
that be for now that looks fine that all
looks pretty good and let's go ahead and
take check draw a bitmap draw a bitmap
is so you can see you can see here that
again it's using that same pre stepping
pattern so there's no that does not look
like it's trying to accommodate for any
sort of offset stuff there so that's
good this all looks like it's working
properly so it looks like the drawbitmap
code is also working properly why up so
it's really just the inputs to it it
looked like that would be wrong for the
most part I believe so let's see here
we've got our saturation change code
which someone asked me to add that's
just kind of sitting there that
obviously is operating on all the pixels
so it really doesn't care so here we are
in some draw a rectangle code this draw
a rectangle code looks like it's
treating the Y's and the X is relatively
straightforwardly and again that's
construing an outline it wouldn't really
care again which direction the Y was
going per se so I think that's probably
fine we've got our mat and that looks
good as well again no apparent pre step
problems there so this all looks good so
it looks like most of our code looks
like it's pretty sane nothing
particularly weird going on there but
here we now we're starting to get into
stuff
that's got it baked in so you can see
this is now handling these two things
a symmetrically right we are sort of
having all of our of our points come in
with Y going the wrong direction right
so you can see there is that negative in
there and what an interesting thing
about this is it looks like if I wanted
to I could do entity ground point here
as a v2 and take that screen Center
right and just do screen Center plus
plus that right plus the entity base P
XY right because this is just this is
the exact same equation in both cases
right nothing particularly weird going
on there and that means we can also do
essentially probably that that same
thing where if this is the equation for
the center it's the entity ground point
X and then the entity base is offset so
we could we could also similarly its
route point entity ground point we could
similarly just take these guys together
like so and then just add in this this Z
offset here right like that
yeah so that looks all pretty reasonable
see anything strange there now this is I
feel like this is something that this
has sort of that that zenus in it so I'm
gonna go ahead and put it to do here
we're gonna introduce a to do term I
think that we can search for later which
is like you know Z handling is going to
be our term this is our to do and I'm
just going to put that in here
in fact I'll just make a little cut and
paste er that I can use here and so as
we go through this when I see things
when we're we've got that Z handling
baked in I'm just gonna tag them and
that way we can go through on a second
pass so after we finished getting the
top down stuff going and we want to
start working on the Z and how we handle
that we don't have to go through and
look again cuz will already know kind of
where it is all right so let's take a
look here now we've got the render group
to output call the render group to
output call is just what interprets
everything in our push buffer
it looks to me it looks to me here like
we don't have anything particularly
weird going on in here
these are just kind of passing through
for the most part and calling utility
functions they are not really
interpreting the the Y at all
this guy is again our test code so we
don't really have to care too much about
that well we'll revisit that again in a
little bit
our allocator obviously nothing weird
going on there our push render element
is just a thing for creating stuff on
the push buffer so here we go down to
push piece push piece again doing that
negation so we want to get rid of that
negation certainly now the alignment the
alignment is interesting because I would
like to also know where that alignment
is coming in the alignment would have to
have the Y would have to have some
opinion of how the Y is supposed to work
as well and so we should probably go
take a look at how we are computing
those alignment values when we load the
bitmap right because if I remember
correctly we kind of have a thing in
here where we where we sort of load our
bitmaps and make those alignments like
so you can see these alignments are
actually done they're kind of baked with
the top down miss in them right this is
a top down value and that's technically
wrong so I don't know exactly how we
want to fix that I would say that we
probably want to fix that right here at
the head end so I think what I might do
is say all of these alignment values
should actually be correct coming in so
I'm gonna do set top down a line or
something like this I'm going to go
ahead and introduce a function that we
can use so that we can keep the data
being specified the way that it was
because that may be a very intuitive way
to specify that data coming from an art
tool but since we want all of our stuff
to be in this particular coordinate
system which is not what was
which is where we read these values out
of if you remember correctly and you
know we'll have to think kind of more
about how we're gonna get these at the
end of the day but at least for now
we want to make sure that we've got that
handled properly and so those alignment
values just taking a look at them yeah
so I thought that should pretty much
handle it so if we take a look
hmm keep head torsos top-down online the
only problem there well I guess they are
all they're all what they are all Hiro
bitmap types so I guess this will work
okay but it's gonna be a little bit more
complicated function if you think about
it because since it is a thing which
actually has three of these in it we
have to go sort of looking to see how
those are going to be aligned I guess
they're always all the same size and so
I guess it doesn't really matter so I
guess mm-hmm the thing that I'm trying
to get across here what is happening am
i closing down mischeif is mischief just
crashing or something mischeif was
closed before remember the other time on
the stream and I don't know who is
closing it is it me I'm not sure oops I
don't actually want to do that I wanted
to load it in the blackboard there we go
yeah I'm not sure what's going on there
but anyway day 1:04 so what I wanted to
say about that was just that you know
we've got these these sort of bitmaps
here we've got these bitmaps here that
are like you know head torso I don't
even remember what they are
head Cape torso yes okay torso we've got
these bitmaps and we were previously
specifying stuff from here like down
right we were saying how to get there
from here and we have to flip that
around so that now instead we're telling
you how to get it from the bottom up
right Matthew
math style so that this is our
coordinate system in order to do that in
order to
that we need to know how high the thing
is right because without knowing how
high the thing is we wouldn't know
actually what that difference was going
to be and so the weird thing is that
that actually is going to work because
all of these are always the same size at
the moment but that's kind of one of
those things where each one of these
should really probably have its own
align eventually when we get into
animations stuff more because we
probably won't want them to have to all
be the same size that's just the way
they happen to be now because they're
exported for the same source so anyway
let's see if I go ahead and make this
function set top down the line and
that's going to take the hero bitmaps
yeah here are bitmaps so then all that
really needs to do is just take a look
at the first one really and take a look
at whatever that height of the first one
is and it's gonna take the align the Y
component of the align and again we just
want to kind of flip that around now
it's a little bit delicate because again
we actually need to make sure that we
get it exactly right and if we were to
flip it like this what would happen is
remember the height is going to be one
greater than the maximum Y value for
that bitmap right because let's say that
there were 50 let's say the height was
50 well the maximum Y value would
actually be 49 so if Y was set to 49 we
want it to be on the zero width row
which means we really want this to be
minus 1 right we really want to talk
about it it's it's a little bit of a
fence posting thing there right I'm not
a fence post oh I don't know what you
call those just the off-by-one kind of
thing we want to make sure that we
reduced fi 1 so that when we have an
alignment that's right on the edge it
becomes 0 which is what we actually
wanted so that's actually what the
alignment actually has to be so here we
go it's passing that align we set the
align and now we can go ahead and and
and record it properly right like so I
think that's all we really have to do
for that I don't think there's anything
else so when was that
downline is fixed so that's good let's
pop back over to the render group so now
when we subtract the alignment that's
that'll work properly both in X&amp;Y they
can be handled symmetrically no problem
they're both correct and so that's good
but again that's assuming that the
bitmaps are also bottom-up which we have
a necessary done yet so we're gonna have
to do that as well let's keep going
through here we have again that negation
on the offset Y which we didn't want
we've got our pushed render element here
everything else in here looks relatively
good it's just storing things up nothing
particularly weird going on there we've
got our rect outlines again nothing
we're there iteration coordinate system
so all of that looks relatively good to
first approximation let's go ahead and
close this out and so now we should get
a situation where we are moving properly
which we are and everything should be
going in the correct direction but all
of our bitmaps should be upside down and
the reason that they're upside down is
because we are not loading them bottom
up yet and so that's the next thing that
we have to do there which will be I
believe pretty pretty straightforward
okay so let's let's get started with
that open up handmade that's too creepy
so when we load our bitmaps right we've
got our bitmap debug bitmap loader here
when we load our bitmaps you can
actually you can actually kind of see
we're looping through them here you can
actually kind of see that when we get to
the end we actually go through some
trouble to flip them because the BMP
file format actually normally does store
the things bottom-up but what we did is
we pre stepped to the end of the bitmap
right and then set the pitch to be
negative so if we want to undo this that
so we were like flipping things from the
fact that they were already going
bottom-up so if we want to restore what
it used to work look like we can just
set the pitch back to be something that
steps through the rows in the order they
were actually in the bitmap file and
then just not do the pre step right so
take take get rid of that right and so
if we do that now we should actually
have things that are organized in the
appropriate fashion now one thing I
you want to do though actually now that
I think about it what I'd like to do is
I'd actually make like to make this look
like this and I'd like to just leave
this out like so something like this and
the reason that I wanted to do that is
just because in order to in fact I
couldn't do it like this as well just
whip that guy around what I'd like to do
is later on we might end up loading
things that aren't in that order in fact
I think technically speaking the height
in the header of the bitmap if it is
negative it's a top-down bitmap and we
just don't have any of those right now
and so what I'd like to do is sort of
say okay assert that that result height
is greater than 0 or equal to 0 I guess
and later on we might want to support
the ability to load in either direction
and so this is kind of a nice way that
we can just flip things if we need to so
if the bitmap itself was actually
top-down that would actually not cause a
problem for us we can just turn this
case back on with an if statement or
something so I'm not going to delete it
entirely I'm gonna leave it there but
we're just not going to use it at the
moment and so now we're back to as you
can kind of see we're back to relatively
good in terms of everything being sort
of aligned properly but I don't know if
you can see this here they're sort of
still a there's still a bit of a weird
like offsetting kind of a problem like
I'm able to walk through the tree line
above where the hole actually should be
right so we're not and you can see I can
walk into this line so we're still
offset where we're drawing just a little
bit offset from where everything
actually should be and similarly you can
see if I jump my z is actually going in
the wrong direction as well right I'm
going down instead of instead of up on
my Z which is obviously not what we
would have wanted to have happen ok so
but we're getting there we're almost
done so let's go ahead and fix that Z
thing first because that was kind of a
little bit funny as well so let's take a
look at why that is happening so when we
do our push piece and we
push our entities ease on there I'm
trying to remember exactly how all this
stuff works but I believe we have this
negation here where we're doing the
entity Z this negation again this is
sort of a Z howling thing which haven't
looked up but this negation was designed
to make sure that you go up the screen a
in terms of going up in Y right which
used to be negative now it's positive so
I believe that really all we're seeing
is the fact that that was negated to
make it work in the old scheme so I
suspect that yeah that that was the the
entirety of that problem
so that's leaves us with just this one
which is that we don't quite you can
kind of see we just don't quite pick the
right pace so it's like everything is
being offset up a little bit and it'd be
nice to figure out what was going on
there one possible obviously candidate
for that is that we've done our
alignment wrong even though I tried to
kind of handle that one thing I suspect
is that there might be other alignments
like for drawing the tree weed that we
haven't actually fixed because again
this was all very ad hoc it's very much
test code and so yes you can kind of see
here here's our wall function it's got
an alignment that's baked in and that
alignment means is that alignment is
going to be wrong right that's just an
incorrect alignment and so we want to be
able to adjust and here we go the sword
same way right so we want to be able to
make sure that these alignments are
adjusted and so that they're not all
kinds of all kinds of wrong in terms of
going bottom-up or yeah and in terms of
being expressed in top-down but done in
bottom-up and those appear to be the
only ones that we've got so that should
basically handle it so in order to do
that I guess what I'm going to do is say
I'm gonna do a little thing here where
we'll just do alignment and I'll do
top-down a line and we'll just do
something that actually just returns the
value for us like so and that way I can
do that pretty easily here again this
not code that I think will ever actually
need to use because we'll actually be
getting these alignments from the data
itself eventually when we have more art
assets and we have sort of more of a I
guess a stable data format that we're
loading that isn't just bitmaps but for
the moment while we have these in the
code I just want to make it easy for me
to deal with so that should make it much
easier to deal with so let me just
double check to make sure we've got them
all I think there was one more here if I
remember correctly it wasn't there one
more no there wasn't
so nevermind I guess we've got we've got
the sward we've got the wall and I guess
we just never used one on the familiar
so the familiar is just flat out oh it
uses the hero bitmaps align okay so
that's fine all right so well we really
need to do now is just make sure that we
have that top-down alignment function so
that all of those things are aligned
properly yeah and we can go ahead and
put that in here
there it is top-down line and that just
is going to do exactly what this other
function was doing it's exactly what
this other function was doing only now
hmm it does it just on the vector so
that if you happen to want to have you
know to do it without a full hero
bitmaps thing you can so here's the
bitmap there's the align and so what
we'll do here is say okay the align Y
again equals sir that that bitmaps
height minus one minus the align Y and
then we just don't return the Alliance
exactly what it was and so here we can
just do top down a line bitmap we'll do
it on the head we were and we'll pass it
the alignment that's all it has to do
like so and now
what was that yes cannot convert again
these all need to be pointers there we
go and now we may even be back to parity
yes we are there we go
lovely so now we no longer have any why
flippin going on and so that's good so
we're getting closer we're definitely
getting closer we've got the the
everything is bottom up which will help
us to when we do our OpenGL or honestly
I think it's probably I don't mean to to
spoil the surprise but honestly I think
we'll probably be able to do Vulcan I
don't know I mean we'll see but I'm just
assuming that based on the way that the
rendering stuff has gone so far it feels
like our software a renderer will be
fast enough to play the game and so we
will have the luxury of waiting for
Vulcan or something like that and that's
really what I prefer cuz way more low
level you know that'll be way more world
level stuff then then if we're really
open gel but anyway point being a lot of
that stuff tends to be about bottom-up
coordinate systems as well and so it
kind of also helps us not have too many
differences between our software and our
hardware pipeline which again just
eliminates frustration and confusion so
that's pretty good alright so next thing
we should probably do here we obviously
had introduced a bug somewhere with our
ground stuff is now flipped our grounds
are in the wrong places and so it would
be probably a good idea just to quick
take a look at what's going on there I
have no idea what is going on there so
we should probably take a look at that
and just see if we can figure out why
our grounds are wrong I don't know when
that when that started happening but so
in here we've got our ground renderer
like so it goes ahead and loops through
all the ground buffers we have and it
pushes them using the width and the
height let's see here
as is that an alignment value yeah it's
got the Delta XY so this is all this is
all done in Y up as you would expect it
to be I don't really see much in the way
of roblems here I'm going to go ahead I
am going to go ahead so that looks about
right
so our subtraction here that gives us
our Delta we know that all about is done
meters which is good so there's some
something that's a little bit odd but I
don't super understand is our push bit
map call actually directly in pixels can
that be true that's happening let's find
out I'm really glad we're doing this
coordinate system stuff because I don't
like having guests about these sorts of
things I like to lock them down and then
not have to think about them anymore so
that's gonna be very nice so when it
does a push bitmap call it looks like it
depends on what our actual setup was
here because it's going to call get
render entity basis P right it's going
to do this on it
which is kind of a lot of randomness and
so it is going to do stuff like meters
to pixels and stuff like that and so I'm
not entirely certain why what exactly
that's that is doing I'm guessing that
must be the alignment it is the
alignment so that's gonna be that
alignment is correct
because it's always going to be no
matter whether you're going top-down or
bottom-up it's always going to give you
the center right because there's no the
center is the same whether you're
flipped or not so that shouldn't be
causing us any problems so I'm wondering
if it's just in our ground chunk
construction code if we've baked in the
flipped y into there and we should
remove it if that is the majority of the
problem I'm
not entirely certain but let's take a
look so when we come in here we are
looping through a bunch of chunks
we are yep we sure did there it is and
that of course will cause the problem so
yeah perfect so I think we have now
successfully gotten rid of a bunch of
craftiness right we've got about eight
minutes left but we've gotten rid of a
ton of the craftiness there in terms of
people negating Y and other kinds of
ridiculous like that that we were doing
oh just working again there was nothing
wrong with that that wasn't bad what we
were doing it's you want to focus on
whatever it is that you're focusing on
so you don't want to spend a lot of time
all the time thinking about oh wait I
got to worry about this I got to worry
about that yep you won't you need a
certain degree of concentration so it's
not bad to do stuff like just negate why
because we need to do something or
whatever you saw me do that a bunch of
times and that's actually totally fine I
wouldn't have done it on the stream if I
thought it was a bad idea the important
thing to remember is always to know when
to stop and correct things and again
it's a little bit difficult because it's
one of those things which requires some
experience to know because it's a
trade-off right any time you go and stop
and correct things you're losing
momentum on whatever you're working on
you're losing the context mental context
or what you're working on there's a
bunch of cost involved to going and
doing something right that needs to be
done right but there's also cost to not
doing it right and so it's constantly
this trade-off that you're kind of
weighing and so I just kind of felt like
now is the time that we want to go
through and do that but again I just
wanted to make sure that everyone knew
it's totally fine that we did it that
way it's the way I recommend doing it we
don't want to always be in a situation
where we're paralyzed by worrying about
whether we're doing something correctly
or not you need to be able to make that
forward momentum make that always work
out fine as you sort of iterate on
things but then the important thing and
the thing that separates a codebase from
one that will work and extend overtime
from one that's just going to collapse
on its own weight is whether you take
that time like we're
doing now to go through and say alright
we've got enough down here I think we
know what we want now would be a good
time to solidify that so that we don't
keep accreting problems right so that
looks pretty good to me I think we're in
good shape there because now we sort of
gotten we've gotten this straightened
out now we may have there may be a
couple of things lurking in there
somewhere that we haven't gotten to but
at least we've got a pretty good handle
on these all working properly this all
bitmaps including the render target are
assumed to be bottom up is also true
right but we've got this situation where
we got unless otherwise so we haven't
really taken any look at either of these
two and those are obviously going to be
a bunch of work that we want to do and
so yeah so that's something that we want
to take a look at pretty soon here
that'll probably tomorrow's job since
we're getting to the end of the stream I
think it's probably a good time to to go
ahead to go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A I
can't think of anything else that I want
to do let me just think if there's
quickly if there's anything else that I
wanted to do before that's just a
five-minute thing I don't think so
because I think we want to start looking
at Z tomorrow but yeah yeah I think
we're all good so I'm gonna I'm gonna
call it there and I'm gonna go to the
Q&amp;A so if you could please go ahead and
post questions with Q :
before them so I can see them and try to
keep them to stuff that we've done on
the on the stream here so that these are
on topic questions if you want to talk
about on off-topic stuff come back 15
minutes before the stream starts some
day like 4:45 and that's when I answer
off-topic questions and stuff like that
all right
any questions questions questions
anyone
has this one wait a minute all right
this is not good what is happening here
my little question prompter is not is
not getting questions I wonder if my hex
chat is doing something weird well I can
read them here has this work fixed the
normal map issue or will we need to
address that specifically well I'm
trying to remember if we had any flips
in there but we can certainly treat
check we have we kind of need to go
through that with a fine-toothed comb
for other for totally separate reasons
as well but what I can do is I can go
ahead and turn this back on and and we
can take a look at what it looks like at
the moment so yes it has is the answer
Italy at least it has fixed the which
one of the bitmaps was at the top at the
bottom because that was just the case of
us of that routine wanted to interpret
it in this direction right
do you think that making the why
compared to develop will also help make
sense of game mechanics like gravity not
really because we didn't really have any
problems with that before most of the
problems that we have with any kind of
game mechanic stuff is just the fact
that we just the fact that we don't have
real geometry so we have to fake it a
lot of times for in a 2-d game and
that's a lot of complexity there for
stuff like gravity but there is one
thing that's nice about having y always
be up is that it always looks like math
right you know when you think about like
sine and cosine in the circle and
clockwise and counter clockwise
rotations those are all correct now
whereas before they wouldn't quite have
been right will we be implementing a
matrix affine transform in order to
handle changes to coordinate systems we
did so that's that's what this is I
don't know if you remember basically
this right here nope sorry not that this
this is an affine transform so I mean I
guess this might be a time to sort of
just briefly mention on the stream
because we're probably at some point if
we actually want to talk about matrices
more specifically we could talk about it
but Origin x axis y axis so what I would
invite you to think about remember we've
talked about this on stream a bunch of
times matrix multiplication stuff right
so let's say I have an incoming vector
and it's got px py and let's say one
it's three three dimensions X Y one
right this part here is where you get
the homogeneous coordinate system part
so if you're talking about multiplying
an incoming vector by a matrix right
well we've already seen what happens
here you remember this equation I've
harped on many many times which is that
our new point is always equal to the PX
times the x axis right
so I guess I'll just write JA an X for
that py times the y-axis and then of
course plus the origin right whatever
the origin is right we could call that P
origin or something we've done this so
many times right
we've done this and done this and done
this and done this well what's this
equation P XX p YY p 0 right well you
know from matrix the way we talked about
matrix multiplication right the way that
it works is you take like this and you
know this position in the matrix and you
multiply it by this you add them
together with this multiplied by this
you take this multiplied by this right
so it's PX times this py times that one
times this right and what you see if you
do that remember we did the column
picture before of the of the matrix er
the P X component multiplies the things
that are in this first column px keeps
multiplying that right it's PX times
this for this row its PX times that for
this row and it's 1 times this for this
row right so what you end up with is you
end up with this right here being the
things that are multiplied by px right
and this here are the things that are
multiplied by py and these are the
things that are multiplied by 1 right
and if you put that together what you
get is whatever is in here look we can
just go if we call that a whatever this
this row is in fact I can just do it for
you a x a y AZ I guess we might call
this a w bx b y UW + CX CY CW like so if
this is our matrix then what you
immediately see right by doing this
thing if we were going to do this
summing right because you remember how
it goes it looks like this it's PX ax +
py b y + 1 right CX that's on the top PX
a y + py b y + cy and finally just 1/4
down here so you get aw
plus BW that whoops no I didn't do that
quite right
sorry P XA w XA w py DW c w right so if
you take a look at how this works right
I mean all I did was the make
transportation like I said many times in
the stream right it's just a dot product
it's just this this this this this this
right you start here and here and you
work in and you multiply that multiply
add multiply add right then you go down
to the next road we do the exact same
thing what hopefully you can see here is
that PX is the common term for here py
is the common term from here and there
in the one right is the common term from
here
so this basically just equals px times a
whatever a the a vector right if this is
the a vector ax ayaw right its PX times
a plus py times b plus c right that's
what this is that's what this this
matrix multiplication computes and hey
guess what that's this equation right
they are exactly the same take a look at
that in fact you can look at them both
the same time if you want to write same
exact equation P prime equals px a ok so
px X py b py y plus C P Zero so what
that tells you is if you wanted to use
matrix math to do the things that we
were doing literally all you're doing is
filling out your matrix exactly like
this the x-axis x-coordinate goes here
the x axis y-coordinate goes here
nothing goes there right because we
don't actually want any additional value
we don't want px aw we don't have
anything for that right we've got the
y-axis is X here the y axis Y goes there
and nothing here and then for the CX CY
CW that's the origin the origin x origin
Y right
and typically people put a 1 here but
doesn't actually matter what you put
here for our purposes we don't care what
actually comes out but if you started
doing matrix concatenation you would
care and that's something we probably
won't cover today because we'll talk
about that if we actually start doing
major stuff but this
is the homogeneous matrix that you often
hear about this is you know for a fine
transforms right and for those who care
the upper part here that's the linear
part and this part here really is that
the affine part is the reason I say that
is because often times and again this is
sort of CG lingo to some degree because
I'm not sure a mathematician would
really be all that ok with how it's done
in CG but in CG terms the way that it's
usually said is you know if you take
that equation that we had P prime equals
px X ax s py y axis plus the origin
right alright this will just say oh if
you take that and you classify sort of
how it behaves well you remember I drew
the diagram I said ok if this is the
y-axis this is the x-axis this is the
origin right then the px X plus py y is
the thing that like scales and rotates
our points into the correct position but
it doesn't displace them so you know if
the origin of the world's coordinate
system and the origin of the transform
coordinate system coincided it would be
at the right place but if the world's
coordinate system is actually out here
right you need to add that origin and
that's why we add that origin in is to
displace the new coordinate frame to the
place where it actually is in the world
in addition to rotating and scaling so
typically what we talk about is the
rotation and scaling part is the linear
part and the death disk can make that
quite big enough that's the linear part
and the affine what makes it a fine is
the fact that we add in the origin right
so the fact that we have a displacement
in addition to a rotation in scaling is
the affine part right and another way to
think about that is the zero coordinate
doesn't move in a linear transform
there's no amount of rotation and
scaling you can do that would
the point zero-zero go anywhere why
because the point is zero zero which
means that the x axis and the y axis
literally drop out of the equation so if
you just have P prime equals px X plus
py Y you would literally not be able to
do anything with the zero point and so
because it's the center it's the
transform center right it's where that's
where the transform occurs around it's
where the scaling occurs or at the
center of scaling center of rotation so
nothing will change it but that's where
the affine comes in the affine part
allows you to displace everything by a
certain amount right and so that's what
how it becomes a fine eventually okay so
hopefully does that answer your question
I don't even know my little question
question grabber thing is not working we
have to figure out why I don't actually
know so I can't actually see what's
going on here but let's take a look the
mods had to do a lot of work today just
so you know uh-oh what happened were we
on the twitch frontpage or something I'm
sorry mods it had been so good for a
while we hadn't had people spamming and
trolling but I guess sometimes it
happens I'm sorry that you had to deal
with that and we all appreciate your
work very much as always I'm sorry that
you had to do that
Stegosaurus Casey maybe I missed it but
when will the zero during be done to
visually correct sprites in front and
behind the character as soon as we get
our Z slicing stuff figured out we can
add a sort for that but right now we are
a little it's a little too early because
we're not exactly sure what exactly
we're going to be sorting on so you got
to give it a little bit longer it's not
quite yet time to call the ball on that
q it's more correct to call that the
translation part the entire upper part
is a find so pseudonym 73 again is the
resident math person so much like I said
math people might be uncomfortable with
it I suspect that they are so maybe
maybe I guess what we could say is let's
just use what would be an unambiguous
term for this so that math people won't
have to be nervous about it because you
know they invented this stuff so one way
you could think about it is this right
here is like rotation and scaling right
it's also sharing but we don't actually
allow that really this right here is
translation right or you could think of
it as displacement or you could think of
it as the origin but it's not really the
origin probably the wrong way it's the
displacement cuz origin means things
that maybe are subjective so it's really
the part that's gonna translate so this
rotates the scales this translates this
part right here is there just to make
the matrix math again work out it
literally doesn't really need to be
stored so when you implement this you
can often just implement it like this
which is exactly what I've done here you
notice I just I just stored the three
vectors instead of doing this because
this part will always look like this
right up into the part where you start
doing projective things because there's
an there's a thing you can do where you
start introducing projection via the
homogeneous coordinate which is this
extra part that we added here it's like
that we have no need for any of that
stuff at all and so really for our
purposes we can really think of the
matrix is pretty much just being this
part but because the only reason I went
down this little math hole here was
because someone was asking about it I
just kind of wanted to point out what
those things are so that you start to
have a little bit of awareness of it but
I wouldn't really try to super
understand it just yet because we
haven't really talked about it much and
we haven't really seen any reason why we
would need to do these things and so you
know you typically want to wait to
understand something
until you actually have a good real good
reason to if you can because then it's
sort of a little more what I mean it
sticks a little bit better and so I just
wanted to give you this because someone
asked about it I just want to give a
little bit flavor but it's not really
the right time to dive into a lot of
this stuff
when you exit the program Visual Studio
says there are about eight threads
terminated is there more than one
threaded hand-made here right now yes
there are many threads in handmade error
right now unfortunately and the reason
for that is that the operating system
creates a bunch of threads without our
permission
basically so let me see if I can in fact
I'll just go ahead and break into the
bugger here what you can do is you take
a look at the threads here this threads
window and what you can see is this is
the thread that we actually wrote this
is our code and here are all the threads
that Windows is running so you can see
like directsound has two threat three
threads directsound
requires three threads so just the fact
that we started playing sound was there
right you've got one that's sitting
inside the mm api you've got a bunch of
empty DLL which are presumably kernel
threads doing something I don't know
that's a terrifying name right there oh
my god I don't even want to know what
that means
why is that in ntdll oh how the mighty
have fallen
all right anyway it doesn't matter point
being these are all threads that are
running we didn't write any of them we
didn't even ask for any of them but
they're just a consequence of using
Windows services because a lot of
Windows services are implemented with
threads in your process space now
eventually we will thread handmade hero
and we will have more threads that we
wrote but at the moment we aren't we
didn't intend to do that we didn't write
threads ourselves and do any threading
that was Windows creating threads for
its services that it just sort of forces
us to have and there's really nothing we
can do it about that
Coover Caleb would it be possible to
have the renderer set up so the world
curves back as you move along the y-axis
yes that is but that's kind of doing 3d
rendering at that point so the reason I
well I mean I guess what I would say is
the reason I don't want to do that is
because I don't really want it to look
like that the game so I apologize for
not showing how to do it but it's really
there's very little extra to do but it
involves having to do perspective
correction on your textures if you
really wanted to correct you don't
really have to do it probably I mean you
could get away without doing the
perspective correction and then
literally we've written everything that
you need actually for it because all you
would need to do again is is use the
texture mapper that we already wrote
right right now we're texture mapping
things this way and what you would need
to do is start texture mapping them this
way right like we have it so that you
have something that points like this and
it's assumed that this is always going
to be scaled outwards like that what you
would need to do is the thing that
allows you to produce smaller rows this
way and so typically the way 3d render
is actually work as they rarely operate
on quads they usually operate on
triangles and so you know in OpenGL are
something that you're talking about
something that looks like this but you
could write one that that's still you we
could still write one that was doing the
quad map or that way but anyway that's
really all you would be doing there's
just a couple of annoying things that
you have to end up doing to make things
work properly if you want to do it that
way and so I'm not going to cover how
you do that but it's not it could it
could be an exercise to the reader and
especially if you go read fabien z--
post if you remember I talked about the
rigorous blog post that there's like 12
articles on there or more that are like
it's seconds more than twelve I think
that are like graphics pipeline articles
he talked
about I think he probably talks about
perspective correction in there / w and
stuff like that
did I get all the questions I think I
got all the questions any other
questions
since I can't guarantee that I got
everything since my little questions
groups screener seems to not be able to
find the the hex chat dump
I wonder if my hex chat is busted
anyone all right looking like we could
probably go ahead and
and end
all right folks
I'll see any other cue Cullen's on there
so I am going to go ahead and and save
the mischief board hopefully I'm not
closing at this time hopefully it was
just me closing it before and it's not
like crashing out or something
so let's go ahead and close all this up
and thank you everyone for joining me
for another episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always I'm glad that we're doing a bunch
of cleanup it always feels good to get
crufty stuff out of the code and yeah I
mean I feel like the render is going
really well I've been happy with how
things are going I think it's gonna be a
lot of fun to do optimization work on it
to some kind of looking forward to that
so here's hoping that our near-field
light sampling won't turn into too much
of a rathole since I really just don't
know how we're gonna do it but so we'll
continue on we'll probably need a couple
more days
just to go through and finish up
cleaning out all of the coordinate
system stuff and just making sure that
that stuff works the way that we want it
to but hopefully we're in the
homestretch here maybe a week or two
more of doing sort of the lighting and
the cleanup before we can get into the
optimization stuff which I think it's
gonna be fun
and it looks like it's pretty fast too
even without having been optimized at
all yet I'm thinking that maybe that
means we'll be able to run the game and
software rendering for a good portion of
the development which is kind of awesome
as well so anyway thank you for joining
me I hope you come back tomorrow 5:00
p.m. same same time same place on Twitch
again if you want to participate in the
pre stream discussion we can ask off
topic questions that's our stuff come
about 15 minutes early about 4:45 p.m.
hope see you all there
in the meantime if you do want to follow
along with the source code at home you
can pre-order the game on handmade hero
org and it comes with a full source code
already as well as the assets that you
see here on streams so you can go ahead
and play around with it and learn for
the series it's a good way to do that we
also have a patreon if you want to
support the video series you can
subscribe to that we always appreciate
it there's a forum site where you can
ask questions and it's also got
community ports too Mac and Linux on
there as well as a as a anti episode
guide so if you want to catch up with
sort of the early
so it's if you're new to the series and
kind of want to start from the beginning
that's a great place to do that as well
finally if you're trying to watch the
series live and you want to know when
it's going to air there's a tweet bot
which is pretty helpful basically what
the tweet bot does is it tweets out the
schedule on the weekend and it tweets
out the when the show is starting every
day in the morning it says what time
it'll be and then an hour before it
tells you that it's going live so that's
a great way to do it too all that stuff
is is good so check it out and yeah and
I will sign off for now and I will see
everyone back here tomorrow 5 p.m. take
it easy everyone