hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we code a complete game
live on stream we are probably in a good
position to upgrade our profiler today
we fixed a bunch of sort of sensitive
stuff with it before yesterday it could
not do a couple things like it did not
profile across code reloads and you know
sort of some pretty complicated
intricate little little things in there
but we fixed them and so now our
profiling seems to be pretty solid but
our view like we have not really spent
any time rendering our profile and so
it's it's not really very usable right
now so even though you can get sort of a
basic idea of what's going on with our
profiler we need to take a little bit
more of a close like we kind of got to
get down into there in some place where
we're actually slaying it and give it
some upgrades like actually allow it to
show you know sort of more detailed
information give us a way to interact
with it that makes sense
we need to sort of get get that going so
I am going to start playing around with
that today and if you want to follow
along with me at home and you are one of
those folks who has purchased the
pre-order of the game
make sure you unpack day 258 source code
because that is the source code that I'm
starting with at the moment so let's
just make a brief sort of let me give
you a brief reminder of where we are in
terms of terms of the profiler and what
we might want to do with it
so at the moment you can kind of see
here we've got our we've got our
cutscene going here and we really don't
have anything in the way of UI for this
in fact it does it's not even smart
enough to start large in a way that we
can even view and all we really have
right now is the top level thing being
displayed by them and then the threads
that have ever been seen the system
there's nothing getting loaded in the
separate threads at the moment so they
don't show up as anytime take
whatsoever at this point but there are
reserved slots for them at the moment
and I can sort of move over here and I
can ask like what any particular thing
was we can get the file and line number
where that block began and how many
cycles it took and it's obviously
graphically displayed in terms of
percentages we can see that right now we
really even when we go into the game in
in release mode this was pretty tiny so
there's really not much work going on
right now if we don't include all the
debug like if we if we actually compile
in release mode but basically this is
just the top level so let's say for
example we were curious about why we're
taking so much more time in debug mode
than release mode right because for
those of you who were here yesterday we
ran in release mode this red block was a
tiny little sliver in release mode in
debug mode it's nearly a third of the
frame there or maybe exactly a tenth
flame possibly I should say even more
than throw to frame so why is game
update takes so much longer in release
mode is it in debug mode is it actually
just because the optimizing compiler
does that much more stuff to it or is
there something that we're doing in
debug mode like checking that takes all
that time and maybe we want to get rid
of those checks or make those checks
optional so that they don't slow us down
in debug mode you know stuff like that
is interesting to see we can't see it
right now so it would be nice if our
profiler could you know click on this or
something or have there be some way that
we could make this be interactive in a
way that that is useful right and
furthermore you'll notice that like
things behind this thing are still
interactive at the moment and we don't
want that either we solve that problem
right our system handles that graceful
you can see that if you're over this you
don't get any highlights for like these
things here right like there I'm
highlighting it but as soon as I move
over this it stops so our our system is
like unified in terms of hit handling
but right now we don't even mark any of
this as as hittable so if you're
hovering over it
you can still select things underneath
it which is surely not what we want it
anyway
so all of that stuff is busted and we
would like to sort of get in there and
fix that I think we also I'll double
check locks I guess we can do this
without you even change thing if I
change over to software rendering
I'm pretty sure there's a way to do that
somewhere I like that
so if we change over to software
rendering I think we also saw some
weirdness yeah you can kind of see if we
change over to software rendering we get
a nonsensical display here right you can
see that we have like it's all pink and
I don't know what's going on and I just
remember this being weird and it's like
it's filling the box right so it's like
it's not like it's not drawing anything
but it's definitely a little confusing
as to what it's doing and I'm not sure
what the you know I I don't really know
why that's happening so I would be
interested also to take a look at what
is going on with the profile render I
don't think it's a problem with the
actual profile because you can kind of
see that as I'm moving I'm still getting
you know debug original I think the
profile is actually working
I just can't interact with it properly
and so I was wondering if maybe our
multi thread rendering is busted because
when we're in the other mode when we're
back in this mode you will notice that
we are not actually drawing anything on
the other threads really because they
hardly ever hit and so I'm wondering if
maybe there's actually bugs in that
multi-threaded stuff that we're just not
because we aren't really using the other
threads yet in the in the non software
render case maybe we're just not seeing
them for that reason so that's like the
state of the profiler and obviously just
a ton of work we can do there so let's
do some of it or at least start
we've got draw a profile in is the
function that draws our profiler
first thing I'm going to do is just take
a look to see if it makes sense to me
why we're not drawing multiple threads
correctly
so if I take a look at what we're seeing
here you can kind of see that we've got
a rectangle that draws at the beginning
and that rectangle is just to sort of
darken the background it's basically a
backing rectangle and that was why it
was a little darker behind the profile
window we then have some information
here where we try to compute what the
lane height is the way we do that is we
look at how many lanes there are total
and we then say okay however many lanes
there are total we're going to divide
the total height by that
now that appeared to be working because
you'll notice we only have three active
lanes at three active threads in the
hardware renderer they're the two asset
loading threads and the main game thread
we never launched really any other tasks
on any other threads so our assists our
profiler would never see any other
activity on the high priority queues
where the other four threads are so we
saw a nice three division which is right
then when we search a software renderer
the profile system finally saw those so
the threads come in and you notice all
the parts got tinier even when we switch
back so this this Lane count thing I my
observation of what I saw there I
believe it to be working properly now we
come down through here and I want to see
whether or not the thing that actually
draws things into lanes is actually
making sense because for all I know
maybe that's busted who knows so let's
take a look here we are with our stored
event system we're looping over all of
the immediate children of the root node
that we're trying to profile we are
drawing it by saying okay let's grab a
color that's just based off the grid
pointer again there's really no rhyme or
reason that we just need some pointer
there right and here we are with
computing the min and Max X I'm assuming
the minimax X are computed properly
because they looked like there it could
be computed properly in the main bar and
they certainly look correct here so I
don't suspect as any throughout the
computation and that seems borne out by
what we see visually now here in the Y
computation you can see we're doing a
rectum in max here is the min and
X and then here is my computation for
what the min and Max why are you can see
we've got the lane index here oh well
there you go so for starters we're never
actually setting this lane index so
that's gonna be a problem regardless
that means that everything is being
drawn into lane zero even if it was on
some other Lane
now the profile nodes themselves I
believe we've already done the work
right I'm pretty sure that we've done
the work of figuring out what Lane they
should be in because we're doing that
during the collation now so I feel like
like thread ordinal is is all we really
need to know so I feel like we can just
go ahead and say that the lane index is
a thread ordinal now at least we're
starting with a little bit more of a
reasonable thing now we're starting at
the max y and we're moving backwards so
we're saying that the min is going to be
the lane index plus 1 times the line
height and the the max is going to be
lame with index plus zero that seems
about right to me
basically that saying start at the one
down from where you're going to be and
then go up which is you know two preusse
the minute max remember y is going it
increases as we go upwards on the screen
because we're in math coordinates here
not screen coordinates where oftentimes
y would go increasing down so here we
have our push rect call we're pushing
the REC that we created there that seems
reasonable as well
we take a look to see whether or not the
mouse is in the rectangle and then we do
this print out this should probably be
switched to an interaction as well or at
least that interaction should be added
to it again to allow for clicking and
stuff so that might be the next thing
I'm gonna take a look to see what we end
up getting here with our with our change
to having the lanes drawn correctly I'm
not sure what that will do for us but
we'll see we should maybe see some noise
down here during loads as well yeah you
saw them right there that was the asset
system loading in there and so now let's
take a look at what happens if we switch
to the software renderer so it looks
like now you know I'm seeing I'm
definitely seeing the hover work
properly and it just seems like our
rectangle fill is a little bit broken
while we're in here what I'd like to do
is
turn off the background fill like get
rid of this to see if there's some kind
of weirdness there so it looks like it
looks like that background fill is a
little busted and I'm not sure why
because here is what we would expect to
see in our software profile and we do
here's the main game thread running here
are the two asset loading threads
they're not doing anything at the moment
and here are our child render work
threads you can see them each taking a
little bit of time but they basically
kick off roughly the same time and end
depending on how much work they had to
do so that's you know roughly what we
would expect kind of cool right I really
enjoy having tools like this you can
actually see what's going on excuse me
so that's kind of nice and we we can
sort of see what's happening there so
that's lovely now what I don't know is
why that background clear only seems to
work in the in the the this phase I
don't know I don't know why that would
be the case I'm a little confused by
that to say the least
why would that be the case why would it
be first of all it may be in fact it
probably is the fact that we don't
support alpha blending with like it's
probably the case that we don't have
alpha blending for our rectangle right
that seems like it's probably true
because I don't know that we ever
implemented a read-modify-write for
active well no you know what we might we
might have we should check that but what
I don't understand is let's say that it
was just the alpha or something that was
broken what I don't understand is why
it's drawing pure purple and why it's
drawing purple on top right
like if it was drawing solid in the
background and then still drawing the
threads on top of it that would make me
expect oh the render the drawing routine
is just a little bit busted in the
software under because I don't know why
we were concentrating bitmaps and we
hadn't looked at solid rectangles in a
while or I don't know what but given
that that's not what I'm seeing this
feels like that the sort is wrong but
that the sort is only wrong in the
software renderer right and so that's
what that feels like is happening but
I'm not sure I don't know hmm so what's
the problem there we're drawing this to
the backing transform and we're drawing
these rectangles to the back and
transform so maybe that's actually just
kind of wrong and we really need another
Z level there that does seem possible
right that there'd be a backing
transform a drawing transform and then
kind of forward it's like look we would
need more Z's effectively I could see
that being the case and so it's possible
that it's just the sort that is being
weird and and I guess what I wouldn't
know at that point is why the hardware
renderer doesn't sort the same way as a
software renderer because they should
both sort the same
and actually since they're sorting by
why you would expect this one probably
to be above all the time so I don't
really know I'm a little bit confused
whether that's a little bit perplexing
it doesn't make perfect sense to me I'll
be completely honest with you it's a
little weird a little bit weird so yeah
let's see here if I were to make another
one of these so we've got you know where
this is I don't know you buy a transform
this is probably not the best way to do
this either like it seems like we want a
more granular way but you know
we'll we'll stick with it for now so I'm
moving this to another layer that's in
between I just want to see if that
changes it so there's the profile right
seems to be working okay here's the
platform controls going to turn them on
and so that did fix this sort yeah so
that's fine but I don't know why it's
purple still so we still have another
kind of weird thing going on there like
that should not be purple and I would
like to know why it's purple if I go to
the handmade render code I don't really
know what happens with a draw rectangle
it does well that that does not look
right I'll admit that
if that's the code we're actually
calling for draw rectangle that doesn't
actually support alpha alpha blending
does it yeah
so at the moment our draw rectangle code
does not actually support alpha blending
at all it would seem so
that is probably why that doesn't work
although I'm not sure why it would be
pink because we're passing black right
we're passing black with an alpha of
0.25 so I'm not sure why we would get
that result specifically but you know
fixing this would not be too difficult
certainly if we were to take a look here
at the well I guess we don't have to
really do that if we were to unpack the
pixels here we could presumably do our
alpha blending just fine so it would be
nice to write this routine as an
optimized routine right it would be nice
to take a draw rectangle quickly and do
that properly and I guess you know one
thing we could do if we wanted to is
take a look at draw rectangle quickly
and actually just sort of cut it down to
two you know to be just the thing that
draws a rectangle we could actually do
that and use essentially the exact same
ops here that we were doing and just get
rid of all the Texel stuff we could do
that I'm not sure it's worth our time to
do it but we could do it and I don't
know let's see how long that would take
us I don't know seems worth maintaining
a little bit of parity here just for fun
so here's our draw a rectangle code
and here is our filling code right so we
kind of know as we go through these
which one we're doing so I guess I would
want to sort of keep to a certain extent
this notion of what we're filling
between that's this code right here
right the min max X this this
information I guess and then I'm gonna
just if zero this out and then put it in
this new code here like so so let's take
a look we still want to pre multiply our
color presumably that shouldn't change
we don't need to know any of these
access length things because we're not
rotating this rectangle this rectangle
is supposed to be screen oriented I
believe we could still support the
rotation I just don't know whether
that's something we care about so I'm
gonna say no for now so I'm gonna say we
don't care about any of this right we
don't care about any of this at all
let's see Phil rect so we know our fill
rec we already have our fill rect it's
there so we don't care about any of this
I don't think so I think we can just
start with this all we have to do is
intersect our clip region which I assume
we pass yes all we have to do is
intersect our clip region with our fill
region then we can go ahead and do our
our testing our clipping masks all that
stuff this should all be exactly the
same we can then I think get rid of most
of this stuff
probably a lot of that can just go away
we'll take a look in a minute we don't
have any texture memory we don't have
any of like this stuff texture pitch or
any of that let's see what else we got
here let's see what else we got
all of this stuff can stay for now and
this stuff will all still be here we'll
just have to fix the defines below so
let's see we've got all of our pixel
fill we've got our clipping we've got
our destination we've got our U and Vees
which we don't need anymore fetch we are
not doing none of this right because
this is all Texas stuff this is all our
fetch our Texel fetch we don't want any
Texel fetch we don't want any violence
and we just want to load the destination
then we want to go ahead and convert
well we don't need to convert that the
texels actually at all I don't think we
don't need to do the bilinear blend we
do need to do the modulate by the
incoming color in the sense that we just
need it to be the color right so
whatever the actual incoming color is
that's what we actually want here
exactly
no mul PS necessary there's that color
and then we are clamping the color
values we don't we don't really need any
of this
I don't think we'll leave it for now but
we don't really need to do any of that
we've got our our gamma correction which
is all good our destination blend and
all of this stuff looks about right so
that's fine all right
these are undeclared identifiers that is
true I'm gonna get rid of them there we
go
and I guess we have a pixel inclusion
test here now that I think about it we
don't want to do the pixel inclusion
test we just want to see like whether
the the all we need to know is
essentially which pixels whether we're
inside the the X&amp;Y properly right
let me see what actually happens there
so pixel P Y P Y X n I don't think we
need I don't think we need or want any
of these things right we don't want the
U or the V or any of that
pixal PX not sure if we care about that
either let's see I get rid of these for
now and I'm gonna go ahead and loft
these things up because now they're used
by multiple people so I'm just gonna say
that those come here I'm gonna delete
them from the other place where they
occur which is here and I'm gonna move
the Ayaka stuff up to the top again
because that's something we might use to
profile that we can alright so let's see
here so the right mask and the clip mask
actually should be the same right so we
shouldn't have to do this at all
we should just be able to do this right
and this just needs to be defined and
then I think we're pretty close to good
pixel px don't care about that all right
so in theory now we have a draw a
rectangle call in theory that we'll do
our fill for us with alpha blending I
think that is my assertion anyway I'm
pretty sure don't quote me on that and
is it actually currently drawing these
let's find out it doesn't look like
reloaded for whatever reason oh you know
why it probably didn't is because this
is now built into the platform layer at
the moment because we didn't make a
third layer for the renderer all right
so let's go ahead and see what that code
does we are actually in it now so we can
we should be able to see what it
actually looks like well that's not very
good is it
I don't see any rectangles at all which
is not a very good amount of rectangles
let's see what we messed up here let's
set a breakpoint here we go so I
probably should be I would rather be
single threaded here but of course let's
see who we got
let's
let's look at just this thread if we can
I want to look at just this thread can I
step thread do we have step thread here
I'm gonna go with no frieze threads
collapse groups fan groups expands yeah
well I'll tell you what if you don't
want to make it easy for me to step
threads then I will simply turn off all
the threads how do you like that here's
the high priority queue right so if
instead of the high priority queue
actually working I just said that there
were no things in the high priority
queue I'm assuming I could get it down
to one
okay so here we are on the main thread
doing our rendering and our rectangle
has an area which is a bummer to say the
least
let's figure out if our rectangles ever
have any area well that would do it
apparently our fill rect on our cliprect
never intersect so we never actually get
to any of our rendering code which would
be good reason why we would never see a
rectangle
I should think I'm not sure why that
would be this is the same code in each
case so I'm gonna leave it actually
there I'm not sure why we would never
see a rectangle maybe I need to make
sure there was more of one to begin with
I mean there's an obvious rectangle
there we go
so now we can actually look and see
where we are at set up some stuff and
look at the watch window so I mean ymax
y min x max X obviously plenty to fill
there so let's see why we are not
filling the right mask is equal to the
clip mask so what is our right mask our
right mask is all set so it should right
everywhere we are loading the
destination in we are taking our colors
that's
that's not what's going on here
there we go there's an A in there right
so shouldn't okay there we go
all right just want to make sure all
right so our Texel are our textile gr
Tex will be our all-black which is what
we would expect we're squaring to get to
absence we're doing our blend so we're
gonna multiply by the textile alpha so
this is just giving us what our blends
should be which should be 75% right
although I guess if it's well what is
our inverse textile a so our textile a
is two five two five two five two five
our inverse X will a
he's point nine nine oh I see I see is
our alpha in the right format here
because these are all going to be 255
ish and we're multiplying right so this
is just to convert the destination into
zero to one space so that seems fine
actually
so that seems pretty reasonable I feel
like we should be seeing that but we so
totally are not seeing that right
nothing looked obviously wrong there to
me anyway
and I guess we should look to see are we
always just producing the exact same
pixel value
our right mask is still full I didn't
start to like 30 minutes in today so
we're so not in Q&amp;A right now
I should probably actually only start
the timer when I actually start about
what're you gonna do
so there's the right mask it's full
here's the pixel value that we're
writing into right that's where we're
that's our destination target and here's
our output value let's see here
well we are definitely producing the
exact same value there's no question
about that
so I guess the thing that I need to
figure out is why why are we producing
the wrong alpha blend
I think what I would like to do is just
use structured art here for a minute I
think that'd make it a little bit easier
for me to track so what I'm thinking is
instead of setting these as the actual
correct color values what I'm going to
do is instead just stuff the color value
so I think what I'll do is I'll say oh
you know the color R is gonna be 1.0 the
color you know G is gonna be 1.0 and so
on maybe I'll do it so I can see the
channel so there'll be no green just
aren't be okay and so let's take a look
at what we get here
our you know we have our textile our
f/32 actually I don't remember how you
get these it's this guy there's our text
red values which are all ones which is
what I would expect here's our
destination our value which is what
nines I guess and then when we do our
blended our
we get a three this makes it seem
I feel like I'm not understanding that
the space these are in because it's been
a long time since we did this when we
modulate by the incoming color the
incoming color is in zero to one space
the the destination is in zero two to
five space right but it looks like
it looks like we're okay we modulate by
the incoming color but the Texel values
were still 0 to 255 so that's where the
255 came from so basically we have to
re-encode this RGB to be 255 right so
basically this has to happen first in
order to bring everything up to the
correct level if that makes sense
because everything is actually zero to
one space we need it in 0 to 5 space
because we're no longer loading a Texel
so in order to slot in where the Texel
would have slotted in we need that to
actually work now the roughness code is
not the code you would actually write
just to fill a rectangle but I was just
trying to use the minimum amount of sub
change you know I'm saying all right
it's still not getting color properly
our alpha looks right but our color
looks wrong what happened there
RGB a for our texels RGB a
pre-multiplying the color up front seems
like it should be okay is the a value
not is the a value handled differently
no because the Texel a value which comes
in right here
he's actually fine
mmm so why are we getting all the same
color
blended are blended G blended B times
the R squirt PS
we multiply we multiply our color value
by its reciprocal square root
all right anyway let's see here so we
have our destination blend we've got our
textile a and we do one minus that all
of those seem correct to me so I'm not
sure why our color is not being passed
through properly
maybe our color values aren't what I
think they are but I'm pretty sure they
wouldn't have been blown out to 255 255
255 to anything other than you know the
zero to one range so it seems to me now
let me go double check actually in in
this case I'm going to take a look at
draw rectangle quickly
I wanted to see what it does to the
color values here so it does the
pre-multiply and then just leaves them
in that format right yeah and that seems
fine and we do the same thing here
pretty multiply the color value waltz
Dylan's very one range then blow it out
do we not want to do that with the I
feel like we want that even for the
Alpha we want that to happen basically
across all the color values so I'm
pretty sure that's what we want
everywhere yeah so I'm not sure why
we're not getting why the color channels
seem to be unseparated
like why why is that happening someone
explain what is our max what is this max
color value nonsense here ah so this
looks suspicious as well so we were
actually doing things in double it looks
like our blends when we load them in are
into two to five times they're in
squared space right so really we need to
square the color first as well does that
make sense because that's what we were
expecting to have so we actually want
our chart mm square there we actually
want the color values to be squared in
that space - hmm now the question is do
we want the Alpha value squared I don't
think so because we don't threshold that
one so I'm gonna take a look here
here's the unpack here's the srgb
conversion but they're not really by
linear blend modulate the incoming color
clamp I'm not sure why we clamp to be
honest
and then we do in of 255 for X so I
can't say I necessarily understand
I guess the Alpha value stays 0 to 1
some handle but I don't understand why
that would be probably because it
doesn't get squared because the Alpha
value never needs to get squared I guess
that makes sense since the Alpha value
is not getting corrected to srgb space
the Alpha value isn't squared but
everything else is right so really this
is probably the the culprit that's
tricky
I think we got it now yeah
you can see the color values aren't
quite corrected correctly this I'm still
doing something slightly wrong there
although that that may actually be the
hardware renderer not color not doing
the Alpha correctly for all I know
I'd have to because it's not gonna when
we do a solid color fill it's not gonna
use srgb for the input color so actually
I think that means that the hardware
renderer is actually the inaccurate one
in this case but either way all right so
if I read an able our threads again
somewhere in here somewhere
there it is oops
so if Eirene able our threads and I let
this go then we should be lovely
now our rectangles are basically the
same except I'm not sure who is right on
the color side of things if that makes
sense
so you know what it's we ended up doing
a lot of a rendering day instead of a
profiling day that makes me think of
another thing we might want to do here
when we switch between these two
renderers the fonts are different and
actually everything's a little bit off
right and one thing that someone
reminded me of on the forums actually
that I had totally forgotten is that and
in fact you know what
I did this so I could show you who is it
diver ball he pointed out that in order
to make sure we never fetched off the
texture in bilinear land we had
introduced that one pixel apron remember
all we always actually only use the
interior part of the texture
and there's a one texel apron around the
whole image that we don't use so we have
that UV fix up that we do and we are not
doing that on the hardware renderer so
if we did that on the hardware renderer
that would probably improve our the way
it lines up the hardware vendor is
effectively not rendering the real thing
and so when we call in in this code here
where we're like render entry bit bitmap
where we do OpenGL rectangle we actually
don't want to do the standard OpenGL
rectangle the one that we're doing here
we actually need to correct the texture
coordinates and what we could do is we
could pass those texture coordinates in
potentially like we could do like you
know menu the max UV where these are set
ahead of time to like the right thing so
effectively anyone who was using this
before would just get the default
parameters of this is min UV min UV this
is max UV x max UV x n UV
X min UV oh wait that's not that was a
one okay max UV X Max and UV X and then
these are this I can just replace here
remember you know what I forget what I
bound it to never mind I don't do a
surgeon replace when you do why and max
uvy all right so if you run it now we
should get exactly the same thing we
were getting before right no change but
now if I go ahead and pass the corrector
corrected Texel coordinates I'm hoping
that we will get a closer match and so
in here where we call this OpenGL
rectangle here what I'm going to do is
I'm going to pass a min UV and a max UV
on through so in order to do that I need
to compute essentially the text the
Texel offsets exactly the same way we
were computing them in the software
renderer which means we're going to
start one texel in and end one texel
back so in order to do that I have to do
like you know one texel one texel and
here I have to do like you know width
minus one texel height minus one text
little kind of a thing right or I should
start 1.0 minus one texel so what I need
to do is I need to compute how big one
texel is and unfortunately it's gonna be
different in U and V because U and V is
0 to 1 and these bitmaps are different
widths and Heights so the range on the
height and the range on a sorry the
range of the width and the range of the
height are going to be different so I
have to compute how big a Texel is in
each of them and yeah it's pretty easy
to do all I need to do is know how big
they are and so I'm assuming that there
is that information here I'm assuming
that I can just ask right
like so and be done so that's one you
know one texel in you and one Texan v
but since that can now divide by zero
what I would like to do is just do an
entry bitmap with and entry bitmap
height I would like to make sure that
those are both actually valid before I
do anything because in case we load
somehow is 0 with the bitmap or for some
reason I don't want the game to crash
I'd rather just not render anything
which seems harmless enough right
so already you can kind of see that the
fonts look more like they look they're
more correct now and so here's the
switch wow I I can't even really tell
the difference much now I think we're
still off by a little bit but it is
really hard to see the difference
between our dren Durer's like really
hard
that's pretty great I can sort of see
the difference on the fonts it looks
like we are I would say that we are not
pre stepping our software renderer to
the correct pixel center so I think
we're off by a little bit in the pixel
center I think that's really it but
otherwise we line up perfectly now with
OpenGL which is pretty awesome all right
yay so I'm going to close this out
cool so for those of you don't know I
started a bug list in the github so that
we could keep track of some of these
things that you know we need to
potentially fix right and you know these
are basically just things that we sort
of found maybe we talked about but
haven't fix that or that people on the
forums need help with for like compiling
on different compilers or stuff like
that so while we're in here we could
probably fix a couple of these actually
I know that our srgb typos like I had
made a change to the to the there was a
typo in the sRGB detection I think it
was in win32 handmade here and there was
a typo I fixed it and I forgot to save
the file I think or something like this
happened I think it's right here
where was that SRB there it is it's this
one right here remember this is not
supposed to be OpenGL default internal
texture format that's not what it's
supposed to be it's supposed to be
whether or not it has that the extension
that allows us to to do srgb so it was
actually to see whether or not it
supported srgb frame buffer so that was
actually what we're supposed to do it's
supposed to be like if it doesn't
support us are to be frame buffer then
don't set that right that was what we're
supposed to do and similarly if we don't
support an sRGB frame before us think
about this before if we don't support an
sRGB frame buffer the other thing that I
think we would want to do is actually
not not set the texture format either
right because if it doesn't support an
sRGB frame buffer we don't want to like
basically what happens when we're doing
that srgb remember because we
implemented some saw for renderer we
load the texels out of the texture we
gamma we ungawa correct them we do our
ops and then we're e gamma correct to
put it into the frame buffer now if the
frame buffer rege am a correction is not
going to happen then we don't want to
we don't want to convert to linear
because we'll get a more correct image
by just leaving everything in gamma
space all the way through we'll get a
totally messed up washed out image if we
don't gamma correct on one side but do
on the other if we you know use apply
the curve on one side but not the
inverse on the other side so I think
what we actually also want to do here in
order to be a little bit more compliant
as we go forwards and try to if we try
to support some it doesn't support those
those texture formats in OpenGL in it I
think we need to pass a thing which says
you know the 32 you know frame buffer
supports srgb or something and what we'd
want to do here is say if the framework
supports RGB and we have the srgb
extension then we will use it right if
that makes sense I guess actually here
it is it's right here too so really
these go together so I guess what I'm
saying so if we have all the extensions
and we believe that the the the
underlying stuff works right
right because if not everything is if
not absolutely everything supports the
sRGB transforms then we don't want to
turn on just one side goes turning on
just the frame buffer or just the
texture will lead to the completely
wrong image and that would be real bad
so I think that's actually what we want
to do here when we do our open jellinek
here
I assume at this point have we set this
correctly
yeah because we've queried all of our
swap interval stuff so this is pass
through so let's just double-check this
now to make sure this is not really a
test of it in any particular way but
just trying to make sure yeah man that
is just so cool how close we match I'm
pretty psyched about that all right so
anyway really hard to fight the urge to
not go back and correct it exactly to
match someday we probably will because
I'll just won't be able to not do it
anyway so we've got our our bug resolved
there so I'm going to go ahead and close
that out that is in this here we fixed
the typo so we just entered name we're
checking isn't always the one so here's
another one - someone was saying that
that GL ARB frame buffer srgb is is also
one that's checked that it's sometimes
present for the same purpose so what we
might want to do is try to do that bug
as well so people can look and see if
that helped so here what we could do is
just say well in either case there's our
versions of these so let's just go ahead
and support
the ARB ones as well right I don't
actually remember what they are but
let's take a look
so texture srgb ARB because they're
something like that
good job thanks google that's good let's
see well here's the GL ARB frame buffer
srgb so that one at least we know is
oops that one at least we know what that
one is so we know the other frame buffer
1 so there's the the original extension
1 and here's the ARB 1 and then now we
just want to look to see what the
texture version of that is and I don't
actually know maybe there isn't one
texture srgb armed well
yeah not seeing a lot of other stuff
here there anything else about it the
frame buffer ones there but I don't see
the texture one let's see about if I
just search for the actual extension
that we use which is this this guy right
here how do we know if it's supported
how do we know how do we we don't know
apparently maybe it's just by default
supported in OpenGL 4 and it's not in
three or something I don't know well
so I don't know about that I would be
interested to see I can't scroll down
here there we go I would be interested
to know what that actually was if
someone knows of an r1 please open a new
bug for this at some point or post on
the forums what it is so that we'll be
able to know but all right yay okay so
I'm gonna put a little to do in here and
just say like to do is there some kind
of ARB string to look for that indicates
the Oh X texture srgb do what I could do
also if there was an ARB one this card
maybe would be reporting cuz the drivers
relatively modern well it's kind of an
old card but what I could do is just
look and see what's actually coming out
in that string maybe I can just spot it
right maybe if I set a breakpoint in
OpenGL get info maybe I can see like in
here somewhere
what's going on
so here's a bunch of stuff let's see our
frame before sRGB is there you know I'm
just gonna go ahead and search mmm I
don't have I don't know how to get a
temporary buffer in for coder never
thought of it before
I'll just go go to the bottom of the
file srgb X texture and frame buffer so
it doesn't look like there is an ARB one
I guess that's it
so there we go
so I don't know what to make of that but
that's where we're at
cool
all right
all right let's do brief q and a brief
brief brief and I will close that down
and we should probably do a couple
others of these they're not too many
like basically these can be could
probably be not too too much
Jessie use I've implemented a quick and
dirty flame graph for handmade hero here
is the link is that a flame graph I
guess yeah I mean you just kind of move
down if you want to stack the things up
it's I can't say that that's super
readable but I mean yeah I guess that's
kind of works
he's the stream being off tomorrow at
April Fool's joke no I have to go to a
wedding dinner thing so it's actually
not an episode just I'm just not here so
I can't stream Kubica that what happened
to the sufferer forest it was running at
30 frames a few months ago even without
Oh - it was pretty decent I don't know
about that
it was never able to render the
super-stacked cutscene stuff without Oh
- remember Oh - was always on by default
in the software renderer always because
we had that handmade optimized so you're
not comparing apples to oranges there if
I go back in here and and actually put
on optimization it should be pretty
reasonable kind of what that just did
okay there we go
but it was though it always struggled
with the the super deep cutscenes
because it has to overdraw a lot and you
know if we were gonna try and optimize
that we would cut down a lot of overdraw
but yeah so it always had trouble with
like this scene for example because it's
stacks and stacks and stacks of these
little subtle layers that it's nothing
to do all of those fills right so on
scenes that have less layers it's better
but you know it's still problematic also
the debug code probably eats of a bunch
of that time unfortunately so like you
can see the software's actually done
right about here actually come to think
of it is that just you know what's
actually causing the problem with our
suffer renderer that you're noticing
that the difference between what it was
because this off runners done right here
so we're about twice as fast as the
framerate is right now it looks like
it's just the open gel texture download
right see what I'm saying about debug
tools being so important like you can
just immediately see that there's no way
you would ever see that otherwise hold
on a second here we need to wait we need
to add a three-way switch so we can pick
between these but if we switch this so
that went through to rendering type on
startup is going through GDI
I'm interested to know what the what
that looks like now
yeah much better
certainly
let's see if we can get back to it there
yeah I mean that's like twice as fast
right as it was so yeah I think part of
that is also remember we're doing that
weird thing for the streaming which
totally screws up OpenGL so that's not
even open gels fault just that's just
how it is
yeah that's holding like 60 Hertz on
this thing which is pretty great but you
can see when it switches to more layers
when it gets to about 4 layers it can't
quite hit it it's not quite at 30 it
doesn't quite take 30 but it's it's not
quite there what is this nonsense debug
collation it might if we turn off the
debug collation it might be able to of
course we would then lose our ability to
profile but you know
q for Caleb so let me get this straight
modern picky connections have several
gigabytes a second a bandwidth and it
takes several frames to upload a texture
for the back buffer well it's not that
simple it's a lot more complicated than
that actually and it's probably not the
right time to go into it
but there's so many things that go into
having to get a texture down to the card
for usability that there's just a lot of
pipelining it's it's it's problematic it
has to be swizzles it has to be mapped
into the aperture we're not doing a very
efficient download right now like what
we should do is probably do it into a
pixel buffer object if like if we were
trying to optimize our opengl throughput
for the picture for the back buffer we'd
probably want a pixel buffer object and
we want two of them to ping-pong so that
we get rid of one of the copies so like
and OpenGL right now is not set up
properly like I was saying before at the
moment OpenGL is happy to run in this
weird mode to make sure the streaming
works so probably if I turned on the the
double buffer flag we would get a bunch
of improvement there too so so there's
that
yay I feel like we don't we're not doing
a clear like the clear in the Safa
render obviously there's no clear which
is fine we won't really need one because
we'll be drawing stuff back here pretty
soon but just worth noting that we don't
have a clear on software renderer for
whatever reason alright alright folks
I'm gonna go eat some dinner leave this
the way we found it probably don't want
optimizations on okay close that down
and that down thank you everyone for
joining me for another episode of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you want to
follow along with the code at home you
can always pre-order the game on
Hammacher org and it comes to the source
code so you can do exactly that you
could also go to the forums and ask
questions if you've got questions you
can go to our patreon page if you want
to support the video series you can go
to the tweet bot to find out when we are
live and that is exactly what you will
have to do to find out the schedules for
next week I will be off stream tomorrow
so there will be no stream tomorrow but
we will probably pick back up on Monday
assuming normal schedule so please check
the tweet bot Monday morning to see what
the schedule for the week going to be if
you would like to do some more profiler
implementation that's about it until
until next time I will catch you guys on
the internet have fun programming
everyone